My searches for understanding how to integrate different temperature sensors and gadgets into home assistant
I kept coming across the intermittent tech channel and when Alex suggested that we chat with
Quintin are today. I thought it was a great opportunity to really geek out Quintor. Welcome to the self-hosted program
Thank you very much. Thank you for joining us Alex
And I are both impressed with the amount of output that you have on your channel
But also the depth of detail that you seem to go into like project after project you must
You must put a lot of work into that
Yeah, it's it takes up a lot of my free time
But I'm I guess I geek you would call it by heart and I like finding
Going to the bottom of things and then trying to explain it to others so they can do it also
Well, I appreciate that
Well, it's kind of the ground basis why it started as a blog and then it transitioned into a YouTube channel
So yeah, there are some things that just don't translate into text, huh? Yeah, very true
and and the other way around too, so like
Heaps of code do better on a blog. So now I do kind of both. I
Appreciate that because I agree completely with that and Alex has been striking a good balance with that himself
So Alex was at the recent home server series that put quindor on your radar this time. It was yeah, so
You've been building a server lately. Haven't you with ZFS and doing some stuff with Ryzen and Proxmox and all that kind of stuff
Yeah, my my old server was about six years old now
I think and there were some disks starting to fail and I started to have some other problems and
One of the ways we noticed that is I actually run demotics and home assistant still at both
And well at some point the lights didn't turn on because a disk was crashing stuff like that
So I thought okay time to build a new one
That's the side of self-hosting people don't talk about very often is when it breaks. It's your fault. You got to fix it
Sometimes it's an opportunity
Yeah, so this server looks really sweet. It's a hundred terabyte 10 gigabit server that that's the that's the branding on all of all
Of your videos. How did you come to some of the decisions around?
Choosing the hardware and and and Proxmox and stuff like that for me. The server is kind of
Multi-purpose. I have my youtube channel as we just mentioned and for that I need a lot of storage
I generate about six to eight terabytes of footage raw footage a year
and I also like to live edit from the server, but my old server wasn't really up to that and
Next to that. I run my home animation VMs like with demotics and home assistant from it and for work
I also run some testing environments and things like that. So I
kind of wanted to renew it and
more cores is more better in that regard and
the new
Ryzen 3000 series was launching
So I was like, okay, let's move my old Ryzen
a 1700 desktop to my server platform and then buy a new Ryzen
3000 series and basically buy a new desktop but get a new server out of it. Now have you found the Ryzen switch because
Intel these days
I don't know if you've seen the the latest videos from like Jay's two cents and Linus tech tips and all that
But they are beating up hard on Intel these days. Yeah, well this sort kind of started during the Ryzen 1000 series
So as I said, I was one of the first guys to get it and I did a whole series called the road to Ryzen
Getting the first eight core where I came from a quad core and Intel
well, they quickly followed with six and eight cores, but now I have a 12 core and
Intel basically has nothing that can compete with it even
In the areas where they used to be better
So in IPC and power usage and stuff like that the right especially the Ryzen 3000 series is just better
Yeah, I'm curious specifically which workloads you see a big improvement on is it encoding work? What types of?
CPU loads are you using that benefit? Well take my video rendering from the Intel box
I had before and granted it was a few years old that basically became four times as fast. That's wonderful
we have from a four and a half gigahertz quad core to it basically a four and a half gigahertz with higher IPC 12 core and
the CPU was about the same during that era in price and
From the server. That's now an eight core server
Well, like five years ago that would have been ultra high-end and now it's just like it's eight cores. It's okay
It's something isn't it and you said something in there that piqued my interest because it's something we've attempted
To various degrees of success your live editing over that 10 gigabit connection. You've built on that server
How is that and had did you have to do any particular tweaking to your network your switches in general your network card?
Configuration to make that work. Well, it started in the design of the server
Reusing a desktop platform, but wanting to have high bandwidth
Capabilities you need to take a lot into account
So for instance a desktop platform is mostly limited in regards to PCIe bandwidth
so I did some research and made some videos about that and how to look up how many PCIe lanes there are and your
Motherboard and how they're distributed and then how you should basically distribute your cards over the available PCI slots
so that there won't be a bottleneck there and
After that, I run Proxmox with ZFS under it
And I did a little bit of tuning in regards to flash based caching in ZFS
So basically on the server the the project I'm editing
After a little while, especially from ingesting footage is basically all on the cache drive, which is an NVMe drive
so I can basically edit at full 10 gig speeds and
although that's still slower than locally, especially the latency that it doesn't come from a hard disk and
Well one gigabyte a second. That's plenty fast to edit video. I gotta say you're making me want to try it again
That's great. And then the storage is taken care of you're investing your money in one place
You have you can you can focus your performance on the server. That's really clever
Yeah, but also things around it like backup scripts and stuff like that
We're all kind of lax in setting that up on our desktop or workstation and stuff like that
But on my server, I basically have directories where everything goes. So I have some scripts running which make
backups to my as I call a DIY cloud backup solution, which I set up a few years ago and
That always runs that just runs during the night when my desktop is off, but my server is on
So I know if my stuff is on there, it's good
Because using ZFS you have the advantage of stuff like data sets and do you do make use of anything like ZFS send
For remote backups or like how do you do you even worry about off-site backups?
Yeah, I don't make bad use of ZFS send or receive but I do off-site backups using a
Basically a DIY cloud backup solution. I built a few years ago
Um, do you guys remember a backup service called crash plan? Oh, yeah with a horrible Java client and everything. Yep. Wonderful
Okay, granted, but they were the first to offer online backups with an unlimited plan basically for like a few bucks a month
So I've been using that for a few years and it was great and they allowed you to back up 10 PCs
So I backed up my mother's and father's PC and my sister's and mine and my laptop and some VMs
I had and that was all fine. And then they announced well, we're stopping and
a lot of other
Cloud hosted backup solutions out there. They're limited to
One client only so let's say you have black place and you have their unlimited plan
They limit you to have only a single client, but I have like eight or ten clients which have all my data
naturally, so I basically got together with a few friends and my parents home just got
Symmetrical megabits fiber
so we basically chipped in got five ten terabyte hard disks and I set up a
s3 server on their LAN which we could access remotely and
Ever since I've been backing up to that because it turns out if you buy five times ten terabytes with
Like an atom based server and run minio for s3
you can use all kinds of backup tools out there which talk as s3 and currently using RESTIC and
Back up anything you want to that and if you share that with a few friends
It's even a lot cheaper than the cloud if you take in if you look at it for like five years
Absolutely, I love that you chose to essentially implement
Self-hosted s3 services simply because of the client compatibility. That's probably a similar direction
I would have considered going because you're right you get so many good backup clients now and
Yeah, even if even if once a year around, you know, like an annual sale
Everybody goes in and you buy one more hard drive or two more hard drives to add to the mix or whatever your whatever your plan
Is have you thought about that long term? Like will you just continue to add this at an add to at a time or what?
Your thoughts around long term five years like you were saying
well
Since I went to ZFS route
Expandability isn't really a thing yet. So we went with five times ten terabyte
Which would basically be enough for the people involved for those five years and just don't even have to worry about it then no
No, that's gonna be fine for a few years
That is fantastic. Well going back to your new server
I don't want to spoil it because it's a series of videos and there's a lot of details in there
but something that Alex mentioned to me that I I wanted to sort of
Not only get you to chat about here on the show, but it kind of is a great example of your attention detail
You spend some time in this home server build specifically paying attention to the PCI Lane setup
I'm not really familiar with that part of the series. So could you fill me in on those details?
Basically if you're using a desktop platform
those are basically geared towards having you have everything on board and
Then having a graphics card and nowadays, maybe an NVMe SSD
So the PCI lanes so it's what is particularly is it just more more of them and more performance on the desktop boards versus a server
board have you heard of the
The eight times or 16 times graphics card situations like when you're plugging a graphics card in it says I'm running at eight times speed
Or 16 times speed or whatever. Sure
okay, and those refer to the number of PCIe lanes that are available for bandwidth between that device and the CPU one of the
nice things about Threadripper is that it has
Like I forget the exact number but it has like 30 or it might even be 60 PCIe lanes
Yeah, Threadripper has 64 and the newer generation that launched this year actually has 72. Holy crap
So like an NVMe SSD will will generally have a an x4
Slot so that will use four of your PCIe lanes
Which is why it's so fast because it's basically plugged directly into the matrix
When when you're looking at a desktop platform like Andreas says
One of the ways they save money is by not including so many PCIe lanes in the chipsets
if you do want to use your desktop chipset and
Platform for a server and you want to hook up 24 drives and some NVMe cache and have 10 gigabit
You kind of need to take that into account because just plugging all those cards into your motherboard
It might work, but it'll be very limited in regards to bandwidth
You're able to get so in my case if I plug in my graphics cards even into a times one slot
My times four slot will get limited to times two instead of times four PCIe lanes
and that means I can only get about five six gigabit over my ten giga leg instead of getting ten and
That's of course easily testable using network performance tools
But if this happens to your HBA which is hooked up to your hard disks
You'll be scratching behind your ears like why isn't this performing the way I thought it would but yeah
Okay, because Ryzen needs a graphics card, right?
It doesn't have a built-in GPU of any any description like the Intel chips might so one of the one of the videos
Andreas shows he literally
has a GPU that's just garbage just for installing the OS and then he pulls it out and he shows the difference between
his network card running at 6 giga second on a
X 2 or X 4 link and then pulls it out
And then suddenly the extra PCIe lanes are available and he gets the full 10 gig speed
It's actually pretty interesting to watch that is fascinating
I love that you took the time to actually demonstrate that to you. That's that's great
As you said, I think it's the details that the bigger youtubers they might build something cool
But they don't really have time to work that in the videos
So I thought like okay, let's do a whole series about this so that people want to do the same
Actually know what to take into account because what's your background?
I've picked up in some of the some of the episodes that you might have an enterprise you storage you type background
I'm just curious. I've been doing enterprise storage and mainly backup focused storage
And and backup solutions for the past 20 years now
In the bigger enterprise situation
So if you have like five and a terabyte or even a few petabyte and you want a storage solution for that or a backup
Solution and basically you're a guy. So what what we're doing at home is is kind of cute to you, I guess
in some ways, but it also
Teaches me a lot of stuff. So it's it's a win-win for that for both
Both sides basically and how do you square off?
You know because in the enterprise everything's about being highly available which will lead into another topic shortly
You know, how do you square off desktop hardware of you know?
Having a single power supply only and stuff like that against that kind of enterprise. Let's have redundant everything
so in the enterprise
Time is basically money
So if you can spend more money to not have downtime basically
That's most often worth it. So having a dual PSU which will cost you
$600 instead of having a single one which will cost you $200
But being down one hour costs you $2,000
Well that choice is easy
Mm-hmm, but at home
$2,000 for like oh, sorry
$600 for like a dual power supply is a lot of money where two hundred dollars will work fine
Except indeed if it fails, but then if it fails
I'll just run out get a different power supply plug it in and I've been down maybe a day and during that day
And well not two thousand dollars per 24 per hour were lost
So I can't really
Make the same judgment call. So my time is worth less money than it is in the enterprise
Yeah, it's a good rationale and I can't argue with it, you know
But one thing that has come up in your latest video is a highly available home assistant
I am super interested in this
So please talk us through what that is first of all what that means because some people listening to this may not be familiar with what?
Highly available means in the enterprise next to having redundant components on a single server
they also have a term ha or called high availability is that if a
Complete hardware box would go down
basically, there's a cluster of hardware boxes, which then would take over the function or
VMs or guests or whatever that other box was running and then basically started again
To make that service it was running or providing available again
So a really simple example of this in the real world would be if you only have one car
That's a single point of failure in your life, right if your car breaks down and you can't drive it anymore
Suddenly you think to yourself. Well, I should have a backup car. Well, this is what we're talking about in terms of
Site reliability engineering here. It's a bit of a DevOps II type topic
but it's very important in in cloud architectures and that kind of thing as well and
I don't see any reason why we can't start implementing some of this stuff in our home setups
I home assistant and stuff like that when you're running
Services in your house that you rely on to control your lighting your heating etc, etc
having home assistant able to be able to
Move between a Raspberry Pi and your server and a NUC under the stairs, you know
So you've got two or three different devices that are capable of running that setup. You might have one
That's your primary beefy, you know your best car or whatever to get back to that analogy
But you might have your backup car that might be a bit old and a bit rusty
But it will get the job done in a in a pinch. Yeah, that's that's exactly as I've well
I'm still trying to build this or looking into it, but that's basically what I have
I have the the beefy new server, but the old server has become one of the nodes in a Proxmox cluster and
It certainly can't do everything the new server can but if if the new server would fail for whatever reason I am
Well, we'll go into it deeper, but you can basically start the home assistant VM again on one of the lesser power machines
So you won't get all functionality maybe but you'll get the functionality you need
So what what considerations do you have to make with home assistant when you're trying to run it in two places at once?
Effectively, are you are you a has I O user first of all, or do you run it out of a container or an LXC?
or what I've been looking into that and
To start off
I've been a has I O user in a on a Raspberry Pi and then I basically quickly moved into a VM
Because if you want to do something with influx DB and Grafana and stuff like that
The the pie will die a very quiet death. Well the SD card more specifically will will fail very quickly. Yeah. Yes
That's not good news for me
Yeah, cuz I'm feeling all what you're saying right now thinking to myself
Yeah, I really don't want to be troubleshooting a struggling pie at 9 p.m. When I'd rather just sit down on the couch
I can relate to that
You know if you do a lot of this stuff
There's certain times of the day where you just want to be done and when it's something as important as home assistant
This just happened to me recently
Instead of going to bed. I was I was resolving a home assistant issue and I thought to myself for a minute
You know what?
I need to have a way to just switch over to another system or have a snapshot or something. So
it it might sound silly to think about making your home assistant system highly available, but
Listening to the two of you. I think you both make a very compelling argument
It's making me rethink some of my setup even though it's so new which I just hate that
Yeah, that's how it goes but making
Locally run home automation highly available isn't talked about much or at least I don't see a lot of topics about it
but for me, I've just
Encountered this where the box is down because of a hardware issue and I know the VM is on there and I have another box
but I just well
If you don't take any precautions
You're you're done and that's basically what we're talking about here
Making sure that by whatever means possible
The VM if that hardware goes down you can basically start it somewhere else and doesn't even have to be fully automated, right?
Because a lot of stuff in the enterprise has health checks and heartbeats and all that kind of stuff that does automatic failover
But at home, you know this this weekend, for example, I spent a bit of time with has I owe automating snapshots and stuff like that
so I now have the tar files are syncing from my house I owe instance to a
folder on my ZFS
Array, and maybe I could run a house
I ovm on my desktop for a week whilst I wait for a part to come in or something like that using that snapshot
So is that the kind of approach you were taking?
Yes, but a bit more enterprising. I guess you could say so first
I built a four node Proxmox cluster with basically hardware ahead around the house
And even if you just have two boxes instead of one, that's fine. You can build a Proxmox cluster
With that and then the first thing I set up was in Proxmox a few versions back. They introduced
ZFS
replication
so basically
Proxmox will take a snapshot every 15 minutes of your VM and
Send it to the other box and the same VM is over there. It's just turned off. Oh, that's slick
I didn't know you could do that that could turn the recovery time into five minutes. That's really great. I
Want to make sure we chat about something before we go because Alex and I have been getting really into
LED light strips that are controlled by home assistant and you have a really cool DIY project called Quinn LED
I'm not very familiar with it, but it looks like it could be right up our alley
I started this when I started building the house. I'm currently living in I
Wanted to have a dimmer for LED strips and LED lights. It's mainly for LED strips
which I could control using demotics at that time and
I started looking into this and Philips U just became a thing and I started looking into that
I was like, okay, I can do this in my whole house and it's cloud connected and then I have to pay like
$20,000 I was like, that's never gonna happen
How can we do this otherwise and I started looking into this and I basically built the the Quinn LED
OG as I now call it. It was in
2015 I think and I basically designed a PCB in a board with some custom code on an ESP
8266 was an ESP 01 at the time and built a little dimmer board which integrated into demotics
Now fast-forward a few years. I've built more boards. I've built the Quinn LED quad and deca
That's a four channel and ten channel board which I for instance use for all the lighting in my home
But also in my film studio and stuff like that because it's able to do very high PBM frequencies and the newest board
I've released is the Quinn LED dig uno
That's a single channel
Digital LED controller so where analog LEDs can basically only set the strip to a single color
or brightness intensity
Digital LEDs can do this per LED
So you can make all kinds of effects and patterns and all kinds of cool stuff
one thing that I never really considered because the smart LEDs was the first project that got me into
You know, I used to build my own racing drones
I mean I still do but that got me into electronics and soldering and that kind of thing
but the first thing that got me into
Building my own stuff at home was LED lighting and I've got three or four of these things around my house right now
And then I watch your video about this
Dig uno with a fuse in it and polarity protection and all the rest of it and I'm like, oh, yeah
No, I probably should have a fuse in there, shouldn't I?
The Quinn LED dig uno basically was like, okay, I want to do more with digital LEDs around the house and
you can just take an ESP8266 or an Arduino or something like that hook up the pin to the LED strip and
Then you can make the effects
But if you want to install this in somewhat more permanent fashion
You want it like controllable in home assistant and you don't want it to burn down or if you're working it up at 380
Working it up at 3 a.m. And you cross the wires the wrong way
You don't want everything to blow up and that's basically everything I put into the dig uno design
so if a fuse reverse polarity protection
there is a level shifter on there because a ESP sends out 3.3 volts and the LED strip expects 5 volts and
Most of the time it works except when it doesn't
So I kind of incorporated all that into the board
But for people who want to move on from the breadboard with DuPont connections, and if you wiggle it it well turns off
To a bit more permanent setup.
I absolutely love and and thank you for this. I love that you have open-sourced the PCB design
I just think that's so cool.
I basically want it to be available for everyone
I want to talk about two year convert for a few minutes and for those of you that aren't familiar with this wonderful project
There are a bunch of smart plugs that you can buy based around the ESP8266 chip
Tekin in the US makes some and I'm sure Andreas will fill us in on a few
that are available in Europe. These things they try and
Connect back to the the manufacturers data center for some reason to get their firmware updates
And so what two year convert does which there'll be a link in the show notes is it emulates the update server
On a Raspberry Pi or any other device with two NICs what one has to be a Wi-Fi adapter and one has to be an Ethernet
But essentially you turn your Raspberry Pi into the update server of this company
You then flash Tasmota or whatever other firmware you want to onto these devices and then you own them forever
It's really really cool and two year convert is something that you've got into a fair bit, right Andreas?
About a year or one and a half ago a lot of two year based projects like light bulbs and also
Smart metering plugs became available for really interesting prices. These were like 10-15 bucks apiece and
At the time I wanted to measure some stuff in my home for power usage and things like that
And I basically want to have that data in home assistant so it can go to influx and Grafana and you can do all the stuff
with it
But these plugs as you said for some reason have to have an online connection and you can use an app and stuff like that
The hardware is in there. We just want to use it in our own way
But for some reason these manufacturers they don't allow that they they want you to run their firmware and then
And then connect to their data centers and then be allowed to use your data
And I really don't know why it needs to know when I turn on my Christmas lights or not
What are they doing with that data?
I often wonder particularly something that is so random as a switch like what possible information can they have from a switch being on or off?
Presence detection at least at least they know you're there. Do they I mean, I've definitely left my soldering iron on when I'm not home
I
Mean there's such a big community
Basically liberating these kinds of devices with ESP home and Tasmota firmware that I think like okay if even one
manufacturer would just give us the ability to easily do this by hitting a switch in some kind of web interface like
Allow custom third-party binary you take all responsibility click here
It would be an instant hit with the home home automation community, I think but
Nobody does this and is our data worth that much
I mean, I I can't imagine it is and there's so many motivating factors for doing it for myself
I just want it to completely function offline with no internet connection
So when I take the RV somewhere where we have no connectivity
I want everything to remain functional all of my automations to continue to work
I'm not as concerned about the privacy aspect, but that's number two on the list. Those are two pretty strong motivators right there
so I'm already adjusting my buying habits based on what the community seems to be able to
Reflash at different times when I'm purchasing and I'm I know more and more people are doing it and it reminds me of
the battle days with cheap routers
DWRT
Yeah, it's just like that all over again
Only more of them and of different varying quality now
There is a fun Twitter account that I like to follow called the Internet of shit and this talks about how the Internet of things is
It's vulnerable to quite a few things and it isn't always updated and that kind of stuff. It's it's pretty funny
Well and and to Andres's point a little bit more
Why do all of these companies want to be cloud companies with infrastructure and vulnerabilities and services to maintain and API's to update?
Why does a smart plug manufacturer want to even get in that game planned?
Obsolescence Chris you think it is planned. It could be that's the office. That's a little conspiracy bacon Alex
Well, yeah, think about it right if you're a hardware manufacturer and you're selling
it's what's essentially a
one or two dollar circuit board wrapped up in let's say another two or three dollars worth of plastic and
Then you've got to get an FCC rating and all that kind of stuff right there isn't gonna be much money to be made
I wouldn't have thought on a $10 smart plug. The margins are gonna be quite small
so you've got to find some way to get people to buy these things every X number of years and
One fun way to do that is to accidentally I mean air quotes accidentally brick the device
you don't even have to break it you just bring out a new app and
And then the new app can't talk to the old devices, but all the new devices can only talk to the new app
Philips hue hub did yes. Yes, exactly. That's exactly what I have that exact situation because I went into an old
Office that was shutting down and they had old Hughes lights all over the place and I thought well
How great is this and of course?
none of them could be controlled I had to go spelunking for an old app that I
Had I guess had gotten at one point and so I was able to retrieve it
I'm not even know if that normally how it works on the iOS App Store
And then I had to bring it through a generational upgrade process is obnoxious
So, I mean if you can own your hardware, I highly recommend doing it and this two-year convert
Collection of scripts is is really pretty cool. And there's been some updates over this course of this year
Two-year or the two-year compatible device manufacturers patched a lot of the exploits that were being used
And then in September sort of time an update came out and people have found another exploit and that's what we're currently using
So bear in mind this could go away at any time, but a device I bought this week is the Tekin
SS 30 and this thing has four individually controllable
AC ports and four
And four controllable USB ports. So in home assistant, I now have five switches that I can control on one like power strip
Using the the TAS motor firmware and it's really great because I know that that's just going to carry on working now until the end
Of time or until that device physically fails. Wow, that is really great. Is this the one that's only $24 on Amazon?
Yep, believe it or not. I'm gonna drop a link to that in the notes. That's really cool
and all you need to flash it is a Raspberry Pi right and then you own it forever and
They may not make that device forever and or they may patch that vulnerability
but that one now that you own it's good and if you were to buy a couple at a time, you could just kind of set
Up a production chain and just flash a few of them and get it over with and the thing that home assistance enables is now
That you you can use hue and your own flash plugs and all
All kinds of stuff from all kinds of brands and basically connect it all together as long as you can get it into home assistant
And it does that with a lot of cloud enabled stuff too, but getting in it and in there native with Tasmota or ESP home
It's just it makes it work so flawlessly every time
Mm-hmm. Yeah
I really do appreciate that aspect of home assistant because it means that some of these old IOT devices aren't throwaways a
Home assistant doesn't care that these hue bulbs that I got have old firmware on them
It still controls them just fine every now and then they pop offline
It's a little obnoxious
But it's so great at the same time to have three or four different vendors products all controlled locally by one piece of software
But the key thing that I've found is now I shop with home assistant compatibility in mind
That's where I start or a refresh ability for that. But yeah, right? Yep. Yep a good good point
That's another way to look at it. That's basically why I started one of the reasons
I designed my own hardware and dimmers and boards and stuff like that
It's all geared to being controlled with home assistant now
It's an ESP so you can run anything you want on it
But from what I gather and the people in discord and on my website and stuff like that
95% uses it with home assistant. Well Condor. I just want to say thank you again for not only all of the great details
I came across your channel when I was looking for cheap integration thermostats and the home assistant which has made my life more comfortable and
I also just really appreciate the level of details
so we will link to the intermittent tech YouTube channel in the show notes keep up the great work and
Keep us in the loop on future projects and we'd love to chat about them. Sure will do
Thank you for having me. Is there anywhere you would explicitly like to send people? I mean are you on Twitter?
I know you have a discord for example
Um, well people starting with the YouTube channel and if they then want to join the discords the link and stuff are there
So start with the YouTube channel. I think that's a good starting point and you can get more self-hosted show
On Twitter at self-hosted show. I'm on Twitter at ironic badger
I'm at Chris LAS and I'm there under intermittent tech and you can find links to all of those good things in the show notes
at self-hosted.show slash nine