2022, it's here with a bang.
We've dragged in our favorite Canadian out of the cold.
Welcome back, Brent.
Hello, everyone.
And Chris, as always, how are you doing?
Happy new year, sir.
Hey, you know what?
I want to say thank you to the team that stepped in for the holiday 3D printing
episode, that was a lot of fun.
And now, I mean, it feels like I haven't done this forever.
Yeah, who are you again?
What is this thing in front of my face?
Well, I thought maybe if I brought Brent with me, I'd be accepted back.
Maybe we'll see.
The jury is still out on that one.
It always works with Alex.
The quickest way to Alex's heart is through a Brent.
Oh, it's true.
Also, video games, you know, my favorite game of all time, I think, is probably
Factorio, but I potentially have a new one, which is vying for a top spot at the
moment, it's called Anno1800, have either of you played this game?
Oh, this is the first I hear of it.
Yeah, same.
What kind of game is this?
It's a city builder where you manage like supply chains and that kind of thing.
Oh, it sounds like it's up your alley.
You're pretty much playing as the East India Trading Company, minus the slavery
part, so that's kind of nice.
But yeah, you just trade goods back and forth and build cities and yeah, it's a
fun, relaxing, single player game.
When was this released and how'd you hear of it?
Ages ago, I don't know when it was released exactly, but I think I heard
about it first when Linus of Tech Tip fame mentioned it on one of his videos
and I thought, oh, I'll go and check it out and downloaded a demo and liked it.
So I bought it.
It's kind of great when you discover a game that's been out for a while.
So that means it's got a couple of patches under its belt.
You can find stuff online.
There's a community, sort of a sweet spot, you know, you know, a game doesn't
have to be cutting edge brand new for it to be enjoyable.
Absolutely.
Not speaking of stuff that's no longer cutting edge and brand new, I thought
I'd just do a quick bit of follow-up on the Linux Unplugged Predictions episode.
Unfortunately, I wasn't able to make the recording of this year's
predictions episode itself, but I thought I'd follow up on the prediction
I made last year, about 20 terabyte hard drives being available, I think,
for 250 bucks at Best Buy.
That didn't quite pan out.
No, it didn't quite, did it?
No.
I mean, there was a few shenanigans going on that kind of scuppered my, my plans.
First of all, supply chain, obviously we all know at this point, what's
going on with the supply chain, but second of all, it was Chia.
We had a hard drive mining crypto coin come out of the woodwork.
Yeah, there's just no way with all that was going on, that was going to happen.
You think maybe you got a better shot this year?
No, but I'm just going to say it anyway.
I mean, I was trying to, you know, with this Anno 1800 game, I've got a 1080
TI graphics card, which I've had for several years now, which was actually
incidentally paid for originally by Bitcoin mining four years ago.
And now with this Anno 1800 game, I've been looking for a new GPU.
And I was looking, you know, just to see what was out there.
The cheapest 3080 that I could find was on Facebook marketplace near me for $1,800.
What is going on with that?
Ridiculous.
Yeah, we've been building a new replacement server here and the number
one cost because the audience has been so awesome by providing the main rigs
has been storage and the just a limited amount of storage.
So I had to buy a batch of two terabytes and a batch of four terabytes.
I wanted all four terabytes, obviously, and I had to buy them all at the same
price, which I'm not super comfortable with, but it's going to be in an array
in array array, so hopefully if one or two pops will be all right, but they're
all used this and, you know, we paid a fair amount for them, even buying in the
after, you know, whatever you call it, the lightly loved market, I assume,
because they're enterprise drives.
So I hope I hope the last.
I've just recently learned about this whole hard drive used market.
Is this Alex, do you think something's going to happen with this market?
Is this Alex, you think something worth even considering?
I mean, how cheap are we talking?
A 14 terabyte.
So here's my reference point.
A 14 terabyte easy store that I can shuck from Best Buy.
I think I picked one up before Christmas for about $190, $200, something like that.
I think it's also what is your risk tolerance and do you have a setup that
can tolerate one or two drives at least failing?
Yeah, that makes sense.
So the new server, do we keep that in mind?
Yeah, yeah, we can.
We can sustain a couple of dis failing.
I think in total, we're OK until three fail simultaneously.
And I normally wouldn't think that's likely, except for these are probably all
originally from the same manufacturing batch.
They're all the same exact hard drive, the same exact model, all bought at the same
exact time.
I thought that was a rule not to do that.
I'm pretty sure there's a rule against that, like the bathtub curve or something.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But beggars are definitely not choosers.
And in this case, that's what we got.
Have you considered calling your buddy Alex over here and shipping him a couple of hard
drives and then you could use some of his basement space as a offsite backup?
Maybe we could do that.
That'd be a fun project.
Now, I know this is a lot of power, but what about a full server potentially?
Why?
Well, because I think I might have one that I'm going to totally sink.
And I mean, but you know, I think he has more servers than hard drive space.
You're pretty offsite.
You know, that's a good offsite backup, you know, in terms of offsite backups go when
in the East.
I mean, if a nuke hit DC, would it come out as far as Raleigh?
Probably.
I don't know.
I mean, if that happens, I think I probably got bigger problems, really.
Oh, I don't know.
I don't know.
You're on the West Coast.
I don't think the fallout would make it quite that far.
I'm joking.
Of course, there'll be bigger problems than that.
There's one or two mountains between us, I suppose.
Maybe I'll do all right.
And then really life should just go on as normal.
There would be no other repercussions.
No, I mean, if the federal government disappeared tomorrow, I don't think anybody would be too
upset.
Do you?
No, I just vote with blockchain.
I think that's what happened.
Oh, so is that your prediction?
Was it 200?
What was it?
I think I missed the 20 terabyte easy store for 250.
Dollars or less.
Okay, okay.
Can I ask you what you think, Alex, your success rate might be?
Zero percent.
Oh, man, but he's doing it anyways.
A couple of years ago, I was pretty confident about it, but I don't know the way things
are at the minute and, you know, chip shortages and all that kind of stuff.
I'm not so sure anymore, but, you know, can't blame a guy for trying.
No.
What about diminishing returns when it comes to hard drive?
Like, I don't know, squeezing that much data into tiny like it's a physical space.
Is there any?
Terabyte is a terabyte.
Yeah, but I guess what I'm saying is, is there any physical limitation to how far this can
go?
Oh, there's been a lot of innovations in that space for better for worse, for sure.
Yeah, they do all sorts of shenanigans to fit more bits and bytes and stuff onto a single
platter.
You know, that's way beyond what I think about generally on on the regular.
I think about how much space I can fit into a single drive slot.
And for for me, in my backup server, for example, I've just built a new backup server that has
five hot swap drive bays.
And so for me, I want to be able to cram as many terabytes into those five slots as I
can.
So trying to get the most terabyte per slot for me is the name of the game.
Yep, I totally agree.
Totally agree.
So Santa brought you a few gifts and some of them speak home kit.
And this is a topic we've danced around on the show because we appreciate not everyone
listening even cares about this kind of stuff.
You've been prepping for this episode for years.
Yeah, you know, honestly, before I gave home assistant a go, I gave home kit a go.
Like, I just tried to do everything with home kit because there's there's things I like
about it.
If you're not familiar, it's it's basically a software framework that Apple created that
exists in the iOS ecosystem and now the Mac.
And it allows for land based smart automation and device controls.
And it's because it's land based, it's really quick.
And because it's Apple, it's integrated into the OS and it's integrated into any of the
Siri speaker devices and anything that you can invoke Siri on, you can control a home
kit device with.
So that it kind of opens it up to a pretty wide ecosystem.
Even the Apple TV remote can be used to control home kit devices.
And of course, Apple builds home kit automations into their shortcuts app on the iPhone.
So you can build automations in your smart home using the shortcuts app, just if you
really live in that ecosystem.
But obviously, because it's Apple's ecosystem, it's a big sandbox, but it is absolutely a
sandbox and it does have walls.
So absolutely, I'm already bumping up against those walls on, you know, day 10 or whatever
of my iOS transition.
You know, I've been using Android for the best part of a decade and I figured I'd give
the iOS side a proper college try this year.
So I'm going to keep going with this phone.
I'm going to try and do a year.
We'll see how it goes.
I like it so far for the most part.
There's a couple of things, but coming back to home kit, what's really nice is how it's
it's seamless, right?
And when I pull down on my notification kind of control center thing up in the top right,
I get a button there called home, which has some favorites within it.
And one of the things that came up right away without any configuration at all was my LG
TV.
So I can just turn it on and off straight from my phone.
No need for a specific app.
Yeah, as you would expect, Apple is pretty good at what they do support.
It works pretty well.
And home kit itself seems to be fairly robust.
They've open sourced a lot of it.
It uses encryption that seems to be pretty strong.
And they're promising broader integration with matter as that develops.
They're one of the partners there.
So there's some things to like about it.
And I think as we get into this, I want to talk about how you can integrate it with Home
Assistant.
I don't know if you've tried that yet, Alex.
Not yet.
I mean, you know that I have dozens of home automation devices around this house already.
The only one that got picked up out of the box was my LG TV.
Okay, well, so I think let's let's start here.
I think where I want to take this is if you have family members listening that want some
home automation, they're not comfortable with Google or Amazon doing cloud control services.
And they're not interested in running something like Home Assistant or OpenHAB or a smart
things hub, but they have iOS devices, right?
This is a category of user that's perfect for this because they can really get a lot
done here at the studio.
Here at the studio, I actually use automations with HomeKit to turn on and off the lights
when I arrive and leave.
I don't actually do it directly on Home Assistant.
It's triggering Home Assistant devices, which we'll talk about.
But the automation is actually being triggered by shortcuts on my iPhone.
Also, I use that same setup to scan NFC tags to trigger automations.
So there's some nice things you can get without having to run a whole back end infrastructure.
So what happens when Chris's iPhone isn't there?
They have this concept of a hub, and it's either the Apple TV or an iPad that you're
willing to leave on the LAN, probably plugged in, or a HomePod, big or small.
They can all act as a HomeKit hub.
It becomes the primary orchestrator of your HomeKit network.
And if you're comfortable with this, it also will act as the proxy to iCloud.
So Apple establishes a secure connection between your iPhone and iCloud.
So when you leave the house, you can pull down that control center, and all your devices
still work, all their status information still works.
And when you trigger them, what's happening is a proxied request is being routed through
iCloud to the HomeKit hub, which in my case is a HomePod.
And then the HomePod is executing it locally on your LAN.
Okay, that's pretty legit.
That's similar to the Nebuchadnezzar service, right?
Right, and it's all encrypted between your HomeKit hub and your phone.
So Apple doesn't have the key to that.
So they do have the ability to exchange it.
So in theory, they could probably intercept it.
But as far as where the encryption keys are held, it's on your iPhone or your iOS device,
could be the watch, and the HomeKit hub.
So how do I add things that don't have HomeKit support to this ecosystem?
Can I do that?
I do it through Home Assistant, but we'll get there.
I wanted to mention HomeBridge.
HomeBridge is really the way to do this right now.
You mentioned LG televisions.
Before LG natively supported HomeKit, everyone was doing it with HomeBridge.
And you could run it like on a Raspberry Pi, and it essentially, it'll talk their proprietary
API, whatever protocol or service it might be.
The bridge will talk that, and then it will translate it to HomeKit.
So it'll just show up to your iPhone as a HomeKit device.
But it's really the bridge making that representation.
And so people were controlling LG televisions using this bridge, and LG got wind of it.
They thought, oh, well, maybe we should work with Apple and just build in the HomeKit support.
And that's how that actually started.
So I don't need the HomeBridge.
That's just nice to have.
Yeah, and you really don't if you're a Home Assistant user.
But again, if you want to go the route of controlling stuff without the whole infrastructure
of managing Home Assistant, you could use HomeKit to do 90% of what you need.
And then those random cheap devices that are quote unquote smart devices that are not HomeKit
compatible, you could run HomeBridge on your Mac or on a Raspberry Pi or on a Windows box
or a Linux box, and you could get that other 10%.
And it does a bunch of neat stuff that Apple's probably never going to really do, you know,
as any community builds on.
So there's some other advantages to HomeBridge.
It's not necessary unless you want to support non-HomeKit compatible devices.
OK, well, thanks for clearing that up.
The terminology here is so confusing, you know, HomeKit and HomeBridge and Home Assistant.
And it's kind of hard to keep all this stuff straight in your head when you're fresh to it.
Why don't we come back to that in just a second?
Linode.com slash SSH.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
And you go there to support the show.
That's how this works.
You go there, you support us, we keep on going.
And it's like the circle of podcasting.
It's an ecosystem, if you will.
You know, Linode is how we host everything.
It's also how I'll do like a quick R&D.
I want to try out an open source project or I have an idea for something that I want to
build.
I guess back in the day, I'd like get a VM on my local machine, but those always kind
of suck.
And not to mention it makes my machine busy and I have to have a certain machine that's
always capable of doing that.
When I flipped to using Linode for this kind of stuff, it changed like the kind of hardware
I'm buying now.
It like opened up a whole new door, man.
It's really it's really pretty great, even just for like just research and development.
And then, of course, you want to flip it to production.
It's the best place to do that, in my opinion.
They got 11 data centers around the world.
Their machines are screamers, just super fast.
Lots of distributions to choose from, including now images for Rocky Linux and Alma Linux
and CentOS Stream, if that's your thing.
And on top of all of it, a really great user experience.
Every system over there is a great value, great performance, and a nice experience setting
it up.
If you like to do it yourself and build it from the ground up or just deploy an image
with something ready to go, like say Next Cloud, maybe Discourse or GitLab, they've
got one click deployments for that.
And then I'm often finding that I'm taking advantage of their things like S3 compatible
object storage just by using their command line client or just not even having a machine
in between or just using a web interface.
They have all kinds of nice things like that, like a DNS manager that's going to let you
get done what you need.
Kubernetes support, if that's the way you go, just a lot to try.
And pricing is 30% to 50% cheaper than any other major cloud provider.
So go to linode.com slash SSH.
Get that $100 to really try it out.
Kick the tires, create an account, see what I'm talking about, and support the show.
linode.com slash SSH.
Alex was touching on a bunch of the terminology here, but Chris, it sounds like you've put
a bunch of links in the show notes.
Link Ninja, and I didn't overdo it.
I just tried to put the best of the best in there that helps you go through it all with
screenshots and stuff like that.
So if you're trying to set this up for yourself or like a family member, hopefully those will
work as a resource.
But Alex, I think what you really need to kind of wrap your head around is connecting
HomeKit and Home Assistant.
You've got such an established Home Assistant set up now that I don't really think it's
worth like developing and I guess cultivating your HomeKit devices because you're essentially
going to replace them with everything that's in Home Assistant when you connect it.
And so every device that is in Home Assistant will now show up to your iPhone as a HomeKit
device.
So you connect the devices to Home Assistant and then they show up on the iPhone.
And so that means non-HomeKit devices show up, obviously.
That also means things like your automations and your scripts and those types of things,
even camera feeds now also show up as HomeKit devices.
Camera feeds?
Yeah, it depends on the camera, of course, but yeah.
Oh, that's pretty cool.
So I've just right now installed the HomeKit integration and I now have about 20 different
devices asking me to scan a QR code and add them to the Home app.
Yeah, that's why I'm saying like it's kind of easier to just I had to just take a weekend
and because I was all in on HomeKit and I just had to move them all over if I recall,
although read on it because it's been so long since I've done it that they may have changed
the way it works now.
But then future devices now I just add them directly to Home Assistant.
All right.
So live listeners, I am going through the process of adding a camera into the Home app.
I have added the HomeKit integration.
Now I'm going through my notifications and adding by scanning a QR code in the Home app
on iOS, I'm adding an uncertified accessory and I get a great big warning telling me it's
not secure as I do it.
It's now connecting to the camera, which is in the kitchen.
What's that kitchen hub?
I don't even have a camera in the kitchen.
Oh, yeah, it'll try to guess.
Yeah, it will try to continue.
OK, blue iris, all cameras and camera that you know of.
I mean, let's be honest, Brett and I have both been in there.
There's a few cameras you don't know about.
Oh, it's my driveway, not my kitchen.
That's pretty cool.
Yeah.
Now what's nice is all your devices on your iCloud account and your family devices can
get access to those.
So Catherine could have all of those devices on her iPhone and my kids, like when they're
at the RV, have access to those devices on their iPad so they can read or be in bed at
night and they can just grab their iPad and turn the lighting off when they're done now,
which has been great because they just discovered that on their own.
And I didn't even have to tell them about it.
And they have also the tablets, but now they have it right there on the device that they
already have.
So why not have that additional integration?
Absolutely.
Yeah, that's pretty cool.
For me, answers some of the biggest questions I had actually, and I've deliberately left
all of this research to do it kind of live on air, live on the episode to make it more
exciting or something.
I don't know.
It answers some questions that I had about how to actually integrate this stuff.
But when we were talking the other day, you suggested that I might need an Apple TV.
And I know we touched on the iPad and things like that as like a home hub.
Why would I need that?
Is that for the kind of relay thing that you were mentioning?
Yeah, so the Apple TV can act as that hub.
And it will do a fine job because it's powered on all the time.
And you'll probably have it plugged into Ethernet.
So it's actually a really good device for that.
And they have a low power mode for it and everything like that.
And there's even some information when you go into the settings screen.
You can see like what its status is as far as your home GitHub goes.
And when you put it on your network, you plug it in.
If that's the first device you have, that's if you don't like, say, or you have a home
pod, it'll just sort of negotiate and it'll become the leader automatically.
You'll never know. You never really have to fuss.
It just does it.
Now, I've just tried to add my robot vacuum and it tried to pick that up as a camera for
some reason.
I think because of the map portion that the Xiaomi RoboVac thing that I have, Roborock
S5 is the one I have, and it's trying to use that map as a camera and it's just failing
and spinning.
And so this isn't perfect by any stretch, but I can certainly see why this would be
useful.
What I would do for some of those devices is just disable them in HomeKit because like
so say you have like my sensors that have six different sensor feeds.
Each one of those will show up as a device in HomeKit.
The humidity, like all of it just shows up as a device.
And some of it there isn't like a parallel.
There's nothing in the Apple world that equates to that kind of device.
And so I just disable those.
So basically, it's like a one time curation where I go through and I just I take a look
through and I just I take some stuff out.
There's a couple of different ways you can do that.
I don't remember the best way, but I found it online by looking and I just went through
one time and disabled everything that I didn't want in that HomeKit screen once.
And it's been great.
But yeah, there is edge cases like a device that has two camera feeds and stuff like that.
But I think Apple only expects devices to have one single camera and those kinds of
weird edge cases.
But when you're looking for like controlling smart devices or lights or kicking off automations
or scripts, it's great at that kind of stuff.
But it doesn't fully replace going to the Home Assistant web UI or app if you're even
a moderate power user.
I don't think it helps either.
My other primary HomeKit kind of ecosystem, the Philips Hue stuff, I recently replaced
that with a Combi to ZigBee bridge and ZigBee buttons everywhere.
So the couple of low hanging fruit that I had that would have worked now don't work
because I've kind of taken that control back in house.
But if you do connect HomeKit up all to Home Assistant, then those will show up.
Those will be devices as buttons you can use in HomeKit.
That's pretty cool.
Yeah.
And so then that means also your iPad gets that, your watch and any of your Siri tubes
get that.
And I think the Siri tubes actually make for kind of a nice home automation voice control.
It's a decent compromise.
I think it's not a perfect privacy story, but it's clearly better than Google and better
than Amazon.
Yeah, I'd be lying if I said that wasn't part of my motivation to switch for a bit.
And I like that their protocol is LAN based.
It's not API cloud based.
It's LAN based.
Now, the voice translation that Siri does is cloud based, although Apple does seem to
be moving to doing that on chip more and more.
They do that in the latest iPhone.
So it's conceivable future HomePods may do local transcription.
So that part still goes to the cloud.
But once Siri realizes what you're asking for, that happens on the LAN.
That happens immediately.
It's faster than some of the other ones because of that.
So another question I have for you, with the Nebuchadnezzar cloud service, I can connect
the Google and Amazon PUCs, tubes, whatever, voice assistants to react to various phrases.
And I can program those with Google, for example.
You do it in the Google Home app.
I can create key phrases that trigger certain scripts in Home Assistant, that kind of thing.
What's the equivalent in the HomeKit world?
That's a great question.
I'm really glad you asked because I should make this point.
You don't need Nebuchadnezzar cloud or any of that to have HomeKit and Siri work together
and have Siri trigger all the HomeKit stuff because it's doing it through the HomeKit
integration.
And Siri is executing those commands from the hub device or whatever Siri device requests
it directly to the Home Assistant using that integration.
So it bypasses the need for the complicated setup to get Google Assistant to work completely.
So also, I think it's just a great setup because you don't actually need the Nebuchadnezzar
cloud part.
You don't have to do all the cloud stuff if you don't want to.
So you just get the HomeKit integration set up.
And once you have all the HomeKit devices associated with Home Assistant, Siri just
works.
It'll work on your phone.
It'll work on your HomePod.
It'll work on your watch.
It'll work on your Apple TV.
It all just happens immediately.
Very nice.
Now, we're going to take a quick break from the Apple stuff.
We'll come back to that shortly.
I have a request to ask of our listenership.
My mother sent me a few videotapes for Christmas.
They are mini DV format tapes.
I rang a local video shop that does like digital or analog to digital conversions and they
wanted to charge me something like $20 a tape and I've got about 10 or 20 of these things
to digitize.
That seems a little bit expensive to me.
Also, what seems expensive is looking on eBay at these used camcorders.
They're like $100, $150 for a 10, 15 year old outdated proprietary format camcorder.
So I was wondering if there's anybody in the audience that has any suggestions about how
I could acquire a mini DV camcorder for cheaper than $150 or would be willing to pay for it.
Or would be willing to loan me one for a few weeks.
That would be kind of cool.
If you have any suggestions about how to actually go ahead and digitize the tapes properly,
please let us know at selfhosted at jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Tailscale.com slash self-hosted.
Go there to get a free personal account for up to 20 devices and you support the show.
Yeah, it's Tailscale.
It's a zero config VPN.
It installs on any device in minutes.
It manages your firewall rules for you and it works from anywhere.
Devices connect directly to each other using WireGuard's noise protocol encryption.
It builds a mesh network with the best VPN security in the business.
And it does it quickly and easily.
You'll create a secure network between your servers or your computers or your cloud devices.
And even when you're separated by firewall, subnets or the dreaded double NAT,
Tailscale just works.
I use Tailscale to keep all of my family's computers connected.
I provide them tech support.
I give them access to the secure resources behind my firewall.
And I have it running on everything from an arch 86 server to a Raspberry Pi with
openSUSE Tumbleweed and my iOS devices.
But for me, some of the best parts is just that every device on my network now has a stable IP.
No matter where I'm at, what Wi-Fi network I'm on or if I'm on cellular, it's always the same IP.
So my bookmarks that I've set for all my different dashboards and everything work every time.
And devices only connect after they sign through your existing identity provider.
So you could easily enforce multi-factor authentication
and you can deauthorize the machines you need to.
Maybe an employee has moved on or so forth.
And the fact that my Tailscale VPNs are always on and work with every OS that I use and has
a GUI based ACL editor, well, that's just like icing on the cake.
It's dead simple to use and it's fast.
That's the main reason I liked it.
And I ended up using it every single day.
So go try it for yourself for free.
Up to 20 machines and support the show at tailscale.com slash self-hosted.
That's tailscale.com slash self-hosted, one word.
Hey, Chris, I've got good news.
The NVIDIA Shield, our favorite video player has been updated to Android TV 11.
It has a stadia button now.
Wait, are you serious?
No, I mean, it's apparently called it 95 Google.
Yeah.
Oh, boy.
And they didn't get rid of the ads either.
I went and looked for a screenshot.
Still has the ads on the interface.
That kind of home launcher thing is all money, baby.
You know, I don't know what is going on, but I was trying to watch Deadwood and I have
the NVIDIA Shield in the bedroom and I don't watch TV back there a lot, but I was just for
whatever reason, we were watching TV back there that night and I hit play and I start
watching it and about five minutes in, it starts buffering.
I'm thinking, what the hell's going on here?
So I pull up the Raspberry Pi on, you know, SSH on my phone in my bed, like a lazy bastard,
and I pull up H-Top and sure enough, Plex is chugging away transcoding.
And so I go get the information in the playback and it says that the audio codec is unsupported.
And so it's transcoding the entire thing, even the video, because the audio codec, whatever
it is, I don't know, is unsupported on the Shield, but shockingly, it doesn't have to
transcode it for playback on the Apple TV.
So I can't imagine what codec the Apple TV has that the NVIDIA Shield doesn't, but I
kind of designed my Plex setup to never transcode because I'm doing it on a Pi that's doing
like a thousand other things.
So once it starts transcoding, all bets are off, you know, that TV watching session gets
wrecked.
I think the NVIDIA Shield, we did an episode on it a long time ago, but it is the single
longest running piece of hardware in my entire house, near enough.
I think I've got a UniFi access point and an NVIDIA Shield that all date from 2014,
15, something like that, and I haven't replaced or upgraded either of them.
It's like the Android LTS, right?
I think it helps that it's the same chip that they used in the Nintendo Switch, though.
Yeah, and a couple of NVIDIA devices they sold to OEMs too, so I'm sure they still have
engineers working on drivers and getting Linux running on there.
So I'm keeping mine for now, but I am tempted to replace it because of this codec issue,
although it really hasn't been a problem in the past.
So what would you replace it with, Mr. Apple iOS boy?
Well, what do you think?
I actually think the Apple TV is pretty decent, especially if you only buy these things every
four or five years, and they don't update it very often, so they last about five years.
The performance is better than even the NVIDIA Shield, and that really is saying something.
This isn't supposed to be an exhaustive comparison between the Apple TV and the NVIDIA Shield.
Perhaps we'll save that for a future episode.
But there's a couple of things before I buy one that make me worry a little bit about
doing so, potentially.
Number one is I'll list my use cases and then perhaps you can address them.
Are you talking about the Apple TV or the Shield?
So I'm talking about use cases I have on the Shield that I'm worried I won't be able to
replicate on the Apple TV.
Gotcha.
First of all is iPlayer.
So obviously living in the States and being British, we like to get real TV from the BBC.
And the way we do that is we have a WireGuard VPN that goes into one of my parents' houses
in England, and our IP address is a residential IP, so so far as the BBC are concerned, we
can just stream iPlayer as if we were in that building, and there's no problems there.
Whereas if you were trying to use several commercial VPNs or host something up on Linode
or DigitalOcean or AN other cloud provider, that IP block is kind of blacklisted by the
BBC.
We've also heard stories that they blacklist certain models of Rokus from listeners, so
you know you've got to be really careful about the devices you try and do this on apparently.
So that's number one is how am I going to get a WireGuard tunnel on an Apple TV back
to England?
And then the second one is something like Kodi.
So Kodi, as I'm sure most of our listeners know, is like the jack-of-all-trades, like
if it won't play in Kodi, it's a broken file type video player.
So for me, those two things, Plex and Jellyfin, I'm assuming, are both absolutely fine on
the Apple TV?
Yeah, those are fine.
Those are both really good questions.
I don't really have an answer for you on the WireGuard VPN other than solving that at the
network layer, which I could imagine a couple of tricky ways to do that, but no particularly
great ways to do that.
But I could imagine a routing situation where you're taking care of that at your firewall
or at some other device.
That's the only way I could think of it.
I think you'd probably want to go that route because it's not on the Apple TV.
It's not unheard of to have people route the Apple TV and install third-party apps.
That's been more common on the Apple TV than it is on other iOS devices, but I don't really
find that to be a good long-term way to go because eventually Apple releases an OS that
breaks it every time.
You used to be able to, to your second question, there was a period of time where you could
make an Apple TV a hell of a Kodi box.
It was awesome.
But time moved on, Apple updated the hardware and the OS requirements and that ability went
away.
And I have replaced Kodi with Infuse.
I've mentioned it before on the show.
I think Infuse is the best set top television style interface to video playback.
It's got the best codec support.
It supports Samba shares.
It supports SFTP.
It supports syncing to Plex and Jellyfin.
It supports DLNA.
It supports just attaching a disk and watching files locally.
It's got tons of codecs.
It has a super active development team.
And all respect to the Plex team, they're just focused on making a great video player.
They don't necessarily need to own the back end.
If you want to roll it with a file system, they'll go that way.
If you want to sync it to a Plex server or Jellyfin, they'll go that way.
And so Infuse for me, I even subscribed to the Pro version because I think it's absolutely
worth it.
And I took about a year off from Kodi.
And man, I tell you what, I used to be one of Kodi's biggest fans.
You can find really embarrassing old videos of me on YouTube where I'm really advocating
Kodi.
Actually, man, you can even find videos of me advocating XBMC before it became Kodi.
Like, it's the loyalty runs deep.
I think there are videos of you advocating how to run XBMC on a PlayStation 3 running
Linux.
Back in the day, do you remember DLP televisions, the ones with the reverse projectors?
Yeah, it was 720p, baby.
And we were happy.
God damn it.
Yeah, it was.
It was great.
But I took a year off from Kodi and then I went back to it last month.
And oh, my God, I realized it's just from another era.
Like, I think if you have momentum with it, it's fantastic.
But if you take a year off and then come back to it, we don't design software this way anymore.
And it does all this crazy stuff and it's a lot.
And Infuse, it seems simple at first, it's deceptively simple.
But as you begin to use it, you realize it's very powerful.
And it has a fantastic video playback engine too, which is job one here.
And it's great at jumping around, the just only downside, but if you're a Jellyfin user,
you're used to this.
But if you're a Plex user, I think the only downside is that it doesn't have skip intro,
which I love, but they do not yet support skip intro.
I think it's on the roadmap.
It does have a feature that Plex needs to have, and that is it blurs spoilers.
So when you go into a show and you look at a season, it blurs the episodes you haven't
watched yet, and I can't tell you how great that is.
Whilst you were talking just then, I've actually gone ahead and installed it on the Mac.
I'm recording this on and connected up my Plex library within, what, two minutes?
Yeah, pretty, pretty impressive.
It's doing something now where it's processing my files or something like that.
But I've got a 4K HEVC 10-bit test file that I know is of a very, very high codec, and
it just played instantly on my Mac.
So if you turn on the iCloud sync settings, you can then go install it on your Apple TV,
and all of those directories and stuff will be there on the Apple TV immediately.
It may have to do some scanning, but it's nice like that.
And the thing about the Apple TV is the Apple processors have been really good CPUs for,
what, five years now?
And so even though it doesn't have the latest processor, it's still just about better than
anything else that's shipping in any other set-top box, and that includes power use.
It's a low-power device, too, so it takes less power when I'm running on solar than
the Shield does, which, you know, not a big difference with these devices, but I'll take
every little gain I can get.
Marginal gains, Chris?
Marginal gains?
Marginal gains matter in the solar business.
Yeah, they do.
Well, whilst we're on the topic of media servers, I know we talked about Jellyfin a couple of
episodes ago, mentioned it on LUP as well, I think.
And Bryn, I know you've been building a Jellyfin box for your family.
How's that been going?
Yeah, I finally dove in.
I think I ran out of excuses to try Docker, try my hand at Docker, and Jellyfin was a
nice excuse to do that.
I have to say, I think it's the beginning of a new era for me, which is very exciting.
I mean, you guys are old-hand at this, but Jellyfin itself, I think I've been really
impressed.
It's the first time I really tried to run a centralized media solution.
And in my situation, my brother's in one home and about 90 steps away, I'm in another cabin
and we kind of watch movies back and forth a lot.
But we share network, which is kind of neat.
So I'm able to kind of optimize this thing while they're sitting there watching TV, which
is kind of fun.
But it just opened up a whole new world of possibility for me.
I have always wanted to be able to, I don't know, sit at the dining room table and be
able to put on my favorite album or change to, oh, I feel like jazz now.
And I can see Jellyfin being able to do that because you can sort of tell it to play the
music on a different device.
And these are maybe features that I should have had in my life a long time ago.
Perhaps you two are just laughing at me because I'm late to the game here.
But it sounds and feels really transformative, really.
Well, I'll tell you, I'm curious because I know that we've shared Plex servers with
you for some time now.
So you're pretty well familiar with Plex and how it feels and how it operates in its feature
sets.
How does it feel as a longtime user of Plex switching over to Jellyfin?
Yeah, I think I'm looking at it from a bit of a different perspective now because I'm
looking at it from a bit of a different perspective now because now I'm kind of administering
Jellyfin, which I've never done with Plex.
But as a pure user, and I will say I have much more experience with Plex in that regard,
it doesn't seem quite as polished.
But I could see that it's starting to get there, like occasionally, I mean, I'm now
using the Jellyfin app on my Android phone to browse the interface and then sort of send
that to the TV, right?
So I'm doing things I never did with Plex.
But occasionally, that connection just kind of drops down, like the TV portion of it will
just kind of give a black screen and the interface just goes away.
So I can definitely see some glitches that I've pretty much never experienced with Plex,
I'll say.
Well, inevitably, this is what usually leads someone to just get a set top box that connects
to their TV and you just have a Plex client or a Jellyfin client on that device.
And that's why Alex and I think about this a lot because you just want that to be a really
nice experience.
When you're sitting down, like we were sitting down to watch a movie, and we were all hyped.
It'd been a couple of nights we've been talking about it.
We finally sat down to watch the movie, I hit play, and I had a file error.
And I was able to resolve it quickly.
I figured out what was wrong pretty quick, probably took us about five minutes.
But that is it's so like disruptive because you got you got a whole night going.
It kills the momentum of the entire night for a good five minutes.
And that's a best case scenario.
You know, that's a best case scenario, five minutes, I think it's by far the time of day
you want to least be doing this kind of troubleshooting, right?
That's how I ultimately ended up going with just Apple TV and infuse.
But I like that you're going down this route.
I'm actually kind of more excited that you're playing with Docker.
I think that's going to be really great, too, because that's going to open you up to a world
of trying all kinds of apps.
And those skills will work on any Linux box.
If it's a, you know, laptop, a server, or, you know, a VPS machine, it's the same commands
and tools to install software on all of them.
That sounds really nice.
And I think it's also going to be a huge paradigm shift.
You've both talked about how the day you kind of wrapped your head around Docker, your whole
idea of how to run computers changed.
And I'm really just starting that journey.
For me, it was, as an old IT guy that was doing this for, you know, for years before
we even had anything like containers, I mean, FreeBSD had jails.
But for me, it was finally a real solution to separate my application from my data.
That had always been something that I thought the lines blurred too much when I would set
up a home server.
And with containers, and Docker, I think, is the most widely used container technology.
With containers, I finally had a really solid, reproducible way where I could blow away the
application.
I could completely destroy the container, pull down a fresh one.
If the config was all the same in my Docker Compose, it just reconnects everything.
It starts right back up.
And that was the day I was like, oh, man, this means I can finally move an application
and its data around.
I can pick all the data up off of one server, drop it on a new server, take that Docker
Compose file, pull down the image, and it reconnects like it's always been running on
that box.
It just fires right up.
And it makes disaster recovery such a thing of beauty.
And it makes actually being able to move off of a box so much easier.
So when you need to grow and expand down the road, it's so much simpler.
You know, I was giving this also as a gift to my brother's wife because she loves watching
videos and stuff.
And we don't have the greatest internet connection, as you know.
And so I've been ripping all of her favorite DVDs.
She has just boxes of them.
And so this was a nice gift to give.
But the morning, Christmas morning, I thought, OK, I had stayed up late, you know, putting
a bunch of stuff on there, make sure everything works.
And that morning, for whatever reason, the interface on Jellyfin just stopped working.
I couldn't access it.
I couldn't do anything.
And I thought, oh, this is hard sinking.
And I think Christmas morning is maybe not the time to be troubleshooting.
But what I ended up doing was just, OK, I'm going to start from scratch.
It wasn't that hard to kind of build this thing.
So I'm just going to delete the container and start over again.
And I had that aha moment that you just described, which was brought the container up.
And then everything was identical to the way I had left it, except it was now working.
And that was the lightbulb moment where I was like, oh, not only have I rescued my Christmas
gift, but this is amazing.
And it just then made me realize, OK, I've got to do this everywhere.
There's no way that I don't want to be playing much, much more with this.
I do have a few questions for each of you, though.
I was constantly wanting to use the tools that I've had for many years to try to interact
somehow with, like for troubleshooting, I was like, OK, this thing's not working anymore.
How do I troubleshoot this thing?
And I know it's a whole world, but any like beginner tips on how to interact with these
containers and how to make them easy, I guess?
Right.
I have a web page over at PerfectMediaServer.com, of course, which I'll put a link to in the
show notes, which will hopefully take you through all of the basics of my ethos on why
you should be thinking about using containers.
Largely it's a regurgitation of what Brent just said.
But then throughout the rest of the page, it talks about things like Docker Compose,
where you get your containers from and why and how do you pick one over another and what
about Podman and all those kinds of things.
So if you have a bunch of questions, I would direct you to that page.
I will just say quickly, just to help you get your head around it, like you got to realize
that it's own contained environment.
So if you want to execute a command in there or something like that, you have to use the
Docker command line tools to execute the command inside that container.
The other thing that's kind of nice about Docker Compose, well, there's a lot of ways
to do this, but I think Docker Compose is probably the best way for a new beginner,
is when you launch an app with Docker Compose, you can do Docker Compose up.
And if you don't tell it to otherwise, it'll give you the output on the screen.
And you can sit there and watch the log output.
Oh, that actually sounds really interesting.
Yeah, it's logs.
Really, the key to your answer is you want logs.
So however you have it, whatever tool you're using, you just want to be able to get to
the logs.
That's really what I wanted.
And I had no idea how to get to it.
So I just kind of nuked the whole thing.
And yet, that gave me exactly what I was looking for.
So I don't think that'll be the case every time.
But in this case, it worked nicely.
There is an alias that I use, which I created a long, long time ago called detail, literally
detail slammed together as one word.
And for me, what that does is it prints out the last 50 lines, it tails the last 50 lines
of a container's standard output.
So that's nice.
One thing you'll run into with containers is that not every app logs the standard out
by default.
And so sometimes, you'll look at the logs for that container, and you won't see anything
in the logs.
So you might need to fill that particular application, enable things like debug or error
logging or higher modes, sorry, than error logging, you know, more than warning or info
at those kinds of things.
You need to turn it up to the highest chattiness that it has in the logs.
Some containers that will drive your potty, other containers, it's the bare minimum.
Traffic's a good example of where they don't put enough stuff in the logs that they should.
We've mentioned it on the show before, but as a tool called Dozzle, which will put your
containers logs into a browser, and then you can search through the containers running
on a specific box and look at the logs in a browser, if you want to do it that way as
well.
Well, before we go, I should mention we're doing a meetup at the end of January here
at the studio.
January 30th, it's a Sunday, we'll do a live recording of Linux Unplugged.
And then it's a Hangin' Chow.
I have a birthday around there, so it's kind of a half birthday celebration, but I'm not
making a big deal about that, because I don't want people to think it's a birthday thing.
I did buy some bubbly for you that I hid in the fridge, so there'll have to be a birthday
pop of the cork on that one.
Meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
If you're in the Pacific Northwest or you want to fly in on your private jet, we do
have an airport nearby, you can go there.
Meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting for that.
Also thank you to our subscribers, selfhosted.show slash SRE.
You get some bonus content, you get a post show, and it's ad-free, so thank you for supporting
us and we do have the new network membership.
Jupiter.party, if you want to support, for about the cost of two shows, you want to support
the whole network, you get all the shows.
Plus you get Linux Action News ad-free, it's the only way to do that at Jupiter.party.
I'm really sorry Chris, but I won't be able to fly in on my private jet for your birthday
party.
That's alright, I understand.
We should really fly to you, I mean you're the one with the newborn, and the weather.
It's really our fault.
I do.
You know, you're up in the frozen tundra, up in the north, it's vaguely warm down here
at the moment.
Yeah, it's rough here in Seattle, we're known for our rough winters, that's for sure.
We'd love to get your feedback on content ideas, things we talked about today, great
apps that you're running on your network, something you just self-hosted recently, feedback
on the show, or sponsors.
All of it.
That's selfhosted.show.com.
And thanks for listening everybody, that was selfhosted.show slash 62.