Well, welcome into episode 68 of self-hosted everybody. This is a big episode today. We've got
Chris with me in person sitting right here. I get, I get the desk too. I know I can look into the
whites of your eyes today. That's very strange. You've got a, if anybody has seen, is it Lewis
Rossman, right? You look, you just need the cat. You look exactly like Lewis Rossman right now in
that a huge lounge chair with the microphone. I don't have the muscles and I'm a little bit,
the anger's down a little bit. Yeah. You're not quite as am.
I'd also like to welcome in today, Wes Payne.
Hello, hello. It's good to be back.
Hey Wes, how was the trip in? You got here just a little bit ago.
It was a little longer, a few extra flights that I didn't expect, but it was well, well worth it.
50% more flights if I, if I understand it right.
Unfortunately so.
Yeah. So these two fine gentlemen are joining me today at my house for the
big Jupiter broadcasting East coast meetup, which is on Saturday and looking like it's going to be
a hell of a party because not only do we have probably over a hundred people showing up,
but there's some town event going on too. So it's going to be, I mean,
we're going to, this is going to be one of those where we have stories for a while.
As this episode as the meetup will be the day after. So, you know, as on Friday,
so the meetups on the Saturday, those, I think this, this town event is like an Easter,
like spring fling thing. It's going to be food trucks and all sorts of crazy stuff. So
if you're in the rally area or even if you're not stopped by, say hi, it'd been amazing to see you.
It was nice for us though. So we got in a couple of days early so we could, you know, hang out and
pre-show a little bit as we do and do some barbecue and do some talking and catching up.
So Brent is actually in route right now too, as we record just, you know, and it's great to see
your new place. Well, it's probably not as new to you anymore, but it's new to all of us.
Oh yes. And it's like the size of a bed and breakfast, like, like it's an estate. So,
so it can fit all of us easily. I don't want people thinking I live in some McMansion,
like it's a pretty nice house, but it's just below McMansion. It's not ridiculous. It's not
ludicrous. We're comfortable. And you know what? It actually seems pretty reasonable when all of
us are in town. Right. Exactly. I mean, hosting people, because, you know, one of the reasons
we bought this place was we host family from England for three, four, five weeks at a time.
And when you've got four or five people in a house, like you don't want to be all on top of
each other for that long. So, and a baby and a baby now, of course. Yeah. I've got to have room
for the drums. Right. Of course the drums, the printer, the workshop, right. You know what I
wanted? Like, of course, you know, when somebody arrives, like, you know, they want the tour,
right. But I wanted, I wanted the tech tour when I arrived. I feel like we're in a real
life episode of MTV cribs today. Right. It's self-hosted cribs. Um, and so we thought we
should start with the very basics, like how Alex is getting power into his house, because
you got a pretty impressive solar setup. Oh yeah. There you go.
Oh, interesting. Did they put like a netting along the bottoms for, to keep out critter guard? Yeah.
Okay. So there you go. That's a kilowatt hours, eight kilowatt array.
So they're probably getting their main sun starting right about now.
In the summer, we get perfect sun from about 10 a.m. to about 3 p.m. Oh, nice. And then these guys
get in the way slowly. Yeah. You can look on the monitoring app for solar edge. Yeah. And it,
you can see the shadow moving across the roof. Like it does per panel breakdown.
Yeah. So that's the panels. Yeah. And then they brought, they brought the cables in through the
attic and down, down through the back. So that, that was the room we were sat in. That was the
bonus room. So they brought the power sort of through this metal conduit out the back and
through the attic of the, of the house. So you can see the metal conduit coming down the side of the
drain pipe there and then into this solar edge inverter thingy that's here. That's it. Really?
There's a, it's really not that complicated until I suppose if you were to put a battery wall in
there, it would get more complicated. It would not probably go around here. This, this thing is a
wifi bridge. I used to have a Zigbee bridge, but it kept dropping out for some reason. And the
repeater was in the bonus room just up there. But this one now is in into the basement, into the
server area. And it's just based on just 2.4 gig wifi. It has its own SSID, just for some reason
talks, talks that way. And then I plug in an ethernet cable into their little solar edge,
little white box receiver thing. And then it connects out through to the internet that way.
And then they have a web portal for all the deets. And that's how they can monitor.
Yeah. Wow. And they have an app of course. Do they have an API? That's the question.
Yes. That's how Home Assistant gets it. Oh yeah, that's, that's great. Yeah.
I mean, I was actually looking at a Kickstarter the other day where they do smart, uh, breaker
panels and each breaker has the smarts built into it to read. Why are we not having this already?
There's also a group that'll analyze just your house power using machine learning and try to
give a best guess of what appliances are running and then assign the individual usage to those.
And just by looking at the load, the average load. Yeah. How do you tell between, well,
I was going to say a fridge and a server. Or how do you tell between a hairdryer and a toaster?
I don't know, but maybe they have ways. Subtle signs in the data they think they've had. Yeah.
Well, great. Thank you for showing this to us. I'm just waiting for that episode where we get
connected and you're like, okay, I'm ready to build the battery wall. I do want to do that.
And as you've seen, I think we could cuss. I know you're going to do some fancy and nice,
but I'm telling you, we could DIY that thing. We could. Yeah. I mean, as you've seen, just
before we were going to record, we get some lightning and some pretty big storms blow through
here. And sometimes they knock down trees and the power goes out for four or five hours,
just on a random Tuesday. And that can be quite annoying. So there's two options for me for a
power wall. Number one is to build a dedicated like UPS for my house, which sounds awesome.
Cause I mean, it just in this room, I think I have four UPS is just to make sure everything
stays on during those little Brown. I mean, what have I probably counted? Yeah. At least have I
counted six UPS? Well, there's one for my desktop right there. There's another one over there for
like my 3d printer. And then there's another one over there for all my guitar amp equipment and
stuff. And there's stuff where the servers are, taco stuff. And some of the other stuff in that
closet, the backup closet. Yeah. We didn't get to in a minute. Uh, there's another one in,
it's ridiculous. Screw the whole house. Vacuum. Yeah. Whole house. UPS. That sounds great.
I just got fed up of Brown outs. Yeah. I guess the goal should be is like,
as these UPSs get to the point where the batteries are aging out, that's when it's time to do the
power wall, right? That's what you do the power wall. Yeah, true. True enough. Yeah. So we also
got to see the server basement. I've been wanting to see this set up for a while.
Nice. I'm loving it. So let's walk us through what we got here. We've got a nice wood built rack.
I mean, maybe not as nice as the one brand build. Maybe, maybe it is. That's custom order. Maybe,
maybe it isn't. Can't say. Well, tell me what you think we've got. Well, I'm seeing a, I'm seeing,
seeing a couple of APC UPSs. I'm seeing, uh, your carrier's modem or whatever it is over there.
Just in modem mode. Of course. We've got this big rack here. That's a system with how many disks?
I forget. I know you've told me, but I forget. Uh, and then what is this guy down here? This
little bitty machine that's open sense. Oh, okay. That's the firewall. I've seen a couple of switches
there. Yeah. You've got a POE switch. So with eight ports for POE running two cameras at least
and two acts, maybe three access points off that guy. Okay. So there's room for future expansion
on that. I think I've only used five out of the eight ports. So I do plan on running another couple
of cameras. Oh, temperature sensor here. Yeah. So this isn't ESP 8266 hooked up to a DHT
22 temperature sensor. So it does temperature and humidity down here. I put it sort of behind the
server. Now I think about it. Maybe I should put it away from the server. So it doesn't, you know,
so the heat from the fans at the back doesn't affect the readings too much, but seeing a new
AO tag Z stick and I see it's plugged into the back of the machine there. Is that what I'm seeing?
Maybe actually that one's in a drawer upstairs. I ditched the Z wave stuff experiences with it.
Yeah. And I went the Zigbee route and got the Conbee Zigbee USB. Nice. Is that what I'm seeing
plugged in there? Yeah. There's a Conbee two in there as well as connections to the UPS. So this
must be the Proxmox box then. Yeah, that's it. That's the one that does everything. And so then
home assistance around on this. Home assistance on there. That's got the i5 8500 in there. It's
the ASRock mini ITX, no, a micro ATX board that I put in there last autumn.
What's this? 10 or 12 disks. Why does it say disk failed? I'm just kidding. He had me.
He had me. And then I've got this cool like little KVM switch. I don't know if it's...
Oh yeah. Great. Actually connected up because this is... Oh, there you go. H-top up on the screen.
So I've been running H-top for the last eight years maybe. And it does the keyboard too,
which is nice. That's super handy. So there you go. Yeah. Love this. And it just runs.
And it's not loud at all, really. Well, not really, but I do have the fans turned up because
it's in the basement. Yeah, why not? I don't care about it. You know, just keep the airflow going
through. And I figure actually in the basement environment, having a little bit of air movement
is probably a good thing. Yeah, probably a little bit of a dehumidifier. It's probably doing me a
solid. Nice. There it is. The famous setup. I do have some future projects for myself and Brent
because Brent's staying with me for the next week or two after you guys leave. So we're going to
rewire quite a lot of what's down there. And you redo all the ethernet into a patch panel,
wall mount a lot of the switches that are down there, probably run a couple more cameras,
pull some more ethernet. That's always easier with two people.
Yeah. And then the other thing we got a little peek at because Alex's place is so big, he can
have a closet that's basically like an offsite backup. I did think about this. So the server is
at one end of the house, the right hand end. And then the room we're in to record is my bonus room
above the garage, which is the left hand end of the house. As I think about it, maybe we should
call these wings. Yeah. So if there's going to be like a pipe bust or something like that. Well,
that's it. That's the insurance, isn't it? You know, if a tornado was to blow through or a
hurricane was to blow through and knock the house down, I am out of luck with both of these boxes
in the building. Maybe. I mean, you could still see one part of the structure could remain standing
maybe. And you're having them on opposite sides. So yeah, maybe. Or when the worst event happens,
you know, whichever side you're closer to, you can try to grab the box on your way out of the house.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Grab the baby in one hand, the server in the other. Come on wife,
you can carry yourself. Someone grab the dog. I'm pretty sure he can carry himself too.
So this is a bit of a like storage for like boxes and gear. And then I see some backup power
supplies. I see some switch gear. I see a patch panel. Yeah. Printer two switches. What is this
guy over here? Is this an HD tuner? HD hard run. Yeah. Are you getting, are you pulling it over
the air? Yeah. And it works in here like that? Yeah. I mean, it's just pointed towards the
antenna. Painting a picture for the listener. I just have an over the air kind of flat wall antenna
just resting dangling on a shelf pointed at the ceiling. And it just works well enough. And to be
honest with you, the only time I use over the air tuner is when we've got some weather coming through
and I want to watch the weather reports. Yeah. Yep. Me too. So you call this the backup closet?
Because down in the bottom right hand corner over there, there's a little Lian Li Q25B case with
three hard drives in it. And just above it is the... Oh, this is just a silent little machine
running here. That's the HP290 slim I keep talking about that runs my Blue Iris. I wouldn't even know
it was on. Nope. I can feel just a tiny bit of airflow, but that's it. The backup server's off.
I turn that on once a week, does its thing and then it turns off. I have a sense too that we
haven't even seen everything. Like I think as we'll be here for the next few days, you'll be
like, oh right, I wanted to show you this too. I do hope so. Yeah. Yeah. That's always how it goes.
Well, I think we're only just beginning to get a sense of all the automations at play, right? We've
sort of scrapped the surface, the big ticket items that we've, you know, we've heard about on the
show that we've been looking forward to, but you know, you see Alex over there, comfying his chair
and you can tell he's controlling pretty much everything. Yeah. Just before we were going to
record, Chris was like, can you turn off the AC? It's a bit noisy. And he went to walk over to do,
I was like, dude, sit down. Like an animal. I know. I know. And it was funny because
I've also noticed like, you know, there's little temperature sensors throughout.
There's some buttons here and there. What do you think of them? These are the little, uh,
Xiaomi Bluetooth low energy ones. Yeah. I like that they have the actual temperature display
on there and just on the wall behind you, uh, underneath the little red hat Bluetooth speaker,
there's a little ESP 32 3d printed with the yellow cable going into it. And that is what
he's talking on Bluetooth low energy to all these different temperature centers throughout this, uh,
half of the building. And then down the other end, I've got another one, which talks to the ones
down that end. And then they all feed through ESP home into home assistant. Nice.
Yes. Uh, also everything has sort of been augmented with, uh, you could see where Alex
has seen a problem and like, Oh, I can 3d print that solution. So definitely desk parts have been
augmented. Uh, things mounted to the wall have been augmented with a 3d print. Uh, there's just
little bits of 3d printing solutions here and there. You obviously are like, you see a problem
and you're like, Oh, I'm going to, I'm going to print the fix to that. Well, I didn't spend money
on a 3d printer to buy stuff. It's a replicator. Dang it. So I want you to turn around. I've given
you a hard time about raspberry pies in the past. There was a drawer marked to do. Yeah. And in that
drawer, I want you to kind of pie shame. These are all the projects I have in progress or to do.
Oh, they're each in a case too. Yeah. I don't know how you managed to come up with an idea
more haunting than a to do list, but a to do chore of physical objects. This is, this is going to be
about where I'm at. Do you like this? You've got four pies within arm's reach. Cause there's one
over here to a Cody box and there's one attached to the 3d printer as well. So there's five pies
within arm's reach of me, just within arm's reach of me and I'm using one of them. I like this case.
These got some good cases here. Of course you've got the flirt one, which I love too.
Got the flirt case. We've got the geek worm aluminum case. The geek worm one is particularly
good for the 3d printer because you take one half off and 3d print a specific bracket and
then screw the two together. And you've got some heat dissipation for the PI four and one half.
And then the custom bracket attaches to the 3d printer and it's good to go.
You got, you can't give me a hard time anymore. You've been outed now. I know.
I know. The thing is though, I buy stuff like, um, home automation gear. And then I think,
Oh, I'll, I'll install that later. And then don't open the second drawer on the right there
and look at all the Shelly gear. I've got shamefully, I've bought, I'm just haven't
got around to install. I have a, I have a basket full of that stuff right now, but I'll get to it.
One of these days, you know what? And I'm not even kidding in that basket are some wise cameras
who I've got to deploy. And that got sent into the show a couple of times this week. Wise took
it over the backend about security and people wrote in wanting to know what we thought about it,
including Eric Johnston. He wrote in and said, Hey guys, you know, you've talked about the ways
cameras quite a bit. They're actually wise, but you're talking about the wise cameras quite a bit.
And I thought you'd be interested to know this. Gizmodo wrote an article and the headline is
you should probably stop using your wise camera right now. The verge, the verge wrote a headline
that said, I'm done with wise. And I think the gist of what happened, I was traveling, but I
think the gist of what happened is it turns out, it turns out there's a pretty nasty vulnerability
in the V1 camera. They no longer sell. They had to be on your land first, but if they got on your
land and got some information off of your wise camera, which supposedly they could do if they
just had land access, then later on they could access your camera and including information
about your camera even remotely. So like Wes comes, comes to my house, gets onto my wise cameras,
then he's peeping on me from remote from then on out. I did make you guys a dedicated guest
network. That explains it. Just to be safe. So I mean, some of this is hyperbole, right? Some of
this is just journalism, clickbait stuff. You know, you should stop using your wise cameras
immediately. Okay, fine. Yes. I understand why they write that headline, but since the original
publication of the article, uh, wise themselves have released a response, you know, stating like
Chris said, um, we'd like to let our users know that these vulnerabilities required some form of
local network access. And that does really rule out most attack vectors. I mean, unless you have
a really crappy wifi password or you just leave an ethernet cable hanging out your mailbox by the
street. I mean, most people aren't going to get to your, uh, to your local network. And so for me,
yeah, fine. The V1s were vulnerable for a while, but what really actually bothers me is how wise
is a company handled this vulnerability. Yeah. That's the problem, right? Is they just essentially
swooped under the rug and discontinued the model. And I guess maybe the logic was is we're not
making any more of them. Yeah, I suppose so. We're not obligated to do anything better than just say,
well, we're not telling you to keep using them. Yeah. And if you updated the version two or
version three, you didn't have this problem. So they figured, well, I really got away from that
problem. But the reality is people have these deployed, right? Doctors offices, maybe even,
who knows, it is a little worse than that. So the V1, two and three were all vulnerable,
but they silently released an update a few months ago for the V2 and three only. So they've left the
V1s hung out to dry. Yeah. Yeah. Just leaves a bad taste in the mouth. Yeah. And then you combine
that with bad communication. This could be really bad for wise because wise has aspirations to become
the IOT of everything vendor from internet scales to door locks to everything. In fact,
if you open up the wise app now, they have a shop section in there. They're selling lights. They're
selling every single kind of IOT Wi-Fi connected device you can think of. They're selling it now.
And you have to have a brand that's trusted in order to do that. And if you don't have a trusted
brand, you're dead in the water. I agree completely. I'm a bit surprised by Bitdefender,
who are the security research company who uncovered this floor. They sat on it for nearly
three years before telling us about it. So, uh, not only is there the original vulnerability
that, you know, we're talking about here, there were other previously undisclosed vulnerabilities
that have been, uh, bypassing the authentication as well as allowing remote code execution,
uh, reported in both 2019 and 2020. That's when they were patched. Sorry. But, uh, I mean,
I just feel like wise has to step their game up. This isn't good enough.
You know, when they discontinued the V1, they issued a vague, like, uh,
Hey, this has some enhanced security risks. So you probably don't want to use it anymore.
So knowing what we know about this, that you have to be on the land initially to exploit it.
And then when they discontinued the product, they said, Hey, by the way,
you should probably stop using it. I think their exact wording, I found it at one point,
the company issued a warning during the V1 retirement saying, quote, it has an increased
risk of attack increased risk because you do have to be on the land because it has to be this
particular one that they're not patching. And because it is a retired product,
where is the line here? I agree with the V2 and V3. They, there should have been patch notes.
The only reason that they're end of life thing, the product is because it says here in their blog
post, they can't support the necessary fixes in that product. And so for me, if it was only being
end of life as a consequence of that gesture, goodwill, give us 25% off a V2 or V3 camera
or something, you know, something. Yeah. Cause you know, they rolled the dice to make a $25
camera. They had to put really cheap parts in there. And that's why some of their AI stuff
until the V3, honestly, guys, the wise cams are not good until the V3. The V3 is a really
good camera for the price for 35 bucks or whatever, but V1 and two, they were rough.
We've been using the V3 as our baby monitor. Yeah. It's the night vision on that thing is,
is incredible. It is. I I'm, I'm gone right now. And half of, half of the way I'm monitoring the
RV is with wise V3s. Now for me, five minutes, he pulls out his fire and he's like, Oh, look,
there's Levi. I got to check on the dog. It's your own form of doom scrolling. It is. But for me,
and I think maybe for a lot of the people in our audience, when I deploy something like this,
a $25 or a $35 camera, I go in assuming it's going to be monetized in some other way that I
don't agree with. And so I, I blocked DNS requests from the camera. So the cameras can't properly
talk to the internet. I have to be on my land in order to use the cameras. And that's just
always the way I've, so they don't talk to, and that means they don't get firmware updates either.
I have actually restored the DNS access and done the firmware thing once, but then that's also
caused problems. So it's not ideal. And that's why I've kind of backed off. If people have noticed
on the show, I don't really talk about them as much anymore because it is a bit of a compromise
product, but for the price and for the functionality and for the ability to integrate it with home
assistant, using things like wise bridge, it's a compromise I'm willing to make still. And I'm not
going to stop using my wise cams because of this, but I'd already built kind of for this scenario.
Does it change any of your thoughts on adopting additional wise cams? You know, is this still a
reasonable trade off? Cause that seemed kind of how they got on the scene, right? Like, look,
it's not perfect, but it's cheap, it's workable, and it gets you started instead of maybe a,
you know, hundreds of dollar fancy IP camera. Yeah. I'm always on the fence. It's like the
wise, the great thing about the wise cams, USB powered Wi-Fi, they don't even have to be
wired. They can go outdoors. You can get them to work with home assistant with pretty much
minimal effort and you don't have to run wires or anything like that, right? It's just, those things
are so great, but they're also just not quite the right tool for the job. They're not quite the
right ones to run 24 seven, do 4k video. You really want it wired. You want POE and that kind
of stuff in my opinion. So that's always the, that's always the balance I'm trying to make.
Particularly as they're moving into the wider smart home ecosystem, like you were saying,
they have ambitions to, I think they make a doorbell now they make, probably making a 3d
printer before we know it. So I think that the long-term outlook for me and wise is, they're
just a cheap, convenient solution to non-essential problems. You know, if the webcam we're using for
as a baby monitor broke, I'd probably just buy another one because they're so cheap compared to
a dedicated baby monitor. Um, and we have the flexibility of pulling up the app anywhere on any
device and you know, they're very flexible, very cheap, but you do pay a price for that.
And sometimes they have a great sale. They have great sales sometimes too. I think it does say a
lot, you know, we just talking about all the things you have automated in your home, but that
flexibility really is, you know, you know, you could set all that up if you wanted to, but just,
just the point is that sometimes it's really nice not to have to Linode.com slash SSH. Go there to
get $100 in 60 day credit. And you go there to support the show. Go say hello to Linode and
support the show. Linode.com slash SSH is where we're running everything. And just before we left,
I wanted the matrix server to really hum like a top. We upgraded that thing to 96 gigs of RAM
and 48 epic CPU cores on Linode and two terabytes of SSD storage. We're cooking with gas now.
Is that enough to run matrix? Barely, barely, barely. But you know, what was great is
we've just slowly increased the size of that Linode. We started at, I mean, we might've started
at a $5 Linode cause it was just an experiment. And then we just kind of turned it up as time has
gone on. And this time we really cranked it up to 11, but you know what else I was thinking?
I wonder if there'd be a way to use Wisebridge on Linode to have like a remote Wisebridge,
like a connect, maybe like some, like a VPN back to my land. There's so many things you can
experiment because they have great price plans for big enterprise operations. If you're out there,
or for just, you know, individuals, they'll want to do something and experiment their
pricing's 30 to 50% less than the big hyperscalers out there. They have these crazy UIs. They've got
a great API. If that's the route you like to go, they've got a really nice command line tool. So
one of the things I've done is I just have a tab in my dropdown terminal. I'm almost,
I have like almost all of the Linode command line client commands that I use in my history on that
tab. I can throw stuff up on object storage in no time. And the great thing is if you ever run into
any trouble, have any problems getting something set up, Linode comes with amazing 24 seven
customer support by phone or by ticket. And they don't do that thing where they like escalate and
escalate and escalate. They stick with you. Each person is trained and ready to go.
They've got the best support. And I hear that over and over again from the self-hosted community.
That stuff matters. And what I love about Linode is they've built this in a way that really is fast.
40 gigabit connections, SSDs, MVME PCIe storage, AMD epic processors. They are their own ISP.
It just goes on and on. So go try it. Go build something. Go learn something. See why it meets
our bar of requirements. And no other provider has. Check them out. Get $100 and support the show.
Linode.com slash SSH. That's $100 for 60 days on a new account. And you support the show by going
to Linode.com slash SSH. Now, I'm really not sure how I feel about Plex's news this week. They've
added a universal watch list, which allows for search and discovery across all the streaming
services. We're talking Netflix, Disney Plus, HBO Max, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
And they've done all this client side. And we all took a look earlier before the show. And
I'm curious to get your thoughts. Hmm. Hmm. Hmm. Hmm. You know, I remember when we talked to the
CEO, I I remember then thinking this is the way they're going because this is probably the most
legitimate play they can make for this space. And they are also in a very unique position where they
have a huge established user base that has a large local library that has the shared function
where you can have friends. So like Alex and I, we share our Plex libraries with each other.
And so that last piece was kind of the online streaming. So now you can look for a movie
and you can see it across all of your friends, servers, your own server or the online streaming
services that it's on. Now, to facilitate this, Plex raised 50 million dollars in funding last
year. So we knew this was going somewhere. And then 20 million just landed even more recently.
Previously, and probably likely still, their primary revenue came from Plex Pass. Now they're
transitioning to this new model where in this mix, when you search for a movie, sometimes it's free.
And that's going to be ad supported and they're going to run a pre roll. And they believe that
in 2022 ad supported revenue is going to easily surpass the Plex Pass. And OK, so these I think
this is the general like, OK, I can see where they're going. I acknowledge it. Yet in the pit
of my stomach, I'm very concerned. They do make some concessions on the blog post to say,
categorically, we do not and do not have any plans to upload your data to our servers. You know,
we don't really care what's in your libraries, et cetera, et cetera. Maybe that's a good thing,
since it does seem to be all happening client side, like your Plex server didn't get updated
to support this. No, I didn't change my my PMS version. I didn't change even the Android TV app
didn't get update. We went to check the history before just to see if if it was. But no, it's it's
all the client itself. The app obviously had some frameworks built into it to check Plex's service
to change what it's displaying to me at any given moment. And then just at the bottom left hand
corner, it now says discover brackets and beta. Yeah, these kinds of things, you know, being able
to search across all of the services. They live and die on these business relationships, and Roku
has tried this. Apple has tried this. And Plex, you know, this this was brought up to the team
over at Plex, and they said, quote, We are a little bit of a Switzerland in this regard. They
believe that they can be the Switzerland of streaming. And they're going to create deals
directly with Samsung and LG to build in Plex that's that scans across all of these services.
On the back end, they're building deals out with all these different streaming platforms.
On the back end, they're building deals out with all these different streaming providers
and trying to leverage their public APIs where they can. But this has never worked.
Yeah, what's the business model? Like, I mean, we tried it, like I said before the show and
the experience was it's all miss, right? We often clicked into an app that I didn't have installed,
or the service linked me to I think was to YouTube in particular for a particular movie.
I clicked on the movie and nothing happened. All I really did was just pass a search parameter to
the YouTube app. But it was like a limited version of the YouTube app. Like even even when it did
work, it seemed like on net, it was kind of a worse experience than watching from your local
times. Yeah, I can imagine after you got every single streaming service app installed, and you
got every single streaming service app logged in, then you go back to Plex, I could see that being
a little smoother. But what would be even credible, and I understand they can't do this is if you
could just stream it all in Plex, because that's what you use Plex for, right? It's basically just
a shell forwarding you to where the content is. Yeah, and they're just trying to deep link to
the specific content in that app. I don't see Disney, or Netflix, or Amazon Prime, or HBO,
letting Plex do that, you know, bypass DRM, it would probably make the particular streaming
service app less sticky. So you know, that's just a lot of the friction of just changing apps for
a lot of people is enough to keep people in the Netflix app or in the app. Yeah, you you kind of
lose your moat effect, right? Disney wants you to have to go into the Disney app, they want you to
experience the Disney plus experience. Right. So even if Plex isn't competing in terms of being
the actual media dealer on that on being the dashboard and the interface, right, they are
all right, if you you know, if you launch the Disney plus app, they can feature their new movies,
they can put banners up for the for the content they're trying to drive traffic to and they don't
have that control over the Plex UI. Hey, didn't you know we sell toys for these two? Yeah,
so this is somewhat like some kind of a bastard child of tracked.tv. And just watch.com because
you can set up lists to add certain things to watch lists. And when a particular movies coming
out in the future, I can say, Oh, remind me when this movie comes out and where I'll be able to
watch it. What's really interesting, though, is, is that at the moment, it feels promising, yet
simultaneously not finished. Yeah. I like being able to search for a movie. And in the results,
I see what server it's available on immediately. That's really nice. It was more of a manual
process to find out if you had a movie or not with the quality there. So if I search for a movie,
it says HD 1080p on my server and yours, it might say 4K, for example. I'll be like, Oh,
I'll go watch it on Chris's right. And funny enough, that worked really well. That fires
right up. It's all inside the Plex app. That's the experience you want. It's just when you go off to
the other streaming apps that it's it's nice to know what services a piece of content is on and
if you can buy or rent it, because I have been in a situation where the family wanted to watch a
movie. We didn't own that movie. We didn't have that one online. And so I ended up doing that
thing where I went, I found some website that lets you search across multiple streaming services.
And then I fired that app up. And then, you know, so it fixes that process, right? There's always
three different versions of those sites. You're never quite sure. Are they actually up today?
That's true. So they fix that. And, you know, I mean, we've talked about this before on the show.
It's like, what else are they going to do, guys? They can't be like, hey, if you've got a really
big pirated collection, like we're the best app to play your pirated collection, like they can't go
that route, right? So they've got to find some legitimate way to do this. This isn't going to
get them crushed by the copyright lobbyists. It's been obvious for a while, just as a user
of Plex, that the core app, certainly as I see it, certainly what it started out as,
as a home media streaming solution that is probably synonymous with pirated content,
if we're being honest, that is not their core business now. And the app itself and the performance
and the bugs and, you know, just the feature set that we're getting is proof of that. And this
finally is, in my opinion, Plex tipping their hand and saying, this is the future of Plex.
And so for me, I think Jellyfin is becoming more important than ever right now.
Yeah, I agree. In fact, that's why I've been kind of watching the new Jellyfin releases and a new
beta, 10.8.0, just shipped a few days ago. There's some nice stuff in here. A lot of transcode fixes,
some DLNA fixes are in here. It feels like they're entering that real sweet spot where they're
focused on this kind of stuff. You know, that's a lot of how these things work in tech. They,
you know, when they get big enough, they have to become some legitimate business.
Harvey Dent, right? If you live long enough, you see yourself become the villain.
Yeah, possibly.
But I mean, with Jellyfin, right, we have a viable alternative. The only real
major criticism I have is that it's in a language that I don't personally know how to contribute
to. It's based off of the MB history. So there's a lot of, you know, Windows.net style, I think it's
or it's maybe C sharp. I can't remember.
Yes.
Yeah, C sharp mono. I feel the same way. It's sort of, it's a foreign thing. I'd love to be
able to help, but it's not my bill house.
I would be in there.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Dangus wrote in with some Plex free music self hosting tips is Hey guys,
love the show. I wanted to mention a few apps for those outside the Plex ecosystem or maybe
planning to migrate. I've been an avid Jellyfin user for a few years now and I've been getting
into my music and hosting it as well. Namely Sonic XD for the desktop and Symfomium, I think.
Symfomium for Android. Both of these are fantastic audio players that connect to both Jellyfin and
subsonic and Plex sample. It looks fantastic. It's a bit of an investment. If you're not already in
the Plex ecosystem, they wanted to pass these along. So it looks like Symfomium, Symfomium,
S Y M F O N I U M and Sonic's D S O N I X D for the desktop.
I can give you some real time feedback on my Plex amp experiment.
Oh yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Let's do it.
Both the wife and I quit Spotify a couple of months ago and up until about a week ago,
it's been going really, really well until we actually, until I actually had a conversation
with my wife and said, how are you finding Plex amp? And she goes, well, it's missing this. And
now you mentioned it. It's missing that. And I don't, can you, can we download this and can we,
I'm like, I've just, I looked at my server and I've got like five or six terabytes of music now.
And I'm still missing a bunch of stuff. And Lidar, you know, we talked about the,
the Deezer script a while ago, just can't cope with that kind of volume. It's just spinning
its wheels and just gets lost in it. So, uh, I am really enjoying Plex amp on my side. I've got
pretty much all the music I regularly listen to. Um, but we have, we have resubscribed to Spotify.
I was tempted recently. I was tempted because it's really nice to have Spotify on the studio
equipment and on Linux. It's nice to have Spotify sometimes, but I haven't yet folded.
I have, I have, I have remained canceled Spotify free.
I'm using YouTube music over here. I'm a weirdo.
How is that? How's that going? It's okay. I used to use, uh, the Google play music
back when that still existed, partially because I could upload a bunch of my own
black files to it. And so I still have those. And yeah, I don't know. I like having a subscription.
It's very convenient for discovery for just random stuff. I don't care about,
but because I can no longer upload to it, I do find I'm more interested in some of these,
you know, Plex amp. Doesn't Apple music let you do that? Let you upload your own?
Yeah. We should get wears on our iPhone. I've been trying that for three years.
When he got me, I'm on one.
Yeah. Well, it's six. I got you to have a kid first. See, I took the long play on that one.
First I convinced you guys to have a kid. So then you would be felt, felt motivated
to get good camera optics. Hey, I'll tell you what, there was an example of streaming service
entropy this week. Um, Snoop Dogg has decided to take hit one of his,
my, or a couple of his most famous albums, one of which is called doggy style. Uh,
and I listened to that album surprising amount actually. And I went on Spotify the other day
and it's, it's gone. Do you know why he's trying to sell it as an NFT?
So I fired up Plex amp boom straight away. You know, so I have a, I have doggy style in Plex amp
and all that money you saved on your Spotify subscription. You know,
now you can buy the NFT about, I don't know, man, I'm sitting here. It's a little bittersweet.
I don't really want to talk about this next story, but for some people out there,
maybe they care. New version of home assistant came out, but it doesn't matter. I'm not upgrading
because I can't, but come on. It's packed with amazing features. I knew they would do this to
me. I knew the version that, cause this is where they dropped my Z wave and I knew they would do
this tons of new stuff that I want, but it is really good. Yeah, it is. It is a few things
that stand out to me. The one, uh, there's a, there's a couple, let's start off with the,
uh, group stuff. So now you can create groups in the user interface directly. Previously,
you would have to drop to the YAML, uh, configuration to do that. It's a nice little
change, um, along with a new hide entities function, which lets you hide the constituent
lights say of a particular group. That's really nice. That is, I want that already.
Now, another one that got me pretty excited was switch as X. So in my home assistant YAML right
now, I have a bunch of, uh, I don't know what you call them, but they basically convert a switch
into a light or a cover, right? Or as from, in my case, a smart plug into a heater or something
like that. Right. Yep. And switch as X now lets me set directly in the configuration of that,
uh, smart plug. I can now show that as a light zones, the entire zone can now have a state.
That's really nice to see. So like my, my kitchen is a zone. My living room is a zone. My bedroom
is his own. Um, and they've done optimizing on both the front end and the backend side of home
assistant as well. So, and I love that. Of course, of course, I'm not going to get that version.
And now it's no longer called a Lovelace either. It's just called the dashboard. Now too,
that is a shame because obviously it was a tip of the hat to Ada Lovelace. One of the fathers of
or can you call her a father of computing, a mother of computing, one of the perennials.
We have a word for that. There was another feature in there that caught my fancy. And
this is particularly useful when writing automations. There's a little test button
up in the top of the automations thing, which lets you test the conditions to make sure they're
right. And yeah, it's a nice little one. Damn it. This really sucks. I want this version so bad.
So if this isn't enough, what is enough to make your upgrade time? It's a matter of having to
redo my entire Z wave. And you know, all of my, I mean my, my heaters, all my heating stuff,
all my, all my temperature sensors, my outdoor sensors, my motion sensors, they're all a UV
sensors, my humidity sensors. They're all Z wave. You're just putting off the inevitable though.
I know you're going to have to do it. Have you considered learning Python and starting to
maintain the old version yourself? Well, I'm doing just about as much work cause I'm first,
I got to learn, I got to learn Nick's OS upside and down. And then I got to figure out how to
deploy everything. I was deploying in a container in Nick's OS and I got to learn how to move
everything over to MQTT and do Z wave to MQTT. And then I'm going to have to figure out node
red if I go that route. So I might as well just learn Python and probably save myself some time.
They've really done this at their worst time too. Cause here we are traveling and all this stuff
and I'm just learning an entire new way. I want to build my system. So like now I don't want to
do it the old way and then be like, this is old and busted. It's just the worst. I should have,
I can't believe they didn't call me first and ask me.
Just to reiterate, the reason Chris is all butthurt is because they're deprecating
a Python two based integration, which has been coming for how many years? Two years,
maybe. I don't know. I just don't sympathize with you on this one. I don't. I know it's a pain in
the butt. Okay. Can I, can I plead my case set differently? Can I, I'll take a new approach.
You can try. If they'd only gotten that damn damn migration wizard to work properly,
I could have migrated to the supported stuff, but the migration wizard didn't work. So now
I'm still a victim, right? No, it's fine. I'll, I'll hang tight for a bit. And then you're probably
by summertime. I'll get, I'll get caught up. I'll still keep the home assistant, uh, install at the
studio. I'll keep that up to date. You're like a Will Smith level victim. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Yep.
That's true.
tailscale.com slash self-hosted to go there to get a free account for up to 20 devices.
And of course you support the show. TailScale is a zero config VPN. It installs on any device
in minutes. You can manage firewall rules for you or for, I don't know, maybe Wes over there.
And it's just a great way to work from just about anywhere. So of course, as you know,
right now we're on the road. And as you can imagine, tail scale is saving the day.
I have different devices, even my VMs connected to my flat tail scale network,
and all of it is using WireGuard's noise encryption. It's beautiful, secure, and simple.
You'd be shocked how fast you can get this thing set up. You install the client, it generates a
URL. You associate that with your account and you're good to go. I've even got it on my iPad
so I can pull up the feedback and I can read through all the emails on my iPad to get it
ready for the show. And even in situations where I've got carrier grade NAT, I'm behind a firewall,
I'm on like some limited guest Wi-Fi that Alex has set up, it still works. Tail scale just works.
It's how I'm also keeping connected to my kids' computers so when they have problems,
they're just on my flat tail scale network. And yeah, you can even divide things up if you need
to worry about that kind of stuff. And if you want to throw a DNS server on the network,
tail scale works with that like magic. So I've got it run on everything from Arch x86 boxes
to Tumbleweed Raspberry Pis to iPads and Android devices. And it's just great. The best thing is
it's like every device gets a network IP that is assigned to it and remains consistent no matter
where I'm at, no matter where I'm at in the country, all of my bookmarks still work. And
tail scale works with whatever your single sign on provider is. So if you want to use a single sign
on provider you already have with two factor authentication, that's going to work too. You're
going to be really impressed. You'll probably get it going in a matter of minutes regardless of your
device or operating system. So go try it for yourself. Protect your data with wire guard
scale encryption and build a flat mesh network in seconds for free up to 20 devices. And you support
the show when you go to tailscale.com slash self hosted. Go see why I love it so much. It's going
to change how you think about networking. It's going to change how you can get access to your
data and it's going to help keep you private and secure. Tailscale.com slash self hosted.
I'm still finding it weird that I'm in the same room as you two gentlemen. This is uh,
this is nice. I could get used to this. We should, we need to get like, uh,
six more sponsors on every episode and we just do every episode like this. Yeah.
Just pay for the flights. Turn it into an LTT video. Probably need a time machine too
to make that five hour flight each way work. Well think about the automations we could do in the
JP private jet. Right? Oh, that's where we go. We need a jet. We need one. We keep flying west.
If we always fly west, then it will be fine. We can make that work, right? Oh yeah. I think
cause it's a glove. That's how it works. Yeah. Or is it east? I don't know. I mean you just
go one direction long enough. It doesn't matter. True. So we have some feedback from Josh today.
Hi Chris and Alex. Thank you for the podcast. I've recently been starting out in the world
of self hosting and I've listened to every episode. I am fortunate enough to be able to
keep something small at my dad's house. Now, given the chat on a previous episode,
I've been looking towards an SBC single board computer based NAS. Hopefully this will consume
very little power and should be able to cope with semi-regular incremental backups. I'm thinking
about something, uh, maybe in the weekly backup range. There seems to be mixed advice about this
online, including a lot of feedback suggesting that using an SBC is flawed as these disks will
be hanging off the USB bus. Uh, do you feel this is something to be concerned about or is this an
acceptable compromise to reach the low power and small form factor solution I'm looking for?
I'm hearing low power a couple of times in here. So it sounds like that is a,
that is a primary concern for Josh here. And so you probably are going down the right path Josh,
but I wonder, have you considered the magnificent world of the compute module four? Because there
are carrier boards where you can get PCI slots, you can get a SATA, you can have an EMMC, which
is much superior to an SD card for a boot drive. And so, uh, you know, if I were going to build a
NAS today based around some sort of SBC, it would take a really, really, really strong argument for
me to consider anything else but the CM4 simply because nothing else has the network effect,
the community effect, the software support. And when you're building something that you want to
run solid and run for a while, that matters. You know, there may be faster SBCs out there with
ones that already have PCI slots, for example, but the CM4, the compute module four combined with a
carrier board that can accommodate you in my experience is such a solid setup. It's really
hard to argue against that. What do you think Alex? It's just a backup, right? Yeah, true.
If you have something hanging off the USB bus and it fails, it shouldn't matter. It is your backup.
As long as you have monitoring in place to let you know that something's gone south,
you know, the backup is the perfect place to experiment and do something that's slightly more
risky. Uh, so long as maybe, I don't know, like maybe have two, uh, you know, three, two, one.
Yeah, the prices, you probably could too, right? I mean, the most expensive thing here is going to
be the storage. That's going to be the most expensive thing. So let us know what you do,
Josh. Cause you know, sometimes we get these questions, but we don't always get the followups.
So we'd love to know. Kevin writes in, I have five or so VPS servers on Linode.
I have one domain name at my DNS provider with subdomains pointing to each server.
It's great for SSH access. I want to run a web server from each one of them. I've obtained a
wildcard TLS certificate from Let's Encrypt on the first server using Lego. I've confirmed the
wildcard cert works on the first server where Lego is installed. It serves a new page with HTTPS on
the subdomain with that cert. I then set a cron job to run Lego and renew that cert monthly.
What is the safest way though, to propagate that wildcard cert from one server to all four other
servers automatically each month? I've got wire guard, I've got SSH, just not keys. I've got
Ansible vault I could potentially use. I've thought about doing these with cron jobs that
copy these over SSH, but how do I automate communicating between the servers? How do I
protect the SSH keys, the SSH certificate and other connection credentials and move all of
this around? This feels like one of those where there's like a thousand ways you could solve this
problem. You could do it the proper way, the established way and move the certificates around
between the servers, but we were talking about this as a group before we recorded and Wes,
you came up with an interesting idea. Yeah, it's kind of sounding like maybe the, you know,
handling of the secrets, distributing that to multiple machines. That workflow hasn't really
been worked out yet in this case. That's a fine thing to experiment with, but if that's not an
essential, you know, if that's just going to be an implementation detail to the actual point of
getting this done, you don't need to be the one handling that part of it. What about just something
like S3? You know, I mean, you can, you can secure that. You can also set a time expiring links. That
was the kind of thing you were worried about and you don't have to host it. Exactly right. Yeah. I
mean, you can do, like you say, authentication on an S3 request. It's easily accessible over the
internet safely, securely. People do it all the time. I'm sure you've all seen the, uh, web URL
of an S3 item in your URL bar at some point. Uh, you know, it's a chicken and egg problem with SSH
that you come across all the time, right? I want to automate this thing, but I need my SSH key over
there already before I do the thing. Yep. Yep. That's three solves that particular problem or
any kind of object storage really. Uh, but the reason I think that we talked about S3 in particular
is that it's authenticated. And if you're putting a secret up there, like a certificate,
it's, uh, you need to have some kind of authentication in front of it. And you could
just use object storage at Linode already because that's S3 compatible. Good to go. So nobody's
going to suggest sync thing. Okay. So don't use sync thing. We did mention it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
I don't know. Like it's, uh, uh, how secure is it with third party bounce service and stuff like
that? I mean, it's probably fine. Yeah. It just doesn't seem like the right tool. Does it? I mean,
it seems like you could do it, but it doesn't seem like the right way to do it.
Go old school and use BitTorrent. Yeah. There you go. Or BitTorrent sync. You could do that.
I think you mean Resilio. Resilio sync. I mean, the thing is with the S3 solution,
it would work in much a similar way as sync thing, right? I guess with sync thing you could,
and this is just solutionizing off the top of my head, which I hate doing, but anyway,
you could, uh, encrypt the secret on whatever box is running Lego
and then sync the encrypted thing with sync thing and then have the logic to decrypt it
at the remote site that way. And that would be kind of secure as it's going over the wire,
but I bet you that's how I would do it. If I, if I were to solve this problem,
that's probably what I would do. Here's the downside on each of those other four remote
systems. You still need the decryption password. Yeah. Probably stored in plain text,
probably on disc. So are you in any better solution than just doing it with a sync thing
naked? I don't know. Probably not. But if anybody has an idea, let us know. Self hosted.show
slash contact or send us a boost like Optimus Gray did. Optimus boosted in and he said,
I hope to see you next week. If gas prices aren't too high, that is, but don't work Brent too much.
I want to see Brent. He sent us 500 sats to say that if you want to give us a boost,
it's like the bat line into the show. You go get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com,
load that wallet up and send us a boost and we'll get it here on the show.
I want to say a big thank you to our SRE site reliability engineer subscribers.
You make this show possible over at self-hosted.show slash SRE and they could join the party,
Jupiter.party if they want to support the entire network and get access to all the
special features of the shows. Yeah. I wonder, you know, I wonder if we'll have some extras.
We should probably plug the extras just in case we get any extra content that we record here with
the group of us extras.show. Wes, thanks for hanging out with us. Thanks for having me.
We, I, we really didn't give him a chance to stretch his wings. You know, we could get into
some topic on the road that Wes could probably really dig into. You should think about that.
So Wes, you're just going to have to come back so that way we can do it again.
Oh, I think we can come up with something. I think we can indeed. Go find our contact page,
send us in your thoughts. Let us know what you think. Maybe you got a solution for one of the
things we've talked about today. Self-hosted.show slash contact is the place to get in touch.
You can find me on Twitter. I'm at Chris LAS. I thought we weren't doing the Twitter thing anymore.
I decided to do it this week. Okay. Okay. It's cause Elon's on board now. Okay. I'm on Twitter
also at ironic badger. I'm also, and this is something that the listener wrote in and let
me know about, we need to plug the discord more heavily. So apparently we don't say enough about
it. So we got a discord. Here we go. We have a discord self-hosted.show slash discord. I'm over
there at Alex KTZ. Are you on the Twitter? Is there anything you want to plug Wes?
I am at Wes Payne and Hey, maybe check out that podcast. You and I do Linux action news.
Hey, Hey, Hey. Also there's a self-hosted matrix. Our matrix service colony.jupiterbroadcasting.com.
If you want to get into some trouble over there, we'd love to have you and get in there. There is,
I think a growing to self-hosted room community over there. Isn't it ironic that the self-hosted
podcast has a discord server and luck and JB as a whole have the matrix server. And I'm just not,
well, we kind of have came first. The discord server, I think came first.
All these problems that you talked about in last week's love about hosting a chat server
are exactly why I didn't want to do it. We should mention, if you want to hear some
horror stories about self-hosting matrix, we just did that in Linux unplugged the
most recent episode, which I should probably have the number for since we're talking about it. But
you know, let's just say when, you know, if you're, I just want to, I'll just say this part,
if you're doing it for five or 10 people, maybe even a hundred people, it's fine. Don't worry
about it. If you want to do for more than a hundred people or maybe 2000 people, there's
some things that go, they go a little wrong. They go a little sideways with the default config.
And we covered that at Linux unplugged.com slash four five two.
And if you have any other questions about which episode did Chris talk about this particular
thing in Coda radio, we have a show notes website over at notes.jupitabroadcasting.com.
All the episodes are in there and that's actually a fully self-hosted website.
Now, as always, thanks for listening, everybody. That was self-hosted.show slash 68.