Well here we are fresh back from Denver we're joined by Brent again who's still
hanging around and Chris hey hi how are you doing gentlemen?
Hello hey Brent thanks for coming in again.
Hey thanks it's good to be here.
You're like our de-Google correspondent and we're going to be talking a lot about that this week.
Yeah well my dumb ass mentioned de-Googling just the week before we're taking a massive
trip and I'd have zero hours to actually do any prep for the episode.
Luckily the audience saw fit to write in with about 800 emails telling us all the different
ways that they're doing it so we're going to come across some of those later on in the show
but in the meantime this episode is brought to you by a cloud guru the leader in learning for
the cloud linux and other modern tech skills hundreds of courses and thousands of hands-on
labs get certified get hired get learning at a cloud guru.com did I followed through on my
challenge Alex I de-Googled my map experience which was crazy because we are on the road and
I was navigating Denver and now Colorado Springs for the entire time that the duration of this
challenge so I will report back on my results when we get to the feedback but I think we should
start with this news story that I don't know it's kind of a bummer actually.
I was really sad to see this yes back in episode 33 we did a review of the Helios
64 arm-powered ultimate arm-powered NAS and unfortunately the Cobalt team today
have announced on their blog that they're pulling the plug.
Yeah no more they're not even going to do the next batch that there's already orders
in the pipeline for they say it really comes down to just two key points there's ongoing
difficulties with manufacturing and procuring parts and costs of getting higher and higher
that's been a problem and they say number two they made a rookie mistake they stretch
themselves too thin they essentially went into the Helios 64 while just being a three-man show
and they should have brought more people on board and they burned out.
You know we got a really interesting insight into this manufacturing difficulties during
our System76 factory tour last week where Jeremy who is the guy that designed some of
the firmware chips and some of the firmware itself for the launch keyboard was saying that
they had to redesign on the fly two or three times some of the circuitry in that keyboard
because parts would go out of stock within hours and that he decided in the end to go
ahead and order several you know hundred units of the parts they needed before he'd actually
finished the firmware so that it didn't go out of stock before he finished writing the code.
So if that's what System76 are up against then they're probably a much larger player
in this space than Cobol. I can only imagine some of the issues that those guys are having.
It's a shame though because I think there's a lot of passion for an ARM powered NAS
specifically for those of us who are looking for low power solutions.
We had some hopes that Helios was going to produce that for us.
Well I think this speaks to some motivations that I've been feeling lately particularly
after the last week getting the tour of the factory and seeing all the CNC machines and all the
powder coating stuff and I mean if ever you get the chance to be in Denver and do a tour of System76
I'm not affiliated with them in any way you know they're not a sponsor of the show or anything
although they do sponsor other JB shows.
Just Coder but yeah.
Oh just Coder that's right.
I mean you know maybe we should have a sponsor of this show because they make those Thalioses
would make great NASes so maybe they should be.
It was a truly inspirational experience for me so I'm sat here thinking okay Cobol who was my
my hope my light in this space has just bowed out maybe Alex should start a company and
build the ultimate NAS you know maybe I should do that.
I think you've got a little bit of experience Alex and some trials and tribulations that you've
gone through already so maybe you're perfectly suited.
You could prototype 3D print the enclosure.
Well you know that was one of the things that struck me I know this is turning into a System76
factory tour recap but this is one of the things that struck me most during that tour actually.
I asked them you know do you use 3D printing for your prototypes and they were like well
no it's just easier to do it in metal isn't it and I'm like is it?
Yeah they used to back in the day they did.
I think one of the realities is that it's with the equipment they have it's faster to
make it out of metal.
It's really you know I think the reason why you keep coming back to it Alex is because
so it is so hard to appreciate the amount of work that goes into manufacturing and it's
that's an obvious thing to say but when you go to the factory and you see every little
thing they had to consider and when they're bringing things in as a block of aluminum
and what's coming out on the other end is a keyboard or a case you really have no idea
how intricate that process is until you see it and I think that's what is probably I mean
that's what resonated with me and stuck with me and I gotta imagine probably for you too.
Yeah well one example was Carl who is the founder of System76.
I was just stood next to a shelf with loads of different parts in it and I picked up
what like an innocuous little nameplate you know about the size of a dog tag or something
like that and he jumped straight into a five-minute discussion telling me about all the different
you know reasons why they pick that particular size how it goes through their laser etching
machine and how they're considering doing direct engraving instead and all that kind
of stuff and I'm like wow if that's if that's the amount of thought that goes into a nameplate
or a serial number plate oh this is going to be a big mountain to solve if I want to
try and do it myself.
That's where I that's what I take from it you take from it maybe Alex could make a NAS
that could be cool I take from it oh my god I would have to build a factory and I would
have to learn all this stuff.
Oh well that sounds fun doesn't it a daunting but fun.
Yeah if I had another life if I had if I had like you know another 100 years I definitely
would get into it for sure.
You manufacture stuff every week as well and you ship podcasts every week okay you're not
manufacturing aluminium into you know computer cases but you ship and manufacture stuff just
the same.
That's true and there have been many times when we refer to our production pipeline as
kind of a manufacturing pipeline and if one component is delayed or you know gets out
of out of order it does cause a jam up there is a lot of that kind of building tech around
that maybe that's why I don't have the appetite to do it again but I definitely would sit
here and encourage you I'll be customer number one I'll be number two well there's a lot
of roadblocks to overcome but if I could just bring it back to COBOL for a minute you know
one of the things I picked up on in my review was that the product wasn't 100% finished
and I've got to believe that with this news that some of the issues that were present
with that NAS now will never be solved you know things like the backplane breaking some
of the the plastic tabs you know the power connector and data connector on three of my
hard drives it turned out eventually yeah problems with the two and a half gigabit network
adapter there was a bunch of other stuff as well you know you can go and listen to episode
33 if you want the full review well I worry now this means that some of this stuff's never
going to get fixed do you think you killed them do you think that bad review killed them
Alex you murdered them oh don't say that I mean I didn't mean to I was just trying to
be honest it was presented in a way that I felt was constructive to say that there are
these it's a very promising piece of hardware I mean the aluminium chassis was was really
lovely there was just a couple of key things that let it down you know in terms of manufacturing
tolerances and a couple of firmware things but overall they did a really great job and
I I wish there was some way we could tell them that you know even though we weren't
100% positive it was just because we loved the idea not because we didn't want them to
carry on and succeed I agree completely and they don't completely close the door in their
blog post we'll have that linked in the show notes if you want they do kind of leave it
cracked a little bit like maybe they'll come back but I wanted to shift gears and talk
about something that could solve a big problem for me I actually went out and I pre-ordered
a bunch of wise three cameras a long time ago and I have a box of wise three cameras
that I haven't installed because they do not yet have an RTMP firmware an RTSP firmware
or an RTSP firmware for wise three but Alex I think you've solved that this week yeah
I don't know where I came across this but I found a docker container that is called
docker wise bridge link in the show notes of course and essentially what this does is
you give it your wise username and password and it goes and sort of acts as an intermediary
between the wise API and the cameras and somehow it hooks into the local feed on the cameras
on your LAN and then presents you with a normal RTSP stream so I've just got that feeding
into blue iris and it just works that's fascinating and yeah it will it can actually do both it
can pull from the wise servers using your credentials or with your credentials it can
use that there's a library that the app uses and it essentially does a discovery on your
network and the wise app does this as well and if it detects the camera it uses LAN mode
and it just does that locally and avoids the cloud relay and you can also in your docker
composed there is an environment variable you can pass through that says LAN underscore
only that says don't even don't even try the remote thing only stream if you can locally
detect them and that was the piece I was curious about that's why I dug into this and that
means I could absolutely do this here in the RV which means I could replace these wise
cams that have been giving me trouble the version two was good but just didn't have
enough horsepower didn't really work so great at night and the wise three solves those and
with this docker wise bridge which seems to have a decent community around it as well
and some active development I think my problems have been solved and I'll give this a go I
think once we get back into our home base so far as I can tell it only works on the v3
cameras so I've got a couple of v2s flashed with the RTSP firmware and a couple of v3s
and the app will in its logs show me a bunch of errors for the two v2 cameras I don't know
if that's because I'm running the you know custom firmware or whatever whatever it is
but the performance with the v3s is great we've been using it as a baby monitor for
my daughter and the night vision on there is just it's like daytime it's wonderful
they blew it out of the park with the night vision it's tricky with the firmwares so this
is an issue and I'm glad you brought it up because we need to mention this on the show
and they have it on their github page there is a slightly older version of the firmware
for v2 that is compatible with the bridge but if you use the latest firmware for v2
it doesn't work and that actually holds true for some instances of the v3 model too so
there's a version that does work and there's a version that doesn't work with the v3 and
the pan camera as well anyways the links in the show notes you do need to check into that
because I may have I may have a really old firmware and so I'm going to have a hard time
getting just the right compatible firmware in some cases but they have all the information
you need back in episode 48 we talked about the pi kvm you know that wonderful raspberry pi that
captures hdmi and basically acts like a bmc kvm type thing well good news their version 3 hat
has finally entered kickstarter mode it is a little pricey so the main hat which doesn't
include a raspberry pi costs 145 so by the time you've added a pi as well and a case it's going
to be north of 200 but you do get a lot of useful stuff in there like a usb c bridge and csi you
know cables all that kind of stuff now wendell's done a video about this on his channel on youtube
so if you're curious you can go and find out more about it over there i do wonder about the price
and what do you think chris at that sort of 200 level is that is that too much so it looks like
right now on kickstarter uh it's 145 bucks and you'd get it by october 2021 which seems pretty
reasonable to me the price is it it's yeah it feels high for a hat um now i think the price is
a little more reasonable if you make the assumption that just about everybody already
has a raspberry pi for that would want to use something like this right if you're going to use
a raspberry pi powered keyboard video mouse switcher you probably already got a couple of
pies laying around so i don't think i think you just kind of null that out because that's already
a sunk cost and so it really is just 145 bucks now you tell me alex like how solid is this is this
are you still using it is it worth 145 bucks now that you've used it for a bit i'm i'm i'm thinking
i probably couldn't get a good kvm at that price i probably couldn't so i'd have to go i'd have to
go with your word though if it's worth that well i'll tell you what i'm comparing it to in my mind
at least and that is a motherboard with ipmi built in so i'm actually going back to england
in a couple of weeks to go and introduce granddaughter to grandparents so i'm going to
introduce my granddaughter to grandparents so hello if you're listening and as part of that
i was thinking well it would be nice to upgrade my you know nearly 10 year old server in england
with a slightly more modern motherboard and a slightly more modern ipmi implementation that
isn't based around java and an eighth gen motherboard costs me around 150 give or take
depending on the features that i want and i was looking at some asrock rack stuff which thanks to
chip shortage seems to be in the 300 250 to 300 range and so if i look at that and think i've got
a built-in ipmi directly on the motherboard that i know is going to be absolutely rock solid versus
an external device which in my experience has been good but it's still an external device and
you know it's another power supply it's another operating system to keep updated etc etc which
in some respects could be a good thing in in other respects could be a bad thing so the cost is kind
of a wash you know it's about the same to get a built-in versus this external unit probably just
go for the built-in one to be honest with you um except for the fact that this pi version using
the hdmi switch which is linked in the blog post in episode 48 um that i talked about in that
talked about in that episode i've actually got three devices hanging off this single pi and
that has actually worked really really well so if you're able to spit that 150 between
three devices suddenly that tips the scales quite a bit i also could see some value in there if you
needed to add it to devices that ipmi wouldn't be an option like i'm you know i'd love to have
console level access to my studio machines right now while i'm remote while i'm here in denver
for your other raspberry pies yeah that too it would be a great way to get console access to
my raspberry pies oh okay all right now you're making me you're making me think maybe i should
back this damn it alex well now i've actually been in lady dupes uh i've seen how you cool
your air quotes server cupboard it's pretty cool yeah hey man i just gotta get airflow that's all
that matters i just gotta get airflow how hot was it in the uh in the rv whilst you were parked at
system 76 last week 107 yeah it was 107 i think the hottest we ever got in here though was actually
nebraska i think it got near 120 in here while we were recording which actually it was impressive
because the server quote room was the coolest place in the whole rv at that time leno.com
slash ssh go there to get 100 dollars in 60 day credit on a new account and you go there to
support the show hey guys guess what this week's episode marks our one-year anniversary going
independent again yay how about that how awesome is that it's so cool it's so cool because lino
helped make that possible amongst amongst our member support and those of you who went over
to lino.com slash ssh we're here now rocking a year of independence and lino they've been
independent since 2003 so they've really figured this out like that's 18 years of focusing on just
being awesome at cloud computing they started when it was new and they have just evolved with
it and they have remained competitive and sharp they have 11 global data centers serving nearly
a million customers and businesses around the globe but really their mission remains unchanged
since 18 years ago make cloud computing simple affordable and accessible to all if you set up
thousands of servers or if you've never set up a server before lino can make that work i know it
sounds like an impossible task that's why i rave about them they've really done a great job we've
been using the absolute schmack out of their s3 compatible object storage we created a denver
bucket and we created a system 76 bucket and all of the media across multiple cameras multiple
recorders all gets uploaded to those buckets and then our next cloud instance what we put on there
also saves to their s3 compatible object storage and then my system's backup there as well right
here from the rv it's pretty awesome and it's really just a great way to use lino and not even
have to have a server running in front of it it's sort of it's sort of like feels like a power move
they also have a great dns manager they have kubernetes and terraform support they have super
fast networking because they are their own isp and their pricing is 30 to 50 cheaper than other
major cloud providers out there you know it's also a great way to go with a multi-cloud strategy
perhaps you want something local and you want something up in the cloud or maybe you want
something across multiple cloud providers and then network them using something like nebula
lino can be part of that strategy as well they made our jupiter colony reunion road trip possible
as well our meetups were powered by lino and it has been a hoot so go sign up today and see what
i've been talking about that 100 you're going to get you can really use that to try the service
out you can really get a feel for what it's capable of that's 100 to really try something
or learn something lino dot com slash ssh that's lino dot com slash ssh here's an email from hans
hans says hey guys you touched upon password managers and bit warden in episode 51 like brent
i'm using keypass xc good good choice what i like about it is that it's easy to back up because the
whole database is just a single file currently sync it between my devices via self-hosted sync
thing instance running on an arm board in our laundry room laundry room servers very nice
that being said this setup is a few years old and if i would start from scratch or if i had to share
the password with other people i'd definitely give bit warden it look one thing i wonder though
when you host your passwords in a more complex application like bit warden are you taking any
extra measures to secure your servers i suppose it's reasonable to trust the security of bit warden
itself but if an attacker would gain access to your server would it be easier for them to do
harm as compared to what you would just host an encrypted key pass database file to thanks and
keep on going hans well i think it depends on how open your server is if it's connected to the
internet you've got to assume at some point you know it's possible it might get compromised
but it it speaks to a larger philosophy that i tend to subscribe to with this kind of stuff of
don't be the tallest nail you know take some basic precautions have things like fail to ban installed
on your ssh logins open as few ports in your firewall as you possibly can use something like
wire guard or tail scale or something like that to actually connect to the service in question
so that all the data that travels between everything is encrypted you know and use things
and you know and use things like ssh keys instead of passwords just just those things alone are
going to make you more secure than the average server administrator vault warden is the new
hotness these days bit warden rs is the old name um and i do agree with everything you just said
alex don't don't be the tallest nail but also consider the security of the box of possible
limited internet access and also keep in mind bit warden is using local encryption so it encrypts
and hashes your data on your local device before it sends it to the cloud server even even if it's
their service or your self-hosted service so that gives you some peace of mind knowing that the data
that's at rest on the server is encrypted now alex you mentioned being a shorter nail um have
either of you in all of your years encountered situations when you were one of the taller nails
and ran into issues i mean like had a server compromised basically that's what i'm asking
yeah it's never very exciting um it's usually like a server gets turned into an ftp box
or somebody gets a process on your machine i mean i think i've had maybe a client or two
that that's happened to um it's never anything uh more exciting than somebody trying to mine crypto
or something these days can i admit something to you both oh yeah i used to run remote desktop
open to the internet with the password 22 you maniac for like three years and how'd that go
alex well uh it didn't end well brent it didn't end well at all no what happened tell us uh they
decided to wipe my hard drives oh no oh that sucks that sucks i suppose maybe that's better
than using it for something nefarious or maybe they did and then they wiped it so there's no
track so maybe they did do something nefarious i have no idea i mean if your password is to to
maybe of you know maybe old alex didn't know how to check yeah i mean back in the day that was that
was that was something you know you just didn't really think of like way back in the day things
were just on the internet when i when i first got exposure to tci tcp ip networking everything had a
public internet address on the network and it wasn't until sometime later that we had firewalls
and gnats and so for a short period of time you could basically connect everything
there was some crazy stuff we did back then i didn't want to put you guys on the spot but i
would be curious about how to go about detecting some of this stuff you know even from a most very
basic level well i i mean i'm sure alex you probably have a few ideas my first couple that
come to mind would be know what processes should be running on your box check your logs i mean
almost every single time that a client machine or something was behaving poorly i could almost
immediately just suss it out by running top i mean really because you know you know what
that machine is supposed to be doing and if there's some process going crazy on there that
has nothing to do with the responsibilities of that box you got a pretty good idea what it is
and then you look at your logs right you look at the active users that are logged onto the system
and you kind of start tracing it back usually you'll look at the process and there'll be like
some weird path or url for a for a process that looks normal but it's in the wrong place or it's
being run by the wrong user and you kind of track it back from there it depends where your expertise
lies if you're a networking guy you could use something like snort which is essentially a
packet filter and it looks for certain patterns of packets yeah or bandwidth charts as well you
know that sometimes will be an indication something's up as you'll see your bandwidth
usage spikes up and would you guys say that containerizing some of your services is a way to
help this situation no no all right no i mean really in a way it makes it worse i think it
makes it worse because there's more processes and more things going on on a box in some cases
but you do have better security in terms of networking control and process isolation and
the ability to just destroy a container and recreate it if something did go sideways so it's
i mean it's a mix i think it's good and bad but i'm sure alex you must have saw you must have
thoughts well containers good everything else bad right that's my viewpoint but uh oh man i think
i think containers are better in this situation because let's say you've got an nginx web server
listening with your volt warden behind it or whatever the web server is that's exposing your
passwords to you if somebody was to compromise something in that code and do a buffer overflow
or do something that meant they could get something out of memory that they shouldn't and
extrapolate some data that they shouldn't get the blast radius of that is going to be limited to
the scope that that container has access to and so running things in the container is more secure
simply by virtue of the fact that you are scoping what that container has access to on the host
system yeah i mean it will have access to any of the data that the container has access to which is
likely important data but it's contained to that region that's inherently more safe than say
running apache or nginx on a box and you pop apache and now you've got access to anything on
that host that apache had access to which if you're lucky is not much but sometimes is way
more than it should be so yeah um that it's it's gonna be different every time too there's not a
one-size-fits-all solution it's trying to make sure you're secure and monitoring in multiple
locations we got a lot of email about people's wi-fi systems we got some people who love mesh
setups some people who hate mesh setups but we got one email in about a free mesh wireless solution
it's at freemeshwireless.com it's an open source package that you load onto hardware um and then
we got some people that said don't do it just deploy multiple ap's so i'm still collecting
information and taking it all in and i got a few devices to research too so i wanted to say thank
you to everybody who sent in suggestions for different wi-fi setups wow there's a lot out
there including some of you who said you know what just stick with unifi it's fine it's fine
well okay just one guy and several folks brent were happy with your recommendation
of checking out mikrotik it's almost like i know something
at the meetup in denver several of you let me know that you are massive fans of cloudfree.shop
and they are sponsoring today's episode use the coupon code self-hosted and get a dollar off one
of their new version two smart plugs with energy monitoring built in also those of you in the uk
who have let me know that you wish that cloudfree.shop shipped to the uk well good news
mylocalbytes.com have launched in the uk offering a very similar thing you can use the coupon code
self-hosted at both cloudfree.shop and mylocalbytes.com to get a dollar or a pound off
each smart plug both of these stores are owned and operated by a couple of our listeners so
head over there support the community and check out their cool stuff
we had a lot of emails in regards to de-googling and it really ran the whole spectrum we're going
to try to get to some of them but legitimately brent you saw the list there's just no way we
could read all those emails yeah you gave me a little sneak peek at just the number of sheer
number of just scroll through the list oh we did our best but we've it's a lot of email yeah
but dustin was one of the first to write in and dustin was at the boysy meetup with us brent
he says on today's self-hosted you guys talked about de-googling this is my journey and it has
been for two years and i'd say i'm about 90 of the way there dustin goes on to say this includes
replacing g-suite for my podcast and i've also gone with the model of self-hosting when it makes
sense so here's what he's done for mail contacts and calendar he switched from g-suite to fastmail
for notes and docs he's using joplin using next cloud to sync it for photo sync he's using next
cloud for his phone he's gone with the iphone se 2020 so he's not dealing with google there
for dns he's using next dns we got another vote for next dns as well uh for maps he's using a
combination of apple maps and the open street maps app on the app store and for the browser he's
sticking with firefox and safari and for his chromebook well he's replaced that with the
thinkpad x 260 with arch and now fedora on there he's still working on the home assistance he's
going to maybe consider the home pods and look at mike croft he says google photos has been working
great for my wife uh but i'm not using it and he's using free tube to bypass youtube but it has been
a bit of a challenge i suspect some good tips there although um fastmail uh isn't self-hosting
it is you know having somebody else host it but if you're gonna have somebody host something
email is a good one to do don't don't really do don't do don't do email what i noticed from
that feedback is that it took him well he's on a two-year journey and so gentlemen uh what does
that tell you about what you've just got on the alex has really really gotten us into something
what have i done i've opened pandora's box oh man um all right so carson and others wrote in about
about maps carson says he settled on here maps as a replacement wego.here.com a lot of people wrote
in about open street maps brent that's what you use yeah that's what i have been using until all
these suggestions came in and i well maybe i'll keep that till we talk about the maps a little
bit more well i want to talk about it right now because uh that's the route i decided to go during
a freaking road trip and i even really briefly tried ways even though i know it's owned by google
i just wanted to just do a comparison and ways actually screwed us up the worst out of all of
them during the middle of denver rush hour it had me get off the highway to like bypass the traffic
and then i got off the highway and i was stuck in more traffic and then it did a quick update and
it said get on the highway yeah it felt to me like a an attempt at like a dukes of hazard style like
walk around the traffic but uh but it didn't work out too well for us oh goodness so i know a lot of
you wrote in with the apps that you love and i tried them and boy do they stink magic earth was
one that i liked and that uses open street maps with a proprietary gooey on top magic earth have
linked in the show notes but um they they all have one critical flaw even apple maps has this critical
flaw and it's search for example i'm here in colorado springs and i searched for pikes peak
which is a very popular tourist destination apple maps sent me in the wrong direction they sent me
to some like business that was named pikes peak that was like 10 miles in the wrong direction
literally the opposite direction um the magic earth using open street maps wanted to send me
to a location 5200 miles away from my current location i was 25 30 minutes away when i started
from pikes peak and after i was done trying to use these other nav apps i ended up an hour away
and it was really bad um eventually what happened is my wife looked it up on her phone on google
maps and got uh got an address and then telegrammed it to me and then i put that into apple maps
um yeah it was interesting because she she kept using out google maps during this anytime i drove
or anytime i was looking anything up or looking at i used anything but google maps and she stuck
with google maps so i was always comparing the two and they clearly have the superior um search
however apple maps surprised me and i looked into the privacy and security of apple maps because i
mean that was really what part of this was about was reducing the amount of time that i was
out was reducing my cloud footprint with this and the thing i liked about apple maps is surprisingly
you don't even have to be signed in to any apple id or i cloud to use it the data that they do
collect is associated with a randomly generated identifier they reset like every few minutes
and it is not tied to your apple id they convert precise locations into less exact locations before
they store them and then they apply that to your current device location information and origin
within 24 hours and uh any any of the personalized features like where your car is parked or
suggested departure times um your favorite locations any of that kind of stuff that you
generate it's all stored on device they don't send it up to the apple servers at all it seems to me
the way they've defined how apple maps works is sort of their privacy first approach that they've
been um sharing throughout the years yeah i'm not gonna say it's perfect but it feels like they got
most of it right considering all of the sort of technical stuff that has to happen to get you
around on a maps app and well or or another way is it feels like they designed a product to say
to say screw you to google on data collection and stuff like that and did it work well um the
display is probably the best the other thing that i found surprisingly good is the voice routing it
does it has really good clear like very clear about which lane to be in which isn't too uncommon
and it's very clear about intersections and here in the colorado denver area they stack the
intersections so it's you go you drive through an intersection and then three or four car lengths
later there is another intersection and so when you look on a map you're not really sure like what
light to turn on and the voice prompt is very clear it'll say go through this light and at the
next light take a left be in the middle lane and when you're when you're now you're new to an area
and it's dark and you're coming up on two intersections and you know you've got a left turn
or a right turn that kind of clarity just makes it low stress then additionally they tie in with
the watch so it taps your arm when you need to turn and when you were driving i was able to just
look at my watch and tell you what the next turn is yeah that was really handy i will admit that
um halfway through the trip i kind of gave up on my phone and my map app because well we're doing
this this experiment and um my methods were failing so uh you were in the nav seat and you
were helping me out and that actually worked out all right i think i'm going to stick with it i
don't think i'm after that i mean i said i do it for two weeks and i think i'm going to stick with
it um i'll let my you know my wife will still have google maps as a backup but for me i'm
uninstalling google maps off the phone wow yeah that's quite a success yeah it's not open street
maps uh although i am playing with those still and i do really like the way magic earth displays
things so for some circumstances like if i already know the address and i'm not searching up
something they may have a place still but um i i was i was pretty impressed um you know if you
only could have one app and you didn't care about google tracking you i'd probably still suggest you
use google maps you know i for the trip used um the same app that i've been using for probably
the last two years since i've tried this de-googling a while ago uh mostly successfully and uh so i'm
on android and i've been using open street map the osm and plus there are things i love about it
things i hate about uh the one thing you mentioned search uh i find it's great if you know approximately
where you want to go if you're trying to find an exact business or even an exact address on a
popular street it's not necessarily going to have it it might have some of the street numbers but
certainly not all of them i found that to be a little bit frustrating but it gets me there i will
say 90 percent of the time it works for me but i like getting lost in new cities so maybe that's
a unique approach well there's that if you don't mind getting lost that's a feature yeah for brent
uh the thing i liked about the open street maps app is that you could download your maps offline
hold on a minute hold on a minute osm and plus is 25 dollars that's quite a lot isn't it for an app
well you know it's not 25 for me when i get it from uh f-droid ah there you go you see
i've been using view ranger uh for quite a number of years whenever i take a hike or something like
that i actually this is a very long term usage for me uh from back when i lived in england
it supports things like ordinance survey maps and you can download u.s geological survey maps
you can buy them uh and actually buy the tiles directly in view ranger they're changing their
name to outdoor active uh so you can find them at view ranger.com i've found that one pretty good
brent there mentioned f-droid um we got several people including ross who wrote in and said i
like the aurora store it's an alternative front end for google play which keeps your data away
while giving you access to those apps that are exclusive he's like that's the only way i could
get the starlink app i i will admit i have aurora droid installed and i prefer it over f-droid most
of the time it has a few little tiny bugs but i didn't know that was a feature so that's great to
hear ross says that he switched to proton mail from gmail and i've used proton mail and i like
it a lot um so there's something there there was also uh a lot of people wrote in about their
different approaches to contact syncing and brent did you cover in last week's episode how you do
that i think i did but i'll do it again uh i'm using nextcloud for contacts and i've found that
to be pretty bulletproof actually i was worried at first when i did it a while ago um because contacts
is arguably the thing that's most important to me uh getting all of that right and it's been
bulletproof well dale writes in i just listened to episode 51 and i think brent mentioned nextcloud
yes confirmed we just had that confirmed by brent thank you and i wondered if any of you have heard
or used etsy sync that's e-t-e-sync.com it's a self-hostable project whose value proposition
is secure end-to-end encrypted and privacy respecting sync for your contacts calendars tasks
and notes i've been using it for about two years now and more recently i've been using it on my
gnome desktop i pay for them to manage the hosting and syncing but you could absolutely host it
yourself highly recommend it thanks for the great show and all the best dale e-t-e-sync.com we'll
have a link to that in the show notes i looked at it uh before the show and it it's a solution
that really is kind of targeted at just a end-to-end encrypted sync of contact calendar
task notes like it just solves that problem that's what they focus on and they've got apps in the
apple app store google play they're on f-droid too and of course you can get it on your phone
and of course you can get it on your desktop it look it looks pretty legit actually i think i
just decrypted what their name means e-t-e-sync is end-to-end sync isn't it ah i was wondering
it's one of those moments you figure it out and you're like oh i feel like a dummy now
you know if i could mention one thing about nextcloud uh on android at least that made it
possible for me and integrates it at a system level everywhere uh is this little app called devx5
um it takes the nextcloud syncing which is cal dev and car dev and just sort of makes that
available at a system level in the same exact places and ways that all of the google stuff
appears so it's just seamless so that would be a huge recommendation from me say it again for me
devx5 available in f-droid and maybe in other stores can you put a link in the show notes
for us brent oh probably so what did you guys think of the meetup it was pretty cool to meet
some of our listeners huh yeah we saw a chris and the badger shirt there which was exciting
because i hadn't considered that somebody would get a shirt with the intention of bringing it to
the meetup that was great that was optimus gray rocking the chris and the badger yeah i thought
that was super cool he posed for a picture with us and we had to stand on the correct sides as
well you know i was on the badger side and you were on the chris side right my daughter thought
it was so cool that people wanted to take selfies with us so i was like really that's the thing you
think is cool all right okay well i thought the free donuts were pretty cool lino put on a heck
of a show for us yeah uh you know brent and i and west went to grab those donuts that was quite the
journey because it was 150 donuts and it was in downtown denver during friday rush hour i don't
know what we were thinking and so at a certain point i saw a little bit of canadian road rage
you emerge out of brent when this truck brent had gotten to a battle with a truck downtown and
he had to kind of cut in front of the truck because a lane was ending and the truck driver
never forgave him for it just brent get angry i mean i disgruntled i got slightly more aggressive
in my driving oh wow uh it was one of those situations where you just got to get over and
you got to do everything you can and uh it wasn't too bad actually i thought but that that truck
decided to very aggressively pass us on the right hand side he had to work at it too oh yeah and
promptly cut us off again on the left hand we're just trying to make a donut run i don't think he
realized what we were trying to accomplish i know i know hey before we go i want to say thank you
to our members our sres make this show possible self-hosted show sre if you'd like to sign up
you get a discount on our merch at jupiter garage.com and you get access to the exclusive
post show with your own rss feed at self-hosted.show slash sre and i want to mention you can find our
sponsor a cloud guru on social media essentially any social media site they're just slash a cloud
guru youtube twitter the facebook's you know the social medias slash the cloud guru and as you all
well know by this point self-hosted.show slash contact is the place to go to get in touch with
us you can find me on twitter at ironic badger i'm at chris las and i'm at brent gerber and the show
is at self-hosted show thanks for listening everyone that was self-hosted.show slash 52