Coming up on the show, we react to home assistant password shaming both of us and then attempt to solve an age-old cloud problem.
Backups. I'm Chris. And I'm Alex and this is Self Hosted.
The podcast is the middle-aged man now. We're 40.
Yeah, the podcast is feeling like he's still got some pet left in him
but also has a few miles on him or her. Midlife crisis coming up. Is it a, is the podcast,
does it have a gender? It's a thing, right? The podcast prefers to be referred to as they.
Podcast pronouns. Yeah, there's a title right there. I'll tell you what. Anyway, you were gonna tell me about your off-grid solar stuff.
We've not heard about that for a while. We were chatting about this just before we hit record because I'm off-grid and
podcasting on solar right now.
I was just talking to you actually because you're thinking about getting solar and I think that the thing
that people have to wrap their head around is
what are you planning for? Are you planning for like a grid blackout or brownout? Are you planning for going out into the woods?
What's your scenario? And
then how much battery do you really need versus could you supplement with a generator? Like for me right now,
I think I've hit a sweet spot of
enough battery
capacity that I can run on it for a day or so and if it's a sunny day out,
I can get charged. I can get a 30-40% charge right now in the winter,
but I can't get a hundred percent charge off of solar right now.
And so I need to run the generator for about an hour once a day right now when I'm off-grid and
that's fine. I feel like that's actually a really good spot because the more battery you have, the more generator or solar you're gonna need.
You can't, you know, you can't charge all you have to have the ability to charge all that stuff up.
So I feel like I've kind of hit the sweet spot that because it's winter, you know, we're not getting prime sunshine.
And I'm only running the generator about once a day and otherwise we're getting, we're getting along.
I think I'm kind of in that sweet spot.
And I think that's something you should think about when you're speccing out your solar system for your house is
what are you covering for? Are you covering for a couple of days of no power?
Or do you really just need to cover for a couple of hours?
And if it goes longer, maybe you could run a generator for an hour or two.
I think I want to cover just the the average daily low-level load of the house.
I want to make the house more sustainable. So, you know, like just all the lighting, all the computers that are on in here,
whatever that works out to be.
My electric bill is normally in a sort of hundred to hundred and twenty-ish dollar range. So it's not too crazy.
And for me, it's about sustainability and I was watching a David Attenborough program, Our Perfect Planet, the other night.
Beautiful 4k HDR on the LG OLED. Oh, it was magical to watch that thing.
Streaming from the Plex server.
Correct. Yeah, through the Nvidia Shield.
You can't help but watch these Perfect Planet things and be left with a sense of guilt about what humanity is doing to the planet
and how we're consuming too many resources and stuff like that.
So, you know, I think about how I might be in a position to do something about that as just an individual
when in reality we need to as a species collectively actually effect change.
But as an individual, there isn't much I can do, but reducing my use of fossil fuels even by a little bit feels like a good place to start.
Yeah, I love the idea of even just offsetting the computers that run all the time.
So during the day, I've reached the point where all day long I'm running off the solar power.
I'm bringing in more solar power than I am using, which is a great spot to be because that means my home server,
all my stuff is being sustained by the sun.
And I'd love to do a similar setup at the studio, a couple of panels on the roof.
If I could just bring in, you know, 400 watts or so, I could probably cover most of my computer gear that's running 24-7.
And, you know, I think about long term Alex, say even just 10 years, 15 years down the road,
maybe the majority of cars or all cars sold will be electric.
How does the grid in the United States, at least, handle that if we don't have some people offsetting their load with solar?
It seems like long term, the direction things are going between crypto mining and electric cars,
there's going to be more demand on the grid than ever.
So being able to supplement a little bit might not only just be a nice thing to do for the environment,
but also ensure that you have enough power to go around.
Free Bitcoin, baby.
Yep. Get that crypto going and maybe, maybe spend your time learning.
This episode is brought to you by the all new A Cloud Guru.
They are the leader in learning for the cloud, Linux and other modern tech skills.
Go check them out.
They have hundreds of courses and thousands of hands on labs.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at a cloud guru dot com.
You could spend that time mining crypto or you could spend that time learning job skills and getting hired.
But, you know, I think maybe you and I are thinking about off grid and backup power today because a lot of our listener services are down and offline as we record this right now.
That's right. Yeah.
OVH, one of the largest VPS providers in Europe, have suffered a major fire this week and it's, it's taken,
literally taken out one of their data centers and had dramatic effects on some of their other regions, data centers, whatever they called for OVH as well.
It's just got me thinking, great, there's another disaster that I hadn't really thought about.
What if AWS or DigitalOcean or Linode, what if they catch fire?
Oh, that's another one to plan for.
Yeah, the thing that's tricky about OVH is data centers one through four, we're all kind of like in the same area.
So after midnight on the Wednesday of the week, we're recording this OVH cloud had an alarm go off.
The cause as of this recording right now is still unknown.
However, the founder and CEO speculated it may have been a UPS fire.
And he noted in a video update that he released a couple of days ago that UPS number seven had been serviced earlier that day.
But obviously more investigation is required.
In total, OVH had four data centers in this area and one data center, SPG two was just totally destroyed by fire.
And then part of SPG one was also damaged and then SPG three and four, they're fine.
But as we record, there's still some outages because there's some areas the staff can't get to.
There's network issue, there's still some power issues, and there's even the fact that they still have to validate that the cooling system is still fully functional.
It's like bad, Alex.
This is a weird one to me because every data center that I've worked near or in in some occasions,
they've all had argon fire suppressant systems and just fire was something that you kind of assumed would never get out of control in a data center because it's a controlled environment.
There isn't a huge amount of flammable stuff like on a data center floor.
It's just metal boxes with some cables and stuff like that, essentially.
So it's kind of surprising to me that it was able to get to this level.
I mean, if you look at some of the pictures and we've got a Reuters article linked in the show notes.
That building was toast.
Yeah, the CEO says something about it using the older style construction techniques and that the newer buildings that weren't damaged were using the newer style.
I wonder if that style is fire suppression, you know, or materials or something.
But it kind of got us thinking like, you know, we got kind of a sad note in from listener Kerry said my server was in data center one and I have lost it, I'm afraid.
I didn't have any complete backups because I didn't really have anywhere to back up to that server already blew my personal self-hosting budget.
I feel like I've lost a loved one.
I guess I'll get a box at home and I'll have to back up to that from now on.
But that's going to get very expensive.
That is tricky.
Well, it is.
It is going to get expensive.
But I would argue that the emotions you're feeling right now are also expensive.
And just in a, you know, not dollars and cents necessarily, but they're expensive in a different way emotionally.
And only you can quantify how much your data is worth.
I mean, I don't know what was on this particular server for you, Kerry, but I certainly know in the past when I've lost data, it hurts.
Like genuinely, you spend the next few weeks, months, sometimes longer wishing you'd done things differently, thinking, oh, if only I'd spent a couple of hundred on a Pi and an external hard drive and I wouldn't even be in this situation.
I mean, if you think about what most typical VPSs are, they are probably less than 100 gig disk, probably only a few gigabytes of RAM or something like that.
So we aren't talking about a huge amount of data to back up here.
And what I would say is if you've got no backup, I mean, literally zero, don't try and aim for perfect.
Just get a 128 gig USB stick off Amazon and then just get in the habit of downloading your data once a month, once a year even.
Because I'm sure right now you wish you'd had something, even if it was 11 months old, you'd have something.
Something I've seen really common is a lot of people these days when they have cheap cloud hosting, they're going for like a NUC with a disk hanging off it or something that they're syncing to locally and getting that peace of mind by having the data on their local network.
And I got to admit, that's kind of what I did for the Jupiter broadcasting stuff is we have next cloud up at Linode and then we have next cloud installed on the server at the Jupiter Broadcasting Studio on the LAN.
And we sync the stuff that I really care about.
We don't sync everything because it's hundreds of gigs, but locally we've we actually that's what it will also archive.
But so I should probably back up the studio server now that I think about it, but we back up the cloud locally to anything that's that's not ephemeral and anything's not ephemeral.
We try to keep locally. And then my intention is to back that server up somewhere.
Alex's house back plays. I don't know what, but I've got the cloud part covered.
I don't necessarily have the local part fully covered right now because I ended up and it's sort of where I connected with what Kerry was saying is I just ended up with terabytes of data, terabytes.
And I don't know. I don't really know how to even get that offside over the wire.
It's so much data. Never underestimate.
I think the saying goes the bandwidth of a truck driving down a highway full of hard drives, get it on a hard drive and mail it to me.
That's the best way.
What you're saying is I should pack up the RV and drive a hard drive down to your place.
That makes the most sense, right?
You can if you want.
Three thousand dollar backup trip.
But, you know, so that's something we all struggle with.
But you remember when we went and saw Wendell, how he was implementing at his data center on his land, he was backing up his place was nuts.
Yeah, he was backing up his client's cloud data for them to his to his service, just in case their cloud providers had issues.
It's something you do kind of have to think about is when I'm building something, what is the risk to losing this?
Like, there's some things I have on the cloud that if they were if they were if they were lost, it'd be inconvenient, but we could regenerate from source material.
Not everything.
Yeah, it is. It is about evaluating the I don't want to say like opportunity cost or whatever, but everything has a cost.
And, you know, photos, for example, are irreplaceable.
You can't recreate those moments, videos, whatever.
But, you know, a PDF with an invoice of some work you did 10 years ago, maybe that.
OK, it might be nice to have it, but that's all just nice.
But, you know, the cost of a one time backup off site to a pendrive or something like that is so small compared to the amount, just the amount of time you're going to spend noodling after you've lost some data.
Whilst you reconstruct what was actually on that file system and remember, oh, yeah, that was on that box as well.
I lost that, too. And some of that stuff won't occur to you until years later.
That's very true. And it feels so you just feel like you've like somebody cut a hole out of you sometimes.
And I think that especially when it comes to the pictures, I have opted to leave on for the iPhone members of my family, our iCloud photo backup for everybody.
I even end up paying for like some sort of family storage plan.
So that way I knew because my mom is on there and, you know, my wife and I just wanted to know that everybody's photos were backed up, even though I also back them up.
My my phone, every picture I take goes off to next cloud in 100 percent quality.
But Google Photos also duplicates everything.
I'm off the Google Photos sauce because I'm using the iCloud photo, but it's like, you know, trading one one service for the other.
I mean, there are arguments to be made for Google's privacy policies versus Apple's, but I'm not sure I fully trust either, to be honest with you.
Yeah, yeah. I mean, I'm kind of gambling that Apple's are a little better and that they're not mining it for data.
But make no mistake, bro, Apple are mining you for your cash.
Right. No kidding. No kidding. And we have talked about Google Photos alternatives.
And it's not that I'm not going to implement one of those.
That's actually been my intention. But I still feel like I get some value out of just paying Apple to back that thing up because they are so valuable.
And that's really photos are it like pretty much everything else.
I'm comfortable how I back it up, although I know there's a couple of areas that I could probably do better.
I mean, do you feel like there's an area where if you were to audit your backups right now, you'd look at and go, oh, no, Alex, you got to fix it.
Yeah, I do. So the last couple of months have been a bit crazy for me.
My wife and I had our first daughter and she spent she came a little bit early and she spent a couple of months in the hospital.
So things have kind of been decaying whilst I've been there.
Congratulations. An official on show. Congratulations. Yay. Yay.
I've known this the first time you said anything on the show. So, yeah, I didn't want to go public until she was home just in case because anyway, she's home.
She's healthy. Everything's good with the world.
So, yeah, I purchased the Helios as to be my on site replication backup device.
And then when everything went down in January and Ella was born, I was in the middle of rebuilding my server at that point,
because that's when the whole GVTG thing started playing up and not working quite as I'd hoped.
So, you know, I was at the hospital most of the day, but I'd come back here for two or three hours just to unwind and just mess around with hardware and stuff.
And I never quite got to putting my backups back in place.
And it's one of those things you think, oh, I'll get to it. I'll get to it.
And then before you know it, a year later, you have a problem, you think, crap, I never got to it.
Yeah, I do have plans which we'll share with you soon as to what's going to replace the Helios in that situation.
But I'm tight lipped for now.
But we do have a we do have an upcoming segment on backups that will hopefully give you some ideas and inspiration.
Linode dot com slash SSH.
Go there to get one hundred dollars in Linode credit.
This could be the opportunity to try out Linode.
Linode dot com slash SSH.
You also support the show.
Linode is how we host in the cloud.
We've built all kinds of back end services for the show and for Jupiter broadcasting on Linode.
And I have a peace of mind knowing that Linode has great support.
So if I ever get stuck, well, I know they're going to take care of me.
In fact, they just received Linode, just received the People's Choice Stevie Award for favorite customer service in the computer services category.
That's huge.
You guys having great support has been one of the key things that people write into our show when they switch and tell us about Linode.
They have eleven data centers worldwide.
In 2016, they became their own ISP and have full control over their own network and have built out super fast connections to their worldwide data centers.
They have a brilliant cloud manager that makes it simple to use Linode.
If you're a brand new user or if you're a pro, you're going to love what they have.
Then there's the pricing Linode has dialed this in.
The value is nuts.
They have systems, of course, are like five dollars a month.
Right. But you can do different combinations depending on what you need.
Maybe you need a lot of memory or a lot of CPU.
Maybe you need GPU. Maybe you need several GPUs.
Maybe you need it all.
I got to be honest, we recently just decided to go all in on our matrix server because it's getting busier and busier.
And it's awesome what Linode lets you do.
And even when you need to upgrade an existing machine or clone a machine or snapshot, it's all just brilliant in their cloud manager.
I'm really impressed with the complexity that they can make seem so simple.
You know, like I'm I'm managing servers in data centers around the world and they just make it all seem so intuitive.
So I like that. And you can really get a sense of that when you try out our one hundred dollar credit.
One hundred dollars when you go to Linode dot com slash SSH, see what I've been talking about.
And of course, you support the show when you go there and you visit that URL and you use that and you sign up.
It tells Linode that our audience is supporting the show and that Linode should keep supporting us.
It helps us put these shows out for free.
It makes content like this possible.
It's the circle of podcasting.
Go to Linode dot com slash SSH.
Don't be using that stinking Linux unplugged Linode code.
Got to be using that self-hosted Linode code.
That's right. Live long.
Hashtag SSH, live long and and go to Linode dot com slash SSH.
My home assistant box password shamed me this week.
Did you get this? Yes.
Did you get it for the SSH add-in?
That's what I think I got it for.
Mine was node red, I think.
Oh, node red.
Alex, you're using a bad password with node red.
Well, maybe even home assistant itself.
Yeah, I don't know. I've been a bit busy.
I didn't actually read it.
I just saw the notification and dismissed it.
I was like, oh, whatever. I'll get to you later.
I dismissed it and then mine came back.
Mine is for the add-on core underscore SSH,
which uses secrets which have been detected as not secure.
Probably a lot of people in the audience are getting
this if they're on home assistant.
It's a new feature, quote unquote,
that has been integrated and frankly, probably a good one.
Yeah, but the Internet being the Internet, people are pissed.
I don't really get, oh, maybe I'm just becoming
a grumpy old man now I'm a dad and outrage culture is just,
I don't know, I'm just tired of it.
So there's a link in the show notes to a post by Troy Hunt,
who is an incredibly well-respected security researcher.
And he's the guy that is behind the website,
have I been pwned?
And this website is incredible.
You can tap in any password into their database
and it'll tell you that yes, this password
is out in the wild.
And as Troy puts it, if your password is in this list,
I've seen it clear text, which means that the bad guys
have seen it clear text.
So no matter your opinion on how secure you think it is,
I guarantee it's out there in the wild somewhere
and somebody knows what it is.
So don't use that password.
It's actually pretty clever for the home assistant
developers to build this in.
So the way it works is your passwords are hashed,
the first five characters of that hash,
so just the first five characters of a hash
of your password are then used to query
the have I been pwned website.
It then returns a result of possible password hashes
that match and then home assistant checks that list
against your hash locally.
All of that validation is happening on your box.
And what I find really interesting,
and Troy goes into full details in the article,
he basically goes through the home assistant forums thread
where people are bitching and moaning and whining
about this feature being turned on without their permission
to give you an idea of how, I don't wanna say stupid,
but honestly, when I was reading this Troy Hunt article,
I was like, yeah, this thread is stupid.
Someone was complaining it was sending out data
over their metered connection.
He then proceeded to say, it's a few bytes.
Like 36 kilobytes, yeah.
Yeah, we're talking five times smaller
than the average webpage load.
If you notice that on a metered connection,
then you've got problems.
Right, we're not really talking very much data.
And it's probably, although we don't know for sure,
only happening when you start up home assistant
or reload the config.
How do you feel about doing this on your local LAN?
I mean, I'm definitely guilty of reusing passwords
on the internet.
I'm certainly guilty of doing it on my LAN.
That seems to be the crux of everyone's argument
is my LAN, my rules, I have a safe, trusted environment,
and I don't wanna have to use good password hygiene.
I don't want long passwords that are unique.
And I can definitely relate.
They're sort of, when you do this for a living,
every now and then it's nice to be a little lazy.
Like, what's the saying about the guy who makes shoes,
his kids always have the worst shoes.
You know, like, cause you just get home,
it's the last thing you wanna do, right?
It's just the last thing.
So I do understand that.
However, this is where I fall down on it.
The home assistant community is kind of a special case
because they're playing around with IoT smart devices
that are network connected.
There's a higher threat level,
a broader threat attack surface, if you will.
And so I feel like you have to be a little more secure
when you are willing to ride the IoT train, you know?
Because the problem is any one of those individual devices
one day could become compromised,
and then that becomes a launching off point
where they can go after other devices on your LAN.
And we see it happen.
And to that point, Troy actually makes this point
in his article that LinkedIn,
I mean, we're talking a proper website here,
had a data breach because one of their developers,
Home Networks, had a weak SSH password,
which allowed people to pivot through
that developer's Home Network into LinkedIn servers
and compromise LinkedIn that way.
Yeah, they brute-forced his iMac.
And so, you know, I put myself in that developer's shoes
and I think, well, holy crap,
someone could pivot into Red Hat from here
and I wouldn't want that.
So I think to myself, okay, actually, Troy,
you've probably got a point here.
I do need to step up my game.
And he uses 1Password.
I think he's on the advisory board for 1Password.
But we talked last episode about Bitwarden.
And I really cannot emphasize enough,
you know, there are command line clients
and stuff like that that you can use
so you can put it in scripts
and do all sorts of fun stuff if you want to.
And I think that's gonna have to become
a 2021 rather late New Year's resolution for me
is to try and use that CLI stuff more on my LAN at least.
Yeah, good passwords, I think, matter
when we're kind of riding the cutting edge of technology.
Even if you're not intentionally exposing your LAN
to the internet, you never know
when some crazy thing could happen.
It's unlikely, but it could happen.
But really, you also never know
if one day somebody is gonna rock up
onto your Wi-Fi or something,
or somebody joins your LAN that you put on intentionally,
but they have some misconfiguration or infection.
So it's kind of like multiple layers
of protecting yourself is the best kind of protection.
And I think when you look at logins,
you could look at maybe not only unique passwords,
but when possible, also using keys to do SSH sign-ins.
So that way you have to have maybe a key and a password.
And that just takes it a little bit step further.
Like that LinkedIn developer,
if he had had a decent password or password and a key,
then the attackers would have never gotten onto his iMac
and then never gotten into LinkedIn.
And when the whole COVID lockdown thing started
and we had a lot more people all of a sudden
working from home, that was one of my first concerns is,
well, now all of these corporations are as insecure
as people's home networks are.
And you never know when that could be an issue as well.
I just think as much of a pain in the arse as it is,
there's enough tools and we know enough information now
that it's worth doing.
The only thing I would have changed
with how Home Assistant has implemented this
is give me an option to turn it off for a bit.
I'm not fixing it while I'm out here in the woods.
Simon sat checkbox for seven days or something.
Or until next update even, that could work too.
I do believe they're actually working on
making it opt in or opt out now.
So for what it's worth,
the outrage has had some effect on the feature.
But I mean, I think it's great.
I think anything that we can do,
and here's another point about the Home Assistant community
being a special case as well,
is a lot of people are coming to servers for the first time
because of Home Assistant.
They're running a box in their house for the first time
that's got SSH listening on something,
maybe for the first time ever.
And anything that Home Assistant can do
for those kind of newer users
that aren't enterprise grade buffoons like me
that just reminds them that, hold on,
if you're exposing your house to the internet
through Nebuchadnezzar, through WireGuard,
through whatever it might be, there is some risk.
And then when you couple that up
with some leaky washing machine
that's running an old firmware from eight years ago,
there are risks to these things.
And I for one applaud the Home Assistant project
for having the stones to put this in.
Yeah, and it definitely, I think,
will improve the community security overall,
which is a good thing for them.
And as they make this a commercial product one day,
because you know this has got to be
the direction this thing's going
when they try to make it a consumer product
and not just a more advanced prosumer
or enthusiast product.
Nerd product.
Go on, you should say it.
It's a nerd product right now.
But one day, maybe one day,
they're gonna try to sell it to average Joes
who have bought all these smart devices
and now they just need something
to make it all work together.
And buy the $100 Home Assistant appliance.
And you need these kind of things built in.
And they just recently had a run-in with add-ons
that were leaking information.
So I could see why this is an area they're investing into.
And I say good on them.
And I think it'll be a smooth transition.
There is also something worth looking into
is they're working with K-Aninemy,
which is a Cloudflare hosted service.
So Cloudflare's kind of proxying
some of these requests to anonymize them.
That's also made some people uncomfortable in all of this.
But I did a read through of the setup
and it actually, it seems like they've done
a really, really solid job here.
So we'll have a link in the show notes
at selfhosted.show slash 40
for the Cloudflare information on that.
If that has also perhaps gotten the hairs
on the back of your neck up a little bit,
it's worth reading about, we'll have information.
I'm super curious to hear what you all do
for your local LAN password situations.
Do you use a password manager?
Are you like me and reuse the same password on every box?
Let us know, selfhosted.show slash contact.
Datadog.com slash self-hosted.
One word, datadog.com slash self-hosted.
Go there, try it out and get a free t-shirt.
Datadog is gonna solve problems
and help you communicate them.
Analyze code level performance
across your entire environment
and troubleshoot issues faster with Datadog.
You see Datadog's continuous profiler
automatically collects information
from your production servers all the time.
So then when you're ready, when you need to,
you can quickly look and analyze all of the data
with minimal overhead and get finally
a unified picture of your entire environment.
Correlate code performance with server metrics
and other monitoring data in real time, beautiful dashboards.
Datadog.com slash self-hosted,
just to look at these dashboards.
And then they have a lot of tightly integrated additions,
add-ons, tracing, log management,
and that continuous profiler
that brings it all into one platform, that's Datadog.
And imagine getting yourself a visual dashboard
that you can use to communicate issues with your team.
Developers to sysadmins, sysadmins to executives.
Make plans, predict future performance, try it all out,
and take advantage of their machine learning and learning.
Datadog enables you to pinpoint
the root cause of an issue faster than ever.
So try their products out for free for 14 days
by visiting datadog.com slash self-hosted.
For a limited time, if you start a trial
and create one dashboard, you'll get some free swag,
a Datadog t-shirt.
And I miss swag, I miss event swag, I miss t-shirts.
So go get one, datadog.com slash self-hosted,
create an account, get that trial going and get a t-shirt,
and then begin visualizing your entire infrastructure.
Datadog.com slash self-hosted.
Listener Chris writes in,
I run a number of services from my home server
that are internet facing.
I understand that the smart best practice
is to minimize that as much as possible,
but some of these things I wanna access
whilst I'm away from the house.
Some of them are also used by family members,
and so it's unavoidable on some levels.
My question is this, how do I know if a service
is hardened enough to raw dog it out on the open internet?
Wow.
We're just gonna, let's let that sit for a second.
How do you know, how do you know if you can raw dog it?
Yeah, I mean, I feel this one, you know, Plex is one,
you know, Plex you kind of feel safe about,
but how do you know about some of the lesser used ones,
like Subsonic or something, right?
I think it's safe to assume that everything is porous.
Everything.
Yeah, I hate though that the answer
always is put it behind a VPN.
Why?
I mean, with WireGuard these days,
it's really the, the barrier to entry,
as long as you don't screw up your subnets like I did,
the barrier is pretty low.
But you have friends and family
that are using your Plex server
without connecting to WireGuard.
You know, like Plex is such a great example,
or JellyFan, because you do often wanna share with others.
That's true.
And I could see that being true with others as well.
Nextcloud he mentions in here,
but BabyBuddy, I'm not so sure about that.
You know, that starts to get a little more niche.
And I hate to be the guy that just says,
well, if it's big, you can use it publicly,
and if it's small, you should hide it.
But that's kind of a general rule of thumb that I follow.
You know, you try to figure how many eyes have been on it.
You know, another angle to consider
is security by obscurity.
Now, if you think that, you know,
you just have a random URL that you're using
to access this service,
and you've put it behind a reverse proxy,
and probably these days you're using Let's Encrypt
to generate a certificate for it,
so that you know that things are secure.
Well, I've got bad news for you, I'm afraid.
If you go to crt.sh and type in your domain name,
you'll see every single certificate
that's ever been issued by Let's Encrypt
for your domain name.
And so you think to yourself,
okay, well now my super secret string
that I came up with to hide this service
is now out in the public domain.
So really, it's not secret at all.
One thing you could do to kind of work around that
is use a wildcard certificate.
That would kind of sort of help,
because it wouldn't, you know, publish the actual string.
But it just goes to show to me that, you know,
security through obscurity is really not, it's an illusion.
Yeah, and I was gonna suggest throwing it out
on like a VPS, like Linode,
and run your software there for a bit
on the public internet and monitor the logs.
But you could run something for six months
and nobody nibbles at it,
and then on, you know, day one of seven months,
somebody nibbles on it.
It's tricky that way.
And so it really, the only way to have full peace of mind,
and that's what I've opted to do here in LadyJupes,
is just to have absolutely zero outside inbound.
That's the only way I've found
to be completely comfortable with it.
I don't necessarily always follow that rule myself,
because some services like mail servers,
web servers, media streaming servers,
they have to be public by their very nature.
So you have to hope that those just have more eyes
and that they get a little more attention
and that they've been a little more audited.
But remember, logging is your friend.
So if you ever suspect something's weird is happening,
go check your logs, see if you have weird logins,
see if you have somebody hitting your website all the time.
Use DataDog.
Yeah, yeah, use something that will,
you go through there and alert you.
That absolutely could be a good way to go.
It's a good question, though, listener Chris,
because I'm sure it's one that people struggle with.
So let us know what you out there would do,
selfhosted.show slash contact.
Now, we have Joseph who writes in.
He says, I have a bunch of those Tekken smart switches
flashed with Tasmoto, and they work great.
I have a need for smart switches
to replace my wall switches, though.
You know, for example, like my kids' closet lights,
which are always left on.
I would also love to replace the controllers
on our ceiling fans with smart devices,
something that would toggle the light on and off,
and also set the fan to high, medium, or low,
or even off completely.
My preference would be for something I can self-host,
non-cloud connected, open source software.
Are there any devices which would actually fill this need
or similar to the way the Tekken smart plugs do?
What are your thoughts?
Well, this is an easy question.
The Shelly devices are exactly what you're looking for,
and I think we've talked about them on a previous episode,
but just to recap,
they're about the size of an Oreo cookie,
and they go inside the light box behind the switch.
So you don't change the switch itself,
but this little cookie-sized box has a relay inside it.
You need to do a little bit of wiring.
So, you know, mains voltage, be careful,
or get an electrician if you're not comfortable.
They make a few products.
So they make a 2.5, which will let you do
up to two switches in the same box.
They make a single unit as well,
and they make a bunch of other stuff
that does like rolling shutters for garage doors
and all sorts of stuff.
So go to Shelly.cloud and check out their stuff
if you're interested,
but it's exactly what you're looking for,
and you can put TAS motor on them.
So Mahendra writes in,
in the latest episode,
you suggest file run for a simple file browser.
I wanted to suggest another minimalist alternative.
It's very light with no database required
at github.com slash file browser slash file browser.
God, that rolls off the tongue, doesn't it?
It's very simple, easy to remember.
Yeah, it is just a web-based file browser
that sits on top of a directory.
Each user gets their own directory,
and it's just a standalone app.
Pretty simple.
I like it.
Even easier than the one we had talked about before.
So I'm gonna think I'm gonna grab this and try it out.
It is nice.
Yeah, I tried it out before the show,
and I kinda wish I hadn't bothered with file run now.
This is, I think, my new standard kind of
throw it up and forget about it remote access software.
So yeah, great job.
Thanks for writing in, Mahendra.
Now I've mentioned Chowdown a couple of times
on the show before as a self-hosted recipe app.
I still use it.
I still love it.
It stores all of my recipes in clear text files on disk,
but there are some alternatives,
and we've had a couple of listeners write in,
and one of them is called Tandoor Recipes.
What do you think of this one, Chris?
It looks really good.
This, if anything, would probably get me
to start doing something like this,
because it has a planning aspect,
which is useful for a guy like me.
I can do a little meal planning,
but also has a sharing feature,
and it's all on a progressive web app,
which means my wife and I could share it on our phones,
which I think would be really nice.
And then the other thing I would need is,
and it does support importing from Chowdown, is import,
and it has Chowdown import
as well as Nextcloud, Cookbook import,
Mealy, Paprika, Saffron,
and a couple of others it can import from.
I think it's easy to try out.
Now we have mentioned this one previously,
because it goes by the name vabeen1111 slash recipes
on GitHub.
That's the repo it's in.
I think the Tandoor name must be new.
I don't know how old exactly it is.
Yeah, it is a new release too,
so that might be maybe they did a name change.
But they are using MKDocs for their documentation,
so I've got to give them a plus point for that.
Yeah, it says here that they're happy to announce
they've released a new version
which gives the application its well-deserved name
and logo, Tandoor recipes.
So there you go.
It runs out of a Docker container.
It will also run on Unraid, Synology, Kubernetes.
You can do it manually as well if you want to.
There's a bunch of interesting stuff
about syncing and storage in their documentation.
So it's going to take a lot for me to throw away Chowdown,
because I do genuinely really like it,
and I've modified the CSS so I've got some fuzzy search.
You know how I love my fuzzy search.
Oh, that's cool.
You know, I've customized Chowdown for my own needs,
but then maybe the grass is greener.
Maybe I should try this one out.
I mean, it does have the import functionality.
Downside though is it needs a Postgres database,
and I've already got like,
it feels like a dozen different database containers running.
Do I need another one?
That is a constant internal battle,
and sometimes I'm just down to, ah, who cares?
Just run a whole bunch.
You've got the resources.
And other times, like the sysadmin in me
is just not having it.
You can't run three copies of Postgres.
That doesn't make any sense.
They're different versions.
They have different security issues, different features.
What are you doing?
And it's a recipes app at the end of the day.
Do you know what I mean?
Just having the files in clear text on disk
feels more future-proof to me.
So if this person loses interest
in maintaining this particular app for whatever reason,
I'm not up the creek without a paddle, so to speak.
That I think is a great feature of Chowdown.
That kind of clear text backend gives me peace of mind.
That's just a peace of mind for that kind of stuff.
And if Chowdown stops working for some reason,
I can just pull it up in any text editor
and it's still readable.
Yeah, it's almost as good as writing them down
on an index card.
You know, you laugh at that,
but I'm pretty sure if I asked my mom
to go and find me a recipe for something,
she would find it in less time than it takes me to fix.
Oh, Chowdown's not working?
Okay, well, let me just SSH in and do this, do that,
do the other.
And before you know it, 10 minutes later,
you've forgotten that you're actually looking for a recipe
and then you go and order pizza instead, so.
Yeah, and meanwhile, she's got the index card ready to go.
It's very true.
There's something to that.
A reminder, you can find our sponsor,
our Cloud Guru on social media.
They're just slash the Cloud Guru.
It's really easy, like on Twitter, Facebook, YouTube,
pretty much all the social media platforms,
just slash a Cloud Guru.
Also, our members, thank you to our members,
selfhosted.show slash SRE, you support the show.
You become our site reliability engineers,
you get a limited ad feed and extra content,
the post show, selfhosted.show slash SRE,
if you'd like to support the show and become a member.
My wife's CAM3 came in this week,
so we're gonna have a little chat about that today.
Yes, that's gonna be the post show.
I ordered a few of them, so I got thoughts.
Of course you did.
So you can go to selfhosted.show slash contact,
and that's the place to go to get in touch with us.
You can find me on Twitter at ironicbadger.
Oh, I'm there as well at Chris Elias,
and the show is at selfhostedshow.
On Discord, I'm at AlexKTZ.
So thanks very much for listening, everybody.
That was selfhosted.show slash 40.