Well, we've got a special interview for episode 45 today.
We're gonna have our guest coming up in just a moment.
So I wanna thank our sponsor, A Cloud Guru.
They are the leader in learning for the cloud,
Linux and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses and thousands of hands-on labs.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at acloudguru.com.
So today, instead of a bunch of different segments,
we're really kind of just doing one thing, Alex?
We are indeed.
Yes, we've got Paulus who is the founder
of Home Assistant on the episode today.
And Chris and I talked to him about all sorts of different subjects
from how Home Assistant's becoming more turnkey ready
through to the ESP Home acquisition.
And there's a couple of interesting tip bits
about the future in there as well.
Well, I don't know if you remember,
but you and I chatted back in 2017
on a Linux action show special about Home Assistant
what feels like a hundred years ago now.
Yeah, no, I do remember.
Well, I remember it was somebody from Jupiter broadcasting.
I didn't realize it was you.
Yeah, and man, have things come a long way.
So thank you for joining us to catch us up on stuff.
I am the happy owner of a Home Assistant Blue device.
Love it.
Awesome.
I put the order in during the live stream,
so I got it fairly early.
And I got to say, months into it,
the performance holds up compared to the Raspberry Pi 4.
I think it is outperforming the Raspberry.
I mean, it's a beast.
The M2 is just like, it's amazing.
So are there any plans for more expansions in that direction?
Is that going to be a focus going forward?
Because it really seems like a pretty sweet integration.
Yeah, so there are definitely plans.
Nothing to announce just yet.
We realized with the M2 Plus,
like we only made the case, right?
So it's just a board.
And when people think of home automation,
they obviously think of like ZigBee or Z-Wave or Chip
or Matter, whatever it's going to be called.
And so that's something that we want to address.
We want to include that as well.
And I think the Home Assistant Blue
was really like the ultimate race car,
but it was not very accessible in that the price was not...
The price was pretty steep for a device
that also you needed to add like a ZigBee stick
and these kind of things.
So I think we are definitely going to look into something
as a successor.
Nothing to announce just yet,
but it will also be hopefully lower priced
and more capable out of the gate to be used for smart home.
Yeah, I can absolutely see how that would be way simpler
for new users to get into the space as well.
Yeah, and I think when we look at these things,
we don't just want to create a box that competes
with like Philips Hue or anything, right?
Like we're Home Assistant,
so it needs to be kind of hackable, playful, open.
Like it just needs just like the Odroid N2 Plus
or the Home Assistant Blue.
I mean, you can flash anything on it that you want, right?
We're not interested in building a lockdown box
that will just keep the users out.
That is completely understandable,
especially now having used one.
But so what about guys like me
who will always have a use case
where I'm going to want to run it on a server?
Like here at the studio,
we have a server that's doing like 100 other things.
And so running Home Assistant in a container
is perfect for the use cases
of just controlling studio lights.
And we're not really using any integrations
and stuff like that.
How do you see that user base being addressed in the future?
Right now, we have four installation types.
We have the Home Assistant operating system.
We have the Home Assistant supervised,
the Home Assistant container,
and then Home Assistant core,
which is just like running it in Python yourself.
And all the other three installation approaches
all rely on containers.
And so they all use the same image.
So it's like the core technologies are all very similar.
Yeah, it's all the same thing, really.
The only one that's different is core
because you maintain your own Python virtual environment.
The other three are all Docker based.
So it's all the same thing.
So those four installation types
are pretty much set in stone right now.
I think that if you, in your studio,
you can either run the container
or you can run a virtual machine
with a Home Assistant operating system.
The benefit, of course, of the virtual machine
is that you have one-click updates of Home Assistant.
Well, with the container,
it really depends on your container management software,
which can be Unrate or Portainer or Synology or whatever.
That software then has to do the update of the container.
I think that's the only real difference.
In the end, all of these containers,
they're all run Alpine, they run Python,
and we maintain that, right?
So we have a big wheel server.
We make sure that all the dependencies work and compiled
and are just up to date and running.
And that's just a big benefit as a user.
And I think that moving forward,
you just wanna run Home Assistant container,
that will be possible.
I see.
So it's not like it's ever gonna go away,
but you just feel like there's a lot of benefits
to Home Assistant managing the entire stack
because of all of the interdependencies.
Yeah, I mean, there's just so many moving parts.
I think that if you look at our requirements.txt,
which is where we define the Python dependencies,
it's like over a thousand, right?
Because each integration comes with its own Python library,
which is a requirement we made ourselves.
So it's obviously our own guidelines.
But the reason we always do this is that
we want integrations to rely on an SDK.
So an SDK is a Python package at the standalone
that translates the protocol into Python objects.
And that way, other Python projects,
not just Home Assistant, can also use this package, right?
So we don't want protocol-specific information
inside Home Assistant because we wanna make sure
that other Python-based home automation systems
or just one-off scripts can use these protocols as well.
Wow, so it kind of sounds like to me
what you guys did as a team as you looked at the,
kind of, if you will, the whole problem and you said,
quite frankly, it is easier for us as a team
to just do a whole OS than say,
you must have considered, well, bless Ubuntu LTS
as the supported Home Assistant platform.
And anything else is DIY, but if you want our official way
or our official image, it's all Ubuntu-based.
Yeah, but the problem with that is that
your virtual environment that runs Python
is going to be, has to be maintained as well.
So, I mean, this is, of course, how Home Assistant started.
It was just a Python application
that we distributed through PyPI.
Sure.
And people would run into, like, they would do pip upgrades.
And then, of course, some people will upgrade
from the last release.
Some people will update from, like, six releases ago.
And people got stuck all the time.
And the way it works with our Docker containers
is that we install all the Python dependencies
fresh in each container.
And so, when you update your container,
all your old dependencies are thrown away.
We make sure you have the latest and greatest
and the dependencies all work together.
And that way, it just works.
Yeah, that makes sense.
I could see how that also is just much more manageable
and supportable by you guys as well.
And I got to say, you know, on the blue,
it's working really great.
I kind of am, I'm a user of both use cases,
just the core version and the whole OS stack.
And I do really like the snapshots.
I feel like the more recent updates that have also set it
so you can have a snapshot right before you upgrade
is brilliant.
All that kind of stuff just keeps getting better.
Yeah.
And I think, you know, the features are really driven.
You know, we look at the way people use Home Assistant
and we look at the issues we see on our forums
and our Discord.
And then we just ask ourselves, like, why is this?
What can we do to make it easier and better?
And we just constantly try to, like, kind of tackle this.
And, you know, we're really focused on making
Home Assistant easier to use while still also,
you know, making sure that our power users,
of course, can do their things.
And, you know, it's been really paying off.
I think that, like, we launched Home Assistant analytics,
like, a month ago, two months ago already, right?
And I think, like, around, we didn't do much promo,
but, like, 45,000 people have opted in.
And you can actually see our operating system
is, like, 65% of our users.
Oh, okay.
I mean, that was pretty unexpected.
Like, we knew it was high.
I think, you know, internally, we were like,
ah, that's probably, like, 50%.
But it's actually 65%.
And I also understand it because it's just convenience, right?
Like, if you want to be a system administrator at home,
you can be, of course.
But if you want to be, like, automating your home,
you can be that, too.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on your new account,
and you support the self-hosted podcast.
Linode is my playground to learn,
and it can be yours, too, without $100 credit.
And sure, maybe, ultimately,
you decide to self-host something on your LAN.
But every now and then, and that's more and more these days,
there's a job that's really perfect out in the cloud
on a service provider you can trust,
and you have full control.
That's one of the things I like about Linode
is unlike entry-level hosting services,
they don't try to lock you into their platform with gimmicks.
Linode gives you full back-end access
to customize and control your server to fit your needs.
And their DNS manager allows you
to easily switch your domain to your new server.
You can manage SSL certificates with breeze
and deploy applications with a single click
or build the server up from scratch if you want.
If you need a simple personal server for a blog or portfolio
or maybe a game server,
in fact, they make that really straightforward.
Or maybe you want to set yourself up a next cloud server
and sync your own files.
Whatever the scale of your task or your business,
or even when your app goes viral,
Linode is going to reliably serve to millions of users.
It can be just you and your friends and family,
or it can be millions of users.
And we've really put it to the test here
at Jupiter Broadcasting.
And like I say, it really is a fantastic playground
to learn as well.
And that $100 credit means you can play around
with all kinds of different hardware
and configuration stacks,
which has been a massive advantage for me.
Before I deploy something in production,
I'll sometimes spin up a couple of versions of it
on different stacks.
Maybe this one's on NGINX and this one's on Apache.
Maybe this one's on Ubuntu, maybe this one's on CentOS.
I'll try them out and test them right there.
And then I'll just keep the winner and destroy the others.
That kind of flexibility and not having to mess around
with some slow VM software on my laptop
to test that stuff out, it's just brilliant.
And then of course, there's the perk as a listener
of supporting this here podcast too.
And we use our S3 compatible object storage
as the backend storage for our next cloud,
which means we're not constantly managing disk space
all the time.
They've really got this stuff dialed in
because they've been doing it since 2003.
So I want you to go try it.
So go to linode.com slash SSH.
Go there, get that $100 in credit and support the show.
linode.com slash SSH.
Yeah, so I mean, Home Assistant's been headed down
the more turnkey route for quite a while now.
And I think hasOS is, or am I calling it the right thing?
I'm still confused by the name change.
It's been headed down the turnkey route for quite a while.
What else do you have planned in that space?
I mean, there's been a lot of work
around automations recently,
as well as some other aspects of the experience.
So I think that our goal really like in the longer term
is that we wanna make sure that a lot of people have access
to having like great home automation at home
that focuses on local control and privacy.
And so having Home Assistant be accessible
is important to us, but for example,
we've also, the company behind Home Assistant,
my company Nabucasa, we've also recently acquired ESPHome.
ESPHome is a firmware for ESP devices that runs on a,
which is a firmware that can run on a lot of products
that come from China, like light switches, lights.
And with ESPHome, we are also trying to make it easier
for people to get access to devices that work locally
and work private and work with Home Assistant.
So yeah, our long-term goal is really just to make it
accessible to everybody.
And I think that launching hardware
was a really obvious step.
I feel that for a long time,
I didn't wanna go down that route because logistics,
just like all that stuff.
But at the end of the day, we were looking at it
and we were like, we've been working on making it
so much easier to use.
But then the first step of instructions is,
download Azure, download this image
and flash it to an SD card.
And most people don't even know those words.
Yeah, it's true.
That has me thinking about something like,
you know, the made for iPhone program?
Yeah.
It makes me think with ESPHome in particular,
I know it's aimed primarily at hackers
and people that wanna build and make and solder
and all that kind of stuff.
But it's got me thinking, it's acquisition of ESPHome,
why isn't there a made for Home Assistant program?
Well, I think that the main thing about making it
a made for Home Assistant,
is that we don't have an API ourselves, right?
Like we always integrate with the other products.
I did consider like starting one
or like having like at least some certification
and more official certification,
but we see that there's not much interest in it
in a way that like, you know,
manufacturers will come to us and be like,
well, what's your API, we'll integrate.
And I'm always like, no, that's not what we want.
We want you to create an open API.
We will integrate with it,
but other projects should also be able to allow
to be integrated with it.
And then we see a lot of companies be like,
ah, that's not in our interest.
Or, you know, we were talking to Ring
because, you know, they wanted to say like,
hey, can we get like a partnership going?
And then we looked at it and the first step is sign NDA
to make sure that you don't expose their APIs.
And like, we're open source, this is not gonna happen.
And the same thing happened to us with Sonos,
who also was like, yeah, we wanna keep it to partners only.
It's like, ah, okay, that doesn't work.
Oh, that's super frustrating to hear that kind of stuff
because some of those companies you listed,
you know, Ring and Sonos,
they're big players in this space.
And that's kind of frustrating to hear
that they're not compatible with an open source ethos yet.
Well, their partnerships are not,
but I mean, we still integrate with them, right?
It's just less official because they still have APIs
and people have been able to figure out those APIs.
And so we will still integrate with them.
It's just, if you are a partner,
they will make sure it stays working
or they will give you a heads up so you can adjust.
And that's something we don't have, right?
So we sometimes get caught off guard,
like some brand will change an API,
Home Assistant stops working,
we have to update our code, ship a hotfix
and it will work again.
Which leads me nicely into my next question,
which is about the velocity of change.
Now, I've been using Home Assistant
for a couple of years myself,
so I've been through quite a few breaking config changes
over that time.
I feel like, and this is just anecdotal personal experience,
that that experience has gotten better,
that the pace of change hasn't decreased,
but the amount of changes that break stuff,
that has decreased significantly from my perspective.
What things are you doing from a Home Assistant side
to make that velocity of change more easy for people to handle?
So the biggest change there, and this is actually,
it started out with a policy change,
and then it resulted also in code changes.
So there's this thing called Convid flow.
So through the UI, you can set up an integration.
And what we said is that this is going to be mandatory
moving forward.
So it used to be that you could go into YAML,
and then for example, let's say for your Philips Ubridge,
you would say, this is the IP address.
And then, well, Philips used maybe a bad example,
because you would still have to press a button in the UI
and it was storing some extra data.
But for some things you have to like,
here's the username, here's the password,
username, password, and IP address of a device
on my network.
But then when the IP address would change,
Home Assistant wouldn't work.
And Home Assistant couldn't find the new IP address
because you had it hard coded in your configuration files,
and we're not changing your configuration files.
And so those cases, we really had to handle through UI.
We had to like say, hey, this is a temporary IP address,
but we still have an identifier.
So if your Chromecast changes IP address,
we can still find it and we will set it up again,
or your Shelly or whatever you have.
And then we realized that,
oh, actually a lot of our breaking changes
is because people are adding support
to having to like go from one device,
support multiple devices, or these kinds of things.
And so when we go for a config flow,
Home Assistant is responsible for how it is written to disk.
So Home Assistant knows exactly the configuration format.
And if we have to change it,
because we are going to support multiple devices,
we can actually migrate that data
because we own how it is stored.
If it is a configuration file,
and this is kind of silly,
but we kind of programmed our way
into like a corner we can get out of.
Because if you look at configuration.yaml,
we have all these advanced structures
to break up your configuration files.
There's packages with includes,
include their names, include their list,
and there's all these different types.
And what that means is that Home Assistant
cannot go update your configuration file anymore
because it doesn't know where your configuration file is.
We would have to reverse track all your includes,
and then we need to find like a yaml writer
that respects your comments
and respects your indentations exactly how it was.
And it's just, it's impossible.
I think safe mode was a really good invention.
Well, not invention, idea, right?
Where Home Assistant still starts
and then just goes back to a safe mode.
Yeah, so safe mode was really driven by the blue, right?
So we had the blue in mind
and we were like, okay, we're gonna have a box.
We're gonna sell this people,
like it will actually allow more people to use Home Assistant
that previously were not using Home Assistant.
So how can we make sure that they can always boot
and always have a UI?
That shows you just how long it takes
to develop a product
because they were released a long time apart,
those two things.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, it took us a year to make that case for the blue.
So it's, I mean, a pandemic happened
and like what other stuff,
but yeah, it took us a year on all to just get a case.
So I hope our next product will not take that long
at least, I mean, we'll see, but yeah.
Yeah, it is very tricky.
It's fascinating though how thinking about
from a developer perspective,
how to ship something for an end user,
we got a feature like that.
I think that's kind of telling how created that use case.
So I'm curious, let's shift gears to the personal side.
If you do have some self-hosted services,
what are you running on your LAN
and roughly how much storage do you have
on this quote unquote LAN?
So I run Unrate at home
and I made a server that must've been like
six, seven, eight years ago or something.
Like now it's six years.
It's getting really old.
It's like a core I5 still.
And I think it takes up way too much power
compared to what it does.
You know, and I chose Unrate
because this was during the beta phase of Unrate.
So beta phase of Unrate 5.
And Unrate 5 was where they introduced the Docker containers.
So that was like almost kind of right away,
I kind of shifted into like this perfect world
of having all these containers at home.
And so I'm actually still the maintainer
of the Home Assistant core templates for Unrate.
Love that.
So that's how I used to run Home Assistant for a long time.
I was like, I just have my container at home.
And then I have like, I have Plex running
and some other stuff.
And then you had to go and make it a whole OS.
No, I'm kidding.
Yeah, I hear Plex in there.
Interesting.
What's that set up like?
I mean, so I mainly use Plex
because there's a bunch of that.
So I'm from the Netherlands,
but I live in the United States.
And there's a bunch of content from the Netherlands
that is geo-blocked.
And so I cannot access it in the United States.
So I have to jump on a VPN
and download either stuff from YouTube
or whatever.
And then I also don't want my son
to be on YouTube unsupervised.
So that's also why I pull in some videos.
And then I'll just have a Plex account for my son
and he can kind of just browse through it.
I do that same thing for my kids.
Yep, exactly.
It's a great use case for Plex.
Well, that's it.
And then how much storage roughly would you estimate?
I think it's like eight terabytes.
I just got some smart errors the other day.
Two months ago, some CRC smart check error.
So I just...
But then, I mean, with Unrate,
you have this parity disk.
Your parity disk needs to be the same size
or bigger than your biggest disk.
And so my biggest disk were like four terabytes.
And so it's like, wow,
I should really update to like eight terabyte disks.
And so I only updated my parity disk now.
And that took like more than a week, right?
Because you have to like pre-clear it
and all that stuff.
Yeah.
And then I still have one disk
that is like on riser FS.
And I think they stopped using riser FS
and they're using something else.
And I was looking into, should I migrate this?
And then I was like, no, this is just like, no.
It's too much.
It still kind of works.
And so I actually only updated the parity disk.
And then I've...
The old parity disk I installed now as in my rate
because there's only a couple of errors.
And then I read online that like,
ah, it's okay if you have a couple of errors.
And that was already after I did my whole process.
But of course, I mean...
That just means it's time to start shopping.
Yeah.
Exactly. Yes.
I'm waiting for some like deals, right?
Because those disks are expensive.
I was like, I use the Western Digital Red, I think.
Are you familiar with shucking drives?
Is that of any interest to you?
What is that?
So you buy a USB hard drive from Amazon
or Best Buy or something.
This is Alex's favorite thing to do.
I'll show you.
I've literally got one over here.
It's just like it sounds.
You grab the disk off Amazon
and you shuck it out of the case.
I paid for this Iron Wolf NAS Pro $170 for a 10 terabyte drive.
Oh, wow.
And all I had to do to get this was buy a USB enclosure drive
and pop it out the USB enclosure.
It took five minutes and it's a normal SATA drive.
There's nothing special about it once you get it out of the case.
If you look just on eBay, just for this drive on its own,
I could sell this thing for $350.
In fact, why don't I do that?
There you go.
You got to pay for that solar setup somehow.
Yeah.
So the shucking technique is Alex's favorite.
Sometimes it requires a little more work than that,
but it is a great way to get drives at a great price.
Oh, that's a good tip.
I heard you talking about solar, Alex.
Yeah.
We're actually working.
We have an intern at Home Assistant.
And well, he actually is an intern at Nabucasa,
but he's working on Home Assistant stuff.
And his focus right now is create a solution.
How do we use Home Assistant to give the user insight
into the energy usage and allow optimizing it?
So, of course, Home Assistant has been always very focused on home control,
home automation, and it's been our strength.
History has not been our strength that much, right?
Our database has been clunky and it's pretty shitty.
So, I mean, we're actually changing this right now.
So in the next release, it's going to be what we call statistics.
And it's going to be a new table in our database.
And it will take a snapshot every hour.
It will analyze certain entities that you have.
Right now, it's temperature and energy.
We calculate the min, the max, the mean, the sum, all that stuff.
And then the goal is to start generating dashboards on your energy usage
and to show predictions and show comparing current period,
current week to last week, these kind of things.
Now, that second part is not going to be in the next release,
but we're already going to start generating statistics in the next release.
Sounds fantastic.
And I'll tell you, the solar company that's doing my install,
it's a local one in North Carolina.
They want to charge me $800 for energy monitoring.
So I'm using the, I think SolarEdge is the manufacturer of the panels.
And they have a cloud API, which Home Assistant can poll every 15 minutes,
I think, to get the data.
But I'm like, it's in my house.
Why do you need to go to the cloud to get this stuff?
So I'm thinking I might get one of these Shelly energy monitors.
And then with everything you've just said, I think I might be in business.
No kidding, right?
You know, Paul, I know too, I got to speak up for the van lifers out there.
The Victron Venus system speaks MQTT.
And so I know there's guys out there that are pulling that information
into their Home Assistant setup as well.
Yeah.
And so we're really been looking at, or we have, I don't know if you,
we tweeted it from the class tweeted like two weeks ago, I think.
But he has already has a lot of paper mockups.
And he's been like playing.
I think he has interviewed like 20 different people.
And he's been really focusing on, can we kind of gamify it?
Where like, for example, if you know your yesterday's usage
and we show your today's usage, can we tell you like, hey, tone it down a little?
Because otherwise you're going to use more than like yesterday.
I've actually had an idea.
A friend of mine, I've just had my first kid, by the way.
A friend of mine was telling me they were doing that,
automating nap time, a light in the nursery with Home Assistant.
You know, certain times if the light bulb's green,
then the kids are allowed out of the room.
And if it's red, they're not.
I'm thinking we could play games with colored light bulbs
and children at this point.
That's where my brain's going.
Oh, I do it.
I do it.
That's, you know, I train my kids with a series of light changes at night for bedtime
and then noisemakers come on throughout the rig.
It's real.
It's brilliant.
I can't wait to play with that.
And gamifying, it feels like that's an idea that could be applied to a lot of things.
As somebody who uses Home Assistant to manage an off-grid setup,
I would love something around energy history
and a gamification system that would encourage the family to maybe conserve energy.
Because one of the things I did that really encouraged family adoption was
we got a fire tablet and we just put Home Assistant up on it all the time.
It's on the wall and it's always there so the kids can see what's going on.
And once I did that, it like it clicked for everybody.
So to get something up on that screen would, man,
they just take my off-grid game to like the next level.
Yeah, I think honestly just getting people inside in it is like step one.
Then all of a sudden they start to realize it's like,
oh, I can actually, you know, we can generate more energy than we use today.
Let's go for it, right?
I think that's going to be fun.
So my last question, I think, before we let you go is about automations.
This kind of goes back to the turnkey aspect, I suppose, and simplification.
There's been a lot of work around making the YAML automation interface
built into Home Assistant easier.
But I always find myself for the more complex things reaching for Node-RED.
And I wondered how you felt about people like me doing that.
Do you want us to all be using YAML all the time or do you not really care?
I don't really care.
In fact, I think it's great that our APIs are so generous that you can get anything out
that you can actually build Node-RED and do a full automation engine
without being part of the Home Assistant integrations.
And I think that, you know, each has their own.
And I think because Node-RED exists, we don't have to make a lot of things ourselves, right?
A lot of feature requests that would normally come to us are now,
ah, I will just use Node-RED.
And I just saw a pull request, I guess it's been like one and a half months ago,
from the maintainer of the Node-RED Home Assistant integration,
who makes the nodes for Node-RED.
And I think he's been working on getting the triggers from the Home Assistant automation
YAML into Node-RED as well.
So we have a lot of triggers that are not very accessible yet,
a lot of advanced triggers that are not accessible in Node-RED yet.
But that would allow Node-RED to use anything that a normal YAML automation can,
would be possible inside Node-RED, which I think is really cool because
all of a sudden it makes Node-RED a lot more powerful or any other automation engine.
And, you know, in the end, one way or the other, if you have like local control,
local data, we succeed.
Yeah, I totally agree.
And I think my number of input booleans could use some spring cleaning.
So I'm happy to hear that.
ProvadoVPN.com slash SSH.
That's P-R-I-V-A-D-O-V-P-N.com slash SSH.
Go there to try out Provado for free and of course support the show.
ProvadoVPN is a zero log VPN.
That means there's no records of your activity.
We looked into this for you guys and we wouldn't feature them unless it was this way.
And even in the event of a legitimate authority requesting logs associated with your activity
when connected to Provado, they got nothing to give.
And even better, they're backed by Swiss privacy laws.
In addition to having that strict zero log policy, ProvadoVPN is based in Switzerland.
That means you're protected by the absolute strongest consumer privacy laws
in the world.
And Provado has the tech where it matters.
They own and operate their own data centers and fiber lines.
And the network is composed of hundreds of servers physically located in 45 countries
and 58 cities around the world.
What that means for you is you can connect in seconds and no matter what server you choose,
you're going to get incredibly fast speeds every time you connect.
ProvadoVPN's network was built from the ground up and fully optimized for lightning fast speed.
So visit ProvadoVPN.com.ssh and try it out right now for free.
The free account provides the same service level and unlimited speeds as the premium version,
as well as 10 gigabytes a month of data transfer and access to the top 12 servers for one device.
And all ProvadoVPN users get access to their dedicated team of customer support.
It's 24 seven.
And they also have an unlimited plan with hundreds of servers,
P2P traffic support and more.
So go check it all out at ProvadoVPN.com.ssh.
So I mean, if you buy a Chromecast or whatever,
then sometimes you have to like connect to an access point and then like your phone.
And then sometimes it crashes and you're like lost and you don't know how to set up the Wi-Fi.
So we're building a Bluetooth spec that is going to be built into ESP home.
It's going to be built into the Home Assistant apps.
So if you buy it, well, I mean, if eventually we hope you're going to be
able to buy ESP home products.
But if you build an ESP home product and you give it to your friend,
they will just be able to go on with Bluetooth.
And we even have a web Bluetooth SDK, so you can use like a Chrome browser
to actually just set it up.
Oh, that is cool.
Yeah, right.
And I mean, I think I really want like, you know, they're like on tindy.
People are selling their creations.
I just want like more of that because those products are way cooler.
Like, it's just like, you know, we had the tech reader last year
and there's like actually for the energy meters in the Netherlands,
they actually have a protocol called P1.
And we're going to have an ESP home based device somebody's building
that like, you know, people can just plug it in and boom,
all the energy data is available in Home Assistant.
So I'm sure you do.
But do you realize just how perfectly positioned you are to uniquely so to do this?
No, no, definitely, definitely.
It's because, you know, ESP home, like we acquired it.
Maybe because like the original founder was like burned out and,
but he was still getting like all these donations, right?
So we couldn't really say, hey, we're going to hire somebody full time to make this great.
So we acquired it from him.
We have now Jesse working on a full time and like, you know, just we keep,
you know, pumping out cool stuff.
Yeah, a full time employee is going to, you know, they've got some time to fill.
You know, it's, yeah, well, the thing is, because we're so big, like, you know,
we are 13 people full time now.
And yeah, thanks.
Lucky 13.
But the thing is, they work all over the place, right?
Like we have the operating system guy, we have the supervisor people,
we have the front end people.
And so we're actually very thinly spread because there's just so much happening.
For sure.
Yeah, yeah, it's both a lot of people from when you started at one,
but it's also not a lot of people for the scope of work there is out there.
Exactly.
Can you even imagine how many people, you know, a commercial entity,
let's just hypothetically say you are owned by EA or some,
some massive conglomerate like that, right?
How many people would they employ to write a piece of software like Home Assistant?
And it's just, to me, that speaks to the power of open source, right?
I mean, we definitely couldn't, we couldn't have things in the world like Home Assistant
without open source.
So, no, I think so.
I mean, there's just, you know, we, if you, we get people from like all over the place
that are brilliant programmers, but they have their day jobs.
And like, you know, it's, it's funny.
We have a couple of people.
One is a CEO of a company.
The other is like a director of software engineering.
So he's like a manager and like, they just don't get to code at work anymore, right?
So they come home and they're like, well, yeah, absolutely.
I agree.
And also those sorts of people who have had a lot of training in programming and stuff
like that in the past.
They've got a lot that they can bring to the table, but their motivation might be sporadic
and, you know, it's not really suitable to do a full-time job that way, but absolutely
can contribute, you know, a couple of weeks worth of evenings of your brain to an open
source project.
Well, that, I mean, that's how our core was originally all on threads and like we had
like deadlocks all the time.
And then somebody came along who was, who works in Mozilla and he had a lot of Python
experience.
He made like pylons in the past and yeah, he, he rewrote our core to async and that's
what we still run today.
And that's why we're so fast.
So that's just a random guy that came along.
You know what else I love as well about the number of people you've just shared work
from Nebuchadnezzar is the fact that that means that somebody like a Mozilla isn't
needed to come out and buy you out to keep you sustainable.
It's, it's a self-sustaining funding model you've created here.
I think that's great too.
No, it's been really great.
I think, you know, we have no investors and no loans and these kind of stuff because it
misaligns incentives, right?
Just, you know, they want like return on investment.
Yeah.
I mean, it's, it's, it's working great so far.
I mean, I expect as the pandemic like wheeze off that maybe people are spending less time
at home, maybe spending less time on home assistance, who knows?
But they might need remote access.
That's you know, I mean, I, I happily, happily pay that because I think it's a, not only
is it a fantastic service and I like how you are implementing it, but I also appreciate
sort of the virtuous cycle of it incentivizes the company to make home assistance better,
which just continues to drive more value to my subscription.
And it, it's legitimately one of those arrangements that I happily pay.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
Same.
I don't really need it.
I could quite happily set up my own reverse proxy with WireGuard and I used to, and then
Nebu Kassek came along.
That's the origin of the name, by the way, that, that word Nebu is, is quite unusual.
So Nebu is, it was some God of the wisdom in some, somewhere in some religion or language.
And so then we had like the word, yeah.
Okay.
I like it.
And then we also have the URL, nebu.kassek, right?
Cause that actually, we, we kind of set it on Nebu and then I was looking at domains
and all of a sudden I said Nebu Kassek and I was like, that's it.
So it's essentially comes down to Wise House.
Is that a trade?
That's great.
That is good.
Yeah.
And now we're, we're waiting.
Razer had a smartwatch called Nebu in 2015 or 16 or something.
I was just waiting for their trademark to lapse and then maybe we can
Get a little more, a little more mileage out of that name.
That's great.
I mean, I know, I know lawyers are, have a reputation, but can you confuse a house
automation system and a watch?
You know, smartwatches, smartwatches you can talk to nowadays.
And so, yeah.
Who wants to even worry about a fight?
Why just, yeah.
Yeah.
But boss, thank you so much for joining us and updating in on these things.
And also thank you and thanks to the team for making a piece of software
that has improved my family's quality of life on a daily basis.
I just, not much actually touches our lives in that way.
So we're just really grateful for that too.
Awesome.
Well, you're welcome.
So I hope you enjoyed that interview with Paulus.
Now we're not going to actually do any feedback this week, just in the interest of time.
But next episode, we're going to discuss the
distributed file system question that Chris posed last week.
We've had lots of feedback in the mailbag about that one.
Oh, I can't wait to see what people have suggested.
I feel like I'd be cheating if I read ahead, but now I kind of want to go in there and take a look.
But I'll wait, I'll wait, I'll wait for the show.
So that way my reaction is fresh.
Awesome.
Yeah.
If you have any tips, selfhosted.show slash contact on how you could take advantage
of the random amounts of free space on the hard drives all around your land.
And thank you to our members at selfhosted.show slash SRE.
You can support the show and become a member at selfhosted.show slash SRE.
And you get a limited ad feed, full production, just a little bit tighter and cleaner.
Extra content at the end of the show as well with a special members only post show.
And thanks to our sponsor, a Cloud Guru.
You can find them on social media everywhere.
That's basically a social media site.
They're just slash a Cloud Guru.
That's really simple.
And as always, you can find me over on Twitter at ironicbadger.
And the show is selfhosted.show slash contact.
Indeed.
I'm over on the Twitter as well at Chris Ellis.
And the podcast is over there too at self-hosted show for news and announcements.
Thanks for listening everybody.
That was self-hosted.show slash 45.