Happy holidays, listener! We have a special episode for you this week. Some old friends
join the show for a 3D printing special with Alex.
Well, I'm joined today by a couple of special guests, long-time JB friends and former colleagues,
I suppose. We've got Cheese on the line. Hey Cheese, how you doing?
Hey, hey, how's it going?
And Drew.
Hello!
Both of you are now in Colorado. You're both in Denver, serendipitously, I suppose. Cheese,
you're working for System76 these days, and what about you, Drew?
I am working for the Community College System, so we handle basically high-end IT and server
needs for 13 different colleges across the state.
And you do chew my ear off about OpenShift on occasion.
Every now and then, yeah.
It has been known. What about you, Cheese? What are you doing for System76?
Right now, I'm working with the marketing department, doing videography, photography,
some animation, graphic design stuff, all sorts of fun, cool things.
I feel like breaking out into Troy McClure at this point, you may remember Cheese from
shows such as The Friday Stream and all sorts of other Linux Unplugged, all sorts of stuff.
If you're a long-time JB listener, these two guys will be very familiar to you.
So I've got these two today to talk to you all about 3D printing. This is a topic that
we covered very briefly in an episode of Self-Hosted recently, and lots of feedback came my way
that you'd like a bit more information.
So I have two guys that are at different points in their 3D printing journey.
So just very quickly, Drew, perhaps you could give us a very quick overview of where you're
at in your journey and that kind of thing.
Sure.
So just a few months ago, I purchased my first 3D printer and have been kind of getting up
to speed since then.
It's a smaller unit.
We'll talk more about the actual gear a little later, but it's a very much the beginner's
entrance style unit that one might pick up.
It's not super fancy.
So you're looking at this discussion through the lens of someone who's been printing for
a few months.
And what about you, Cheese?
Where are you at in your journey?
Well, I've been printing now for a couple of years.
After encouragement, I believe it was from Linux Fest Northwest, where we all met up
and you had printed some things, which encouraged me just to bite the bullet and buy a printer.
So I've been using basically the same printer as Drew for quite some time over the last
couple of years and learned that I enjoy the hobby.
So I want to expand that and picked up a new printer recently.
Yeah, I think I 3D printed a carabiner clip to hold my luggage together or something.
Yeah.
I believe it was that.
And you had also printed the on-air signs that were powered by the little NodeMCUs.
Those things are so cool.
Yeah, I think that's what pushed me over the edge.
Well, I'm glad you like them.
Of course, they're running WLED, so I hope you've been keeping them up to date.
There's lots of new features on that stuff these days on the ESP side of things.
So I've been 3D printing a little bit off and on for four, I guess, years.
Quite a long time, I guess.
I got into it through wanting to print little parts for my racing drones.
The perfect use case for me was to print custom holders for all the little tiny circuit boards
that go into an FPV racing drone.
And so I learned very basic CAD skills, computer-aided design skills through stuff like Tinkercad
and Fusion 360.
I am not very good, but I can 3D print a cube or a little square box I made for something
easily enough.
And so I've had probably three or four prints.
I think I'm on my fourth printer now.
I've had some of the cheap Chinese ones, and I've got Prusas these days, but we'll come
on to that stuff a bit more later.
But first of all, I thought it might be helpful to talk about what is 3D printing a little
bit for those that aren't familiar with it.
Would either of you two like to take that mantle?
I feel like as the junior here, that you as the senior printer should take that.
All right, fine, fine, fine.
Okay, so what we call 3D printing is actually technically probably referred to as a bit
like calling a Docker container a container and Linux container.
It's that whole Kleenex debate, right?
So what we're actually talking about is what's called FDM printing, fused deposition modeling.
And essentially what that does is it takes a spool of plastic filament, it can be of
different materials.
So there's three main types that I print with, I'll come on to those in a moment.
But essentially what FDM printing does is it takes in a spaghetti sized piece of plastic,
squishes it through what's called a hot end, melts that plastic at 220 ish Celsius.
It varies on the different filament that you use, the chemical properties of that filament.
So it takes that filament in through a drive gear, squishes it through the hot end, melts
it.
And then the pressure of the drive gears forcing that filament through, forces it out of what's
called a nozzle at the bottom of your hot end.
And so the hot end is the thing that contains the thermistor and it's what contains the
other chamber where the melted plastic is and all that kind of stuff.
And right at the very end of the process is the nozzle, which is what, you know, if you've
ever watched a video of a 3D printer printing, it's that kind of nozzle shaped thing, funnel
shaped thing on the bottom where the plastic actually gets extruded out of.
And essentially the basic premise is you can use what's called G-code to move stepper motors
left and right, up and down, forwards and backwards.
You can use G-code to control the movement of that nozzle such that it will form layers
of plastic.
You know, we're talking an extruded line of plastic will be half a millimeter wide, a
millimeter wide at most.
And what it will do is it will build up layer upon layer upon layer of plastic to form models.
It has some limitations.
Obviously you can't print stuff with certain overhangs in certain shapes because the layer
by layer construction of these things presupposes that there is a support underneath.
So there's all sorts of different ways you can get around that by including supports
in your models and things like that.
But ultimately there are some shapes that just aren't very well suited to 3D printing,
you know, a complete sphere would be quite tricky because it wouldn't be able to stick
to what's called the print bed.
And so one of the most difficult parts of 3D printing, which I'm sure both of you can
attest to, is that first layer adhesion.
Definitely I know whenever I first started, layer adhesion was definitely a thing for
me.
I was using the inexpensive removable bed that came with my printer and quickly found
out that that probably wasn't the best idea, especially after cracking off one print and
then kind of putting a crease in part of the removable bed.
Well, you're doing better than me.
I had a Creality CR-10 as my first printer and I went to Ikea and purchased a mirror
tile, which is I think about 12 inches square.
And I actually had something stick to the glass so hard that when I was trying to unstick
and unpeel this damn thing, that the print actually smashed the mirror when I took a
chunk of glass with it.
That's impressive.
Yeah, I mean, I was able to get mine leveled out pretty good, but I definitely had to go
to a glass bed.
So even with the original mat that came with my Ender 3, I honestly didn't have many adhesion
problems with PLA, which we'll get into the types of plastics that you can use.
But PLA I had no trouble with.
It's when I started going on to more exotic filaments that I'm using now that I really
started having adhesion problems.
Fortunately I was finally able to suss them out, but it's taken some time and a lot of
experimentation to get there.
It does.
I think we should dispel the myth right now that 3D printing is out of the box, ready
to go hobby.
It's not like you can go to Best Buy and buy a 3D printer like you could a paper printer,
for want of a better word, and just press go and expect it to work first time every
time.
That's just not the reality.
They are very finely-toleranced machines.
We're talking microns of a millimetre makes a big difference to how well a layer sticks
or doesn't.
A few particles of dust can make the difference between a print sticking or not.
Well, and it's not just that.
There are so many different things that can really matter here, like the temperature that
you have the filament coming out at, the temperature that you have the bed sitting at, whether
or not it's in an enclosure depending on what type of material it is.
There are so many different variables that you can mess up and just totally throw off
the whole thing.
All right, so let's break down the filaments for a second.
We mentioned PLA.
That's probably the most beginner-friendly one that's available, and probably the most
popular to be honest.
PLA has a few interesting characteristics.
First of all, it's very easy to work with.
There's very little in the way of stringing.
It doesn't require a particularly sticky bed in order to adhese properly, but it can be
quite brittle.
For stuff like my racing drone parts, for example, when it got a bit cold outside, I'd
slam my drone into a tree or something, and the stuff would just snap, it would just crack.
It's good for indoor stuff like plant pots, or I've got a rocket lamp behind me that I
3D printed, for example, so a Saturn V rocket.
It's good for that kind of stuff where there's very little load and very little stress on
the print.
But if you're wanting to do anything where heat is an issue, let's say you're printing
a bracket for your car, another 3D print I've done, a functional print, is a dash cam bracket
for my car, and a car in the south of the United States gets pretty warm in the summer.
I'm talking to a Texan and I'm well aware that you guys get warm too, but you know what
I'm saying, right?
If you were to try and use PLA in that environment, very quickly that plastic would get to what
it's called its glass transition point and start softening drastically.
And eventually, if it's under any kind of load, even if it's just from a dash cam, a
few grams, it would start to warp and twist and eventually melt.
Yeah, and I think that that depends on your print too because a print that I had made
for some friends, they had an above-ground pool and on that pool was a railing that,
I don't know the diameter of that railing, but they had no cup holders, right?
So everyone was trying to figure out like where do I set my drink down.
So I made some cup holders and it just had these little hooks that hooked over the top
of the ring on the pool and was able to put your drink there.
And they probably sat out there for a little over a year before one of them finally failed
and one of the little arms had cracked.
And I don't know if that's because somebody bumped it or how it happened, but it can hold
up to some extent, but under a magnified windshield in the heat, direct heat, probably not the
best.
There's no chances there.
So for that kind of application, you want to be looking at something called PETG.
There are a few other types that are suitable for sort of higher temperature environments,
but PETG in particular is one of my go-tos.
It's sort of chemically related to PLA, so it takes the best bits of PLA and another
plastic called ABS, which is famously difficult to print and work with because of things like
warping, which is where during a print, the corners of a print will lift and then the
entire model is put under intense stress and it can start to crack and all that kind of
stuff.
But PETG is probably the best of both worlds.
It's got pretty much the same ease of printing as PLA and almost the same heat-resistant
characteristics as ABS.
The downside to PETG is it can be a very sticky thing indeed.
That was the filament that stuck to my glass bed and took a chunk of glass with it, for
example.
So chemically, it's very good at bonding with the build layer, the build surface on certain
printers.
So for my Prusa behind me, for example, I actually have two separate sheets.
I have a texture sheet from Prusa, which is actually designed for PETG and a separate
one for PLA just so that I have that separation of concerns.
I don't have to worry about glue sticks or any other kind of nonsense or tape or anything
like that.
It's worth mentioning too that PETG is the slightly more exotic material I referenced
earlier that I was moving towards and was having adhesion issues.
It does require more heat than PLA to really get it to flow nicely and you also can't
print as fast because to get it to where it's flowing well, if you get it flowing too well,
then it bubbles and you need a hotter bed to really get it to stick well.
It's a lot more finicky, but not as finicky as something like ABS or anything like that.
So we're talking about with PLA for example, the hot end is around 180 Celsius and typically
I run my bed at around 60 Celsius.
With PETG, I can run my hot end anywhere from 220 to 250 depending on the particular filament
properties and the bed is anywhere from 80 to 90 degrees Celsius.
So there's a good step up there in the temperature and therefore energy required to use this
filament, but that's why it performs better in heat sensitive environments.
Speaking of, different filaments from different manufacturers can have vastly different responses.
I'm using various filaments from Micro Center and I have my bed turned up to about 100.
I find it works a little better, but I can print with the PETG itself down at about 230
which is the low end of what Micro Center actually recommends for that filament.
Really it just depends.
Yeah, most manufacturers will print a recommended set of settings on the side and that's generally
a good place to start, but you will need to start printing things like calibration cubes
and temperature towers and torture tests and all this kind of thing.
If you're moving to a completely new supplier of filament and you're not seeing the results
you would expect, there's all sorts of things on a website called Thingiverse that you can
actually download for free to import into your printer's slicer software and send across
to the printer.
So speaking of slicers, Cheese, we haven't really touched on that much at all yet.
Would you like to?
Yeah, so a slicer is basically exactly what it sounds like.
As Alex had mentioned earlier, with FDM you're laying down layer by layer, so a slicer will
take your 3D model and separate it layer by layer, drawing the path and or creating the
G-code that allows the printer to know in X, Y, and Z in space where the nozzle needs
to be at any given time.
And then once you've taken your model and you've sliced it, then you can import that
G-code directly into your printer and print your model.
So there are a couple of different pieces of software, Cura, which is one that I'm a
little more familiar with, that's C-U-R-A, it's really great.
And then Prusa, the manufacturer of 3D printers, actually has their own piece of software.
I think they, it's a fork of slicer was the original name and now it's just referred to
as Prusa Slicer, but it's kind of the de facto for them.
It's spelled Slic3R, if you're looking for that on the internet.
Yeah, that's it.
It's LeetSpeak spelled, right?
But yeah, it's a great one as well and I'm learning more of that now that I've purchased
a Prusa printer, but Cura is also fantastic and there are a lot of settings that you can
take from other resources.
So I know Chep is one of the guys I took his settings for Cura originally and they worked
really well for me, better than the stock settings that were suggested by Cura itself.
So I'm pretty curious to know how the humidity has affected you, because I know you've just
moved from Texas to Colorado, but obviously there's a drastic humidity difference between
the Gulf Coast and the Colorado air and PETG is famously hygroscopic, so what that means
is it will absorb water from the air around it.
So me and Riley, for example, with my relatively high humidity, I have to keep my filament
in a dry box full of silica gel in order to try and keep it relatively usable.
I was wondering, have you noticed any difference in how you store your filaments and how easily
they print or not at the different altitudes and humidity levels?
Well for me, I haven't really experimented with much outside of PLA.
So I know the PETG, like you said, has a lot more, is hygroscopic as you mentioned.
But I will say that with PLA, I have noticed that moving from Texas along the Gulf Coast
to here in Colorado, even the PLA, it gets more brittle than normal.
So it's not like I keep it in a humidifier or something, but once I get through the batch
of filament that I have now and I move over to PETG, I'll know a little bit more.
But so far, the humidity and the change in humidity has affected the PLA, but not significantly
to the point where I can't print with what I have.
How about you, Drew, how's your experience been?
So I've only been doing this a few months.
I'm not sure how quickly PETG under circumstances like yours, Alex, would really take on enough
water to need to be dried before printing.
But it could be a month, it could be three or four months.
I mean, it really depends.
For example, you were living in Georgia before and now you're in Colorado.
Similar thing as cheese really, an ocean level of Gulf humidity moving up to the mountains.
So here I have had my PETG sitting out for a while and I keep it in a box most of the
time.
But I don't like after a print is finished, heat up the end and pull the filament and
put it back in the box.
I tend to just kind of leave it on the roll.
You should be fine where you are now.
I mean, I was wondering whether you'd noticed any difference in terms of how, because I
know for example, things like boiling a kettle takes longer altitude and baking recipes are
slightly different.
Yeah, exactly.
So no, I haven't had any issues just leaving my PETG on the roll for weeks.
Still prints fine.
All right.
Well talking of software, we mentioned PrusaSlicer and Cura, those are the two main slicers.
There's another piece of software that I think everybody ought to know about called Octoprint.
Wonderful piece of software.
It's like the best thing.
Wonderful.
Seriously, if you are getting into 3D printing, just do yourself a favor and Google Octoprint.
It is something that you install on like a Raspberry Pi and you connect it to your printer
via the USB slot and then you can control your printer remotely.
It is damn near necessary for anybody who's really going to do this as a hobby.
You really need a way to be able to touch your printer without having to walk to it.
Absolutely.
I totally agree.
I have a Pi 4 running my Octopi instance.
So the piece of software is called Octoprint, but the developer of Octoprint makes available
a build for the Raspberry Pi called Octopi, making the Raspberry Pi ecosystem almost synonymous
with 3D printing in my opinion.
And I actually use that to run the Python application, which is Octoprint.
There are a bunch of different plugins you can get.
So for example, I have one that's called Spaghetti Detective, which looks at my webcam feed and
tries to use machine learning to try and figure out if my printers come unstuck for any reason.
That's a fun one.
There's another one that does Telegram integration.
So I get notifications and I can control my printer via Telegram bot.
I can get GIFs as well, all that kind of stuff.
There are hundreds of plugins.
I couldn't possibly list them all.
MQTT is another one.
Yeah, MQTT is awesome.
The time-lapse plugins.
Yes, that one is great.
The webcam plugin, just in general, to let you monitor in real time.
There's even cost estimation plugins.
So based on the G code that you provided, it will estimate how many grams of filament
and how much that filament costs and therefore how much a print's going to cost.
So there are a lot of things in OctoPrint that there's really nothing out there that
compares to it that I've seen, and it's probably one of the best uses for a Raspberry Pi, especially
if you have, well, specifically if you have a 3D printer.
For sure.
Now I would probably suggest running it on a Pi 4.
I've been running it on a Pi 3B Plus for a year or two, but I upgraded about six months
ago to a Pi 4 and it's night and day difference.
It's so much faster, and I would highly recommend a Pi 4 as a baseline if you're just getting
into this.
So a few months ago, everybody from JB came out to Denver and we all had a jolly good
time, but Linode was giving away Raspberry Pis at our little meetup, and I managed to
win one, right?
Yeah, you did.
That's what my Raspberry Pi from Linode is doing.
Awesome.
Rad.
So the final filament I think is worth talking about is TPU, which is a flexible filament.
Have either of you experimented at all with flexies?
Not yet.
Looking forward to it though, but not quite yet.
It's a world of pain.
Not at all.
I mean, I'm familiar with TPU in that I've purchased phone cases before, but as far as
actually making it myself, no, I haven't.
So with the Creality CR-10 I used to have in London, I was printing a lot of drone parts,
as I said, which included stuff like GoPro mounts.
Like I say, when I smashed into a tree, I wanted some give in the parts, so it didn't
just smash into a thousand pieces.
And with the CR-10, it had what's called a Bowden tube extruder, which essentially means
that the gearing, which feeds the filament into the hot end, is on the main body of the
printer connected to the extruder via a plastic or nylon tube.
Whereas the Prusa has what's called a direct drive extruder.
And I've had a lot of success 3D printing with the flexible filaments on the Prusa simply
because there's a lot less chance for a flexible filament to kind of collapse on itself and
start tying itself in knots like spaghetti on the direct drive printers.
Yeah, I haven't had much experience, actually no experience with TPU yet, but from what
I've heard, the direct drive is kind of the way to go for that because, and depending
on the extruder itself, right, the extruder itself can have one gear or multiple gears
in it.
So with multiple gears, you're able to pull filaments that are maybe a little bit more
difficult to pull through and through the hot end and out the nozzle.
So I'm looking forward to it.
I kind of want to print my own phone case, but we'll see.
I don't want to buy a whole roll and then just be sad because I can't print with it
and now I have a whole roll of TPU.
One thing I will say is TPU is incredibly hygroscopic, so just bear that in mind.
There are some more exotic filaments, you know, carbon fiber based ones, but once you
start getting out of those main three that we talked about, so PLA, PETG and TPU, once
you go outside of those three mainstream ones, there are significant compromises to be made
with all the different other plastics that are available.
There are too many for us to get into today, but that's an overview of most entry-level
filaments for most beginners.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account and you go there to support the
show.
What I love about Linode, straight up, it's fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You should really go try it for your next project.
It also makes for great R&D if you want to learn something and spin it up super quick.
I guess back in the day, I used to fuss a lot more with VMs on my workstation, but these
days I just jump on the Linode dashboard and I get it going in no time.
One of the things I love is when I'm setting up a system, you can actually get console
access through an SSH session.
They even just give you the command right there in the dashboard.
You highlight that, copy that thing, post it into your terminal, you hit that sucker
button, and then you're actually in an SSH session looking at the console of your Linode
machine.
It's awesome.
It's just those kinds of things that make it fun for when you really want to get down
deep, but they also have the one-click deployments and stuff.
Maybe you want to do a GitLab.
Maybe your own Jitsi server.
Get rid of that Zoom.
One-click deployments for that kind of stuff.
They've been rolling out PCIe MVME storage so things are real nice and fast.
They have 11 data centers around the world, so you're going to find something close to
you or your clients or whoever you want it to be close to, because there's 11 of them.
Linode's been doing this for 18 years, and they just keep dialing it in and making it
better and better.
Go see it for yourself.
Use it for your next project.
Deploy something.
Maybe run a game server up there.
Go have fun and use our promo code and get $100.
It's lino.com.
So then there's a question about, do I need an enclosure to 3D print?
The answer is maybe.
There are a lot of factors that kind of go into it, but the main one is, do you need
to really contain the heat for one, and two, are there environmental variables in the area
that you're going to put your 3D printer that you might benefit from using an enclosure?
And in my particular case, I have lots of pets with lots of loose fur, and that was
the primary reason that I bought one.
I'm pretty sure it saved a number of my prints already.
Yeah, I mean, there's lots of cases I've had where just a single corner has lifted on a
print for no discernibly good reason, and then I realized that the air conditioning kicked
on halfway through that print, and I'm like, huh, I wonder if that draft from that vent
up there was just enough to cause that part to cool down just enough to lift or something.
So yeah, like you say, it's highly dependent on your environment.
It's also highly dependent on the plastic that you're using, so some plastics give off
odors and smells, and sometimes you might want to actually extract those fumes away
from the printer, from the enclosure, but generally speaking, most people run an enclosure
to prevent, like you do, pet hair or dust, or to maintain some kind of temperature for
more finicky plastics like ABS.
I could see it being really valuable to have your printer in an enclosure if, say, you
had your printer in your garage, and the ambient temperature of your garage may shoot down
during the winter, or different variables just in the area in which your printer is.
So I could see there being some uses other than just to help maintain the dust and noise
and fumes of a printer.
Yeah, I totally agree.
Garage is a great shout, particularly in a garage as well.
You're going to end up with a lot of environmental debris in there because they're not as well
sealed as a house, for example.
All right, shall we take a few moments to discuss the various different printers that
we all have and the gear that we've got?
Yeah, let's do it.
Andrew, would you like to go first?
Sure, as the newbie here.
So I bought an Ender 3 Pro, which I then very quickly upgraded various parts of.
One thing that I saw on the Ender 3 subreddit that I really, really enjoy is that when you
buy an Ender, you're not buying a 3D printer, you're buying a do-it-yourself 3D printing
kit.
Yes, you are.
Yes.
That is absolutely so true.
I have replaced a number of things on my printer already.
I went from the Bowden tube setup to a direct drive, and I've also replaced the original
hot end with an all metal one, which is to say the original one had a piece of plastic
tubing that goes all the way down almost to the nozzle to feed the filament.
And the one I replaced it with has a fully metal body so that you don't have the issue
of if you print it too high of a temperature that that tubing starts melting inside the
hot end, which can happen once you start getting into things like PETG.
So I just didn't want to deal with that.
I went ahead and upgraded to the direct drive.
I've also upgraded to what's called auto bed leveling.
So with a normal 3D printer out of the box, typically, at least for the lower end ones,
you have to manually go down there and measure down to the millimeter every corner and adjust
the height so that it is the same distance from the nozzle all across the whole bed.
Potentially every single time you print as well.
Exactly.
Yes.
All the calibrations of the previous print cause your calibrations to be off.
I mentioned I had a CR-10 in London, which I sold before I moved to America, and that
had manual bed leveling on it.
And it was just the most frustrating thing in the world.
You didn't know if it was going to work until the first layer was all completely done.
Right.
Yeah.
So now with the auto bed leveling, it literally will, before print, go through and take measurements
in nine different spots, and you can tune that depending on the firmware you're running.
But on mine, it's nine different spots across the bed, saves that value, and then when it
goes to print, it pulls that value up, shows itself a mesh, and says, okay, this area is
a little lower, so I need to compensate for that.
This area is a little higher, need to compensate for that.
And so it takes something that's not level and essentially adjusts itself to make it
level.
One of the best upgrades.
You have just outlined my primary argument for not buying an Ender, very, very eloquently,
and I appreciate the fact that you did.
I'm curious to know, how much did you spend on it in the first place, and then how much
did you spend on upgrades?
Yeah, I'm curious.
So the original Ender, I found on clearance at Micro Center for 200 bucks.
That's a great price.
Yes, yes it is.
So I snapped that up, and then the upgrade kit with the auto bed leveling, and it also
had the silent board, which is the upgraded V2 board, as well as the V2 screen, which
the V2 is the next version up from the Ender 3 Pro.
So I got all of that for under 100, and then the direct drive was about 60 bucks.
The all metal hot end was about 40, and then I also replaced the cheap brass nozzles that
typically are the things that come with it and that most people buy in packets of 20
because they wear out after three prints, in my opinion.
I replaced that most recently with a Nozzle X, which the nozzle alone was $40.
So far, it is worth every penny.
I'm 60% through my first print with it, and it has had no issues so far.
Fingers crossed it's going to be a great upgrade that outlasts the actual printer.
So all in, I mean, we're talking what, less than 500 bucks?
Yeah, probably around 400 bucks or so.
Yeah, and I feel like I've got a really good machine going now.
Those are some solid bargains, dude.
I think the next time I want to buy something off from Goodwill or something on clearance
or Micro Center, I'm going to deploy Drew to go and find it for me.
That's right.
Deal helm, Drew.
Find any 3D printers wherever you go.
That's right.
I like it.
You know, to be honest, though, Drew, I think that that's probably about the same that I
have into my Ender, somewhere sub 500 bucks, I would say.
So you went with an Ender as well, did you, Cheese?
Yeah, I went with the Ender 3, the Ender 3 Pro.
Probably the same printer as Drew.
I got it for 180 ish on sale through Creality.
Good deal.
I think they're wonderful printers.
If you enjoy tinkering, you don't mind assembling it, you don't mind adjusting it to get it
all dialed in, and you don't mind incrementally upgrading it.
I think that's particularly interesting because I know that you've just bought yourself a
Prusa.
Yes.
Which is something I'm a huge fan of.
And I'm really curious to get your take on someone, you know, besides me, that's just
used both an entry level now and what is considered the Rolls-Royce of FDM printers, the Prusa
i3 Mark III.
I'm curious to know what you think now of now you've used both.
I think there's a place for both.
I think the Ender is great to get started on and see if you like the hobby.
And then I think most people find themselves looking at Prusa or other high end 3D printer
manufacturers for something that is more just kind of turnkey and reliable.
Yeah, 100%.
And that's definitely what I've gotten with the Prusa.
Well let's not forget as well that the Prusas are $750 as a kit and $1,000 pre-built.
So they're twice the price.
They are twice the price.
I just splurged and bought the $1,000 kit, the pre-assembled kit.
It came in obviously pre-assembled.
See, I have strong opinions about this as well.
I think that everybody that's buying a Prusa should, if they have the time and the means,
you know, should go through the process of building it.
Because the first time I built a Prusa, I've built two now, I learned so much about electronics,
about how different screws fit through different things and just quite what 3D printing is
capable of in terms of, you know, part tolerances and the strength of different pillars and
all that kind of stuff that's required.
Highly fascinating procedure.
Yeah, I mean, I think it's worth doing that.
I'm not against that.
But I felt that I had kind of already done that with Ender and I could see that when
I had gotten to the point where I wanted, because I generally don't purchase things
like this for myself or I wanted to have something that was turnkey, right?
So I just wanted to pull it out of the box, set it on the table, plug it in, go through
the initial setup.
Some of the things that you get with the Prusa that you don't get with, say, an Ender, the
Prusa comes with a handbook that goes through everything you need to know about the printer.
It's about as thick as a Bible.
It's amazing.
Yeah, it's a great handbook, great documentation.
Not that you can't find great documentation for an Ender or something like that, probably
not through the vendor, more so through third parties, but there's documentation available
there.
Prusa sets the bar, in my opinion, for documentation, for customer support and also, you know, not
to come across as too much of a fanboy, but everything they do is open source.
The hardware designs, the drawings, everything is open hardware.
It's all based off the original RepRap movement.
It's all designed around 3D printers printing more 3D printers, which is kind of a, it's
machines making machines, so Matrix, watch out.
But in my opinion, as a company, Prusa do so much right.
They're based out of the Czech Republic in Prague, Joseph Prusa is incredibly present
on social media.
He also does a lot of YouTube stuff.
You'll frequently see him on with Joel Telling, he's the 3D printing nerd on YouTube.
And you know, there's so much in my life that is open source, working for Red Hat, obviously
open source is at the core of everything that pays my mortgage and it's been a huge factor
in my personal journey with Linux and everything else.
So the fact that I can also buy a piece of hardware that is totally open, 100% open,
and the vendor has shown a commitment to doing everything open for a decade or so now.
For me, Prusa is just a, you know, I'm a fanboy, I'm going to admit it, but Prusa is pretty
much untouchable in my opinion.
Yeah, I mean, Prusa does a lot of good things, right, they even have their own prints library
similar to Thingiverse.
But in that same vein, the Ender 3 from Creality is open source and open hardware.
The
Only because of Prusa.
Absolutely.
Well, they set a bar, right?
But
And it didn't used to be.
If I recall correctly, it wasn't open and then Creality bowed to public pressure and
eventually released drawings that were of a questionable quality to start with and then
they've improved with time.
Well, I mean, I don't know about that.
I haven't, you know, I'm not here to bash on Creality, but I'm just saying that they
also have open source, their hardware, you know, but I think that it's good to have someone
like Prusa in the market to help push those narratives and to help push the way that things
should maybe be conducted in an ecosystem, right?
So by making these things open hardware and encouraging others to do so, I think it's
awesome.
I think I look at this through the lens of drone racing, where there's an awful lot of
commodity parts put together onto flight controllers and things like that.
And Chinese clones are a real problem in that industry.
You'll have a lot of guys in the West that put a lot of IP into developing specific radios
and flight control algorithms and all this stuff.
And they will put that board out to be made at a factory in China at a decent price.
And then two weeks later, a complete copy clone of that thing is floating around for
half the price on the internet, you know?
And for a while, I kind of felt like Creality were in that similar space of just copying
IP.
They have proven me wrong, I think, in general.
They've done a lot of stuff to open source a lot of their drawings and stuff like that,
but there's still a way for them to go, I think.
Definitely think there's a way for them to go.
I mean, I think there's a way for the entire industry to go as well.
And I think, you know, going back to kind of why I had ended up going from Ender to
Prusa, Prusa has a lot of nice features, right?
It's got auto bed leveling built in with a really accurate probe.
It's got a really nice bed that comes with it and the steel sheet to put on the bed.
And Drew had mentioned earlier that it draws a mesh, essentially.
So mind you, all of these printers, regardless of which one it is, the bed is not going to
be manufactured perfectly true.
It's basically impossible for that to happen.
That's why you see people use mirrors on their 3D printers is because mirrors are generally
more true than a piece of glass.
Because if you had a mirror that wasn't true or flat, then you would have a funhouse mirror.
And I don't think, you know, everyone wants to wake up in the morning staring at a funhouse
version of themselves while they brush their teeth.
So there are a lot of nice features that come with the Prusa.
You get the direct drive extruder, which you can also love this feature, remove the filament.
So instead of, say, with my Ender, I would heat up the hot end and then just yank the
filament out.
With the Prusa, it will heat up the hot end and then reverse the drive gears in the extruder
to pull the filament out.
And I just pulled the filament out of the top of the extruder.
It's pretty nice.
Super nice.
Super clean.
The steppers and the drivers for the motors or the steppers themselves and the drivers
for them are super quiet.
I hear the fans more than I hear the motors, which wasn't true.
And I'm sure, Drew, you can attest to this that the original Ender board that you had
in your Ender 3, the sound from whenever you upgraded from the original board to the version
2, just the drivers for the motors.
Dude, it's night and day.
Reduced.
Absolutely.
Yeah, it's ridiculous how loud the Ender 3 Pro is out of the box.
So let me ask you both, what kind of stuff do you print these days?
So I've been printing lately things like cases and stands for various items that need them
around the house, some things for some musical instruments and things of that nature.
My wife and I, when we first started getting into 3D printing, part of the goal was to
design things, print them, and then use her Cricut maker to print vinyl, which could then
be 2D printed to have her designs on them and then go on to the 3D objects to sell through
her store.
That's very cool.
So that's coming.
We both need a little more experience with our individual parts, like I need to get a
little better.
I haven't designed anything yet as far as 3D printing is concerned.
That's the next level up, right?
That's a whole nother bowl game, man.
Absolutely.
I'm getting used to making the filament do what I want it to do before I try to make
it do stuff that we're going to sell.
Understandable, absolutely.
For me, I've been printing, well, shortly after, I would say maybe four months after
we got our printer, COVID hit, and like many makers at the time, Alex, I know you're one,
and had encouraged me to get onto the bandwagon as well, started pitching in and making face
masks or shields using our 3D printers and some other materials.
So I spent a lot of time doing that, printed a ton of those for schools and nurseries and
random public places.
But I enjoy printing cases, little electronics projects.
I think after seeing your recording sign project and it also got me kind of into microcontrollers
and I think that 3D printing helped kind of drag me there too.
So like I've printed a little project that has a 0.96 inch OLED screen that basically
connects to OctoPrint, tells me the progress of a print, sits on my desk, it's powered
by five volts.
Just recently finished printing a case for a stream deck that I'm planning on making
using a Arduino Pro Micro, some sliders and actually some of the Jade switches that are
left over from the launch keyboards.
Sometimes in our shipment of switches we get bent pins and so we have like a bent pin bucket.
So I raided the bent pin bucket and found some switches to include in the project.
So looking forward to getting that one done.
But I think as you start with the hobby you find just things that you can print online,
things that are useful, then you drift into kind of designing things and the next thing
you know you're just absolved in it I guess.
It's kind of like a drug addiction to some extent, right?
Maybe a drug addiction would be cheaper at times.
At times.
I mean at times, right?
Maybe.
I mean I wouldn't imagine over the long term, maybe short term, but like Drew said, buying
the upgrades and upgrading the thing, you just kind of get into this something I don't
know what it is.
It's like this thing that just pulls you forward to like let's make all of the things.
How can I just make this myself instead of just being a consumer and just grabbing the
first thing off the shelf that kind of fits your needs or solves your problem.
It's nice to be able to actually make something yourself to solve that problem.
Totally agree.
An example of that in my life recently.
My daughter recently figured out how to crawl and so obviously we started needing to baby
proof the house so I've printed corner protectors for you know things like coffee tables and
the outlet prong protector things.
All sorts of little things like that you know.
Have you printed any little door locks for like under the cabinet?
No, but I think I will need to pretty soon.
I do a lot of stuff like shelf brackets and little widgets to help me you know in the
workshop when I'm doing woodworking that kind of stuff like little templates and routing
guides and jigs that kind of thing.
There's just so many little things you can do with it.
There's a great subreddit called r-slash-functional-print and there's all sorts of great stuff on there.
So if you're struggling for inspiration, take a look at that subreddit.
Have you guys on the note of all of these printers and Alex I'm sure you guys have,
Drew have you had a chance to see the new Prusa XL printer?
That's a big boy.
I have not.
How big is it?
It's XL.
It's not double XL but it's XL but it also has automatic extruder tool head changes.
So you can have multiple filaments loaded like I think it's five filaments loaded at
a time and it will just pick the head and pull the hot end and head.
Typically a Prusa is nine inches tall by eight inches front to back and left to right.
The Prusa XL is 14 inches square, that's its build volume is front to back left to right
up down 14 inches so significantly larger and in order to do that they're charging $2,000
as a starting point for this printer.
Bear in mind a normal Prusa starts at $750 and they've got the Prusa Mini as well which
starts at $300, $400 something like that to compete with the Enders.
But like Cheez says, the really cool game-changing feature that they've got on this new Prusa
XL, it's not just the fact that they're changing the heads or anything, they're changing the
whole tool.
So it's five separate, you can have up to five separate extruders on this thing.
So you could 3D print five completely different materials.
So you could have dissolvable filaments, soluble filaments to do supports for example that
you could then submerge your print and they would just dissolve.
So there's all sorts of really interesting different applications you could use for that
one.
And it has a really neat new bed technology.
The way that they've segmented the bed, so instead of it just being a flat bed, they've
segmented the beds leaving like cooling and expansion channels in between so that as the
print, as the bed heats up and expands and contracts, you'll be less likely to have warpages
on the bottom of your prints where they're adhering to the bed and stuff.
A lot of cool new tech definitely coming out from Prusa, which I think is going to set
the bar for everyone else going forward and hopefully we'll continue to do this ourselves
and next year we'll sit down and see where we are.
But I did have a couple of questions for you Alex and Drew as well.
Do you guys weigh your filament before you put a print together?
So if you know that you're going to have an extended print, do you weigh the filament
that's on the roll before you load it into your printer to make sure you have enough
filament or do you just cross your fingers and hope that you have enough filament?
I do the cross and clench method, yeah.
The Prusa has a filament run out sensor so I'm not too worried.
Yeah, my upgrade kit also came with a filament run out sensor which I haven't actually installed
yet.
I need to do that but I also haven't gone through enough filament yet to really make
it necessary as of now.
Got you, got you.
But I mean do you weigh your filament?
How do you measure to know if you have enough filament on a roll to complete a print?
Do you just do the same method, just the cross and clench method?
Yeah, pretty much.
Yeah, eyeballing.
You're like, that's roughly half a roll, we can roughly get this much out of it.
Well, I haven't gone even through half a roll of any of my individual rolls yet.
I've got like eight different rolls of filament sitting around and I've kind of played with
each of them so far, you know.
If you consider that each roll of filament is a kilo, typically it's a kilogram, that's
a lot of plastic.
So you'd be printing something pretty massive in order to go through an entire roll in a
single print.
Yeah.
I think where it matters more is where you're trying to use up the dregs, for example.
Absolutely, and that's why I'd asked, yeah.
I got pretty good when I was doing the mask making that you referenced when COVID first
started, kind of doing like a hot swap.
I would sort of sit, you know, a printer's next to me on my desk, I'd sit and watch it
and then I would have the second spool ready and I just sort of get a lighter and fuse
it together really roughly and then sort of file it down a little bit and sort of show
it and it would be fine, it would jam occasionally, but most of the time it was fine.
I never thought of that.
Whilst doing that I would do the same, but I would just watch OctoPrint and then hit
pause.
You could do that, that's probably safer.
And then just swap the filament out real quick.
That's probably safer.
I never thought of, I mean that's a good way to do that, I mean I guess you could potentially
introduce clogs, but.
I could potentially burn my house down, but apart from that.
I mean only, you know, the nozzles are only a few cents each if you get the cheap brass
ones that Drew had mentioned earlier.
What about maintenance?
What do you guys do for maintenance on your printers?
There is an excellent video by a Welsh guy on YouTube whose name escapes me, but I'll
put a link to it in the show notes, where he talks through dismantling a Prusa for example
and all the different oils that you need to put on various different parts and what have
you.
I tend to do it on an annual basis or as often as I can be bothered.
It really depends how much you're printing, how many hours a day you're printing, that
kind of thing.
My printer sits idle much more than it's printing to be perfectly honest, so I don't feel the
need to do quite so much maintenance.
But if I was running a print farm or something I would definitely put it as part of a regular
regime.
Gotcha.
What about you Drew?
I don't imagine you've done much since you haven't had a printer too long, but what kind
of maintenance do you do?
As far as the printer maintenance that Alex is talking about, I haven't done any.
However, once a week or so if I have an issue that I notice, like the x-axis is a little
wonky on a print, I'll go through and I'll check the belts, spot checking various things.
One thing I will say is after every print I will go through with a microfiber cloth
and just wipe down the bed, wipe off the nozzle, make sure that everything's clean and ready
for the next time I go to print.
That is one thing that I would say is well worth doing is just having something around
to just wipe down the bed and wipe down the nozzle at the very least every time you do
a print.
Just because you can get stuff that maybe attaches to the nozzle, although it's less
of a problem if you have one of the nicer nozzles than it is with brass, but still it's
good practice to clean up after yourself in your workspace.
I would say that I do that as well every time I have like a little spray bottle of isopropyl
alcohol and a microfiber cloth that I just spray down and wipe the bed every time I finish
with the print.
I used to spray mine down, but now with the PETG because I am printing on tempered glass,
I do use glue stick.
So I tend to leave the glue stick.
I don't wipe that down after every use.
I'll do a number of prints before I go through and wash it off and reapply.
That's one of the beautiful things about the Prusa though is I can't remember the last
time I cleaned my bed.
Maybe that's bad, but it just works every time.
I'm looking forward to that, but I'll probably still clean my bed every single time I print
something.
It's a habit, dude.
I just can't not.
I used to just out of habit from the CR-10 that I had, but eventually I just stopped
and whilst I was doing the masks, I got pretty good at figuring out what was actually needed
versus what the internet told me I needed to do.
Generally speaking, as long as your house isn't in the desert full of dust, you should
be fine with just the occasional wipe down.
When I say clean, all I really mean is literally taking a microfiber cloth, running it across
the bed, running it across the nozzle, job done.
We're not talking about you have to get in there and scrub every nook and cranny or anything
like that.
No.
I had to do that on my glass bed with the Creality that I had.
Take some dish soap and wash it with love and care and affection and then never touch
it and get my  it was just a pain in the ass.
After every print.
Pretty much, yeah.
Oh, God.
Wow.
That's horrible.
Bear in mind, this was like four years ago before things have come on a bit of a way
since then.
That's fair.
Yeah.
I mean, for anybody listening, if you're getting into it and you want to take my route
where you're kind of spending a little less money and doing some DIY upgrades, go get
yourself some decent quality glue stick.
It makes a world of difference.
It really does.
100%.
Now, thank you both for joining.
I really appreciate you taking the time out of your schedules to come and talk to us today.
Is there any way you'd like to send people to follow you or anything?
I mean, you can follow me on Twitter at Cheese Bacon, that's C-H-C-B-A-C-O-N.
If you have any questions or just want to talk shop, feel free to reach out.
My DMs are open.
Yep.
Same here, Drew of Doom on Twitter.
Feel free to reach out.
Well, thank you both very much.
Thank you for having me, man.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Maybe 2022 will be the year that I finally get a 3D printer.
I know my kids would love it.
And then I know I'd start printing stuff for my RV all the time.
I want to say a special holiday thank you to our members over at selfhosted.show slash
S-R-E. You make this show possible.
Don't forget you also get the extra post show.
And we now, after a lot of, I guess the term is popular demand, as they say, we now have
a network membership at Jupiter.party.
You can gift it as well.
We'll have that for a little bit longer.
And also till the end of December, if you sign up, we're taking two bucks off.
So normally the membership is just the cost of two memberships, but you get access to
all the show special stuff, all the goodies, the behind the scenes stuff and love the member
stuff that you get only with self hosteds, member show, the coder QA, all that and Linux
action news, totally ad free and any new content we add as well for just the price of two memberships.
But right now, until the end of the month of December, we're taking two bucks off for
a year.
This membership is designed to let us be picky, to make sure we choose the right sponsors.
We get a lot of emails that come in and we don't want to be in a position where we have
to work with a sponsor that we don't actively believe in.
And this lets us be picky.
It gives us runway because these good sponsorship deals, they don't happen overnight.
They take months to develop a relationship.
You give us the runway to do that.
The episodes where there's fewer sponsorships, those are the episodes our members actually
make possible too.
So it's a pretty special thing and it puts you in the driver's seat because you're funding
the content and that's fundamental.
That changes everything.
Jupiter.party if you'd like to be a member for the entire network or selfhosted.show
slash SRE if you'd like to be a member just for this show.
And even if you can't support us through a membership, we are so grateful for your downloads,
for your community support, for maybe telling a friend, maybe leaving a review somewhere.
So happy holidays from the self-hosted team and feel free to reach out to us at selfhosted.show
slash contact and ho, ho, ho, we'll see you right back here next year.