Joining us on the show today from serverbuilds.net is JDM.
He's my go-to hardware guru.
We also cover the new Raspberry Pi release
and I stage an intervention for Chris's Raspberry Pi habit.
I'm Alex.
I'm Chris, and this is Self Hosted 21.
Alex, have you ever had the perfect system
end up being the machine you built yourself?
There's no such thing as the perfect system, is there?
It's just between upgrades.
I don't know.
I kind of think the workstation I have upstairs
is one of those kind of perfect builds
where I had kind of the confluence of the core series
of CPUs were in a good maturity.
Six cores was a good bang for the buck.
It was a good price to get 32 gigs of RAM.
Fast storage was cheap enough
that I can have multiple disks.
I just love this box I built.
I feel that way about this one I'm talking to you via.
It's an i7-8700K with a couple of NVME storage
storage drives and all my actual storage is in the basement.
But I've got an SSD for Windows and an SSD for Linux
for pass-through and stuff like that.
It does everything I could ever dream of.
It's just a champ.
What's yours?
Mine's my Linux box upstairs that I run Manjaro on
with my three 27-inch screens.
It's got an AMD 580 graphics card in it,
Intel six core CPU, 64 gigs of RAM in this thing
because I like to run lots of VMs.
And I have multiple disks.
I have a dedicated disk for my home.
A dedicated disk for my root and a dedicated disk
for my VMs and a dedicated disk for my steam games
and also my sync folders.
That's the way to go, man.
It's pretty great.
Now it's fun when you're building a desktop
but it like really matters when you're building a server.
And that's why it's really great that we are joined
by a very special guest today who helps the community
figure these things out with his website, serverbuilds.net.
JDM, welcome to the show.
Hey guys, thanks for having me.
Man, thanks for being here.
And for those that are not familiar with serverbuilds.net,
can you give them like the elevator pitch
on what the website is?
Well, our website's a little stale at the moment
but the forums are really where it's happening.
That's where the action is.
Yeah, the forums and the Discord.
So we got almost, probably what I would say 10K users
like including Reddit, Discord,
but it's a very community focused,
well, for lack of a better word, community.
So I try to engage as much as possible
but anyone can write a guide and post it on the forum.
And then if it's good enough, like we'll help you edit it
and it can become featured.
But mostly I write guides on hardware getting used
or enterprise off-lease hardware.
Sometimes it's not even used, sometimes it's brand new.
It's just old stock, but it's all very affordable.
And I basically just try to make it easy
if you're like used to building gaming PCs and whatnot
and you wanna build a server, it's just as easy as that.
Yeah, but you do help kind of give people an area
to focus in and some of these guides are pretty useful
because I think Alex, you've used one of them in the past
to build your setup.
I certainly have.
So yes, hi JDM, welcome to the show.
Thanks.
I built when I immigrated a brand new server
and I built your anniversary,
I think it was 1.0 build at that point,
which has a pair of dual LGA 2011 Xeons,
128 gigabytes of RAM, 100 plus terabytes
in the Rosewill LSV4500, I think case.
And that was all about a couple of thousand dollars.
So, I mean, the bang for buck that you and your site
enabled me to get was just astonishing really.
That power, you know, five years ago would have cost
three, four, five times what it cost me a year ago.
The CPUs that you have,
if you look at the retail price of them,
they could be in the 2000 to $3,000 each
back when they were brand new,
but now you can get them on eBay for maybe a couple
of hundred bucks, $150.
I think the magic sauce really that you have,
there's a few tools that you kind of share with the community.
There's an absolutely awesome spreadsheet,
the CPU Compendium spreadsheet that you have,
which lists every single Xeon in that era
and compares the price to performance, to TDP,
to, you know, everything that you're trying to think about
when you're building one of these servers.
So stuff like idle power draw is obviously quite important
for a 24 seven home based box, but then, you know,
Plex transcoding performance might be important
for some people, or, you know,
there's just a whole bunch of stuff that's in there
that's just really great.
And one of the things you actually helped me with,
I don't know if you remember this,
about six to eight months ago,
was I was having some temperature issues in my build
and I was posting on the forums,
or I think it was Discord actually,
with, you know, all the pictures and things like that.
And it turned out that the fan configuration I had in my box,
I just didn't even look, I just bought Noctua's
just because that's what I've always done.
And then you told me, no, Alex,
you need high static pressure fans because of XYZ.
I was already to buy a new case at this point, you know?
And I changed the fan configuration based on your advice
and you saved me probably another few hundred dollars.
So thanks for that.
Oh, absolutely.
And we try to do a full service recommendation
where if you're in that situation and you're like,
okay, I've got the hardware,
but I don't have these little tiny details fleshed out,
I try to do my best to pay attention to that.
And say like, okay, well, if you're in a server chassis
and you do need those high static pressure fans,
here's not only the ones you should buy,
but here's those fans compared to what else is on the market
and here's why they're a better value.
You can get like, you know, for the ones that you got,
they were, I don't know, five pack for 28 bucks
or something like that.
Yeah, they weren't really even very expensive, so.
Right, and sometimes it's just about
buying the correct hardware
and it doesn't always have to be the most expensive.
And especially for servers, I mean,
why did you go that route?
Like, I know you came across it and all that,
but what was so attractive to you about that
versus going for something more modern?
I like the idea I had dual 10 gig on board
as well as IPMI and dual Xeon is obviously quite attractive
from a Plex transcoding perspective.
My use case was that I wanted to be able to run
a couple of Kubernetes clusters at once
in addition to my normal server workloads, that is.
I needed to be able to have at least 96 gigs of RAM,
but I went for 128 in the end
because I'm a baller and why not?
That board actually tops out at like 512 or 768.
Yeah, it's kind of insane what you can get
and it just blew my mind.
I mean, I kind of, because I was emigrating,
I didn't really have a lot of time to, you know,
dig into the minutia like you and your team obviously do.
And it was just really helpful to have all that information
in one place and be able to say, right,
if I buy this board, I'm gonna expect roughly
this performance, it's gonna all work together.
And you were actually lining up vendors as well.
So I bought from, I think the IT Mart at that point.
We've been trying our best to work with a lot
of these vendors that do either off lease servers
or they're like resellers or refurbishers
and there's a ton on eBay, but they're all very professional
in the business of reselling server hardware.
And you can get some really interesting stuff
that the public just doesn't even know about.
For example, like you said, there's a vendor
that we do group buys with,
and he had a few 6.4 terabyte NVME drives.
They went for, I think, $600 a piece on group buy.
And if you think about that for a second,
consumer NVME drives, your two terabyte brand news,
maybe 270 bucks.
So if you're getting 6.4 terabytes for 600
and then the best part is that it has
a 60 petabyte write endurance.
So that drives never gonna die.
Oh, could you ping me next time that comes up?
Right?
Absolutely.
I mean, that's the kind of thing that you would see
in the discord.
And I mean, maybe that was a little bit of a rare deal,
but stuff like that does come up.
We try to establish that relationship
because these vendors, they don't know
that there's communities out there for that.
They're just selling to businesses and things like that
where if I can establish the link between the vendors
and this large community that's still growing,
I mean, it's growing at a fantastic rate
that helps everyone.
I think what you do so nicely is you bridge the gap
between Googling, I want to build my own server
and actually having a functional list of parts
that all work together, which is just really nice
at different price points as well
and different performance points.
So we've talked about the anniversary build.
That's kind of like the no compromises build almost.
There's another one that you guys do called the NAS killer.
Tell us about that one.
The home NAS is something that's becoming very,
very popular.
You can run a bunch of applications on it.
You throw a bunch of hard drives in
and you've got local storage that you can serve
to your network and it's nice to have
because you don't have to rely on the cloud.
You can have it local, it's fast
and overall it's a great idea.
However, companies like Synology or QNAP or WD,
they have their own little NAS devices,
but really they end up being very expensive
for the hardware you get.
And so the NAS killer was my vision
of how you can build a NAS for the same price or cheaper
and have the hardware be much more powerful.
So I found some early E3 Xeons
and the pass mark was like 7,000 compared to,
even the high end Synology is only like 1900 pass mark.
So you're getting four times the performance.
You can build it yourself and then you have anywhere
from eight to 15 to 30 drive bays,
just depending on what your setup's like,
but really the NAS killer series has evolved
and currently we're on NAS killer four,
NAS killer five is in the works.
The hardware is getting newer and newer as time passes
and stuff starts to go again, like off lease.
So you start to see the hardware,
even though it's a little bit older,
starts to come through and prices start to drop
a little bit more.
But yeah, the NAS killer is our most popular guide
and I think there's like 30,000 views or something
is just on the forum post alone.
But yeah, it's just designed to be the all in one home NAS.
You can run any software you want,
but it's designed to give you that starting point.
Now you're gonna make me wanna build one of those,
but I can't figure out how to fit it in the RV.
I could make that work for sure.
Do you have any advice for anyone who's looking to build
a low power box that's gonna be on 24 seven?
So I mean, something that could form the basis
of a self hosted router, for example,
running open sense or PF sense, something like that.
What's really interesting about computer hardware,
especially I would say within the past five to seven years,
performance hasn't increased a whole lot.
So like IPC instructions per clock, yes, it's improving,
but really where the improvements have come about
is through power usage.
If you look at the modern 1151 socket from Intel,
for example, Intel's eighth and ninth gen CPUs,
they're extremely power efficient.
For example, the HP 290,
it's a little like all in one consumer grade device,
but it idles at like seven Watts
and there's a 54 watt TDP seller on it.
And that's the TDP, not the power usage.
But at idle, it's only about seven Watts.
I use one for my PF sense.
And I think that box was only a hundred dollars
on eBay shipped.
But we just look for like little deals like that.
And it really just depends on what your needs are.
But like you said, for PF sense,
it's not gonna be super high.
PF sense or for home assistant or something like that,
that's just gonna be always on.
You know, if you don't wanna build a huge box like I did
and run them all as VMs with pass through
and stuff like that,
it's a really good idea to consider
one of these smaller lower power x86 based systems
because, you know, legacy software is gonna support it.
And one of the issues with using the Raspberry Pi
for all of this type of stuff
is that you have to hang everything off the USB bus,
number one.
And then number two, every ARM CPU is different.
So there's no guarantee that
just because a vendor says they support ARM
through, you know, a Docker container
or something like that,
there's no guarantee it's actually gonna run
on your setup.
So, I mean, that could be proved by
the recent Raspberry Pi 4.
And if you look at the software support for that
compared to the three and any model below,
it's totally different.
The Pi 4 went through some more significant changes
with the video that are for the better
and a couple of other areas with the bootloader,
which has caused that lag.
But the two to three series,
and there was lots of iterations in between there,
was pretty successful.
I look at it like this, Alex,
it's early days still with the platform
and like any early adoption,
there's a series of trade-offs, but also benefits.
Like for example, the USB bus,
it is a limitation of the Raspberry Pi platform,
but there are several small board computer platforms
that now either have eMMC in addition to PCI
or SATA even.
And then of course with the Raspberry Pi 4,
a guy like yourself,
you really could do all of the storage
over the gigabit ethernet,
which is now on its own dedicated connection.
You know, you could iSCSI everything really.
I might have bought a Raspberry Pi this week.
I think you should try using the network
as your primary storage location.
I think that'd be an interesting experiment.
It's in England.
So I bought one of those brand new eight gigabyte
Raspberry Pi 4s to use as a remote ZFS storage endpoint.
I was gonna ask if you got the eight gig one.
Yeah, I did.
I mean, I really don't need eight gigs on a Pi,
but why not?
Why not have the headroom for future tasks?
Because that means in the future,
you could also throw something on there like sync thing.
You have plenty of overhead
for all kinds of additional applications
that are just a container away.
I mean, it's not necessarily a bad idea.
And I would also just say in my hands-on experience
with say the Pine 64, Rock Pro 64 and the Pi 4,
I could run everything in every container on either.
I didn't run any particular compatibilities.
The OS kind of abstracts that aspect.
Once you have the core OS,
as long as it's a mainstream Linux,
like Archbase or Debian base, you're pretty much good.
Yeah, cause you were talking about Raspberry Pi OS
for a little bit on LUP 357 and how they've,
I mean, they've just renamed Raspberry into Raspberry Pi OS.
And talk a little bit about why you don't really rate it
versus say an Ubuntu.
Well, that's a good question because I think the,
for me and it's something maybe I haven't made
implicitly clear on this show is the transition
for treating the Raspberry Pi a little more seriously
came when Canonical announced that they were going to make it
a first-class Linux platform for them.
Like it's actually got staff that are working
to support future Raspberry Pis.
And that resonated with me pretty strongly
because the Raspberry Pi models tend to stick around
for at least five years.
You know, you can still buy older Pis.
And Ubuntu LTS is a professional grade operating system.
It might not be everyone's favorite,
but it's a professional operating system
that is designed to run in production environments.
Raspbian to me, or I'm sorry, Raspberry Pi OS,
there are just formerly known as Raspbian.
I think it's great.
And I think it's really well suited
for new users of the platform.
for people who want a lightweight desktop
with a web browser.
But for those of us that want to use it as a home server
or like a backup server, even like in your case, Alex,
which is a great use case,
I think you need something on there
that is a little more production grade.
And just to the point of low power consumption,
just keep in mind that with low power consumption
generally comes low performance as well.
And it may be relatively higher performance
compared to another model.
But if you compare it to, for example,
a low power consumption Xeon
that has eight cores, 16 threads,
Raspberry Pi is never gonna touch it.
Even though maybe the power consumption's,
let's say 50 watts at idle on the Xeon,
yes, it's more power for sure,
but how much more compute horsepower do you have?
Here's a really interesting consideration though.
So my sister is not a techie.
In fact, she works in pharmaceuticals.
And when the Pi for eight gig came out this weekend,
I ordered one and sent it to her.
She put it together,
plugged in the USB hard drive in half an hour
over a Skype call.
I can't imagine asking her
to put together a remote Xeon system for me.
I know that building computers is just like adult Lego,
but I've been doing it since I was 13.
She's never even so much as, I mean,
when her Mac breaks,
she goes to the Apple store and takes it there.
It's someone else's problem.
So the Pi, for me at least,
fulfills a really great need of being like a computer
in a box that I can still mostly own every piece of,
like I can choose the case,
I can choose the bootloader and that kind of thing
without having to install a CPU or a power supply
or something like that.
I totally agree.
And I think that it absolutely has a purpose
and I'm not against a Pi or anything like that,
but you do have to consider that it's still not x86.
So if there's applications that you wanna run there,
you do run into that hard limitation.
I think that's very fair.
You have to go into it with the acknowledgement
that there's just not the level of software compatibility
to both the point you guys have both made
and I have to agree with.
And you are probably not gonna get
quite the right bang for your buck.
I wonder though,
because I run three right now is what I have remaining,
Raspberry Pis that are currently running
and even with the overhead of being inverted from DC power,
I think all three of them are maybe drawing 30 Watts.
I'm not sure cause it's mixed in with my router,
my switch and a wifi access point in there,
but the draw is so substantially low
that I can run them for days off the battery power.
That's pretty great.
Yeah, so Chris, your server seat,
I think that's what we're gonna dub it now.
JDM had potentially some ideas
for what we could do to maybe replace,
I don't know if we can replace the Pi,
obviously you love yours,
but yeah, maybe we could do something a bit different.
I'm open to the idea, I gotta be honest.
I think the Raspberry Pi would be a good
like one year experiment right now,
but I really wish at the end of the day,
all of this was virtualized, that everything was in a VM.
So I'm trying to stage a Pi intervention here, JDM,
help me out.
So what has built in KVM, a battery backup
and is X86 and low power?
Do you know?
A ghost.
I was gonna say, it sounds like a SuperNUC.
It's a laptop.
Oh, very fair.
Yeah, okay, all right.
So I have actually found great success
using even low end consumer refurbished laptops
for situations like yours,
because a lot of times they have NVME slots.
So you can have one or two NVME slots,
even on like, let's say a $300 laptop.
And maybe it has like an Intel Pentium Gold,
I believe the model is like the G5405 or something like that.
It's a two core, four thread, it's got Intel quick sync.
So if you wanna do Plex transcoding,
you can do 15 trans codes easily.
It's got an X86 CPU, so you can run Linux,
you can run Windows,
you can run basically anything you want.
You can do 16, 32 gig of RAM,
and it's got ethernet wifi,
again, built in battery backup.
You can leave the lid closed,
tuck it away somewhere on a shelf.
That screams to me, laptop.
You know, I didn't expect this line.
I gotta say, that's pretty interesting.
Did you have a specific laptop in mind?
The ones that come on eBay that I've been eyeing
and I've used personally,
like right now at my home,
I have an LTE network that's completely separate.
It's a, I kind of jokingly call it a PLAN.
It's a physical LAN, it's not a VLAN,
it's totally separate.
But right now I'm running that off of a router OS
on a Lenovo,
I have to look at the exact model number.
Maybe you can put it in the show notes,
but it's just a Lenovo.
Like I said, it's got the Pentium Gold,
and then it runs a USB LTE connection,
and that is just for my smart home devices,
so it's totally separate from my regular LAN.
But you could do something similar
where if you wanna run Docker
and containerize everything on the laptop,
you could do that.
Yeah, I was thinking the ThinkPad.
Yeah, and the other advantage
is if I have to go into crash cart mode,
it has a built-in screen and keyboard.
Absolutely.
And that has saved my butt quite a few times,
and especially in your situation,
leave the lid closed, leave it plugged in,
and then you can actually run it off of a UPS
or whatever battery you have,
and then you also have the laptop's internal battery.
So the possibilities are endless,
and you obviously don't have to go that route.
You could go for a NUC.
Those are a little bit more expensive
for the performance you get, actually.
But again, you don't have the screen
and KVM and all that.
Right?
I mean, it's hard to argue with a used ThinkPad
because honestly, it's still gonna be more powerful
than the Raspberry Pi.
And what I'm using these Pis for
is gonna work great on a laptop
if it's just a headless Linux with KVM.
Home Assistant, of course, Plex, obviously.
SyncThing's a big deal for me.
I have a very simple Markdown viewer application
that I like to use.
Those things will be no problem.
The one that's tricky,
and I don't know exactly what to do with, is Shinobi,
because that's a lot of disk I.O.,
and it's a lot of network I.O.,
and Shinobi's one of those applications
that just wants to have the entire OS,
which either means I gotta virtualize it,
or I gotta put it on dedicated hardware.
Could you give me a quick rundown of Shinobi and what the...
Yeah, it's basically just a closed-circuit,
self-hosted capture system for RTSP camera feed.
So I have a bunch of Wwise cameras
that have a firmware on them
that just lets me capture the video off them
directly over the network.
And this thing provides recording of those videos
and playback and viewing,
kind of like a DVR system,
and you can pull up all the feeds
and look at them in a dashboard
and cut out clips and segments.
And it's great,
because sometimes I take my RV in wild places
and I wanna have surveillance when I'm not there,
or like right now it's in a shop
and I wanna check in on what's going on every now and then.
I found that it basically keeps the box
totally busy the entire time.
I don't wanna run two laptops.
Well, okay, that's fair.
Are you aware of what QuickSync is?
Yeah, like Intel's built-in,
improved H.264 encoding accelerator.
Correct, and it's seen huge generational improvements.
So this is something that's been very popular
on serverbuilds.net.
We've been recommending QuickSync
transcoding boxes for Plex.
A seventh-gen Celeron two-core can do 20 transcodes
from 1080p to 1080p or 720p.
Without us, what?
Did you just say 20?
20.
Wow. Wow.
Okay, so that's a scale I just did not appreciate.
That's including laptop CPUs.
The biggest performance increase
that we've seen with QuickSync
and through my testing has been generational.
So you go from seventh-gen to eighth-gen to ninth-gen Intel,
and currently we're on 10th-gen.
You can get a 10th-gen Intel QuickSync laptop
for about 300 bucks off of eBay,
but it really doesn't really matter what the processor is.
It's more about, again, the generation.
There's some indication that faster processors are faster
and do support more transcodes,
but even the very baseline models support a ton.
And you were talking about Shinobi.
I'm not sure if that can leverage QuickSync.
It might be able to,
but I know that its competitor Blue Iris,
which is a Windows-based application,
can absolutely leverage QuickSync.
And they just had a recent update
where it almost completely removes the CPU usage entirely.
I actually use QuickSync for Twitch streaming and recording.
So I have an i9-9900K in my desktop,
but if I were to use NVENC,
which is NVIDIA's encoding on the GPU,
I would lose a little bit of performance,
and there is some indication that it does mess
with your frame times a little bit.
Whereas if I use the iGPU,
which you do have to enable manually in your BIOS,
but that iGPU is not doing anything.
There's no monitors plugged into it or anything.
It's just sitting there idle.
So using it to encode a Twitch stream, for example,
or a YouTube video, it works fantastically.
The quality's amazing.
It sees about 0.6% CPU usage while it's doing it.
Wow.
That's pretty great.
Hardware circuitry, huh?
Yeah, that is really great.
And the other thing that's tricky for me
along with this is heat, because it is in this seat.
It's tricky to keep my ambient temperature
below 80 degrees Fahrenheit.
I wouldn't worry about it too much with the laptop.
They can handle it.
And like I said, QuickSync is very power efficient.
It doesn't really require too much of a CPU resource.
So for example, if you were to run that original setup
like we were talking about,
you could run Docker on Linux on the laptop.
And then if you were to run Plex on it and you say,
okay, we'll want Plex to leverage that CPU transcoding,
you can actually pass just the iGPU through to Plex,
through the Plex container and leverage it that way.
But if you were to do a separate NVR build,
like you said with Shinobi,
or I would prefer Blueiris
because I know it can leverage QuickSync very well.
I would recommend a separate box.
And maybe I just keep a Pi doing that
and then move everything else.
The laptop idea is a good one.
I'm trying to ride the Raspberry Pis out for a year
just as like a self-education program.
And I know that a lot of people out there in the community
are trying to use Pi.
So I just, I wanna be well versed in them.
And I definitely am now.
I'm definitely deep.
I'm like tribbles with the Raspberry Pis
in the RV these days.
But I could see this probably,
I don't know, I'd have to go look back
when we started this, see where my year mark is.
I could see switching to this.
This is how it goes with JDM, Chris.
He has these little nuggets of ideas
that kind of sprinkle into your brain.
You go away for a couple of weeks and you're like,
damn it, that's what I need to do.
I need to buy an old ThinkPad now.
Well, you know what's funny is for like a hot half a second,
I think I glanced at an old laptop in the studio
and I looked at that and I went,
huh, I wonder if that'd work as a server.
And then I thought, nah, not a laptop.
Especially if you could power it directly off DC
if you got the voltage right.
Absolutely you can, they're mostly 19 volt DC.
Yeah, I bet I could make it work.
The other thing that I want you to think about,
and I don't know, this is for me personally,
this is the way I work.
But you said that you're using Pis
because you like to play and you like to learn
and that's something you're trying to learn.
For me, I don't like to play with things
that I just want to play and work.
Yeah, there is that, yeah.
So if you can get your baseline set up
where you've got your router virtualized
and all of your services that you need to work work
on like, let's say the laptop setup we're talking about
or something else, then you would actually have
more freedom to play with the Pis
where you don't necessarily have that back of your head
saying, oh, well, if I mess this up,
then I need to redo everything.
Yeah, there's advantages to,
like I don't want to be too critical of the Pis
because I'm impressed that the advantage to me
diving into this and really using them
is I truly am learning what they're capable of and not.
And I have to say, they really have run pretty solidly.
The biggest mistake I made early on was I used Raspbian
and I had to rebuild a couple of things.
But now I'm quite happy.
In fact, having my storage on the USB bus
hasn't really been an issue because I'm getting
these Samsung T5 disks.
They transfer it like 280 megabytes a second,
which is as good as my wifi is gonna do
for the Plex playback.
So even the disk IO, I've been fairly happy with.
And then I'm gonna also add in there because of the cost,
what I'm doing now on this trip I'm taking
is I've brought a cold Pi ready to go in a case all set up
and I have them installed in Velcro
to the inner walls of the seat.
So if one of these Pis dies,
I just grab the cold standby, literally just pull
the one Velcroed in, pop the new one in,
it has Velcro on it already, put all the same connections in
and power it up, it's good to go.
Oh, but cold Pi is not as tasty.
It's true.
But I do feel like I am constantly walking on eggshells.
I will acknowledge that aspect of it.
But that could also just be because it's such a new platform
to me.
Right, but I think that you would gain
a lot more experience where you can sort of
piecemeal implement things that you're testing with the Pi
if you have a good backbone.
Yeah, I could be riskier if it wasn't my production device.
And that's the same reason I ended up splitting out
my PFSense.
I mean, I used to run it on top of Proxmox
with a quad Intel gigabit NIC card in the main hypervisor
in that anniversary build.
I ended up building a separate PFSense box.
I've since switched it to OpenSense,
but I ended up building a separate box
because I didn't want my internet to go down
every time I rebooted my server, right?
The uptime now is 115 days or something.
But when it happens, or what was happening with me
with Proxmox was I was getting hard lockups,
kernel panics, basically.
And so every time that happened,
I had to walk down to the basement and push the button
because IPMI wasn't working or something.
It was completely weird.
And I just ended up thinking, right,
my internet needs to be separate from my server.
That's just something that needs to happen.
Part of building a home lab is identifying
those key points of this needs to not fail.
What do I need to do to make it perfectly reliable?
And then on the other hand,
what kind of hardware do I want to play with
where I have that freedom and the flexibility?
Yeah, a home lab, and this is a bugbear of Morgan, actually.
He was on the show a couple of episodes ago.
He and I were talking the other day,
and he was like, a home lab is not just someone's server.
A home lab is an actual thing with multiple switches
and multiple servers and whatever.
So the purists out there will be probably cringing
a little bit at my definition of a home lab as one box,
but-
Hey, home labs can be virtual too.
They don't have to be just physical.
It's true. That is true.
So I have a question for you, JDM, about your setup
and how many terabytes you have
and what does your home lab look like?
Being a hardware guy, I'm expecting some good stuff here.
Yeah, it's been an interesting process
because we just recently moved to Denver
and that was a cross country move for us.
But as some of you may know,
I do stream occasionally on Twitch.
And in the past couple of streams,
I've been implementing a storeinator.
So that was kindly given to us by a fellow
server builds member who works at Backblaze.
And I spent a little bit of time implementing that
and I've got 30 drives of mixed eight and 10 terabytes
running Unraid on that box.
I have to wipe the pool of drool
from underneath my chin right now.
A storeinator, oh, that's the stuff of dreams.
I just recently posted about it on Twitter
and it was nice to have Unraid retweet me,
but it's been an interesting challenge to get that to work.
In the past, I've run pretty much all super microservers,
a couple of 3Us, 16 bays, and then a 45 bay DAS,
which is a direct attached storage.
It's just basically a JBOD, just a bunch of disks
and that connects to the main server.
So in the past, I've run that and I've condensed down
a little bit into the storeinator
where I can have 45 bays in for you.
So are you running Unraid on that?
Yes, I run Unraid mostly and shout out to you guys
for having the best Docker containers.
I run exclusively LSIO when possible.
Oh, we'll have to change that
because I'm not part of them anymore.
Are you officially not part of them?
I'm officially not, no.
Oh, okay, well.
I use them too and I still think they're great.
Thanks for any work that you did do on them
because they've been pretty great.
But aside from that, yeah, I do run Unraid
and of course, Plex and all that.
That's kind of where I got started was the Plex subreddit
and I was a mod there and helped out
the team there for a while.
I started doing a couple of hardware builds
and split off into serverbuilds.net
because we just really took over the Plex subreddit
and I didn't really want to continue to do that.
Right, it's fascinating because it's a theory.
I think we probably said on the show a couple of times
but Alex and I talk about it off air all the time
that a lot of this journey starts at Plex
and sometimes our audience kind of hates to hear that
because we got a pretty hardcore open source aficionados
out there and they prefer we talk about other things
but I think you really gotta give Plex credit.
It draws a lot of people into this space
and it's kind of like the toe in the water
that leads to bigger and bigger things.
So JDM, I'm curious, now that you've kind of got
a fairly sophisticated setup, what do you find to be
the most frustrating or troubling aspect of the setup?
Like what's the thing that you have to constantly deal with
or manually fix?
Luckily, not much because I choose my hardware
in a way that I don't need to do anything with it
once it's implemented and now I'm more geared
at helping other people find hardware
or I can start playing around with software
because everyone has their specialties.
I love hardware, I love working with hardware
but software is definitely one of my weaker points
so if I can start to gain experience with that
because I have that solid hardware base
where I have the freedom to do whatever I want basically.
That is my goal really is just to start moving
into more software, developing my own experience with that
and relaying those experiences to other people
because everyone has their own way of doing things
and not to say my way is any better than anyone else's
but we both, you guys and server builds,
we have our own communities
and I'm sure that there's a crossover there
but we do have our own ways of doing things
and if there's more information out there
on how to do something or if there's a gap in knowledge,
I'd like to try to fill that.
But as far as challenges go,
I don't really have a whole lot.
Right now it's kind of getting everything
to where it is what I would say like peak efficiency
so I'm trying to cut down power usage where I can
if it's downgrading a processor or moving
to a different system.
Dialing it in in a sense.
That's great, that's a great, I love that phase.
And unfortunately, I kind of live by the motto.
It's like, oh, I have a spare part.
It's not really a spare part.
It's an unfinished build now
so now I have to do something with it.
That could get expensive real fast.
Oh, absolutely.
So back when we had Wendell on the show,
I asked him how many terabytes he had
and I had this vision of like a top gear style leaderboard
for guests as to how many terabytes they have.
Oh, sweet, yeah.
I don't know if I've asked every guest
but I'm gonna ask you, how many terabytes do you have?
Raw or formatted?
Oh, I don't think we've ever clarified.
I guess, I mean, I think we should consider raw potential
versus available.
Yes, because Wendell just dropped the petabyte bomb
so I mean, I don't think we're gonna compete with that
but maybe.
I'm not quite there.
I do have multiple unrated setups
so I do have the one in the store inator.
I have one that's in a 15 bay
and I have another one that I'm prepping for another 15 bay
but I'm nearing half a petabyte.
Wow, okay, that's pretty cool.
Where do you buy your drives from
and what sort of things do you look for
when you're buying hard drives?
I exclusively buy WD Shuckables and.
Me too.
Exclusively.
They're fantastic
because they're really just HDST Helium drives
to the most part with a little bit of firmware trickery
but there's really not a whole lot to consider.
Buy eight terabyte WDs or higher,
so eights, tens, 12s, 14s, soon to be coming out 16s
and they're the best value for the money
and nothing can touch them right now.
That's a great tip.
Alex is a Shucking fan and it's his favorite thing
so I don't think you could have had a more perfect answer
for this show.
Yep, yep, yep, yep, I love it.
There's a couple different models.
There's the Elements, there's the Easy Stores
which are a Best Buy exclusive but it doesn't matter.
They're all the same drives inside.
The only thing that you have to consider
just like SAS hard drives,
if anyone's familiar with SAS hard drives,
they have a 3.3 volt standby.
There's a guide on our forum on how to surpass this issue.
A lot of people use Kapton tape to just tape off the pins
but you can just simply remove the correct SATA wire
and it'll function.
Just cut the wire, yeah, cut the green one.
I don't know if it's green.
Please don't cut the green wire.
Check which one you're cutting.
If you're using like a server backplane,
like a Super Micro,
they already have the 3.3 volt standby taken care of
so you don't even need to worry about it.
But yeah, they're extremely versatile.
They're even great in their own USB 3.0 enclosure
for those Raspberry Pi guys that we won't talk about.
All right, well JDM, thank you very much for joining us.
It's been a real pleasure to talk to you.
Is there any way you'd like to send folks?
Yeah, you can check out serverbuilds.net.
Like I said in the intro,
the website's a little stale right now.
Really everything's happening on the forums,
which is forums.serverbuilds.net.
And you're on Twitter, aren't you?
I'm on Twitter.
I don't really do a whole lot on there.
Apart from give me grief about my TV stand.
That's true.
At JDM underscore what with three A's.
You can also just hit me on Discord.
Everyone bothers me on Discord.
I think we've got about 8,000 members in our server.
So it's growing and it's pretty large.
We'll put a link to the Discord
and the forums in the show notes.
And I think it's a great companion Discord to our own.
Those are two Discords in a pod.
Is that a thing?
Can we make that a thing?
Oh, absolutely.
I think we should do like a partnered Discord something
and maybe just cross link or something like that.
I love it.
And you've given me a lot to think about.
I think the laptop is a serious route
that I'm gonna consider when the Pi experiment ends.
And now it's just a matter of how soon
does the grand experiment end
and can I find the right ThinkPad on eBay?
I'm kind of hoping I can stretch it out long enough
to get a great deal on a 10th gen
to really take advantage of QuickSync.
Think about it this way.
You don't need a ThinkPad
because that is their sort of mid to upper tier laptop.
You just need the hardware.
The screen doesn't matter.
Keyboard doesn't matter.
Mouse doesn't matter.
It's really just what CPU does it have?
Does it have the NVMe slots that I need
or hard drive slots?
How much RAM can it support?
And that's about it.
It makes a good point, Chris.
Wise words, JDM.
Maybe we'll have you back when I do make the switch.
Oh, awesome.
I would look forward to it.
And just one other thing.
There is one guide that I do want you to check out, Chris.
I wrote it about a year ago.
It's called how to create a mobile media server
with Plex's new app for Windows.
So right now it's a Windows thing only,
but it would be somewhat interesting to you particularly
because what you can do is, just to give a TLDR,
you can use Plex's new app,
download media from any shared server onto the app,
like you're syncing it locally,
and then also run Plex Media Server on that computer
and then share that media out.
Oh, sure, sure.
It's really easy and it's got a nice UI.
It's not an intended use for the app, but it does work.
So check that one out.
I just found it.
I will.
Thanks very much, JDM, for joining us.
Thanks, guys, for having me.
I hope I could, I mean,
I know we talked about a lot of different things,
but the rabbit hole goes way deeper.
We'll have to chat more.
Well, I look forward to chatting on Discord,
but I look forward to having you back on the show too.
Of course.
Thanks for having me, guys.
Appreciate it.
I'll see you guys next time.