So the last episode, 69, we recorded on 420, and today, somehow, is Star Wars Day!
Happy Star Wars Day, everybody!
Yay!
I mean, that joke was funny when I was about eight years old, and it's... still funny now?
Is it?
I've never been a big Star Wars guy.
Oh...
I'm not like an anti-Star Wars guy at all.
I'll enjoy me a little Star Wars, but I just haven't really been into much, other than the Mandalorian, which is fantastic.
But who shot first? That's the question.
We all know who shot first. Han shot first. Come on.
Well, of course, joining me today, we have Chris. Hello, Chris.
Hello!
Brent.
Who you all know from Linux Unplugged.
And we also have from our Discord, for our community spotlight this episode, Fuzzy Mistborn.
Hello, Fuzzy.
Hello!
Nice to catch up with you again.
We met you at the meetup, didn't we?
Yes, you did.
And you were the guy with the Steam Deck that we were all very jealous of, and the electric car, and...
We'll get into all that business in just a little bit.
But I think Chris has got an update about his new show festival.
Oh, really? You're going to... Oh, thanks, Alex.
Yeah, well, actually, I wanted to mention it here on the show because we are kicking off a total website rebuild project.
And Alex, you joined me with Brent and Wes on the last episode,
and we talked about what we want to do, and how we kind of want to build the new website,
and we're taking in ideas, and we've launched some GitHub projects around it.
And so all of the details are in Office Hours 3.
So if you go to officehours.hair.com,
then you can listen to that episode and hear what Alex and I had to say about what we want to do with the new JB website.
And we're really looking for input because we have to have it done by the end of summer,
because Scale Engine, who we've been with for like 12, 13 years, I was just looking,
they are no longer in the WordPress biz.
Nothing like a deadline, is there?
Yeah, and so they're getting out of it by the end of summer.
And so we got to get the website moved, and we want to rebuild it, and we want to self-host it, of course.
So officehours.hair, help us figure it out, join the conversation.
We'll figure it out together.
There's a link in the show notes to a very active GitHub issue, actually,
where there's lots of people throwing out lots of different ideas about how we can self-host different stacks,
anything from Ghost to GitLab to Grav to Hugo, all those sorts of things.
Like Chris says, there's an Office Hours episode where we all discuss the various requirements that we have, I suppose,
and trying to build like a podcast network website, you know, where there are...
How many shows do you have? Like six? Eight?
Yeah, six shows, I guess. Five active shows, then you have extras, so six.
Yeah, and then you've got a bunch of archive shows, too, which you want to present to people.
And then there's about, I don't know, a million guests on all the shows that you need to update, all their various content.
There's a lot.
And you think, well, we could design a whole database around this.
You could design a whole CMS, you know, if you're not careful.
We're trying to be cognizant of the fact that people will be giving up their free time to help us and all the rest of that.
If you've got any opinions, any thoughts, please head over to the Jupiter Broadcasting GitHub organization
and give us your feedback in the issue number eight linked in the show notes.
I'm excited about what we might build.
We've gotten some really good ideas already, things we hadn't even considered,
like maybe the ability for certain community members to update episode pages and show notes
with things that were either missed or maybe links that die.
There's all kinds of ideas that are floating around right there.
So we're just kicking off the conversation, but we also need to move kind of quick.
It's one of those things.
I can't tell you the number of times as a listener of a various podcast, I go to the show notes.
I'm like, what was that thing?
And they didn't put it in the show notes.
And I know that we are guilty of that, too, because I have listeners writing and tell me that we're guilty of it.
And it would be great if they could, you know, submit their their feedback.
Now, a few episodes ago, we had the orange one on for our very first community member spotlight.
And today we're joined by Fuzzy Mistborn. Hello, Fuzzy.
Hello.
Yeah, so you're drinking a tasty beverage over there. What do you have?
I have a beer from a local brewery that is a triple golden ale.
I see both Brent and our guest have a beer.
I don't have a beer.
Actually, this is a hopped cider.
Thank you very much.
Oh, okay. Okay.
So you and I have been talking for many months, probably over a year at this point in the Discord.
I'd say we're pretty good friends in there.
We've been talking about so many different projects and, you know, EVs, for example,
so many things in common. I thought it'd be great to get you on and talk about various things.
So let's start with that electric car, shall we?
I know it's not self-hosted related, but I'm really curious about how your journey with the Ionic 5 is going.
I've had it now for about a month and so far it's been fantastic.
Of course, the first two weeks of it, I go up to my parents who live about four hours away
and I drive down to Raleigh, which is about eight hours.
So I put about 2,000 miles on the car in about two weeks.
Is there any way to do it? Proper shakedown test.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly. Exactly. That was definitely an experience.
So I definitely got to try out, you know, the rapid charging and seeing how all that works.
How was that? How was the charging? Because it was down, what, I-95?
Yes, pretty much 95 most of the way.
The first time I did it, by my way down, I was kind of ultra conservative and charged wherever I possibly could.
But on the way back, it was only about two charges.
A little bit more comfortable in what the car could do.
And I knew kind of what the range of the vehicle would be when it was saying, you know, you've got 30% left.
I knew I've got X number of miles.
You were feeling a little more adventurous at that point, I see.
Well, you know, whilst you were busy in that delicious old RV with Nixie Pixel, Chris,
I was given a little spin around the block in the Ionic and Fuzzy put his foot down a couple of times.
That was fun. I was pinned back in my seat for sure.
Yes, that is definitely, that still brings a smile to my face every time I drive it.
I throw it in sport mode for a couple of minutes just to accelerate and just like, pew!
That's like the boost noise.
Pew, pew!
Now I want to know, like, are you collecting or do you see any possibilities to collect metrics?
You know where I go with this kind of thing.
I start thinking like, let's collect some data.
There is a Home Assistant integration, but it's honestly not super great, but that's not a fault of the developers.
I mean, there's some stuff missing that I want to see added,
but the major issue just is that Hyundai limits you to about 30 API calls a day.
That's not very many.
No, so the developer actually has put in like there's blackout times at night where from like,
you know, you can customize it, but I think the default is like 10 p.m. to 6 or 7 a.m.
It doesn't make any calls whatsoever just to try and preserve them for you.
But yeah, it's kind of limited in what you can do.
So what I do use is I use a better route planner,
which is great for planning trips because it shows you, you know,
basically you type in, it's like Google Maps for electric vehicles.
And you, you know, say I'm coming from here and I'm going to here, going down to Raleigh,
and it'll say, okay, and you know, here's the car I have,
and it'll basically figure out, okay, you know, you're starting at this percentage battery,
you know, the weather's going to be this, you know, the wind's going to be this,
so therefore it can figure out, okay, you need to stop here, here, and here and charge this amount
to get where you're going.
And as part of the, part of the, one of the ways I improve that is you can get little
ODB2 Bluetooth low-energy devices and plug them into your ODB2 port in your car,
and a better route planner can integrate with that and pull the state of charge off the car.
So therefore it'll, it'll update in real time.
So for example, like when I left to get down to Raleigh the first time,
I said I was going to arrive, you know, my first destination with like 10% charge.
I got there with like 30, and I could see it counting back up as it, you know,
based on the real-time telemetry it was getting.
That's a legit feature.
I didn't actually, I didn't even think about it.
I didn't even realize that electric cars had ODB2 ports.
I suppose they have to by law, but it just never even crossed my mind.
It just seems like such an old archaic, you know, the whole CAN bus thing just seems so old.
You and I got burned by that automatic thing, do you remember?
Oh, I loved automatic too, even though they were sloping up all my data,
but they tracked every drive that I did in the RV for the first few years.
So I had this brilliant heat map of everywhere we had been in the RV.
It was, it was great, and it got all my fuel mileage info for me.
I'd love to have that again.
We've talked about that a little bit on the show, trying to recreate that.
Yeah, there's an app called Torque that I've been trying to play with
that might let thing, let me kind of upload it into Home Assistant.
I couldn't quite get it to work and I haven't had a chance to go back to it,
but that would supposedly let me upload that information directly into Home Assistant
and have sensors and data that way.
But honestly, I charge the car once a week, you know, on Sunday night,
Sunday Home Assistant will ping me if the battery is below, you know,
I think 50% and you know, I can go and plug it in.
It'll charge up overnight in a couple hours.
And honestly, I basically, you're only supposed to charge about 80% at any given,
you know, you're only supposed to charge to 100 if you're actually going to be going somewhere long distance.
So usually 80% is enough to get me through the entire week.
That's so cool.
So how about a seamless segue? Shall we switch gears?
Oh!
That was questionable.
Top Gear?
Oh, yes, Top Gear. Where's Jeremy?
I've been following your blog for a long time at blog.fuzzymissborn.com
and there's so many posts on there that we could talk about,
but there's one in particular which really has my interest peaked right now
and that is the Renovate Bot one.
I'm curious to ask you what you're using Renovate Bot for
and what your experience has been with it.
So Renovate Bot, I have run on my infrastructure Ansible GitHub repo.
And basically what it will do is it will go through,
I don't even, I don't even, honestly, you can self-host it, I don't.
So I don't know how often the publicly hosted one goes through,
but it's honestly pretty fast, like maybe in every hour or so it runs.
And it basically runs through whatever I tell it to run through
and will tell me, for example, for mine,
it'll tell me if there's new Docker images available.
You know, for all my Docker compose stuff,
I'll, you know, state, you know, home assistant slash,
you know, whatever slash, what does it say, 2022.05.01.
And it'll go through and say, oh, well, there's.02 available
and it'll create a pull request on the infrastructure repo
that I can then go in and say, yes, you know, merge this
or hang on, this is actually a beta or, oh no,
I'm seeing there are some issues with it.
So I don't actually have to merge it until I need to.
So what exactly does it do?
It's like a GitOps style way of working, right?
It looks at the upstream images and says, you know,
there's a new home assistant container
and it creates a pull request, right, against your repo
and then what?
Basically that's it, it creates a pull request.
I can see, you know, basically you can actually even,
you can customize, I don't even honestly scratch the surface
of what it can do.
You can, you know, go ahead and auto merge, you know,
minor updates, so if it's like, you know, a.01 release,
you can tell it just to automatically merge that for you,
you know, and save the major revisions for, you know,
manual review or, I mean, honestly,
I barely scratched the surface of what it can do.
I know a lot of people use it for maintaining their dependencies
for all the different, you know, projects.
They'll use it for, and they'll have just renovate bot,
go through and just automatically update
and merge a lot of the dependency upgrades.
Now, another post that you have on your blog
is your love-hate relationship with drone.io.
But before we get there,
and because you mentioned Top Gear a moment ago,
we do have the Top Gear style leaderboard storage question,
which one of our amazing listeners has added
to the self-hosted Wiki.
So what we're gonna do is set some rules, right?
It's raw storage.
How much raw storage do you have on your LAN?
Here's the, I'm gonna maybe cheat a little bit.
So I have about 10 terabytes that I store offsite
with the, you know, external hard drive
that I leave in the office, you know, at work,
so that way I have, you know, cold storage.
So if we include that, it's about 80 terabytes.
But we don't include that
because we literally just said on your LAN.
I know, but it's on my LAN for like, you know,
a couple hours a month.
Unless we count tail scale as the LAN these days.
So who knows?
Oh boy.
What do we think, audience?
70 or 80 terabytes?
Let me know in the chat,
and we'll submit a pull request to the repo
before the end of the show, hopefully.
I need to do a calculation on my end
now that we have these new servers in-house, too.
There's two boxes, and each have 48 terabytes of storage,
and then we have 24 terabytes of storage in the old server.
Not to mention the Bitcoin node has, what, two?
Is it two we threw in there?
Eight terabytes, eight terabytes.
Yeah, in the Bitcoin node.
Yeah, that was an easy store that you shucked.
Yeah, and then hid in his drawer for a year or two.
Right.
So I should do the final calculation
just so we have it up to date.
All right, so we're going with 80 terabytes then, are we?
Eight, zero.
Oh, that's because everybody likes him in the Discord.
That's what's up.
Thank you, thank you, audience.
Jeff Gehling has 84 terabytes.
So that puts you in fourth spot, Fuzzy.
Good job.
Yeah, I've got some worsting in the back bin,
but I won't conclude that.
Well, what you do is when you get it online,
you come back on the show, and then you can beat him.
I actually have to get more room in my storage server.
I am maxed out.
That's just it.
Density is a thing, people.
Hey, man, it's not my problem.
If you want to be on the winner board or not,
I mean, it's just not my problem.
You just got to do what you got to do.
All right, so should we get back to the drone.io love-hate
relationship thing?
What's that all about?
I'm actually not an engineer or any kind of technical field.
I'm a lawyer by profession.
So I sort of dabbled in all this for fun.
And so I started looking at drone because there were some
things that I wanted to automate in terms of building Docker
images and some other stuff.
And I know GitHub Actions was out there,
but this is self-hosted.
I want to learn how to do this all myself.
So drone is a CI-CD system with continuous integration,
continuous deployment, where basically you can,
it's very similar to GitHub Actions or Jenkins or some of
the other ones that are, I think Circle CI is another one.
Basically, you can do anything you can do in a Bash script.
Like I basically use it to do a bunch of Bash commands
on some things.
It builds a bunch of my Docker images for me.
I built actually, one of the recent things I did was I
actually started building an Ubuntu server image every week
that gets deployed into a Nextcloud.
So that way I just have a constantly up-to-date cloud
and knitted ISO image.
I've had a few issues with drone myself, actually.
Like just for no apparent reason, a job that I've set up,
the build will stop running automatically
for no apparent reason.
Like I will push something to my GitT instance.
The build will detect that it's been pushed,
but nothing happens.
And I can't figure out exactly quite what's going on there.
So I delete the build in drone and then I recreate it
and it's fine for a couple of weeks.
And then the same thing happens
and it's infuriating, if I'm honest.
Drone, so the issues I had with it,
as I kind of laid out in the post, were, you know,
it's really good,
but the documentation was pretty poor in some ways.
Like the one thing I remember,
I was actually looking through the post again recently,
cron, cron jobs.
You couldn't tell it a time zone.
So therefore it defaulted to, you know, GMT, you know,
Greenwich Mean Time.
And I couldn't figure out how to get it on my time zone,
which was annoying.
So I had to always think five hours difference.
Hey man, I've made a career out of that.
Ba-dum-bum.
Actually, I'm just kind of curious
because you did tease a little Home Assistant action there.
Can you give us just kind of a rough idea
of the Home Assistant setup, what it's running on
and sort of the key things you have it doing for you?
Just like a picture.
I run Home Assistant in Docker.
It's running on my Proxmox server downstairs
in the basement.
The main backbone of what I run here is Z-Wave.
All my switches are Z-Wave.
I have a bunch of sensors that are Z-Wave though.
I've started using a lot more ZigBee sensors
just because they're cheaper
and I found they work a little bit better than the Z-Wave.
Better in what way?
So I got these Z-Wave sensors
that were for a company called Dome.
I think it was the name, Dome.
And I think they've gone out of business
since they made these.
Uh-oh.
Yeah, so they work, oh, they work pretty well,
but they're also, I think they were about 35 or 40 bucks
versus the ZigBee Aquara buttons are like 20.
So I have them all over the house
because one of the big things I have here
is I have all the lights are on automation.
So every time motion's detected,
with certain current parameters are met,
the lights will turn on
and then after a set period of time, they'll turn off.
Sure, nice.
Did you then I assume go through the Z-Wave migration
that I have been putting off?
Yes, I did.
I am on the Z-Wave JS.
I've been on it for probably over a year now.
Oh, rub it in.
Originally, what I had done was I actually,
I got to the Z-Wave network rebooting
took like five, 10, 15, 20 minutes sometimes
for me to reboot Home Assistant
where it would just sit there spinning
and it would take forever for the network to come back up.
And so I actually got tired of that to the point
where I actually created a separate Home Assistant instance
that only ran Z-Wave.
Huh, interesting idea.
And I bridged it with MQTT to my main instance.
And you're still doing it that way now?
No, no, no, so I was doing that for a while
and then the Open Z-Wave came out
and I'm like, oh, let me give this a try
and see if this is better and it was,
but then obviously that got deprecated and moved on.
So I'm like, well, I'm kind of on a dead end here
and I've already done the pain once
I might as well change it all.
So I upgraded to the Z-Wave JS
and honestly it's worked brilliantly.
There's been a couple of things where like the lock I have,
the Schlage lock, I had to create a couple of sensors
to kind of get back some functionality
that was default on Open Z-Wave
for like what guest code and what door codes use.
Cause one of the things I have is if a door code is used,
like if I create a one-time guest code, if it's used,
it'll actually delete that code after it's used.
That's great.
That is cool.
So it recycles once a week.
I get a telegram ping saying, here's the new guest code.
I can give that out to people
if they need to get into my house for whatever reason,
then it'll delete itself.
I would imagine you're probably in pretty good shape too
because I thought I heard today on the live stream
that the Z-Wave JS maintainer now works full time
for Nebuchadnezzar.
So they're gonna be probably keeping that
in pretty good shape.
Yes, I had heard that.
I think I'd seen that as well.
And I'm actually in the process of building a new house.
And so I'm actually gonna keep using Z-Wave there
for the switches just because I hadn't been able to find
any kind of Zigbee equivalent that allows dimming
and switches for a reasonable price.
I know Inovelli just came out with their blue switches,
but they're like $45 a switch.
The brand I like is Zoos
or I guess it's sold by the smartest home
and they're about $25 a switch.
Yeah, Z-O-O-Z is the brand.
Now I know that you have some like whiz bang traffic
like system to tell your kids it's okay
to get up in the morning.
Like as a new parent, I need to absorb this.
Tell me, yeah, I wanna hear about this too.
One of the things that I did
that my wife absolutely loves
is I have a Raspberry Pi that I installed Volumio on
that acts as a sound machine.
So it just plays white noise for the kids
and there's a door sensor on the door
that when it's closed and the light turns off,
it turns on the sound machine.
Now I've gone through different variations
of how you turn the sound machine off in the morning,
but it'll also automatically turn off in the morning.
What I do is actually that's kind of in handy
for doing things like the okay to wake clock,
which are useful for toddlers
because they obviously can't read a clock yet.
But they can, they do know their colors.
So my three-year-old for a long time,
what I do is about, it used to be an hour,
but then he started getting up earlier.
So now I've pushed it to about a half hour
before he's supposed to wake up.
I have a Z-Wave bulb in his room that will turn on red
and that's kind of, he knows if he wakes up,
he's not allowed to get out of bed.
He still does sometimes,
but most of the time he knows if it's red,
he's not supposed to get out of bed.
Whenever the time actually strikes
that he's allowed to wake up,
it turns green.
The other thing I've done is I have an ESP board
running WLED under his bed
that also if he gets out of bed
in the middle of the night and the door opens,
the light turns on red, pretty dims,
that way he can see and not trip over his feet
or actually get into bed at night.
He finds that to be a lot of fun.
That's really cool.
I mean, it's pretty cruel of you to keep your kid
in their bedroom until midday, but hey.
I wish midday usually 5 a.m.
I know, yeah.
Speaking of quality of life improvements,
like I could see how that would make the entire household
just way better instead of this random time thing
that many of us have experienced.
It worked well for the first little bit.
He's gotten, he goes in phases of obeying it and not
because yet he's three.
So I can't exactly fault him.
Hey, maybe I need to get one of those from my wife.
Actually, one of my all-time favorite automations I have
is so I have it on my blog somewhere,
but you basically I have two pieces of aluminum foil
that's over a piece of cardboard
and I have it underneath the bed tied to an ESP 32.
And when I get into bed at night, the lights all turn off.
That's great.
That's hilarious.
And if one of us gets out of bed at night,
the light turns on, you know, again, reds,
that way you can see and not trip over all the stuff
that's on the floor.
Is this motion?
Is it pressure sensing?
What's happening?
It's pressure sensitive.
So basically, it's when there's enough pressure
on the cardboard, it basically pushes through.
There's a capacitive, I don't know if it's capacitive
or whatever it is, but there's enough of a connection.
It changes the resistive load so that the ESP
can pick up that slight difference
and trigger based on that.
You nerds.
Honestly, I was shocked how well it worked.
Again, there's like, you know, Sleep IQ sells
like a $200 version of this kind of a thing.
I think I put it together for like 50 bucks.
Well, Fuzzy, thank you very much for coming on.
I think you're going to stick around
for the second half of the show.
Is there anywhere that, whilst you've got the mic,
you'd like to send people?
Blog.FuzzyMissBorn.com.
Very good.
And of course, on the Discord as well.
Yes, that's probably one of the best ways to get me
if you want to talk to me.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account
and you go there to support this year's show.
Linode is the tinker's cloud.
You know what I'm saying?
Like, you could just deploy everything with one click.
Like, I was just looking today and they have a one click
for PyHole on Linode.
And I started thinking like, that could be great
for my son's laptop.
That could be excellent for mobile devices.
So if you want to go that route, you can.
But if you want to tinker, like I'm saying,
like you want to go all the way down to the metal
and then like deploy your own custom system,
Linode lets you do that.
They got guides, they got information on how to do that,
and they've got the best support in the business.
But if you like performance,
they've also got something for you there too.
NVME hard drives, AMD EPYC CPUs, dedicated GPU rigs
if you want 40 gigabit connection to the hypervisors,
11 data centers around the world in strategic places
where they are their own ISP.
You see what I'm saying?
Nobody does it like Linode.
And I love their object storage.
Their S3 compatible object storage is like my superpower.
I use it for all kinds of things.
I needed to just test a new RSS format
and I just needed to like have an XML file
that was publicly available for like 30 minutes.
Like, what was I going to do?
Put that on a web server like an animal?
No, I put it up on object storage like a gentleman.
And of course their API is great.
Their command line client is quick.
There's so many things I love about it,
but just go try it out for yourself.
Best customer support, super fast networking,
crazy fast rigs, and a Linux culture that runs deep.
That's Linode right there.
That's why I choose to use them for two and a half years now.
Everything we've built in the last two and a half years,
I put it up on Linode.
Go try it out and get $100 while you support the show.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Now today for the show,
I thought I'd spin up a Google Analytics alternative
called Plausible.
This is a lightweight open source web analytics engine.
Hold on, I've got a Google,
would you call it screen on my desk next to me?
Oh yeah, the assistant.
I think it's grumpy because it's literally just pulled up.
It's time to ditch Google Analytics on the screen.
It's listening.
It knows now, now they've logged that.
Absolutely, yeah, so I'm in trouble with the big G.
But anyway, this Plausible thing
doesn't require any user acceptable cookies.
You know that annoying GDPR pop-up thing?
It's fully compliant with that
as well as several other things.
It's made and hosted in the EU.
So let me clarify, there is a hosted version.
I'm talking about the self-hosted version,
which is just something you can run in a container.
I chose to put mine up on Linode,
but you could run it at home, any way you like.
I found the setup process was kind of a pain in the bum.
Oh really?
Took me about two or three hours to get through in the end.
The reason for that is because to spin up this thing,
it's about, I think it's four containers as a database.
There is a, it's like a queuing engine,
like a Redis style thing called ClickHouse.
There's the app itself, and then there's an SMTP relay.
So those four containers come together
to form the app that is plausible.
But of course, their documentation
doesn't quite tell you all the little tricks you need to do
and all the environment variables you need to specify
to get it up and running properly,
which is super annoying.
The Docker compose script
that they have actually linked in their documentation
is about two years old.
And so I was going through following this thing
and looking at the version numbers, and then I thought,
right, I'll just go and check the latest tag in Docker Hub.
Yeah, two years old, completely out of date,
hasn't been touched.
So then I went to the real orange one's GitHub
and looked at what he's doing,
because I know he runs plausible too.
And his GitHub repo combined with their documentation,
I eventually got it up and running.
And once I did, I was super duper happy with this thing.
You know, I had to embed a little JavaScript header
in each webpage that I wanted to track.
And within a minute or two,
I could see people showing up straight away.
So my MKdocs website at perfectmediaserver.com,
my ghost blog at blog.ktz.me,
I even put selfhosted.show on there as well,
just as a test.
And I gotta say, it was pretty flawless.
Are you getting real time numbers?
Yep.
Ah, I love that.
Okay, so you took a couple hours to get up and running.
And now once it's up,
is it something that you're putting like on the public web?
How is that working?
Is it behind a firewall and can you give access to others?
So there's a few different things you can do.
By default, it's limited to authenticated users,
you know, to the admin user that you create
and any other users that you create in the app itself.
But when you and I were talking before the show,
I thought, oh, it'd be cool if I could just show Chris
what I'm doing here.
And so for the selfhosted.show thing,
I went into the site settings for that specific site.
And there's a whole list of things I can do.
So I can not only make this publicly available,
I've just switched this on.
So I'm actually gonna put this in the chat room
so the live stream can go and have a look
at the analytics that we pulled up today on selfhosted.show.
So that's a public version that we can do,
but I can also give specific users
like an obfuscated link.
So I can say, right, I want to share this specific thing
with this email address
and I'm gonna give them a password
and it expires after a certain length of time.
Can you imagine doing that for like a sponsor or something?
Right, that is a fantastic feature
just from like working with somebody for a short period of time.
The one thing that I found when you gave me the link
and I kind of looked around in there
is it doesn't seem like it goes as deep maybe
as Google Analytics does.
Like Google Analytics, you could just keep drilling down
and down and down and getting more specifics.
This is a little higher level.
Like it tells you everything you need to know.
Your unique visitors, your total page views,
your bounce rate, and the average visit duration.
And of course, your top sources and your top pages
and the locations in which they come from
and the types of devices they use.
So it's all, it's all what you need.
It's not, nothing's really missing
and it'd be fine for what we use,
but it did seem like maybe not quite as detailed
as the Google stuff might be.
Do you agree with that?
That's the price you pay
for not having surveillance capitalism
be the driver of everything.
Right.
I'm not trying to get political,
but I am gonna have a little bit of a rant
about the death of democracy and social media
and everything in the last six to ten years
and I could go off the rails, but I'm not going to here.
I'm gonna keep it on topic.
And you know, that's one of the things I like
about Plausible actually is that because it's so lightweight
and because it's so privacy friendly and privacy focused,
I turned off privacy badger to make it work
on my web browser, but I didn't, you know,
I had a look at the trackers and it was very minimal
what it was doing compared to what Google Analytics does.
I really liked that.
I mean, for me, that's a feature.
I completely agree.
We stopped using Google Analytics
just because I'm creeped out by Google, but you know,
I didn't really replace it with anything.
So something that we could run ourselves
on our own infrastructure and you know,
use that data just so we get an idea of maybe
how our website's performing because you know,
one of the things you can figure out is maybe
there's something wrong with the site.
Maybe there's a design issue.
There's insights that you miss and you know,
your web page for online businesses
is the front of your store.
So that's pretty great.
And I guess they do have a pay version too as well, right?
So if you wanted to, you could go all in
on their hosted version.
It doesn't look like it's that expensive
unless you get like millions of views
and it gets up to like 90 bucks a month
if you get 2 million views.
Yeah, I suppose compared to Google's low, low price of free,
but you are the product, it's expensive,
but I'd rather support companies that are willing
to give their software away like this than Google sometimes.
Now Fuzzy, I know that you use a different one.
Was it called Umami or something?
Yeah, I think it's pronounced Umami.
I think the orange one on Discord was talking
about plausible at one point.
So I was like, oh, I kind of want to get away
from Google too, like everybody does who self hosts.
And so I went and tried to try to spin it up
and I ran into the same exact problem you did where I'm,
generally I try and avoid apps
that require more than like two containers.
I just don't like ones that are that complicated.
I just feel like it's defeats the purpose of Docker.
Like I remember one time I tried to spin up a Unify thing
and it was literally like 10 containers.
I'm like, no, no.
So Umami is only two containers.
There's the database portion of it
that I can run in MariaDB.
And then there's the actual Umami collection thing.
And from looking at what you posted on Discord
and the website, Umami looks pretty much exactly the same.
I don't know in terms of like features
and the dashboard and everything,
but like I can see the same exact things
where I can see what pages got hit,
where the source was from, the country,
you know, desktop versus laptop versus tablet, all that.
I can see the same thing.
So if you're looking for something a little bit simpler
to set up, it might be a decent option.
I'll put a link to Umami in the show notes.
Now, Alex, when you were showing me earlier today,
plausible in your excitedness,
you were describing the different containers
and how at first, maybe once you're getting into it,
it's a little bit more complex to get set up.
But you did say that that was actually
a really nice engineering decision for scalability.
Can you talk on that a little bit?
Yeah, absolutely.
So if you look at the way in which, say,
GitLab is architected, right?
They provide a big bastard container
that is like six gigs of RAM, does eight million processes,
and completely is antithetical to the entire purpose
of containers and microservices, right?
It's one big monolith that they deploy.
And if you want to spin up an extra worker
or anything like that, like, it's just a mess.
And I really hate that way of doing things.
And the Unify controller and Plex is kind of the same, right?
It has a database built into it.
And actually, if you're thinking about it,
it would be nice if Plex had a separate database container
that lives somewhere else that I could back up
and version independently of Plex itself.
And that's one of the things I liked about Plausible
is that because it has so many containers,
you've got that queuing engine,
the click house thing I talked about
that operates in a similar kind of space to Redis
that basically takes all the requests in in real time.
Its only job is to listen and receive stuff.
And then Plausible has workers that goes
and processes those requests in real time.
Now, a poorly architected application
would only have one container doing that.
And it would ingest all of that stuff
into the primary container.
And then when that queue or that buffer
or whatever it is gets full,
the container would start to slow down,
it might have a memory leak, it might crash,
all that kind of stuff.
But by having the queue somewhere else,
you leave Plausible itself as this controlled environment
and it's able to not fall into that same trap
as a lot of other applications do.
Also, the data store being an external Postgres database,
I have no problem with that.
Yeah, no, I don't have an issue
with databases being separate, I just, I don't know.
When I start seeing that many containers,
it just becomes frustrating for me to have to manage and...
No, I get it, it puts you off, doesn't it?
You sort of look at this thing and you go,
I can grok and understand this in three seconds
if it's one or two containers,
but if it starts to get to three or four or five or more,
you're like, eh, I'll do it next time.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
That's sort of my line too.
My last question on it, Alex, really is,
did you notice much in terms of load time difference
on the sites after you put it on there?
Because you toss a little bit of JavaScript
in the header, essentially,
and then you're off to the races.
Did you try benchmarking or at least refresh
and see if it seemed any slower?
Because I've also experienced that.
I used to use a locally hosted analytics software
that actually slowed the website down,
so we had to bail on it.
I personally didn't notice any difference
and that's totally anecdotal,
but I run Privacy Badger anyway,
so I don't have a lot of Google Analytics
and a lot of JavaScript running anyway.
What I will say is on the plausible website,
take this with a grain of salt,
they say that their script is 45 times smaller
than Google Analytics.
So... Smaller tends to be faster.
Yeah, and they reckon that because it's so much smaller,
a site with 10,000 monthly visitors
will save four and a half kilos of CO2 emissions per year
simply by switching to plausible.
So, do your bit for the planet, people.
Right. Drop Google to save the planet.
Tailscale.com slash self-hosted.
Go there to get a free personal account
for up to 20 devices and you support the show.
Tailscale is a zero-config VPN.
It installs on any device, manages your firewall rules,
gets you going in just seconds from anywhere.
Devices connect directly to each other
using WireGuard's noise protocol.
So you build a mesh network
using the best VPN security in the business.
It really changes the game.
I have to say, too, I was really excited this morning
to see that they just raised $100 million
in Series B funding.
And here's what they said about it.
Why'd they do this?
Because they're paranoid, they say.
This isn't their first rodeo
and we don't know where the economy or the market might go.
And we don't want to be pressured
into juicing our growth numbers beyond where they belong.
We don't want to put revenue ahead of quality.
Man, it really shows in their product, too.
You know, you have a flat network
where you get a static IP address
for every device you care about.
You can assign them a DNS name.
It's always connected. They're always encrypted.
It even works with double carrier NAT.
It is fantastic.
And I opened a support ticket with them recently.
I exceeded my number of subnet routers that I'm allowed.
They have a soft limit of one per free account.
I had three, so you know,
three times what the soft limit is.
And it says, you are encouraged to upgrade your account
if you exceed for, you know, a length of time.
These are only soft limits, don't worry.
We won't enforce them, but you're encouraged to upgrade.
So I sent in a support ticket saying,
hey, which tier should I be on?
You know, I kind of want to give you some money
because I think you're awesome.
And they wrote back and said, no, it's okay.
Just tell people about us. It's cool.
They've also written a blog post
about how they've built a sustainable infrastructure.
So listeners of our show might be really interested in that.
And it goes into their whole philosophy
about making this thing work for the long haul.
And I am so grateful because it's changed the way I work
and it changes the way I do tech support with my family.
It makes it when I'm remote.
It makes it so seamless now.
Go check it out and support the show
and get it for free for up to 20 devices.
It's tailscale.com slash self-hosted.
Alex, we've been having a few adventures.
Why don't you tell us a story?
Well, I took Brent down to my basement the other day.
He still has all those limbs. It's okay.
I think they're all still intact anyway,
because one of my hard drives
has been dropping off the SATA bus this week.
I didn't know why.
And so we went down and took a look at this thing.
And I think I did this maybe two or three months ago.
I took the cable out and then put the cable back in
and it worked perfectly for another two to three months.
Oh yeah, that's what I've been doing with my machine here.
You guys are awful.
Right.
Well, hey, look, sometimes it ain't stupid if it works, Brent.
Yeah, but it is almost guaranteed
to only work for a short period of time.
No, not at all. Not with cables.
In my experience, cables can be finicky little buggers.
You need better ones.
Maybe there's a little vibration, something got loose.
Exactly.
I learned long ago to put SATA cables with a little clips on
because the ones without clips do vibrate out.
I think my issue is likely
I'm not running out of hard drives.
Yeah, yeah.
I think there's about 10 spinning drives in this server.
You know, it's quite a few. So there's a lot of vibration.
So realistically, it could be a cable.
It could be some crosstalk issue
with all those SATA cables running together.
They're plugged into an HBA card, which is a SAS cable.
So it's four SATA cables going into one SAS plug on an HBA card.
So I was thinking maybe it's a bad cable.
So I ordered a new cable off Amazon, put it in, and then...
You ordered the short one.
...realized it was too short and thought,
I'll just go and grab a SATA cable just to tie us over.
And then found in the drawer
that I actually already had the correct cable.
Oh, I've done that. Yep.
I've done that for sure.
So anyway, I connected up the drive
and it wouldn't mount.
Proxmox was going crazy with, you know, XFS errors.
And I was like, uh-oh, here we go.
Smart wasn't showing me anything, but I've seen this before.
It usually means the end of the drive in my experience.
So brought the drive upstairs, took it out of the server,
brought it upstairs, connected it to my little diagnostic station
I've got behind me over here, and ran...
Was it XFS repair?
Yes, it was. I think.
And that rebuilt the log or the...
I don't know, something like that.
The journal?
Yeah, that's it.
It took a good five, 10 minutes to do that,
which was a bit squeaky bum time.
And then it just mounted perfectly.
And, you know, I was listening to the drive the whole time
it was on the table next to me for any audible noises.
You know, I've heard a drive clicking before and it seemed fine.
It was running cool to the touch.
It was behaving properly with the testing that I was doing.
So I thought, okay, let's put it back in the basement server.
And so far, so good.
Oh, I thought this was going somewhere completely different.
I mean, it could.
That'll be the next episode.
RAID is not a backup, people.
This is true.
Alex, I'm curious what you think the issue was
and what you think the issue might be considering
it still seems a little kind of like it may happen again.
Seems fine now.
I actually ran a bajillion SnapRaid checks and fixes
and syncs and rebuilds and everything I could throw at this drive
to stress it without actually wiping it and doing like a bad blocks run
or something just to try and poke the bee's nest a little bit.
And for me, I think it's going to be fine.
But originally I suspect there was either an issue with the power supply cable
and maybe it sort of the voltage dipped slightly and it dropped off the bus
a little bit in the middle of a write transaction or something
and that corrupted the log or the data cable was bad, which I have replaced now.
So, you know, in terms of variables and stuff like that,
if something goes wrong with it again, I will know it's not the cable.
I will know it's the drive.
Now, this is a shucked drive originally and it's still within warranty.
So actually part of me is kind of curious just to send it into Western Digital
and see what they say.
Did you keep the shucked bits?
No, there is some like forget the name of it.
It's like Magnuson Moss Act or something that you can you can quote to them
and they have to fix it either way.
Yeah, because they can't prove that my shucking broke the, you know,
the whatever it is inside the drive.
That is shockingly pro-consumer.
I know, right?
It's almost like we're in Europe.
Chris has a drive that he shucked,
but he definitely modified the drive by breaking the pin off,
which was quite clever.
Well, now that is physical damage.
I don't do that.
I do the captain tape or I just snip the three-volt rail on the power supply cable.
I wanted it fixed forever and let's be honest, I'm never sending it in.
I'm never going to do that.
We also didn't have any tape.
Yeah, we did look for the tape and I'm like screw this break.
Alex, I'm curious.
What did you end up doing with the cable?
Which one the faulty cable?
Yes, the faulty one.
Did you just put it back in your drawer with the others?
I think I might have done.
Alex.
Who knows?
It's a mystery box of fun.
Next time there's a drive problem.
Yeah, right.
So here's my solution to the 3.3.
I'm showing the live stream on camera.
I just cut the three-volt cable in my SATA.
Like I have these like you plug one SATA cable in here, power cable in and then you get four like power plugs here.
And if you just cut the three-volt wire here, this one, then you don't have to worry about captain tape or you know,
physically damaging your drives.
You just run them all off these.
There must be some voltage going through those.
Could they like arc or something?
Do you do anything to?
There's some electrical tape on it, but I mean, it's three volts.
Yeah, it's three volts.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So it's at most it's going to be like a little tingle.
I don't mean for you.
I just wondered, you know, maybe I should try licking it next time.
See what happened the old the old D cell test.
Yeah.
No, I think it's more fun.
Just leave it uncapped and that way you next time you're rooting around in the case.
Just a little a little, you know, like operation.
I've got a question for you guys with wedding rings and stuff.
Like when I run digging around in a PC that's on I will take my wedding ring off because there was one time at the Apple store where I didn't and I actually shorted out a customer's motherboard.
It hurt quite a bit too.
I have never taken my wedding ring off to do any hardware work the watch.
Sometimes the watch sometimes I will if I'm like, you know rooting around deep inside the case and physically can't reach wherever I am, but I've never had to take that.
I've never had an arcing from my ring.
I have to take off the watch.
I don't like the watch on the wrist when like, you know the edge of the case and I'm rooting around in there and I'm smacking the watch up against those sharp edges scratches it all up same when I'm like working on like a project in the RV.
I have to take the watch off.
I actually don't wear the ring though anymore.
I just sort of gave up on that.
My whole body size changes all the time.
And so I'd go from like a ring that was too tight to a ring that was too loose.
This is also why I became a suspenders guy.
See, I learned my lesson.
My parents used to have those old school Christmas lights and I was always one of putting up the Christmas lights and there were enough times I broke the bulb and was trying to get it out and I stupidly did not unplug the strand.
And I shocked myself more times than I care to admit.
Well, it's one of those things that once it happens you watch out for for the rest of your life.
I imagine right?
Yeah, it definitely is.
I think the thing that zapped me was one of the MagSafe 19 volt things like a laptop and yeah, it's done quite a bit and actually there was a it took a little bit out of my wedding ring.
Like it was there's a little notch in it.
You can just see oh man.
Yeah, that's here near miss.
I had to fill out accident report forms and all they sent me home.
And that's just like an awkward conversation when you come home to it's like a well kind of damaged my wedding ring, honey.
Yeah.
Oh, well, we got some boost into the show last week.
We got some people boosting both good and bad things into the show.
Rubik come in Ruby Ruby Kinman Ruby man, Rubik.
All right, Rubik man.
I think my wife and I are moving to a new apartment soon.
We have permission from the landlord to install a camera pointed at the parking lot.
Can you recommend one that works with home assistant for a decent price now?
He doesn't tell us what his connectivity situation is.
So what are your thoughts Alex?
You could just get a dog and point that at the car park, you know, that would bark quite a bit.
I mean the obvious choice despite all their flaws really the wisecams.
Yeah, that's what I was probably going to say too.
We're actually going to have our next boost here that kind of makes it that makes them even more appealing sexy pants boosted in for 210 sats.
So this dropped on reddit yesterday.
It supports USB Ethernet adapters tail scale and it runs an RTMP server.
It'll even make you tacos.
Well, maybe not that but it's essentially a series of wise hacks.
That I think make these cameras even more compelling especially when you can when you combine it with something like wise bridge.
So I have a link in the show notes to a github repo that lets you essentially root the devices and get more out of them.
Can you imagine the possibilities of running tail scale on the camera itself?
That's cool.
That opens up a whole new kind of like, well, it's a whole new world as they say.
The other cameras as far as like just connect them to Wi-Fi and they have decent apps that also work with home assistant is the logi circle.
However, I've had mixed results with that, but that's also another option.
If you have a recommendation for a cheap portable camera that's easy to power and easy to get connected, send us a boost and let us know.
I actually have a good one.
The eufy cams, I've actually been a huge fan of.
They are basically the same price as the wise ones.
They come built in with RTSP.
They're running throughout my house.
I have about six of them.
I have the doorbell and they work just fine.
And I also hear in the home kit community that they work really well with home kit setup as well.
Haven't tried it, but that does sound good.
Sir Lurks-a-Lot wrote in with two boosts.
The first one reads, autonomous spinning blades?
Oh, homeowner's liability insurance coverage or not.
I would be uneasy about this Robomower running unsupervised, which is all too likely, I fear.
PSA, lawnmowers are not toys and can cause serious harm to both critters and children.
Nevermind stupid adults.
This ain't a silly vacuum.
Just think bloody toes and see how that sits before deploying.
Situations vary, of course, just remain aware that unplanned lawn intrusions and obstacles do happen.
I mean, it's actually a fair point.
So last week we talked about a robot lawnmower and none of us actually mentioned the safety angle of it.
However, I think it's just kind of an assumed that people would be careful with this kind of thing.
But then Lurks-a-Lot had another boost for us too.
They continue.
Oh, so I finally saw the video of this OpenMore project.
I imagine something much larger and dangerous from a DIY project.
Well, I still believe in safety first.
This does not conjure quite the nightmare scenarios I imagined when I hadn't seen the thing yet.
Yeah, it's more like the size of a vacuum.
There was a, speaking of the little robot vacuums, a local town here in Washington, Bellevue.
A homeowner called the cops because they thought somebody had broken into their house.
A burglar was in the house with them and they were panicked.
Turned out robot vacuum wasn't actually a burglar.
Oh, gosh.
I'm actually thinking, as I said, getting a new house and it's going to have almost an acre of land.
I'm actually looking at some of these robo-mowers just because I don't want to have to mow that much land.
Seriously.
You're just going to have to get a lawn tractor, dude, and just be done with it.
Just admit it.
I don't want one because they basically cost the same.
Like, they're like $2,500 and the robo-mowers are like $2,500 and they'll install it for me for free.
Has anyone told you that you get to sit on top of a giant engine and go,
vroom, vroom, vroom, vroom, vroom, as you go along?
They're so much fun.
Says the guy who has an EV.
Yeah, no.
Oh, okay.
All right.
Well, you can get electric ones too.
Yeah, those are even more expensive.
But yeah, no, I actually have been looking at these robo-mowers and I actually want one because they actually do have a safety thing where if you pick them up, they actually shuts off.
Oh, sure.
Okay.
That's good to know too.
Yeah, I'd be looking at one too.
Crashmaster18 wrote in, said he really liked the live format we did last week.
Having multiple people on too, hopes it sticks.
And he also likes the idea of the open mower.
He hopes that we'll give him an update if one of us picks one up.
It'll turn off if you do that.
Right.
Don't pick one up.
And the final bit of feedback for this week, Kars Pieland writes in with 3,690 SATs.
Thanks for the show.
Nice and simple.
Well, thank you, Kars.
Thank you very much.
You think 3,690 SATs mean something?
Because sometimes they mean something.
There's a 69 in there.
I think it's like 3 plus 3, 6 plus 3, 9.
Oh, could be a math thing.
To me, I was thinking like the GTX graphics, like a video card kind of thing.
But, oh, could be.
I don't know.
Alright, we did get an email in JVP.
Just wanted to give us a review on his end of Frigate, the NVR created by Bearded Tech in our community.
And he said, I did hear about it here on the show.
I have to say the Docker Compose setup was super easy.
I have five PoE 4K cameras that come with an advertised on-camera person detection.
I'm using this on an older laptop with a Core i7 and it actually runs quite well.
Frigate not only outperforms the stupid phone home app that these cameras came with,
but with the Home Assistant integration, it's really cool.
And I'm looking forward to making some integrations with lights soon.
Plus I can view my cameras through the HA app, Home Assistant app, outside my house
without sharing another service or having to open another port.
So there you go.
He says I'm about to block these cameras from the internet.
I'll just use it all with Frigate Plus.
So Frigate NVR is a project our community member Bearded Tech is working on.
And these cameras, well, JVP didn't give us the model.
So JVP, you'll have to write back and tell us what the model is
because maybe those are the ones Fuzzy is looking for.
Now, as always, I want to give a big thanks to our site reliability engineers, our subscribers.
You do make this show possible over at self-hosted.show slash SRE.
We've also got a network-wide membership at Jupiter.party as well to support not only this show,
but all the other JB fine shows like Linux Unplugged, Linux Action News, and Coder Radio.
Absolutely.
And of course, you can always send us a boost with a podcasting 2.0 app.
Go get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com.
Go get more Brentley at linuxunplugged.com and catch Fuzzy on our Discord at self-hosted.show slash Discord.
And I'm at chrislas on the Twitter.
I'm over there at ironicbadger for the time being,
but who knows what that crazy spaceman is going to do with it.
We'll have to see on that one.
Maybe we'll finally get a Mastodon user out of you yet.
Maybe?
No, maybe, maybe.
Probably not.
Maybe, baby.
One other plug that I meant to do, I almost forgot,
is we're actually going to be starting a new initiative on the off-weeks of Self-Hosted.
So this show is coming out on the 6th of May, so it will be the, what, the...
6th plus 7th.
What's 6 plus 7?
13.
That's my birthday.
I'm not doing it on my birthday.
Oh, damn it.
Do it on the day before.
Oh, well.
Do it on the day we do it live.
We do the show live on Wednesdays now every other week.
Now, I wanted to talk about a new initiative that we're going to be doing
in between the live shows that we've started doing now.
So that is, we're going to take a look at the awesome Self-Hosted list as a community.
I think we can help improve this thing, right?
And we'll take a look at a specific category.
We'll hang out on the live stream for an hour or two
and just try out some of these apps as a group
and figure out which ones work, which ones don't work,
which links are dead, which applications aren't on that list that should be,
that kind of stuff.
And eventually try and make the awesome Self-Hosted list awesome again,
you know?
Awesome-er.
Yeah, maybe we should get little hats with that on, little red hats with
make Self-Hosted awesome list great again or something.
I don't know.
I don't know. I have some notes on that idea.
Maybe we'll refine that.
There's probably some merchandise in that somewhere, but we'll see.
I think that'll probably do us for the show today.
So thanks for listening everybody.
That was selfhosted.show slash 70.