you probably didn't see the uh teaser for the stream today it's actually a lady badger
it's hard to tell but it's a lady badger it's a lady badger it looks like a medieval lady badger
yeah i think so but she's she's still a big self-hosted fan or is she renaissance it's hard
to tell maybe we should ask her she could be larping i don't know that could be a thing where
did that come from i made it i just decided i was looking for badger people and that's what came up
so you made it nms paint did you yeah basically paint.net well here we are it's episode 75 there's
a lot to get to today alex is about to jump on an airplane and our buddy brent is inbound we're
sitting down in the middle of a thunderstorm over at alex's house real life update brent is supposed
to be departing toronto literally right now as i'm talking to you as we're recording and his flight
inbound from calgary landed about 10 minutes ago so i don't think that's happening i think
i think brent will be here tomorrow morning and more most likely okay and when do you fly out
tomorrow night yeah you have you might be two ships passing each other in the night on the
yeah it's unfortunate uh it is unfortunate well we'll get into it but i wanted to start today
by discussing something that i don't know if we have it on record but i know at least off record
you you called this one alex this week nebuchadza announced the works with home assistant program
they write today we're introducing the works with home assistant program to allow manufacturers to
show their support and commitment to home assistant and its community and like you would expect with
a program like this alex they got like little badges that says works locally with home assistant
works via the cloud with home assistant works with z wave you know the kind of the kind of
works with it's an interesting program i don't want to foreshadow anything about my other
predictions this year but uh nailed it i called that one yeah he did it's nice it's nice to finally
get the w bro yeah it is nice to see this in fact it's kind of perfect because i just recently had
a good reminder of how how crappy the experience is right now and i have to say i'm a bit disappointed
that they didn't announce a hardware partner at launch but they did say uh they're gonna have
their first hardware partner announced soon but you know just recently i was kind of doing like
a virtual rebuild of my home assistant setup like let's say in theory my home assistant yellow or
whatever it's called now shows up and i rebuild my home setup and i thought maybe that'd be a good
time to just move over to zigbee i know i could just stick with z wave but it seems like zigbee
and matter will eventually be the future so i started researching one-to-one replacements
for my z wave devices like my outdoor switches sprinkler controllers uh motion sensors power
smart plugs that also have real-time power data monitoring i tried to find solid zigbee alternatives
to those and getting any kind of signal out of the noise if one device over another is compatible
with home assistant is a really bad experience and at best you're kind of just taking a stab
like you really can't order anything with absolute confidence that it'll work in home assistant and i
do i will say over the last couple years it's gotten better like more and more stuff i just
buy works with home assistant locally but it's still almost impossible and i i would i would argue
in navigatable for a brand new user to this space presently so if this takes off this would make it
massively easier because i would just filter by this on amazon or wherever i'm shopping it is a
crapshoot absolutely and you know the the only way to know for sure something's going to work is to
buy it and try it and even then that's not a guarantee it's going to continue working for
the longest time i refer you to my comments about the govi led strips i bought in the last episode
you know even though that was relying on a third-party api provided by govi it worked one
day via a custom integration and then govi decided to rate limit the api so even then it's not a
perfect guarantee so i'm delighted to see this program come into existence i think it's a signal
that the project has ambition in a certain direction you know if you think about all the
other made for programs i think made for iphone was probably one of if not the first kind of
certification sort of like this in our industry it guarantees companies some kind of interface
to develop against so you look at the iphone as the perfect example right they had that 30 pin
dot connector for a decade now we've had the lightning connector for i think a decade and
we're probably due usbc on the iphone any day now uh we can hope anyway and so when i look at this
announcement i think wow geez okay cool so if i'm you know making the cheapest possible thing i can
and i don't want to pay any license fees or minimal license fees to get a little cute label
on the box to put it on the shelf in home depot or wherever it is uh around the world that little
blue home assistant logo looks pretty good right i mean if you can put the alexa one on there and
the google one on there why not slap home assistant on there yeah and here's a couple of things about
the program that i like uh the program requires manufacturers to maintain the integration of their
products in home assistant they have to provide product samples and give engineering contacts for
the home assistant team to escalate to huge manufacturers will be able to use the works
with home assistant badge in return on their products and documentation and the terms of the
works with home assistant program are enforced in agreement signed by both nebu casa and the
manufacturer so it's not just like they're handing these labels out and so i think when i see one of
these labels as a consumer i'm going to be able to trust that it actually does work and i'm not
joking like i would just filter on this and only buy these products it really lives and dies in the
manufacturer adoption but what happens in a situation like we had and i'm not saying it will
happen soon but like just happened with the z wave stuff your migration that you've been moaning about
on air for ages and ages what happens in 10 years time when home assistant needs to deprecate a
certain interface right and i i don't know what it is i'm not even going to speculate let's say the
replacement for matter has come along and it it deprecates support for all previous matter devices
for whatever reason i'm just making this up but it had that made for home assistant logo on the
box what are the terms of this relationship is it a made for a specific year of home assistant
releases is it made for 10 years like what's the contract here i would like to know and if if the
home assistant team are listening please tweet at me or let me know something like that because
it's important for us to know these details as as nerds i'm excited to hear who their first
partner is and i would love to hear more details i think you're asking some good questions there
and maybe time will tell when you said when you called this i want to say it was like back in
december when you said something like this should come this year it immediately clicked like yes
this is exactly what they need and this makes the experience so much better and then you combine
a program like this with something like the home assistant yellow or or you know a future iteration
when the supply chain isn't all screwed up a out of the box ready to go you drop it on your land
and then you just go buy the works with home assistant labeled devices and everything's just
out of the box good to go from home assistant from nebu casa you know it's a huge potential
revenue stream that i don't know if they're interested in i think they should be if they
want to help keep the business growing and you know make it a better overall product
i think we've seen over the years in this technological space that the only real way
to have a cohesive user experience and i'm talking like apple level of integration here
is not convergence and we saw that with the ubuntu phone years ago and you know everything
they did with the unity desktop back in that era the only way to have a cohesive user experience
is to control everything unfortunately it's it's true i think and that means from all the way up
from the home assistant yellow all the way up to the light bulb i screw into my light fixture
and everything in between if they can offer a cohesive suite of hardware and software and have
it all guaranteed to work together no matter what you know air quotes whatever that means
then home assistant starts to become a viable recommend for people like me to slightly less
slightly less technical members of my family like yeah yeah because right now you know it's
it's the bastion of people that like to tinker as much as home assistant has improved extra ui
elements and wizards and blah blah blah i mean i rarely drop to the yaml these days like i used to
but it's not perfect and if something goes wrong within 10 minutes it's still in the domain where
you need to set it up for your non-technical friends and family you could bring them a box
and give it to them and show them the web ui but you've already set up the dashboard you've
already integrated all the devices you've already done all the network provisioning
you've managed all of that and this helps transition it into a different phase and
just my last thoughts on this and i hope this is a benefit that we continue to see just as
home assistant as a community grows but it means we have someone out there advocating
for local api and local controls but to that point and this is raised in the discord as we record
it's a bit of a slippery slope and i am worried that works with home assistant
if you give it enough time becomes doesn't work with other open standard maybe i guess it depends
on how the standard works because everything about home assistant would probably be open source in
this regard right i mean we'll see i'm not saying they're going to pull an mb but who knows you know
and the other thing is what about the testing that's done are they as an open source project
going to publish all the testing of their hardware vendors i can't imagine many hardware vendors
wanting to sign up to that but as an open source project do they not have a duty to do that i don't
to do that i don't know i'm just asking the question questions that we will probably get
answers to over time but may not like them all we got a message into the show via the jupiter
broadcasting telegram group and it was just a simple question hey do you guys use a self-hosted
to-do app and it's funny because this is exactly something i've been looking to host in my rv right
now something i could really focus just on road trips and stuff like that and i came across i'm
going to attempt to say it's the kunja v i k u n j a it's a self-hostable really good looking to-do
app and it has a little bit of everything that i like from inboxes for different tasks it has
namespace and user sharing so you can collect different projects together and then share them
with somebody like you know a spouse or a family member or a friend it has team support and of
course it also offers a hosted version which you could just pay for if you'd like they include a
how to use it in docker guide so that's probably the route i would take if i were to deploy this
i haven't yet but i'd love to get any feedback from anyone out there in the audience that's
either use this or another self-hosted to-do app this to me seems like the one to beat you can find
it at v i k u n j a dot cloud and yep it's got kanban boards alex i know how you like your kanban
me oh it just gives me the heebie-jeebies of like trello and jira yep yep yep did you ever really
stop and think about self-hosting your to-do stuff i gotta be honest with you i think i
just fell into using apps on my phone which are connected to proprietary services i thought about
it quite a lot actually when i was deep into my sort of emacs kick which lasted about three or
four months and i was doing all the org rome stuff which came out of rome research line of thinking
the what's it called second brain linking your thinking type stuff i was sort of going down this
whole productivity rabbit hole and realized i was spending way longer trying to be productive than
actually being productive so i looked at a few things built into emacs org mode primarily being
the one i looked at but mobile experience the mobile experience matters a lot because that's
where you know 90 of my random thoughts occur to me is oh i need to remember to change the filters
on the ac unit or i don't know remember to pick up this from the shop on the way home or something
like that and i ended up falling into the camp of just using todoist which is not a self-hosted
app unfortunately but for me it's worked very very well it's got some integrations with gmail
which i use all the time at work so there's a bunch of stuff i have to do in my day job
where i need to remember certain case numbers and add comments and all that kind of stuff
and i can just click a button in gmail and it adds it straight into todoist and i can
you know keyboard shortcuts and natural text input and all that kind of stuff
that's not really what you wanted to hear but i really like todoist i understand todoist and
its many integrations and its api are really really handy and i think that's the hosted
service to beat vikinja or however you say it what i was really impressed by is they maintain a
really clean user interface where you could just bang out tasks super quick but they also let you
really dig in and set all kinds of different bits of detail you can add relation you can add
attachments you can do progress tasks you can just do percentage updates you can have repeating
intervals priorities labels you can subscribe to certain tasks even if you're not the user if you
just want to get updates on it i mean it's got it's got like all the power features i love i think
it's going to come down to what it's like to maintain and run it so i'm tempted to give it a
go but i'll wait a week or two and get like input from the audience to hear what they're using for
self-hosted to do apps or maybe i should just not give it a go maybe you've got experience
out there that says otherwise and i should just give in like alex and use todoist leno.com slash
ssh go there to get one hundred dollars and 60 day credit on a new account and you go there to
support the show linode is the best way to run an application on linux in the cloud it's how
we run everything we've built for the last two and a half years or so it's really really fast
they have great performance they have 11 data centers around the world mvme pcie storage they've
got amd epic processors and their cpu rigs 40 gigabit connections coming into the hypervisors
and they are their own isp so that's like all the things you need to just have fantastic performance
and on top of that they have the best support that's where they really try to differentiate
from the hyperscalers they're going to lock into their crazy platforms they really try to
differentiate with the customer service and the community support i'll say that they've been a
big supporter of jupiter broadcasting and they're making it possible for us to go down and get a
tour of jpl and do a bunch of west coast meetups they invest in the community because they know
it returns a net benefit to them because linux is what they run on everything go build something go
learn something try linode out go get that hundred dollars and try out their s3 compatible object
storage maybe you want to play around with their vlan configurator their powerful dns manager
or perhaps you just want to try something maybe you want to performance test your network maybe
you want to deploy their new kali linux support and do a little penetration testing to make sure
everything's buttoned up you can do it 30 to 50 percent cheaper than you can at the hyperscalers
and you can support the show so go try out the best in virtualized cloud computing if it runs
on linux it runs on linode sign up today and support the show linode.com slash ssh that's
linode.com slash ssh to get that 100 and support the show linode.com slash ssh we've got a live
brent update for you his departure flight from toronto is delayed by 10 minutes so i don't know
i don't know if he's off his original plane yet or through customs or or anything but it's seat
of the pants stuff i think it's going to be a full-on run running down the airport kind of
movie style moment for brent i think yeah yeah poor guy hopefully things go smoother for you
and the family hopefully so yes uh it's just a direct flight for us tomorrow rally to london
heathrow hopefully the baggage handlers are on point tomorrow i did buy a couple of extra air
tags to throw into my suitcases attaboy that's so fun the last time i traveled i did that and
we checked baggage and then you just watch and then as soon as it starts to get close and it
detects it again you know your bag's almost there and then you know you can tell when it comes down
the chute it was luxury checking i am actually i hadn't thought about the baggage reclaim part
i'm actually genuinely excited for that now yeah it's great you know i was going through the uh
inbox and a lot of people have caught that you're going to london obviously because we have the
meetup coming up and all of that and we clearly got people to want updates on your remote backup
setup you have across the pond well it's uh it's all change fairly soon anyway i think largely
speaking the fundamental stuff is going to stay the same but when i emigrated three or four years ago
i left my old server in england along with all the data that was on it and i just left it there
because i arrived in this country you know as a prospector with nothing but a suitcase and a
rucksack don't you know oh my god alex it's true though it literally is true and the container
that had all of my actual stuff in it took like three or four months to come across the ocean so
and now you here you are in a american house in the suburbs with big thunderstorms full of crap
lots of toys yeah you're doing it right you know the general idea was to use that server in england
as my primary endpoint for when i needed to come out at a residential ip address for i player
but also there was about 20 or 30 terabytes worth of hard drives in that system
which i pulled together using zfs i used to do zfs mirrors but i ran out of space and so i ended
up turning it into like a z2 array i think i can't remember the specifics a z2 array of like
five or six different three or four terabyte hard drives maybe they're eights but it doesn't really
matter the idea there is that over wire garden bear in mind this predates tail scale by what
three or four years i had to rely on open vpn originally to get an ssh to get into the the box
in england via open sense i had a site to site vpn between the two so that all the traffic was
encrypted and then encrypted within that tunnel as well over ssh and zfs send i used jim salter's
syncoid and sanoid to do all my snapshots on zfs and then syncoid is what's used to manage those
snapshots and sync them to the remote endpoint but last year when i went back to england i did a
motherboard upgrade on that server and there's a blog post which i'll link to in the show notes
about the motherboard i'm using however shortly after i left england my father informed me that
they were selling the childhood home and moving and where they were moving to which if you've
listened to the show you'll know didn't really have the best of internet connections it's up in
uh it's up in the northeast and of england and the internet there was i think i'm generous in
saying two megabytes down and 0.5 megabytes up oh it's miserable yeah so they have got starlink
and it's a lot better now for stuff like tablets and phones and i player and whatever else they do
for normal people yeah it's way better for that kind of stuff but in terms of running a server
um it's not you know i'm i'm not throwing terabytes through that link anymore because
the you know the the main data set's already over there but if ever i needed to restore that data
you know starlink's probably just not the right way to go then somehow the gods smiled on me and
my mother-in-law who lives in rural norfolk she has had internet that has been awful for us to
for as long as i can possibly remember again it was in that sort of four or five megabyte down
one or two megabyte up region just dsl adsl uh if it got a bit windy the speed dropped you know
because the lines were suspended over such a distance she messaged me a month ago and said
hey good news i'm getting fiber to the property fiber out there i was like fiber to the property
i can't even get that you said yes right you said yes i said yes and so she now has i'm led
to believe a 500 symmetrical megabyte connection so my primary old british server is now going to
move from my father's to my mother-in-law's who i will bribe with something i haven't figured out
what yet a gadget maybe yeah she's already said yes but okay the fiber comes in at the wrong end
of the house from where we had a 4g connection for her before an lte modem on the roof because the
dsl connection was so bad uh and this is a lady that works fully remotely over the internet and
has done for years now uh so the internet's very important to her livelihood this is going to be
huge for her then and so for me i'm going to be drilling holes in walls and running ethernet
through brick walls not just uh american cardboard walls proper walls 18th century cottage walls no
less which are you know three three feet thick type deals honestly that sounds like a pain in the ass
to work on i don't think i'd want that yeah it's gonna be it's gonna be fun so i'll be doing a bit
of work whilst i'm over there running ethernet for her and i think my reward will be to host the
server at her house now since tail scale is now a thing i will be running all of my backups over
tail scale to that particular server and dispensing with open sense on the remote site i don't see the
need anymore tail scale works on my nvidia shield so i can run i player through android tv it also
works on my phone my ipad my laptop so i can come out with a british residential ip address with 500
meg up no problem i just don't really need wire guard anymore it's uh naked wire guard anyway i
mean nano tail scale uses it under the hood yeah when you were talking about how you had a point
to point vpn and your sshing over that and you know it's like that that's funny that's how i did
things for like 20 years but now that sounds like a really old way of doing things it's so nice and
i know tail scale sponsored the show so i don't mean to sound like a shill but they're not currently
sponsored this week so this is this is unpaid this is all true it's just you know it's your opinion
ah they well there you go that's how you know it's true i mean the reason that they sponsored
the show in the past is simply because we found them and we thought this is the way it should have
always been this is the way and the other prong of my backup setup is i have a sinology box living
at my mother's house she only has i think it's fiber to the cabinet is what they call it in
england so they run fiber to a cabinet a few hundred feet away from the house and then it's
copper for the last few hundred feet so she gets about 60 or 70 meg down and maybe 10 or 20 up which
is sufficient for a backup server it's not sufficient for an awful lot of other things but
it'll do and i run that using auto restic which is a wrapper around restic i think i've talked
about this previously but that's the summary auto restic runs over tail scale and it just works i
actually went to check up on it the other day and was pleasantly surprised that it's still working
six months later that's what you want to see man that's what you want to see so that's going to be
quite a bit of work because you're going to have to shut that thing down move it set it back up
you're gonna probably have some networking stuff to configure out over at mom's and i mean you might
want to spin up a home assistant instance for her i don't know i mean i could see you doing that too
i could see this kind of rabbit hole i might take one of these spare raspberry pies i've got in the
drawer behind me as a backup for the mother-in-law's house so that i have another tail scale endpoint
that isn't the server itself inside the LAN so that i can kind of island hop within the LAN
look at you traveling with a raspberry pie mr baller over there that's a good idea though
i'll get to customs and they'll be like anything to declare and i'll be like yeah and a million
dollars worth of raspberry pies in my bag that's kind of funny but it's getting to that but really
uh i think what we should talk about is the fact that you're going to have a meetup while you're
over there that is very exciting and it's really coming together absolutely yes so in order to
accommodate a certain mr joe ressington there were certain requirements that had to be met
and one of them that was non-negotiable was being outdoors i kind of feel the same way as well so i
mean i know i shovel that on joe's shoulders but also it's it's my requirement too everybody can
just feel a little more comfortable this way so we're going to meet underneath the london eye
there's a big square green space between the shell center the london eye and the hungerford bridge
and we're going to meet there on the 5th of august around about six o'clock british summer time
we've got to be very specific about that yeah you got to watch out because the meetup page
is in jb's local time so the meetup page can send you a ride yeah so when it says 11 a.m
ignore that it's 11 a.m chris's time we will be there at six o'clock in the evening british
summer time and uh we'll be there until late i mean officially it says nine o'clock i think you
know three hours or so i do have a flight back here the next morning about eight or nine in the
morning so i probably won't be out getting completely uh completely plastered but i will be
there and i have stickers if that's the final thing that gets you to come to come to the meetup
we have limited edition self-hosted diamond cut stickers that's so cool alex you're going to get
over 100 people i hope so i can tell you right now if you've got 99 people on the meetup and you
can tell the way this meetup page has been trending i've done this enough times to tell you
you're going to get over 100 people well they have to beat the rally lot how many did we get there i
think it was about 100 oh it was a little bit more it might have been closer to 200 in raleigh
i mean it's like the raleigh meetup is a good crew oh i like the way you i like the way you work sir
i think it was a little bit more so they're gonna have to put they're gonna have to try harder i
mean they don't want the americans to beat them right meetup.com slash jupiter broadcasting for
the meetup details i of course am looking forward to hearing how it goes we have created a jb meetup
matrix space as well of course this meetup is also being organized in the self-hosted discord
but in general we have created a jb meetups matrix space on our self-hosted matrix instance
there is a london colony meetup in there and there's now a brand new chat room for a west
coast road trip that we're going on in september jupiter broadcasting has been invited to get a
personal tour of the jet propulsion lab in pasadena by a friend of the show tim canham who
is the operational lead for the mars helicopter that runs linux so it's an amazing opportunity
and linode is helping us get down there they're going to help just like they did last year so
we're going to do a whole series of meetups so that meetup page is going to be more useful than
ever as the summer comes up and of course in that matrix space which will have linked in the show
notes if you want to find out where we're going to be at or if you are a local in the area and you
want to give us a shout out so we know there's someone in that area to meet up with or maybe you
know a great place we could stop in the washington oregon california region join that matrix space
linked in the notes and say hi it's going to be it's going to be a massive road trip i mean we got
a lot august we got the london meetup and then in september we're going to have oregon california
jpl it's it's going to be great alex jpl's down in la right yeah yep just uh pasadena area so
the outskirts wonderful yeah i'll have to figure out how i'm going to do that in the rv but we'll
get it dialed in i i hear that the uh the best way to do it is grand theft auto style you just drive
through the desert real fast and then you steal a jet plane and then you fly right in i think that'll
work alex i think that's gonna work visit humio.com hce to ingest and view all of your logs in one
place humio is a centralized log management and observability platform the company was founded by
developers in denmark in 2016 as an alternative to legacy logging solutions that make it cost
prohibitive to ingest and search data volumes seen today's it infrastructures i have been there these
used to be problems that we spent a lot of effort and money trying to solve but the real beauty of
humio is that it can take logs from any source and make them usable you don't need to constantly
massage the format it doesn't need a schema you just pump them all in there and then you have them
when you need them and of course the dashboard is great the platform is really pretty crazy
humio's index free architecture means you can ingest over a petabyte of data per day and search
that data with sub-second latency and humio is up to 80 cheaper than the competing platforms like
splunk or elastic thanks to its reduced hardware and computational footprint but you know the best
way to get going with humio is the community edition humio community edition so you can
humio community edition is the largest no cost data ingestion offering on the market today
allowing you to ingest up to 16 gigabytes per day with seven day retention not a trial period
you've got it for the long haul this is perfect for self-hosters who just want to ingest their
home logs and get a single view of everything happening in your environment rather than having
to go to all the separate places to look from your logs from every system every app every
component in your home humio gives you the ability to bring it all together and correlate it in one
place for easier troubleshooting i mean just to give you an example you can monitor your power
consumption your download speeds water consumption your router information i mean just basically
anything that you can get stats and home assistant well you could visualize it in humio you can also
help monitor power consumption but you know power consumption that's huge in australia
humio community edition gives one listener full visibility of a solar and power grid
home assistant and no dread all that data into humio he really likes to impress his
neighbors with that his voltage recently dropped from 240 volts to 160 volts so like you know
things like the display on your microwave work but the actual microwave function that doesn't
work he was able to dig through the logs in humio see it on the dashboard and take action to protect
his home computing infrastructure when it's your hobby you want it easy you want it quick and you
want it usable and you don't want it to have to be a job so get started with humio community edition
for free at humio.com slash h c e that's humio.com slash h c e what an opportunity jpl is going to
be so so cool i really hope you can find a way to meet up with chris on the way down if you're on
the west coast i'm going to start looking at flights i think that could be i think could be
worth the flight hey oh yeah that's a special opportunity totally all right you and i can
talk more i just didn't want to bring it up when you're in the middle of traveling but we could
talk more when you get back do i bring the family though oh that's a tricky one you know it's a work
trip quote-unquote so it's a jb work thing i mean i don't know it's up to you though i'd tell you
the mother-in-law who we just referenced is a physicist by trade so i think she'd be down i
think she's in raleigh for september so i think you might have to grease those wheels with the
mother-in-law as well it's already happening oh man so uh laurence writes in hey chris and alex
i love the show and i'm really looking forward to the uk meet up next month this is a broader
self-hosting question but with your combined experience i'm hoping you may be able to point
me in the right direction i'm a solicitor or attorney for those in the u.s looking to change
careers to the cloud and i'm unsure where to begin hey we should have fuzzy mistborn answer this
question eh given that he was on just recently and he's in that trade uh so as is the way a
pie was my gateway drug and it sent me down the rabbit hole on what has become quite the adventure
learning linux i've had offers from a few very expensive training providers purveying various
grades of snake oil and supposedly guaranteed jobs but in keeping with the self-hosting spirit i'd
like to try and do it myself i'm currently following a couple of udemy courses and self-studying to get
the aws cloud practitioner certification along with a couple of others uh and i imagine landing
any entry level role will be quite difficult without any prior experience any sage advice
would be greatly appreciated keep up the good work guys and get well soon chris thanks laurence
well thank you laurence i am feeling much much better now i'd say i'm like 95
percent better this is a great question and it's something that you are not alone in struggling
with because you get to this point where you've got a lot of hands-on um lab time where you've
built things and tried things or maybe you've deployed something in the cloud but you don't
necessarily have work experience and you want to take it to that next step that can be situational
but i will say one area that i looked at when i was hiring is i would ask people if they have
participated in any projects on github because it's just all your commits all your work everything's
documented right there and it can be an example of a work ethic it can be an example of you
participating in community even if it's not necessarily specific to the job you're applying
for i mean my own personal story i was working in retail at the apple store for a while and i
just ended up getting interested in linux in my spare time and then i was lucky enough to be able
to go and do a computer science master's degree for a year and that was kind of a deep dive into
programming and you know databases and all sorts of other really difficult stuff that was honestly
way beyond me and it's way beyond what i do in my day job now my advice would be such as it is
anyway find an area that you find interesting enough to self-study on whether that's infrastructure
whether that's development whether that's testing whatever it might be and just do it you know find
a project that you know solve a real problem and find a project around your house that needs
automating if it's infrastructure for example or you know if it's development find a problem that
nobody else has solved or find a problem that's been solved you think you could solve better and
just just nibble away at it yourself and i'm not a huge believer in certifications per se i i get
free certifications through redhat which is a lucky perk of the job but i've i've only done a
handful and it's because i just don't necessarily think that simply by having those letters next to
my name it means that i actually know an awful lot more than the next person yeah it means that i
learned the answers to that specific test on that day in history five years ago maybe i don't know
it's it's it's useful in some ways because it gets your foot in the door with employers to say yes
i've done xyz but in other ways i'm much more interested in hiring somebody who is able to speak
passionately about a specific area and can demonstrate some open source work so you almost
just i think you almost just hit it there too like i wonder if it isn't a passion thing like he isn't
he isn't tearing into a problem and becoming the most knowledgeable person about that problem in
the world thus discovering a community their problems and providing a solution and then
getting employment through those networking connections instead it almost feels like
lawrence you're the biggest problem you're trying to solve is employment and i get that but getting
a job is not an ends of means itself it it's like just part of it like it the job should be reflective
of what you're really passionate about um and it's a tricky thing because i think i realize you gotta
get a job you gotta get money you gotta get paid but it feels like you kind of put the cart before
the horse like you're kind of trying different stuff you're excited about a lot of it you know
you want to work in this area i see this all the time but you don't have a specialty you don't have
a focus you don't necessarily have a passion and if you do well then that's your obvious answer
and that's what you should probably be going after recommend that you give coder radio a listen as
well mike and chris talk about this kind of stuff all the time i mean it's a bit more small business
focused but sometimes they talk about you know how to get into the industry and that kind of thing
yeah thank you that is it's probably a good tip all right so brad writes in who wants to know about
our thoughts on tap business cards so you know some are tied to websites some are tied to apps
i was curious if this is something you guys have used or consider i want to be more environmentally
conscious and most business cards they just get thrown away i wonder though how much telemetry is
gathered by these card companies and what they'll do with it regards brad have you seen these
digital credit cards there's app versions there's physical versions some of them are nfc based some
of them are something else seems open to abuse yeah but saying that i've had a contactless debit
card in my pocket for five or six years and it's it's only been cloned once theoretically i like
this idea right i prefer not having another piece of paper and if i get if i get a business card
that i actually care about i almost inevitably end up like scanning it with my phone or you know
some contact application but i did do some digging around there is there are projects out there in
fact one that's been going around this week that lets you build your own business card out of your
own parts and then you run linux on the thing and um i guess you could be a little more secure in
that i honestly i don't think this is ever going to take off i really don't and the reason why
and i'm just maybe it's old man chris here but back in my day our palm pilots had little
infrared blasters built into them so you could exchange contact information did you just play
the palm pilot card we have been trying to solve this problem literally since the late 90s
since fax machines were popular to have in the home we have been trying to solve this problem
and we have tried different technologies and nothing has stuck even even as palm pilot friends
you know we were kind of like all right let's let's try this and you'd line it up and it just
never really took off you know what's going to happen in the real world is you're going to make
a connection with someone and then you're going to unlock your phone pass it to them and they're
going to type in their number or send you a text or a telegram or hey what's your discord or your
twitter or whatever that's the reality it feels like that's going to be the reality as long as
we have multiple vendors making multiple operating systems that want to implement their own standards
and don't necessarily have incentive to interoperate with maybe each other right as long as that's
as long as we've got a coke and pepsi of phone manufacturers and coke and pepsi don't want to
share their secret recipe i don't think we're very likely to have universal electronic cards
that actually be adopted it needs to be as easy as like you know you bump watches you tap phones
and it's completely seamless and unless it's that it's never going to take off i thought i saw the
answer at conference a few years ago which was scanning a qr code on a conference's badge but
all that turned into was another way to track me and that's the last thing i want real-time brent
update for the show and he's missed his flight unfortunately by about 10 minutes so let's hope
that air canada take care take good care of him tonight uh anyway matt writes in hey self-hosted
crew i wanted to start out by saying thank you to the entire jb team for consistently putting out
top tier linux content stop i've been listening for a few years now and y'all how did i do with
that not bad have really helped me in my journey to becoming a linux sys admin i've been building
up my home lab and since i got the promotion a few months ago i was curious if you have talked
about smoke detectors water and flood detectors or that kind of thing on the show previously
i've been able to replace all the pipes in my house and i haven't had any leaks
but i'm concerned that something might happen in the future thanks again for all that you do
he loved the word y'all there's three y'alls in there and he's trying to make the british man say
you're doing great alex you're doing great i do like the word what have you done for smoke
detectors and the lot now do you have those integrated have you kept them separate they're
bog standard five dollar smoke detectors from amazon and i've got one above my 3d printer
i have a z wave smoke detector like i said i got a lot of z wave devices this i purchased november
20th 2020 so i've had it for a couple of years now and i've never had a fire so i don't really
have a lot to say but i bought it on a recommendation from the home assistant community
it's the first alert z wave smoke detector carbon monoxide alarm you just join it to your z wave
network like you would all your other devices and it shows up in home assistant with the alarm
component and i like it a lot it's really easy to replace the battery too it's just got a little
side tray that pops out so when you do have to replace the battery you can and because it's z
wave you could it's not a big battery hog it's just two double a batteries so i'll put a link to
this in the show notes for at least smoke detector now what about leak detectors previous friends of
the show shelly actually make some flood detectors which uh i'm reliably informed by one of my
neighbors who has a rental property out at the coast work extremely well and i'm fairly sure
that akara aqara make a leak detector as well and then of course sticking with the z wave theme over
here the aotech water leak sensor these aotechs they work great with home assistant they uh also
make some great sensors they're just a little expensive although their leak detector is only 36
bucks and 36 dollars it's money well spent to prevent a leak and then of course another actual
z wave device although i i don't use it but we've had people write in is the ring leak detectors
which i'm told are pretty decent and actually talk z wave never used them myself but if you
already have a ring camera or you want to experiment with it you could try the ring leak
detectors as well can't vouch for it personally but we've gotten pretty good email on it all
right we got some boost with some new podcast apps cos peeling was in first this week with
3690 sats and he was writing in about his pi os setup from our chat in pi for every problem
he says that i use tumbleweed on my quote desktop pies and then i use raspian on the headless cody
pies and he uses nfs to avoid using the sd card all together he says thanks for the show that's
all well and good but what happens when the nfs server's down well then you're probably not
watching your movies anyways or the network switches down or yeah yeah no i i agree you know
but i stream all of my television over the network now and it's been okay but yeah yeah nfs to run
the system that that could lead to a bad day sir lurks a lot boosted in with 1337 sats because i'm
also a big believer and a fan of the of your support of the matrix ecosystem i do run my own
home server i've done it for a couple of years now and i've given you lots of feedback and moral
support for running matrix but i wanted to chime in and say that i fully support your use of discord
as well it's not a zero-sum game self-hosting is a journey and shows like this are to help
light the way but if neophytes are on discord you got to meet them there to bring them into the
tent hallelujah well put lurks a lot he goes on to say with a double boost coming in with another
elite set of sats he says also once they're on the path you know the show could help nudge them
to matrix one day i'm glad you have a couple of matrix room for the self-hosted show maybe
encourage people to engage and pay attention over there hey i'm paying attention over there
he says too bad there isn't a bridge good enough to bring them together it's a shame
but that is the way thanks lurks a lot yeah thank you and i think it's uh it's important
you know that we talk about this stuff because there's always a there's always prevailing wind
in in tech that for one company to win or one standard to win all the others have to lose and
i think it goes back to a steve jobs quote originally i think that i'm referencing here that
there's this idea that for apple to win microsoft has to lose and it's just not true and i think
the same is true of discord and matrix yes and i think this type of debate should i host it myself
should i just use the dang service uh what are the pros and cons i think that's something the
audience probably struggles with quite a bit i'd say it's probably the biggest part of self-hosting
is deciding is it worth my time or not fun deck hermit boosted him with 2000 sats he says there
is a podcast called the amp hour that's located in raleigh with a host named chris and he says
maybe there'd be some event organization that could happen sometime and who knows man there
is a good community in raleigh that could be a thing that happens i like the name too rally iot
riot that's a fun one he came in with an another double boost fun deck hermit did another elite
set of sats he says not only does the authentic proxy application adhere to the specific protocol
it can also form a protective layer around dumb applications like pup cloud or jacket
hmm it has an internal build and built-in proxy but that is optional we had that feedback from
a few folks actually that uh not only can authentic be the authentication provider but
it can also do the same job as orthalia is only able to do as well so you end up with the best
of both worlds so uh i suspect that's just bumped up my list of should try soon agreed sucd boosted
in with a baby row of ducks 222 sats because i use the software called flight aware on the raspberry
pie uh and you can order it as a complete hit ready to go so it's 120 bucks basically but it
comes with the transponder it comes with the pi zero the power supply the indoor antenna with
a magnetic base all the cables you need the sd card everything to just have your own flight
aware setup that could be genuinely a cost-effective way to get hold of a raspberry pi in 2022
i was gonna say that all right bronze wing boosted in with elite set of sats 1337
feeling my pain alex says my home pods and siri also seem to be way worse recently i used to be
able to say hey you know who it's movie time or open the middle garage door now she usually takes
at least a moment it's very frustrating get slower please keep us up to date if a fix shows up so an
old update on that alex you know one handy thing that i have is i kind of have an ab environment
i noticed that the siri tubes in the studio are all still working perfectly fine they still control
all the devices they recognize everything i say it's only the siri tubes in the rv
and i kind of almost wonder if it's something to do with the home assistant home kit integration
like something's gone awry in that setup but i'm not sure yet i had a theory that it was to do with
the profiles that these assistants build up on you over time so you know how they do the voice
matching at right at the beginning uh where your voice is just a generic voice amongst the herd but
over the years right they'll hear you speak more and they'll learn more and more and more and that
as those profiles are supposed to get better they actually get to a point of diminishing returns and
then they just fall off a cliff the other way that's a theory because what i was reading is
that if you go into your google account or whatever and delete the profiles they have on you
that people's experiences have improved dramatically and i just thought perhaps we could crowdsource
some folks willing to test that out for us you know this is a great example of the knobs that
we don't get access to anymore with all of these new services and devices they're just completely
hidden from us and it's just they they seem to get worse and worse and worse and there's no way to
do this and worse and worse and there's nothing we can do uh and bronzewing says so you know he
goes on to say i'm looking at mycroft it seems like maybe the right way to go but 300 is a
steep hardware entry i reserved one but i just couldn't pull the trigger when it actually came
time to buy it so i got two homepod minis instead but the voice recognition space just seems really
rough right now i feel like i completely agree with bronze and wig and there is clearly a solution
home assistant based local based but the bar is high in terms of performance let's just remember
christmas 1998 when alex got his first family computer and we were all sat around this thing
i think we got it from pc world and it was a time computers pc and we had via voice on this
thing i don't know if you remember that program of course i do you had to train this thing you
had to speak sentences into this thing to train the algorithm and it would input text to you on
on the screen and let's just pump the brakes and saying how bad they are before we actually
realize how good they are first of all please yeah the fact that they can even pick us up now
when we're holding these mobile devices in like any environment pretty much is incredible because
back then you needed a really close microphone maybe even a headset microphone for good dictation
and getting that microphone to work with that computer was not a given
oh old computers oh man optimus gray boosted in just a day ago with a full row of ducks
2222 sats he says i was just listening to the podcast and i was syncing everything up
but you know what this episode 71 might just be one of my favorites it's got cooking proxmox
bit warden with ansible what else could you want also i agree brent needs some gas money
and don't tell alex that we'll all be touching his chair when we have a house party over there
i still have the sign up here no touchy the chair and you see this on the stream but that
just makes people want to touch it that just makes them want to touch it it's still up there
it's like uh it's like a sign that says don't kick me then people want to kick you true it's
true yeah i do have a punchable face i've been told i like the idea too that brent's
gonna have a party while you're gone like you know a teenager having a party while their parents are
out do it i mean there is a million cameras around here he won't get away with it no no
but there's not much you'll be able to do i mean you know it's probably gonna be archie's fault
archie's gonna be a bad influence i imagine yeah yeah that dog does like to drink we got a double
boost some double boost this week that's great guys 500 sats from optimus gray again uh he says
i live in a three-story townhouse about 650 to 700 square feet per level one unify ap on top
and the lower floor but i get poor speeds on that second middle floor do i really need a third
unify ap i tried the unified tools but all my neighbors with their isp modems and routers set
to blast just seem to be configured poorly uh just run ethernet everywhere just plug your phone in
via ethernet that will solve that problem yeah right yeah what about wi-fi 6 i don't know if
you have modern enough devices to support wi-fi 6 that uses a bit of extra spectrum that some of
the other neighbors might not have uh obviously every device doesn't support it but generally
speaking the unified tools do an okay job of defining you know the the spectrum that's
available if you scan the channels it will automatically move things around for you
i do have a firmware on my robo vac which might be of interest i don't know if you have a robo vac
or anything like that but i can actually send my valetudo based robo vac around the house
and it will generate me a wi-fi heat map of the wi-fi access points wow so you get an idea of
where the signal is the strongest from the neighbors and stuff like that that's pretty fun
now you don't necessarily need a fancy pants vacuum to do that there are apps on your phone
which will let you do the same thing that might be a good place to start i wonder too optimist
like a price aside why not get the third ap it sounds like you've got a ton of channel crossover
from your neighbors similar situation where i'm at here at the studio it's i open up my wi-fi
network screen and i would be i mean i've never really counted because i just have to scroll and
scroll but it's probably like 35 40 ap's i can pick up it's disgusting and i have to imagine
there's just a ton of channel overlap you could be faced the same thing especially in a townhouse
like i am could totally see that the other thing is you could be just on the point between those
two access points where the signal is about dropping off from both of them and your devices
don't know which one to pick so they might be flip-flopping between the two all the time trying
to do that handoff thing and depending on how they're mounted the generally the wi-fi signal
is a bubble right it's like a it's like a mushroom top it goes out up and around it doesn't necessarily
go down below the ap it doesn't like go behind the ap so you may have a mushroom dome of wi-fi
on the bottom floor and then you have a mushroom dome of wi-fi on the top and they're both just
not intersecting the middle floor as much plus you maybe got something in the walls too that
could also be an issue i've seen places that have metal in the walls and that blocks the signal
we got a baller boost from dean dean i'm gonna say 70 10 70 maybe dean 10 70 sent us a boost
just a day ago 10 000 sats he's boosting the dip he says i just wanted to show my appreciation for
the self-hosted show i thoroughly enjoy the topics you discuss especially naz storage and home server
options keep up the great work well thank you dean for boosting the dip sats are on sale right now
we got 100 sats from user 65 94 that said thanks and also 100 sats from josh the chest
said it's a great time to boost the show sats are cheap if you want to send us a boost you can do
so by getting a podcasting 2.0 app at newpodcastapps.com or just go grab breeze if you
don't want to switch your app breez.technology or if you want to nerd it up but i don't think
anybody did this week you can use boost cli which is a command line tool pretty cool i guess you
gotta be pretty elite for that now the chat room we're asking for some real-time feedback on the
wi-fi based robo vac heat map i've just put a link to that in the chat it's called valoroni i think
and uh take a look in the show notes it'll be in there as well that looks really cool alex
i figured it'd be a neat visualization but i didn't realize it would be that neat so yeah
what's such a neat and wild use case for a robot vacuum well the thing is i have a dedicated iot
network which is 2.4 gig for all of my you know robo vacs and cam smart cameras and all the other
wi-fi crap shellies that are in is in this house and so i used that to figure out where to put
you know different access points and it turned out in my kitchen there was a spot that was
underneath the stairs and just behind the washing machines and the fridge that was of course just
which is where my dining room table is you can picture it that had no wi-fi signal and obviously
the dining room table is where i spend some hours a week you know with laptop whilst you know cooking
is happening and what have you so i just got one of those unify in wall ap's and slapped it into an
old phone socket and and pulled the wires through the wall into the crawl space it was good to go
it was you know probably only an hour or two's worth of work very nice and that's a great idea
for an iot network talk about getting a real on the ground view of your network i want to say
thank you to our members our sre subscribers make the show possible they let us be really picky
about the sponsors we work with they give us the runway to keep the show going if we have to say
no to some sponsors and as a thank you we create an ad free feed of the show and also we tack on
a post show that is exclusive to them if you'd like to sign up support the show become a member
at self-hosted dot show slash sre and then i imagine shortly after the new although i probably
shouldn't commit to anything but after we get the new website out the door like the next thing on my
list is upgrading the member feed so we have live versions so you can do your boosts for the member
feeds and all that kind of stuff so that'll be probably later in the year after we get the
website out at the end of summer but all that stuff is being worked on for our sre members because you
guys matter a heck of a lot to us i think it is really important just to hammer home how important
independent media is these days you see stuff in all sorts of spaces about how there are sponsored
videos here and non-disclosed sponsorships and all that kind of stuff and having a audience funded
show really allows chris and myself and the rest of the jb team to be authentic to you guys yes we
have a couple of commercial sponsors but primarily the show is funded by you the listeners and i think
keeping independent media independent is hugely valuable to our society i couldn't have said it
better myself so self-hosted dot show slash sre if you'd like to sign up you can find our discord
community over there as well at self-hosted dot show slash discord and don't forget we have the
matrix space linked to the show notes if you'd like to join our matrix community as well lots
of stuff coming up in the next few weeks obviously we've got the london meetup on august 5th meetup.com
slash jupyter broadcasting for all the details there chris has his jpl jb super road trip in
september on the west coast yeah you can find different ways to get in touch with us at self
hosted dot show slash contact i'm on twitter at ironic badger i'm over there too at chris las
and of course the network is at jupyter signal thanks for listening everybody that was self
hosted dot show slash 75