Know this is gonna seem like a dumb question, but do you have rats in North Carolina?
Not that I've seen but I imagine so. I don't really know
I don't know what like the rat territory is, but I do know they are in the Pacific Northwest and some RVs fall victim
To rats. It's like disastrous. Are these the culprits for the footprints on your suspension?
No that I think was a raccoon, but I'm thinking like critters are a problem, you know here in the Pacific Northwest
Mm-hmm. So I I ordered a suite of
these really high-powered
outdoor
Noisemakers that just they're hypersonic frequencies
But I think they kind of sound like birds to the critters like Bert hungry birds and they flash lights and all this kind of stuff
But they're just so loud that they I think they also bothered Levi and so I thought here's what I'm gonna do
There's a home assistant solution for this. I
Got I got myself a series of outdoor z-wave smart plugs and a couple of indoor ones
I'll have links in the show notes
and I set these up so that when we leave the
Noisemakers automatically turn on and then when we arrive back they automatically turn off and that way we don't worry about bothering our dog Levi and
You know, I'm not getting blasted myself with ultrasonic noise, I guess
That's great. I mean, I remember as a teenager. They used to play in the shopping center near me
I suppose you call them a mall here. Don't you the shopping mall? They used to have these high-pitched kind of
Things used to go them back up and down and to this day
I think I can still hear quite a lot of high frequencies considering how old I am. They just drive me crazy
There's a house across the road that has one for the deer that run through our neighborhood. Oh, yeah
For deer, huh? Yeah, I mean I assume that's what it's for. Yeah, I've seen I've seen him for deer on the front of cars
yeah, I can feel like a
Like a real weird pressure on my ears, but I don't hear anything
But then it has like this test mode that puts it into human hearing and it is it's loud and you can hear it
Yeah, yeah, so I thought okay. Let's just turn those suckers off, but I don't want to remember
I don't want to have to you know, think about it
I want to just be sitting I would be home and have leave I get a headache all of a sudden
So I thought let's do it based on location. Why keep a dog and bark yourself. Yeah
So far so good
Absolutely. Now should we talk about the hoopla with Spotify this week and Neil Young? I think it is a fascinating topic
Well, there is a self-hosting angle. I think at least that's where my mind went immediately
Yes, if you have these tracks yourself, they can't pull them from your library
I mean, that's the first obvious statement, but I think it's bigger than that even that's just it
we're streaming in general and I suppose we'll get to the
specifics of
How we're handling this in a minute, but these my general issue is streaming services
is that you know, we've seen it with time and time again with
Netflix and now with Spotify and countless other services where there is a catalog of content, you know
Whether it's friends whether it's Neil Young
That is there one day and gone the next in fact
There are entire websites dedicated to what's going off of Netflix this month
Now the story that we're talking about here is Neil Young obviously a very famous
Hugely famous artist in the music world issued Spotify an ultimatum over Joe Rogan
Which always seemed like a risky move as soon as I saw that because you got to figure
Spotify gets a few thousand plays off of
Neil but gets
Millions and and Joe Rogan not only drives millions of listens
But Joe Rogan is like the linchpin of their entire podcast advertising business. He is their strategy now
Now I don't recall how much they paid for his show, but it was something stupid like a hundred million dollars or something ridiculous like that
and it's worse than that actually if we think about it and Neil Young a
Stream of music. It doesn't matter if it's Neil or the Foo Fighters or I don't know Lady Gaga
Whoever it is a stream of a song costs Spotify a fraction of a penny
per stream, right a
A stream or a listen of a podcast episode generates revenue
so who is Spotify
incentivized to a side with and
Be promote, you know, yeah, and it really underscores this issue of not your library
It's theirs and what you get access to is subject to change that drives me crazy
But you're also just sort of a victim of these big corporate games that are getting played
Right. It's at the end of the day. They don't care about the customers at all. It's it's ego fighting ego
It's company fighting company and we're just kind of left in between or you like another example of this which just drives me crazy
you see something like
Paramount decides they want to launch their own streaming service. So now there's no longer gonna be Star Trek on Netflix even though
Having Star Trek on Netflix long term is better for the franchise because it means more people discover and binge Star Trek
But they want to have exclusives. They want to have stuff just on their platform. And so they're pulling it off of Netflix now
And I say this not even kidding. I signed up for Netflix for Star Trek back in the day when it was DVDs
You know, I mean I wasn't customer number one
but I may have been like customer number a hundred like I was really early in the Netflix as soon as they went public because I
Wanted to get Star Trek on DVD because I had this aging VHS collection
I mean I signed up for Spotify the very first time when I was doing my
Music undergraduate degree. So that would have been oh, yeah
2008 9 something like that
Because they had a fantastic classical music library as a music student. That was obviously very important to me at the chair. Sure
Music's been a huge part of my life. Anyway, for those that don't know I play several instruments drums guitar
Euphonium which is another one that I play which most people probably don't know what it is
But it's a brass instrument like a tuba. It sounds like we need to get some sound hits for the shows
Let's get going. There is actually a very embarrassing video on YouTube of me playing the euphonium from that time period
If you look hard enough, I'm sure you'll find
There will not be a link to it in the show notes because it's very embarrassing
But anyway, my point is is I've been a subscriber now Spotify for a decade plus, you know
So what is it 10 pounds a month 15 dollars a month? I don't know. I'm part of the family plan now
So, you know over 10 years I've spent a thousand ish
Maybe more maybe a bit less with Spotify and I think this has really got me
Questioning whether I continue to give Spotify specifically my money
I'm a little annoyed that this is what's getting people to unsubscribe. I unsubscribed at the end of last year
because
What they're trying to do to podcasting would forever change this industry what they want to do is
They want to bring everyone onto their platform and kind of create exclusive content that they can insert
dynamic ads and
They're okay
if you distribute it on a feed to in some cases but a
Really super abbreviated version of this story because I've told it before on air is right after JB went independent again. I
Got an email from someone at anchor
Anchor is owned by Spotify. It's part of their podcasting arm
Offering me to bring the JB Network exclusively to Spotify. They would sell ads
They would take over all the ad deals and do digital inserts
They were saying it is essentially going to be a 70% pay cut in ads
but
Every show would be sold and they would insert them dynamically and to sweeten the deal if I went exclusive
They were going to let me play any any song in the Spotify library in the shows
So all of our shows would have access to the entire Spotify library, which was the one part of the email where I went
Whoa, like you could create entire new kinds of podcasts if you had access to that commercial library
That is a pretty cool hook and I'm not the only one they were sending that that too
I was one of I was part of a net that they were casting and
The whole thing was based around their whole well like you're we're just gonna take over your ad
It's gonna take over the ads and we just cut them in like they would just they have a little thing that just waits
For like, you know half a second of silence
Right in the middle of a sentence and then it just cuts in an ad and if it's on an open feed
Then you can't you don't get to access the Spotify music library
At least that was the terms that were given to me and that's their goal, right?
They want to they want to be the YouTube or Netflix of podcasting. And so that's why I ultimately
Unsubscribed and that's why I've begun promoting the podcast index at podcast index org and podcasting 2.0
and the new podcasts apps comm and value for value lightning payments to the to the shows via these apps because
We have to embrace decentralized solutions that you can host yourself
In the podcast industry like as podcasters that are technically capable of it
It's something I've had to double down on and that's why I cancelled Spotify because they're trying to wreck an industry
But I am glad to see more people realizing that they have issues
We didn't actually cover the reason why Neil issued an ultimatum, which was in his opinion
Joe Rogan was spreading the kovat misinformation
Anti-vax stuff, you know stuff like that
And so for me as a triple vaxed guy, I just think come on
How are we not past this kind of nonsense yet? Just yeah do the right thing for society, you know
I also
You know, I also can't imagine but maybe I imagine it does happen
People aren't seriously taking medical advice from Joe Rogan, but I imagine it does but you'd be surprised. Yeah
So that whole thing, you know in this it could be a Joe Rogan thing. I mean it really
Fast forward five years. There will be some other big thing. That's like this huge existential crisis that all of us are freaking out about and
You know Spotify again could make a decision where it's once again screwing the customers in some way
Like there wasn't really a great scenario for them. They couldn't get rid of Joe
You know, so there wasn't a great scenario
But it just highlights this core issue that I think this show can address so well
And I think the music one is one that we should probably readdress
Because we've each kind of changed earth or at least evolved our thoughts on it a little bit. Yeah, so I haven't pirated
In fact, I haven't mentioned piracy on this show at all
very very deliberately because I think it's an angle of self-hosting that is very well covered elsewhere and I
Really don't want to get into it on this show
But I think times like this kind of highlight the importance of owning or having your own stuff
Truly the importance of having a local copy that nobody can delete from your hard drive or whatever
It is if you actually care about it, I suppose
And so what I've done is I've been using a tool called lidar
Recently and I haven't been pirating music in the traditional sense. So I've still been paying some money
So I found a plug-in called automatic music downloader
There'll be a link in the show notes, which is a script which plugs into lidar
but it also plugs into something called Deezer which is a competitor to Apple music and
Spotify and Deezer Hi-Fi is a $15 a month
Subscription for lossless audio. And so for me as a music nerd audiophile self-confessed
You know, I have some lovely floor-standing speakers and expensive headphones all the rest of it. I like lossless audio
I can hear the difference. I've done a B testing. I just I like it. Okay, and so for me
I want to be able to have a local copy of
All that music that I listen to pretty much the same stuff over and over again on Spotify
Anyway, locally and so for me this walks this whole setup walks a fine line between piracy and kind of not
I mean, I'm sure it's against their terms of service to do this
But I'm still paying money to Deezer and therefore I assume that each download counts as a play
So the artist still gets some recognition as well
So what do you think on that?
Yeah, I think this I think you've really hit the sweet spot, you know because you want something
That's gonna tie in with whatever management system
You've chosen to use right like anything else you bought would be an app with a store that's integrated
you want something that's almost like
Music as a service via an API and that's kind of basically what you've built here. Oh
Man, this is great
I think if I could pay a dollar an album or maybe even maybe even a bit more to be honest with you and there
Was a service that integrated just as well with all of my automation for media collection
I'd probably pay it and so for me at the moment
Anyway, this that price is $15 a month to do it semi legally
So, you know the ethics of the whole situation are a little questionable
But for me, I'm comfortable with making that that kind of concession
what this doesn't solve though is the front end and
We talked a little bit a few episodes ago about plex amp when it came out
I think it was about a year ago and I have been using the crap out of plex amp for the last month or so
it is fantastic if they've done loads of little updates and
I've got to say, you know, I'm not really missing Spotify at all
Yeah, you gotta see this app. We'll have a link in the show notes. You got to see this
They've also released. I don't know if we've covered this on the show, but they've released a Linux
App image so you can actually use it on the Linux desktop Mac
Windows Android iOS
It's so great and I'm happy to report that I've tested the offline playback, which is huge feature for me. I love that
So yeah, okay. I'm seeing this. This is like a whole new world coming together for me. You're opening my eyes Alex
I'm seeing a new world
I mean it does rely on plex which I'm sure most people listening to this podcast have access to a plex server somewhere
But the thing I really like about plex amp is it has this whole kind of concept
I guess that they borrowed from the Spotify ethos of the related artists the recommended mixes recent playlists all that kind of stuff
So the more you use it the more tailored the recommendations get to what you're sort of in the mood for that week
And I really like that about it. I have tried the
Fin amp, which is a jellyfin music player kind of in the spirit of plex amp. Yeah, not as good
No, of course not, but it's open source. It is an F droid as well
You can just get the APK and it works, you know
So if you want to use jellyfin as your back-end server, you totally can it's just not quite the same experience
But I'll toss a link in the show notes
Linode.com slash SSH go there to get $100 in 60-day credit and you go there to support the show
Linode is how we host everything up in the cloud and some jobs just work better up in the cloud
And if you're thinking maybe it's time to try out next cloud, I highly recommend it
We've been using next cloud on Linode for over two years with their object storage as our back-end now Linode themselves
They started in 2003
One of the very first companies in cloud computing and now 18 years later
Linode is the largest independent open cloud provider in the world with 11 global data centers serving nearly a million customers and businesses
Around the globe the Linodes remain focused
They stayed competitive and they've made cloud computing simple affordable and accessible to all
It really is the best-in-class experience performance wise
Options wise and when it matters, you're really gonna appreciate the customer support Linodes rolled out Rocky and Alma Linux images
If you've been wanting to give those a go as well as CentOS stream
They have one click deployments of next cloud and things like that if you want to use that and of course
They have an S3 compatible object storage that I rave about all the time
So you could always deploy something on there and just let it grow and then you'll really appreciate things like their nice dashboard
That gives you a heads up on your systems performance. What's been going on?
Sensible alerting that's just set up and available by default a powerful DNS manager Kubernetes and Terraform support
I mean I can go on and on and on not to mention the MVME PCIe storage
They're rolling out right now and pricing 30 to 50% cheaper than the major hyperscalers that have complicated platforms
And they just want to lock you in
But maybe the best part you can support the show
linode.com
SSH go there get $100 and 60 day credit on a new Linode account and you go there to support the show linode.com slash
SSH
All right
So some other hoo-ha this week is that Google have announced that they're gonna shut down free
G-suite accounts unless you start giving them some greenbacks
Boy, did it kind of like touch a nerve with our audience and I mean obviously not everybody
Well, we got a lot of upset people that wrote into the show people are hitting me up on telegram
angry
We got lots of email about this
So on Wednesday Google announced that it's getting rid of their G suite legacy free edition
Which allowed those that snuck in before 2012 to get free Google app services tied to a custom domain
Rather than a gmail address so that would mean that for a lot of our listeners who are
Generally more tech savvy early adopter type people who have a finger on the pulse
That could mean that they losing years worth of purchases tied to that Google Play account
potentially in the hundreds or thousands of dollar range
But also friends and family members who they've signed up for these services as well with their at custom domain.com
Email addresses are suddenly gonna have to start paying a minimum of I think six dollars a month for this thing
Yeah, and imagine you sign into your Android phone with that ID. It's your everything. It's your contacts your calendar. It's
everything and yeah
Those Play Store purchases as well and it almost seems like Google was unprepared for people to be upset by this
but that seems
scientifically impossible because you think Google as an organization would be aware when you give people something for free and then you take that free
Thing away people get upset that happens 100% of the time. That's math
So they had to know but their response after the fact
Which I think was just a couple hours ago as we're recording it would almost seem to imply like they were completely caught off guard
I mean if you're a PR person, that's the easy route to take isn't it?
There's a bit of a story to this this week
So they announced it a few days ago that they're going to do this shutdown
Then there were some news articles came out about how they might be facing a class-action lawsuit from several users
And then as Chris says, you know a few hours ago, they have relented to the pressure
There's an article on Ars Technica
Which there's a link to in the show notes where they say that Google is launching a survey of affected g-suite users
The company is surprised by how many people this change affected
What like they didn't have metrics Google's supposed to be the data company
I'm sorry, that's that's bullshit. You tell me they didn't check active users before they made this announcement. I'm not buying it
Yeah, I'm calling I'm calling BS on that
But they have announced a couple of extra nice things as a result of kind of capitulating to this
This upswell is uprising of nerd rage and they're promising a data migration option
Which will include your Google Play content purchases. That's really what they got to do
I mean you're gonna have an at gmail address now, so you're gonna have a dirty peasant email address, I suppose I
Think it's important for the longevity of people buying digital content
I think a lot of people kind of suck it and see with DRM without fully exploring the ramifications of
What would happen if Google did exactly this? Yeah, you're out of luck mate
You know, that's it the the money you spent on that thing was just a rental really a long-term rental sure
But you don't own it
That's true
Every time something like this happens a group of people kind of come to a new realization about the arrangement they find themselves in
Just like Spotify, you know
I've got access to every song in my pocket
For the duration that my dollar gives me access to that library or for the duration that that particular artist
Likes Spotify, you know, it's yeah, it's never been a better time to self host or something, right?
Reflecting on our summer de Google challenge. I just kind of have been coming to like maybe a new kind of arrangement
You take your your data valuable stuff like your email your contacts your photos you put those somewhere else
So perhaps you use something like proton mail or fastmail or you self host the email and you use prism for the for the pictures
but you still have a lot of Google services like YouTube and
Maps obviously in the Play Store. I think you still want a burner Gmail account, but why not a new one?
Why not a new Gmail account with very little details in it, right?
And then you self host with a combination of like things like next cloud you self host all the other stuff and kind of you
know, it's not it's not like a binary
No Google at all kind of it's like this
Limited risk exposure approach to Google. I mean f-droid is quite good. You can go quite deep with LinearJS and f-droid to replace
Android properly, you know without some of the the more sneaky Google Play services that are in there
In fact, I've got a friend who was looking to switch to iOS
But he's very happy with his Android hardware and doesn't want to actually throw the phone in the bin
But he doesn't want it to be tracking him quite so much either. And so he's actually going that route of
LinearJS and f-droid and going to see how long he can stick it just
D-d googled no micro G nothing good for him. It's it's I think it's a good thing to try and figure out if you can do it
Or where your line is I think more and more about
Gmail and just what a brilliant brilliant move that was
Because if you really use Gmail as your default inbox
which so many people did because it was just the most amount of storage you could get back in the day for free, but
as a result
Google knows
Everything I buy because all my receipts get sent to my inbox
So they literally even even things that are way outside the Google ecosystem
They know, you know, they know what I buy and that is
It's gross
And it makes me more and more think about maybe it is worth considering self-hosting email
It's just fraught with issues
but
Or something like proton mail
But yeah, anyways, that's just I find that to be really gross
And so if you can just maybe create a limited risk exposure to Google, that's the way to go. I feel like
Because they're just always going to be expanding their data mining
I'm just looking for the episode on two and a half admins. I think it's episode 72 email cartel
Joe Jim and Alan have a really great discussion about I think Jim's in the camp of
Microsoft and Google are the only options
Microsoft and Google are the only options because they're the big boys and if they don't work then it's not your problem
It's Google's problem or it's Microsoft's problem. Anyway, it's a fascinating discussion. I won't spoil it too much here
2.5admins.com episode 72. That's a great discussion
Public safety announcement time. Let's Encrypt are going to be revoking a ton of SSL certificates in the next few days
As we record, it should be probably over the weekend or by the end of this week
I think pretty much as this episode airs. So you haven't got long if you're listening to this
You should just be able to if you're using something like caddy or traffic or some automatic cert bot based
System to generate your TLS certificates just reboot that container and it should work out that those certificates are going to expire
Worst case is that you're going to log into your thing and see that this is unsafe message
And then you can restart your reverse proxy and it should just renew everything
For more details on that. We'll have a link in the show notes
tailscale.com
Self-hosted go there to get a free personal account for up to 20 devices and you support the show by signing up for
Tailscale, which is our favorite zero config vpn solution it installs on any device in minutes
You can manage firewall rules. It works from anywhere you create a beautiful vpn flat network for yourself
Load it up on a smartphone or a tablet and get access to your devices while you're on the go even when separated by firewalls
Subnets and I can attest even the dreaded double net tailscale will prevail them all
I mean, I really am so excited about this technology
That i'm just elated to have the opportunity to actually have them as a sponsor. You got to try it out
It'll change your game. I've been running on everything from my arch86 servers
My new tumbleweed boxes. I have raspberry pies with raspbian and ubuntu
All of it it all works. They have an install for all of it. It's quick
It supports your single sign-on system and that includes two-factor authentication
Under the hood. They're using wire guards noise protocol for encryption
So you get the tech of wire guard that you love with the flat mesh vpn network that tailscale brings on top of that
My tailscale vpns are always on they interconnect my systems and every os I use
I even use it with my family like my kids their machines all have tailscale installed as well
So I can ssh into their boxes
It's solved so many problems for myself and it's just a unique opportunity to have them as a sponsor
So I want you to go try it try it up for 20 devices for free
And you support the show. It's tailscale.com
Self-hosted all one word self-hosted you go sign up you get the 20 devices for free
You support the show and you're doing like awesome mesh network with wire guard stuff. It's the best go try it out today
tailscale.com slash
self-hosted
Now long-time listeners of the show will know that i've been hosting a server at my dad's house for many years since I emigrated
Three plus at this point
He's moving house. So I'm going to be hosting a server at my dad's house
He's moving house and that doesn't sound like a big deal people move house all the time except for the fact
He's moving from somewhere with cable internet 300 down 30 up style internet
To somewhere with two meg down dsl and barely half a meg up
Has he not thought about how this is going to affect you?
No, he hasn't oh my goodness
I'm gonna have to rethink my entire iPlayer strategy man. Not only that but your entire backup strategy like this is huge, man
Yeah, potentially. So we're looking at a few options for him ee who are a carrier in the uk, uh, cell phone
mobile phone provider in the uk they offer a home internet package, uh, which
Straddles the 5g 4g spectrums and I think it's about 50 pounds a month
So it's quite affordable for unlimited data unlimited in air quotes probably
She's that sounds pretty good though
Yeah, so my mother-in-law actually lives in rural norfolk and we recorded a podcast over a 4g
Um mobile broadband because she had a similar dsl situation where she was getting you know, a meg or two
Either way, which really you know in in this day and age is no good
So she's been using this service from ee for a few years and it works extremely well
They put an antenna on the roof. It points directly at the mast. It's a few miles away. It's a house. It doesn't move
Right, and it's fine. The downside is you have bandwidth quotas on the 4g plans. It's a few hundred gig
I think she has two hundred gig to go with but she's a single, you know widow
She doesn't use a huge amount of data, but the 5g plan has that unlimited tier, which I found really interesting
So the spectrum obviously of 5g either they want to get people hooked into 5g now
And they're offering that carrot to dangle people in
Or the spectrum just actually permits that kind of usage. I don't know. It'd be interesting to to find out now
What I wanted to ask you about is I know you've put an absolute metric ass ton of time into figuring out
multi-wan connections
And my dad's looking at starlink obviously, but there's a big wait time for that
And so in the meantime, what we're thinking of doing is getting a couple of different providers to kind of figure out
If that would improve his situation. Is there you know, what should he be looking at for these kind of mobile internet type?
On the on the server side anyway, not not necessarily the carrier stuff. Yeah
Yeah, I'll tell you I think probably the number one important thing is the antenna on the roof outside of the building
That makes such a huge difference. And then the other thing to kind of look for is you have different categories of
Categories of modems and antennas. So you have like a cat 12 modem and a cat 16 modem and essentially the
bigger the number
The faster it is the more connections it can do to the tower that kind of stuff
so that's what you want right is you want an antenna and you want a
lte device like a
Like a router or or a mi-fi device that can take advantage of that
And so that's what I had to end up do is I got um, I got I got something from a company called
Pep wave or it's a pep link. I'm sorry. I yeah, it's pep wave is the anyways
It and uh, this is built for for uh, you know a mobile setup
but they have setups for residents and buildings as well and
um, they have
with that a
Vpn service that does a bonded connection and you can do this on your own if you're really good. Um,
Wes and I did build one on a raspberry pi
And tested it for a bit and it worked and we did uh, we bonded two connections out to linode and it worked
but
The thing about uh, the vendor solution is it works in conjunction with software on the router
It's aware of packet loss. It is very intelligent about what it sends over which vpn and which connection and it
Overall just does a better job managing it
Um, so you can kind of stack this stuff. So, you know tier one antenna and a modem
and then tier two is
What you bring that into?
Um, is it is it coming into just a little crappy mi-fi box that's been doing wi-fi right there off that box because
You're gonna have a really limited wi-fi setup. So that's something that can happen is
People can get a little mi-fi device and then they go to use that well those things suck when you get more than a couple
Of devices connected to them and their range is only a couple of hundred feet. So he's got this uh, speedify article
Which he found on tech radar uk. It sounds like it does a similar thing
it bonds a few connections together over a vpn and uh, my initial reaction when he suggested that was
I remember back in my college days. I had a few cable modems that had some questionable firmware on them
And I ran those things. Yeah
Into a pf sense set up to get free internet when I was a student
And I remember, you know back then the internet was obviously a lot less sophisticated
But I just remember bouncing from one modem to the next and being logged out of websites all the time
And it was just super annoying. Is that kind of stuff still a problem today?
Not with the right solution that is getting better and better because the endpoint that you bond into that's the connection that goes out
To the website so that ip doesn't change but like with this speedify setup, you know
what I don't like about it is
They'll give you a couple of gigs for free and then after that
You got to start paying, you know, you watch a netflix movie a single netflix movie
Maybe even half the netflix movie before you've used up what you which you get for free
Well, I mean the amount of videos I send him of his granddaughter
I mean right well and you're going to the trouble of paying for an unlimited lde connection and then
Getting all of this hardware and then you know this kind of stuff. It just doesn't to me
It doesn't make sense so much. I do. I do appreciate that. It's more approachable
In the us i'll link to some bundles people can get that just kind of bundles all the hardware and software together
It's a little trickier out there, but I think really what I i'd start small
And see what your dad's comfortable with like you can even get
Mi-fi devices that have small antennas that you can connect to them
And you can just mount the antenna to the window facing the cellular tower and the little antenna has a section cup
It's a flat little antenna and that can actually make a significant improvement because it's um
What is it called alex? It's like the richter scale where an improvement in db in cellular reception is like a significant improvement
So like a 1 db increase is is is a significant increase in signal. Yeah, the logarithmic
scale that
And so even just getting up a couple of dbs can make a huge performance difference and latency difference
And so just starting like with that if you just got a mi-fi and an antenna like netgear makes one that mounts to the window
Uh, he'd be all right, but even better
Obviously as you know would be an antenna on the roof maybe on a pole that's above the roof line
Yeah, that is the way to go
Yeah, that is the way to go. Uh what i'm worried about with this ee solution in particular is they supply the modem
And isp provided modems are notoriously
Crappy. Yeah, and you can't run wire guard on them and you can't do a whole bunch of port forwarding stuff
Which I find very useful when we're doing remote management and if I have a backup server there
Yeah, i'm a little bit worried about uh
Will it be one of those things where you could take the sim card out and put it in a nicer piece of hardware? I
Need to do some more research now if you're in the uk and you know the answer to that question
I would love to hear from you
If you've replaced the ee router with something else as well
I would love to know what you've replaced it with and how it works because ultimately I would love to get to a situation where
The wan connection isn't really very important, you know
So that way when starlink does become available we can just plug. Yeah, my dad into the open sense
That's running in the house and it's just another one connection that we load balance or something like that
Um, so yeah, if you if you know the answer or if you've done anything similar, please get in touch at self-hosted dot show slash contact
Yeah, you have a little mini dv tape follow-up for people who don't recall alex ended up getting his hands on some dv
Tapes that he wanted to import and you put the call out there for some hardware
But I guess it was a little more complicated than we remembered things being it turns out 90s tech sucked worse than we remembered
I have in my hands a cannon vixia hv40
This thing one of those in the studio
If you don't want that send it to me because mine died and I got to replace it and then I could do video in
The studio. I think this thing was the rolls royce of camcorders back in the day. It has an hdmi out on it
Yeah, oh, I know. I used to have two of them, but now they've both slowly died on me
So I met up with a listener who actually lives 10 minutes from my house
He heard the episode last a couple of weeks ago
And messaged me and said hey alex. I've got a mini dv camcorder. It's got an hdmi out
Do you want to go for coffee and you can have it for a few weeks and I was like, yeah, that sounds amazing
Thank you so much. Uh, so, you know, I met up with him got coffee brought it home. What is it? Wait a minute
What is he doing with this thing? He needs to sell it to me. That's this is this is what needs to happen
This is what needs to happen. Oh wicked. I'm sure you'll i'm sure you'll hear this episode
So very excitedly I brought this thing home got it unpacked got it all set up
And put in one of the tapes and it just said unsupported format
And i'm like, huh?
Now I was thinking maybe it was something to do with the because on mini dv tapes
There's this long play and short play format
So you could take a 60 minute tape and make it into a 90 minute tape or something like that sp and lp
That's it. Yeah god
Tech 15 years ago was just ridiculous. Wasn't it? It's so bad. How do we make it work?
And importing footage off those tapes meant you actually had to like play the tape back. You couldn't just copy the file time. Yeah
Now these days you just have an sd card you just copy it off it's fine, you know
Yeah, we complain about dongles these days. Give me a dongle any day. Yeah
Yeah, um, so yeah, I was you know, I had my hdmi capture device. I've got a usb
One of those just knocking around and I was like right? This is going to be perfect unsupported format. Womp. Womp
turns out
My tapes are in pal format and this camera is an ntsc camera now. I'm almost positive
You could switch it to pal though. Can't you?
I don't think so. I've had a real good dig. Oh if you uh,
Hmm, i'd have to look again. Maybe we can walk through it on a facetime call or something
Because I couldn't find it. It says it on the box though. That's the trouble ntsc printed right on the box
Yeah, it might just be stuck. I can't remember
But the other thing too is the f the firewire port allows you to do a dv import and that might not be well
Either way, you're probably screwed but that is a thing you can import off the firewire port too
I'll play with mine after the show if I can get it to power up. I think it's totally dead though
It's been you know
It's been 100 years. So just one stupid little format issue
It's so dumb too that the u.s. Was ntsc
You guys across the pond
Were pal. I think pal was maybe the superior tech too, but I don't think it was 50 hertz versus 60 hertz
I think that was the entire reason it existed if I recall
And then they started using it to do region locking of like vhs tapes
And I remember xbox games back in the day. I think even 360 games were still region locked
It sounds so silly now, I mean we still have weird issues like that
But so now you've got to make it harder is not only is you really need
Something that is very rare a working mini dv player, but you need a pal
I need a european one in america
And the stupid thing is these tapes were in europe until my mom brought them for christmas
You know, I know that back in the day they used to have just little tapes
I know that back in the day they used to have just little mini dv
Players like a vcr that you'd put the little tape in and it would have a little hdmi out. They do exist
Uh, they're they're two three hundred dollars something like that on ebay
I think that's probably the route i'm going to have to end up going is buying one of these and then selling it on
So i'm effectively renting it for myself. You got to figure those tapes won't last much longer
Yeah, I mean there's only a dozen of them behind me. So it won't take too long. That's the annoying thing
It's not like i'm digitizing a hundred of the damn things like I need a three hundred dollar
Doohickey to do it. No, it's just a at this point. I'm kind of tempted to just pay the shop
Oh, you know
Now, uh, have you thought about what you're gonna do?
Encoding wise are you gonna bring these in as hd 64? Do you use something else now?
I'd like to try and use my
New m1 max and try and make the fans spin up and do some video encoding
Sure make that thing work earn its keep
I agree with you. I still haven't heard the fans on this thing
I've had this laptop for what three months two months now and it's a absolute beast
It's a monster and it it takes a stupid amount of workload
And it doesn't even say it doesn't even make a noise
and I I don't know like maybe istat menu needs to be updated because or it's
I I swear like it
It just doesn't seem like it matched what what shows in the load just it never seems right
It never seems like the system's ever maxed out
Yeah, I think there's a bunch of stuff with how they're doing
So we're used to computers that are general purpose and throw everything at the standard cpu cores just have main cores. Yeah, exactly
Yeah
I'm, not sure that istat is particularly good about how it visualizes like the neural cores and you got the efficiency cores versus the
Faster cores and all that kind of stuff, but that's going to become a thing
Throughout, you know intel cores too
And that's going to be pretty cool when it does hit systems you can build a home server around because I'm all about that
Why have like all those little background tasks that are always running on your box?
Hit those high power cores if they could run on the efficiency cores
We just need to make sure that like the linux kernel and all that supports that but that work is ongoing
I just wanted to mention super quick
I know this is really super really tight notice depending when you're listening to this
But if you're listening on january 28th 2022
Then just this sunday we have a hangout at the studio. It starts around 11 a.m. In the pacific northwest
We're uh up in the marysville area. So I'll give you an idea of where we're at and we're getting together on january 30th 2022
It's a sunday and um, alex will be flying in with his private jet
And hanging out. Oh, yeah, sure
Signing, uh postcards my reusable falcon 9 rocket boosters as well
It's really nice of them to let you
To play with that you guys have really become the best of buds. Yep, you know, yeah old elon
Me and elon best buds. Yeah
Yeah, you guys you guys really bonded over 3d printing when he came to that one meetup that we had and uh ever since
Talking of meetups. I'm actually considering hosting a small one in rally in the spring
We'll just uh, i'll take my my red egg somewhere ceramic egg
And we'll cook out some meats in a park somewhere and hang out for a few hours and meet some of you because it you
Know I found out you know this week through the mini dv feedback
There are tons of you on the east coast that are willing to to meet up
So yeah, we don't get to do many events out there. You know east coast is
It's a far far far drive from seattle
I would love to be able to get out there more often
Some daft stat like 80 of the us population lives within a two-hour flight of atlanta
Just to give you an idea of how populous the east coast is
Wow, I could see one day having like a I would love to just have a little
Operation running out of like colorado or something like that because it seems like a pretty good central place to visit
From as well. Hmm. If only we had some insiders in colorado already, huh? Hmm, maybe one day
Thank you to our insiders that support the show our sres
You guys make the show possible at self-hosted dot show slash sre that membership gives you an ad free version of the show
and
A post show a little extra self-hosted you also get access to that if you become a member for the entire network
Jupiter party if you want to support all of our productions get all our shows ad free including this one
And don't forget about future meetups
You might not be able to make it to the pacific northwest but meetup.com slash jupiter broadcasting is where you go
And that's where we should do it. Alex if you eventually launch one
We'll put it on there so people can go to meetup.com slash jupiter broadcasting
For one on the east coast or the west coast and then when I travel
It's happening. It's happening. I want to go
I got fomo already and you haven't even made the event yet. So fire up the dupes, you know, let's go
Seriously, I think you probably got better weather than we do on average at least in the springtime. No kidding. Oh, yeah. Oh, oh
Oh, that sounds nice. That sounds really nice. Well, we'd love to get your feedback and links and all that kind of stuff
To what we talked about today. It's all on our website
You can go there at self hosted dot show today's episode is self hosted dot show slash 63 and the contact page
Specifically is self hosted dot show slash contact. Thanks for listening everybody. That was self hosted dot show slash 63