Hello.
Is this thing on?
Hey, Alex.
What's going on?
Hey.
Good to hear from you, Chris.
Hey, Alex.
Hi.
Good to hear from you.
Right.
So I've been meaning to bother you about this for a while.
Uh-oh.
I have an idea.
Okay.
Do you want to hear it?
Of course.
Well, you do podcasts.
Yeah, that's what I've been told.
That's allegedly what happens.
We've both been doing a lot of self-hosting lately.
I love it.
I'm all about it these days.
Self-host all the things.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah?
Well, that's the show.
Right there.
That's the idea.
What do you think?
Well, I'm not anti-cloud.
That's my only problem.
I'm not like an anti-cloud guy.
Well, nor am I.
Oh.
Okay.
So I don't want to buy a piece of hardware, a thermostat maybe, a security camera, smart
plug in my case, that two, three years later, maybe even six months, the manufacturer goes,
that's not the business model here.
Right.
And then it's just a shiny paperweight.
No.
I mean, that's literally just happened to me.
Yes.
There's no...
Never again, I say, Alex.
Never again.
And I want to give people a way to find out how to do a lot of this stuff, like a discovery
portal, if you like.
You know, say, I want to build a home server.
Where do you start?
There is so much information.
It's a lot to consider.
Google is overrun with keywords and SEO optimizations.
No kidding.
And so you and I, between us, I think can cut through a lot of the chaff and...
A few hard learned lessons over the years.
A few.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, we could definitely cut.
I like this idea.
I like it a lot.
In fact, it's an area that I also want to kind of continue to push and explore myself.
So I could use a little help, a little guidance.
And what about if we included some guests along the way?
Maybe people who...
Working on stuff?
Yeah.
All right.
Now you're getting me excited.
On the crew.
Crew too?
Yeah.
JB crew, listeners.
That's true.
They're always building stuff.
Get viewer audience questions.
I think we should get a few developers on the horn to talk to them about what they're
doing.
Yeah.
That's a good idea.
All right.
I'm all in on this idea now.
Okay.
Thank you guys so much for watching, and I'll see you guys next time.
Bye.