Think I've come upon the most American thing I buy on a regular basis that I should introduce you to is it a gun
Related item. Well, you could definitely hold your gun. They're 511 tactical pants
Tactical pants Alex all of the pockets you could ever need so, you know how you were saying you want to go on a walk
But you don't like to bring your phone. It's because you need a pair of tactical pants
They have pockets in places that distribute the weight so that you don't even feel it big old phones
Like the big old phones you get all go in the tactical pants. You need to try some of these
They're not that expensive
Hashtag no sponsor. I'll put a link in the show notes
What are they made out of though? Because I thought a lot of these tactical I can't say it tactical trousers
I can't say I can't I can't call them pants these tactical trousers
They they're often made out of the same material as like a sail, you know, like in a sailboat or something
Sure, like really thick. Yeah real thick doesn't doesn't wrinkle, man
These are constructed using a premium polyester cotton mechanical stretch tactile rip strop fabric. I don't know what that is
Sounds like a fancy marketing term to me it is but it's really great
I just I gotta say plus the other thing if you're like me they have elastic in the way
So it expands and detracts with you
Because that's something I'm always doing. Anyways, I'm just saying try it out. They're only 30 bucks
Are they revolutionary and were they made with courage mine were I don't know about yours
So I just think with your big phones. I think I think you'd appreciate it. I just one one American
Bit of life that I've adopted is tactical pants. Okay, I quite like I mean, you know in Raleigh over here
I need I need shorts from like March. I've been in perma shorts, which is lovely speaking of that
I just had a chance to see you you and I just got back from visiting
Wendell in Lexington and it was fantastic. We did some road tripping
It was a lot of fun. And we had a chance to really kind of look at business setups small and medium-sized business setups
So Wendell does some contracting and one of the things that he does for his clients is he backs up parts of their infrastructure
On his own. So if they're in the cloud, he'll back it up locally. And if they're local he'll back it up to the cloud
Well, we thought maybe we should chat about some lower cost setups today
Because this is an area that I have recently got into I used to be a
Build it as big and powerful as possible kind of guy, you know, I go to Unix surplus
I got a huge super micro box put all of the Xeons put all of the RAM put all of the disk in there and
Fire it up. You sent me the best text this week
Alex I've accidentally ordered to service
This is I really had a moment
I saw the Raspberry Pi 4 shows up on my doorstep in an envelope and I'm just thinking well my server shut up in an
Envelope, that's just that's just something else. I'm I'm picturing Steve Jobs MacBook Air manila envelope moment here, right?
Yeah, and I so I rip open the envelope and I realized there's two raspberry pies in there
And then I really was floored because not only had my home server been delivered in an envelope
But I had accidentally ordered two of them and I wasn't financially ruined
You know years ago I could spend for a client or for wherever I worked easily spend
$15,000 on an x86 rack mountable server
Easily sure. I mean even if you're looking at used enterprise gear the minimum price of entry is going to be three or four hundred dollars
I would have thought
Like an old think station maybe or you know anything with a Z on in it sure, you know
you can build them for two to fifty but
It's gonna be a bit of a potato at that point, right?
Well depending how you do it you could probably for well under a grand get a decent NUC setup with some storage
So there's a lot of ways you can go about this, but I actually am doing something kind of special
Little excited to announce here on the show that I'm beginning a new personal project
I am so serious about this that I'm actually taking time off throughout the rest of the year to work on this project and do little
Bits, it's called project off-grid. Well, you know, it's serious when it has a name. I know I've named it
As long time listeners will know I've got a I've got a 40-foot RV
That over the years I've been I've been experimenting with I've had a QNAP NAS in there
I've tried different things and I've really come to
This idea that I want to build a system where I can go completely off-grid and I've set myself some goals
But it starts at at the tech level. I want all of my home automation to be completely on the LAN
No cloud connectivity required because I often travel places that don't have connectivity now
That's an important thing right is not required. Although there are will be optional components
Which will interface with cloud services on occasion, right? Yeah. Oh, yeah hundred percent. Yeah
Yeah
It's sort of like it's sort of like I'll come back online and I'll sort of soak up the things that I needed
Maybe it's media files or articles and then and then as I drive down the road
I can sync those offline and then when I get to my destination, they'll be available for me
So this includes things like offline readers offline media and it means getting things like sensors and all of these that work on the LAN
But it also needs to be because it's in a very small living space. It needs to be quiet
It needs to be low power. In fact, ideally one day even run entirely off of DC which
Eventually would be powered by solar all part of this project. It's a multi-phase project this project off-grid
Currently, I'm trying to solve this traveling without signal issue
Also, I'm often double netted either by a campground or even just the ISP
I have in my hometown. I'm I'm on a 192 network all the time. It's horrible. It is so limiting
So that's why I'm gonna do a wire guard relay server, but we'll get to that in the future
because you have a really
interesting
Like life problem to solve here
I mean most of us most of our houses don't drive down the freeway and suffer a was it
A category 5 earthquake every time it does. Yeah, I think it's actually 4.7 on the Richter scales
What they say the scale category is hurricanes. Sorry, bro
Yeah, most of us don't have to deal with that
So I think it's a really unique set of challenges you're gonna have to deal with but on top of that
I've just solved my house in London. So I'm gonna be buying a house in America next year at some point
So a lot of these things that you're gonna solve
I'm just gonna lift and shift and copy and paste those into my my house solar is on my list
For example, I want to do some DIY Tesla Powerwall style stuff with old laptop batteries and things
So that that should be a lot of fun
But I'm really curious about this setup from a networking standpoint
So as it stands today you get your internet through a little antenna on your roof that comes from a hillside
Like two miles away, right? Yeah. Yeah, it's a wisp
So in my main what you could consider a home base where I've spent the most of my time and I have like full
Hookups and everything. I have a monthly ISP. That's just a local ISP that comes in over a wireless link
It's a decent. It's like a 15 megabit up and down connection
So it's not amazing but I can get things in and off my LAN at reasonable speeds
That thing comes into something that you tipped me off to that. I think it's a pretty great little device
It's the GL AR
750 s gigabit AC travel router. It's tiny or it's also called the slate. It's another term for it
It's about the size of a pack of playing cards. I would say maybe a little bit bigger, but not much
it's certainly in the same ballpark as a Raspberry Pi in a case and
Yeah, this thing I tipped you off because I I stupidly left my predecessor to this in a hotel room in Florida last month
So I had to buy a replacement and this this little travel router is is wicked, right?
It has several cool features, but it supports out-of-the-box. No custom phone ways required wire guard. Mm-hmm
Huge as things run in an open WRT. It has wire guard support plus it has
BGN and AC 802 11 and
3 gigabit network ports. So here's my use case for this device. I
I'm traveling a fair bit. So I'm going around different hotels and things like that and I use this thing to
Make the captive portal experience less painful
so when I get to a hotel
I'll plug this little device into a USB battery bank or a wall charger or whatever it might be
it doesn't really need much power and
Then I will connect to the SS ID that this little box spits out
When I do that, I can connect to a local IP address, which I think is 192 168 8.1
That's the subnet by default that it has I then log into the admin interface of this little travel router thing and
Then go into what's called the Wi-Fi repeater section
And when you do that
What you're able to do is actually look at all the SS IDs are broadcast in the place that you're in
Select the one that you want the router to associate with and then perform the captive portal on your laptop as if you were
Connected directly to the access point and that has a few benefits because it means devices that don't support captive portals natively
will pick up that authentication token via the router because it's the router effectively that's authenticated via its MAC address and
Then it also means that hotels that try nickel and dime you through a two device limit
I can connect 20 30 40 not that I have that of course
But you know, I have five or six devices when I travel sometimes between my wife and I and a two device limits
Just so annoying and this little device gets me around it
But to add to all that as well when you add in a VPN support at the router level
It means that any traffic that traverses through that device
Then goes through a VPN as well. So most hotel Wi-Fi is open and leaky and
This device just solves that problem perfectly. So it supports open VPN and wire guard
So whatever your flavor is you can make it work with this device that wire guard supports a big deal for me because I'm often
on what I consider
Untrustworthy lands campground Wi-Fi is very commonly just sort of thrown together
it's it's one flat LAN everybody just has at it and
Being able to isolate my systems from that as well as use wire guard to protect the traffic is really nice
So I have it in
My standard home base mode. It's going into that wireless ISP over Ethernet
It actually is you know, it comes off the back of the antenna as Ethernet that goes into the slate and that's how I'm using
It right now
But when I travel I use that Wi-Fi repeater mode to either connect to a MiFi and I will just choose
Whichever MiFi has the best signal and then I just connect it to that or campground Wi-Fi and it's
Surprisingly fast the specs of it aren't incredible. It it has a
775 megahertz CPU, but
you know open wrt doesn't need much and
I've offloaded some of the larger network tasks to other devices, which I'll talk about here in a moment
But it's pretty neat and again, it's DC
So everything in my setup right now, although a lot of them are using AC to DC adapters, but all of them are
Capable of doing just straight DC in the future because I essentially have a power wall built into my RV
I've got two lithium ion batteries right now, which will last me about 16 hours
It's amazing, but I plan to double that in in the future. Maybe when I go to solar
So I could maybe get you know quite a bit of time and if I can save that cost of converting to AC
I'll get even more time I can go off-grid
Yeah, little 5 volt USB. I think it's it micro USB. It is all it needs
It's great. And you know, it's so this this little box has a couple of other tricks up its sleeve
It has three gigabit ports on the back
Two of them are designated as LAN ports out the box. And the third is what's called a one port. So
The example I gave in a hotel where you connect over a repeater to the Wi-Fi
you just plug in an Ethernet cable and you can then use this router as a
Wi-Fi to
Ethernet adapter if you like. Oh, yeah
Also has a USB port on the side
So you could plug in a USB modem or an Android phone and use that to tether via this device to all of your other devices
And then the last trick that it has up its sleeve is it has a micro SD slot in the side of it
Additionally, it comes with a really easy to use GUI, but they include a more advanced power user GUI
That's just in the advanced section. So they don't they don't bury it
And then on top of that you can turn on SSH and then you're on the command line and you can do anything
So it's not limited either. It looks like a very bootstrap kind of UI to me. So it's it's quite modern. It's responsive
yeah, so this device I think I paid about 60 or 70 dollars for it and
We'll have a link to it in the show notes
It's a really great pickup to be honest
And I think I'm gonna try and keep hold of this one and not leave it in a hotel this time
Yeah, yeah, I really like it
I have had some compatibility issues with an AT&T MiFi where the MiFi would crash
But when I switched it over to use the 5 gigahertz Wi-Fi, it seemed to get a little bit better
So just test it but I love it and I'm keeping it. It's part of my network arsenal now
So that's I've got that set up and then I have a Wi-Fi system that I need to replace
Eventually, but we can save Wi-Fi for a future episode because it it works right now
What do you use at the moment? Can we name and shame it? I I really like it
So I don't want to shame it. It just has a fatal flaw
So I got before Amazon purchased them. I got the Eero system the Eero
Oh, mm-hmm. It's fatal flaw is that it does require some level of cloud connectivity
Occasionally to function properly. Is that not true of the ubiquity stuff as well? Because I know that I have to run my
ubiquity controller in a container and
To configure the access points. I mean I have never left it offline for more than a few days
Is that true of the arrow too?
Well, so here's the way it works with the arrow and that's why it's a fatal fall
Like what you're talking about can be from like a licensing check-in or stuff like that
But with the arrow if it loses its state for some reason and it loses power
Which can happen when I'm say switching from one power source to another every now and then there's a hit to the system
maybe I'm going from generator to battery or from shore to battery and
That brief interruption can sometimes reset systems when that happens in some situations
If arrow cannot contact their cloud servers, it won't start the LAN
Why what possible reason could they have for that because it assumes its state is invalid
Because there's some there's some signing that has to happen between the communication of the head unit and the nodes
And when that signing can't be verified, it doesn't start up the LAN as a safety measure
Safety, right? I'm not buying that. I'm sorry. It's just a telemetry thing. If ever I heard of it
I knew this going in I knew was a bad call, but it is truly the fastest most reliable most problem-free
Wi-Fi I have ever used so going forward
It's the Wi-Fi systems I'll buy for all of my family
Like if like as a Christmas gift if they need Wi-Fi every now and then like every like five years
I'll do this. This is what I'm getting them and Amazon's bringing the price down even more now. It's so bulletproof
However, I got to go with something that's offline and the and the funny thing is the RV has a lot of interference
So I actually need a two node system to get great signal everywhere to do video streaming
It's bulletproof unless your internet goes out and then you're screwed
So, okay, I wasn't gonna go down that rabbit hole, but you made me do it
But it's it's it's otherwise a good system, but it eventually has to get replaced if I'm gonna go off-grid
But right now for the last few months almost coming on month three. I have I have gone down the route of
Decloudifying the RV and bringing everything on to a single Raspberry Pi
Of which I run home assistant smoke ping duplicati sync thing
Plex and
ranteo
Alright, so let's put let's break these down one by one
The one that stands out to me is being like a huh is plex because doesn't that need big CPU to transcode stuff
I am taking advantage of the of
Raspbian on the Raspberry Pi 4 and it does have hardware decoding and there is there is support now in plex for for that
But when you're just talking three televisions and a max of six users ever it's really
Surprisingly not that bad the Raspberry Pi has more overhead than you'd think with all of those services running on that
I'm around eight percent
CPU usage and then when I'm maybe doing like last night I was doing a docker compose update
watching Star Trek the original series
Blu-ray rip off of the Raspberry Pi plex direct play I assume a to an NVIDIA shield
So I'm pretty positive was direct play as well as doing package updates after the docker stuff was done
Like I was doing all of that on the host system
While also watching plex and I was tearing down a container as well
So I was doing quite a bit and it was really holding its own
The the biggest bottleneck is really the SD card
It makes all of the difference to spend a little bit more on that SD card. It really makes a difference
So I was experimenting during a lot recording this week with with my pi 4 and I copied the root
Directory so just slash like the bottom of root using our sink
I think I did was our sink tack AVX or something like that
And then you do slash and then the target of the SS USB SSD that I had attached
And I noticed that when I was doing package updates and stuff like that
It wasn't it wasn't night and day, you know, like going from a mechanical hard drive to an SSD was like, whoa
Holy moly, this is I'm never going back to spinning rust as my boot drive
It wasn't quite as night and day as I'd hoped on there
But you are right that the SD card is the major bottleneck at this point
Mm-hmm, and you can't yet USB boot the pie fully
So I must I must make it clear that my slash boot was still on the SD card
Even though slash was actually on the SSD, but yeah running you're running
What this is that six or seven six different containers that are fairly active really?
I mean they I mean including there's a couple of things on the host system like Samba and net data that aren't in containers
And only 8% CPU usage. I remember on the first pie
Trying to run. What was it called? XBMC with I think was RAS BMC with Sam Nazarko back in the day and
You know trying to run just a single HD video stream
It was so bad. The CPU was just pegged and I had the MPEG 2 decoder license
I paid extra for and it was just pegged
And yeah, we've come a long way with these pies how um, so I have a question for you about how warm
That your pies getting yeah, there's that so I think a couple of caveats here
I've gone with the flirt cases for my pies
And not only because I think it's a really sturdy case, but because it has some thermal management built in it
It comes with thermal paste and then the case actually makes contact with the CPU and that thermal paste and it acts as a heat
spreader and
I've watched a few reviews on YouTube and it you know brings it down an actual measurable noticeable worthwhile amount
I'm also using the flicker case and the whole thing is made out of well
The side of it is made out of aluminum
Machined aluminum and the uh, the inside of the case actually dips down to touch the CPU with a thermal pad
Yeah, that's a better way to put it
Yeah, and then the top and bottom are made out of this kind of soft touch rubber material and the case itself was 15 bucks
Which I paid 15 for a lego case a few years ago. So, you know price wise it's it's for what you're getting
It's fantastic. It takes the raspberry pi which on its own naked to sort of fit into the case
The raspberry pi which on its own naked just sort of feels like a hobbyist toy
And you put it in this case and now it feels like a premium consumer product
so I did that to help reduce heat also a big part of this is um,
I I really think having the ethernet on its own bus
And and having the network separate now from the disk made it wasn't just the cpu
But that was the other piece that made this really doable for me
gigabit is
Closer now to full gigabit than it ever has been but also when you're doing network traffic
It's not polluting the usb bus, which is where with a pie the majority of your storage is going to live
So yeah, I totally agree with that now, um in your list of applications. You mentioned something called ranteo. I've never heard of this
What is it?
Oh boy, this is one of those life-changing
Applications that I found uh-oh. It's like i've finally come home
I'm I finally have a note system
That truly works for me and it's fully offline
It supports markdown
I can bang out notes in any old dirty text editor. I want or I have a web ui
Hallelujah, this is changing my life and the secret that really brought it to the next level was when I combined it with sync thing
Oh, man. Oh
Oh alex, this is such a game changer for me sync thing, huh?
Not next cloud sync, you know, it's neck
There's so many ways you can skin this cat really so that's perfectly acceptable if nextcloud works for you have at it
I I use nextcloud for my work stuff. I wanted
um something that was totally offline available as text in the rv at all times because i'm going to put
maintenance logs in there
Information about repairs all the documentation for my network
Uh family notes that hidea and I need to keep track of like doctor's names all that
I want to have available offline
And the way my brain works if I can dump out something in text i'm much more likely to capture it
And I prefer to use an actual text editor
So rantio or however you say it rantio, whatever it is is a
very simple web ui
That sits on top of a directory structure of markdown files
You can create arbitrary directories. You can just add markdown files. You can add markdown files to the root
And it will render and display it like notes
No database no database just flat files. That's great
That's where sync thing comes in because then I sync those flat files to a notes folder on all my systems
And wherever i'm at whenever something pops in my head
I just toss in that notes folder and then it's on my rv either when it comes back online or like right now
It's online. So it's just synced up immediately
And then when I want to retrieve it or more importantly when I want high spousal approval factor for retrieving information
It's got a nice web ui on top of it. I don't know why notes is such a difficult problem to solve
It seems to me that evernote solved it a long time ago
But you have to pay for that and it's a cloud service, right?
But in terms of the self-hosted space for note taking there's a few options
So there's joplin there's nextcloud has a notes thing built right in
I mean you could use git if you wanted to I mean literally the the options are endless
but I think a couple of things that you mentioned really
Spiked my interest and one of those is there's no database. So it's a flat file structure
A lot of apps seem to miss that fact because I want my notes to remain
agnostic to the application
Which they were written in or for or synced by also a perfectly usable
Uh scenario for me would be issh into my server and I just cat the file to get a quick like command
I need to copy or something totally
Uh, and then also I guess you could back it up with git and it still remains viewable by rantao or whatever it is
Does it support like rich stuff like pictures or screenshots or stuff like that?
Yep, it has a content folder and you can toss it has content
That's where you toss the markdowns and has images and that's where you toss the images and then you just you know
You link back one folder and it just it figures it out. It's really easy
Well, you might have gone and done it you might have gone and found it
I think i've reached peak services to pie. Um a
It's now becoming a little mission critical and b
If any one of those were to go haywire could slow down the other so I think i'm going to stop about there
And now i'm going to go to a second pie and my plan is to go to three pies total
No more than three
And you're not going to run kubernetes on those and do some fun stuff with that
I might let you talk me into that in the future. I might we could
I need to buy a couple so I can figure it out first and then make myself look clever by telling you
Great good plan. I put my so I put my second pie into production last night
This will be a dedicated network services pie. So this now runs pie hole
And I may move smoke ping and a couple other just like network level infrastructure things to that pie
Smoke ping is pretty cool. You put me onto this way before you knew who I was
Um with the last episode about five or six years ago
And it was actually one of the first containers that linux server did back in the day
Such a good app you get the best insights and for me
It's really interesting to see how the different networks that I go to perform
I go to bed and I wake up in the morning. I check smoke ping and I go. Ah, okay. It's gonna be one of those days
Now there's another one that's actually come onto the scene fairly recently called stat ping
Um, so I have it running on a digital ocean droplet and I I use it to monitor things like service uptime. It's like a
Alert genie ops genie type thing where it will ping a certain ip over either tcp or http
And just tell you whether the service is up or down
You can also use it to communicate with family members that there is planned maintenance coming on the plex server for example, which can be nice
so
you know if some if i'm needing to swap out a hard drive or um
Um blow dust out of a fan or something and turn the server off for a half an hour
I can just put a note into stat ping to say server off between these times
Don't message me about this thing because it's it's not an accident
The other really cool thing about stat ping is it's a really quick way to see the last time a service had an issue
because it just tells you right there when you load the page the last time this went down was at this time and date and
We use that here in the in the studio to check on our services
If you want to see a quick demo, you can go to status.ktz.cloud. That's mine
And you can have a little look at that. Um, so what else you got on that list?
You've got home assistant, which I think definitely deserves its own episode. Yes
That's the primary function of the pi 4 really but duplicati. What are you using that for?
I'm using that to back up my docker compose files and my config files and a little bit of data
to both dropbox and google drive
I don't really use either one of those very much
But this is kind of an I have you know amounts of storage in each one of them and we're talking text files here
So it does a aes 256 encryption. It, you know wraps it all up into into a nice locally encrypted
A bit bit of bundles essentially and then sends it up to the cloud and um, does it every single night?
So if I make just even the smallest line change, I make sure that gets captured and sent off site
I really like duplicati. I've been using it for over a year over here as well
And it's it's pretty bulletproof. I mean the error message can error messages can sometimes be a little bit
Vague but for the most part, it's it's pretty great and I use it to back up terabytes worth of data to google drive. So it's um,
Pretty good
I was considering putting my docker compose folders in the sync thing and then just syncing them to different folders on my laptop
And then doing the changes there. I have to say when you're working with docker compose
Which we'll talk about more in jupyter extras in the near future. We're going to do some container essentials in a future jupyter extras
So extras dot show for that, but I have to say when i'm working with docker compose files
Visual studio code blew my mind. I opened up the yaml file. It's like oh, hey, I noticed this looks like a docker compose file
Would you like me to load docker support?
And then it it really helps with identifying where things need to go in the yaml file because if you just have it on
The wrong indent
It'll break docker compose and it won't launch and so this gives you a visual guide when you're kind of new to yaml
It's it's very nice. That's one of the primary complaints. I hear about yaml as a file structure is
People don't seem to like the tabs
Although without structure, there's no order and without order. It's just chaos. So yeah, quit whining because
Yaml's amazing and i'm not i'm not listening. It's readable, right? It's at least readable. It's better than json
It's better than json. Yes, which is the alternative. So yes very much
So down the road, uh
Which we'll do a future episode on I plan to set up my third and last pie
As a shinobi local camera capture because I have a couple of cameras in the rv now they go off to cloud storage
It's no good. It's going to go local
Um, but that's down the road. There are a couple of caveats. I want to make clear to people
I would not be able to do what i'm doing with raspberry pies
If I didn't have a big old x86 rig here in the studio doing some of my heavy lifting
Now that could have easily been a droplet or a linode vps. It doesn't have to be a local box
But for me some of the large job extraction and data processing
Is happening on the studio land and then i'm just syncing the essential bits that I need to the rv
And the storage too because you know a usb two and a half inch hard drives limited to about four terabytes, I think
Let's say I mean you could maybe have half a dozen on the pie, which is still impressive
Granted, but it's not it's not going to match what you can put into a big x86 box, right with spinning disks
That are you know, six terabytes or more each eight terabytes. Um, that is the other limiting factor
What i've gone with is i've tried i've tried to find good deals on
Uh usb3 ssds that are powered by the bus and I just hang that off the pie
So there's that those are the caveats there as well as of course in my opinion
Although feel free to tell me otherwise i'd love to know what's working for you out there
I think on a raspberry pi
for the for specifically
Raspbian is really your only bet if you're going to use it in production
For the moment anyway. Yeah, there's so many drivers and little itsy bitsy things here sentos just got basic boot support
But it's still not very stable. Um, I have reason to believe that the
Ubuntu folks may have some work in progress to make it
Um a little more doable including gpu support and whatnot. But right now
If you want to update the firmware on this thing
if you
Want to take advantage of the gpu and really have the most I think stable running linux system
It needs to be raspbian right now, which is debian based. What do you mean gpu support?
Oh, no, I just mean like the drivers for gpu acceleration are different. And in fact the architecture is completely different
But it's it's a it is a different. It is a really different product from the three
It it looks the same and it has it looks similar and it has a similar name
But it is an entirely different beast. So it does have those caveats
I don't want to come on here and say you can throw out your x86 box with a raspberry pi 4
But I do want to say as somebody who was a big metal make it as fast and big as possible kind of guy
I'm blown away what i'm doing with these two raspberry pies right now
And at this point i'm going with multiple raspberry pies just to sort of isolate things out
I I don't want my dhcp server and dns server to be on my application server
So I i'm choosing I ran pie hole
On my main raspberry pi for a bit just to see if I liked it and it worked perfectly fine
and then the other thing to bear in mind as well, of course is
Application availability the pi is of course an arm cpu not an x86 cpu
So not every piece of software that's ever been written has yet been ported or built for arm
Docker containers make it largely irrelevant to a certain degree these days
Although it depends whether your container maintainer
Supports arm builds, um most do but not all so that's just something to bear in mind as well
But I think you know the the overall kind of impressions of this device for me
Is that for the price you really are going to struggle to match this performance?
Any other way that in in this particular form factor and that's what really wins out with the pie is that
A couple of things is the form factor the price and the network effect
There are dozens and dozens of other projects based around the pie
So if you get bored of hosting these services on the pie, you could turn it into a full screen
Calendar that hangs by your front door so that all your family know when you're coming and going and it is so much the network
Effect like i i i'm really curious about systems like the atomic pie and other boards that are out there
People are really focusing on raspbian and raspberry pi so you can like just google anything and put raspbian on it
And you'll get a guide for it and that sort of um
Network effect makes it so much more approachable for people that are not
So much more approachable for people that are learning how to do this kind of stuff
I I really can't underestimate it and I I can see myself down the road
Maybe looking at things like atomic pie or or even saying ah, screw all these raspberry pies. I'm switching to a big knuck
but
Right now i'm i'm liking the set of compromises and advantages and with the pi 4 the price has really the price performance is just
Blew my mind way beyond my expectations
Part of taking these things offline in the rv
It has been this feeling that I own this stuff again
And i've never been bothered by not owning it like never really was I don't have an issue with that kind of stuff generally
Having it back. I now appreciate it in a way that it gives me it sounds silly, but it gives me genuine happiness like I feel
Proud and i'm happy to have this stuff like I feel like it's mine like i've created something
But we're able to use technologies like containers to just stand up
instances of applications
exactly as the developer intended
with
almost no knowledge of the application itself, you know, so
Technologies 10 years ago just didn't permit us to be able to do this kind of stuff
No, it's it's it's enterprise grade stuff that i'm running on a raspberry pie
in my rv
Yeah going that can go that goes down the road at 65 miles per hour. It's it's mind-blowing and it's it's working
And it's only getting better. Uh, we've talked about this before but we're really at a really special time where web applications are decent
Container technology is prevalent
The hardware is cheap enough
And the motivation is there to self-host this stuff like it's such a great time to be doing this
So you heard us mention it a couple of times but be sure to check out xers.show. We'll have a special on reverse proxy
And a special on the basics of container technologies
So if if you want to understand some of these fundamentals a little bit
We wanted to cover those early in the in the lifespan of the show
And we're publishing those in the off weeks of this show at xers.show
And you can also join us in the jb telegram group. We're using a hashtag ask ssh both on telegram and twitter
for user questions
Um, we've had some really good ones come through and we will get to those over the next few episodes as well
But uh on twitter, you can find me at ironic badger and chris i'm at chris las and so thanks everyone for listening
That was self-hosted.show slash three