We teased last week, Chris, that you've been doing some camera stuff, right?
And I think I certainly because I'm just about to buy a house.
I certainly want to know more about your cameras, the good and the bad.
But let's just address the elephant in the room.
You were pretty hard on Shinobi last week.
First of all, congratulations on the news on the new house.
That's going to be epic project material for the show.
That's amazing.
Yeah, so last week we talked a little bit about Shinobi.
I'm a Raspberry Pi four.
It was going bad.
I don't know if you remember, but I was like pegging out the CPUs
and I hadn't even added all the cameras yet.
Three cameras is what you said.
Yeah, well, I'm happy to say I've got five cameras now
and the CPU usage is high, but that's because I've also turned on motion
detection and recording, which saves some storage space.
So you're able to get five cameras with all of those kind of
advanced features working through a Pi four.
Yeah, I suppose for full disclosure, the fifth camera is more of an on or off.
I actually set up my dash cam as a camera feed that feeds into the Shinobi DVR system.
Of course you did.
So I just turned that one on or off.
So that's not motion detection based because that's that's really where
a lot of the process here goes.
Alex is the motion detection.
Turns out last week I was trying this out on Ubuntu LTS and fine
distro Alex, but not quite there for the Raspberry Pi four yet.
And when I switched over to Raspbian, when I just nuked and paved
and rebuilt it on Raspbian, when I when I selected the hardware
acceleration options and I could just choose auto, but when I just
turned them on in Shinobi works with Raspbian and my CPU used
to just completely drop to the floor.
It was just it was gone.
So what is that then?
It must be some hardware acceleration at play here.
Yeah, I think so, because like every now and then the camera feeds
just kind of stop recording.
And I think it's like a GPU acceleration failure.
So about every couple of days I've rebooted the box.
Now that I've switched over to motion capture, that hasn't been an issue yet.
But so maybe I should recap a little bit.
Just to remind you, I have those wise cameras, those little $25 wise cameras.
I've mounted them all around the inside of my RV.
Had to run like the USB cords and stuff, which is what it is.
But I popped on a new firmware onto those wise camps.
It's pretty simple.
You just download their official RTSP firmware file.
The downside is, is I don't think it's really quite feature complete compared
to the official official firmware.
What do you think?
As I understood it, it's like a fork in time.
So they, it's not a build that they keep up to date with the modern features.
I believe they fork every couple of months, although there's no
commitment to doing so that is so here's a snapshot in time with RTMP turned on.
We'll release another one when we feel like it.
It seems to be like a very highly demanded feature though.
So it's unlikely they're going to abandon it, but quite frankly, my goal
here is to cut these things off from the internet anyways.
So I, I care less.
Why do you need a dash cam into Shinobi?
Like are you using one of those wise cams as a dash cam?
Yeah.
I haven't actually gone down the road yet, but I have one set up looking
out the windshield in your car.
Oh, on the RV.
Oh, okay.
Wow.
I mean, if you're driving a flipping bus down the road, I can see, I can see
that little camera not being a thing.
I was thinking in your golf, man, I was trying to figure where that
little thing fitted in your golf.
No, I put it up front there and, uh, we'll see.
I haven't actually been on a road trip with it yet to test it, but anyways,
I got this RTSP firmware, popped it on the file.
You just rename it to like demo dot bin, I think reboot the cameras
holding down the setup button.
They'll detect the file and just reflash themselves.
And your real only immediate tell, unless you memorize the version numbers
is when you relaunch the wise app, they'll now be an advanced RTSP section.
You can turn that on.
It'll give you the URL and you can plug that in anything.
Uh, VLC, Shinobi, there are a few things though to make it work, right?
So if you want to try this Alex, I put a link in the show notes, um, on an
article that tells you how to optimize Shinobi for RTSP capture, because there
are a couple of things that aren't necessarily obvious, especially if you
want to grab the audio and maybe the other disclaimer of using these wise
cams like this is they don't support that device standard that so many
security cameras support.
I think it's what, Oh, Oh, N VIF or whatever.
What's that for?
It's like a standard control and features baseline that all cameras, if
they're certified to support this, then, you know, you can plug them into
whatever security software and control it remotely, make it pan or tilt or
get certain time information off of it.
So what is it like?
Um, not E P N P what's the other one?
D D N L a or something.
Is it a similar kind of universal protocol like that?
Yeah, you could think of it, but in terms of like, this is how I control
certain aspects of the camera, um, so then vendors of software can just make
a general interface that works with any camera that meets the standard.
The wise don't have that, but they're $25.
So you can forgive a lot for that price.
Can't you, the $25 and the other thing that surprised me, and I haven't pushed
it beyond two, but I have a feed that's going into Shinobi on that Raspberry
PI 24 seven, but I also can pull them up in home assistant and I can pull them
up an MPV.
So I now have a tab and home assistant that's called my security tab.
And in there, I have a, a tile for each camera and a tile for each motion sensor.
And I've also integrated our ring camera.
Yes.
I got one of those a long time ago.
I no longer have an active subscription, but I do have an account still and I have
an API key so I can actually pull the ring feed into home assistant.
So that's kind of a neat real time snapshot.
That's really neat.
Yeah.
I wanted to ask you actually, so remember when you were doing the
security, so remote access for Shinobi and I guess home assistant as well.
I'm going to add to my question trying to use the wise app is a bit rough remotely.
I found, um, I don't know if that's just the URLs I'm using or whatever, but I
haven't had great success.
Like my nest cam, which again, I bought a long time ago.
I can just pull that up wherever I am in the world and it just, just works.
And the wise cam doesn't do that for you.
The wise app for some reason, no reliably, I can't seem to use the
home I set in of that, I have not solved remote access yet.
Theoretically I would solve it with a wire guard VPN.
However, I am behind some enterprise grade double net systems here,
carrier grade as they like to call it.
So I have this super convoluted system that I'm working on where I wire
guide out to a remote system that establishes a two way tunnel.
And then I remote from my other systems into that.
I have IP table set up and some DNS and all of that.
And it routes everything for me, but I haven't gone that far yet.
So right now I use the wise app for remote access when I, when I need it,
but I don't generally.
So I'm really kind of using this to go back in time.
If something were to happen, you know, maybe there was a mini fire or an
accident with the kids or a mini fire.
I still sound scary.
Like a fridge fire, no big deal.
Just burn up the whole side of the rig or something, you know, maybe for
insurance purposes, I want that or burglars comes in or some crazy listener.
I don't know.
It's all on camera, crazy listeners.
I have had them show up at campgrounds.
I have had them knock on my door at rest stops.
I love it.
Actually, most of the time when we're on the road, I love it.
Um, one time and I bet he's listening, somebody showed up.
We were in Montana and we were in a gravel lot and somebody
came, pound, pound, pound, police, open up on my door.
My heart just dropped.
Like I just stopped breathing for a second.
I opened up the door and it was a listener is just screwing with me.
Good job.
You know, I felt if I ever get the chance to troll you like that,
I would definitely do that.
It's all right.
It's okay.
I'm good.
Just makes me jumpy.
Luckily I live far enough away that it's unlikely.
I'm just going to turn up at a random parking lot with dupes.
Unless they come to you.
And we should clarify, by the way, we had a few people that didn't actually
know that Chris lives full-time in an RV.
Yeah.
Since, uh, what?
I mean, it's been about five years now I've upgraded once in there.
So I've been in this one for about four years.
Full-time yeah.
With the wife and the kids and a dog, we affectionately call it
lady dupes on the network.
So we have JB one, which is the studio that we record most of the podcasts
from in Seattle anyway, Chris and Wes.
And then, um, lady dupes is Chris's home on wheels, I guess.
Yeah, the remote studio set up with, uh, multiple cellular networks
and, um, a little recording spot.
So I can do shows from the road.
I can work from the road, but we also have offline media part of my, well,
this is all part of my project off-grid is to really, really make that thing
a fully workable machine, even without internet connection.
And that's why I wanted to get these cameras into Shinobi is I was slipping
into, uh, the Logitech circle cameras.
They're not great, but they're kind of the best cloud connected
priced camera in my opinion.
And then you have things coming along like the blink cameras that are really
cheap and then the wise cameras came out at $25.
Yeah, they cleaned up.
So the fact that I could get something at that cloud connected or cloud
subsidized price, but then I can use it for my, my own offline system.
It makes me comfortable putting these throughout my house.
Cause before that, if you wanted to have a camera that was cheap, you pretty
much, you know, at that $25 price point, it was, in fact, it was pretty impossible
to beat that price, to be honest.
Um, but you could put a, you know, a raspberry pie with a raspberry pie cam
somewhere and that would get you in the sort of $40, $50 price point.
But even so at that point, like the, the other ones you mentioned, like the
logi stuff, the blink, et cetera, like the nest stuff, I mean, the nest is
expensive, but it's a, it's nice physical hardware, like it's machined to
aluminium and all that kind of stuff.
It looks nice.
Um, so the cameras that I've been looking at for my new house, um, which hopefully
I'll move into in about six to eight weeks, um, I don't want wifi cameras.
So this is for me, the biggest downfall of the wise cameras.
I've got two or three here and they're perfectly fine, but frames drop on
occasion and some, you know, it's chewing up wifi bandwidth where if I'm buying a
house, I'm going to live there for the next 10, whatever years you're going to
wire them, I'm going to run a cable, you know, I'm not driving down the road like
you, I'm going to run a cable and kind of run POE.
It's going to be a POE camera.
Good for you.
So I'm looking heavily at the unified gear right now, but damn, it's expensive.
Yes.
I just, just one 1080p camera is about 130 bucks.
I know my entire setup is probably under $300, including the
raspberry PI to record it.
Now that does not include storage, which right now is still in flux.
I'm cheating and I'm using a big old thumb drive as I experiment, but I like
what you're doing because you're investing in something that could
last you a very long time.
I hope so.
I don't, I don't consider these wise cameras probably more than
like a three year setup.
They're disposable, right?
They're like the little windup cameras you used to have.
So you could do a full POE setup.
You could do high resolution that could be swapped out to even higher
resolution down the road.
What are your minimum requirements?
Do you think?
One for the driveway, one internally on the front and back doors and, uh, the
other, uh, in the garage too, cause that's another ingress point.
That's one of the last cameras I did here at the studio, because I did a trial run
of this camera set up here at the studio.
So I have a similar wise setup here at the studio.
In fact, even larger.
And my favorite camera is the one in the garage, surprisingly.
Yeah.
I like to just, like, if there's a noise or something, I like to check in and make
sure that everything's okay and the car is okay.
So where my desk is in this current house, I can't see the front door.
So I have, I have a monitor up top and I just throw my nest driveway feed
up there all the time.
So when I'm just sat here working from home, I can just, you know, glance up and
say, oh, that's what that noise was.
But in terms of my requirements, self-hosting obviously, uh, is important.
I don't want to have to pay a subscription, um, for two reasons.
One is it's a hidden cost effectively in the ticket price of the item.
You know, you, you spend, let's say for a nest cam.
I know I keep coming back to those, but that's cause that's the ones I have.
I have two of those right now.
You spend a hundred plus dollars, nearly 200, I think on the external one on a
camera, and then you've got to spend another 50, 60 bucks a year for
their cloud connected service.
Now I appreciate for most people, that's a great solution because for most people,
they don't want to have hard drives in their house.
They don't want to have to think about it.
It's just press a button done. Thank you for me.
I've already got a hundred terabytes in my basement, so I may as well use that
with the unify, uh, NVR stuff that they, that they let you self-host.
Would you put a nest camera in your bedroom?
Well, I've already got a Google home in there.
So a camera though, that's doing person detection and object detection and sound.
I don't need a camera in the bedroom.
Nobody wants to see that.
The very powerful object detection and person detection that comes with the
nest cameras is also, I think what's gives me out and I'm not necessarily cloud
bad guy.
I do want to be comfortable walking around on camera, just being myself.
Maybe I'm in a robe or something like that, uh, in the RV because of such a
small space, I literally have nearly full camera coverage of everywhere in the
entire RV.
So there's really no way where you can be off camera unless you're in the
bathroom.
Yeah.
And so I really wanted to be comfortable when I looked up and looked at that
camera lens and saw that light was on, I didn't want to be thinking about where
that could get, could get processed or get stored.
Well, there was that whole thing, wasn't there with the, uh, was it Siri?
I think our Apple employees were listening into those recordings.
Actually, I guess nest also has had a significant rash of people compromising
accounts and then, um, like jumping on people's nest cams and talking through
the two way microphone system.
Have they, uh, didn't know that.
Yeah, I heard some tech journalists ranting about it on a podcast recently.
And then they looked into it and found that it's a fairly regular thing that
they go out of their way to kind of keep quiet.
Well, you would, if you were them, so, uh, you know, black Friday's coming up soon
in the States and, uh, Best Buy have started their shenanigans already.
Are you deal shopping already?
Well, I am.
Yes.
Obviously I'm looking for appliances for the house, but couldn't help notice
going in there, looking at TVs and stuff like that.
I mean, what's a guy to do, right?
Oops.
I haven't bought anything yet, but they have a 75 inch, uh, LED LG TV for like $900.
Stop it.
Uh-huh.
You don't even want to know what I spent for my first 60 inch Pioneer plasma.
Well, I've got one of these TCL Roku jobs, uh, in my lounge right now, which
I bought last year, I think it's 55 inches and it was like 300.
I like it.
Yeah.
I remember.
For the price, it's great that the image quality, uh, like, you know,
dark scenes and stuff like that.
Like the episode of game of Thrones a few months ago, that was just dark.
Like all I saw was like compression artifacts.
I literally couldn't see anything.
That's my TV right now too.
And I really want to get an OLED, but damn, they're expensive.
Yeah.
I feel like I'm going to wait one more cycle of television so that the top of
the line bumps down one notch because one of, I think, I don't know, this could
be past Chris being an idiot, which happens a lot, so future Chris will
determine, but current Chris is thinking that home kit integration could be a
pretty big deal in the televisions because I have had tremendous success working
with home kit and home assistant, and there's no cloud connectivity required.
It's all over the land.
And so integrating input control and power control and things of that nature
into home assistant.
Well, did you know those TCL TVs, the Roku TVs have an API?
Oh, so I mean, if one was willing, you could probably do it yourself.
Well, I turn my TV on and off using curl effectively.
It's just a command from home assistant.
Oh, no kidding.
Yeah.
I do it already and it works great.
Oh, that's wonderful.
You can set inputs.
You can turn the TV on and off.
You can turn it off.
You can set the volume, all that.
I'm legit jealous of that.
Like, I think I'll tackle a full solar install and be completely off-grid
before I get my TV fully automated.
Yeah, probably.
See, I had a Harmony hub before that.
And again, that was a cloud connected device, which Logitech decided to switch
the APIs off for in January or February this year.
Right around the time I was getting into home assistant and writing that talk for
LinuxFest Northwest that I was doing, you know, the DIY smart LEDs, which leads me
very, very nicely into a little plug I wanted to do on the show today, which is
that LinuxFest Northwest's 2020 is a call for papers is open.
Yes.
Are you going to submit?
I am going to submit something.
I don't know what yet.
We've got about 60 days at the time of recording.
So it closes like mid January, I think.
Um, so yeah, if you've been thinking, oh, I'd like to talk at a conference, but I
always miss the submission dates.
You've got a couple of months, give it some thought.
Don't rush into submitting upfront cause there's no benefit from doing that.
Take your time, put together a good proposal, try and think of something
that people want to listen to.
I just got a great idea.
I'd have to get clearance.
What if I did a talk about the lady jupes automation, but at the start of my talk,
everybody stands up and they follow me out to the RV and I just give
them a tour of it in person.
Does that scale?
Well, I'd have to do it in probably batches of like 10 people or something.
Yeah.
I mean, it's an RV, Chris, it's, it's small.
Did you use how many people were in there for the barbecue?
We probably had 15 people in there.
Yeah.
It was, it was a whole thing.
Um, I'd, I'd love that though.
Like if, if you've got some legit automations finished by then.
Yeah.
So far, this has been our most comfortable summer just due to the
automations that I have got.
When you can make your quality of life better.
Yeah.
You know, that's something I was thinking about talking to you about with these
cameras, one of the things I noticed when I was taking my time and kind of doing
it slowly and, and applying some craftsmanship to it, like we talked about
with Wendell, I got a much deeper sense of satisfaction when the work was over.
Like, and it struck me cause I'd had a day where like a lot of things were
thrown at me cause I'm doing some traveling and all this stuff had come up
and it was like this crazy weekday and I got home and I had a little bit of time
in the, in the, in the evening and I had the energy and so I banged out a few of
these things and got the, you know, the Shinobi system reloaded and got the, got
the, got the two additional cameras installed and I had did a really good
job with the wiring and I, I, like I showed you, I Velcroed the components
inside the dinette seat.
So everything looks and is routed really clean and nice.
And the power cables are all clean and it's really proud of myself.
And I had like this sense of accomplishment after having kind of a rough
day where I was kind of like, I got knocked down all day long.
I came home and, and like, I felt really good about what I had done.
And I realized that that's sort of like, my dad used to talk about, he'd come
home and he'd work on like part of the deck and fix that part of the deck in
the evening and feel he'd have a rough day at work, but at least he got that
damn deck fixed, you know?
And that's, that's how this, even like working with home assistant and
automating things has made me feel.
Making stuff, whether it's, uh, home automation or whether it's 3d printing
or building something out of wood, I, I just, I need to do something, uh, I
know home assistant isn't analog technically, but a lot of the stuff
it's controlling is so, for example, I had to, um, replace the, this is a
rental house I'm in right now.
And I replaced the, uh, thermostat controller board thing on the wall
that changes the, the AC and the furnace.
Uh, I replaced that with a nest thermostat that someone was selling
cheap locally on Craigslist.
They found it off the back of a car.
No, I don't think so.
In the boot, I should say.
Uh, in the trunk.
Yeah.
I had to learn all about, you know, HVAC wiring over here.
You know, there's five, like wires that do different things.
And like, you just trace one end to the control board down in the basement.
And then there's five wires at the top, the same color, and you just
figure out which one goes where.
Um, and for me, it was really interesting because the HVAC unit, like the wire that
had been run was a five core wire, but only four wires were in use with the old
one and someone has just stuffed the fifth one back in the wall.
And I, so I didn't know it was there.
So I went to Home Depot and I bought a five core thing and I was prepared
to pull it all through.
And then I went down to the basement to look at the other end of the wire.
And I was like, there's a loose wire here.
Oh, shit.
That's both great.
And also a bit of a pain in your back.
Yeah. So I've now got a five core wire sat here.
I've opened, but I don't know what to do with, um, but I learned a bunch
of stuff that, that weekend, uh, like you say, it's, it's that sense of
accomplishment that self hosting and self building and making and all that
kind of stuff is, is really, you know, not to be underestimated.
Yes.
And I, I just didn't expect that.
Um, I got into this for practical reasons.
I wanted to, to really just sort of declutify the RV and be able to go offline
completely so I could go like kind of on a tech diet over a weekend, somewhere
with no connectivity, because I just didn't really expect that applying a
little bit of craftsmanship to it and taking, making it take a little bit
longer, but doing it right.
We give me that much more sense of satisfaction.
Um, and I'm proud of that system.
And I'm really proud of the system we've built here at the studio as well.
Not quite as good as I thought it was going to be, but it's, it's, it's
quite as much craftsmanship, but it's running really well.
And yeah, we didn't expect like to get that sensation from this.
I just thought it'd be a practical thing.
It's it speaks to the, one of the key points of my, uh, Lennox fest Northwest
talk this year, which is solve a real problem because if you do that, you have
the motivation to see the project through to the end, and then once you've done
one, you're like, well, that actually wasn't as hard as I thought it would be.
What else can I do?
That has helped with Shinobi because to be honest, it's sometimes it's
felt a little rickety.
It feels sort of like it's tossed together.
It's kind of awkward.
It has, it has a bunch of different user levels and a super URL that's only used
for really managing users and restarting services, and it's kind of an odd duck.
And you need to really kind of follow docs and read community
threads to, to put it all together.
I'd ran the wires, I'd set up the cameras.
I invested all of that time and money.
And so I just sort of kept plucking at it until I, you know, had wittled
into a setup that's mostly good.
I'm, I'm now going down the route of experimenting with motion detection,
which is interesting because you take the camera shot that comes in the GPU
processes it, then it sends it off at a lower frame rate to FFmpeg, which then
analyzes it for motion using a series of MPM plugins.
And then if it detects motion above a threshold that you set.
So my case, I have them pretty low.
So if there's 2% motion in the frame, so that's like 2% of the area
changes, it triggers motion.
You can change that to whatever you'd like.
You can also say, if, if it exceeds a certain level of, of motion,
just don't bother, just drop it.
That can be useful with an RTSP feed that has frame drops or like bars
across the video feed that where you can see there's been some signal loss
that you could essentially say, ignore if it's just what, if it's essentially
the whole frame's changing, something's going on, drop that.
But if it's somewhere between 2% and 70%, record that.
So that's what I'm doing right now.
And that uses CPU, but I'm saving disc because I'm only recording
when there's motion.
And I have some cameras that see very little activity during the day.
And, um, getting that just right now is, is like a finessing process
because each camera has different contents with different lighting
and different areas.
And I can go in Shinobi and I can highlight with boxes exactly the spot
so I want motion.
So in some cameras I have just the windows selected and the couch is
completely out of the shot.
So we can sit there on the couch and not trigger recording.
Yeah.
Those zones make a big difference.
And saves a lot of disc.
Yeah.
Unless you get it too sensitive and then it's just recording all the time.
Like I did it first and it just blasted my desk.
I have a, in my Google photos, I have a period from about three years ago where
I started messing about with my own cameras for the first time where every
single time my dog walks past the camera, I've got a snapshot of my lounge.
There's thousands of them.
Okay.
So I just listened on my run this morning to last week's Linux action
news, where you and Joe talked about, uh, proton male and hoard male and
squirrel male and self-hosting all the males.
And to that end, uh, we have a relevant ask SSH.
Ah, great.
It comes from Tom Broughton.
Uh, one of the biggest questions I have is whether I should self host my
own email or use something like the mail in a box I've been trying to
get away from Google who hasn't, um, I write a lot of notes.
I'm not convinced by proton male or others that require you
to have their client installed.
It's quite a long one.
So I'll, uh, abbreviate, um, is self-hosting email robust and secure.
What do you use?
Is it worth the risk or would it be better to just pay or use a service
that gives away your privacy?
This is like, this is one that I debate in our Jupiter broadcasting
telegram group frequently, because I am of like a dozen mindsets on this
because part of me says, no, don't ever do it.
It's way too much hassle.
It's not so much the difficulty in setting up email.
That's that can be relatively easy.
It's that you get so frustrated when you get blacklisted and then your
family in front of you and you're like, okay, I don't want to do this.
I'm frustrated when you get blacklisted and then your family and friends
are affected that are using the service and you have to hunt this thing down.
And it's so insulting.
It's so it's so irritating.
Emails so basic.
It should just effing work.
Yeah.
And what happens, it'll smack you when you least expect it.
You'll be like seven months, a year into it.
You'll be busy.
You'll be traveling.
You'll be on vacation or whatever.
And it breaks eventually it will happen, but that's true of
self-hosting almost anything, you know, home assistant, trust me.
Break when you least want it to, when you're, you know, trying to do a
demo to your mother-in-law of the ramifications though, of not receiving
email can be pretty broad depending on the individual that's a fair point.
Now here's another take on it.
The federated by its basic nature aspect of email is vitally important.
And I think it's critical that hobbyists continue to self-host
email so that way it continues to be even a thing that's possible.
Cause you could see this get locked down so that a certain agreements
get set up by certain commercial carriers.
And then they have like protected email that passes between their
systems and people outside that might have to qualify.
So, I mean, you never know where this could go.
Don't we kind of have that with WhatsApp and telegram and like,
aren't they miniature emails in a way?
Or are they miniature IRCs or are they all just miniature using it?
They're not decentralized at the core of, of email is it's a
decentralized, anybody can do it protocol.
Also, it's a handy to have a quick way to bounce out emails from
systems that do reporting, you know, like my Shinobi system would be nice
to just have a quick little easy way to send out some emails.
There are several ways to do that, but.
So I've never self-hosted my email.
It's something that's crossed my mind on more than one occasion, but I
just, whenever you tap that phrase into Google, should I self-host my email?
The almost unanimous answer is no.
Yeah.
Well, that's because folks like me that set it up for themselves and for
friends and for family and for companies over the years say, don't do it.
Yeah, don't do it Alex.
Cause there's the whole spam blacklisting thing.
If your server gets compromised, some ISPs don't open certain ports.
Although these days that's less of an issue.
Yeah, well, it's difficult to understand how valuable of a target
an email server is until you run one.
You don't even have to be a popular one.
You could have one with a dozen users.
One of those accounts gets compromised and that server
is immediately used for spam.
It's, it's amazing.
It's speed and efficiency at which these lists work just takes one weak point.
It could be in your software stack, could be in a user account.
So one of the listeners actually replied, Matty McGraw, who I think
was our ask SSH last time.
Oh yeah, he replied to the ask SSH, uh, as did you, cause this was a while
ago with a link from our self-hosted, the Reddit self-hosted Reddit.
And, um, the, uh, the title of the article is you should not run your
own mail server because mail is hard.
You know, lots of stuff is hard.
That doesn't mean you shouldn't do it.
I don't actually agree.
Mail's hard either, uh, setting up a basic IMAP server and an SMTP
server, that's not hard.
Think about the price of entry, right?
So th this article claims that he presupposes that you're a sys admin
with tech knowledge, who knows basic networking, basic protocol
knowledge, all that kind of stuff.
I agree.
You, you need to, so just to get to zero in this situation actually
assumes a lot of basic knowledge.
And you probably should be a fairly decent one at that.
So the answer to the question, Tom, is probably not for most people.
I would say it's, in my opinion, at least it's something I've never done.
I don't have any desire to do it. Oh, I kind of do.
Oh, but Gmail is so easy and I know that's a cop-out and they can mind
my data and all that kind of stuff.
But like you said, the ramifications of email not working, like I'm buying
and selling a house right now, if those contracts can't come through.
That's a problem for me.
Yeah.
Taxes.
And it's a problem if I need to get emailed from the school about the kids.
It's a problem.
I mean, there's a lot of ways it's a problem.
I would, if I was going to do it, look into what VPS people have had success
doing it on.
I don't think I would do it on my home connection unless I had a very kind of
special home connection or a business connection.
You raise a good point.
My Gmail goes back to when I was, I was in lower sixth in England.
So I guess I was 16, 17 when Gmail was brand new and invite only.
I think that's 2005.
So I've got emails in there going way, way back and I've quite often
reconstructed portions of my life using my Gmail inbox.
So has Google.
Well, there you go.
Every Amazon purchase, any receipt ever sent to your mailbox.
Think about that.
Saying that I got, I got a, an email or it was a targeted Facebook ad the other
day, actually saying, Alex, are you missing home British airways for Christmas?
Oh, wow.
I thought that was kind of interesting.
That's pretty clever.
Yeah.
I mean, would you have, maybe you were actually, I mean, if you weren't trying
to buy a house, you might be.
Right? Yeah, yeah.
Um, uh, yeah, to be honest with you, like targeted advertising is a bit
of a double-edged sword, right?
I mean, on the one side, I don't want to see any ads ever, but in reality,
that's not the world we live in, is it?
So I'd rather see an advert about something that's relevant to me
than, I don't know, shoe polish.
I don't mind if Amazon wants to review my purchase history with their own
servers and then figure out what I might be into that doesn't really
bother me that much.
It's more like the total surveillance to try to piece me up into many different
markets for many different ad purposes.
That's sort of what bothers me.
Yeah.
I, uh, I don't know.
I feel like we should set ourselves a challenge.
We're going to really regret something like this, but like some, something crazy,
like I don't like where this is going.
If we make it to 100 episodes to celebrate, we launch our own self-hosted
mail server for our, for our email.
We do some, you know, we get our email, we get our email, we get our email,
we do something, you know, we get our own, like, you know, we, we could just use
our self-hosted dot show domain and we could just have like show at, and we'll
throw it on the raspberry PI seven.
I just say, maybe we should, somebody should hold us accountable to that.
Cause we'll surely forget that.
I hope we do forget that one.
Me too.
But anyways, I'd say, I'd say consider all of, all of the things like do the
research about where you'll be sending the mail from if it's had issues, because
if you can just get on a list that an entire block of IPS, like an entire VPS
provider can be blocked and maybe you've been a good citizen, you've never had a
problem, but if anyone else in that IP block has, then you're pretty much
screwed.
So you really need to do some due diligence first.
Yep.
That's where email is hard now.
It's not actually setting up the software.
Totally agree.
So before we go, I just remember the reason I even went, went to that best
buy area of conversation was to bring up the 12 terabyte easy store hard drive
situation.
Oh, it wasn't a talk about beautiful 75 inch televisions.
Wasn't to talk about TVs.
It was to talk about hard drives, uh, $179, I think, um, right now for a 12
terabyte hard drive in the U S um, so yeah, if you're in the market for that
kind of thing, you can shut those drives, do the 3.3 volt mod that we talked about
last week and get yourselves a darn good hard drive for a pretty unbeatable price.
Yeah. Or grab some of those and just set your family up with
backups for the holidays.
Yeah.
USB hard drives with a raspberry PI.
Why not?
Right.
I think it's probably about that time.
Don't you?
Oh, all right.
I really have had a lot of fun setting up these cameras and I can't wait to talk
about some of the other things we've been working on.
I know you've got some stuff coming up.
Oh my gosh.
Could you imagine the shows we're going to get out of you getting a new place?
No, it's going to be good.
I'm looking at running a cat six, a cable so I can do 10 gig ethernet and all this
stuff, you know, it's going to be great.
Oh, I, I think it might have to take multiple trips, just might have to come
down there and maybe the timing once everything is settled would be around
the spring by coincidence.
Gosh.
Well, I mean the things I'll have to do for this show next year.
All I can say is Riley and April is a, well actually that's Linux fest Northwest.
So March rally in March is lovely.
Surprise, surprise.
Surprise.
Thank you for listening everybody.
And you can find me on Twitter at ironic Badger.
I'm at Chris LAS.
The show is at self-hosted show along with the show notes at self-hosted dot show.
And you can find more of Jupiter broadcasting on Twitter at Jupiter signal.
Yes.
Maybe a quick plug for Jupiter extras.
We've done some recent extras with the merger FS developer, as well as some
basics on containers and reverse proxy.
So extras dot show for additional and supplemental content to this year's show.
So thanks for listening everyone.
That was self-hosted dot show slash six.