YouTube is such a time sink. I started watching videos about bonsai trees last night, Chris.
Wait a minute, Alex.
Bonsai trees.
There's videos about bonsai trees? No, sir. No, I will not have it.
Thing is, right, there's, you know, there are many, many hobbies that over
decades, millennia, whatever, have been knowledge passed down from person to person. And I think
these days, YouTube is just an incredible resource that anybody can learn anything about anything.
And you were saying you went down a new rabbit hole yourself.
Yeah. It's funny that you did this because just before we started, I was binging old diesel bus
repair videos. How strange is this? So let me tell you about these guys. They're like middle
American bros that are just, you know, the most down to earth guys that go out into fields and
find old broken down buses, like diesel buses have been parked there from maybe 15 years or
whatever. Like the bus I was watching today was from before World War Two. And they go fix them
all up and get them running down the road to get them to their shop where they can restore them.
I suppose that's a good thing about, quote unquote, simpler, older technologies. There's
there's not going to be masses of electronics and laptops required to fix it. It's all mechanical
stuff, right? Yeah. And kind of to your point, I've used YouTube now as a resource for figuring
out how to fix my RV, for doing a lot of the home automation, little tricks and little things I
needed just to figure something out or even Zelda. I mean, I hate YouTube, but I love YouTube.
You know what I mean? Yeah. It's a chronicle of some of the best and worst bits of humanity,
I suspect. Well, so it sounds like you have been sucked into several rabbit holes this week then.
Yeah. The hard thing for me is like just observing something like that. Like bonsai trees. It's an
example that I don't know why the algorithm decided that Alex wants to learn about bonsai
trees this week, but it did. And I clicked on the video. So I guess it was right, the algorithm. And
uh, yeah, two hours later I knew everything about material and wire selection and clippers.
It's funny how that works. It's funny. Can I tell you about something I did last week after our show?
Yeah, sure. I've decided to take the RV on a project off-grid test drive just to see
if the basics would work. Would my camera mounts hold? Would the sensors stay up? How did things
work when I actually went offline? Because I've been building all of this to be offline while I'm
online. And so I've never really tested it. So I took the RV out on a half day mini road trip last
week and we found a spot by the river that we took our bus down by the river and we did a camping
kind of just set up for lunch for about an hour and a half, totally offline, no cellular signal.
And there was some positive things I discovered in this test and some negative things. I'm,
I'm very happy to say my camera and sensor mounts all held, nothing fell down in the
Richter 4 earthquake that we are going down the road. But there was a problem that I didn't catch
at first. So I'm that guy, I pull back in, I'm like, look at a successful test flight.
We also did some other maintenance things on the RV. So I'm like feeling like,
look at me, I'm taking care of stuff. I'm testing stuff. It all worked my big plan
and until about the next morning when I realized things in the RV weren't working quite right.
And it turns out I have to solve a little problem when I disconnect the RV from shore power
and the lithium battery power kicks in that transition from shore power to inverter power
from the battery causes a real momentary blip in the power. It's not enough to knock the raspberry
pies offline. All the raspberry pies stayed online, but the disks went offline and I didn't
catch it till the next day. So it took me a while to figure out what was going on.
And I don't really know how I'm going to solve this problem because a UPS would be
the obvious solution in a home, but in the RV a UPS is no good. They freak out when you're running
them off of battery via an inverter. They do not like that. Plus it's a horrible inefficient use
of power. You lose it in that conversion, just like 40%. It's really bad. So I got to come up
with some way to keep power steady and smooth to these raspberry pies and their disks, but that's
something that's not a UPS. That's an interesting problem. I'm sat here trying to think of something
and I'm glad that you said UPS is out because that's the obvious thing. Yeah, I've tried that.
I even tried like a small little APC one that's really essentially just a portable battery in a
UPS housing. Still no good. Do you have an Omnicharge or am I making that up? No, I don't.
It's essentially a UPS with a battery bank smushed together and this thing might be
sufficient for you. I know another route is there are raspberry pie hats that have a lithium battery
on them. So you power the pie through the hat and then the hat provides power via the GPIO pins.
All right, I'm going to send you a link to this Omnicharge thing. I think you need to have a look
at this. It's got a small little OLED screen in it. So it tells you all sorts of cool stats.
You got me already. The battery percentage is not just three or four little blinky LEDs. It's
an actual percentage. It tells you the amount of current and wattage being drawn from the battery
in real time. It supports pass through so you can charge and withdraw power from it at the same time.
The USB ports support quick charge. I don't know what version, but they support quick charge
and it comes in several different sizes. So there's like a 20,000 milliamp version.
There are big ones, small ones, all sorts of different things. It has a couple of other cool
things. Now, the one that I have, I got as a Kickstarter about three years ago and mine has
an AC inverter built into it, but the newer ones have USB-C out that support power delivery.
Oh boy, that's it right there, isn't it? Yeah, I think that's going to be your solution.
So this is essentially like the coolest battery bank, portable battery pack I've ever seen.
It's pretty sweet. Have you seen the big mother that they make as well?
If you scroll down into the pro series, there's the Omni Ultimate, which has got like a little
solar panel in it, I think. And that's how many? 38,000 milliamp hours.
I do remember this from when it was a Kickstarter. I am very happy to see they made it because I was
very tempted when it was a Kickstarter. They just kind of came out during that time when I was on
a Kickstarter break. This is legit. This is great. And USB-C, I know the Pi 4 requires a slightly
higher voltage than normal, but boy, that. All right, Alex, thank you. That might be what I do.
I think long term, and I'm just kind of waiting to redo my power system overall, but I think long
term, it's just power these things via DC somehow. Just go direct off the batteries and just get
the inverter out of the picture. Well, Omnicharge has a DC out as well. That's great. Okay. So I've
actually charged my MacBook with a direct DC to MagSafe cable and it works just fine because you
can manipulate the voltage in the firmware using the OLED screen. You can manipulate the output
voltage of the DC port just on the Omnicharge. Stop it. You're kidding me. No, no, no. I think
this is exactly what you need. It's like a UPS that is not a UPS, if that makes sense.
How's your wallet been this week? It's still recovering from the TV.
Yeah, I bet. Yeah, that takes a hit. Are you enjoying the hell out of that thing?
OLED, if you are on the fence about buying an OLED versus an LED TV, I think it's genuinely worth the
money. It's like an extra thousand or whatever, but it's a lot of money, but it's really, really
worth it. We've been watching a lot of 4K high encode video codec or something. HEVC is the
acronym. Oh, HVAC. Yeah, yeah, yeah. What does that stand for again? Well, I think it's just
like a newer version of H.264, essentially. It's like H.265. I could be wrong. Selfhosted.show
slash contact if you want to correct me. So I've been watching a lot of Blu-rays that I've
been storing for a while through my PlayStation 4 and I must say it's really something. If you're
watching some of those David Attenborough shows, there was one particular scene we were watching
where he was doing heat map cameras of tigers in inner city Mumbai and the blacks were just,
it was as if the screen was off. It's genuinely not hyperbole. It's really something. But now
the coolest thing about this TV is that it integrates directly with a home assistant
integration. How has that been? So that's what I really want to know. Yeah. I've been going on a
huge home assistant binge this week, which we'll get to. Well now I guess. Yeah, let's do it now.
Let's do it now because it really kind of all ties into this, doesn't it? Yeah. There was a new
version of home assistant released 0.102, which has a few new interesting integrations in it.
The principle one that I'm looking at is the WLED integration. But before we get to that,
I'm going to touch on the LG webOS integration. Now this allows me from my home assistant interface
to turn the TV on, turn the TV off. Okay. That doesn't sound that amazing, but it lets me select
the input of the TV from home assistant, but it's also contextually aware of what the screen is
playing as well. What? If I'm watching a YouTube video, the title of that video shows up in my home
assistant. See, I can do that only with Plex videos right now. Nothing else. So you... Works
for Plex too. So webOS is reporting back. How does it know? I mean, this TV must be watching.
Well, you've got to create a developer key or some kind of like API key to let the integration work.
But part of the reason that these integrations are so great is that they have knowledge of the
APIs that these different platforms use. So they're able to take advantage of API specific features
to my specific model number of TV. And this must only work when you're using the apps built into
the TV. Well, I can change the input to HDMI and then it doesn't know what's being played. If I
was playing it on the shield, for example. Right. But then it would just tell you in home assistant
that you're on that input. Right. Yes. So what that means is I can set up some quite interesting
automations now. You know, this is getting to the territory where it's getting a little bit Ironman,
you know, a little bit Tony Stark where I can just set up a scene and it will dim the lights,
change the lights to a certain color and brightness, change the input on the TV.
And then the TV using audio return channel will turn on my receiver and set that to the correct
input. And, you know, then it will turn off all the lights in the rest of the house that might
otherwise reflect in my screen. It can set the temperature in the house to a certain level if I
just want to get cozy. You know, it's just a case of thinking about how all these different facets
of your house link together and how you can just create automations that improve your quality of
life. If you would have had this conversation with me eight years ago, I would have thought
you were being a silly, fussy man right now. You know, turn off some lamps, you're good to go.
How much effort does it take to walk around, flip off a few light switches? By the way,
these lamps probably would have had fluorescent bulbs in them back then. And I just would have
said, you know, what's the big deal? But now, having gone deep into this with my own home
assistant setup and my own smart light solutions, it feels like it has made our home feel more like
a home. It feels cozier. I don't know, I was surprised by what a difference it made in the
feel of the place. And I don't think I would have appreciated that as much had I not just
given this a go. And I think sometimes home automation is conflated with remote control
unfairly. Remote control is just the beginning, you know, being able to turn that lamp on and off
is fine. But it's when you start integrating everything in one place that the magic really
starts to happen. Right. If you want just to remote control a light, get yourself a Clapper.
Job done. Right. We're not trying to make Clapper 2.0 here. We're trying to actually make your home
contextually aware. And that's why the integration with the TV is so key, because I assume you must
be able to kick off automations based on the sensor data from the television. So you can have
that stuff happen automatically. When you switch to an input, you could have those lights change
without I mean, it's not even like something you have to invoke, right? That's a good point. Yes,
because you know, Home Assistant has the concept of sensors built into it. So there are entities,
which are things like my light bulbs and the TV. But then each of those things report back to
Home Assistant to say what their current status is. You can then use that sensor information.
Maybe it's a binary sensor that something is either on or off. Or maybe it's a temperature
sensor that something or humidity sensor that's returning a certain value. And then you can have
Home Assistant constantly reacting to those sensor inputs. And very quickly you end up with a complex
house of cards, sure, but it's actually very easy to manipulate. So the other change that I've made
this week is that I've switched from a Docker container on my Ubuntu system to HaasIO.
Okay, so I was wondering what led to this because I have debated this a lot, because there's a lot
of advantages to using HaasIO versus vanilla Home Assistant. And just briefly, I would describe
the Home Assistant version that I have installed as vanilla using the Docker image. And it's just
the project with no plugins, no add-ons. HaasIO is more of a community spin that has some plugins
that are very easy to install, but it's a much broader thing. It's more than just a core project.
And I just, I debate that. I'd say it's a platform. HaasIO is a Home Assistant platform.
And what made you decide to switch from vanilla to the platform?
Well, I was browsing YouTube, Chris.
I knew it! And, you know, there's that Dr. Z's guy
that releases a million YouTube videos a week. I don't know where he finds the time.
I think it's all he does.
And he's just browsing around, going into the HaasIO store and installing,
you know, add-ons left, right and center. And I'm like, why am I not doing that myself? It just,
that just looks like too much fun. So which plugin though, there must have been
a plugin or two that said, okay, this is worth the hassle because I've reviewed those plugins
and I've thought to myself, eh, not quite worth it.
There's a few. So the main one for me was the VS Code plugin.
You can direct from the Home Assistant interface, click a button that lets you load up
Visual Studio Code in the same browser window that has syntax auto-completion and highlighting
directly supporting Home Assistant. So if you start writing an entity
in the configuration file, it'll tell you that you've missed the required field or something like that.
That's so slick. So it's a Visual Studio Code editor for Home Assistant.
Pretty much. Yeah. It's just a normal VS Code instance under the hood using the,
there's a container that you can run VS Code in. And I think they're just using that under the hood
because if you log into the appliance that's running Home Assistant now under the hood,
and you do a Docker PS, it's just running a dozen containers under the hood.
So Home Assistant on HASSIO is still running in a container. You're just abstracted away from it.
So this is why I thought to myself, I said, you know, Chris, if you ever really had to have one
of these plugins, you could just go get that container. Couldn't I just run that container?
Of course you could, but you have to go and, I mean, it's a very small barrier to entry,
but you have to add that to your compose file. You've got to configure then all the plugins in
VS Code to be compatible with Home Assistant, set up the remote access, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And I don't get to just browse a repo and just hit install either.
Yeah. Now the other thing that is often overlooked with UI based stuff is discoverability. So in the
HASSIO add-on store, there are only nine or 10 plugins. Tasmo Admin is a really cool one I've
also been using to update all of my Tasmotor devices. ESPHome is another cool one. It allows
you to configure single board like NodeMCU, ESP8266 type ESP devices with only a few lines of
YAML. That thing is super duper cool. There's Node-RED in there as well and AdGuard Home built
right into Home Assistant. But the main one that I saw Dr. Z's using is something called Hax. Now
this is Home Assistant Community Store, and this is nothing to do with like a HASSIO necessarily.
All this on any Home Assistant instance, but Home Assistant Community Store is what it sounds like.
You give it a GitHub personal access token, and then it will go and crawl GitHub for every GitHub
repo with a certain label or a certain tag. I don't know exactly how it works, but it's amazing.
Yeah. So that's at Hax.xyz, H-A-C-S.xyz. I will throw a link in our show notes.
This is really cool looking. Oh man, I kind of want to get this set up.
There are hundreds of things in GitHub that you would never have found otherwise,
and this thing will crawl the APIs and find them for you.
So it sounds like you've been using the hell out of this thing to manage a bunch of the stuff.
I mean, a lot of that is right up your alley.
Yeah.
What was the migration like from Home Assistant Vanilla to HASSIO?
I'm rebuilding from the ground up.
Oh my God. Well, I mean, in January, which is when I started with Home Assistant,
I didn't know what on earth I was doing. Some would argue I still don't, but I'm
a little more familiar with the situation now than I was then. We mentioned a little earlier that
one of the new integrations I was most excited about was something called WLED.
WLED. Now, why is that exciting, Alex? Well, in my Linux Fest Northwest talk,
I built a smart set of LEDs that were using MQTT. In fact, we talked about it last episode.
MQTT is wonderful for contextually aware stuff. So the LED controller knows what Home Assistant's
up to and vice versa. But WLED's better because it's a native Home Assistant API integration,
as opposed to MQTT, which sort of sits on top as another layer.
That alone means that the performance is better. But couple it with the fact that
the WLED developer provides a precompiled binary that you can just flash with ESP tool
in about 10 minutes end to end. And it's just wonderful.
Okay. That does sound really nice. Super quick. So you get a new device, not a big deal.
Yeah. So there have been two traditional ways to do it. One is the custom Arduino code,
which is what I did, which I used the bruh automation stuff. And the other was ESP Home,
which is why I installed it and started looking at it this week. And with ESP Home, you gain
simplicity of configuration, but you lose configurability for things like effects and
that kind of thing. But with WLED, if you really want to go in and change the data pin or something
like that, let's say you've got a NodeMCU that's got four or five sensors on it, as well as
controlling your LEDs. You can go in and compile a custom firmware just the same as you could with
the custom Arduino code that I was using before. Or you can just flash the precompiled binary.
It is amazing.
That is really handy. There's all kinds of great ideas on the site too, esphome.io.
Now I read a blog post about WLED this week, which we'll put a link to in the show notes.
And essentially for $16, you can build yourself a smart LED strip that is fully
compatible with Home Assistant that you own completely.
Really nice. Those things, I mean, $15? You can get some really crappy LED strips for around that
price on Amazon, but not ones that are fully automated. So this thing, I guess it joins your
Wi-Fi and then it starts communicating. Give a fair description on the quality of those LEDs
though, because that's a big thing with LED lights is the quality of light that they give off.
Some of them are less good than others, but that depends
entirely on the LED strip themselves that you buy.
I mean, are you including that in the cost when you say $15?
Well, yeah, a 300 long LED strip with 300 pixels. So that's one microcontroller per LED
is $28 on Amazon.
Okay. Oh, that's all right.
So the reason I said $16 was because I generally only put $20 or $30 off a single microcontroller
because I want small mood lighting. I don't necessarily want a whole long strip.
If you're going to do a long strip, I would go with a 12 volt LED strip.
These ones in particular are five volt. And why that's particularly nice is you don't need any
buck converters or anything like that. You can just plug it straight into USB and you're good to go.
Okay. Here's a little comparison. The TP-Link KASA smart LED strip lights is what they call them,
which are 6.6 feet long, $70.
Wow.
Yeah. And that's using obviously with their cloud service too.
It's probably KASA generally stuff works pretty well with Home Assistant, but just to kind of
give you a comparison. So if you wanted to do a lot of LED lighting, that really adds up.
And that's kind of the great thing is like, if you can do it at that price, you could do a lot of it.
Yes. Yep. You absolutely can. Now I'm not quite finished talking about how awesome WLED is yet.
So you flash the firmware and then what makes this way better than anything that I've used before
is that it turns your NodeMCU or your D1 mini into a mini wireless access point.
And you then connect to that with your phone, navigate to an IP address in your browser,
and then you can configure everything about the LED strip straight from your phone.
You don't need Home Assistant necessarily because they also make an official WLED app for Android
and iOS. So I was looking through the firmware and there's a bunch of super cool stuff in here.
And bear in mind, this is running off a $6 microcontroller.
Okay.
It will integrate natively with Philips Hue, with Blink, with MQTT, with Alalax.
That's how you do it.
I try not to set it off for people, but I probably do.
Your Echo devices.
And then you can go in and configure the specific number of LEDs that you have.
It does current current estimating. So it will say like you're using 150 milliamps right now.
You got to really watch it with those LED lights, Alex.
Well, some of them actually you do.
So there are some microcontrollers that can draw up to 30 watts on the whole strip just on idle.
So you do have to pick them with care.
These ones I picked so that they're fine.
But there's a video from a guy called The Hookup on YouTube
and he goes through all the different types of LEDs, which we'll put a link to in the show notes.
He goes through all different types of LEDs and their phantom current draw and all the rest of it.
So, you know, there are some things you got to be aware of,
but I just can't overstate how excited I am by WLED and Home Assistant this week.
Like, I haven't been this excited about a project,
and I'm talking about Home Assistant here, since I discovered Docker for the first time.
What specifically do you think this week brought that up again?
Because I've been feeling that way a lot.
I think for me, it's just that I think to myself,
I wish I could integrate with this or I wish I could control that.
I go and look for it and it's there.
It's already there.
Someone's already done it.
And there are products I've been looking about maybe buying,
like some Kef speakers maybe that have like the Kef LS50 wireless speakers.
There's a native integration already there in Home Assistant
for these speakers I don't even own yet.
And it's like, it just feels to me like I was watching the State of the Union
Home Assistant YouTube video.
I spend a lot of time watching YouTube.
Are you getting that?
I'm noticing that.
It's a theme.
And just looking at the excitement of these people who are actively working on the project.
It's in the top 10 in the Octoverse for contributors of all GitHub projects.
It's up there with Ansible and Kubernetes, for crying out loud.
It just feels to me like everybody is waking up to the fact that
having a open home automation system is just awesome.
And I love that.
And I think it's also compounded by all these different manufacturers
have their own apps and their own cloud services that are all their own silos.
And it's nice to have something that can aggregate and bring them all together.
On top of that, it's sort of like the deal is changing constantly on these devices.
You and I were just recently discussing that Wise had to announce
they're removing person detection from their cameras.
So I bought this last round because I was really impressed that Wise managed to develop
on camera person detection on a $25 camera.
I was like, all right, I'm in.
Well, I got an email says they have to pull that because the company they partnered with
to develop that AI on the edge devices has exercised a clause in their contract.
And Wise has to ship out firmwares now that removes that feature.
What's that going to mean for you and I who are running the custom RTSP firmware?
Well, this is back to my main point is I feel like I'm insulated from these types of changes.
When a company decides they can no longer support feature A or product Y,
I'm not impacted by that because the way I have my system set up
is I've flashed it with that RTSP firmware.
I'm leaving that firmware, Alex.
I'm not changing it.
I've configured my network to record everything to the Pi locally.
I don't use the cloud service and I actually have everything blocked at the DNS level.
So they can't even communicate with the Wise service.
Oh, good man.
Yeah, I'm leaving it and then I'll let them sort it out.
They say they will try to add person detection back in 2020,
but it's going to be cloud based likely and not on the camera.
And I much prefer on camera because then it's in my actual recordings too.
Maybe I'm missing something here.
Why do they need an API for motion detection if it's on camera?
It won't be with the new system is what the implication is.
No, but right now.
So how can they pull a feature that's local?
That's what I don't understand.
Their new firmware will remove the functionality.
So they licensed the tech to do the person detection
because to get it working on these incredibly low powered cameras,
it was like a feat of engineering.
It was something that Wise was extremely proud of.
And it's kind of like the tech that can do it.
And there's really nobody else has developed person detection,
human object detection that can run on processors that slow.
So do we think that we'll be able to still buy those Wisecams
for the next year or two and flash that?
That's a great point.
I bet you if you bought them within a certain timeframe,
they would probably ship with the person detection firmware.
Yeah, but even if they don't,
maybe we can install the current RTSP firmware that you and I have.
Yeah, I did.
I did save it offline just in case it ever disappeared.
Yeah, good idea.
So it's possible.
I wonder if you go too far ahead, though,
in the firmware is if you can't go back.
Yeah, you know, say it's down the road is firmware 1.8
and the RTSP is like version 0.9.
Maybe that could be a challenge.
So it may be worth if you've been on the fence
just pulling the trigger now, not to change the topic,
but just for a second, it's crossed my mind.
It's funny how these things we do like I'll get a new TV
or for me it was I want to solve heating problems.
It just spiral into a bigger and bigger project.
And if you're willing to do it, it can be some of the most fun.
So I'm totally on board.
Just a big shout out to Homocyst.
We've talked a lot about it recently,
but it's just because we are so elated about it.
What do you say we do and ask SSH to round us out?
Let's do it.
All right, Kai wrote in, he says,
peeps, Kai calls us peeps, Alex.
Hey peeps, if I wanted to set up a simple
Kodi-based media center Raspberry Pi
with an external SSD drive connected to a TV via HDMI
or HDMI as you would say.
Jerry's triggered right now.
Would a Raspberry Pi 3B with one gigabytes of RAM,
one gigabytes, be powerful enough to do that?
He says, because I have a spare one,
or is it time to get a new Raspberry Pi 4?
I think it's on the edge actually, to be honest with you.
On the edge for what?
Because direct play, the Pi 3 will do most anything,
even 4K H.265, right?
Yeah, Pi 3 with video drivers would.
It's generally the bit rates that start to be an issue.
However, if you're looking at standard 720p content
or if you're 1080p and it's stuff that's below 15 megabits,
I think the Raspberry Pi 3 with Kodi would kill it.
It'd be great.
It would eat through that stuff no problem,
especially if you're feeding it via an SSD on USB 3.
And you know the thing, Kai, that I would say here
is you already have one,
so it would take you about 10 minutes
to find out if it's suitable.
If you're like Alex over here and you're rocking 4K
and you want high bit rate,
you want really good looking picture,
I would be tempted then at that point
to throw in for a Pi 4
because looking at your overall setup,
the Raspberry Pi 4 is gonna be
the least expensive aspect of it.
Still even cheaper than the SSD.
But like Alex says, give it a go with the 3.
If you're not looking at ultra high quality,
high bit rate stuff or even serving to multiple people,
if you don't plan to install Jellyfin or Plex,
Pi 3 is gonna kill it.
If you wanted to go up a notch
and you wanted to do something like Jellyfin and Kodi,
which is a nice little kumbaya,
and you wanted to do it to a couple of TVs
in your house,
that's when I'd probably go over to a Pi 4.
What's crazy, you can do it with either one though.
I mean, that's where we're at today.
Yeah, it is crazy.
But one important hardware difference of course
is that the Pi 4 uses the mini or micro HDMI cables.
So you'll need a dongle for that versus the Pi 3.
Yeah, yeah, you're right.
Geez, of course the other advantage would be,
so that's the dongle's a downside.
The advantage is you get better throughput to that disc
on that USB 3.0 bus.
Yeah, because the, well, there's two things at play here.
They finally separated out on the Pi 4,
the ethernet and the USB at last are on different buses.
At last, at last, freed at last,
and it makes a big difference.
And then the other difference is the Pi 4 has USB-C.
So you might need different cable or a better power supply.
And then the only other thing I would sort of,
it's not a word of caution, it's just something to be aware of
is the Pi 4 gets kind of toasty.
And I'm gonna add onto that,
even though I'm running three of them
and I absolutely love them, it's early days still.
Mm-hmm.
One of the Libre Elec project,
which is a really slick way to do a media center
on a Raspberry Pi, is just within the last couple of weeks
rolling out early support for the Raspberry Pi 4.
And that's something to consider
because the Raspberry Pi 3 is solid at this point.
I've been looking around and trying to find a good answer
as to whether it supports the newer HDMI 2.x standards,
but it looks like both are only 1.4.
If I'm wrong with that, please write in
with selfhosted.show slash contact and let me know.
Yeah, or do like I did, hashtag ask SSH on Twitter
or in Telegram.
We're always lurking and collecting information
or always lurking and collecting those.
I've done a neat thing on Twitter
where I've taken the hashtag ask SSH
and I've plugged that into Feedly
and Feedly supports just treating it like an RSS feed.
So when somebody posts it, it shows up in my feeds.
Oh, that's cool, I should do that.
I've got an if this, then that integration, but-
We are such nerds.
I might do a Feedly, that sounds good.
All right, well, Alex, I am super excited
to hear about your future adventures.
I've been really tempted to try out Hass.io
and you may push me over, we'll see.
And that's been selfhosted.show slash eight.