How you feeling about recording this week you think you're gonna be able to get that thing to record well
I have my own account now, so I feel like I have
Jumped a few hurdles. Oh
Really mm-hmm Alex may be an account on his laptop here
So now I don't need his fingerprint. You know I've had that finger laying around, but it's kind of getting a little yeah
I've had her on ice, but the ice is last forever. You know you had to make a call on that finger
I get it. Yeah, I think you could have brought it with you. I
Think you probably could you know he's got so many laptops over there
You probably could have taken that laptop in that finger, and he wouldn't even noticed
I'm not sure which one he's got more of fingers or laptops. I think there are one two three
four
Laptops on well that's sort of a mini desktop, but just on this one table surface right now
Yeah, well it makes for good video for the live stream, so that's good. There's also that one over there with some rather
Graphics stuff on it that is
An homage PC is it really oh, it's this is a big deal. That's an homage to a great television show called
Silicon Valley and
one of the characters in that show
He has a signature line of servers for the data center, and he wants his signature on the servers
But he's such an egomaniac that that just happens to be what his signature looks like
It ends up looking like a penis and so
And it's a great storyline because like the the product team like tries to like show him all these other options that are
Clearly better options, but his own ego won't let him choose anything else and so they end up shipping a penis logo on
All of them you know I've wanted to ask Alex from like about day three that I've been here several weeks ago
But I was a little too shy to ask him about the penis
Can I ask what you just assumed the reason there was a penis on his PC?
I assumed there was some backstory that I wasn't privy to but I just couldn't bring myself to asking the question for him to explain
The joke so thank you for informing me. Can I ask you to the thought cross your mind, huh?
Alex likes penises more than I thought he did
Did that did that cross your mind? That's also a worm penis because it's on a power source. Yeah, yeah
I
Think the first time I saw it. I was like no. I didn't just see that
That's not meant to be like that and then I saw it again. I was like oh, there's something going on here. Oh really yeah
Yeah, so the first pass you thought oh, no, that's just me seeing something. Yeah, yeah, so you thought you were the weirdo
I see I see I'm in a foreign place sure yeah, and you want to be charitable to your buddy right try so
It's like I'm not ashamed of you Alex. I'm ashamed of me for thinking it's a penis
Yeah, yeah, it's my fault not your fault. That's me. It's not
Well I I tried to have a meal before the show so I don't run out of energy and
How'd you do? I don't know I think I did all right. You know I had some salmon
I feels like a good choice was it like smoked or was it poached or how was it poached?
I'd answer. I don't actually know cuz it was prepared for me. I'll be honest
The life made it last night, and I brought it I brought it to work with me it could have been broiled who knows yeah
I just don't know I brought it to work with me
I just thought you know it'd be nice to have something to eat before we start cuz you know how I get
You know how I get I know how you get too
Oh, I get the both of us useless
I think is I just yeah wander around aimlessly without the right amount of food. I was watching this
doctor talk about ADHD and he was saying how he recommends that people with ADHD when they're working on something keep like a
glass of juice with them
To help their burnt their brain burn better. I guess I don't know I didn't have a glass of juice when I was watching
It so I couldn't really follow what he was saying
It's office hours with Chris
Hey everyone welcome on into the office. Thanks for being here. Hey Brent get comfortable come on in hello
Thank you. You kept my chair nice and warm. I did I kept a little heater on there for you
That's kind of you. You know I also made a little room over there for the mumble room. Hey virtual lug. How's it going?
Hello, hi guys yeah, they're welcome on into the office gosh darn it gosh darn it welcome on in Brent
You're still in North Carolina. I am it seems. I just won't leave now
I'm wondering at this point in time. You're just days away from going tomorrow in fact tomorrow. Okay. I know you I know how things go
I'm wondering
Do you have more projects at this point that are on the list than when you arrived?
And are there more projects undone than done?
Is this a problem so we did have a list uh-huh prior to my arriving which was quite ambitious and
I think maybe Alex should have a look at it because I haven't looked at it in like two weeks
But the number of things we've added I think amounts to the size of the original list as well, so I think you're probably right
I think we have done some amazing things
Alex unfortunately always also is great at starting projects, and then he kind of quickly gets distracted by starting other projects
So we've both been kind of like that and trying to finish projects in the last few days now
Okay, so let me ask you this when you're working on a project normally
All right, would you say this is a problem you have in isolation on your own?
Or would you say this is more of like when you're working with idea guys?
Yeah, you know cuz I've run to this you and I have this too like we could come up with a million projects while you're
Here so is this something that you also do you have this project creep on your own? I didn't expect these
Introspective questions here, but I mean I'm enjoying it. I think I think probably when I'm with you and when I'm with Alex I
take the wonderfully
Natural place for myself, which is like a support role
I was a photographer's assistant for a very long time and so that kind of there's a switch there that just kind of kicks in
so
That doesn't answer your question. I'm just buying myself some time
So I think unfortunately yeah, I probably do lean that way when I'm doing my own stuff at home
So won't want I always just wonder what the solution is to that because I can that can happen to me, too
I think it's a human trait
I mean, it's exciting to start something new
Especially if you're learning some new techniques or trying out some new tool that you have or something like that
But you don't really reap the rewards unless you finish the project. So I don't know a reason why I'm thinking about this is
we're redoing a bunch of back-end stuff to do the JB website and
I
Just kind of recently thought
We probably got to break this up into chunks because it's quickly spinning off into like a new way for us to produce
The back-end source of truth for the shows. It's quickly spinning off into like this, you know new CDN project and
you know, we have a deadline scale engine has been a
fantastic host for like a
decade at least and
They are just kind of not really in the WordPress hosting business anymore
And so they've given us a deadline of summer to get off of scale engine for WordPress
Oh, so they told us a while ago, so we've known it's coming
And so like we have to execute on that
But I don't want to blow it up right and so I've been recently thinking like how do I prevent this project?
Scope creep that I think we're all a little a little kind of inclined towards in our crew
It's so true. That's just been the back of my mind. I feel like we have to do it in a modular way
I'm not sure how to do that because it's all connected. But also we have to keep each other accountable somehow
Yeah, maybe it is like it's not like Trello right Trello like it might be useful for organizing
But that's not what's like gonna make us get the work done
Because as you said there you had a list, but you haven't even looked at it in two weeks. It's true
And every day I'm like, okay, I'm gonna do this today and Alex is like, hey, I was thinking we could do this
Oh, all right. Let's do that. So anyways, it's been a wild ride, which I think maybe that's just it
We're just attracted to adventure. Well, I'm glad you could join me one more time from from North Carolina
I imagine and I understand how it is. You're gonna get back home
You know, you got you'll get you'll get sucked into real life back home again, and we won't see you again for a while
So this has been fun, you know, it's been fun having you in the States and on a high-speed
internet connection while we do the show and
All of that speaking the same language, you know those kinds of things
You know, it's true, all right
All right. Well, I had a little bit of podcasting news
I just wanted to update everybody on how things are going in the industry because this one made me kind of smile
after coming out talking like they were going to
change the podcasting landscape
One of the big tech players has decided
Not for us. We're dropping out of podcasting
It's not what I've complained about because I've honestly never felt like they are much of a threat
But Facebook has announced they are removing all podcasting features from the platform on June 3rd
And they're gonna stop allowing people to add their podcast to the platform
Starting this week as we record the episode. I have to admit I didn't even really realize they had those features
Oops, isn't this kind of actually a sign that this was a good move that right there? Yeah
that's a good time to abandon something when
It's not quite working. I wonder if we aren't gonna go through a bit of a podcast bubble correction
In fact, if I were to speculate I would argue we are already in the midst of it
I think we have been all of this year a bit of a podcasting bubble correction and
the IAB just came out with these ridiculous figures for
Podcast revenue sponsorships, which are just totally unsustainable
So I think we're kind of at the end of a bubble a little bit in sort of the
Industrial side of podcasting where every business needed a strategy. I don't know if we'll see much more
Retractions Facebook just didn't have a lot of establishment here
YouTube is continuing to pay podcasters to move their podcasts over to the YouTube platform
I don't know what they're using to like who they pick
It's all kind of just hush-hush behind the scenes and they have to sign NDAs and stuff
So there's like no real no real dirt out there
Telling us what's going on
but it is I
Guess kind of a bit of a win
It feels like to have Facebook kind of bow out
Doesn't that just sort of feel like one less thing to worry about one giant down, right?
One less pain in my neck, but it was so funny because they can't it was when like right at the at the peak
Hype of Clubhouse. I don't know if you remember this but for a hot minute everybody was talking about Clubhouse. Yes, I do
That's when Facebook announced this whole idea like oh, well, we're gonna become the kings audio audio is a medium
That's grown like crazy and that's when they made all these big plans
You know
You mentioned the bubble kind of maybe starting to come to an end or at least change a little bit and I was I was gonna
Say something that was opposite to you this morning
I ran into I got some gas that I put into Alex's truck and at the gas pump
There was a podcast advertisement on the gas pump and I thought
These are everywhere now. This is just getting ridiculous. Oh, yeah. Okay, I should be clear
I don't mean that podcasts are gonna stop growing and then more and more people aren't gonna do podcasts. I mean, I think
We sort of reached peak
Industrial interest in podcasts like big platform players that want to create the next platform
I think we've got our entrenched players now and
They're gonna try to make money. We'll see a few more consolidations
I I don't think podcasts themselves though. We're gonna stop
this is sort of the magic thing about podcasting and why we're so damn lucky to be doing this form of media is
it just always organically grows because I
think as people we are drawn to just the
Orital medium where we where we tell stories and we help each other process what's going on right now
Through story like it's it's cliche kind of but like it's a virtual campfire thing
where people put the headphones on or they're listening in the car and
It's a more traditional experience. It's being delivered in a new way
but it's it's something that I think is almost built into us and how we share information and how we
figure things out and so I think because it's so accessible and
Because it it seems to touch on something that I think goes deep
I think it's gonna grow forever and I hope I hope I hope I hope now that we're like 15 years into this thing
that certain aspects like RSS feeds and
Just the kind of built-in decentralized nature of the podcast industry. I hope protect it
More than most industries would be protected from consolidation. My only caveat there is
That's exactly what they said about radio back when farmers were using it to broadcast on their fence lines and talk to each other
and give each other crop updates like
Everyone had a radio station. All of the radios frequencies were like stepping on each other
Anybody could do it. It was just a matter of how much how much power could you put out?
And then that you know, obviously that consolidated it got regulated and and it became you know
Something that no one really has access to I don't know if we'll go that far because we're 15 years into it
But like I said, it has happened before
We'll see but it still feels good. Even if it's a small win. We'll take him still feels good. I'll take it
Yeah, I have been
actually sticking
With fountain FM as my podcast app and I I definitely know this has been a struggle for some of our listeners
I've heard from people who tried it so that way they could do the boost things for a bit
But then they didn't really like cast a manic or fountain FM or one of the other new podcast apps
And I also had a little bit of trouble at first. I think for me a couple of the more recent updates
It made a nice improvement
There's a couple of things in here now that I really find useful
The clipping community has kind of become my favorite way to find new podcasts
Have you seen this you've tried this?
Well, you've sent a lot of clips and I've sent clips to you
But also I love in fountain how you open it up and there's you know
The the home page is kind of by default just clips. There have been a few shows that I listened to that I haven't
Maybe hit play on in the last few weeks and then someone throws a clip there and it's like oh, yeah
And you just it's like a you know, the clips can be a various length
So it could be 10 seconds could be 30 seconds could be a few minutes
And I found that to be a really great way to jump into a podcast
I haven't you know heard in a little bit but also like you say to discover new ones, so
it feels like a
cheating almost so at first I
Did not like the clips because I just wanted to get into my podcast
I had a you know, I'm getting on the road. I got a drive. I want to listen to my shows
but
What changed the game for me is when I started realizing I was listening to podcast clips instead of going to YouTube on my phone
Right. Do you understand like how much healthier that is?
Oh, yeah, right. It's so much healthier. Plus I'm discovering new podcasts that have been
Such good listens. So it really changed the way I think about the clip
So now I went like if I got a couple of minutes to kill and I just want to kind of like take a dip
Into some content
I'm firing up fountain and I'm listening to the clips and it has become a network effect because people because as I've shared clips
People have followed me and then I'm following them back
And so now I've got like a little network in there of people that are sharing clips
You wouldn't have to do it use it for that. But man, have I found that stupid handy, you know at first
I didn't want to start over clean
but then having a blank slate and kind of subscribing to like a core few shows that I listened to and
Then adding some new shows based on the clips has kind of like really brightened up my podcast subscriptions again
I'm really enjoying that and plus I have my old app
I can always flip over there and see if I'm missing something so it's not that bad
I found the clip creation process was really neat as well. And I think you have enjoyed it, too
It does like transcripts and you can really get down to it. It's really nice
Yeah, and so you edit it like you would edit text instead of editing in the audio waveform
So you just if you don't want a sentence in there or you want to start at the right point
You just select the text and cut it or whatever and then it creates the audio file
But then it also creates a web link so people don't have to have the fountain app and it'll create an audio file
And it'll export a video that uses the album art and does captions of the transcription is so well done
It's great for sharing like on telegram or matrix or Twitter or whatever. I found it. It has cut way back on my youtube time and
I really like that about it and they've made some solid improvements. The performance has gotten better. The battery life has gotten better
They don't have carplay yet, but they are working on Android auto and carplay
And I do effing love the boost man. I love sending the boosts because as a podcaster
You know, I pay more attention to like a username when I see it on a boost because it sticks out, right?
It's on my screen. I memorize it
And so I hear other people with the same username sometimes boosting the shows and then I'm boosting though. It's it's fun
It is a lot of fun. I still remember sir. Lurks a lot was one of the previous ones. I think last week
Yeah, I gotta remember these is great lurks lots in the mumble right now and I recognized when he John he joined
Oh, I'm like, oh, yeah looks like boosted. That's great. It's great. Yeah, it is pretty good. The other thing is I feel like
Calling them boosts has been pretty astute
You've been mentioning how it's been really boosting your mood recently and some other podcasters mentioned the same thing, right?
Yeah, that is it is a boost. I like it's better than the name of super chat or something like that
Tony wrote in he said so you've convinced me on the future of podcasting 2.0
Value for value and even boosts, but the problem is it assumes that you already have some skin in the crypto game
I've never owned any crypto and I'm looking for a way in it seems that there's plenty of ways to go wrong and likely get
scammed
Good instincts Tony. He says can you recommend a safe starting point for a noob? I'm UK by the way, which is good to know
This is the biggest in my opinion hurdle to the whole boost platform
the
monetary mechanism is
Satoshi's which are a unit of Bitcoin
There's a hundred million Satoshi's in a Bitcoin and so you can send like 500 sats and it's like less than a dollar
To get those you have to buy some sats and you could buy
Tiny amounts of sats at a time you could buy a couple dollars worth of sats at a time
But getting it is tricky in the US. I've been recommending strike
Strike is just a really solid quick app
it is
Regulated it you will have to go through some of the identification processes all of these that are legal and regulated
Have to identify you because it's the rules and regulations of the banking system to prevent many money laundering and you know
Terrorism and stuff like that and all the other things you could probably assume
So you have to go through some form of identification if you use one of these apps, that's the downside
They are used by millions of people though
They are using traditional industry rails to do that kind of regulatory approval and identification
But it is a pain in the butt in the UK. I've been recommending blue wallet, which makes this also really straightforward
What you want is something that participates on the lightning network lightning is kind of like SMTP in the sense that it is an open
protocol it's an open network and you just have to have you know a system on that network and
The benefit to it is that it's peer-to-peer and it's extremely
Stupid cheap to send a monetary amount over that network way cheaper than is possible with something like stripe
Or PayPal or visa or MasterCard way way cheaper, right?
Where you could send fractions of a penny over the lightning network and it's economically feasible to send less than a penny
You can't even send a couple of dollars over the traditional banking network
Without the fee being more than the amount you're sending
So that's why our lightning and boost kind of play a role there
But I I think it's also and I know you already know this Tony
But I think it's also important to point out that there's a network effect of more and more podcasts being on there
Voltage just did a case study of the lightning network and podcasting 2.0
If you can actually believe it or not, and I'll have a link to this in the show notes
There's over a million sats streamed per day. That's not even the boost. That's just people streaming as they listen. Yeah
There is but this is actually even an old number. They say 6.4, but now there's over 7,000 podcasts
Using value for value and lightning when we started talking about this. There was 4,000. That's how fast this is growing
This is a big deal, right? It's not huge in the Linux community
That's where it's not very big but outside of this it is picking up. It's picking up with music artists as well and authors
So voltage did a case study on it and it's absolutely great
It's really bang up. So a link to that. It's starting to grow but podcasting 2.0 itself is
Really more than just the boosts
Podcast and I talked about this in Koda radio recently podcasting 2.0 itself is a set of new standards. It's a spec
It's a whole bunch of new features for podcasting that are really really powerful and you can go look it up the podcasting 2.0 namespace
There's so many great things in there
They solve problems that JB's tried to come up with solutions for for years, but they do it in a standardized open-source way
That an entire community is contributing to and it adds features that not only would make podcasting more accessible to people with accessibility needs
They not only make podcasting easier to find through Google search and stuff like that
But it just adds features that would make the content better as well or make it more accessible
Like we have a question in here about will we ever release office hours as an opus file?
And JB used to release things as an AUG Vorbis an AUG Theora a WebM an MP4
Couple two mp4 types and an mp3
So we had five to six different file versions for every episode and we had to create five or six different RSS feeds
And as a result, if you go searching on places on the web, you can find all these old HD feeds low quality fees
You've probably seen this if you've ever gone around for a little while. Oh, yeah, and it sucks, right? Well, guess what?
One of the things in podcasting 2.0 namespace is a file type enclosure namespace
so you can have multiple file types in one feed entry and the
the software on your phone
Could expose that option so you could choose as a listener
You could choose the opus version of a show or the mp3 version or it would probably default to the mp3 unless you chose
Something different and that could be exposed all via one feed entry
just small little things because
The the reality is is that the podcasting RSS spec hasn't been updated since 2009
It's been a little bit and things have changed
That was well before mobile podcast players had the presence they have now
And it's just it's a whole set of features that I'm as you can tell
super bullish on I just really just I really want to advocate for it because
I think it behooves the podcasters out there to get into this. I think it's it's to the benefit of the medium long term
And sometimes when you work in a medium or when you work in an industry
You have to do things to keep it healthy to keep it going
You can't just sit on your you know existing success and not ever push it forward
That's what I'm a big believer in so that's why I talk about it so much
And I have a link in the show notes to a really good medium post that completely introduces
The entire thing from top to bottom talks about how the podcast index fits into this
How the namespace fits into this it talks about what pod ping is which is one of the really cool features about this
So one of the neat things is
as a publisher
When you publish an episode
You can announce it to the pod ping service and that pod ping service
acts as a store of information that the podcast index in but also all of the podcasting 2.0 apps
participate in so everybody gets a
sensible
Controllable json announcement a basically little json file update that says here's some new feed information new shows out
so instead of
every podcast player and every service having to like
pound an
Http rss file, you know, just an xml file sitting on on an htp share
Instead of having to hit that all the time and and pull it down and see if there's any updates
The pod ping network tells things when stuff when things are updated and it's completely decentralized
It doesn't require the podcast index. Although the podcast index is a front end to it. It doesn't require your specific
Apps implementation. It's a completely open spec and that's part of podcasting 2.0 as well
Without that
You have to rely on services like spotify and apple
To do those kinds of updates for you
And it talks about all that and of course it gets into value value for value
Which is a system?
For podcasters to receive direct payments from listeners for an exchange of value
Either it could be monetary. It could be time. It could be talent. It's you got something out of the show
So you give something back which I think is really in line with the open source esos
And I think ethos and I think something open source developers could embrace too. So I feel like there is
a really solid opportunity to perhaps begin a culture shift in the free software and open source software community to start
Recognizing that the software that they use has real value like mumble. For example
I would absolutely I would absolutely support the mumble developer if I could check a box to stream some sats
You know and when you really start thinking about this like when you really give this actual
Consideration and don't just dismiss what i'm saying when you really think about it
You could you could actually do away with a lot of these foundations
Because at the end of the day these foundations all of these free software projects end up ceding control and copyright to these foundations
Because running a business is a pain in the ass
Asking for money sucks. It's hard
And honestly, they just want to dev
They just want to dev bro. They don't want to be a dev
They just want to dev bro. They don't want to do the business and ask for money and stuff like that
And so they get sucked into these foundations and then these foundations end up centralizing the free software community
And if we solve the monetary problem if we made it possible
using
By the way, all free software an entire free software stack
Where I could check a box in mumble
And it would stream sats from a from a lightning waltz that I have on my umbral node or wherever I have it
And maybe it's a couple of sats a day. Maybe it's 50 sats a day. I mean these are pennies
but at scale for every you know, even if it was 10 every
Every third mumble user. I mean it would really make a difference
And they wouldn't be drawn to these
solutions that ultimately
Five ten years on sort of suck the life out of these projects
At least in my opinion, I mean when you really think about what we could be accomplishing together
We really have an opportunity to improve the life for developers for content creators
And to do it using all free software that's completely decentralized. It's really compelling
So I I do I do really like the value for value aspect of podcasting 2.0 and I think it's intensely important
But it's not the actual entire story
Didn't plan to go on that
rant thank you for it though
I guess I got the feels about it, you know
She's louise. I mean when you get inspired I guess so. Does that make sense to you?
I mean actually I feel like it doesn't because I saw you in the telegram group just the other day asking like hey
What podcast app should I get so it's even even my friends, you know, like we don't think we don't think new podcast
Newpodcastapps.com like I just I haven't like I really haven't gotten the message out there even though and I and I and I know
I could do better
But because I get so passionate about it, I just kind of like go
And i'm clearly not i'm not connecting it, you know, i'm not i'm not getting at home with people
I don't think i'm not as successfully as I could maybe one of my questions for you would be
do you think a someone who's new to podcast could jump into one of these apps and
A year down the road be like, oh, yeah these new features and kind of grow with the app
Is that a do you think they're appropriate for that? I think some of the features
If you showed it to a new user, they would just be like, oh, yeah
If you showed it to a new user, they would just think the feature should have always been like that like chapters
Or like the ability to show an image up on the screen at a moment during the show or transcripts
or the other thing you could do with that multi-format enclosure is you could have a low bit rate high bit rate and
An app developer could choose to implement the ability when streaming to dynamically switch depending on your connectivity
That's just something youtube does automatically a new user to a new podcast app would just expect that kind of thing
They wouldn't even know any different. In fact, I think it's harder
I think the real challenge is people who love antenna pod and overcast and pocketcast because those apps
Have let people develop
routines
And a process and a way of listening that new apps don't necessarily re-implement because they got their whole they got their own whole paradigm
And I think it's much harder
For those users to stick than it would be a new user who doesn't really have expectations of what an app does. Is that grog?
Oh, yeah
That's my thing on that. I guess that's my thing
I like it, you know, you know how I get when I get when I gets to talking about the podcasting. Yeah, you love the podcasting
It's really exciting. Honestly, what's going on over there? I listen to the podcasting 2.0 podcast, you know that dave and adam do
There's so many developers and community members that are all working on pieces of it right now
There's so many things in the work
So it is early days and that's another thing I suck at is I can't just keep my mouth shut and let
The early day stuff ride out for a little bit longer
You know, I got to be out there doing a podcast like two years or in the case of bitcoin like 13 years before anybody
Cares about it, right? I got to be like out there. Mr. Early adopter not in a bragging way
No, no, not in a breaking way like in a shut up and be strategic you moron way
Why aren't you a better businessman way that kind of way, you know, that's how I feel. Anyways
moving on
The github interaction on the website stuff. Oh, wow
Right. Oh, wow. Yeah, how good it's super great. Yeah
Thank you. Everyone really so we have been reading it
we have been conversating around it and trying to figure out like
What makes sense what resonates with us how we want to kind of break this thing into multiple phases?
So I asked west to come into my office earlier
And i've kind of decided like let's take let's sit down and kind of take a look at what we do know
And what we don't know where we're at. And so that was sort of the framing for our conversation around the website
Wes pains back here in the office with me wes welcome into the office. Thank you. You even brought a chair in
I mean, there's not much room. You're kind of standing over me, but it works
Yeah, brent wanted me to only have a stool but I decided you deserved a nice comfy chair because after all
You're basically the cto of our summer projects here
You get you know
You get full veto power as far as i'm concerned on anything before we deploy it
and I feel like we're kind of coming to a bit of a
Firm understanding of what we know we are going to bite off and tackle this summer. Yeah, that was kind of mission one
We got stuck with this. Hey change up the website, but we started thinking about it. And you know, the website is really just
one output of many that we have and they all the outputs kind of stem from
you know, whatever we use as our source of truth and so
Making changes to the website is one thing but we got to kind of factor in how does that affect everything upstream and
potentially downstream of it and sort of pick
Of the pieces of automation because it's not just the website, right? We've got some existing automation around publishing the episodes taking
you know going from the editor's great output and putting it in all the right places where the audience can reach it and
What parts of those do we want to commit to changing?
To facilitate whatever the next stage of the website is and then what other changes does it make sense to do?
At that same time and are there some things that make sense to hold off just for a little bit
so that way we can kind of keep this in a reasonable set of goals because
We could pretty easily spin off into building a totally new
Complex monster that would like address all of our workflow issues we've ever had and that would be wonderful
But we don't really need to do it all at once and we do have like an actual deadline to get the you know
To accomplish the website component and I think there's still like shows to record too. Yeah, there's that so we've kind of figured out
It seems like for phase one. We're probably going to keep fireside as our back end cdn
And and what we're calling sort of our source of truth for the most part at least what goes public?
What do we mean by source of truth one place to collect all the information about the show that defines a defines an episode, you know
So that's that starts with things like the title the description the set of tags associated with it includes the links it includes
Information about who sponsored that show if any it includes the hosts the guests
It might include something like a transcript in the future, you know, so there's one spot to go
To modify things to make changes to find the reference for that episode and one one place of data that then can feed
Any other system that needs to take it and you know
Translate it into whether that be translated to the feed translate it to some markdown for a website engine
Or something else you can probably imagine listener happens all the time
Like we get an episode out there like oh, we forgot a link or oh this link needs to be changed
We should have this person's name to the guest list stuff like that happens
And so you want like a source of truth that the editors and the hosts and everybody else on the team
Knows that's where they go to make changes. So we're going to kind of use fireside as that right now
But we're going to lay our own website on top of that
And then the other bit that's pretty important for us to work with the podcasting 2.0 spec
Is we're going to start biting off generating our own rss feeds, which so far we've kind of been reluctant to ever really take on
Well, you know, we messed that up and people can't listen to the shows we're off the air. So that's a big deal
But we also want like you said we want
Enclosure option support we want transcript support. We want to improve chapter support
There's so many things in the 2.0 spec that we want to be able to work into this and to do that
We have to just sort of manage the feeds ourselves because we find that the platforms out there that generate these feeds for you
While they're nice and reliable and they have good cdns and all that kind of stuff
They're not really aggressive about adding these features. We have a more advanced audience
That's a little bit more of an earth. Well, not a little bit that is, you know, a lot of early adopters
And so they want these features
Before other podcast audiences are demanding them. Maybe that's because sort of underscores a lot of what we're doing actually
I think we're you know
Partially realizing that that some of this stuff being able to have the feed, you know
That that meets the audience's needs that meets our needs
We're not just making a podcast. We're pretty committed to the podcasting medium, right?
It's kind of the primary output that we have we have other outputs sure, you know
Like we have the videos on youtube and stuff like that, but the feeds that's that's the heart of jupiter broadcasting in many ways
Yep, so we want to make sure we get that right. So we figured out feeds. We're going to generate a new website
It's going to be a static website. We're going to take that on a new live page all the sort of
accessory side pages and stuff like that
page all the sort of accessory side pages like
You know the calendar page the donation page matrix info mumble info
We're going to try to make it pretty straightforward to create pages that won't have to be updated too often
But will hopefully be high performance and and and load fast for you and look clean
We have that kind of stuff dialed in and we kind of have a high level of requirements figured out to support all of that
You know
You've been thinking a little bit too about a more modern
publishing workflow about a new way we could host this because what we're transitioning from today is a wordpress site
That runs on scale engine and it's been good
But it really was a different way of running this stuff and there's kind of a more modern way to architect this few years ago
We were manually adding posts to the wordpress every time an episode came out, right and that's very flexible
It means like, you know you as a as a small business person like you have complete control
You don't have to learn a whole crazy system. It's it's designed around interactivity
But when we switch to a more automated workflow
Interactivity was less of our concern instead of you know automation and reproducibility. Yeah
And and really just the ability to just do things at scale
There's really no reason why an episode needs to sit around and wait for somebody to go through and create a wordpress post
After an editor's done that's what we realized a while ago
And we set off to fix that with our cast a blast to back end
And that's been now that's really carried us a long way
And this is kind of completing that and you have invested west in back end infrastructure to help automate some of this stuff
Where do you think? Where do you think? We're really going to be adding to our existing system. Is it going to be
Employing things on github more like where do you think one of the big tweaks is going to be in our in our back end infrastructure?
Yeah for the moment
We've kind of got a you know a collection of automations that tie together primarily
Closed systems, right? Like we can't give the audience access to the wordpress. We're not going to give them access to the fireside
Unfortunately, so those are all kind of just closed off pieces that we you know
We've got credentials to we join these apis together and shuffle data around but in the future
We'd absolutely love to have more things available on github both for you know collaboration reasons internally
But also externally with the audience to share, you know
We're not going to be experts in all the tools we use we we know already the audience has a ton of great opinions say on
static site builders and so if we can
You know publish the stuff that we're doing and get some some help or input from the audience on
On tweaking the website to be as cool as possible
I think that's a great idea and we're not going to get totally there in phase one
I'd love to see us keep our source of truth on github as well, but there's some complications especially like
We have a sort of you know time sensitive
Scheduling workflow sometimes where we we need an episode to come out at a certain time, but not before
We've got you know restrictions on necessarily who might have access to things
when
And we rely on fireside for some of those things right now
But in the future
I think we can change that we just got to pick off the right size chunks so that we can actually accomplish these things
And not totally break
everything
The github conversation and discussions have been really useful for kind of thinking through some of that and that's just it
You know, there's it's sort of a nice way to kind of move through this and figure. Okay
Yeah, we have to have this like we as we started whiteboarding this out. We realized
Scheduling the publishing is actually a little bit more of a complicated problem that we initially thought and that's one of the one of the ways
Keeping fireside as our source of truth solves that because it has a mechanism built in for scheduling
but what we really like about eventually moving the entire workflow to github and we think we have ways we could do it is
That's where we could eventually bring in the audience and somebody could do a pull request against show notes
and either make an addition or a subtraction or a correction and
Not only would that be powerful around the you know, the the week that the episode comes out, but imagine
somebody's listening to an episode five years from now and
There's a bad link or something's dead in the show notes
They could help us keep that as a living relevant document
That's still useful to people even stuff that's in the back catalog that we would never go back through an audit anymore
So I guess what I'm saying is we have motivations and reasons to take it beyond what we want to do in phase one
It just seems like we have to be reasonable about what we choose to bite off at this stage
Yeah, you know, we're trying to find our squeakiest wheels and right now that's the website and then the feeds
It's just so core and you know, it kind of makes sense to you because the data is quite similar
It's both very driven on on the shows and the episode
So we need the same a lot of the same data for the feeds as we end up needing for the website
So I think I think there's going to be some nice combination there where we can get two birds one stone and a whole lot of podcasts
Very good. Well, thank you. Mr. Payne. Thanks for coming to the office and going over this
We press on and it's gonna just get better and better and the summer is gonna be exciting looking forward to it
All right. Now you get back to work. Wait, you're supposed to give me that expense card. I'm sorry. You got to go now
All right, so I actually kind of wanted to do something a little different for the boost segments
If you want to share your story lurks a lot, but you told me in the matrix room the other day and I love these stories about how
You decided to take the challenge and figure out how to do the boost thing
Which has now sent you down the rabbit hole of self-hosting and running an umbral instance and all that kind of stuff
I mean, what do you what do you uh, what do you want to share?
I mean, I don't want to put you on the spot, but i'd love to hear a little bit of the story
Wanting to do more self-hosting was something I want to do. Anyway, I just like to learn
And play with the stuff and you know, I don't know i'm an enthusiast always have been but
It's really just been all of this talk about the podcasting 2.0 and the value for value
just kind of really piqued my interest because
for me, um
The main appeal of bitcoin has never been this whole like speculative
Oh if I buy a little and hodl it and i'll be so rich kind of thing that draws a lot of people in
um, I like kind of more the uh
What do you call it? The um, the idealism behind it of enabling people to do things and giving people
You know like a decentralized kind of you know, consensus based system for money. I like that a lot
Yeah, you know for me. It was the decentralized network the the shared computing thing. I've always loved
Clustered computing especially clustered computing over the internet and that's what drew me into it as well
As well, but i'm wondering if if you kind of got these this sensation I did
Which was really kind of a cool sensation was when I first self-hosted a service I felt
It felt good. Like I had taken control of something and a term that gets used often is like I had sovereignty over it
It was cool to have that feeling with my data
It was a whole other experience to have it with money to be like
I don't have to go to paypal to ask for this money
I don't have to go to stripe to ask for this money. I don't have to go for the bank to the bank when somebody
boosts the show
It shows up on the note in my office here at the studio and it's physically like there
It's really like it's like having a register and it's actually mine. It's we have sovereignty over it
And that is such a it's such a hard concept to convey
But it's one of those things like self-hosting that when once you feel it you love that sensation
So you're getting both at the same time right now. It's pretty great
So what are you going to try experimenting with?
well right now i'm really kind of learning a lot about the lightning network and stuff and so
um, I do have this excitement about
Participating helping keep the network healthy and running a bitcoin in the lightning node
But like i'm not set up for routing man. This channel stuff is hard to figure out with the lightning
Yeah, yeah, it is. There are some good resources out there including some good youtube videos
I'll try to find a couple and throw them in the show notes if I remember after the show because there's some good ways
To get started there
But that is it is a complicated thing
It is legitimately probably just as complicated as running an email server. I mean it is
it is not for the faint of heart what you asked me about like
That sensation that you get once you self-host something for me
Like the first thing is I went ahead despite everybody's advice
Which is which is actually kind of spot on and i'm hosted my own email
And i'm still doing it because I still like it and uh, then the big one for me was when I got my family
To switch to my own matrix server and now my whole family
We have our own pet and it just feels good to not be on google's hangouts or anything else like it
Congratulations on that
That is awesome, man. Well done
That is that is a big win right there
Uh, well, thanks for sharing
Uh, I appreciate you, uh coming on and hanging out in the office for a few minutes and I want to uh
switch over to you now brent because
You were setting up your own node this last week because one of the things we want to experiment
with office hours
Is in the podcasting 2.0 spec for the value
Um namespace the value element or whatever you want to call it
they have this
concept of splits
And the idea with the split is and if you go look at the podcasting 2.0 show, in fact
Let's go pull it up right now on the on the website. If you go look over there. You'll see they have these splits between
a bunch of participants
in the show
This is like an automatic way so that when people send in boosts
You can set splits to go to the host to the producer to the editor
So so here on the podcasting 2.0 show, which is the weekly show that talks about the work going on
They have most of the split going to the podcast index
Then they have some of their split going to their chapters editor
Another bit of the split going to sovereign feeds. That's how they generate their podcasting 2.0 feed
And then they have a couple of really small sats going to the boostagram bots
Because those if you send them one sat they can help like
Announce on mastodon or in a chat room that you've got in a boost. So they kind of also play with that a little bit
But one of the ideas here of these splits
Is in the podcasting 2.0 app when you go to send a boost you can actually see how the podcast
Has decided to arrange those splits and in some cases you could even override them
But the thought is is that it's a way to send value to the individuals who are contributing value to the podcast
On an ongoing basis so
And you can do it per episode or you can do it for the entire feed
So you could say automatically on the episodes that brent participates in
Participates in there is a split added to hit to the rss feed for office hours
Where brent gets 10 of all of the boosts for the show?
Another idea i'm experimenting with along these same lines for coder radio and for lup
Is why not send a split to an open source project?
You send a boost into the show
10 that week for that episode goes to
I don't know the mumble developer. Let's just i'm I guess i'm picking on mumble, right?
They have to be on the lightning network. So i'm collecting a list. So if you know of any send me a boost
Then you know
It's like a way where you can boost the show and like 10
That week goes to a project or something or in this case, you know
10 goes to brent and 10 goes to drew and you know
We kind of or something right? Like I don't actually know what it would look like
But what I find appealing about it as a longtime podcaster is it's all transparent
It's all front and center and it's a way for the audience to kind of
directly
Give value to like say maybe just maybe the week we're doing like brent gets the split or something
Like you are a brent fan and you think he's been doing great work
You know, it's just an opportunity. I I feel like there's something there
So I said brent go set up a lightning node have at it. Let's try this out. Hoorah
How'd it go? You're pretty smart because you told me several days ago and I think
With the experience we had in january setting yours up
It takes a few days to download the whole blockchain on your node. Yeah, and you do that ahead of time
So I got to it. Thank you to alex for getting me into ansible a little bit. So I took the opportunity to jump in
do a little bit of ansible foo to get this thing up and running which is a
I guess a whole other story that we told in linux unplugged this week
but it was going great once I sort of figured it out and um
I learned the challenge of having several sysadmins sitting on the same server because it turns out alex is doing a bunch of
Experiments and he rebooted the server which actually I guess the node never came back up. So for about a half a day yesterday
We were not downloading the blockchain. So i'm a little behind
On downloading it but um, I think it's gonna work just fine once it gets going and uh, unfortunately
We don't have it up and running at this very moment, but I feel like after the show
Maybe we can uh start playing with it
This might be one of those giving the milk away for free moments
But there's like a vps that focuses just on lightning nodes called voltage. Oh
And you can
Basically go there depending on how much you want to pay
And they have some pretty cheap plans for individuals and they run a hosted node for you. See that's a great idea
I think that's really attractive actually
That might be like for the hosts
That don't want to run their own node, which should probably be the majority that seems like a pretty nice way to go
but then
the hosts that do want to run their own node have that option and then and i've never used any of these hosted services, but
understanding the way the technology works
You absolutely could sort of use the hosted node as your front end
And then the wallet could possibly be like on an umbral box on your land or something like that, too
So that's kind of fun and cool
so there's again
A lot of work that still needs to be done, but you can feel we're getting there, right?
Like there's progress made almost every single week
People are trying it out
I'm trying to find the right balance and how to talk about it
You know that kind of stuff
well
And it feels like this show is an appropriate place to just kind of
Throw all caution out the window and just try these things. So bring it on. Yep
So we will be trying that out eventually
Probably the first show where we experiment with taking over our own feed generation is going to be this one
And the other benefit to doing that is then the members will be able to boost as well
Because right now our core problem is that the platforms we use don't support the value tag
And so the member feeds don't support it and on the daily I hear from a member who's like I'd really like to send you
A boost it's like the most requested feature right now. Yeah. Yeah
Speaking of boosts
Dpg sent a boost in two days ago says he's loving the office. He wants to know about our support for codecs
I mentioned this earlier. He's asking about google's lira and also just about opus in general
Or are we going to be stuck with mp3 forever?
You know, I think momentum on these alternative codecs was lost when at the when the patent expired or whatever it was on mp3
Years ago now and momentum was just kind of lost
Opus is probably personally for me the most appealing on that list there
If you could point me in the direction of a couple of podcast apps, I could test with opus
It's not beyond the scope of something i'd be willing to consider once we get a 2.0 compliant rss feed
because over the years i've probably gotten a couple of hundred requests for opus and
That's one of the benefits to joining the mumble room is you get the opus codec
Which we have turned up to like 96 kilobits or something like that. It just sounds fantastic at 96
So maybe maybe maybe
Maybe maybe
True grits wrote in with a thousand sats. I would be fine listening to normal jb content
They write ads and everything if I could just get the unplugged live stream boosts enabled. There you go
Plus one for that feature request
I know man. I know
I know we're getting there. It's just not that simple it is
It requires the building of our own entire infrastructure to do it, but we will get there one day, right?
Which we will thank you for pushing us in that direction, but there's work to be done
It's definitely gotten the conversations really going
All right
Thank you everybody for sending a boost if you'd like to boost us do podcast apps dot com
And I like the blue wallet if you're outside the us and strike if you're inside the us to charge it up
Now we got an email into the show about matrix and things
It says hi chris longtime listener for just about all your shows and i'm an occasional participant in the telegram group
I've been listening to you talk about matrix for quite some time now and i've messed with it on and off over the years
As well i've had high hopes for matrix and perhaps it will work out
But I do wonder if your attention on it is sucking all of the oxygen out of the room
Perhaps there are other technologies which could be even better that are not getting the spotlight
You've been a big advocate for decentralized and self-hosted options. But what about distributed and serverless?
Could perhaps that not be even better?
Think no synapse to even have to manage that's attractive. Yeah, really projects like talks
Session jammy, they're foss and they aim to do the core of what matrix is doing but without the need for any servers at all
I know matrix is a bit more ambitious, but perhaps it's aiming to do more than what people really need just food for thought
Thanks for all you do. That's a great solid question right there and
I'll tell you I have thought sometimes would would actually look something like matter most almost be better
For what we're trying to do, you know, we want to have a place for our community to come together
That has discussion channels essentially for each show and for other topics like bitcoin or
Nicks and you know just stuff that maybe isn't particularly for one show but something our community still kind of follows or at least some
Of our community, but maybe not all of them. So we don't want it in the main room that kind of stuff
and um
You know, obviously discord has been heavily heavily heavily considered as well as just sticking with irc
But I think ultimately what draws us back to matrix is two key factors
number one
is
The federated nature means that it allows our audience to scratch that self-hosting itch if they want but still participate in our community
Which is really cool
Uh, it also means that they could just join matrix.org if they like because right now we have registrations closed on ours
So that's a factor but what really has drawn me personally and and probably why i'm talking about it more is
More and more and more free software projects are making that their community
And so i'm in a red hat room. I'm in a gnome room. I'm in a plasma kde room, right?
I'm in a security and an open source radical thinkers room. I'm I i'm in an accessibility room
That's trying to do accessibility for gtk stuff and i'm i'm in a room for people that are trying to do
Outreach for people that are you know for groups that aren't really in open source yet
And they're trying to bring new people in and it's like all of these diverse
Opinions and rooms all on one giant network
And I can join as chris at jupiter broadcasting.com, right? So it's like
Or chris last whatever. I think it's just chris. So it's like it has that identity aspect to it
It has that network effect to it. It has that self-hosting element to it
It has this sort of feeling like this is going somewhere like the trend line is in the right direction as well
Which is usually when I start adopting something as an early adopter i'm like, okay, it's early
But I like the direction of that trend line and that's when I get on board
But that's not to take away from all the other stuff you mentioned or the stuff. I just mentioned
It may end up ultimately not being the best decision
but I think what we really have to remember and what I try to keep in mind is like
98 of the
Listeners don't even participate in any of this stuff, right? They don't got time for this
They got stuff to do or they just can't be bothered and honestly, they're probably better off and healthier for it
Let's see. Let's be real right the internet can be an awful place. Although our communities are great
Uh, so I also have to realize like this isn't the stuff that makes or breaks the business, right? Like
If I if I bet the farm, uh on matrix
Doesn't really any impact impact anything on air. Does it?
Uh, we just maybe you know, maybe don't get the right kind of interactions, but
So far we've been getting great interactions from our matrix community. I mean they're going right now as we talk and uh, you know
I knew about sir lurks a lot's journey into self-hosting after he got into boosting because he said something in the kota radio feedback
matrix and like so it it does definitely create communities and
Uh, we have a really really awesome bitcoin community in there because it's a bunch of level-headed
Bitcoiners, but they're all a bunch of level-headed people that respect each other and talk rationally and aren't a bunch of like scammers and
Like that's been a real source of good conversation as the market has just been totally tanking
to have a bunch of level-headed people in there talking about it and and you know sharing their thoughts and
definitely a diverse set of opinions
And I really found that fulfilling and I just don't i'm not getting that anywhere else outside of matrix right now. In fact
I think you're seeing a real drawdown in telegram activity as that discussion has moved over to matrix as a result
I don't know if what your observations are on this brand. I know matrix is a company that's
What your observations are on this brand? I know matrix has been a little bit harder of an adoption curve for you
So maybe you see things a little differently
No, I I actually do have to agree
Uh, I know I haven't necessarily witnessed the stuff on on the matrix side as much as you have because of some of the
Challenges I think partly due to some of the older hardware i'm trying to you know, make use of but I
Gotta say I noticed just this morning that the telegram chat
Was feeling a little
I don't know. I saw a few tumbleweeds passing by in there and I thought oh, yeah
It's not because the discussion is not happening. It's just because it's happening elsewhere. Yeah, and maybe it's better than matrix
I mean, i'm sorry the telegram is honestly in my opinion
more
Followable now like it's not just like you show up and it's like oh god. I can't keep up with this
Yeah, it used to be a little overwhelming actually. Yeah
So it's not all bad. No, I think it's just different really I I do appreciate the feedback
I am totally open to more uh feedback on the topic because you know, i'm not married to anyone particular thing
It's just where i'm at right now
James wrote in hi. I keep on wanting to help the show by subscribing or these new boosts
16 a month for a membership is too much for me
But there doesn't seem to be an option for supporting a single show at a lesser cost
I downloaded fountain went to buy whatever it is. It gave me a code and left me hanging no instructions on how to buy
I've never bought bitcoin before so i'm still stuck with no real idea how to support your shows
I'll research it later. But wondering how many others are put off you're coming in cold
What happens is you go into something like fountain or castamatic or another one of these new apps?
The way lightning works is traditionally it's invoice based
So you generate an invoice in that app?
And it gives you a long code or a qr code, but a long
string
It doesn't buy the bitcoin for you
Because that would probably get them in a whole bunch of new types of regulations and legal troubles all over the world, right?
Like you can imagine how much there is to navigate there because of all of the know your customer requirements of the financial system
So they generate the invoice and then the idea is
That you go use a lightning compliant
app
like strike or
blue wallet or cash app something like that and then you paste that long code into that app and
It will then recognize the invoice amount and make the transaction happen
But it's not obvious and that is why if we didn't have such a technical savvy audience
I just wouldn't even bother even doing this
but
Like if we don't figure out
These rough spots
If we won't early adopt some of this stuff like matrix
Like boosts, it's never going to go anywhere and
We can see the network effect building, but we still have hurdles to overcome
But man, is it so so so much better than it was a year ago. It's so much better now and like
Strike makes it so
Stupid simple and it used to be really complicated
The only tricky part now is you got to do all your like, you know know your customer id stuff, but they just
They're required to do that now to the memberships
Now to the memberships the boosts are additive. They don't replace the memberships and 16 is a lot
I get that that's just based on what our costs are
And we do offer individual show memberships. Maybe that might be your way to go like unpluggedcore.com or coderqa.co
Those are those are cheaper because they only get you access to that one show but it's still a way to support
I hope as
Things get more regulated
as laws pass
As things get more normalized it won't be that hard for an app like fountain to just charge up the wallet right from inside the app
That's going to happen eventually you can imagine you can see it
Especially if they could just tie right in with apple pay or google pay for the transaction
It'll happen, but we're just not there yet because of the regulatory environment. So in the meantime, there's this two app process
Makes sense, I guess
Not not ideal, right? I think the other thing chris is
Is I think we could do a better job of describing the various options and it's something you and I have talked about
and uh, I think something i'm going to work on in the next week or two is
Just describing our various options a little bit better
You know you've described via audio on several of the episodes and a variety of podcasts how to do some of the boosting
But I think writing that down in tech text with maybe some links to these various apps might be a really nice way to
To someone who's never done it before and also I I feel like you know
This may be kicked off a little bit of the website discussion was it's sometimes a little bit hard to get all that information
on the websites
the way that they're structured currently so
I think we're going to try to do that as best we can right now the new website
Hopefully will help help with that. But I think it's worth putting a little work into that
As it stands. Yeah, having an audio is all well and good
but it's not very accessible when you're in the moment and you're trying to get it set up and you're like
Well, what did he say? And if it was just a dupe dupe dupe kind of thing, you know, just an outline
It'd be a lot. It'd be a lot straight more straightforward. We'll get there. This is where I know i'm making a big ask
Right. This is a big ask i'm making here. It's a calculated thing because it's not something I take lightly
but
If we get it figured out for jb
Then the next linux podcast that comes on
Automatically has a couple thousand people ready to boost their show, right? The next open source project that comes on
Has a couple thousand people ready to boost their project the long-term benefit goes so much farther beyond just jupiter broadcasting
That i'm willing to make the calculated ask i'm trying to be generous in how I ask it
I guess i'm kind of banking on the idea
The people that have been listening to me long enough
You kind of know how I operate right and they know where i'm going with this and they can they can see my logic
Is kind of what i'm hoping
And you know, I get I you know, I get it I get it
It's not super straightforward. I don't want anybody to get frustrated. There are other ways to contribute value that are not just monetary
Honestly, just telling people
about the show and advocating for our shows is
Extremely valuable because podcasts are not something people just generally pick up and listen to
That's why these clips thing in fountain has actually been a big thing for me because generally, you know, it's an hour-long show
I'm just going to listen to some randos that I don't even know talk for an hour. Like i'm not going to do that
Right who does so but you know if brent comes to me and says hey, you know
I really think you'd like this episode
They talked about xyz and you know
We've talked about that and I really thought they had some good insights or they they had this great tool
They talked about well, then I listened to that episode. We do that all the time with each other. Oh, yeah
So that is extremely valuable right going and leaving us a rating or a review somewhere
On a on a popular podcast directory very valuable because that obviously helps juice their their metrics
You know leaving a comment on a youtube video and giving us a thumbs up that even helps on the channel there, right?
There's that's it. There's big ways and small ways, uh to help out and contribute and sometimes people like to physically contribute
You know, they show up and help us here
Sometimes they like to show up in the mumba room and contribute that way and it's all of it
It's really super appreciated. Of course the financial contributions super appreciated because it is a business
And it has to run and we got it. We got things. We want to do. We got a big road trip. We're planning for
And my plan is to head down to the shop this weekend
And get suspension problems
Finalized I kind of got like a broken suspension system on our last road trip because the you remember how bad the roads were
It was oh, it was memorably bad
So bad, so so bad
like
The worst you've ever experienced third world bad almost like they forgot to finish the road
So we did like some emergency fixes just so we could get out of tucson and get home, right?
But the work wasn't done. There's probably like another five grand worth of work that has to happen. So we're going down
Uh this weekend i'll probably do lup
Live from oregon, so you'll be back home for lup and i'll be live
Wes is on a trip. So wes won't be there this sunday. Oh my goodness
Should I just travel to the studio and keep it company? Well, yeah. Yeah. Yeah, somebody here to run the board, right?
I don't know. Yeah, I gotta think about that that is gonna be tricky. It's gonna be tricky
so that's you know, there's just there's a lot just a it's funny like um
How much mundane day-to-day life stuff goes into making all this possible, right?
Because this road trip to to get jupes fixed up is really in service of a bigger road trip
We have planned later in the year to do meetups and stuff like that. It's just how it works. It's
So, uh, let's see
We don't have an office hours next week
But we will have one a week after because we're doing this twice a month fortnightly fortnightly
Which if i'm doing my maths right that means our next episode will be on may 24th
Really? Yes, I think right at noon pacific 3 p.m. Eastern
It's weird how it's it's almost like dinner time where you're at
You got dinner figured out
um
I think we were gonna go for sushi, but then decided to do that for lunch instead
So I don't know what we're doing for dinner. Hmm, you know, alex hasn't
Got the smoker up and running in a few days
So maybe pizzas in that fancy oven of his I don't know what we're doing honeymoon period is officially over is what i'm hearing clearly
You're not cooking they're not cooking
You want to go get something fine when how about after he's done with the podcast thing fine
fine
Time to go home. Well
I'd love to have people join us on the 24th over jblive.tv hang out in the mumble room
Come on into the office. It's a virtual office. So it's available to anybody
Don't forget you can send us a boost with your jb bug fix request or comments
And of course, we do have the github page where we are collecting continued discussions on our website improvements
And then we're going to try to cover them in each episode as we proceed
At least that's the plan I guess right brentley something like that. Yeah
Um mumble room. Thank you so much for making it today. Appreciate you guys
Have a great rest of your week. Hope to see you next time
Bye everybody. Goodbye chat room. Thanks for being here. All right, that's it. Bye. That's it. We're done. Bye
Office hours is over. Get out of here. Thanks for being here
Okay, I gotta have my office back now
geez
Come on