So, is it Stefan or Stephon?
Because I keep realizing I'm saying it both ways.
No, Stefan is fine.
That's my fault. French Canadian coming out.
Oh, it is absolutely Brent's fault.
Sorry.
No, it's just 100% your fault.
We already discussed this in the LUTpo show.
I'm fine with it.
Brent.
I know. I'm trying my best.
But, you know, language equals heart.
Jeremy, yeah, I know.
I know for sure.
You understand, right?
Brent gets drunk.
He starts talking in French.
It's the tea that gets to me.
The tea.
It's Office Hours.
With me, Chris.
Brent's here too.
Welcome in, everybody.
Hello.
I'm here.
You know, I put out a candle.
I lit it a good hour before we got in here.
That way people think it smells good all the time.
What's that flavor?
I can't quite pinpoint it.
It's bacon.
Oh, yeah, right.
The sizzling was missing, so I couldn't quite pinpoint that.
I got it from a place called Mandles.
Not far from the studio.
Real place.
Really sells stuff like that.
We got a special show today.
This episode of Office Hours.
I'm glad you're joining us.
To make things extra special,
the star of the show,
the man, the legend,
the community leader,
our website hero,
Mr. Stefan is back.
Hello, Stefan.
Welcome into the office.
Hi. Thanks for having me.
Thank you for being here.
You know I mean it when I say it.
First of all, you've been doing a hero's amount of work
to see the work in progress.
But you've also inspired
a lot of community members
to get in and start working
and just cranking through
all this stuff.
We really are seeing something come together
that I think is pretty special.
I thank you for that too.
I think you led the way on that
and people followed your lead.
Thank you for that too.
I'm not sure if I can claim that on me.
I'm happy for the community.
The community is great
and pretty smart.
They know what they're doing
and they're coming up with stuff
where I really need
a second to process what's happening
and so on.
There are a lot of talented people
in the community.
But also,
Kiro is also doing
tons of work.
Without him,
I would be so far behind.
So he's doing a lot of the...
He did all the content
parsing and so on so that we
have the content we can work with.
He's like
super consistent and super helpful
and it's really been
a pleasure working with him also.
Brent, it's been pretty great watching
the GitHub stats and
everything come together. We've had some big
development since our last Office Hours.
Yeah, I was a little astounded because
a few days ago I pulled some of those
stats and put them in our little
show doc for this show. And this morning
I had to update it because it had almost doubled.
So in the last 30 days or so
there's like 13 authors who have published
112 commits.
Yeah.
Stefan's like, oh man, I just spend all my time looking at
pull requests and stuff these days
instead of actually building
things, which is sort of an interesting problem.
It's an interesting problem to
have. It's also like
a bit of a
challenge for me to do it this way
because, and this is
also something we realized, so we
went from my MVP
project side
to the official
Jupyter Broadcasting repository.
And that
like brought a lot of attention
to the whole
project. And
yeah, then we realized, I mean before
it was just Brent,
Kiro and myself working on
that. And we had like
a good report and everybody
had his own little part
of the project. So Kiro
was all the scraping,
Brent a lot was the content and me
was the site and the build process itself
and so on. And now you have
like input everywhere and every
process and people chiming in
and then you need
to make sure that the
vision is like
upholded, but the vision
never was clearly defined.
And I think that was like
yeah, I underestimated
what we
what would change if we make it public
so soon and that
you need to put out like a lot of information
what you want to achieve and
what is important for you and
how people can best contribute
because otherwise it's a frustrating
experience for everybody
who wants to contribute and then
I don't have the time to explain something
or they're working on something
I completely didn't intend
because I was unspecific
and so on. And so my role
changed like a lot
or is changing. Yeah, it's really
interesting. This is the very first time I
well, two things a
contribute so deeply to like
an open source spirit project, which
has been a ton of fun.
But be of course
also am one of the people
who are trying to organize all of this work.
So I'm learning a ton and
one of the things now that I'm
spending most of my time on before it was
writing content and stuff like that.
But now it's just trying to organize things
and to
we have been using
the GitHub issues as tickets for
features and ideas and like
asking questions and things like that.
And previously
just like two or three weeks
ago, we were just listing those things
and the small
tiny group of people who are working on the project
understood all of the assumptions.
So, you know, a ticket idea might
just be make
community page and there was no other
information. And so we quickly realized
that's not helpful
to a group of 10 plus, you know,
13 plus people who are working on stuff.
So I've it's been interesting
that I've had to be
much more intentional about
what we're trying to achieve on
each ticket and define
ideas to look at or
ask for ideas or even just
like here's the vision
and that's been actually super helpful to
define what the end goal
is. It's been really fascinating
actually to work with so many people
and it's been great. And the suggestions on
how to solve certain problems have been equally
great. Equally great. So thank you to everyone.
And also, Brent, I must say I
think you're doing a stellar job.
Thanks. I would not have
guessed that this is like your first time
doing something like that. And it's really
helping me out. I mean, maybe
you don't feel that way
or I don't know, but it's
really appreciated and it helps out
because that's
like you
help out in areas where I'm not
so good. So
it's really good.
So you don't mind the giant list of
assigned tickets I give you in the morning.
I wouldn't go that far, but
I manage. Yeah.
So yeah, you
are managing. It's been great. But you are right
when we opened it up to the public, we got
we got we get people that are working
on stuff by the time I go to sleep and by the time I wake
up, something's been created.
And so we've been feeling like
it's probably time to focus
because what I realized
and I think Brent probably realized pretty recently
too, is with this road
trip we have coming up in September,
we really have a hard deadline
of getting this done in August.
And that means we really probably have
to kind of focus on very specific things
to get that done. And I
feel like I'm
only really starting to wrap my head around it now because
well, it's part of
the squeaky wheel problem also, but we've been
really asking ourselves what role does the
website serve and what
will it serve in the future as we kind of start
our migration process away from fireside
and we migrate to more
of building our own back end infrastructure
and that has
sort of meant that there's
been times where I've felt like, well, okay, we should
do things like generate the RSS feeds from the website
and then there's a time later I'm like, actually, no,
now that I think about it, that's not going to work. We can't
do that. And so I've been looking at what
do we still have ahead of us and what can we trim?
And I'm curious if either
one of you have thoughts on areas
that we should probably look at just
focusing in on just for the next
few weeks so that way we can make the
flip over without
losing track of two that we could probably use some
more help with design too. But
curious on your thoughts on that.
Yeah, it's true. So
I had a bit of a
not a breakdown, but I was
getting a bit nervous and I was
contacting Brent
on Sunday and I was like, we can
continue like this. And I realized
that was maybe a bit more dramatic
than I intended, but
I just wanted to say that
exactly what Chris said
that we need to focus on what
we can really achieve in the next three to
four weeks because it's not more
and be realistic about it. So
I was down with COVID for a week,
which was not fun and
impacted my productivity.
And
so we really need to
be realistic and also
be honest in
we won't stop when
we release.
I mean, we just continue. We just
need to know what we need to have
to start the transition
and then work on it. And we're calling
it milestone one. And I think
we will in this week
clean up the tickets a bit
and really assign tickets
that will go into milestone one,
which we really need for production
and then make a milestone two.
And that's like four weeks after
going live what we want to
add feature wise next.
And yeah, we really need to hunker down
on on milestone one and get that done.
Yeah, it's the
final crunch is approaching. And
so now it's like, OK, what do we have to have to
just get this thing, you know, to launch off
the ground? Because scale
engine has very
politely been reminding us
that their deadline is serious and that they
are out of the WordPress hosting business and they'd
really like us gone by the end of summer. So
we got to do it.
And I understand. And we do have a
few details to figure out on
like back end hosting stuff and whatnot.
But we have a lot of options.
So in some ways it feels like that's in
not that it's unimportant, but it's
not a critical decision,
whereas like
what do we work on? What do we pass
for now? That feels a little
more critical. And there may be things that
you know,
we could, like you said, we just don't need
in in version one or phase
one or milestone one.
And so that includes like the whole
process. So I am
this multi site workflow
I already created so
that we can
in the future not use
fireside anymore, but using
to build everything that can
take a bit of a backseat
because that's not needed to like right away.
We don't need to replace the fireside sites.
And so that's
like a lot of work
that can be done later.
But and I feel like
we are
feature wise, we are like
there. So we could
easily, I think
switch over because like the
episodes are there. You can use
the video player, the audio players
and also thanks
to Keyroad who implemented the
Podverse player, right?
Yeah. Also a special shout
out that Mitch from the Podverse project has
joined and that has been great too to see.
And they figured that
out by themselves. So I
had like zero input.
Keyroad needed to explain some stuff to me.
So yeah, and
it was really, yeah
all his work and
yeah, that's working good now.
That's a great example. People have swooped in and really
helped out. You're right. We are really close.
I have like a couple of controversial hot takes
just in design wise. Like I actually
don't, I don't really want the video
player on the episode pages. The reason
why we have a video player on the existing
JB site is a limitation
in the WordPress theme. And if
we don't put something there, the page doesn't
render properly. So we've just been embedding the
video. But we don't really need it. And that
Podverse player is so great. That could be front and
center or right around that area.
But yeah, that kind of stuff. There's a few other notes, but all
small stuff. I think you're right. We're close
and we could always iterate on the design too
once it's done. And so I'm
really pleased with like the build times.
So every time you commit something
the site gets built and then deployed.
It sure does. It's incredible.
So I mean, it's generating like
21,000 sites
and deploys it in like
under two minutes.
That's insane. And that's
like GitHub free tier runners
and so on. So that's nothing fancy.
And I think try doing that
with Jacket or something like that and
will be like probably
25 minutes
or 30 minutes. I mean, it sounds
so not important,
but if you do a lot of changes
and do a lot of deployments, you want
to make it fast and also
like locally when you do stuff
you want it to be fast.
And so I really
like that. Yes, the chat room is
asking, Dan's asking in our Matrix
live chat. Yes, we're using Hugo
to generate the site. It just
it sort of worked out to be the perfect tool
for the job. I had had it in the back of my mind
for years as a possible
replacement. But you know, it gives us something
to work with. It's tooling that people can understand
and then the output is just a really
nice, flat, fast website,
you know, and which is sort of what I feel
it's the opposite of what WordPress gives you
in a lot of ways. So I also did like a lot
of WordPress sites in the past, but not
like for the last eight years
or so because I just couldn't
stand it anymore. And
so I really like Hugo because
you doesn't
need maintenance. It's like
super fast. You can't get any faster
and it's like
it doesn't need fancy hosting.
Has it been much of a barrier for people
coming in to work on the project? Have you noticed that
or are people picking it up pretty easily?
All at the same time. I was new to Hugo,
new to GitHub,
new to Git itself
and kind of new
to setting up a development environment locally
as well. But even with
just the very super
minimal documentation that you had up
on the MVP site a while ago
and it's pretty straightforward to get in there.
Now I did get like an exclusive
tour of how Hugo works thanks
to Stefan and we spent like, I don't know,
three hours or something hanging out doing
that. But I have found
that the structure is fairly simple and
as long as you understand a
few little principles, most
of it is fairly readable. And so
you know making
modifications, especially to content
has been very straightforward
and that was the whole point was to make it sort
of very markdown friendly,
easy for hosts to go in there
and change information and
make a few little tweaks. So I found that
quite nice. Now
I can't speak to the backend
stuff and what's happening there.
Other people have dove in and it seems
fairly friendly.
What interests me is like do you prefer it
compared to like
a WordPress backend, like
a web front end? Do you like
the workflow of just using your text editor
and doing stuff? I mean I love it
because that's how I do, you know,
my own personal notes. That's how I record
things in my own knowledge base. I've just
got a bunch
text notes in Nextcloud
or whatever. And I would say
we have a dream.
We have a dream talk.
The show doc
is the source of truth one day and
we put everything in the show doc, guest
information, links, everything, show
description and we maybe have certain
specific
things we put in there to make it clear to anything
reading the doc that this is host, this is guest,
these are links. We accommodate
that and then you basically feed
that to whatever is generating the
website and then goes and generates all
the feeds and generates all of the posts
on YouTube and everywhere else.
One day. That's really the dream
and so our workflow
would technically be text, although we
use Hdocs, which is a markdown
real time editor in the web,
but it's just stored as text
in the database that we would probably
be pulling and then using
one day. We're not there.
Cairo again did something in this regard
because he built this content
scraper and it's running now once a
day and looks for new episodes
and then automatically adds it to
the current site. So that's basically
that.
It's really neat.
I'm
super happy how it turned out, but
I'm also like, I like that
we are using plain Hugo
without any Node.js tooling and so on.
There was a bit of a discussion
in the community. We should use Node.js
and so on and so on and more JavaScript
and I am a bit
reluctant to adding that. So my
idea is keep it as simple
as possible. I really like
that you just need Hugo as a binary
to do everything. Also like
the stylesheet compilation and
all that stuff is done by Hugo and
you don't need the whole Node.js
setup and so on because setting up Node.js
can really be annoying, especially
if you are not
experienced in that. So it
can be rather painful.
So we have like in the community
people from all kinds
of backgrounds and I want to
make it as easy as possible and
saying to them, you just need the
Hugo binary and that's it.
Makes it like super
easy to enter.
Approachable, but also we were talking about
this with Wes behind the scenes because
we like to make sure that Wes has
his input on any of the tech decisions
we are making and for us the
advantage of it just being the Hugo binary
keeping it really simple and not making any Node
dependencies is it makes
our deployment and server
strategy super portable
where we A. can
shop around if we ever need to.
Don't know, we might not need to, but it's nice to have that
ability. But B. it makes it
just a simpler maintenance thing for us long term,
right? And so that to us
is extremely valuable,
especially considering a lot of the fancier
stuff we could do outside the
website and then just put the results on the website.
I'm not necessarily a
100% opposed to doing
something that adds a lot of value,
but I totally am agreement
with you, Stefan. It's like we keep it simple,
keep it down to the binary. We keep it portable. We
keep it approachable by new developers and
we make it easier for JB to maintain.
I mean, 10 years
we've had the current website 10, 11
years in different iterations.
So that's the kind of timeline
we could be looking at here.
And I mean, you always
should consider when you're introducing
complexity that the value is there.
That's not just complexity for complexity
sake or for like superficial
benefits.
And all of this is open source,
right? So if we keep it simple
and we keep it understandable, it's possible
another podcast group could take
this work and they could deploy something that meets
their needs. And the simpler we keep it,
the more likely that is to happen too.
There's that element. It's not like totally
driving every decision, but it's
as we do some of this stuff, it's in the back of my mind.
Yeah. And also that's why I chose
like we have the CSS framework
called Bulma. I chose
it because it's like super simple.
It is only CSS and HTML
components
and has no like JavaScript and
anything doesn't make any assumptions
what you want to use it for.
And it's just very
extensible and very good documented.
And it's also like serving
us well, I guess, because the community,
the people who didn't know Bulma
kind of start to liking
it. And yeah,
it's a good framework how
we can introduce new components and
so on. So that's not like super chaos
and yeah, better
to style. Yeah. So
I think that's also good.
And also like, yeah, on the design front,
we have like a lot of stuff still
to do and clean it up and
so on because that's like
the least important part or the
parts that has not many
unknowns. So it's not like a risky
part. You just need to some hours
sit yourself there and
clean it up. The design can be extra
tricky too, because like that is
something that is, you know,
it's touching on the brand identity a bit too.
So it's like we probably want to loop in some JB
people on that and that could take time,
but we do need the help with the design.
It's all up on our GitHub and we do have
the matrix chat room as well where people can
collaborate. Reese has recently been jumping in looking
at some of that stuff. There's been some folks
there, but Brent, you have probably a better read on it than I do,
but it feels like that's still an area where maybe
we could use some additional help
as design. And if you go to
jupitabroadcasting.net and take a look at it, you probably
see some areas that could use some sprucing. Yeah,
I mean, the episode page itself
definitely needs some love.
So it's just like the
bare content just here
it is. I mean, we're
not winning any awards with that.
You know, this is
version one. I have
I've been trying to be pretty diligent
about putting design
tags on some of the issues that touch
on design stuff. And I did just
this morning write some pretty
clear, maybe guiding
tips for
what we need those pages to be
some thoughts on just like
hey, this could move here. This could move here
like very clear for
some of the conversations Chris, you
and I and Wes had recently
about that. I've also
tagged them as like good
first issue because I think someone who has some
design background
Hugo makes it
pretty approachable to kind of work on some of that
stuff. And we've gotten a few people from
websites like firstgoodissue.com
and stuff like that that have come in
and had a look and some community members
who've kind of bitten on those
strategies of mine and it's working. So
I think we're getting there. We could use a little bit
more help, I think. But there's certainly
an issue that we can link to that
clearly states
at least five things that I
think need to happen right away as a priority.
We can throw that in the notes.
Yeah. Also, I think
design or web design
doesn't scale well with different
or with multiple users. So there's
like you need to have like a clear
vision and like two, three
people really coming up with how they wanted
to look and then other people
to execute. But I think
the design itself
doesn't scale well as like a development
process of code or so.
That's like a bit tricky.
And I mean, it's like your brand
and you must
like decide what
you want, right?
So you must be happy
with it.
That's a really good point. Thankfully, you know,
I think as a photographer and working with a lot of designers,
maybe I'm well suited to at least
be a guiding light on that. I can't
do the implementations, but
certainly I can provide a little bit of guidance.
So I'll keep doing that for sure.
But we have really good people for
implementation.
Okay, I see what you're saying.
You're saying get to it.
Yeah, all right. I love it here.
They just need to be
told or explained
what to do and then they
can do it. I have
no doubt. Yeah, that touches on something I've been
impressed by actually in the last
even two weeks. It's like every time I come up
with an idea because I'm trying to use
the jupyterbroadcasting.net
site as my main
resource whenever I'm working
on our show episodes and stuff like
that so that I can see, you know,
how does it fit into my usual everyday
workflow? And then it
becomes quickly obvious like, oh, wait a second.
Like I don't want tags first. I want a description
or hey, there's some hosts missing
or something like that. So it's been a great way
to just kind of test the site and
see some of the features that
I kind of wish were there and some functionality
that we currently have on the current website
that's maybe missing. So that's been great.
But I've been impressed
mostly by how I can just like,
you know, of course, late at night
dream up features that
I wish were there like, oh, I'm going to make a ticket
for this thing. That would be nice. Oh, I'm going to
make another ticket for this other thing that like
I don't know if we could do that, but that would be nice.
And it's amazing. Like sometimes then
I'll, you know, do an eight hours of
sleep and wake up and someone's already done it.
And it's insane.
A huge thank you
to everybody who's just like picked up
some of these random ideas and made them happen in a
short amount of time. It's been really impressive. So
I think, yeah, I
can't say enough good things about that.
And it also seems like everybody
is like having a good time, having fun,
which is also, I think, always important
if you work on something
in your free time, it
should be enjoyable and
the people should be nice and they
should be good to each other, which they all
are because it's like a stellar community.
And yeah,
it's really, it's
work, but it's also like fun.
I've caught Kiro
mentioning in our matrix chat a few
times that he's like, oh geez,
I wish I didn't have this day job so I could just keep
working on this project.
The best community, really.
And it's such a great demonstration
of the value for value stuff that we've been talking
about, right? It's not a monetary thing.
But it's so immensely valuable
and the website has needed
this for so long.
Right?
Are you now like a bit like
why didn't we do this sooner?
Perhaps. Yeah, I mean, maybe.
It was, you know,
there's always so many things to be working on.
Not every time we've opened something up
to the community has it gone super well because
you know what I think, you noticed
when we went public
with it, how a lot of things changed.
That's generally how we have started a lot of
projects in the past is we just boom,
start from the very beginning like that and it just kind of goes in a hundred
different directions.
So I think, you know, this time it
had a little bit different of a trajectory
because we kind of started
it low key and
then we started talking about it on office hours
and that's really kind of like,
you know, the core JB audience.
It's like the JB completionists
that are listening to all the shows are catching office hours.
So it's a smaller group. And then when
we put it on the GitHub and, you know,
started the matrix room, it just sort of
blew up from there. But having that kind of
staged growth, I think helped
us get a few key individuals like yourself
in and get a few things established
before it just went totally
haywire. That was the missing recipe
I think that made it actually get traction
this time. Also,
I really think having GitHub involved makes
a big difference. Like we've really debated this in the past.
Should we use our own GitLab?
Should we use something else? Or should we go
on GitHub? And I think it made a difference
this time organizing this on GitHub.
I think that also helped.
Because everybody
who works now on the JB
site now gets like
progression on GitHub and
represents and so on.
I mean, I'm always like happy when I
see the green dots every day and I think
yeah, I've done something good
and everybody sees it.
That's nice.
We're passing around screenshots
internally of it, you know, watching it.
So everybody's watching it. It's great.
I think that's been a factor.
And it feels great to actually have
this accomplished now because we had to pull
it off now. I don't know what we were going to do.
Maybe I was just going to throw together some really crappy Hugo
site that would have been really bad. I don't know what
I would have done. So, pretty
great. Like I say, it's been
extremely valuable for us and we're just really grateful.
We've got 13 people now working
on that. That's not nothing.
Well, and in the matrix room as well, there
are more than 30 people discussing
ideas and stuff like that.
And some people joining every single day.
So I think it's
trending in kind of an amazing direction.
It's great. I don't know at which
point I'll be overwhelmed, but I'll let you guys know.
I need
help. I need help. You can't be overwhelmed,
Brent.
What will I do then?
You know, I need you
for being overwhelmed.
So.
That's right. Well, you can.
He can. He just can't be overwhelmed at the same
time, right? You guys have to alternate.
Yeah. Okay. That's true.
You'll be overwhelmed at my nighttime. I'll be
overwhelmed at your nighttime.
That's also a deal.
And every project needs one sane
person. And that's you.
You're the dedicated sane person on this
project. So. Deal.
Do I get a badge? Maybe.
That would be great. We should come up with some swag.
That would be really nice for the people involved
with the website. We'll circle back to that idea.
Well, okay. So we should
say if you'd like to participate, if you're listening
and want to get involved, we'll have links
in the show notes to the GitHub page.
There's also the J.B.
website matrix group where sort of the on the ground
chat is happening. Is there anything
else we should point people to that are
hearing and kind of getting curious, maybe want to participate?
I think we did set up recently
a contributing
.md, a little bit
of documentation there. It's
a bunch of ideas collected. But if you're
new to the project and you're
thinking, oh, how is the best way
for me to approach getting
involved? We've tried to describe
it there. So that's a good place to start.
Read that. It's not too long. If you have any questions,
please just ask me directly or ask
anywhere in a ticket or something and we're
happy to help. But that
is probably the best approach.
There you go. Stefan, thank you for joining us.
We really appreciate you being here and
all your hard work, obviously. Thank you.
I'm going to take a moment and I'm going to thank Linode for
sponsoring Office Hours. They are
crazy enough to actually support the
shenanigans, if you can believe it.
So let's go right now and say hello to Linode
together. Let's do it together. Linode.com
and guess what?
I got slash Jupiter. You did.
You got the whole planet? I got the
it's a big planet too, Brent. It sure is.
Yeah, it's true.
You guys know this, but I'm going to tell you just in case
you didn't know this. You need to wise up.
Linode is the best place to host your stuff.
For Linux geeks, for people that are speed hounds,
for people that want the absolute best
flexibility, the best dashboard,
the best support. Linode's model is
different than the hyperscalers. They work
on locking you in and then just selling you more
and more services. Linode has a
very straightforward pricing structure that's
30 to 50% cheaper than the major cloud
providers that are out there. And you go
there, everything's right there. It's up front.
You're not going to get any gotcha surprises on your
bill like you do with the hyperscalers. You know
what I'm talking about. I've accidentally
spent 300 bucks on the bosses credit
card once. I learned that one the hard way.
Linode doesn't do that. And on top of all of
that, they've got great services like a powerful
DNS manager, S3
compatible object storage cloud
firewalls, physical servers if you need
it, database as a service service,
which is actually
really great. And then the other thing that's fantastic
is just their standard deployment on any
rig has all kinds of sensible defaults
for things like alerting about bandwidth
or storage. You can take snapshots, you can do automatic
backups, and it's all super
clear and easy to understand too.
If you guys can't tell, I'm
legitimately a big fan and I think you'll
love it too. And what puts it over the top is that
100 bucks, that's Linode coming in with the competence,
right? That's Linode coming in
saying with 100 bucks, you're actually going to
be able to try anything on our platform that you want
and you're going to be able to try it for a reasonable
amount of time to form an actual opinion.
That is that's what that 100 bucks is saying.
That's if you think about it, that's a
bold statement. They want you to try it and I think
you're going to love it. So head over to linode.com
slash Jupiter. Support this here
crazy office hours production and
you get yourself 100 bucks of machines.
I mean, I don't know what you want to use it for. You could use it for storage.
I suppose that's technically still using a machine.
Linode dot com slash
Jupiter.
Brent, you got to go
get yourself over there right now because you know what?
That's where I got your node.
Hey, I put I put a node
for Brent up on Linode. Why not? Right?
Why not? We kind of just
use it for everything. Really?
But what don't we use it for? There are very
few projects that you come up with that
doesn't involve Linode, it seems.
Like with the website, we're thinking about, OK, well, what makes sense
to store in the object storage
at Linode, right?
And it's just F3 compatible object storage.
So, I mean, you could run a minnow server on your own box
one day and run it there.
I want to mention something.
I touched on this earlier, but
you made me think about it today. So it's your fault.
You're welcome. You sent me a message saying
why are we getting so much spam?
What's going on?
And I would characterize. So
what we have is we have a Brent and I have a shared
office hours chat room.
And the emails that come into office hours
automatically get posted
in this chat room. So that way we can both see them.
And 95 percent
of what comes in to that
inbox is
garbage, scam,
marketing. It seems legitimate.
Oh, they would pay us. They would
pay us. They would absolutely
pay us. You should see some of the stuff they would
pay us to do. And some of it's like
I read one. I just finally broke
down and read one of these emails on Coder Radio this
week.
They want us to sneaky link like
this is just one example. They want us to
sneaky link to gambling websites
and put posts on
our page that encourage people to click
on for real money gambling, as they put
it. And then because they recognize
this is like such a sketch
business to be involved in, they're
willing to pay us a premium to
do it. They say this in the
in the introduction email. Yeah, I read that
one. That was pretty good.
And
they're all like this, right?
So I want you guys to understand
that this is a pervasive problem
because Office Hours,
it's not a big show, right?
It does all right. It does
better than the average podcast, but it's not
you know, it's not a big
show. And we're getting
a niche of a niche of a niche.
It's a show we're making for people who like
Jupiter Broadcasting. We just basically
don't give any F's. Although I am
thinking about maybe changing the name. But anyways, I'll come back to that.
I like the name, but like so does everybody else
every other podcast out there.
But we're getting this kind of stuff
as a small show. And
so you can only imagine how it scales up if
you've got any kind of reach and how the offers
get more and more tempting if you have any
kind of reach. And this
in a nutshell is why nearly all tech
media sucks. Not
all of it. You know,
there's definitely people out there
that do it right. Some of our
friends do it right.
But in the Linux niche specifically, it's
really, really bad.
And
this has a side effect
of misinforming the community
a lot. So there's a Linux project out there
right now. In my opinion,
based on research and background
conversations I've had is like 90%
hot air. But
they really know
how the tech press works.
They know the big secret
that I'm going to tell you about. They
already know it because they've been around for a while.
At least the person running it has.
And the big secret in the tech
press is that
the reader or the listener
or viewer, depending on what your medium
is,
the listener, the viewer, the reader,
they are not the customer.
When you go to like a ZDNet
or an Ars Technico or a register,
you're not the customer.
You guys all know this. You've heard it a million times.
If you're not paying for it, you're the product.
The tech
industry is the customer, specifically
the advertisers that exist
in the tech industry. But you got to be friendly with
the entire tech industry for those advertisers
to be friendly with you because it's all
about access.
And as long as the Linux press and tech
press in general make money via ads,
they're just
never going to serve the reader as the customer.
It's their business model. It's not nefarious.
It's not evil. It's the business
model. It's simple as that.
The reader is not the customer.
The listener is not the customer. The viewer is not the customer.
It's as simple as that.
I have been doing online media for
15 years. I have been
making it my primary way to make a
living for nearly 13 of those 15
years. So I have
some standing here. I'm telling you,
you're not the customer.
It's unfortunate because
what it means is that they're
more inclined to print puff pieces
about a project or a
company that probably didn't really
earn that coverage. They're less
critical because they want to maintain
their access. They want to maintain
their network because they live
and die on their access to information in these companies.
And
they just
do business as a standard practice this
way. They don't do it to deceive you.
There's nothing evil about it.
It's just the business model. And because
paychecks depend on things working this way,
I don't think they think about it that much.
So you'll see nothing but puff
articles for companies like Solar
Winds or Linux projects that are trying
to break into the enterprise that really haven't delivered
on anything yet.
So this is why I go
on all the time about membership
programs and boosts.
Because membership programs
and boosts
keep Jupiter Broadcasting's audience
the customer. And it's my job
I feel as the editor in chief of JB
to make sure that the audience always
remains our largest customer.
So that's why I think boosts
come in. That's where I think membership comes
in. It gives you
the confidence to know that the
audience is our customer.
Now, of course, I
know that the audience has to be
the customer because that's ultimately
who's going to hold us responsible.
I know that personally,
but it matters that that's how the
business sees things, too. Right. You understand
like long term
the way incentives work, it's necessary
that the business also recognize
the audience
as the primary customer.
So that's why I feel like boosts
are really significant for podcasting
because a lot of podcasters
don't have the infrastructure or the numbers
or the skill or the know-how
how to do advertising. Thus
that's not really an option for them. But even
if they could get advertising, most of them
don't know how to do it right. They don't know how to do
the reads right. They don't know how to set up relationships
right. They don't know how to build boundaries.
It's very difficult. It's a very
pervasive industry. It constantly
is pushing on your on your
on your line. And you have
to have a skill set to push back to while
maintaining a friendly relationship. It's
a very hard thing to do. And
with YouTube, that
problem slightly alleviated by the monetization
platform that YouTube offers. But the
issue there is it incentivizes you to be a slave
to an algorithm that makes
content that's horrible right.
But with Boost, there's no algorithm.
There's no Google
auction happening in the background to sell
a mattress ad. It's
the audience directly sending
value to the podcast. And value
for value is the only way
to solve this problem at
scale on the internet for small
creators, large creators,
for small free software projects, and
big software projects. It is a
fundamental shift in how
the business, the project,
the creators are incentivized.
So,
with that said,
let's get into some of these Boosts.
Because we do have some great Boosts. I know that was a
really big build up Brent, but I felt like it was important
to get that out there because I think people might be
missing the message and the noise
with everything going on right now. And we do
occasionally get people who, and we're
listening, who challenge
why we're doing Boosts,
why we're dedicating
such a large
time slot in some of the shows
for reading Boosts. And I think you
mentioned something that I think is worth
mentioning here, which is that
often in the Boosts, some ideas
and projects and like
tools and things get
mentioned that we would have never had
a chance to talk about. And it gives us a little
chance to just mention
them quickly here and explore them
and add to our
toolbox, which is really amazing too.
And share that in a really nice way.
So I know it's had
a ton of value for you, even just
seeing the Boosts come in on a daily basis.
But in terms of like a
utility for us as well,
I mean, we've gotten a bunch of great tips
from the Boosts. So thanks to everybody there.
Yeah. And the other thing that they've been
doing, which we didn't expect, is
they've been keeping us on our toes about
following up on items that we bring up on the show.
The audience remembers and asks
us about it. And we always have
every intention of following up on stuff, but
we just got a lot going on. We forget, you know, we're
working on the next show. We forget what we talked about the week before.
And the Boosts
have been a great way to kind of keep those threads alive
and interject questions or
discussion or criticism
that we wouldn't have otherwise brought into the show.
Right. So they're great from that standpoint
as well. All right. Well, let's
do it.
And now it is time for
the Boosts. So Gene
boosted in seven days ago
with a big old boost,
30,000 SATs.
He said, would a desktop OS
on a powerful server setup in another
room with maybe some
sort of thing client in the office,
would that work with horsepower
combined with silence? You could
do like the random desktopy things in
VMs or LXC to keep it isolated from
the production grade stuff. Rel or
Alma Linux nine and its super long
lifestyle could provide you a stable, slow
moving base for the system with
things like OBS officially having flat back support.
You could really probably load whatever is
needed. And he says, P.S.
I updated my boost from 10,000
SATs, which is about two dollars and 20 cents
to 30,000 SATs, which is about six
dollars and 60 cents to help
Brent with his travel fund. Oh,
that's nice. I really like
that. That is nice because we have some fun projects
we want to work on. We want to get Brent down here before
the September road trip and
bang those things out. And so that is very helpful.
We started a project list, which is
always a dangerous thing for us.
I like the idea.
I toyed
around with something like this over the network
years ago where I put a powerful box
in one room and then just dumb
clients throughout the house.
It does work pretty well.
I don't think it's the right setup here because there are
times where we're actually physically needing to plug things
and unplug things from the back of the boxes, especially
with USB interfaces and cameras.
What is
I'd love to do a project like that.
I think that'd be so much fun. Awesome
Matt boosted in seven days ago with
nine thousand five hundred
and thirty eight.
I sent it in a couple of times
so I just combined them just by putting
some parts together. I came up with something that looks
like this might fit your needs. He's talking about our replacement
OBS rig. Relatively
small and quiet fifth gen Ryzen
for under nine hundred dollars.
It has Intel Wi-Fi so everything should be compatible.
And of course you could just
tweak it based on your needs. And what
what awesome Matt did is he
included a PC part builder link.
So so great. It's like all the
parts right here. It's actually a
it's a kick butt box. It comes out
at like nine hundred and sixty bucks
but seeing this makes
me feel like yeah we probably could. We probably
would be OK with a DIY
PC again. In the back of my mind
I was like a failure would be awesome
under nine hundred and sixty bucks.
That's a hard price to beat these days.
I know you bought the current one I think
with some of your Bitcoin back in the day.
Do you remember what it was sort of equivalent
worth back then. I think they were
all the machines we bought were right. And we bought
like identical machines. I think they were all
like right around eight nine hundred bucks.
They were kind of in that price range.
One of them I think we put extra disk
in so that was slightly more expensive.
But yeah I was looking back at it.
It was a cheap time to buy machines
compared to some of the prices.
So double boost from Awesome
Matt. One thousand
five hundred and sixty nine sats and just says
love you all too. They mentioned he's awesome
because he is awesome. Of course it's
it's in the name I suppose.
We got a boost from Delian
seven days ago three thousand five
hundred sats or Dylan I suppose Dylan
and I really appreciated
the discussion about podcast production.
I've been making my own show casually for a
few years to a small audience
and I recently switched to value for value.
Question what are you using for
soundboard during the boost segment?
It's a good question.
So we've used a couple of different apps
over the years. There is
Sound Ducks D U X for
Linux which I like a lot. And then on the Mac
Fargo F
A R
R G O I think.
F A R
R A G O I think.
And that's a pretty good app for the Mac as well.
And I think you'll either
way you go you'll like it. Just don't go crazy like
I do. It'll drive people crazy.
I think also part what he's asking here
is where'd you get the clips that you're using.
Oh you think so.
I think maybe. I would
I would be asking that as a follow up anyways.
Well here you go. I'm asking as a follow up.
Those you know it
depends. Like sometimes I see a boost
come in and I'm inspired to go grab a
soundboard bite for that boost right
then and there and I just have to track it down.
Some of them came from
the podcast index guys they have like
on their GitHub they have like a bunch
of boost sound clips you can
use. And then others are just ones I've collected
over the years. I mean I have
I don't know something
like 40 different soundboards. There's one
you grabbed recently from
I think it was like a show you're watching or
a news piece and it's my favorite
so far. Can you give us a taste.
Coming in hot with the boost.
I love that
one. Yeah I got that news report.
Yeah.
It wasn't a news report
it was a YouTube car channel.
That's what it was. And it was this
super broken down dilapidated
car that they had jacked up
and put a massive engine in with
the intakes out of the hood and everything like that.
So it's just this junker
this total junker. I don't know something
about it I love though. I can't help it.
We got a double boost from Dilan
500 sats double boost tell me if I'm
crazy but I previously produced my show using
mumble with multitrack recording output
and then painstakingly edited the resulting
tracks in Audacity.
Now I just record live and
I edit nothing similar to a twitch or really
a video on demand stream. My
co-hosts are in a jitzy me room recording and streaming
at the same time with OBS using my desktop
PC running mangero smart
move or reckless.
I like
this. This might be a series that
is a good that is a good series.
You know I always like going a little reckless. I always
do. It keeps it fun
and you don't want it to get
boring. I think
you went overboard. I think I think where
you went wrong Dilan in the past is you went
overboard like we have a mumble room here right now.
Hey mumble room. Hi guys. Hello.
Hey hey. Hey they're hanging
out with us. They get a low latency open stream
but we have never done the individual
track recording simply
because of the work overhead right. Each
number in the mumble room
would become a track. And so
if you've got four
twenty thirty people in there that's
four twenty thirty tracks. That's crazy.
So we do mix the mumble down
to a single track but then
each one of our individual hosts is
also their own individual track.
Ultimately
you can make it sound
significantly better. There's just no
if ands or buts about it. Brent's voice
is different than my voice
and our voices and just the way we're recorded
are different in the mumble room. And
so each one of them needs their own EQ
needs their own touch with the compressor.
It needs its own pass over.
Each one has its own unique background noise.
So really you do need to process
them separately for really really great audio.
That being said
go check out Jupiter tube.
Tell me what you think and then go compare
it to the release version
of this show. Office Hours 8
will come out on Friday once Drew is done
with it. And you can compare Office Hours 8
to the PeerTube release
and you can kind of get an idea of what
the difference between live to tape is versus
fully edited.
And I think you'll agree the fully edited is going to
sound better. It's going to be better paced.
It's going to be a little more refined.
The fully you know live mix
version isn't necessarily unwatchable or un-listenable.
So it's just kind of depending on your
on your audience too. And then lastly
what is sustainable for you.
Like none of it really matters if the other
way was just burning you out and you weren't
going to be able to keep it going and now you've found a way where
you can keep it going and so the show goes on.
Like ultimately that's what really matters right.
So I don't think it's reckless.
I think if that is the case then I think it was
probably a smart move. But don't be
afraid to experiment and feel free to use
our show this very episode as an A B
because I think that'd be a good little test.
Get a sense.
Our first row of ducks comes in this week from
The Golden Dragon as always.
I'm a duck. D-U-K Duck.
And he's got a question
to you with 2,222
sets. Brent what
strategies did you use to learn coding
and what have you like say
when learning Hugo and what have you
learned. I'm trying to learn some dev
stuff and I'm looking for strategies to start
coding. Side note
I love that I'm basically
following the journey of The Golden
Dragon and his learning
development skills across multiple shows
as he boosts into like Coder and Office Hours.
I feel like I'm learning more about him every time.
So what have you found
useful Brent when you're trying to pick all this stuff up
and you've been trying to pick it up quick too.
The question was posed in past tense.
What strategies did you
learn you know did you use
to learn coding. And I think actually I'm
probably
more likely in the same
bolt as The Golden Dragon is
I'm just on the very tip of learning.
So I think the number
one thing for me was
and I learned this from Tim Ferriss
of all people is the concept of
being very careful
what you learn.
It's more important to learn the right thing than
it is to learn a bunch of wrong stuff.
If you want to learn Python for instance there's
about like a hundred thousand videos on YouTube
about learning Python which is
actually not that helpful
and it's too bad
that there are so many I gotta
say. So I before
even diving into any of it
just looked at
I guess
trying to determine who had quality
and recency and who was
getting down to like the very essentials
of what someone needs to learn
at first instead of just like
here's how to do all the things and I don't really
know if it's the best way or it's the
the right way to learn
it quickly. Be very discerning
I guess is all of that boiled
down to a few words. And so there's
one gentleman I think his
YouTube channel is HeckWithTim.
I think he works at
Microsoft working on
I forget now but one of their projects.
He is super
no fluff
but very complete in his explanations
and it's
like okay here's everything you need
to know for like stage one
compressed into like a thirty
minute video with chapters
which is such a helpful thing when you're trying
to learn it's like oh I'm trying to learn about
you know Python's
functions. Well maybe
you gotta listen to it three or four times.
So that's what I would say. Number one
be super discerning about where you
learn. So my first
research part
was like where are people learning
successfully because I don't
want to go learn somewhere unsuccessfully. It's a total
waste of my time. I have like a hundred
other things I want to be doing
and so that was super important to me.
The other thing is like try to find
some folks that you know or in the community
the JB community even just to recommend some
things like some of the back channel
conversations I've had with Wes
have been fascinating. So I've been like
oh Wes I'm just kind of like learning this thing but I'm
struggling a little bit. Do you have any like tips or tricks?
He's like yeah here's four
other things you could look at
that are like progressions in your
learning. So having like a
soft mentor like that is actually
super nice too.
So those are two things I think
I would recommend very strongly
is careful where you learn
and go find someone who can
really give you those shortcuts.
I think you just did.
I think you just did that.
There you go. Very good.
Cospeelin boosted in
seven days ago with 3690
sats.
Boost. Whoa. This is
the first Office Hours I've ever listened to.
There's a lot more in this show than I thought.
I'd like to make a joke though and I'd like
to say this show sounds like
a podcasting 2.1-RC1
boardroom which he thinks is
great. A note about the ads
he says I don't mind it when the podcast
inserts the ads but the dynamic ads
no good. Thanks for the show.
We totally are following
I mean we don't follow nearly the podcasting
2.0 development stuff that obviously
the podcasting 2.0 show does. I mean how
could we? But I
feel like we're giving it a
bit of coverage from a boots
on the ground podcaster who is
trying to figure out how to implement this stuff
into his business and
I kind of look at it as
a competitive advantage as well like
you know not like it's a bad
competitive but if we can if our shows can have
more features that give you things
like chapters and transcripts and more host
information and higher higher
context and all that kind of stuff that's great
right. Why wouldn't we want that stuff and I've
always kind of wanted to have the premium
feature set for our shows. So
I'm following the podcasting
2.0 stuff from kind of that perspective
and recognizing
the shortcomings in the podcast
industry recognizing the opportunities
we've missed with mobile
apps and the opportunities that
we've missed by constantly
constantly encouraging people
to do things outside the podcast app
which has been detrimental to our growth
in the long term and all that stuff
and so I follow it for that purpose and the guys
invited me on the podcasting 2.0 show
this week so they will
they'll have an episode out on Friday when we do
and go check that out if all
things go as planned I'll be on
that this week's episode.
So I'll share some of my thoughts there.
Next cause Optimus Gray
boosts in with
a real doozy six
days ago with twenty two
thousand two hundred
and twenty two sats. How
about that for a row of ducks. Thank
you very much and here's something
for your trouble.
That's a big old granddaddy duck.
He says
for us Jupiter party members
can I ask for possibly a new
feed. If the lightning and boost support
is going to take a while could
we have a separate feed of just the bonus
content like the
you know the post show for self hosted
the coderly and
the non the non like live
stuff that goes out into the member feeds.
So then we could subscribe to the normal
feeds and boost like we always do but then
also still get to enjoy the bonus content.
Hope to see you all at the West Coast meetup.
That's a good idea. No that's interesting
just a bonus content feed
so you can subscribe to all the regular feeds
and then just have one feed. It's just the
special stuff we create for the members. How did I
never think of that before. We might actually be able to do that quickly.
I got to figure out the plumbing
but that seems like
something I should have thought of. So
thanks Optimus.
Those ducks are powerful.
Those are good
ducks. Dave Jones our
buddy Dave Jones speaking of podcasting 2.0
boosted in two days ago with
two thousand one hundred and twelve
sats. B O O S T
He says Alex Gates is the real deal. He's the
smartest developer I ever met. Shout out to
Alex. He was on the show
last week and
that's
I say high praise from Dave.
High praise from Dave there Alex. That's pretty
good. Oh a guy one boosted
in seven days ago.
Yes I am still listening because
we took time off. I thought
I thought maybe nobody was listening anymore. You know
I thought I don't know the new
show relatively small show
goes off off the
air for almost a month. I thought nobody's
listening anymore but oh a guy
was and then we got a double boost from oh a guy
seven days ago
two hundred and twenty two sats baby ducks
double boost. I've seen a variety of
duck like boxes with AMD Ryzen
APU's. I feel like there's something
in there for an OBS machine maybe
something you're looking for. I think he's right
interesting. Those would be well
they're not fanless or are they fanless.
I'm always
looking for fanless but why do you think
they're not. I don't think the ducks are
they might be quiet but if they were super
quiet. Yeah
that'd be fine. Bird
dad zero two thirty four boosted with four
hundred and twenty sats
coming in hot with the boosts in
regards to a bulletproof peer tube setup
maybe build a beefy server and have
it be the main aggregator of all the streams using
something like teleport recent stream
restream or NDI.
That way the endpoints
are flexible and the final output is only an appliance
you need to worry about who
says he'll send in more feedback
via email with more
deets. Well that's
that's pretty great. That's pretty great
and then speaking again
of podcasting to know the pod father
Adam Curry boosts in with ten
thousand sats
and
this is a little bit of brilliance. This
we got to take a moment
to make space in the show
because what the pod father has realized
I think is genius. He says
Spotify is the shit
coin of podcasting and
I think he's right because
it's hot Spotify highly
decentralized implementing
proprietary standards
going to build and build
i.e. pump and pump and pump
until they realize there's
nothing really behind it. There's no
money to be had here and then it will
pop and collapse down to
some like really crappy product where
is Bitcoin decentralized.
There is no central
authority. There's no Satoshi Nakamoto anymore.
He's gone. It's an open protocol.
It's been online for 13
years widely distributed all over the internet
completely decentralized tens
of thousands of nodes.
I think he's right.
It's the open standard. I love it
that right there is some genius.
That's what that was pod father. I was
what I saw that I'm like that's brilliant.
That's so brilliant. All right.
We got another baller boost and this one
was a moment for me. This
one came from someone who I
hear on other podcasts boosting all the time.
So it was special because
I feel a real community
is building here in the boosts
and we're watching it happen across multiple shows
the dreb Scott boosted
in three days ago with 33
thousand three hundred and thirty
three sats
I'm a duck D.U.K.
loaded with talent. I'm giving that
a special duck status too. I don't know why but I feel
like it. He said I heard about you guys while listening
to podcasting to know and Dave mentioned
you guys interviewed Alex Gates.
I came over to hear Alex and ended up subscribing
enjoy the show.
You know what you get a special boost
boost. There you go.
I believe that's a Fletcher special dreb Scott.
Thank you. I was nice. I felt like
I just got boosted from a boosting celebrity
over there. I got you know I was like a little like
dreb Scott boosted the show.
Nice. It's funny like
it's a really neat community because I listen to
other podcasts and I hear these individuals
boosting in and dreb helps with
podcasting to those chapters.
He helps do their community chapters. So great.
Our last big boost
of the week came in from this is a great name
Lord of Bytes three days
ago twenty thousand four hundred
and eighty sats coming in
with the moves. First of all let
me say you're the best podcast group out there.
I've been trying to get into Linux for ten
years. Every time I start to play with Linux
I lose interest in a couple of months.
It wasn't until I found you all
that I really started getting into Linux
your shows in the community keep me inspired
every day to learn something new in Linux.
I also love that I'm getting involved
in my first open source project helping out with the new
website. Keep up the amazing
work. Yeah I was just going to say Lord of Bytes
have been sharing a whole bunch of
great insights and stuff and working hard.
So thank you.
We love you. Value for value in multiple
ways there Lord of Bytes. Thank you.
How incredible. Really
good to see.
Oh
bring a tear to my eye. And then
we do have a couple of thank you boosts
that I wanted to get out there. We got five hundred
sats from Al Carney pointed out
that you know maybe the Linux Foundation being on
Spotify not so bad. Maybe it'll
bring in new listeners and new users to
Linux. I remain skeptical
but that was their boost.
Four hundred fifty sats from a listener
letting us know. Yeah I am
still out here too. And then thirty
thirty sats. That's right.
Three thousand thirty sats from Marcel
another V4V legend says he's still
listening. Thanks for the show.
And he liked our fake mattress ad.
That's great. That is great.
I want to say thank you to the Mumble Room for joining
us live. You guys
are fantastic. We chat a lot in the pre and post show.
Maybe you know what we ought to do
like an open Q&A episode.
Get some questions ahead of time
let the Mumble Room ask questions
because that's part of the idea of office hours is
people might want to know what's going on
have input something like that. So maybe
we plan to do that in the next episode if I remember.
So get your Mumble client ready
because you can pop in you can ask us questions
or get clarifications. We have
details at Linux Unplugged dot com slash
Mumble. We'll probably eventually have a Mumble page
on the new Web site. Right. It's
on my personal to do list.
Someone asked me today they're like are you working on
this. Should I work on this or are you
working on this. Like no no. Soon
soon. That'll be great.
Meanwhile you're going to be hanging out
there at Alex's pad watching the
place for him while he gets ready for the
London meetup on the 5th at 6 p.m.
local time. That's that's getting really
close. Mm hmm.
Yeah man. And then we have
a big batch of
West Coast meetups. The Times
and like the general
vicinity's are now all posted at
meetup dot com slash Jupiter broadcasting
then we're going to ultimately end up a
JPL. By the time we do the next
episode we should have the form
available. We're going to do an audience lottery we'll
have. I think what we're going to do is a next
cloud form that you can fill out and then we'll
use a tool to randomize the results.
We'll pull a list of primary
winners and secondary winners so that way if people
know show we have backup list we can call on and
stuff like that. We'll have details
on the GPL lottery
soon. We're just trying to
figure out a fair way to do it so that way we can get
about you know
15 JB 20
JB community members inside
the Jet Propulsion Laboratory
for a very special tour from
Tim Canum the operations
lead I believe of the Mars
Linux Copter at JPL.
Very excited about that. And on the
way down to JPL and
on the way back up we'll
be doing multiple meetups
and all the details are at meetup dot com
slash Jupiter broadcasting.
Up first those that London meetup then
the West Coast tours will be coming up.
I think that's everything Brett.
You feel like that's everything. That's a pretty good show.
I think. Yeah. Yes we should say
if you'd like this if you'd like to send a boost in
you could go to new podcast apps dot com
and I've been loving Fountain. I'll put
my referral link in the show notes.
I don't know if it gets me anything anymore
but it might make it so
you can follow me and then see the clips I publish.
So I'll put a link to that in the show notes for Fountain.
Podverse is really great too.
And you're going to see that embedded on our
new website very soon. Very excited about that.
And then of course there's a whole bunch
of apps like Boost CLI
Breeze so you don't if you
don't want to switch podcast apps that's all at new podcast
apps dot com. You can send a boost in that
way. You can send us an email if you go to
office hours dot hair we have a contact form
over there. We also have
our RSS feed so you can subscribe
and then we do the show live
on Tuesdays at noon
Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern over at
Jupiter dot tube. We publish on Fridays
but we do the show live on Tuesdays
every fortnight. Right.
Not every Tuesday but every fortnight. Thank you.
Every fortnight. It's just Jupiter
dot tube for all that stuff where you can
also watch the archive. We have a calendar.
It is on the calendar. You're right. Jupiter broadcasting
dot com slash calendar. We've got a calendar
on the new site too right. It's just the same
thing. So far it's just the same
thing. It works. It's not beautiful
but it works. You know what's funny is
Stephen was going to join us
here for this office hours and he and I
were like sitting there trying to figure out
like time zones. He's like when's the show
live. I was like you're in like I think
plus 10 from my time zone
but I'm in a different time zone now and
JB is one behind my usual. So
I was trying to do all the math and then we
were like oh wait we have a calendar
for this.
I forget it too. I forget it too.
But it does convert to your local time zone.
I mean we invested millions of dollars
in those time zone robots.
That's the AI that we have in our site.
And if you haven't caught
Brent's recent brunches
they are now posted at extras.show
Some great conversations
over there. So go check those out.
Alright that's everything.
Get out of here. It's my
office. You're just visiting.
I appreciate you but you gotta
go. Thanks for coming. See you
next time.
Bye bye.