PeerTube is one of my favorite new tools right now, I think.
The minimum viable PeerTube implementation that I didn't necessarily come up with at launch,
but now weeks into it, it's been great. It's just an archive of our live shows,
and it's just a great way to watch the shows live when we're doing them.
And now with the new website and the integration with the embedded player on the new website,
so it can just ping the PeerTube API and get the latest live stream and then auto embed that on
the webpage, it's now getting integrated and automated. It's so great. And it's all laying
the plumbing so that way when we're generating our own RSS feeds, we can do live streaming in
the podcasting 2.0 app. So you can just listen to our live shows in your regular podcasting app.
That's also going to be powered by PeerTube. There's a real net effect, I think, of going
with PeerTube again. I debated it because we did it once. I had issues with it. I don't think it
was the right take, and then we shut it down, and then we relaunched, and we kind of did this
minimum viable PeerTube, and it's been so much better. It's been a great tool. Very happy with
it. So if you haven't checked out JupiterTube, you got to go over there, Jupiter.Tube. You can
get archived versions of this live stream and all the other live shows. It's Office Hours with me,
Chris. Well, hello, everybody. Welcome into the office. Come on, Brent. Sit down. It's showtime.
Hello there. How are you doing? Hey, do you still have my butt groove here?
Yeah. Yeah, I keep that just right. I got a little model of your...never mind. You don't want to know
how I do that. We'll just move on. I just want you to feel at home, you know? It's a safe space
here in the office. We have so much going on behind the scenes this week that we could make
the week of shows just about the work we've been doing, but we're going to kind of condense some
of it down right here into Office Hours this week. Brent, would you say it's fair to say
it's the final countdown? I think we're slightly past our optimistic final countdown, but yeah,
it certainly is. The actual dead deadline is really coming up. It's getting me a little nervous.
Now, you've been at Alex's house for, I think, about seven years, right? You've been there now?
Yeah. Yeah, six or seven. Yeah. And the opportunity came up for you two to work
together on some infrastructure, and we saw a whole new, I think, push of work getting done.
And so we wanted to update everybody because there's been so many developments since our
last episode that we just had to kind of stop and kind of do a sync up. And so we had a chance to
sit down with Alex and Wes after Linux unplugged last week, and I wanted to play a little bit of
our chat with you just to give you an update on where we're at in some of the infrastructure
decisions that we've made for the new Jupiter Broadcasting website.
We sent out an invite saying, let's build a website, and they came to our party. It is going
incredible. It's a really special day because Wes Payne's here. It's been a bit. Hello, Wes.
Hello. Good to have you in the office.
It's nice to be here. Sorry we didn't have a seat for you.
But hey, I'm happy just to sit right on top of Brent.
I don't know why he has to collect all those seats. I think it's totally fair. I think it's
fair. And Brent, I hope you brought the candy because Alex is here and we did promise candy.
Hello, Alex. Welcome back to the office. If you've been on the office before,
I think you have once, maybe. But it's good to have you here.
I definitely interrupted an episode with the no touchy the chair sticker a while back.
That is very true. He also interrupted one by turning the internet off.
Oh, that's also true. Yes.
Okay, good. So your presence has been felt.
Definitely.
Right. Good. Well, actually, this week, we've got a lot to talk about because I've gotten the sense
that there has been a lot of work to get the new Jupiter Broadcasting website
ready to go from an infrastructure standpoint. I know we have a new domain,
we have some changes, and it sounds like we're getting a lot closer to actually having this
thing finished. So what are we going to talk about, Brent? What's the latest?
Well, a heck of a lot of stuff has been happening on the website this week, so much that I it seems
I can't ever get caught up on all of the sort of action that's happening there, which is a really
good problem to have. I'm not complaining at all. Totally.
We're going to need another Brent.
The team that we've amassed has been really impressive in the work they've been doing.
And the discussions that have been happening have been super fascinating to watch. Chris,
I know you got involved in one or two of them this week as well,
and you got some features that were really cool.
You know, every now and then I've needed to jump in. But for the most part, I feel like it's rare
where something hits like a roadblock that needs me to make a decision. But one area I was providing
some feedback just recently was how we are doing the live embed on the new website. When you go to
new.jupiterbroadcasting.com, you'll see there's a live link. When you go there, we now have a
dynamically inserted PeerTube live stream. So on the back end, using the PeerTube API,
when the new whatever we're streaming, maybe it's Coder, maybe it's office hours,
maybe it's Linux unplugged, maybe it's self-hosted, whatever we're streaming,
the API actually read. You can get that. You can query that information. It makes all of
it available. So when a new stream goes live, the API registers that. And then on the back end, I
don't even know really how they're doing this. Maybe you can tell me. We're getting on the back
end, basically the latest PeerTube live stream auto embedded now on the new website. We don't
have to do anything. Tell us how it's happening, Wes. Yeah, I mean, there's a little bit of
JavaScript right here in the page that's going to go reach out to the PeerTube API, figure out the
latest live stream that's happening, and then dynamically pull the embed code and toss that
into your page. Oh, so it does it on load. Oh, so whatever the live stream is at that moment
will automatically get embedded. Also, just major props to Arwen Thorne. I probably messed that name
up, but just an awesome example. Not only did they make this functionality work in really quick time,
but also added some helpful sort of just improve the general doc system. The code itself is really
well documented. And it's just a nice case where they're not otherwise super active on GitHub,
but just showed up to help us out. Well, and there were a few complicated ways to solve this
problem thrown around where we were trying to come up with ways where we would maybe add a
feature to a chat bot that would then auto embedded on thing and then kick off a build. And
like we were kind of coming up with like rather complicated solutions. And this is a rather
elegant way to pull this off. Nice, simple, easy. Yeah, I like that a lot. And it means we don't
have to go edit the page every time we go live. One last thing we can mess up, right? That's so
cool. You know, Arwen actually created a GitHub account specifically to commit that idea to our
repo, which was really great. And then unfortunately ran into getting flagged as spam because of the
way they have their email set up and vanished along with the changes that they submitted. So
it was a day or so that we were trying to get them back. And they figured it out. They fixed
their email, I think. And we got all those changes back. And we're like, oh, no, that code was so
great. It's gone forever now. But yeah, it came back. Thank you. And is now part of the production.
Lovely. Thank you for actually pushing through all those trials and tribulations to actually
get it across the finish line, too. Yeah, we appreciate it. Yeah, it's been great to see
a lot of new people who have maybe worked on a lot of projects solo, but haven't really worked
in an open source community kind of project. And so there's been some really neat mentoring
happening as well, which I think has been another one of those features that we didn't really expect
to happen. And has been really great to watch. And everybody's been super, super nice and
handholding too much. I'll tell you what I found actually really interesting this week,
as I started to get involved in the project is, is my it's my first time dealing with an open source
project where almost all the discussion happens almost exclusively on GitHub.
Like when I was involved with Linux server back in the day, we did all the chat in IRC or
Discord. And we had private team channels where we, you know, took all the decisions and stuff
like that. But the thing that I've really started to appreciate is just how difficult it is to
communicate all of your thoughts in such a low bandwidth conversation, without either sounding a
little bit rude and dismissive of, well, we shouldn't do it that way because of X, like,
unless you phrase things carefully, it can sound like you're being a little bit up yourself. But
I've been really impressed with the, I guess, the level of discourse that's been happening in all
of the issues that I've certainly been involved when involved with. There is some discussion
happens in the matrix room, but not not a lot. I wouldn't say the majority happens there. It
pretty much all happens on GitHub, which is, I think very, very interesting. Yeah,
we've been actively trying to encourage it to happen on GitHub for, I think, two reasons,
one that I've made public and the other one that I've kind of kept to myself. But you're it worked
on you, Alex. The first reason is, then we can all work sort of asynchronously, because it seems
like almost half the people that are committing ideas and pull requests aren't from anywhere near
the North American time zones. And so there's work happening at night. And so if you haven't been in
the matrix chat all day, whichever time zone you're in, you're not missing stuff. And so you're if
you're working on a specific issue, then everything's there. The other reason is, it forces
you to write your ideas in a really concise and clear way. And it forces you to also make them
very clear for others. And I think sometimes if you're doing real time chat, that's not always the
case, you can't sort of sit for 10 minutes, even I've done this on certain issues, sit for 10
minutes and really think about how do I communicate this very clearly so that there's no question
about what my ideas and even go in and edit it an hour later, when you're like, Oh, I forgot to
mention this other thing. Thank goodness for that edit button, because stuff doesn't care to be an
hour later all the time. Yeah. So I think that's actually another feature of using the of tracking
all of those conversations, hopefully quite concisely, but really with some quality and in
the GitHub issues. And so I just implore anybody that's listening to this, I don't know who's
who's listening, but if you are Hello, if you are on the fence about contributing to an open source
project, this is the perfect one to get started. Because there are so many people who this is their
first one. And you will be in good company. Yeah. And that also doesn't mean that the quality of
work has been low. No, not at all. Very, very, very impressed with people who've been new to the
this kind of GitHub workflow, even who've had extremely high quality of contributions. That's
been super impressive to me. I feel like it's a treat to just watch all the activity happen.
I totally agree with that. And I also appreciate that when I have been required to like,
provide some input, somebody has been willing to like take me in matrix because I'm not watching
all the GitHub threads all the time. So there is that space to be like, Hey, can you go look at
this? And then they just link me to the issue on GitHub that I need to take a look at. And I think
that has been a useful combination. Yeah, it's nice. It feels like kind of one community and not
disparate places. You know, you see a lot of folks kind of onboarding and matrix getting tips for
stuff, maybe throwing out pie in the sky ideas or talking about, you know, sort of vaguer things
before they're ready to shape it into a specific issue. And it's really nice. And I think the
reason why it's working well for people who've never contributed to an open source project
before is a lot of them have contributed to their own projects before. And that's absolutely a
factor. And I think a big part of it is Brent and Stefan's stewardship. I think they've helped
integrate people and, and kind of act as that PMO because it needs somebody who can, especially in
our situation where there's sometimes business requirements that we just have certain things we
want done, or we want to make sure we have certain features or things like that. And so you need
somebody who can interface all of that. And I think that's also helped make it a successful project.
It kind of makes them the spirit of the project in a way to, you know, sort of the ambassador
of the culture and how things get done and welcoming new users. And that's, that's really
nice to have established. Although, are we celebrating too soon? I mean, we kind of have
like a mission accomplished sign behind us right now. We're not actually done yet. Careful. There
are some very large sub projects that still need some work, sort of like the archive, for instance,
and some people are working on that on the background. But one of the main thrusts of my
being here at Alex's place for the last, what, three weeks, something like that, has been to try
to get Alex involved in the project. And he did mention that he he has been involved. But Alex,
you did some crazy neat stuff that I only understand about 50% of. Can you walk us through
that? Well, for the last couple of years, we've been running the Jupyter broadcasting
infrastructure sort of here, there and everywhere. I think it was about a couple of years ago,
that we, we started deploying some infrastructure for the self hosted show. And I wanted to use
infrastructure as code to do that, you know, things like ansible and terraform to do that to manage,
you know, things like DNS records, why would we want to log in manually to the Cloudflare
interface, for example, type in some numbers like cavemen, and every time we make a change,
that doesn't really thrill me that kind of stuff. What does thrill me is, you know, having a specific
label in my Docker compose file, and having the the code have the ability to pass through that
entire compose file, pull out the text from those specific labels in ansible, and then use an
ansible module to update the Cloudflare DNS record to match the IP address with the DNS entry that
that I'm looking for. So that's one of the things that we've done is the the website has moved from
jupyterbroadcasting.net. Now it's at new.jupyterbroadcasting.com, N E W, new.jupyterbroadcasting.com.
And there it will stay until we're MVP version 1.0, whatever you're calling it. Once it's in
production, obviously, that will turn into jupyterbroadcasting.com. The other thing that
we've done is automated using GitHub actions. So for those that aren't familiar, GitHub actions is
a free continuous integration platform that's kind of built into GitHub. It's honestly has made
tools like Jenkins almost kind of irrelevant overnight for projects like ours. So you know,
I mentioned Linux server a few minutes ago, but but back when I was involved in that project,
we had our own Jenkins server that was had remote workers at team members houses and it would SSH
in and run jobs on their, you know, Raspberry Pi's, for example, to build Pi images and super neat
stuff. But let's be honest, that's kind of a pain in the bum. And so what GitHub actions gives us
is the ability to run jobs on their infrastructure. And, you know, GitHub's owned by Microsoft,
so everything runs on Azure. So it's, it's reasonably performant. And most importantly,
it's free. So why wouldn't we use it? It's not completely open source. That's one argument.
But free and open ish. I don't know. I think it's fine. And not, not irreplaceable either,
to be honest, Alex, like we if we needed to eventually change where we build the site at it,
it would take us an evening, right? It's not the end of the world. So here's the thing we were
we're building this Hugo site, and it's 20,000 pages, I think 20, just nearly 21,000 pages at
this time. On my MacBook Pro, which is one of the M one chips, it takes nine seconds to build the
website. Nine seconds. But I want it now. However, what we're doing is building it on one of the
Linode boxes that we use for the self hosted infrastructure. And this box is hosting quite
a few things. Now, actually, it's hosting the new JB website. It's hosting our notes infrastructure,
our notes infrastructure. So hedge doc is up there. There's a bunch of stuff. There's probably
a spin. Yes. Yeah, there's probably about, I don't know, 15 or 20 services up there,
between all the various things, and just throwing another nginx container on there hosting a Hugo
site is absolutely no sweat for this thing. What does make it break a sweat, though, is building
the Hugo website. So when it's building the site, it's engaging all four cores of this box, and it
takes 44 seconds. So not the nine seconds of an M one MacBook Pro, but 44 seconds is still pretty
good enough. Faster than I could have manually created the WordPress post and posted the episode
still. So that's something. And the real nice thing about it is as part of the workflow that
happens in the GitHub action, everything happens declaratively and sequentially. So you say,
right, first of all, I want to clone the new code onto the onto the box. And then I'm going to SSH
into the box and do we're using a make file, which is another thing I'll touch on in a minute that
we simplified. It builds the website, and then only once the build is successful, does it actually
pull down the old container and replace it with the new one. So the downtime when it performs an
update is about a second or two, which I think is perfectly acceptable. Now, something I alluded to
a moment ago is the make file updates that we've done. The version that was there before was a
Brent confided in me that the the chap that submitted those changes had never written a make
file make file before and did pretty good considering indeed. However, I think the thing,
one of the principles I like to apply to this sort of project is simplicity is best keep it simple,
stupid, you know, and the make file that was there was trying to do a couple of things it was
trying to cater to local build environments and also Docker build environments. And so
we've taken the decision to just standardize on Docker as the build environment for everything.
That way, people across all architectures, all servers, all places, you know, it doesn't matter
where you know exactly which version of Hugo you're running, you know, exactly which encapsulated
version of libraries you have, etc, etc. So hopefully, it should make things for people
across the world who want to contribute to this thing easier to contribute to, or move it if we
ever needed to move it to a new server or new location to absolutely yeah. And then we were
talking about well, where once we've built the site, do we push it to a Docker registry somewhere
like Docker hub or GitHub container registry or GitLab or, or any, you know, there's lots of
options. And ultimately, because of the way we've we've actually decided to do it, we're just SSH
ing into the server using the GitHub action, fetching the latest changes from Git doing the
build, and we don't actually push an image to a registry at all. Yeah, simplicity. I mean, there
were some great ideas of how to accomplish that. And many of them had multiple parts. And I think
landing on simplicity is going to be good for future proofing this thing. Again, it keeps costs
down, it makes the deployment time faster. And we don't actually need versioned artifacts of the
website. If you think about it, we already have that by the commits in the repo. Yeah, that's
true. That's actually really nice. That's one of the things I love about this system. That's great.
And I also feel like I have to be more accountable. Like I have to explain my changes now too,
because you got to say what you know, what is this commit about? I'm like, well, here's what I'm
updating and why I'm doing it. And I never did that before with the WordPress website. I'll tell
you that it's sometimes bugging with start working, stop working, you never knew what was happening.
That's the thing, right? I mean, there are several principles in software development, which we're
trying to inject into this project. One of which is feature branches. So any new feature for the
website goes to feature slash name of feature, you know, let's say update host, image, whatever it
is. And then that goes through a peer review process. So any changes that make it to production
are now automatically built and applied by the user. And that's a really good thing.
Now automatically built and applied, but only once they've been reviewed by two or three people,
whatever the processes we land on looks like. And then for infrastructure changes, we have a similar
thing. So it'd be infra slash, you know, update IP address, for example, that kind of thing. And
then myself, maybe in ways or Brent could review that and, and merge that stuff. So yeah, and you
did create a separate repository for the infrastructure stuff. I think that's an important
distinction as well. Yeah, I mean, didn't actually create it was actually the old self hosted show
GitHub organization. And we've migrated that info repo across. So the really nice thing about doing
it this way is I haven't really had to build hardly anything at all, all the code was already there.
And I've been using it to manage my personal infrastructure for the last five or six years.
And so it's pretty battle tested. There's a there's a couple of there's a couple of things in
it that I know how it works. And I'll document those things. But for the most part, it's,
it's all in the make file. So I have a question in terms of performance. So we have it on a
linode box. One advantage that scale and scale engine had as a host is Alan builds a CDN and he
puts a lot of the PHP files and the CSS files and the image files across this CDN, which
theoretically helps with performance, although I think performance has not been fantastic,
because the the flaw has been the database isn't super fast, it all has to connect to that database.
So what are we doing for performance in terms of like global audience and reaching this all
in one linode box and that kind of stuff? Right now diddly squat. Yeah, right now. Well, yeah,
it's a we should be clear right now. It's a test site. It's a development site.
But we would like people to look at it new dot Jupiter broadcasting.com.
There were some ideas floated in the GitHub around using s3 to host the Hugo site rather than a
container ran into some issues, which we may be able to work around some other way. I don't know
yet, but it took about 17 minutes to upload the website to an S three bucket versus the less than
one minute to build and deploy it as a container. Now, I am a cloud flare noob. I've only just
recently accepted cloud flare into my life after resisting for a long time. But I know you're more
familiar with it, Alex. But I'm, I'm pretty sure there's some some caching tricks we could do at
the cloud for cloud flare level as well, too, right? They do have a proxy service, which
should help protect us against things like D doses, as well as provide us with more of a CDN style
caching layer. And since it's a flat file site, maybe that's sufficient. Yeah, in theory. But the
issue is when you enable the caching button on cloud flare, it changes the IP addresses. So you
end up being low balance between a couple of things. And then the headers don't quite route
properly. And I haven't quite figured that out yet. And if anybody is an expert on that, please
jump into there's a GitHub issue open for this issue. Right now, come and help me figure it out,
please. I could see that being one problem, especially on release day. You know, that was an
issue we had before is on release day, this site would get slammed for the first few hours and then
file, you know, this page doesn't load and stuff like that. Now the files will be hosted on a
different CDN for the mp3s and whatnot. So that'll help because the cloud flare released I can't
remember what it's called our two, I think as like a layer that sits in front of s3 and caches
everything there. So maybe in time, that's something we can investigate. But for the MVP,
I think we'll stick with what we've got. Yeah, I mean, there's also a lot of ways we could pull
that off. Because we could also use linodes object storage, and maybe it builds on that
Linode and then it uploads to object storage, and then our two sits in front of that or something
like that. I mean, there's a lot we could play with. But I think we'll have to just get a feel
for how the performance is, because the component that I don't really know, and I'm sure was always
a factor in the past, was the database, I think, for us, the bottleneck was when people would come
to the website after like Linux unplugged came out, or Linux action show came out, the database
would just get absolutely slammed with page loads. And then you're generating that WordPress page,
every single time the page generates, even with some of those caching plugins, there's still a
lot you're dynamically generating. Not a problem with Hugo, of course. Another issue you've got to
solve for with s3 is TLS certificates. So the s3 object storage that Linode provide, they provide
an out of the box TLS certificate for linodeobjects.com, whatever the bucket name is.
But you would then have to figure out how to configure your own Jupiter broadcasting.com
TLS stuff. Right, right. And at the moment, with the containerized version that's deployed,
that's all handled through traffic and let's encrypt. Yeah, I mean, maybe that'll be performing
enough. We'll just see, right? I mean, I would prefer to leave all the s3 stuff out if we don't
need it because it just keeps it simpler. I guess we'll find out when this episode releases, huh?
Yeah, we just need more people trying it. Mini stress test. Yeah, we just got to build more
traffic and then because when we flip it live, what I'm thinking is eventually we just start
de-emphasizing the fireside pages and we stop sending people to the individual fireside pages
and we start sending people to jupiterbroadcasting.com slash office. Just one
great place to go. So and then we'll start sending more and more of the traffic back to
our main site again because we've spent the last three and a half, four years sending people to
our fireside pages because that's where we could really apply leverage at that time.
But this is a way better setup. So thank you for all the work on the info guys. I feel like we're
in a way better position to go live now, but also we're in a better position to maintain it over the
long term as well. So it's good to be figuring that out before we've even gone into production.
Everything is in git and everything is in for his code, which just gives me the warm fuzzies, you
know? All right. Thank you gentlemen for coming into the office. I appreciate your time. Appreciate
you being here. Brent, where do we want to send people that are listening if they want to
participate? Yeah, I think we'll put a few links in the show notes, but a good place to go. If
you just want to see what the heck we're talking about, new.jupiterbroadcasting.com and I think
our Jupiter broadcasting GitHub page is probably the place to go. So now is the time to really put
this thing through its paces and a mini Mac, you had a suggestion regarding the GitHub aspect of
this and how you can actually integrate GitLab too if one wants. Yeah, indeed. In fact, so for
those who don't want to use get because it's owned by a company that you don't want to mention your
name. So all the GitLab users know that they have the possibility to create their own homepage on
GitLab hosted on GitLab. And there is a possibility to in fact deploy a Hugo website similar to
Git actions within GitLab. So you are limited to these GitLab homepage service, but you can in fact
do the same thing as you do now on Jupiter broadcasting. You can do it in combination with GitHub
and then have your own GitLab homepage based on Hugo and then you can just redirect your favorite
domain to that GitLab homepage and you're good. I don't really have an excuse, but I feel like we
don't give enough plugs for Git T as well, which is also a GitHub alternative. Doesn't necessarily
do some of the stuff we're talking about right now, but Git T is also a great solution. I've heard
really good things about Sourcehead as well. Oh yeah, I noticed Git T also just has an app you
can one click install an umbral now. I bet you they got a Linode something something or other.
I bet you they got a Linode something something one click as well. In fact, I want to say holler
over to Linode. Linode.com slash Jupiter. Linode is investing right here in office hours because
they want to invest in the community. I mean this isn't like come on this isn't going to be
JB's biggest show and Linode is savvy enough to know that. But they also know that the community
is worth investing in that it pays dividends and that's also why they're making our road trip
possible again this year. So go to Linode.com slash Jupiter and get $100 in 60 day credit over
at Linode and you support the show. It's where we host everything that we do publicly now. Linode
also has a bunch of really nice advanced features. They support Terraform, Kubernetes, Ansible. They
have a really clean simple API that already has a bunch of pre created libraries for Python and for
Rust and for all the things. They also have a command line client that is choice. I really
love that. In fact, a little pro tip. Install the Linode command line client on your actual Linode
machine, right? So then when you're SSH into your Linode box, you could create a snapshot
of that very box on that box before you do a system update. Just take it to the next level,
guys. It's really easy. And of course, they have great things like S3 compatible object storage,
which you could always use as the seed for, I don't know, R2. And then you could just like
have the most insane great CDN with incredible reach at great prices. Oh, and by the way, Linode
30 to 50% cheaper than the hyperscalers out there. But there's a lot of ways you can host,
but none of them are as good as Linode. They've got the best support. They got the best performance.
They got 11 data centers and nobody else invests deep into the community, into the media,
into the events, into the projects, even into things like road trips that just connect
all of us together. Who else is doing that? Nobody. So go to Linode.com slash Jupiter.
Support the show. Say thanks for your support and get that $100 to mess around. It's pretty fun.
Linode.com slash Jupiter. And you know, we like it because we're rebuilding this whole thing from
scratch. We could have hosted this stuff anywhere. You know, we could have put it anywhere and we
went with Linode. We choose Linode over and over again. You know, like a good marriage with your
loved one where you choose to be their partner over and over again. We choose Linode over and
over again. Linode.com slash Jupiter. Speaking of Linode, you know what else we have hosted on
Linode? What's that? Our massive matrix server. Oh yeah. Alex was showing me just how massive
that server is and it's a lot of triple digits is all I saw. Yeah. Yeah. You know, you don't
need the 96 gigs of RAM to run matrix, but it helps. You know? How many cores? I think it's
got 48 cores or something like that. It's, you know, here's the problem. You know where you
end up using all 48 cores is if you have 40 people logging in at once because every time a user logs
in and sinks their element client, it pegs one of the cores to a hundred percent. So if you have
a dozen people logging in at once, that's a dozen cores locked up. They can't do anything else.
And so ultimately we're like, well, there's a lot of ways we can solve this and we need to make this
better and we need to use workers better. There's a lot still to do, but there is a way we can just
throw hardware at this and it will survive. And the server has been great. It's been, and the
community is continuing to grow. We just launched another matrix room that we wanted to let people
know about. It's for the Ohio Linux Fest that's coming up in December, December 2nd and 3rd.
You can find out info at olfconference.org. We'll have a link in the notes.
And this has been a thing that's happening more and more. And we just want to encourage the hell
out of it. Somebody contacted us and said, Hey, I'd like to organize my own meetup with fellow
Jupiter broadcasting listeners in the Columbus area. So we said, that's a great fricking idea.
So we created the Columbus club. So if you'd like to join our matrix room and coordinate
for our Linux Fest meetup in Ohio, you can go to bit.ly slash Columbus club.
And there's already people in there organizing right now. It's already happening.
I noticed a bunch of venue suggestions. It's like months away. It's amazing.
Didn't we said we would set something up, but did we actually tell anybody?
Like did they just find it? I think we only mentioned it in Linux and plugged quickly.
And I think it was only on the pre pre show or something crazy like that. Well, it's a thing.
It's official bit.ly slash Columbus club. And another shout out for Ohio Linux Fest.
I really enjoy it. I've only made it once. And it was like before two of my children were born,
but I really enjoyed it. And I think it's a great crew out there. And it's going to be
at a brand new venue this year. The brand new Tower of Hilton Columbus downtown hotel.
I don't know if that's a good thing or not, but new seems nice.
I'm not sure it's completely done being built. I heard rumors in our little room that they were
finishing some stuff. Really? That is a new hotel. Well, I mean, it's in December, so a brand brand
new. It's got that new hotel smell. Either way, I love a brand new hotel. I really wish I could go.
There's so many events this year that it just hasn't worked out for me. And it's really stinging
me in my, you know, my my missing events open wound. Your events feels, you know, if this goes
well, you know, I think we could have a meetup room for every major city, like some in Europe.
Why not? We've got one already. I think we should have some more. I shouldn't say this,
but I got to document it while I'm thinking about it. But I shouldn't say it while we're
in the middle of this project. But we need a website. We need a website. People can go
and organize meetups. It's not meetup.com. We need something specifically for J.B. audience
members to sort of self organize in their areas. So you're feeling like these matrix rooms maybe
aren't quite enough. And so I'm curious of the future. I think they're supplemental, right?
They're supplemental to meeting a meetup organized because you could have most people would use the
Web page and they'd have some people that want to help organize the details or have questions.
They join the matrix room like like you have with the regular meetups. But this would be one
specifically for Jupiter broadcasting members to create their own. I know there are a few
open source like options, meetup alternatives, let's call them. I wonder if we can embed
something like that. Me, too. I wonder if anybody out there knows. I believe the the no agenda show
had a community member create the no agenda meetups page at no agenda meetups dot com.
And then you can either find a meetup or submit a meetup. I don't know exactly how it works. I've
never done it, but it seems like it's a tool that's built specifically. Maybe maybe it's
forked. I don't know. I can't really tell looking at it, but it's it's for their community to self
organize and do their own meetups. And maybe that's taking it too far, but it seems like that's
the next step. I'd really I encourage this kind of thing because number one, if these things
started picking up momentum every now and then we could drop in like rock stars like, hey, what's
up, everybody? Brent's here. Just a surprise visit. Yeah. Right. I think that'd be pretty great.
So anyways, but it starts it starts with just a good old community chat room,
bit dot l y slash Columbus Club. If you have suggestions for other areas, if you're interested
in starting to meet up in your area, let us know. What do you think? Should they just hit us up on
Matrix? How should maybe boost it in? What, Brent? So many options. Um, it's a good question,
you know, and it brings me to the idea of, like, feature requests. And we've been trying to figure
out a good place for that. But I feel like any official channel, like if you want to send it into
one of the email addresses, I think you could probably go to new dot Jupiter broadcasting
dot com slash contact. There's a contact form there. That'd be a good way to do it.
It seems on topic. Otherwise, just hit us up somehow. But keep it brief, please.
It's time to get to some of the great boosts that have come into the show. And man, did we get a
bunch of great boosts. We got a stack of boosts. We got a boost bank that's busting. Last week,
we talked about why we didn't trust crypto and how there's crypto. And then there's Bitcoin.
And we talked a little bit about the future of boosts and how we're considering keeping the
segments tight and flowing and all of that. We got a lot of responses. So we are going to
consolidate some of the boosts. So if your boost doesn't get directly read this week, I 100%
promise you we did read it. We went through all of them before the show. We're just kind of pairing
it down a little bit for reasons that I think will become clear as we go along. So Bradley,
why don't you kick us off with our first from Mr. Castaversa? Sure. Rusty Castaversa wrote in
thousand cents. Getting involved with crypto in general is hard, and I don't trust things that
make it easier. I also don't want to give my ID. And thanks to your suggestion of Fountain,
I earn SaaS through listening and can send them back without giving up what I consider to be
private info. I think this is great that Rusty is thinking about the privacy and the KYC stuff so
that know your customer regulations are just kind of like what you got to do if you're going to be
a financial institution in the US. It's not necessarily this way outside the US, although
I imagine it's probably pretty similar. It's got to be similar up in Canada, right? Yeah,
I believe it totally is. Welcome to the West, where we're going to track all of your financial
info just in case you might be a terrorist. And so if you don't like that, and I can understand
why you wouldn't, because you don't necessarily want to have your ID attached to a Bitcoin address,
then I recommend RoboSats. You need the Tor browser, but RoboSats is fantastic. Just take
your time with it. You can anonymously buy Bitcoin. You find a seller. You can read reviews
about the seller, and then you pick the one that supports the payment method you want. Maybe you
want cash. Maybe you want to check. Maybe you want PayPal. Maybe you want cash app. Maybe you want
whatever Apple Pay. RoboSats will let you do that, and then they'll help you escrow it and make sure
everything's safe and good to go. And it's all done over the Lightning Network. So the privacy
is just absolutely outstanding. It's how I'm going to be buying all of my long-time holding
Sats going forward. As far as spending money goes, like the ones I'm just buying right now,
as far as spending money goes, like the ones I'm just boosting around town like a maniac,
I think Strike's fine for that, because you're sending it over the Lightning Network. They're
going into a node wallet. They're getting mixed with everybody else's. And then shout out to
Fountain. In the last three months, I have earned 36,084 Sats. That is not trivial. Yeah, just by
listening to podcasts. That is impressive. I play their game. I listen to some of the supported clips
and the popular clips, but I don't mind that. I would have done that anyways. And I boost and
support some of the clips and that helps you earn more. And then I've also referred some friends
and that helps you earn more as well. But that's 36,000 Sats in the last three months. And I can
just send those around to different shows that I listen to without ever buying anything. All I'm
doing is just listening. Getting paid for what you already do. Al Carney wrote in with 1,024 Sats.
From my limited understanding, Lightning is not Bitcoin, but rather a layer on top of it.
I would assume that the extra convenience comes at the cost of fewer protections from bad actors
that the slower moving blockchain would provide. This is a good question, Al Carney, because in
blockchain world you can have fast and less secure and you can have decentralized and more secure,
but then you get slower. And so that's kind of the trade off. Lightning is sending Sats. It is Sats
that are being sent over the Lightning network. It's not a derivative. And Lightning does its
finalization on the Bitcoin blockchain. So all the transactions that are finalized are using
Bitcoin and the security in there. The reason why you can send them instantly, you don't have
to wait for the blocks to get processed, is because Lightning is based around channels.
These channels open up between nodes directly and they lock funds, it's called liquidity,
into these channels. And so if you want to send a 5,000 Sat boost, we need to have a channel that
has at least a 5,000 Sat capacity that the two ends have agreed to. Because those Sats are locked
to that channel and that's been settled on the blockchain, you can actually use that to move
these around. And so you get instant settlement with Lightning, it's private, it's peer to peer,
and it's actually using Sats and it's inheriting the security of the layer one blockchain,
which is Bitcoin. So Lightning is layer two, rides on top. It's a beautiful system.
And it's, I think, one of the bigger innovations that's coming out of Bitcoin and it'll eventually
be used for other things besides Bitcoin, I would imagine. And we have some pretty good
channels open with some important players too, don't we? Yeah, we have like a big million Sat
channel open to Fountain FM, so people, if they're using that app, boost directly in.
I got a channel open to your nodes, so you get a split on office hours. And instead of having to
route all around the network and take those little tiny fees, which are like fractions of a penny,
you just get it directly from my node. In fact, when I look at my stats, I see it all the time.
My node is communicating directly with your node, nobody in between us. A boost comes in,
it lands on our node, you get part of the split and our node helps route it. It's so great.
Node to node network.
Yeah, it is. It's one big happy node network. We got a row of McDucks. That's 22,222 Sats from
Marcel. Thank you kindly. He says, it's easy to dismiss RHEL when 99.9% of all the distros out
there are HANA Montana Linux. I don't think any amount of Sats should automatically get a message
onto the show either, by the way. It should just be based on the quality of the comment.
You shouldn't be able to advertise your own thing for a thousand Sats, for example.
You know, as a team, Marcel, we have been kicking this around because we want to keep the
productions tight. We don't necessarily want to run long every single week. And we've been floating
around different ideas. One idea we're currently having is we'll just read the top four boosts in
every show. And the top is just in terms of comment quality, not necessarily Sat amount. We'll read
the top four boosts every show. And then we'll also read the baller boosts in the show. So you
get your baller boosts read and otherwise we'll just read all of them because we read 100% of them
and we'll just pull forward the top four is what I'm thinking. And I don't know, it's new. Maybe
it's a practice we should try here first. It seems like something we'd probably want to standardize on
all the shows just to make it consistent. What are your thoughts, Brent? Yeah, I think it's actually
a surprisingly good problem to have. You know, I remember months ago we were just trying this out
for for the first time and we weren't sure if this was going to take off. But clearly it has and
people are loving it. There's like, you know, so many little games and like nifty little inside
jokes and stuff. I love that about the boosts. But, you know, we don't want the shows to be like
just boosts. I think that would actually take away from the content we've been working so hard to
produce. So, yeah, I think we should try it. This show is a good way, you know, a good place to try
that stuff. But it doesn't mean we're going to land on the right solution right away. So keep
sending in your suggestions and I guess your opinions in this case. Let us know what you
think of the top four idea plus baller. Top four plus baller boosts read on each show. Let's,
if we can remember, let's try it next office hours and see how it goes. And, you know,
boosting your feedback because we're just kind of figuring this out. This is the show where we run
with scissors for sure. DFJ 225 boosts in with eight thousand one hundred and ninety two sets
coming in hot with the booth. I love that one. He says, I appreciate the boost and the crypto
conversation last week. I can see the positives with Bitcoin and podcasting and other independent
efforts. But guys, I think it's hard to separate out the use cases from all the other, quote,
crypto bros who are hyping things up in order to just make a profit. And they largely look at
Bitcoin as just an investment vehicle. Sadly, I think it's hard to stand out from this noise.
To me, this is a key difference from the early days of Linux. The hype was not from people
looking to get rich quick. I agree and disagree, DFJ. I think you were probably just hanging out
in the in the good crowds. There was in the late 90s, in the early aughts, a mad gold rush
in corporate Linux. And there was a culture shift where we stopped calling things free software
and we started using the term open source more. And then it kind of became like this big deal
when different companies would start switching to the use the word open source. Like when Red Hat
did it, it was this big upset in the community. Oh, they've gone so corporate. And there was
a genuine gold rush. The story of how Linux got to the X86 server market is a fascinating one
and maybe one we should dig into someday just for like a little bit of, you know, context, I suppose.
Revolution OS isn't bad to check out. It's on YouTube. And I'll have a link in the show notes
to kind of just give you an idea of how far things have come from those early radical thinkers
to today's corporately deployed and managed Linux. There was a huge gold rush in the early days of
Linux. And, you know, I think a lot of us in the desktop and just enthusiast space managed to stay
fairly well insulated from that, just like those Bitcoin stackers who are just stacking sats and
staying humble and going to work every day. They're not really making a big deal about it.
That's that's a huge percentage of the Bitcoiners out there. Fryer Tech boosted it with 2000 sats.
He's going to send in an email, too. But, you know, he had a message for those who are experiencing,
quote, boost fatigue. And this is not our message. This is a message from Fryer Tech. But I think
I feel like Fryer Tech at some point has been a business owner. He writes, I hope someday you have
the luxury of running your own business where the hours of work never end. You have to ensure you
deliver a quality product to your customers and you have to make it a safe space and place for
your employees to thrive. If you feel like you're hearing too much about how you can keep supporting
a business that you kind of depend on every day, maybe you don't realize how much value for value
is actually helping you. Stop complaining, Karen. Spicy. There's, you know, a bit of I had this
realization, too, like I think I know what somebody's job is like or what an industry is like.
And then this is like when, for example, I became an IT contractor for doctors and lawyers and an
airline. And I thought I knew what those businesses were beforehand. And then I get inside and I
realize I knew 10 percent. They end up spending way more time on stuff I never knew about.
And the cost to run a business, you can never understand how wildly expensive and ridiculously
costly it is to run a business until you've run one, especially here in the States right now.
It's incredible. So I appreciate the sentiment, Friar Tech. Thank you very much. You know,
it's not our audience's problem, though. We just try to produce a great product, give them something
that they want to support. And the ones that get it that do participate in the value for value
system, they are so, so critical to the, you know, the long term survival of both the network, but
also our passion and our enthusiasm, because when we do see somebody get it and they're contributing
to the website or they're sending in a boost or maybe they're sharing the show with somebody,
you know, or they're participating in a live stream in a way that contributes value. It's like
that's what keeps us going. That's what makes us keep going after 15 years. And so the people who
do get it are super valuable to us. Dylan wrote in with three thousand five hundred cents.
Boost, you know, actually, as an aside, this is Brent. I feel like Dylan wrote in and mentioned
how to pronounce their name and I totally forget. So apologies. Sorry. OK, here we go with the
boost. Fun fact, you have to be invited to a matrix space to enjoy it. So unless JB provides a link
to it on, say, their site, you can't reach it. I can browse the rooms on your server in an app,
but it's not as great, in my opinion. Yeah. So a space. Let's back up a little bit. A space
space is kind of what it sounds like. It's an area, a place to organize all of your other rooms.
So we've got rooms for the shows and different meetups and Bitcoin and all that stuff. And so
you need one directory to organize it all. That's what a space is. And so we have a Jupiter broadcasting
space where you can get an overview of all of our matrix rooms when you go to bit dot l y slash
Jupiter Colony. But better than that, we're going to have the matrix linked. We're going to have
the mumbling. We're going to have all this stuff linked on the new website. In fact, it's already
there if you want to check it out. Heck, yeah. New dot Jupiter Broadcasting dot com. Peter wrote in
with 5000 sats boost. You guys get it. Crypto equals scam. Those initial feelings of distrust
is a healthy sign of a critical mind. I think people should be critical of this stuff as well.
And I hope that our position that Bitcoin is not like the rest of crypto will be the signal through
the noise long term. Yeah, I think that critical mind and the distrust is good. But I think I also
think there's some really cool technology behind like, say, Bitcoin and lightning and some of the
open source projects happening there. So I think I would suggest, you know, be cautious, but also
stay curious and go check those out. They're worth they're worth looking at. True Grits wrote in 6000
sats coming in hot with the boost every time. I love that one. I'm very much not tired of the boosts
nor of the sound bites. I very much enjoy them. Fountain is getting better and better and better
as a podcast player. And many of the early bugs have been well sorted out. Are there chapter
markers set for the beginning and the end of boosts? Maybe if people are tired of them, they
could just skip them. Absolutely. In fact, Drew goes to the hard work of chapter in every single
boost individually. And might I add very creatively and hilariously sometimes, which I appreciate.
Yeah. We got a double boost from true grits satellite sets. You mentioned that the boosts
have a split that goes to Brent. How? How does that work? How about the SAT streams? Does that
get split with Brent as well? Yeah, it's the same system. So when you boost in in one boost a gram
with a sum or you just stream on the back end, that's all the same splits because it just goes
by what we define in the RSS feed. So the part of podcasting 2.0 amongst the many features it's
bringing to podcasting is a value tag that you add to the RSS feed. And in there you just say,
you know, this X amount, this percent goes to this person, this percent goes to this person,
this percent goes to this person. And it automatically figures it out if you're
doing a one time big boost or you're doing a stream in the back end. It's all the same tech.
And what's beautiful is because the lightning network is so cheap for transactions, you could
actually do one, two, three sats at a time and that still works. So Chris, the way I understand
that the lightning network works is on these lightning invoices. So whenever you send a
certain amount of sats, it automatically creates an invoice. Is that how these streaming works?
That doesn't seem very efficient. Generally, the way it would work is for you to send me sats,
right, you would invoice me and then I would scan the invoice like with a mobile app. It would just
auto fill the information and it would send you those sats. And it's nice and quick,
but it doesn't actually have to be invoice based. The lightning spec does allow for just sending,
just spraying sats in a direction as well without qualifying them. Yeah. Here you go. Here's some
sats. Yeah. But you know what? It's great for these types of things because you could also see
how like you could use it for car rentals, scooter rentals when you're in a city. Oh,
that is a great idea. Nice. Yeah. I could see it go in places, Brent. I really could. All right.
We got 2,222 sats, a row of ducks from hashtag reckless. He says a cold shower in Raleigh is more
like a warm shower. Really? Let's be honest. So true. We both were talking about our cold showers.
I did get the water heater fixed Thursday last week. You know, it's been, I think over here,
it's been three, two, at least two weeks now, maybe three of trying to get contractors over here on,
on, on some kind of home warranty that Alex is trying to take advantage of. And it's,
it's not fixed and they're all back now. So you're all taking cold showers while we're taking
somewhat warm showers occasionally. You know, it's, it's actually kind of embarrassing for
the contractors. Alex had a firm talking with them this morning, so we'll see what happens.
Oh, maybe something will happen. You know what? This is just prepping you for hashtag van life
where these kinds of things happen on the regular. You're just getting ready. I think,
I think I, I much prefer getting my own hands dirty and being responsible. Yeah, really.
Hashtag reckless says, I had some thoughts about donating versus buying too. He writes,
I donate as a member because I want to support the show and I'm buying the ad free feed. I boost
because it's fun and I'm buying a potential shout out on a future show. Possibly this is another way
to reframe the buying versus donating argument. A thousand sat boost minimum would probably make
sense or something more. He says maybe even 10,000 sats, but I want to back up the part that I liked
that I thought made a lot of sense. I boost because it's fun and I'm buying a potential
shout out on a future show. I donate because I want to support the show and I'm buying
the ad free feed. That's a really smart way to look at it. Yeah, it's a neat way to frame things.
And, uh, I really appreciate that perspective as well. Got me thinking. Optimus Gray boosted
in with a row of Mcducks. That's 22,222 sats. This old duck still got it. Brent, I hope you're
ready for the cottonwood cleanup at the studio. There's still cleanup to do. There is some,
it's much better. Chris. There is some, it's, it's fine. It's fine. It's fine. Um, I'm purging
some of my non JB podcast and I've been thinking about unfollowing any podcaster that does the
dynamically inserted ads. Guys, I'm getting Spanish ads from an English podcaster. Why?
The podcast is okay. I mean, it's no JB. It's okay. But I'm thinking about maybe we should
just start unfollowing the podcasters who have the auto inserted ads. You know, this is, this is
probably going to cause some backlash. People are going to hate this stuff, especially if they're
coming in in a different language. You know, one thing I've noticed since being here at Alex's,
cause he's got all these gizmos is he's got this fancy system on his television that skips ads on
the YouTube, uh, I guess app that he's got on there. Yeah. It's like a separate app. That is
crazy. Cool. I don't quite know how it works on the like, yeah. Tell me how it works. You know,
it's crazy, right? Because I, it even skips like their Patreon plugs. It skips their swag plugs.
It, it skips when they're asking for likes. And of course it skips the ads because it's community
contributed. I, people watch and then that also use this extension or this app and then they
contribute it in real time. And then so by the time you sit down, which, you know, after video
has been up for a little bit, everybody's filled out all the info and you sit down to watch it.
And it just, it glides over all of that stuff. That is amazing. I mean, this is,
if this thing took off, it would screw YouTubers. It really would.
Well, but it, you know, if this keeps up with podcasts,
it might actually come to podcasting as well. And I wonder how that would change things.
That's why you got to be careful. And it's like with these dynamically inserted ads.
The other thing is it's how successful is that ad going to be? How good of an ad is that for
the audience? How good of a fit is it? Like the reason why Linode sponsors the show is because
Linode is a great fit for our audience. Right. And we're users of Linode and that doesn't just
happen accidentally. It's like, we analyze what we use and what we think our audience would use
and what we think is a good company and who we can feel comfortable about recommending.
And then we carefully approach that. And the dynamically inserted ads are the opposite of
that. And it just, yeah, I agree, Brent. It feels like it's going to create backlash.
And here we have Optimus Grey. Sounds like it is creating backlash.
I feel, Chris, like we're so lucky that we are super passionate about our sponsors and have been
able, you know, in great thanks to the memberships and to everyone who sends in memberships. Thank
you. It allows us to be passionate about those ads, you know, although I do have this mattress
that I just got that I want to talk about. We should, we should, we should get into this.
Let's hold on now. We'll talk about this off air. All right. If we can get a mattress,
maybe like some Squarespace and a toothbrush or something, maybe some underwear. No, you know,
I actually am super grateful for the members. And I feel like looking back over the last two and a
half, two years or so when we went independent again, I think launching the memberships might
have been one of the more critical maneuvers we made because it gave us this runway that we find
today. The ad market sucks. And the kind of kind of pitches we're getting from some of these
companies, you guys would never want to hear us do. And so the members have given us that that
insurance policy that we don't even have to be worrying about that right now. And I don't know
how bad things are going to get, but right now we're getting by thanks to our members and,
and also the support from the boosts and other people. It's just, it's just great. It really is.
Yeah. All around. It's great. It's super great. So thanks to everyone.
Cdubs boosted in with 10,101 sats, which is a binary boost. I'm thinking,
and we don't have a binary boost. Yeah. I think that's Morse code. I don't know if that's
binary. What's the difference? Yeah, I guess. Yeah. Um, but we need a binary soundbite, maybe
something from the Binars episode of TNG, but in the meantime, uh, Cdubs, you get a hard drive.
Cdubs also sent this in either using blue CLI or something based around it,
which is super geeky. He says, Bitcoin is not crypto. I sent this from my own note using a
program. I wrote myself using the hardest money ever. Well, that is impressive.
That's the other thing, right? It's a monetary network. It is both a store of value and a way
to it. It is also the remittance and payment network and it's all open source and free and
you can build stuff on top of it just like you can free software and Linux. It is so cool. He says,
I love the fact that there's no visa or PayPal that is selling my purchase history to the highest
bidder. There's no authoritarian that can just say who I can or cannot receive funds or send funds
to. And there's no fed diluting the supply. Let's go Bitcoin and let's go podcasting.
Thank you, Cdubs. Also a big thank you to Gene Bean who sent some LeetSats to say
plus one on the member chat channel ideas. Wooden501 sent in 3.5 thousand sats to say,
hey, uh, don't let the cheap boost die. Well, don't worry. We have a plan, Wooden. Tell us
what you think about the top four. And Trevdev sent in 2.5 thousand sats to say that the boosts
are his favorite way to send feedback. And we got more boosts as well. We just couldn't get to all
of them in the show, but we did try to consolidate the ones that had sort of a shared message and we
one hundred percent read all of them. Thank you, everybody. If you'd like to send a boost into the
show, go to new podcast apps dot com. You can grab a new podcast app there or maybe you don't want
to switch apps. I know like a lot of you is out there. He loves your antenna pod. Well, guess what?
There's Breeze, B-R-E-E-Z dot technology or boost CLI. All of it's listed over at
new podcast apps dot com. That's all you got to do. Grab that. Get yourself going. Don't forget,
we also have the matrix room to participate there. And then last but not least, the thing that you
always got to check out is that Web page where we got the links, the subscribe feed and the contact
form and office hours dot hair. And then Brantley, why don't you give them one good solid plug for
the new website? And then I think we're out of here. Yeah, I'm going to do a plug for Podverse.
I think their embedded player on the on the website has been amazing and you can do some
cool stuff with that thing like chapter support is right there on the Web page, which is awesome.
So if you want to check that out, go to new dot Jupiter broadcasting dot com. Give it a try.
Try to break it and we'll fix it hopefully before launch. Now is the time to dog food. So let us
know what you think. And with that, we're all done. Thank you, everybody, for joining us on
this week's office hours. And that's it. You got to get out of here. I need this room back.
The office hours are closed.