hello freak bitches welcome to another episode of the bro joke and experience
and on this episode I welcome my friend who's difficult to describe fascinated
by him and I hope you'll be too and he is weird and brilliant and sometimes
totally insufferable I'm gonna jump ahead just a little bit because the
intro goes on for a bit it's always good to see you buddy I'm so happy you came
on man yeah it's great to be on the show your audience is just so different from
your normal Apple users and that's a good thing it's cool well you know I was
an Apple user way before I did this show I've been a fan of yours Macintosh since
the 1980s hmm haha well you know we just kind of
figured that out even though Apple is big it's still like half a percent of
the total users people who listen to your show are a different group they're
weird well that's good so you must be a fan of the show then right I am I am a
fan I mean it's nice to sit back in the car and listen to you ran I've always
liked you well uh appreciate that what do you think of that what is what is
your takeaway from that crazy clip something feels wrong and I can't quite
pinpoint it well one thing that's wrong is that Joe Rogan never interviewed
Steve jobs yeah that's obvious but I'm trying to think of it from the
perspective of what if you know and and I heard some weird compression artifacts
and that really gave it away for me yeah it's like the speech wasn't consistent
between words right that kind of gave it away and it didn't sound like jobs to me
I don't know if there's something about the cadence of his speed or like even
the quality of it it was totally off for me there's parts that kind of sound
like jobs but so this is you can listen to the entire thing it's a 19 minute
interview over at podcast.ai and the entire 19 minutes is generated by
artificial intelligence what about the script I wonder I think if you dig into
it they'd probably tell you they they're actually talking they're taking
suggestions and and topics for future ones because it was that the
conversational quality was kind of awkward you know what made me think of
you're my concern is is like are our days number I mean you point this thing
at the JB back catalog you could probably just generate future episodes
you know what I mean would they be better I don't know but maybe we could
take a week off it's office hours with me Chris
hello everyone we're back in the studio Brent's here hey Brent hey
mumble rooms here too hey mumble room hello we just have a few folks in there
and in the quiet listening join us on a Tuesday at noon Brent you're still here
yes somehow I'm still here is today the last day are we taking bets according to
my schedule because I happen to check it this morning first time in a few weeks
apparently I'm supposed to leave tomorrow well you got another trip to
get to as well don't you it's true I am getting home hanging out with the furry
pets my brother's pets and mine because he's doing a small trip and then a few
days later he and I are driving across Canada that's a long drive what are you
didn't get enough road trip it's like three days if you do it well really how
is that possible two drivers ah right yeah two drivers no it's gonna be
intense and we're not going across the entire thing you know we're starting in
the eastern end of BC so we're starting at one end of one of the provinces and
we're driving to northern Ontario which is not we're maybe doing a third of the
country I would say you're just a road trip pro now it's no big third of the
country it's no big whatever we're going to hang out with some family and stuff
and pick up two and a half of my motorcycles that I have there and bring
them back and then not too long after that you may be off to another event too
I almost forgot about that yeah I across much water event I think that's all we
can say at this point yeah we'll see we'll see we'll leave it at that we'll
leave it at that for now and while you're gone we'll just have that podcast
on AI bot stand in oh thanks so we'll just have it you know what's great is we
we have all of your tracks individually so we'll just have drew bundle up and
feed it to that thing and then it can just generate a Brent co-host while
you're traveling okay problem solved right yeah now we just need a way to
generate the video version of you for Jupiter tube we're gonna solve that
that sounds a little more difficult actually especially if you need it to
lip-sync with the yeah maybe maybe we could just have someone like just do
that thing where we just kind of cut your lips out we just have somebody
sitting there upside down try their best to match the generated speech should be
fine you'd be fine yeah so you're not gonna get any rest are you gonna get
some downtime while your brother's traveling I suppose yeah I guess I got
two days yeah there's somewhere but I'm also needing to repack you know laundry
and I have to start thinking about firewood for the winter because that's
my main method of eating my space and I gotta say with the trips this year I
cannot spend much yeah much attention on that I actually Alex was figuring it out
when we saw him in California and he discovered because I don't know he's
interested in my life perhaps he discovered that I've been in the US more
this year than I've been in Canada and we're slowly converting it's true yeah
we're gonna make you a native eventually well I mean I've pretty much worked out
all the A's and a boots yeah we've pretty much got rid all those I noticed
you saying I'm just trying to help you make you feel at home you know so I'm
just curious what are your impressions from the last few weeks is a bit hectic
was it was it crazier than you were expecting was it more kind of just
always things happening or was it about what you were coming in with in terms of
just how much we've been doing really since you got here yeah really I think
it's actually I had last year's trip to work with I think had I gone into this
year and not had that experience it would have been easily overwhelming last
year we did great I think we had a more relaxed schedule would you say I would
say we probably had more time in places you know like we spent it felt like a
week in Salt Lake City or four or five days at least yeah that was nice yeah
which was not the case this time I love how you thought this was gonna be the
easy trip but it turned out so hard that I swore I'd never do this again that's
how bad it was a guy who lives full-time in an RV swore he'd never do another
road trip like this again I'm done yeah it was a lot harder than I expected and
I think more grueling and I think in part because I haven't road tripped as
much so like you don't just like I guess you don't just like pick right up and do
seven-hour drive days like it's no big deal I guess you kind of have to work
your way to it and I think towards the road towards the end of the road trip I
was actually my stamina was building again just it was a little more
exhausting so I drove the RV the entire time and you and hadia traded off on the
car and so we'd get to somewhere in it and I had just been driving all day long
so I just was always kind of behind on energy and a little more exhausted and
then when we weren't driving as you know it was always a show day and often it
meant that show prep had to happen after like seven hours of driving which was
also ideal and our schedule at the best of case like when you're here in studio
and everything's working well and your home is home and not in the RV repair
shop or on the road even that schedules a little tight right you you've been
doing it for a long time but so there's this rhythm and I think throwing you on
the road with all of the mysteries that are what could happen on the road really
adds to the tension there and like you said if you're driving for seven hours
you can't really work on shows like or do business stuff oh fair and it was the
end of a quarter beginning of a quarter which is just not a great time for a
business owner to be on the road so I was having to deal with that stuff and
not always successfully that was just a matter of timing you know I think the
one thing we timed well was the weather was very tolerable the entire time and
we really I think time the bottom of gas prices you know because they were coming
back up as we were returning home and they've continued to go up as we've been
home so I think you know that was the intention of when we time this was let's
not fry ourselves and let's not bankrupt ourselves on gas we did
accomplish those two things but what I didn't think about is let's not do it at
the end of a quarter beginning of a quarter that's a business thing you just
got to think of and then what happened was we had technical challenges back here
at home base back here at the studio while we were down in California we had
failures here and that created all kinds of disruption that just sort of threw
everything in the entire manufacturing pipeline out of whack it was like a
domino effect that happened and it started really kind of minor stuff you
know things went okay for the most part but like just small thing like our
recording gear didn't work at one of the beat-ups it's like a small thing I'm
taking full blame on that one but it's it's one of those concepts which is you
know we bought a new recorder which is the same recorder we've used for years
and just grabbed an SD card the morning that we took off and never really tested
it and that broke one of my sort of cardinal rules which is test absolutely
everything even if you think it's gonna be totally fine and I was like no we're
good like we've used this a million times and that was the beginning of that
mistake I think and we got to the event and had some SD card errors and it was
the only SD card we had on hand which is also a thing no backups I have a bunch
of SD cards but I had left them in the RV yeah we were at the meetup when we
discovered the SD card is yeah and we're at the meetup and so I couldn't get any
audio with our recorder which was kind of sad because those little interviews
that I get to do with with fans are really fun yeah you did a few on your
phone which was surprisingly good considering the space but it's not no
no I think it was a bit of foreshadowing wasn't it and you know you said something
there that I realized also is we didn't properly get to test all the different
production like each show has a slightly different production line because they
have different aspects to them or the different co-hosts yeah different
requirements and we didn't test all of them before we left because again time
well you would really have to do at least a week's worth of shows yeah from
the RV pretending that the studio isn't available to you before we even left
which is just not possible just wasn't time I mean we were leaving under such a
tight timeline so you know that was our bad we didn't get a proper we didn't get
a proper pre-show pre-flight test in and so we just kind of didn't expect
problems because in fact one show like Kota radio went just fine when X action
news went fine on the road then self-hosted 80 came around and it was
one of those problems where we were having an audio issue where the audio
just sounded squelchy and yeah really clappy and also too quiet at the same
time that was the audio going out in the live stream but nowhere in any point
where we could monitor not anywhere in the studio or in my headphones could we
hear it turned out to be an issue with how our jack processing was processing
the signal from the RV but there was no visual indicator none of the VU meters
showed it and of course when you're operating a studio remotely which we
were for self-hosted it was streaming through the studio there was no visual
indication of any problems so we didn't know anything was wrong until we were
live and people were like hey you guys don't sound very good and we're like oh
what and it wasn't even the Barry White thing which we're used to yeah that
hasn't showed up in a little bit it just was unusable well and the thing that
grabbed me was it's an issue in the studio that we've never run into before
yeah of course right yeah and so it wasn't like the road gear that we hadn't
tested in a year or whatever it was the setup that gets used multiple times a
week and this is yeah we had it we had an edge case and no real explanation yet
as to why that happened we tried a series yeah yeah we have theories but we
haven't been able to fully reproduce that one and then when we were
attempting to troubleshoot that I use a tool called rusk desk one word rust desk
freaking great it is great I loved it to remote desktop tool for the win like
total team viewer killer and I rust desk into the studio machines to get things
going and I rust tested into the Reaper machine where we used to record and I
could manage the mixer through some software I had X it's called the x32
edit software so I had that up and I'm working on things I'm trying to figure
out what's going on with our cell phone studies or something wrong on the mixers
or some levels that are off and I launched the app and I import the
settings from the mixer and as it's loading the entire machine locks up and
I dropped my remote connection one of the most vital machines in the entire
recording chain it locks up and I lost communication with it for for like a
week I just until West was able to get up here and actually a kick it for me
and that really hobbled our remote production that started a whole set
series of series on series on works arounds like work around on top of work
around well and I meant you had to kind of change your expectations and the gear
that you were using in the RV as well yeah like you you kind of struggled with
having to reorganize oh yeah I had to kind of because we had to work around
the machine where we brought in the audio the machine was responsible for
bringing a remote audio I had to completely bypass it remotely it meant
we couldn't do self-hosted live we just all these things that we had to sort out
and then it really was a knock-on effect from there there in attempting to build
all the workarounds to fix that other things broke ironically you know coder
always went pretty well like I always coder managed to go fine for the most
part did them all live even didn't have to do one of them off there land went
fine well I see a pattern here every time I'm in the room there's something
to that and then we had other issues an app updated that we didn't realize it
updated and it no longer let you set the in and out audio interfaces oh I forgot
about that that was just random another issue was at one point one of the
services we use for VoIP like one of the backup ones that we go to when we're
having problems they were having their own outage and at first we weren't sure
if it was us or them like that kind of stuff was happening while we were trying
to record and then we had the absolute hardest Linux unplugged ever where after
the Pasadena meetup in the JPL tour West flew back home to fix the studio and he
got everything up and running you and I connected in from the RV back it's we
were in Sacramento at that point and I'm thinking this is gonna be easy it seemed
like everything was this is the one yeah finally we're gonna have an easy one
West is in studio he can fix the crash machine he can run the board we've got
Ethernet from Jeff you know he's hooked us up with power we're comfortable we've
got power we've got solid internet we've got West back at the HQ running the
board this is gonna be the easy one and whatever whatever that was so wrong
because we ended up having these horrible echo issues between each other
that is still sometimes in here we have to solve and again I actually believe we
thought it was at the RV because that seemed the most logical place for it to
be happening but now I'm actually suspecting it's here in the studio well
you ran into it yesterday morning with coder and I had to switch to a back of
body interface and that's what the second thing in the studio that seems
like a mystery that we've never run into before that yeah the studio setup hadn't
really changed no no no we'll have to trace that one down I think yeah so
that's a lot of fun and we have three machines in here that were built around
2017 2018 and they're just getting old and they run what 24-7 and the reason
for that is because when I when I did turn them on and off the failure rate
was even higher so and you know like things change so yeah it's sort of like
one of those problems that we're gonna have to sort out in part with some new
hardware but also just like recheck our audio chain and work through all that
but I think what I decided is no more just we've never nailed it you know like
I thought this was the road trip we were gonna nail it and it was gonna be a by
the numbers road trip we're going up and down i-5 should be simple we're not
going any further than Sacramento we're gonna have solid Ethernet setup we're
gonna have power this is gonna be the easy one in fact maybe I picked one that
was too easy it was actually what I was thinking before the road trip crazy man
I know and now afterwards I'm like I'm never doing that again and I'm gonna
rethink how we do remote shows and I think what I want to do instead is I
want to switch to doing shows at venues where ideally we'd have a low ticket
price that just enough to cover our operational costs to get us out there
and do the show and cover hotel or whatever we'd have to do or gas if I
drive it and we just do shows at venues that would you know let some lousy
podcasters in and then afterwards we do the meet-and-greet we do the food and
drink but everybody gets a chance to talk to us if they want we walk away
with show content that's been produced and then we because what we do right now
is the exact frickin opposite we travel we spend days traveling we set up a
meetup we meet up with somewhere between 30 and 100 people maybe if we're lucky
200 people and then we you know we go all out we party for like five hours with
these with these folks then we go home exhausted probably hungover and then we
have to do a show the next day and it's like well what we just we just did all
the traveling we just did all the meetup stuff we just spent five hours doing
stuff and we don't have a show and by the way when did we work on the show
it's crazy right and so we are we're constantly running full speed because we
know this enough that we know like okay we need to be working on a show we got
so we're working on meetups working on shows we're doing travel days we're
doing it all together and it's just crazy when instead we could go to a
venue we could have the meetup we could produce a show we could have an easy way
to meet and greet so everybody who comes out as an opportunity to say hi
because sometimes people travel for like 25 hours and don't even get a chance to
say hi because it's just kind of a you know everybody's just hanging out
chatting I don't know I haven't fully figured it out yet I think in part we
were doing this because there were no events there was no Linux fest for us
to go to right well I feel like when we did in Denver that was like the very
beginning of any events happening yeah and is probably partly responsible for
the great amazing turnouts that we had as well and it felt like back then that
was exactly the thing to do yeah and okay we struggled and then actually the
funny thing is everything we struggled with on that trip we salt on this trip
and never had issues with internet etc yeah yeah I know we solve it and there's
a whole new set of problems every trip mm-hmm and and we did pre-records as
well right and even then so yeah I feel like another advantage to doing this
idea that you have of doing live on the road shows is that actually as a fan
it's really fun to see the production happening I know we have peer tube
Jupiter tube and that's kind of neat but to see it in person and to see all the
moving parts and stuff is actually part of the attraction and so we've had
listeners want to you know come to the studio and or even be in jupes when we're
doing some recordings and that's just sometimes not possible right with the
how much we're juggling so I think actually doing a live show since sounds
like a lot of fun from both angles from I hadn't thought about that listeners
yeah it is kind of a behind-the-scenes thing too isn't it and I imagine now I
hope going into 2023 I hope that more of our community events are back and those
might be possible venues we could do shows at as well and so we don't really
need to be creating the venue in the show and the event so much maybe now and
instead we can kind of go to ones that are being organized by the community or
maybe people in our community in our audience know of venues in their area
that would be amenable to some lousy podcasters coming in there and talking
about geeky Linux stuff and then maybe you know we put together is some sort
of new formula we come up with for getting out there and seeing people and
doing shows on the road and keeping it interesting for us helping us reconnect
with the audience which keeps us grounded and also keeps us energized
without having to kill ourselves on these road trips and then you know for
me personally too it just puts a ton of wear and tear on my RV that I pay for
out-of-pocket personally for years because you know you damaged something
on one road trip and it breaks six months later you know who pays for that
I do right and so there's an element of that as well it's like well do I really
want to put all this wear and tear on my personal home for for this when you know
maybe there's a smarter way to do it I personally prefer to travel that way you
know I prefer to have my workspace I prefer to have my bed my bathroom I've
heard from listeners who have worked in hotels and I have heard some awful horror
stories about hotels and it makes me never want to stay in the hotel so we'll
see but you know sometimes it does seem like it would be a better way to go and
I think we should be careful like I don't want this whole conversation to
feel Debian Downer or anything because actually we had an amazing time at
every meetup that we went to and occasionally you know the morning of
or like oh we're so kind of beat that you know do we really feel like doing a
meetup right now but then we get there and it was like that was the best part
of the trip for me oh yeah every meetup was absolutely great and like way out
did expectations and everybody's amazing and and like you're drinking out of a
cup that everybody's signed right now just as a memory and I go in here too
yeah that's just been amazing it really it was it was really great and honestly
like by the time we got to Portland I was ready to quit podcasting I was ready
to quit RV and I was ready to just quit I was done and and the and the drive
through Portland was brutally grindy it was just horrible traffic and then the
meetup just flipped it all around for me yeah and so I I feel like yeah the
meetups are totally worth it we ran into a heck of a lot of trouble in other
areas having to do with the shows that we do every week which is hilarious and
lady jupes was fine too which is yeah thing we had zero mechanical issues in
either vehicles because we also took a chase car no car problems no jupes
problems jupes executed and functioned 100% and no like near accidents I
remember last year we had a close call and so from that perspective like a lot
of stuff worked but the stuff that didn't work just sometimes shadowed some
of her our emotions yeah the whole trip well and there's I think there's an
element to like I mean this sounds weird but if you get an accident there's
almost this like well what can you do what could you do well I've been there
done that right it's like it really sucks especially when it's your home but
like what can you do but when you have technical failures and gear failures and
application failures it feels like well we could have prevented that did it eat
at you in a way like that while it was happening like shit I should have did
better or because I feel like partly with all the software updates and like
random things I definitely wish we could have tested more I think what really was
rough about it just from like a psychological standpoint was a lot of
the technical issues struck after we were already live so then it's like okay
you're live you don't want to leave dead air but you also are trying to visualize
a virtual studio because the RV is a virtual studio you've got to visualize
the entire wiring of a mixer in a virtual studio in your head and then
also because I'm not here in this studio I also need to visualize the entire in
and out layout of this studio how it all works where in that layout this problem
could potentially be keep all of that state in my head troubleshoot it while
also trying to like play music or chat with the chat room or just keep
conversation going which is great when you or Wes are there and you can help
with that but and then also there's just this pressure of well the longer this is
a problem the longer people have to wait and that gets that gets to be kind of
old I have to say and when it's every single live stream for two weeks in a
row you start to get like god I'm just sick and tired of doing this you know if
you were maybe in the metaverse you could trace your trace your lines on
your virtual mixer there I think the other thing that wasn't related to show
production but did kind of tilt things towards like this has been an awful road
trip it was an awful road trip punctuated with a lot of great stuff
like Jeff and his setup and his hospitality and Brittany's hospitality
was just absolutely legendary easily the meetups were just incredible
rejuvenating motivating and then JPL the tour of JPL was something I'll remember
for the rest of my life and would like to go back every few years and do again
right so like hard road trip punctuated with a lot of greatness here and there
and so it's a weird mix but one thing I think that tilted it for me towards the
negative and it's still an issue today is my home server that runs the heating
the lighting the security system the camera system and parts of you know the
network it died and man was that bad timing just a really bad time when did
it die and oh I know when it died oh yeah oh well it died while we were in
Pasadena at the chorus at the Airbnb everything was dying where we weren't
yeah you're right it was remote failures every single time and it was just one
evening at the at the Airbnb I wasn't able to get pull up home assistant check
on jupes anymore and then my backup recovery strategy my date is fine but I
had like this pie I could swap in that didn't work you know cuz I never tested
that great idea bad execution and so this was weeks ago now two weeks ago
that this died and we still haven't had five minutes to plug an HDMI monitor in
and see what's wrong with that pie well and to make it worse we had to tear out
the entire setup out of your RV yesterday yeah before we even got a
chance to troubleshoot it we ripped it all out because I'm finally getting my
living room slide fixed and they are completely taking apart the entire slide
because they're removing the floor it's crazy and so the server had to come out
they're taking like one of the four walls out of your home yeah and then
rebuilding one of the floors in our living room and so the pie had to come
out and so we have it here in a box but I'm just gonna rebuild it my home
assistant yellow came in and I've got an idea I'm honestly I'm really tempted to
get a NUC maybe like an i5 or an i3 NUC with maybe 16 gigs of RAM something
that supports quicksync you get the right NUC and they only pull under load
like 15 watts yeah I think we we did touch on this in the last self hosted
if you want to hear more about it right yep and I think I'm gonna get one with
thunderbolt I think is the way to go with that we'll see we shall see but I
want to take a moment and I want to thank Linode for making the road trip
possible for supporting us for just being crazy like that and investing in
community Linode comm slash Jupiter go there to get $100 in credit for a 60 day
account for 60 days on a new account and go there to support the show also if
you're learning Linode has a lot of really great resources this is an area I
don't focus on a lot in the other shows but it's something I think maybe I'd
like to let you guys know about if you're curious about Kubernetes or
learning just things like infrastructures code in general maybe
terraform ansible puppet chef or salt they have an infrastructure as code
ebook series it's about 200 pages each tools covered as a standalone project
you learn a little bit about them you get a little kind of overview on how to
work it all with Docker and how to use github and work with all of these tools
it's free I don't even think you I don't even think you have to give me your
email address let me go look I don't even think Linode asked for your email
address I think they just let you download the ebook yep instant download
13 megs you don't have to give me your email address and then you get a great
great walkthrough on this stuff they have so much documentation over here
learn k8 slabs cloud simplified there's all kinds of stuff over including video
series to Linux beginner video series they also have one-click deployments so
if you've never really deployed a server before it's so easy and they make it
they've just updated their marketplace UI to make it super clear what's new
what's hot let's go try that and if you want to do something like a little more
advanced well you can go crazy like we did they'll give you documentation on
how to build it up from the metal we've got a Nix box running on Linode and I
have this crazy VPN conglomerate box that's made by a pep wave for my mobile
router and it's their own custom Linux distro and Linode makes it possible for
me to even load that and then they have s3 object storage they have a fantastic
interface an API for days that makes it really easy to integrate take snapshots
use a command-line tool go see why over a million customers worldwide love Linode
some of my friends have been using it for a decade I've been using it for
nearly three years and they have some of the best performance and some of the
best pricing Linode comm slash Jupiter that's where you go to get $100 and 60
day credit on a new account and it's a great way to support the show Linode
comm slash Jupiter and I will put a link to that infrastructure as code ebook in
the show notes in the nizzles so that way you can go grab that and you can
learn a Kate yourself on that that's some good stuff right there you know
about learning Kate and Brent I'm starting to learn a Kate about it hey
what have we learned a Kate about our website because while you and I were on
the road work continued on and the community has just been really really
sticking with it and producing some really great features some great fixes
and nice tidying up I mean there's a lot we could talk about here so where do you
want to go what do you want to focus on today yeah I feel like it's been a big
week both because I've been away from the website work in a way that first I
was really worried about and we touched on this in the last office hours but
actually now that I'm having the chance to reflect on it I feel is actually a
huge success story oh okay hold on zoom in on that for a second zoom in and
hands on that Brantley mm-hmm so I was worried that maybe the momentum would
kind of start to slow because I've been in there you know let's say helping
people accomplish amazing things I'm not the one doing the amazing things I'm
just kind of nudging and so it's kind of worried that us being on the road meant
that I could spend less time doing that and that would mean people would be less
excited about contributing but actually it's been the total opposite the
community even gave me or trying to test PRS while sitting in the front of lady
jeeps bouncing around the i5 because they're like you you're busy on the road
like let's do this when you get back about working on the website while going
down the road right right well that was my only opportunity to really check in
and you've got a pretty nice work area there but it's it's very tricky as
things are jumping and bouncing around but so I feel like a thank you for
taking care of me everyone while I was on the trip and making sure I'm a little
bit more sane and not trying to push myself too hard but also just for taking
the helm while I was gone and I promoted CG bass player this week to having some
access to do some triage and things like that congratulations space player yeah
they've been amazing at submitting some pretty great PRS in the last I don't know
a month or two even and I just thought geez there's some great people who I've
built a lot of trust with and they've been just helping organize everything
along with everyone else who's already been doing that so thank you for making
my job a little bit easier but what that's also meant is that there's some
really amazing PRS that have come in in the last week and they aren't quite I
would say they're not quite merged yet I was struggling this morning cuz I was
like we got to get these merge office hours creates a deadline you're right
Elray helped me walk off the ledge there because actually we don't want to hurry
PRS to true to talk about them what we want is actually great PRS and what's
happening is that one of them in specific is to automate the sponsors
page I made a sponsors page back in I don't know a month or two ago when we
were first going live because I thought well a good function is to be able to go
to our website when you're trying to sign up for you know Linode or something
like that and to get the URL we mentioned them in the shows all the time
and you can go to the show notes and sometimes get them but that's not always
true and having them all in one place one right right and if you also think
about this website as a platform that other podcasters could adopt one day
that's a feature other podcasters would want to that's a very good point so I
was like a monkey creating this sponsors page just with text um you know I was
copy and pasting right because I I don't know what I'm doing and that was good
enough for version one our first milestone of the website when it went
live and it looked fine but here's what I love is that I came around and I was
like geez we haven't updated that updated that in a while and so I made a
few updates you know we have some new sponsors or new links and descriptions
and stuff like that so I threw them in there but just in my PR which was just
text updated text I wrote we shouldn't do this like this again we should we
should automate this we've been talking about automating it and sure enough the
next day chance wrote up a PR to automate the whole thing and there's
been a lot of discussions and like improvements and back and forth between
community members on improving that initial PR and I think that's the real
that's exactly what we want it's like not quick PRs to be submitted to the
website to add functionality but this like constructive building of this
amazing modular piece of technology that we're gonna throw at the website and
then it'll be solid so I feel like it's maybe you know a day or two away from
being merged into our production but it's still super exciting so I want to
mention it that is a really cool thing you know people are looking at
accessibility people caught some bad links for like my my referral to
fountain there's just little things to big things right and it's stuff that we
just as a team don't put a lot of focus on because just culturally we haven't
really built that that muscle but we're bringing in what feels like a team of
people who are thinking about those things that we don't catch little stuff
that we just don't catch sometimes because we're moving on to the next
thing all the time and I think that was your real insight in in wanting to make
the website an open source project was that the listeners have a very
different perspective of even just our website yeah and we do yeah and you know
we don't I've been trying to use the website as much as possible to find
those little errors in it but we don't always you know go to our own website to
use it we have the back channels that create the content that make it to the
website right and so the listeners have been amazing at catching those things
like you mentioned yeah I love that part of it so we have more to talk about the
website I think when we get to the boost but I did know that there is a JB and a
hacktoberfest thread tell us a little bit about that good catch I heard a
bunch of listeners in the last I would say three weeks suggest that we should
participate in hacktoberfest now you and I were on the road and I was like oh
that sounds interesting I actually am not that familiar with it so I'll have
to add that to the queue of things I need to look into but it came up over
and over and over and Reese was kind enough to write an issue about it and
said hey we should just do this here's how you do it it's pretty easy so it
turns out Chris have you heard of hacktoberfest before I think I'm
familiar with at least what it used to be I'm not sure if I'm familiar with its
current iteration but I think it's a digital ocean originated idea but kind
of is just kind of the I think the idea is to encourage people to participate in
open source and there's a way you can kind of show that you've done that and
you then can get some stuff from them or you could get some stuff from them
that's about as much as I remember how am I doing I think you're doing great
okay yeah that's the whole that's the whole the pitch right there I think you
hit it you nailed it it is a digital ocean okay initiative and it turns out
it's been happening for nine years yeah that really caught me and their website
is actually super fun to browse and has a bit of that you know digital ocean
playfulness that we've seen from time to time now they've taken the spam issues
seriously I think that's probably what people if they have any kind of negative
association with hacktoberfest it's probably that there was a period of time
where it seemed to be like just generating random spam contributions
just so you could enter into the hacktoberfest drawings or whatever they
are but I think that they've addressed that with some of their measures yes so
the idea with hacktoberfest for us at least in this project which is focusing
on our website is to maybe push us to work a little bit harder to get some
contributions in for those who have been maybe thinking of participating but
haven't quite jumped in that's a great time but for us on the maintainership
side is just to look at our you know hundred-plus issues that we have and to
sort them in a way that maybe are easier to solve some of them are pretty
nebulous in their description so I've been going through and trying to make
them a little bit more well-defined so that someone can say okay I'm gonna work
on this issue and it's very well-defined I just need to walk through the steps so
I've been working a little bit on housekeeping shall we say and so if you
are thinking of participating there's a few steps and it's actually really easy
so you just need to register hacktoberfest isn't calm Chris can you
check that for me it is hacktoberfest calm so you just need to register any
time before October 31 make some pull requests or our project or any other
hacktoberfest linked topic on github or gitlab as well and have one of your PR
actually it's four of your PRs merged oh okay so it's kind of like a sign of
success I guess I see and they need to be tagged as well with hacktoberfest yeah
so that's where I come in is I've been I created some tags hacktoberfest tag and
there also needs to be a hacktoberfest dash accepted tag so I'm going to be
pretty diligent on trying to make sure that those who are participating get the
right tags that they can you know get the recognition for their work I mean I
think what I like about this is the range is pretty pretty wide like if you
don't really have a lot of skills we have some issues that are like fix a bad
URL yeah you know how to make a right good URL you could probably do things
okay and I think that's the real benefit here is that there's a ton of different
ways to contribute and so if you don't know how Hugo works like me then there
are a bunch of different ways you can help us out and I've been trying to use
issues as a way of tracking those different tasks some of them are just
like hey we need these links to be external links and here's how you do it
we just don't have time to do it so if someone wants to just sit down for an
hour and do that or even less so we will link to our hacktoberfest tagged issues
I think I have maybe at least a good handful I spent late last night while we
were walking watching Rick and Marty out of this this cup here the signed cup
from our Portland nice about that meetup meetup cup right on the one little bit
of wine a little bit of website work a little bit of Rick and Morty it was fun
and so I did tag a bunch of them I will keep trying to add more and if any
listeners have other ideas for topics that can be solved in this hacktoberfest
what would you call a window of time well yeah we will try hard to push to
make a lot of contributions in this time so if you want to participate it's
actually pretty easy we've got some links to doing that and we'd love to get
you to participate so thank you yeah the period of festing is now you must
participate during the fest window and before we completely move off the
website I just I noted that you had a couple of notable PRS in here and one
from Elry about deploying previews this is such a great example of how amazing
our community is like when you hear us talking about this and you're like what
are these guys really tangibly talking about we'll put a link to this PR
request number 456 in the show notes just so you can see just how incredible
this conversation is and the people working on this are so so so great
really I mean I feel like every week already just comes in with something
really awesome I'm I feel like you know we've been saying thank you Elray for
weeks now on the show and unfortunately we have to say it again thank you Elray
Elray Elray you said Elry earlier I did I it's it's actually Alex so thanks
Alex yeah Alex we could do that or we could do biggie you know the biggie the
big L I think you're on to something yeah cuz I mean otherwise we get Alex
infused with Alex that's just it right I don't do that mm-hmm yeah mm-hmm so
thanks biggie we appreciate your biggie energy and we'll have a link to that
just that's a great example but some of our first boosts well not our very first
but some of our boosts are actually about the website ask not what your
podcast can boost for you but what you can boost for your podcast oh we got a
we got a big boost a couple of big boosts coming you know what actually I'm
gonna stop right here stop the show for a second you know and just say we got
some remarkable audience support via the boost and what you'll see is there's a
few core members of our audience who really are stepping up and supporting
office hours I'm blown away by some of that this week so let's start with
optimus gray who sent in a row of grandpa ducks twenty two thousand two
hundred and twenty two sad things are looking up but all but duck so I love
this so optimus drove for like 24 hours each way to come to the JPL tour crazy
and also made it to the Pasadena meetup mm-hmm and so on his way back on his
drive home we got a series of boosts some ideas this is my first stop on the
way home from the Southern California meetup with Brent making fun of me and
rightly so I now have a list of favorite JB members they are Wes Alex Mike Chris
Wow these are in order of importance he's
bacon drew yeah his meow not mine jar jar Joe Hayden Levi and then Brent Wow
at the end Brent can only move back up the list if he works on a toy drinking
bird that can continue to touch Alex's chair over and over again I think that
sounds like it's worth doing Wow wonderful reference there also perhaps
the California State Border Patrol asked you about fruit and vegetables because
you had a Canadian with you hey now I had no problems coming from Nevada I
have always been asked at the border if I have fruit and veggies or produce or
whatever it's always been a thing they've always done that and I always
think is that just like pretext for stopping me are they really they set up
these all these border crossings at the state border just to stop every single
person and ask them if they got fruit in their car it's just the weirdest thing
they don't grow things in the panel oh that could be there's no way you could
be bringing any fruit or produce because Nevada ain't got nothing let's see Wow
look at you coming in with the shade jizzing optimist Greg comes in with a
double grandpa duck boost thank you kindly okay maybe I was trolling Alex
Brent and Chris too much in my last boost sorry Wes but maybe next time I'll
troll you how I do like the ideas who's giving us a show name because this is
something we need to we need to figure out another back from the road trip I do
like the name chat or sats for a JB extra sub channel like a brunch with
Brent I came up with four name replacements for office hours when I was
driving home oh it's 29 hours not 24 hours I had a lot of time to think I'm
gonna check those names in the podcast index on duck duck and on YouTube and
I'll report back are you ready this is amazing
optimus gray then comes in with a third boost boost with twenty thousand four
hundred eighty sats here are the three show name ideas after visiting JPL you
ready for these I think so I think we should write these down I feel like I
don't want to lose track of these cuz we've got to come up with a new show
name you got a pen over there Brent Lee's pulling out a pad of paper yeah I
need a pen I got a I got a marker I see nothing in my alright you ready hmm so
his first name suggestion is I of Jupiter interesting not bad right he
says it's kind of like the idea is what's JB looking at looking for looking
towards another one orbit of Jupiter uh-huh so if you picture like a bunch of
ideas and things and projects floating around yeah what's going on around JB's
kind of like a subtext his next one is IO which is a moon of Jupiter and of
course input output which is kind of akin to like listener feedback and then
output on the podcast so IO so both because it's a moon and because we do a
lot of input output with the audience in this show you know I feel like that is
my favorite one is short also yeah short is interesting I also unfortunately feel
like it might be the hardest to look for which is the Brahma having right now
yeah you could almost see like three three less than three letters might be
really hard for a lot of searching I mean it could be like Jupiter IO yeah
you know the only problem with that is in it with all of these really and it's
my fault because I named the network this way oh Chris but doesn't it make
you think of like it should be like a space podcast about Jupiter isn't that
what we talked about I enjoyed the last meetup on this trip remember a good
system crashes a good system crash means more content for podcasting I guess that
is the upside system crash not 12 system crashes thank you thank you
alright lurks a lot came in with a lot to share with elite set of stats office
hours his new name needs to have a space theme like the network there you go so
so Jupiter base is his suggestion Jupiter base we think of that I could
live with base he also recommends Jupiter production lounge I'll play on
JPL that's funny I could see that too I'm writing all these down guys I'm
writing all these down I'm gonna look at these I'm gonna think on these after the
show because I really do want to come up with a better name and something that's
unique to the show I think and kind of fun he says also each location could
have a spacey name so lady jupes could actually be called Jupiter station so
you know you're coming to coming in from Jupiter station kind of like a ground
control to major Brent just gonna have the right names to have fun and then
lurks a lot comes in with a triple boo wow is it really a hundred and thirty
three thousand seven hundred sats that's like a mega leet sat it may be a typo
thank you to our community who has been sourcing the boost clips on our github
so he wanted to comment on how we have fun with like the leet sats thing you
know and he says for me the childish leet elitism and macho thing is all tongue
in cheek it's just a fun sarcastic joke and a poke at my own imposter syndrome
tendencies but it's fun to gamify these things as a form of self motivation so
to that end achievement unlocked I have used boost CLI and done from my um bro
you're doing a good job good job lurks a lot that's impressive man that is tell
me lurks a lot isn't that sort of like the ultimate technical unlock
achievement I mean it really does doesn't it feel good he says it's an
achievement unlocked I agree I'm so proud of you that is man click building
gentoo back in the day it is it is it's a lot like that if it has that same kind
of thing you really learn how a lot of this works and much like when I did that
with gentoo I gained a whole new respect like that was truly what got me to
understand and appreciate Linux was building gentoo and arch systems and
learning how it actually worked compared to Windows and then I learned such a
deep respect and appreciation for that system and I feel like it's the same way
when you do boost CLI in some ways I'm kind of envious of you lurks that's just
such a fun place to be again so that's great and he came in get ready for this
Brent are you ready for this I think so a quad boost from sir lurks a lot
hundred and one three hundred and thirty seven sats thank you for so very many
things over the years most recently I have been inspired by the Nixos
challenge the world of podcasting 2.0 lightning and Bitcoin thanks for dog
footing matrix and Hugo thank you for your faucet and self-hosting advocacy
and especially for fostering a real sense of community stop it stop it geez
that's too much thank you for the thank you for the support you know like we had
some great support come in this week for this episode we really really do
appreciate and Brent still on that split too true so you know we did we have
talked about that on on love a little bit but that was fun with the the SAT
stakes and the grocers the SATs the gas I mean honestly the better thing might
be just as you know like if you could just convert the stats to cash but we
didn't want to do that that was the easy way out so that's not fun enough bit
refill lets you buy Texaco and Chevron gas cards which works as long as you're
in the States but once you enter Scandinavia you guys you don't have those
right no yeah no I wonder if there's like a shell like shell is is pretty
common and you have them here so I wonder if they sell shell cards on bit
refill oh we didn't look hard enough did we'll have to check we have to check
then we got ten thousand sats from orange Fox who I think might actually be
Alex Gates using breeze said the worst thing about the office TV fans is when
they try to make Battlestar Galactica references without ever seen BSG I agree
and this is this is the problem with the show name is everybody thinks it's an
office podcast and then they're disappointed when they start listening
and it's not an it's not an office podcast yeah it's not it's not about the
TV show there are plenty oh my god there are plenty of those I never had any idea
so okay we do definitely need a new name there's just no doubt about it we have
another boost that came in from true grits with 1701 the enterprise sats
so instead of making a side business off the new JB hosting platform maybe y'all
should turn it into a Libre podcasting package interesting hmm and then gene
bean was thinking along the same lines as another set of leet sats packaging
the website bits up in a way other podcasters could consume while also being
able to get updates would be awesome you know there's something to this I think
there's something to creating a platform that other podcasters could package up
and use and I don't know how far we take this but I'm down to experiment with
taking it further especially if community members have ideas on how we
could make it I guess more portable would be the word to use I know we need
to have a good licensing conversation we need to sort all that stuff out but I
think it's a direction we could take things especially once we think we have
it in a pretty feature complete state and then maybe later on as we develop a
way to generate RSS feeds that's something we could share too and
ultimately and I think we have to remember the RSS feed is our radio
signal that's our broadcast tower the website is an endpoint and so I think if
we created the system that where the two work together somehow you know you put
some of this information in the RSS feed and it automatically populates the
website and the website is is also one of the end consumers of that RSS feed so
the source of truth is there are assessed I think that'd be incredibly
powerful really interesting and very useful for other podcasters because all
then they would have to do is point that website consumption whatever it is
endpoint at their RSS feed and it would just pull it in and begin to build their
you know Hugo based website for them that'd be my idea you know that gets me
thinking I was originally gonna say oh well we haven't really heard of others
out there outside of the JB community really latching on to the project that
we're building here but then that got me thinking well maybe we haven't described
what it actually does well enough you know if you're right it's been
described as a website for us well that's it what if you change what
content it's looking at and you change out the logos I mean I wouldn't be a fan
my main thing one of the main things was nice about getting away from fireside is
every fireside page looks alike so that would be one downside as if all of the
websites just looked alike again but the upside would be a big improvement for
the listeners and also something that's podcasting to I know compatible and
forward-facing I had a call this morning before the show with an individual named
Matt who is working on a fireside competitor and fireside side note for
those of you don't know we're talking about yeah fireside FM it's pretty great
podcasting hosting platform but a little bit slow on the features and what these
guys want to do is come along with the same idea a CMS a front-end website a
back-end CDN infrastructure but all in on podcasting 2.0 so that's what their
competitive advantage is gonna be is they're they're all the podcasting to
those stuff out of the box they're hoping it's funny this is probably what
you wanted like six months ago a year maybe right yeah it would have been nice
but yeah but I don't know if I'd want to go back what we have now is so much more
powerful so much better for us well and better than actually we had envisioned at
first yeah yeah and there are some features that I think we're gonna come
up with in the next month or two yeah that we've been wanting for a long time
and that are actually pretty awesome and it's made things like transitioning to
peer-to-peer smoother it's gonna make transitioning to having our own RSS feeds
smoother I mean it's it's gonna pay off down the road for stuff we're not even
doing yet yeah I completely completes agrees and then true grits came back in
with a dubs boost again let's give him a little bit of a tutting 1701 sats oh so
he also gets the Trek boost you're doing a good job he says I wish there was a
more granular way in fountain FM to determine which podcast I earned sats on
and which ones I spend sets on I would throw all of my earnings on podcasts
that don't support lightning and boosts but then turn off earnings for the
podcast that do I don't feel like I really earn the sats when they're just
getting streamed right back out also do you guys know if the streaming counts
towards your flow I haven't been able to determine that so this is a great set of
questions grits and fountain FM has this feature now where when you're listening
to podcasts they stream sats to you and they just recently tweaked the way you
earn those sats and they've made it a lot simpler and clearer and I'll have a
link to their explanation in the show notes but just really briefly you now
get paid in fountain for your first hour of daily podcast listening the earning
rate changes every day for each user and it's random some days you might earn a
little but on some days you'll earn a lot you no longer need to support
podcasts or create clips in order to continue earning or to earn more so the
flow idea is kind of out there are no changes the way promotions or regular
clips work that change was done in fountain 4.9 and as we record on
Wednesday October 11th 2022 5.2 just came out they've added a lot of stuff
autocue support which was one of the number one features I heard from the
audience carplay and Android auto has also been added as well as some bug
fixes performance improvements some UI cleanup the way the clips work is a
little bit better now I gotta say I'm really like in fountain I I want I want
pod verse to be my daily driver because it is the GPL one but man the stuff they
keep doing in fountain just keeps bringing me back I love the clips
because I spent time following different people and so now in fountain one of the
things that I just love is if I've got a few minutes I'm burning like maybe I'm
doing a quick chore or something I just go to the clips page and I just hit play
and I just listen through my clips and I find new podcasts I look at that
somebody clipped coder right there this is the joy that you bring Chris I just
so I mean the folks at fountain are doing such great work the folks at pod
verse are doing such great work too we're just spoiled in podcasting 2.0 so
grits go give that post a read just so you can kind of wrap your head around it
if anything they're making it easier now so hopefully you might see on some days
a slower earn rate but it's just gonna be a simpler way you just essentially
listen and I mean the way I basically worked it out one time it's like a SATA
minute or something I was getting so it's slower than it used to be but not
so bad but do you think that's tricky for those who've been trying to really
dive into the system and earn things because it almost feels like it's the
second change almost this month that they've made to this earning system so
do you think they're just trying things to figure it out or yeah they're the
first ever do something like this and I think it does take a lot of work to make
sure it doesn't get gamed and scammed and so I think they've been sorting out
and make it clear enough to so people set the right expectations and don't get
upset I think you got to tweak all of that the idea is kind of compelling so
the sats come from people who buy promoted clips and in the UI when you
open up fountain it brings you to a clips page first and generally there are
eight clips in the UI the first two are clearly labeled they're a different
color and those are the promoted clips everything else isn't everything else is
community generated those two promoted clips at the top are where the sats come
from that's where the sats that you're getting streamed to you when you're
listening that's where they come from and then what grits is asking is well if
I stream those back to the podcaster like what's the point the point is is
you can control the flow rate back to the podcaster and you could preload
your wallet and the streaming you're getting from found it could just kind of
be a supplement you know you know you're getting a little kickback I think it's a
neat system but it is definitely early days still and then true grits gets our
very last boost of the episode with 4040 sats since you guys told me not to clip
and drive last episode which I agree I don't actually do however I do most of
my podcast listening on the road by the time I get to my destination I have
forgotten what the clippable moment is or I don't have time to do it it would
be nice if there was a way as the listener to drop a marker on a podcast
and come back to it later like a user set chapter marker of sorts fabulous
idea it is man because I have the same problem I want to make clips of
different podcasts all the time I've got a lot of people following me on fountain
now so I kind of wanted like you know give them something and I I never ever
remember what it was I wanted to clip when I get home or get to my destination
it's a huge problem but I also don't want to like tap out a big old note like
audible has this feature where you can like kind of bookmark and leave a note
but you're tapping out like a whole note to yourself well that's not safe you
have a little button that just drops like a flag or something like that is a
great idea I think fountain should think about that like a little marker right
there we also got what do you think how do you think this last one on the thank
yous here goes there but how would you pronounce that last one there is a JLT
my old man vision is JLT Gordon yeah is that what it is I'm zooming but then I
lost my place in the dock because I had to zoom in so I could read it yeah we
got 4,300 sats from JLT thank you JLT and we got 500 sats from rustic
aversa just to send a meow to editor drew and I feel like there's a
relationship starting you know a friendship built out of meows I guess
we didn't have a lot of different boosters but the boosters who supported
us this week really really stepped up I don't know if we're gonna see that next
episode so if you've been thinking about sending a boost in getting a comment in
it'd be a great week because it just takes someone like you to support us
anybody out there listening could go to new podcast apps calm grab a new podcast
app one that's podcasting to know compatible become part of this new
movement the edge of podcasting technology the real leading edge exciting
community driven stuff not the stuff that's driven by Spotify I don't know if
you saw this Brent but Spotify just announced that they just bought a content
scanning company that specializes in scanning podcasts spoken word content
and finding offensive violations and automatically flagging them Spotify just
bought that company they're gonna probably integrate that into the
platform it's just gonna be great mm-hmm yeah it's what we've always wanted yeah
I just are so so looking forward to that now you know we're gonna we always get
letters from YouTube after we do a live stream now I'm also gonna I'm gonna be
getting letters emails from Spotify now it's gonna be part of the whole routine
you know it's just a ridiculous direction podcasting needs to stay
healthy it needs to stay decentralized so you can do that big cut by becoming a
member at Jupiter party you get all of the network shows ad free or you can
send a boost into the show and you can support every single episode as you see
fit new podcast apps calm we have a lot more projects coming up including the
things we talked about with the website our new RSS feeds and all of it and a
new name for the show which we're gonna have to do sooner than later because
it's just getting to me is it it's getting to me so it's all coming up so
don't go anywhere don't don't don't be a stranger you know every other Tuesday
it's easy unless Brent's traveling then we're gonna have to have AI Brent in
here I mean I'm okay with that yeah I mean we'll see how it goes right every
other Tuesday the office door is open to you it's over at Jupiter out tube noon
Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern also have it at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar
so you can just get in your local time zone but when it's not Tuesday every
other Tuesday at noon or 3 p.m. then you got to get out of here the office door
is not open I got work to do I gotta take a nap thanks for joining us see you
next time