I'm starting to learn Python because I thought it might be a useful thing.
It is a useful thing. What's your use case? You got any ideas?
Well, I think that's the best question of them all. I don't have a well-defined use case,
but what I'm what I've been looking at this week is what are the general use tools in the world of,
you know, what we're doing that might be good to know even just a little bit about. So have just
a base knowledge about Ansible, for instance, have a base knowledge about Python, have a base
knowledge about Git, because I think Git is fabulous. I'd like to know a little bit more
about it, but I don't have an everyday use for it yet. But how do you build in an everyday use for
it if you don't even know what it's capable of? So it's more of like dipping the toe in and seeing
what it might be able to do for me. And Python seems like an easy place to start. It's useful
for a bunch of different types of problems. Relatively easy to learn, it seems. And Wes has
like tons of advice for that. So he and I were going off yesterday with he's like, oh, you should
try this, too. Oh, and if you need a repl, try this repl. It's really great. And we yeah, he's
such a great resource. So anyways, that's great. Yeah, that is great. Even if I do nothing with it,
this whole process is fun. I encourage this. I think that is really great. I think just getting
a base understanding of that kind of stuff is really is super beneficial. Kind of get a better
understanding of the language, too. Yeah. And you never know when you're going to come across a use
case for Python. Last night, I was reviewing different applications to extract information
from the Starlink dish. And there's a huge Python library somebody's created that essentially
handles all of the interfacing with the dish. And you just pass this thing a simple request.
And that Python library does all of the complicated back end communications to Dishy.
And, you know, there I am just randomly looking at tools to pull off pull off stats.
And, you know, going down a Python rabbit hole. So it happens all the time. Well,
and that's kind of what I've noticed is that a lot of these, like, do it yourself kind of
micro hacks, maybe I'll call them tend to be written in Python, because it's just like,
seems like it's relatively easy to get into. It's extensible, obviously, which you were just saying
someone wrote a module for it. And, and it seems pretty ubiquitous, depending on the types of
problems you're solving, whether it's I guess, it's used a lot in the gaming industry quite a
bit. And also in machine learning stuff. So everywhere, dude, everywhere, everywhere. Well,
ansible on the back end is Python. So I thought, well, geez, like, some of the best tools out there
are using Python to do things. So maybe I can get a basic understanding of it just to.
But I do now that I'm talking about it with you, which is always helpful. I'm noticing a trend in
these things I'm trying to learn, which is automation. Ansible has a way of automating things.
Python is a way of automating stuff. Git can help you automate a bunch of things. So maybe that's
where I'm headed. I could see that. I could see that's a good area to get into. It's a bigger and
bigger area as infrastructure gets bigger and bigger. I think personally, even I'm just getting
tired of re remaking all my infrastructure from time to time. So yeah, there's that too, huh?
Yeah. Well, the whole NixOS challenge, you know, changed my way of seeing the world.
Office hours with me, Chris.
Hey, welcome into the office. Make yourself comfortable. Twice a month. I open the doors
up and I let the people in. And of course, Brent, he's always here, too. He's got himself his own
little seat. Hey there, Brent. Well, hello. That's cozy in here this week. I appreciate
you making it cozy. Well, you know, you take the time. You like the fire. The stuffed animals are
a nice touch. Is the bunk bed a little bit too much? No, man. We'll take a nap after the show.
I think it's going to be great. So I appreciate it. We got a packed show today. In fact, I just
kind of decided to just I just struck a few things from the from the show notes. Just had to make
room. I had to make room because I wanted to start with your recent experience about trying to
improve your network connectivity, because you're out in what basically would be the idyllic scene
setting for like a movie that takes place in the mountains with beautiful scenery,
just gorgeous, gorgeous atmosphere. But unfortunately, kind of tricky for high speed
Internet. And that is a constant thing that we're battling with. And so you did some what?
What, some upgrades? I think you better start from the beginning and kind of explain to us how you
get connected to the Internet and then tell us what you did to fix it and upgrade it.
You know what I mean? I do. Yeah. So just picture a little cabin tucked away
somewhere in the Canadian Rockies. And I'm living on a property with my brother. So he has a house
maybe 100 paces that way. And so the way we get Internet is, hmm. It's like Starlink before
Starlink came. So there's a tower on the mountain that you could see out in the field over there.
So we get wireless point to point connectivity, line of sight kind of stuff to the other mountain
on the other side of the valley. Now, is this a it's like an actual Wisp,
a business or is this like an acquaintance? It's a business, thankfully. They were recently bought
out. So there's a lot of confusion on their end as far as which customers should be getting what.
Luckily, that's playing in our favor in this case. But they've just basically forgot about us for a
long time. And so when I moved here, I thought, oh, geez, I'm used to like fiber is what I used
to have. And so I knew it would be a compromise being here. And it was OK, like I could do most
things. It's not the first time I've lived in the middle of nowhere trying to run off
cell signal or something like that. The downside, I think here as well,
is that my cell reception is equally bad. So it was fine. Everything was fine. We were doing
all of our shows, Chris, through audio and everything seemed fine. And then a few weeks ago,
we decided to jump to doing some fun video stuff. And that's when I think we really started testing
my network because it didn't really have to work very hard before. And now it's really cooking.
And I came to the realization that my network just wasn't going to cut it. It was fine in the
evenings to like, you know, stream TV shows at like 480p or something. But this is not good
enough, I think, especially when I'm now uploading a bunch of video to you. And my upload is like
a tenth of what the download is. So it was a pretty, pretty bad shape. So it's been about
two years that my brother and I have been wanting to perform upgrades because the little dish that's
hanging off of his roof when the installer put it in. They did an extremely bad job.
Oh, go figure. I'm going to describe it to you and you can feel badly for me.
So the tower is on the west side of the house, but the dish for some reason was placed on the
east side of the house because that was the easiest way to lay out cables on the exterior
of the building. You know, these installers, they just drill holes in your building and they just
run wires wherever they want. But also the the mast that they placed the dish on was just too
short for the like the incline of the roof. So the the dish itself was actually pointing
at the metal roof trying to reach the basically the the the mass that's on the mountain over there.
But it couldn't aim low enough because, you know, there's a valley between us. It couldn't aim low
enough. So it was like bouncing off of the metal roof to try to get signal. You were never going
to get what you were paying for ever with that. No, no, not even close. And we knew that we knew,
OK, this is a terrible setup. It can only get better from here. But we you know,
you got to climb on the roof and we had to come up with a way of extending the mast as well.
So it took us about two years to have a great enough reason to do that. And thankfully,
JB toying with video was the the reason. And so we got on the roof the other day.
We got on the roof the other day. Well, we got on the roof the other day.
And luckily, we had thought about this and had some parts. So we bought an extension
to put on the mast. And when I moved to this cabin, it had a do you remember satellite dishes?
Everybody had them to get like fancy TV back in the day. Well, there was one hanging off this
cabin. And so I was able to take the mast from that, get a grinder, cut it in half and just take
the vertical section of it. And we had a union and connected that to the existing mast for the
Internet dish. So we were able to raise it about two feet, which is great. But,
you know, this is a really sensitive piece of equipment. You just can't just take it off,
throw it on and expect it to be pointed at the right place. It's very, very directional.
So luckily, we were able to call the Wisp, the ISP, and got the best guy on the phone ever.
It was like some surfer dude guy that's usually out in the field making doing installations and
stuff. And he's just like, Hey, how can I help you? He's like, Oh, yeah, I'm usually in the field,
but I just happen to be in the office today and nobody else is around. And so I could totally
help you guys if you want, like, what do you need, like an hour of my time or something? Is that
about what you need? So it was great, because he as an installer could totally visualize exactly
what we were doing, you know, hanging off the roof, trying to trying to do all this stuff. And
he could guide us and be like, No, no, just do, you know, let's, let's use this method to try to
point the satellite and stuff. And and the other great thing was that he was able to give us in
real time the signal from their antenna on the mountain. So instead of us, you know, trying to
do speed tests or something from here to try to get that data, he was able to give it to us real
time. So it was amazing. He basically gave us a baseline, which is the internet connectivity that
we had previously. And he gave us he's like, okay, we measure a bunch of stuff, but it kind of
combines it into like a quasi score. And he said, basically, you're getting like a one out of eight.
score. And if we go to a new install, to try to see if it's possible, and we get a one out of eight,
we don't give those people service, because they're not going to be happy with anything. So
you guys have been running on like our worst coverage for years. And anything we do can just
get better. Wow, in terms of speeds for our baseline during the day was the best because the
tower wasn't. I'm probably the only person using the tower during the day. At night was worse,
because you know, everybody's doing the Netflix thing or something. So during the day, I was
probably getting like 15 megabits down, and maybe one up. But in the evenings was actually the worst
because it the stability went way down. We couldn't even watch videos at 480p sometimes, like
depending on the weather and stuff like that. So he said, anything we do is just going to get
better. So luckily, we you know, my brother and I, we got on the roof and extended this thing and
called surfer dude back and he helped us turn the dish and get it all optimized. And now, now we
have an eight out of eight signal. Whoa, which is fabulous. Well, we have we could see the tower
over there. And that's how we knew it was pointed. Our dish wasn't pointed very well, right? It's
like, well, actually, it's over there. And it's totally missing it. So we have a very good line
of sight. We just didn't have the right setup to take advantage of that. And so I think we're doing
far better now. You know, despite my getting on the roof and hanging off my fingernails for a
little bit, I didn't get any you asked me like, Oh, try to get some audio because it could be
really great. And he would have been awesome to have a little audio bite of but I gotta say I
was feeling busy on the roof doing stuff that I didn't quite get a chance to grab some so
apologies for one there, but you use your imagination. So I will say now our speeds aren't
way like they're not magnitudes better. So I'm getting like 25 down and two up. But surfer dude
says that's pretty much their limit, which actually, we're not even subscribed to that. So he
said like, because because there was a buyout, you guys are kind of like grandfathered in you're not
supposed to be on that plan, but I'm just not going to touch anything. So as the instructor
he was like, I'm not going to send you to sales because they're going to catch that they're going
to change things. So I'm just gonna leave it like that. But he did say the difference for you guys
now is going to be priority. So he said, the way it works is that if you have one out of eight
signal, you're on the bottom of the list for priority traffic. And he said, now you're one
of the best signals on that tower. So you're going to get the best priority out of anybody
connecting. And that's exactly what we've seen super stable at any time of the day. So I think
it was totally worth it. Wow, that's interesting to the way they prioritize it, depending on your
signal, because in some ways, you'd think that people with the weakest signal would need the
most help. But nice work. You know, those things, it's like a lot of work for a, an improvement,
but not like a complete solution. Right. And of course, the tricky thing too, is you can do all
of that work, make your connection really solid, you know, your now your connection to your whisk
could be as ideal, but then there still can be issues on the land side or on a wifi side that
have to be worked out because any kind of remote constant communications, like I'm sure people that
are doing work from home have experienced this. I know I did. Wifi issues can, can, can really
plague you even with a good internet connection. I was working at a cloud guru when the very
beginnings of the work from home lockdowns started. It was super common for the first few months
that you'd always have somebody who just joined the video meeting who had really bad wifi because
they hadn't, they hadn't been doing zoom calls from home on the regular, like people who typically
work from home had, who had their whole setups already figured out. All of a sudden you had all
these folks that had done all that stuff from the office. Now all of a sudden having to do it from
home and they just found out that even though this is something that happens over and over again,
they were paying for like this great internet service. They had horrible wifi and they had to
and they kept dropping off the calls, right? And they're not even taking advantage of it.
Well, and this is true for my neighbor too. She, she pays Comcast something like 80 bucks a month
for her internet. I was over there and her wifi, her router just crashed and rebooted. And of course
her, her phone or, you know, whatever just automatically connects to the next open wifi.
Well, that's her neighbor's ring camera. That's waiting to be upset, waiting to be set up. Yeah.
Yeah. So her router crashes, then her phone connects to the next open wifi AP,
which is a ring device just waiting to be configured. And then she doesn't get any
internet even once her router comes back online because her phone doesn't switch back.
Oh my goodness.
She's like, oh yeah, it happens all the time.
For how long? That's for as long as I've had it. Yeah. I'm like, okay, all right.
That is crazy.
I just couldn't, right? But it's funny you're, you're messing around with all of this
because not just last night, I went down the rabbit hole of figuring out an extension pole
and suction cup mounts and all kinds of twist mounts to, to tie a, you know, a thing to a pole
and 3d printed Starlink adapters because I've decided I'm going to attempt to install my Starlink
via an extendable flagpole from a Harbor Freight, the 20 foot extendable flagpole.
And then I will attach industrial grade window suction cups to that and, and suction it to the
side of JOOPS with a, also a floor, a ground stand. I'm going to put the Starlink up over
JOOPS's roof that way. I've thought about different ways. I don't have a ladder to mount
the Starlink to, which is what most RVers do. But in the process of trying to figure out what my
options were for people who don't have ladders, I ended up discovering this Starlink for RVers
Facebook group, which I haven't done a Facebook group thing ever, literally ever. Well, maybe not
true. Maybe once ever. I mean, it's like, I haven't logged into Facebook. So I had to go through
this whole process of like recovering my Facebook account and identifying myself to Facebook and all
of this, just so I could get access to this resource. Oh, it was the worst man. You're
motivated. I was very motivated because I was really trying to put all this together so that
way I could hopefully get it in time for Montana. You know, cause I'm leaving for Montana and I'm
leaving for Montana in a couple of weeks and we've never really had internet where we've gone,
which has been good and bad. It's good from a turning it off for a couple of days, which I could
still do just by not turning on the Starlink, but it's bad from like a running your business
standpoint. So my thought was, is this will be the first year we go to Montana with Starlink.
And I want to have a way to get it up above tree lines because you really don't want to have
anything blocking it, or you're going to have dropped packets, anything. These posts just have
like a lot of good information, including all these crazy ways that different people are
installing the Starlink on their mobile setups and then deploying them on the roofs of their
rigs and whatnot. Tons of inspiring stuff. So I got back on Facebook for the first time in like
a hundred years and it was arduous, but I too have been playing around with polls.
And getting up on roofs. I have more to do too. Well, you're going to have to update us on how
yours goes once you get to Bozeman. Cause, uh, I would imagine it would be pretty great if it
worked great, but I would also imagine, you know, it's not tested and you can't really test it till
we get there. So you might have to do some troubleshooting on site. Definitely one of
those things. Definitely one of those things. Well, so I wanted to talk about our peer tube
a little bit. You down for that? Oh yeah. I can't wait to hear all the stuff you guys have been
doing. I know a little bit about it, but give me, give me the meat. We mentioned it on luck. We've,
we've relaunched Jupiter dot tube and I'm coming at it with a whole new attack angle. So if you're
not familiar, we launched this about a year and a half ago and then I shut it down and I listed a
bunch of reasons why. And back then I was trying to use it for each individual show. I was going to
have a channel for every show, which needed an account for every show. And there wasn't a way
to automate it. And, uh, that was horrible. But now I've had a rethink and I've, I've decided
just using it for live and special events or maybe a special one off video production. We do
hedging for the eventuality when I shut down all of my Google accounts, but also giving us a
decentralized media distribution platform. And that's something I've been focused on a lot this
year. Decentralized community with matrix, decentralized value with boosts and decentralized
media. Now with peer tube, I think this is a big deal. Plus I figure with more people working from
home, we should probably try to have a product that addresses that crowd. Somebody who wants to
watch from their desk. Somebody also who's probably been listening for a while and maybe would like
to switch to the behind the scenes feed. And this has really just been part of something that we've
been working on since I'd say the beginning of the year. It's decentralization, decentralization of
everything that we can that makes sense. And so, uh, and I love, I like the fact there's no
takedown bots. I like the fact that it's a free software stack. I like the idea that we have a
place. You always know you can go to, to catch an archive version of a live show if you'd like,
you know, that kind of stuff. Um, but there's, there's other motivations too. The podcasting
2.0 community is working on baking in live streaming into apps and peer tube might be some
of the plumbing that makes that possible. So I want to be there for that. I think when you add
work from home, when you add the decentralized aspect of it, when you add the kind of strategic
nature of hedging against Google and creating an outlet that's going to be able to do that,
of hedging against Google and creating an outlet that people know to go to over the years. And then
the, the long-term integration with the podcasting 2.0 apps, that was pretty good motivating. You
know, there was some, that was, that was enough, but then we got a really solid response from our
community on helping us admin it and manage it. So I'm going to be creating a matrix peer tube
room for Jupiter broadcasting, like a JB peer tube room where we can kind of organize in there.
And I'll put a link to that in the show notes for this episode. So for those of you who are
interested in participating, I think, you know, there's a lot of things we could talk about,
maybe opening this up to logins via some sort of OAuth or mastered on login. We could talk about
potentially limited community publishing of certain videos. I don't know about that. I don't
know. There's a lot we could discuss. I'm willing to, I'm willing to go there, but so we'll create
a separate peer tube matrix room, which we'll have linked in the show notes.
I think we should also create a, um, good hub issues for our peer tube instance. That way we
can track a bunch of stuff there. I'll have that to my docket. If you think it's a good idea.
Totally. Thank you. That would be great.
I was curious cause, uh, JB has done video previously. So is that going to change the
way we do things on the audio front by, by chance?
No, not this time. So that's probably the biggest difference this time around
is we're going to stick to audio first production. All our release episodes are going to be audio.
We're all still doing multi-track recording, multi-track editing. We still have drew cleaning
this up, processing the audio, mastering and mixing it, publishing it. All of that still remains.
These are, these are going to be more like behind the scenes feeds with just a little bit extra,
because for the first 10 years of JB, I did a lot of, a lot of live switching. That's just sort of
a skillset I have. So I can, you know, we can do live switching. We can show screens. We can do
that kind of stuff without impacting the content of the audio show. That's a lot of,
that's a line that I learned a long time ago. You can mess up really easily. You can start
referencing stuff. Oh, look at this, you know, and that kind of stuff. But we learned our lesson.
You know, it's been, what, two years since the last PeerTube instance, JB PeerTube instance was
up. I was curious if you've seen improvements since then, both in, I don't know, admin user
interfaces and feature sets that are kind of tinkling your fancy, but also on the back end,
are things a little easier or different or exciting in any way? Yeah, it was almost just
about two years ago, and I think it was two versions of PeerTube ago. So some of the things
that have been improved is the back end tooling to import videos, import bulk sets of videos.
That was a big issue of mine. And then something that I did differently is this is a live,
this is a live events and specials PeerTube instance. It's not a, every show gets published
there, PeerTube instance. It's a lot easier to manage when you don't need like eight different
accounts on this thing. When we deployed it this time, I was like, wow, this has gotten a lot
better, both on the back end, on the front end. But you know, it could just use a couple of features
and one of them, I'd really love to be able to edit a video because sometimes we start a stream,
there's 20 minutes of music, no, not really 20, but there's 10, 15 minutes of music,
and then the stream actually starts. Well, I could go, I could go lock that off. That'd be
nice, right? If I could just go up into PeerTube and lock that off. And then the other feature
that I really, after I deployed, I was like, God, I'd really like to have this is a permanent live
URL that you can always go to. And then the videos available on demand later at a separate new URL
and PeerTube offers one or the other. You can do a once live stream with a unique URL that's
available later, which is what we're doing, or you can do a permanent live stream that isn't
available later. It's like this URL, and it's just this is a live stream. It goes away after
you stop streaming, but it's always at that URL. Well, today, as we record version 4.2 of PeerTube
is out and they've added both those things. They've added live editing so you can go up to
an uploaded video and you can set a new start time. You can set a new end time. You can even
add an intro and outro to the video by uploading separate video files. You can even add a watermark
to the video if you want. That's now in PeerTube, which is awesome. It sounds like you weren't the
only one who wanted these features and just in time to I updated today and I actually don't
see it in here. So I'm going to be playing around with that because I guess I have to,
like, find the studio mode or something. But sometimes I want to get the stream up and going
and I'm just putting around in here for like a half hour, getting the studio ready.
It's not really anything that anybody like. It's like a lot to slog through when you go to
playback. So I'm going to start probably trimming some of that off. Then they've added some new
stats, which will be interesting to see. Now that we're doing this, it will actually be interesting
to get data on how much of the live stuff people watch. And they have fixed the replay permanent
link thing. So now they're telling me I can have a permanent URL that never changes. And I can also
carve out unique URLs for playback later. With this sprint, they've really nailed everything
I wanted in PeerTube. I think you'll have to come up with some new wishes and add it to their
future requests because there's got to be more that you want. Come on. I would love our community,
especially those that are interested, to dig into our PeerTube. I really would. I'd love you to go
over there and dig into it and figure out ways to extract the videos, figure out ways to build
playlists. And also, I would love to know if there's a way we could set up on-demand VPSs
or maybe audience members could contribute some machine and we could set up web torrent seeds
that could act as essentially a community CDN for live events. I think it'd be great.
And yesterday I was streaming the WWDC 2022 event and it was rocking. PeerTube did so good. I was
very impressed. I was very, very happy. But we had one viewer in Israel and he, I think,
was the only viewer in Israel at the time. And as a result, he got some stuttering.
And if we could spin up an instance in his area or if he could have an instance going in his area
that when our PeerTube instance goes live, he participates in the web torrent in that area,
then we could create a community CDN. And I think that'd be really powerful. So I'd love to have our
community dig into it because PeerTube is an open platform and there's a lot we can build on top of
this. And if we start building some momentum around that, I'm willing to commit resources to it. So
we'll get all that going in the matrix room on the new JB PeerTube room that we'll set up.
I think it should be pretty exciting. And I like where this is leading, man. You know,
Green Bean boosted in. Boost! Seven days ago for a thousand sats. I've never run PeerTube,
but I'd actually be quite interested in helping y'all put it to use. Stuff like this is super
interesting. I just haven't had a use case for myself. If that resonates with you, like if you've
wanted to play with some of this stuff, you've got some skill sets, but you just don't like
have a particular use case, maybe you can work with us on this. So check for a link in the show
notes on that and then stay tuned to Office Hours for future developments. We'll have the Cooking
with Brent series up there soon. Right, Brent? Well, it's a work in progress, but you know,
you might find it there. I will say, speaking of cooking, I know Wes was cooking quite a bit
in talking about how he set up the PeerTube instance on the latest Linux Unplugged. I
think that was 4.6.1. He dove into sort of how you guys use NixOS on the backend, and I thought
that was a really great conversation. So if you're interested more in how that was built,
I think that'd be a great place to go check it out. That is a good plug, indeed. All right,
so while we're talking about podcasting 2.0, I have been trying out the various podcasting 2.0
apps. Loved me some Fountain FM, and I recently tried out Podverse, which I like because it has
iOS, Android, and a great web client. Really great web client. It has the value boosting built right
in. It has some neat features like cross app comments, and it has that live stream support
I was talking about. So I reached out to one of the co-founders. His name is Mitch,
and I invited him on into the office. So Mitch, you and I just sat down. We started chatting,
and I asked you if you were the creator of Podverse. I've been checking out the Podverse
podcast app recently. One of the things I love about it, that's why I tried it out besides the
fact that it's a podcasting 2.0 app, is because Podverse has a web client, which is fantastic,
an Android client, and an iOS client. All the platforms, and they all sync up, and that got
my attention. So I started asking you, are you the creator, the founder, the CEO? And you said,
I'm a co-founder, and this has taken a ton more hours than we ever expected. So let's start there,
because I thought I read somewhere that Podverse kind of started as a Clips tool, right? It was
going to be for making podcast clips, not a full podcast app. Yeah, correct. So it's myself,
Creon, and Gary. Creon is another developer with Podverse, and Gary does graphic design.
And it originally was just supposed to be like a quick little project to get me started learning
how to program. This was like eight years ago. I was a big fan of podcasts and wanted a way to
share it with people. It was like a very isolated thing. It was something that was a big part of my
life, but I didn't have an easy way to introduce other people to it. And eight years ago, there
were not many options for sharing clips. So I went down this journey of learning how to
write code and create apps. So it's turned into something much bigger than that. Now it's not
just a clip sharing app. We try to do every feature we could possibly want. That's one of
the things, though. For a good clip sharing app, it needs to be my primary podcast app. I don't
want to be bouncing in and out of the app. So it ended up kind of just naturally becoming something
much bigger than that. I hadn't thought of that. Of course, that would sort of be a natural
evolution of it. It makes total sense. And then I suppose the podcasting 2.0 stuff kind of came
around just at the right time for an app at this size and this stage. Tell me a little bit about
that. Yeah, so that started about a year and a half ago. I think it was like September 2000.
Boy, I don't even remember years anymore. The before times? Yeah, the before times. It's all
blur with all the COVID stuff. I was just actually looking in the community to try to
branch out and find some open source collaborations. And I sent an email to
James Cridland of Podnews. And he sent me an email back saying, hey, there's this new thing
called Podcasting 2.0. Here's a sneak peek. He sent me the first episode before it was released.
And I listened to it. I was like, oh, man, this is exactly what we're looking for because we're
an open source app. We're like principles first in that respect. And we just want what is best
for podcasting. Podcasting 2.0, it's two things in particular. It is the world's largest podcast
database. It's managed by Dave Jones and Adam Curry. Adam Curry, also known as the Podfather,
one of the original creators of podcasting. And it's also extending the RSS spec, which all
podcasts use, so that new features are possible in podcast apps. And this is really exciting if
you are familiar with the podcast industry because RSS has not evolved much at all,
what, like 10, 15 years. And now that this group has come along and there's apps like ourselves and
RSS hosts participating in this, we're finally getting some consensus and people agreeing on
what features we can add and how we can add it to RSS feeds. For almost 20 years, people struggled
to get agreement, to get enough consensus to actually adopt these new practices.
And it seems like it just sort of was a great timing of things where the application development
process was at, where the podcasting 2.0 community was at. And correct me if I'm wrong, but really
before the podcasting 2.0 spec, you had maybe Apple would create some random tags for their own
internal use, and then you'd have app developers just kind of begin baking in support for those
tags that Apple had just added. There wasn't any standards that had been announced or discussed or
debated. It just, where Apple led, people had to follow. Yeah, it was pretty much Apple and
set all the norms and the industry just followed from there. Before Podcast Index came along,
we had 50,000 podcasts in our database. Now we have over 5 million in our database.
They do so much heavy lifting for us. We do a continuous syncing operation with their database.
And that work of just parsing 5 million podcasts, that's a full-time job for multiple people
in itself. And we get to leverage that for free because it's an open platform.
Do you take advantage of Podping to update the clients of new releases? Are you doing it through
traditional RSS fetching? How does that work?
So we sync with Podcast Index through API endpoints. We don't use Podping directly,
except for with the new live stream feature where we do listen to Podping directly. There may come
a day where we are listening for all of our updates just from Podping, but for now, if we listen to
the Podcast Index API, we get more than just Podping updates. A lot of feeds still are not
on Podping yet, so we get all of the updates that Podcast Index discovers. But yeah, like I said,
we do listen for live stream updates through Podping, and it is a tremendous innovation
because it allows you to send all kinds of real-time notifications to podcast apps.
Yeah, I'm looking forward to seeing just more and more apps adopt that over time. I'm sure
there'll be things to work out, but so I've kind of been, you know, sampling different podcasting
2.0 apps recently, and it's made me appreciate just how freaking hard it is to actually build
a podcast app. And I think a lot of people, when they look at a podcast app, they think,
how hard could it be? It's RSS feeds. It goes and gets files from the RSS feed, and then it plays
it using a built-in API. Like, how hard is that? But what I've discovered chatting with Oscar from
Fountain and just kind of using these different apps is that this is actually a really hard problem
to solve. And I'm curious, what are some of the biggest challenges that you guys run into? Is it
like user expectation stuff? Is it like code stuff? What are the big challenges on creating Podverse
maybe you didn't expect? Biggest challenges are typically just because the content is all hosted
by the podcasters themselves. And if you were to go through a platform, let's say like YouTube,
which is totally centralized, they control how everything goes into it and how everything goes
out of it. It's much easier to know what to expect as a programmer and how to code for those
situations. But with podcasting, there's some self-hosting involved. And so there's different
file types that might not work, handling all the different conditions that you end up running into
over five million podcast feeds in the world. Another problem for us is dynamic ads, because
we are a clip sharing, like that's one of our primary features is clip sharing. And dynamic ads
will screw up the timestamps. So if I say, here's a clip from three minutes to five minutes in this
show, and it's just a reference point, and then we send that in a link to somebody, if they're
dynamic ads, it might jump to 30 seconds ahead or behind. Of course. Right. So how do you solve
for that even? Can you solve for that? For now, we just don't. Dynamic ads are just not our favorite
thing. And to be honest, for some podcasts, it works great if they don't have dynamic ads. If
they do, you still get an approximation of the clip. We're open to solving it in better ways,
but we really don't ever get complaints about it. It seems like people just, most shows don't use
dynamic ads. And that's such a big problem to solve. And we would have to do our own detection
and we'd have to figure out other people's rules that they could change on a whim. We would need a
standard that we can follow reliably. Yeah, really would. You would have hoped, just a crazy idea,
but you would have hoped a standard like that would have been created before dynamic ads started
rolling out. But this is the result of nothing really evolving in the podcast industry for the
last 15 plus years. So on the topic of funding, I'd really like to pick your brain as a developer
and as somebody who's implementing this stuff, what are your thoughts on the boostagrams,
value for value, and building an application on top of the lightning network? How has that whole
thing gone? Value for value is very exciting. This is one of those developments that I didn't see
coming with all the eight years of working on this app until podcasting 2.0 came along.
Yes, so it's the ability to send value. In our case, it's Bitcoin directly to the podcaster,
content creator, as you're listening. So we've been out of this for a long time until recently.
There's been other podcasting 2.0 apps doing this, and we only recently were able to get
involved with it through the Albee extension. It's very exciting to be able to support creators
directly without having to go through middlemen. And yet Albee allows us a way where we, as an app,
don't have to be custodians of people's wallets, which was a big sticking point for us, that we
want to be able to facilitate these payments, donations basically, or boosts as we call them,
but we don't want to control people's wallets at the end of the day. We don't want to be stewards
of it. That's just so far outside of scope of what we're trying to do as a podcast app.
Yeah, I could totally understand that. So if I'm using Podverse to boost a podcast,
does Podverse get a split in there to help sustain development? Have you guys talked about doing
something like that? So currently, it's voluntary. We do offer the ability to send us a split. So
on the website, if you are on a value-enabled podcast, which there's over 6,000 value-enabled
podcasts currently. Including our own podcasts. Including your own. And the wonderful podcasting
2.0 pod. It's actually an open source library that anybody can add to a website if they want.
It's a web component. You just load a script through a CDN, and then you put a web component
on the page. Which, if people are familiar with HTML, it's just a very simple element that you
put on the page. And then it generates this form, which then calls webln methods. There's a new
standard called webln, and it allows browsers to interact with browser extensions. So you can
have browser extensions, is how I think of it. So ALBEE is webln compatible, and that form is
webln compatible. So if you have ALBEE installed on your browser, then that form will be enabled.
It'll be able to send messages to the ALBEE extension, and then ALBEE goes ahead and sends
Bitcoin to the creators. Fascinating. I've been wondering about ALBEE. It looked like maybe
I'd want to check out. I actually installed the extension, but I haven't set it up yet. I really
like the idea of having it on a web form. Some people just love their existing podcast app.
They don't want to switch. That must be something you guys are constantly thinking about, too.
Some people. Not everybody. Some people are still using the default podcast app.
Some people have made a real conscious decision to switch apps. What are your thoughts on getting
people to entice them to try out Podverse? It's a really difficult problem, and I think
I'm really bad at marketing, so I don't have a great answer. You understand how people get
entrenched in whatever habits, whatever platform you're using. It has to take something really
compelling to pull you into a new app. I don't really have a solution other than that. We just
keep trying to add exciting features, try to do things in what we think is the right way,
where we're all free and open source software. We don't sell people's information. We don't spam
people. We don't add our own advertisements and stuff like that. We're just trying to make the
best product we can, and hopefully word of mouth will take hold. That kind of raises something I've
been thinking a lot about lately, though, which is how it would be nice if our apps could share
data between themselves in compatible ways to make it easier for people to switch between apps.
Not just in, like, I'm going from app A and now app B is my new app, but that you could bounce
between the two. It's conceivable if we have export-import standards between apps, but to my
knowledge, I'm not aware of existing standards for that. So that is something I'd like to explore.
You have support for OPML imports now, right?
Yes. OPML is good for your podcast...
Manual.
...manual. Well, it's your podcast subscriptions,
but what about your listening history? Like, since we're syncing across devices,
a lot of people actually like the mark as played feature. Like, we get emails about it saying,
you know, if it's not working, they'll tell us, like, hey, I want to see which ones I've listened
to already. That was a big draw for me for Podverse. You know, I'm listening in the car
and then I get back to get down to the studio. I want to finish it up on my studio speakers.
I like to play it on my desktop, so syncing between them is... That's got to be an interesting
challenge. I was curious, too, what your thoughts are on cross-app comments. I see a couple of
different trajectories in the podcasting 2.0 community right now. Some podcast apps are already
just going all in with the lightning comments. What are your thoughts on cross-podcast app
comments? So maybe I'm on Podverse and I leave a comment and somebody's on Fountain,
they leave a comment. In theory, no matter what app you're on, you'd be able to read those comments.
Yeah, well, so at least one version of it is very doable, which we've already implemented on
web and mobile. So yeah, the idea is a unifying thread, like the podcaster has one thread in
particular they want all of the apps to use, which is a brilliant idea and very useful, I think,
rather than being scattered across 10 different comment threads.
Amen to that.
The part that I'm not sure how we accomplish is sending comments through the app. So currently,
the way we have it set up is it'll render the comments, but if you want to leave a comment,
you have to press it and it'll open the web page that is where it actually is hosting the comment.
And I see it's doing a little bit of thinking as it collects them, too.
I get nervous when a loading spinner takes more than three seconds.
Hey, but it was because there's a big picture in there. That's why
somebody loaded up a big picture in their comment. I didn't even know you could do that.
Yeah, so this is Activity Pub, which is like a federated,
I would compare it to Twitter and people's common experience.
Sort of like Mastodon's back end, right?
Yes.
I'm vaguely familiar with it because I know PeerTube uses that as well.
So there's like a root comment and we just collect all the comments based on that and then
we render them in there. And if you were to click on it, it would open that Mastodon instance and
you could then leave comments through that page. So we have that set up with Activity Pub and also
Twitter.
And then, of course, the Fountain App's been experimenting with lightning comments, which
I think I think Activity Pub makes more sense to me just from a technical standpoint.
But I'd be curious to pick your brain on what you think about lightning comments.
It doesn't really fit with what we're trying to do.
I don't we haven't thought about it very much. I don't see the value added.
If there's more demand from listeners and podcasters, it's something we could explore more.
But we're not really like a crypto first app or a podcasting first app.
It just so happens that it's getting really easy to add these value enabled features.
And it's an exciting thing to participate in. So we're going down that road.
I like it. I'm glad you I think that's a good balance to strike.
And I think Bitcoin and lightning is the safer of any of the cryptos to enable.
So I think that was a you know, it's a nice, I'd say, cautious move that is really I mean,
the boost I get, I love them, man. I love them.
They're the I've been doing this for 15 years and I've never had an interaction with the audience
like I get with the boost.
And then the other thing that's really neat and you may have noticed this as well is I noticed
a bit of a community growing in podcasting today. I'll hear some of the same folks boost other shows
and then, you know, I kind of get to know people through them boosting other shows and stuff.
It's been really, really neat.
What I love about what you guys what you guys are doing is you've touched on a couple of times.
It's free software.
Could we just expand on that just a little bit to kind of wrap this up?
Why free software? What's the licensing?
And are you ever going to make money at doing this if it's if it's all free software?
Yeah, well, hopefully, hopefully.
Partly, I just love open source software and it's like motivated me to learn software.
It's hard to maybe explain, but just ever since I was a kid growing up in the 90s,
I just thought it was amazing that you could create something for free and give it away
all across the world instantly.
It's just like one of the coolest concepts.
I get it.
Obviously, you do. Linux unplugged. You get it.
Also, it's just we're trying to make software we really want to use and something that gets
in the way of what we want to use is advertisements and tracking.
And the perfect app in my mind wouldn't be closed software because what are we trying
to accomplish with that?
Just make money, I assume.
Like so open source allows us to be transparent.
People know exactly how our code works if they want to inspect it.
So we have nothing to hide.
And also, people can make it better if people don't like how we're managing our platform.
If we make some sort of decision to remove content, for example, and people are unhappy
with it, they have access to all the tools we have to start their own instance with it.
I think it fits with the spirit of podcasting too.
Podcasting is a mostly open platform in itself.
So yeah, that's the primary.
I just I love open source software and it excites me.
And there's also not that many great open source podcast apps.
There are many open, but they're kind of like hobbies or like a side project, like a weekend
thing somebody did for a couple months before this.
The only one I was really aware of is AntennaPod, which is Android only and it's a great app.
But Android only.
I'm not even sure what the leading iOS open source app would be.
Probably Podverse.
Maybe, maybe now I hope.
I mean, I love it.
You know, the only thing if I could if I as a podcaster could have anything I wanted from
Podverse, I know it's going to be really crazy, but I'd love to be able to embed your player
on my website so that it's a basic player on my website with all the play controls that
you guys have and the artwork display and the description display that it could expand.
And then if they wanted to click into it, they just go into Podverse and be in the whole
Podverse experience or something like that.
But something I could embed on my page because we're looking at rebuilding our website.
And we're looking at what we want to use as our podcast playback when people just want
to listen on the website.
None of them are as good as Podverse's, you know.
Wow, well, thank you.
Thanks.
It's funny you say that because it's like one of my top items on my whiteboard is embed.
Oh, really?
Embedding is coming soon.
Well, let me know.
Let me know.
Yeah, we saw guys who have been promoting us a lot.
They're doing they're just been really nice.
The sleek podcast.
They ended up embedding our whole web page in an iFrame on their site.
It's like, OK, go ahead.
That's one way I suppose.
I'm looking for something a little more low key.
No, no, we'll have a proper clean design for it.
Well, Mitch, thank you, sir, for coming on here and chatting with me.
I'll have a link to Podverse.fm if people want to check it out.
Of course, Office Hours is in there and I can link to Office Hours.
So I'll do that.
That'll be in Podverse.
I mean, what else do we anything we didn't touch on that you'd like to mention or anything
about support or anything like that, just to let you know anything kind of open ended
for you to touch on before we wrap up?
Not really.
Just if anybody has any questions or feedback, Podverse.fm.
We have multiple contact options through there.
Also, if anybody is interested in helping with translations, we have a translations
community and we're trying to we have this nice setup that makes it really easy for people
just pop in and start translating words and you don't have to translate everything just
like here and there if you translate some words and then it ends up automatically getting
making a PR that goes to our repo.
It's called Web Blade.
I'm not sure if you've ever heard of it before.
I'll have to look into that.
That sounds really great.
It's really cool.
That actually makes it possible, huh?
That's so cool.
Also, I should mention Podverse is probably in your local app store.
You know, go find it there.
App Store, Android and F-droid.
Hey, F-droid, good man.
I love to see that.
Very good.
I will keep up the good work.
All right.
Thanks, man.
A special thank you to Mitch for joining us, spending a little bit extra time coming into
the office and hanging out and the hard work he and his co-founder are doing on Podverse.
We'll have links to Podverse's main page, office hours in there and also their GitHub
because it is all open source.
So we'll have all that there.
Hey, Brent, little breaking news here in the studio.
Really?
While we were, yeah, while we were watching that, I got a knock on the door.
And who was it?
That's kind of random.
I mean, you know, I did not expect this, but it was FedEx and they were arriving with my
review unit for the HP Dev1 laptop.
That is impressive.
Well, I know it's just a white box at this point, but geez, I kind of feel like this might
turn into like a box opening video all of a sudden.
Oh, and I got there's a little note in here.
There's a little note in here.
It says, thank you for taking the time to check out our Dev1 notebook.
Hope you enjoy it as much as we do.
Looking forward to hearing what you think about it.
Best, HP Dev1 and System76.
That's awesome.
So I'm curious what you're planning on putting this thing through.
Have you thought about that at all?
Oh, you know, a battery of tests just to kind of get an idea of what the heat and fan noise
is like.
And then a lot of just functionality tests.
So my buddy Mike on Coda Radio has had his he actually bought one.
So he's had it for a few days longer.
And he did his his first impressions on Coda Radio, which came out on Wednesday.
And we talk about after we talk about WWDC, we talk about his HP Dev1.
So I'll probably give some first impressions and Linux unplugged this week, I would imagine.
I would like to know, are you going to run just whatever came on it?
Are you going to replace it as well?
Any thoughts around that?
You know, I feel like I should always run it in the default config for a period of time
and get a sense of the product.
And so a lot of times if it's something like this, because this is unique, right?
This is Pop OS on the Dev1.
This is Pop OS on HP hardware.
This is a little different.
So I feel like in that case, I am probably going to try to optimize the bulk of my review
for Pop OS, but I imagine in the last couple of days, I'll probably throw Fedora on there,
maybe NixOS on there, you know, that kind of stuff, because it's all AMD in here, right?
And my question is, is how much simpler does that make just trying out different distros?
Because I suspect it makes it much simpler.
OK, well, I'll look forward to your review.
Also, the pricing, it's about a grand.
It's not unreasonable if this is a well-built, long lasting, well-performing Linux laptop
that doesn't make too much fan noise when it's under load.
I could see this kind of being like, you know, when JB gets to the point where we're kitting
out remote hosts like yourself, this would be like the recording laptop you would get.
Because this would be so much better for you because it's so much newer and it's got GPU
acceleration that would take care of things like visualizing the audio bars that are probably
being rendered by CPU right now and that kind of stuff.
So I'm going to try it out, let you know, it literally just came along with this in
here. It wasn't in the show notes. I was kind of confused.
No, no, I'm just just throwing it at you because I had a little knock knock.
I got a message from Mike from Koda Radio that his review unit just showed up.
So I thought, oh, I'll go check to see if, you know, everybody's getting there.
So I'm sure everybody who's getting one just got theirs.
And also in the box came with the System 76 launch keyboard and this HP 935 creator wireless
mouse that they seem to be really jazzed about. So that came in the box as well.
That can either deck in the reviewers out, I suppose.
I think it's just one standard config for this.
Like when you buy it, if you go to buy it, it's just one config.
There's no customizing. But then I guess the RAM is removable.
Supposedly that might be something. I don't recognize those screw types, though.
Oh, that's never a good. I don't know how I don't know how upgradeable it is.
You have to call your machinist friend to come design some screwdrivers for you.
Yeah. Is that you?
It could be. Yes, it could be.
Is that Alex? Who's my machinist friend?
Anyone local? We need someone.
I need to know this guy. This is important.
Well, that's very exciting.
Let's do a few boosts there, Mr. Brent.
Yeah, we got some great boosts. I recognize some names. You know,
they're starting to get very familiar here. Marcel wrote in seven days ago with
thirty thirty sats, which I feel like there's a bunch of subliminal messages in those.
Thirty thirty, huh?
I see some down the line with equally obscure numbers, but who knows?
Boy, this one's this one. I usually have a guess. This one has me stumped.
Marcel will have to reveal because I have no guess.
Yes, please let us know. So Marcel writes, I know you all know this,
but injected ads into podcasts are the worst.
They're jarring and 90 percent of the time something I would never, ever be interested in.
I've stopped listening to podcasts because of it. I know podcasters need to eat,
which is why I boost and support Jupiter.Party. I also support lame podcasting 1.0 shows on Patreon.
I like how the J.B. ads are recorded by you and how they're different every time.
I signed up for Linode for that exact reason. Thanks for not doing injected ads.
Yeah, I've always felt like that's part of the value of our reads is that we do them
and we get like hands on with the product. I can't say I would never, ever, ever consider
dynamic ads because I heard from the podcasting 2.0 pod that I think it was pod being has
supposedly created, supposedly created this system that transcribes the podcast.
Then it uses some magic A.I. to figure out a natural beat to put a cut.
And then when it puts a cut in there, it underplays a little bit of a jingle
as the as the host was finishing their sentence, a little bit of a jingle
into the ad start, then the ad plays and then a little bit of a jingle back.
And it resumes where the podcaster was continuing to speak with all with the music fading out.
And then on top of that, supposedly it'll even auto update the chapters and split them into
part one and part two so it doesn't mess with the chapter markers and stuff like that.
I don't like it. I'll just be honest with you. The value, I think, is in the back catalog,
perhaps for some podcasters. So imagine a little behind the scenes here, Marcel.
It's like we do these shows and some of these shows continued to get downloaded
for a decade almost. If somebody were to go listen to an old episode of Linux action show,
they'd hear an ad for GoDaddy in there right now. Would it make sense to slice that out
and instead put a, you know, a current sponsor in there if it was a difference between
the podcaster, you know, making or breaking it? Maybe I don't know, but I think it has to be done
right. Maybe the folks at Podbean are starting to figure it out. The tech still new and people just
rushed to it because it was, in my opinion, an easy way to make money on your back catalog.
So True Grit's boosted in seven days ago with 3409 stats, which I think that's a Tesla thing.
I don't get the reference, but someone will fill us in.
Says you mentioned on a live stream once that you were testing out PeerTube
and that tended to be generally behind, say, maybe Twitch or YouTube because of the peer
to peer streaming nature. What if the live streams were actually streamed to PeerTube first
and then sent out to YouTube and Twitch after that? Would that solve the problem or would it
just make it worse? That's a great question. Very on point true grits with today's episode, too.
We are considering that, but probably not. I'll probably keep going to Twitch and YouTube until
they stop giving me free bandwidth, which I assume is inevitable. My my dread and I know this just
sounds like conspiracy bacon right now, but my dread is that some Western government is going to
outlaw encryption in some way and that it's going to create a horrible conflict in the free software
community. And I'm going to fall on the side that encryption should be available to everyone,
that it's a human right. And so I, you know, I could see a day and age without me doing anything
politically controversial, without me like, you know, becoming like the Alex Jones of podcasting.
I could see the current status quo shifting to where maybe, you know, my stuff is labeled as
dangerous or misinformation or something like that, because I'm not, you know, I don't know.
I mean, I'm just thinking what could happen. I'm also thinking what if one day I wanted to
get down the road and not have a Google account, that kind of stuff. That's just been on my mind,
you know, but so I think about until they kick me off, we might as well take the free bandwidth and
get the free network effect. And then what we'll do is we'll just do more stuff on the
peer tube over time. We'll stream earlier over there where we can play whatever we want without
getting, you know, kicked off like the WWDC stream or some special event or like, you know,
cooking with Brent and true grits actually sent in a double boost. They're going to say that
they're still waiting on the membership feed to support boosts. Chris, what's going on with this?
Can you update us? It cuts. It cuts. It cuts. Yeah, it's in the progress. We have to build
a bunch of tooling. So my plan is to start actually with the office hours and self-hosted
member feeds we're working on and probably eventually code a radio member feed and make
them boostable first. You know, once we get that kind of dialed in, probably transition
the older shows, but not start necessarily with the biggest and the oldest show. You know what I
mean? I want to break everything first. I feel like office hours is the place where we get to play and
often things might not work, but often it might lead to some great things. Thanks for the double
boost, true grits. Nev boosted in seven days ago, 500 sets. I think the best part of the live feeds
are the conversations you and the community have. For example, when the Libidwadia changes dropped
and we're all complaining about Gnome, a Gnome contributor came in one day and there was quite
the long debate about an hour long between Neil and him. In my opinion, content like that should
be available somewhere, even if it's behind a paywall. I often find myself commenting on the
live feeds more than on the shows themselves. I specifically remember that episode. It was
fabulous. Um, we kind of let that discussion go on because it was, there was so much quality there.
And I think, did we, did we do the show late by an hour because of it or? Yeah, yeah, I think so.
And then it, and then it continued after we wrapped up the show, it continued. It sure did. Yeah. The
show is just like an earmark in that conversation. Um, but that is available to members, right?
Jupiter.party. So if you are a member, it is on the feeds there. So that would be a good place
to find it if you're looking for it. I believe the episode is fairly easy to find. I don't have
it on the tip of my tongue, but, um, you can use, uh, notes.jupiterbroadcasting.com to, uh, find
when that was mentioned. Boost! Dylann wrote in seven days ago, 3500 sets. Great to see you so
motivated on a new show like this. Excited to see more of office hours. Well, it's really cause
Brent keeps showing up. Let's be honest. No, I am very excited about office hours. I've been
enjoying it. The one thing I'd like to expand on in the pre and post show is interaction with the
mumble room and just asking questions about what's going on at JB or in the matrix room,
but we're getting there. We can also do it through boosts. Uh, and so far we've been doing this
sponsor free. I think that'll probably change next quarter, but, uh, right now I've just,
you know, we've just kind of been doing it to see as a grand experiment, but I think it'll stick
around. I've been enjoying it. And I really appreciate you guys boosting in subscribing,
trying to find it in the, in fountain when you can't find it. Like everybody, I feel like people
have been going above and beyond to participate in the show. So I am super grateful. Uh, our buddy,
Dave Jones came in this week. Boost! He says, uh, man, I'm loving office hours. I just started
listening. What is open sets? So Dave, Dave boosted in 2000, 112 sets, 15%, uh, 15% split of that is
going to go to open sets. 50% of all of the boost to office hours and Linux unplugged for the last
three weeks have been contributed to open sets. OpenSats is a 501c charity that contributes 100%
of the funds sent to their general fund, which is what we're doing. They send 100% of that to free
software projects. And a big reason why JB is embracing boosts and lightning payments is because
I actually believe this is a way through our audience. We can build a network of people
participating in this payment system that will then be in a position to support free software
when free software projects come online. And that's a big part. It's like, this is like a
five, six year pic, you know, picture that I have in my head, but that's where I see this going.
And I think it starts here. And I believe open sets could be an avenue to that future. So I've,
we've been contributing for three weeks. This will be the last episode because this is the
last episode of the month, by the way. And cause I'm going to be off the week that in two weeks.
And so that's what we've been doing for the last three weeks. We've been given open sets a cut.
I love them. I looked into them. They look completely legit. You can also contribute
to their operational costs if you like, but right now we're just doing the general fund.
So it all 100% goes to free software, a lot of it in the Bitcoin ecosystem, some of it,
the best software in the Bitcoin ecosystem. And it's just been our way to contribute back
to open source. And it's been nice. Like we've sent some money their way, which I think is really
great. You know, I did notice that, uh, Dave sent in two, one, one, two sets. And, uh, if you're a
rush fan, that's one of their more famous albums. So I don't know if that was intentional, but
you know, send some love. I could see it being intentional. You have to let us know, Dave,
Dave. The golden dragon wrote in as well. Big ups for boosts. I think that the split
for open sets is phenomenal. Helping to fund open source projects in a meaningful way is
always a plus one in my book. See you next boost. Thanks for opening the office. These are so fun.
Thanks golden dragon. See you next boost. How about this one? Turquoise Fox boosted in seven
days ago with 10,000 sats boost. And, uh, the boost to Graham just says fund the open source.
Marcel wrote in again, double boost, by the way, cannot find office hours in fountain
tried with Chris and Jupiter broadcasting, but, uh, didn't find anything. Sorry about that. That
has been tricky. I did contact them and I haven't heard anything back on that. Although then, uh,
I noticed that, uh, Lima boosted in and said that they were able to find the right version of the
show and send it to that. So I don't know, man. And for me at first, it wasn't showing up.
And then I got ahold of the devs and told them like, you know, this show isn't showing up,
but it's in the podcast index. And then I went back immediately to like get a screenshot for them.
And I searched for it again and it fricking showed up. See, Chris, I'm just curious if it,
if it wasn't showing up for Marcel, how did he boost in the show? You must have snatched this
some other way. He could have been using breeze. Oh, okay. Okay. Or there might've been a boost
where Marcel explained it and I missed it, but that's a good question. I would like to know how
a mystery, a mystery. Maybe we just passed the test. I don't know. Gene Bean wrote in as well,
another double boost as a podcaster at what level of sats per minute does the streaming of sats
while people are listening become financially beneficial versus just a nice gesture?
This is a fabulous question. That's a great question. So to be clear right now,
I don't really see it as a replacement. I see it as an addition because messaging into the show
is a tricky thing and airtime is a very valuable thing. And so this has always been a balance that
we've really tried to strike here on the show. And so this has been the first time when there has
been a medium where somebody could send us a message from the podcast app while they're
listening. And I would receive it in a web app that gives me a feed of people's comments. And
here's the best part. I can't reply. There are times I would love to. I've even thought about
trying to figure out how to sometimes, but the best part is that I cannot reply. I probably
spend 20% of my working time, maybe even more than that, really managing, interacting with the
community. It is a massive chunk of my job. And so to be able to have something that comes in
that I can process as a JSON feed, that I can export as a CSV file, or that I can read in a
web interface and it's tagged with episodes, game changer for production, game changer for how I
receive feedback. And I love how fresh it is because there's coming right from the podcast
app. So I see this as a way to take something that has been sort of out of balance from the
beginning of podcasting to balancing it now. And I don't see it really replacing memberships or
sponsors forever, but I do wonder if there was some massive economic downturn and sponsorships
pulled back or people got really sick with memberships and everybody just got membership
fatigue. So we had less Jupiter party members. I could see that maybe over time people transition
to small amounts via streaming sets, but spread across thousands of listeners. Maybe it would add
up, but I've never really done the math because I don't really see it getting there for quite a
while. We're so early on this, right? There's really still so much infrastructure to be built.
We don't even have yet a way to do this from like the website. That's all that would have to be
figured out. I'd like a way for people to be able to boost from the matrix chat room using a bot,
all that kind of stuff. It's getting here. It's close. We're just not there yet. So I don't see
it. I don't see it replacing anything yet. I love the idea. I suppose if I had any fantasy
about the future, it would be me living in my RV somewhere beautiful off-grid with my
internet connected dish somehow. My space dish. I'm living off of boosts because I would just
live minimal, you know, quietly. It's just somewhere peaceful where nobody was around,
just me and my podcast. And I get on and talk to my internet buddies. That'd be fine by me.
And every now and then I come into town, you know, I do that for spurts of time now.
I think it's a great question to keep in mind, you know, in the future of this development.
You know, in a year from now, we should ask ourselves the exact same question.
That's a good one to ponder.
That is a good one. We also got a thank you boost in from Dylan. He sent 500 sats
into office hour three.
That's actually a double.
Yeah, he was just sending a boost into office hours three welcoming into the Suspenders Club.
I am a, I am rocking suspenders. It's funny as a man, there's not a lot of things people
will comment on your appearance about, but like, if you change your hair or you shave
your face or, or now I've discovered if you put suspenders on, it now becomes a topic
of conversation that is socially acceptable, apparently for anyone to talk about. I, on
the other hand, am very uncomfortable about anyone commenting on my appearance at all.
Right? Like I always find it very awkward. Like I, I find like I leaned into the hair
thing, obviously that fight I just gave into, cause let's be honest, come on.
But like the, like the suspenders stuff and the beard stuff, I always find it very weird.
You know, it's very uncomfortable. A little bit of news before we wrap up.
Brett, check this out. You're familiar with Umbral.
Oh yeah. You made me play with it a whole bunch of times.
It's one of my new loves of 2022. It is a personal server OS for self-hosting
with a brilliant app store, tons of some of the best free software out there.
Plus it integrates nicely and with Tor. So you can have things that are technically
accessible remotely, but without opening a port on your firewall.
And it's how we do our Bitcoin lightning node. So when people send in sets,
it's landing on an Umbral node that's physically here in the studio.
One bit of feedback that Umbral got, and I got it too is, Hey, I love that, you know,
I can run my own Bitwarden or I can run my own mumble server, or I can run all of this stuff,
but I don't really want to run a Bitcoin node. I don't want to allocate 500 gigs of disk space.
And now with Umbral 0.5, which came out today, as we are recording, they have extracted the
lightning node and Bitcoin node as their own components that are an app that you can install.
So you can now install Umbral just as an app platform to run things nicely inside Docker,
and then if you want it to be a Bitcoin node, you just install that app. And along with that,
they've completely redone the UI. So they got a whole new look and they've now introduced the
ability for apps to be independently updated without having to do a whole OS update like
they had in the past. Before you'd have to update the entire image. Now they've broken that out.
They've also got some credential management stuff built in here now.
I'm very excited about this update, Brent. I feel like, again, if you've got a Raspberry Pi
sitting around or something equivalent, this is fantastic. You could go get this going up
in seconds, but I feel like they just they took it to the next level with this release
because not only did they uncouple the Bitcoin and lightning node stuff, which is, I think,
something you should install, even if you don't use lightning much. It's nice to just
help decentralize the network. I love that kind of stuff, but I think it's smart that
they detached that. And then the other thing they've done that's really smart
is they've now got an official one liner that you can copy and paste. You got to make that
determination if it's safe or not for yourself, but a one liner that you can copy and paste now
and you can get up and up and running on any Debian or Ubuntu based system. So it doesn't
even have to be a Raspberry Pi anymore. You don't have to do any weird scripts like I did.
They've now got an official simple one line install to take any Ubuntu or Debian based system
and make it run as an umbral box. And then once you've done that, you get their platform for
installing applications, managing them, and it is great. It is really great. I know you could just
run stuff in Docker because you're a big shot out there, but this is so great. I don't often I don't
often brag about like these things that let you I'm not even a portainer guy. Like I'm not I'm not
a Web UI to manage your containers guy. But man, is this great and I am big on sovereign data and
bringing your stuff home and I am big on decentralized computing and I'm big on putting
your stuff on your own land. So this has like prism in there. It has Pyhole, it has Node-RED,
it has Nextcloud, Home Assistant, Uptime Kuma, so many great apps, plus a bunch of stuff for the
Bitcoin ecosystem and the Lightning ecosystem. So it just felt like a special day because we
got a brand new version of PeerTube today. We've been talking about that. And we got a brand new
version of umbral, which has been in the works forever. And they all landed right as we were
recording. This is a huge step for both these projects. And for umbral, 0.5 now marks the first
release as just a general personal server OS. I feel like they're doing a good job of listening
to their audience. We've mentioned a few times, you know, this is this is the second time in this
show some project listens to some of your hopes for where the project can go. But it does also
seem like a little bit of a shift of direction for them, which I'm curious on your opinion of
that. You know, they kind of came in as the Bitcoin, you know, making your Bitcoin node
easy to get up and running, especially on a Raspberry Pi. And now it seems like they're
maybe I'll call it maturing or refocusing slightly to being sort of a, you know,
run your great community Docker containers here. Oh, by the way, we also do Bitcoin and
lightning nodes. So I wonder what you think of that. That'd be good interview question. My sense
of it would be they got into this market and realized what a demand there is for doing this
right. And realize that they could address even more people if they decoupled the Bitcoin stuff.
And I think that's a clever insight. And I think they're doing in a way that isn't making it any
less of its original purpose. It's still it's still great as a Bitcoin node. In fact, I'd argue
this is even a better way to do it now because now you can update that independently of the major OS.
It's a tight line to walk. If we get an opportunity to chat with them,
I might take them up on that. I think I think we should try to do that. Sounds fascinating.
All right, Brantley, let's see. We're not going to have an episode for this month after this.
This is only one episode because our regular episode on the 21st that would be live and then
released on the Friday the 24th. Well, I'm going to be in Montana with the family. So we're taking
that week off, but we'll be back after that. You can always check out Jupiter broadcasting
dot com slash calendar for our live times. And of course, if you just follow Jupiter tube,
you'll know when we go live as well and you can always hang out there. And of course,
the show comes out on Fridays. If you go to office hours dot hair slash subscribe,
you get the RSS feed and then you don't got to worry about it. It's true. Go get more Brent
on Linux unplugged. There's always stuff going on over there. I always appreciate that. So true.
So true, Brent. How true is it, Chris? It's so true. It's time to close the door.
Clear out, everybody. Office hours are over. Go on. Get out of here.