This is KOTORadio, episode 410 for April 20th, 2021.
Hello one, hello all, welcome in to KOTORadio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show taking
a pragmatic look at the art and business of software development and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by Cloud Guru.
You know, Cloud Guru has Cloud Playground, Azure, AWS, and Google's infrastructure in
their sandboxes on their credit card, not yours.
Sweet.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at cloudguru.com.
My name is Chris and picking out his orange iMac, it is our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
So say we all.
You're really on this BSG thing.
Can I tell you, those of you who closely follow me and perhaps former members of my family
on Twitter know that the old Mike has been having a bad time and yeah, Chris just laughs.
You found a happy place in BSG, you know, is that what you're telling me?
No, I'm in love with the president and I don't mean Sleepy Joe.
I mean president Laura, Airlock, Rosalind, right?
President Rosalind.
You know what?
I got bad news about Rosalind though, bro.
She's got, she's got, well, I don't want to spoil it for you, but you better brace yourself
for some bad news.
Oh no.
Is she a Cylon too?
Have you not seen the end of BSG?
Yeah, I've seen the end where it's like a huge disappointment.
I'm not sure I would say that.
You could describe it as a collapse of a television show in front of our eyes.
Somebody let the writers get a little too up their ass about it, but no, absolutely.
I completely agree.
I think it, I think, I think the ending of BSG is a travesty, especially when you could
remember that it started with that mini series that was so fricking epic.
So okay, you know what, f**k Apple, let's just go into BSG today.
The core concept of BSG was there are some humans left from 12 colonies, right?
We're together so far and there's a magical 13th colony that we're worried about, right?
Like we don't know about the 13th colony.
Earth is amazing.
We don't know about Earth, right?
But my love, and I really hope to be my second wife, Madame President Rosalyn, always has
a whiteboard behind her of the remaining survivors.
And that number tends to go in the, how can we put this?
If you were in the Robin Hood app, that number would be read all the time.
It's in a bad direction, for sure.
You know what?
They're a little militant and I won't say fascist, but maybe a fash, no, they're straight
up fascist, right?
I mean, they are fascist.
Well you're in for a ride, my friend.
You are in for a ride with her.
So I got to tell you, I want to have a brief conversation about Gaius Baltar and why he
should be hung by his balls.
This is relevant, you know, because people, this is what people are talking about today.
This is what people are talking about in 2021.
Mike has discovered the 90s.
Hey man, I'm the guy over here watching Seinfeld, so have at it, because at least yours is newer
than mine.
So I just find something about a beautiful redhead who's totally willing to kill like
everybody.
I mean, if you haven't seen Battlestar, like.
You should watch Voyager then.
You might like Janeway.
I do like Janeway, but Janeway is a little too like girl power there.
Roslin's like, it's not that I'm a girl, I just want to kill everybody.
She's just like die.
Janeway is just really motivated by coffee.
That's really what, that's, that's, that's the thing about Janeway.
She does seem to have some addiction issues, which again, I totally sympathize with.
Well, good news for you.
You didn't have to spend money on a Thaleo because nobody wrote in claiming that they're
making an independent living with desktop Linux yet.
Yes, I like making bets that I know I'm going to win.
Yeah, yeah, you got that one, right?
Although I think we both thought the Discord would end up selling to Microsoft and just
breaking as we start recording today, Microsoft and Discord have broken off their talks and
Discord has announced they're going to go the IPO route.
So that's ended.
I thought that would happen.
I'm going to explain Discord to me.
It's slack for, for casual people.
It's like, it's like gamified up a little bit slack, a little, little more casual, a
little more community and gaming oriented.
So no spreadsheets.
Yeah.
More consumer focused features like Twitch integration and, and other things like Reddit
integration right out of the box, that kind of stuff.
You know, I like it.
It's just, I don't know.
It's just, I'm not a huge fan of yet one more communications platform controlled by one central
group of people.
So I haven't really gone crazy with it.
There is a Jupiter broadcasting discord, but it's kind of on pause while I figure out what
I'm doing with matrix.
And why is this better than IRC?
The same reason slack is, you know, you get besides just your previews and more rich text
chat and emojis and you know, gotta have your animated GIFs, but you got voice chat and
video calls and there's other features and there's a good permissions model.
And of course getting it spun up and started is super crazy easy to get your own server
going.
It's like just a couple of clicks.
It's like, for example, actually, I know several projects that are just using discord now to,
to coordinate their, their project work, like the Ubuntu mate distribution uses discord
because it's cheap, you know, it's free for them.
I think in most cases and I'm sorry, but mate, Ubuntu, I don't know.
Yeah.
I know.
Uh, and uh, it works, you know, and the young people love it.
That's the other thing.
A lot of, not a lot of network effect kids these days, Mike, they love it.
I bet they also like, you know, freedom of expression and shiny iPads with liquid.
What is it?
Liquid, uh, liquid retina, HDR, XDR, double micro mini led.
Craig Federico, you're just making shit up now, aren't you?
They totally are.
Uh, so yeah, we are recording on Tuesday this week because we wanted to give you our sort
of instant reaction to the apple news and event and find out if either one of us bought
anything.
Uh, but before we do, we do have like just a couple of emails.
Maybe we'll just do that since, you know, feedback's a huge part of this show.
Daniel writes in and he's just kind of throwing down, he says, hit me up, Mike.
I've had enough.
I'm going to fix your genome shell wallpaper problem.
We had a couple of people write in, they don't know what we're referring to.
I guess they, you know, they need to listen to the whole back catalog obviously.
Oh, gather round children.
Wait, hold on.
You know what you just did, right?
You just gave me, you just gave me an opportunity there.
Stay a while and listen.
Ah, my, my uncle.
So, uh, gnomus functional is, uh, for all, you know, intensive purposes, functionally
broken because the extensions can crash the entire shell.
That's the problem.
You had that happen with an extension that literally was just rotating your background
wallpaper.
But it's just me, right?
It's, I mean, thousands of people have had this happen, maybe tens of thousands.
I'm sure tens of thousands.
I think it's gotten better.
So some people are not as familiar with the problem as they used to be when you first
ran into it.
Um, I would say something being about add architecture choices, but I won't, right?
It's architecturally nothing's changed so it can totally still happen, but this problem
still exists.
If you have an unstable extension, it will crash your entire shell.
That's why the guys over at system 76, the folks over at system 76 are using typescript
and rust to build everything they're doing.
Yeah.
They're coming out with their own shell, right?
Isn't it a cosmic cosmic?
Thank you.
Yeah.
That's interesting.
I mean, I think, I mean, it's easy to say it on a, on a lame podcast where we only love
Apple and we hit all our operating systems.
There you go.
YouTube.
I gave it to you.
But in theory, if you could silo off the extension processes from the actual shell, that would
basically solve the problem.
Yeah.
Like even just if it just killed all extensions, but the rest of the shell kept going.
Well, you can't kill all extensions though, right?
Because most of genome shell is actually extensions.
Good point.
Think about pop OS, all of pop OS is basically like your solution would be each extension
has its own process.
Well, I would actually pose a question.
What is the failure case that putting high res images, switching on a monitor, like a
five K monitor crashes the extension, which therefore crashes genome shell when pop OS,
all of their stuff or not all, but a lot of their stuff right now, I know they're doing
cosmic, but right now are basically good.
No extensions.
Cosmic will be as well.
Cosmic is a series of extensions.
It's effectively extensions, but that does not bring down your system.
If like moving a window, using their magical keyboard stuff, you know, they're, you know,
their title.
This is the dichotomy of the free and open source desktop is it all comes down to experience
of the developer code quality.
You know, they're building things with standards and a certain practice and the style of testing
that they're doing in house and not every extension developer is doing anything near
that.
Okay.
And because of the architecture of the shell, it can become a problem, right?
I guess I would be more merciful to the extension developers that the Arctic architecture of
the shell makes it very easy to make very stupid mistakes, but yeah, I wish I had a
good explanation because it still bothers me as well.
So I think they're aware of the problem because I had a conversation with Neil McGovern, who
is the executive director of the Gnome Foundation, and they're kind of tackling it in like pieces
that they can.
So with Gnome 40, they broke off input into its own process now, and that's a big deal
because Linux can be a little weird when you got a lot of disk IO going on and then all
of a sudden you got some network IO or something.
You can get a stuttery mouse or keyboard and they've solved that by breaking that off onto
its own process.
I asked him about extensions, but I just really couldn't get a firm commitment from him on
it.
It just kind of was like, yeah, it's something we need to look into, but we think there's
a lot of ways to address that.
Yeah, no, I think it's a hard problem.
I mean, honestly, it's technical debt in a lot of ways.
Yeah, I was, you know, but Wes made a good point, you know, as he always does, damn it.
A little hippie.
I'm so jeezed.
No, he's always made it just.
Wes was right.
If he would write it in Clojure, it would be better.
No, he was pointing out that this type of market, like the users of the Linux desktop,
there's an advantage to making it something approachable.
You know, when it's JavaScript you're working with and these extensions can change a lot
of things, like that is kind of what the demographic of the Linux desktop wants.
To them, that flexibility sometimes is a premium feature.
Right.
So people who like their software not to work.
No, I get that.
Well, okay.
All right.
So Shem wrote in along the topic of JavaScript but on the server, and he wants to make the
point to you that essentially boils down to that JavaScript is great on the server if
it's for something you don't care about.
He says, I was listening to 407.
I know.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, meth is great for people I don't care about either, but keep going.
And so you guys were talking about JavaScript on the server and Mike had his rant about
the child.
I would say reasoned argument like Jordan Peterson.
Let's keep going.
Okay.
So that is at his reasoned argument about JavaScript and TypeScript.
While I agree with most of Mike's point about JavaScript and it is pretty terrible on the
server, I think you missed one aspect.
A lot of people will reach for JavaScript or Python or Ruby because they're dynamic
and you can prototype quickly, which means you can get a working back end up and running
without much fuss.
However, we see companies like GitHub.
They use these languages and as they scale, they start to buckle as you get to larger
code bases and you get tricky and trickier requirements and edge cases.
But if you're just building a small site that doesn't need any fancy back end, maybe it
won't ever get much traffic, then JavaScript or TypeScript or node or Dino will be fine.
But I think too many people pick it without realizing the limitations that you're placing
on yourself with that choice.
Thanks for the entertaining chatter.
Keep it up.
What do you think of that?
Like, it's not so bad for prototyping, especially if you're never really going to put it in
much of any kind of production.
Now now will you allow it?
I mean, I guess if I were in the Air Force and I had to really not crash my plane, I
might take amphetamines.
But I definitely wouldn't make that as a life choice.
Yeah, you don't want to fall asleep and crash the airplane.
We got a lot of different feedback around tooling again.
We got some on the subreddit, too.
Some people feel like we like I went too hard on Linux last week.
I thought we had a parlor page.
Yeah, we need to do that.
I don't know how you do that, but they're back, baby.
So I guess we better get it started.
Maybe you know, maybe it'll go big.
And I want to talk about how the topic of Mac and Linux and Windows has come up again
in the show a lot.
And it seems to kind of be a reoccurring theme and something to keep in mind on this show,
specifically this one.
Really, this is going to be a big one.
It's not Linux radio.
It is Coder radio.
And the tooling that we use to do the work has always been a big part of the conversation
on the show.
And you know, it's going through a lot of changes right now.
We've got a lot happening with Gnome Shell, like we just touched on.
Obviously, the M1 platform and Apple's tooling around that is shaking things up a lot there.
And then you have Windows making big investments in WSL.
And then there's the whole hardware side of things, right?
As far as like laptops and desktops and monitors and keyboards, like it's just kind of been
a thing again.
And a lot of that conversation is being driven by the feedback that we get into the show
at coder.show slash contact.
We really do appreciate everybody giving us their feedback on their take on all of this.
But to be clear, and I think I'm pretty confident in speaking for you on this one, Mike.
But correct me if I'm wrong.
We don't care what OS you use or what computer you use.
I care.
You should all use Snow Leopard.
Okay.
Well, there's that.
We just want you to get your work done.
You know, wear a robe and get your work done.
That's all we care about.
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
Whoa.
Okay.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
What was that last bit there?
Just something about a robe.
You know, I'm just saying.
Where is my robe?
It's probably not going to be until like the 11th or 12th that you're going to probably
start seeing it.
Uh-huh.
See, you opened the robe door, but now the door is open.
So when is the Coder Radio Limited Edition Totally Objective-C Developer Rope coming
out?
Oh, perhaps a special edition.
We should collab on this.
Yeah, you know what happened was as we were sorting out international stuffs, we totally
missed the window of manufacturing.
And I had to go with, of course, like a super fancy black one and all that.
And you understand what you did wrong, right?
You didn't listen to Madam Victoria Newman.
Yep.
Her wisdom.
Come on, give it to me.
Give me the unfiltered soundbite.
I don't know.
Can I play that on the show?
You know what I'm saying?
Yeah, do it.
Do it.
I don't even know if I have it anymore.
Hold on.
I got to check.
I might have gotten rid of it because, you know, it has a swear word in it.
Oh, my God.
Nasty words on Coder Radio.
That's never happened before.
We've never gotten caught.
There's a swear word in it.
Let's see.
What kind do I have in here?
I bet you I could find it pretty quick.
Actually, you know what I should do?
I should put this on our soundboard because it's come up twice now.
Because my deep seated hatred for the EU just.
All right.
Here you go.
This wasn't.
I wasn't going to do it.
But this is for you.
F*** the EU.
And you know what?
F*** them good.
That's all I can say.
Now, my thoughts are that, you know, whatever works for you, whatever machine that you can
get the job done with, that's fine.
Whatever gets you in your groove, good on you.
Alex wrote in, he said, gentlemen, I've been listening to the show for years and I've also
been using Linux and various distributions as my primary desktop for 11 years.
I don't really ever have the intention of getting a Mac.
Doesn't really matter how fast they get.
The one time I had used it for work and I had to build an iOS app, I found the ability,
the inability to control the operating system frustrating.
It's not about features.
It's about how Apple treats and disrespects its users.
That's the entire point of Linux and open source software.
Frankly, I just wrote all that because I'm tired of hearing about the topic while I'm
over here just getting my work done on my Linux device.
It's weird because by writing into the show about the topic, you have therefore precipitated
this talk.
The topic.
Yeah, I do find myself, I go through cycles where I obsess a little bit about my tooling
and then I go for a year or two and I don't think about it very much and then I obsess
again very much about my tooling.
When I, my heart started pounding during the Apple event when they got to the Mac section
because I was really, all right, you know what?
I'll tell you what, we'll save that first, linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get a $100 60 day credit towards a new account and of course you support the
show.
That's linode.com slash coder.
I host it all on Linode.
I just spun up a new mail server, Wes and I, I mean, let's be honest, it was Wes and
I.
It was a new server.
I hated it.
And then I reflashed the existing Linode from Ubuntu 1804 to CentOS Stream 8 and what was
fantastic about it is I was able to keep the same IP address and all of that stuff.
So all of the MX records and DNS that we had set up didn't have to be redone.
I just wiped it and put a new OS on there from one of their images.
They have all the distros you could possibly want and I wanted to try out CentOS Stream
because I think it's actually going to be a pretty good server distro, but they also
work with Kubernetes and Terraform if you want to do infrastructure by code.
They have S3 compatible object storage, which is fantastic.
When you wrap your head around the use cases of storage in the cloud that doesn't have
to have a server standing in front of it that you can make public or private, oh man, it's
a game changer.
It's a game changer for just like config backups, it's a game changer for distributing files
to clients, it's a game changer for static websites.
That's definitely one of the best use cases is you can have a site up and going and available
using Linode object storage with just a little HTML and CSS and it's crazy snappy fast.
It's a great way to do like a resume or a list of something or build your own custom
homepage.
There's so many different ways to use Linode too because they have like $5 a month rigs,
they've got custom CPU rigs that are super fast with AMD EPYC processors, and of course
they have plans that'll just mix and match all of that as you need it.
They have one-click application deployments, they have tons of great documentation, 11
data centers around the world.
I mean, I could go on and on about the reasons why I love using Linode, not to mention they're
an independent company that is dedicated to offering the best virtualized cloud computing.
Essentially, if it runs on Linux, it's gonna run on Linode.
Go deploy for test or production and really try out all the different features with that
$100 credit.
You can really try it out.
So go to linode.com slash coder, you go there, that lets them know, hey, I heard about it
on Coder Radio.
You go there just to say thanks for supporting the show and check out their services.
That's a great way to keep the Coder Radio program going.
Go to linode.com slash coder, get that $100 60-day credit for your new account and you
support the show, linode.com slash coder.
So did you have the opportunity to watch this Apple event today, the spring event, spring
into spring or whatever it was?
I did watch parts of it.
I did have to disappear for a bit, but I have to tell you that a purple iMac is not something
I would turn down.
So I question the screen size, but all right, let's get to this.
So I streamed it.
I got here this morning early and essentially I've been essentially making content since
8.30 AM and it's 6 PM right now.
So we did a little hangout and watched it and I recorded that on jupiter.tube.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
It starts about 24 minutes in.
If you'd like to watch it with our reactions, super quick rundown for those of you who can't
be bothered to watch it, don't really care, but would like to be informed for the sake
of conversation.
So the people with lives, yes.
Apple finally launched AirTags, their Bluetooth locator for items.
They also announced a purple version of the iPhone 12, not a new iPhone, but just a new
color.
Oh, there's a purple iPhone.
Hang on.
I gotta go.
It looks good too.
There's a paid service for podcasts.
There is a new 4k Apple TV with a much improved Siri remote, which is compatible with previous
Apple TVs and the big ticket, two big ticket items really, but the first big ticket item
is the redesigned iMac with an M1 chip and the new iPad Pro with an M1 chip.
So let's just break some of this down.
I have the least to say about the podcast subs because it's the least that I know about
right now.
I actually wanted to talk to you about that.
That was the one that really got me.
Well, let's do it.
But no, if you have no comments on it, then you're good.
I mean, I just have to look into it.
So here's what I do know.
It's that 15 to 30% cut ratio.
So for the first year, Apple takes 30%, then it's 15% after that.
They won't require creators to exclusively publish for Apple, but they want you to make
some distinguishing features and you do have to use their tools to publish the member only
item.
Okay.
So they're commoditizing their compliments again, right?
You'll have to use their app and they're going to have a new way to promote podcasts.
All of that leaves me a little concerned, but it doesn't concern me nearly as much as
Spotify does at this point.
Really?
So I thought you'd be here on fire about this one.
I don't love it, but it looks by all intents and purposes, like if it was something the
audience wanted, I would do.
I don't necessarily think that's going to be the case with the J.B. audience, even though
even though I'd say about 25% of our listeners are using Apple podcasts.
Well, no, I just say in general for like the podcasting market, like I thought this would
be something that you would find just bad.
Well, I mean, Spotify, I mean, what they're doing, I mean, I've always found confusing.
It's kind of weird, but this seems like Apple being like, it's better on an iPhone, right?
I don't know.
Yeah, that is true.
It would limit it to iPhone users.
If I were doing an Apple podcast, I could see it.
Maybe boiler alert.
I guarantee ATP is going to do all of this.
You think so?
Yeah.
Why not throw shade at rich millionaires who got lucky because Yahoo is dumb and buys things
they shouldn't.
If your audience was really heavy, like if we had a 60% audience using Apple podcasts,
it might be worth considering.
I think there's a lot of overhead though.
If you want to be featured, there's a lot of there, like you got to do the special kind
of artwork and stuff like that.
But isn't that like part of being in the Apple ecosystem?
Yeah, definitely.
Like really?
Yeah.
It's the same for apps.
Yep.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
This feels like the application of podcasts and soundboard that drew you soundboard that
because you're going to need it.
Oh my God.
I will keep an eye out on that one in particular and I'm so I'm sort of reserving judgment
until further review.
I think the thing that I do like seeing initially is that they're not forcing the content to
be exclusive to Apple.
That seems encouraging because you could take that same content and make it available.
How we make it available to current members.
Again, it's IE6 though.
If there are things that don't work, if you're not an Apple, then I don't know.
I feel like we're always playing the same songs here and maybe it's because we're old
and sad and whatever.
But this is what you get when they turn to a services company is a is a gradual expansion
of what they can monetize.
I am the Apple fanboy on this network, which geez, you guys could have done a lot better
in terms of like actual fanboys of Apple, but like they make beautiful hardware, which
they deprecate mercilessly with the M1 chip after you spend five thousand.
I'm sorry, I get upset.
It's true.
But they do make beautiful hardware.
Honestly, I'm staring at my iMac Pro.
I won't say with hatred, but let's just say the disappointment of a mother who is visiting
her son in prison because he was convicted of rape.
It's pathetic that my MacBook Air can run circles around this machine.
But again, I mean, I forgot what I was talking about.
I just want to smash this thing in the floor.
Yeah, your MacBook Air doesn't have fans.
That's even better.
You're just like, oh, and I sometimes forget to charge it for two or three days and it's
just like fine.
OK, so we probably don't have much to talk about the Apple TV 4K.
They added the H12 CPU.
So yeah, underpowered still for games.
It's kind of disappointing.
If anybody is playing games on Apple TV, they need psychiatric help.
I want to talk to you about purple iMacs.
OK, I want one.
So no, no, no, no qualms about the lack of M1X or anything, huh?
It's purple.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's true.
I mean, this piece of shit here is space gray.
Why would it by the way, why would anything be space gray?
Why don't just call it gray?
They didn't do any space gray because they're not.
None of these are, quote unquote, professional machines.
They're saving the space gray for the professional machine now because they know it's a piece
of garbage.
Anything that space grain and I'm like, yeah, I'm talking to use the ons.
You suck.
They're still selling the Intel, a couple of the Intel iMacs, and one of them still
has a spinning rest hard drive in it for the fusion drive.
I'm obviously joking.
The iMac Pro is a great machine.
I can probably use this for a year or two until I spill something, some liquid that's
definitely not alcoholic into it.
Right.
My lawyer would be very pleased with that statement.
What I will say is the fact that they're selling thousand dollar machines with spinning this.
I mean, it's just embarrassing to be clear.
It's not the M1 machines.
It's the old Intel machines.
But yeah, I agree.
I know.
But like, come on.
Honestly, I think it's pretty pathetic that these new iMacs are coming with a base eight
gigs of RAM.
And nowhere on their website does it say how much RAM these iMacs will take.
So before the show, I called up an Apple sales engineer and got quotes for the show that
they will offer an eight core with 16 gigs of RAM, up to 16 gigs of RAM max, 16 gigs,
two terabytes of storage, 16 gigs of RAM max.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
These new iMacs max out at 16?
You got it.
Same limitations that the Mini and the Air have and the Mac.
OK, so long time ago and long time ago and months ago, we were talking about the M1 limitations
and one of them was the RAM limitation of 16, right?
Yep.
Do we really think they're struggling?
I mean, I feel like that's a limitation they could have overcome.
But I don't want to say I'm Mac Pro.
I'm sorry.
You have 32 gigs of RAM like a true computer.
I was checking on one of my systems today and I looked and I was using 20, 22, 24 gigs
of my 32 gigs of RAM and I was like, oh, oh, no, I have a spreadsheet that.
So by the way, if you work at Microsoft and you're an Excel programmer on the Mac team,
you need to think about what you've done to my computer.
You sit down, pour yourself a drink and just say, is this what I don't know why running
my payroll tax calculations like maxes out my CPUs?
Yeah, I don't have that many people anymore.
I'm a starving artist.
I'm like Da Vinci, except I'm not, you know, old.
What, you got a vape pen there?
I think you're nuts.
Chris, go fork yourself.
All right.
So listen, 16 gigs is it's just not enough.
And but here's the other thing.
I know it's silly to say it, but because they didn't make a space gray one, this is how
Apple works.
That means this isn't for the professionals.
They're going to replace the 27 inch probably at WWDC or in September.
You know what this is for?
I'll be a jerk.
This is for the digital agency where we're hip and we're branding and you buy the one
that matches the colors of your branding for the receptionist.
Or it's the family computer.
You know, there's some families that still have one computer that they all share that
it could be that.
Yeah.
My son has a Thalia just saying, but keep going.
Did you notice how heavy they went on advertising features like continuity and handoff that
have been around for years?
I mean, I often sell things I built years ago as new features, but I need money.
I think Apple has clearly identified iPhone users that have Windows machines as the target
for these IMAX.
That is 100 percent who these IMAX are for.
And when you go on the IMAX product page today, the bottom half, the whole deal, the rest
of half of the page is really about handoff features and stuff that's been in Mac OS and
iOS for many, many years.
What do you think of the new keyboard?
I like that they put the fingerprint reader in there.
It better be comfortable to type on.
If they may if they've made another lemon keyboard, that's just going to be an unforgivable.
Well, I think it's going to be the magic keyboard, right?
It's got to be a facelift.
Have you ever done any purchases on the computer with Apple Pay?
I've done many, many, many inebriated purchases with Apple Pay.
It's a way, way quicker system.
I like it a lot.
I'll sometimes if I'm in the middle of buying something and I'm on the Mac, which when did
this just recently happen?
This scenario.
Oh, oh, yeah.
I mean, I decided I'd subscribe to Ben Thompson's Dither podcast and I stopped what I was doing
and I went over to the Mac and opened up and opened up Safari and did the transaction in
Safari just so that way I could use Apple Pay because it's so much quicker.
It's so convenient.
It's stupid because it takes care of like all the shipping info, all the name.
You have to fill out all the damn fields and all the payment information.
It just does all of it for you.
It's really slick.
And so having that stuff built in, having the user switching based on your fingerprint
is a slick feature and again, makes it great for the family machine, too.
Okay.
Yeah, I mean, I'm not buying one.
Well, then my cast was.
I thought to myself, if Apple does something with the Mac in this episode, that's an iMac,
I might end up getting one because I have been thinking about just setting up a workstation
here at the studio and that would be perfect.
But I'm not going to do a machine that can only do 16 gigs of RAM.
So because this is an Apple show today, right?
Am I the only one who likes the new AirPods Max?
Do you have a pair?
No, I'm using whatever weird German headphones who gave me.
But if I had the money to burn, I'd certainly try them.
I used to have money.
Oh, wait, this is going in that direction.
One of the things that I have found as a dad who has some ADD that sometimes, sometimes,
you know, it's like ADD gets this fun, cute wrap.
But one of the negative sides of people who actually have something, some sort of attention
deficit disorder is it also means sometimes you lose governance over your own thoughts.
You lose governance over what's on your mind and what you're paying attention to.
And when you have a noisy household, it sometimes robs you of your ability to even think of
a notion or a concept for a few minutes and it gets frustrating and it gets, it gets mentally
tiring as your brain is constantly trying to grasp on to something and it creates a
frustration and a grumpiness and it creates a tiredness.
And what I have found is that, and this is really pronounced for me because I have three
kids and I, like an animal, have chosen to live in a very tiny space.
And so sound isolating headphones have been a game changer for me where I can put something
on and even if I can just bring the volume down 80%, it's like regaining a little bit
of my sanity.
If I, I'm still waiting for like reviews and I've heard they have good sound isolation,
but I can't really get a feel for how they do with like human voice and, and people noise.
But it's just outside my price range for something like that because I have, I have ones that
work well enough now, but if they were superior in that regard, I'd be pretty tempted.
So I'm in this weird place where I live, like my main problem in life is that zoom is hell
and should be outlawed by the Geneva convention.
I'm sorry, I just had a flashback.
What was I saying?
You're thinking you could use this as like a reliable set of zoom headphones that aren't
gamer edition.
Right.
That are always paired to my Mac and I can just pick them up and be like, okay, what
is your complaint?
Right.
But don't you think the little ear air pod ones would probably be better for that job?
Well that's the problem.
The AirPods have actually, like I have the old, old, old AirPods, the original versions.
Yeah.
And you know what?
They're overpriced.
The sound quality is not great.
Yeah.
But you know what?
God damn it.
They've been doing the job for years.
Yeah.
I have definitely had the problem where I've run them down when I've had a lot of meetings
in one day and then I'm doing this game where like I'm popping one in the case for a little
bit and I'm like swapping them back and forth.
Yeah.
I've had, yeah, I've had that after a while.
To me, they're like adium.
You know, they've got some troubles, but you know, we should apologize to the Coderadio
kids.
There is a decade plus of backstory here on just everything we're talking about.
That's true.
Also, is it me or the new iMacs look like next products?
There's a surprising lack of branding on the front too.
When I saw them, they looked like those, no, but design, they looked like those computers
you see on TV where they tape over the logo and it's just generic computer.
You know, it's like a Mac under there, but they've taped over the Apple logo, you know,
that's what they look like and they really don't have much less chin than your iMac
pro does today.
No, it looks very, I'm sorry, but it looks very nineties Apple slash next.
I think what's going to sell some of these though for some people is I think these are
fanless.
I'm not positive.
They might not be, they might be a small fan in there, but I bet you they're very quiet.
One though, if I ran a company, let's call it blue ocean or let's say green, green grass
or pink, nevermind, let's just move on, silver, silver surfer, yellow, silver fox.
Come on.
I know you, that's what you ought to call it.
Let me tell you some, if you want to have a special about cougars, I'm ready and able
and I'm, you're going to get a little gray, you know, in there, you're going to all of
a sudden you're just starting to look all dignified and no, no, no, you don't understand.
And I, listen, I'm in my thirties and I have been undercover doing this operation for you.
Yeah, and I can report back.
This might be an unfiltered episode though.
Yeah.
Are you sharing like some breaking news with us?
This is CNN breaking news.
Yes.
Code radio listeners.
And I do apologize to the angry dads and moms who email us.
Mike does love women 10 years older than him.
So at least if you are not 44, this is, this is the episode where we really learned that
Mike definitely has a thing for president president Roslyn for sure.
I can't explain, you know what, Jar Jar, Jar Jar, my man, you're great.
You sort of suck cause you're incompetent.
Madam president.
I love you.
You better brace yourself for some heartbreak, my friend.
I just saying you got some, you got some VSG to watch.
I'm only halfway through.
Why?
No, she's got to win.
Oh yeah.
I don't.
Beltar is like, Oh, I'm going to be president because I'm Beltar and I'm an asshole.
He is such a jerk.
I just want to choke that guy.
Like I just, and I don't want to do it like quickly.
I just want to watch him suffer.
We should move on.
So what are the odds on you buying one of these IMAX zero, zero, zero.
I run VMs all day, every day, but you're, you're making it work with the eye with that
there air air, which has doubled the memory of one of these IMAX.
Your pro does.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's where you're doing it.
I see.
Not, not my pro.
My, uh, my, uh, my, even my air has 16.
Yeah.
Well you can get these with 16, these IMAX, but that's it.
No more than 16.
That's it.
I don't know.
I mean, you know what, as much as I dunk on the IMAX pro, it's the undersecretary of almost,
okay.
I don't know.
Like it's a good machine.
It's better than, yeah, it's just loud and kind of hot.
You and that IMAX have been through the war and back and you know, it's had your back
many times, but if you're honest with yourself, it's just not quite been the same since it
had the spider in its screen and it had to be taken out to get cleaned.
It's never quite been the same, but that's all right.
You still love it.
I just want to say the CIMAC has never left me loyal to the end.
Datadog.com slash coder radio.
This is a tool that's going to solve some problems and to help you visualize and communicate
with your team, analyze code level performance across your environment and troubleshoot issues
faster with Datadog.
Datadog has this thing called the continuous profile and it automatically collects profiles
from your production servers all the time, and then you can go back and analyze your
data quickly with minimal overhead and get a unified picture of your environment by correlating
code performance metrics with other monitoring data in real time in their dashboards and
their dashboards are gorgeous.
You got to go check that out.
Just go to datadog.com slash coder radio for that.
But what they do is they bring it all together with integrations.
You can plug into other applications and APIs.
Of course, they got tracing across the entire application stack, log management, that continuous
profiler I mentioned, and it brings it all together in one platform.
One platform.
One place.
Datadog enables you to pinpoint the root cause of issues faster than ever.
So go try Datadog out for free for 14 days by visiting datadog.com slash coder radio.
Here's the deal.
It's been a while since there's been events with swag.
So for a limited time, if you start a trial and create one dashboard, you'll get a free
Datadog t-shirt, but you got to go to datadog.com slash coder radio.
That's datadog.com slash coder radio.
You know what surprised me the most from the event was the iPad Pro.
I love the way Apple leaned into this.
I don't know if you saw this, but this was the best part of the event when Mission Impossible
style they have a burglar come in, you know, they go down a duct, they're down on a wire
pass lasers, he breaks in, he steals the M1 CPU and then he busts into another room and
he puts it in the iPad, he closes the case and then the camera pans around and the burglar
pulls off the mask and it's Tim Cook and then they say, we've added an M1 to the iPad and
they just went all in on just putting the best chip they've got in the iPad now.
Okay.
I mean, but I don't give a crap unless they're going to change the app store guidelines.
It doesn't matter.
It really doesn't, you know, so they got eight core CPU in there.
They're saying it's 50% improvements over just the last one and they put Thunderbolt
in this thing, which is brilliant.
It has proper external display, but you're not allowed to use it.
It has all this nice stuff, faster storage, two terabytes, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
And I'm sitting here going, okay, great, but give me the OS and the applications that can
take advantage of any of this or just stop reviewing apps for functionality and allow
any non malware app in.
And then this very powerful, by the way, it was powerful two years ago when Lana Del Rey,
oh, by the way, Lana Del Rey, lovely, did her little presentation, right?
The problem has not been the hardware.
The problem is their insane policies, why they want to gimp the iPad.
I mean, I think it's worse than that though, because I think the OS also is limited in
a lot of ways, especially on the iPad.
There are sneaky, hacky, old school Mac OS and the next step things in iPad OS.
So spoiler alert, it's all basically next step OS with lipstick on it.
That's why we love it.
I say that in air quotes, right?
But Apple won't let you put that in the app store.
I feel like what we might be in the middle of is part two of this story.
I mean, why do you bother even putting 16 gig, Mike, Mike, six, this thing can get up
to 16 gigs of RAM in an iPad, Mike.
If you spec at a 12.9 inch iPad all the way out with 5g and 16 gigs of RAM and two terabytes
of storage, and I am definitely not doing that right now, but yeah, keep going $2,400.
That's how much an iPad would cost spec'd out.
That's just like one week of running a meth lab.
It actually is more expensive than the highest tier M1 MacBook pro and the MacBook air with
all the available upgrades.
It's more expensive than that.
All right, fair boy.
Then let me ask you, let me, let's turn this around on you.
Why don't they just let the iPad loose just so you know what iPad apps and you could separate
them from iPhone apps are in fact full computer applications and right, cause it's iPad OS.
It's a different OS too.
It's really not.
But I know, I know, but I'm playing, you know, I'm playing along, but like should just have
like, you know what?
If you're dumb enough to download something stupid, then right, right.
Well, and like I said, I think it was just last week.
It's like just turn on that gatekeeper crap that they have on the Mac and do notarization
and problem solved on the iPad.
I don't think we're going to get that.
I think that's ridiculous.
It's never going to happen, but this is so clearly part one of a two part story for the
iPad.
Okay.
What's part two?
Part two is WWDC and iOS 15 on the iPad.
No, but what, what is part two?
Like in your, okay.
So the, the problem I have been covetching about Mazel Tov is not the hardware or even
the APIs, but Apple's insane policies for the iPad.
It's got to be both.
It's got to be a change of policies, a change in app store.
Range of policy.
Yep.
And, or no, no, I'm sorry.
An update in policies and update.
Dude, you're high.
Like, come on.
No, no way that they're not going to let developers, like what they need to do is let developers
treat the iPad as it were a windows and you can write any application you want and sell
it the way you want to.
I don't know.
I don't know if that's going to go that far.
I think there'll be some concession in regards to apps.
It'll be something dumb like interapp operability and then we're going to find out a year later
that other developers who are big names have had that before.
Just like the 15% thing where it turns out Netflix and Amazon had that for two years.
I think that's exactly, that's, that's the line I'm thinking combined with maybe windowing
in iPad OS or something like that to change how you can manage multiple applications because.
I'm going to push back on windowing.
I think the iPad is the perfect device for pop OS slash magnet on Mac OS tiling.
Yeah, tiling.
Yeah, absolutely.
Or they could even come up and I think they've prototyped a tabbing type where you basically
have tabs and you know, that's maybe up on the corner or a pull down tab screen and you
can tab between your apps and I don't know what they would do there, but something where
you could move information between screens easier, stuff like that.
It just seems like they have to know that they've added a keyboard, a mouse, 16 gigs
of RAM, two terabytes of storage, and this crazy ass pro XDR type display they have on
the iPad pro.
None of it really makes sense unless the iPad can do more.
There's no reason to spend $2,400 on this machine unless it can do more.
Let me just undercut my whole argument.
I'm going to buy one of these and I'm going to try to build the app I've been dreaming
about for two decades and when it gets rejected, my God, we're going to have some content Chris.
Developer Steve Troughton Smith on Twitter says putting M1 in the iPad without a software
story to explain why it needs the extra hardware and features and power offered by M1 like
Thunderbolt really feels like foreshadowing, implying foreshadowing for WWDC.
You know what?
I got to tell you, I'm all in an iPad.
Okay.
Old Coder Radio listeners, you know, I believe in tablet computing.
Yep.
I lost a lot of money.
Well you went with the windows Metro.
Who me?
Windows eight man.
Yeah, you, you did.
You got all in on the Microsoft hype, brah.
See they went, they went around this same route, but Apple is doing it in a, they start
with the basic tablet and they've built up a pencil and now they've added a keyboard
and now they've.
Can I just say that like the Microsoft problem was the hardware was crap and it didn't last
long enough.
And the Apple problem is the hardware is amazing.
Yeah.
Right?
Like, and they're just like jerks about how you could monetize your business.
Yeah.
And the OS is limited too.
You know, it's a double whammy for sure.
Yeah.
The API is our tie.
I personally think if you know enough about objective C and if you don't, you deserve
to be lined up and shot, but that's, what was I going with this?
Just a classic story there.
I wonder.
So here's my thought, Mike.
I've had gay bars.
Yes.
No, no, that's not where I was going, but you know, you never know.
What are you high?
But what I was, if this thing has thunderbolt and now they're claiming to add proper external
monitor support.
Go for it.
I want to hear it.
I love where you're going.
But could you get a stand and take a thunderbolt dock with say a wired keyboard and audio interface
and ethernet port and display port with a monitor hooked up to it and plug that in doing
power pass through, plug that into the iPad and get a full monitor keyboard mouse.
I think if you can't, it's retarded to have thunderbolt.
Yeah.
It has thunderbolt has to be doing more than just storage.
That has to work.
I mean, come on.
No one on an iPad.
No one needs that much data transfer.
I'm sorry.
Yeah.
What are you going to do?
Especially because of how locked down the file transfer API is iOS, which by the way,
I was going to run a fantastic blue ray backup program to the iPad backup.
Oh, that would be sweet, but you can't do it because they don't allow that.
If I did not have an iPad pro today, I'd be picking up the 12.9 inch iPad.
I would not be speccing it out like crazy, but I'm definitely not on the checkout screen.
Let me tell you what I'm not doing.
Okay.
What are you going to not do?
Yeah.
I'm not going to personalize this one and say Chris's hair is fantastic that I'm just
not going to definitely not doing that right.
Okay.
I didn't just upgrade it to 250.
Sure.
$1,200.
Whoa.
$1,200 to go to 256.
Yeah.
That's a lot of money.
Are you looking at, is that the old one too, or is that the new one?
New one.
Oh my God.
The base model is almost 1100, 1099.
It's a lot.
That's a lot.
It's just so much.
It's more than a computer.
So it really has to be doing more.
And this doesn't even have an LTE chip.
Oh.
I know.
And the LTE is very, very useful.
I have found that to be very true.
And they charge a lot of money for that.
I don't know about that.
If I didn't have a perfectly functional iPad that is perfectly fast, I might be tempted,
but it's just the cost.
It's just outrageous.
My kid dropped mine and broke it.
So I'm in the market, but damn, that's a lot of money.
So do you think we're going to get a more pro line of iMac, like a 27 inch iMac at WWDC
with an MX1?
Yeah.
I think we are.
Because you know what?
Because they made it 24 inches and I think they're going to start using size, screen
size as a demarcation in RAM.
I'm thinking that too.
RAM.
Anything that does more than 16 gig is more engineered at professionals and it'll probably
be space gray, you know, boring colors for professionals as they like to do.
I also just as a total aside, because I can't help myself, I also wonder because the iPad
Pro has the M1 and these new iMacs have the M1, if Hector Martin and his team over at
Ashi Linux are successful and we're getting Linux working on the M1, it should be functional
on all of the machines that Apple announced today, which is pretty cool.
They're getting the initial boot support merged in kernel 5.13, which is the next kernel after
the one that comes out this weekend, and including a brand new bootloader to help manage kind
of Apple's unique boot environment.
And that's all getting merged into kernel 5.13.
5.12 comes out this weekend, so it's really not that far away.
And then once they get that working, it's just drivers development, but I forget her
name, but this software developer who is working on GPU support for Linux has already got like
the full OpenGL style cube spinning on Linux on the M1 GPU.
They've got basic 3D instructions working already.
So they're making really good progress, and it appears that the M1 hardware loads some
of the firmware blobs necessary to initialize that hardware outside and independent of the
OS, so some of that stuff just comes up when the machine comes up and they don't have to
fool with it at all in Linux, which is saving them some time.
And now it's just figuring out the driver fundamentals.
But you know, the fact that they're drawing a cube and can spin it on the M1, that's a
big step.
They can do it.
Yeah, that's a big step.
If that happens, if they get to a point where they say you can get the desktop running and
you can use a web browser or something like that, I will buy whatever M1 is on the market
at the time, even if it's not an M1X.
That'll be the moment.
Drew, just, you know, you know what to do.
Run the market if it runs Linux.
Until then, they're going to have to do something more impressive to get me to switch.
Not that I don't think the M1 has plenty of performance, but if I'm going to make that
kind of transition, it's got to be something that will last me years because of the prices
of these machines.
So we shall see.
I think it's going to be maybe WWDC, maybe September.
My last thoughts are, like always, Apple is a step above everyone else in video production
quality.
Apple felt a little different for this event, but they nailed it right on the hour mark,
right as my recorder was hitting an hour, they were wrapping it up.
And they really outdid themselves once again with all of the transitions.
And I like this new thing that's happening on YouTube where there are a couple of creators
who have just taken all of the transitions and put that in a video.
I'll have one of those linked in the show notes.
And even if you don't watch the rest of the event, it's worth watching the transitions
because they do a hell of a video production on these.
And so we'll have that linked in the show notes.
And then our commentary of the live event itself with the whole thing with minimal commentary,
that'll be linked in the show notes and it starts about 24 minutes in.
They really do a fantastic job though.
So if you are even somewhat curious and want something you could watch for an hour, it's
worth checking out because they do a hell of a job and you get a little more information
in there.
So we survived an event without either one of us going broke.
And overall, I think probably pretty good stuff.
The theme that I keep coming away with here is that Apple has a real hit on their hands
with this M1 stuff, so much so that they just went full in on calling it that in the iPad
too.
And I have seen a lot of interest from general people out there in the world following this
stuff that just like tech in a way they haven't seen for a while.
And it still plays into my fear that it's going to be appealing to a lot of techies.
Some long term friends I know, Mike, one of them, I guess, was the developer of a desktop
environment that people in the audience would know of, has just walked away from burnout
and bought himself a MacBook Air.
Well, of course, because he deserves to have a life and be happy.
That's what happens to Linux developers.
It's anecdotal, but I keep hearing stories from people.
No, I don't think it is.
I think, you know what, I'm sorry.
You can't develop a Linux desktop environment and be happy.
You just can't.
It's a challenge for sure.
I like how you were like, I can't say yes to that.
I heard from somebody after I mean, I heard from a few people that like you guys are way
off, but I heard from people that are actually creating apps and or a desktop environment.
And I heard basically you spot on and it's really burning me out.
I heard from one individual who I won't share their name said that there are just glaring
technical issues in the Linux desktop that we're not addressing and people that are not
acknowledging it are not helping.
They're harming the desktop.
Well, first of all, and forgive me, Master Chris, this is Coder radio, not Linux radio,
right?
I don't give a crap about Linux.
I mean, I like Linux.
I'm very friendly with the system.
Seventy six people competition makes everyone better.
And I'm just I'll put my cards on the table.
I think right now Apple is winning because this M1 chip is an ace, right?
This is it's the ace of Trump.
It takes every trick and that is a card playing term, not what you idiots think it is.
But that doesn't mean that like Dell or Seventy six or what's that stupid Linux vendor you
like?
Wow.
They'll never advertise on this show.
Purism.
You're thinking of purism.
Yeah, that's the one I think is incompetent.
Yeah.
Because you guys are morons and you believe in false, which is a waste of time.
Wow.
Is this BSD radio?
Because it feels a lot like it.
Chopping bombs, chopping bombs, pow, pow.
Resoft, there's a waste of time.
It should all be BSD.
Woo.
There.
Ooh la la.
We're done.
Free BSD.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Good night, everybody.
Yes.
No, I think they have done a tremendous job.
I think they are being very competitive and if we're being honest, they've brought the
fight.
I've thought about this too recently.
You know, isn't GNOME 40's adoption of a horizontal workspace layout kind of an acknowledgement
that Apple was right when they implemented a horizontal workspace layout?
Shh.
Do not tell.
No, you can't say that to them.
That's uncomfortable.
Okay.
Why are you trying to trigger the neckbeards?
No, no, no.
I'm just trying to point out, I'm just trying to point out that there is room for improvement,
but I think I completely, totally respect and appreciate the position of people who
wrote it and said, I don't care, man.
I just, you know, I want my Honda Accord.
I want to get in my Honda Accord.
I want it to drive me to work so I can get my job done and I want to drive me home and
I don't want to spend a bunch.
That's right.
Cause Fonda rolls a Honda and she's got back.
I agree.
You know it, boy.
You know it.
Mr. Dominic, do you have anything you want to plug this week?
I guess if somebody is making more than $75,000 a year on making a Linux desktop application,
let us know.
There might be a Thaleo in it for you.
Is the bet still on or is it over now?
I mean, I'm willing to keep that bet forever because I know I'm never going to lose, but
what do I win?
Hang on.
What do you win?
At some point I have to win something.
Maybe.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
What?
I have something here.
Okay.
What?
If the robes actually ship, which I know they will, you're amazing.
I'm thinking smoking jackets, Coder Radio only smoking jackets.
Oh, that'd be good.
That'd be good.
And I will do the operations on it this time and I will take all the pain.
Man, I thought you were going to say something about Seuss.
I seriously thought you were going to be like, you have to run Seuss for a week or?
Nope.
No Seuss.
Okay.
Please stop saying Seuss.
They keep emailing and texting me and I just, I have to have a life.
I'm sorry.
That's right.
Seuss, but Coder Radio smoking jackets.
If the ropes ship and if a hundred people tweet us seriously and say, we want smoking
jackets.
And then if we can pull that off.
After the robe thing, you're going to try to make smoking jackets a thing.
Oh man.
Yeah, but you're not going to love the way I make these smoking jackets, but we're going
to do it.
It sounds like you're going to use some sort of forced labor.
You're not denying it.
So it's probably true.
All right.
Well, very good.
Also, thank you to our members, Coder QA team out there making the show possible.
You get the limited ad feed as a thank you.
Oh, and the quarterly is done.
So it'll be posted later this week.
So if you want to get the Coderly, it'll be in the downloads area or it will be in your
members feed, and if you are not yet a member and you would like access to our Coderly report,
get it at coderqa.co.
You can find Mike on Twitter.
He's at Dumanuku.
His company is at the Mad Botter Inc.
I am at Chris LAS and the whole dang network.
Well they are at Jupiter signal over there with all them productions and shows and whatnot.
This particular show is at Coder Radio Show.
Links to what we talked about today is at coder.show slash 410.
Over there you're going to find our contact form that's a big part of the show, so do
let us know your thoughts as well as our RSS feed and subscribe links.
All of that will be over there.
That's our special event coverage.
It's all over now.
It's all done.
Cleared the tubes.
Take a deep breath and we move forward.
So join us for the next regularly scheduled Coder Radio happy hour at Monday, 5 p.m.
Pacific, 8 p.m.
Eastern at jblive.tv.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio program.
We'll see you right back here next week.