This is KOTORadio, episode 336 for December 17th, 2018.
Hello everyone and welcome to KOTORadio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and its related technologies.
I'm here in the Pacific Northwest and our host every single week is joining us live
from the beautiful shores of Florida, no doubt, in a nice 75 degrees, no rain, no traffic,
it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
There's a gator in my pants.
Okay, alright, come on, did you really, have you ever seen a gator since you've been down
there?
Once.
Really?
But it was underwater, yeah.
Was he looking at you kind of weird, like I'd like to eat you?
No, they kind of like standard water and poke their eyes up.
Yeah.
It was on a golf course.
So if you ever go golfing in Florida and there are water holes, you're almost certainly going
to see a gator.
So you are technically our Florida man, as Pixel Pimp points out in our live chat.
You are the Florida man on the Jupiter Broadcasting Network.
I'm not sure that that's a mantle, I'm not particularly equality.
But I don't think you get a choice because you are in Florida.
Well, but I'm drinking Heineken, not Miller Lite.
Yeah I chilled Heineken at that too.
So those are the most tasty.
It was in the freezer.
Yes, that's right.
You know, in some parts of the world, they don't drink cold beer because it stuns the
taste buds and you can't fully appreciate the entire flavor profile.
But if you drink cold beer, you can drink more and then you can become a Supreme Court
justice.
Can I, oh, can I be honest with you?
No lie.
I just, I just discovered like double distilled or double filtered or whatever it is gin where
it tastes like 25% less Christmas tree.
Have you, have you seen this?
It's, it's a slightly different color, but it's gin, but it, it doesn't taste exactly
like a Christmas tree.
It tastes a little bit less.
That's what I discovered this week.
Had a good week.
Went over to system 76.
You know what?
I am so jealous of you.
I also got invited and yet, you know, I, I, I, I spawned into the process and let me tell
you the last like two and a half years, this process has been taking up a lot of RAM.
Yeah.
It's a memory leak.
I'll tell you the thing there is, this is, I'm going to get, I'm going to get real honest
with you for a moment.
Break it down for me.
The best time to have children is when you're young, you know, the, the age that you and
I are, you know, relatively young, but it is also your best time to travel, to have
good health, to have the most energy you're ever going to have, to feel the best physically
you're ever going to feel.
It's when you have the most physical leverage.
It's when you can afford to burn the candle at both ends the most.
It's when you bounce back.
I healed two and a half, three weeks faster than the doctors thought I would heal because
I'm a healthy mid thirties male that hasn't, you know, lived.
I'm not 60 years old having my, my spleen and all, or my appendix, I mean, rupture.
And yet the harsh reality is it's also your best time to establish a family and create
a life for yourself and have a home and have children, which ties you down and restricts
your flexibility.
And I, the only reason I mentioned this is because it was, I feel like my, the, the,
the 10 years that, well, 13 years I've been doing Jupiter broadcasting, it has been the,
the number one balancing act that I've had the, the, the, the most time with the hardest,
the hardest time, the hardest time with, and the most time I've spent agonizing over.
You know what I mean?
Like you joke, but in a way you miss out on an opportunity, but you also have an opportunity
to spend time with the kid.
It's like it both are good and both also are not good.
It's a, it's very hard for somebody like me because I'm always beating up on myself.
Well there's so much more to that too.
It's not just like that, but your appetite for risk dramatically goes down.
Yeah.
Yes.
Right?
Like when you're like, oh, this way more on the line, right?
This kid needs like food and diapers and health insurance and you know, all these things
that cost a tremendous amount of money as I'm, as you know, of course.
This is old, old dad's wine radio.
Well, I think, I don't know, you know, it was a variable that I couldn't fully appreciate
when I was younger and so I go into this with a full head of steam.
And then I think, do you know that I almost went anyway though I almost brought the kid
with me that, you know, I, I think that actually would have been okay.
You know, a certain a pink queen at system 76 Emma offered to babysit.
Like I was this, I was this close just like buying it cause he's still young enough that
he doesn't need a seat.
Yeah.
He could be a lap child.
I'm like, can I do it?
And I thought, you know what?
No, I, who knows what will happen.
It depends what you wanted to get out of it.
Did you want a nice father son kind of like experience or did you want so young though?
Right.
He won't remember it.
He won't remember.
Yeah.
And then you also, you're, you're not focused on sort of the business side of why you're
there.
Right.
So tell me about it.
How, how, uh, now how many, uh, system 76 Thelios or Thelios as they say, uh, it is
now.
Yep.
Yeah.
It is Thelio.
I was corrected.
And then I double checked.
How many did you smuggle in your carry on?
Well, so first of all, uh, okay, where to start with this?
Um, I think if we're going to just put all our cards on the table here, um, assuming
they're listening to this, but also our audience has been listening now for a while.
Uh, you have been pretty, pretty like, um, open to the idea of Papa West.
You've been open to the idea of them launching their own manufacturing plant.
Um, and you've even put your money where your mouth is and you've bought system 76 machines
since this change.
Yeah.
So at least just, just for the, for the record here, I've bought, let's see, a Ray tell two
Gallagos and Oryx, who was that four machines?
Yeah.
You, you maniac.
I've definitely put my money where my mouth is.
I, on the other hand, went a different direction.
I, I sort of, I sort of went, Oh shit, this could be the beginning of the end for system
76.
And I think, I think it's funny because I think normally you and I would have been reversed
in our opinions because to me, I looked at this and I went, these are a bunch of Linux
geeks that work out of a pretty nice office in downtown Denver.
And what the hell do they know about building a factory?
What the hell do they even know about buying a building, let alone putting it with laser
cutters, acid dippers, powder coat machines, huge ovens, assembly lines, managing inventory.
What do these guys know?
What do they know?
Right?
They've been, they've been managed.
They've been working out of an office.
They build PCs to order.
They work with upstream OEMs to customize laptops.
What do, what do these guys know about building?
Like that could sink a company, the, just the rent, just the rent on this place could
sink a company.
As a small business owner, and I had this conversation with Carl, as a small business
owner, I just, the risk just overwhelmed me.
Like it was an, it was, it is, it is, it is moving an entire company into a domain they
have no knowledge of.
It is something that entire corp companies exist to manage.
That's why Apple doesn't even build their own machines.
What's a company out of Denver going to do to pull this off out of Denver?
Like they're not, they're not, they're not offshoring the build.
They're not cutting costs that way.
They're hiring people in Denver, Colorado, which is not one of the cheapest places in
the nation, and they're buying or renting real estate and setting up a factory.
So to say, and, and then, because that's not enough, they're launching an operating system
and they're also going to become an OS vendor.
I just thought, I just thought it was too much.
And I thought a company that I had been a customer for, for 10 years was going to go
under.
And so I just sort of pulled back and I just thought, well, I'll go into await and see
mode.
I do know that the people that are very talented, maybe they can pull this off.
Maybe they can make this work, but the odds are way against them.
But maybe, maybe, maybe.
So it's, it's been, you know, an interesting 2018 watching them.
So coming, that is, that is the, that is the mindset that I went in with though.
So before you, before you dive in, I just want to say for our end of the year show,
I have a lot about that because what that sounds to me, and I don't want to put words
in your mouth.
You were asking about Ken, a little company like this scale.
Yeah, but it's not just like scale.
It's scale where the, where there's a global economy at play and manufacturing is particularly
there.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm not, scale is maybe the wrong word, but can they compete in a, in a big
world, can a little, can, well, we had an episode, remember they're selling to a niche
too, right?
It's not, they're not making it up in the margins.
No, they're not.
So what did you see?
So when I got down there, I, there's a couple of things that were kind of obvious to me.
First of all, it's been a very hard three months or so for them.
The last three months have been pretty tough.
They launched Thelio pre-orders or Thelio pre-orders at the beginning of November.
It is now as we record, you know, mid-ish December and people are starting to get a
little antsy.
They haven't gotten their shipments yet.
So when I got in there, what I saw was a company who had just, and I mean just like by the
hour cleared the biggest hurdle they've ever faced.
What they had, they had timed this event so that the factory floor was online.
There were a stack of Thelio systems ready to ship out to customers.
They set up this beer garden area where we could sit and watch presentations and enjoy
a drink and all of that in the factory.
And that seemed really fresh.
Like the, like the tables had just been built.
They were just assembled.
It was really, really fresh, but there was a, a wall size stack of Thelio workstations
ready to go.
And the first batch of machines went out the door that day, were you able to demo one?
Oh yeah.
Several of them were ready to go.
Yeah.
Did you happen to try a rising thread ripper configuration?
I think that was one of the ones they showed us where they were showing the cooling system
and they maxed it out at a hundred percent load and then blew smoke through it with an
acrylic side so we could see how it cools itself.
And it was so quiet that I'm pretty positive it hasn't showed up.
The sound of the machine did not show up on the recording.
Okay.
Yeah.
And they went through a lot of their thought process.
They were working on building the system for three years and this is going to be a decade
long platform for them.
This is going to be their desktops for the next 10 years.
And they have a Thel, they have Thelio and then they have Thelio.
They're going to have a Thelio minor, which is like the size of a NUC.
They're going to build a Thelio like a NUC.
And then they'll have a Thelio major and ones in between that are huge, massive desktops
with multiple Xeon processors and tons of disk and all of that.
But the standard Thelio workstation is really small.
It's almost the size of a mini ITX.
I'm showing pictures on the live stream if people are watching live right now.
And that was probably the biggest surprise when I got there is how small this thing was
and how much thought was put into little tiny details that even Johnny I would be impressed
that they sweated over.
So they've been transitioning this company.
They've been moving this company to a place that figures out how to cut this stuff.
A place that figures out how to paint this stuff.
They had to figure out how to make the screw holes smooth enough that it was a pleasant
experience to screw the individual thumb screws in.
It has been a massive learning process.
And they demoed different acrylic systems that they built as a training exercise.
They build systems out of acrylic before they go to metal.
And they're using 3D printers to fashion temporary parts or sometimes really nice parts that
just make it safer to ship.
And they've designed a daughter board that controls thermals in a somewhat intelligent
way that PCs don't normally do.
It manages the power but it also controls the thermals because it uses the sensors from
the motherboard and it uses data from the operating system.
And that's handy because the motherboard doesn't actually know what the temperature of the
GPU is.
And the motherboard doesn't know when the GPU is at 100% load.
Their daughter board design has been one of the more interesting schematics they've released.
The hardware being open source.
I won't say it's brand new because it's frankly not.
Other people have done things like this.
Well, that's something the Mac does.
The Mac does.
That's what the SMC controller.
Yeah.
The Mac OS does this.
But I think the way they're doing it for a Linux manufacturer is pretty, I won't say
novel, but pretty impressive.
But go ahead.
Yeah.
That's really it.
It is able to combine data from the motherboard, data from the operating system, and then it
makes intelligent cooling decisions, aggregating all those different data points together.
And you combine that with like 140 millimeter fan on the bottom and 120 millimeter exhaust
fan and the damn thing's just silent.
And then the board also is sort of a SATA pass-through backplane, so it does SASP essentially.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I guess in a way, I kind of want to talk to you more about like this massive transition
that they've made as a company.
They've gone from sort of management of PC manufacturing to hands-on cutting the individual
ports out, acid dripping the systems, running them through a baker, and then assembling
and testing them.
Like it's just, it's a whole other scale.
Like it's a different business now.
One of my disappointments in not going, and not that I mind spending time with my son,
of course, I don't want anybody to write in saying, oh, you're a bad dad.
That's not the case.
Be, you know, whatever, happy to be home.
And for those who didn't listen last week, the kid was sick is why I stayed home.
I have been through a similar process that I'm hoping on our end of the year episode
to go over of like attempting to, I'm calling it scaling, but I think you're right.
It's actually like gaining breadth and depth and all those kinds of things.
And it has been difficult to say the least.
And one of the things I did wonder when I got the invitation, Chris, a few weeks ago
was, this seems kind of cray cray.
I mean, you know, like the, I'm sorry, but the YouTube commenters and Reddit commenters
rightly say that I have a soft spot for system 76, right?
Like I like what they're doing.
I like their hardware.
You know, I'm 50% in Mac OS and 50% in Linux.
And when I'm on Linux, it's usually my Galago, right?
And frankly, I broke my Galago, was able to go buy parts and fix it.
Now, granted it's not as like nice, cause you know, my craftsmanship isn't frankly where
their overseas workers were for the Galago.
But if I had to buy another desktop, I would certainly consider Athelio or Thaleo.
Is that Thaleo?
Having said all of that, like all the nice stuff, this seems like a big, big, big jump
for me.
Like you are, like first I thought, you know, I think it's fair to say the Linux community
was a little raised eyebrows on Pop OS, like you guys are going to take on writing your
own OS.
And you know, Pop, I like Pop, I run Pop.
Pop is a skin on Ubuntu, right?
Right now that's what it is.
It's a good skin.
It suits my needs, but then to go into full bore manufacturing and in the United States,
I mean, listen, I'll slap on a MAGA hat if I have to, but I've had some failed endeavors
in some, and we'll talk about it in our end of the year episode, some IoT chip manufacturing
down here in Florida.
And if Carl knows how to do this, then Carl, please buy us and I'll just retire.
Like buy me out because that seems incredibly challenging from a cost per unit perspective.
And you know, we don't, so my understanding, Chris, is that none of the failures have actually
shipped into customers' hands.
Maybe they've shipped, but no customer has.
They did the night we were there.
They shipped out.
But no customer has one yet.
They are probably getting them today, tomorrow.
So one thing when you're manufacturing hardware is, and then I kind of learned this the hard
way, failure rate, right?
It just is the case when you're manufacturing your own boards that a certain percentage
will fail.
Yeah.
And I think they have a bigger problem with the casing and things like that because they
are shipping inside Thaleo.
It is a gigabyte motherboard.
It is a part that they've sourced and they can test outside of the Thaleo casing and
all of that before they build the system.
But I would say a significant, significant amount of the underappreciated engineering
that will go into Thaleo is how many things they have custom built to make sure the damn
thing survives shipping.
Like they have a 3D printer that custom builds brackets to hold like GPUs and cables in place
and all of these things that they have learned over the 12 years they've been shipping systems.
They put those lessons into Thaleo to get it through.
It's funny because I asked twice just to clarify, I'm like, just so I understand, what you consider
as a company as the most traumatic, difficult, most deadly period of life for the entire
lifespan of your systems is the shipping period to customers?
And they said, yeah, getting these systems to survive shipping is the number one challenge.
And so they're able to build certain things now that their previous system didn't have.
I completely get that actually.
Like have you ever dealt with UPS on a company to company scale?
Yeah.
It's not yet.
Like shit just disappears, right?
We've lost, we've lost entire gear shipping it for conferences.
Just gone.
Just gone into the void, really like, and then you have this awkward choice.
Do you call your insurance company or not?
Or did you buy insurance with the thing?
Will they cover it?
Or did you buy UPS insurance?
Which I never did.
So I just ate the losses.
Yeah.
A $3,000 backbook into the void.
Seriously.
Nice.
Yeah.
Encrypted hard drive.
Okay.
I keep interrupting.
I'm sorry, Chris.
No.
So what else did you see?
See, I'm jealous.
And first of all, this picture, if you're not listening live, by the way, you are missing
the full code radio experience.
Carl's beard.
Yeah, I know.
Can we just stop for a minute?
Yeah.
I saw him a couple, what is it?
A year ago, two years ago.
It was all brown.
It was like, you know, it was a respectable beard, but now it's got a little bit of salt
in there.
It's got some gray.
Yeah.
I tell you, this guy looks like he's ready for the Linux community.
So Carl is a really interesting CEO.
I think he's one of the more interesting CEOs that I've met because-
I'm personally insulted, but keep going.
He's got a, System76 has a very strong, very unique culture and it starts with Carl.
It absolutely does start with Carl.
And Carl is one of those CEOs that he can be in the middle of a big speech and one of
his employees can interrupt him and he'll stop and he'll listen.
And he doesn't even, doesn't even faze him.
He's one of those people that once he enters the room, everyone listens and Carl is very
soft spoken and the room goes silent so that everyone can hear Carl.
And he is, he's one of those individuals that operates at a higher plane than the rest of
us that are doing day-to-day stuff operate.
He lives at the big picture and yet he is maybe the one that is the most anal about
the details.
Every first hundred Thaleo systems or so that have been built, he's personally gone hands
on, made sure like the wood lines up correctly, that the screw holes, I'm not joking when
I say that they've developed a process to make sure that the screw holes are the correct
smoothness so that way the feel of when you tighten the screws feels right.
I mean this is the level of detail they're going down to now.
Carl is the one showing people how to put some of these things together and in fact
he took a good chunk of time away from the tour when we stopped and we had a break and
we were just kind of going around chatting with the employees.
We got full access to everybody.
There was no restrictions and what he did with that time is he went through the production
line and checked on every system at every stage of production to make sure every single
detail had been seen to.
And he's trying to get his staff to absorb these principles and I think he's dialing
down as they increase production.
But Carl is maybe the most fascinating thing about System 76.
Also the other thing that I've noticed about the company is their retention is very high.
A lot of people that are working there, some of them have been working there since about
the beginning of the company still and they're still there.
The people we mentioned on the show have been working there forever now.
The people that have started working there since I've been following them still work
there.
There's been some churn.
There's been some people that have poured one out for Ryan Sipes but there's been some
churn.
Ryan Sipes is great and frankly no one wears a cape and a top hat like he does.
Let's keep going.
But that says something about the culture of the company too.
They're friends there.
It's a cultural unit.
In fact, this is a weird thing about them.
A lot of them, like the support department, the software development, a lot of them have
the opportunity to just work from home and yet they still choose to come into the office
so they can hang out with everybody.
See, oh damn, okay, first of all, do you understand I'm going to have you sent to federal prison
because you keep wiretapping my home and office.
I just had this conversation this morning about one of the weaknesses at TMB is that
we haven't built a great internal corporate culture because you know what, most everybody
basically works from home and it's kind of a very mercenary situation.
We just don't have that like...
I was thinking about this this morning too.
In fact, I'm thinking I'm going to do a quarterly department meeting at the Linux Academy building
so everybody has to come in, everybody flies in so it's like a shared experience and do
a quarterly team building thing because we just had that company holiday party and everybody
walked away from that feeling super fired up.
Everybody was like, man, this is a great company.
The people here are great.
This is going to be an amazing year.
I get just energized everybody and I'm like, well, they spent hundreds of thousands of
dollars to pull that off but if we could do that at a department level, yeah, and the
same with your company.
It's like the same thing with a small business is it...
It's a much more scale, right?
So flying people from the few people from New Jersey to Florida is not a big deal, seriously.
It's just a question of...
One of the things we've had is we've been doing this a long time and there's one person
who stuck with me through frankly before the show started and remember when the show started,
when Zeus and...
No.
Yeah, no one does.
There's only one person left from that era and there's all these in jokes he and I have
that mean nothing to anybody.
Do you know what I mean?
They mean nothing.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
Carl, I'm very jealous.
Yeah.
He's done a good job but they are not out of the woods yet in terms of this huge transition
or the other way to put it is they're not out of the learning curve yet.
They're still in the learning curve but if they're not a year ahead, then I thought,
like they're on the upper end of that hockey puck.
They're on the upper end of that hockey puck.
I thought they would be like, you know, way down before even it starts to curve up.
I thought it would take at least a year at least to even get this far and they're farther
than I expected.
So I wouldn't be surprised and I would say after going there, everybody should probably
set their expectations a little lower.
I take it back.
That's your favorite.
It is.
You're right.
You know what?
That's mine too.
I play it for my customers.
I just want to make this certainly clear.
The ship dates a little fuzzy.
I would say lower your expectations on when the laptops are going to come.
It could be a year and a half, two year process to learn how to do that.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Laptops?
Oh yeah.
Slow your roll buddy boy.
Yeah.
That's the ultimate goal.
They sell more laptops.
So I asked him about this.
I said, Hey Carl, you sell more desktops or you sell more laptops?
Thinking he'd say laptops.
He said, yeah, we sell more laptops.
But he says, this is what he says, this is what he says, Mike, he says, the desktop sales
have paid for this warehouse transition.
I think the desktop's got to be higher margin.
Yeah.
Right?
So now they're going to look at how to pull off laptops, but that's after they figure
out really how to do this part.
And you know, there's a lot to this.
There's the, there's the, it's hard to explain really, like they, they have analyzed all
of the parts and they, they figure out what they can mass manufacture.
So they can do this in batches, right?
They can, they can build the Thaleo casing and assemble all of that before they've ever
put a single part into it.
So there's parts where they can optimize and they're learning all of that now.
And then they can apply it to laptops.
And they're, you know, they're experimenting with that Thaleo custom IO board with some
of their own custom boards, but maybe that goes a little further down the road.
Who knows?
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
It was an interesting trip.
I, I walked away wanting one of these machines pretty badly.
I'd say I, if I bought one of these, I think it'd be probably the best desktop I ever owned.
Well, first of all, as a big shot corporate vice president, doesn't your assistant buy
it for you?
I mean, isn't that how this works?
I got to get one of those first.
That's what I got to do is I got to get me an assistant.
Yeah.
If there's anyone out there in the audience that's been following me for a really long
time and has figured out how I work and want to be my assistant, let me know.
All right.
So overall impressions, you're, you, you would not, you would not deter anyone from picking
up a Thaleo.
No, I want one.
Yeah.
But what finish the dark walnut or the, you know, I liked the dark in person.
I thought I'd like the lighter one and they sell a lot more of the dark.
It turns out.
Yeah.
I, you know what?
I almost pulled the trigger on one tonight.
The, the manufacturing I'm showing right now on the stream involves a lot of modern shit,
like a 3d printing, like I mentioned, and they have, they have a laser, they have an
80 amp laser cutter that has a, has a laser beam that will cut through pretty much anything
that steps in front of it, including your legs.
So like, Oh yeah, they're using really advanced and modern technology to build this thing.
So they're not, they have an interesting advantage that they don't have a manufacturing legacy.
They're coming at it with a perspective of how can we use Linux?
How can we use 3d printing?
How can we use lasers and that kind of, so they can buy the newest equipment instead
of being like, well, but that's the other thing I think is I think they've been able
to buy some of this stuff used, but it, the market is established enough now that you
can buy a used laser cutter.
You can, you can, you know, and the 3d printer that is large enough to do this is, is not
$20,000.
It's $10,000.
That kind of stuff.
Yeah.
It's really fascinating to watch a company that their strong suit before was customer
service software and, and management of parts to now actually building them.
And to see the other thing as a, as a former now small business owner is to see how different
individuals of the team have stepped up to you know, like in the, I'm showing a picture
of Kate here.
You know, it was the industrial designer of this thing.
People each individual members of the team that did something in the past have now had
to step up to do something that they didn't do before.
And they had to grow as a team to pull this off.
So it wasn't just that the, you know, Carl and a few others, but the entire team had
to add something new to their repertoire.
And they all did it.
That's the thing.
Like they all, like, I don't, I think that's it.
I think that's the lesson I'm taking away from this is if cult, if the culture wasn't
as strong and if the bonds between the people there weren't as strong, this would not have
worked because you can't do this.
You cannot pull this off.
It's not possible to do what they did.
It isn't, it isn't doable unless everybody is pulling in the same direction and people
are willing to pull a new weight that they didn't have to pull before.
And maybe they're willing to have a really shitty three months or maybe they're willing
to have a really shitty six months.
And if the team, the entire, if the CEO can be willing to do it, but the team isn't necessarily
willing to do it.
And when the entire team is willing to do it, you can do something that I swear to God
is not possible.
And it's just, it's really remarkable.
Very impressive.
I think that's what it is.
Yeah.
It's a culture.
They have a shared goal, a shared idea, and they're all in it together.
Maniacs.
Well, it's nice.
It's something you envy.
You know, you go there and you're like, gosh, the army wouldn't be man being part of this,
you know?
I envy it deeply.
I mean, this is, oh, there's so much here that I don't want to dive into until our end
of the year episode, but there is something to be said from being in a market, a geographical
market, that's in a certain state where you can have a culture of like-minded people and
take a lot of risk towards a certain goal.
Right in this case, it would be an open desktop Linux platform.
Yeah.
They joked about having a mutual suicide pact.
Well, yeah.
Yeah.
It is.
It's humbling to see it because they roll with their weird.
And I think having Kate on their team, she's their designer.
She's their Johnny Ives, really.
And she's really helped with the, yeah, she's helped with the branding so much and they've
she's helped them embody what they all as a team represent with, you know, the robots
and the kind of sci-fi look.
And I appreciate that as somebody who named his company Jupiter Broadcasting.
I saw a lot of that is they're now communicating, they're communicating their unique style via
their branding now via their hardware.
And I believe within a year or two, I think that's capable this team could pull it off
with Pop OS too.
And Pop OS is getting close too, but that's where Pop OS fits into this whole thing is
it's part of communicating System 76 as well as solving problems for customers because
they, they have their own support data.
You know, they have their own customer base.
They know what these people want.
They also know what kind of hardware they want to ship and they know what they need
to do to ship that.
And it all kind of comes together with the branding, the story, the hardware and the
OS.
And when they're eventually in a couple of years making their own laptops, it will complete
the circle.
It sort of closes the loop.
And the crazy thing is, and Carl reaffirmed this is they haven't taken any outside investing.
This isn't, this is being done with this, with the financing of the sales of their existing
Linux products.
They're financing this with the sale of Linux hardware and Linux desktops, which in itself
is a bit of a success story for Linux that doesn't get talked about very much.
Well, I think that's the best place to leave it.
All right.
Yeah.
So, and I'll have, I'll talk more about some of the hardware details and the software details
that I saw in Linux Unplugged tomorrow too.
So I've saved some of that for the Linux Unplugged show too, cause there's lots to share, lots
to share.
But, you know, we joke a lot about Yoda on this show, but there was a, what would you
call it?
A retrofactor?
I don't know.
Just kind of like a profile piece on Donald Knuth, one of the founding fathers of computer
science.
I'd just like to wrap up the show today.
I know we've talked a lot about Linux and System76 and next week's episode is our end
of the year.
So these are two kind of non-codey code radios.
But if you want to know like the deep low level of coding, I was once forced to read
The Art of Computer Programming by Donald Knuth and it's thick, like a very dry steak.
But let me tell you something.
He is, the New York Times calls him the Yoda of computer programming and frankly that's
what he is.
If you're looking for someone's papers and he's written books, he's written a bunch of
academic materials for you to study.
If you're looking for someone to get a little deeper, let's say you're a web developer and
you want to learn more about, oh jeez, see it's hard for me not to slap around JavaScript
developers.
Actual, let's just say if you want to learn more low level stuff, I would encourage you
to read some Knuth.
Okay.
Knuth, Knuth, put it this way.
When I was a young whippersnapper, Knuth is key, it's one of the first things I was taught.
And a gift I got was the entire set of The Art of Computer Programming.
Oh, that's a value of like almost $300 my friend.
Yes, which I was then compelled to read and report on.
Okay.
Very good.
It's worth it.
It's a nice piece.
It's got good photos too.
I was just skimming it as you were talking about it.
The Yoda's are looking good.
Well, it's universal, right?
It's not like, you know, JavaScript for dummies or C sharp for dummies.
It's literally The Art of Computer Programming.
When the show's title is The Art and Business of Software Development, well, he's the art
of software development.
This is the guy.
There you go.
Thank you.
I strongly recommend that everybody read his, at least volumes one and two.
The subsequent volumes and he has Fast Seals, which he calls them, which are like little
editions, can get a little rough and very like data mathy, but the first two I think
are very important.
You know what?
I will put links to some of the eBooks and this article in the show notes so people can
go grab and make it easy for the lazy web, coder.show slash three three six for that.
Mr. Dominic, is there anybody you want to link to anything you want to plug before we
get out of here this week?
I'd like to plug a Carl O'Chel's beard.
No kidding.
I'm a little jealous.
No.
Go to at Domenico on Twitter and the bad fodder dot com.
You know what the worst thing about Carl is, is that he's working his butt off and he's
still in great shape.
And it's the.
It looks amazing.
It's so frustrating.
What a jerk, right?
I don't know how he pulls it off.
Actually, I know how he pulls it off because he stayed in shape since like his early 20s.
He's like a workout enthusiast.
I tell you what, that's the trick.
I'm so lazy.
Anyways, you know what I would do if you're lazy, just want to get these episodes every
single week.
I go to coder.show slash subscribe.
Easy peasy, lemon squeezy.
You get the week's episode whenever we put it out on a Monday.
We put on Tuesday.
We put on a Friday.
You get it.
Coder dot show slash subscribe.
Also, we'd love to have you participate in our subreddit coder radio dot reddit dot com.
And last but not least, give us some feedback, your thoughts, your stories.
Coder dot show slash contact.
Thanks for being here.
And we'll see you right back here for our year end wrap up next week.