This is Koto Radio, episode 305, for April 16th, 2018.
Hi everyone and welcome to Koto Radio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look at the art and business of software development and its related technologies.
This episode is brought to you by our two fine sponsors, DigitalOcean and Linux Academy.
I'll tell you more about those great sponsors as this here show goes on.
Me, my name is Chris, but what's more important is our host.
He's perched, established, and ready to go.
Over in the bayous of Florida is Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike!
I want Szechuan sauce, I want that Mulan 1990s Clinton-era Szechuan sauce.
Have you tried it? Have you tried it?
Yes, I have actually.
Yeah, it's, you know, it's alright.
Well, Mr. Dominic, we had a lot of follow-up to get into from last week, but we're going to kind of do something different with it.
Instead of just reading emails, we're going to have it inspire a couple of things in the show for the next couple of weeks.
Including, we're going to do a little bit of historical deep dive into Big Blue this week, just to sort of set up another conversation we're going to have in a couple of weeks.
And the early dominance that IBM had, and the fight they had in the 80s.
And then we'll get into a more modern hoopla that involves your current workflow.
But why don't we start out with some emails that came into the show.
Are you ready, good sir, for the feedback?
I'm ready like a dime store hooker.
Okay, alright, I can't ask for more than that.
And somebody calls right on that dot.
You know, the thing is, the thing is, I'd pay for you.
I think you'd be money well spent, I gotta be honest.
You'd be money well spent.
That's the nicest thing anyone said to me.
So we got an email that said, hey guys, keep an eye on Swift Playgrounds.
Remember you said that the canary in the coal mine, or I said the canary in the coal mine for Apple switching to ARM processors would be when Xcode starts coming out for the iOS platform.
And a couple of emails pointed this out, but I like this one.
He says, you know, look, this is the way it's going to go.
Swift Playgrounds is going to grow up into an Xcode replacement.
It also means that Apple would have to create a layer much like art to make sure that people don't brick their iPads.
Then Mike can finally preach the iPad Pro Bible once again.
What do you think?
iPad Pros with like a grown up version of Swift Playgrounds, sort of like Final Cut came out of iMovie?
I mean, that is like a certain version of Lovecrafting.
Yeah, a couple of people write that in.
I don't know.
I don't think that's the case.
I could be wrong.
I hope not.
I mean, Playgrounds should really stay focused.
Well, it's not even that Playgrounds should stay focused.
It's, you know, the more dev I do, the more I realize I need all the toys, right?
Like, this is not a minimal, minimalist paradise here.
This is a bring me all the toys.
What do you mean by toys?
Like, you know what?
Sometimes a Mac is the right tool.
Sometimes a Linux system is the right tool.
And sometimes a Windows 10 machine is the right tool.
I can't.
And all three of those are like actually powerful systems.
I can't imagine coding on an iPad and doing my day to day workflow on that without like being filled with a rage that could consume a thousand cents.
Yeah, well, don't think of today's tools.
Think of, you know, five, 10 years of iteration where you've got, you know, different smart boards now.
Like, OK, what is an iPad when I hook it to a mechanical keyboard?
Is it even still an iPad?
Maybe not.
I mean, maybe not.
Yeah.
So then we're now we're talking like a surface, right?
Which, yes, I think is a fine dev machine.
So, OK, good.
All right.
Well, we'll be there.
Yeah.
Esteban says go with your gut.
He wrote him with a couple of emails, but I really like this point.
He made he says forget about the nice songs and poems about following your heart.
Your heart can and will mislead you.
But your gut, your gut always feels right.
That's always right.
I agree.
Go.
And here's your problem with the heart.
My heart was with the language.
You might be familiar with this, Chris.
I don't know if you know this.
In 2014, something happened.
There was this language called Objective C.
Here we go again.
Yes.
And then my heart was carved out like I'm a deer on the side of the road rather swiftly,
one might say.
Oh, bitter.
That was good.
So I did it.
Yeah.
Next.
That was pretty well done.
Esteban, your feedback is the best only because you set me up for another hit at Swift.
We got we also had a pretty good point on the subreddit.
Just really.
I don't know.
Maybe not.
Pretty good point might not be the way to put it.
But we got a feedback.
Well, because it wasn't really a point.
It was just an observation.
We got a feedback on our episode last week.
No bad guys, only survivors.
Code Radio 304.
And Andy writes, it was a it was a really valuable lesson for him.
He says he went back and re-listened to certain chapters a couple of times.
And he really felt like it was a great reflection on how to how to sort of understand failure,
learn from failure, which he's also been able to use as a contractor.
So he says, I also enjoyed your recent forays into being shocked that PowerShell is a thing.
He's talking about me there.
Yeah.
But like that, we went down to Microsoft and talked to them and got that story.
So he's covering a couple of bits here.
But he says, I really found it informative and useful specifically today because he has
had to deal with the other end of empty promises of enterprise software salespeople for years
now.
And he says crossing the chasm is definitely on his reading list.
So it was great to be able to serve somebody who is on the other side of the contract agreement
that we often like sort of proverbially talk about.
It was super useful for him to hear insights into the other side of the argument.
So I thought that was pretty cool.
And a lot of a lot of people really like that episode, which just makes me feel bad for
all of you.
Really, you just have to burn things down from time to time and and replant a forest
and then you don't like my thank you.
You beat me to it.
You know, you know, our cousins, Uncle Jay and of course, Bain is a very similar philosophy.
Oh, man.
You know, you know, I've started watching this.
Have you heard of Alex Inc.?
I have not.
It's not that great.
But it's an ABC sitcom starring What's His Face from Scrubs, the main guy from Scrubs.
And he's a he's a he's a mid 30s father who quits his full time job to launch a podcast
network.
And it's oh, does this hurt a little bit?
It is awkward.
I'm watching it with my with my kid.
And I'm like, that is kind of like what life is like.
And it's funny to watch something that you do because I know developers see this is I'm
not even going to resonate with developers because this has been common with development
for a long time.
But nobody in the mainstream has really talked about podcasting for four decades.
Yeah.
For as long as it's been around a decade.
And now all of a sudden there's a TV show about it.
Pandora is launching podcasting support.
It's really something to be sort of just sitting here watching all of a sudden this industry
just I don't know, be awesome.
Really?
Yeah.
Like enter the next level of consumer awareness, you know, like it's reached another section
of it's moved on from the early adopters.
See, I never understood why podcasting and this has nothing to do with the topic of the
show, but let's just go into it because I'm bored.
Why podcasting isn't just treated as like an extension of AM radio, like I used to love
AM radio.
I mean, before Imus was an asshole, I used to listen to Imus in the morning.
Right.
You know, when I lived in New Jersey, when I was younger, there was a you know, you remember
Chrissy.
I mean, I'm sure they still exist.
You have the local stations.
Right.
You have like your, you know, Washington state weed smokers.
One oh one dot AM.
We had a one to one point five in New Jersey.
Right.
And you get like the local feel.
Oh, yeah.
And you're right.
So why do I I'm obsessed with you being a drug addict, by the way.
Yeah.
All these drugs.
All these years.
But why don't people see it as an extension of like talk radio?
Seriously, because in my mind, that's exactly what it is like.
I'm wearing over the head headphones that are cushy and hot and my ears are literally
on fire right now because I live in the goddamn jungle and I'm using a microphone that looks
like a swollen penis.
It's huge.
Yeah.
That is a particularly phallic microphone you have.
So I mean, it's black.
It's not good.
It's not wrong.
Wrong.
My setup.
But we've gone down a path anyway.
Why do you think podcasting is not treated just like an extension of AM radio?
Well, because it's sort of a no rules medium and it's such a varying degree of quality.
It's a lot like software development that in that regard, you know, like there's some
great software developers and there's some horrible software developers.
And I think also just the sort of homebrew nature of it.
It's it's it.
That's changing, though.
I think that is going to change as now you've got all of these major radio networks that
are releasing podcasts and maybe it will start to be seen as that.
Well, I have to say, like the Wall Street Journal just recently did theirs and they've
upped their game.
Yeah.
And so is the New York Times.
It sucks in a way, but then at the same time, it just got up our game.
You know, always got to be up on our game.
Well, listen, put on the video stream and I'll just take my shirt off.
There we go.
Boom.
Yeah.
We've got a lot of pop requests that come into the show.
You know what I've seen some great beards and some plump Linux developers.
I would love to see Linux developer.
I don't know, man.
All that mud in those beards, that just is the nightmare for me.
I just triggers me.
All right.
Well, we do have a topic today to get into and it's kind of an important one, so we shouldn't
run people off because it's going to be setting up the next couple of weeks of shows.
So before we dive in, let's do our first bit of duty and business and thank the fantastic
folks over at DigitalOcean.do.co slash coder. Now let me go check here, getting out the
prop piece of paper that I have. Yes, verified with the back office staff, there is no S
on that do.co slash coder. You go there to sign up for DigitalOcean, simplicity at scale,
and you'll get a $100 DigitalOcean credit. Did you hear that? $100 in DigitalOcean credit.
It's a limited time offer, so I want you to take advantage of it while they're still giving
it out. Do.co slash coder. DigitalOcean is incredibly fast infrastructure on demand.
You can get spun up in less than 55 seconds. Every single DigitalOcean droplet, from the
three cents an hour, which is my favorite or even cheaper than that, to the super expensive
hundreds gigabytes of RAM, massive Xeon CPUs, everything in that entire lineup, SSDs, all
of it. 40 gigabit connections into the hypervisors, all of it. Great, beautiful, easy to use dashboard
on all of it, and a straightforward, well-documented, full-featured API that you can start programming
against, take advantage of existing libraries, or open source code that's been completely
designed and built for you. DigitalOcean has predictable pricing, entire application stacks
that are ready to go, and you can also deploy a base system if you like. You combine all
of that with fantastic documentation and their new flexible droplets. For $15 a month, you
can mix and match resources the most appropriate for your application. Or, I mentioned it,
they have those really high-end Xeon CPUs for CPU-optimized droplets. If you have a
really compute-intensive workload, very, very useful for that. And then, on top of that,
for storage, they have Spaces and Object Storage. Spaces is S3-compatible, and Object Storage
just shows up as another device right on your rig. That's so sweet because it's great for
backups, it's great for centralizing storage, it's great for adding just new disk if you
have something that's growing on your existing droplet, and recently they've adjusted their
prices. So, if you've been a DigitalOcean customer for a while, you can go upgrade your
system for free. Pay exactly what you're paying now, and you just get more RAM, more disk,
more CPU. dio.co slash coder. Go to DigitalOcean, try it out with a $100 credit. dio.co slash
coder.
All right, Mr. Dominic, you tweeted something that kind of stuck with me, because you did
this towards the beginning of the month, still thinking about it. You said, I've read this
twice now, and I'm absolutely convinced that Microsoft is becoming the platonic ideal of
IBM that I mentioned a few weeks ago in Coder Radio. And then you include a link to the
resignation of one of Microsoft's long-term engineers who, after 21 years, was leaving.
And you said the platonic version of IBM. And when we were talking about Sun Microsystems
on the show, we sort of got a new appreciation for how important some of this backstory of
the tech industry is to really kind of understand where it's going. And we danced around IBM
a lot when we were talking about Sun, and then we danced around IBM a lot when we started
talking about Microsoft again. So I thought maybe this would be the week we hit the pause
button and we just do kind of what I'm going to call a high-level deep dive, so the important
bits about IBM that we need to know for the wider context of our future discussions, with
a little background history. And maybe even take a moment and go to sort of IBM's real
peak over the PC industry in the early to mid-80s. Are you a complicit co-host in my
schemes here? Do you think this is something worth doing?
Listen, let's put on our black suits with white shirts, and let's make sure we have
high socks. Let's go to IBM.
You know, just to kind of give you, we're going to talk about IBM's influence over tech,
but IBM really kind of had big influence over the way employment works in the US. I don't
know if it's true, but they definitely, IBM says it's true, that they pioneered the 40-hour
work week and group health benefits in a company. That's a pretty big claim, if that's true.
And IBM technically got started in 1911 when they leased unit record equipment and were
famous for creating punch cards. In fact, they really became the Computing Tabulating
Recording Company, CTR, until an individual named Thomas J. Watson took over in 1924 and
renamed them to International Business Machines, or IBM.
And so let's go back to sort of IBM's origins, sort of a quick overview. This is a clip that
I grabbed from a 1985's broadcast of the Computer Chronicles. Now, to take you up to speed in
1985, IBM had just recently wrapped up a potential monopoly lawsuit with the federal government.
They were trying to push for a new expansion card format, and there's a lot of discussions
about white label BIOS development. And so at this point in time, the Computer Chronicles
goes back and looks at IBM's origins.
In many respects, the history of IBM is the history of computing. The parent company's
founder, Herman Hollerith, devised the first practical card punch calculator. It was used
for the first time to tabulate the 1890 American census. The IBM card soon became the symbol
of the early computer age. IBM's first mainframe, the Mark I, ushered in the post-war era of
data processing, for the most part restricted to scientific applications. But IBM's choice
market was always business, especially big business. As advances in memory and storage
took place, they were applied and promoted for business use. In this manner, the company
developed an almost exclusive hold on the data processing departments of major corporations.
By the 1960s, IBM was the leader, both technically and commercially, with over two-thirds of
the mainframe market. Its pervasive customer support and computer families gave it a major
advantage in almost every aspect of business computing. By 1966, the company began to look
at the small business market and expand it overseas. Today, suddenly cleared of its history-making
antitrust suit, IBM continues to expand its share of the market. And it does so in the
same way it has in the past, secretively, cautiously, and with ruthless efficiency.
They didn't really have a clear picture of how IBM was ever going to be supplanted. They
were so dominant that here was an interview that took place right after that clip plays
in the Computer Chronicle, and listen to the resignation in their voices. It's just a foregone
conclusion.
Jim, IBM saw some opportunities here a few years ago and jumped right in and took the
lion's share of the PC market. Do you see any effective competition now? Are we all
going to be working toward being compatible with IBM?
Well, Gary, in 1984, we saw IBM capture 26% of the worldwide PC market, and we at DataQuest
expect that that market share will continue to increase through our forecast period, which
ends in 1989. I would certainly expect they would command 40 to 50% of the market by that
point in time.
So, I mean, you really get an idea of how dominant IBM was in the PC market, which is
a market they don't even play in anymore. They don't even bother anymore. I think it's
kind of remarkable that that transition where they go from, how could anybody ever replace
them? That was the IBM. They were so dominant, right? And now they're more thought of like
cloud services and enterprise services and mainframe still, but it's in a lot of ways
where Microsoft is in their world of the compute little kingdom. Amazon's in their world of
the compute kingdom. They own all of that. Now we have lots of little IBMs, it feels
like. Baby IBMs, mini-IBMs, where they don't have unilateral influence, but they sure have
a lot of influence in the section of the galaxy they own. What do you think? Is that fair?
I think it's fair, right? I mean, I think IBM really, it's interesting to think about
how long they've been around, right? And how much has, can we say changed since they've
been around?
No, they're still around.
Well, I mean, of course they're still around. They're a big player in AI.
But since 1911, over a hundred years ago, things have changed.
Right. I mean, I like to think of IBM in terms of the ThinkPad in the more recent history.
And at some point, it became just not worth it for them to actually manufacture their
own computers. Which is a little sad.
It is, and it's really telling. So now though, even despite that, the company's taking in
about a hundred billion a year and has around 450,000 employees still. So they didn't go
away. And I think that's maybe a key lesson that when we start talking about where Microsoft
is going, if you get to a certain dominance, I don't think you quite go away. Like Sun
never reached that. They didn't, they never reached the level of influence that IBM or
a Microsoft or a Google has. Whereas, you know, I think once you get to a certain scale,
a certain size, unless you're acquired, you just never really go away. You still have
a certain customer base you're going to serve for our lifetime, is what I suspect.
So when you say the platonic version of IBM, do you mean like a less hostile version? Like
a less like over overusing of their influence? Cause IBM was known for playing. Yeah. I mean
like the, the, the purist, the best idea of what IBM should have been. Right. Although
I will say it's interesting that you mentioned Lucent because Lucent like died amid accounting
scandals, right? Like, yeah, that's true. Maybe not the same thing.
I have a visual guide to the history of IBM linked in the show notes. If you go to coder.show
slash three oh five, you will find that. And I also have the entire computer Chronicles
1985 broadcast linked in there, which is, which the whole episode is a profile of big
blue sort of a during its mead. It's a, it's a peak PC industry influence, which is a fascinating
time to take a snapshot and then to look back at it now. Yeah. So that's all in there. And
also a link to the New York times when IBM dropped, or when the US government dropped
its antitrust suit against IBM, which the federal government said they no longer dominate
the computer business, but the rest of the industry didn't necessarily agree. And there
was quite a bit of controversy about it back then. And it's also interesting that, you
know, we think of the Watson machine now, that big, huge, you know, chest destroying
IBM mainframe. Well, it's not just Sherlock Holmes is a right-hand man. Thomas J. Watson
ran the company when it was still called computing tableting record company to IBM. He ran it
from 1874 to 1956, I think, or in, I'm not sure exactly his timeframe, but he ran it
for, or yeah, anyways, he ran it for quite a while as his name was Watson. So I, some
of these, the Watson project we hear about now may actually, I guess, be a reference
to him and not a Sherlock Holmes reference that I always thought it was, which is kind
of neat, just a little bit of history. And they've been around for so long. They've seen
so much. And of course they don't necessarily have the best history either. They sort of
have a famous dark aspect to their history when it came to those punch machines. But
now they're in the cloud. Now they're a business technology company and a cloud company. And
Lotus is still around. I don't know what to make of any of it, Mr. Dominic, but I do know
what to make of Linux Academy. Let's go to Linux Academy and then we'll get to the hoopla
of this week. There's a great promo going on. This was, well, it's a new release over
at Linux Academy. Go to linuxacademy.com slash coders. They have 70 new courses, challenges,
and learning activities coming out in the month of April. Linux Academy is a full feature
training library with everything you need to learn new skills and advance your career.
Linuxacademy.com slash coders. This one does have an S. There you can sign up for a free
seven day trial and try out the platform. Pick a timeframe, set a course, and stick
to it. They'll build learning goals and help you. Along the way you can try out their hands
on labs that give you scenario based learning. They have video courses on every self-paced
in-depth topic you might want to learn about. They have flashcards, which are forked by
the community to help you study. They have learning paths, which are series of courses
and content planned by instructors for specific career tracks. And if you want to get certifications,
they've got courses created specifically to prepare you for those as well. They've got
iOS and Android apps, study tools, lesson audio, study books that you can download and
use offline, practice exams and quizzes, and those labs I mentioned that will spin them
up on demand. If you ever get stuck, they've got a human being to help you along the way.
With 70 new courses, challenges, and learning activities, it's never been a better time
to try out Linux Academy with a seven day free trial. Linuxacademy.com slash coders.
20 new courses, 50 new cloud assessments, hands on learning activities, and new challenges
are all coming this month to Linux Academy. Linuxacademy.com slash coders. And a big thank
you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Coder Radio program. Linuxacademy.com slash coders.
So let's talk about our workflow. This is a topic that we keep revisiting every single
time we think we're done. And then it keeps coming back. And it won't, it just is not
getting fixed. And it's getting very frustrating for me, as you can probably tell. Since the
last time we talked about this, the last time we really talked about this is when the rumors
were going around that Apple might ship ARM processors in the Macs. Now we've gotten new
news that the Mac Pro is going to be delayed until 2019. That they've hired a Pro workflow
team to pretend to do work so that way Apple can analyze how they work. And they brought
down TechCrunch's Panzerino to do a one on one interview to kind of just get an update
on where things are at. And it looks like there's not much news for the Mac Pro other
than it's going to be later and we're still at the drawing board. But this Pro team that
they've hired, which is a group of producers and editors and content creators that are
shooting real world projects at Apple and then trying to edit them on Apple Gear with
developers sitting over their shoulders going, oh, what do you think about when that happens?
How do you feel when that happens? How can we do this better? And trying to find frustration
points to influence the design of the Mac Pro. In other words, Mike, your computer woes
aren't solved. You're going to continue to have to wait and see. Oh, we did get news
that they are absolutely definitely working on a new monitor. So that's going to be coming
as well.
I'm happy right now.
And so this totally comes out right after the ARM news. And there's no way this thing's
going to be Intel. It's supposed to ship in 2019. So I think we can just put the ARM discussion
aside and just focus on this part.
Yeah. So you know what this tells me, Chris? And it's interesting because I've listened
to a lot of takes on this and my response was completely different.
Okay.
Mine was the Mac Pro is not for me.
I would perhaps too boldly say this wasn't a machine for you with the price tag. If the
iMac Pro starting at $5,000, this thing's probably starting at $7,000 or $8,000. Possibly.
I think my take on it was also a little bit different than the other takes. My take on
it was holy shit, Apple really doesn't know how to build a computer anymore. Like everybody's
always talked about when Steve Jobs died, Apple lost their way. I think it's more like
the recent talent drain they've had lower in the ranks that has gotten some coverage.
There's been some well-known ones like Mr. Skeuomorphic when he left, Scott Forstall.
That was I think one of their massive technical assets that truly understood the hardware
and the operating system. He was gone and he was a power user. And I think over the
years they've had power users leaving Apple. And I don't think, I mean, I just don't think
there's a really super strong computer enthusiast in the company that's in a position to influence
product design.
Now, come on.
You don't need to hire these million dollar a year editors and producers to find out that
you just need to create another version of the Mac Pro Tower. I think they don't know.
The fact that they didn't see-
How could they not know though? There are people who are obviously tech enthusiasts.
No, I think it's a group of out of touch old white men that are running it. Look at the
people who come out on stuff.
I don't know, dude.
Phil Schiller, Tim Cook, they're all-
Yeah, but if they're old white guys, if that's going to be the thing we use, they're us or
older, right? I mean, you're slightly older than me, but like there are rough generation.
So their idea of a computer should be very similar to what I mean.
But they're so out of touch. They've been running Apple. They haven't probably gone
to the Dell website and looked at how you configure a Dell or anything like that in
years. I guess I'm not trying to say it's because they're old white guys. I'm saying
it's because they are people that have just gotten out of touch over the years by being
Apple executives, running the company and not looking at PCs.
I don't think you're making like some weird social issue here. But first of all, if you're
a business like Apple, the idea that you're not going to look at your main competitors
seems crazy. Of course, they probably go very regularly to Dell.com and play with the configurator
and see what Dell-
Oh yeah. No, I think the issue with the leadership though doesn't understand why you might want
more GPU power over CPU power. I don't think they grok the concepts. And that's how we
got the trashcan.
It's funny. I see it completely differently. I don't think they grok the concept of why
upgrading RAM at the user level is important. Right. When do you suppose the last time Craig
Federici or Tim Cook or Phil Schiller has upgraded the RAM in a laptop? Maybe never.
Maybe 10 years.
Probably never.
See, they don't live that world. They don't understand it. I think they really for a long
time thought the iPad was going to do it for a lot of people.
And so-
I think they did too. I mean, it's obvious when they had the original Mac Pro Summit
that they were shocked that people didn't think the iMac Pro was the right answer. Which
in reality it probably is for a lot of people, right? But I don't know, man. This whole thing
of them being out of touch feels kind of like, there's nothing stopping them from making
the device you and I want. Let's just have a little bit of self-awareness here. Are we
just out of touch?
Right.
No, no. I mean, I think it's pretty clear in the product. The failure of the trashcan
and the inability for them to recognize still the limitations of the iMac Pro. The iMac
Pro is being lauded right now in this conversation as, it's great. It's going to be more than
what most people need. But in reality, the iMac Pro still suffers from thermal limiting.
There is not currently a Mac in production that does not suffer from thermal throttling
when you push it. That is embarrassing. None of them, none of them are sufficiently cooled
because of design compromises. And when I'm pushing my MacBook trying to encode a video
and I know that the CPU is being downclocked so that way it doesn't reach thermal thresholds,
it's like, what did I pay all this money for? That's embarrassing. And they just don't get
these concepts. They don't understand why USB-C isn't enough. Why even though only some
people have an SD card reader need that they should put it on every model. They just haven't
lived that. And so they think the solution is to bring these pro people in and hire these
yes men to tell them what they should be building.
But that-
Well, it is interesting the people they brought in, right? They haven't brought in people
who are going to be critical, which I get it. You don't want to pay people to insult
you. But hiring a Chris Fisher would have been an interesting look at it, right? Saying,
you know what guys, I'm an IT admin and I'm a video podcast producer and I have a budget.
So I would like a month, because I think you and I effectively want the same thing, but
you would lean on GPU and I would like to buy the cheapest model, but be able to upgrade
it for five years.
Yeah. I think if I could have, if Tim and Johnny came to me and said, what do you want?
I would say, take the Mac Pro cheese grater tower and sell it at a base of the cheapest
you can sell, one CPU, 16 gigs of RAM, one SSD drive. And then let me-
Add to it later.
Yeah. Six months, I'll throw four drives in. And then in six months after that, I'll throw-
Okay, but I have that on my desk here.
Yeah. Well?
It's a Dell Optiplex 7050, right? Is it possible that you, me and John Syracuse and everybody
bitching about Apple's like, quote unquote, abandonment of Mac Pros is just wrong? Not
wrong in like that we're wrong technically, but wrong in that-
We should be using Windows.
Right. Apple's not making a mistake. Apple's just choosing not to serve you.
So that's my option. So there's just a couple of specifically Adobe applications. Ironically,
Photoshop isn't really one of them, that I need a platform to run and they're the latest
creative cloud versions. I'm not going to run like version seven of Photoshop, for example.
And so if I have to run that, I prefer to run it on a Mac than run it on a, on Windows
because my, you guys know my history. I'm just not a, I'm not a huge fan of using Windows
as my work OS and daily driver. I have some Windows systems and it's fine for what I use
it for. And I don't care if other people use it, but it's just not what I want to use.
And so, and it's not what I want to have in production 24 seven in my studio either.
Well, because it'll restart five times. Oh, jeez.
So my options right now are Windows or Mac. And I just, it's the, it's the, it goes back
to that tool thing. Like these are the tools of my trade and those are the, those are the
two platforms they run on. I find that infuriating. So I'm constantly spending a lot of my time
and energy trying to come up with alternatives on Linux constantly. I'm always searching
for Linux alternatives. I'm always trying out different projects under Linux. And I
mean, I probably burn four or five hours a week and it's just, I'm getting really worn
out and I'm getting, I'm starting to lose the faith that I'm ever going to find a solution.
So now I just need Apple to figure their shit out because I don't want to use Windows and
I'm kind of getting to the end of my rope of trying to re re-engineer everything on
Linux every, every week. So right. But that's insane. So you're, you're basically going
to like spin your wheels and like just wait for Apple to solve this problem for you.
What if they decide not to, right? I think it's pretty obvious. Well, I think even if
they, even if they build a good Mac pro, I'm not going to be able to afford it. So I think
I have to move on anyways. Right. Exactly. Like if the iMac pro starts a five grand,
you know, the Mac pro is going to be starting at eight, like there. And also it's not going
to be what you and I want. It is not going to be a black or gray or whatever color tower
that you can slot in parts. It might be like several different takes on the Mac mini for
all we know. You know, right. It could just be, I know I'm almost thinking that's what
it is. It's just like a super beefed up. I can't remember the name, but what does that
Nvidia machine that recently came out? You're not thinking of the, you're not thinking of
the Intel NUC, are you? You're thinking of the Intel NUC, the one after it. Maybe it
isn't, it's like, it's a new, like a skull, something NUC that is Intel latest Intel
I seven with an AMD dedicated ish. Yes. GPU. Yep. Yep. That's that things that NUC is.
It's funny you say that. That is exactly what my thought process is. If I could move my
remaining workflow items over to Linux, um, then I, that would be my go to workstation.
It's small, it's interchangeable. It's quiet. It's relatively low cost. It's expandable.
It has Thunderbolt. Um, it's everything the Mac mini should be, but I would use it to
run Linux. The issue is even on Linux to do my job that all the tools I need are still
commercial. They're still proprietary. So I'm not fully, um, right. You're not a freedom
beard. Well, I'm still not even getting, I'm still, I still can get drug around by the
nose horn a little bit. You know what I'm saying? Like I can still kind of, so in part
of me, part of me feels like maybe Apple has gotten the, um, the smell of fear that they're
losing their pro market. And so they're maybe over the next few years, we're going to see
some 2019, right? They said 2019. Yeah, but, but this pro team isn't just influencing the
Mac pro it's going to go into the, how the Mac book pro works. And I think the pro moniker,
I think that's, I think you're going to start seeing, I wouldn't be surprised if you see
a mea culpa of some kind on the Mac book pro, like an SD card reader or a totally revamped
keyboard or something like that, that they say is influenced by the pro team. Well, if
there was a keyboard, that would be definitely something worth talking about. I think maybe
the bigger meta issue here though, it to even take it away from Apple and say the meta issue
is I have a tool that I depend on several tools and the vendor of that platform seems
like they've completely stopped. They've lost how to serve me. They don't know how to do
it.
Right. So you went to a bar and the bartender doesn't care to serve you, right? They don't
care. This is the problem, right? They just said, you know what, Mike or, you know, Chris,
we only carry, you know, Peruvian amber ale. We don't carry what you want. I don't know.
I made something up, but like the DOS Uber IPA, right? Like this is how I feel. And I've
been a pretty, like I have bought many Apple machines, both for my businesses and for myself.
And I don't know, every time I like deal with them, I feel like I'm not their target customer.
They're happy to take my money cause they're a business, but they just don't meet. Like
every machine I buy from them is, is very expensive and it's like deeply compromised.
There is the Mac pros keyboard, which is in my opinion, basically unusable. Um, and by
the way, another great bug I found in my $3,000 Mac book pro HDMI doesn't work very well.
It's unreliable. Plug it in. You have to unplug it, replug it. No, no, no. Max, you're supposed
to just work, dude. You're fine. You're fine. You're probably, it doesn't work. And then
I looked it up and it's like, yeah, it's because of the interchange between USB-C I have the
Apple official Belkin adapter that costs $70. And it's just like a bug in the, in the OS
for, for HDMI, right? There was a bug with HDMI. Well, you mean on the flip side on Linux,
you just have, nobody's even bothered to write that score yet. Nothing's up to resident looks
like shit on my phone and on windows is just going to be fixed the next driver release.
We swear we promise just update next. It'll be fixed. We swear. We promise it never gets
fixed. I'm going to push back on it though. So running my Dell on windows 10, which I've
been doing for a, I'm going to be doing quite a lot actually. Everything just works. I can't
believe I'm saying that about windows, but what dude? No, it just works. Yeah, it does.
I have had, I have more day to day problems now running my Macbook pro, which I am trying
to do in clamshell motor of HDMI, which people say, Oh, well you should get a DP. Yeah. What
is it? DPI DVI. You should get a mini DVI adapter to thunder pole and you should buy
the special licensed one. And uh, but like I'm not buying 20 adapters. Like I paid $70
for an HDMI adapter. I think it ought to work. Um, I'm sorry, but like, so this is the error
case. If the laptop goes into suspension or falls asleep because I like got up to take
a phone call and it, uh, resumes, you know, wakes up, it sometimes won't notice the HDMI
adapter. Then you have to restart the machine, plug it in, unplug it to get it to pick up
the HDMI. Sometimes it doesn't work. I have hit a bug on my editing Macbook where I'll
be working on a project. I'll close the lid. I'll arrive at the studio. I plug in my single
Thunderbolt three cable, which provides power, video networking, et cetera, USB. I plugged
that in, opened the lid up and the screen, I have a mouse cursor, but both screens are
red, like bright, bright, bright, bright red. And the only thing I can do is power off
the Mac book and power back on. Well, and all these compromises are in the name of what
thinness? Yeah. Right. Like, well, and you know, like the old West has stagnated in,
in terms of stability with, you know, and supposedly, but again, they're turning around
on all of that. It, it really, the thing is, it's like, I have weird ass issues on Linux
sometimes too, you know, like my Gallego pro does strange semi military plane lifting off
in my lap things all the time. So I would be willing to bet if you stuck her around
on a windows 10 for six months, issues will start to crop up because in my experience
in all of these systems, the first couple of weeks tend to be like the golden weeks.
Like you just, right. You have not only is it something fresh and new, so that's kind
of nice, but then you don't have like the cruft and all this crap that just eventually
starts causing problems. I don't even know how to explain it. So, so can I take a swing
here? Go for it. Would you agree with the statement that OS stability and quality has
just gone down over the years? Yeah, I was just saying that yesterday. Actually, I was
just having kind of an off the air conversation with Joe about how, uh, it's totally feels
like it's gone downhill. Like, uh, I thought by now all of these little weird things would
be worked out by now. Like we would have like fought the good fight and we would have figured
this stuff out, but we still have video issues. So what do you think? Yeah.
Uh, I mean, I think, you know, I, I think it's kind of a shit show to be honest. I think
Apple doesn't know what they're doing. I think you might be right. They may do a maya culpa
and change their mind. I think you're, they really wanted to converge Mac OS and an iOS
and that's maybe becoming hard for them, right? Or they're about to do it. They're getting
windows. Windows has the opposite problem where they're so obsessed with legacy that
they can't like, you know, high DPI up some of the control panel stuff. Linux is doing
too many things at once to really get anything done, right? Which is a problem. Well, it's
got to, you got to figure it must have a super high churn rate compared to other longterm
operating system projects because you've got people that are, you know, contributing while
they work at Intel for a few years and then they go over to Samsung and then you have
people whose passions burnout. I think you're right to summarize it. I would say Mac OS
is suffering from a lack of attention and focus from Apple and proper prioritization.
And so that platform has suffered. Windows suffers from a long legacy of technical debt
and a super deep spaghetti code infrastructure. And honestly, you know, just team bureaucracy
where different things get prioritized different ways and different things are broken out with
different levels of funding. That's windows. And then on Linux, I think what you have is
a bunch of shallow developers who don't go super deep on a lot of stuff. They, a lot
of them want to work on that big, big core foundational problems, but those cause burnout
and they don't solve the last 10% of user polish problems that we constantly run into.
And so each platform has its own particular toxic eroding of its, what should be better
stability, should be better performance, should be more reliable. But these toxic natures
to all of them have, I think, sort of prevented that. And I do feel like long, long, long,
long term, hopefully open source would be better because it can just slowly and slowly
and slowly iterate with, with no need to ever generate revenue. So in theory that would
be best longterm, but we so often reset and we have so much apparent development churn.
I'm not sure if I just want to say like Wayland, right? Like that entire nightmare. Yeah, it's
been basically in the works for 10 years and it's, you know, just now shipping is default
on a couple of distros and Ubuntu is actually rolling it back for their 1804 release. So,
you know, what really, what we really want at the end of the day is we want a nice system
that is almost gotta be top of the line. You might have to pay premium and it just comes
and it works. Like you've, you've tried to now order non max and other systems, even
Dell systems, and they've completely blown up in your face. Like we're not there yet
together. So the hardware side of this is a bit of a shit show too, because the whole
hardware industry has been obsessed with mobile now for eight years, nine years. Well, the
whole hardware side is nobody's making money. Yeah, that's just a problem. So yeah, I don't
know. I mean, you would think that there was a space for a vendor to come in and say, we
have good machines, high quality components and a stable operating system for you to just
get your work done, right? It's just not the case though. Like you're right, windows after
a long, after a couple of months generally becomes a fricking nightmare, right? Running
windows after, you know, six months is really not fun. A bit rot tends to set in and things,
you know, just right. And you, what you really started to notice with windows is like how
many different installers are there? You know, there's so many different install wizards
and some of them still want to install as a system tray app to like check for updates
to the installer. Like that's still a thing on windows, this mishmash of installation
methods and all of it. It's just, there's a real legacy there that it eventually does
catch up to you. I just, I don't know. I, that's why I've been trying to make the plasma
desktop work, to be honest with you, because being able to mix and match my OS, my desktop
environment and my hardware seems to be the only long-term solution. But it, like I said,
I spend a lot of time trying to make that work and it's still not successful, but that's
why I keep spending time every week, at least taking a crack at a segment or a show. Like
right now I'm trying to learn this editor called Reaper, which they don't even want
to admit is available for Linux. They make it available for the Mac and for windows and
they make a Linux build, but you got to go through like this double duck blind, this
system to get a download link. So you can try out a beta version of their editor for
Linux. And it's like, well, how long is this going to stick around? And can I even count
on that? So I feel like in a lot of ways, 2018, we've talked a lot around this issue
and about this issue, but it's, it's getting worse and it's been getting worse since about
2015, I feel like 2014, it's just started getting shittier and shittier. And, and maybe
with this pro work group and this 2019 Mac pro announcement, you're starting to see Apple
turn it around because I'll give them this. I'd rather they delay it and get it right
and then screw it up and do another trashcan. You know, so see, this is my problem though.
I don't think the issue is like, they don't know how to do it. I think it's just like
philosophically not something they want to do is anything they've done before. Basically,
since they've done a tower, they'll never do it again because they've already done it.
Well, it's more that like they see that as a commodity business, right? We're like, if
you can slot in parts off the shelf that, you know, they're not a commodity, they're
more of a luxury, they're more of a brand. And it's not a thing they want to compete.
But like, I'm, I'm, I'm tired of waiting, right? Like, that's why I'm, you know, looking
so closely at pop OS. I'm looking at windows 10 because I just seen an OS to like do its
job, be able to be put on any hardware and get out of my way.
Right? Yeah. I, I don't know. I, I think this particular problem is beginning to change.
I think it's going to start getting a lot better on the Mac side. I really do. I don't
know if it's going to be right for me because I, the hardware just will be out of my league.
But you know, with Mac OS 10.13.4, they now have official eGPU support for external AMD
GPU. So you can hook up a brand new AMD GPU to a MacBook pro. That's a huge deal for professionals.
The fact that the iMac pro does at least address a lot of compute needs. I might not want to
use it and I might be a little hurt that it has a, still has thermal throttling, but it's
overall a very fast machine and it seems to be a good value for $5,000 when you include
the 5k screen. And so that's a good sign. And so this Mac pro, you know, it's a ways
off, but they may bite. They may be in the right direction now. I mean, eGPU pro work
group team, even though I think that's a little weak sauce, iMac pro and now delaying the
Mac pro until they can get it right. All kind of indicate that they're starting to take
this seriously again. Just might be too little too late. Not to even be cliche or quaint
about it, but I think it's just too little too late. And I think that's just the reality
of it is there's going to be other categories of machines now that at different price points
and maybe, you know what, maybe I'm wrong. Maybe in a few weeks, if you're still on Windows
10, you'll think it's great. And then maybe this won't be an issue for you anymore, but
I doubt it. We shall see. The Coder, it's like we're stuck in a Coder radio. Did you
ever see that episode of TNG where they just kept getting in a loop over and over again
because they were crashing into a Frazier's ship and then they just kept right. Yes, yes,
yes, yes. Yeah, that's what's happening to us here. So really quickly, before we leave,
I'm going to point you to an article that you'll find in the show notes at Coder dot
show slash 305. And I think this is really kind of interesting compared to what we keeping
in mind what we talked about last week. And it's an article that is kind of legitimate.
It's the science of breaking out of your comfort zone. Now, I read through this whole thing
and I found a few areas in here that I think are particularly good. And if you're stuck
on an idea or a project right now, this might be exactly what you need. This is something
I have found helps me a lot. And you know, if you if you're if you're really from a recent
failure or a setback and you need to get new fresh perspective, I really encourage that
you go read the science of breaking out of your comfort zone. You know, really, if you
think about it, our brains are engineered to seek out comfort zones because it minimizes
stress. There's patterns and routines that you can recognize. It's it gives you a state
of mental security, but it also can kind of kill new ideas. It prevents you from seeing
the big picture. So the idea of this article is to give you a few tools to potentially
break out so you can maybe be more productive. You'll have potentially an easier time dealing
with new and unexpected changes. I know it all sounds really hippie and fufui, but it
works. And I thought it was sort of a nice sort of conclusion to what we talked about
last week. And it is a lifehacker article. But I think you I think you would find it
useful to take a look. We'll have that over at the show notes. Mr. Dominic, is there anything
else we want to talk about this week before we get the snot out of here? Sounds good.
Follow me at Dumanuco on Twitter. Boom at Dumanuco on Twitter. You can follow the whole
dang network at Jupiter signal. You can follow me. I'm at Chris LAS. And like I said earlier,
we have that new so show website, which means we also have a new show feed. So you can go
to coder.show slash RSS to get that new feed coder.show slash RSS. Or if you just want
easy links, coder.show slash subscribe. We also have the subreddit, you can always participate
in that. And we'd love to get your emails coder.show slash contact. It's a lot of URLs
I'm throwing at your face. But I believe in you. I have faith that you can remember them,
or at least remember one of them. You can also join us live we tend to do this show
on Mondays. And that URL is Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar for the time. Thank you
so much for tuning this week's episode of the coder radio program. I hope you join us
right back here. We do this show every single week. And you can count on at least more insightful
and deep commentary from Jar Jar Binks.