This is KOTOR Radio, episode 486 for October 3rd, 2022.
Hey good buddy, welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show.
Taking a pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
Live from Sacramento, California, my name is Chris and joining us, hopefully from his place intact, it's our host,
Mr. Dominic. Hello Mike.
What's up? I am not dead.
No, the roof remains, eh?
The roof remains. And, sadly, my backyard swimming pool, I don't have a swimming pool, but I did for about two days,
has receded backward from whence it came.
Thank you for all the well wishes. I tried to keep folks updated who were asking, but, you know, I was very lucky.
So, can we talk about the Popo real fast?
Yeah, oh yeah, tell me about it, I'm curious.
I believe that the reason I did not lose power was because I am on the evacuation grid with the Popo in the emergency center.
Oh yeah, I used to live on a hospital grid, that is the best.
They keep that, they don't care, right?
So, it was very, we were very fortunate, a lot of folks down here did, I took a walk this morning, I'm going to post them to Twitter.
There's like a footbridge right outside my house, a tree, two trees actually, literally crushed it.
Wow.
Like big, you know, I don't know what kind of trees, I'm not, you know.
You're not a tree expert, a treeologist.
I'm not an arborist or whatever that is, but literally smashed it, so we got extremely lucky.
It was some intense stuff and, you know, heart goes out to all the folks over in Naples and Fort Myers who really got shellacked.
People worry, you know, because you're our Florida man on the JB Network.
We're a Florida man, I mean, maybe it's time to, I don't know, stop subsidizing crap that destroys the environment.
Just saying, as a guy who just had to deal with this.
Yeah, man.
Oof.
I don't have to deal with those kinds of storms, but I feel like once in my lifetime I'll probably have to deal with a massive earthquake over here on the Pacific Coast one day.
I feel like that's worse.
Yeah, probably.
I think you're probably right.
You know, today is not only is it a special episode because you survived another Florida storm, but it's also episode 486.
Nice.
I'm such a nerd.
I have been waiting for episode 486 forever.
That's the number I keep.
This is your moment.
This is my moment.
And I just wanted to go back in time really briefly and play a 486 commercial that really focused on the upgradability of the Intel 486.
Oh, Lord.
Want to run all your software fast?
Then look for the Intel Inside symbol on your next computer.
It says you got a real power source on the inside.
Like the upgradable Intel 486 microprocessor.
Power it up and run your software at light speed.
Intel, the computer inside.
Yeah, you got to get that 486 goodness, man.
You got to have the 486.
There was also a commercial at the time, and I wanted to play this because it is brilliant for the specs.
Listen to the specs.
This guy rattles off about his fancy new PC he's buying in the early 90s.
It's it's adorable.
I got a Packard Bell 486 SX, 20 megahertz. I got a hard drive with 100 megabytes to make the memory. I got a monitor, it's super VGA and a printer, 24 pin.
I got accessories and software like Windows and Lotus works.
You put it all together just before you're 98.
That's what it's all about.
Yeah, man.
Isn't that something? Super VGA.
I don't know why that one caught me particularly.
100 megabyte hard drive.
That's a lot.
I know.
One day you'll have that in your pocket and one day that'll be what it cost to open CNN.
Yeah, right.
You know, that's why I just I don't know.
486 is such a I remember I think in part that was really when I came into like recognizing there was different processors and computers and that different processors were faster and started to pay attention a lot more during the 40s.
Six era.
And I felt it was kind of appropriate that you found this Aqua EMAX or Aqua Max.
Aqua Max, baby.
It looks like it's from this era, man.
They've updated the copyright on their project as of 2022.
So I think they're still actually actively developing it.
But the thing is like retro.
Yeah. So so when I first started running Mac OS, I was a budding EMAX user and then I was quickly slapped around.
We told the story a couple weeks ago and picked up them.
But this is the EMAX client I used.
And the reason I'll put it in the show notes because I forgot to do that this morning.
But the reason I put it in is there is a pretty passionate hacker news thread of EMAX users.
Just saying, like, we're here and I have to tell you, Chris, I've gotten the DMS.
They are they are here.
We see you.
We love you.
We're not talking about this anymore.
No, no more, unless unless one of them ends or like, you know, like an EMAX contributor shoots a contributor.
Please don't do that or vice versa.
Please don't do that.
It's we get it.
You're there.
Respect. Check out Aqua Max.
I get it. You can live in EMAX.
Check out Aqua Max.
If you're on the Mac, the best part of Aqua Max is it looks like Snow Leopard.
So yeah, it's that classic, classic Mac OS look.
look oh man I sincerely wish we had never mentioned Vim or Emacs on this
show yeah yeah that was a mistake you know what else it was also a mistake to
admit that I was gonna try a new Android ROM but I'm here for it I'm ready for it
Francis writes in and says check out Calyx you should check out Calyx OS or
Calyx I'm not sure how you pronounce it C A L Y X Calyx OS sounds a lot like
Calyx though wait a minute I like this and it's only for pixel devices I
believe it's an alternative to something like main Android or graphene they both
have a similar niche but Calyx or Calyx has a built-in firewall I've been using
I'm very happy and Sasha wrote in and said I recently got a pixel 5 and I
loaded up with Calyx OS and it's been great unlike graphene Calyx OS comes
with micro G which means I can still install Play Store apps via the Aurora
Store app they also use an app called shelter there's been some paper cuts but
so far they like it a lot and it's still a Google phone to some degree but it's a
better compromise I of course put on graphene OS on my pixel device recently
so now that I've put on graphene OS I'm hearing from everybody that I should be
using Calyx OS which is exactly what happened back in the day when I used to
put ROMs on my old Android devices I would do it and then immediately be told
by everybody that I use the wrong ROM when I should try out this totally
different ROM and it feels like I'm right back in that again however I do
feel like perhaps what it is is that graphene OS skews more towards the
privacy conscious and I think there's a spectrum here and I think the Calyx
folks are maybe more traditionally lineage type lineage type folks that
they want to they want a lot of the functionality of their smartphone they
just want to be a little bit more removed from Google where graphene OS
has taken some plumbing improvements like they're using se Linux to sandbox
Google Play and the Google Play services so you can actually install Google Play
services in the Google Play Store on graphene OS run them in a sandbox that
prevents access outside of that sandbox where on Calyx or Calyx or however you
say it they're using micro G which is a port it's a re-implementation of the
play API and it's partially open source I believe and there is a aspect of it
that runs highly privileged in the system app domain like the regular play
services whereas with graphene OS everything is sandboxed and they're
running they play services at a lower privilege level that is enforced by se
Linux so that's my big understanding of the two but there is a whole underbelly
here I scratched accidentally there's a lot of people out there that are getting
pixel devices and then they're free flashing them which is just not what you
expect right you think that's what people buy other devices for but they're
getting the flagship device and they're reflashing it well kind of makes sense
right there's no carry or nonsense on the pixel if you buy it from Google I
think mmm right well if you flash it doesn't even matter you wipe it out
anyway so yeah okay yeah I guess I could see that right it's probably one of the
easier devices at this point because used to have manufacturers that would
make devices for that community and they've kind of backed off from that
hmm and they're decent phones so you're gonna stick with it I think I'll use
graphene for a while I've been pretty happy now that I got the play services
on there and you need the play store if any app has an in-app purchase basically
you know so that's where I got hung up I had an I had I wanted to put photo sync
on there and to get access to the cloud services I I needed to pay for it and so
I was like that started a whole process and then if you have an eSIM you need
the play services to activate the eSIM to really basically hooked it into
everything oh yeah so that's okay you know we've kind of dropped the Android
play services thread but I remember years ago we used to talk about how oh
no they're putting more stuff in play services so now it's like you want to
activate your SIM gotta have those play services yeah yeah okay yep and eSIMs
are really taken off now yep so I'm not a huge fan of that I I think graphene OS
is a little more secure too in the way it launches processes so overall it's
like if you're trying to get away from Google it seems like that's the way to
go to me and I'm I think I'm missing something because Calix obviously has a
lot of people that like it and I know the founder has a little bit of a
celebrity around him for Calix and I think that might be playing a factor as
well but I can't quite tell I'm such a noob to all of this that I'm kind of
discovering it as I dive in and then people tell me oh but did you try which
is exactly what happens on Linux you know try a boon to all you better get
Zeus tell me about it so so I have two side tangents here because that's why we
waste our time running show notes one did you see you probably didn't cuz
you're on the road that very quietly very sneakily Apple announced that they
can no longer activate the data plan and you can no longer hotspot just through
the iPad settings app on iPads oh no that was like a great feature you got to
go talk to those carriers but that was great I used to use it so this is like
you know back do you remember the old days Chris when you could travel freely
stay a while and listen all levels of Tristam yeah I used to take an iPad
because no matter what I could have connectivity and if at the time I was a
t-mobile customer and you know they were t-mobile I know they're better now but
if they suck I would just do the one month like $30 Verizon thing and be
like whatever I'll do Verizon while I'm in usually like Colorado or North
Carolina somewhere like that and you could do it all from the settings app
inside that just right there right so even if my phone which had t-mobile
service was crappy well I had this Verizon connection in a pinch if I had
the tether or whatever and I never had to talk to a sales rep this was the key
right I get locked into some other plan those were the days yeah that was nice
I'm sure it must have been carrier pressure over time to get rid of that
yeah they feel like the carriers hated that it's funny how those things quietly
happen because you're right I had not seen that yeah turds yeah try to sneak
it in that's probably all my thoughts on graph you know it's because I'm still so
new I'm still trying to learn so do let me know I mean it's getting to be a bit
much but I would like to know your thoughts on what I brought up today
coder dot show slash contact or you can boost it in but then just a little PSA
our last meetup on this West Coast tour is happening the Friday that this
episode goes out so coming up on the 6th of October in Portland we have our last
meetup meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting and I'm heading home kind
of sad but also relieved from a technical standpoint this road trip has
been very hard probably hard enough that this is the last road trip like this I'm
ever gonna do so this is the end of an era in some ways and the last meetup of
that era I'm gonna come up with something else but I think I'm done
doing this format I mean you know what I thought this is gonna be the one Mike I
thought this would be road trip by the numbers because listener Jeff has been
an MVP of this road trip he set us up with a great parking spot at his place
in Sacramento with power and most importantly of course it's secure and it
could be locked up why we went down to Pasadena and internet he gave us Ethernet
so I thought geez this is gonna be we're gonna we're gonna be we're gonna be
stationary I'm gonna have Ethernet connectivity I'm gonna have power
hookups what could go wrong right instead I had multiple devices fail in
the studio that I rely on and then I had a software update here in the RV that
happened in the background and changed the functionality of one of my
applications so you can no longer select the input and output for audio devices
which was a fundamental feature that I used and then of course we had routing
problems and all it just has been it has been a nightmare an absolute nightmare
so I think this is the last one I'm gonna do and I'll come up with a new
I'll come up with a new way to get out and see folks in the future so meetup
comm slash Jupiter broadcasting for the last meetup on the West Coast Road tour
and probably the last meetup of this type of trip I think that's just
probably the way it's got to go just the way it is as they say and that West
Coast room will continue the West Coast crew at on our matrix server at bit.ly
slash West Coast crew that'll remain and as we figure out future events and stuff
like that we'll let people in the area know in there so check that out too well
we all saw this one coming but I think it still is worth mentioning and
analyzing a little bit Google has announced that they'll be winding down
stadia in January 2023 and TechCrunch wrote a piece and I completely agree
that says stadia died because no one trusts Google they say it's that simple
it's a kind of like the writing was on the wall when stadia launched Google has
exhibited such a poor understanding of what people want they write what they
need and will pay for at this point that people are wary of investing even its
more popular products I think you probably agree with that I don't
actually I mean I I do agree you shouldn't trust Google but I think there
are just two fundamental flaws kind of higher level have you seen the state of
high-speed internet in the u.s. yeah like this is not a stadia specific
problem but until you know the dragon that is Comcast and all the other ISPs
are somehow forced to be dumb pipes where this is all you know made into a
utility a la municipal bit of fire was effectively right fiber optics I don't
think folks outside the u.s. particularly folks who have better
internet like South Korea and much of Europe can really understand just how
the situation is here I'm pretty lucky that I live in a place where for some
insane reason Verizon used to be here and laid a fiber optic line and now some
company called frontier is happy to sell it to me but they're not making more
we've talked about it before but this is a huge problem right the city of New
York paid Verizon and I'm not just picking on Verizon but they're easy
target to fiber up all of New York City and Verizon just like didn't do it right
it just turned out that it's too hard too much money and there's lots of
arguments about regulations and why does it cost you know to build a mile of road
in the u.s. is like five times what it costs anywhere else and the answer is
because you can sue anyone for any reason and that's probably bad regardless
of why the fact is the we still have internet caps in a lot of places many
places have just one provider who gives you the crappiest service possible and
that's just a challenge for streaming gaming the other thing I think is kind
of I guess maybe misguided here is the problem if you're a VP at Google is you
need to make an impact on the scale of Adsense and search and YouTube it might
probably just wasn't worth it right these guys are careerists these are
business guys they're not you know they're not like super into the tech
side of things maybe we can take a flashback in time when I was a kid I got
the Sega Channel and I don't are you familiar with this at all Chris is it a
channel no no I don't think I am this is an ancient precursor to this game
streaming stuff that was run over coax it was a partnership between Sega of
America and I think Cox cable okay and it was literally this idea you put this
thing in your Genesis they ran a coax line and you could play a wide library
of Sega games because at the time Sega would just pitch the publishers a little
bit of money and they're like yeah sure we'll let you do this because nobody had
it it worked fine because they were 16-bit games Wow this is back in 94 I'd
never even heard of this yeah this was in the in the mid 90s things have
changed quite a bit right and the reason I didn't have it for very long is
because they canceled it they canceled it meaning Sega and and whatever thing I
think it was Cox it was Cox or cable vision at the time I can't remember but
this idea is one not new and it always hits the same problem of the ISPs do not
want to give you the bandwidth you need because they simply don't have to right
in his bandwidth paying performance all that stuff reliability a lot of folks
down here are realizing after Ian that oh it turns out if there's only one ISP
in the neighborhood they're kind of not you know paying over time and double
timing it to get you back connected right right which is you know this is
I'll put on my little commie hat which my inner my inner elephant will die a
little bit but if something is essential it's not a product it's a utility right
this this is probably just a utility and if you look at some other countries the
reason they don't have this set of problems is because they treat
connectivity and my mind correctly as either a pure utility or a pseudo
utility yeah we definitely seem like we've crossed that threshold yeah oh I
mean kids were going through school over the internet right that that should have
been just like it that's the line it's over there's this should not be a
for-profit or utilities are technically for-profit but you know it regulated
best service minimal price industry what that said you solve the problem of it
was never gonna be big enough for the VP that ran this or whatever the guy's
title is to actually care right if you're at Google and you want to advance
you need to be in you know Adsense search YouTube right maybe if you're
lucky you can use this to parlay your way into a more influential position
right God it's horrible but you're probably right I think too on top of
that so there's the aspect of just really poor internet connectivity in the
states which is the primary market for this thing but additionally you have on
the flip side maybe folks that are living in the cities or living where
connectivity is is really quite good maybe they have gigabit things like that
well then they're probably more in a position to buy a gaming console or to
build a gaming PC right so then where you have perhaps really great
connectivity you kind of have this issue where they already have the gear they
want they've already bought their games on Steam or from Nintendo and so they're
not really the ideal customer either so there's just this middle customer that
is I think like what you're saying a pretty small niche here well also from
let's just assume you have the connectivity like you're saying like I
was a stadia customer but it never made sense you you have to stream it plus by
the game you could buy for two hundred and something dollars I mean 300 bucks
whatever it is an Xbox s and then 10 bucks a month you get Xbox Game Pass 15
you get Game Pass Ultimate and not only did it work better that was it you just
it was like Netflix for gaming right yeah that I think was a killer too for
stadia was just having to pay 60 bucks for a game for a service you knew
inevitably was gonna die but now speaking to that though Google has kind
of done the right thing here and they've offered full refunds on the stadia
hardware if anybody bought the controller or the chromecast ultra and
games they bought which I did yeah I'm happy yeah I mean I guess why it's not a
big controversy right now it's also well you should have seen Twitter it's also
quite the admission that yeah we were just shooting this you know back of the
shed yeah you have a link to on live in here and that's the name that's the name
young Luke I haven't heard and I mean I've wanted this for a long time we've
all wanted this yeah I was an online user back in like 2012 when they were
you know I think it was like 2010 2011 somewhere in there they launched the
beta and I got in on that oh man and I even liked that I have always wanted
this as a Linux user who wants access to more games I've wanted this because this
seemed like a viable solution and then when stadia came along and they're like
we're gonna stream you games but you got a portrait games to Linux and Vulcan I
thought well maybe the weight of Google and the popularity if they integrate it
with something like YouTube or if they could integrate it with some of their
more popular products it was one-click link and now you're in stadium you're
gaming you don't have to buy anything that would have taken off like wildfire
I thought but they didn't go that way and they didn't inevitably convince very
many developers to port their games to Linux or Vulcan and then at the same
time valve came along with proton and an improved gaming experience on Linux and
then the deck and it just sort of made stadia seem pointless the only thing
funny about it Mike is that even just two months ago stadia's Twitter account
was assuring people that were tweeting them that they were in fact not shutting
down no worries there they said international corporations never lie
yeah I guess they were so cocky when they launched it Google just had the
Dreamcast and the Sega Saturn and those consoles like on display at the Google
campus as like consoles are really dead now they're never coming back after this
you won't believe what we're about to announce and they have these glass
displays of these failed consoles on their front lawn where they usually have
the Android statues in in anticipation of the launch before they made their
announcement I just want to say as a Sega fan like lifelong Sega fan if
you're copying Sega's console business strategy you're you've made a horrible
mistake in fact when they picked up that Dreamcast and that Saturn they should
have said wait a minute this seems bad why are we doing this because the
Dreamcast came out with this Sega started this with the Sega Channel on
the Genesis we're gonna pretend the 32x doesn't exist because it you know nobody
bought it it was me and two other guys the Dreamcast was the first online
gaming network that was a console it plugged into your 56k modem it was a
partnership with it was epics internet or earth link I can't remember but
somebody can fact-check me and it failed for basically the same reasons like
saying has been trying to do this since 94 trust me I was there I was working my
teenage job to get a damn Dreamcast I'm so sad right now never mind so the Wall
Street Journal written by Christopher Mims over there has a piece called the
next battle between Google and Apple is for the soul of your car and actually
makes a pretty good case that this is heating up essentially Tesla and some
other mobile car creators are basically mobile phone makers now but other car
creators have really upped their game on the infotainment and so it is now the
number one requested feature when customers go to buy a new car if you
can believe it is Apple CarPlay or Google Android auto support and the
infotainment system is now the number one source of consumer complaints about
new car issues is the crappy infotainment systems and so you have this
situation where the car manufacturers are feeling more and more pressure to
let Google and Apple in to solve this problem for them and of course Google's
solution involves Android automotive which is which is more extensive than
Android auto same similar name I read real similar name very dumb but Android
automotive is a full car OS that takes over everything and Google has announced
partnerships with a dozen automakers including Honda BMW Nissan General Motors
the Chevy brands and Apple has announced a dozen launch partners for their next
generation of CarPlay which isn't a whole OS but is an expanded version of
CarPlay that likely depends that on car manufacturers meeting certain
requirements and those include Volvo Ford Honda Mercedes Porsche and others
and we got a little tease of Apple's whole scheme at WWDC where they showed
that CarPlay software taking over the entire instrument cluster from the over
the entire dash with your gas gauge or your charge gauge and your RPMs and your
speed all of that gets taken over by CarPlay now but they haven't yet
announced a dedicated OS and it would seem kind of out of character for Apple
to actually license an OS yeah that's just not really their style it's more
like the manufacturer will have to build to a spec and then Apple will sell them
the OS yeah sit down kill Emilio no one's asking you yeah this is like a
whole new OS war that is brewing and what scares me about it is that people
making the decisions historically are horrible at software they do suck it's
true where does this take us when you have companies that are building devices
that can kill us that are essential and have a horrible history at software and
UI and now they have to try to bridge this gap and in some cases like Volvo
and others they're gonna have their own OS as well so you have Volvo car dot OS
which will be running Android automotive in an emulator great and so you and then
you also have like the ECM and you have the other car computer modules that are
also separate but maybe has Volvo software on it that ties it together
follow us that then like runs I guess an API set that Android automotive can talk
to but the whole thing like it sounds horrible it sounds like it sounds like a
massively complicated software stack in a car and that sounds dangerous to me
and I'm wondering if you feel the same way if you feel opposite if you have any
thoughts on this I mean I'm not sure that we need this but you know I drive a
Chevy let me tell you what happens I look at the non-digital gauges and I'm
very happy with that I plug in my iPhone and it does the carplay thing on the you
know the dash I will tell you when I don't look into my iPhone whatever
horrible operating system Chevrolet has or GM has put on that it's crap oh so
bad it's so bad it get like even things like tuning FM radio stations were
easier on my old Chevy that did not have any of this crap right that was just
like it was knobs remember knobs knobs were great mm-hmm
we had a real-world problem in in my house of I have so much Apple stuff that
we're basically incentivized to always buy the Apple accessory for something
or the Apple compatible accessory right ecosystem so is your car gonna be one of
these things now to where it's like well I have an Apple watch and and I have an
iPhone and I could see like Apple's going into this car crash detection will
it work better if you have an Apple OS powered car I would I would imagine so
right hmm I hadn't even thought of the fact that safety features like that
could be a thing yeah you're right what if I run a car that's running Android OS
but you know I just rent which I used to do all the time before kovat right in a
strange city rent a car right now the situation is most modernist cars that I
rent I can plug in my iPhone and I have my familiar interface my maps save
destinations all that if I do that in a car running Android OS there's Google
gonna make a deal with the manufacturer to not allow carplay on that car right
to somehow block that screen right I don't know I feel like if you wanted to
innovate somewhere with vehicles this is me I see why they want to do it because
it's more of like a luxury thing that they can charge for but how about full
electrification right I know that's hard but life is hard you can do it and don't
worry if you're GM if you fail the government will just like make let you
do some weird crazy bankruptcy that nobody else gets to do so there's that
right of course and if you're Ford you'll realize that the government's
gonna punish you and you'll somehow not file bankruptcy right I'm just saying I
don't know they have little downside risk they can they can kind of afford to
screw around with this a little bit but I feel like their failure to do a good
job here has created a market opportunity for Google and Apple no it
also is gonna screw over local mechanics but this is yet another thing totally
proprietary totally computerized I was thinking about it to it and I don't
know maybe there's just no getting around this but you know I just got done
putting graphene OS on my pixel as an effort to see what's the downside of
moving away from Google services and trying to replace them with my own
things like next cloud and graphene OS and it'd just be kind of funny to kind
of go through this multi-year process of de googling just to end up buying a car
that forces me to use a Google OS that would really suck and then I realized
it's a very first world problem but it's gonna be a problem like I'm gonna I'm
actively trying to send this company less of my information and then the
auto manufacturer comes along and just sells me a $70,000 car or whatever with
Google stuff built in I just don't know about that you're right I like the idea
that's on a removable upgradable device my phone gets upgraded very frequently
my car does not and I've always preferred to have the computing in a
little separate module I doesn't need to be wireless it doesn't need to be that
fancy I don't mind plugging it in to let it charge to let it have fast
connectivity and then like you said all of my saved data that I want to use
comes up on the screen and that works just fine I also think it's a little
alarming as we just build in more and more layers of complexity that we're not
really requiring these companies to I don't know prove that they can build
these things first like they just ship it and my wife has a 2013 I think Ford
Focus and the sync software on the 2013 Ford Focus feels like alpha crap it is
busted by design it is horrible I've talked to other focus owners they hate
it and it got better in later years but it took them years and years and years
of iterating before it got very usable and it's not like they issue updates to
the old cars so my wife's driving around with what is basically she was a beta
tester for Microsoft sync and you know that car is it's a frustrating car
because of sync it's such a silly thing to have like the motor works fine
everything mechanically about the car is fine but sync drives us crazy every day
yeah I cannot tell you how desperate my chef is to get me to subscribe to on
star it's just bad I mean there's are all just horrible horrible systems and
there's a reason everybody goes in and plugs in their iPhone or their pixel or
whatever let me flip it around on you though so what if this happens let's
just take it down the road a bit too when we work so we work some of this out
because you know like some automakers they're not even they're opting to go
their own route entirely like a few of them are gonna be integrating the Amazon
echo stuff into the car which that just sounds horrible
great I hate voice commands in the car so much but let's just say we get down
the road this stuff gets sorted out and we land on a Google Apple future in my
opinion Google loses this because ultimately this kind of product lives
and dies on the consumer feedback and preferences and if this sync system
that's in my wife's car somehow like big had become like some sort of standard
there was on a dozen different car manufacturers systems they would have
suffered in sales I mean there's a reason why sync never took off Microsoft
tried this like if they always do Microsoft was early they tried this they
tried to get other manufacturers to use sync but the problem was is Ford's
customers hate it and it hurt sales it cost them money so I think long term
this isn't gonna work out for Google because they can't even they can't even
properly name the products they have Android auto and Android automotive as
we've just described with stadia they can't stick with anything and the
reality is the car markets big but it doesn't have the scale of the web not
even close only a small part of the market especially these days will be
able to afford new cars it'll have this tech built in so it's always going to be
a small niche product and that spells doom for Google Apple I think it's a
little bit more of the roll of dice Apple can live and survive in niche land
because they design their profits and the way they organize their deals to
make money that way juicy margins exactly you got it you got to have them juicy
margins right after all it's business business no one Apple they'll do the
thing they always do all our stuff is great but this is the good and that
one's kind of you know whatever they'll leave the old plug in your iPhone and
get crappy carplay or what is current carplay and then they'll do the whatever
car OS thing and that'll be are you buying a Mercedes my friends right
that's I mean it's Apple and also if you're Mercedes you have a BMW it's
probably BMW let's be honest you probably want to partner with Apple
because a lot of your values in your brand and your whatever like lifestyle
feeling and you know I'm at least in the US I can't I don't can't speak for the
regions but it's pretty clear that Apple is the luxury brand here totally I that
was absolutely well put this the brand Association they'll you know the car
manufacturer wants to get a little bit of that shine because Apple's like in
the top three brands of the world or something like that so they're gonna
want that shine they you know that's just how companies work but I also think
like we have the flip problem of it's one thing when Google is building
products and services for the web and they shut that down okay you know that
stinks but it's a web service will be fine but what about your 60 70 thousand
dollar car when they just kind of give up on that what are you gonna you can't
reflash it you can't put a new ROM on your car you're just stuck with
abandoned software okay so don't yeah I mean you you've just made a very strong
case to not buy a car powered by Android OS so I do think there is a little bit
of that brand factor that the stadia factor where I think everybody when
stadia was announced the first thing everybody did was wait for Google to
kill it and they I think that does affect them as a brand I think it
because it impacts the way I view this effort to hmm I mean there's really no
way for them to fix that right no they've they've it's they've done it
they've become known as the company who kills stuff I mean there's killed by
google.com right and and to be fair they're the company who they're they're
standard for big enough for us to care to keep it alive it's just stupidly high
right when you were the default search engine the default advertising network
for the entire internet you're just in a different you know you're thinking on a
galactic scale not a not a county scale right
god bless duck duck go who knows I mean I accidentally used Bing this morning in
edge it was terrible right so yeah I don't know what to say yeah ask not
what your podcast can boost for you but what you can boost for your podcast DPG
boosts in with 2,000 sats and he says I'm boosting him to say that my upgrade
from an 11 Pro Max to a 14 Pro Max has been absolutely amazing waiting three
years seems to be the sweet spot for iPhones good luck on the road trip Chris
I hope to do a cross-country one someday and meet my wonderful internet friends
out west well that'd be amazing DPG 11 to 14 does seem like the sweet spot
that's got to be a great upgrade that's a big jump that's probably the strategy
if I wasn't on the upgrade program and that's kind of the cycle that my wife
has been on I think she's on an 11 right now and I don't know if I'm gonna get a
14 for her I mean that would be a decent Christmas present but I definitely think
she'll want the 15 just for battery life reasons and whatnot I love that you know
that's the thing about these iPhones there's always people out there that are
always gonna be upgrading so Apple might not see unbelievable numbers I don't
know if we've gotten any hints yet but there's always customers there's always
gonna be customers they'll be all right yeah I think so Dave Jones the pod sage
boosted with 2011 12 sats he writes I'm boosting the intro because I have faith
you guys are gonna deliver it boosted during the intro Dave he also double
boosted in with another two thousand one hundred and twelve sats
and he's calling me up he says barbecue in California blows it's like ordering
spaghetti and meatballs at Subway come down south and we'll get you guys taken
care of I'd love to take you up on that Dave I would love that Dave I'm already
down south I know what do you what is the is there a big barbecue culture in
Florida is there the pride about barbecue like there is in Texas and the
there it well it's not quite like Texas yeah yeah it's not quite like Texas so
the trick about Florida is the more generally speaking the more north you go
in Florida the more southern it is wait a minute the more north you go the more
southern is because you're getting closer to the southern states right
because a lot of like southern Florida like for instance go to Miami let's like
it's like Cuban food which is awesome oh yeah oh my god Cuban food this and like
I thought I'd had a Cuban sandwich and then I moved here and I had never had
one before until that day I gotta come to Florida I've been there for like two
minutes I gotta get down there it's see the problem of Florida too is it's weird
man like I'm just saying it's a lot of stuff going on down here and there's a
whole Disney area that gets real creepy like it's sounds like a party down there
except for the storms you know but it's otherwise it just sounds like a hot mess
of parties well I know I just got a flyer from DeSantis it is now officially
known as the free state of Florida whatever the hell that means really did
they make an official like proclamation I just wanna say this is laminated like
I don't know how rich his campaign is because he's running for governor again
I have gotten lots of political crap never laminated though never like this
like I'm a dude I kind of want to hang this up except they don't because I
don't know what free state means because that sounds a lot like like Chaz
doesn't sound good right it sounds like sounds like we're gonna need a SWAT team
in here to just like clean it up and we're all gonna realize that what looked
like a protest was really never mind we're gonna move on all right yeah I
know Johnny Johnny yeah with a 2500 sats says I'm considering upgrading my
$4,000 MacBook Pro to a $1,000 dev one thanks guys you know John I think you
can muddle through I I know it's gonna be tough but it's a tough problem it's
rough but somebody's got to do it and why not both I say why not both you know
true although with that said I got my last Mac hold out to finally I thought I
had him a month ago but to finally switch to Linux today oh yeah oh cuz
Xcode update broke his his Unix binaries that kind of stuff that's what it takes
right for a dev stack yep mm-hmm non-standard locations on Mac
pag dot boosts in with 1701 sets which is a Star Trek boost live long and
prosper says thanks for all the great shows by never watching Star Trek I did
a great sin and I have to ask for forgiveness to fix this going forward
I'd like to know which season you recommend to start with would you
recommend the old og1 or a new one like strange new worlds I'm looking forward
to your answer really enjoy the shows thanks for a fellow mid from office
hours okay oh I see from the right for inspiration for the boost amount for the
enterprise right right mmm nice oh god I have to tell you I literally live in
fear of this question on a daily basis I constantly think what if somebody asked
me where to start with Star Trek and I obsess over this question because it's
it's probably one of the most important questions a person will ever ask you I'm
dying to know what you think I don't think we're gonna agree I don't know I
think a couple of days ago my answer would have been different but while we
were down in Pasadena for the JPL tour we stayed at an Airbnb for a few days
and the most incredible thing happened it was perfect I swear to God I swear to
God this is what happened I walk in the first thing I did at the Airbnb is like
because you walk in the living room I turned the TV on there's a big TV Star
Trek the next generation comes up and it's encounter at Farpoint episode 1 and
then it's like a 35 year anniversary thing so it turns out they're playing
every single episode in chronological order and we showed up right as
encounter at Farpoint starts we left the TV on the entire time we were there we
made it all the way into season 4 Cupid which is episode 94 in the production
run we made it all the way through like best of both worlds you know like the
good stuff and I have to say man mm-hmm Star Trek the next generation gets so
damn good around season 3 and then just continues to deliver until the end of
the series basically I can't believe this we're gonna agree I cannot believe
this really is this what your recommendation was I could have sworn
you were gonna say oh gee you have to do it in order I don't know I don't know I
think you I think you got to learn to love Star Trek and then go back and
watch the original series I feel like the problem and with og Star Trek is
it's great after you watch TNG especially for more modern particularly
younger audiences you know even I think people in our age bracket roughly might
find some of the stuff in that a little interesting yeah I I think the first
couple seasons of TNG are very much toss inspired they're like the original
series and yeah a lot of people don't like the first couple of seasons yeah I
mean I do think it's either og or original series the problem with with
strange new worlds is you have to have seen the original series to really
understand what the hell is going on I feel like right because it's playing off
the original series I think you get a lot richer experience you definitely get
a richer experience I think you could watch it in isolation if the production
and pacing of older Star Trek like the next generation I say older but you know
it's from the 80s and and deep space 9 if the pacing which I find to be perfect
but if you find it a little slow I think strange new worlds would be like my
backup plan right start with the next generation and if it's just not sticking
then I'd probably try strange new worlds because maybe you just like that style a
little bit more then you start to build an appreciation for the universe and
then you can kind of pick up the other ones ooh but DS 9 though yeah wait a minute
no no I think you could see I don't think you can do discovery because it's
too different from the other ones deep space 9 holds up because it was it was
early into that ongoing narrative storytelling and so I think it it holds
up in binge watching I'd say it's TNG or DS 9 yeah I agree I agree let us know
how it goes and if you feel differently if you've got a better suggestion I've
even thought about like breaking it down to a list of episodes that cross all the
different Star Trek's so you know you a couple of key moments from TNG deep
speech would be deep space 9 Voyager toss you know in Enterprise and you throw
them all on the board and you make a big list this is an important question so
boost in your answers if you've got a better one because somebody will ask
again and I want to do them right our last boost this week came in from
nano bills that's how I'm saying it he boosted him with 50 sats and he said if
you need to use flat packed VS code to reach your whole system you can use flat
seal to allow that and I wanted to mention that because we've brought up VS
code and flat pack a couple of times on Linux and how it's limited to the file
system there is an app that you can install as a flat pack called flat seal
one word and that gives you a GUI to manage all of the permissions on your
flat pack apps on your Linux desktop and you can go in there and say I want to
allow access to the file system I want to allow access to the camera or you
know whatever it might be so check out flat seal it makes all of that a lot
simpler to manage thank you to nan to tubes bills for boosting that in I'm
sorry that I butchered your name I'm not trying I swear that's just how I am and
then also a couple of quick thankies mr. quackers boosted in a row of ducks
quacka walka it's a treasure Sean of the dev 512 sats want to give
him the shout out and thank you everybody else who's either streaming or
send some sats in that or sent a boost in that I didn't read on the show we're
just picking some of them to try to keep the segment a little tighter but we do
read all of them if you'd like to boost us go get a new podcast app a new
podcast apps comm I have been rocking pod verse for about a month now GPL it's
available on all platforms including the web and I know out there fountain is
super popular as well it's got a great clipping system you can earn some sats
while you listen I'll put a link to that in the show notes as well mr. Dominic is
there anywhere you want to send the good people this week well I'm gonna try
again I didn't get it done last week but I'd like to send you to add to my new
go on Twitter and Dominic em comm I should have something new up there soon
ooh well you do have the recent Thalia review up there too so I do you did get
that out so to give yourself some credit you know I liked the review all right
well that's pretty much all I'll plug them I think we could mention we have
the contact form emails are a big part of the show and they are down now
because we've been on the road and we've read through our backlog so go to coder
dot show slash contact and send in topic ideas questions you have for us
corrections suggestions things that you think we'd like to talk about coder dot
show slash contact all of that's over there and coder QA dot co is where you
go to become a member of the show you get the coderly report oh it's a new
quarter it's a new quarter for the quarter quarter coder I'll get it right
one of these days and we'll be recording that fairly soon I suppose once I get
back you and I can get that schedule we get a coderly out for our members we do
that once a quarter yeah let's do it and it's just a great way to support the
show you get an ad free feed as a thank you as well
coder QA dot co or all the JB shows at Jupiter dot party the podcast here on
the Twitter's is at coder radio show and of course everything we talked about
today links stuff like the RSS feed links to our sponsors any that kind of
stuff coder dot show slash 486 that's where you'll also find our RSS feed and
of course links to our matrix chat so you can join us and chat with us
throughout the week doesn't just have to be on Mondays when we're live over
Jupiter tube at 9 a.m. Pacific noon Eastern but you're welcome to join us
then as well we love having you join us live thanks so much for tuning in this
week's episode of the coder radio program and we'll see you right back
here next week