This is Coda Radio, episode 443 for December 6th, 2021.
Hello friends and welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
My name is Chris and joining us every single week like the podcast soldier that he is,
our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello.
You kind of just sliding right into the show today.
I hadn't heard from you this morning.
I thought, oh, he must be either a in a meeting or be deep into something.
I looked over and you were there.
You were there.
I was like, oh, he's here.
You know, it's just been running from thing to thing.
Well, let's take a moment, you know, and we'll spend some time together.
We'll just pretend like now that's going on.
That's what I like to do.
I like to just black it all out.
And I noticed to kind of kick things off that you have finally gotten your hands and I don't
know if we've ever talked about the warp terminal on the show before.
I feel like we might have mentioned it once before, but it's a rust based terminal that
supposedly going to be on multiple platforms, but is out for the Mac now.
You got in on it and I just kind of want to know what you think, because I've heard people
talking about it.
And is there really I guess there is room on the Mac in particular for a better terminal,
isn't there?
Something we've complained about before on the show.
Oh, yeah.
I mean, I will say this warp terminal I'm using it as my daily driver for now.
It is a lot prettier than terminal dot app.
And it's just lightning fast.
And it's got that command palette sort of like V.S. code, but looks better.
Yes.
And it's got a bunch of built in stuff.
If you use GitHub or some other continuous integration stuff, I kind of only cracked
the surface of it because it's only been about a week.
But I am loving it so far and I'm hopefully going to learn more about some of the more
advanced features.
The number one feature that you love and that I love is that it's written in Rust.
I don't know why that matters, really, when you're using it.
It doesn't, but we should Rust all the things.
I wanted to mention because I got in trouble last year that I didn't say on the show and
I almost did it again this year, that the Tuxy votes are open right now.
This is a thing we're doing in Linux Unplugged.
It's not a coder thing, but I specifically got yelled at for not mentioning it here,
because it's an opportunity for you to vote on the best open source projects and distros
of the year.
People wanted to get their vote in.
So you go to tuxys.party, it's tuxys.party, and you go in there and you vote for your
favorite distros and projects and text editors and all that stuff.
Then towards the very end of the year on Linux Unplugged, we announce who the winners are
and give out awards and they get entered into a hall of fame and all of that kind of stuff.
It's a good time and the CoderRadio audience deserves their vote, so tuxys.party is where
you go get that.
And I'm sorry I didn't mention it last year.
So you made your position pretty clear on the Web3 stuff, so when we got this email
from Sonya into the show, it was pretty clear that Sonya doesn't actually listen.
And I should say, we get a lot of pitches for interviews on this show, and a lot of
them are bad pitches.
Yeah, a little inside baseball.
Doing interviews on the air is kind of a huge pain in the butt.
You've done a lot of them for the Mike Dominic show, so you know what a pain it is.
And then there's a huge market in PR firms that try to book people to go on shows to
promote their stuff.
You tell me about it.
So Sonya wrote in.
She's a PR manager at Decentology.
It's an innovative company behind the Hyperverse, Mike, which is an open, composable, smart
contracts marketplace that makes it easy for developers to discover, build, and monetize
Web3 applications.
What the hell does that mean?
She thought, well, she'd contact us so that way we could talk about it a little bit, because
you see, their mission is to onboard the next 10 million developers to Web3.
So they're willing to provide equal opportunities and knowledge to anyone interested in entering
the field.
They're going to have a hackathon initiative, which they call the HyperHack.
She actually says this on here.
Even Web2 developers will be welcome.
She wanted to reach out there on the show, and she loves it.
She loves the show.
She loves our stance on Web3, and she wants to promote her Web3 company.
I don't think Sonya listens, Mike.
I don't know why this one tickled me, because we get so many variations of this.
Yeah, I didn't even see this one.
I must have, my Darth Maul filter must have just been like, no, sorry.
All right.
So listener Michael wrote in, and he did kind of have a pragmatic take on the crypto blockchain
hype.
And he writes, as a daily pragmatist, I do get annoyed with the next big thinkers spouting
new ideas that will revolutionize all the things.
But it doesn't mean they're necessarily wrong about all the things.
We have to push the boundaries and discover new possibilities.
Now 99 out of 100 times, they're going to fall flat.
But that one out of 100 times, we get transformative things like modern web app frameworks, NFC,
Bluetooth.
Sometimes it's actually hard to see in the moment the bull versus the real actual value.
But patience is the key.
The media hype clickbait machine incentivizes grifters, and that's a sad state.
But you just have to ignore them.
Society has always had this problem.
The snake oil salesman of the 1890s or the tube speculation crash of 1637.
Capitalism can incentivize innovation, but leaves the door cracked to grifters looking
to scam a quick buck.
My job is to look through the hype and see what actionable kernels of value I can leverage.
A good example, he says, blockchain as a technology is being used to power technology used by
title companies, a public record of ownership and title transfer for the state's large assets
and real estate.
Similarly, the import export documents for some international shipping companies are
now seeing similar applications using the blockchain.
That seems like a pretty reasonable take on actual value coming out of this.
That seems a pretty reasonable use case, right?
Like I don't think we've ever said the blockchain as a technology or concept was bad.
I think what's bad is doing things you can already do and slapping the hashtag web three
on it.
And claiming that you're going to topple the tech giants that own the market now is just
a little bit of a fool's errand.
I mean, we'd love to see it, but not going to happen.
Never.
We warned you about that about 10 years ago.
I'm wondering, though, you think maybe the mad botter might consider getting paid in
Miami coin?
Have you seen this?
This is near your neck of the woods.
Isn't that just cocaine?
I mean, I've been to Miami.
I'm pretty sure it's cocaine.
You are quick sometimes.
I have to say.
No, this is a real thing.
It's been around for about four months now or so, five months, maybe more.
Miami has launched the Miami coin.
It's worth about 30 million dollars right now.
You mine it and then you keep 70 percent of the revenue.
Give the rest to the city.
The city uses that to pay for certain city initiatives.
And Austin wants to have an Austin coin.
New York is thinking about having a New York coin.
Think about this.
And for listeners out there, think about this for a moment.
How does this make you feel?
If your local nearest large city had a cryptocurrency that you could buy and trade and sell and
that they use the revenue from that to pay for certain things where taxes didn't close
the gap.
I just hope you're ready to reorganize your entire business around this.
Miami not only claims that you can pay your taxes in Bitcoin.
They claim that the mayor and several city staff are getting paid in Bitcoin and that
city citizens will get a Bitcoin dividend from their profits.
Can you picture a world where almost every major city has its own cryptocurrency and
now you have to figure out how to sell a product like this is just going to be a whole new
cluster?
So I have two initial reactions.
What a nice PR stunt for Miami.
Well done, guys.
But this is just a bad idea, right?
This is the reason like every state, you know, you have their own currency here.
Remember the Oracle's Confederation?
That's exactly where I was going with this.
Yeah, it feels like we're going backwards in time.
They figured out that that's kind of stupid.
So there was a federal currency and we call that the dollar.
Imagine the possibility for different kinds of corruption when these different cities
have different implementations and policies and rules around their currency.
It's going to be wild.
Couldn't you like devalue a rival city's coin?
So this is inside Florida baseball, but Orlando, Miami, and to a lesser extent, Tampa, although
Tampa doesn't feel to a lesser extent, but they are in this like big fight to become
the tech hub for Florida.
Which is probably why Miami is doing this, by the way.
Wouldn't it be in the mayor of Tampa's interest, the mayor of Orlando's interest to totally
do whatever they can to devalue Miami coin and just screw the city of Miami?
Wouldn't it be like in any foreign powers interest to go after like major US cities
coins?
And then the other thing that will happen is these currencies will shoot up in value.
The Miami coins gone up like $10 million every month.
So these coins will shoot up in value.
The cities will use these high values to purchase Bitcoin.
And then as they begin selling their currency to buy Bitcoin, the currency will begin to
drop because there will become more supply on the market and the currencies will just
do this over and over again.
They'll go up, the cities will buy Bitcoin with that currency.
That's where they'll actually stash it and then the currencies will drop and it'll happen
over and over and over again.
It'll be a constant pump and dump scheme that basically raises the Bitcoin price artificially.
It's not good for crypto in general, I suspect.
So this is like my my constant thing with all this crap, right?
The block chain is amazing.
I think there's a lot of innovation that's going to happen there.
Fantastic.
Miami does not need a coin, right?
We need to really start talking about block chain as block chain.
I mean, I think I've made this clear.
I am not a crypto optimist.
I think.
Oh, really?
We were there, right?
We were there when all this started and was like, what are you buying drugs and hookers?
I mean, it's where it's come on.
Yeah, I always kind of feel like I mean, you got to keep in perspective like cash is probably
used for that 100 times over.
Sure.
And like, I can't say that I haven't bought some Dogecoin and then, you know, sold it
at a slight profit.
That's fun.
But I only do that once a year on Guy Fawkes Day.
That's the way to do it.
I think, you know, there is some fundamentals there people find valuable, obviously a shared
ledger that's cryptographically verifiable.
That's pretty beneficial, right?
A decentralized way to send money from person to person.
If I could send every contractor of JB cash directly and not go through like some sort
of intermediary bank or PayPal or service, I absolutely would.
Why wouldn't?
I want to be able to pay everyone and anything directly.
Of course I would.
I'd love to be able to do that online.
So have you heard of the IRS?
Yeah, that's definitely a thing.
Right.
And that's an area that's interesting.
You know, it seems like they're treating Bitcoin and things like that as an asset, not so much
as a currency.
So when you cash it out, that's when you have to pay your taxes.
Capital gains tax on Bitcoin.
I love it.
Yep.
Onto some more productivity follow up.
We got a bunch.
I just got a couple in here we could fit.
Longtime listener Remy wrote in and said, Hi, Mike and Chris.
On Thursday, local time, I got the new episode of Koda Radio.
So I'm a little behind.
I want to give you a productivity hack while I could.
I recently upgraded my macro pads, special small keyboards with rearrangeable keycaps.
And then he has small pieces of paper with legends under them instead of generic keycaps.
And we'll have a link because he has some photos in his blog post.
And it's awesome.
So we printed out these little squares, transparent keycaps.
He puts a little squares under there, and he says it makes an enormous difference in
debugging C++, which you'd be remotely connected remotely to a coffee machine.
So he could kick off also that I mean, if you're going to go through the hassle of having
custom buttons, obviously, one of them has to brew coffee.
Yeah.
But I had I just had to share this one from Remy because one, it's just great to hear
from him.
But to the blog post that he linked with it is really rad because you see, you see kind
of what he's done with it.
The buttons are backlit.
And then he's printed these little squares with different colors and different words
on it.
And he just hits that and executes the macro.
And it's kind of like a more analog version of the Elgato Steam Deck.
And there's something about that I really love.
I got to get one of those because, you know, getting up to brew tea is just not civilized.
No, no, it's like an animal.
Actually wrote in just some really, really straightforward, simple productivity advice.
First and foremost, use a consistent note system and task management system.
Personally, I've been using a bullet journal since 2019.
The consistency is part of it.
A bullet journal is a lot of work, in my opinion, but I've kind of landed on using things for
like my personal quick tasks, like things I got to do for Christmas.
I use things on iOS.
And then for my work stuff, my work projects, I've taken to using Todoist because it supports
sharing.
It has a really, really light kind of a can board kind of project thing you can also share.
And it has more management with just general group stuff.
And the nice thing about Todoist is there's a bajillion integrations with tons of different
things.
So it's easy to get to dos in there and out and stuff like that.
So I've landed on Todoist for my work stuff and things for my personal stuff.
I think things is the best design to do app on iOS.
Longtime listener Hudson wrote in saying that the Kansas Advantage 2 keyboard made a, quote,
huge difference in the health of their hands and wrists.
This is a monster.
We've talked about it once before on the show.
It looks like something out of Star Trek, Hudson says, and he's right.
It's three hundred and fifty dollars and it's really just this different take on a keyboard
more in.
It's just better for the way our hands are actually built.
But it's a change.
That's a big step for me.
I have found going with the ergonomic split keyboards that have the little feet so they
can get positioned right are a nice intermediary step that, you know, probably a hundred hundred
dollars less or getting a really nice mechanical keyboard that doesn't bottom out when you
press hard.
And if you type hard, it gives you kind of a good response.
That kind of stuff helps.
And then changing it up can help, too.
Now we recorded early last week and we talked about Drew DeVault's complaints around Python.
And we didn't really zero in on quite what Drew was worried about, not editor, Drew,
but Randy Drew on the Internet.
And Will thinks he's nailed.
He says the rant about Python packaging is really kind of hard to suss out.
But reading through the lines, I think he spent too much time ranting about modern software
development in general.
And that's why it was, well, I don't know, pip works for me and stuff like that.
He says what he's particularly upset about is that Python leadership has so far taken
a very hands off approach to its packaging ecosystem.
Core Python has historically had some packaging tools that are old, depreciated and marked
for removal in 3.12.
Most projects use set up tools, which is an independent project, up until the last few
years.
Now set up tools has become the de facto standard.
Reading through all of this, it's kind of easy to understand how some things get a little
complicated.
And he thinks this is what Drew was really kind of complaining about because Drew is
looking at it from a perspective of wanting to be able to package this stuff in a Linux
district.
You know, something else that we haven't really touched on, but Will brings back up, is the
situation where all the Rust moderators resigned.
He says, I interpret what happened there as the mod team resigned as a move of last resort
after a back and forth with the Rust core team.
We haven't really heard much.
And I haven't seen anything else on this.
No, there was a super vague statement by the core team about how they're dedicated to like
working with, you know, the different sub teams or something.
It was really like, I don't know.
He says there was some serious shade thrown by the outgoing mods, quote, we recommend
that the broader Rust community and the future mod team exercise extreme skepticism of any
statements by the core team claiming to illuminate the situation.
He says that's some serious shade to throw without any other context.
I think you're right, Will.
That was something.
Yeah, it's just kind of gone nowhere.
Just kind of gone nowhere.
All right.
Last one.
And I think we're done with the productivity ones for a while.
But see, what happened is people are just kind of catching up.
They're like a week or two behind.
Oh, boy.
So absolute zero had a really great one.
And it's a whole system about writing things down before you go to sleep and labeling your
tabs with an extension.
And what I want to do is I want to link it in the show notes because it's just probably
too long.
It's like a, let me see.
It's like a seven step system.
Jeez.
Yeah, I know.
But he says you get to your creative sweet spot a lot faster following his system.
I kind of like the idea.
And if we were doing the productivity episode today, I would probably read through it and
talk about it.
But I wanted to get link it in the show notes just so that all of you out there, you know,
could go get it and, you know, follow Mike system.
People wrote in wondering if you have a system you follow like a daily regime.
Yeah.
So long time listeners now I've been a little sloppy with them.
I actually have to get back into it, but, uh, well, no, I used to talk a lot about the
Pomodoro technique.
It's a like 25 minutes on five minutes off for coding.
And that's on my basic dev kind of productivity hack.
Uh, and that means, you know, close Twitter, close your email.
Uh, I tend to mute Slack and, uh, I just want to just as a side note muting Slack is a power
move that I'm just going to put it out there.
Double side.
I sent an email and it said, if you're getting too many notifications and you got noise like
family members around you, use the sound canceling headphones, but don't connect them to your
machine that has the notifications like your laptop.
Oh, it's so good, right?
That's the small part I never do.
And I'm going to totally do now.
Right.
Like use, use like an iPad or your phone or whatever to play whatever music and not the
device.
Right.
There's like totally D and D out or whatever.
Yeah.
That's, that's really good.
Uh, the other thing I do is I buy those little, they're called field notes like love field
notes.
Yeah.
So I like the, uh, the grid ones cause I tend to just like sketch either sketch out designs
or like database designs, UML, all that kind of good stuff.
And I don't use them as like some archive of everything, you know, for the end of time.
It's kind of, if I'm doing something or on the phone with somebody, I need to remember
something.
I just write it down.
It's weird.
I think they have a little stupid catchphrase.
I'm writing it down to remember it now, not later, which is exactly how I use them.
Same.
I have one right here and every now and then like if something comes up during the show
or you suggest something or whatever, I'll write it down.
And if I write it down, just that function, I'm probably 80% more likely to remember it.
And if I don't write it down, I'm probably a hundred percent going to forget it.
And I just use it for temporary stuff.
Right.
When I first started using paper notes, I thought I needed to put everything down and
I felt bad for not doing it.
And then I realized, no, there are a specific kind of note information that's, that's ephemeral
and is better captured when writing.
And I use it for that all the time too.
I like it.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you go there to support the
show.
Linode is how I've hosted everything for the last couple of years.
In fact, I've got a massive project I'm working on there right now that'll tell you more about,
but something I started doing before I launched this new project is I switched over to creating
a flat mesh VPN between all of my Linodes.
I use the open source project called Nebula to create essentially a flat network backhaul
between the Linodes that we have in different data centers.
They've got 11 data centers around the world and Linode is their own ISP.
So their interconnects are screaming fast.
So there's a unique opportunity here to kind of create a super fast flat network between
my machines.
But the project I'm working on, I started building it here in the studio on a Raspberry
Pi compute module.
And so I added the Nebula VPN to that compute module.
And now it's part of that same flat network as all of my Linodes, but it's actually even
better than that because when you're creating a Linode machine, you can add your SSH key
right there at that point in time.
When the machine's done, you just log in.
It's so great.
So I've done that and I have a master control SSH key that I've put on the Linodes that
we've deployed for about at least a year now.
So over time I'm kind of going with best practices and I'm shutting down internet SSH access
to my machines and only allowing it from the Nebula VPN.
And I have a master control Linode that I log into that's part of that Nebula VPN or
my Raspberry Pi, which is part of that Nebula VPN, or I could add any machine really.
And I can get access to these machines safely and securely.
And Linode actually takes steps and efforts to make sure that their machines are VPN friendly.
So if you'd like to set it up as a VPN endpoint yourself or use a mesh VPN like I am, it's
very accessible and they work hard to make sure that's possible.
But what's really kind of great about Linode is they have that performance to price ratio.
They're 30 to 50% cheaper than the major hypervisors out there that want to lock you into their
crazy platforms.
And they're constantly investing in their platform.
They've been doing this for 18 years and they've stepped it up over the last five years.
I mean, it's like they just put the pedal to the metal and they've never let off.
They've recently been rolling out super fast PCIe MVME storage.
Of course, they've got the latest and greatest AMD epic processors for the data center that
are on their highest CPU end machines.
They've got 40 gigabit connections coming into those networked machines.
It's just like on and on and on.
And then on top of all of that, they've got great services you can layer in there that
take it to the next level, like object storage and cloud firewalls and a powerful DNS manager,
Kubernetes support, VLAN support.
I mean, it just is such a package.
And then to top it all off, they're supporting a big part of our community.
Not just in the media space, but some of my favorite open source projects are supported
by Linode and some of my favorite events have been supported by Linode.
They understand that kind of investing in that ecosystem pays dividends long term.
Even if they can't do a pro and con and maybe they can't necessarily like hit a key performance
indicator by doing it, they know long term it serves them because they've been part of
this community.
So go try it for real.
Go try it for yourself and support the show.
Linode.com slash coder, that's Linode.com slash coder.
Get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and support the show, Linode.com slash coder.
There's a story going around today that we have to talk about on the show.
First of all, I really can connect with this because I have been in some surprise meetings
where everyone in the meeting got fired.
But today it came out that the CEO of Better.com fired 900 employees at once over a Zoom meeting.
It's brutal.
Somebody posted the video online and I grabbed just like 10 seconds of it.
But the whole thing you might want to go watch if you really like the cringe.
If you're on this call, you are part of the unlucky group being laid off.
Your employment here is terminated effective immediately.
Just good morning and thanks for joining us on the call today.
Hey, look, I'm real sorry.
This has been hard.
Hardest thing I've had to do for the second time in a row because apparently he's done
this at a previous company, too.
The 43 year old CEO has.
But quote, the market has changed and, you know, we got to do what we got to do to fulfill
our mission.
So 900 of you are gone.
900 employees in one shot.
Yeah.
All over Zoom.
Some of the American employees will get some severance and stuff like that.
Some of them are going to get like a package.
So they're going to get taken care of for a little bit.
But what a wild thing, huh?
And man, I have been in this spot before where I was told that no one had been laid off in
25 years at this company.
You'll always have a job here.
And then I got called into a meeting one day and told that everyone in our department was
being laid off and being replaced by contractors.
It's a family until it isn't all of a sudden.
What do these people do?
Better.com.
Actually, let's go take a look.
I haven't done it.
Maybe somehow they've had to lay people off with a domain like that.
You'd think they'd be making money.
But Better.com.
Oh, are they down right now?
They might be down right now.
Well, they're backed by SoftBank.
Also, I don't know if you've noticed this, but there's some East Coast, West Coast bias
here because the headline is not Better.com CEO.
No, no.
The headline is New York CEO fires 900 employees on Zoom call because those East Coasters are
such jerks.
I was going to say an enlightened California CEO who's been meditating for six hours but
never just like can a bunch of people know I saw that I thought, oh, man, there's some
serious bias there.
OK, so Better.com, the right mortgage could save you thousands.
So it's like some sort of mortgage grifting business, it looks like.
And they're backed by SoftBank, thus explaining how they afford the domain.
Better.com.
Got it.
Yeah.
They're doing stuff with mortgages.
It's not a bubble kids.
Isn't that something?
And, you know, it's not like it's super easy on the freelancer side either.
So I, if you allow, a little behind the scenes, I am working on a new Linux show.
But what happened to the M1 power hour?
That's such a great name.
We should do it just because of the name.
But you know, like you have to ask yourself as like a small shop, like, what are my core
competencies?
Like, where can I actually add value?
And for me, like, and also I have to ask the question, what do I enjoy doing?
Because if I don't enjoy doing it, I'll burn out after a while because, you know, a new
show is a big commitment.
It's something you're doing over and over and over again, potentially for as long as
possible.
You know, as close to indefinite as you can achieve.
That's the goal.
Like your goal is to create work for yourself that never ends.
Right.
So you better like it.
It's been really hard for me because I've had this really clear idea that I chicken
out and I kind of think, well, maybe I should go a different direction.
I've been chewing on this and I'll link to a blog post at Seth's blog and I like it a
lot.
It's called the freelancer's dilemma.
And he says, engaging the marketplace requires creating value for people who have a choice
and deciding what you offer your customers is your choice.
It begins by being clear about what you own and what you're good at and what gives you
satisfaction.
So I've been thinking about that recently.
I'm hoping to have it ready for the new year.
We shall see.
I don't know because it involves moving a few other things around to accommodate for
this.
But it's such a saturated market.
Right.
But I feel like I've got something new in me that I want to do.
But I can't tell if it's just, you know, I want to scratch an itch or if I really feel
like there's a place for it in the market.
It's kind of one of those like, you know, if you really mess it up, there's not a lot
of room for failure.
So the consequences are pretty significant.
Maybe not irreparable in large part because we have members, but still significant.
It's possible I'll be wrapping up another show to make room for it.
You know, like that's a big decision too that has to be made.
All of that's been on my mind recently.
There's not a clear strategy available to me.
There's not really anybody in this niche that I could emulate.
And there's not really any kind of like guide to follow.
I just kind of have to decide and execute and hope for the best and then pivot if it
fails.
Can I pitch a concept?
Go for it.
We take famous like Apple World podcasters and we just like sit them down with Pop OS.
Oh man.
Anything but KD.
KD is a little too stable.
Yeah.
Something good home based.
Oh, they'd find, they'd find issues with plasma for sure.
Well, okay.
Well, just like I want like a Linus tech tips, like destroy your desktop environment in the
first five minutes.
Yeah, man.
That's been rough to watch.
I have to be honest.
Yeah, I did.
I just saw the most recent one.
So, so another Linux show.
No, you, so you were telling me you're not bringing Stow back for me.
Just not happening.
No, unfortunately, not unless they turn that game around and tell you what, as the editor
and chief of the network, I could do anything I want, right?
I could, I could launch Stow again.
So I've been tempted, you know, I've been tempted not to launch Stow, but I've been
tempted to do something that's kind of a new genre, a new area of coverage.
But the reality of that is, is that we have so much momentum built up around Linux and
open source software and credibility and, and resources, right?
So yeah, for sure.
Kind of the, there's a, there's a nice network effect of if I build up another Linux show
and I spend my time doing something for that show, like learning something or talking to
somebody that's knowledge that becomes applicable to the other Linux shows as well.
So it's sort of like a network effect of, even though I'm working on multiple shows,
a rising tide sort of thing for knowledge and network connections and all that kind
of thing.
So there's a lot of advantages in that regard as well.
It's probably an area that, you know, I also have the most history with, you know, I've
been covering Linux stuff for almost 13, 14 years.
Yeah.
And you have the people, right?
If you ever need like to slot in a guest host or something, you have enough Linux gurus.
Yeah.
We'll see.
But so it's not always so easy on the, yeah, you know, I'm not going to necessarily get
fired tomorrow, but I could make one misstep, one miscalculation and essentially lead to
my own firing.
So it's not always easy.
Like canceling stow.
Yeah, exactly.
Or canceling Linux action show.
I'm still hearing about that all the time.
I got an email this morning.
Yeah, but come on.
And Linux action news and Linux.
I would actually argue Linux unplugged is, you know what, let me bait the trolls.
Linux unplugged is a better version of Linux action show.
Oh, Linux unplugged.
You know, it was, if you were going to bill, I think if you were going to build last today,
you would probably just build that show really.
So you're probably right.
It would just be Linux unplugged.
You would never do last the way you did it.
You know, and we're going back into what, like the 2010s now, 2006 is I think when the
show started.
Was it really?
Yeah.
And then video, I think was 2008 is when we got video, I started watching it when it
was on video.
Yeah.
You would never do that again.
Well, maybe you would do video again.
I don't know.
But never that format.
I don't think because podcasting is like so mature now.
It was a product of that era, you know, and it was closer to the nineties.
So it was a little more acceptable.
Like we were really cheeky and in on like the theme music invoking nineties, Sonic the
Hedgehog vibes, right?
It was tongue in cheek, but now it would just sound extremely antiquated.
Well, and so this new show, this is a Luminary exclusive or Spotify exclusive or.
You and Joe Rogan.
Right.
It's going to be a crypto exclusive network Christ.
You have to give your wallet, you know, you have to get on the block chain to get it.
Yeah.
You just have to invest in a little pod coin.
And then you know what I'm about to NFT the Jar Jar sound like I'm just saying.
Jupiter Party, you have been asking for it and I have finally gotten it together.
It's a membership for the entire network and for the cost of just two memberships, you
get access to everything currently.
That's four shows.
But when that grows, you automatically get access to that as well.
And when you're checking out, if you use the promo code, the signal, they'll get two dollars
off for a year.
So right now it's a limited time to sign up and support the entire network and get access
to the ad free version of every show to get access to the post show of self-hosted.
And of course, to get the full live version, which has tons of extra content of Linux unplugged,
all of them fully produced and ready to go in a feed for you.
And you can support the entire network for just the cost of two memberships.
So to get access and sign up right now or to give it as a gift because we've added gift
options to just go to Jupiter Party and then use the promo code the signal and get yourself
two dollars off for a year.
Jupiter Party, your membership makes a difference.
We're just a small, independent team doing our absolute best to make content for you
and you can help make that a reality and keep us going.
Jupiter Party, promo code the signal.
So Apple has a plan to crack the business market and I'm actually buying this one.
So Apple is beginning through partners to offer a thirty dollar a month M1 plan.
You can lease an M1 Mac for thirty bucks a month and Apple is also launching a business
essentials program that we talked about briefly on here that gives you like centralized management
tools and free backup storage for Macs.
Sort of a similar management system to the iPhone, although I would suspect probably
not as complete.
And then additionally, on top of that, Amazon has announced that you can now get Amazon
EC2 M1 Mac instances.
You got to give them 24 hours of heads up, though, because they're racking physical
Mac minis at AWS.
There's a poor guy named John just racking up M1s.
But you know, I actually think Apple is aiming at the small business market, not the big
enterprise market, but like the hundred, two hundred size market.
And you know what I really think the sign was of that?
And I mean, it's not like I'm joking.
I think it was adding the HDMI port back.
The only reason really for an HDMI port that isn't a higher res capable signal projectors,
projectors.
Yeah, I've been in many boring meetings where I've had to dongle up to a projector.
It's a meme at this point.
It's a meme that Apple wants to kill.
And it's something that the that I think I think the dongle thing was felt the hardest
by offices that had to connect to different peripherals or different projectors and whatnot
or conferences and tech events.
That's where the dongle stuff really got people just like either in some situation where they
couldn't connect or, you know, just a bad taste in their mouth.
I just want to say right before Covid, like I have many times in an airport been the customer
of those stupid Best Buy vending machines that will basically sell you a bunch of dongles
for your Apple devices that should have more ports.
I see people lined.
I used to go there anymore, but I used to see people lined up there all the time getting
themselves a dongle or a pair of headphones or something like that.
And Bluetooth headphones, because, of course, they can't wire their headphones and they're
going about to get on a plane.
And that's the times when it really sucks.
The most is those situations.
But you think they got a shot here, you know, picture your hundred person company, two hundred
person company, thirty dollars a month for an M1.
And also you can buy into this Apple business essentials program where they'll provide support
and centralized management.
Think this is going to do it?
I kind of see them separately, right?
The Apple business essential support, it really, really sucks to be an MDM company now.
Because I don't see a reason unless you have some weird cross-platform needs, why you wouldn't
just issue iPhones and iPads.
And I just, just like a big part of my business used to be, and I'm sure still is for people
who are more iOS focused, is writing enterprise software for tablets, right?
For iPads.
That seems huge to me, the business essentials thing.
The hardware thing, you know, the problem with Mac OS as a business OS, I think for
a lot of like those one hundred employee companies, is if you get a new device every year, do
you also now get the new version of Mac OS?
And I think for a lot of IT departments, that's maybe not something they want.
Yeah, I think if you're going to go the Mac route, you kind of have to be committed to
at least upgrading every other OS release.
Yeah.
Are they going to force you to, right?
Is this like the iPhone program where it's, you know, N dollars a month, then when the
new one comes out, you just automatically get it?
Because I could see that being like the IT, you know, department's headache every year.
Or is it optional?
Yeah.
I didn't read the specifics.
It might be every two years and then it's optional if you want to replace it.
But yeah.
Yes.
I follow what you're saying there.
That would be a maintenance problem.
Maintenance problem.
And I don't think a lot of enterprises anymore have like custom line of business Mac OS software.
I know we're going to get emails from folks who do, but so yeah, I mean, Microsoft does
this too, right?
They do surface, not pro, whatever they call it.
They have a plan just like this.
Right.
What about for your business?
Instead of dropping two grand on an M1, 30 bucks a month until you don't use it anymore
and then you send it back.
Okay.
So what if a Martini gets poured into it?
Well, I wonder, huh?
What is that?
Because they have to have some accommodations.
There's going to be damage to these things.
Yeah.
Exactly.
I bet it comes with apple care plus and then you can buy the additional coverage.
Ah, yeah, of course.
So then if it's covered by apple care, you're good.
And if apple care says screw off, you're probably just, you, you, you bought the machine.
So I don't know.
I mean, it's kind of a sweetheart deal for a business of my size cause it's just not
that much money.
Yeah.
That's what I was surprised by is it seems cheap for apple.
But maybe this doesn't make sense.
Like I wouldn't be surprised if you have to buy like 50 or 60 units to get this plan.
Ah, yeah, sure.
I really doubt I could get like eight, you know, you know, spend $240 a month and just
everybody gets a new M1 all the time.
That seems crazy to me.
Well maybe one way you could manage all those new Macs is a bunch of folks sent into the
show, friend of the show, Jeff Gerling's Ansible GitHub page for managing his software setup.
He's got a playbook for setting everything up on his Mac and he just, when he gets a
new Mac, he rolls this out.
He says it automates the software on his Mac for software and web development.
Some things are difficult to automate.
So I still have to do a few manual steps, but it's all documented here.
What it would is, you know, whatever might be the exception.
And I think he gets things up and going in like 15, 20 minutes on a brand.
He goes from brand new Mac to ready for full development in about 15, 20 minutes.
That's epic.
Yeah.
It makes me kind of think, because I know I also should learn Ansible for the server
stuff.
But actually, I want to come back to that real quick.
I got to be honest.
I didn't even realize you could do anything on a Mac with Ansible.
I didn't know it was compatible with Ansible.
I assumed it was not.
So that's an area I need to learn a lot more about.
But I got a confession to make that I realized I should have been telling you on the show.
Red Hat announced that CentOS was transitioning from a standard release that follows the Red
Hat model to a continuous delivery of minor versions called CentOS Stream.
It's not as bad as they made it sound.
What it really means is instead of waiting for like Red Hat 9.1 and 9.3 and 9.5, you
just get those little intermediary updates as after they've been QA tested and ready
to go.
That's really that's the main difference, because then they build Red Hat 9.1 or 9.2
from that work.
So it's actually it's not bad.
But Stream 8 came out.
That's when they announced it during the CentOS 8 lifetime.
So CentOS Stream came out and it was where they were kind of proving things out.
I just talked to Carl George in Linux Action News this Sunday about this.
It was like, OK, prove the theory works while you already have a distro that's been built
the traditional way.
Now convert that in real time to stream.
So I thought I'm going to avoid that and wait for Stream 9, which just came out and is born
since this whole stream idea came around.
It was created as a stream first distro.
It's the whole, you know, from tooling on, it's all built for this.
That seemed like the distro plus it's based on Fedora 34, which is a great release of
Fedora.
It includes GNOME 40 and it's so it makes Stream 9 essentially an LTS Fedora.
Although it doesn't have all of the kernel components to make it a great desktop, it
has everything you'd really need for, you know, a development job.
So Stream 9 is it just seemed like this, oh, this is going to be this moment.
And I was going to migrate all of my studio machines over to Stream 9.
I'd been waiting since the announcement back in December.
And then it came around and I really didn't find myself all that excited.
I didn't even, it didn't even occur to me to download it.
And here I had been waiting for 11 months for this.
And then when it finally arrived, it didn't even dawn on me to download it because I was
just so disinterested now.
But you know, can you guess what it is that caught my attention, which has taken my heart
and has made my eye drift from CentOS?
Is it SUSE?
It is.
Get out.
I am 100% serious.
Yes.
I am really, really liking Tumbleweed as a server OS.
Mm hmm.
Wait, Tumbleweed?
Oh, you're so brave.
You're so courageous on the server.
I'm like, no.
Give me the LTS.
Well, I mean, you know, we're a team of Linux guys, right?
So like when things break, we usually have it fixed in like 15 minutes if they break.
They're so leet.
You hear the condescension?
Yeah.
No, it's really because I get content out of it.
If I was just like hosting services for customers, I would probably go more with leet.
I like that they have the option though.
But because for us, it pays to be on the cutting edge.
We basically do it so that way the listeners don't have to.
Tumbleweed has been a surprise.
One of the big shifts that I made this go is I'm not using it as a desktop, which I've
always found very frustrating, but also I'm just not using Yast that much.
I really don't.
Where I always really hit my head against the wall with SUSE is when I am using Yast
to manage software.
And I am glad it's there for some people.
But this time around, I went and got the zipper cheat sheet and I've kept that around and
I'm doing all of my software management using zipper.
It's a great example of how you can build a nice UI around a command line tool that
displays information that is very easy to read for the end user.
And it's easy to make decisions and weigh the pros and cons and decide what actions
I should take.
And that's in a nutshell what I'm really liking about SUSE is it feels like they've engineered
a little bit extra on top of tools that you have to use on a frequent basis to manage
your box, where Ubuntu and Arch by design, but Ubuntu specifically, it doesn't really
feel like Canonical's adding value to that layer of tooling.
They do have tools that are valuable.
Don't get me wrong.
Like they've built tooling around ZFS snapshots.
They have some great tooling around firing off some quick VMs and containers and all
of that.
They have some good tooling, but like apt itself, that's not their domain.
That's Debian's.
Debian isn't changing anything, right?
So it's not really going to change ever in Ubuntu until Debian does something.
Where SUSE, well, they are their own upstream.
And if they want their package manager to be better and give the user more information,
they can just directly improve the tooling.
And I think over time that's begun to add up.
And so there's nice little areas where it's like, hey man, you know, you just issued this
command, but on Tumbleweed for safety purposes and for recovery purposes, you probably want
to use this command, but you know, your decision.
And I really appreciate that kind of stuff.
And it's displayed in a way where it stands out.
So it draws your attention so you don't miss the information.
And there's a lot of just nice things in that regard.
And I have to give credit where credit is due.
They were first to ButterFS at massive, massive deployment scale.
And I think it was a little early when they chose to do it.
But Fedora just got around to it, you know, three releases ago or so.
And it's in a great state right now.
And the people out there who say ButterFS is horrible, well, I think they should take
another look.
I grant you, for my large data sets, I still use ZFS.
But for my laptop hard drive or a boot SSD or a Raspberry Pi SD card or SSD, I'm using
ButterFS everywhere now.
And SUSE has been building on that for so long that they have fantastic snapshot tooling
built into all of it.
And they're really taking advantage of the ButterFS file system in a way that some distros
are just finally getting around to.
I'm in shock.
I mean, part of what I really like and appreciate, their Arch version is really solid.
I have it running on a Raspberry Pi Compute Module 4 upstairs.
I just booted that thing off a USB stick and installed it to the eMMC like it was a hard
drive on a regular Intel x86 PC.
I just booted off the USB stick, went through a regular install, chose the eMMC as the target
disk.
And my partition installed it.
None of this flashing image and boot into a pre-installed, pre-configured environment
that already has a login that always feels cheap on ARM devices.
It was really nice.
And so I can run it on my ARM VMs in Parallels on the new MacBook.
And I can run it on the Compute Module 4.
And I'm going to be running it on the new Jupyter Broadcasting local server.
And I think what I'm thinking about doing is learning Ansible, because I've got some
people like Wes who can help me, and eventually just repaving the Linode JB infrastructure,
which is a mix of CentOS and Ubuntu, and redeploy it all using Ansible on SUSE potentially,
if it goes well.
The next test will be a local server.
And if our local server turns out, well, I like it with Tumbleweed, then I think that'll
be stage three will be deployed on our Linode servers.
And Nuke can pave all of them and redeploy on some, maybe Tumbleweed, but maybe Leap
using Ansible.
Probably Leap for our cloud servers.
So you were right.
That's the moral of the story.
The lizard people have yet another convert.
Congratulations.
When we restarted the show, you held strong to it.
And I tease you for it.
And I admit it does go off the rails when I start using Yast, but if I stay out of Yast,
I'm really liking it.
And yeah, I basically use it.
Yeah, I think you were right there.
It is.
All right.
Well, we got to keep an eye on this, your ongoing reptilian adventures.
I'll let you know how it goes in lizard land.
It may go about, if it goes poorly, I'll report back, but hopefully it doesn't.
Thank you to our Coder QA members out there who joined early and made this show possible.
Thank you so much for being a member.
The quarterly is out, and there will be another one next quarter, and you can become a member
for the show at coderqa.co.
We appreciate you very much.
Go find Mr. Dominic on Twitter at Dumanuku.
His company is at the Mad Botter Inc.
Anywhere else you want to send the folks?
I'll go to alice.dev if you've got some proprietary legacy data that you want converted into something
useful.
You got to go to alice.dev.
You got to go.
You got to.
The podcast here is at Coder Radio Show.
I'm thinking about changing out this outro.
Now that Jack's out of Twitter, why am I even plugging it anymore?
Nobody even uses Twitter.
Go join the Matrix.
There is a Coder Radio community on our Matrix server.
Our Matrix server is colony.jupiterbroadcasting.com, and it's actually pretty nice.
Go hang out there.
There's a persistent chat on Matrix.
Want to play around with element?
Now's your chance.
Our server is colony.jupiterbroadcasting.com.
Links to what we talked about today are at coder.show slash 443.
Over there you'll find our contact form.
That's a huge part of the show, so please do participate with your feedback and subscribe
over at coder.show slash subscribe.
We'll see you right back here next Monday.