This is Coder Radio, episode 409, for April 12th, 2021.
Oh, hey there. This is Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and business of software development and the world of technology. And of course,
this episode is brought to you by Cloud Guru. Cloud Guru now has that cloud playground.
Azure, AWS, or Google Cloud sandboxes on ACG's credit card. Not yours. Get certified, get
hired, get learning at a cloudguru.com. My name is Chris and our very own Florida man
who truly has his heart in New Jersey. It's our host, Mr. Dominic. Hello, Mike.
You know, I was going to come in hot with the Jar Jar, but you got me on that one.
I did.
Yeah.
I thought about it today. I thought, you know, you've been in Florida for a few years now,
but you're a Jersey guy through and through, you know?
This is sort of like the Yodas fighting Palpatine. He falls and then inexplicably just gives
up when he was winning the entire time.
Right. You kind of just ended up in Florida, but your heart's still in Jersey. But you
fight the good fight down there, you know? And somebody has to keep count of the Gators
and that's your job.
Can I tell you, I saw a 10-foot Gator just like chilling on somebody's lawn the other
day. I'm like, yeah, this is not a great place to be.
Yeah. When animals can eat your dog, I don't think that's where I want to live. I like
my dog too much.
Or like your kid.
I kind of, but then it's like, but your stomach's in Texas this week. So, you know, I stalk
you on the Twitters like I do. And you tweet this picture of a steak breakfast. Like, what
is this thing? A T-bone you're eating for breakfast?
It was a New York strip. So very on-brand with the New Jersey.
Oh, amazing. Didn't even realize it. Didn't. That's perfect.
So this is, you know, once again, what happens, you fall asleep on YouTube. Inevitably, Jordan
or Michaela Peterson comes on.
Yeah. Okay. I was going to mention that you're tweeting, you're tweeting Jordan Peterson's
daughter. Just picture. I was like, what's going on there? Like, are you being an evil
genius and getting like some of her followers to notice your feed or are you actually trying
to get her attention?
Why not? Indeed. Why not? I think, I don't know. I think she's, uh, she's, she's probably
not on the market, but I'm not sure. Isn't she in Canada? You'd have to move. You'd
have to move. Last I heard they were like, he was like in some sort of weird Russian,
like hospital or he's back now. He's back. Yeah. He's got a new book too. So, you know,
watch out. You get in on this book thing, man, these guys, they can just like go MIA
for like two years and then they've come rolling out with a book and now everybody's talking
about him again because they wrote a book, wrote a book, you know,
I was trying to write a book at one point and I guess I just failed to disappear. Is
that like a necessary step? You just, you gotta, you gotta peace out for a bit. You
gotta be aloof and mysterious, you know? And then if you don't have any strife to write
about, you just got to create a bunch of it.
Well, you could, I could just read the YouTube comments. I mean, there you go. There you
go. Okay. So remember, let's go back in time for a moment. Let's do a robe, Mike. It's
going to be so much fun. Let's do a robe. All right. So I had to make an executive decision
this week. We had to just decide to move forward and at this point in time, cancel the international
robe orders. And I hate to be on air saying that, tried so hard to be able to not have
to say that, but with that loss of this battle, I have committed myself to winning this war.
And I have eaten my humble pie from this experience, learned a lot, and I'm going to be talking
more about what I have figured out. I've done like a whole post-mortem on the whole thing
and realized where the failures lie. And I'm also entertaining several ideas of how to
solve this problem in the future. And I'm going to work towards solving this problem.
And I will, at some point in the future, well, at least I hope, have another batch of robes
that I will then have at that point, figure out all the international stuff. And I will
either be shipping it directly or I will work with an intermediary party like in the EU
to have them act as a local distributor or something. I will figure it out.
What would, what was it, Valerie? Valerie, I can't even remember the unfiltered soundboard.
Which one?
The one with some interesting comments about what to do with the EU.
Oh, yeah. What was her name? Yeah, you're right. Victoria Nuland.
Victoria Nuland. That's
Yeah, yeah, yeah. F the EU was her famous quote. Yeah, I didn't, you know, because we
have like a 30, 40 percent outside the U.S. audience, right? It's a significant demographic
for us. I even got notes from people who said, hey, man, I'll even pay $185 of shipping for
a $65 robe. I just want some cool swag for one of my favorite shows. And when you get
notes like that, you're like, wow, OK, I'm going to figure this out. Like, this is something
I really do want to figure out because I want to have all kinds of cool stuff that we can
ship out, maybe in small quantities and whatnot.
I just ordered my LUP beer stein.
So, yeah, so the beer stein is is sourced through Zazzle and they have international
shipping partners already. Where it got tricky with the robe is we went with something that
no fulfillment center fulfills. Right. If I wanted to do a T-shirt, a cotton T-shirt
or a ball cap, or if I wanted to do a face mask right now or a mug or a mouse pad, I
could source that pretty successfully. And there's a lot of fulfillment places that just
manage international shipping. They have incredibly competitive international shipping rates because
they have facilities in those areas and I could fulfill that. But I didn't really want
to do a cotton T-shirt or a ball cap or a mug for the show because I feel like Coda
Radio being around for a while, like we're kind of beyond that stuff. That's like, you
know, beginners merch. Right. We're a sophisticated podcast now. We've been around for a while,
gone through a few losses, come back from it. You know, we're like we're like that couple
now who like has gotten back together and we know each other's flaws, but we're still
just going to work, make it work because we're not going to find anybody better. And like
we're just now we're like in it forever. And so it's like, you know, you don't want to
have beginner swag, you know, like first relationship stuff. That's embarrassing. Like you want your
more sophisticated grown up stuff now. There's so much here. The fact that you're still determined
to do this is amazing. I've been watching Battlestar Galactica. Let's just take the
new one, not the not the 80s one. And I would say we are more like the exhausted command
structure who has the number of survivors behind. You know, President Rosalind has the
number of survivors on a whiteboard behind her at all time. And that number is not going
up in a positive way. Right. So I think, you know, I mean, we lost Objective C. Mm hmm.
You all fail to admit the glory that is the Phantom Menace. Right. Right. Continue to
insist that Katie is good. And I still cannot change the background on my desktop without
seeing tremendous crashes. Well, listen, all I'm getting from that is you're just encouraging
breeding within the audience. That's what I'm getting from that statement. I don't really
know what to make from that. That's exactly what I'm saying, because then we can be bold.
We can and we can be very progressive. This is our growth strategy. We could indoctrinate
them into the Coder Radio program at an early age. Coder Radio diapers, disposable diapers,
and we could just do it as a subscription. Oh, man. Oh, yeah, man. But diapers, cloths,
any of that stuff, you know, formula, anything that's a consumable with the babies, man,
that's a whole stage of life. That's just prime for making money. You know, anything
like that. You know, also, we ought to launch a whole pregnancy line of clothing of special
swag just for pregnancy. And, you know, there's a lot of dads out there that like something
a little more comfortable, too. So we could have one for the ladies. And like on the stomach,
it just says compiling. Yeah, that'd be great. And then for different stages of the like
different trimesters, different progress loading bars, you know, like a whole it's like a whole
set that you buy that gets bigger and bigger as you're as the progress bar increases. The
shirt actually gets larger. So it's more comfortable as you're further along. I mean, why has nobody
thought of this, man? I'm just saying money on the table. I have seen one that's for dad's
successful process forked or something. Oh, nice. Yeah. You know, you don't really get
into anything if you understand the scope of the task before you start. That's true.
For development, for media creation, whatever. Now I have seen the scope of the task and
I think I see a path forward, but I don't know yet. It's very beginning of my journey.
It's humbling. It's been a long time because I've been doing this for a while. It's been
a long time where something like this has has gotten me. It's vexed me. And I've had
to like, oh, shit, I don't know anything about this. You know, I'll get it, though. I'll
get there eventually. Or you will die trying. I will, man. I will. I'm going to give it
my damned best one way or the other. You know, we have some feedback to get into. I feel
like Chuck here is just poking at you. Chuck writes in just for Mike, according to a new
report that was released, Objective C has slid down the popularity rankings yet again.
And it's pretty bad. This is, of course, Chuck has sent us a link that we'll have in the
show notes. This is according to the Tiobi index for April 2021. And Objective C has
now fallen out of the top 20 most popular programming languages as of April. Why would
this upset me? This proves that somewhere in hiding the square bracket Jedi order that
is Objective C developers has survived. OK, all right. I'm not seeing the connection,
but I'm going to let you have it. You know, it's yours. Well, if there are so many people
reporting that they're doing Objective C, unless they're all quarter radio listeners
who decided it would be, you know, they're doing it like, ironically, drinking a PBR.
That means that somewhere in the and I can only imagine a kinder land. My brothers and
sisters live. They're still going. You're right. You're right. They have not been taken
out by the Swift drones. Well, actually, this might make you feel better. Swift also saw
a decline in popularity. Yeah, it has slid from the 11th place to the 15th place in a
year. Not so good. Meanwhile, the snake, Python, continues to gain popularity and continues
to see particular growth in the data science and artificial intelligence and measuring
machine learning spaces, which I know drives our audience crazy. That seems to be what's
driving a lot of its growth. And Visual Basic and JavaScript essentially stayed put in their
ranks coming in at six and seventh, respectively. Damn it. PHP and ninth and SQL as a language
in 10th place. So apparently writing SQL is more popular than Objective C or Swift.
Well, yeah, that makes sense to me, though, right? Because SQL, you're going to get a
lot of SQL. Yeah. And you're not just writing SQL. You're running SQL and like insert other
language here, right? Yeah. No, that's it. And it's in like so many things. So I mean,
it's the back. It's a back end storage for so much, especially if you're using like an
ORM. And at some point, it's like, you know what? There's just such an there's an inefficiency
here and I need to write just like a custom query. Yeah. We're a stored procedure. Oh,
yeah. Hey, oh, lino.com slash coder. Go there to get a $100 60 day credit towards your new
account and go there to support the show. $100 is real money. Let me let me check this.
Who authorized this $100? This can't be real. What's that? It's absolutely real. It's been
real for a while. Uh huh. OK, so they just got to go to lino.com slash counter. Oh, all
right. Well, if you go to lino.com slash coder, you will get a $100 credit to try out lino.
They're my hosting provider. Been using them for a couple of years now. And once it was
the moment to launch JB 3.0 and I realized, holy crap, I'm going to need a lot of infrastructure.
It was just obvious to go with Linode. I wouldn't do it any other way. I am absolutely happy
a couple of years in. And one of the things I think that's great about Linode is they
have a lot of different distros and the various version of those distros to try and use and
deploy. And I find that immensely useful when I'm testing and prototyping stuff. I have
a project that I'm working on right now. Spoiler alert, it's hosting my own mail server. And
I just thought, let's try it out on several different Linode setups and see which which
set of packages, what system, which distro works the best for me. So I just set up a
few different Linodes and tried it on each one. I took a shot kind of like just a racing,
you know, just race to get installed on each one and saw which worked best for me. And
I think that's immensely valuable. That's immensely valuable for me. And it also gives
me a ton of experience to kind of judge where different distros stand up. And I just find
that very, very handy. It's an example of why Linode's pricing structure makes this
kind of stuff really super simple. They're often 35 to 50 percent less than the major
cloud providers like AWS or Azure, while still being faster, better tools, a cleaner, much,
much, much cleaner design. And they're independently owned and they have been since 2003. Years
ago they became their own ISP. Now they have 11 data centers around the world, super fast
interlinks between them, 40 gigabit connections coming to the hypervisors, crazy fast native
SSDs on the machines. It's great. And they back it all up with fantastic customer service.
So you're not going to get stranded. You're not going to get stuck. They're going to work
with you by phone, by ticket, by email, whatever is best for you. Linode's committed to making
that happen. And they're dedicated to offering the best virtualized cloud computing. If it
runs on Linux, it runs on Linode. So go try them out. See what I've been talking about
at linode.com slash coder.
Now let's get into just a few more emails because, you know, we get we get some feedback
from time to time. I actually thought we would get roasted for the hate we tossed Android
last week because I was intentionally being a little incendiary and I didn't really get
it. I guess maybe we've scared all those people away. But Jacob wrote in and said the Mac
is garbage. When I started my career over a decade ago, I was developing on an employer
provided MacBook. About two years ago, I switched to developing exclusively in a Linux environment,
usually Kubuntu. My current work recently switched the entire organization to MacBook
only hardware. And coming back to Mac OS after almost a decade of Linux, it feels like the
desktop environment has just stagnated full stop. Multi monitor support is minimal at
best. You still can't span a window across multiple monitors or even disable a monitor
from within the OS. After comparing how capable and stable plasma was for me to the child's
toy that Mac OS desktop environment seems to be. Well, it seems like Mac OS has just
become an afterthought for Apple when compared to how iOS has advanced over the years. And
I know here's a hot take with the M1 chip, but I won't be surprised if we just see a
unification of iOS and Mac OS in the next decade now that it's all in one platform.
My thoughts, Jacob. It's a kid like desktop environment.
It's definitely dated, right? It's obvious that there can really, so they're holding
back because in the hardware side, like the M1 is a true achievement, but it's obvious
that they have something big planned for the next, let's say three to four years. And,
you know, with, uh, they still call it catalyst. No, they gave it a real name, right? Combine.
No, it's not that, but I like that. That's just, that is what it should be called the
mulch mulch, whatever it's, they're going somewhere and they're not ready to go there
yet. And it may well be like a hybrid OS.
I find this conversation silly because I just think Apple has said it clearly Mac OS for
the Mac machines and iOS, and then they'll share the fundamentals. A lot of the fundamental
tech APIs, they're going to share a lot of the fundamental tech stack they're going to
share. And now a lot of the fundamental hardware architecture, but they're going to have a
separate desktop and OS for a mouse and keyboard driven interface versus an iOS driven one.
And this reality cannot ever change until you see full fledged Xcode on iOS because
otherwise you're always going to need a Mac.
I also challenged Jacob here, and I don't know how much I have to virtue signal about
how much I love Linux and how long I've used it. And the fact that I've hosted podcasts
about Linux for 14 years, I don't know if I need to virtue signal all that first, but
I find this complete bullshit that the Mac has stagnated and I'm not Apple's number one
defender when it comes to a Mac environment. But you know, it strikes me that a couple
of releases ago, they completely rewrote their desktop render from OpenGL to Metal, completely
rewrote the whole damn thing and shipped it within one release cycle. Meanwhile, Wayland
has taken like 12 years to even get to the stage it's at right now. So, you know, they
can actually ship when they need to ship.
And then the other thing that I think is pretty remarkable about Apple that you're still seeing
the Linux space flail around like a bunch of idiots that don't know the value of a decent
modern file system is Apple managed to deploy and ship APFS within a super respectable time
window. And not only that, but they managed to convert both their mobile and their desktop
user base and you never heard about mass reports of data loss. I'd like to see a Linux distro
pull that off. And meanwhile, they're struggling to figure out if they should even ship Butter
FS or ZFS. It's a total joke because their file system is just completely something out
of the 80s now. And Apple has completely successfully rolled those things out. And honestly, that's
just scratching the surface. That's not even bringing in the stuff that they've done security
wise that I actually think has held up pretty well over the years. I mean, you can bitch
and moan about gatekeeper all you want, but the implementation seems pretty solid. And
the one thing they haven't done, which everybody said they would, even now that they've gone
to the M1 platform, is they haven't locked that sucker down. You can still turn gatekeeper
off. You can still right click open and say, yeah, I know it's not safe. I want to do it
anyways. They've still left all of the sideloading style ways to get software on a Mac while
bringing default security that is obvious and just works for end users that they don't
have to think about. And I don't really see that in Linux because they're too busy fighting
over snaps and flat packs. And if things should even be sandboxed in the first place, not
to even mention there's no monetization strategy for people that are creating third party applications
for the desktop. And at least people can make money on the Mac and have been doing so for
10, 20 years. And I don't think any of that stuff should just be tossed away because plasma
lets you define your monitors better. And then on the monitors angle, I will say this.
Let me see the Linux box that can currently do what my MacBook is doing because I thought
let's give this a go. The GNOME 40, it sure is a hell of a lot like the Mac now with its
horizontal layout. But let's see how the Mac handles four different resolution monitors
at different types of arrangements and rotations in a different refresh rates and some that
are HDR and some that aren't. Let's see how the Mac handles that. Well, surprise, surprise.
It handles it about a hundred times better than Linux does. And while plasma is the one
exception that handles it just fine, GNOME Shell, even GNOME Shell 40 and all the other
Linux desktop environments lose their crap every time my system reboots or goes to sleep
and all of my monitors and all of their rotations are completely screwed up, hasn't happened
once on the Mac yet. So I don't know what you're saying, Jacob, because to me it seems
like multi-monitors still have a mixed bag unless you have one precarious special setup
with a special right kind of video card and the right graphics card with the right desktop
environment. So the thing is, I think we have to acknowledge where it's weak to acknowledge
that it needs improvement. And then to appreciate the fact why people are not switching over
to it and to appreciate the fact why the advantages of the M1 with a desktop operating system
that solved all of the above issues that I just named right off the top of my head, then
I think it's worth considering these problems so that way we can fix them and make this
more appealing to people that would actually create software that makes it more usable.
But until we get all those things fixed and checked off, the Mac is still a viable platform
that has done plenty of progress and we shouldn't discount that. And by the way, that's not
even getting all the advances Windows has done recently with WSL and Windows 10 and
the improvements they've done there. I mean like more than ever, Linux really needs to
get its game up. And I think some distributions like Fedora 34 are doing a fantastic job of
it. I got a little excited there, I apologize.
You did. I would say like if I were like a true Linux advocate, I would be less concerned
with the Mac except on the like, hey, you know, M1 battery life is amazing and more
concerned with the pace at which Windows is getting good at doing the Linuxy stuff is
pretty quick. Yeah. And they seem to be partnering with Canonical and the good folks at SUSE
and basically whoever the hell will take their call. And I don't know, like we're still talking
about file systems and like I think this whole snap versus flat pack thing is a waste of
time. But that's because I have strong and well documented opinions on monetization on
desktop Linux. I don't know. I guess if you're worried about eroding desktop Linux market
share, I would be worried about Windows 10.
And you know what that whole me getting worked up on my soapbox didn't even get into is the
development options that are available and the lack of a coherent development story around
the Linux desktop, unless maybe you go to a distro like elementary OS open to is trying
to do flutter. Right. But that's a very new, very it was just announced like a month ago
for their future applications. Right. And that would be the blessed development platform.
But I, you know, can I throw in a story that we missed? Yeah. Infoworld, which not one
of my favorite sources for reasons that we can discuss a different day, has a article
on the decline of Heroku. You remember Heroku? Oh, yeah. It was a very beautiful, easy deployment
thing if you just knew getting Ruby. It caught my eye because they're now owned by Salesforce.
And I actually personally like Heroku, but things like doku exist and the pricing structure
is just a little nuts if you know how to do anything with like Docker or frankly just
run a server. So one of the co-founders, none of the founders are at Heroku anymore. Adam
Jacob writes on Twitter, Heroku is like a fallen civilization of elves, beautiful, immortal,
beloved by all who encountered it, but still a dead end. That's such a sick burn. You burned.
Now I'm waiting for the Python trolls to write me in. Isn't that kind of like Ruby? Beautiful,
but can't do half the stuff Python can do. The snake wins again. You know what? The snake
always wins. So before I completely close out on my whole rant about my concerns about
the Linux desktop, I say go check out linuxunplugged.com. I think I may have mentioned this on the show,
but I interviewed the Lutris developer and he shared his perspective on a lot of uncomfortable
issues facing Linux desktop software development still. It was an interview I was expecting
to go a different direction and that's the direction it went and I think it tells you
a lot of what people are struggling with from a developer's perspective who are trying to
write software for Linux desktop, not to even mention some of the other basics to make it
a decent workstation still. And I absolutely think if you get the right setup and if you
know what you're doing, like you buy from somebody who makes something that works or
you know how to get it all assembled, it's gonna work just fine. You're gonna have a
good experience, you're gonna have a very powerful workstation. I think all that's true,
but I don't think it's fair to say that the other platforms don't have it going on. Last
but not least, Adrian says that I too have stopped playing with my Android ROMs for quite
a while. I just used to tinker all the time, but now honestly I've been running stock Android
since the pixel line. And he says there isn't really much keeping on Android, but iOS doesn't
even have a file manager yet. So you see, geeks do care about this stuff. They do. They
do care about that nitty-ditty gritty stuff like file systems and file managers. And yes,
it does. It does have a file system and a file manager. You just can't do much with
it because it's typical Apple. It's just very broken. I'm impressed how many apps can integrate
with it, but it's not really a file browser for just like the iPad file system. No, no
it is not. System76.com. They are systems that are born to run Linux over there and
our friends had a special note they wanted me to pass along. This is my prop piece of
paper that I have today and I am just milking it. But on this piece of prop paper, I have
this supposed theoretical note that they have a few things going on. But the thing
that I thought I should let you know about is that new keyboard that's probably going
to be your new keyboard is Ni. We've talked about the System76 launch before and now we're
starting to get some real hints about the launch and what it's going to look like. It
looks like it's going to be a clean milled chassis with individually addressable RGB
LED backlights, which I think is great, hot swap sockets, and a really simple layout to
manage everything for like lighting or custom key bindings and combinations that will be
saved to firmware. Love that because that means it's going to be persistent between
different OS loads and distributions. And they're going to also ship a System76 keyboard
configurator. And of course, the design and the firmware will be open source. They're
starting to tease it right now. We don't have like exact images, but since it's all open
source, you can actually see some of the renderings up on their GitHub page. So go to System76.com
to see the progress on that. And while you're there, go check out the new Thaleo. I think
it's Mira. Mira. Yeah, this the one. That's the one, Mike. Like that thing is the perfect
sized Thaleo for me. Like if I was going to get a Thaleo, that's the one. And it does rise in
CPUs, 128 gigabytes of RAM, and they've meticulously engineered, they tell me, the cooling system
now on that thing. And they have this awesome like exploded diagram of it. I can't imagine
why they did that. It's so rad now. You should go to the go to the page of the Thaleo and
look at their exploded diagram of how they assemble it. It's modular. It's it's rad.
I mean, they really did meticulously engineer it. They've really gone all in on it. Not
to mention, it's just like one of the best looking desktop lines out there ever built.
I mean, they are handcrafted in Denver, right here in the United States, but they just look
so cool. So go to System76.com to see it all. And if you buy something, leave them a note
saying the Coda program sent you. Longtime friends of the program. And I just love working
with them because I think they have they've really nailed this. And this is a problem
that Mike and I talk about all the time. And System76 has a solution for you. It's systems
born to run Linux at System76.com.
Did you see this news that Apple admitted that it keeps iMessage off Android for competitive
reasons completely? Of course. What other? I mean, duh. OK, see, OK, OK. I thought that
might be your take. And I kind of want so I thought maybe you should take that side
of it because I think this is, man, I hate to see this because it's it's one of these
things that tricks consumers. They don't appreciate the ramifications of getting kind of locked
into the iMessage ecosystem. I don't think average users get it. And the key argument
that Apple has is that here is that simply hoarding it over would be it would make it
easier. The reason they don't want to do it. Check this out. This is like actually these
are in court filings for the epic case that came out is because it would make it easier
for parents to put kids on Android. That's they think would be the biggest loss. That
makes a ton of sense to me, right? Because iPhones are expensive and kids are stupid
and break things. Yeah, that's why they should let parents do that. Not to mention family
members. They even had something in-house going for a little while. Eddie Q said in
2013 there were plans to make iMessage for Android that would be fully cross compatible
with the iOS platform and that users of both platforms would be able to exchange messages
seamlessly with each other. That's a direct quote from Eddie Q. Then later on, in a deposition
Craig Federighi said iMessage on Android would simply serve to remove an obstacle to iPhone
families giving their kids Android phones. And then Phil Schiller in an email said when
an email wrote in said, hey, iMessage is like the number one reason I can't leave the iPhone.
Why won't you put this on Android? Phil Schiller wrote back, moving iMessage to Android will
hurt us more than it will help us. This email illustrates why. So they got Craig, Eddie
and Phil. All right, this is where Mike becomes evil. I don't understand why this is getting
the play that it's getting. Well, it's because it's them admitting to monopolistic behavior
in one sense, admitting that this creates lock in and then. How? How is it admitting
to monopolistic behavior? If you if you have a product or I guess this is a service, right?
Why would you let your chief competitor interrupt with it if that only serves to lose you customers?
I think you only could really make the argument that they should win. And if they are of such
a market size that it becomes it makes it impossible for anybody else to exist in the
market, which I don't think they are that size. Right. And there's tons of messaging
services now. And so it would be different if you couldn't SMS message an iPhone, right?
If it was like it's iMessage, like, believe it or not, the next old next machines were
like this. You could only email a fellow next user. Amazing. So they learned their lesson.
But it's I don't I don't see this as a big problem. Like I have taken a look for, you
know, because my son decided to smash my phone during FaceTiming grandma, because that's
what we do. Oh, man. And I did not get the accidental damage because that's what I do.
You self insured. Yeah, that's not that good with health insurance either. No, but that's
how you make it sound like it's not a total like financial catastrophe is, oh, no, I just
self insured. Yeah. I mean, I'm selling the iMac Pro if I can find any fool willing to
buy it. I'm actually was looking at a mirror, believe it or not. One of my chief reasons
for being on iMessage is kind of gone. Right. But I was not impressed. Even I was that the
Samsung 21 or something that the Verizon guy was like drooling over. I was like, oh, but
what does it get me with the iPhone? It's like it's two hundred dollars cheaper. I said,
ah, he said, but if you get your if you're getting a plan, then they're both like the
same price. And that's if you don't even care about the privacy ramifications of like having
all of your stuff backed up to Google servers versus Apple servers. All right. And I do
have like like concerns about that because I'm even strongly considering every quarter
moving my business off of Google. Right. It's just that sort of you want to talk about lock
in. That's pain that Google AppSauce. Is that what you're talking about? That Google really
Google Drive. Yeah. Yeah. That's yeah. I'm hooked on. I'm hooked on the mail. I'm hooked
on it, man. Yeah. It's that's that's tough. So I don't know. I mean, what's your angle
on this? Because I think this is like the biggest no story ever. I mean, there's absolutely
a part of me that would love it to just be like a like an open spec. If they would have
open sourced FaceTime like WebOS. Well, remember when Jobs is up on stage and he introduced
FaceTime and he said and tomorrow we're going to the standards bodies and we're going to
open source it. And then, of course, that never happened. Apple got sued. Apple had
to rearchitect FaceTime. And I just I imagine this virtual parallel alternative, whatever
you'll have it reality where Apple actually followed through. And a lot of the stuff like
iMessage and FaceTime and AirPlay is all open source standards that anybody could implement.
And so the Apple ecosystem would just go so much further beyond just iOS devices and Apple
devices. But that reality never panned out. And you're right. I can't come up with a good
justification as to why they should give their competitors something that makes their platform
special. And I think if Google had played their cards right, they would absolutely love
to be in the same position that Apple is with iMessage. I don't think they'd do anything
differently themselves. And now because they're in the underdog position, they'll push for
standards like RCS and perhaps improve the situation for people that aren't on iMessage
that are communicating with iMessage people. Because it sucks. You know, I'm in a couple
of family group chats and the Android users stink the chat up. They really do. It's like
they don't support tap back for just quick replies to comments. They often embed images
weird. They don't support the same reply inline stuff that iMessage does. They crap up the
chat. It's always like, oh, yep. There's cousin Jimmy using the Android device. Messing up
the whole group chat now. So it'd be nice if I didn't have that experience, but I cannot
come up with the compelling argument with the market realities that we have in the market
shares realities that we have as to why Apple should.
I almost feel like the sexier story to come so far of the epic IBM. Oh, my God. Oh, Apple
would not like that. The epic Apple lawsuit is just how premeditated Apple is at controlling
their app server, which I guess we knew. Yeah. But what I didn't know is how long Epic was
planning to do what they did. Yeah. So that's the other side of this that's come out, is
that Epic was playing a bit of a long game themselves and even even hired a firm. Yeah.
Yeah. So according to Apple, Epic hired a PR firm in 2019 to work a media strategy called
Project Liberty aimed at portraying Apple as the bad guy, which is probably where that
video that came from that that 1984 mocking video that they had just right away. Yeah.
And that they were preparing for this all along and that they knew this was they were
going to run a risk with Apple and that they were just kind of getting their ducks in a
line. And this is some of their example that it's premeditated. And that's where we're
at right now. Right. Epic doesn't have to prove that Apple's a monopoly. Epic just has
to make a case that Apple has monopoly like behavior. And it's a pattern of behavior that
would suggest that just like Apple is going to try to make the case that Epic had a pattern
of behavior of preparing for this about specifically trying to violate Apple's policies. And Apple
actually kind of has a solid argument here. First of all, they point out that Epic Games
earned more than 700 million dollars in revenue from the iOS app store and that Fortnite is
distributed on other platforms that take even more commission than they do, that have the
same limitations that the iOS app store does in terms of having your own built in app store.
And they say they can't really be a monopoly like Epic is calling them because they're
not a leader in the gaming market. They really are not super strong in gaming. And so they're
not acting like a monopoly in the games, the gaming market, because they're simply not
one. They wish they were more established in the gaming market. They say Epic's monopoly
maintenance claim is premised on the notion that the antitrust laws preclude Apple from
imposing conditions on license use of its intellectual property and impose on Apple
a duty to deal with Epic on the terms of preferred by Epic to the determined of other developers
and consumers alike. I don't know if you were going to make a call on this one right now,
which way would you call it, Apple or Epic?
Who I think is going to win. Mm hmm. Apple. I do too. I listened in on one of the live
streams of the court preparing to hear the in person trials and they were doing this
test pilot of live streaming these court sessions to the public because of Covid. You couldn't
go to the courthouse to witness them if you wanted to. So they were live streaming them
on YouTube and I and about 20 other people were watching this and and Apple's lawyers
really had their together and they really knew how to talk to the judge with respect
and Epic's lawyers seemed a little sloppy. They had to catch themselves like a couple
of times, didn't refer to the judge properly. But additionally, Apple's lawyers and legal
team were pushing to do this in person in court and Epic's legal team had been pushing
to do it all remote over Zoom and Apple made this case for why why that would be more advantageous
to Epic and I think the judge went with it and the judge ruled that they have to do these
in person in the court. They can have some remote testimony over video if need be, but
they're going to proceed with the in person trial and just listening to like that planning
session for the court case, it really felt like Apple was very confident.
I mean, we're not lawyers, right? But Apple doesn't have to prove anything, right? Apple
can say Epic has to prove that they're a monopoly, which they're really not. By the way, it's
defined right. Listen to Kara Swisher if you ever want a detailed explanation as to why
that is or any of the really the verge or any place like that. And the other thing is
Apple does have a contract with every developer, right? That's the developer agreement, which
Epic was very obviously in breach of. So what Epic has to say is, yes, we breached this
contract, but the contract was illegal because they're a monopoly. Well, that's a big lift.
I mean, I could see a world where for however much money Epic screwed them out of in terms
of the 30% cut or whatever number the cut should have been because I'm not sure if Epic
is at 30 or 15%. Epic may end up paying them damages back, right? It seems like like both
things are true, right? Apple is going to face some sort of regulation for the app store
and it's just going to be industry wide, but they're also going to defeat Epic in this
case. So also, I think it's worth remembering that Google also kicked Fortnite out for doing
these actions. So it's complicated for Epic in that regard. And they're only choosing
to go after Apple because I think that's the case they can win. But Google kind of did
Apple a favor by going along with Apple and kicking them out afterwards. And I think what
regulation does come down, it's going to be a much lighter hand than it would have been
a couple of years ago. And Apple is already making the argument that look, we've done
nothing but lower the rates in the app store. We've only lowered the price. And now developers
that make less than a million dollars have even gotten a bigger break, which is, by the
way, they'll say the majority of developers in the app store.
And if you if you listen to that interview with Kara Swisher and Tim Cook, he went out
of his way to say, I'd even let Parler back in, which, you know, I'm sure he's no fan
of Parler, right? But which is not going to happen. Yeah. Well, no, but why? He's defending
his flank to say we don't pick and choose based on whether we like the people, right?
It's we have more terms. You follow our terms. You can be in our store. Mazel tov. There you
go. If you're really curious about this or if you're like a little anti Apple, read the
emails that were disclosed from the epic side about them plotting this entire campaign.
They do not come out, come off as freedom fighters here.
OK, now let's hit the pause button and alternate reality mode here for a second. But think
about all of the shit we have bitched about when it comes to the app store and all of
the clear abuses of power that Apple has clearly flexed over the years when it comes to independent
developers, developers, especially even you. Wouldn't it kind of be nice for somebody to
come along and punch him in the nose and get them to clean this act up and maybe even make
it possible? Like, imagine just for a moment, Mike, for just a moment, if even one one outcome
of this is that Apple was mandated to allow third party payment processing so you could
use Stripe or something for subscriptions or whatever, it would be better for developers
and users around the world. Yeah, I mean, there's going to be they're not going to.
I it's not going to happen. I mean, this alternative reality, though, it's not good. I feel like
I feel like that's the right. But that's the red line for them. You know, like my my position
on all of this apps or stuff has mellowed out quite a bit, which is ironic because I
think other people have become more militant as I'm kind of like, well, well, I think what
it is is you have resigned yourself to the reality while others are now getting their
livelihood is now being endangered. And so now they're making a noise where I think DHH
is just like utter shock with how the App Store operates was. Yeah. Amazing. Right.
Well, they came for you first because honestly, like, you know, if they go for somebody like
DHH, that's going to get a lot more attention. But they come for you like we bitch about
it here on the podcast. Right. But they they still get away with it. But there are there
are tens of thousands, if not hundreds of thousands of me, like, you know, relatively
small software companies that I mean, I should be fair. I currently do not sell any unless
I'm maybe publishing like the Fleet Week app for for the Navy. So but I do not sell any
of my own apps on the on the App Store right now. I'm not saying I never would, but we
talked about this a million times. I don't want to rehash it too much, but I constantly
have this problem where I look at my iPad Pro, I'm like, this is an incredible device
that I would love to build software for. But then I look at the investment that would be
required. And I read the, you know, the annually updated Apple developer, you know, not just
the human interface guidelines, but the actual rules. And there's always like one or two
that I'm like, is this close? And there's it's, it's getting better, right? They're
liberalizing some where you can like ask them questions to a point. But it's it's it's a
risk to invest all this capital and energy into developing something on a platform where
they can just say no, you nailed it. That's exactly what the situation is. And so that's
why I just think like, imagine a world where third party payment or third party apps, some
sort of sideloading, like like it is on the Mac with gatekeeper, you could still have
where developers, they what's it called? What's it called on the Mac when you sign it? Notarization?
Yeah, no, yeah. Why couldn't they just use the notarization system that they have for
the Mac on the iPhone? Obviously, not by default, right? They're trying to get a cut, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah, I just I know we should leave alternate reality world because
it's just it's just a waste of energy. But I acknowledge that I think Apple's gonna win
this thing. And I think Apple has the stronger case. And I think epic is from all all evidence
we can see at this point in the public is likely in the wrong here. They knew the rules.
But man, man, oh, man, if I could just have them win this so that we some of these things
could be improved. I think it would address the primary issues people really have with
the iOS platform. Well, the stronger case and where I think we'll actually see some
sort of regulation and then we should jump off of this is basically the Spotify case.
Oh, yeah. Right. And Apple's already backed down quite a bit on that because Apple is
both the platform vendor and a direct application competitor. Apple does not make nor please
should you try any video games, right? So they are not, you know, they're just as far
as epic is concerned, they are indeed a store. And if you know anything about how selling
software used to work, the deal with Apple is far better.
Data dog.com slash coder radio. Now let's let's talk about data dog. This is a tool
you should be using to help visualize your infrastructure analyze code level performance
across your entire environment and troubleshoot issues faster than ever with data talk and
communicate them with their beautiful dashboards. Go look at their dashboards, go look at them.
Data dog.com slash Coder Radio just to go see these things. And data dog has this feature
called continuous profiler. It automatically collects all the metrics from all the places
your applications, your servers, your servers in production, your servers and testing like
you can make it all clear and delineated. And then you can analyze data and results
quickly with minimal overhead and get a unified picture of your environment by correlating
code performance metrics with other monitoring data across your entire infrastructure in
these real time dashboards. They have tightly integrated plugins for other applications
or APIs that you can use and tracing and log management that makes it really easy to parse
through all this stuff and get the information in the log super quick. And then you bring
that continuous profiler in. It's all in one platform, you bring it all together and enables
you to pinpoint the root cause of issues faster than ever. Save time, save money and communicate
better and try Datadog's products for free for 14 days by visiting datadog.com slash
Coder Radio. And for a limited time, if you start a trial and create one dashboard, you'll
get a free Datadog t-shirt, free swag. You just got to go to datadog.com slash Coder
Radio.
What do you think about talking a little history here on the show? You know, COBOL, we all
know COBOL, the common business oriented language. It's been around since 1959 in one form or
another, so clearly older than I. And it's actually just recently got a little bit of
love from IBM. IBM has released version 1.1 of their COBOL suite of tools for Linux and
the x86 environment. And they talk about like maintaining interoperability between some
of their large mainframe platforms to legacy software never dies. It never dies. In fact,
this set me down a whole rabbit hole. I was actually kind of really getting into this
for a bit because, you know, COBOL, it runs so much, almost like still almost all of the
major ATM networks run COBOL. Tons of government systems still run COBOL. For you as news for
a little while, a lot of the COVID-19 cases and deaths and positives and negatives and
all of that is being tallied on systems where the code is written in COBOL today. Oh, yes.
It's still getting actively used, right? And it just blows my mind that this thing's been
around since 59 and is still you can still get jobs for it. And it's it's just been recently
updated and ported to Linux for the x86 environment and with with new features added just like
last week. Just nuts. I mean, I'm pretty sure the Florida unemployment systems written in
COBOL because they famously couldn't find vendors to to help them. Maybe it was for
them. But well, so this is the trick now, right? Is it's becoming it's becoming a lack
of developers to fulfill IBM's long, long promise of like these these large systems
like the system 360 that launched in 1964. IBM pitched it as a promise of if you develop
software for this today in 1964, you will run it in 40 years. And they did actually
deliver on that. I found this awesome clip that IBM made a few years ago, I think like
back in 2004, even they made this this hilarious, cheesy video about how awesome how awesome
their mainframes are for inclusion into the Computer History Museum. And I just grabbed
like a moment of it for us.
You know, the 360 and the mainframe didn't just revolutionize the IT industry. With the
360, the modern software era was born. You didn't have package software before the 360.
Our computers enabled NASA to land the man on the moon in 1969. The modern financial
services industry was built around the mainframe. And even today's airline reservation systems
have antecedents going all the way back to the 1960s.
We've done a lot of things based on 360 technology. Some of the programs we originally created
back in 65 are still running today.
The mainframe is here to stay. It's a technology we all grew up with and we know we're comfortable
with. If I look at all the different technologies out there and what we can achieve and what
we have achieved on the mainframe, it's the most reliable technology that we have today.
Yeah, it's here to stay.
Here to stay.
That was pretty good. And then I got one more really short one. This is IBM's technology
chief back in 2004 on the 40th anniversary of the launch of the IBM System 360, talking
about how long-term compatibility was a key promise of what IBM was delivering. And of
course they delivered some of that using, of course, Coolball.
As I look back on those days, while the making of a revolutionary product was one thing,
what was huge was that System 360 was a platform for genuine innovation. It was a defining
moment in the information technology industry. You could say that the System 360 was innovating
by anticipating the future, an information technology platform that would be compatible
with systems yet to come. IBM made the promise then of computing that's always there, computing
that offers what our industry has affectionately come to call the illities, availability, scalability,
adaptability, flexibility, manageability. And the System 360 family was the foundation
of those promises, promises IBM still extends today.
If they can find developers for it. So maybe it's time to go write Cobalt, kids, because
they're still looking for people to write applications.
It gives me hope.
We have one last email, but maybe we should save this for the Coderly.
Let's save it.
Bonus Coderly email. That'd be kind of fun. We haven't done an email in the Coderly before.
So that is recorded every quarter and we release that for our members. It's a way to support
the show. We have a membership program at CoderQA.co and you become a member and you
support the show. You get a limited ad feed as a thank you and that Coderly report. Did
I say that right? Anyways, we're recording one very soon, very, very soon. So it'll be
in your members feed in just a few short days. So if you're not a member yet, you can sign
up now at CoderQA.co and then you'll get that when we release it and we thank everybody
who is a member.
Go get yourself some Mike on Twitter. He's at Dumanuco and his company's at the Mad
Botter Inc over there. Anything you want to plug this week, Mr. Dominic?
No, if you need any Python or dare I say Objective-C development done, let me know.
There you go. Nice. I'm at Chris Lass on the Twitter. The podcast network is at Jupiter
Signal and the show itself is at Coder Radio Show. Links to some of the things we talked
about today and that entire video for that IBM mainframe party at the Computer History
Museum. That's linked in the show notes too. That's at Coder.show slash 409. You also find
our contact form over there as well as our RSS feed. And I'd encourage you, I'd personally
like to invite you to join us to the, to the live stream at the Coder happy hour, the live
stream, Coder happy hour live stream, Monday 5 PM, 8 PM Pacific at jblive.tv. Did you get
it? It's a live stream and you're invited. It's the Coder happy hour live stream. I've
got to get it right. And I would like you to be there. It's the Coder radio happy hour
live stream. I got it. Now you got to go cause I worked so hard for it or, or just download.
See you next week.