This is KOTORadio, episode 419 for June 23rd, 2021.
Hey good looking, welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and business of software development and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by a Cloud Guru.
A Cloud Guru has the Cloud Playground, Azure, AWS, and Google Cloud on their sandboxes and
credit card.
Not yours.
Get certified.
Get hired.
Get learning at acloudguru.com.
My name is Chris, and battling technical issues so he can podcast, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
Hello.
Man, what a week, right?
Like I'm losing my voice.
You're fighting tech demons.
Oh yeah.
It's not even the half of it.
It's just the last 15 minutes.
This was like crazy.
The M1 failed me.
Yeah.
So what started out as just a quick journey to install a program to capture audio from
an audio device turned into you like booting into recovery environments?
What happened?
Well, first of all, I guess we have to do a little inside baseball for Mac here.
After that, Piezo made by Rogameba, that was a tongue twister, requires a kernel extension
to directly record audio because many, many things in Mac OS require kernel extensions
that you might not think should.
So that used to be just a matter of going into security preferences and enabling it.
Now you have to reboot into a recovery mode, enable it there.
It took a total of four reboots to get this working and it blew away my desktop settings
of all my files organized and my background.
No.
Yep.
God knows what's going to happen after the show when I decide to try to use any of the
Linuxy, Unixy stuff in homebrew.
You think it just reset the PRAM or whatever the hell they call it?
It reset something.
Wow.
That sucks.
Well, imagine a typical user who maybe doesn't even know what a kernel extension is, is trying
to install this software and gets a prompt, hey, you got to reboot and go into a recovery
environment.
And then when you booted back up, it was blocked initially.
It was blocked.
Yeah.
So, and it kept having to reboot to unblock it.
It's just too much protection.
They're turning it into an iPhone.
Ooh, that's a bold statement.
I think they are.
Well, you know, Phil Schiller did say on the stand in the Epic trial that they consider
the openness and I think security vulnerabilities on Mac OS to be unacceptable.
Sounds like they're right on their way of solving it and working out Rogue Amoeba, which
Rogue Amoeba is one of the best software creators on the desktop for any platform.
I mean, they just make incredible software in the audio realm.
I respect that a lot.
And if I were ever going to have a Mac, I would have the Rogue Amoeba apps on there.
They'd have to work.
I'd have to go through all of that, I guess.
What a pain in the neck.
Wait a minute.
Now my desktop background is just, hold on, real time update.
It's just the color blue.
Yet on the other workspace, it's the default, whatever, for whatever version of Mac, I think
I'm on Mojave or something.
Doesn't really generally manifest itself.
But my previous experience with Mac OS when I was doing Hackintosh is it felt like a bit
of a house of cards and you pull out one thing and a surprising amount of things just quit
working.
Yeah.
And you're in a very specific, very defined environment and situation.
Something's super not right here.
Oh well, we can move on.
You're going to have fun after the show.
Yeah, this is wrong.
Unrelated to this, you also picked yourself up a new Thaleo.
I'm extremely jealous because I've been wanting one so bad, but I just can't get over the
GPU prices right now.
Yeah, the GPU prices are nuts.
I didn't go super hard on the GPU.
But yeah, I don't have it yet though.
I guess production's taking a bit longer than I thought it would.
So I will let you know once I have it.
You're a unique individual in that I can ask, on average, when you buy a Thaleo, Mike, how
often does it take to ship?
Because I've never bought one and you've bought several.
Well, that's true because I do those contests, it's always a Thaleo as a prize.
Usually a couple of business days.
Whoa, that's way faster than I expected.
Yeah, I think it depends on what configs.
I noticed that the lower end ones tend to ship faster.
Oh, sure.
Maybe they have the parts in stock already and stuff.
Well, maybe.
I also wonder if they don't like pre-configure a bunch of those because probably they're
high seller.
Yeah, and they're not a huge cost.
Because I did go up to the 12 gig NVIDIA GPU in this one.
I think when the GPU prices come back down, I'm going to be really tempted.
We'll see.
Yeah, well, I'll do my decibel readings on it.
So that's how I am about the background noise.
Yeah, I'll be really interested to know how that is, how that stacks up now.
Well, I'm going to be out at System76 in August.
I'm looking forward to that.
I'm heading out to Denver and also Salt Lake City.
We're going to do meetups at both locations, August 7th in Salt Lake City and August 20th
in Denver.
We'll have all the details at meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
And if you're interested in going to a Denver meetup or a Salt Lake City meetup, please
do.
And our friends at Linode are on board with this trip, and not only are they making the
trip possible, but they're going to help us produce some exclusive content during the
road trip that will feature team interviews, the people we go and see.
I'm hoping to get a little bit of the inside story on the creation of the launch keyboard
while we're there, and we'll have an episode on that as well.
And I'll do a few coders live from the road.
So if you're a Coder Radio audience member in those areas, or if you can make it there,
come see us.
Again, August 7th, Salt Lake City, August 20th in Denver, meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
I'm really looking forward to it.
It's been a long time.
And the last event I went to really stunk.
It was like almost two years ago, and I regretted going to it while I was there.
It gave me just this horrible, horrible feeling about the future of cybersecurity.
And then that was it.
Then it was lockdown time.
So yeah, it's going to be great to see people.
And I'm getting the RV ready right now, which is not in great shape because my slides broken
and all that.
But working on that at the moment to try to get it ready, and then we're going to load
up and we're going to do a meetup in Denver.
Of course, Mr. Dominic, you are welcome as well.
Everybody's welcome.
Everybody.
I know not everybody can because everybody's got jobs and stuff they got to do, but we're
opening it up to everybody who might be able to make it out.
You know what?
You know, I love System76.
The problem is if I show up in Denver, do I have to bring an extra carry on for another
staleo, a few launch keyboards under my shirt?
Yeah.
Yeah, I know.
That's why I think some of us are going to drive so we can just load up our trunks, you
know.
I'm from Florida.
I just can't even imagine how far that is.
Yeah, I know, right?
Hey, guess what I have right here?
I have a box.
What's in the box?
Let's see.
Stand by, sir.
I'm going to open it up right now here on the show.
It is.
It's a big box, too.
It's heavy.
It's a big box filled with the Coder Robes.
I got a whole batch of them right here.
Yep.
Oh, yeah.
I got mine yesterday.
Oh, did you?
Yes.
Yes, I did.
I took it.
I put a picture on Twitter.
I didn't see it.
I failed in my stocking.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, man.
Turned out great.
Oh, look at that.
I got a whole batch of them here.
One's for Wes.
Going to give him a Coder.
So when you saw people were sending in their Coder Rope pictures.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's great.
People should keep doing that.
They're not all done yet.
So if you haven't got your Coder yet, there is probably going to be another several week
delay.
I apologize.
But then the next batch and probably the final batch will ship.
And it really is just down to supplies.
We've had a lot of people ask us to do another run.
I will consider it when the whole global supply shortage is over.
You didn't have fun?
Oh, my gosh.
And the threat on this is particular, too.
So it just took them forever.
And so maybe in the fall.
I don't know.
But boy, did it turn out, huh?
It's great.
Woo-Wee.
It really is.
C-C-C-Coder.
Yep.
One size fits all, Tali with pockets.
Classic.
You can wear it.
It's an all day wear.
It's the Coder.
I'm really happy with that.
I'm very, very pleased.
It was nice.
It was nice to see that go out.
God damn it.
It blew away my Xcode tool chain, too.
No way, man.
How can this happen?
All the command line tools are gone.
It reset my terminal.
What did it revert?
Did it revert to some image?
I think it reverted all the utility stuff to base settings.
Yeah, I typed git and it's literally trying to install git.
It's telling me to run Xcode select.
It sounds like it reverted back to, because you know, the system partition stuff's read
only.
Sounds like it reverted back or something.
So it just wiped out everything but user land?
Yeah, sounds like it, doesn't it?
Yeah, obviously.
That explains the settings being weird, too.
Wow.
I deleted the directory under photos, under pictures with all my custom backgrounds.
What the hell?
And it's the same user account, right?
Yeah, I only have one user account on this machine.
You know what's not crazy and unreliable, though?
What's that?
The coder.
Yeah, that's true.
And finally, it's just slow.
Just real slow.
It's just slow.
But a lot of people wrote in and said that the material is higher quality than they expected
and it was worth the wait.
And that's what I wanted to hear.
Rick wants your reaction, maybe my reaction, too, to this.
He writes in, he says, guys, Sir Tim Berners-Lee is launching an NFT for the original Objective-C
source code he used to create the World Wide Web.
I'd love to know your thoughts on this.
What do you think?
It's Objective-C. I love it.
Honestly, if you had the money, would you buy it?
Absolutely.
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah.
I also hate this, by the way.
I do hate this.
I hate this deeply.
I hate it.
Yeah.
But that said, like if Linus Torvalds wanted to make an NFT out of his original Linux commit
or something.
How about an NFT of him throwing in video with a finger?
Yeah.
I don't know.
I think these, I'd actually just rather have a printed version with him with his signature
on it than an NFT though.
Knowing you would have to be on like a nice canvas made only of the finest.
Right.
That'd be great with a sapphire glass frame.
Jeez, man.
I just don't like where this is going.
Where does it end?
I wonder.
And it's not like it's the only copy.
I hear people that try to make the art analogy, but I have a hard time with it.
And I'm not really Mr. Anti-Crypto coin and stuff.
I think Bitcoin gets a bad rap.
I think people that give Bitcoin a hard time for its environmental impact haven't done
any research and don't know what they're talking about.
And they couldn't tell you the environmental impact of everybody switching to electric
cars and charging Teslas in their homes.
And if that takes any more power than a Bitcoin, nobody knows.
And so I think Bitcoin gets a hard rap.
I'm not anti any of this kind of stuff.
I think it's worth exploring.
But something about this NFT stuff where you're selling something that you can make
endless copies of doesn't feel like legitimate and fair to the purchaser.
It's weird because you just described like the people who say they shouldn't have to
pay for software.
Right.
Well, you just made their argument.
It's true.
Well, a topic that Jimmy wanted to write in on is touching on our Linux dying as a desktop
OS conversation.
He says, my dearest sexy coder host, as someone who's run Linux since the late 90s, this has
been something on my mind for the last five years or so.
It seems to me, even as much as Linux has caught up to the other big OSes in terms of
functionality and applications, we're now back in the same place we were about 20 years
ago.
By this, I mean the mobile and their general ecosystems, even with really cool projects
like KDE Connect and where KDE and GNOME are taking their desktops, we're still over a
decade behind.
We're not even playing the same game, let alone the ballpark.
When you're in your 30s with kids, with things in your house like tablets, TVs and cars and
lady tubes all connected and syncing, not even to mention an ever-growing connected
outside world, well, Linux can sometimes feel like a bit of a hindrance, something that
needs to be tweaked constantly to get some of the basic features I've mentioned even
half working.
Not only is that annoying, but then when you're busy and you just want things to work, it's
going to be more of an issue.
We also have the problem that more and more of us, as time goes on, will start to use
our phones for payments, door access and even ID cards.
Linux is out on all of that.
Take that along with Windows now getting better for developers than ever, Apple doing their
thing and automation with servers in the cloud, serverless and containerization.
It's hard to see how Linux is going to stay relevant for most people going into the future.
Only a niche few who are working on the core technology behind the scenes and being paid
by large corporations, assuming fuchsia doesn't get too popular.
It makes me sad to think about this, but another way to look at it is look how far this little
free and open source community and project actually went.
From a small nerdy project, often mocked for being only for hobbyists, to powering the
entire internet and complete infrastructure of every large service billions of people
rely on day-to-day.
Hell, even Windows has it baked in now.
Who would have imagined that in 2008 while tweaking their compass settings on Ubuntu
Hardy Heron?
Linux beat all others and ultimately won.
So if the day comes in the next decade where I have to pour one out for my homie tux, I'll
do it with a smile, fond and proud memories.
I don't think you're ever going to be pouring one out for your homie tux though.
I agree.
I mean, you still have people that are listening to records.
Like, I'm just saying some stuff never dies, but this is going to have, it's going to still,
it will, I think probably for as long as you and I draw breath, there will be Linux servers.
And as long as there are large amounts of Linux servers, won't there always be devs
and sysadmins who want to use what they're running on the server on their desktop for
what they're maybe building for the server?
Yeah, I would go even further.
I think it's going to be as long as you and I draw breath and our grandkids draw breath.
Yeah, it's one of those entrenched forever kind of technologies.
And because of the licensing, they can just perpetually keep it going.
So it's going to be one of those things that just keeps on going.
Like, you know, they stretch out commercial operating systems, you ain't seen nothing
yet.
They just keep rolling, baby.
And talk about this often because it often is perceived as an elitist attitude.
But I actually don't even agree with the premise that if only nerds like developers and sysadmins
and geeks use Linux, I don't buy the premise that's a bad thing.
I think the operating system is particularly good at catering to those particular niches.
And why not build a system that just super delivers to that user base while the commercial
platforms focus on the mythical new user constantly?
I think it's actually a very reasonable place for desktop Linux to land.
And that doesn't mean that it needs to have some cloud syncing service.
It just means that it needs to work with whatever solution I, as a geek, build for myself.
Yeah, I would even take it a step further that the mythical new user is probably going
to increasingly be a tablet or more likely phone user.
Yeah, or maybe Chromebook.
But yeah.
Yeah.
And I know it's been an education, but then, you know, I've never been on the Chromebook
train.
Yep.
All right.
Yeah.
So one more on this topic, then we'll move on.
Tim writes in with a bulletproof Linux recipe.
I use an Intel NUC as my desktop and a Dell XPS as my laptop running for door.
They both have integrated Intel graphics and nothing weird in them.
And you know they're always going to work.
For gaming, I have an Xbox.
For my wife, who isn't really into computers, she uses an iPad.
I used to be really big into Windows and PC gaming, but honestly, Windows 10 wore me down.
Operating systems that make decisions for me on my behalf, that's just a little bit
too much for me.
And I'm never going to go back.
Say what you will, but staying on the rails and just not doing anything out of the ordinary
is all it really takes to use desktop Linux.
Upgrade only when you have time and maintain an Ansible playbook to make it easy.
I love that.
Just all you got to do.
Just learn Ansible.
I said, but that's how you do survive and you won't be tempted to use an operating system
that needs an internet connection to search for a list of locally installed applications.
I kind of agree with Tim to a degree, though.
If your workload allows and you kind of just use Linux on rails, like a System76 system
or like my ThinkPad X1 Carbon that came with Fedora or the Dell XPS developer line, they
are going to work every time you load Linux on that thing.
And they work really, really reliably.
But that is a large user base and it's a very viable customer base.
But it also doesn't work for folks that maybe need to do machine learning and they have
to push their video driver forward and their kernel driver forward or people that are doing
media production.
It also doesn't work for people that are doing development that targets upcoming Linux platforms
like maybe the next version of RHEL.
They can't really ride those rails.
So there are use cases where you need to use Linux, but you can't necessarily use it on
rails like Tim suggests.
But he makes a good point, I thought.
Are you suggesting the Mac-ification of Linux?
In a way it is, right?
I think the developer line, the XPS developer line feels the most like that, in my opinion.
Well, and then some of the stuff you mentioned, System76, that's kind of their whole pitch,
right?
They made a big push, at least last year.
Yeah, and I think with Pop in a way, they're kind of building that, but more oriented at
power users.
Because Pop doesn't feel like they're watering it down.
They're doing tiling window manager and keyboard combinations.
Right.
With Pop, they assume you know what you're doing.
With the current Mac OS, they break your machine when you try to record audio.
Lino.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in credit on your new account, and of course you support the show.
It tells Linode, hey, thanks for making the Coder Radio program possible.
Linode is the largest independent cloud computing provider.
No matter what skill level you're at or what technology stack you prefer to use, they're
going to help your ideas come to life on the web.
And their boxes are screaming fast.
A lot of times when people are trying them out for the first time and they send me feedback,
that's number one.
It's faster than I expected.
Linode really knows what they're doing.
They've built out a network of 11 data centers.
They are their own ISP.
They've done super fast native SSDs for each hypervisor, 40 gigabit connections coming
into the machines, and then they wrap it all up with a beautiful, simple dashboard that
doesn't get in your way, but lets you get access to the power features where it makes
sense.
I mean, you can even do your own custom images on Linode.
So if you've got a stack that you want to build and then just deploy that image, they're
going to accommodate that.
They have S3 compatible object storage.
And I point this out because you can do really economical front end Linodes that are using
the S3 object storage as their back end file storage, and you don't have to sit there and
worry about allocating the right storage to that Linode.
It all just works.
And then, of course, anything that's S3 compatible, you can use there.
That includes even just mounting file systems.
Linode also features things like cloud firewalls so you can protect your machines at the network
level and prevent that traffic from banging on your door.
And then when you just want to get started quick, Linode has those one click application
deployments.
I did that recently just for a quick Docker stack as a way to just get an application
up and running and test it.
I'm really grateful for that kind of stuff because if you're working with that tooling,
you get a Linode deployed in like, I don't know, 25 seconds.
It's just really just so quick.
The way I do it with my Linode too is I already have my SSH keys uploaded.
So when I'm deploying a new Linode, I just check the boxes, yeah, attach my SSH keys
to that Linode.
And so they spin it up, and I just SSH into it, and I'm in.
It's so, so great.
And then the Docker stuff was already installed with this particular one click that I did.
So it was just a matter of putting together a Docker compose file and turning the application
on, and I was off and running.
So, so quick, so easy, and then it's really fast.
And I picked the Texas data center, so that would be right in the middle of everybody
that'd be working on the box.
So go get that $100 credit so you can really see what I'm talking about here.
Just a lot to take in.
And so I think $100 really lets you soak it all up, gives you an opportunity to learn,
see what they do for themselves.
So that's why you gotta go check it out by going to linode.com slash coder.
Get $100 in credit on your new Linode account and try them out, linode.com slash coder.
What a week.
New York Times ran a hit piece on Google's CEO saying that he has paralyzing indecision
that locks Google up, and they got a bunch of VPs to go off the record and on the record
to just crap all over him.
One Google executive who departed in February said, if I had to summarize it, I would say
the signal to noise ratio is what wore me down.
Since 2020, 36 Google vice presidents have left the company, and some of them are getting
vocal about why.
Attempting challenges, they are way too risk averse.
Several Google executives told the New York Times that the company is suffering from all
kinds of issues that are related to their size now, including this paralyzing bureaucracy
that seems to really kind of slow down at the top, and a bias, they say, towards inaction,
and a fixation by the leadership on the public perception of the company.
And they say Sundar Pichai has to go.
I don't really know that many regular people who aren't like super-duper tech nerds, really
ever one had the love affair with Google that I think particularly folks like the open source
community definitely did.
So like when I talk to regular people, you know, the normies, if there's a tech company
that they hate, it's almost always Facebook.
Yes, right.
And they're like happy to not spend as much money as they would on an iPhone on a mid-range
Samsung.
Yeah, yeah.
They're proud of their...
Right, I mean, when I talk to tech people, like it's like, you know, the other developers
I know, it's weird because like I kind of always had a little bit of ire towards Google,
but that was me banging my people should pay for software drum.
Right.
They're dumping on the market.
But I don't think that's what this is about.
I don't know, right?
There was the whole Google tried to get a government, the military contract thing, and
then they have like a worker strike or something.
Yeah, they had a walk, they had a big walkout.
It doesn't read like the typical Google criticism.
What this reads to me as is a bunch of hotshot VPs who had the next brilliant product idea
to take on Company X pitched it, Google didn't act on it, and then Company X came to market.
Like the story that I saw bubble up in the Google ecosphere before this one is that Google
internally has been working on an AirTags competitor, and there's people internally
that are salty that they didn't get it out before Apple got AirTags out, and now they
feel like they're going to look like a MeToo brand when they release their tracker.
And I think that might have been maybe the impetus for somebody to reach out to the New
York Times, or completely alternatively, this entire thing is a brilliant PR piece by a
firm that is really earning their dollar right now, because my read on this is good.
I think this is great news.
The fact that Sundar Pichai takes a while to make a decision as a leader at Google,
thank God, thank God.
And the other part this story touches on is that people are salty they didn't buy Shopify.
Good.
I'm glad Google didn't buy Shopify.
Like when you look at this from a market strategy standpoint right now, there's a lot of heat
coming down from different governments about antitrust.
So maybe having somebody at the helm of the world's most scary data collector that is
cautious and thinking about things and taking his time to make a decision, maybe that's
a good thing.
When I read this, I think that's exactly what I want Google's CEO doing is thinking long
and hard about the decisions and industry moves that they make.
I think this in a way is almost like a PR piece for Google to twist the way the regulators
are going to look at Google.
I'm not saying that's what it is, but it's so good for that that it almost could be.
I love it, so you think there's some VP covetching to the New York Times being like, damn this
Sundar guy, he's not being as rapacious a capitalist as I would.
Well, I mean, yeah, I think it's in a way I'm glad.
I agree that for Google maybe it would be better if he was being a little more ruthless.
They probably should have snapped up Shopify.
They could be a little more dynamic, they could be a little more aggressive, and they
would probably be doing even better.
But dude, Alphabet itself is worth like around $1.6 trillion right now, so maybe they're
not doing it wrong.
You know, Wes in the chat room makes a good point.
There is some rings of truth in there, that Google does seem to lack focus, that their
decisions are slow, and then when they do make a decision, it's generally reactionary
to the market.
Those are all true.
I mean, there's a connected story going on basically in all the press right now of all
the big tech companies are fighting like hell to prevent this regulation.
Yeah, when there's been like in the US, there's been like five different proposals on how
they could break these big tech companies up for antitrust.
The EU's got stuff in the works.
They're getting surrounded.
If you're any of these other tech CEOs, you've just got to hate Zuckerberg the most because
he really brought this down on them.
Yeah, you're right.
Right, well, at the Facebook election, route Cambridge Analytica, the politicians would
not be, it seems weird to say, but not so long ago, the tech companies were like the
great, you know, the great hope, right?
The darlings.
Right.
America's best industry.
You know, this is the future.
We're going to have all these new and they remember biotech was going to be the next
thing.
Mm hmm.
And, you know, autonomous automation was going to be like a good thing.
Now you say you do automation.
You're like, oh, so you're trying to put my uncle out of a job.
Right?
It's the worm has turned, and it's all because of Marky Mark.
That is an interesting insight.
I think you're right.
That really was the beginning of this whole thing.
And then when they when they hauled him in front of Congress, he's like, I welcome regulation.
Of course, the big companies love regulation because it puts barriers up to little guys.
I'm not so sure Apple does.
You know, did you see the story that Tim Cook called Nancy Pelosi?
Yeah, I saw that.
Yeah.
Also, it's not in the headline, but Google's senior vice president for global affairs,
Kent Walker, also has made many calls to lawmakers in recent days, too.
They're essentially trying to push back.
But I guess the reception's been cold.
Supposedly Pelosi told Cook that she needs specifics on what doesn't work for him.
And Cook says these changes would disrupt iPhones in the market and actually cause like
grief in people's life if you make these changes.
And it's so crazy, man, because basically from the start of the show, you and I have
been saying this is the way this is going to go.
This is the way it's going to go from day one.
And now here we are and I think they're going to get up and Apple is totally unprepared.
You know, they're not making the concessions they need to make.
If Apple would have given up on their 30 percent cut years ago, they'd be in a way better position.
But they antagonize developers to the point where they became outraged and they're trying
to claim that forcing them to open up third party installs on the iPhone would just completely
wreck the iPhone of all security, which is complete and total bullsh**.
Because of course, you'd still have to have a developer account.
You still have to have an entitlement that is signed by Apple.
They would retain the ability to revoke those apps and entitlements.
They could revoke your developer account, even if you didn't go through the app store,
just like they can do now on their platform.
They could do it to third party apps that get sideloaded.
They still could have to require signing.
The whole thing is such bullsh** from Apple.
It's like they don't think it's like they don't appreciate the train that is coming
their way, because what makes Apple work is the integration of everything.
Like if you took one message away from WWDC, it was that all of those features are coming
to all of the platforms at once, iOS, the Mac, the iPad.
They're all getting all of the features at once.
And they work together with things like universal control.
That's what makes Apple's ecosystem compelling, the fact that the AirPods work so well with
the damn phone.
And so if regulation comes in and breaks all this up, they're going to be so screwed because
their secret sauce is taken from them.
And so they are playing with a kind of fire that could destroy them.
And it's wild to watch a company go from nearly dead to now so far up that they're going to
be sliced up by the government.
I mean, are they going to be sliced up or are they going to just have to like take less
than 30 percent?
I don't know.
I'm not sure.
I mean, Apple has been building a legal team for a while.
I don't think anybody is getting broke.
The only one I think might face an actual breakup is for some reason the Instagram thing
seems to have pissed off the lawmakers significantly.
And I feel like Facebook could lose either Instagram or what is it, WeChat that they
own?
Yeah, WeChat, right?
Yeah.
That's what I could see only because like Apple is doing hardware integration and software
integration between their family of products.
Microsoft bundling Internet Explorer.
I mean, that might be how they're looking at this.
Okay.
But let's take me.
Right.
Like one of the reasons I keep floating back to Mac is like as I buy Christmas, right?
The home pods are great or like the AirPods Max, right?
These are I'm using them right now for my audio output.
Right.
I'm using the mic for the input.
These are really nice.
They automagically know which device I'm trying to use.
I don't have to do, you know, the Bluetooth dance that I used to always have to do.
Or I don't have to get cables that are going to get frayed and then only come out of one
ear like my other headphones.
I can, you know, quote, throw, what is it, AirPlay?
Stuff from my computer to my phone to the HomePod to the HomePod in another room and
seamlessly pick it up.
I don't think that's anti-try.
I don't think that's really being a trust.
Now, Apple saying that who can and cannot have software in the App Store isn't either,
to be honest, except when they say users may only get software via the App Store, right?
So I guess I argued myself actually into your position that the problem to me that Apple
has is if I want to, you know, if the mad botter wants to make the next great iPad app
and Apple for some reason doesn't like it, then I'm posed.
I can't go to, you know, Tim Sweeney at Epic and say I want to put it in your store, right?
This is where the whole store analogy kind of falls down because if, you know, if 7-Eleven
doesn't want to carry my slushy brand, well, quick check might or wall on might.
That's not the case on iOS.
I just can't imagine regulators stop at the App Store.
Like they open, once they crack that door open, where else are you going to go?
You could say maybe AirPods need to be broken out or something.
I mean, I don't know.
I don't know.
So the reason why I think is I think there is an appetite in the U.S. public.
So there was a survey done today and 53 percent of the citizens of the states that were surveyed,
53 percent somewhat support Congress's big tech antitrust bills, 44 percent rank tech
regulation as a low priority or the lowest.
I think 53 percent is a pretty significant number.
And the reason why I think it's significant is the poll was actually commissioned by a
tech industry funded group.
So if anything, it's going to like it's going to bring those numbers down because it's depressing
the numbers.
And if the numbers are 53 percent when they're depressed, I'm a little concerned about that.
However, the survey showed that when you were given specific examples of how they might
break up the big tech companies, respondents said they would then oppose them.
But initially the concept of breaking up big tech so that way it's fair for consumers and
small businesses, people like that idea.
And so it gives our Congress critters an opportunity to go up there and sound like they're doing
something for the people and play tough without actually having to do anything that really
is going to change the lives of the American people.
Like there's so many other things they should be focusing on right now.
Even with all the crap we talk about this, but this is what they're going to focus on.
Honestly, if they can get on the other end of this and what's really changed is we get
more access to installing apps on our devices, great.
I think where my primary concern comes from is watching what they did to Microsoft and
how they neutered them.
How Microsoft went and just kind of just became an old slow dog after the antitrust stuff
came in.
For better or for worse, I suppose.
I guess I just I can't get past the idea that they're just going to go for the easy win
and say Instagram can't be part of Facebook.
Yeah.
Oh, and by real time follow up, Reese in the chat room points out it's WhatsApp.
WeChat's the China chat app and it's WhatsApp.
Yeah.
We'll see.
I suppose.
Boy, this stuff is really rolling on though.
It really is coming up.
It's coming up and I think they're not playing a smart game here.
I think the tech companies are about to get rolled by DC and that when you look at other
industries like the defense and oils and other big industries like pharma, they know how
to handle this so much better than these tech companies do.
They suck at this kind of stuff.
I mean, the fact that Tim Cook called Nancy Pelosi and that leaked out is an example of
something that just doesn't happen with the other big companies.
Well, and she obviously leaked it, right?
Yep.
Playing hardball.
Good luck, Tim.
Datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
Take a look at your code level performance across your entire environment with beautiful
dashboards and troubleshoot issues faster with Datadog.
Datadog has a continuous profiler that automatically collects the profiles from your production
servers all the time, capturing it in its little capsules so that way you can analyze
it anytime you want and get access to it quickly with minimal overhead.
You can get a unified picture of your environment.
You can correlate your code performance with your server performance with your network
performance all in real time dashboards that are gorgeous.
Go to datadog.com slash Coder Radio for a limited time.
If you start a trial and create one dashboard, you'll get a free t-shirt and you can see
just how freaking gorgeous these dashboards are.
They've done an incredible job and I underscore that because that can really make a difference
when you're in a discussion, a meeting maybe with somebody that's upstairs.
You can show them this information and they can grok it.
And Datadog has over 450 integrations with different enterprise applications giving you
tracing and log management and that continuous profiler all in one platform.
So Datadog enables you to pinpoint the root cause of issues faster than ever.
So go try them out.
Go to datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
Get that 14-day free trial, create that dashboard and get a t-shirt boom, boom, boom, boom all
while you're supporting the show datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
Well speaking of Microsoft, they're doing all right now.
They just hit the two trillion dollar milestone, unbelievable.
Their shares have gained 19% so far this year.
Only Apple and Saudi's Armco or Aramco have hit the two trillion in value, which is an
oil organization.
So Apple and an oil group have hit two trillion and now Microsoft, two trillion dollars.
So I guess maybe they did okay after all that antitrust stuff.
That's huge.
That's sweet, sweet Azure money.
Nadella is just, I mean, he's basically locked himself in the Hall of Fame of CEOs now.
If you're a CEO while your company creates, hits a milestone like this, like he's set.
Even if he does nothing else, remarkable for the rest of his tenure.
Yeah, he's done.
He's good.
Yep.
And you know, congratulations to our friends at Microsoft.
I don't know how much this really matters to the employees there.
Not even a little.
Boy, is it happening in the shadow of Bill Gates just eating a lot of shit these days.
Oh, poor Bill.
I know.
Today, Warren Buffett announced he's leaving the board of the Gates Foundation.
It's like there's a hit against Bill Gates, like a public PR hit.
Honestly, I really think there was.
He was like the last like loved tech guy.
I mean, it sounds like there was some hanky panky.
Yeah.
And you don't think Warren Buffett did any hanky panky.
That's why I find all the Bill Gates stuff kind of like, yeah, I suppose they're all
kind of weirdos.
They're all kind of weirdos.
You don't get that rich and that much power if you don't have like a sense of entitlement
that you just like do weird stuff.
True.
All the things are mine.
Yeah.
Well, so it's all in the shadow of Microsoft becoming hooch.
But Gates is sort of just an after story now, I suppose, about it.
I don't know.
I wonder what's going on there.
I wonder where that leads to.
You think the goal is to just discredit people in tech in general, like big tech leaders?
Because Bezos gets a lot of shit, too, although I'm not a big fan of either one of these guys.
I think that there's just a cultural moment right now where the tech guys are no longer
seen as the level born nerds who are going to build great things that are going to save
us all.
Right.
Hey, you know what I didn't realize when we started the show today?
Tomorrow is the big Windows 11 reveal.
I think you mean Windows 10 X.
Now, I think you mean the artist formerly known as Windows 10 X.
Wait.
Is this Metro again?
Kind of is.
Whoa, that's a deep cut.
I actually think it's Plasma, dude.
Have you looked at these screenshots?
I just put a link to The Verge in there.
It looks very KDE.
It does have the essence of KDE going on, yeah.
It's like Gnome and KDE had a baby, and it's Windows 11 UI, and a Chromebook.
I do not like the icons in the middle of the taskbar.
That sucks.
No, I don't like anything about this.
Yeah.
So there you go.
Significant updates, Nadella says, Windows 11 will be likely demoed tomorrow.
There's already a leaked version online, so we kind of already know a lot.
It sort of took a lot of the excitement out of the event.
All the rots are already gone over in detail.
Yeah, what does he think?
Does he have a summary of what Paul thinks?
He thinks it's Windows 10 X.
Yeah, okay.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Because it is, right?
Microsoft also recently announced their 30% cut on PC games is going down.
They're dropping it to a 12% cut for games.
That's 18% of throwing the finger at Apple.
They're expecting Windows 11 to be a free upgrade for any PC running Windows 10 right
now.
That's because it's 10 X.
I think so.
They say this is going to be the Windows release that focuses on Windows enthusiasts.
Are there Windows enthusiasts?
Is that a thing?
He's unaware of such a creature.
I mean, not even Paul Therot, who makes his living writing about Windows.
I would not even describe him as a Windows enthusiast.
If you listen to his podcast, Windows Weekly, I would not categorize him as enthusiastic
or even happy at all.
Right.
I think it's what happens to guys who cover this for a while.
Look at us.
It's true.
Oh, man.
It's just impossible to stay positive after you watch this.
Just take like a decade or so on an OS and you will hate everything about it.
That's true.
Any tool you use extensively, you become aware of all of its problems, and then you kind
of fixate on that for a bit.
So meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting, I just want to mention that one more time.
If you're out in the Denver or Salt Lake City area in August and want to come roast with
us, I imagine it's going to be real hot, right?
In Salt Lake City, it's going to be real hot on August 7th.
Yeah, I would think so.
Why am I doing this to myself?
Why didn't I go up to Canada?
Oh, the border's closed.
Yeah.
Because you miss events.
I do.
That's what it is.
I just decided to do my own thing.
I'll be honest.
I'm tempted.
If I can somehow get away, I might do it.
Oh, how fun would that be?
Do you miss the events at all?
I mean, like-
I don't miss the bad, lame events.
Yeah.
But I think once we get out of this weird state, which we, you know, 2022 in terms of
like no conferences and stuff, I'll probably still, like there was a couple that are good.
Like DevFest Florida, I always enjoyed.
I never went to Southeast Linux Fest and no offense to anybody who runs it, but I've heard
mixed things.
Maybe at a good year, maybe at a bad year, but Linux Fest Northwest, I regret not going
to.
Yeah.
I miss that the most.
That's the one I miss the most.
Yeah.
I really was.
I wouldn't go to WWC at this juncture.
Cause I don't do enough iOSy stuff to care and Google IO is just a train wreck.
Yeah.
And those may stay virtual.
Who knows?
We'll see.
We'll see if it actually stays virtual cause it's just better.
I wonder if by the next time we get together on our regular Monday recording, I wonder
if you'll have a Thaleo.
It might be too soon still depending on parts and stuff.
Probably not if it hasn't shipped.
Right?
Yeah.
It's two business days from pick up.
So even if they would have to have it done tomorrow.
Yeah.
It's a long shot.
Then I still wouldn't get it because it'd be Friday, Monday.
Yeah.
So every day, my buddy Alex from self-hosted, my co-host from self-hosted will be in studio.
So I might invite him to sit down with us if you're open to that.
Sounds fun.
He's going to be staying for the week and we're going to be just hanging out and working
on projects.
Yeah.
I've been kind of getting the studio prepped for him cause.
Prepared.
Yeah.
You know, it's just sort of when I'm just working here, it's just a space for me really
and Wes, but we have a room that he can stay in and stuff.
So it was just getting that ready, getting new linens and stuff like that.
The weird like ancillary things you do to support the business that have nothing to
do with like creating content.
Yep.
Just totally like we're out there getting rooms ready and stuff, but it's so I'm totally
looking forward to it.
So that'll be fun.
And I'm like, that'll, that's going to spice things up for next week.
So there you go.
And maybe we'll have comments on the, I was tempted to try at windows 11.
I may give it a download and try it out before next week's coder.
I might.
Oh, I'm going to try it out.
Are you?
Yeah.
I'm going to try it out.
Okay.
All right.
Why not?
I'll give it a go too.
Well, anything you want to mention before we get out of here?
Yeah.
Just subscribe to Coder Radio.
There you go.
That's good too.
You can follow the show on Twitter at Coder Radio Show.
If you'd like to become a member, coderqa.co, support the show, get a limited ad feed and
get our coderly reports, links to what we talked about today at coder.show slash 419.
That's where you'll also find our contact form, our subscribe links for your podcast
catcher of choice, our back catalog, all of that.
And then we record the show typically on Mondays, except for this week, at 5 PM Pacific, 8 PM
Eastern at jblive.tv.
Another way you can find out is if you just follow or subscribe on Twitch, whatever they
call that, twitch.tv slash Jupiter Broadcasting, then you get notified when we go live.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio program.
My voice held out.
Now I can go shout and go celebrate and lose my voice.
Thanks for joining us.
We'll see you back here next week.