This is KOTORadio episode 378 for September 7th, 2020.
Hello friends and welcome to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look at the art and business, software development, and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by a Cloud Guru, the leader in hands-on cloud training. The only way to lock in a new skill is by doing.
That's why ACG provides hands-on labs, cloud Linux servers, and much more. Get your hands cloudy at acloudguru.com.
My name is Chris and joining us every week is our host from the other coast. It's Mr. Jar, I mean, Mr. Michael Dominic. Hello, Mike.
What's up? So happy to be here.
Wait, that was Mario.
You know what? I've sometimes thought your Jar Jar is a little Mario, which I kind of prefer. I got to be honest, doesn't trigger me as much.
Is it because I'm Italian, you racist fiend? Is that why?
Yeah, obviously, clearly. It's not because you just sound exactly like him.
Couldn't be.
I'm super elated to be here today because we had a terrific response to the Coder QA team. Thank you everybody who went to coderqa.co and became a member.
We'll talk more about that in a little bit. But the other thing that's really exciting is we managed to get Wes for today's episode, mostly because we struck him on a day off.
And so he had no excuse. Hello, Wes.
Hello. Yeah, I mean, what could be better on Labor Day than a little bit of labor of love? Coder Radio.
I know. This right here is documented proof that Mike and I are still not great small business time management guys because here we are working on Labor Day.
And if we really had it together, we probably wouldn't be.
Your machines.
Yeah, that's what it is.
You just never stop working, which you're right. It's not good for the family or the health, but maybe the bottom line.
What's a Monday when you've already worked a Sunday?
I am like on cloud nine today because Linux Action News is back and everybody's freaking out. They're loving it. Episode 153 Linux Action News dot com slash 153.
If you want to stay up to date on what's going on in the world of Linux and open source, if it impacts your career or if it benefits you to stay informed, just check out Linux Action News dot com because you get it in like 30 minutes or less.
Just a nice tight summary.
And Joe and I have been following this stuff forever, so we've got some insights and contacts we can reach on to inform our opinions.
And I'm really proud of it. Linux Action News dot com slash 153. It's back.
You know, a product launch is a big deal.
You know, it's like it's that's like that's our version of a product launch right there.
Exciting, stressful.
Finally, I can stop keeping up on the Linux News myself and just let you and Joe take care of it.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
Wes really has this time management thing down. He's delegating. I like it.
Yeah. I mean, it's smart, right? Outsource your news collection.
Now, we do have a little bit of feedback to get to. Coder dot show slash contact.
Joey wrote into the show about freeloading enterprise users.
So get your flame retardant pants on, gentlemen, and let's answer this question.
Also, I like that I think Joey is maybe a new listener or messed this one up because it's, quote, Hi, Chris, Wes and pain.
You know, if we change the spelling, it might just be derogatory about old Mike over there.
Yeah, maybe it's just, you know, P-A-I-N, right? Thanks, man.
OK, that kind of works pain in my Georgia. That's right.
He says, I wanted to bring your attention to a topic that I'm confident will be interesting for your audience and you guys to talk about.
Recently, there has been a big move by large industry players, including Microsoft, to stand behind open source, quote unquote.
However, one of the overlooked aspects is the fact that these open source developers are not paid for their work.
And often software companies take their open source work and repackage it and sell it for millions.
How can this be sustainable? And won't these projects just eventually be taken over by the large companies like Microsoft and Amazon?
Do you have a hot take on that, Mike?
So I'm a little confused by that, to be honest. There's a lot of contribution in terms of money going on.
And isn't it the case that like Microsoft now employs a bunch of people who work on Linux?
Yeah, I think, you know, what they're probably what Joey's probably referring to is, Wes, maybe you can help me jog my memory, but there's been a couple of database projects recently in the last two years.
Like Mongo?
Yeah, that's one that have that have really struggled with companies like Amazon or Microsoft repackaging it up or essentially ripping off,
reimplementing and making millions and not financially contributing to the project.
I think and those projects have been fairly vocal about it. So that's probably where Joey's getting this from.
I kind of see part of where it's coming from.
Yeah. Well, I think there's multiple things here.
Like there's open source in the sense of the license and then there's like open source in the sense of community and like individual project maintainers and owners.
And maybe there's more and more of a trend where your open source project gets successful.
Either you start a small business that you try to build and then you run into problems because Amazon wants to sell your stuff to a larger scale than you ever could.
Or you just end up hired by one of these giant companies and keep working on your project.
And do either of those really fully count as the thing that maybe Joey's getting to around the spirit of open source?
I guess the part that I could see where it's unsustainable is if these products so overshadow the original product or project,
it may be hard for them to get talent to work on it.
And then they could sort of shrivel, I suppose.
But this is what I go back to.
This, A, isn't a new problem and, B, hasn't really been fully solved for any particular slice of the market.
But when you go back in time, this has really kind of been going on forever.
It is a little more pronounced now because of the scale, I think, of cloud services.
But large enterprise companies ripping off entire sections of open source stacks and then implementing them under the scenes and not telling you about it or not having to release the license depending on the project is super common.
It's a practice that already happens.
And I think a lot of developers that are working in this space probably already know that before they even get started, that it's a reality.
Is the problem the creators of the projects not being able to make money?
And just because I'm contractually obligated, I have to mention Sun and Java at least once a month.
Yeah.
So it's a problem that West makes some open source project and then Oracle comes in and is like, great job, West.
Thanks for the BSD license.
We're just going to commercialize this.
Have some cake.
In part, that's part of it.
And then I think where it's really kind of the double whammy is if one of these projects decides, you know what we're going to do is we're going to offer our own hosted version of our project fully managed for a service fee.
And then AWS comes along and offers the same thing as part of AWS.
For pennies on the dollar, Chris on Amazon.
Yeah.
Got it.
And then it's like a double whammy at that point.
And that is like, boy, that's hard because that was their revenue path to sustainability.
And that's clearly been eclipsed.
But at the same time, it's sort of the way the market works.
And when you make something for free, somebody can take it and build on top of it.
I think there's a solution for this.
There's this new technology.
A guy who comes to my user group, his name is Bill.
He calls it.
He wrote a letter to the hobbyist something about stealing software or like, I don't proprietary.
Is that a word?
Yeah.
You know, we ought to try as a shareware model.
Oh, yeah.
Let's bring on the three point five inch floppies.
Let's do it.
Yeah.
Speaking of your friends who come and hang out at groups and and their buddies with Bill, Tim Sweeney and some of his cohorts have their latest filing.
They're asking for a preliminary injunction, but also in the court filing, they release data on numbers of users and the impact this whole shenanigans has had.
So Epic says Fortnite has one hundred and sixteen million iOS users, which is a third of the game's three hundred and fifty million total users.
Oh, crap. Wow.
Oh, yeah.
And this one kind of hurts.
They say their iOS daily active users declined by 60 percent since its removal from the app store.
That is pretty significant.
Now, it's not going to kill them, but that is a decent chunk.
Hundred and sixteen million users out of three hundred and fifty million total.
I mean, they're really playing with fire here.
But I suppose you could look at this from another angle and say we've got to change these policies before that share gets even larger.
I guess. I mean, I know I had a pretty spicy take that was unpopular on Twitter that like the judge said and Apple said you could just go back on and pay them 30 percent during the lawsuit and that would be OK.
Yeah, that did seem like a decent compromise on Apple's part.
Right. But Tim Sweeney again shares many character flaws with me.
Has decided to lose a bunch of money for no reason.
I don't kind of get this.
It's an interesting stand to just, you know, fully rely on.
We're just going to keep complaining.
I suppose it does let them make these continued arguments.
If they went back on, they wouldn't have these big numbers to drop.
Maybe, you know, slightly smaller numbers anyway.
I guess.
Yeah. And the damages would be a lot less.
Now, Miguel Itacasa on Twitter had a pretty popular thread and I'm curious to get your guys' take on this.
He says, I bet Fortnite could work in Safari without going through the App Store like Confucius famously said in 500 B.C.
When there is a billion dollar budget, there is a way to compile the code to WebAssembly.
I mean, isn't there something to that?
And of course, the Twitter thread goes to point out all of the GL limitations and file size limitations like 10 megabyte module limitations and these things.
But Miguel's response to all of that is, yeah, but where there's money, there's a way.
And you essentially identify the technical problems and you build accommodations for them and you just avoid the App Store altogether.
I mean, I don't think you could pull that off, at least not on mobile Safari.
But Wes, what do you think?
Yeah, I think that would be the trickiest part.
It doesn't seem like Apple's gone out of their way to support all the things that might make this easy to do.
Yeah.
But there is that point.
I mean, you know, Epic has a lot of resources to throw at these things.
It would probably also be beneficial for that ecosystem for, you know, a major game and company to start pulling more resources into it and explore if that might actually be workable.
Yeah, it's an interesting thought experiment because there are tons of limitations right now.
There's no WebAssembly threads in Safari's WebAssembly implementation.
It doesn't have WebGL2, but Firefox and Chrome have had that for years.
And it's never going to.
There's also, like, I think the game install on devices once all the assets are pulled down is like 30 gigs.
Yeah.
There is a little weird back and forth, too, in this thread, you know, where on one side people criticizing this idea are pointing out some of the problems.
And then Miguel's response is basically, well, you've got money.
You could do it.
And then the other side of things is people pointing out, well, how is Apple going to respond to this?
And him not really liking any of that sort of theorizing.
So I'm not not sure it's a real fair playing field on what money really makes possible because at some point there are actual technical limitations, especially on a tightly controlled platform.
Hand wave money is essentially his answer.
Right.
I completely disagree.
Having used Xamarin forms when it was independent and after Microsoft bought them, by the way, Miguel is the Xamarin guy for people who don't know.
Let me tell you something.
Microsoft just injecting those Benjamins has made it so much more stable.
Is that sarcasm or is that sincerity?
I can't.
You know what the saddest part?
It's 100 percent sincere.
Yeah, OK.
I mean, money definitely goes a long way.
Don't get me wrong.
Yeah, it's possible if you have the right team.
I mean, we put man on the moon in the 60s.
So with a calculator, effectively.
But I think Wes is right that Apple will probably, if you even try this, react in a very I I'm going to cry if I think about what they might do.
Right.
Like they're they're not going to take it.
I don't know.
I don't buy it.
I see you don't think so.
I find this take that Apple wants to hurt the Web and that Apple wants to limit what the Web can do kind of ludicrous and ridiculous on its face, because not only did the iPhone originally launch with 100 percent focus on Web apps.
But if you look at overall in totality, Safari has been extremely competitive on mobile.
Yeah, it doesn't have WebGL to.
Yeah, it doesn't have WebAssembly threads.
Well, yeah, isn't that competitive just mean it's the browser to use that works well on the device that you paid a lot of money for?
I mean, I think one of the things that you got to fundamentally credit them for is rendering the real Web, not the baby Web on a mobile device.
And then the other super clever thing they did is they figured out that if a user double taps in an area that seems to be associated with a CSS element, zoom in specifically to that element to take out sort of the play in the zoom and bringing things like WebGL and other features to mobile.
And making it a very competitive mobile browser.
If you look at that, like they pioneered that essentially mobile browsers before the iPhone really sucked.
And so I don't think Apple has gone out of their way to limit Safari.
I just I don't think it is the number one priority on the platform.
And so it lags in some areas.
Well, and doesn't it just make sense that they have a business interest in incentivizing things to focus on the App Store anyway?
I mean, I would say I bet Apple would define web browsing and web applications very differently.
Like they want a great browser for you to go to like New York Times dot com.
But I don't think they want people building full featured Web apps and using Safari instead of the App Store.
I could be wrong.
Maybe.
But then why would they have invested all of the energy they have into making it possible?
And why do they still make it possible for you to put website bookmarks on your main iOS long screen as an icon like an app?
Well, isn't there always a balance there?
Right. You've got to give users what is helpful to some extent, no matter what, even if it isn't exactly what you wish they were doing.
Yeah. And as someone in the chat saying every other browser on iOS is, in fact, Safari.
Right. They block.
So, yeah, I don't know.
Yeah. And as of as of the current released OS, you can't even change the default web browser 10 years into the platform.
So ridiculous. But I guess that's changing in iOS 14 for certain approved browsers.
Oh, yeah. Can't innovate my ass.
That's right. Just aside, we are doing Koda Radio Live again on Mondays if you'd like to join us.
So do head over to Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar to get it in your local time.
It's noon Pacific, three p.m. Eastern for us at JBLive dot TV.
And we'd love to have you in the chat room.
There's, you know, a couple of times a week now live shows we got to live to live shows a week right now and feeling pretty good.
Speaking of doing things for the consumers, there's a story that was dropped in the notes that I can't really necessarily see a downside to.
So we'll just wrap up the Apple stuff with this quote.
Later this year, the App Store will help users understand an app's privacy practices before they download the app on any Apple platform.
On each app's product page, users can learn about some of the data types the app may collect and whether that data is linked to them or used to track them.
You'll need to provide information about how your this is to developers.
You'll need to provide information about how your apps privacy practices, including the practices of third party partners who code integrates with your app.
Facebook SDK. Exactly. Mm hmm. In the App Store Connect starting this fall and the way it kind of is being sold to users as a type of nutrition label for privacy that'll show up on all App Store apps on all Apple platforms.
Is there anything bad about this from a user's perspective, Mike?
I mean, I can understand from monetization from Facebook and users users.
Yeah, that was the hell with them. They won't pay five dollars for an app. This is more paperwork for developers. I'm against it.
It is for sure. I mean, I mean, I want to get to that, but I just mean we have to keep in balance here for the end users.
This seems like a net win now. I totally appreciate. Yeah, I'm trolling.
Well, no, I mean, for the developers, this does is a major pain in the ass.
I wonder if, you know, we already have nutrition labels and like life and do people read them.
So I think about like the analytics, you know, packages that people can get the track app usage and crash reports and even can do pretty significant data collection.
That is in a lot of apps. Yes, it is. That's bad. I don't know what to say.
I mean, forget about that. The Google SDK is in the Facebook SDK is alone are.
You're going to see a lot of scary stuff and all the apps you use, right? Yeah, that's where it's kind of funny is.
You're right. It will be annoying to developers, but it's probably something they should have done a little bit better job thinking about already.
Just having to drop all these things in there that. Yeah, right. Well, you know, this big corporation takes care of it.
And I just include it because I need this one feature. That's what it is.
This should have been in there from day one. And now developers have been running amok, you bastards.
And now you got caught. You got caught reading clipboards. You got you got caught tracking people.
They've delayed something like then they just delay some aspect of of the tracking blocking stuff.
But yeah, well, that's because Facebook fought them, right? Like literally Apple blinked.
Yeah, it's interesting they blink on that, I guess, because Mark Zuckerberg is a lot more stealthy than Tim Sweeney is what we're learning, right?
Well, maybe, although one is a policy that they agreed to when they entered the app store and one is a policy that is being applied retroactively.
So maybe Apple is just. More considerate in that scenario, is that crazy?
You seem pretty bullish on this. So, like, do you think this is going to impact how you you guys download applications?
I mean, for my kids, it might. Yeah, sure. Yeah. OK, I could see that. And my wife, I could see it mattering.
I'm already kind of skeptical, you know, when it comes to my usage, but I could definitely see it for them.
My daughter accidentally downloaded a Roku app remote control and it somehow got her to agree to a $15 a month subscription to enable the app's functionality.
Roku? Yeah, it's just Wi-Fi, right? It's just sending Roku remote commands over Wi-Fi.
It auto detects the Roku device and just sends it commands over the API, right?
Fifteen bucks a month. And so I'm looking at my email. Thankfully, I caught it right. But I mean, after after it charged me and I even had it turned on to like ask for my permit.
I don't know what happened, but it's tricky the way it gets people into it. And she didn't know she was doing anything wrong.
So it's a complicated thing. So that's the next. But that'll be the next frontier and all that kind of shenanigans.
And I think it matters because it definitely has knock on. It's going to impact the Play Store for sure.
Also, obviously, this is all going to play into larger antitrust stuff that the ball seems to start rolling there more and more.
All of these stories will play into that dynamic.
Let's take a break and tell you about Linode cloud hosting Linode dot com slash coder and you'll get a hundred dollar 60 day credit towards your account.
One hundred dollars. Linode dot com slash coder. Simplify your cloud infrastructure with Linode's Linux virtual machines and robust set of tools to develop, deploy and scale your modern applications faster and easier.
They have 11 data centers around the world, enterprise grade hardware and their next generation network, which is fast.
They have a lot of nice rigs, too. Now, the shared plans start at five dollars a month.
So that dollar credit you could I mean, you could do anything you want. Right. But I actually would encourage you to play around with their configurator.
It is slick. They have a ton of OS options. They have easy ways to deploy with one click.
They also have what I have messed around with a little bit for setting up different WordPress installations.
They have these stack scripts that make it really easy to set up a really high speed WordPress deployment.
And you can just it's all really easy to read the script and make your own.
So that's nice. Of course, everything's SSD, 40 gigabit connections that come into the machines.
They have a beautiful cloud manager and a nice way to track everything that's happening.
And if you want to integrate it in with something a little bit larger, more production grade, they have fast and simple Kubernetes cluster deployments.
Really easy to get going. They also have a container orchestration engine to make it simple to manage multiple containers, dedicated GPU rigs.
You just have to go to linode.com slash coder for a $100, 60 day credit. That's linode.com slash coder.
They're my cloud provider now. I've been using them for about two years.
And we just built a matrix server on there for the network, and it just screams.
It really is great performance. This is reliable infrastructure. They have been in the game for a long time.
They're trusted by a lot of leading tech companies, and they've been in the community.
Linode.com slash coder and thanks to Linode for sponsoring the CoderRadio program.
All right, gentlemen, so why don't we get into something kind of neat?
Something special happened since last week that really didn't get very much attention.
On the 5th of September, C++20 was approved, which I didn't really understand or appreciate what this meant.
So I did a little bit of reading before the show, and now I understand that this will be the sixth revision of the C standard.
I like that some of the positioning around this has very intentionally been another opportunity for you to consider C++.
The standard became technically finalized by the WG21 at a meeting in Prague in February of 2020.
So we knew this was coming, but it just happened.
The draft was approved just recently as we got together today.
And I like this idea as a topic, Mike, which you suggested because no one's really talking much about C++ in 2020.
Yeah, well, you know, all the cool people like Wes are on Clojure, Elixir, some language he's probably inventing in a basement somewhere.
What we really have to appreciate is that C++ is the only language that steering committee is also a venue for a Bond film.
They're in Prague. I'm assuming they're playing Baccarat, right?
That's what I'm picturing. I'm thinking, right? Yeah.
A lot of slinky dresses. It's a good time. Yeah. Fancy cars. Fancy cars.
Drinks that are stirred, shaken, not stirred, not stirred, shaken, not stirred.
Yeah, right. I'm going to pitch it to Wes in a second.
The over overriding thing that I got as I was reading up on this, it's just how damn big C++ is as a language.
And I mean like big in terms of like it has all the features I've basically heard of and basically any language, right?
You can program in many different ways. It's a little nuts.
I've been playing with it some for a kind of fun side project.
There's like a new way to do pointers that didn't exist the last time I actually had to do C++.
So that's amazing. I don't know, Wes, have you have you fooled around with modern C++ at all?
Yeah, that's what's been interesting. You know, I have played a little bit, but I did most of my C++.
Well, probably like 10, 15 years ago. So it's kind of fascinating to watch.
I do think you're onto something just, you know, looking around at people commenting on the release.
I like this. Even as a C++ programmer with too much spare time, it has become obvious that learning and using all of C++ is beyond impractical.
To the point where I find that my C++ code more than ever looks kind of just like C.
And yet, you know, I think C++ suffers a bit from being, you know, a little bit legacy despite being more modern.
And where you get into, you know, you see a lot of arguments is that like what standard is used, what standard parts of the standard are being supported for the compiler that you are actually using.
And then, of course, the problem with a lot of, you know, long term, long lived languages is like, how do you how do you learn what modern best practices are if all the tutorials are out of date?
And, you know, I think there's been a lot of pushback, especially compared to a language like Rust where, yeah, C++ has pioneered a lot of these zero cost abstractions.
But you got to know more about it versus a language like Rust that, you know, those are pushed right from, you know, right from the start of the tutorial that this is the way that you go.
Yeah, I mean, a great example of that is so a big feature in C++ 20, which should be easy for me to say, but isn't, is modules, right?
They've introduced modules, which I am not a deep C++ guy, so I don't know a whole lot about.
But if you read the back and forth on the groups, there is quite a lot of controversy about how that was done, how that should have been done.
And it almost reminds me of like, you know, we always end up with that argument of like, what is the tasteful subset of the language, right? Right.
So I don't know. It's I mean, it's still not Objective C, so I'm not particularly excited, but whatever. You have nowhere to go from there, right?
I cornered you into the Objective C. That's hard to beat. Well, I think the other question is going to be, you know, how if you are a C++ advocate and you're really excited about C++ 20,
how do you go spread that word and get, you know, folks who are interested in doing a little lower level stuff, who, you know, some of the advantages, speed, control, specificity of C++ might be useful.
How do you convince them that it's worth learning and going through all the warts and figuring that out?
You know, like the module stuff's really interesting. But again, like if you if another option might be learning Rust or another modern language that has better or at least more modern concepts of, you know, package and dependency management,
it might still be an excellent tool for folks who've been doing it for 10 years. But how do you keep that mind check going?
Well, that's a great point about Rust, right? Because I have in the doc here, I have Rust, Go, and Swift. All three of them share one thing in common.
Well, in addition to not being as good as Objective-C. I just can't help myself.
All of them were created with the idea that they would be basically C++ but better or like C++ without the C or something like that, right?
And I mean, Swift, even Swift, which is why I include that disgusting thing on this list, because Chris Latner himself said he wanted it to be like Objective-C and C++ without the C.
So how do you convince someone who's like new that they're going to? Yeah, like you're saying, right? You got to deal with, you know, 30, 40 years of warts in C++.
I know it's not 40. When you could just like, I don't know, write in Rust and learn that you're a bad programmer because nothing compiles or write and go and get a cute plushie from Google or write in Swift and have an inferior development experience.
Wow. But you get to go to WWDC, then you can justify that.
Not in 2020, you don't maybe. No, it's true. It's true. You know, the thing, just as an observation, is Rust is front and center in a PR announcement, much like machine learning or AI is.
Just last week, Amazon announced AWS Bottle Rocket, which is a container Linux distribution.
And right there, front and center in the official Amazon press release, they talk about how the user land is full of Rust tools that they've written. It's Rust, Rust, Rust.
Why? I don't get that at all. Is that a selling point for a container solution?
It is, I think, because Rust is known as the safe language, the safe language to write your tools.
And that's sort of just sort of like it's almost like a celebrity programming language now.
And it's like why you have movie stars in your movie, in your big action movie, you want to have Sylvester Stallone.
If you're releasing something that's supposed to be safe, reliable and enterprise grade, having Rust on the label sells.
Who are they selling to?
Developers, IT admins, sys administrators. You know, I mean, in this case, in this example, this is the AWS Bottle Rocket project that they announced.
It's open source. It's up on GitHub. It's pretty wild.
The whole thing's there, the issue tracker, the Kanban board, all of it.
They got their Trello thing going on. And it's all there.
And yeah, the tools are all the user land tools, as they call the space above the kernel, as they put it, is all Rust.
So it's a distro.
Yeah. Yeah, it's a full distro.
Sitting on top of a lot of essentially best practices now using containers to deploy your applications and taking advantages of eBPF in the Linux kernel,
taking advantage of SE Linux and all that stuff and making it designed with the idea that you're not SSHing in, but you're probably using it with an orchestration system.
And I don't think it's any just mistake or accident that Rust is featured in their promotional material about it.
Right. I mean, I think it goes back to that sort of like the defaults and where the community pushes you.
I mean, I've definitely seen some pushback on the Rust hype from experienced C++ programmers who point out that like, yeah,
a lot of these same sort of concepts, abstractions, you can write clean and safe C++ code.
I think the question is, A, how often does that happen, especially for some X random software with a mixed range of experienced developers?
But then B, it doesn't have that same air, right?
When someone chooses Rust, you see that, oh, yeah, right.
They want those safety features. And even if they're doing a bad job of writing Rust, which the people writing the PR never check out or look at,
it just has that air of the community takes that seriously.
Well said. Right. You can write Rust and turn off all the safety features, right?
Like literally unsafe the whole application. Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's really well said. That's why I kind of compare it to tossing in machine learning, if possible, to a press release with a product, a tech product.
If it's a monitoring product or something, something that uses the cloud, you know, it often will have machine learning and artificial intelligence.
And they just kind of include it in the press release. And it's vague.
It doesn't actually tell you what the implementation is or how useful it is or how core to the product it actually is or what it actually does.
But they still put it in there. And it's kind of like that. But it sells or else they wouldn't do it.
Salad shack now with machine learning. I actually would be down for that.
If there was a salad shack that could learn the salad I liked and maybe even suggest future salad ideas, kind of seems like a great idea.
Whoever is listening, there is your next great app opportunity. The salad genie for Chris. There you go.
And Mike only charges 30 percent as a licensing fee.
Yeah. There you go. Per salad. Now, you imagine like an Uber Eats that you just open up on your phone and you just push a button and it just knows what you'd want and gets it for you.
That'd be that's what Google ought to use all their AdWords machines for.
It's just fascinating to watch this language continue to evolve. And then I'll also be curious to see, you know, we've already seen some movements.
We were just talking about Linux, you know, some movements to support maybe using Rust to write like some modules for the Linux kernel.
When will that start creeping into like some of the major adopters like scientific computing or, you know, game engine design that C++ is really entrenched in?
Like, is that going to start shifting and what kind of time frame is that going to take before you start seeing Rust sneaking in there or another language?
Didn't I say, yeah, Microsoft is adopting Rust, April, August 4th, 2020.
Microsoft is adopting Rust and, quote, Rust is the industry's best chance at safe systems programming.
Oh, geez. And they say here C++ can't be fixed. Coming in hard, coming in real hard.
I'm sorry, I need some ointment for the flames.
I'm going to I'll drop a link to this in the show notes of audience members. That's probably a that's a good one to read for a moment.
Seems kind of spicy and I like it. Huh. The best chance, Microsoft says.
And there's an article at Medium written by somebody at Microsoft, Tino Carr, I think, on Microsoft's adoption of Rust and why they're adopting it.
Microsoft determined that 70 percent of security patches pushed towards computers are related to memory related bugs.
So I mean, that's saying something. They certainly have plenty of C++ and that their operating system of theirs.
Yeah. And yeah, right. Defaults matter. And you can do those things with C++.
But if you know, if you can't always trust that that's going to happen, maybe something that makes it easy and right there already.
So you've got extra safety. So, Mr. Payne, you doing any any developing for the day job?
Anything you've been working on? Sure am. You know, actually, I've been having a lot of fun.
I'm doing Python development at the moment and I've been using this neat framework called Fast API, which I was trying to hint to Mike that maybe he should check out.
Oh, really? Python. So not closure. Is that a challenge, sir?
You know, maybe it is. Yeah. I would love to see if because you've been doing some Python, too.
Right, Mike? Not only am I doing some, I'm hiring another Python developer. Plug, plug, plug. Oh, hey.
Where do they get info for that? If I was prepared, I would have put up the job post. So maybe next episode we'll have it.
Follow me on Twitter. We'll have it for next episode for sure. There you go. This is interesting, Wes. So fast API.
What's this do? Well, you know, it's an it's a framework for Python that really just tries to make things very nice for developing APIs.
And, you know, so much of stuff these days. It's either computers talking to computers or humans talking to computers.
And you're going to need an API. And some of the frameworks that have existed currently can do a lot more than that.
Right. I mean, they can make just sort of simple Web apps. They can be a background API.
They've got all kinds of integrated ORM solutions, maybe maybe solutions like Django that has like support for building forms built into it.
Fast API just sort of gets out of your way, provides some really nice integration with a library called Pydantic.
It's a data validation library that takes advantage of Python's somewhat recent introduction of type hinting to just provide a lot of nice affordances out of the get go.
So you can stand up your API. It comes with, you know, open API and Redoc built right in.
It's got data validation right integrated into the solution with really nice error messages by default.
So you can focus on actually doing the hard work of the back end of the API calling out to other services and databases that you actually need to talk to.
Wow. Hey, check this out. Neil linked in the IRC on the live stream to Fedora Magazine dot org, which talks about building a small Web service using fast API.
This is pretty cool. This is a great walk through introduction to it. Oh, neat.
This is really it came out kind of recently to June. June 1st, 2020, as we record, it's at least fairly recent.
Neat. Well, how did this come about? Because this is actually I did not expect Python to be your answer.
I have to tell you, I thought it'd be something either much more esoteric or I don't know, something really enterprising.
I guess I just don't I don't think of Python when I think of enterprise software development.
Yeah, you know, I mean, I think it sneaks in in more places than you might suspect.
Python's also been improved recently, somewhat recently with, you know, better async support.
So there's better concurrency built into the language.
And yeah, there are going to be some, you know, high scale services where maybe Python isn't going to work for you.
But for a lot of APIs and web applications where a lot of your, you know, a lot of your calls end up being dominated on latency calling into the database or other large operations.
Python works pretty well, and it's just so developer friendly, you know, like it's easy to get started with, especially with libraries like fast API.
And it has such a rich ecosystem. Yeah.
If you if you want to call into, you know, any cloud service, yeah, they've got a Python API.
If you want to use any database, they've got a Python API.
Yeah. And the reality is, I know I know a lot of enterprise applications that do use Python.
So I don't I don't know. I just didn't expect that. But it's pretty great.
Yeah. Well, a good majority of Google right of of their support stuff is actually like all Python.
So, yeah. Yeah. I mean, I've used entire backup systems that are powered by Python.
Chatham points out Ansible is written in Python. A lot of Red Hat's tools. I mean, tons of. Yeah.
But I just thought that what I expected. So, Wes, how does this compare to like a flask?
It's a little more purpose driven, I'd say. You know, flask is great. I've used flask before and enjoyed it.
But it's a little more loosey goosey, perhaps you might say. I mean, like you can do whatever you want in flask, which is awesome.
But if you're really just like trying to get like an API that you can build to a standard, you have fewer choices.
And that can be a good thing because like fast API has chosen your data validation library for you, which is Pydantic.
Which I've been enjoying a lot. And so it really sketches this model where right from the get go, you're defining, you know,
request and response types that are leveraging Python's type hinting.
And all of that's integrated so that that gets pushed into the open API specification for you so that that's already provided for you.
And, you know, for your clients to consume if they want to go that route.
And then in the back end, as you're writing it, you know that you've already validated all this data.
It's also got just nice basic features like, you know, it's going to catch any uncaught exceptions for you.
Make sure that just turns into a 500 without any embarrassing back end info.
It's like they've taken all the bits of like, I need to write a thousand APIs to expose these new features for my clients.
I want to make that as fast as possible and not have to deal with all the little fiddly bits and choosing which library over here that might handle this one part of it.
I'm noticing automatic interactive docs, too. That's awesome.
Exactly. Right. It's just like it's none of it's none of it's stuff that you couldn't do in any other framework or just building yourself by assembling libraries.
But sometimes your application isn't unique enough to really warrant that kind of special care and attention.
And I think that's the use case that fast API shines.
And you've seen it somewhat for like, I think, as more people are doing machine learning and Python's pretty big in that community can be a nice way to serve up models, interact with those systems.
It probably won't be the best if you're trying to build like a classic Web application.
Yeah. OK. Maybe use Flask or, you know, especially Django for that.
But if you're really sort of an API driven business or project, it's probably worth just checking out.
The other part I like is that it's just, you know, it's really I have mixed feelings about about, you know, the adoption and strong opinions around static types in general.
But I think that they found a really nice sweet spot here of leveraging sort of the optional typing that's been added to Python and focusing like you see it all over their docs.
It's clearly a focus is having those type ins partially for that, you know, that you can go do more static analysis.
But also they recognize the importance for new users and developers of integration with the IDE.
And because there is so much type information provided in these libraries, you've got auto complete just about everywhere you might expect.
And it does a pretty good job of, you know, having a similar experience to an actually statically type language.
So what's your environment for doing this Python work? What do you mean?
So you mentioned IDEs, are you using PyCharm or Code?
I thought this time around, I've used PyCharm a little bit in the past, but it's been a long while.
I've also had a totally Vim based setup, which I liked pretty decently.
I'm not like a, you know, a huge IDE super rich support.
I kind of enjoy like having a terminal open and then like an editor open.
And I'm going to be in a REPL anyway, probably if I can.
But I thought I'd strike the middle ground this time around since I was setting up, you know, building new projects, working on new stuff.
I just totally invest and try out VSCode and I've been having a lot of fun with that.
Oh, another VSCode user.
A code convert, you could say.
Yeah, it is funny. I still find myself like I use Vim half the time anyway for editing some stuff.
But as like a separate Python dedicated window, it's really nice.
I've also actually been enjoying the Git support a lot, too.
Yep, absolutely. Those are some of the reasons I just love it.
That and it's got a fantastic YAML plug in. It's got a fantastic Markdown plug in, you know, SFTP opening files on remote servers.
It's just it's a treat. It really feels slick.
I just I'm really happy with it. I mean, I'm open to trying other ones.
But interesting. I love it.
So all three of us because that's what you're using mostly these days, too, right, Mike?
Yeah, I'm actually all on code now.
People are going to think we're fanboys, but it's just what works for us.
They're bought and paid for by Redmond.
Yeah, making that big V.S. code money. Yes.
Well, it was just this morning.
I was really kind of feeling how no events have started to impact myself and sort of what I would normally be doing business wise.
I assume, Wes, you must be doing the work from home thing.
And Mike, I was also curious to get an update from you on the business stuff, but I'll share mine here in a moment.
But Wes, what about you? With this new gig, are you are you doing the work from home thing from the start, essentially?
Yeah, you know, actually, it was kind of weird.
It's the first time I did an entirely remote onboarding as well.
Like, I have never been into the office.
I did have to go run over to my manager's house because he had a laptop that I picked up from him in a socially distanced manner.
You know, so that was a little awkward and a weird like first way to meet in person.
But the interview, the interview was online. The onboarding was online.
At this point, I don't know if I'll ever even have to go into the office.
Interesting. Yeah, I wonder if that's going to be true for a lot of people.
And I feel like it's going to impact podcast downloads.
I got a note from a guy today. He's like, oh, I just tuned into Linux action as I didn't know it was done for a while.
I didn't know it was off the air. You know, people are just kind of now catching up on their podcast.
But what about you, Mike? Is the business feeling it?
Or at this point, have you reached a new normal for the sort of lockdown state, no events kind of thing?
I think we've pretty much gotten used to it. I mean, I was pretty early on locking down because I'm crazy.
I will say not having like community events has been starting to feel that.
Yeah, but same. Other than that, it's you know, I'm sitting and I have my little standing desk in my home office.
Now I'm happy. I'm fine. I'm wondering how much even comes back next year.
Right. Not a thing. And if it lasts that long, I wonder how much comes back.
And that would be a loss, I think, because for me, it's it's a big part of I think how I get connected with the fact that we actually make something.
Because otherwise I just sort of put it out there and maybe hear from one percent of the audience, maybe two percent of the audience.
And, you know, it's true. And, you know, that's just the reality of it.
But it after a year of not talking, not actually speaking to a real human that listens, you know, other than like through Bumble or through a chat, it's it's it's unsettling.
Because when I go to these meetups and I know you guys know this is true, but like you you end up with a table full or wherever you're at of people who are interesting, like they're in the industry or they're they're trying to get into the industry or they have a history.
Like all these really interesting details in it. For me, it helps me connect with the fact that there's real people out there that are really listening to the show.
And a lot of them are doing things that I really admire or find super interesting.
And that kind of gets me going and keeps me motivated. I'm not really having any motivation problems, but I do feel like it's sort of dipping.
But also there's been no event for us to really cover show wise, like we haven't gone somewhere and done something from the show floor and covered it.
Right. So it's just been lacking from the network all year.
And I kind of miss doing that, too. I find it interesting the different modes of like remote interactions as well.
My team's sort of been exploring that around stand ups and like when do we communicate and when do you need to communicate, you know, sort of blocking issues like I need to talk to you so we can resolve this for work stuff.
But then also trying to figure out like how often do we actually just need to have a chat where we all sit around and bullshit so that, you know, like we feel like we're a team and see each other's faces.
And, you know, what you might replicate hanging out in the lunch room. That is a hard thing to get right.
And it can be a really hard thing when you're a really busy team as well, because then it's kind of hard to justify doing that kind of stuff.
And you always get one or two people that are there with the mics on mute and they're like typing away and you can see they're not even like looking at the video call.
What did you say? Oh, sorry. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And I find those Zoom meetings kind of fatiguing, too, because you always sit there and nod and smile.
Mm hmm. Yeah. Mm hmm. So, yeah, it's hard to get that. It's nothing like having the team all together in the same space.
Let's just take like Linux Fest Northwest or the one that happens in South Carolina, whose name I never remember or Ohio Linux Fest, which is coming up soon.
So you think they're just not going to happen or you think people are going to migrate virtual?
I think it's I think it's going to be virtual, which there's parts of that that I like.
You know, you can get core aspects and it makes it available to more people. I like all that stuff.
I've been able to attend events that I'd never attended before. So that's positive.
But the hallway stuff, the going out to eat, the building relationships over a period of time, you know, like Alex from Self Hosted.
We met at Texas Linux Fest and then we met at another fest that happens, you know, like three or four months after that.
And we just resumed a conversation that started at Texas Linux Fest and then took it online.
And then Linux Fest Northwest came around and the next thing you know, we have Self Hosted.
And it was just this process of meeting someone, going out, sharing a drink, sharing a meal and talking about similar things and making a connection that is possible online, but just is so low bandwidth in comparison.
That's it. It takes a lot longer to really suss out like, do we vibe on that human to human level?
Because we're just talking over the little little bit of text.
It's truly a bandwidth issue. It's like your human senses need more resolution than I think video provides, than seeing somebody from the top up, you know, half up.
And when you're out and about, you know, at an event, you interact with people in a technical sense, but also it's like regular humans, which you don't always see online.
You get to see how they, you know, comport themselves at the restaurant. You get to see how they interact with other people and strangers.
And it gives you a much richer view of a person.
I'm really glad you said that, because that is a huge aspect of it for me is you when you're only online, when everything's virtual, it's like social media is reality in a way.
People the way people present themselves and the photos they share and the topics that they talk about.
But when you go to an event and that same person is there, you see a three dimensional human being who is maybe actually a little overweight or doesn't have all their stuff together and also has flaws.
And isn't a perfect person.
And that was a huge, huge revelation for me as the journalist aspect of this job, because I often go in with press credentials, which means I get access to the journalist area and meeting some of these names in tech journalism.
And taking them from like these these icons and tech journalism to just these human beings that are clearly flawed.
And and that was for me, it was like, oh, oh, I see. They're not like it's not like this impossible thing that I could never aspire to.
They're just a guy or a gal who's been working at this for a long time. They're just like everybody else.
And not having that veil of social media removed from time to time, I think, makes me feel like I live in this echo chamber that is super intense and often doesn't fully represent my point of view.
Not all the time, but just on various things. And maybe makes me feel like I'm not like that's not a game I'm good at.
I'm not good at social media. I don't tweet a lot. I don't share a lot of stuff. I try to reply to people, but it's just not where I'm.
It's so it makes me feel like I'm not as good at at the job because that's when you're online and everything's virtual perception is reality.
And it's not an area I really have the motivation or energy to be hyper competitive in. I don't feel like tweeting 17 times a day about stuff and taking pictures of every little thing.
And like every now and then I'm inspired, like when I'm out in the woods or something, I'm inspired to take a photo and I'll share that.
But that's about it. Or if Levi's being cued. Yeah, obviously, if the pups being cute, that's got to get shared.
Actually, the reality is probably zero point one percent of all the adorable Levi pictures ever get shared. I mean, we need more.
But you know what I mean? Like without these in-person events, I feel disconnected in a way and I feel like it's not real.
It's not real life. It's just it's not it's not there. It's not connecting for me.
There is a couple of community events that I routinely go to. They're like quarterly right in Tampa.
Three of them have tried to do these online, like almost like a replacement kind of thing, right?
Like virtualize it. And it's just awful. I mean, I I don't know, man.
To me, it doesn't work without like the side, you know, of, oh, let's just run in and grab a beer or a cup of coffee or something.
It's very just feels like another Zoom meeting, right? Where somebody is pitching something and just not loose, very formal.
And you don't have those breakaways, right? Like those ways to be like, oh, I'm clearly driving with you.
That's like I'm just going to chat with you in the corner for a little bit and get to know you better.
You can't do that on a Zoom meeting, at least not without a lot more awkward formality.
Right. It's the difference between when I interview someone and we get connected on a tool and we're live and I say, OK, and well, you know,
and it's all this big buildup versus going to their house and sitting down with them and recording an interview of just a chat in a chair.
It's like these virtual meetings, you're kind of on you're presenting a little bit.
There's a camera on you. It is a human being. I think we can't help it.
When when you see your face in a little box and you see other people are watching you, there's just parts of your brain that turn on.
You're in presentation mode. At least that's how it works for me.
And that's not to say I can't hang out with a friend or something or a family member on a call.
And that's fine. But for these conferences and events, for me to actually be comfortable,
I probably need to have my camera off because otherwise I feel like I'm distracted by the fact that I'm sort of in presentation mode.
But then it's sort of it even reduces the network effect even further.
I know I'm I'm clutching about something that I, you know, I should just be grateful is even happening because these events are taking a real beating.
But I guess at this point into it coming into September and I'm thinking about how usually October.
Well, this is what makes me this is what got me started thinking about this, actually, unless I'm wrong.
I think the last event I did was Texas Cyber Summit, which was in October.
Yeah, you're right. Wow. That really was like a universe ago.
Yeah. And, you know, it's like, you know, after after a breakup, you know, you want to go out and like be free and flaunt it.
You know, I feel like I want to get out there and, you know, shake my moneymaker and, you know, socially distance maybe.
But now that's a vision. Yeah. I think he means his microphone. He's shaking his microphone.
Oh, yeah. You know what? They're talking to people and seeing people and stuff like that.
But so do you feel that once this is over, you're going to go out hard or do you think it's going to take a toll?
I don't know. I don't know. Like I envisioned a lot more live content in 2020.
I even pictured doing some of these shows on location somewhere because why not?
Like I've been doing this for so long. Why not change it up?
Maybe if I can find a spot that kind of has a live feel but isn't too distracting and loud, it could be a lot of fun.
Take a train ride down to Seattle, set up a little temporary recording space and doing it live from downtown Seattle today.
I thought I'd be doing a lot of that in 2020 and I've done none of it because it was the winter and then and then the COVID lockdowns and it really hit Seattle hard initially.
So it just all came to halt and all the events got canceled.
I ended up not being able to make it to scale and Linux fest got canceled and just boom and all shut down.
And so a year has gone by and what I thought would be a rather common part of the business and the content has not even materialized at all.
And it's woe is me, right? I mean, I'm not trying to make it sound like it's some big loss,
but it's something I just have been reflecting on recently and thinking how I envisioned at the beginning of the year things would play out really differently in that regard.
Right. And you miss a couple of conferences and you're like, OK, well, that sucks. But then after a while you realize, yeah, you'd really do have this yearning in some human part of you that wants that connection.
And there's the aspect of employment, too. I feel that conferences are a great way to network and get jobs if you're looking for work.
A lot of times they're actively recruiting at booths and there's always folks who have open positions that are walking around in the hallway track.
I see it happen every conference I go to. Yes. And that that could be really useful right now.
And that's also not happening. And I realize it can't. But as soon as it's safe to return, I will go back out myself.
I think it's an important aspect of community building and building all these relationships and seeing these people who we talk about in the headlines actually in person.
But it's not for everybody. I get that. So anyways, let's end it on something positive.
And I want to say thank you to the Coder QA team. Last episode, we announced that we were launching a membership program to help keep the show sustainable.
And we would include a few perks for those members. And you can go to Coder QA dot co if you want to sign up.
You get what I'm calling a very limited ad feed. There are some contractually obligated ads in there, but they're very they're tight and tidy.
But it's essentially ad free, but it's fully produced and edited otherwise with the full mix. And it's available when you sign up at Coder QA dot co.
And I just want to say thank you to everybody who became part of the Coder QA team. Now we have next.
I say the end of this quarter, right? That's when you need to do our code early.
Did I get it? You code early. You got it. This is our new thing.
We're doing West is we launched a membership program to help cover the production cost of the show and keep it sustainable.
And as a thank you to the Coder QA team, we have the ad free feed with limited ads.
And we have the quarterly coderly quarterly update where we'll look back at trends and news items and stories from the show and kind of do a recap.
I love that. Yeah. Yeah. I'm also I am kind of cooking up other ideas for the membership stuff like annual shows.
And if you're a member of any of the programs you would get and kind of other perks that are just applicable to all members.
So you've been thinking about it. I don't know if there's any more Jar Jar coupons.
I forgot to check before we went on air, but you can try coupon Jar Jar to get to get it knocked the two dollars off knocked up.
Boom, not just cut it right off. Crazy Chris is cutting two dollars off if you use promo code Jar Jar, although it may be all used up.
But go to Coder QA dot co to find out. And then it's just six dollars a month forever as long as you keep it active.
Thank you to everybody who did sign up for that. It was really nice.
And so it's super nice because, you know, not everything is in place yet.
Right. Like we don't really have a long runway at the moment, and it's not a certain future by any stretch of the imagination.
And if it wasn't for the goodwill of the community and the great folks behind the scenes that help make it all possible, like Mike and Wes and and others.
I don't think I could even be attempting something like this at this point in time, but I'm hoping that we've got the right recipe.
We've got the right combination of people and we've got the right support from the community.
So it's really, really nice to see people jumping on the Coder QA team, Coder QA dot co.
And that's all I have for that. Mike, you got anything you want to send people to?
I know you said you might have a job opening soon. Where where would people be best to like stay tuned for that kind of thing?
I would go to themadbotter.com or follow me on Twitter at Dumanuco.
Excellent. Excellent. I can do that. That's easy enough.
There are host bio links in the show notes, too, which will take you to Mike's Twitter.
Mr. Payne, we ought to plug Linux unplugged the double recording on Sunday, which is the 12th, I think, or the 13th.
It is the 13th. Yeah, we've got a double coming up.
Yeah. So check the calendar on Sunday, the 13th.
We're doing an extra Linux unplugged if you like to do the live thing.
And of course, we'll have a regular episode. You can catch Wes and I on Linux unplugged every single Tuesday.
The same bat time, really. Just a different bat day.
You can do it at noon over there as well at jblive.tv.
You can follow the show at Coder Radio Show on Twitter.
We also have links to the membership at Coder dot show, links to everything we talked about, including stories and more at Coder dot show slash 378.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of the Coder Radio program. We'll see you right back here next week.