This is KOTOR Radio, episode 405 for September 26, 2022.
Hello, friends, and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and business of software development and the world of technology.
From Sacramento, California, my name is Chris, and joining us from his podcasting base, it's
our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello, Chris.
How are you in sunny CA?
Warm.
It is warm here.
It is like in the mid-90s, you know?
So I'm getting like a little last little surge of summer, but we're doing all right because
listener Jeff hooked us up with a great little spot and some power hookups, so I got the
air conditioners going.
I really can't complain.
You know, it's pretty comfortable as far as mid-90s go.
And it's been a good trip.
We've already done two of the meetups, so we're halfway done, and that's been really
exciting.
They've gone well.
At one of them, I got there early and managed to get a whole dinner, too, which was great.
You know, a little barbecue, and we're doing breweries the whole way, so there's always
great drinks.
Nice.
Yeah.
Our next meetup is this Friday as we release 6 p.m. at the Congregation Ale House in Pasadena,
which will be just after our JPL meetup, so there's just so much going on.
I have been running nonstop.
I'm talking like getting up at 3.45 a.m., 3.30 a.m., 6 a.m. since we got off the air
last week.
It's been a mad dash.
Vacation it is not, but guess what?
We did get an email into the show, and it's a little spicy, so why don't we just kick
the show off with a spicy take?
Let's do some spice.
Thrill 64, or I'm sorry, Thrill 46 via Matrix wrote in, hey, Mike and Chris, long time first
time, have I been duped?
I bought a PinePhone Pro, and the Rock Pro 64, and I own a PineBook Pro.
Wow, you're all in.
And all of them have been sold as basically developer editions.
I bought them thinking an army of developers would be creating software for these devices,
and then soon after we'd see a generation of consumer devices ship that would create
a user base.
Here we are, years later, and most everything they make is still in beta mode.
I'm not sure anything is close to mainstream adoption, and I feel silly for buying these
quote developer devices.
Developer for who?
Has it all been a scam?
Is it a scam?
No, right?
It's not a scam.
It's really, really hard to start a developer ecosystem in the age of the giant, shall we
say, oligopoly ecosystems that exist.
And I kind of think the PineBook, I don't know much about the phone, but I feel like
a lot of the energy behind the PineBook has kind of been taken by the framework laptop
too in recent years.
Is that a fair assessment, Chris, of the kind of the tinkerer crowd?
Yeah, I could see that.
The dream of the PineBook was that Rock Pro 64 platform.
I kind of feel what they're saying here.
For example, they're selling the PinePhone Pro Explorer Edition, but it really isn't
any more refined than the previous PinePhone that wasn't a pro that they called a developer
edition.
Like nothing really changed.
The software state is really kind of the same.
And they kind of always wave it away by saying, with a little note on there, say, well, you
know, we're really transparent and upfront.
The PinePhone Pro Explorer Edition is aimed at Linux developers with extensive knowledge
of embedded systems or experience on mobile Linux.
And I kind of see what he's saying.
It's like they always are promising, well, these are for the developers today.
Look at your hands on it, and then later down the road, we'll make better versions that
regular people can buy, normals, except for that never comes.
It's just this perpetual beta for all of the products.
And it's kind of like they've just come up with this way of saying, well, but if we just
tell them it's just aimed at early adopters, then it's fine that it's not ever a complete
product.
Maybe that's true.
Maybe.
But, you know, all right, this could have happened with other platforms, too, right?
And I feel like if you're jumping in super early, you're taking the risk reward of, I'm
coming in super early, probably going to be a nothing burger, this new platform.
But if it does take off, then I'm in there on the ground floor, right?
And you could really, if you're a developer yourself, for the writer, take huge advantage
of that.
And if you're a user, well, then, you know, you get to be one of the first users on the
platform, which is kind of cool.
Having said that, but basically, if you're looking for like an App Store ecosystem, I
don't think you're going to get that.
I do think the alternative to the big oligopolies or the duopoly is going to be like the web,
right?
PWAs or...
Yeah.
I still have dreams about WebAssembly.
More, you know, literally websites, right?
Web apps that are just posted somewhere.
The future, you mean?
The future is 2006.
You know, one thing that does strike me, Kyron, I'm probably saying that, Kyron, actually,
in the matrix chat says, developing for the PinePhone is a nightmare.
All of the OS providers have done things differently.
Yeah, give that a ding.
I wrote a hack for Posh that meant that the phone would wake on call properly, but it
only works on Mobian and postmarket OS.
Everything else is weird.
The battle between Qt and Gnome is one that needs to be won as well.
That's also a great point.
That tear between GTK and Qt on mobile is even more acute.
And there's a lot of effort on both sides, and they're not really super compatible environments
in terms of look, flow, and feel.
Like Pine could never, never make...
They could never pull that off.
Right, they're not going to be able to change that.
So they have to wait for upstream, and upstream is too busy fighting between toolkits, and
they're not really fighting, but they're just too busy really doing their own things to
make something cohesive that a hardware manufacturer like Pine could ship.
Right, so this sounds like the Android fragmentation issues on steroids, basically.
I think so.
I mean, over time, things in Android have gotten better, but that took the commercial
hands of Google to work with vendors, to create the Treble project, to work on the AB boot
system.
You know, it's funny.
Last night, Listener Jeff and I flashed my Pixel 3 to Graphene OS, which is an alternative
Google-free...
Did you get any beads?
No.
Maybe once I get a few more apps working, that's when I unlock the beads.
It's not bad, man.
It's not bad.
You know, you're definitely limited without Google Play services.
But if you wanted just a basic smartphone with some...
You know, I mean, there's F-Droid and Aurora Store.
There's some...
I have Nextcloud on here.
I've got VLC.
I've got K9 Mail, Element Chat.
I've got an open source fork of Telegram.
I've got a Chrome fork that's de-Googled.
I got an open source keyboard that's pretty good.
You know, honestly, it's not that bad.
They can really do something with it.
I don't know how far they can really ever get away from Google.
They're always going to be subject to Google.
But this just seems like the way we should have gone.
This is where the community should have focused, is things like Graphene OS.
We should have just acknowledged it.
I don't know if these Linux-native environments or this Linux-native hardware, like the Pine
stuff, is ever going to have more than a few thousand users, you know, tens of thousands
of users at most.
It's just never going to get that...
It's never going to get that critical mass.
I've just had to come to accept that.
And so now I'm kind of looking at things like Graphene OS and thinking, boy, we probably
should have just gone this way all along.
I'm still waiting for my Firefox phone.
Are you getting a 14?
Did you tell...
Are you skipping it?
I am...
I mean, I'm not getting one now, right?
You know, I could always drop my phone.
Now, why haven't you just gotten their upgrade program?
You know, I've been avoiding the upgrades.
I'm still on a 12 Pro.
I bet you that upgrade program would be a write-off for you.
It would, but honestly, the last time I upgraded, I think I upgraded from an 11 to a 12 Pro.
And I screwed up one of my TFA apps, and that created such a hassle.
So I use my phone as an actual phone slash overcast player.
I just don't care that much, right?
I am noticing the battery health over the two and a half years, whatever it's been,
it's telling me it's 80% now.
If I got one, I think I'd want the Max in purple, which one is...
I did have one in the car.
I did look, but it's late October, and it's also like $1,100.
So it just doesn't feel worth it to me.
How about you?
Or you're on the upgrade thing, aren't you?
Yeah, I decided to do it.
But I actually intentionally waited because I don't want it to arrive until end of October
because I'm on this trip.
Right.
Yeah, I think it's...
You know, they got me...
They'll almost always get me with the camera.
And they got me with the satellite calling.
And then I'm actually downsizing, so I think I'm actually going to save a little bit of
money because the payment scales to the size of phone you get.
But we'll see.
We'll see.
Maybe Graphene OS will work out.
I'm skeptical, but I am hopeful.
I really like...
The original Pixel 3 is the perfect size phone.
It's perfect.
It fits in my hand so well.
It fits in my pocket.
It's a little tall.
It's a little narrow.
It's such a thing of beauty.
I think it might be the best Pixel ever.
The Pixel 3, not the 3a.
The 3a is fine, but I have the Pixel 3.
I'm telling you, if I could replace the battery in this and be happy with Graphene OS, I would
try to make this my primary phone.
It's just such a beautiful size.
So I'm hopeful.
We'll see.
Maybe the iPhone 14 will be my last iPhone.
Here's my spicy prediction.
Nope.
Yeah.
I think you're probably right on that one.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account, and it's just a great way to
support the show.
Linode makes cloud computing simple, affordable, and accessible.
Linode is our cloud hosting provider.
It's where we deploy everything we've built in the last few years.
And we love the fact that Linode's performance, price, and support are all there just the
way we like them.
And we love the fact that you can tell they're Linux geeks too.
That's really what got them to build Linode nearly 19 years ago.
And now today, here they are 30% to 50% cheaper than the hyperscalers out there that have
really specific platforms with specific features and languages that really just want to lock
you in.
Linode's an alternative cloud provider.
They have infrastructure, 11 data centers around the world.
They are their own ISP.
They have a fully functional, clean, easy to use API.
They integrate with your infrastructure management, and they can give you a full Linux platform
that you can manage.
And on top of that, they have one click deployment applications that are really simple.
And they have a bunch of great services on the back end that you might want to use too.
I personally, I use the snot out of the S3 storage.
They have S3 compatible object storage.
And I've just discovered yet another use for it.
I have Duplicati, which is a great Linux backup application.
And you can just point it directly at S3 object storage like Linodes.
And it's just so fantastic the flexibility you get with that.
You combine that with the API and the command line client that lets you easily create buckets
and move files around.
It's just a great way to share files in general for us here at JP.
But on top of that, the performance of their systems is just absolutely fantastic.
If you Google search cloud CPU benchmarks and you look at the results that Linode has put
out from an independent study provider, but Linode is hosting it up on their website,
the report reveals how the different VPSs and cloud providers stack up and how much
faster Linode systems are.
It's a great report.
It's from Cloud Spectator.
It's their CPU benchmark report.
You can go look that up, or you can go find it on Linode's website, and you can see how
Linode's performance stacks up.
When you combine that with PCIe MVMe storage, the fact that they are their own ISP means
their connections scream, right?
And then you realize the pricing.
It all comes together with Linode.
That's why we use it.
I think you'll love it.
Go try it out.
It's fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You got to try it for yourself or your next project.
So go get that $100, support the show, and kick the tires for yourself.
Linode.com slash coder.
That's linode.com slash coder.
All right, Mr. Dominic, you are back on the Linux train.
Been using it for just over a month full time, I believe, you've gotten some hardware.
So I think that's definitely played a factor, the Dev1 and the Thalia, which we'll talk
about in a little bit.
So tell me what it's been like living the Linux life full time again.
It's been pretty smooth.
I'm living that pop OS life, the Thalia, of course, and the Dev1 come pre-installed with
it.
I am mastering the tiling keyboard shortcuts, which is just a much better way to handle
the whole tiling thing in PATH.
I'm liking it.
You know, it's funny.
I was getting irritated with Monterey, Mac OS Monterey, and some of the weird changes
that Mac continues to make to the Unix tools because they have to.
I don't know why.
Right.
They always they always are making changes.
They're always making like strange Apple specific things.
I think a lot of it has to do with their developer tool chain goes through Xcode.
Every time you update Xcode, crazy shit happens to like your C headers.
But yeah, so decided I try it out again.
And honestly, a big factor in me purchasing this Thalia was I did briefly try a review
unit and I kind of missed Tactical Strategy RPGs and of course, MTG Arena, which also
runs on Mac, but I love it so far.
I mean, it's been very good.
I wrote a review of it.
It's pretty it's pretty fast.
It's I mean, it's got to be the fastest machine I've ever owned for day to day.
What I do.
Well, starting with the Linux side, the Pop OS side.
The only thing I'm noticing is some of the more interesting newer tools, like in particular
warp terminal, don't have Linux versions.
And that's been kind of a minor annoyance.
Having said that, the version of Bash on, I think I'm on 2204, does auto complete significantly
better than the version of Zshell on Mac OS.
So it's less of a hole in my day to day life, but it's still there.
I mean, every once in a while I'll get the like some of the JetBrains tools.
I feel like they render the fonts too smally.
But other than that, I mean, I have been very happy.
I have notably not installed any additional extensions on GNOME, because I just decided
to avoid that problem and stick with one desktop background.
Have you ever played around with the fish show?
I have.
We covered it like for.
Yeah.
OK.
I mean, that's pretty great on Linux.
You know, a lot of good auto completion in there and stuff like that.
It's great.
But I'm lazy.
Right.
Yeah.
I'm having a I am having a tougher time with pop.
I mean, I love our friends over at System 76, but I am having a I have I have a harder
time because I've been using traditional GNOME for a while now.
So switching back to cosmic and like not having the gestures to swipe to horizontal workspaces
I have found has been a little tricky because one of the things that I have really ingrained
with my GNOME shell usage is every major application window should probably have its own virtual
desktop.
And that's really doable on like a laptop screen when you're swiping sideways between
virtual desktops.
And I just kind of I find that workflow falls down with the cosmic layout.
But so you've been so you've you've now you've been using desktop Linux on the dev one.
You've now used it on the Thalia, which is a beast.
I'll talk more about my experience with the Thalia because I got one for review as well.
And I ran a ton of tests against it.
But I'm just curious to to just get to capture what is it for you that or is there a difference
between using desktop Linux on the dev one and using desktop Linux on the Thalia?
Just the form factor differences.
Anything.
I was thinking actually in performance and if you can feel a difference, if you can tell
between the hardware or if it kind of the interface is just sort of fast, regardless,
just that kind of impressions.
I mean, the dev one is pretty fast.
I would say this is kind of horrible.
This is maybe damning with faint praise.
But the reason I'm able to use the dev one instead of a MacBook finally as my day to
day driver for a laptop, you know, when I'm like working at a bar, coffee shop or whatever
is or even just like in my kitchen because six year old the speakers, the onboard speakers
don't make me want to stab myself in the ears.
They are the they're the best Linux laptop speakers, I think.
Right.
Which I would even say like I had the Gen one XPS and then I had a later generation
XPS was not the case.
You know, I kind of use the Thalia of different things, right?
Like the dev one.
It's kind of sad because I spent well, we could you have the link in the notes where
you can see the neo fetch for the Thalia spent like twenty one, twenty two hundred on the
Thalia.
And I use it a lot less than I do the dev one.
Ah, sure.
But when I'm using it, it's definitely heavier workloads.
It's usually something where I'm, you know, using a Windows client application that we
developed, hooking into a local host version of some Python or Ruby API that we wrote running
on the Linux host VM, right?
So it's like a Windows 10.
I'm still using Windows 10 for my VM because, you know, why not?
And a Linux and the pop OS host to do local API testing without, you know, touching the
actual database on a staging server or production.
I think that's great.
I mean, I like that workflow.
That's a little much to ask of the dev one, I feel.
Though I'm sure it's possible it would just lag a bit, right?
Yeah, I think your your impression is correct.
I was shocked at a couple of the jobs that I tested.
Just how much faster the Thalia was that I thought the Thalia failed to do the test.
But you know, when you look at the benchmarks and I'll link to a couple of them in the show
notes and the cool thing about these is you can actually then there's a command in that
link where you can run that exact benchmark against your system and see how it compares
to the dev one and the Thalia that I tested against.
And when you look at those benchmarks, it's almost what you'd expect.
The dev one delivers a lot for eleven hundred dollars.
The dev one is just like very impressive.
It just can't touch what the Thalia can deliver for like twenty five hundred dollars or twenty
seven hundred dollars or however you can figure it, right?
And you just that really bears out in the testing.
I mean, that they're just there's that reality of it.
In fact, when I was looking at it.
The dev one and the Thalia were pretty neck and neck on things that were like disk I.O.
related.
So if your job involves a lot of IOPS and disk I.O. stuff, you're not going to see a
huge increase with the Thalia unless you bought like a very fast drive for the Thalia.
But if you go with like the stock parts on both of them, when it comes to things that
are disk bound, they're just about match the Thalia is a little bit faster.
Obviously when it comes to CPU bound stuff, that's where the Thalia can really, really,
really, really pull ahead.
That's not the whole story, though, I found.
So I have some negatives.
In fact, I have kind of like a killer for me, perhaps, on the Thalia, a fatal flaw,
if you will.
But I'll get to that in a moment.
I'm just curious to know now that you've kind of deep dived into Linux again, just before
we move to finalize on the hardware stuff, what have you found that isn't working for
you very well?
What have you found that still seems to be busticated?
So I'd say a few things I did.
So I was playing Civ 5 with some of the System 76 folks and some other community people.
And I think this is not Pop or Ubuntu's fault.
I think this is more the developers of the Civ 5 port of Linux, because it was the native
version, not the Windows version.
Just like never imagine GPU CPUs with more than eight threads or eight cores.
You had to go in there and edit an INI file, which it just feels very Linux-y, right?
Having to Vim in to get a game to work.
I remember doing that for World of Warcraft years ago, having to just change a bunch of
settings via Vim.
Everything was kind of working out of the box.
I'd say a big thing I've done differently is I gave up on my irrational hatred of Flatpak
and I've just embraced the Flatpak lifestyle with the exception of VS Code still.
Yeah.
Yeah, VS Code, I agree.
Because I need it to be able to hit parts of the system that are right.
I agree with you on that.
If you embrace Flatpak and you're on GNOME, it is just an easier life.
Things are just a little simpler.
And those applications break less, too, because they're not tied to all the other system dependency
ies.
Yeah.
I would say the only...
Okay.
I had two issues so far in about a month.
One is literally right before we came on the air, I had plugged in the...
I don't know what you call it, Chris, the U22 thing, the Zoom...
Oh, yeah.
Yep.
The U22.
The little...
Yep.
The U22.
And for whatever reason, Pop couldn't pick it up, so I just had to reboot and then I
picked it up.
I have no idea why.
Yeah.
That could be...
Pop is using PipeWire now.
Okay.
He's using PipeWire.
It's just new stuff.
I occasionally notice that it incorrectly, and this is only on the Thalio, so I'm not
sure what's up with that, will take my Wi-Fi to 2.4 megahertz or gigahertz, whatever it
is, instead of five, which cuts the speed in half.
But again, I disconnect the Wi-Fi and reconnect it and it's fine and it only seems to happen
after I let it go to sleep, but I haven't been able...
It's only happened twice in a month, so I'm not sure if that's...
Yeah.
Like interference, because I don't know how well this will age, but there's currently
a hurricane coming to where I live in Florida, so all the kids are out of school.
Right now, both kids are like gaming away, right?
One's on a Nintendo, one's on an Xbox.
Everything's got an online connected DRM bullshit thing, so it might just be my router is currently
getting smacked around a little bit.
I've had that on the Dev1 recently.
Okay.
I've had the Wi-Fi not reconnecting, and I'm on Nix, too.
I'm not on POP anymore.
Okay, so that's weird.
Yeah, maybe it's a kernel driver issue.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
That's where you go to get a personal account for up to 20 devices for free, and that's
not just like a limited time thing, and it's a great way to support the show as well.
So Tailscale is a zero config VPN.
Just about everybody must know about Tailscale right now, because I feel like it's been changing
the remote networking landscape for the last year, just changing the way people do work.
It manages firewalls for you.
It takes care of NAT for you, and you can get it installed on your device, be it a computer,
a server, a phone, a Raspberry Pi, I don't know, a VPS, a VM, a container, home assistant.
I mean, you can get it up and running within minutes.
You quickly and easily create a secure, flat mesh network between your systems powered
by WireGuard's noise protocol.
Yep, it's a WireGuard mesh network, and they have a bunch of great features inside of there
as well, like TailScale Send.
You can use TailScale Send as sort of like AirDrop for all of your TailScale devices,
so you can send files between them easily.
And then there's TailScale SSH.
And also, just part of TailScale, it allows you to establish an SSH connection between
your devices.
You're not moving around SSH keys like an animal.
No, you're actually authenticating your SSH connection using WireGuard.
It's pretty awesome, you guys.
And you can try it up for free to 20 devices to really get a sense of this thing and see
how intelligent it is.
Like, when you're moving files between devices, if they're on the same LAN, TailScale knows
that, and it does it over the LAN.
You can use your TailScale IPs, it'll be protected, but they can transfer directly to each other.
And it's not gonna just route all of your traffic over the tunnel.
TailScale intelligently chooses what traffic is supposed to go to the TailScale network.
You know, it's TCP IP.
It knows how this can work.
You just needed software to do it right.
That's TailScale.
Then you combine that with their single sign-on support.
You combine that with the fact that they have ACL controls that allow you to share certain
machines or just certain ports with individuals.
It's so powerful.
It'll change how you do VPNs forever.
So go try it out, tailscale.com slash coder.
One more time, tailscale.com slash coder.
The big thing that we haven't mentioned is the Thaleo has seen a redesign of its case.
You touch on this in your review.
They've taken away that wood veneer side, and they've replaced it with more of a customizable
strip that you can put different looks on.
It's a clean, sharp look.
I like it.
I see one that's custom branded for events.
You know what I'm talking about?
Yes, I do.
Yeah.
So I like the new design.
I was sent the Thaleo, the regular small Thaleo.
Did you end up...
Now, but you got a review unit.
Let's talk about this for a moment.
You got a review unit.
I think you got a similar one with a different graphics card, and you turned around and said,
okay, great.
I'll buy one.
So which one did you actually get, and what made you decide to pull the trigger on buying
it?
So I actually got the wrong review unit.
Oh, interesting.
I got somebody else's review unit, so I had to send it back anyway, but I'm like, you
know what?
I'm just going to buy one anyway, so I'll just buy it.
I literally bought the first production one off the line, I was told.
I bet.
Yeah, well, if you're buying it when the review units are going out...
Since I bought it before it came out.
The difference between this and the review unit is the review unit was more of a base
model.
This is slightly upgraded.
I went for a slightly bigger GPU, and I went up to 32 gigs of RAM.
Obviously, you can max it out at 64.
I know I've already heard from people who want to know why I didn't just do that.
The answer is I didn't feel like spending the money that second.
Sure.
While you're looking it up, I'll tell you what my review unit was.
So mine came with the AMD Ryzen 9 5900X 12 core, base clock of 3.7.
They can peak up to like four something, though.
32 gigs of RAM, one terabyte Samsung SSD 980 Pro.
I had the NVIDIA GeForce RTX 3060 Ti eight gigabyte card in there.
And for most of my review, I was running Nix.
For some of it, I was running POP, but Nix OS with kernel 519.6, so the latest kernel,
ButterFS on the hard drive, and NVIDIA 515.48.07 as my NVIDIA driver.
And so it's a pretty beefy rig.
That 3060 Ti is no slouch, and that Ryzen 9 5900X 12 core is no slouch either.
How are you finding it for, I'm very curious for like video encoding if you're doing any
of that.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, it's a screamer for sure.
It exceeds any of like my requirements by far.
It really does.
I really pushed this thing.
I was very, very impressed.
I don't know if you noticed this, but it gets warm.
To the touch?
Let me see.
If you really push it.
If you push both the GPU and the CPU, it gets really warm.
Really?
And if you look at the internal design of the thing, and I'm not saying it's dangerous,
but I'm saying it's warm.
If you look at the internal design of the thing, there's an intake fan on the bottom
that's blowing upwards from the bottom of the case, and it's blowing over the GPU.
And then there's an intake fan above the GPU that's sucking in for the CPU.
So I reason that you're essentially blowing hot GPU air into the CPU air intake.
And so you get to a point where the CPU just cannot fully cool itself, so it begins to
thermal throttle pretty quickly when you're pushing both systems.
Now even thermal throttle, this thing, and I have it in the benchmarks, it's a killer,
but it is nonetheless thermal throttling.
And if you stress the CPU and the GPU, like maybe you're doing a machine learning analysis
job, something like that, training some models, the whole case gets warm to the touch.
You know, the RAM gets in the 80 Celsius degrees temperature.
The CPUs are getting to their max.
All of it is within spec.
I want to stress that, but it got a lot warmer than I expected.
And when you're when you're pushing that 3060, it's no joke, man, that machine is taking
over 300 watts of power to run the CPU and the GPU at full tilt.
So it is a massive draw.
And when it's idle, when you're not running the GPU and you're just kind of doing your
day to day stuff, it's still in the 100 watt range.
And that's just the reality still of the X86 platform.
This is not a knock against the Thaleo.
That's just the nature of this platform.
It's just striking when you're comparing it to, like, say, a MacBook Pro Ultra Max, whatever,
and you run some of the same tests and the MacBook Max Ultra Pro, whatever, never audibly
kicks its fans up, never gets warm to the touch and still does really well in the benchmarks.
And it's using maybe 30 watts to do all of that.
And the Thaleo is using 300 watts.
It's getting better performance, but it's not like in the next galaxy better.
And so for me, ultimately, I think I would want a bigger Thaleo.
I'd want a larger Thaleo.
So there was more maybe room between the components to cool things.
Not that I think it's really a problem, but if I'm buying a machine like this, I want
it to last eight years and I don't necessarily want to heat soak the RAM, the Northbridge
and some of the CPU components.
So I would probably get a little bit bigger Thaleo.
And for me, that was kind of the fatal flaw and why I didn't order one, because I am in
desperate need of an improved studio setup.
I am going to spend some time running this as an OBS machine and just putting it under
that workload where it's doing streaming, it's doing some capture, but it's not going
to max it out.
And I want to see what the thermals are under that load.
They may be completely acceptable in that scenario because I want to underscore when
I'm looking at these high thermals, I'm rendering.
What I did is, for example, is I had FFmpeg rendering a video on a couple of cores while
I played a video game, not like a crazy video game like CSGO.
And this machine can easily, easily handle that kind of load.
And I could get into thermal throttling territory within five minutes in that scenario.
Just things like that.
And then I just tried different benchmarks and different tests.
Again, even thermal throttled, it's still a monster, but you know, it's just something
to be aware of.
And I think it's in part because it's just it's a small unit.
The base Thaleo is adorably small.
It's kind of like peak PC design in a way.
It's a great case.
It's a great size.
The revisions to this case with that with that new replaceable strip, but also the back
paneling just is cleaner.
They've labeled the ports.
They've really embraced the ports on this Thaleo.
And the case is really solid.
And they've also included brackets and and things that really clamp the gear down, like
the GPU and stuff like that, so it doesn't fall off in shipping.
So it's a really solidly built PC.
It's just also very small, with extremely powerful components packed in there.
And they're all running within spec.
They're all absolutely within spec, but it's a little hotter than I expected.
And over 300 watts is a little more than I expected.
So it's all doable.
Yeah, it's interesting, because they also make a different body.
And I wonder one of my questions when figuring mine was how what effect because it's the
same case, do the different GPUs have on thermals?
I care less about thermals than you, because you know what I care about, right?
Speed and no sound?
No sound.
Yeah.
Fan noise.
Now, the last Thaleo I tested was the first first-gen Thaleo.
And that definitely I think I had a whole blog post.
It sounded like an aircraft carrier.
This is much improved, but I would note that my GPU is an AMD ATI, also NeoFetch, terrible,
terrible output here, device 743F.
That means nothing except it just means that it's like the baby AMD GPU.
So I'm not seeing that I have my hand that I'm not feeling any kind of thermal pressure.
Right.
Again, we're just doing squadcast right now.
So I have what?
Yeah.
Not bad, right?
And exactly, if you're just pushing one of the subsystems, like most video games, once
they're loaded up, they don't really push the CPU a whole bunch.
And when you've got like 24 virtual cores to work with, only a couple of them are doing
anything.
But what I've noticed, Mike, is the Thaleo Mira and Major and the Mega and the Massive,
those are the other bigger Thaleos that are physically larger as well.
They all have side venting.
And maybe that's just because they haven't like they haven't gone back and redesigned
those cases.
Or I don't know, maybe they have.
But I've noticed they seem to have a beefier cooling system, like the Mega and the Massive
especially have a lot beefier side cooling.
Maybe there's something there.
I'm sure we'll find out something I want to experiment more with.
And I think they could probably rightfully argue that it's not actually a problem because
you know, they've tested these things just to say that they are intricate and obsessive
over details is is understating how much they look at this.
I mean, they made a panel that's the that's the PCP, the chips in their damn keyboard
for the.
Yeah.
It looks so great, actually.
I may still end up buying one once I do the OBS test.
If it you know, everything works out fine there in a real world usage, like when I used
it as my desktop for a couple of weeks.
Totally fine.
Good, solid device.
You know, you've got to live with certain quirks of Linux when you have a large device
like that, like hooking up multiple displays can still be a little glitchy, but all manageable
and just such a rockin system.
You can really just push it and it just takes it.
So I really enjoyed my time with the Thaleo.
I'll give it I'll give it a chance as an OBS machine, but I haven't pulled the trigger
yet.
I'm glad you got one.
I think it's I think it's going to be good.
Yeah, it's nice.
I you know, it's funny.
I I'm I just went down a rabbit hole on this weird AMD GPU that I bought mostly because
I'm very sure that GPU prices are going down soon.
I just feel pretty strongly about that.
I wrote that in my review, but I didn't realize how low end this beige gobby again, awful
name.
Seriously, AMD, just crap.
It's holding up pretty well.
I mean, I was playing Spider-Man remastered on it, getting decent frame rates.
It looked bad as good as it would on a PS4.
My PS5, you know, pumped all the way up could could probably beat it.
And maybe there's tweaks I can make and be a little more aggressive, right, and ludicrous
to make it run better.
I'm kind of interested in what this new AMD architecture is going to do Thaleo aside,
to be honest.
This is a very affordable.
This was a two hundred dollar upgrade.
And the you know, the great thing about those AMD cards, they're going to work great with
your Linux desktop.
It's not going to be a struggle.
You're not going to go get some sort of weird Nvidia package and run through some sort of
install script.
You just plug it in.
If you got a modern kernel and they've upstream, the drivers just works.
And well, and usually for a couple of years, they're the same drivers.
So you just buy another one, a bigger one when you have the money and can almost always
just swap it in.
Yeah.
That's what I'm saying now, I think I'd probably go with a with a, you know, a medium, mid
of the road, mid road that I could get by with and I'd be happy with today GPU.
But I don't think I'd I'd go for like the biggest high end purchase you could just yet.
I agree with you.
Wait a little bit.
Save a few hundred bucks.
Yeah, I think so.
That's the way to do it.
But Thaleo is a it's a really solid system.
It made for a great next box.
And obviously it ran pop great as well.
So clearly I I want to say I was tempted to do I want to say it's the best desktop PC
right now that I know of.
I think it might be when you consider the unique case design, the work that goes into
the internals, just how slick of a system overall is and like the quality of like the
corners, the port holes, just the button even for the power.
All of it is so refined, so obsessed over.
I just don't know of any other desktop PC with that kind of care, that kind of uniqueness
to it.
It's a pretty special machine.
Booster Graham, let's do a few boosts.
What do you say?
Booster Graham, Booster Graham, Woden 501 boosted with 5000 sats.
He says, I got a future trip idea.
Once the new Intel fab opens in Columbus, get a tour set up and then take a trip way
over on the I-70 to meet us Midwest folk.
We've got craft beer and hotels.
Some of them have beer taps right in the rooms, he writes.
What that sounds very dangerous.
Holy crap, I would wreck myself.
That's amazing.
OK, well, you got a boost in and tell me which hotel specifically that I do want to get to
the Midwest.
So we're doing our West Coast tour right now.
I'm in Sacramento as we record because, you know, we did the East Coast.
We did the we did the we did like Denver area.
So it seemed like it was time to the West Coast.
But I you know, there's still so much room in between.
So Midwest is definitely on my list.
So send me the deets.
Sergeant Apple boosted in with two hundred and fifty sats boost.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Twenty five hundred sats.
He says on the future is the Web idea.
You guys have been kicking around.
Do we think Apple will ever come around and get on board with the Web?
Looking at iCloud Web apps, they're definitely short on Web skills.
Won't they just fight and stay native until the end?
Yes.
There's all the fight and stay native till the bitter end.
So, yeah.
Why would they do that?
Why would they not do that?
I mean, and do you think long term this is what I mean, like I'm talking long term.
Maybe this is what makes their platform less relevant.
You got to remember, like the vast majority of software that gets written is for businesses
and other organizations, not the whizz, bang a let's blog about it, you know, indie apps,
right?
So I. I guess both things can kind of be true, right?
Like I think they're super cool.
Rogue Amoeba Panic.
They can still exist.
And that's awesome as native Apple platform developers, for example.
And I'm sure although there really isn't the equivalent on Windows, right?
That's kind of the weird part.
But OK, but the vast majority of us who are either, you know, doing contracting or are
writing, you know, business type applications or even utility applications are probably
going to be better suited targeting Web technologies.
The big pink elephant in the gin bar here is what the hell happened to WebAssembly?
Like I'm on a Carmen Sandiego level mission here.
Yeah, like I've I did dip my toes into certain subreddits.
And it just seems like there's like some zealotry, but not a lot getting done.
Who would have thought?
OK.
All right.
Well, let me know if you ever do find where in the hell WebAssembly is.
I sure would like to know.
I'm hoping it's not like that weird spin off of Carmen Sandiego where it's we're in time
this WebAssembly.
I guess you mean a couple of dinosaurs and Richard Stallman having to go get it.
You know, that's where it goes.
That's where it ends up.
It always ends up with RMS tire boosts in with twenty one hundred sats.
And he says, what is Mike and your opinion on what is better, Web apps or electron apps?
From what I can tell, most electron apps are just Web apps and browsers that have lack
security.
Also, he says shame on you for getting him back into Magic the Gathering.
He sold his cards six months ago, but you talking about it is making him regret selling
them out.
And he says on the uniform topic, Pearl snapshots are awesome and boots are where it's at.
So if you had to pick Web app or electron app, do you have a choice?
Do you have a preference, I should say?
Yeah, I would say Web app.
But my my revealed behavior seems to be electron app for like things like slack and element
I.O. or element, whatever.
Me too.
I would answer Web app.
But then, of course, I like having I like having things as their own.
I just like the proper notifications.
Yeah, that too.
Yeah.
But by the way, on the Magic the Gathering, you don't need to buy a big collection, my
man.
Buy singles.
You'll be fine.
There you go.
Yeah, you'll be fine.
Just get a few singles.
Where can it go from there?
Nowhere.
Oh, but the beer taps in the hotel rooms were great.
That's fine.
Everybody's going to be OK.
OK, you got me.
All right.
Ammar boosted with a thousand twenty four cents.
He says, Hello, Chris.
Hello, Mike.
I wanted to be a hipster, too.
I looked into Fleet as soon as they announced it.
But I I saw that they say in their FAQ section that it's mainly written in Kotlin, which
means it runs on a JVM.
All their stuff does.
Yeah, that's true.
They're considering open sourcing parts of the product or the technology behind it.
Both of those points are a big no to me, especially today in the V.S.
Code era.
But thanks for the show.
Yeah, it seems like Ammar also wanted to be a hipster.
Didn't work for him.
I'm concerned about JetBrains if before Fleet even officially ships as a product.
You and others are saying, where does this fit and why are they doing it like this?
That seems like a bad sign.
I know your point was the business market may keep it alive, but I don't know, man.
Just a little bit of a red flaggy.
You know what I mean?
Just a little red flaggy.
Oh, yeah.
I mean, the the IE6 level dominance of V.S. Code is it's nothing to sneeze at.
And Optimus Gray rounds this out with a big old row of McDuck's twenty two thousand two
hundred and twenty two sets.
Quacka Wacka.
It's a treasure.
Yippee.
And we're going to see Optimus Gray at JPL, too.
He says, I'm not a CPA.
But I have a program for them.
You may want to see if you can write off the recording mobile office when you're on a work
trip.
Again, not a CPA.
He says, I also gave a listen to the Drew cleaned up version.
And it's weird because he always listens live.
I missed the post show title talks, but, you know, I'm a member of the QA feed, so perhaps
I'll get it that way.
I need to be smarter about this kind of stuff.
He's right.
I could probably write off my mobile office.
There's probably a lot of things I could be writing off that I'm not.
I hate to solicit advice over the Internet on this kind of thing.
But if this is your area, specifically, if you're kind of familiar with what I do as
a business, reach out.
My tax bill is crushing and I need every defense I have.
So and I say that with no joke.
You wouldn't believe it.
You know, you just would not believe how reamed I get as a small business owner.
So I believe it.
Oh, yeah.
No, I know you would.
Oh, and the CPA is out there.
They know.
I think the people who just work nine to fives have no idea, have no idea how much money
we end up paying.
It's it's incredible.
Also, I just want to give a shout out to TACOF 751, who said, go check out Web three is doing
great.
It's the number three.
Web three is doing great, where the author is doing a fantastic job of documenting all
of the ridiculous things happening in the stupid world of crypto and Web three.
And it's brutal.
Didn't like the IRS dude or the head of the Fed to be like, this is all taxable security.
SEC said that about Ethereum the day after Ethereum announced their proof of work.
No, I'm sorry.
Proof of stake merge that, you know, for a security that one of the basic tests is, is
there a group of people managing it and is it something you're investing in expecting
a return based on the actions of those group of people?
That's Ethereum.
I mean, a lot of these cryptos have a group of people that are asking you to invest in
their thing, implying that you're going to get a return.
And it's called the Howie test.
There's multiple aspects of it, but that's one of the things that makes you a security.
And when you're a security, it's a totally different ballgame.
And you can't promote it like you can say, like property or real estate, you know, like
software.
Right.
You can say anything.
Yeah.
So no, but this is on this guy's site.
Web three is going great.
This is the story.
September 22nd, IRS gets permission for John Doe summons for taxpayers who don't report
crypto transactions.
Yeah.
Now that's for a particular exchange.
But yeah, that's what's going to happen now.
Oh, yeah.
This is, you know, potentially long term, a good thing.
We need a Hunger Games kind of cleaning out of these crappy crypto scams.
We need somebody to come through and just take them all out because so many of them
are pump and dump schemes where there is I'll just super brief because I think people need
to know this.
All of these cryptos after Bitcoin have a group of people behind them.
Ethereum is included in this list.
And the way that it all worked is that now all of them have a small group of developers
and they got what's called a pre mine.
So before the crypto even went live to the rest of the public, maybe they get like 20
million coins or a million coins or whatever their setup is.
So they get what's called a pre mine.
They get access to the coins before anyone else does.
Then once the crypto goes public on exchanges, people start buying and trading it.
Well, if you got something, a million of something for free and now it's worth a dollar, right?
It doesn't have to go big.
That's why so many of these cryptos are worth pennies.
If it goes worth 50 cents and you had a million of it, you're doing great.
And so now you sell.
And so you got the crypto token for nothing and then you dump it on the market.
And it's just this process that you repeat over and over again.
Ethereum is just a more complex version of this because they've done all of these little
things to constrain liquidity to make it easier for them to sell without causing the price
to dump.
And now they've launched proof of staking where you take your Ethereum and you give
it to a Coinbase or a crack and you give it to a third party and they stake it in the
network and you get yield off of that.
The funny thing is the developers have literally not written the code or published the code
to unstake.
Once you stake your Ethereum seems very suspicious, right?
It's locked up until they write the code and they won't be until some big releases down
the road and software is always on time.
Even in the most honest case, dude, the proof of stake merger was delayed by seven years.
They were trying to get it out.
It took them seven years to ship the proof of stake merger.
And now they're saying with the next merge, that's the next merger to that's when you'll
be able to unstick.
In the meantime, the founders that got all their pre-mined coins can sell, sell, sell,
and you can't sell your Ethereum because it's locked up staked.
You cannot withdraw it.
So they can now sell on the market with impunity and people can't pull out.
So it locks the liquidity and it locks the price in.
It is a brilliant scam.
They are pulling all the users of Ethereum and everybody, Oh, I want yield.
I want yield, I want yield and they're all fallen for it.
But I just, I can't believe we're watching this go down and Bitcoin suffers from none
of this.
There's no central person.
There was no pre-mined.
There's no staking.
It's not a security.
It has been declared by the SEC and the IRS as property years ago, reaffirmed by Gary
Gensler, the chairman of the SEC multiple times.
But yet we still see all these horrible scams that take grandma's savings and they just
need to be washed out.
They all need to go.
So maybe we'll see some of them, some of them fade away.
In the meantime, I remain here skeptical, keeping an eye on all things to call it out
as I see it, I'm watching them, I've got their number.
I know what they're up to.
I see that if you buy some of these crazy cryptos, you are their liquidity for exiting.
You understand that you're providing them exit liquidity.
That's how all of this works.
My old man taught me something a long time ago.
If you're sitting down at the poker table and you don't know who the sucker is.
You're the sucker.
Kick it out.
Leave.
Yeah.
Yep.
That's pretty much it.
So that's Chris's little pro tip for the internet.
So Web3 is doing just great.
You can go check that out.
JPEX.
Who would have thought they'd be so easy to sell?
Right.
God damn it.
I should have thought of this.
Yeah.
That could have been us, dude.
Jcoin.
Mr. Hill.
We could have done it, dude.
We were on the air.
We could have done it.
Robes.
We could still do Robcoin.
We could do Robcoin.
Yeah.
Maybe.
You know, I knew I was in a good place because Listener Jeff here, where he's put us up,
he's got a coat of robe.
So I knew he was good people.
You know?
You know, he's a man of taste and distinction at least.
Yeah.
Right.
Well, I want to say thank you to our members for investing in our content production,
for literally keeping us on the road this week.
We'll have a new code elite pretty soon for you because the quarter is coming up.
So if you'd like to become a member, CoderQA.co is where you go.
Or you can be like Optimus and become a member to all the shows.
Get all the special features at Jupiter.party.
Anywhere you want to send the good people, Mr. Dominic.
Go to DominicM.com and read all my Linuxy updates.
And we should say, if we didn't make it clear enough, your written Thalia review is up there
as well.
It is.
And there might be something this weekend, depending on how whacked I get by this hurricane.
Oh, man.
I hope everything goes OK.
You let me know.
Hey, listen, if not, you know, we actually did a show, do you remember, when I was up
in Jersey?
Yes.
We did one during Sandy.
I remember.
So I'm pretty sure we'll be back Monday at noon.
Yeah.
Yep.
Noon, Eastern, 9 a.m. Pacific over at Jupiter.tube.
You can follow the show at Coder Radio Show and the network is at Jupiter Signal.
Links to what we talked about today are Coder.show slash 485.
Our contact form is over there.
Send us an email.
It's a big part of the show.
We need your emails.
And of course, you can subscribe there as well.
And last but not least, you can boost with a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com.
See you next week.