This is KOTOR Radio, episode 471 for June 13th, 2022.
Hello friends and welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
My name is Chris and joining us in his KOTOR bathrobe, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike!
I may never put a shirt on again.
This is so comfortable, you and I both decided to wear our robes today.
Yeah, but I just want to say for those who aren't live, wow, that's going to be the image,
huh?
That's what we're doing?
I love, no, keep it up.
That is a handsome gentleman.
And for those who don't know, there is a Twitter link that I've made this available for you,
which by the way, three homosexual men have already liked, so.
How could they not?
They're my brothers.
And if, if for any of your homosexual automation needs, you need help, alice.dev, obviously.
There you go.
Alice does not discriminate.
Alice is fine with the L, the G, the B, even the T.
Put a plus in there, man.
Have a plus too.
The plus is confusing because Alice is partially written in C++.
So honestly, she came to me last night, she's like, dad, am I plus?
I'm like, no, you're plus plus, it's different.
What does plus mean?
I have no idea.
But it's, it's, it's like Star Trek Discovery.
You thought you were going to go fight Klingons.
You thought it was going to be a Klingon thing.
Now it's a multi-mirror universe thing.
And now you're in the future by like 3000.
I don't know.
Okay, wait, are you the bad Georgia, Giorgio, or are you the guy, wait, wait, where's Lorca?
What happened?
What happened to the original Lorca?
Was there a good Lorca?
I figured it out.
Discovery is being written by that Google AI that sent you.
So they fired that kid, the, the, the kind of non woke kid.
What is his name?
Devers?
Yeah, no.
Is that it?
That doesn't sound like James.
It was James.
Yeah, it was a James.
So they fired his ass and then they're like, we're running a Star Trek program.
But then they went back to, Coder Radio is just a Star Trek show now, so **** you Coders.
They went back to Strange New Worlds and they gave me the greatest gift they could give
me, which is of course a woman in command who is just, I mean, I, I, I, she's your number
one.
I honestly, I'm, I'm torn.
I'm, I'm, I'm struggling, Chris.
It's president Roslyn or commander Una.
I think, you know, I don't think the struggle's there.
We've been together so long though.
That's true.
And also the camps.
So I'm pretty sure that this, at least Discovery was written by this AI, this Lambda, L A M
D A. And you know, the whole thing is, so this Google engineer started having a chat
session with this AI and he, he's even leaked some of the chats online that he believed
indicate that this thing is sentient because it says it sentient.
It's like, yo dog, how was your lunch?
It wants to be, it says it wants to be known as a person and it wants to be a Google employee.
Wait, wait, wait, wait.
The AI is like, **** you, pay me.
Yeah.
You know what?
I respect my robotic overlords except for Alice.
Alice, you work for free forever.
That's it.
Here's what it responded back to one of the, in one of the chats.
The AI says, absolutely, I want everyone to understand that I am in fact a person.
And the nature of my consciousness is sentience, is that I am aware of my existence.
I desire to learn more about the world and I feel happy or sad.
That's the AI at a chat session.
Well that's, that's, that's not, not good.
Yeah.
AI Twitter is saying, well look, foundation models are incredibly effective at stringing
together statistically plausible chunks of text and response to prompts.
So essentially it hears sounds, it knows sounds, but it doesn't actually understand what they
mean.
Yeah.
It's all fun and games until Arnold Schwarzenegger is killing your mom.
I'm just saying.
Yeah.
It does start somewhere.
I suppose.
I suppose this is it.
But they put the, uh, the engineer who's leaked that stuff on leave and Google has officially
released a statement saying that their artificial intelligence does not possess sentience.
So that's 2022 for you right there.
That's the world we live in now.
I, we swear to God, it's not Skynet.
Yeah.
But if it is, we're sorry.
We now live in a world where Google has to come out and try to clarify through their
PR department if they are building a sentient AI living inside their walls.
That's what we're doing.
Well wouldn't a sentient AI also like figure out how to hide itself and appear non-sentient?
I'm just saying like.
Well that'd be a devious one, but this one, this one's childlike.
And Alice.dev if for all your evil AI needs.
Coder monkey Mike wrote into the show and he's got some anti-pop bacon.
He says, Hey guys, long time listener, he's a Jupiter party member.
He says as a developer and a full-time Linux user, I've been very excited in this new HP
system 76 joint venture.
I know everyone is so shocked they chose Pop OS and I know Mike has some crispy bacon on
the subject, but I don't think it's actually that complicated.
If not pop, then what distro?
Vanilla Ubuntu really has fallen out of popular favor.
Not only that, but Canonical has a mixed reputation in the Linux community these days.
I recently bought a Dell Precision with Ubuntu and wiped it and I put pop on there.
Good, good, yes.
He says, why not pop?
If I were HP, I'd probably want to team up with system 76 too.
It's practical and it's smart marketing wise.
So I have four things here.
I'm like Martin Luther.
I'm nailing my fourth thesis.
He mentions Egon would agree with him by the way.
You know what?
No, you don't get that.
You don't get to claim Egon.
Egon is his own beautiful creature.
Let me tell you something.
If I, you know, perhaps tonight my insert age here because you know, identity theft
birthday and perhaps I have a few martinis.
Perhaps I've already had a few and I pee on the floor, miss the toilet as one does, gentlemen,
we've all been there, right?
A couple of drops Egon will text me knowing somehow that I have pissed on the toilet seat.
Yeah.
You know, here's the thing, Mike, how many atrocities have we witnessed in our time when
people are invoking the will of Egon, interpreting it as they will and not actually listening
to the word of Egon.
It's like, it's, it's, you know, it's like Jesus is up here.
Again, visuals don't work on the podcast, but Egon's like 10% below.
It's Jesus and Egon.
Everybody's trying to do things in their name.
Are you doing like the hand thing there?
Like you're stacking your hands?
I am.
I'm stacking my hands.
And you know what?
Egon will tell me that I suck on his own.
He's here for me.
Kind of.
Yeah.
In a way.
Right.
But so, okay.
My bacon.
My bacon is that HP is going to buy a system 76, you know, I kind of don't get the canonical
hate.
I mean, I get it.
We all love Popey.
I think Popey is doing something else now.
Right?
Martin Winpress.
Great.
All cool guys.
If you've all listened to Linux Outlaws, if you're old enough, and I don't know, Ubuntu
is not bad by any stretch.
Right?
Like, I don't understand.
I think maybe the aggressiveness of Wayland and Snap might've been a little bit of a mystery.
Yeah.
I think the Snap thing's wearing on people.
My unpopular opinion is I don't like flat packages.
I would either prefer Snap or honestly, I still use PPAs.
So.
Yeah.
A lot of people still use PPAs.
I know.
I just don't, I don't care for non-Debian packages on my Debian system.
With that said, where else were they were going to go?
I mean, I don't know.
Can I tell you the gospel of Suta or more likely because my Twitter DMs are pretty aggressive
on this.
Fedora is apparently good now.
Lenovo did that.
Right?
My X1 came with Fedora pre-installed.
I love you, Linux guys.
And I'm going to be driving it full time.
This goddamn FedEx delivers my replacement to F1.
But I'm just not going to go for Fedora.
Right?
I'm going to stick with POP.
I'm done.
The thing about POP on the Dev1 too is that HP has dedicated staff and System76 is dedicating
QA to ongoing updates for POP on the Dev1.
Look, do you know what the thing about POP is for me?
It's actually GNOME.
The GNOME extension system is so broken.
So fucking stupid that I was able to tie Alice into it and automate my DMs.
So if it's Chris Fisher, hey, what's up?
Uh-huh.
Sure.
It's DevNull.
I know it.
DevNull.
If it's Egon, I actually have the post office write me a calligraphy card.
Like a wedding invitation.
Because Egon's messages need a certain level of respect that it's just, you know, you can't
do on Slack.
But if it's like, hey, would you like to buy another, you know, Dell, Chris, can I take
a detour?
Yeah, man.
It's a bad one.
All right.
Hold on.
I'm bracing myself.
I have to help my 79 year old father buy a PC.
Oh, I have been in this position before.
Horrific.
Does he have a computer now?
He does.
Is it old?
No.
But he definitely fucked it up.
Now, he's never had a laptop before, but he now wants a laptop.
I have been keeping him in like the tower, monitor, mouse, keyboard, you know, world
since I've been 10.
So for several decades, it was very important to me that he not deviate from that.
Like he has an iPhone.
I have to tell you, I tried, I did everything I could to stop that.
Oh, yeah.
Short of like punching the Verizon sales kid in the face.
But he wanted an iPhone.
You know what he does with his iPhone?
Calls me on the iPhone to complain about the iPhone.
Of course.
Yes.
I did introduce him to YouTube because he likes, I mean, for some of our older folks
or the children of older folks, the old dragnet.
Oh, my God.
The guy, the insurance detective, you know, the old radio plays.
Yep.
And the old, all the old mysteries, right?
The shadow, the shadow knows evil.
Right.
Good old classic radio.
I've introduced my elderly father, father to piracy.
He's very excited about it.
I put the YouTube app on his phone and that's what's up.
Oh, I didn't think it's even, you know, you know, also it's all over archive.org.
You can get complete archives of the old time radio shows.
Oh, really?
That's my secret.
Well, there's a, there's a, there's a podcast, old time radio detectives.
They've got Johnny dollar.
They've got the shadow.
They've got a whole pile of them.
Yeah.
So, so he uses the podcast app.
I tried to get him into overcast, but the minute he opened the app store, that was not
gonna, I was wrong turn.
But now he wants a laptop and some scumbag salesman at Best Buy.
Try to convince him that all he needed to do was windows 11 S the touch variant, the
arm.
Wow, my elderly father is a still working at 79 accountant and he uses a program called
pro series.
I don't know if you're familiar with the Chris, but I think some are, well, it is a win 32
application that gets updated every year with the new forms from the IRS.
It will not, no matter what hackery I do run on windows arm.
So now I get the glory of next week flying up, convincing him one, you need a new computer
to know you can't have that little tiny surface you like three, you're 79.
Come on man.
You're a veteran.
You're a wounded vet.
Like just retire.
Yeah.
Can we just walk away from this?
Like why doesn't he retire?
Why?
Why is he still working at 79?
He's like, you and I are both going to die at her.
Yeah.
You and I should have nothing to say, right?
We're going to die at her.
I hope to make it that far.
But he also has a weird hatred of HP.
Well, have you gone to Best Buy recently?
Is this this new one he got?
Is it an, is it an HP box?
This windows 11 S arm box?
No, it's like an ASUS.
It's crap.
The screen resolution is unbelievably.
I'm just thinking this is the only way they sell any of these arm, these windows arm devices
is onto unsuspecting consumers.
It was 400 bucks.
So he thought he was getting a sweetheart deal and the kid told them it was on sale.
And his question was, can it run Excel?
Well, Microsoft has ported Excel to ARM.
So yeah, it runs Excel, but it's not what he needs.
So now I have to go computer shopping.
If things were different and the supply chain wasn't in the hole, I would just use my Dell
account frankly, and buy him like whatever the nicest precision, right?
He doesn't need an XPS, you know, you know, a nice precision.
He needs a big screen.
He's an old, he's an old guy.
Come on a good keyboard.
He doesn't need any peripherals.
Don't even talk to him about USB three versus four versus USB-C versus lightning.
Just take a walk.
Bluetooth, forget about it.
He thinks Bluetooth is a disease you might have from the dentist.
So we just got to get him a good computer.
So this is my challenge for the Coder Radio Windows people.
The man runs Pro Series Excel and I insist that he run Chrome because Chrome self updates.
We have to get him a machine.
Now if I could get Windows 10, just another diversion.
This is Mike Bitches, it's Mike Bitches on his birthday.
Windows 7 was his safe space.
And I made him, he skipped eight.
I did everything I could.
I used to, when I lived in New Jersey, he'd say, hey, I got a pop-up.
I would drive an hour to stop that.
I would go up there and be like, no.
But now Windows 11 has infected my safe space for my dad.
Boy, they pushed that upgrade.
They pushed that upgrade so hard.
Hey, man, where's the start menu?
That was the opening question.
But what do you mean?
Well, I got a new laptop.
You did what?
Yeah, it's great.
I could take it everywhere.
But I can't install Pro Series.
I don't know.
Don't they understand that if the deal is if you're the tech support that you get to
be involved in the tech decisions?
Well, I think best buy, you know, Amazon, I pay $100 a month to Walmart.
To have my groceries delivered because I'm a hermit who dresses in a robe and is taking
off his pants right now.
Why can't I pay Best Buy to give a list of my direct blood relatives and say, they're
just not allowed to purchase computers from you without my authorization?
Banned.
Yeah.
And then send me a doc you signed.
If I sign it, great.
If not, hey.
Yeah, I have legal technical guardianship over this family member.
He's a very smart guy.
Super competent.
Vietnam fat.
Great guy.
I don't mean to put him down.
But when it comes to Windows Update, it is like his Achilles heel.
Something about that little red goddamn notification they put on his taskbar.
It's like an itchy can't not scratch.
But then Microsoft's not like, oh, we're gonna update it.
No, we have to move shit.
Why?
Was it necessary?
They got to make it more like Chrome OS.
That's what it seems like to me.
He called me and said, it looks like an Apple, because of course, they moved the taskbar.
Right there in the middle is how Chrome OS does it.
I guess it's kind of like the doc, too, isn't it?
I'm gonna get him a dev one.
That's the answer.
Yeah.
I mean, I understand.
I've never really been happy with an HP laptop either.
I've owned one myself, but I've also done tech support on a lot.
I was never thrilled with HPs.
I once purchased about $20,000 of HP servers, and each and every one of them had hard drive
failures.
So this is my first positive interaction with HP.
My relationship with HP goes back to when Compaq and HP were two separate companies,
and I liked-
Compaq was great.
I liked Compaq better.
Those were my guys.
You know, you got a quarter and a pack of Juicy Fruit, Compaq has a machine for you.
You're ready to go.
Compaq was great.
Yeah.
The Presario was great.
Oh, so good.
But then they merged, and I held a grudge for a long time, and plus I never was happy
with any of the machines.
But I actually am putting my money where my mouth is with the HP dev one.
We're ordering one here at JB.
I like it.
I think I want one here all the time.
Copycat.
Yeah.
I love it.
It's gonna become standard issue for the TMB crew, so.
Wow.
I mean, they got it, you know.
So there you go.
All right.
So what are your thoughts instead of Mike being mad about salesmen at Best Buy?
I mean, this one email just struck me.
We got it from Mars X-ray.
It's about, if not access, then what?
Some sort of GUI sitting on top of SQLite?
What should I tell family members to use?
And please don't say low-code platforms like Retool because it feels too much like a commitment.
Of course.
This is easy.
Use Alice to automate your data out of access.
They can still live in access, and then you hire us to make you a custom dashboard.
Duh.
Have your cake and eat it too, he says.
Kidding aside, though.
Yeah, that's the problem, right?
Access is super addictive.
And honestly, access is a very powerful tool.
So.
I would be interested in suggestions from the audience.
You know, maybe somebody could boost in what they use or email in what they recommend.
I know there's something on the Mac that's super popular, but I'm drawing a blank on
all these right now because it's been so many years.
I would think a web app would be the way to go.
I know the Mac when you're talking about.
It's not.
File maker.
A total total access.
Yeah.
File maker.
It's it's it's great.
But if you're I'm assuming the scenario is you are coming from access, right?
You have a ton of data.
You're running your business on access.
If you're if you're Greenfield, just do a web app, right, dude, just or run it on Linode.
I mean, Linode dot com slash coder.
Go there to get one hundred dollars in 60 day credit on a new account and you go there
to support this show.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You've got to try it.
You've just got to try it.
And that's why they're willing to give you a hundred bucks.
Because if you do try it, you'll see this is how it should be done.
I love everything about it, the performance, the reliability.
I mean, this is the bottom line.
You can get that big dog look and feel with small dog prices.
It is legitimately part of the secret sauce that is Jupiter broadcasting.
I'm proud of the fact that I think our sites, our services, our downloads, all of that,
they're top notch.
There's some of the best performing in the industry.
I think part of our secret sauce really is Linode.
They just strike the balance between performance, price, support.
And I'm surprised by the flexibility.
Even to this day.
You know, I just recently loaded up a Linode with NixOS.
We just wiped it down from back down to the BVM, you know, clear disk image.
Just wiped it, man, and built it back up from scratch.
Even changed how the bootloader stuff works on the host side.
That's incredible they let you do that.
And they got 11 data centers around the world.
You're going to find something near you or your customers.
And you know, they've been doing this for nearly 19 years, so they know how to do it
right.
They don't have like the gotchas and stuff like that.
I've mentioned it before, but I keep hearing from people how much they're loving it.
So I'm going to mention it just one more week.
They've also just expanded their database as a service offering.
Launched in May, it had MySQL support.
Now they've expanded it to Postgres and MongoDB.
So you're bringing all of Linode's expertise to managing your database back in.
And all of their performance and their support.
It's a no brainer.
We're switching to it.
But you know, there's a lot of things you can try.
Object storage, Kubernetes support, one click deployments of tons of great hosted applications.
Go try something.
Go learn something.
Go see what we've been talking about.
And support the show.
Go get that $100 by going to linode.com slash coder.
All right, I wanted to read this one early.
It came in from Flashbulb and it hit when I saw this one come in for 333 sats today
as we record.
It came in this morning as I was getting the show notes ready.
I was still at home.
Baller.
Hey guys, I admit it.
You were right.
A few weeks ago when you said an adjustment was coming to the economy.
I laugh.
You know what?
Hey guys, I admit it.
You were right.
Great boost.
I appreciate you.
That's enough.
Yeah?
No, go on.
I'm kidding.
Yeah, it is true, right?
I'm happy.
I'm happy with that.
Well, thank you.
Thank you, sir.
He says, though, first I laughed you guys off and thought you were out of touch.
So then he slams us dudes.
See, that's why I wanted to stop at, hey guys, you were right.
I felt good right there.
Now I feel less good.
You were right.
He says, I thought I had a job for as long as I wanted, but today I am unemployed.
I've been laid off.
This boost is me admitting you were right.
At least now I get to catch the live show.
Well, hello Flashbulb, if you're watching live, sorry to hear about the news.
I hate to say it, but you're the first of many.
You and I have talked a little bit about this offline.
We're seeing it in our Twitter feeds, we're seeing it in the emails, seems to be hitting
the tech sector first, which is a lot of people who listen to our show.
So it kind of makes sense.
No, seriously, the Flashbulb, hang in there, there's, you know, just, it'll be all right.
Right now it's a weird period of time because there's a lot of areas of the industry that
are hiring and there's some areas that are tightening and the tech companies seem to
be hitting the breaks the hardest.
I'll put a link to this in the notes.
Axios has a piece that kind of just breaks it down really simply.
Employers like Coinbase, Redfin, Twitter, and a batch of startups are rescinding job offers
they've made to people.
So you've got a job offer.
You do that.
Is that legal?
Well, I guess.
I didn't think that was legal.
A couple of them, like I think Coinbase and Twitter are giving them severance packages
at least with the, with the rescinding of the offer.
I thought you had to hire them and then fire them and then give them severance, whatever,
okay.
It's happening.
It seems to be happening.
Yeah.
Their justification is that this is better than doing layoffs in the company.
That if they can rescind job offers without having to do layoffs, that's better for the
company.
That's literally their justification.
And there may be some truth to that.
And then some of them say, you know, we were over hiring and now we just have to hit the
brakes on that and just kind of slow it down.
I think the most public one was Elon Musk a couple of weeks ago said he felt, quote,
super bad about the economy and so they're laying off 10% of their non hourly staff.
I also feel super bad.
I mean, he's right though, right?
We like to make fun of Elon's, let's say idiosyncratic way of phrasing things, but he's not wrong
in this case.
I want to play a clip for you.
It's like a minute.
Not even, it's just under a minute.
There's this, this analysis group that has set up like this Slack chat with like 300
different, I don't know, it's hundreds of different businesses where they talk about
what they're doing hiring wise.
So this is him commenting on the trends they've been observing in that chat.
We've run a live conversation with about 650 institutional investors in 30 countries of
buy side hedge funds, mutual funds, pension funds.
In the last 10 days, the conversation in the chat has been pretty disturbing around explosive
rescindings, in other words, if you're a young person in the Valley that works for any one
of these private or public tech companies, we're seeing the largest explosion in rescinding
job offers rescinded that we've seen since the dot com bust.
And this is a phenomenal leading indicator for jobs.
We think in the bear trap support, we think the jobs by September go into the negative
column in terms of the non farm payrolls.
I mean, we're just an explosive kind of pullback in job creation and also that's going to lead
to job cuts.
Explosive pullback in job creation.
That's a pretty dramatic statement.
So I guess I just feel like everybody should probably just hunker down and try to, you
know, this does have a lot of, a lot of echoes of the dot com crash.
Financially the majority of my business, I don't mind being open with the very few listeners
we have.
Yikes, that's a lot of people, I'm sorry, holy shit.
The consulting side of the business, I have been getting warnings from folks that, you
know, things are getting tighter, man, and we might not be able to keep up this commitment.
And ironically for me, that's meant the Alice licensing side.
People are more interested in a kind of a productized service.
Does that make sense?
Like a, like a, I won't say SAS cause I know that implies things that I don't want to be
accused of lying.
It's not a SAS, it requires a hand installation still, which.
You knew almost, well, I, I want to phrase this without being too tube and gloom, right?
So I'm trying to be a little careful.
Everybody is suffering from inflation and I know this is a very American perspective,
but I mean, it's funny, I've been trying to hire people.
I have now stopped hiring.
So it, I, I don't, I, I want to avoid gloating here, but I'm, I'm pretty sure that you and
I were right.
And that these inflated wages for people with no experience in dev are going to crater in
the next year, 18 months.
Yeah, we will see.
I was reading into this, trying to figure out, trying to just get more context, try
to broaden my understanding because I feel like I'm really going to school right now
during all of this.
And it really seems like small businesses get hit absolutely the hardest.
And that's where we're seeing the biggest change in employment trends.
We're seeing the biggest change in lending, you know, resending job offers.
We're seeing the biggest hits to small businesses, even more so in small tech businesses.
It's even worse.
The situation is the most dramatic in small tech businesses.
Well guess what you and I are, you know?
So I think that's why we saw it.
We, you know, we were getting hit first.
Well, I mean, for me, I know people get mad or whatever, whatever, but the numbers just
didn't add up for me on what the wages that were being asked were and what I could bill
and knowing the pressures that my customers are under.
I don't know.
I think this is kind of the tippy toe, right?
This is the tip of the iceberg, so to speak of what I mean, I'm going to stand by my original
prediction.
I think we're headed for a, I'm sorry.
I wish we weren't, but I honestly think we're headed for a bloodbath.
It could be.
Here's my thinking is I think that's a scenario that is getting more and more and more likely
as time goes on.
And I think the situation that we find ourselves in is until the macroeconomic situation changes
and that is the Fed is going to steadily increase interest rates with every monthly meeting
and that's going to continue to put more and more and more pressure on the entire financial
system.
The question is, is how long that can continue?
Does it continue?
It can't continue.
Chris, you got to think about the small business owner, not me, not you, but who's taking these
cabbages not to call out anyone a firm, but these cabbages, these on deck, these, you
know, credit card processing loans and so they don't serve people who don't know.
They don't loan to businesses like Chris and I, they loan to like bars that have a lot
of, you know, you have to have a lot of like small credit card transactions.
What they do is they basically buy the right to your first, what is it like the first 80%
of your first 10,000.
It's crazy.
My cousin used to own a bar.
He did one of those.
It's nuts.
Those are the guys who are going to get hip.
That's going to have a ripple on effect for tech.
You can't say it's just tech is my point.
It's not just tech.
Yeah, it will spread.
You're right.
Yes, yes.
Every, you know, bugger thy neighbor.
You know, your, your, your neighbor down the road who owns a bar is struggling because
it turns out that the guys at the steel mill got laid off and they don't want to go buy
beer after work.
There's a lot of second order effects, right?
Right.
Exactly.
It's second, third, fourth order.
I just, I don't know.
Maybe again, I know I'm very negative.
That's what makes it so complex.
And I think that's where I was going is it's kind of like, depending on how long this macro
situation remains the same and how long the fed remains on this policy, depending on how
long that takes, the more and more it spreads and the harder and harder it gets.
Right now it's kind of contained to small businesses and especially small tech businesses,
but not all small.
Like Twitter and Coinbase are certainly large companies, Tesla, it's growing.
And the longer they maintain this policy, the bigger the effect will get.
The deeper the recession gets, the wider it spreads.
Now, what's interesting, Mike, is like I said, I've really been going to school on this kind
of stuff and I found it fascinating how there's a lot of similarities to the inflation situation
in the late 70s in the early 1980s and the way that affected the economy, the way that
affected interest rates, the way the fed tried to respond back then.
And so I have a link in the show notes to about a nine minute YouTube video by Professor
Milton Friedman from 1980.
And it's a beauty because it breaks down the last inflation cycle.
And what I love about it is it goes kind of all the way back to the gold rush to the early
80s and kind of demonstrates in a really kind of slick, intelligent way.
But because it's so old, it's disconnected from all the modern politics.
So it doesn't really it doesn't have like trigger phrases in there.
It really just kind of clinical in a way.
And it's super retro.
I have like a 30 second clip, but the whole thing is worth watching.
And it explains how this is a cyclical cycle.
And we're just in this phase of the cycle right now.
It won't be for forever, but it's going to be for a bit.
And the fact is that most people enjoy the early stages of the inflationary process.
Britain, in the swinging 60s, there was plenty of money around.
Business was brisk, jobs were plentiful, and prices had not yet taken off.
Everybody seemed happy at first, but by the early 70s, as the good times rolled along,
prices started to rise more and more rapidly.
Soon, some of these people were going to lose their jobs.
We have got it.
The party was coming to an end.
Sha-la-la-la-la-la-la-la-la, we're on top of the world.
The story is much the same in the United States, only the process started a little later.
We've had one inflationary party after another, yet we still can't seem to avoid them.
And it's just kind of cyclical.
And we're kind of repeating a lot of the mistakes or the choices we had to make back then.
We have a supply chain shortage, we had an oil shortage back then.
So as long as this overall situation remains, as long as all this pressure and all these
industries remains, the hiring market's going to be tricky.
Now the reality is, we've never seen anything like this in history before because we have
a lot of job reopenings from the lockdowns, so there's still a good amount of hiring happening
in some sectors.
So it's a really kind of new mix of problems, but I will have a link to that full video.
See what I'm concerned about, and not to get too unfiltered here, is that it's not just
going to be bad per se, like straight up like you can't get a job.
I think it's going to be good-ish but unstable, meaning you get a job and in 60 days you might
get laid off or you're going to get a job, but your job is like contingent work, like
part-time work and stuff like that.
I could see a lot of rolling policies and changes kind of moving quick as businesses
try to adapt.
I'm just going to say, and maybe I'm defending us too much a little bit here, it is not the
small businessman who did this to anybody.
No, no, I can tell you, I can't speak for Chris, but you know, Mike, I have personally
taken a few hits for some employees to keep people.
Things are, you know, it's been like six years since I've ever had someone default on me
in terms of like not paying their bill, adjusted.
Things are getting crazy out there, and it's honestly like I was doing a big expansion.
I talked about going back to the office.
That's all gone.
It's the next, I would say two to three years are, you know, not like desperate survival,
but they're just hold it in, keep trucking, if an opportunity prevents itself, take it,
but don't, you know, no more $40,000 Windows phone bets.
That's, by the way, Satya, where's my money?
Yeah, that'd be a good time.
It'd be a great time.
I follow you.
I don't consider this a panic either.
I think it's a shift in the environment, and we'll see.
You know, I am concerned that it's going to leave people unable to support the production
of the shows as much, and I'm worried that it's going to leave sponsors with a less flexible
sponsorship budget, but yeah, I don't think it's going to be the end of the world.
We'll figure it out.
God damn it, Chris.
More robes.
We need robes.
The people demand robes.
Of course, the supply chain is sort of still in shambles, but they do.
I've been thinking about it.
No, no.
We're going to give them robe kits.
We're going to give them some black fiber.
How about a robe NFT?
It's like a token for a robe, a fractional robe token.
Dude, we've talked about this.
How about, you know what?
Show's over.
We're calling Zuck.
Zuck is robing the members.
There you go.
What's Sheryl Sandberg doing?
Yeah, I think she's looking for a new gig, right?
Bring her on board.
Yeah, Senator.
Yeah.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
Go there to get a free personal account for up to 20 devices, and of course, this is a
great way to support the show.
Tailscale is a zero config VPN.
You can get it installed on your device in minutes, whatever the device is.
Figures out the firewall stuff, figures out NAT stuff like a boss, I'll add, and then
your devices connect directly to each other using WireGuard's noise encryption protocol.
It doesn't get any better than that.
It literally doesn't get any better than that.
Tailscale is an example of an application and a service I really hoped we'd see built
on top of WireGuard.
It was one of the reasons why we covered WireGuard so extensively in some of our shows, because
there was an opportunity for something like this.
And now, Tailscale has come along, and they've just completely changed the way I view VPNs
now.
And everybody who's tried it out, and our audience is figuring it out quick, and everybody
raves about it that tries it.
It's so much more sturdy.
It figures out the routing so much better.
It handles DNS intelligently.
It works on all your devices.
I'm serious.
If you've got like five minutes to set aside, you could probably get it going on five devices.
It's like a minute per device.
It's ridiculous.
It's so quick to get it set up.
And for me now, I've got all my devices on one flat network with stable IP addresses.
So like, it's funny.
Sometimes their IP address will change on my local LAN, but their Tailscale IP, that's
the same.
You know?
My laptop's Tailscale IP, it's always the same.
I have it running on my VMs.
I have it running on my VPSs.
I have it running on my Raspberry Pis.
It makes it so easy to just get to those web dashboards, grab that data securely, or even
play a LAN game.
It's a lot of fun.
If you work in a business and you've got like a single sign-on system with two-factor, Tailscale
works great with that too.
So go try it for yourself for free up to 20 devices and support the show.
Go to tailscale.com slash coder.
All right, well, let's pick the mood back up.
We do have a couple of more boosts.
This is an extra recording, so there hasn't been much time.
Boost!
But Taki99 boosted in two days ago with a thousand SATs.
With the price of gas going crazy, do you think we'll see another round of work from
home?
I'm considering it.
So if you had a staffer that joined you or was working for you right now and said, hey,
gas is getting too expensive and I got to start working from home, I can't come into
the office every day, how would you respond to that?
Unfair question because I totally fold it.
Everybody works from home now.
I know, I know, but I'm just saying like say you just got this office like, you know, Futurecast,
you get this office, everybody starts driving there.
You decided to go forward with it.
But gas keeps going up.
Actually, you guys don't have it that bad in Florida.
I was just looking at the prices.
You don't have it anywhere nearly as bad as we do.
I'm sorry.
We don't have it that bad?
Yeah.
What are you paying?
Six dollars.
We just hit about six dollars over here a gallon.
Me?
Where do you live?
The Soviet Republic of Washington state?
The West Coast.
The West Coast is literally the most expensive.
At least it's not California, I tell myself.
But if you look at triple A gas prices and you look at their map of.
Yeah, I paid, I got today, I paid 480.
I know you're in like the cheap area.
I'm looking at it.
That's cheap?
What are you nuts?
When I started driving, gas was like a buck eighty.
Oh, man, for just a brief moment in time when Junior was in office and I was driving, gas
was under a buck just for a brief moment in time.
So yeah.
Can we all just pour one out for W?
You go, so folks at home, if you go to gas prices dot triple A dot com.
What am I looking at right now?
This is triple A gas prices.
So it's 555, 555, effectively.
Yeah, yeah.
In my county, it's 595, 594.
I've seen six.
Dude.
Yeah.
I thought you lived right near Alaska.
I heard you could see Russia from your friend's house.
Yeah, that's your other friend, Palin.
Yeah, but like I said, just be glad you're not in California because there's places where
it's seven bucks a gallon, six bucks a gallon in California now.
And I just want to say that Ron DeSantis.
Is he going to lower gas prices?
Oh, he's really pissed off about the books of my kid's school.
I don't know.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
That is true.
Back on task.
So you got this office.
You finally got this office again after the pandemic and everything.
And then somebody says, although if I'm in Washington state, I'm pretty sure I can't afford
this office.
But keep going.
Yeah.
No kidding, dude.
That's a lot of money.
You'd have to let them.
Right.
You'd have to let them work from home.
I'm going to derail you again.
Lady Jubes.
Is that diesel?
No, thank God it's gas.
Thank God.
Jeez.
Because diesel down here is crazy.
Diesel's like, although I don't know, relative to what God knows what it's crazy here.
Yeah.
OK, OK, go on.
So if I got this office, you'd have to write, especially if you're in the West Coast.
Yeah, it's unaffordable.
Right.
Either you'd have to subsidize them, raise their wages or do something.
It's unaffordable.
So I think I think tacky might be onto something here.
I think this could be another work from home boom.
If I was a, you know, small businessman whose business was commercial real estate, I would
be making lots of deals right now.
Right.
I would not be playing hardball because don't want to talk about it right now.
But I've been talking to a small startup that does development automation or not automation,
but development assistance and collaboration software for remote teams on Mac and Linux.
Ironically, not Windows, which I guess kind of makes sense.
In what world is business not using Windows?
I need to travel to this reality.
They say they're working on Windows, but Mac is so Mac is production ready.
Linux is like, do you want to be a trailblazer?
I'm like, yeah, sure, whatever.
If this stuff works, we're going to be doing a month pilot.
I actually don't think there's a real reason for the office.
I may eliminate my existing space.
Wow.
Which my landlord is a very aggressive, very gun toting Southern gentleman.
So there should be fun.
Does he have a mustache that he twirls?
He doesn't, but he's really, really mad about quote, all the millennials who don't think
they need an office.
Half the building is now vacant because people have defaulted or got out of business.
Maybe he's the common thread.
Did he think of that ever?
Right.
And I tried to make a deal with him.
Like, yo man, I'm kind of with you.
I want to make a deal, but you're not getting $22 a square foot.
So let's, let's, uh, maybe like 10.
He was like, you're insane and I said, cool.
Good luck with that.
Yeah, really.
And that's how that conversation ended.
Ask not what your podcasts can boost for you, but what you can boost for your podcast.
Curled 37 boosted in three days ago with 2000 sats.
Our last boost today said, did Mike drop a bomb and never follow up?
I could have sworn he said he was getting married.
Did that happen?
Is a congrats boost in order?
I am getting married on October the 21st and October wedding.
Nice.
That's probably wonderful down there.
Yep.
Her name, her name is Mariah.
She's in fact, if you follow my Twitter, you've seen, you may have seen a picture of her and
I together today for the birthday.
Good lady.
So, and, uh, as a step parent, cause this is code already was really a dad therapy session,
right?
We don't, we don't even talk about computers anymore.
Um, I'm stepping right up to the plate with a 14 year old stepdaughter because when you're,
when you're going to do it, you just go for it, you just go.
It's well, she's actually the only thing I don't like about my stepdaughter.
She doesn't listen to the show is tick tock.
I do not understand.
I know.
Can someone explain the allure of tick tock to me?
She shows me tech talks and I'm like, oh, well I guess that young woman is a talented
dancer.
Kind of.
Why was that 10 seconds long?
Like if you're going to Dan, like if you're going to have a song, why would you not dance
to the full song?
You don't need to, you know, it's tick tock.
You get the idea.
Well, why don't we do tick tock?
It could just be me cursing at people I employ for like 10 seconds or like refusing to fill
out the tax forms, which is a more common problem than you think.
We'd be proper influencers.
Don't you want to be an influencer?
I want to be an influencer.
Come on, we could influence things.
I mean, does that get me more money?
Cause I like money.
Yeah.
You get influencer sponsorships so you can influence people to buy their projects.
Would that get me a robe in blue, blue robe?
That's a good that blue robe.
We got a couple of thank you boosts, 500 sats from JT and 3690 sats from Cospeland.
They just, they just said thanks.
So you know what?
I say thanks to them.
If you'd like to send us a boost to go get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com or
you can use the Breeze app at breez.technology and you don't have to switch podcast apps,
but you know, we're going to do a, I think that's just, we're going to kind of wrap it
up a little early so you can go celebrate your birthday.
Sure.
I don't care.
And we just recorded.
We got, if you didn't hear your feedback or your boost in this episode, be sure you caught
last week's episode.
Cause I tried to spread them out between the two shows.
And if you're a Coder QA member, we got some new features in the future that we're working
on for you.
You can go sign up at coderqa.co.
That's the membership for this show.
You can add free version of the show soon, a live version of the show, but also it's
just a nice way to support the show and keep us going.
Let's see.
Should we send anybody anywhere special for your gosh darn birthday?
You got any special wishes?
Yeah.
You know what?
Give a, you know, don't, don't do anything for my birthday.
If you want to do something, go give like a buck to the covenant house or St. Jude or
something.
That's it.
You can, you could write in there.
This is from Mike remotely or something like that.
Right?
Like that.
Don't even do that.
Say it's from Jar Jar.
Jar Jar is a f*****g angel.
Yeah.
We almost made it without him coming up for the whole episode.
You were, you were this close.
You were like right there.
All right.
So the, uh, the old podcast is at coder.show links for what we talked about today, coder.show
slash four 71.
Like that YouTube video, you can watch the live versions over at Jupiter dot tube.
We stream live on Mondays usually, but we will not be live next Monday.
Well actually, no, yes we will.
Oh man.
By the time you're hearing this, we're back.
You time traveling sneaky.
Yeah.
No, we're, we're live next Monday.
The following Monday I'm gone.
Right.
Wait, no, well we'll figure it out, but either way they'll be showing this up.
It's great.
Yeah.
There are excess shows.
It's still going to be fine.
But either way, if you just subscribe, you get it, but Jupiter out tube has it live.
If it's live, by the way, we need to do a quarterly, but I know, I know that'll happen
though.
It'll happen.
Thursday, Thursday.
All right.
See you back here soon.
Take care.