This is KOTOR Radio, episode 464 for May 2nd, 2022.
Hello good looking and welcome in to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
My name is Chris and joining us, probably with a musical instrument in hand, it's our
host Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
Hello and welcome to the very southern episode of KOTOR Radio.
Oh no, this is my fault.
I mentioned Kevin Spacey, now we're all Frank.
And I'm here for it, I'm here for it.
First of all, if I'm going to eat spare ribs, I'm going to do it before the restaurant opens
in an alley creepily wearing half a suit.
Right, I mean that's how you got to eat your barbecue, right?
And then when I take a girl on a date, if we're near a train, maybe you got to watch
out.
Don't go in the subway with Frank.
Although I should have read that Netflix contract quite a bit more carefully, quite a bit more.
Netflix might be knocking on the door of some of their original content actors and creators
because maybe they need to run the hits again, they're not doing so good my friend.
You know what, in America you can sue everybody.
I think we're about to witness peak streaming, we'll see.
Maybe the great streaming consolidation will happen.
I just want to interrupt here.
Someone heard my Kevin Spacey just now in the chat and literally said, bring back Jar Jar.
Oh no.
In 13 years, this is the first time anybody has ever asked for Jar Jar.
We didn't think it could get worse.
But if you some miss me, me some back bitches.
No we don't miss you.
Phantom Menace is better than the new prequels?
You know what, you might be right.
First of all, The Force Awakens is literally A New Hope with like a spit shine.
So that doesn't count.
Sorry.
Oh and Hayden Christensen is coming back because we can't help ourselves.
Let me ask you this though.
Okay, brace yourself because I think I got you here.
Isn't it more of an atrocity because Lucas was hands on with the prequels, whereas these
Disney bastardizations, they're like it's a whole new group of people, I mean it's some
people from LucasArts, but you know it's not it's not George.
But like the prequels were really bad and the acting and the writing was really really
bad and that's all on George's hands, right?
Like which is a bigger atrocity in my opinion.
It's worse.
I'm gonna tell you why it's worse.
See George Lucas is like a guy who was really really drunk and crashed his car and totaled
it.
Disney intentionally crashed the car stone sober for the insurance money for that sweet
sweet merchandising revenue.
That's probably true.
Plus it makes for some sweet theme parks.
I mean of course you need a Darth Vader for Gen Z.
I'm just saying like a look at what they did.
Who's Obi-Wan?
Um, Rey?
Kind of Luke I guess but like really Rey, right?
Oh and we have to add a super handsome dude who's a pilot because well didn't Han Solo
exist?
Yeah yeah he has to be like that certain kind of character too.
He's kind of roguish, right?
Exactly.
You know you know he's a good man but he's got some edges you know like like if you know
if your daughter brought him home you'd be like I don't know honey but damn he's so charming.
Let me throw another curveball at you because in the era of streaming a lot of classic legacy
I guess I don't know what to call them other than IP but I was trying to think of a better
word but you know what I'm talking about like your Star Trek's your Star Wars your Teenage
Mutant Ninja Turtles they've been brought back right like CBS All Access has like a
whole slate of Star Trek shows but they're all written by the same like team so all the
shows are kind of the same even though they're all different they're all different shows
but it's are all written by the same core writers and producers.
Do we have to bash Discovery again?
I mean I'm always I'm here for sure of course I mean that's easy but here's where I'm going
and I don't know if this is true or not but I'm wondering what you think.
Could it be that the problem is is that we are now watching content being created by
people that are younger than us?
So this is okay you have just opened a door.
There I say you have activated the spore drive and we're on the mycelial plane and I'm about
to dunk hard on Discovery.
Do you know what's wrong with Discovery?
What?
And I just finished watching all of Discovery and I thought I didn't like Voyager.
It makes Voyager look amazing and Voyager frankly isn't that bad.
Dude people hated Enterprise at the time.
You know what Enterprise is good.
It is taken to a whole nother level now and when you view it after watching Discovery
and Picard I'd seriously if you're a Star Trek fan.
If you're just curious about how how writing has changed, watch Picard or watch Discovery
and then go watch Enterprise and Enterprise was like the peak Star Trek production where
like the production was all normalized.
They had a whole machine behind it.
They had like these go-to character actors that played like pivotal roles like Jeffrey
Combs and Dorian.
He also plays a Ferengi.
I just watched the episode last night where he plays a Ferengi and it's just so great.
Even their weak episodes are better than the highlights of the season from Discovery.
So we're throwing out the doc at least for now.
Apparently yeah.
We're going with modern Star Trek.
So TNG doesn't count.
That's old Star Trek.
I just want to say I would say modern Star Trek starts with DS9 and Voyager which were
weirdly for folks who don't know like chronologically synchronized right like they're didn't they
air on opposite nights or something like they were they were direct competitors.
For our first couple of seasons of Voyager DS9 ran but I feel like the new era does start
with TNG but it just wasn't fully flushed out until like season six and seven.
Yeah I feel like most of TNG is basically better effects original Star Trek and then
DS9 it's really midway into DS9 where they start to get like the story continuity and
stuff like that.
I really I know people don't like DS9.
I actually really like DS9 and I've mentioned this before but I don't know I'm super down
with the idea that like what if you had to actually hold your goddamn ground right right
like you weren't just like flying away and having adventures that yeah.
And as a result they got some of the best guest stars exactly.
So the problem with Discovery is the most interesting character on the first season
of Discovery is Captain Lorca.
My wife says this every time we watch Discovery.
It's not that he's evil right it's not the spoilers I guess.
So I'll give you a beat one two.
There's your two beats.
If they didn't do the alternate dimension of bulls**t and just make him like a cartoon
character level villain in the next season how about an actual guy or gal it could be
a gal it's not a gender thing it's it's whatever that was a Starfleet captain but kind of like
didn't buy into all the bulls**t right that kind of was like no we need to kill our enemies
because if I'm easy on them they kill my people.
Remember the Battle of the Binaries that's this whole thing right.
His whole argument before they make him a cartoon villain is but they murdered lots
of our people and they're super cool with killing women and children and civilians.
Yeah he was an interesting character he was a new spin on that role.
Honestly he's a more realistic like before they make him a cartoon character he's a lot
more like what like an actual military man would be like like no we gotta win.
Which would be time appropriate that would have been time appropriate back then.
But they couldn't help it because like we have to understand the people like the best
episode I think is the first season the Klingons are attacking the mining colony and you see
the man he's holding his child you know kids and everything and Lorca is just like no we're
getting there we're gonna dunk on them like the thirsty rigid head folks that they are.
And somehow we decided to have feelings again like this is Star Trek's fatal flaw to me
it believes in a reality that can't possibly exist and it is not the warp drive that's
the problem or the spore drive I hate Discovery.
If you watch the rest of Discovery like the emerald chain like that lady has a point right
like she's not wrong all the dilithium crystals are gone no one can do warp travel.
I love it you always identify with the villains it's so great.
No it's just like she's like dude let's make an alliance because we have to keep in line
if we don't keep it in line crazy pirates do crazy things and yeah they do.
Here's what I'm thinking and here's where I go with this.
So I think what it is is that the writers of these shows have a different set of values
so it reflects that in their writing and now I'm wondering as we talk about this does this
also apply to software like so let's just say for a moment that the average developer
of GNOME is like 25 27 maybe 30 years old.
Is that true?
I don't know I don't think so but I have talked to several members of the GNOME project that
are young so they're like you know early 20s.
I mean we're not that much older.
It's a 20 year difference for me and so maybe there's just a different set of values and
10 for me but okay sure.
I'm wondering if that does play a factor in software development if what you know what
age you are what you value at that time what you focus on which may change over time better
or worse I'm not making a judgment call there but I wonder if that reflects just like we're
seeing it potentially reflected in Star Trek and in Star Wars do we see it in software
and is that maybe one of the problems we have in free software is we either have this issue
where it's a bunch of gray beards and once they age out nobody replaces them or we have
the opposite end of the spectrum where it's sort of like college kids or kids getting
out of high school which is great but also maybe not the best if they're the majority
of the project.
Well this is funny because you and I were having a private conversation earlier today
and every once in a while I will mention on Twitter that I'm going to open a Cora Alice
or I'm going to try to and I get more hate for that than just saying I'm keeping it proprietary
to help you guys pay me.
Right and you know what it might be and I think this is what you're driving at I think
you just nailed it is it's like exposure bias because we are exposed to availability which
is Twitter, YouTube, things like Telegram, real-time chat rooms they're kind of a selective
group of people they're not necessarily representative of the broader spectrum of folks who have
a very busy life and don't have time to participate in an online community or don't have anything
to promote they don't have anything they want to let people know about so they literally
have no reason to engage in social media and can't be bothered to and so they don't get
their positions reflected properly in the conversation.
I'm gonna hit it a little harder though the folks being super negative and like mean to
each other also have very little or nothing of their own to promote and so there's no
cost to them right like every time I do or say something stupid there's a cost to me
same for you right you've been everybody makes a mistake sure I mean folks don't know how
hard it is to do a live show every week it's easy to misspeak it's easy to say something
maybe where you assume that people are gonna take it with charity but uh I don't know if
you've ever been on reddit you can't always be up in your head either about well what
is the psychology of the person listening because then it just locks you up and it freezes
you up so it is it is a particularly challenging kind of work because you want to speak freely
so that way you can tell your you know your actual honest truth you can also be engaging
and at the same time if you're processing how are people gonna take this all the time
which you can't help but do but if you're doing that a lot you kind of ruin it you kind
of wreck the conversation and it kind of becomes this watered down discussion and that's a
tricky tricky thing and people can be upset because you know they look at situations differently
anyways I didn't mean to derail you but I just wanted to kind of underscore like how
challenging that that is a challenging thing there yeah it's tough I mean we you know we've
gotten a lot of feedback you know this week some of it you know we've chosen to respond
to privately I mean I hadn't thought about it the way you had that maybe like I'm a little
younger than you right sorry your hair is better though so what do you care but like
we're not that far apart right maybe it is a generational thing that you know and who
knows right like maybe they're right I don't know I just you know to me I I came up in
that time when the big win if you were an engineer was to go talk to your manager or
the VP or whoever the director you know the companies of word structures and get them
to open source anything and even if that was like Apache or BSD open source even if they
were doing it for purely like to edge out a competitor like bad reasons that was a win
you got a gold star here's your tux plushie and it didn't matter who you were right you
could be you know Planned Parenthood you could be the Catholic Church right if I'm trying
to go to extremes now it's kind of like well no but is the person who open sourced it in
some way evil I don't know I you know what there's a reason I'm gonna watch Star Trek
original series again and make myself feel better that's we should move on that's yeah
it's like it's TNG is like my security blanket I love it it's never goes wrong now DS 9 man
do you know why if Quark's bar ever existed I don't think I'd ever show up to the show
oh man I'd come down there I join you and we just do it from the bar in the holodeck
you just throw me in the holodeck actually would be down for that I could go for a holodeck
that's why maybe the VR was so appealing we're not gonna talk about our disappointment yet
are we no I was more like picturing us chilling in the bar you know having some drinks talking
some code or stuff I think that'd be pretty great I could drunk and at least talk to Cleons
and see how that goes see yeah we'll see how long that last all right well now getting
into the show ask not what your podcast can boost for you but what you can boost for your
podcast snooze ejects boosted in with 2222 sets speaking of free software funding from
last episode did you guys know that the Mozilla Foundation is the 100% owner of a for-profit
corporation known as the Mozilla Corporation and did you know that the same person that
runs the foundation also runs the corporation and that the Linux Foundation has gotten into
selling NFTs on their hyper ledger while also selling their platinum membership which is
$500,000 a year to companies like Microsoft Meta Oracle VMware and others do you think
these types of foundations are bad for developers I can't help but notice the people who run
these foundations get rich and only a small handful of the people writing the software
make anything close to a livable wage I note here that this is a conversation that you
and I have been skirting around I think snooze eject kind of nails it right on the head in
an uncomfortable way that we didn't really want to say out loud curious and curiouser
I mean it does become concerning doesn't it yes that is definitely a diplomatic way to
put that yes I don't know what else to say about it though really you can't undo it I
don't think at this point you're not gonna unwind these foundations and in some way they
are at least paying for some stuff I just want to say for over a decade you and I have
been discussing funding software development and it's still a problem and I think that's
where maybe we should leave it I mean I know you're right and I know it's it's hopeless
but this is why I have been talking about the value for value model more and more even
though people hate it when I do but I think they need to hear this I think we have to
consider that foundations and Google and Amazon are not going to solve this problem and I
think we have to consider just building in and and and and creating this culture of a
mindset that if you get value from a free software project you exchange value in some
way back be it be documentation be it code be it monetary I mean I have another word
for that open core sure good that could be a way you could contribute core you could
contribute code back to the core you could help bug test it right you could have open
core can be very liberal right you think the beautiful thing about writing the license
is that you get to write the damn license I don't you can write any light it's like
any contract I think it's a culture problem I don't think it's a I don't think it's a
license problem I think it's a culture issue and I think I believe open source and free
software projects haven't been been selling their value they haven't been pitching they
don't they don't sell they don't sell that's basically they don't sell and they don't tell
users that we actually need this and I am also of the opinion that there really hasn't
been a good facility and means to do it and I think these boost type systems where you're
doing a peer-to-peer payment system where you can afford to send three dollars or two
dollars you can't even do that with the US dollar none of these payment systems make
it viable to send that kind of amount of money and so we have people who listen to this show
and they have turned on sat streaming in their podcasting 2.0 app and as they listen they
just send us a few sats in the background every few minutes and it ends up being maybe
55 cents for them at the end of the listening session or a dollar that you know whatever
they said it to and we could be doing that same exact thing we could be all of the technology
pipeline is there but we would still hit that cultural issue so we have to also fix that
it's something we have to bake in it's something we used to talk about more and it got away
from us and I think part in part because of these sort of centralizations that have occurred
and in part because of blowback that's occurred I mean I've been thinking about this a lot
it's been coming up a lot on the show I've also seen more free software projects embracing
things like matrix and mastodon for their coordination I even joined the podcasting
2.0 mastodon I'll put a link to that in the show notes just because you know I don't not
a big mastodon not a big social media person but it's sort of like a really niche focused
communications platform where people are talking about the back end development that's happening
for podcasting 2.0 and the developers are communicating with other developers about
the things they're working on in this very vertical mastodon instance that might have
legs long term I don't know maybe not but it does feel like we've we've reached a tipping
point that is not healthy for small developers or developers of all these libraries that
kind of end up being the glue bits that you know turn colors on or can do something that
just is it nice to have that gets pulled in as a dependency and turns out you know tens
of thousands of projects are using that and that person's not making a dime and we have
the means we just don't have the will or the care to do it I think that's it not enough
people give a this is really not my role but I'm going to try to take down the negativity
oompa maybe there's a way forward I'm going to shut up about open core because it usually
lends us with a lot of bad emails but sometimes a compromise is better than nothing right
because I got to tell you with the and we're going to talk about Intel in a minute here
but with the M1 chips with Apple's just frankly Thanos level grip on independent developers
right now in terms of mobile but frankly the whole world right I think maybe we need to
make some compromises with values because the the alternative is these big listen the
Facebook VR store we had last week was horrific right fit what is it 50 percent they wanted
yeah basically it's it's unbelievable so if what you're doing isn't working you have to
stop and that's what I feel about frankly the Linux community at this point we're fighting
about stuff for no reason and I know and you know you and I both know a lot of folks who
are pretty deep into the community that are now quietly running M1 Mac pros and basically
not participating much not participating right they got good jobs or they they're doing their
businesses because they're just tired of the nonsense well this is an interesting email
that came into the show that kind of reflects on this so Jimmy wrote in about the cycles
of centralization he says I like to listen on my walks and bike rides but I always forget
to send feedback maybe this will be great he says about the boost since it's right there
in the podcast app while I'm listening but he sent this in via the contact form he says
I know you guys have been talking a lot about decentralization in different contexts and
I wanted to add that I think this is just part of the oscillation of capitalism in general
it seems like industries have a tendency to centralize over time like gravity if you will
for a variety of reasons it's not just because a dominant player buys out others but also
because there is a certain economy of scale that lowers the price of products and services
also coincides with the lower barriers of entry for new users and customers and users
want the most with the least amount of effort and someone will always come around to offer
that which leads eventually to centralization and this routinely happens with technology
it'll even happen with cryptocurrencies eventually and you already do see it happen with companies
like coinbase and robin hood and cash app and stuff like that but he says technology
will then oscillate back and something will break out to decentralize once again like
Batman and the Joker they're doomed to do this forever it's a feature not a bug we're
definitely in a centralization cycle right now and I think Jimmy kind of nails it maybe
some of these things we're talking about are gonna lead to to decentralizing more and maybe
we'll find a balance there it would be really interesting if all of this upset around Twitter
and the Elon purchase leads to Twitter becoming less relevant and then essentially we have
a decentralization of social media so then no one social media platform drives the media
narrative as much as we're seeing today that could be a great outcome it's essentially
Twitter becomes less relevant why do you think it'll become less relevant I could see it
happening simply because the folks behind the media companies are not going to take
a platform run by Elon they're not gonna run their whole slate of programming off of that
do you remember when we were watching the news and all of a sudden they just like started
putting up screenshots of Twitter all the time and it like it was weird right I think
that fades away because Elon changes the general tone on the platform and the narrative I think
that means that they don't want to use it as a source of truth anymore it just seems
like it's a drug that's too easy to hit but we got to keep moving yeah you're right it
is it is very handy bossy right saying he says been listening for a few months love
the show I was wondering what your take is on Elon statement that free speech law should
apply to social media and what that means for the comment sections on places like websites
especially if it results in some sort of legislation do you think this will eventually have a trickle
down concern for small shops down the road once again love the show if kind of one of
the reactions to this is we start like you know following up on defamation and stuff
like that on social media like Twitter do you think that would spread to the rest of
the web yes but I have a probably surprising take on this I don't like a lot of what I
consider an overreaction to history in the moderation stuff like I really don't think
you should go dig into someone's tweets or emails or whatever when they were like 18
or 17 or like a kid to them out of a job I sort of think we just all need to grow up
and like teenage boys in particular are kind of bad people and that's that's fine right
their kids kids are stupid Chris and I are both fathers we were pretty pretty they do
dumb things right that's why you have to protect children that's why they can't so like this
I hate this like witch hunt thing where we go back well when you were in college you
said this misogynist the thing I'm like well I don't know like Chris and I were lucky enough
that social media and for him it's even better was not a huge thing like it was just new
and I remember Facebook wasn't even at my school there are things I said in the really
early podcast like our cast a blast a podcast that we would never say or do now well right
like like I just want to say like teenage boys have some bad ideas because mostly they're
joking and they're like immature so I I sort of I don't know how you can't you can't make
this a law you can't like legislate a free speech shield that no one can ever because
ultimately Twitter is a private corporation I think of it as clubs right if you're from
the north and I they have them down south but it seems to work differently here it's
a private club right if you're a member of the club there are certain standards of behavior
that they expect you to hold I have never been a member of one of these clubs because
I wasn't all right folks here's another Mike lesson in history stay a while stay a while
and listen part of living up north is like wasp exists if you don't know what that means
and if you are one you definitely know what that means and they don't like certain types
of people and it's surprising how expansive they are about not letting them into their
clubs and to me that's annoying it's been a source of irritation for me because I'm
the way I am but I feel like a private company a private platform is a club ultimately and
if the owner of the club doesn't want you there well then he or she can throw you out
they could set the rules so again I hate that technology is so intertwined with this media
crap now it's moderation crap because I would much rather be talking to you about cool python
packages but we we can't escape it I mean it affects my business it definitely affects
Chris's because advertising is a part of a whole mother he could speak to it more but
like you cannot piss off your advertisers and they're more sensitive than they've ever
been before not our specifically like the thing he's getting at with Elon is that the
big media brands will get mad because they don't like Elon and when they were pulled
the ad they were advertising from Twitter is that fair that is definitely one of the
concerns it seems to be yeah right so it's it's like I I don't know my my inner libertarian
is like yeah it's a private club you can throw people out but I can't imagine running my
business the Mad Potter Inc without being able to use any social media because someone
didn't like that I'm like not super I think that's it I think that's the nut of it and
I've been really struggling because I I really don't care but then I realized people view
this as like the platform they go to to express their position and now they're concerned that
ability is going to be taken away from them and other people go there because they feel
like they have to to be in order to even just reach a few hundred people I don't really
know I maybe there is something to it maybe it's more important than I realized or maybe
it's not maybe we're about to discover it's not that important at all and I feel like
that's the fork in the road we're at right now if you had to advertise to small and medium
businesses the idea of getting your company account or even your account banned on Twitter
or Facebook would be it's just not acceptable I mean it it is it is the most cost efficient
way to reach out to these folks all right well since we've already taken the show off
the rails completely I'm gonna go even deeper I've started a conversation that is really
already exploding we're redoing everything online for Jupiter broadcasting us it's a
massive project I gotta have the community's help and that conversation kicked off in office
hours episode three office hours dot hair go there even if you just go there for the
links it's office how office hours dot hair slash three new website energy is the podcast
episode title we sat down with Alex Brent West myself just kind of outline some of the
ideas we have and then we put up a GitHub repo where we can start collecting ideas and
it's just it's huge already and so I'd like to get the coder audience involved that seems
like an obvious step next and so I wanted to let everybody know I brought and bringing
you in behind the curtain for a moment that's happening right now it's a summer project
our hosting provider let us know we have until the end of summer to get the F off the platform
so it's something we have a deadline we're serious about and we're kind of taking in
ideas and we've already gotten some ideas we hadn't even considered before so office
hours dot here to check that out I am thinking things are about to get a little bit more
sketch Intel CEO Pat Gluster anticipates at the end of the chip shortages won't be until
2024 in fact he was originally saying 2023 but now it looks like things are even worse
I got a just a brief clip of him talking to Bloomberg about this issue overall though
the big story is around building up the semiconductor capacity and we had felt like 23 we start
to see that equilibrium now in no small part because of some of the equipment shortages
the equipment that goes into the fabs that we're building we're seeing those lead times
push out substantially and as a result we expect the overall semiconductor shortage
to not be resolved until 2024 now as some of those capacities come online yeah and Apple
in their earnings call a couple of days ago said they expect an eight billion dollar reduction
in sales due to in large part the COVID-19 lockdowns in China that will reduce supply
chain and Tim Cook said they're considering spinning up more supply chain or more manufacturing
but the supply chain issue would still remain an issue so even if they bring manufacturing
over to India he said they still can't get the bits they need to actually build the devices
eight billion dollars by the way is like an entire business right it is all of like the
iPad sales for Apple well yeah I guess but it's a big chunk of change it's a lot of money
and here's what's even scarier is Intel didn't meet their expectations that's not good so
Intel stock is down but it's not too bad it's bounced back a little bit but the CEO in there
in that full clip that I'll have linked in the show notes part of what he says is gonna
make things work out and everything's gonna be rosy and we don't need to worry is that
he says they're expecting a large commercial purchase in the fall for like refreshing machines
at businesses now that people are coming back to work and he expects a whole bunch of business
machines to be replaced and so he thinks that's gonna boost their sales a whole bunch may
happen but if it doesn't happen it looks like Intel could be set for some serious losses
I'm gonna avoid the political stuff because I think we've done enough of that here but
like it would be great if maybe things weren't built in one specific place right just saying
yeah but that that's that is what it is now right so that that's that ship sailed right
that happened in the 80s or late 80s really nice I you know it if I was buying a laptop
right now and my choices were Intel AMD one of the new AMD is right or Apple I would probably
Intel would be my last choice I guess is how I should put it they're frankly not that competitive
but that's why I think they think this what the CEO says in that interview like the commercial
market now is their bread and butter the business machines people that I have work desktops
run Windows I can see that Dell effectively Dell yeah your Dell's in your HP's right and
then you have gamers are probably buying rise in systems or some of the high-end Intel systems
but they're just not a huge percentage of their purchases and now you have Apple one
of the largest PC sellers is no longer using their chips and so they're focusing on commercial
well and the other news we don't have the notice is that Apple's Mac sales have skyrocketed
the reason Apple's reporting a shortfall is because they can't make enough of them in
fact I think they were the only PC manufacturer to show significant growth in the last quarter
yeah it's those M1 machines but it's not just Intel and Apple it's gonna be the whole industry
and you know at first we were back in 2021 we were told you know it'd be better it'd
be better mid 2022 then we got to 2022 or so well it looks like it's gonna be 2023 now
we're not even to mid 2022 and they say well now it's gonna be 2024 both Apple and Intel
are saying this isn't gonna be better until 2024 and I wonder if there is opportunity
for developers in the midst of this chaos and I this could be way off but what if we
saw a bit of a kind of Cuban car moment happen with our technology where because we cannot
get our hands on the new stuff in this case it's supply chain issues but for the Cubans
you know it was an embargo and so they couldn't import new cars and so they had no choice
but to develop a car culture and repair them and keep them running and now they have some
of the most beautiful classic cars in the world and they're like a specialty item that
that rich people import and I have an article about this that talks about how once that
US embargo was created and the banning of American cars and parts was in place Cuba
just essentially did a huge DIY repair program what if we saw something like that happen
again maybe not like full-fledged it's only gonna be for a few years but what if what
if like those kiosks in the mall start coming back that offer screen repair and battery
replacement and yeah it's not as easy but at least they can do it and you know maybe
maybe we start seeing more of that and people reuse stuff instead of get rid of it is that
an impossibility yeah I mean I think that's possible I don't think it's gonna be as widespread
as you'd like I mean the dirty little secret here is for most business users you know the
current processors are just fine yeah I mean we we have a story that I don't think we're
gonna dive into deeply this week but we'll do it next week about it's from Hacker News
why why are all these terminal development companies going to the cloud to the web and
the answer is well because the world has changed having a honking workstation is not that important
for most business users in fact most things are now over the network so I mean we mentioned
warp terminal the forgot his name Zach Zachary something but he's a formal Google Drive engineer
he's a he had a fancy title but you know his whole thing is he basically wants to take
the Google Docs experience to the terminal and that's I don't know I mean I'm currently
hiring something we're gonna talk about a little bit that I would prefer to hire on
site but that seems almost impossible though my point is it makes less and less sense to
spend a lot of money on individual folks as computers than it does to spend on honking
frankly server equipment or cloud services that can synchronize our work between everybody
totally I could see cloud workstations become even more popular in this supply chain crunch
and what a great time to also save cost yeah and then also that really works a lot better
for work at home too because they can just open up that remote cloud terminal using a
client software at home and they have the same experience in security and for for InfoSec
if the person leaves the company or whatever no shows for three days you just disable their
access that's it they have nothing I know we have some listeners that are using cloud
desktops and they've been using them for a little bit so I'd love to know what your experience
has been and if you see this market growing coder dot show slash contact or send us in
a podcasting 2.0 boost and let us know what your experience has been and where you think
it's going lino.com slash coder go there to get $100 and 60 day credit on a new account
and you go there to support this here show Linode is fast reliable fantastic cloud hosting
you've got to go try it for your next project it's what I've used for the last couple of
years now and Linode has been rolling out MVME storage so the rigs are super fast they
have 11 data centers around the world and they're always optimizing for performance
and they have 30 to 50 percent lower prices than the big hyperscalers that want to lock
you into their esoteric platforms and if you're gonna be at KubeCon EU say hi to Linode they
got a booth there May 16th through the 20th in Spain man am I jealous of that if you're
a performance hound you're gonna love Linode if you've never set up a server before you're
gonna be fine at Linode and if you've been racking and stacking boxes for 20 years you're
gonna love how much easier Linode just made your job they have great documentation their
API is clean and simple and the reality is there's a ton of tooling already built for
you to take advantage of libraries command line tools apps it's great Linode's been doing
this for nearly 19 years so they've built a passionate community and a dedicated following
some of your absolute favorite projects apps media companies the whole range they run on
Linode Linode turns out is the secret sauce behind a ton of our favorite online companies
not all of them talk about it all the time because you know it's part of their secret
we get it but we know oh we know and often you'll find people proudly talking about it
because when you've been a Linode customer you generally have great things to say and
one of the things I hear from coder listeners all the time is that nobody beats Linode support
so when you got great pricing great performance great support and it's a way to support independent
productions like this here podcast well that's a pretty good combination so go try it for
real go learn something go build something go try something and get that $100 Linode.com
slash coder stay a while and listen I've been waiting to hear a bit of a story from you
I I have a sense that you had a comedy of errors occur oh yes so we'll do this quick
because we're at the end of the show so we had a partnership uh or have I'm not gonna
exactly name names because I didn't get permission I got an email abruptly telling me that you
know basically go pound sound we were not interested in being in business with you this
was an Alice partnership oh lovely lovely if you're a longtime listener of the show
you can imagine how I would respond to that kind of thing not not well not well and you
know poor form on my part too it turned out that what had happened is that there was another
dude named Michael that they were in a partnership with no and the the yes the person had a medical
issue that I was dealing with and he had to be on leave for a week so his interim got
confused and very awkwardly sent a check to the other company who the gentleman running
that company's name was Mike and fired us of course it was it wasn't they weren't a
client it wasn't a firing but it was like a dissolving our our relationship so this
guy comes back and we had done nothing that we had agreed to do because obviously you
know I thought whatever happened happened and there was this very I can only describe
this this zoom call as the most cringe core thing I've ever had where basically like well
you freaked out what's going on I'm like well you know you guys you you didn't keep your
obligations and then you just ghosted us and then you came back and said and it just ended
up the two of them I thought wait huh they muted there was a misunderstanding he had
the wrong email there's another Michael at something yeah that is literally what happened
it's common there's a lot of Chris's out there too and it's made me think like we really
should have come up with some kind of ID verify in email yeah like maybe not mandatory but
really common practice would have been great well and I just want to say the email I got
was was was like hard it wasn't a hey man sorry things it was a frankly go-pound-sand
email somebody was surprised they just got a big bill and they were angry right and which
is weird because we didn't build them anything because we were partnering with them and doing
a rev share so I was kind of like what and then of course the natural response to so
scummy MBA types well unless I skim this mean but MBA types when they send you a mean email
will never answer your calls again they want it all documented but I tried like the next
morning because the email came in like midnight I'm like you know what I've been there I've
sent the bad email I've sent the bad slack message maybe somebody's you know frankly
in their cups let's just take a breath we'll call in the morning oh I couldn't even like
I was getting straight like you can tell when your numbers blocked because it just rings
out and you always get the voicemail right and yeah it was it still continues to be awkward
so we should write it back and like hey go learn about GPG keys let's get this no I'm
kidding of course that's not gonna work I sent them Alice stickers actually because
I'm a dick tailscale.com slash coder go there to get a free personal account for up to 20
devices and of course you're supporting the show tailscale is a zero config VPN you installed
on any machine or device in minutes it'll take care of the firewall rules and I gotta
say it also manages that dreaded carrier double net some of us end up with hand on heart last
night before bedtime this was for me I'm an old man is about 9 30 p.m. and I realized
that I had just figured out how to fix something on one of the devices in the studio like it
just came to me and I was like oh god it's so obvious and you know the beautiful thing
is is on my iPad I have tailscale and I have the Termulus app and I have my tailscale IPS
for my different hosts already saved in there so I fired my iPad in you know half a second
and I'm connected even quicker to this host that's here at the studio and I'm parked out
in the woods at the foot of the Cascade Mountains on Verizon or AT&T or you know I don't know
brand I don't know which network I was on because I'm on this mobile setup I have but
either way I am natted up the wazoo and tailscale just works instantly you can quickly and easily
create a secure flat network between you your servers your computers your devices this is
a way I've brought my different VPS systems together on their same network and I can actually
connect them to my systems that I have here at the studio there may be running in a VM
it's also how I keep connected to my family's computers and provide support I have a run
on everything from Raspberry Pi to iPads huge arch x86 boxes openSUSE and machines I mean
you name it and the devices they connect through your existing identity provider and there's
a lot of consumer options but you can easily also use a business option and work with multi-factor
authentication de-authorized devices as you need and all of this is protected with WireGuard's
noise protocol I knew WireGuard was going to change the game but tailscale has taken
this to the next level and they've just made a solution here that's changed the way I work
forever you got to try it for yourself and you can try it for free for up to 20 machines
and you go to tailscale.com slash coder free for up to 20 devices and you support the show
tailscale.com slash coder this is a weird awkward situation a longtime free app used
by many in our community is looking to go subscription telegram is adding a premium
subscription according to current betas and we don't know the price yet because that information
is not in the beta builds but we do know it looks like as a perk you're going to get very
special stickers and you're going to get a special emoticon customizer and probably other
things of which we do not know yet but here we are in 2022 and another app that's been
essentially supercharged by being free I got to imagine it's expensive because I've uploaded
like 400 megabyte video files to telegram and they take them right I mean the file storage
alone just based on having 2,000 users on our matrix server I can tell you it's astronomical
if they have you know millions and millions but here we are I just feels like another
subscription are you serious like I love telegram and I use the crap out of it but oh my god
dude another subscription I'm gonna die I want to like cut back and like what I subscribe
to is like really considered stuff that really makes a difference stuff that makes a difference
in my life or or whoever I'm supporting and I just cannot get behind like arbitrary subscriptions
for all of this stuff what else can we do I don't know but there it is telegrams going
premium you don't care you're not a telegram user anymore are you no I don't use telegram
anymore that's how I feel that's how I feel because I know I'm gonna get it I'm gonna
be getting upselled 30 times a day eventually that's how it all it always goes this way
you know it always comes back to you how do we fund software development I swear to god
if they would just let me throw them a few sats you know once a day or something I'd
be happy all right just a little follow-up before we get to your hiring news we talked
about this last week Apple has now shared a new developer update clarifying its App
Store improvement policies it's extending the amount of time it's giving developers
to update their apps that have been updated in two years from 30 days to 90 days but here's
the part that I do not like Apple says that apps that have not been updated within the
past three years and which do not meet a minimum threshold for downloads i.e. extremely few
or limited downloads in a rolling 12-month period are still subject to the policy and
those developers will get notices via email so I guess an apps value is determined by
its downloads you know I could see where they were coming from but there's there was a good
conversation on the iOS dev I think or underscore dev there's two of them on reddit were game
developers were kind of bitching like you guys don't understand we write the game we
update unity and it basically runs for years we and you know we their sales are so meager
for the for most of them right it's a video game right they sell the you how many times
everybody is about to be forced to buy Sonic one two and three again because Sega's releasing
them it's the same it's the same and I'm gonna be one of you so I don't this is not me dunking
but it's like this is a stupid policy if if the app works if the game works Apple should
just leave it on the store here's my angle like you can't have a both ways Apple if you
don't want a sideloading and I got a small team and you know we need an app for doing
business or maybe we're maybe when we're out in the field doing live stuff we have like
a Jupiter broadcasting team app and it's got 10 users so you know okay well should I come
up with some way to sideload that so we all enroll in some sort of developer program should
I should I force all of the volunteers of JB to to get enrolled in some sort of device
management system like what is my solution here other than to distribute in the App Store
and now because I've built something and I've utilized the only distribution mechanism they'll
let me use in any real meaning way meaningful way because I've utilized the only system
they've made available I'm now being punished for it like there are actually apps I mean
they probably should be pulled but there are apps that we've distributed like that just
want you know some quick app that we've created as a tool or a concept that we put in the
App Store we only internally you know had you know we told a few people about it wanted
to be able to tell randos so we wanted it public and you know that probably would not
qualify it's probably been cold let the people sideload Apple make it a pain in the ass never
gonna happen all right well you know what is happening the mad botters hiring that's
happening got several positions yes we are we have three positions yes typescript developer
lot of ionic lot of angular very mobile focus but you know desktop too right because the
world is hard we have three positions a more senior Python developer a junior Python developer
and this typescript position all of them are preferred on site and plant city which I think
is going to be the topic of next week's show Chris what do you think I'm down okay but
there are remote options available with the caveats that we only have what do they call
them employment charters or that's not the right word but in the US you have to have
a license but you have to be registered as an employer in each state so right now we're
only registered in New Jersey and Florida ah so they have to be a contractor if they're
remote if they're not in either of those states they would have we would have to work something
else out yeah yeah yeah or we could open like if it's Georgia it's different because you're
right here but yeah I want a job but I just want to get paid under the table for it is
that doable yeah it's very hard to do that anymore trust me I mean whoa no no so two
Python roles we're very heavy on fast API and flask a lot of ginger to lot of ginger
too and the types of stuff is almost all angular all right we'll have a link to that in the
notes at coder dot show slash 464 oh and a fancy new domain name because I was jealous
of your office hours are you ready yeah are you ready totally ready forget the mad potter
dot com what is that crap whoo so long t mb dot i n c t mb dot inc and inc in the ink
that's that is that's legit you know it's legit that's how you do it dot hairs over
in clown town but that's that's getting to work I tried to buy the dot hair and it's
weird it showed me a giffy of you yeah like flipping your luxurious locks that wouldn't
let me do it I got to be careful also hits the microphone makes a big noise I want to
say a special thank you to our members over at coder qa.co that's a way to give value
back to the show on an ongoing basis and it really makes a difference it lets us be picky
you know I don't talk about it because it sounds like we're bragging but we get lots
of offers every single week for all kinds of weird sponsorships or limited run things
or fly-by-night operations or another really common one is people want to pay us to have
like their marketing person on the show or something like that and our members give us
the flexibility to say no to all that kind of stuff and as a thank you you get an ad
free version of the show you get the coderly report and you can become a member at coder
qa.co or you can support all the jb shows and get all of the network perks for every
single show at jupiter.party and of course if you want to give back on an individual
basis or just a little extra you can send in a boost with the new podcasting app at
newpodcastapps.com all right mr dominic is there anywhere you want to send people this
week go to tmp.inc or alice.dev I do like that new domain that's tight that's nice that's
great for the social era that we seem to dread so much you can find me at Chris LAS on the
Twitters while I'm still there you can join our matrix server it's colony.jupiterbroadcasting.com
go create a free count on matrix.org and then join our server we got two different coder
chat rooms in there it's a really nice community links to what we talked about today for this
year's show coder.show slash 464 our contact form is over there that's a big part of the
show your feedback goes directly in makes the show what it is we appreciate it and last
but not least join us on a Monday noon Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern at jblive.tv thanks so much
for being here see you next week.