This is KOTORadio, episode 490, Prokober 31st!
Hey good buddy, welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show,
taking a pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development
and the spooky world of technology.
My name is Chris, obviously, it's Halloween, and joining us like the soldier is,
even though I'm late, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello, mate.
KOTORba mitzvah, spooky, scary, noobs becoming...
Oh, it's a...
I had a whole thing.
Oh, good, that was... yeah, that's good.
Now you don't get it, see?
This is...
No!
You know what, you Lenart Potter-ing me, you jumped on the stage, you get nothing.
I did.
Yeah, you get nothing.
You're saying that Kanye did?
Is that what you're saying?
No, actually, wasn't Lenart Potter-ing before Kanye?
That might have been.
Yo, Lenart, go get some money out of Kanye, everybody else is suing him,
what the hell, jump in line.
Fired up now, he's at Microsoft, he's telling people like it is out there, I guess.
Got a whole new way of doing boot.
The most gangster Linux community thing to do is to be like,
yeah, bitches, you know where I'm going?
Microsoft.
What?
It is.
It's also very common.
Yeah, well, Microsoft's got a bigger and bigger Linux department now.
Are you saying they're measuring their Linux?
They're also in that late-biocracy-stage company where they've gone through being
like the craziest, most complex bureaucracy possible,
and they've kind of leveled off a little bit where some companies like I think
Google and Apple are still getting worse and worse and worse in that regard.
I'm sure Microsoft has a slow decline as well.
I mean, it's a cycle, right?
None of it's as bad as Adobe, which is apparently going to make,
and everybody was freaking out,
apparently Adobe's going to make certain colors only available as an in-app,
well, no, actually just not available, like they can't license them or something.
I don't know.
I'm not an Adobe guy.
But it really fit in with our trend today of looking at some scary trends
coming down the pipe for tech because, yes, it's spooky Halloween,
and you and I are both dads of young kids, so, you know,
Halloween's a big deal in our neck of the woods.
So I did ask some design folks what the deal is with this color stuff.
Oh, yeah? Okay.
Yeah.
All right, so there's a company in, guess what state?
There's only one state that would pull a move like this.
I mean, I always default to Florida, but...
No, no, Florida wouldn't even know.
Florida would be too drunk or like riding an alligator down the highway.
Yeah, you're right.
You're more like chaotic.
Yeah, New Jersey.
Only New Jersey could think of this.
That's legal.
Yep.
Yeah, it's a gangster move a little bit, too.
It is.
There's a little bit of it.
Is it technically legal?
It sure is.
So basically, some company used to sell print colors,
and they are somehow proprietary colors.
This reminds me of a meeting I had with a large printer company
who was very upset about the shade of blue that I couldn't get.
Oh, yeah, they hate that.
Well, because I'm a spiteful little bastard,
I went back and looked.
Sure enough, that shade of blue...
Now, granted, the reason I couldn't get it was just me being a jackass,
but it is one of these colors.
So apparently, these are all like off colors.
You know what I mean?
They're like in between, you know, hard to get the hex code for.
Yeah.
Basically, Photoshop magic.
When the designer...
Got to have your monitor dialed in.
Right.
Like on my ViewSonic monitor, I basically can't see them, right?
It's why the Apple monitor is $5,000.
It's pretty insane.
So what they did is...
This is actually not Adobe being evil.
Well, well, okay.
So this company who owns the colors,
whose name eludes me right now,
but they're in New Jersey,
and that's pretty much all you need to know
because I'm sure I'm related to some of them.
Hey, cuz, told Adobe,
I see you have that monthly subscription thing going there.
It's an awfully sweet Creative Cloud you've got.
It'd be a shame if you didn't pay us some more royalties
and something happened to those colors.
And Adobe was like, no, we're Adobe.
They're like, cool, you don't get the colors.
But because of the darkness,
and I will stand by this till the...
I've held this position since we started in 2012.
Creative Cloud is in fact a downgrade.
As someone who has acquired Illustrator and Dreamweaver
when that was a thing, many times in his youth,
if you know what I mean.
What a nice cat with headphones on that is, wow.
You know, my software fell off the back of a truck
when I was a kid, my Adobe software.
Well, in New Jersey, you literally just go see your uncle Vito
and they hand you like the four CDs it used to be.
You know, that is legit how it used to go down.
And you could use the CD key as many times as you wanted
because there wasn't checking with any server.
You had the disk, you had the thing.
It was like you had the machine, you have the system.
Well, Creative Cloud pretty aggressively forces upgrades on people.
So the nightmare scenario is you have your,
let's just take the simple case, your Photoshop file
for your very picky printer company,
and your Creative Cloud updates
because you leave your iMac Pro on all night, of course,
to do your updates.
And all of a sudden, you open that same file the next day
and the color is gone, so they're just black.
And not like a nice black, but like a void out black, right?
And that's not how local apps are supposed to be.
But you know what?
You know how the verge says, what's a button?
We should have, what's an app?
Right. What is an app?
Is a local app that gets updated by a cloud service
that's tied into some sort of authentication mechanism
that's always checking in and auto-installing updates?
Is that truly a local app? Sounds like a hybrid app to me.
What if the platform vendor can turn off an app
or remove it from your device?
They totally can. They totally can remove your licensing.
What if, and I just had this ugly experience,
you have an app that you paid for years ago,
you open your iPad, you try to run it, and the app runs fine,
but because the company no longer exists,
their REST API no longer exists, and it does nothing.
So is that a local app then? No.
No, I think they're all, eww, services, eww, we should move on.
See, that's our first scary thing.
New Jersey.
So Matt wrote in to push back a little bit
on license being gatekeeping.
His core point was that, well, somebody's got to sign off
on things that are like professional public works
that need to be safe for the public to use.
Part of the responsibility, he writes,
of a professional engineer is to sign off on projects
that meet all the regulations,
and then they need some point of responsibility
if there are mistakes they've made
that result in some sort of major issue.
He says, sure, this isn't maybe necessary for web developers
or a lot of common software development,
but he says you might be able to argue it is
for somebody working on the 737, for example.
So he says it's not gatekeeping in all cases,
and sometimes it's just good for public safety.
And maybe the argument also I think that might resonate
is holding someone accountable for a mistake.
Sure.
I mean, that is a great idea.
And I actually agree with it,
but it kind of falls apart when you see in practice
how these licensing schemes tend to be used.
I would say with the great exception of the type
of public work he's talking about, like bridges.
Fair. I think you're right.
The actual implementation has shown us
that it is being abused.
There's clearly some use case for it,
which is probably why it came around to begin with.
But now it's just gone too far.
I'm with you on that.
So yeah, that was Matt. Now Matthew wrote in.
So we've got Matt and Matthew this week
with some uniform ideas.
He says if you go with one thing,
it's doomed to failure in the long run.
Your preferences will change, companies will drop items.
That has been on my mind.
Instead, I propose you strive for an interoperable wardrobe,
a modular wardrobe, you know,
anything with maybe like an open source core.
For instance,
my work shirts can be worn with regular jeans
or more formal pants I own.
With this strategy, if you don't want to think about
what you wear, you just grab the first thing off the rack
and you're good to go.
And if you're feeling in particular,
you can grab a pair instead.
Hope to hear the conclusion to your quest soon.
Those are good points.
Interoperable I think might be the way to go.
It's like a mix and match and that I believe,
my wife corrected me,
I thought a wardrobe capsule, because I'm an idiot,
was just like a whole outfit,
shirt, pants, socks, whatever.
I don't know what makes a whole outfit.
But she's saying nah.
It's actually, this is what she says,
she says nah, she says nah.
It's actually mix and match.
It's like different shirts that go with different pants,
but they all go together.
That's a wardrobe capsule.
So I think maybe I need a wardrobe capsule.
I don't know why it's called a capsule.
And not just a wardrobe,
but it's a wardrobe capsule.
I kind of didn't get this email.
It reminds me of the Skyrim created character thing,
where all the pieces kind of go together.
Yes.
So that's what it is.
Yeah, I need a character creator.
And then I asked the audience out there
if anybody else uses a dedicated PC for Emacs or some other job,
and Don noted that he has a dedicated PC
for his banking and his crypto purchases.
So there you go.
And then we made a note in the doc for Mumble Colony,
but I don't remember what that's in regards to.
We do have a Mumble though at jupitabroadcasting.com.
Mumble is still around?
Yeah, still around.
We use it on LUP still
and on office hours quite frequently.
There you go.
Now you learned.
Today you learned.
linode.com slash coder.
That's where you go to get $100
in 60-day credit on a new account.
And it's a great way to support the show
while you're checking out some fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You got to try Linode for your next project.
It's what we use for everything
we've built and deployed recently.
It's part of what makes our new website seem fast.
Linode makes us look good.
They've been rolling out MVME storage upgrades too,
so the performance there is super great.
They are their own ISP.
They have a whole range of systems
from nanodes that are just tiny little boxes
that maybe do like one job,
a nano box to these monster systems
like we use for our matrix system.
If you're a performance hound,
you're going to love the combination
of CPU options, GPU options,
and storage options.
And next year, they're lighting up a dozen
new data centers.
Linode's just simply the best place
to host and run your code.
And they have a bunch of one-click deployments
for tons of open source applications,
GitLab and GitT,
and things that are just really quick
and get up and going like Nextcloud.
They'll also let you build it up from scratch
with just about any distro you'd ever want to use
in the cloud. They've got a big range of distributions,
a great dashboard,
a clean API, and best of all,
you can get a hundred bucks
while you support the show to try it all out.
You just go to linode.com slash coder.
There has been a story that's been super
embarrassing for Apple since we gathered
together last week, and it's really gross.
It all kind of comes together here.
Apple is flexing control over the
App Store in such a
grotesque, overreaching way
that it's absolutely going to limit
development of some industries.
It's already holding back companies
like Telegram. Telegram's CEO
has accused Apple of destroying dreams
and crushing entrepreneurs.
Sounds like my ex-wife.
He said that
they had a feature they wanted to roll out.
They would have been kind of like
an in-app payment thing, but Apple
wants a 30% cut of any of that
type of stuff. Apple's also updated
their rules to say they're going to get a cut of any
NFT sales done
inside an Apple
iPhone. Did they really
relocate to Jersey too? I know,
right?
Their App Store department must be over there.
Also, all of the
little boost or favorite of post
or Facebook thing where you can buy something to
make your post stand out. All of that
stuff now. Apple just announced
they also want a 30% cut of all of that
stuff. This is major.
I actually have a sound bite from Tim Cook
on this. Okay.
I'm altering the deal.
Pray I don't alter it any further.
I know. Which historically
he's definitely going to.
This has really
gotten to a new level.
Alex Gigatexel, he pointed out
a clip from Coderadio 197
back in 2016
where we were kind of going on about how
bad the App Store discovery was
and how bad the search was.
Slowly but surely, what Apple has done is
instead of fixing search in the App Store,
they've introduced new and new layers
of advertising. Along with
just squeezing down
on every way these apps
can potentially deal
with money at all. Even if
they're doing everything within the app ecosystem,
Apple wants a cut. They're also
at the same time loading up
the App Store with more ads. They just got in a bunch
of trouble because they had gambling ads
that people hated right next to developers
apps that were about mental health
and whatnot. There was one in particular
that was literally an app to help
you quit gambling. They say they've
paused the ads related to gambling and a few other
categories on the App Store now.
But the fact that it made it in there in the first
place, that's a shift for
Apple. Remember?
Apple wasn't willing to cross that line until recently.
In fact, we used to criticize them for being
too puritanical. They were like
they had some pretty
strict censorship things. They've kicked
apps out if you could somehow
leap out from the app and then end up on a gambling
site. They've kicked an app out of the App Store before.
And now they're running gambling
ads.
They've paused them.
It's like how
the PayPal $2,500
fine for misinformation got out and everybody
freaked out. Did you know they're putting it back in?
Now I don't know if the misinformation language is in there,
but they've slipped that $2,500 fine back in.
It's like people get outraged.
We get over it and then the companies just
kind of move on and they just tighten it down.
That's Apple's move here. So they've paused
it. They've paused it, they say.
But eventually, that line will
slip again. It'll be back.
And if they're willing to slip on this, what else
are they willing to slip on?
I agree with you,
but let me devil's advocate a little
for Uncle Tim.
For our dear, sweet Uncle Tim.
He needs to keep
the revenue growing. I think it's safe
to say there's not that
many humans left to sell iPhones to
that want them.
Or can afford them at this point.
Or can afford them with the price,
with the quote, inflation, i.e. price gouging.
Is this just a function
of being a public company where
that chart has to go up and to the right
every quarter and
they know...
See, I have this thesis about
these big companies that they know in their heart of hearts
there is not going to be
the next big thing, and if so,
their only way to...
Even if there is, their only
way to handle it
is to basically tax it.
Where Apple is in a lot of
ways functioning as an IRS.
They are
taxing new businesses
and new innovation because
they own the iPhone and iOS and
related platforms.
I guess you could argue Facebook isn't doing this,
but it just seems like he's lighting
money on fire to give people legs,
which is a choice.
You know, the first time I think we've ever seen
this, Comcast NBC
is reporting too that their revenue is
down, that their subscribers
even on the Peacock streaming service are
up, but the Comcast revenue
is down. The
Comcast division took a quarter with a revenue
decline of 14%.
The reason why I bring that up
is because Comcast strikes
me a little bit of what Apple is turning into.
They've built their infrastructure,
they've got the wire to everybody's home,
but now they can't really
get to more
homes fast enough. There's just not enough new homes
coming online to keep number
going up. Over the years,
Comcast has layered
on all this stuff.
Bought up companies and just done
everything they can to make number
go up.
After a decade of loose money,
I know this is my new
soapbox, but seriously,
it set the tone for
everything. It matters. I don't think we've
realized how much it matters.
With loose money, they soaked up all this
money, they bought up all these companies, they formed
NBC Universal, Comcast,
Peacock, and even
after a decade of all that, they still can only
grow so much. Now
they have customers that are leaving
because better alternatives are eventually coming
along.
It's been like 10 years of this.
Apple, I think, is earlier in this cycle.
They're at the beginning of this Comcast
cycle. Yeah,
I mean, I think they are. I think also
maybe this is going to get me some heat
from my elephant-loving
friends.
You know, maybe companies can only get so big.
Right? And when you hit a certain
point of size and scale,
the cost of being that size
is just too
much. Maybe we just watched
a grand experiment in how big can
companies get. Because
unless money gets free again,
money was
better than free
because the interest rate was zero
and inflation was one,
two, four, and then seven, eight percent.
So for a while,
getting a loan was better
than free money. If you were a big company,
it was literally less than being taxed.
You were better off keeping your money in
Ireland or wherever the hell.
And they don't get taxed on the
money they borrow. So they have all
these assets, they have all this wealth that they can use
as collateral. And you write off the interest
as a tax deduction. So you
get the government coming and going.
You don't have to pay taxes on the loan money
you use, and you get a write-off on the interest
for that loan money if there is interest.
And even now, the interest rates are still super low.
I mean, it was such a great deal for them.
And I wonder if we didn't just watch—
because it's been since 2008.
So we've been watching this happen.
Perhaps we watched these tech
companies get as big as they're going to get. This was their
largest phase, and now it's just sort of more
leveled off growth from here. I'm sure they're probably going to still
go up because there's more humans all
the time. But I think the
years of just astronomical
growth after astronomical growth
could be coming to an end.
Unless printers go
again. I'm not sure it may happen.
Wow. We discussed this last week, and you were pretty—
I think eventually it will, yeah.
But I think you nailed it.
Apple also is trying to get a cut
of social media network
advertising. You know, when you buy a little bit
of advertising in the app
to, say, run an ad on Facebook,
Apple wants a cut of that.
It's incredible, because if you zoom out, what's happened here
is Apple turned
on the ATT, the application
cross-tracking. They set
up a block for that in a prompt, which knocked
about a billion dollars off of Facebook's revenue
and cut down on advertising
revenue for all these guys, then launched
their own ads. But just pause
there. Overnight, they flipped
the switch and nailed Facebook
for a billion dollars. That's
wild. When's the last time we heard something
like that? Even
you know, Pierpont Morgan
and the other railroad tycoons couldn't pull a move
that devastating to their competitor.
That's what I was thinking. It would have been
worldwide news.
It would have been a huge deal.
But it was Facebook, so
nobody cares. Well, they are evil.
But if they'd done something that cost the New York
Times a billion dollars,
I think people would have cared. But it's Facebook,
you know, it's just stupid meta.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
Go there to get Tailscale for free
on a personal account. Up to 20
devices. That's a big flat network.
Tailscale is a zero config
VPN. You get it set up in minutes on any
device, really. And it manages the firewall
rules, takes care of your nat
situation, even your double carrier grade
ultra-nats. I can attest to that.
Devices connect directly to each
other using WireGuard's noise protocol.
They build a backend that helps you connect
them all simply and quickly using whatever
single sign-on provider you like,
including two-factor authentication support.
And they build a flat mesh
network that's always on. And it's
smart about how it handles traffic too.
It doesn't tunnel everything to Tailscale.
It just tunnels the stuff that's on
that LAN. And it also
does clever things like subnet
routing so you can actually get access to
entire LAN and it just does it so transparently.
I love
Tailscale Send. I mention that all the time.
It's like AirDrop for all your machines.
But Tailscale SSH just
got better. So Tailscale SSH
allows you to establish SSH
connections between your devices in your
Tailscale network as authorized by
your Tailscale access
controls. Like I have a machine I share with Alex
and I have a machine I share with
a family member just
through the access controls on Tailscale.
You don't have to manage SSH keys anymore.
It authenticates your SSH connection
using WireGuard and
to make things even better
just a couple of days ago
they launched the SSH client via the
web. So you can log in to the
Tailscale console and right
there start up an SSH session
inside your web browser to one of your machines
in your Tailscale network.
So handy.
So powerful because for me
Tailscale is how I also support my friends
and my family. My kids all their machines
are on Tailscale. My dad he's on Tailscale.
They're all on my network and when they
need help this is going to be one of the tools
I have available to me. Or if I need to fix something for
JB it's just another tool available
to me just integrated with Tailscale
and you can get set up in just minutes.
So go try it for 20 devices for free
and support the show by going to
tailscale.com slash coder.
We just love it. Everyone at JB
uses it. Tailscale.com
slash coder.
So in the theme of
scary spooky tech trends
for some reason my old man
cackles have gotten all riled up
over the continued gamification
of software development and now
new research has provided evidence
for what they say is quote significant impact
of gamification on the behavior
of developers on large
collaborative programming software platforms
but they urge caution
too because the
gamification they say can quote
steer the behavior of software developers
in unexpected and
unwanted directions and
if you remove the gamification
productivity drops off an
effing cliff. People
just stop participating entirely.
So not only do you incentivize things you
didn't expect and sometimes
it's like a big boost in how many people
are contributing and sometimes it's like
people gaming the system but it
does seem like there's really something to this
and I mention this
because the GNOME project
just announced they're shutting down their mailing
lists and they're moving to
systems like GitHub and
Discourse and places where they can
implement gamification because they're seeing
good results in the GNOME community
from certain types of gamification.
Fedora has done something
similar. They have a badge for contributors
and like the ButterFS, I have the
ButterFS badge for example. I think it's the number one badge
they gave out. The ButterFS badge
if you're a Fedora user if you
help test the beta that had ButterFS
and this gamification's
becoming more and more of a thing and I wonder if you
think this is a dark trend or a
good trend? Probably
fine.
I sort of feel like anything that gets
people coding more regularly and improving their
craft is good.
I will tell you that since switching to
GitHub I am an addict for the
that little tile
mosaic tile thing on how many commits you do
in a day. Yeah.
Yeah. It works, right?
I mean anybody who's played like World of Warcraft
or an MMO knows if there's a bar
there's a certain personality type that will fill that
bar. Yep.
I would say
maybe it is like taking advantage
of certain dopamine triggers and
you know psychological responses
and certain personality types.
But I don't know. At least
I feel like I'm using it for good.
Although I should say GitHub is
definitely using me.
The study by the way was done by Cornell University.
And I think it's interesting that they
urge caution. I don't know.
I think you're right.
I think you're probably right. Getting more people to
do their craft
and get better at that and
participate in a community and learn those skills
is generally a good thing. More of that's
a good thing. So let's say it's a good trend
then. Yeah so addicting to people to positive
things is good. I got one that's
driving me absolutely crazy
and we're just going to have to put up
with it. And I'm really debating
on how much we even want to talk about it on the show.
It's relevant to developers
in the sense that
developers got to eat,
developers got to sell, and developers got to
promote. But
I think this trend
that's always been there since
the early days of Apple, people
used to attribute everything
Apple did, every arrogant move,
every petulant thing Apple did, they
attributed it directly to Jobs. Then Steve Jobs
died and Apple just got more
petulant.
And we're seeing that now with Elon.
Somebody's tweet gets
labeled as misinformation and you
see somebody posting, oh snap
dog, Elon just labeled this
post misinformation, shoot.
Elon makes
this decision. It's going to be Elon this,
Elon that. It becomes a cult of
personality, completely disregards
all of the engineers and developers and
people underneath all that that are
actually involved in the decision process.
And also I think where it matters
to our audience is if they are on social
media to help promote their app, their site, their service,
their business,
you're kind of watching this a little bit going
where the hell is this going?
And how is this going to affect me?
I don't know if you saw this and just picture
yourself as one of these engineers for a
moment. Because I'm
a Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde
about this. Part of me absolutely
loves the
savageness
of it and then part of me thinks like
God could you imagine being an engineer in this position.
So Twitter engineers were told to print
out their last 30 to 60 days
of code so they could show it to Elon
himself. Then they were told to wait, actually
just shred all that code you printed out and
upload it to this platform.
And Elon has brought in Tesla
engineers to do code
reviews of everyone's last 30 days
of the work. And then
you may end up having a little conversation
with Elon or a Tesla engineer
who's essentially a proxy.
In one way like I said it's
absolutely savage because you'll only
truly get answers to what's really going on if
you go all the way to the source code. At the
same time
Elon is setting these deadlines like if you don't
get it done you're fired. Another one is
they're trying to build Twitter blue so that way it's
a $20 a month subscription.
And Elon gave them like a deadline at
the end of November and if they don't get it done they're
fired. So it's really
just like we're reviewing your code we're going to sit down
at your desk with you we're going to go over it we're going to ask you
questions and oh by the way you also
need to get this new feature built
and if you don't get it done you're fired.
Part of me thinks God this is a brilliant strategy
by Elon because he's going to totally
clean house and bring the head count down which is job
number one. It sounds absolutely terrifying
as a human being to be in that
position as a staffer to have
the world's richest man or his proxy
sit down next to you and ask you well what the hell
are you doing here. First of all Steve Jobs
used to do this all the time.
All the time. Right.
Get it done or get out
was his his his line
right. I only want A players.
He did a speech when he was an
interview. In fact I have it on tape.
It was when he was at next talking about
why B players suck and they're not. I know
A players only want to play with A players
and if you make them play with B and C players they get pissed off
and they want to leave. As a management practice
no it's probably not great right.
But I wisely
thanks to the admonishment of an
older more beautiful haired
friend of mine named Chris Fisher
refrained from tweeting anything about
the Twitter acquisition
because remember Chris Fisher says tweeting
is bad. You'll notice
I very tweet very rarely.
You notice my tweets have gone down significantly
since that episode. I just
put that out there. It's
hard to overstate how
mismanaged Twitter really has
been for very long
and Twitter's headcount doesn't make a
ton of sense. I'm
sort of surprised at all this pearl clutching
about the people at Twitter
when if you look at Twitter
I mean it's a
shitty business.
It's not well run.
For instance someone I saw tweet from one of
the Twitter employees Elon made this change
and you know normally it would have
taken weeks of debate between the teams
and he's bragging about that as they're so
thoughtful. That's fucking terrible.
You should resign
in shame.
You're the tech business baby.
Roll roll roll.
I think it sucks that
they're in California and he can't just walk in
and fire them all like you could in Florida and give
them nothing because
I feel like a lot of that's what should just
happen and I know California has
stupid mandatory severance
but usually I'm more
sympathetic to the employees but
8000 people
and the best they could
come up with Twitter blue is that I can change the
color on the goddamn
highlight in the app and I can
briefly edit my tweet
or undo it to edit it and then they
edit a different kind of edit feature later.
That's
like I know
this is going to piss off a lot of the audience but like
maybe Twitter should have focused
on being a functional business
that is like a peer
to Facebook and you know it's direct
competitor and less about
you know wearing the hair shirt
and being the Virgin Mary on whatever
political ideology you may or may not have.
I think I agree I typically
I typically try to
be empathetic with the employee
in this situation but I think my inclination
would be to go full boss mode here because
he just made a huge acquisition
he massively overpaid
he's got to make this thing work.
He's also I think probably
smart enough to realize he's got a window
of time he's got about 90 days
you know like when a president comes into office
he's got 100 days he's got 90
days and then he's got other things
that need his focus like SpaceX
and Tesla. Additionally
he's in deep with military contracts
so he's got a lot of pressure
there to publicly get this
right. If you are involved at all
with that kind of stuff you see how
when things start looking bad
for you and your company the military gets less and less
interested in working with you they don't want that to
rub off on them. Well it's true if you have
financial strain you cannot
you generally will not pass a background
check and that goes for companies
and individuals so yes. The other reality
here is that a lot of the collateral
Elon put down to make this purchase came
from his Tesla stock and
if we go into a two year
recession I have to imagine
Tesla stock is going down. Tesla
just recently announced
they're lowering the price of
Teslas in China
because China's entering a recession
and so they're lowering the price of the car
so in China you can get a Tesla cheaper
now and it's probably going to happen here and if that
announcement happens you know their stock is going to
go down. That means the value of his collateral
will go down which means that he's
going to be on pressure to either add more collateral
or find another source of funding
all of which means act quick
act ruthlessly turn this thing around
figure out where the rot actually is
because I think all of us regardless
of your position would acknowledge there has
to be some rot inside Twitter.
It's also that but Chris let's just say like
JB and the Mad Botter
merged right
and you were the new boss and
you found out that a couple of my employees
were just going around
talking about what an asshole you are
and you know the Jupiter culture
the TMB culture is never going to be the same
because of Jupiter broadcasting
I mean I
feel like Elon's been incredibly patient
I would expect you to simply fire them or worse
make me fire them right. Well here's
my question for you is maybe this should be a little more standard
practice because what is actually the product he just
paid 44 billion dollars for if not the source code
and the staff right. So it's a great
time to figure out what the hell's in the code. Printing it out
is a little is a little silly printing it on
paper. That was that was corrected. Of
course he wants the code reviewed. In
fact if he didn't waive due diligence he
probably should have done that before.
I mean I don't I don't
know. It's just like
and I'm not saying that I
want Twitter to become a hellscape or anything like
that. It's the idea
that man buys
company. All these people now work
for this guy and they spend it seems
like a good part of their working day just
watching him spying on him bashing
the out of him.
Yeah let's reverse it. We merge
I'm in charge.
You better believe if somebody is running around
saying how much I suck and oh he did this
stupid jackass thing that I just fire them.
Did you see that screenshot
that Elon posted where they admitted
in their internal chats to
fluffing the numbers.
And they said literally we're
basically doing what Elon is accusing
us of. And I'm sure that they are
right. You know
what's funny on Twitter
I have noticed a lot less
engagement. Now granted I've been posting
less maybe that's the algorithm but
my whole feed
is just like Elon Hay and Magic the Gathering
30th anniversary of course.
Mine's Elon Hay and Star Trek.
Right. So we have our vices but
yeah. And I have
been I swear to God less
like you shall post like a coding tip
or something every couple days just
the amount of like political
vitriol like this isn't a club
I want to hang out at anymore. This is not
a bar I want to hang out at. Yeah. And ironically
Mike I my prediction ultimately
is is that the reign
of Elon is not significantly that
much different in terms of moderation and
censorship. Well he already said he's
forming a council which is exactly what they always
said. So it's like it just means
maybe the moderation and the censoring will take
longer as the council has to form
or whatever instead of just like some
Twitter employee internally deciding to flag
it. But it's still going to happen.
It's not. I have purchased
over the years not a ton but
it's not insignificant amount for the size
of my business Twitter ads. And
as much as I hate Facebook I would
take every dollar if I was to
do that kind of advertising again and put it
to Facebook. Yeah. The results
I did a AB the results were pretty
pretty clear.
I mean if he lays off
a good chunk of people and does a $20
a month Twitter blue that
you know to get verified that all of these media
personnel every all the you know Twitter
elites are going to sign they're all going to pay the 20 bucks
to keep their check mark. He may just
turn it around in a couple of days. He's
given a deadline in November 7th. I just looked it up
not the end of November. He gave the developers
November 7th to get that going. He gave
them Halloween with their kids. See
yeah it's so nice of him. You know I think
people who think Elon is an idiot and
you know everything that everything
that's happened to him has just been dumb luck and that he hasn't
built anything and he isn't any kind of engineer
as we've been debating. I think they're missing
the mark. I think what he is is erratic. He's
manic. He's manic and he probably doesn't
have you know a governor that says don't
post that like he just recently posted
something about Nancy Pelosi's husband
didn't even need to get in wait into that right.
Just don't even wait into that. Now that was
just stupid. Yeah that was it was dumb.
Yeah but he has been very
savvy in some ways like he's taking this private
so that way he can basically butcher the internals
of the company and not worry about the stock price and the
shareholders freaking out right. That's a pretty
clever move just because if you're really going to make brutal
changes that's how you do it. I don't know if
we can see are we going to watch this guy run three or four
companies. That's going to be interesting.
He's going to have to hire right. This
is this. He's not the first. This is not
like that unique of a situation.
He's going to be here for maybe a month
maybe two. He's going to do
the dirty work because he and then he'll
bring in a healer right.
A you know
agreeable CEO to the remaining
staff. That's going to be like we've been through
some hard times guys but I'm your guy
now and or gal.
And you know what we're going to build back better.
We're going to. It's going to be Joe Biden.
No I think you're right. I think it'll be a woman.
I think that's I think that'd be a smart move. I said
Joe Biden you said woman. That's that's not a great
clip. It just
can't be Sheryl Sandberg because
that idea wouldn't that be funny.
That'd be terrible. That'd be hilarious.
No one wins in that scenario.
I mean everybody's going to be looking for
a job soon if things keep going on. This is wild
so Metta's revenue
are down just a titch like 4 percent
just kind of a minor miss
with everything going on especially
the absolute decline
in the advertising business which is what hit them.
Wall Street absolutely freaked out about the decline
but then also when combined with the increased
expenses and investment in the metaverse
stuff Metta
was punished. Their stock looked like
like a crap cryptocurrency that
Elon had recently pumped. It was
a crash.
I mean we haven't seen anything like that in a while.
Jim Cramer your good buddy on CNBC
actually cried
on television because he's been pumping Metta
all year. Metta's going to the moon he's been saying
and he got called out on live TV
and he started shedding a tear.
Such an idiot.
No no. First of all be nice to my
good buddy Jim Cramer. We all know each other if
we've ever been to New York. We literally are
all cousins. Second
of all he's not the first person to get seduced
and screwed over by Mark Zuckerberg.
So you know
cue Edward Stafford.
We got to play this. I got to play this for you because it's just
so. Do it. Play. I knew you were
going to do this. It's so awkward.
Alright go ahead. Free cash flow
last year.
9.5 billion. Now less
than 1 billion.
I didn't say this about this.
I made a mistake here.
I was wrong.
I trusted this management team.
That was ill-advised.
Your brochure
is extraordinary.
And I apologize.
Okay.
What did you
get wrong? He just sits there and
thinks about it.
It's like Wonder Woman's got him in the
lasso and he's thinking on all his sins.
No.
That's a lot of money.
You imagine he and his charitable trust
he does this whole thing for charity. I'm pretty
sure he also
majorly screwed up here.
The company's Reality Labs division which houses
its VR headsets lost over 9
billion. I'm sorry. I'm sorry
Chris. We call that the we're on a drunk bender
burning hundred dollar bills y'all
division. So if you add it all up what they've
spent so far it's more money
than Apple spent to create the iPhone. But
if you even adjust it for inflation
Meta has spent more money
on Reality Labs than
the US government spent at least from what we know
on the atomic bomb even
adjusted for inflation. So you could win
a war build the most successful
product of all time and
still not have legs in the metaverse.
I actually think most people's
take on this is wrong because if
you think about it money
numbers have lost really all meaning.
Two hundred and fifty billion is last
year's five years twenty five billion.
Right. I mean the money really like we say
have been saying has been running loose.
And if you're a powerhouse of a company
that's just absolutely harvesting
money on ads by tracking people
and really nailing them with relevant
ads especially like Instagram. I hear that's
really successful on Facebook I imagine
you know from little dabbling I've
done on the advertiser side it seems extremely
accurate. They're harvesting so much
money. What do you want them
to do like put it on the bank and let it inflate
away and then draw attention to how much money they're
making as a as an advertiser
or why not
dump it into something that might be the next platform because
they also have the Comcast problem here.
They've saturated the market.
There's nowhere else to go. So they
either have to just build the next platform
or just wait for Facebook
to eventually fade and die which we all
know it's going to happen. It happens to all these platforms.
So they could you know maybe have
a shot if they could somehow build the next thing
and so why not take that money
why not take that 9 billion
and channel it into research and development.
Now it's a loss. Now it's a
write off. You're not drawing attention to how
much money you're setting on how much money your little tech
companies making and you're investing in the
next thing that might possibly work. I actually
don't think it's that crazy of a strategy.
The issue is investors
don't want to see crazy amounts of
R&D more so than any other tech company
and they don't want to see a decline in revenue
at the same time. If they were spending
1 billion
instead of 9 billion this last quarter if they'd
spent 1 billion in a quarter
I don't think this would be a headline. It wouldn't be a story.
If they'd spent what
Microsoft spends this wouldn't be a story.
But because they spent what Microsoft and Apple
and Google spend combined
it's quite the story.
But then again
it's all relative to how much damn money you got.
That's it.
And if you're making a lot of money and money's been
loose it's all relative.
Yeah...
I mean you're right
but it's a lot of
money no matter how you slice it. But what's he gonna
do? He could turn around and spend
that 9 billion on what? Making Facebook
better? It's a mature
product. I don't really
know what else they could get into that would be successful.
You see them buy these other things and it just sort of
levels off. Okay so isn't this the Microsoft
problem though? Microsoft
circa 1999
I guess. You have
dominance in one place. You are
extremely mature, extremely successful
product slash business.
And okay so then you get Office
right? This is what they did. They island
hopped into different businesses and
then eventually that was a
problem because of
antitrust. I think that's kind of why
Microsoft's pivot into open source
and really building cross platform development
tools has been so surprising because very
rarely do large companies
make a successful pivot like that. Well I think
it's just it's hard to be good at multiple things.
And I
don't know. Also
Facebook's brand has really taken
a beating right?
I mean even my aunties who love
Facebook because God forbid
they miss a picture of their great nephew.
Kind of
hate it now. Mostly because
it disallows them to fight about
their incredibly strange political
ideas.
One of them is Karl Marx.
One of them is Mussolini.
So that's where I that's where I live.
I hate
Facebook because I can't look for a goddamn
bicycle pump without being haunted for three
months. Yeah then once you get the pump you're still
getting ads for pumps for everything. It's like well I already bought it.
I bought the pump three months. We talked about this on the
air. I bought it through. I'm still getting the ads.
It's like guys I bought a pump.
I'm cool. I buy one car mount once.
Years of car mount ads.
Ask not what your podcast
can boost for you
but what you can boost for your
podcast. We got
a boost from Thought Criminal. Love
that name. Nineteen hundred sats.
Pew pew pew. Headline from the
Beacon. Florida man suspended after
going Newland on a striking mascot.
Suggest better breeding in order.
Takes new bride. I think that's
him congratulating you for the marriage.
The wedding. Thank you I think.
I think. Yeah I love it though.
Yeah you know the mascot
has been pretty active the last couple days on Twitter.
Going after
people setting the record straight. I don't know
if you've noticed that. I know. He's
been our personal Elon. Really has been.
I'm sure he'd love that. I'm sure.
Purple Dog need to set their username
boosted with six thousand sats.
Boost! I've done estimates
to come up with a quote. And then that quote
has been ten to twenty percent padded to
account for unknowns. But then a
PM comes and plugs those estimates into
Microsoft Project without the padding
and tells the client we'll be finished
on this exact date.
Doesn't even account for
annual leave.
Bonus points if there's liquidated damages
for being late. Also been
brought into a project where the estimates for a
web app were done by a developer who had never made
a web app. I don't work there anymore.
I agree.
You know I gotta figure out a way
to work in days off.
I've gotta do it. Cause I'm like
on a decade of no days off.
So I gotta figure it out. I think
what I need is a backup crew.
You know like what is it called when you're in
theater and you have like a person
like an understudy. Yeah we need understudies
dude. You know
you just call up the understudy like hey man it's Halloween today
I need you to fill in. Can you imagine?
I think it'd be awesome.
You know what the problem is though the understudies would start
wanting to get jealous. Have you never seen Phantom
of the Opera? We'll have a coup.
Yeah. People would like them more
because they wouldn't be so grumpy. You know
they'd think everything's great cause they'd probably be younger I'm assuming.
Cause I couldn't have an older understudy.
I hated everything back in 2012. That's true.
In fact I've mellowed out a lot.
But the new ones they love everything.
Anything that's new they love it.
I love when I talk to someone super new to
dev and they're like hey man I can just
generate this on the server. I'm like
you've discovered ERB or Jinja
or any of the other technologies.
All these things you're like oh that'll ultimately burn you.
But they're still new to it.
Every time someone says hey did you not see
this thing? It's great. It's called Xamarin Forms.
Be honest with me.
Could you have an understudy that's older
than you?
That's weird right?
I think I'd prefer it.
Really? I think that sets up like a
mentor. So you think you have this
reverse personal relationship.
I don't like it. Like a couple years ago
I got pulled over by a cop. I don't
actually remember why. I don't think it was that big of a deal but he was mad.
Chris was shooting out the window.
He was just like f***ing Mac 10.
And I was drinking. Running on Macbook Air.
I would guess he was like 22
23 years old. Oh no.
Almost half my age and it felt so
weird to get talked down to by somebody
half my age. I was like oh this is weird.
You think alright son. Shut up.
Right?
No. Marcel boosts in
with some Enterprise SATs 1701.
I think the problem is a lot of these
regulations around what's an engineer are just really
outdated. Civil engineering boo-boos
have been the cause for hundreds of lives.
Hopefully JavaScript is never put in
charge of something with that kind of power.
I have some terrible news for him but keep going.
I know. I know.
And the worst part is they're front ends to access
databases. Is complaining about
a stoplight really a
form of practicing engineering?
If you claim that a bit of back of the napkin
math is engineering then doesn't that
sort of invalidate the entire profession?
That is a huge point. Yeah.
Great point.
I'm going to read it again. If you claim that
a bit of back of napkin math is
essentially engineering doesn't that invalidate
the profession? Napkin math
by amateurs is engineering
so engineering is napkin math
by amateurs.
Congrats on the wedding by the way.
Thank you. So wow Marcel
we totally
missed this. You nailed this correct.
The whole engineering no engineering
whatever licensing is irrelevant to the case
that came up. The gentleman who
found that the stoplights were defective in what was it
Oregon? Yeah.
Yeah. He was just doing arithmetic.
He has math. Not even like
fancy. It was freaking arithmetic.
You know let's be honest it probably started like he noticed
the timing of the lights was probably off
and it probably just went from there. Right. He probably had
like an intuitive feeling and then was like yeah
let me time this. I want to see.
That's a huge point. And I can give
a real example of this. I am not a CPA nor
am I an accredited accountant of any kind.
My friend owns a bar. He
once asked me to help him figure out the profit
margin. There was some deal with a local
brewery on a keg of beer. These are the types
of problems I face when I go out to lunch by
the way. Sure. And naturally
and you know what was I
illegally operating as a CPA telling him the margins
were only like 15 percent and they were screwing
him because they lowered they lowered
the price by 10 percent
but they cut the size of the keg by
25. You just have good
lobes for business. I do have
the lobes. Well my sales
last quarter would suggest they don't but
I don't
know if that's your fault though. That might be you know
when they fire people at Twitter I'm just going to get a job at Twitter.
That's my plan. There you go. All
right. We're going to round it out now
with our last two boosts. Neve
boosted in B O O S T
with a row of ducks.
So
my dedicated EMAX machine is actually
my faithful old System
76 Lamer Pro the Lamer
it boots Gentoo.
Oh my God. And then hooks
EMAX in right into a
I guess rat poison
window manager session. Incredible.
I don't really code with EMAX
but I almost exclusively use org
mode for my writing in D&D campaigns
work on my own website powered by Hugo.
Hey on it. And I write notes.
This is like nerd bingo. Yeah it is really
a ding ding ding. Yeah. And he
writes notes and documentation as well
as writes ansible deployment scripts.
You do bingo. Of course you do.
A.K.A.
automating Gentoo installations naturally
because why not. I mean you got it right.
He says for the record Neve
says he doesn't work in tech works in
logistics. I had no idea after
that. I would after that description I
would have absolutely assumed
the the opposite. So thanks for the clarification.
And our last boosts
no almost last boost
from
a Hanukkah coming in hot with the
news just said thanks for the awesome coin
summary with six thousand sats.
You're welcome. I hate to see
the dog going getting pumped by Elon but
it is what it is. And then
we got ourselves a quick little
boost from Mr. Quackers who just
wanted to call him quack relations you Mike.
I think that's a congrats. I'll take it.
It's a treasure.
You
got you got you got people out there
that wanted to send you some good wishes in
their own way. Oh and actually the new wife
sent me a message. Oh yeah.
I sort of I would say
forced but I got her an
iPhone when we first got together.
Was she on Android previous. Oh she's real
mad about it. Oh yeah. Oh really been a rough
transition. She wants to know what the best Android
phone is and it looks like
yeah.
Yeah. Oh really
going back a failed transition
a failed transition.
Are you looking at the Paisel seven perhaps.
She likes the Samsung.
The problem is she had one of those crazy
galaxy
twos. So it's been a while.
What's the what's the primary
complaint with the iPhone quote. I hate
everything about it.
She likes I message which I thought was super
interesting. She really likes I message.
She doesn't like safari.
She doesn't like that it doesn't tie into her Google
stuff as well as
as the Android did. She's got to go all in on the
I cloud for that to really. Yeah but she basically
lives in Google Google Docs
and Gmail. Right. Yeah that's becoming really
common. Yeah. Like her whole for
her for her work it's it's
just like passing paper around. So
then you know I try to
get her air mail the third party
iOS app I use but I
myself have trouble with it. It's
handling Google Docs on iOS
is kind of it's
just rough. Yeah that whole Google
ecosystem is just slightly better.
It is better. I think it is somewhat
better. So I'm thinking of I try
to talk her into the pixel though I tell you what
the Samsung has their crap on it. Why the
pixel. It's the same old same old
story. Also the pixel seven
very well reviewed. You should show her
like the MKB HD review or something. People
are liking it. Well she's asking about
folding ones. Oh interesting
interesting. Aren't they super fragile though.
This is something for the audience
get back to us if you have a folding Samsung
get back because you know I might try one myself.
I would be curious as well. I'd really love to know people's
experience and yours or hers if
she gets one. Well you know how I responded to this complaint
right. I bought her the
AirPods Max. There you go.
They will work with an Android. It just takes
a little bit more work. I didn't tell her that
just a little bit. Yeah
if you'd like to send a boost into the show go to new podcast
apps dot com and upgrade to
a podcasting 2.0 app
and send a boost into the show. Also thank you to
our members for investing in the ongoing production.
We have an email in the inbox this week
from a company that wants us to
secretly work with them to basically
do a link share where they'll send us a bunch
of fake downloads if
we pay them. So usually we
get pitched and they want to pay us. But this
week we got pitched on paying them
to jack up our downloads
I guess and then we could turn around and
lie to sponsors.
I guess. I mean the whole
thing is so funny. Is there a word for that? Frowd
Frowd something
Frowd. Frowd
Frowdlient or something. Yeah
well I didn't like it. Ultimately it would
fail because
people have to use the promo codes and go to your
URLs and actually sign up. Yeah
our sponsors it's not clicks right. You got to buy something.
Yeah you actually got to use it.
You got to sign up and try it out
and so if you just send them a bunch of traffic
OK that's that might count for something
but it's not what's going to matter at the end of the day.
So it only works for so long but I guess if you're
doing that kind of stuff you know you're just
running and gunning for money. Maybe you don't care. That's why I
really appreciate our members. You can sign up at
CoderQA.co to support the show and get an ad
free version or jupyter.party for
the whole network of shows. Get all the special
features like the post shows, the pre shows, the live
streams and more that's coming at jupyter.party
Anywhere
you want to send the good people this week Mr. Dominic.
Go to dominicm.com
and follow me on the
Musk platform at Dominic
that's D-O-M-I-C-C-O
No there's another
letter in there. Whatever you'll figure it out.
You did it. You just called
it. We're all going to do it. It's just going to be a phase
of life. It is the winter of Elon
I guess. Now links to what we talked about
today coder.show slash four nine zero.
What are your trends you see coming up good
and bad for the next couple of years?
Go to coder.show slash contact
and let us know or send a boost
into the show. Over on our website you'll find our
RSS feed as well so you can subscribe and get
the show when you want it or you can join us
live at jupyter.two typically 9 a.m.
pacific noon eastern
unless I get stuck out in the woods.
Well then you just have to tune into our Matrix
channel coder.show slash Matrix.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the
Coder Radio program of a spooky
Halloween and we'll see you next week.