This is Koda Radio, episode 461 for April 11th, 2022.
Hello good looking and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
I'm sitting here in a toasty, rawly North Carolina.
My name is Chris and joining us from a swampy Florida, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello, Chris.
Hello, sir.
Hello.
And we should say welcome back to the show, Mr. Payne.
Hello, Wes.
Oh, hey, boys.
If I only knew the words to welcome back Cotter.
We're glad to have you here, Wes, and it worked out perfect too, because we were all gathered
together here in Alex's bed and breakfast, also known as house, and you were floating
through and I said, come on, sit down, let's do a show.
Let's do a little Cotter, because the audience has been wanting to hear from you.
And it's been too long since I got to talk to Mike.
Yeah.
So we're gathered here together today.
Although it looks like I was looking over the Twitter, as you know, I stalk Mike.
And it looks like you were having some car troubles this week.
Ah, yes.
Once again, technology destroys a perfectly good mechanical device.
Apparently the computer in my car has decided that there shall be no fuel injected into
my engine.
Oh, no.
And it decided this while I was in the car.
Oh, yes.
So that was a double toe job.
And I'm still waiting to double toe job.
Now that sounds like we're going to explicit rating.
And yes, I will.
I will update the audience whenever GM decides to do something about it.
Man, oh, man, that sucks.
That's just one of those wrenches in your life you never expect.
And it's just not easy to deal with.
You know, Optimus Gray in the chat room points out, this might be one of the few times we
do this here Koder radio program when we're in the same time zone.
That's weird.
And you know, you have Koder is like an after lunch thing for you.
Yeah.
Right.
And for me, it's like a pre-lunch thing.
I'm in a totally different time space than you normally.
So maybe this episode is going to be a little weird.
I don't know.
Or you'll be in more in sync than ever.
Maybe.
Well, we're going to find out.
We're going to find out.
Either way, I think everybody is taking a breath of fresh air, a sigh of relief.
Elon's not going to be on the board.
I know you're looking forward to it, Mike.
I really was, actually.
Yeah, actually, I agree.
I was so down for that.
Yeah.
Today, they announced, oh, he's not going to be on the board as we record today.
And there's all kinds of theories this morning as to why.
Do you guys have personal pet theories as to why Elon decided not to go on the board
of Twitter?
Tesla AI told him not to.
It steered him right away from the board meeting.
I like Wes's better.
Mine is dumb.
I think he just realized the SEC was probably not going to put up with his shenanigans forever.
I could see that.
Because he screwed up the filing, too, right?
I think, too, they had a little talking.
Because if you read through this really strange announcement, there's two things that stick
out.
So weird.
First of all, they mentioned a background check.
Why do you even say that?
And then the other thing they mention in here is that he has a fiduciary responsibility
to limit what he says, essentially, is what they say about the company.
You have to kind of agree to only talk about certain things when you're a member of the
board.
It limits what you can say about Twitter.
And I think that was it.
I think he's like, no way.
I wonder why he hasn't done this before.
Why don't Bezos and Musk and Buffet, why don't they buy all these companies up?
You know what?
Just-
I guess Bezos does it sometimes, right?
Washington Post at least.
True.
Monsters.
That's a good point.
All right.
Well, let's move on.
Boostergram.
Boostergram came in from Freak three days ago, 6,000 sats, too.
So he just recently switched all over from Android to iOS.
Rest in peace, Freak.
And he says the one thing that's driving him crazy is he wants to slap his iDevice when
it autocorrects the last word after he presses send.
Android never did that, he said.
That is probably the most annoying thing about iOS.
I can't tell you how many times the F word has been replaced with duck after I hit the
send button.
Like, what the duck, you know?
I did not realize this was the thing.
Now it's been, I don't know, six years since I regularly had an iPhone, but is that a new
development?
No, it's been-
I mean, they've been trying to machine learn how to autocorrect for a while, so maybe it's
gotten worse.
I don't know.
But yeah, it's been like that for a bit.
Yeah.
Yeah, that does stink.
You poor devils.
I know.
I don't know how we do it.
I don't.
We got another boost from Cospeland.
He says, okay, guys, what are your thoughts on iCloud versus NextCloud?
What would be the point?
And thanks for the show.
It feels like two separate solutions.
I don't know, you'd use NextCloud if you don't want to be on somebody else's cloud.
That's it.
I can also see maybe you want, you know, you use bits and pieces, like you might need iCloud
for some of the iOS specific backup kind of things, right?
But you don't have to do it for everything.
You could self host some of the pieces you wanted in your NextCloud.
I can see the appeal, like maybe Mike would want to set one up for like his team at some
point.
I don't know.
But most people are not using iCloud for the same stuff.
Yeah, I don't see iCloud in like a work environment.
I know Apple is supposedly coming out with something like that, some kind of like small
business program.
But I don't know.
When I think iCloud, I still have scars from core data iCloud having to implement it and
just the massive sync bugs.
We had several people that boosted in, boost, asking if they could boost us from the member
feed, which we have not set up.
It's amazing they'd like to do that, but not right now.
But it has us talking internally about how we could do that.
We all shows feed did just get the possibility to boost.
I just added that before we left.
Nicely done, sir.
Pure, pure, pure.
All right.
So it looks like something's going on with tea, which is a package manager that is an
alternative to brew.
Harold wrote in and I said, I thought maybe you guys would want to take a closer look
at this.
Did you notice that they pitched themselves as brew two for web three brew two for, yeah,
web.
Sorry.
Oh, little nauseous.
So there's something blockchain.
I'm just curious, did we ever get to the bottom of what is blockchain about this new package
manager?
You know, I haven't had a chance to actually try tea.
I'm not sure.
Let's find out though.
I'm looking at it and I don't get it.
I don't, I don't get it.
How much money did they raise exactly?
Oh yeah.
Did they raise money?
They raised money.
This is not, so I think this is my mistake.
I thought this was just like a, you know, a successor from brew, like by the creator
of well brew.
It also seems to have like slightly wider ambitions, maybe wherever you develop, wherever
your CICD runs, however you deploy your app, tea is there, which is, you know, with their
$8 million.
Oh.
So this is, this is not, this is a somewhat commercial, which is this my open core dreams
coming true?
Maybe, but now with a web three name.
Of course.
Well, you have to get the VC to open your email somehow.
Hmm.
So this is probably going to warrant further investigation.
Yeah.
$8 million.
Look at this.
To create a new open source software on the blockchain.
Yeah.
It's like, you know, for a while we were seeing everybody bacon machine learning and AI into
their product description.
And it's like blockchain was a fad before that and then AI took over and now blockchain's
back again.
Blockchain's back baby.
And you know, I gotta say just for the record, like I don't think there's a lot of strong
use cases for blockchain outside a distributed ledger for a currency.
Like it's really good at that.
But a lot of times when you see what they're using a blockchain for you go, well that could
just also be a database.
Hmm.
Yeah.
And it's like they're using blockchain because it's like cool and stuff, but you know, blockchains
are in order to be secure, they're generally not very fast and if they're not very fast
and they don't seem to scale what like would you would in theory want for something like
a package manager?
Yeah.
You know, they mentioned being decentralized, but exactly how?
Hmm.
Yeah.
Don't you want your package manager to in fact be centralized somewhat so that you can
trust?
I think so.
I mean, I think maybe you want both, but.
Well, so we've just reinvented PPAs.
Congratulations.
A couple of weeks ago we read an email from listener Brandon who has a big old raspberry
pie cluster going on.
Hooey.
So he's got three pies and a single pie four and all three are powered with power over
Ethernet, which is awesome.
So he's got a little switch to do that.
They run Ubuntu with Ubuntu's Kubernetes K3 solution.
He's got terabyte hard drives connected to them and then he makes all of the K pods available
via NFS.
This is so cool.
He said, I had a job requirement for me to learn Kubernetes very quickly in order to
lead a team building and deploy and that was deploying the K workload.
So he sets up this big old cluster here.
He's like, it's not really a big deal, but you know, it's kind of a fun project and if
any listeners have a few raspberry pies laying around, it's definitely worth a go.
Also it's been astounding to watch the show's 180 on blockchain and web 3 tech.
I left the initial episode from last year feeling pretty unhappy about the general sentiment
on the show, so it's been good to see a more nuanced take on the tech.
The state of the tech in the politics is intersecting and it's actually been pretty piss poor lately.
So it's nice to see some people with big ideas trying to create a better future, regardless
of how it goes or if it's likely planned to go.
Anyways, thanks for the show, Brandon.
Well, there you go.
We got a lot of shit for talking about blockchain stuff.
We got a lot of shit for that.
We had some good positive feedback too.
You know, I also like in that feedback that you hear a lot kind of just the blasé statement
that yeah, raspberry pies are great to learn on and all this, but it's just neat to see
you really can use like some just cheapo devices you have at home to set up a cluster that
actually helps you in a work environment.
Yeah, it's not exactly the same, but you learn a lot of really useful skills.
You can put SUSE on there.
You can put open SUSE on there.
Or NixOS maybe.
Yeah.
Or Ubuntu.
All right, last email that comes in.
Now, here's the thing.
This is a thing we're gonna have to deal with as a show, but we're gonna get through this
together, okay?
We're gonna get through this together.
Five is leading a manhunt.
So at the meetup this week, Mike was unable to attend, and there began a contingent that
broke off that sort of has created this conspiracy bacon that's completely ridiculous that Mike
and I are the same person, and Mike is just a voice that I'm doing.
So I mean, that's absolutely crazy, but Five writes in.
He says, you know, I flew all the way from Minneapolis to talk to Mike about the only
real macOS that I would ever think of compiling Objective-C on, Next Step.
That's a bold, bold statement, sir.
Bold.
But he said, you know what, Chris got to find out I'm not a jerk in real life, just a digital
space.
Also, he pointed out that the super spreader tent was great, but wasn't the same without
our famous Floridian.
So one of the things Alex did is he brought a tent where we put like name tags and a book.
Where is that damn book?
That is a very good question.
We had over a hundred people, around a hundred people show up.
And a good turnout of Coder fans, that's for sure.
Definitely.
I think there's plotting to go down to Florida now.
I mean, I didn't tell them to go for it, but like I said, this group just sort of broke
off on their own.
We tried to control them.
Well, you know, you can always like hire an actor when you're doing this voice, right?
So that's true.
I think it worked out for the best though, because, you know, I was a little, I was like
thinking, do I need to like wear a mask?
Like how do I make sure that we don't meet at this meetup because I don't want to mess
with the show.
And so we've punted that problem one more time.
You know, I was going to go.
I was going to come dressed in a robe, but with just, you know, a space ball style Vader
helmet on.
Yeah.
That's a good idea.
It's funny you say that.
A Vader helmet was recommended to me by someone else, but I was worried about it getting real
hot in that Vader helmet.
You know, and you got to really commit to that.
Yeah.
I'm in Florida.
We define hot slightly differently.
True.
It's a little sticky already.
It won't change anything.
You know, I got an email mentioning next steps, so, you know, it's a little sticky already.
Right.
It's already a little sticky.
We had, of course, some local folks show up.
We had from Virginia.
We had from Pennsylvania, New York, DC, Florida, Canada.
People came from all around.
It was really great.
I think we're going to do it again.
Here's an obvious statement in retrospect.
There's actually a lot of tech business in Raleigh.
Oh yeah, dude.
Oh yeah.
I didn't realize it.
I knew Red Hat was here.
I'm kind of a sleeper, you know, you don't hear about it all the way out on the West
Coast necessarily.
You northern westerners, whatever you are, you got to come down Dixie.
We're blinded by San Francisco and the glittering lights of New York City.
And Seattle.
Is Seattle closer to you?
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
We have to stare at the Amazon and Microsoft folks all the time.
Oh.
Speaking of Darth Vader.
Darth Balmer.
And I guess Apple's opening up an office here now.
So there's going to be an Apple Raleigh office.
And then because we're near Virginia, we got, you know.
The government crowd.
We got some government people coming down too.
But that's great.
We accept all types.
So I think we're going to do it again.
I think I don't know when, but we'll do it again at some point in the future.
So if you didn't make it out, don't worry.
We'll do it again.
You're just going to roll the dice one more time, Mike's got another chance to see your
smiling face.
To redeem myself and handout, I am ordering DVDs of Snow Leopard for everybody.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you go there to support the
show.
Linode is fast and reliable cloud hosting.
You got to try it for your next project, for the next thing you deploy.
It's what I use for everything I've built in the last two and a half years.
Especially now that Linode has been rolling out these MVME PCI drives.
I didn't realize it, but like one of my boxes, I can just click a button and upgrade it.
It kind of depends on my location.
And another one of my boxes I've already upgraded.
I love it when things get faster.
I've recently been using Linode's tools to help troubleshoot and manage our super in
demand matrix server for our community right now.
And it's so, so slick to have these dashboards they give you.
They're not like overly complicated and they have really sensible thresholds you can set
for alerting.
So I know when something's going on.
And you know, for this trip, I went in there and I just boosted that system up.
I made it a monster.
I have a 48 core Linode box right now.
And if you're a performance hound, you're going to love Linode.
But if you need it for something simple, like a portfolio, maybe a simple GitLab, I don't
know, maybe a photo gallery, they have like $5 Linodes that are rock solid and still come
with the same great support that the 48 core rigs have.
That's what Linode is known for is fantastic support, fantastic performance, and really
sticking to the core product and just making it better and better and better.
And with 11 data centers around the world, you're going to find something near you or
your customers.
And since they've been doing this for 19 years, I can guarantee you they're just really in
a groove.
They're not trying these crazy VC backed ideas and things like that.
They're iterating on a product that works and has millions of customers around the world.
And they have great features like built in cloud firewall.
Their object storage is super useful.
They have VLAN support.
Of course, they have advanced DNS support, really powerful Kubernetes and Terraform support,
super fast networking, bare metal servers, if that's the way you want to go, and a new
database as a service, I guess.
That seems like it has a lot of potential.
And of course, they wrap it all up with an easy to use powerful cloud dashboard.
Man, there's so many reasons we use Linode, but I think you'll find something that fits
for you.
You'll see why.
And with pricing 30 to 50% cheaper, I think you're going to be happy to stick around.
So go get that $100 and try it out.
See what we've been talking about.
See why we stuck with it for so long, and we love promoting them on our shows, linode.com
slash coder.
Go get that $100 and enjoy it and let us know what you think, linode.com slash coder.
So we were just kind of casually talking about the warp terminal a few episodes ago.
And we're seeing, I think, a wave of quote unquote developer focused tools get a ton
of funding and warp has raised $23 million.
He's up.
Million.
Did you see this coming?
I mean, $23 million for a terminal?
Yeah, kind of, right?
I knew it was going to be a lot.
If you look at the way they've been recruiting, and Zach Lloyd, kind of his background, I
think he was like head of development or head of product at Google Drive.
Or I'm sorry, Google Docs, although isn't that Google Drive now?
I have no idea.
Yeah, nobody does.
Well, I'm on the Google work plan, and they just keep renaming stuff on me just to screw
with me, I think.
Hey, would you like them to include a little chat in there, too?
That would be great.
A separate new one.
Yeah.
That doesn't connect.
No, I don't need another chat.
God damn it.
G chat was fine.
It really was.
It was totally fine.
It was nice.
Like, oh, Slack is doing the same stuff, by the way.
Let's add every feature we can think of, slow the thing down to the point where you get
notifications on all your devices because we can't synchronize anymore.
What were we talking about?
Sorry.
Well, we were talking a little bit about Zach Lloyd.
You know, he's been grinding away at stuff like this for 20 years, so maybe it's kind
of nice that he finally got a big break.
I mean, I don't know how he's done previous to this, but...
Very well.
He was a monkey-muck at Google.
Oh, yeah.
Fair enough.
It's interesting because they've been doing a lot of the rounds, Warp in particular.
They keep suggesting that one day the terminal could be open sourced, Warp Terminal.
And I've been using it day to day, and I've been getting the updates.
It definitely looks like they're...I'm sure they would phrase it differently, but they're
looking to go towards a cloud-first development environment.
I would not be shocked if there was just a terminal.warp.com, enter your username, and
that's your terminal.
Mm-hmm.
Because the whole thing is...it is Rust native.
Is it Rust or Go?
I think it's Rust, right?
Yeah, I believe it is Rust.
It is Rust.
But it's also partially built using stuff from Alacrity, which is interesting.
Their kind of value add is, one, they treat the terminal, the graphics, a little differently,
so you can do kind of the GUI copy-paste stuff easier than you might in, let's say, Mac
Terminal or G Terminal.
But they're pushing pretty aggressively on this.
You can synchronize your SSH session with a homie, and that's how you can do onboarding
for people, right?
Setting up tool chain with them.
A lot of cloud-first kind of...your settings can live in the cloud.
For instance, you have to log in with GitHub, which I know, when this TechCrunch article
came out, kind of the first time they've gotten a real lot of attention, the good old boys
at Hacker News were not super thrilled to get the login prompt, which I completely understand.
Login to my terminal?
Yeah, you know, legit, it's the GitHub...it's literally a GitHub OAuth prompt.
I don't like that either.
So for my freedom-loving hippies, except you have to be on Mac because for some reason
everybody's doing this all on Mac first, there's FIG, fig.io.
And all FIG is, is context-aware auto-completion of your particular tooling.
Now they have some they support like NPM, Kubernetes, stuff like that, but I can tell
you that I cannot spell the minute I type in NPM because I hate it.
And I am actually going to try this on...well, it works with HyperTerminal, the Mac Terminal,
obviously, Alacrity, and a few others.
Take a look.
This is one...theoretically this works on Linux if you're using Alacrity.
I wouldn't be shocked if there's a Google Terminal available.
They also have a way to just add it directly into ZShell, Phish, or Bash if you don't like
have one of the fancy pants terminals that they support.
Additionally, it works in the VS Code terminal and the JetBrains terminals if you live in
those IDEs.
Wow.
That's really cool.
So this is like...so it's fig.io.
I'm kind of impressed.
Mike seems to know more.
I've actually been using this a little bit at work in my day-to-day playing with it,
but I haven't gone that deep.
I didn't realize they had fancy terminal integration.
I've just been using it like a plain old regular person in iTerm.
Oh, so Super Bowl, how are you finding it?
I like it a lot.
I haven't written any of my own completions or gone super deep into it, but for just running
around in the terminal, doing regular Git operations, that kind of stuff, yeah, it's
pretty handy.
And it's not...I have not found it intrusive at all.
There's never been any of those times I wanted it to just disappear.
It's just kind of an optional extra.
All right.
That's a nice one.
And is it open source?
Is it commercial?
It's MIT licensed, it looks like.
Yeah, but there are some...there is like some investment, I believe that Y Combinator backed
it.
I think they have $2.4 million in funding, maybe.
There you go.
Oh, I'm the one who wrote the note.
That's why.
I don't even remember.
Yeah.
But so this is kind of...we've been talking about these tooling things, and I've been
like bitching that people are mean to me because I want to do something open core.
And I feel like somehow, under the radar, a bunch of people have gotten together and
like, we're going to do terminal stuff, and we're going to basically make it open core.
And are they just not saying open core?
No, they're just not using the word, right?
They're saying free for individuals, which is the same damn thing.
Interesting.
Also, it's kind of nice to see stuff focused on the terminal, like IDEs have been such
a dominant...which is fine, but...
Text editors.
Mm-hmm.
You know?
And I think they both kind of give you access to different things.
IDEs, you get this big smorgasbord of all kinds of options, and it really does like
the epitome of a big gooey app.
But there are times where the terminal style of workflow is better.
So if you can get some of the kind of like static analysis, semantic stuff, aware of
your environment stuff you've come to expect from an IDE in the terminal, heck yes.
Win-win.
Plus, there's devs that grew up with like fancy IDEs that, you know, they might kind
of...a terminal might seem old if we don't sort of backport some of that stuff over there.
Yes.
That's a good point.
It's definitely the season for developer tooling to make money.
March 31, Docker announced they raised a Series C of $105 million.
And when you go through it, of course, it's bang capital ventures.
Of course.
They don't even really get very specific why they did it.
Their whole reasoning seems to be, well, we think the developer ecosystem is going to
continue to grow like crazy.
We expect that this particular market, the Docker address is going to forex over the
next year.
And so we're going to put money into Docker, even though they don't seem to really have
a solid plan, or we're not really sure how these returns are going to work.
But this market's growing.
$105 million is nothing to sneeze at.
Not at all.
I'll jump the gun on you, but you know what I've been using in production, and I didn't
even know they were sponsoring the show until last week?
Tailscale.
That's right.
Tailscale is awesome, isn't it?
It's beautiful.
You can have a bunch of very precariously tied to something Raspberry Pis that have
a 5G connection, and you can make sure they're still alive.
Yeah.
And they're all in that flat network.
That's right.
I mean, yeah, no doubt about it.
Right now, the machine I'm sitting at is connected back to the studio with Tailscale.
That's so freaking great.
But this is a real, this is a genuine endorsement right there.
In fact, why don't we talk about Tailscale?
Tailscale.com slash coder.
Oh, let's go outside and enjoy the day in the sun.
Come on, doggy.
I got Archie with me here, and we're in Raleigh, North Carolina, and I'm preparing the show
out here in the sunshine.
How nice is that?
And I'm using Tailscale to do it.
I thought, what a great opportunity to talk about how useful Tailscale is.
It's super quick to get started.
Just a couple of minutes, you'll install it on any OS.
I have it on my mobile devices.
I have it on my Linux boxes, ARM and x86.
I have it on my VPS servers.
And really before the trip, one of the things I did to prepare was I got Tailscale set up
on the last couple of devices that I didn't have it on.
Now I'm going to sit out here in the sunshine, and thanks to Tailscale, I'm going to enjoy
some vitamin D while I prepare the show.
So this is a little bit of out of time ad read, I suppose, but it just seemed like what
a great opportunity to really demonstrate the power of Tailscale.
Because say I need to get to the booths or I need to get to our notes system, you need
the kind of like web dashboards.
You know what I'm talking about.
You got tons of these things behind firewalls, and I got some apps on Linode.
I got some apps on my LAN.
I got some apps on a VM sitting on my box back at the studio.
Tailscale brings it all together in one flat VPN, and they use WireGuard's noise protocol
to make sure it's super secure.
And they support any single sign on system you might already have, which means if you
want to use two factor, that's going to work too.
And personally, I use it to help with my friends and family.
Like for example, I have it on my son's computer.
If he has any problems while I'm out here, I just SSH into his machine and take care
of it because all of my systems have a static IP address on a flat WireGuard protected network
that I set up on each machine in like two minutes.
It's really nice to have that peace of mind while I'm traveling and just pull that stuff
up like I'm sitting on the LAN, regardless of where that machine's at.
And I know it's safe with Tailscale.
So go support the show and try it up to 20 devices for free.
Get started by going to tailscale.com slash coder.
Wouldn't you like to work out in the sunshine?
Tailscale can help make that possible.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
So you got an email this week from Apple saying that reader apps can now add links for account
signups outside the app store.
So like, for example, Netflix can provide a link that goes directly to the Netflix website
for account signups, which means you could sign up using Netflix's payment system, not
Apple's payment system.
What the hell is going on?
Is it actually that you can process the payment without Apple getting the cut, though?
I didn't think that was right.
How can they stop you?
Oh, I think you're required to report it.
Oh, OK.
I could see that.
But they have limits on what you're allowed to do, and they would probably check it in
app review, wouldn't they?
Yeah, I think it's that you can have the signup form be on your website, but you can't actually
not pay them.
OK, I just found the language.
So the external link account entitlement must provide the reader content, must not offer
in app purchases, and must not offer real time person to person services.
Yeah, OK.
I see.
So they no wonder why they're letting this happen.
So basically, they're letting you link out to your website to read about it and manage
your account, maybe, but not pay for things.
Yeah, maybe like account.
I don't know.
Well, no, it says specifically says sign up.
So it's not even like, hey, there's something wrong with my account and real time service.
Wouldn't that include like something weird is going on with my Netflix account?
So you can't even do the chat stuff, right?
You can't even do like the help me, Howard, right, like, wow, just literally just filling
up a sign up form.
What a fun loophole, you know, or like a set of hoops you just have to jump through.
It's weird to me how this got covered because it was in bold, like most of the tech sites,
but it's nothing.
Yeah, it really is nothing.
It's a big nothing burger.
I think we should just move on.
All right.
There's also this story that I just wanted to kind of clarify on a little bit here.
This is a situation, but it seems Apple, as well as a few other companies, were essentially
socially engineered into providing private customer data.
Meta was also targeted in this.
And the reason that they were all got is because the cybercrime group used legitimate law enforcement
mail addresses, they compromised legitimate mail accounts, and then sent emails from those
legitimate accounts asking for the information, domain was legitimate, you know.
And if you've only interacted with these, you know, it's a request that comes from the
email, right?
There's really no way to avoid this kind of stuff unless we get more serious about identity
verification with email, or we get more serious about these companies not holding this data.
There's just no other way around it.
Yeah, at the kind of scale that we have, right?
It's just these events keep happening.
And they're not interested in having this data.
No, of course not.
That doesn't behoove them as a services company.
And I'm sure if they don't comply quickly enough, they're open all kinds of liability
from the government.
So Wes, you are 100% remote work?
Yes, I am.
And is that staying that way?
It is, yeah.
Well, Eric Schmidt thinks you're an idiot.
He says you don't build a great management team virtually.
So you're never going to be management material with your work from home shenanigans.
He says, this is a quote from the former CEO of Googs.
He says, quote, it's important that these people be at the office, in my view.
It may be true.
I'm a traditionalist.
He adds.
Yeah, maybe.
But I think he may be right.
I almost kind of think he might be right.
Like, how do you build a strong team, a leadership team when you're all remote?
In fact, isn't the fact that we're all sitting here in this house right now together kind
of indicative of that, even though we're all remote, we find it necessary to come together?
Well, I think it might just be sort of a spectrum of how often and what that means, right?
I mean, his thought, his end of the spectrum is butt in your seat every day.
That's his spectrum.
Yeah, so it seems like yes, right?
Probably especially for highly coordinating individuals who need to have a lot of dense
networks across the organization, that kind of face time is important.
But there's a lot of different roles in management.
And so you may be doing cross department teams, but a lot of your management may just be,
you need to be available on those Zoom calls to help the teams that you're helping out.
Mike, Schmidt says it's not just the practicals about working together in person, but sometimes
it's about instilling professionalism in your team.
Schmidt says that when he started at Google, for example, he, quote, had an awful lot of
college students who were behaving as though the workplace was like a college.
He goes on to say, quote, and I used to say to them, this is not a college.
This is a professional thing.
You can't do that.
And or it might be illegal.
So please stop now.
And he says, this is particularly important for your employees that are in the ages of
twenty five to thirty five.
They just can't be trusted to work from home and not do dumb things.
I don't know.
I have mixed feelings on this.
I am much less bullish on full remote work than I used to be, but I don't know.
It seems like one of those things that's nice if you're Google, right, and you have like
the awesome offices, lots of money.
You pay people super well, way above average.
And I feel like it's almost not a relevant debate for like small businesses because this
is an argument that this this is just done right.
This is a race that's been run.
You basically have to offer remote work now, specifically hiring developers.
If you're in anywhere competitive, right, because you know what, it's it's just a super
hard hiring market right now.
I think we maybe also, you know, as you're saying that, like the size of the business,
what you're doing, the type of team you have all seems like it matters.
You know, I agree.
There are times like right now at the sprint, right?
Like we can get a lot done.
We have a lot of high bandwidth, but working with the J.B. crew is like they're some of
the best people they've ever done like professional work with.
We knit really well.
We all have similar temperaments.
We get along great, right?
That is not what I think the normal average experience, right?
Like you meet a lot of people in the office, they're fine people, you're not against them,
but they're not, they're not your friends.
You might not even like have a good vibe with them.
And is that like, that's not the same, the magic synergies that all these execs keep
talking about.
I just don't think like maybe one out of a hundred interactions is like that less.
So Schmidt says it's not a big business versus small business thing, which Schmidt says,
he says it is science.
It is 30 to 40 years of workplace experience that has shown us that humans are inherently
social and he goes on to say that the current virtual tools are not the same as informal
networks that occur within a corporation or a business.
And so if you can't be in person together, you're just not going to be as competitive.
Doesn't matter on your size.
It doesn't matter if you have 25 employees or 35,000 employees is what he says.
It's an interesting theory.
I suppose the market's going to validate one way or another, right?
Like if you can be more competitive just by having an office.
I feel like what Mike is kind of saying in a way, it's like Schmidt sitting in an awful
position of privilege, right?
Like easy for Schmidt to say he is, you know, they have the ability to fly people in and
move them if they don't work in the area, that kind of stuff.
But yeah, for many folks probably they might have, you know, and folks in our audience,
they might already have nicer home working setups than they're going to get in an office.
I think if you're going to realistically have an office for, you know, highly talented tech
people, you're going to have to push towards that, like make the office awesome for lack
of a better term.
The whole cafeteria thing, the laundry on site.
I'm going to need a hammock desk.
Hammock desk, you know, Sousa memorabilia everywhere.
It's the stuff you need.
When I was at Dell's Austin office, they had several huge cafeterias with great food, but
they also had an onsite doctor.
So if you wanted to go see a doctor about something, you could go down into the cafeteria
area in one of the main buildings there in the main building and see the doctor right
there at work.
And you know, for a small business guy who doesn't even have medical insurance, that
was like such a trip to think like I could go to the, I could go to work and not only
can I do my laundry and do my, get my eating done and you know, eat my three meals or a
day or whatever, but I can also see the doctor all on the same campus.
It's mind blowing.
It's both crazy convenient and also like a weird, you know, it's, it's almost close to
being back paid the sort of, you know, company money again.
Anyways, we'll wrap it up in there.
I'm going to leave a link in the show notes because this is something that I care a lot
about, but it's not relevant to the show in any way.
Maybe somebody out there cares though.
There is some research that has been published on the 12th and it's, it says that loud road
and air traffic has been linked to greater risk of high blood pressure, heart attacks
and strokes and scientists are uncovering new details about how, what you are hearing
and how it can stress your cardiovascular system.
How about that?
So I'm going to leave it on the show notes because that's probably kind of spooky, but
I'm a big proponent of thinking about noise pollution when you're building an office or
home or something like that.
Oh, you don't say professional podcaster.
Right.
I know.
And I feel like it's something people just ignore.
So I'm advocating for it.
Anyways.
I think that's it.
Anything else we want to cover gentlemen, before we wrap it up today, Mr. Dominic, is
there anything else you want to talk about?
No.
Good to hear from you again, Wes.
Enjoy the work from home.
That's a big change.
Nice.
Indeed.
Thank you, sir.
And yeah, nice to hear your wonderful voice.
Wes and I get on the plane tomorrow and fly back to Seattle.
Back to the sky in our fart tube.
Yep.
Hopefully it's nice and pleasant, although today it's going to be like 80 degrees here.
It's a beautiful day here in Raleigh.
And then what do we, we maybe talked about doing a LAN the morning after we get back
because we're just that crazy.
No rest for us.
I also have a meeting scheduled for that morning, but it'll be over pretty quick.
It's going to be a busy getting back kind of a thing.
There's a lot of stuff I got to follow up on.
This is one of those trips where I'm coming back with a big list.
You hit pause on your life.
You go do, you know, to go take care of some things and then, oh yeah, it all got worse.
It's waiting for you to get back.
Also thank you to our members, CoderQA.co.
New Coderly is coming soon.
You also get access to the show's limited ad feed and you support the show.
And it's just a great way to do that.
You can also support all of the network shows and get access to all of the special features
at Jupiter.party.
Join the party at Jupiter.party and support them all.
Mr. Dominic, where should we send people this week to find you?
At Tumanuku on Twitter.
He may also be broken down on the side of the road.
So look out Floridians.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's more likely than not these days.
Keep an eye out for Mike's broken down car and say hi, maybe give him a beverage or something
like that.
What about you Wes?
Is there anywhere you want people to find you?
Well, yeah.
Hey, look out for a new Linux action news in your feed sometime soon.
That's right.
If we survive back to Seattle, it'll be there, linuxactionnews.com.
This year podcast is at Coder Radio Show on Twitter and our contact page.
We'd love to get your feedback.
That's a big part of our show.
Your thoughts, your comments, your responses, coder.show slash contact.
Go there and let us know what you think.
Links to what we talked about today.
Those are at coder.show slash 461 and get links to all that as well as our RSS feed,
that contact page.
Pretty awesome.
And then this here live stream, 3pm Eastern noon Pacific, see I'm flipping it this time,
at jblive.tv or you can just like subscribe to the Twitch thing and then just get automatically
to twitch.tv slash Jupiter broadcasting.
Anyways, thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio program.
See you right back here next week.