This is KOTORadio, episode 473 for July 4th, 2022.
Hello friends and welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
My name is Chris and joining us in his flag-themed outfit, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
That's right.
Chris, can we hear that eagle soar?
We got an eagle.
You sure I should let it out, Mike?
You sure?
Let it out.
That's right.
I'm putting down the tea, picking up the coffee.
Look at the way it goes.
Look at that.
I can't remember other British things.
Hold on.
I think it just stole someone's hot dog.
Oh.
Yes.
No.
Geez.
Well, we just ruined their Independence Day.
So yeah, it's a holiday here in the States.
Yes.
Of course, by the time you're hearing, it's over.
We have that whole time delay.
That's kind of the reasons we always just do a show, because by the time you're hearing
this, your holiday is over.
So here we are for you.
I got to say, I have a little bit of, I don't know, slash envy, slash impressed.
I don't know.
You have become like a grill master.
I didn't even realize you owned a grill.
And then you know how I stalk you on Twitter, as I do.
And as one of everyone.
And I'm just seeing all kinds of goodies all the time.
I mean, grilled ribs, grilled corn on the cob.
Those ribs were not me.
But it's funny you mentioned ribs, Chris.
Yeah.
Are you flying down or teleporting via LadyJuice, my serial network?
I mean, if I need to for ribs, I probably could.
There are going to be barbecue ribs, a couple of hot dogs, because we have some children
that have not experienced or embraced the glory that is ribs, which great.
More for dad.
Not a problem.
But ribs there, paired with some Redwood Empire bourbon, as well as some Mexican corn, again,
on the grill.
Oh, my.
Yes.
And French fries, because little kids exist.
But yeah.
That sounds like a lot of fun.
That's nice.
There will be a picture.
Don't worry.
I don't generally see you get like, you know, a three or four head day start on the show.
But this is a special week.
You got a jumpstart, and I think I think there's one man that deserves credit for it.
It can only be one.
And of course, it is the Egon Egon has written into the show again.
He says, Hi, guys.
This is Egon.
As I've told you before, the joy of listening to Mike and Chris chat about the art and business
of software development and the world of technology is the weekly highlight of my commute.
But episode 471 was special.
Birthday drunk, freshly engaged Mike is the best kind of Mike.
I love his vibes.
Coder Radio is the most informative, entertaining tech podcast I know.
But when you started to talk about me and to me, the joy of listening to your show raised
like an Apple stock since 2019.
Damn.
Now it's time for me to give back to the greatest show on Earth, apart from being a Coder QA
member for the first hour.
But of course, a first hour Coder QA member.
That is impressive.
Now it is time for me to give back to the greatest show on Earth, apart from being a
Coder QA member, I will do I henceforth apply for one of the following positions on the
Coder Radio team.
All right.
Get ready.
The official Coder Radio mascot or 90 percent Coder Radio Jesus without the 100 percent
because he doesn't want to get nailed on to things.
So he wants to be the 90 percent Coder Jesus or president of the German speaking Coder
Radio chapter in Europe.
I'll be waiting for your answers with great anticipation.
The Egon.
This is a tough call.
I think Egon is probably qualified for any of these three positions for sure.
And also, I am concerned about the size of the organization just growing and growing.
And so I feel like there may be room to collapse a couple of these positions and just give
more work to Egon.
I feel like he could just do all three, although I have to say the German aspect of it is very
intriguing to me because I failed to tweet this, but I do often grill brats and various
other types of German sausages.
There's that.
Yeah.
I would probably be aware of that.
The radio mascot.
I think that's that's probably pretty good.
The Coder Jesus one is tricky.
That's tricky.
I see.
I think he'd be more like a Coder John the Baptist, right?
He's like spreading the word.
Yeah, that's what I was thinking.
That's exact.
Yeah.
All right.
So why don't we go ahead and give approval since we're having our little production meeting
now to Egon being the official Coder Radio mascot and the president of the German speaking
Coder Radio chapter of Europe.
And we will revisit his exact status in the actual order of the Church of Coder Radio.
But it's definitely high up there.
That's for sure.
Right.
Incredible work, Egon.
Keep it up.
And also, Gary gets a little point in the chat room for managing to mention Snow Leopard
less than three minutes into the episode.
We've got some trains so well.
Nicely done chat room.
You know what?
They know how to make you happy.
Wait, can Egon like wear a Snow Leopard themed outfit with maybe like an adium watch?
We can make this work.
I feel like this is going a different direction.
Like this is a different thing.
So that's a different podcast, I think.
You know, I want to just put one more word out there for the London meetup because I
won't be there.
And I want to make that clear.
But Alex from Self Hosted is going to be there as well as a bunch of community members.
And I feel like this could be the proto meetup.
I've been looking to get over in the London area forever, and it'd be great to bring a
few members of the crew over there and do a meetup.
And so this is sort of like the scouting mission, right?
We're sending over the early scouts to go over and discover the territory.
So meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting, they've got a venue, they got a date.
It's getting solid.
And an obligatory plug for the new J.B. Meetups Matrix space.
This is an area where we are organizing physical meetups and virtual meetups.
We have a London Colony meetup chat room, a Pacific Northwest Colony, a Mumble Colony.
I could see the Mumble ones for virtual events.
I could see us doing a California one because we have a California road trip coming up soon.
I could see us doing one in Raleigh, Florida one, you know, Florida Man community chat
room.
Yeah, I haven't come to Florida.
Yeah, one day I would like to.
I mean, I have been.
I have been.
The nice thing about doing a meetup in Florida, if you do it near Orlando in particular or
even Tampa works good, is that the whole economy, other than Disney, which I don't know if the
governor has his way, we're going to just like send some cats in to catch the mouse,
is basically geared towards this exact thing, right?
It's all like people come in, they do their thing, they leave.
We pay no income tax.
We tax the **** out of you while you're here.
It's amazing.
Really good stuff.
I was surprised by Raleigh.
There is a lot of industry in Raleigh and that I realized is kind of part of it is if
you can do meetups around where there's some big industry buildings where they have offices,
you get a lot of listeners that show up.
It's kind of funny how that works.
Yeah, I wouldn't mind going to Raleigh this time.
Oh, yeah.
Be good.
I you know, I was it was funny.
I was going to go to Linux Fest Southeast or right.
Mm hmm.
Southeast Linux Fest.
Yeah, thank you.
That's the one.
And apparently it either didn't happen or happened early this year or I for some reason
thought it was early.
I don't know, man.
That was crazy.
I wanted to go.
And then I think I saw like my buddy Noah chatting in Telegram or something that it
was live right then.
I was like, oh, what?
Oh, yeah.
Well, Emma told me because she's like, are you coming to any events this year?
Yeah, I'm going to go to self and she's like, but I'm we're here now.
What are you talking about?
Yeah.
This it's you know, I got to get back.
There used to be a good app and I can't remember what it was to track like all the upcoming
events for a given topic.
And I guess I don't know if it's gone.
It's funny how some events are they're pretty clever.
They reach out to media with an email that says, hey, just so you know, this is the details
about our event.
If you get a chance to mention on there, that'd be great.
But just want you to be aware of what's going on because they realize, hey, you know, they
probably talk to hundreds of thousands of people.
So if we tell them then they could tell hundreds of thousands of people.
But then other events just don't think that way and they don't reach out and they don't
try to like get coverage.
And I think it hurts their growth a little bit.
It's sort of an echo chamber thing, too, I suppose.
Yeah.
Well, it sucks to for local events that don't really maybe know how to do the outreach.
And I've had it so many times where I realize like there was literally something in Tampa
that would have been cool for me to go, like maybe do an interview for the show or something,
you know, some kind of like because we have a lot of weird like infosec stuff because
we have a big military base here.
And just like they don't they don't publish anything.
And they're surprised when all their events are super duper small.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get one hundred dollars and 60 day credit on a new account.
And it's just a great way to support the show while you learn something.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You got to try it for your next project.
Maybe it could be the back end for your business.
That's what I do.
Maybe it's just a personal site.
You know, maybe you got a portfolio, maybe you got a blog you want to put there.
Maybe you want your own personal peer tube instance.
It's actually great for that.
And then you can use their object storage back end for the video storage, which is killer.
But if you need like a high performance application, well, they've got you covered there, too.
They got MVME storage, PCI beautiful MVE storage.
They got their own ISP connections.
So they have just screaming 40 gigabit connections coming into these machines.
And of course, they've got processors with AMD, epic CPUs and 11 data centers around
the world.
So you're going to find something near you or your customers.
Linode's been doing this for nearly 19 years.
Crazy cats got started in 2003 because they just saw where Linux was going.
They saw where the technology could take them.
I can resonate with that.
I think you might, too.
And I think you'll see it throughout the service.
And then if you ever get any trouble, you'll find that they have the best service.
You know, somehow those hyperscalers can make billions and billions and billions of dollars,
but they can't do simple support.
Maybe there's something special to it.
Maybe it's not so simple.
Maybe Linode just has it figured out after nearly 19 years.
Either way, go try it for yourself and find out, support the show and get $100.
Go try out my host.
I wouldn't host our applications anywhere else, and I think you'll feel the same way.
Linode.com slash coder.
All right, Mr. Dominic, let's talk about your Linux 2022 toolbox.
Actually, let's issue a challenge.
Your ad read just inspired me.
All right, give it to me.
Use the Linode code.
Use their managed, I think it's Postgres thing.
Yeah.
I think they do a couple, but I think it's Postgres and MySQL for sure.
Yeah, and they got Mongo, too.
They got Mongo, Postgres, and MySQL.
Build, you have to be in the US, blah, blah, blah, the same caveats I always put on it.
I, for some reason, have a spare dev one because I think I entered some alcoholic fugue state
where I just started ordering dev ones.
Yes.
See this is why it used to be a video show.
Your face is priceless right now, like it's amazing.
I almost did a spit take on the mixer.
I legitimately-
That would have been amazing.
I'm watching your reactions to the nonsense.
It's amazing.
You're just like, the sad part is Chris knows that this is 100% definitely true.
Oh yeah, of course, of course, yeah.
So tell you what, the winner who could make me the best web application, not just me,
like post it publicly, whatever, that tracks all the dev slash community events in the
States, particularly focusing on the Northwest and the Southeast, like that's where we are.
A nice format where you can add it to your calendar with links to sign up so that next
time there's an event that makes sense for either Chris or I to go to, we can just not
screw it up and actually know about it, unlike this yourself, which is my fault.
A Linux community event tracker.
Yeah.
I mean, it'd be cool if you could just sign up for an email every time there's one added
or something.
Yeah.
Or a calendar ICS feed.
You know, I know the Portland area has one specifically for Portland, but we need something
for our reporter.
There's a bunch for like, even meetup.com does something like it.
But first of all, their filters are, their filters are just awful, but I'm thinking someone
who knows, you know, knows the show, knows the JB community, and this could be something
useful for other hosts or other even just community members sign up for have better
meetups.
We could put our stuff on there.
I'm surprised this doesn't exist.
I haven't found it.
If it, I mean, if it exists, then you know, all bets are off, but I haven't found it.
Yeah, no, I have not either.
I, like I said, I know of like the, the one in Portland, which I think is actually open
source.
Oh yeah.
It has to be open source.
Right?
Like that's the caveat.
Open source on GitHub.
GPL it if you want.
Oh yeah.
Calligator is what they call it.
Calligator.
That's terrible.
Yeah.
Well, you know, you could fork that.
It's Portland's tech calendar, calligator.org.
And it is a collection of all of the events.
Like here's some data engineering Q and a night, uh, software engineering beyond bootcamp,
mentorship Saturdays, just different events, including they'll have their Linux.
Yeah.
Community events on there and whatnot.
Someone could look at that.
I'll put a link in the show notes.
Maybe somebody could get started there.
You know, I will say the, uh, young man, I didn't, I didn't feature him cause he was
a underage and I just, you know, but who made me, or maybe he was 17, 18.
I don't remember who made me the snow leopard GTK theme did in fact, I guess his gazelle.
I'm just saying I always pay, I always pay my bets.
So that's great.
Oh, right.
Okay.
So you've updated your Linux toolbox for 2020 and you've got some, you know, you've been
playing around some new hardware, certain software has been discontinued.
Some software I think has become more prominent.
Tell me a little bit about it.
Yeah.
So, um, you know, for, for you hardcore Linux heads, I think a lot of this is going to be
like lay doi, but kind of, I've been using the Mac a lot and I still have not been able
to move my, this is kind of sideways, but my, uh, like audio production stuff.
I don't do a lot of it like Chris, but I do enough that it's annoying, but you could like
Photoshop workflow onto Linux.
Although I am learning the gimp.
Also it seems that, uh, old Adobe has plans to make a web version of Photoshop.
There's also photo P which I don't know if you ever tried that.
I don't know that one photo P like P E a, it is like Photoshop seven in the web browser.
It's not bad actually.
Oh, that actually would be perfect.
And it opens and saves.
I think it saves, but I know it opens PSD files too.
So there's something interesting.
So that would be super good.
Yeah.
I don't do a ton of it.
It's always like, you know what, when you're working with a designer on a product, they're
all, they hate cutting assets and they always want to hand you just a photo set up file.
Right.
And they're just like, here you go.
Yes.
Totally.
All right.
So yeah, Rob, I'm just going to run through the list.
Some of this is obvious vs code.
Why?
Because I'm a developer and I don't like to pay for things.
And also Microsoft has thrown just a stupid amount of investment vs code.
It's really good.
We all know that everybody has their preferences.
Move on.
Melt.
I really like melt.
Thank you for putting melt in here.
I don't understand what's wrong with meld.
It's a, it's a gooey dipping tool.
It's comparable to the popular Mac app kaleidoscope, which is also a gooey giving tool, except
meld is free.
It's an almost every app store on Linux that I could think of that runs gnome.
I don't know, man.
It gifts my like merge conflicts or various versions of documents really quickly, really
visually.
You can customize it to a point.
It's one of those tools that I use a lot and just works.
Sounds super boring.
I like it better than the vs code diff tool, mostly because I like having it side by side
with the colorized, uh, like colors, the different versions, right?
Like, you know, blue is whatever colors you pick, but like mine is blue and red.
So I could see like, okay, we have this three way merge, you know, where the hell did we
go wrong?
The next one is color picker, which is again, super simple, but this, my post is really
targeting people coming from the Mac Mac has the, what is the digital cuddle color meter.
Is that right?
Is that what they call it?
I mean, yeah, I know what you're talking about.
Yeah.
This is a better version of that, believe it or not.
This is a case where the Linux alternative is in fact like more full featured, easier
to use and makes a lot more sense for what you're doing.
So it's great.
You can put a droplet or a pipette or whatever they call that anywhere on your screen and
it will get you the color of that item in various formats.
Super useful if you're doing something for a client and you know, they just got to have
their shade of blue, right?
But no one wants to give you a hex code or RGB code for it because they don't know it.
My next one up, I use this damn thing every day on every operating system.
Postman.
If you don't know what Postman is and you either write API calls or you use API calls,
it's free.
Go download it.
You can download it from the Electron app, but it will make your life a hundred times
easier than just having to like curl, test your requests or, you know, have some giant
document of like request samples.
You can save them.
You can group them.
You can have collections for like, I have it by client mostly, but I have it by project
if it's for our internal stuff.
Really good.
You can also do variable, like variable values.
So like if you're on one machine, the API key can be this, if you're on another machine
it can be that.
Super cool stuff.
Really useful.
There is a paid option, which I do pay for.
Getting some love in the chat room too.
Oh yeah.
You got to check out the Postman.
Hammerless says it's one of the Electron apps that doesn't feel like an Electron app.
It does exactly what it says on the tin, right?
It just works.
Tabby Terminal.
All right.
So this is one where I decided to bitch at somebody.
I don't know why Zach and company at Warp Terminal seem to be wanting to duck the when
is it coming to Linux question.
Actually I have a suspicion.
Can I fry some bacon?
Yeah.
You want some?
All right.
So Warp Terminal, we covered it a couple of weeks ago or a month ago.
You can look it up.
We'll put it in the show notes.
They keep making mouth noises about like a web-based version of it because they want
this whole like remote teamwork and they have a lot of features for that.
I have a feeling they're going to do the web before they do Linux.
I just do.
And that to me is a big mistake.
And then Linux users can go run it in a web browser.
They're not going to, right?
Or they'll do some like they package it, right?
But whatever.
So I've decided to go to a web-based terminal called Tappy.
I will say this is the one where I like it over G Terminal.
It has some better auto-completion, some more configurability.
If you're on Mac and you haven't tried Warp, I know they have the weird thing where you
have to log in with GitHub, but unless you're like super worried about that, they don't
track what you do in the terminal.
You can turn all that stuff off.
It is really good.
I'm Tappy for now, but I would be going back to them if they could get on Linux since other
than this kind of production stuff, I'm basically daily driving.
So yeah, what did I miss?
I know I'm missing stuff.
You think so?
It's funny.
I can forget that I'm on the dev one sometimes because I'm really just living in like terminal
windows tiled all over the place and VS code.
That's so nice.
It's so clean.
It's so portable, that setup.
Like you could run that on anything, really.
That's a great place to be.
I mean, you got all the obvious things like, of course, chat apps and whatnot.
Yeah.
I didn't put like, you know, Lutris in there because I was kind of, you know, I will give
the Linux machine over the Mac, like most of my Steam library seems to work relatively
well.
Yeah.
Oh, it's way better.
It's way better.
And it's pretty neat.
It's only a 16 gig machine, too.
I was surprised.
It's a time where if you want a game and you want a good developer workstation, Linux makes
a lot more sense than the Mac and the Mac is in such a bad gaming position right now.
I'll toss in one bonus app.
If you like me end up with multiple browsers to either test things in different browsers
or for different account reasons, there is an app that I've mentioned maybe once before
on the show.
Maybe it's called Junction.
And it's like Bumper on Mac OS.
It lets you choose the browser a link opens in.
So you click a link.
Oh, that's cool.
Yeah.
And this little pop up overlay that lists your browsers, you know, just icons or whatever
browser auto detects on your system.
You tap that browser and then that browser launches with the URL.
That's super cool.
Yeah.
I use this a surprising amount.
I just there's some things I use Chrome for, some things I use Firefox, some things Edge
even good on Web.
So you mentioned Edge.
I had Edge in here and I took it out because I was afraid that the whole thing would be
overshadowed by Edge 8.
I am living in Edge now.
You know, but are you really?
It is the easiest way for me to sync all my insanely long passwords.
And I still have to let Google authenticate with the authenticator app, everything, but
it runs everywhere.
I mean, if it works for you, you know, I have Edge in a couple of spots because for whatever
reason, some of these apps we use for remote shows and stuff just use considerably less
CPU and Edge than they do Chrome or Firefox.
I don't know what they're doing.
So I end up reluctantly using Edge quite a bit for that sort of stuff.
I wonder how many people are using Linux and Edge at the same time.
But you know, it's like, well, yeah, yeah, officer, I did have a drink or two, but listen,
my grandma died and I was running Edge.
Yeah.
Oh, I see.
It's been a rough day.
I see.
So obviously your Discord chat was taunting you and in your despair.
Okay.
All right.
So one of the things we're reluctantly using, how has Copilot gone for you so far?
I know you signed up for the GitHub Copilot.
You're now a paying user.
Yeah, that was, I got to stop doing stuff like that.
It's really, I mean, it's great for system 76.
And content, content.
And content.
But we need to raise our ad rates, all right.
So Copilot, we're going to do this like a nice corporate performance review.
Performance.
Damn, things fast.
I was surprised.
Like it figures it out quick, you mean?
Yeah.
Well, well, it's fast.
It's fast like a drunk driver's fast.
Like it's pretty quick, but it ain't going anywhere good.
That's a little, I mean, languages.
So this is all right.
I'm just going to do the bad stuff first.
If you are writing relatively mainstream Python, Copilot is amazing.
For Python, it's amazing.
I'm struggling to understand what you just said, because it sounded like what you just
said is if you're writing Python, Copilot works really well, which is just, that's hard
for me to wrap my head around.
And then I started thinking, is that because maybe all of the open source software they
fed this thing was mostly Python?
I think that's what it is, right.
It's a, you know, when I say mainstream Python, I'm talking about like basic, you know, I'm
parsing data, blah, blah, blah, rendering a webpage, doing some ginger stuff.
That all works pretty good.
Some of the suggestions are definitely questionable, but you know, if you are a junior dev and
need a little handholding and you're writing, let's just say a Django app, I think it would
be helpful or at least not harmful.
It has some interesting ideas on HTML and CSS.
Now, that's not my strongest suit, so I don't know if it's, I have a very old school way
of doing things on the front end.
I doubt that because I'm doing Angular TypeScript right now, which I know isn't the newest thing,
but it's also not like, you know, straight up jQuery, right?
It gets really convinced once you do something, like once you take one of its suggestions,
it gets real sure you want that like 20 other times.
It gets an attaboy and it really responds.
Yeah, which can become annoying.
I have some concerns that weren't really my concerns, but then I got hammered enough on
the DMs and on the telegrams that I'm not sure that this isn't going to open up like
potential just, you know, they used to say PHP was bad because like all the kids didn't
know what they were doing, we're just writing PHP and copy off stack overflow.
Well this is like without even having to hit control C, control V, right?
This is pretty bad.
Yeah, and it could be for everything.
So if you're using fast API, it seems pretty confused, but that's because fast API is a
Python framework that West turned me on to a while ago, is much newer, much less popular
and frankly not that supported, right?
Yeah, it probably wasn't in the data set as much.
Right, where if you're using Django or Flask, it's like, okay, I get you.
Or honestly, like if you're writing a Python command line app, that's your guy.
He's there for you, like a good neighbor, copilots there.
Like a drunk neighbor, copilots there.
If he's grilling, he might give you food though.
That's true.
Yeah.
That's kind of nice.
I'm going to keep it up for the year though.
I'm going to use it.
I'm going to keep using it for non-client internal stuff because I don't want to get
sued.
So that's the way to kind of walk that line, is nothing you're going to ship to any client.
Yeah, the Telegram freedom beard scared me enough that I was like, all right.
Which I would say if you're a freedom beard on Telegram, did you forget about IRC or whatever?
The argument they made that you'll get sued and your client will get sued for the GPL,
I don't think so.
That seems cray-cray, but I guess it's possible.
My concern would be like copilot generates some crazy proprietary thing or more likely,
my actual concern was copilot basically generates a bunch of security holes, right?
Because it takes the most popular, which might be the most naive and crappy way to do things.
All right.
Interesting.
Well, I'll be curious to circle back and see how it's going.
Yeah.
I'm going to try it with some either Minecraft mod development or some light game development
because I'm doing that project with my kid I talked about last week.
So that's, I want to see how it does on something that's not like web dev.
I definitely get the feeling that like, this is one of those things, right, where it's
like when you're on Twitter and you see the people tweeting about doing dev, you know
half those dudes who are talking about hardcore hacking are like JavaScript developers.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
Go there to get a personal account for up to 20 devices for free.
And of course, your support in the show.
Tailscale is a game changer.
It's a zero config VPN, installs on any device in minutes, manages your firewall rules, navigates
your dub gnats, and it'll work from anywhere.
And of course, devices connect directly in a mesh network using WireGuard's noise protocol.
You build up, then you have static IPs for all your machines.
It's so handy.
Literally, last night, laying in bed, realizing I had screwed something up for the LUP show
notes.
I should just go to bed, but you know what, it was really important, and I was already
home.
And I knew thousands of people would be confused if I didn't go make this correction.
So I pop on my laptop, by the time my Wi-Fi is connected, my tailscale connection's up.
And I'm SSHed into a server, and I'm fixing things.
Within minutes.
It's such a peace of mind.
It really was the missing piece for how I run my networks.
And I've also been able to turn off all the inbound ports on my firewalls now.
So my firewalls are like pristine, man.
It's Fort Knox up in here because it's tailscale.
It's so great.
I got in everything from my Arch boxes, my Nix boxes, my Pi's, my iPad, I mean, you name
it, man.
I got tailscale on it.
Every device is connected to a mesh network with static VPNs.
It's so great.
They're always on.
So they're always available.
And they're smart about how they route the traffic.
Go try it yourself for free for up to 20 devices and support the show.
It's tailscale.com slash coder.
Okay, so we thought to stay in theme with the fact that it is Independence Day today.
We should probably talk about why you and I originally went independent, independent
agents so many years ago.
And I thought maybe we should try to capture this before I completely forget it.
Because once I suggested this idea, I really started struggling remembering the history
of everything because I've gotten so far from it that I really can't remember life before
this way now.
So I'm probably properly broken for ever working in a company, I would imagine.
Yeah, I would think so.
Let's start with you.
So what was it?
Did you start on a career trajectory like I did?
Like I went into the traditional nine to five world first and then did a course correction.
Is that the case for you?
Or did you always just go like, I'm not doing that.
I'm doing my own thing.
It was kind of the opposite for me, right?
Because when I was in school, I did a lot of Java applet work, but that was effectively
what we would call now freelancing.
Yeah.
But it was they just called it, you know, contracts, part time, whatever.
Basically, they don't pay payroll tax because they're bricks.
Then the iPhone came and I did a lot of web and iOS stuff for a long time.
I got like when we talked about this a long time ago, but I was on a contract that was
like a job, but then I was supposed to convert over.
I think I may have actually converted over for like a month and then it was a startup.
They had some severe financial issues and that did not last.
So I was in this position where I literally left the place, went downstairs because it's
New York.
So there's like a bar in the basement and went to the pub and it was just like, okay,
well, nothing has literally changed.
I just lost a client.
You know, we got to remember this is like the big, this is right before the App Store
gold rush.
And then the App Store gold rush happened and I never looked back really.
Every once in a while I'll be like, ah, I'm getting older.
You know, I'm not, you know, I'm doing very different things than I used to do now.
But yeah, I don't see myself looking back.
I definitely think if you're going to do it super young, like I think your way is probably
the more traditional, safer way if you're going to do it the way I did.
You want to be on the new hotness because otherwise you're going to get trounced by
the contractors and freelancers who actually have, you know, experience.
So yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, definitely.
I had a real interesting looking back at it path because I got initially my very first
job was actually at a school district, which is surprisingly bureaucratic and complicated
in, in how pay works and I was part of a union and all of that.
And then I left and I went into a private bank, which was its own kind of bureaucrat
sort of run organization and had, you know, 700, 800 ish employees.
And maybe, maybe by the time I left a thousand, I don't know.
And then I went and did small startup companies.
I worked for a company called Dream Dinners, which was one of the very first meal order
services.
Oh, neat.
Only because it was so early, you'd go to the website, which was all of course a PHP
app, which I ran the backend for.
You'd put your order in, but then you would go to one of the franchise locations and assemble
the meals yourself and then like cart them home.
Like they didn't deliver them.
They hadn't figured like the two side, oh, you would go, wait, you the customer?
Yeah.
You would go, you would go.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
So of course we had a bunch of franchise locations and then they brought in some quote unquote
experts from Starbucks and an expert from Boeing and the company went into the toilet
immediately.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Where is the convert on the Venn diagram of Starbucks executives and Boeing executives?
I guess they both like to fuel things locally.
They looked at as two icons of industry, of course, Seattle, right, right.
And the, and the, the two gals, the two co-owners that ran dream dinners really idolized this
other gal that worked at Starbucks.
Of course, Starbucks had fired her, but so they picked her up.
And then of course, Boeing laid this guy off and they picked him up and they just really
just ran things differently and the whole thing fell apart.
And it was about at that point where I had kind of walked the whole spectrum and of course
I'm shortening.
There's a lot of little other jobs in there of where I realized I can hate working for
somebody else.
It drives me crazy.
I can't stand their pandemic, pandemic priorities.
I can't, I can't understand most of their motivations.
I lose motivation working for them.
I typically, I typically just, it doesn't work out longterm.
And I was looking at that math and thinking to myself, I'm like, you know, I could just
take a handful of clients and I could just do this.
I mean, really, it's not, it's not that big of a deal, which of course little did I know,
doing independent IT contracting with a handful of selected clients, which was great money
transformed into podcasting as I kept trying to refine the podcast and I kept trying to
figure like, what could we do to make them sound better?
What could I do to make the content better?
What do I have to do in order to make the show good enough for somebody to want to spend
their time listening?
And everything kept coming to, well, I need to spend more time on the podcast and less
time consulting.
And so it just sort of consumed everything and I just sort of worked over time to make
it possible to do this full time.
And then about a decade into it, we decided, okay, let's try combining with a larger organization
that has a similar goal set as ours, but has a much bigger budget.
You know, like for me too, man, I was so burned out because I just didn't have anybody doing
marketing.
I didn't have anybody doing this or that, right?
There's when you join a large organization, all of a sudden you get all these resources
and I got health insurance right before I ended up in the hospital.
So that was nice.
And I learned at that point what it's like to be in a VC backed business, a couple of
them because then they are acquired by a cloud guru, but I also learned a very valuable lesson
that the kind of dedication that these podcasts require can't happen in an organization where
the podcasts are not ultimately the end product.
So if the end product is anything but the podcast, there's just no way the organization
will be as focused and prioritized to serve the podcast as they need to be.
That makes sense.
And in order to make them competitive, they need that kind of dedication and focus.
And so that's when I realized it wasn't going to work as part of a larger organization.
That's when we began the process of making JB independent again.
And now it's kind of like I'm in a middle ground where I kind of miss some of that stuff.
I was caveching before the show started that for the last two days we've had tech issues.
After years of great stability, we've started having some tech issues as the machines are
getting older.
And you know, I'm the guy that's in here to do something else and all of a sudden I realized
the computer's broken and now I've gone back 15 years in time and now I'm doing tech support
for myself.
And that kind of stuff, you know, in the past we had like a full team of people so there'd
be somebody in here that could do that and that's all right.
It's not the same but ultimately I think the shows are better for it so the product's better
for it.
And our core team is, you know, you know the people that are around now.
They're great.
They're the best team we've ever had.
So that all worked out.
I'm kind of figuring out a health insurance thing and I'm in process of it right now which
could be great.
That'd be a nice relief because I haven't really had anything before so I'm getting
close to having that all sorted out.
It's been a long journey but I think ultimately it was about figuring out what works for me
and how I can work best and also understanding that and maybe it's in part because I've been
diagnosed with ADD but like I have to be working on something that matters to me and if I'm
working on something that matters to me I can just work endlessly on it and if I'm working
on something that doesn't matter to me not only do I have to like really stay on myself
to like keep going and keep getting the job done but I screw stuff up.
I just don't pay attention to the details.
I miss things not intentionally but because I'm just not laser focused on it but when
I'm laser focused on it I become hyper aware of attention.
I have a hyper attention to detail.
So it's just a big flip in realizing how I work too and then trying to build something
around that.
Who knows?
The next couple of years are probably going to be pretty wild.
Something else is probably going to change.
Yeah what's funny is when I first started going indie my goal was to be a game dev company.
I still every once in a while try to do it but my crusty old Coco's 2D Objective-C code
just doesn't cut it today.
Things have changed so much but maybe one day.
One day.
Time to get skilled up in metal.
Metal!
I'm sorry what?
Yeah right.
But what's funny too is I can sense that there is another shift coming and in part because
I think there's so many macro economic shifts happening and I think budgets are going to
get reallocated and I think everything's going to go through a repricing.
Everything.
And so I feel like that inevitably is going to have some sort of knock-on effect to what
I do but it just is too early to tell.
So it's sort of just like you just go into it knowing that there's kind of a storm down
the road and you just kind of hope you're going to drive through it.
Yeah this is going to be a hell of a year or two year period I think.
Yeah or more.
Yeah.
Hmm.
So it's tough to say but you know I guess part of it is you learn to shift.
You learn to kind of tuck and roll I suppose because look at you right.
Started you want to do game development ended up writing the App Store away for a while
and now you're really you're probably writing more back-end applications and you know.
Well yeah mostly back-end I would say yeah definitely mostly back-end but like this line
of business applications almost all back-end right.
Yeah it's not funny and it's it's each time it's a tuck and roll right.
And sometimes it's just stuff out of your control.
It's jumping out of a moving car.
Yeah right.
Very much so.
System 76 dot com slash specials yep our friends at system 76 are back they have a fourth of
July sale.
Each user is going to receive a tool kit which includes the iFixit.
I think it's the Minow you know it's like their DIY repair kit.
You're also going to get a right to repair declaration scroll.
That sounds fun.
And a sticker.
This is going to come with any purchase of a computer until their supplies run out the
Tinkers tool kit until it's gone.
And now is a great time to get a new machine because of course they've got great prices
right now and brand new Lemur or I'm sorry the Lemur with a 12th gen Intel CPU.
That's what's up.
We're waiting for that 14 hours of battery life clocking at only 2.5 pounds with 4 terabytes
of NVMe storage.
Wow.
Then also the new darter you know the darter was recently released also has a 12th gen
Intel you can get an i7 or an i5 in there.
Nine hours of battery life 3.8 pounds 64 gigabytes of RAM.
Go check out system 76 I will give a personal shout out to the launch absolutely love it.
Got it right here.
I had to launch right in front of me as I record.
It is the best keyboard I've ever used.
So many great systems over at system 76 and they're born to run Linux and they're better
than ever.
So go take advantage of their 4th of July sale.
Get yourself that free Tinkers tool kit while supplies last and you support the show.
So to get the special to get that tool kit the sticker and the scroll go to system 76
dot com slash specials and when you're checking out tell them the coder program sent you say
hi from Mike and Chris would you say hi to our friends over there.
System 76 dot com slash specials.
Ask not what your podcast can boost for you but what you can boost for your podcast.
All right so logic came in with 500 sats four days ago.
He says let's get some resources posted over on matrix need to get more people in matrix.
I owe Mike an account although I have accounts disabled so I have to figure out if I have
to turn accounts on and then create you an account or if I can create them but have them
disabled for the public.
And of course there's no like UI to manage any of this.
I mean there's some projects out there but it runs on Linux.
What do you buy.
But the matrix room is beginning to organize.
I think they're going to come looking for it soon.
So just FYI on that you better watch out Oh a guy one boosted in 120 sats look I'm giving
you the last sats I earned from promoted clips and shows on fountain.
This is a new thing they're doing now where they're giving away sats to help people boost
when you listen to promoted clips actually says he likes it a lot.
It feels like marbles when I was a kid.
That's pretty great.
That's pretty good.
Keep up the incredible work.
Maybe I will get enough sats to send a tribute to my much loved 6502 processor.
The classic the classic says you might become a member to user and boosted in 225 sats four
days ago.
But Vim guys it's still a solid choice today especially with Neo Vim.
No surprise it's listed as one of the most loved ideas in the stack flow in the stack
overflow developer survey speaking of.
Have you thought about reviewing that survey.
This year we didn't do it.
We didn't do it.
We've done it.
We've done it almost every other year.
You know that survey kind of I'm getting done with it getting done with it because it's
always like JavaScript.
It's like always number one.
Yeah.
Unless he means the ideas and they're always kind of the same to ran.
What's it going to be.
People who are lying and saying they're using like Emacs and Vim who are really mostly using
VSCode you know people actually using Emacs and Vim and a bunch of folks using JetBrains
and Visual Studio right.
So I don't know it's it's I don't know did we ever actually talk about it but the reason
I didn't even like put it in the show notes maybe we did talk about it was it it's just
kind of the same for the last several years right.
The last shakeup was really the app store stuff when Objective C shot up the thing and
then Swift came and there was a bit of a jumble.
Yeah otherwise it's kind of just been more of the same Linux doing great.
That's all I care about.
Yeah.
Linux is fine.
It's gaining share.
Yeah.
Yep.
Dave Jones boosted in four days ago with two thousand one hundred and twelve sats.
He says yeah he's all on board with the rope coin could call it RBC.
You know we could get a you know a crap coin out there that we pump and dump with robes
and then if you have like a thousand of them then you could turn them in for a robe or
something like that.
We'll have to figure it out.
We'll have to because definitely.
I love it.
There's there's there's a real like tokenomics to a good scam we'll definitely have to figure
it out.
Don't don't want to miss out on that club three thousand boosted in two hundred twenty
five sats.
Chris you had a good opportunity to tell Mike some of the privacy technologies like coin
join and lightning.
The transactions are visible but it's difficult to trace the addresses to their owners if
they're regularly doing coin joins and spreading them with lightning.
Also with 50 percent of Bitcoin and lightning nodes behind Tor and in different countries
it's going to be difficult for anyone to stop the Bitcoin network.
You see you say something bad about the Bitcoin and somebody is going to come at you.
I didn't you know I you know pleb I don't really tend to argue on this stuff because
I feel like history will will tell us what happens.
Time will tell.
You know the coins I want to be careful the coins are still looking for their killer app
right.
I didn't say block chain.
You know I think block chain is going to be a thing that lots of banks and financial institutions
use but I'm not sure that we're going to see like the I keep going back to it but like
the indie rent you know the indie opportunities there because I think block chain it's slow
it's resource intensive and it has certain attack vectors if it's not of a certain size
of a network and I don't think there's a lot of compelling use cases for block chain outside
of Bitcoin.
I think it's pretty much the one and the only real value and use case I see there long term
is a hard money that is all accountable you know we're all twenty one million of them
are and they are all unique and scarce and it's a store of value because of that.
People love that scarcity thing outside of that like the NFT marketplace is completely
crashed right.
All this stuff just seems like it's totally in the tank and I think we're really seeing
a dot com kind of clean out.
That's what I was going to say.
Yeah you'll see some projects survive but I think for the most part a lot of this stuff
is going to get washed away.
This is I mean it's going to be a couple of years we're going to go through the cycle
again right.
I mean you could even see the VCs are pulling back and I read something just wonderful in
the New York Times this morning.
Apparently Uber didn't realize they weren't making money because they're in a panic it
seems over according to this op-ed because oh we make no money and there's not like drunk
VC money anymore.
So what are we going to do and the answer is this is like my revenge from 2012 right
like the point of a business is to like that number in Excel needs to be black not red.
They're going to have to clean house.
Yeah we're going to see like the fall of the stupid business models.
Now Uber is a bad example Uber is not going to fall right they have too much money too
much momentum but I think it's healthy to be honest I think it's a healthy purge.
It probably is it probably is and I think my prediction since I love to make them in
the show apparently is that in a couple of years after some regulation has settled it'll
go it'll shake out like this you're going to have Bitcoin and maybe a couple of other
cryptos and those will be called digital assets and then all the junk is going to be crypto
and that's going to be the stuff that's just sort of like in this early stage that isn't
properly regulated and isn't ever going to be of any serious value and the stuff that
we take serious the culture will just shift to calling them digital assets they're digital
assets.
You could see like MTG arena like going to a crypto model right and then allowing like
easier car trading and stuff like that but I love it but me makes a lot of sense to me
but yeah I will promise they can solve all that problem without going to crypto sorry
but yeah that's just it right there's there's good I think that's there's going to have
to be a process of I guess people trying it and failing and then realize you know we could
just use a database and what the problem is in what case is the SQL query more resource
intensive and slower than putting this on the blockchain if I'm like literally doing
card trading or something like that and the answer is almost done or I can't think of
one so.
All right the golden dragon boosted in two days ago with a row of ducks two thousand
two hundred and twenty two sets I'm a duck D.U.K. duck loaded with talent because I'm
wary of anything that can use licensing against its users like Copilot it seems super bad
that an A.I. can just grift code from users to sell time to move to another get instance
perhaps no no I mean OK so that this is one one of my great pains in life is that I'm
not using GitHub because I have to do a bunch of manual crap that I wouldn't have to if
I was just fully on GitHub I keep trying it I keep coming back but I think during this
what I consider I think we'll be calling it like a winter for tech did we give it a name
or boy it sure feels like it is it's going to yeah heck winter I'm looking to cut cost
and I know they're not a sponsor anymore but D.O. you got a low those drop prices are killing
me especially the backups you know you know this whole Copilot thing I was on hacker news
and they have this GitHub Copilot search it's both a copilot both impressive but not nearly
as impressive it's like a Roomba right it sure it's like that was super cool but like
I don't know man I have cats and dogs and like the Roomba can't do the job by itself
it just can't that's Copilot and and actually I would say the Roomba is far more impressive
and far more confident than Copilot it's like this hand wringing this pearl clutching it's
just quite using it first before you say it's the end of open source and it's going to dominate
the world and Microsoft's going to all murder away it's just not going to happen I mean
it it's it's really like clippy dude it's clippy forget it's clippy for code that's
what it is as a man who keeps rewriting clippy and calling it Alice over and over again it's
clippy all right the golden dragon double boosted in with a nice message for you another
row of ducks double boost because you both are super awesome and this is becoming a
favorite weekly podcast amongst the few I listen to thanks golden dragon becoming well
you know he actually emailed in too because he you told him last week to DM you for some
Python but did I did I did yes but then he doesn't use Twitter you know they're they're
out there he did email I got him we got hooked up I got to respond to him again actually
look at you guys look at you guys Lima three boosted in with 4,720 sats three days ago
is why has it taken me so long to start listening to this podcast I listen to a number of other
JB shows which I love I'm a sys admin by trade but a coder by education maybe you could
throw a short segment into office hours to do a quick run through all the JB shows to
help spread the word and so you don't have to guess oh for the numbers 4,720 is because
4472 was my first episode based on the episode number keep it up that's clever you know we've
been doing the show for a while and so I think as a result it just doesn't come up much on
the other shows but we should try to mention him or I'm I really walk that line of try
not to do too many self plugs but also making sure people know it's out there I mean like
once a year you have me come on the Linux shows and I just troll people although now
I can't I'm one of these damn hippies now kpok kpok ppok is this dude wait can I help
kpok if you need help if you need help with the right of ascension against your evil Klingon
brothers I am here for you I will shave my head Picard style it totally does sound like
a Klingon name that's so great yeah so 473 sats three days ago he said this is a future
episode number club booze I'm donating sats to the next episode number thanks for the
weekly dose of code and related entertainment keep up the good work boys well thank you
that's a great that's a great idea we also we got a big old like across a couple of
boosts thank you boost from wine deer 20,100 sats damn dude yeah you know what he gets
I think he deserves the baller boost for that he's the baller of this episode he's our back
home baller he's our baller in these parts it's an SNL reference we also got a thousand
sats from LT guy five thanks everybody oh I remember that that's Tina Fey yeah it was
a it's a good the girl the girls are back from college right and they're like yeah and
their moms are spoiling them and stuff on this out of them it's it's a great skit it's
actually a pretty good video it's surprisingly good so there you go thank you everybody for
boosting in if you'd like to send us a boost you can get a new podcast app at new podcast
apps calm I've been using fountain FM and you do earn some sats in there with some of
those supported clips so I'll have a link in the show notes if you want to try that
out and there's also boost CLI and breeze both of which don't require switching podcast
apps who CLI is obviously a command-line client and breeze is a separate app that you get
at be our easy dot technology and you know we should think soon about maybe later this
week recording a special for our members because our coder QA crew is out there and it is time
for their coder Lee report it is it is time we should do it this week yeah maybe Thursday
for I'll chat with you after we we wrap up here but that's a great way to support the
show and you get an ad-free version of the show you get the coder Lee report little extra
bonus show and soon you'll have a second feed option for the live stream coder QA dot co
oh no I know watch out right mr. Dominic is there anywhere you want to send the people
ah you know what go to Dominic m.com I I might actually manage another blog post this week
because I've been putting torturing I mean I would say testing but uh I've been told
that uh apparently they didn't expect me to have a prohibition style party inappropriate
juggling at HP dev ones and now I see that uh Carl has new laptops for me to use his
coasters so I'm just very busy definitely definitely I I've also requested a purple
themed Thalia that doesn't seem to be in the offing so you know there is a very very special
edition Thalia I've heard I've seen it yeah there I wonder if they'll ever sell it because
you know I need a new OBS machine and wouldn't that be cool let me spend thousands of dollars
no way right no way that's why this I'm that's why this iMac Pro is still hitting here sitting
here it's literally for OBS cuz I keep going with doing that video thing we talk about
every few months and one I can't sell this damn computer for some reason no one wants
to buy an iMac it has an Intel but it's also like kind of the ideal production machine
for the level of like you know just twitch production I would be doing so yeah yeah it's
good enough it really is it's fine but then it's Mac and I'd really like to do it on Linux
but then I'm like do I want to spend tons of money on another Thalia or something and
the answer is no this is where I'm at right now this is where I'm at I got to figure all
this out because my OBS machine now that we're doing video streaming into Jupiter tube it's
barely hanging on yeah sure barely so you know we built it to do audio streaming right
so yep well once you add video everything just and I want to do video of like my so
I want to go like full like I'm learning from the 14 year old that like apparently they
have to see your face and a little square on the bottom of the screen oh yeah yeah and
you have to screen cap and you have to make sure you turn off notifications oh yeah because
that IMS should get in a lot of trouble yeah oh we know we do all right how is Leo Laporte
these days you know I think they're doing great over there I think they're doing just
fine I love Leo actually all right you can follow the show at Coder Radio show like you
can watch the video playback Jupiter tube if you want to do that and links to what we
talked about today thems are over at Coder dot show slash four seven three you'll find
our contact form over there send us in some emails if I've missed your email you probably
need to send in again there's that but we'd also love to have a good full mailbag a real
thick mailbag next week so go over to Coder dot show slash contact or send in a boost
with a new podcast app those are also a great part of the show and that's it oh I guess
I'll live we do the show live on Mondays at noon Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern so you can come
over and join us at JB live TV we also stream it over at Jupiter dot tube and then we got
the chat room going up there on the screens and you can interact with us in real time
and give us feedback right then there in the chat room suppose that's probably like that's
peak connectivity radio should have figured that one out so Monday noon Pacific 3 p.m.
Eastern for that if you'd like or just get the RSS feed and you get it Wednesdays when
Drew's all done making it nice and purty making it sound just a little bit better than we
normally do and by a little I mean a lot all right everybody thanks so much for tuning
this week's episode of the Coder radio program and we'll see you right back here next week.