This is Koto Radio, episode 344 for February 11th, 2019.
Welcome to Koto Radio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and its
related technologies. My name is Chris in the rainy, cold Texas area and joining us
every single week is our host in Florida, the man who navigates the swamps to be
here every single week is Mr. Dominic. Hello Mike. Misa here once again. Oh good,
good. But to make sure we offset all the jar jar, we have been joined by the third
pole of our stool and that is the one, the only, Wes Payne. Hello Wes. Hello and
don't worry I've got a lightsaber to deal with that jar jar problem. What do
you think of being the third leg of the stool, right? Because our stool doesn't
hold up properly without that third leg. I will say sometimes you guys are swaying
a little bit to and fro but sometimes that's fun. I don't know what
that could be caused by. It's good to be back. We wanted to try a
little three-way for one episode. We're just trying things out. Wes you have been
doing a killer job sitting in. Everybody writes in just says how much they hate
it. They're constantly going on about how awful of a job you do. That's how you
know you do something right, right? Everybody loves it. Everybody loves it
and we got some good feedback into the show so let's start out there. Email
comes in from Steve and it's about employment versus self-employment and
I'm sensing a theme here. He says I just have a comment regarding an episode a
few weeks back regarding being employee or working for oneself. There are
definitive benefits if you find the right employer and it looks like Linux
Academy is one for Chris. I decided to do what Chris did, accept employment. After
all I was struggling as a self-employed individual but this new employer started
to change my hours working till 7 or 9 p.m. and they also started to have me do
work that I was not hired to do but I continued forward since I appreciated
having a regular paycheck. But one morning we received a company-wide
notice. Our employer was concerned about how often people went to the bathroom.
Shortly after that we had to start asking permission to take a break, eat
lunch and so on. I finally had to give my resignation notice. I guess like a
marriage the challenge is finding the right mate or employer. Steve that's a
great email and so on the panel here Mike you're the self-employed one what
are your thoughts on this? So I have never heard of such a crazy like you
can sort of situation crazy that's that's pretty terrible I don't have a
lot of experience with the whole I get a paycheck every two weeks thing because I
was self-employed very young but I you know you know Chris tax and in West tax
seasons coming up and it's one of those it's that time of year when I start to
think what the hell is wrong with me? It's true. So however someone told me I
couldn't take a pee that would I can't even believe we're having this
conversation like I know isn't that it's not technically torture like it seems
like a huge waste of everyone's time that kind of micromanagement. That's like a
full-time job just approving potty breaks. I mean Chris come on you're a
big shot VP at a big Linux company now. It's true. If one of your employees got
up from his desk was like or your reports got up from his desk to the
men's room or the ladies room you wouldn't you know track that right like
that seems. Well I mean as Wes knows I did ask him to install that camera there
in his bathroom so we could just keep track of things. Yeah but it's been there
for months. Yeah I mean we just need baseline metrics Mike that's all just
baselines. I thought that was part of our health initiative now. Well that's for
that's why I have the analyzer in the urinal but that's for other reasons. You
know I wanted to jump ahead in our in our show notes here and maybe this would
be a good time to tackle this story about the psychological trap of
freelancing. Not that I'm now I'm not like mr. anti freelance anti independent
work I don't mean to come across that way. You're like a reformed alcoholic it's
terrible. A little bit I mean I I guess I would say that I feel better about it
now than I did at the time of the acquisition which I felt pretty good
that's why I went along with it but now having been here for a bit I do feel
better about it. There's um having having worked independently for about a decade
the reach you get as being part of a larger company that has more resources
is it says it's just at a whole other scale and I find myself having to really
combat like small thinking like how do we do things super hyper crazy by the
skin of our teeth cheap and how do we do something that a ten-person team does
with a four-person team like I have to break all of that way of thinking a
little bit because it limits what I can achieve and that's been a hard that's
been a hard shift but I think there's a bigger mindset that I developed as an
independent contractor or as a freelancer and I wonder if you suffer
from this too Mike and it's this it's this unbelievable amount of value that
you learn to attach to your time where now everything in life you're you're
you're measuring against how much time is that going to take how much time does
it take me to wash my car how much time does it take me to mow the lawn and that
becomes like this sick way of thinking about things because it sucks all the
joy out of life the audience doesn't know but you guys know I was just on a
brief four-day trip up north mostly business but I of course my family's
from there so I went to visit and we had a minor issue with a client project and
I just went into this I don't even know what to say like you stay yeah it was it
was it was more like when they Bruce Banner just freaks out and becomes the
Hulk and I was like sorry kid can't play sorry which is a board game I'm sure
most people are familiar with oh we all know sorry Mike yeah of course I have to
you know rewrite this doku instance because reasons right and I realized
something not only did it make no difference materially to TMB my my
company the client didn't even notice the problem right there was no material
difference between doing it on Saturday we're just letting it go until Monday
but I've gone into this and I this is why when you sent me this article I was
like damn and also I would love to after this jump back to the small thinking
thing yeah it's it freelancing should be the in the DSM it's a form of sickness
mm-hmm yeah there's actually been research that's what this article talks
about we'll have linked in the show notes that explains the psychology
behind this state of mind people who attach dollar signs to their time or
value time like money tend to be overwhelmingly less happy than those who
don't because they're non working hours suddenly seem less important quote-unquote
free time gets tainted with guilt because there's a cost associated with
it wow that's me that I am I have to I have to struggle to not have the
weekends be hell because I feel like I am wasting so much time around the house
if I'm not working and so much so that sometimes just to relieve my anxiety
I'll carve out a couple hours on Saturday to work even though I work all
day Sunday every week right six days a week on the exact opposite I work all
day Saturday but then I'm always looking to see can I hustle you know a few hours
like Sunday like after church or whatever and the thing is is that what
this article points out curious your thoughts on this West is we're seeing a
bigger shift in the economy where a lot of traditional salary jobs are going
more towards contract gigs and more and more people are becoming independent
contractors in a sense so it seems like this could become a larger issue yeah
you're right I mean contractors into playing a pretty big role at a lot of
organizations and there is sort of this thought that okay well if you can
convert money to time and with the salary you've already negotiated you're
kind of set until your next review period and you hope for a promotion and
and with freelance maybe you think yeah I could I could just work more but it's
already so difficult to actually carve out time for yourself and I think that
affects salaried people too right you might want to be pushing to finish a big
project and you might have the reverse problem I'm now guilting yourself about
not actually taking any time off from work yeah yeah that's true salaried
folks are not necessarily immune from this because now I mean it's crossed my
mind once or twice but this is just how I work it's now it's like okay if I work
six or seven days a week well it's not what I get paid for I get paid for five
days a week but that's just the way my job works but you want it and you want
to think about holistic outcomes right because we're not just there to turn out
parts on a factory line yeah you're trying to make real things yeah yeah and
it's a it's a process for what we make and it just takes time so the question
is like what do you do if you get trapped in this mindset and I've managed
to pull this trick on myself a couple of times but their research shows it
actually is really something you can do and that is if we tell ourselves that
leisure time is another means to achieve the goal or financial outcomes we're
striving for that can make us more likely to take the breaks that we need
and maybe even enjoy them more and be happier in general so you can if you can
convince yourself that there is a sense in a sense a monetary value or a brain
downtime value that makes you more productive ultimately if you can buy
into that which I believe is true then it makes a little bit easier to enjoy
your downtime it's a it's a process though it's like Mike was saying it's
something you always struggle with but you wanted to circle back to the small
versus big thinking Mike yes so I would love to learn more about how your
thinking has changed because I had some very long conversations when I was up in
New Jersey for my business regarding things we can do things our competitors
are doing and you know the reality of being super small and severely
financially constrained mm-hmm yeah so I think the biggest difference is in
hiring potential you know we're we're kicking around the show ideas like how
could we pull that off and then it takes like ten minutes of the conversation
before we go well I guess we could hire somebody to do that and like that's a
big mentality shift for us because having the resources to hire people at a
decent income with benefits and all of that was just not even something that
was possible for us but I'll tell you this like that the scale is is pretty
different really because I think I've told you this before it I think they
spend more easily easily in beverages and and lunches then we probably had as
an entire budget for Jupiter broadcasting and that's just there you
know Linux Academy is the largest online cloud training platform and there's they
are an institution now they have like 120 something hundred and twenty five
people working here now and so they're just at a totally different scale and
it's meant the biggest problem that we've run into is how do we do things at
a larger scale that make a difference and that are worth doing how do we do
something that maybe attracts a million people instead of five hundred thousand
people those kinds of things in it it's it's a little outside of my reach right
now because it's not an area I spent so much time so long in the trenches
getting by with if I spend money on something that means it's an area I
don't spend money in in another place and it may even mean it could ruin us if
it doesn't go well like there's all these decisions that had to be made let
alone even being able to hire people that I spent so much time in that mindset
that I have to I have to constantly catch myself and what I've been doing is
been looking at setting really large goals that try to make us re
adjust the lens in which we're looking at the problem so we we readdress the
problem in a new way of thinking right has to become the default position think
right about it instead of focusing on the small day-to-day stuff yeah yeah
West knows my struggles pretty well because it's something we talk a lot
about in our in our meetings you know we have we have ketchup meetings and
department meetings and stuff and we're trying to we're just still trying to as
a group trying to hammer this stuff out it's a it's a there are advantages to
being lean and small especially in efficiency in direction changing you
know this isn't working let's move being able to go with your instinct those
things are your strengths when you're small but customer support and internal
feature development and expansion and and growing and growing new shows just
are much more possible when you have a larger budget an example of that would
be the choose Linux show that we recently launched it just wasn't
possible before to have to have the time and the resources to pay an editor and
pay hosts and all that stuff it just we were maxed out without taking on
substantially more advertisers and so it took a different business model really I
think for us to change the game because the business we were in before was
advertising based podcasts of a niche market and now the business we're in is
a much larger online training business which just has a larger customer base
for one thing so I think part of it Mike is is mentality and part of it is just
the core business that we were in versus what we're in now our my job hasn't
changed much but the company I'm part of has interesting yeah yeah I'm sure
another piece of it is obviously capitalization right bigger company yeah
everything's just slightly larger or slightly yeah significantly larger do
you find that you're running up against limitations of the size of bad water
well I mean we had a little R&D project go south very recently so we run into
the problem of we have lots of interesting ideas on things we can do
and very little capital with which to do them right sure so we have to pick one
and if it doesn't work out that hobbles us for at least a quarter and that
doesn't even start to get into any potential like you know we do this for a
long time right I've had all kinds of crazy things like consulting client
files bankruptcy right you can't get paid like there's all all kind you know a
dispute client feels like something's not done but there's all kinds of things
that have happened over the years but the most painful one is actually when
you know we sit down we look at like we do this every year we sit down we look
at the year ahead we always have this fantasy of going towards a more
productized business and we see you know let's say five opportunities we pick one
try to work it out for you know a month or two and we realize we just don't have
the other the financial strength or the you know in some cases marketing know-how
to actually do it which becomes pretty you know there can be other means right
we didn't sometimes when things require hardware that can be tough yeah we
definitely feel it I mean I tend to think of things in terms of like revenue
against investment or investment against revenue and our biggest problem is
really we should pick a couple of these and try them out but we always every
year we have to pick one or two some do some don't and that's pretty it's a
pretty risky hand right it's like going to Atlantic City and just betting it all
on double zero and roulette yeah only if you don't win it's it's it's your job
plus everybody else working with you and repercussions are severe mm-hmm
probably tied into this too is how much identity especially in America we tend
to associate with our career so it's not even like that you just you know oh you
start a business and it didn't work out unless you had you just move on right
that was that was a lot of your life and thoughts and investments yeah yeah
really yeah I agree one way to always measure success is in number of laptops
and it seems that listener Emma that's what I'm calling her now because I'm
sure she listens she has some feedback for average system 76 customers not even
for Mike specifically Emma tweets out today Emma who is in charge of support
over at system 76 she's the happiness manager to put it technically and so
today is clean out your computer day hashtag keep your laptop fans of clear
of dust and debris and so system 76 asks what's your best computer cleaning tip
which Emma responds to the system 76 account to keep at Domenico away from
and make sure all beverages are in a separate room you're getting sick burned
by the system 76 staff in public now you realize that you know this is a this is
a gross gross misrepresentation I have never destroyed more than seven laptops
in the year yeah and a good portion of the more MacBooks to be fair you know
what and and honestly they wanted to go it was that's true that's true that's
true I mean there's part of the up it's part of the Mike's built-in
obsolescence obsolescence program right exactly Apple wishes I could destroy
more MacBooks for people just like kind of walk around oh there you go there you
go West Payne's kind of like the I'm somewhere in the middle right I don't I
don't go through his machines as fast as you do but I think I go through a
pretty high clip but West Payne you were rocking like one of the original
original XPS is for six or seven years or something yeah that's right is it
was it that long it did feel like 12 years yeah it's like that DS9 episode
with the O'Brien and he's in prison in his mind it was like that but with a
laptop I think it's just mostly like especially if I'm doing more development
stuff I I don't need very much you know like an electron app here or there a
chrome a chrome session and a terminal yeah now you know doing more doing more
stuff with with content creation it is nice to have a beefier Rick mm-hmm yeah
I think the one thing I the one somebody just tweeted me recently said hey do you
guys still like your Lenovo t480 oh yeah right and I said yes although I think at
this point I might be inclined to go high DPI however we do rely on a couple of
applications that don't have high DPI support so I don't know but that would
be the one thing I might change about the t480 as soon as I've got one of those
kernels and and maybe we do already but with the the recent changes so that
there's better high DPI support when you have to go log into an actual terminal
you know console on on your laptop when you have to fix something then I'll
switch yeah all right okay so and that'll probably be about another ten
machines or so yeah right I think so well Wes you found this great this great
article on css tricks comm on what hooks mean for view and I wanted you to share
what you found with the class today yeah okay well maybe we can start with like a
little quiz Mike have you do you use view are you react where do you fall in
the single page application framework camp I was originally in angular but
when it was angular JS back in the day I have done some view I you know I don't
have any current projects using any of these heavy frameworks the last one I
did use was view though but it was it was the least of major version back hmm
yeah okay well you know obviously in the in the JavaScript world everything has
to change at a lightning pace yeah and this is this is no different so you
might have seen some of the hubbub around hooks over in react so when I saw
this about view adding hooks as well I thought that was an interesting sort of
convergence of design and really I mean they talked about that right here in the
article that it is sort of you know what you what you end up with is a crossover
between react and view they use a lot of the same language the API is similar the
benefits are slightly different and that's where it gets interesting so the
idea of hooks it's a more functional way to do react and at its core I think
react is a pretty functional idea it's really like you've got a render function
and so you've got some state some data and then you've built this component
that takes that data and then produces produces your view that gets rendered
onto the page whatever that structure of divs and forms whatever you're building
right now the most common JavaScript API for all those react internals is pretty
at least somewhat object oriented there's a lot of classes involved you
might have higher-order components where you're passing state through or nesting
it or like a factory or something and it's just always felt at least to me
sort of like an impedance mismatch now not everyone thinks that and there's you
know so many users of that API but recently they added hooks and the basic
idea is just do this all with functions so you've got your you know you've got
your component and you have a hook and you basically say like I need a little
piece of state give me some state and that's it you call the function you get
your state and you can do this multiple times and then the react engine knows
that once that state changes it needs to rerender whatever component you've just
made that's how it gets to do all the fancy virtual dom diffing and all the
performance benefits it also means like one of the general
trends I think we've seen is trying to have more composition because we end up
with these really complicated components with multiple levels that that you want
to try to share as much stuff between so you don't have to keep reinventing it
but you want to do that in the same way where you're not constantly passing
state all around and have like ten arguments to your functions right that's
just not really tenable to do so so hooks are one way to do that now view
view doesn't really have that problem because it didn't have the same sort of
object-oriented API and they even already had stateless functional
components if you wanted them but they also used this idea of mixins and maybe
Mike can can tell us a little bit more about mixins if we want to get into that
and it just they just don't compose well so I thought what was neat is it is the
view camp had some of the same ideas probably were influenced by some of the
thoughts that the react camp had in terms of like this is just a nice way to
handle state in a way where you can compose and and combine elements and
components together with minimal fluff minimal just arbitrary nesting that you
kind of have to do and in a way that scales better and it's cleaner and then
mixins
well okay so I definitely see their case for it yeah so it's pretty new you can
go try it if you want we will have links and in the in the docks of course it's
just something to play with I do a lot of the Clojure script stuff and we've
kind of already had this style of approach we do we pray for just like
have some functions you have a little state past you it's passed into your
function somehow you track when that state changes yeah and you rerender the
thing now I don't know it's kind of controversial if if the Clojure script
communities kind of redo things and sort of like rebase on top of the hooks
mechanisms or keep the way that they've already done it now time will tell but
I think it's nice to see this this sort of trend of ideas something that I find
at least personally more pleasing to develop with find its way to the larger
JavaScript community okay so in the case of someone using a mixin in view the
hooks I see I'm completely unfamiliar with few hooks and so this is post
dating me right this is newer what what is the advantage of a hook over a
mixin other than mixins being kind of like sloppy right I get why they're not
great yeah so yeah oh cool no is it I'm just trying to conceptually is it if I'm
not using Clojure script right is it the key I just JavaScript just yeah
ECMA script JavaScript whatever will it like I personally don't like mixins
because I think they're frankly cause more problems than they solve assuming
you have a large enough scale of code right you have big enough code base yes
exactly right they're kind of like weird magic and they don't always make it
explicit where logic is coming right you don't know what the hell is happening
basically yeah so that's actually one of the main things that they talk about
here is that that you know folks really do do a lot of what what mixins do but
they make it explicit where logic is coming from so you have a little bit
more documentation and when you have to dive into a big code base that you
haven't touched for six months should be a little bit plainer about what's
actually happening how the data is flowing okay so on a like talk to me
like I'm five level the reason I might use hooks is because they are
effectively more maintainable or they solve the same problems as mixins but
are far more maintainable yeah more maintainable simpler and more
composable mmm very cool limitation on if I'm using TypeScript JavaScript
Clojure scripts Clojure script has one library now I think it's called the H X
that's that's using hooks otherwise reagent the main one already has a
somewhat somewhat similar thing where you basically just define a function
that returns a data structure and that defines your component view hooks are
available already with you with the view 2.x but they're still experimental so if
you're gonna play with them just just be aware of that I assume that the API
works regardless of TypeScript or just regular JavaScript no I might be crazy
because I like I said I mostly use angular now in fact I've been playing
with ionic 4 which is just a addition to angular but doesn't react have
something like this already yeah yeah so react head hooks first okay yeah and
they they've been in development for a while and then they kind of just
recently became generally available and people started really using them by the
time this show ends up on iTunes there'll be a new version yeah be
relevant anymore so you guys can just skip this chapter yeah nice good find
Wes I love it I appreciate the breakdown definitely
definitely out out of my paygrade but fascinating to learn about looks like
there's gonna be a whole bunch of federal funding for AI projects Mike so
you should use that use that small size of the mad bot or to a pivot into AI as
quick as possible yeah yeah I guess there's gonna be an executive order sign
that prioritizes federal funding for AI and will create resources for AI
research establish standards and more it seems like that could be that could be a
pretty big deal to legitimize the field of AI development I might be wrong that
seems like a big news story yeah this is this is a literally breaking news for me
so I have to take a look at it yeah yeah it developed while we were after we were
actually already connected in recording I just saw it go by on the feeds it's
been to me as just the way things happen not necessarily like enshrining it in
invalid validity but more like it's it's one more peg on the system as like oh
right I like the hipster tech companies started using it and you saw some real
results but then like okay finally like the slower moving cycles of government
money are coming out to actually fund this right which will build out the
industry I mean that kind of you can you can get a loss you can get a nice
healthy business that lives off of federal contracts and funding and it all
it may also lead to AI being used more in scientific research which could have
other kinds of benefits it could be a really big deal and I think that the
overall effect adds not legitimacy isn't the right word because it's not that
it's not a legitimate field right now but it feels like it sort of enshrines
it in like it's now a it's now a codified tier of the tech industry in
the States and yeah you're right like the stodgy the stodgy folks over there
in the government there yeah they're hip to it now too they're funding it's not
cool right and that will create a lot of business around it that'll create a lot
of money for development and resources around it which will build out that
industry base it'll draw more people into the field and it's all part of a
cycle if it's successful obviously but you know just anecdotally there is a lot
of requests for machine learning courses at Linux Academy coming in from students
it seems to be a field that people generally the trend seems to be if
people are beginning to look at that job field more then they start requesting
that training so there's sort of a correlation between people looking for
jobs in an industry and the amount of requests that Linux Academy gets for
that kind of training and machine learnings way up on the list and that
would mean that either there's at least a perception of and possibly really an
increase in people you know companies hiring for those roles or people
interested or thinking that companies will want more of those staff we should
come up with a way to use machine learning wouldn't that be cool like
something to analyze our podcasts like and analyze something about the podcasts
I don't know something oh yeah all right let's go with something so they
absolutely yeah I think so we'll just try to train a model that generates
podcasts when we really don't want to go that's what that's what I was thinking
of actually kind of along those lines today Nvidia announced that they are
open-sourcing their face rendering technology called style Gan or it's
style GAN and it creates these super realistic faces I mean I'll put a link
I'll drop a link in the chat room so you guys can see it it's there it's really
something like you would look at the pictures of these faces and you would
think that they are real human being faces it's it's beyond the candy
of them are like a little bit weird but most of them are just yeah you know
especially and it probably helps that there's enough diversity in the human
faces you know there's just a lot of true at least at least for how attuned
we are to looking at faces there's a lot of range yeah I mean in here they're
even putting babies faces there is like this this this Asian gals face here has
like like oily like like you know she's got like her super moisturized skin
coming back from the from the gym yeah it's just amazing and they're
open-sourcing it today hyper realistic face generator so it's coming it's
coming they part of what they're what part of what it really is that they're
open-sourcing is the data set because obviously that's what you need for
something like this right looks like a year the repo here seems that it's
Creative Commons licensed ah thank you thank you yeah it's something like
70,000 cropped and lined up headshots that it uses as source material to
generate the faces and that's part of what they're open-sourcing is that
70,000 high-quality PNG images Wow yeah that is that's a huge thing you don't
always see that you know it's like oh yeah we got this cool algorithm but
here's the data collecting all of your data to actually make a model and you
know it's not it's not a trivial thing to get 70,000 headshots that are
essentially all lined up the same way cropped the same way I mean it can be
automated to a point but somebody had to go take those pictures yeah take those
pictures filter through clean the day you said make sure that all of them are
actually worthy of inclusion and won't mess things up yeah and that you're like
allowed you know what are these sourced from there's probably that question too
yeah yeah you you assume Nvidia has that part taken care of right and then here
they also say this part of it they're releasing pre-trained models which are
stored as PKL files which are pronounced pickle yeah and they're just up on
Google Drive so you can go grab a pickle file off of Google Drive fresh hot
pickle up on Google Drive and generate your own fake face and use that as your
own your you know this would be a great way to be anonymous online but make it
look like you're a real person and then you combine this with deep fakes and you
can have a YouTube channel all the endless possibilities and you'd script
it all with Python and there is some Python results that we could talk about
today there is an annual Python developer survey that's officially
annual now because this is the second one they've ever done the Python
Software Foundation got together with jet brains and conducted an official
annual Python developers survey you guys want to hear about some of the things
they found interested at all and in the world of Python and just for some weeks
22 because there's there's some like some background is I mean pythons kind
of old right it came out in the 90s and it's had multiple faces it's been used
as a teaching language it has you know semi-prominent web development
framework and then now it's having something of a resurgence before AI yeah
yeah exactly which is which is exactly why it ended up in this part of the show
so 84% of Python users in the survey use Python as their main language by the way
also I did a little looking at their data set and their data set seems fairly
legit they have all of their source material posted up in the show which we
will link in the show notes the average respondents were 20 somethings about 39%
of them were 20 somethings 31% though so almost a third 30 to 39 and then 12% 40
to 49 with only 7% being 18 to 20 but so that's the age range and then
experience in the IT field 25% of them had 11 plus years in the IT field so
that's a little bit of the and it's all over the world that they surveyed
although most of the respondents are in India and the US 21% in the United
States and 16% in India with the United Kingdom coming in at 6% in Germany at 5%
China 4% France for Russia 3 Canada 3 alright so that's that's our that's our
base that we're getting our answers from an 84% of those people use Python as
their main language half of them that were surveyed also use JavaScript the
2018 stats were pretty similar to the 2017 results in this regard with one
significant difference in here being that there's a pretty noticeable jump
in bash and shell usage it's grown from 36% in 2017 to 45% in 2018 so Python
developers are using more bash what do you make of that mr. West what do you
think that is I wonder if that's just sort of the general trend in in
developers doing more operations work are they just having more access to
bash terminals they have to kind of muck around more right systems yeah I wonder
if it's that and then Mike do you think I'd be crazy to suggest that it's also
more of them are using Linux in general that's exactly what I was gonna say I
think the correlation between Python developers and Linux usage particularly
now that we're in this are we still in a Mac Exodus by the way can we still say
that or is that I don't know I think it's stabilized a little bit with the
Mac Mini and the iMac Pro I feel like it's sort of stabilized out a little
bit and Windows still isn't that great yeah yeah although Windows even with
all the great Linux options it has it's just more like the core OS hasn't really
gotten I think it's like they're all just there but they've all gotten a
little more competitive over the last 12 months even the Linux side so but yeah I
think they I think they still lost quite a bit I think it's still I've always
felt like the max exodus was going to be something that was just ongoing as
people got sort of bored of the sandbox of macOS or the limited laptop choices
or desktop choices that they might want to just look at an open source desktop
stack all together I've always kind of felt that but we'll see we'll see if
that continues to bear out it's Apple's game to lose really going on to your
point West 58% of respondents are using Python to do data analysis that's pretty
significant I wonder what data analysis counts as because that's kind of a
broad question right because you don't have to be a data scientist to do data
analysis it might just be like munging through a whole bunch of XML or JSON to
process in in some pipeline that you're using I bet just that's a lot of it I
bet you that's that is I bet you that is a lot of it 52% are using it for web
development 43% DevOps and pretty strong 38% are using it for machine
learning that's about a 7% jump not not a substantial but a 7% jump from 2017 I
think that's worth worth noting in its own I think it's worth noting that data
analysis has now become more popular than web development I think that's also
interesting and worth noting and it just shows you where pythons at right now and
it's not none of its bad or good it's just where it's at and it's someone it
speaks I think to some of the particular things that pythons done well which is
mostly accumulated a lot of accelerated libraries implemented in C or assembler
or Fortran and then linked against the main Python implementation that make it
good for that and so well Ruby or node or whatever else of the days can come up
and easily start being like look at this hot new web framework it's harder to be
like look at these neat highly optimized linear algebra implementations but there
is a bit of a story here isn't there about how Python has sort of kept up
with staying relevant and has managed to grow its user base and managed to find
newer and newer use cases and still grow out its ones that it has a stronghold in
that's okay so we we have to talk about then in this survey which is crazy and
it might it probably just speaks right we have to be aware of whatever
selection involved for the people who actually took the survey right 84% use in
Python 3 yeah that's crazy yeah that's a pretty big jump
or am I just old and no too many people who are stuck on Python 2 Python for
some time yeah it has but I still come across stuff on Python 2 all the time
and I think for a long time we were it was you know it was the joke it was like
how not to do a language transition because everyone was like well we
already built this giant code base in two and we don't trust the two to three
converter so like we don't need three and it took a while before like Django
fully worked with three or you know a lot of the big libraries but it seems
like now you know several or many of the larger tech companies that are based on
it have changed to Python 3 it's the default I think a lot of people are
using distros have switched so it's kind of a new Python 3 era so I think that's
kind of it because 38% of respondents get Python from the distribution repo or
homebrew or whatever like the OS provided installation method is 38% are
doing that and so it doesn't get updated until those get updated and if you're on
a maybe a rel from a you know release or two ago maybe that that could lead to
that leg a little bit in and getting people to switch over that could be part
of it and I think that's probably pretty astute there mr. pain you got also
figure there's cloud providers that play a role in this and if those cloud
providers are pushing the version forward on a reliable cadence then that
is also making developers push forward 55% of Python users who use cloud
platforms prefer AWS Google platform comes in second followed by heroku then
digital ocean and then Azure which I thought was interesting and then about a
third of the respondents said no cloud solutions for me I run it all on
premises and as you guessed Mike 69% of respondents are using Linux as their
primary development OS yeah 69% huge that's huge doesn't mean it's their only
OS but it means it's the OS they spend their time in developing Python Windows
came in 47% Mac OS 32% and BSD at 1% but hey it made it it hit 1% right it got
invited to the debate and that's what counts that's true it did show up on the
map I guess no surprise here pie charm is the most popular tool for Python
development with 35% share however a little disruption here a new
contender VS code has gone from 7% in 2017 to 16% in 2018 becoming the second
most popular editor for Python development VS code it's not surprised
sandwiched right in between the pie charm professional edition which is the
most popular and then the pie charm community edition yeah third most
popular and then boom VS code right there how about that it's more popular
than the pie charm community edition and then I mean you know we don't we talk
about it for a lot of other reasons but hey it's it's open source well not not I
don't know about technically the version that you download that's compiled for
you but in theory it's open source hmm I have nothing bad to say about VS code
really I think Microsoft nailed it so it doesn't really surprise me to see it's
growing and I I've been using a good name yeah yeah given LibreOffice a good
name actually the other day I loaded up LibreOffice writer for the first time
and you know a decade or whatever it's been and I'm like this is so
lightweight and quick it's using so little RAM my whole perspective on
LibreOffice writer has changed because of all the electron apps I use now so
there you have it things change okay just a couple more around us all out
then we're done here more than half of Python users are employed full-time 19
percent are students and 13% are self-employed or freelancing it's a
small group now Mike 13% the few the proud yep yeah so that's pretty much it
then we had the ages in here there's several I don't anything else jump out
at you about this survey Wes I get people a lot of people working as a
team a lot of people working independently that worked that jumped
out of me 48% work on a team and 48% work on their own with 4% work as an
external contractor or trainer 4% oh you know I also noticed that a lot of 25%
had 11 plus years in IT and that kind of makes sense I don't know a lot of the
people I know who are decent at Python who might not be quote-unquote Python
developers but use it anyway are people that just learned it as a scripting
language coming up in the 2000s mm-hmm yeah yeah I guess that kid that could
make it stick to that's why that's why Apple's always tried to get folks when
they're in a in a very impressionable stage with IT and computers to use max
now Google's doing oh yeah segment I also want one other thing before we go
is flask is doing great which is a more lightweight web play as Django's the big
one that's like rails but flask is is a nice little guy so it's nice to see you
doing well yeah that is cool you know I want to say to that I've noticed that
Python and the Python community at large do a really good job of reaching out to
kids in a way that I don't see a lot of other communities doing and so I think
that's pretty great too so I think a tip a hat as a parent I just got to say tip
of the hat to them for doing that I think that's really cool now Mike
wanted to get together here on on the Koda radio program and use the brain
trust of all of us to imagine near a future perhaps a far distant future
where the iOS App Store has been opened up for all or maybe even maybe even an
alternate reality just for the sake of conversation let's say that when the
Large Hadron Collider went online the universe split Donald Trump became
president and Apple opened up the App Store to everyone so we have two
parallel universes now yeah yeah so it's less opening to everyone and more even
if you kept the app review policies everyone gets the same financial deal
okay all right I can work with those rules yeah let's let's even stick with
the financial stuff first there's also it's the same it's like the same share
same cut and also like it's the same kind of crap then get you rejected but
it's just the standard is applied from like Joe's Joe's text app to Netflix
app yeah exactly so so the thing that really kind of triggered me on this of
course was the Facebook Google shenanigans from last week but the
response of particularly like ATP and some of the other more Apple focus
podcasts kind of being like well of course there are different deals for the
big boys versus the little guys which is like sure right like for a long time it
has been widely reported that Netflix hasn't has never paid 30% to Apple right
they've always get a sweetheart deal right and Microsoft doesn't either and
you know Facebook's app theoretically can be rejected but let's be honest
that's that doesn't really happen right well and I think that's why they're like
of course they're special deals applications like Instagram Facebook
Netflix Amazon Prime maybe they are they are value adds to the platform and
without those you don't have as strong of a platform as a Android
I would argue that Android has so many other deficiencies which send your hate
mail to Alan broadcasting calm that one I don't I don't think let's just take
the case of Facebook because Facebook and Instagram are the same company now
right if Apple told Facebook so-and-so feature violates our guidelines in the
Facebook app which Facebook really dump iOS those are the most valuable mobile
users in the world I would imagine they'd probably double down on their web
app well they're still a mobile Safari then right and they're gonna be pretty
plus you just can't spy very well with a web app so how's that gonna work right
well that's exactly what I'm getting at right like it it's weird I found myself
in a strange position because I I have in the past been very understanding if
not slightly annoyed at Apple's kind of draconian app review policies but the
financial stuff in particular you know Netflix getting a 15% I know it's not
called the App Store feed right the App Store cut I get why because they make
billions of dollars but don't you think that's going to put the next Netflix
right the you know West clip West flicks whatever at a fundamental
disadvantage because they're cut to the platform vendor who I mean I gotta be
honest I'm not even like I have lots of issues with this whole walled garden
thing now but they're they're cut is double when when you're smaller you're
not operating at very much efficiency at all compared to your larger competitor
so it feels to me the state we have now in trenches the larger more established
companies and actually Apple giving them better deals well there may be
legitimate reasons for it is a backdoor way for them to also stifle their their
potential competition right it's like this is kind of the same argument that
people were making for net neutrality in some ways that the big the big companies
have more leverage and little ones won't be able to start also just real quick
FYI West flicks is just great finish great British bake-off and Star Trek on
a continuous loop well I mean it you know we had that New York Times report
where Facebook Facebook employee basically said yeah our entire business
strategy is if we see us we track what you're doing on your phone if we see a
startup that's potentially going to compete with us we either buy them or
clone them right it's all a snap what they did to snapchat right they
implemented a bunch of their features and Instagram right yeah you I mean you
have to you right is that whatever quote-unquote dominant market position
right there they're doing it in a pretty I would argue pretty shady on it yeah
okay it's in your face kind of way too right and they because they're big they
somehow have this leverage with the platform vendor what if we went into to
Chris's alternate universe and Apple just said you know what we are the best
platform for making money on mobile in at least North America and Europe right
I can't speak to other places so here's the deal everybody gets the same deal
this is it this is the human interface guideline this is the app review rules
and it's 30% then after the first year is 15% if you're doing a subscription
which is the current policy no side deals no accommodations that's what it
is do you really believe that Netflix would drop their iPad app now Netflix I
would argue is in the best position to do a PWA because they're not that
interested in spying on you but like I would eat my hat if Facebook or
Instagram did right Google certainly wouldn't abandon the platform Microsoft
is so busy abandoning Windows right now that I doubt they'd abandon iOS or am I
insane I mean is this just like Mike going off the rails well it's a I think
it's a per case situation here so take Amazon here's a great case study when
they bought Comixology and when they bought audible they removed the ability
to buy books or comics within the app because of Apple's cut and said if you
want to buy in fact they weren't even very clear about it because Apple's
policies won't let you but you have to just suss out if you want to purchase
something you have to launch your web browser and go to their website and buy
it and so this has happened and been like this now for years years now so
there is some precedent for a large tech company to say hey we can make do
without you we're big enough we don't need you so I there it could happen so
this is the exact point so you actually set up the point perfectly now let's
say let's say Facebook created a competitor to Comixology and for
whatever weird reason Apple made a side deal with Facebook right uncle Tim and
a marquee boy got together and made a deal that Facebook's comic app would
only pay 10% and that comic app would have the convenience of selling through
the App Store through an app purchase their their you know issues and
subscriptions where Amazon's Comixology couldn't Amazon that is Apple putting
their finger on the scale right there at a material disadvantage and we haven't
even gotten into the fact that there's an editorial function of the App Store
and they could feature whoever they want true let me ask you this it seems like
it's it what we're really running up against is pressures on a model that
needs to be changed like the App Store has been around for eight or nine years
now and this has essentially been the model with the slight adjustment to
subscriptions recently but recently is like in the last two years like that's
what's recent I think what has to be looked at is the value the App Store
provides to the developer if they're hosting a bunch of game asset files and
they're streaming that using the Akamai CDN all around the world to people's
devices as levels load that's a that's a that's a 30% value definitely yeah
because you're hosting my files you're you're making all the back-end
infrastructure that's that's valuable however if I'm a streaming application
that is simply just loading a video player and then streaming the contents
from my server and I'm paying for the bandwidth and I'm paying for the video
hosting and I'm bringing the bulk of the value to the relationship then I think
it's inappropriate to ask for 30% of the revenue there needs to be a re-analysis
of the value that Apple brings versus the value that the app provider brings
sure and if Apple's hosting the majority of the infrastructure then they price it
that way if it's a streaming app and perhaps they could just make a broad
category streaming applications we only take a 10% cut I agree with that but
that's that's not exactly the argument here right because you have to compare
Apple to Apple's so pun intended right again I'm just saying I think that's the
way you fix this because you're right it does stifle it does stifle the little
the the smaller app developer but as a as a private business or I mean as a
business as a as a as a company that's supposed to make money Apple has every
right to do that but let's just say there was like JB book which was a
fledgling competitor to Facebook and you did the exact same thing that Facebook
did in this latest hubbub your dev account would have simply been deleted
we're talking about we're talking about last week's enterprise developer right
you would have no dev account your apps would have been pulled done you know and
put out of business I think I agree with that mm-hmm so that is Apple picking a
winner right that that's I mean I know I'm gonna sound very like because I do
believe that these app stores actually are in some I'm not a lawyer but in some
way they need to be regulated with an antitrust eye because basically while I
know Tim Cook personally doesn't like Zuckerberg if he did and him let's just
say you know for whatever reason he decided that Facebook was the one true
social network Apple could simply not allow any other social networks on their
platform they have that power they have the power to as they just did last week
allow one developer to violate and yes they did some PR slap on the wrist which
was nice but there was no real repercussions other than you know a
minor day and a half of chaos at Facebook headquarters the face of it
that's and Google and we're talking you're talking tens of thousands of
employees and contractors look at what they did to small developers right look
what they did to the developer of the dash app on Mac which was a a API
documentation and dev documentation macOS application who had a minor problem
with his account because he was from I don't know the exact I don't remember
the details but I remember I spoke to him he was basically he had a problem he
had to use a Eastern European card and Apple freaked out cuz they thought it was
fraud they just threw him out with no communication that would never happen to
Facebook right Facebook intentionally and overtly violated the policies and
got little more than a slap on the wrist now to play devil's advocate here
wouldn't the argument be on Facebook side well that's that's the that's the
reward we get for making our products so appealing to end users that they
demanded on the platform and and that's and Apple's Apple's defense is we we've
we worked business to business with an important quote-unquote partner of ours
on the App Store to make sure that we had a quick resolution to an application
that's really important to our users now I grant you Facebook's actual core app
was never at risk here but if we're talking about like the response of
closing someone's developer account which thus kicked them out of the App
Store as a result of that I don't think that was ever gonna happen to Facebook
because of those two pretty defensible positions and that's a really shitty
thing to say when you're an independent developer who's up against that but that
is the way these businesses work because of the demand of users so there's a
famous Greek quote right the weak suffer what they must which is basically what
you're saying so let's say if we had Chris book again by failing to be as big
and as important as powerful as Facebook you will be inherently disadvantaged by
what is supposed to be in quotes a neutral platform vendor
it would be we just don't have a lot of neutral platform vendors there's always
humans who are picking and choosing and making decisions and they're gonna
always have in other spaces there are rules right let's say you know I really
don't want a competitor to open next door to me right but I cannot get Sun
biz which is the Florida State Department's you know business
corporation registry of course to forbid the registration of another development
shop Apple can Apple can say hey you just can't be on the App Store true right
or you can't make this style of application right I was good I yeah I
was gonna say the web is the is the one true platform except one of the reasons
we switched our Jupiter broadcasting YouTube in bed videos back to YouTube
from our own hosted mp4 feeds is because several carriers out there are free
rating YouTube and I'm competing against free so if you watch a video on our
website it is going against your data if you watch it on YouTube it's free and
that we looked at that and went well people aren't watching because of that
so now we're embedding YouTube videos again and there's not really a neutral
platform right it's the exact same issue of I think what is it t-mobile likes
likes Netflix and Verizon likes YouTube right something weird like that yeah I
don't know I think it's crazy I think everything should be forced to be
neutral but again you can write Alan as you put a broadcasting calm I was gonna
I was gonna go to Linux but then really you have I mean correct me if you think
I'm wrong here West but even even Linux distributions aren't a neutral
distribution platform because you have the opinions of maintainers and and what
not that have to get the software in the distributions I don't really even think
Linux is like a truly neutral distribution platform yeah I mean it's
hard to know quite what neutral is I think at least there there's at least
more more rules and at least in some distributions if you want you could step
up and volunteer to maintain things and she'll be able to lobby for inclusion of
whatever software you wanted if you were gonna do that work and you just don't
have that option it's funny too that you haven't seen like I can see high you
know 30% or whatever when you're when you're starting off you're trying to
bootstrap but we all know how much cash Apple has right 30% is just quite the
it's quite the cut yeah the issue is that they have to drive services revenue
that's the only area of strong growth they have in that area that the market's
watching very closely and so any cuts they make in this area take from
services right I'm just like at one point to kind of sharpen my argument
here because I feel like it's not just the preferential treatment it's there is
a documented list of rules and the punishments are for you know I started
when I was development the apps were opened right or bright before it open
actually the punishments have been well documented over the years Facebook in
particular is is such a privileged place where they cannot only get preferential
treatment like you know call an Apple rep and get an answer they can actually
openly and unapologetically violate the rules and just you know simply get
probation for murder one basically which seems crazy to me that that would ever
be acceptable yeah I mean I I can't disagree with you and we didn't even get
to the conversation around the amount of control that Apple has and why I think
the real reason it was such a minor punishment is because if they had gone
any longer it would have started the conversation do we want to let Apple
have this much control over the internal functions of Google and Facebook and
other major corporations because the answer that is no and if they had put
the pressure on any longer you know that would have been the conversation the
only reason it didn't go that direction is because they pretty much tied things
up in a day and a half and problem solved but if it had gone to a week that
would have been that that would have been the focus of the conversation I mean
PWAs are getting better every year and I I wouldn't be surprised if in the future
these type of internal like order your burrito apps aren't just going to be
PWAs and and that's the world we're going to I agree now we have we have to
get going but mr. Payne you have any final thoughts you know I think that I
think that wraps it up I mean there's so much more to talk about here and we'll
we'll continue to see how this developments and how how this develops
and how Apple does Apple actually embrace PWAs does that gonna be a thing
is that I was just gonna see more on Android and in the Apple remains it's a
little pristine wall to garden I don't know now you probably just have to keep
tuning into coder radio maybe you could subscribe I don't know where to do that
hmm maybe coder dot show slash subscribe we'd love to know your thoughts to coder
dot show slash contact and links for everything we talked about today coder
dot show slash 344 I want to before we go I got a couple of picks and I do want
to say this we have to take all of this commentary on Apple about and the App
Store and put it in the frame of the fact that I'm sitting right here with an
iPad Pro right now so they're doing something right because one of the
reasons I bought the iPad Pro is because it has the best apps and there is that
reality and that aspect of the App Store is it it sells products so I don't I
don't like what they're doing and I think everything you brought up is a
valid point and I think they need to restructure based on the value they
bring developers but they are doing some things right speaking of right I think
you found a virtual machine in the web browser to learn see Wes this sounds
awful right oh oh I'm here I'm here and I did I did find that so I don't know
about you guys but especially like learning Linux I think it's a great example there's
a lot of interactivity you know you type something wrong into the shell and it
yells at you or maybe it deletes all your files but either way you feel bad
and you got that fast feedback and and as as Mike will probably a test it's the
same reason you do stuff in development like like test-driven developments
you've got all these tests you know quickly if you make a change did you
break anything did it actually work oh yeah it's harder to do that in C right
like in Python or Ruby or even Java these days you can pull up a REPL you
kind of play around get a feel for things see you got to go understand
install install a compiler figure out how it works there's no like handy
package manager or anything and then you have to go reason about this old
language that was designed to be like a slightly better assembler enter mini C
which is just like an in browser embedded C environment for learning so
it'll it'll show you what the what the what the compiled output looks like and
sort of disassemble it a little bit and clarify what what's going on and then it
shows you a big old hunk of memory and lets you step through it obviously you
know if you're a professional C developer you can do all of this with all
of your existing toolers all of your existing tooling GDB all sorts of stuff
but if you're just getting started learning C isn't always easy especially
if you're coming from like JavaScript I think this would be a great tool that's
a cool find it's open source to links to all that in the show notes as mentioned
earlier and you're on fire with the fines this week West nice job see geez
you are you are good you are a sleuther of the Internet it's like a sponge now
my sleuthing has gone in a weird direction this week I after that
conversation about Apple being a kingmaker I thought it would be good to
lighten the mood a little bit and I found a browser extension that I just
suggest you install for a day I wouldn't leave this on forever we maybe give it a
go it is a extension that adds a laugh track to any YouTube video on YouTube
I'll give you an example here and a richer country than it was when I
assumed office less than two years ago we are standing up for America and for
the American people and we are also standing up for the world so you can
play that along within a YouTube video and it makes everything better it's just
a nice it's a nice thing to have and you can find a link to that in the show
watch that's everything I think I'm gonna use it on Jupiter broadcasting
videos that's not a bad idea I should that's what I should have got a clip of
that would have been that have been really good mr. Payne thank you thank you
for not only filling in but sticking around now that we're gonna we're trying
this out let us know what you guys think I'm still traveling so there probably be
some more just a Wes and Mike episodes but when we get a chance from time to
time we're gonna try to do the three of us love to know your thoughts coder dot
show slash contact and I think I think I also registered coder radio dot show but
I don't remember anymore so coder dot show slash contact to let us know what
you think go get more Wes not only is the only Linux
unplugged program but he's also on the revamped tech snap joined by Jim Salter
from ours technica and very soon they have a deep dive coming up on network Q
OS which could be very handy when developing and testing software they
just did an episode deep dive on ZFS on Linux in the situation there and much
more so go check out tech snap dot systems for that thank you us for being
here mr. Dominic where do you want to send people this week I follow at
diminuco on Twitter boom easy peasy but I won't say lemon
squeezy Wes stay safe in the snow up there it's crazy 70 year snowstorm yeah
I think the easiest way is to just keep podcasting right that way you'll know
I'm yeah yeah we'll check in on you from time to time make sure you're live by
being subscribed all the show that's just a great idea Wes well thank you
everybody so much for being here I'm at Chris LAS on the Twitter the network is
at Jupiter signal and we'll see you back here next week