This is KOTORadio, episode 492 for November 14th, 2022.
Hey good buddy, welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show. It's taken a pragmatic look
at the art in the business of software development, and you guessed it, the world of technology.
My name is Chris, and joining us, collating the results from his survey, is the spreadsheet
master, Mr. Dominic.
What's up? I'm no Nate Silver, but I'll give it a go.
I think you might have a better shot. They've really been blowing it recently.
A couple rough cycles.
Date's probably been better than the rest for a little while, but you know what I mean.
It's been rough. It's been real rough. And I've been so busy. I've been implementing
the new NSA recommendations. I'm sure you have too. I'm sure you've been making a big
about face and implementing their new recommendations to use only memory-safe programming languages.
The NSA recommends that organizations use memory-safe languages when possible and bolster
protection through code-hardening defenses such as compiler options, tool options, and
operating system configurations.
With tips like this, we're clearly going to become the cyber leaders of the world, with
hot tips like this. How about this one? Configure your operating system. You needed the experts
at the NSA to tell us that. And use your compiler options. Another hot tip from the National
Spy Agency. It's really good. So I hope you've implemented that.
I know you're trolling a bit, but I actually think there are many, many people who read
this article and probably did get some good tips.
Yeah. These are the same people that keep getting surprised and shocked that ransomware
keeps logging up their data and they don't have backups to recover. Yeah. No, I agree.
They're out there. They are absolutely out there.
The register piece goes out of its way to talk about Rust. But I believe when I read
the agency's actual recommendation on the NSA.gov website, because I hang out there
all the time. I don't think they mentioned Rust. They mention other programming languages.
It's funny because of all the languages they list, Rust is actually probably the most hardcore
of the hardcore in terms of you must account for all your memory until you start throwing
around the unsafe keyword and then you can do whatever you want because, hey, hey, hey,
you know.
Here we go. On page three of their memory safe PDF that they put out, software memory
safety PDF that they put out. On page three, paragraph two, they finally do mention Rust
and they give a shout out to Swift as well. So, okay, I stand corrected.
Those noted Apple fanboys at the NSA.
What a weird thing. I mean, it's good. I think the reason why I keyed a little bit is because
I don't know, it feels about 20 years late. When the options are like, use Java or Go
or Rust, it's like, okay, we could have used this a long time ago. It just is, to me, I
think I have this complex of they can never do enough.
Okay, but what makes it late though?
Well, I mean, if this is stuff people should have known ages ago.
Okay, so the counter argument to this, right, and this ties into my still evolving 2FA debacle
that security equals effort plus money. So a reason that lots of things are written in,
let's say Python, is it is a fast language to develop it, right? This is like the whole
raison d'etre for Rails. You know, the biggest risk if you're a small organization is not
that Saudi Arabia is going to hack your stuff. It's that you're just going to run out of
money or go bankrupt or a bigger competitor who may or may not have any employees left
by the time we're done with the show is going to make a free version of what you're doing.
So I don't know. I mean, compiled languages that enforce strict memory safety? Yeah, they're
definitely like, there is a whole category. This is again, this is the Rust promise. There's
a whole category of error, stability errors, but also security errors that are basically
eliminated if you do things the right way in Rust. And that if is very big, because
if it's two in the morning, and you know that you can slam that unsafe keyboard in there
and get this goddamn thing shipped and not have to have the awkward zoom call the next
day, I'm pretty sure that nine out of 10 of us 99 out of eight times would just slam that
unsafe keyword in there. It's if you are the NSA and have infinite money, this is great
advice. And I think in general, looking at your compiler options is something that I
live in, I often don't do. But certainly that I see to me, that's actually the more interesting
piece of advice out of this. Because like, Oh, right, there are tweaks you can do in like
if you're doing iOS and Xcode to, you know, kind of harden up your application, right
your software. Same for you know, you know, LLVM, CPP, all that stuff.
Well, now we can say Rust has been recommended by the NSA.
It's system 76 and the NSA. That's where all the Rust people are.
All right. Well, you mentioned your two factor woes.
God damn it.
We got quite a bit of feedback on that. So I picked a few Christian wanted to recommend
a GPL three two factor tool says greetings. I'm listening to 491. And you're talking about
your two factor woes. One of my biggest fears was losing access to Google Authenticator,
especially when I had a device requiring maintenance and I didn't think about it in advance.
Then I learned about Aegis or A E G I S. It's a GPL three authenticator for Android that
supports multiple devices, multiple backups and exporting your vault. So if you lose your
device and want to enable another one, you can simply import your vault. No cloud required.
It saved me already once or twice. So A E G I S a GPL Android authenticator.
And then another tip that several people emailed in is they print out the QR codes and store
them in a vault or a secured spot. And then they just manually re import them via the
QR code when they when they need to. How is it going over there? Have you been bit by
anything in the time between now and last episode?
So I have been able to restore everything but my Instagram account.
Okay, which is insane because I log into Instagram via Facebook, but they they really just it's
funny how little integration actually happened there. Right, right. I would say that I'm
still of the opinion that all the workarounds that people have sent. It's just too much
for Uncle Tim or Uncle not Tim Cook, but you know, Uncle Ted to actually do. If the reality
for the normies is you break your phone.
And you're therefore you lose all your two FA if you haven't taken some highly like responsible
I'm a man in a brown suit with a fedora hat on steps to prevent that, then this is way
too far on the security versus convenience scale. Now, if you do in fact work as a Rust
developer for the NSA, well, then maybe that's the outcome you want, right? Like, but if
you're, you know, a dude who just wants to get his Instagram account back, and has a
surprisingly small amount of photos of himself on that account, making the override thing
very challenging, and they have no actual support that you can reach out to.
It's a, it's not worth it. And I don't think that two FA as implemented today is the best
solution. Now, I don't know what the right solution is, I would personally envision a
solution maybe integrated into the operating systems that uses biometrics, i.e. face IDs,
and you know, stuff like that. But I see the problem is I can write the objection to each
of these two, right? What's the problem with face ID? Well, if you don't know how to put
your phone on panic mode, anytime somebody possibly wearing blue can grab your phone,
put it towards your face, and now they've unlocked your phone, right forcibly.
This is one of those things where it would be very easy for me to just be like, haha,
I'm a jackass, and I shouldn't have messed this up, which is true-ish. But if we're supposed
to think about normal users, I think the bar is just way too high, right? There needs to
be some override. And yes, that's going to create security holes. Although, you know
what the biggest security hole is, and I kind of say kudos to Instagram for having absolutely
no support, and I know they have no support because they just keep firing people. It's
always like social engineering, right? You can social engineer your way to lots of things.
Who was that, Chris, that YouTuber, the Infosec YouTube lady, who she pretended to be the
wife of somebody who was in Iraq, and she was just trying to get some information on
some account, and then she had a recording, and she played the sound of a baby crying,
and she acted all flustered, and the guy on the phone finds out, okay, ma'am, I'm sorry,
I'll get you off the phone, and just read out the information.
I don't know about that, but that's brilliant. That kind of social engineering works.
This whole situation sucks. We haven't figured this out. You know, Microsoft and them.
To put a fine point on it, you're saying it's too hard for regular people to use two-factor
authentication. It works for a period of time, they get all in, they get all set up on it,
and then at some point they're going to get bit, and they're going to lose access to their
digital stuff.
Right. It expects too much of you up front. It's too unforgiving, right? You know, I tried
to explain it to a relative of mine, who I am encouraging to use some form of two-factor
authentication, and what I ended up telling him was, think about this. If you get married,
and up front you have to hash out every single argument you're ever going to have at the
engagement dinner, and if you ever encounter a disagreement that was not resolved, you
automatically get divorced. That's what losing your two-factor authentication is, right?
You have no way to handle an unforeseen circumstance. Trust me, if you go on Reddit and ask the
InfoSec people, how do I get around this, they're like, you should have been more responsible,
you freaking jackass.
Yeah, that is true. A lot of victim blaming.
Right, which is amazing because these same very people like to, never mind. Yeah.
I completely agree with you, and I think the same problem actually is also true about digital
photography, although not to the degree of severity, but it's a good example of you can
start to make decisions early on about pictures you're taking that you don't take too seriously,
and then a few years down the road, they're some of the most valuable possessions you
own and you've never really given a lot of thought to how you're storing those photos.
I just recently had to go redo all of that. Also, cryptocurrency self-custody is also
very prone to this problem. If you get it wrong, you lose your investment, quote unquote.
Hopefully you're not investing anything stupid, and on both ends, there needs to be a better
technological solution for end users.
I'll give you an example of something that starts to get there. Now, disclaimer, Bitwarden
is a sponsor on Linux Unplugged, but Bitwarden, it doesn't solve the problem completely because
you have to, you still have to present it to people and tell them to start using it,
but when you do their premium, they integrate the password management, the username generation,
the password generation in autofill, and the two-factor code generation for those services
all in one app.
So you can have your secure passwords, you can have your two-factor codes, and it syncs
across your devices, it's locally encrypted. It is what makes it possible for everyday
users to have some kind of access to this, but you have to give them the value proposition,
and you have to tell them about it and tell them to go do it.
Apple and Google and Microsoft are uniquely privileged because they can build this into
the platform, and they have, you know, Apple has a two-factor system built in, Microsoft
does as well, Google, we're all familiar with Google where we have to go launch another
Google app on another device and approve a login.
Because they have access to the platform and they can trigger actions on the local OS,
they can provide a level of two-factor authentication integration that third-party services and
apps just don't get access to. They just don't get access to those APIs, so they cannot create
a user experience sufficient enough. They're limited in what they can do, and the platform
providers meanwhile are doing like OS native dialogues and push services to get that two-factor
in front of you, and it just makes me think ultimately these platform owners are going
to be the ones that we use as all our centralized IDs because of this very problem, because
the normals will not be able to figure out how to do it on their own.
And then, and my last point on this, it perpetuates this problem that is getting worse and worse,
and we're on the right side of it, we benefit, anybody listening to this podcast benefits,
but there is truly a divide now between people who understand a little bit of technology
and people who have no idea. And the people who have no idea are getting preyed on by
all kinds of spyware and monitoring and digital monetization. Their data is getting looked
at, they're getting tracked constantly by their carrier, by their government, by corporation
X, Y, and Z data brokers. They don't know how to store their own currency if they needed
to. They don't know how to do two-factor authentication. They don't know about tools that enable more
privacy and more secure passwords and secure communications. There is this huge, what we
used to call back in the Bill Clinton days, your buddy, that there's this huge digital
divide now. Actual protection of your identity and your pictures, your memories, your services,
your finances, all of that is diminished if you do not understand this technology. And
the people who do understand it are in a better position to have more protection, to have
more advanced investments, to have superior means of communication that can't be monitored
and censored. The difference is really mattering now. And I feel like this two-factor stuff
and all these other digital trends are part of this broader thing that's developing. And
it's like, you're right, we could figure it out. You could learn from this and probably
never make this mistake again and probably go forward with the system that works for
you. But my aunts and uncles and my mom and dad who, you know, are familiar with computers,
I bet they don't use much two-factor authentication at all. And I don't know if I could even recommend
it to them because if they lost their phone, my mom's lost a phone before, they could be
completely SOL and then guess who they're calling and asking what to do and I won't
have an answer for them. It's gone.
Lino.com slash coder. Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account and it's
a great way to support the show while you're checking out the best way to run applications
for developers in the cloud. It's just the whole package. I mean, you got to be honest,
it starts with the pricing, 30% to 50% cheaper than the options out there that are not as
good. But you also have the support flexibility. However you like to take that support in,
self-research, contacting via phone, email, ticket, they're there 365, seven days a week,
real people that can help you. And then the performance. Like that really I think rounds
it all out. They got 11 data centers today, they're opening up another dozen throughout
next year. They have an application platform where you can just browse a bunch of really
popular useful tools from GitLab to Nextcloud to Minecraft servers. I mean, the list goes
on. They have database as a service as well. If running a database server isn't your strong
suite and you just want to focus on your application, they offer database as a service, multiple
different databases, MongoDB, they have Postgres and MySQL all available as a service. They
have really powerful rigs if you need something with a lot of compute or you need some GPU
for the weekend, they've got systems that can accommodate that. And they've got nanodes,
little itty-bitty systems that could run a single blog or an instance or a photo gallery,
something simple or maybe a demo site for a client. Maybe you want to use one of their
one-click deployments to do a file manager in the cloud so you can exchange files with
friends, family or a client. I mean, there's so many possibilities and so many opportunities
to learn and you can do it on a great platform that has a great company behind it and great
performance while supporting the show and getting a hundred dollars. That is a real
great deal, isn't it? It's kind of like I think the best deal in podcasting. So head
over to linode.com slash coder, grab that $100 and try it out. Linode makes the cloud
simple, affordable and accessible. Linode.com slash coder.
Just a little after we recorded last week,.NET 7 was released. Microsoft says thanks
to the open source.NET community, there have been 28,000 contributions and 8,900 different
contributors throughout the.NET 7 release cycle. And of course with this is the new
general availability of.NET Maui for.NET 7, which they're quite hyped about in the
performance category. And then going along with all of this was this quite nerdy, very
geeky.NET conference keynote and the link to them all. Microsoft just clearly decided
to let the geeks run this in a way, and I don't mean that in a bad way, in a really
good way. I think Microsoft is striking the balance between casual professional and letting
their genuine personalities of their developers show without going to like too low key where
it just feels like a crappy zoom call and without going all the way to a WWDC style
over the top production with crazy hair and transitions.
I don't think Frederiki can help the hair.
I'm sure they spend a few minutes in hair and makeup making it just right for every
scene.
He might consider buttoning his shirt every once in a while.
Yeah, they get them in just the right shirt too, there's that. So I watched a few of these,
like the state of the.NET Maui one, and I mean it's clearly scripted and planned, but
I think it feels the most audience appropriate out of all of the big corporate demonstrations.
It's not Saatchi up there, it's just the people who work on these teams presenting the video
videos. They're being a little geeky. They're clearly having fun. I liked it. I liked all
of it together as a presentation. The.NET 7 release, the keynote of the state of.NET,
then the state of Maui. It was really smooth.
Yeah, I mean it's a pretty good conference. I know we don't talk a ton about.NET on the
show. I will say they are still pushing Maui and I am doing something in Maui right now
for a customer. It is definitely more stable than it was before, so yay.
Yeah.
C-Sharp 11, which is part of this. If you like C-Sharp, which I actually think is pretty
good language, it's a lot of quality of life improvements. I don't know. See, I do wonder,
the ecosystem, how many people are really adopting the new stuff this quickly, right?
I get the impression it's much like the Java world where people stick to a long-term support
version for a while.
Yes, I do too.
Still, it's good, right? C-Sharp is adopting features at a rate that is mind-bending how
large that language is now, but you can do what you need to do. One thing I'm looking
at pretty intensely is Blazor, which is their kind of web view, inject C-Sharp, cross-platform,
from the WebAssembly solution. It's definitely not 100% ready for primetime in terms of Blazor
cross-platform, which is what I'm looking at, but I guess I would suggest that one,
the presentations are really good, like Chris says. Two, I kind of thought last year that
Maui was headed for the scrap heap, and I think they're actually going to pull it off.
They're doing the work of getting things more stable, not having weird things happen in
Android that don't happen on iOS, or vice versa. It's always going to be what it is
a cross-platform solution, and I still personally put a little more stock into web-based UIs,
but if I was a.NET hardcore person, I would probably be blogging about Maui, doing podcasts
about Maui, because it's pretty sexy.
I'd love to be a fly on the wall of the strategic planning when they're discussing what and
how and when they're going to invest in Maui. I wish they were a little more transparent
about that kind of stuff.
I think it's hard, right? We don't have to go through the history of pain that is Windows
Phone and Metro UI and all that stuff again, but Maui is in many ways the dream that they've
had for a long time. That keeps turning into a nightmare. There's a Bruce Springsteen song
about this called The River.
I think this time, it only took them a decade. They might pull it off. Now, I do a little
wonder if Maui is going to be one of those things that doesn't get huge adoption immediately,
because I think the target, I could be wrong, but I think the target for Maui is going to
be your dark matter developers who are in.NET shops, which is like your major corporations.
It is very focused on bringing your Windows development skills to these other platforms.
I don't see your small pseudo-Indie, whatever, mobile development company is really going
to Maui, unless they're already on Xamarin.Forms or something like that.
That's weird. I guess I'm feeling that it could be kind of like.NET as a whole, something
that the podcast world, the hipsters don't really talk about, but turns out to have tremendous
market share and line of business apps that nobody ever sees the light of day for because
line of business. So we'll see.
We need a name for that blind spot. What would you call that? That ability to just completely
miss an entire category? We call it dark matter, but there's a term for the blind spot that
causes the chattering class not to see it. It's interesting. I think you're right. I
think there's a huge use case out there that many people are missing.
Well, it's because you never see it, right? It doesn't go on the App Store. I'm sure if
we went to insert your Fortune 500, there are tablets running Xamarin.Forms and soon
to be Maui, right?
What do you think the most common use, just Maui specifically, would be if this thing
is successful, it gets traction? As an end user, what's my experience going to be with
it? Is it going to be an app that's cross-platform? Is it going to be a point of sales device?
Is it going to be an enterprise application that's on local devices, maybe some cheap
Android devices, some business owns?
All of the above. So I think it's going to be... And in a weird way, this is a self-inflicted
wound from Apple in their effort to make the enterprise certificates harder to abuse. They've
also made it more of a pain in the ass to do your line of business apps, native iOS.
So I'll give you an example, right? I live in an HOA community. The house is owned by
a big company we've talked about before. They sent a guy because apparently there's a mysterious
HOA violation that I don't know about. Guy comes with some cheap Android tablet. He's
got like an app. He's looking, he's like, there's nothing wrong. I said, I know. Good
talk, bro. But in there, he's going through and I can see it. I'm like, okay, yep. So
that's a view controller and it just pushed it. And I know that it's cross-platform because
while it's an Android device, very clearly the transitions, the animations are all the
old iOS push navigation transition. So that app could very well be like a Maui Xamarin
forms type thing. Or it could be like an Angular Ionic thing, like what I usually do. Think
about this. This company is huge. They have to have thousands of these guys just running
around checking on all the properties they own.
And it's a great example of an app they don't need in the App Store. They don't need that
in the Play Store.
I took my car to a Jiffy Loop. Guy right there, I'm sitting in the car as I work on it, rings
me up, not on a point of sale, on a tablet with a little thing hooked to it. And he's
doing the whole thing. He takes a picture of the mileage, takes a picture of the van
that had to replace a part, takes a picture of the old part, the new part. Right there,
bam, one tablet.
You see in restaurants all the time too?
Absolutely, yeah.
Yeah, and all of those are just basically internal corporate applications in most cases.
Sometimes they're a web app or-
That are actually making money, one presumes, right? They're actually productive, so.
You hope. You hope. You hope. But it's good to see.NET 7 land and Microsoft seems to
be going strong. I mean, nearly 9,000 different contributors to.NET 7. That's a legit open
source project. I mean, it's clearly governed by Microsoft, but it's a-
Well, Microsoft is clearly the core of the Linux community.
Right.
Oh, oh, oh.
I don't believe you.
All right. And also-
Inappropriate?
So, we thought this was coming, and unfortunately it did land just a little bit after we published
last week. Meta announced they're laying off more than 11,000 employees.
Damn.
About 13% of their staff.
Woo, Nelly.
And Zuckerberg says he's not ruling out further layoffs. That's a hard pivot. That's a- man.
And then, this morning, as the stream went live for Coda Radio, Amazon announced they
would lay off approximately 10,000 employees this week.
So that's your backyard. You think it's going to affect the local economy?
I don't know, because the Meta one actually had some significant Seattle layoffs as well.
So, you know, combined, that's 20,000, 21,000, 22,000 people that are going to be looking
for tech work. That's going to change things.
Well, and Apple, not to be outdone, but being much more subtle, as Uncle Tim is, are going
to, quote, be very deliberate in their hiring.
Yeah. And again, he says specifically because of economic uncertainty. You know, Amazon
lost a trillion dollars in value since their new chief executive took over.
I don't think that's his fault. It's just the timing.
No, but the pressure is there to signal to investors. This is what I said weeks ago,
is these tech companies, these leadership tech companies, these lead tech companies,
are going to make some of the most dramatic changes the quickest to signal that they recognize
that they need to be all about value. And they're going to set the trend for all a tech.
That's how it always works with these big five. And that's what's happening right now.
It's happening in this last couple of weeks. We're seeing it play out. It's brutal. You
know, there's going to be listeners that are going to be hit by this. And so, I mean, that's
why we've been talking about it, you know, is to prepare people.
Yeah, it's honestly, it's happening much faster than I think I, for one, would have anticipated.
The meta stuff is kind of like Mark Zuckerberg is on some bender called the Metaverse, right?
Horizons, whatever they call it.
Yeah, what's called the Facebook brand has been burned to the ground. And he's got to
build the next thing.
No, I mean, I mean, the fact that he's burnt more money on trying to make the Metaverse
happen. It's kind of insane. I forgot. I don't remember the figure, but it's billions, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Like 20 something.
Yeah, the Amazon thing seems supernatural and like, like very natural in that I think
this Christmas year, we're going to be reading stuff in the journal and Bloomberg about how
holiday spending is dramatically down from, you know, the last couple years.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, right. It's a consumption overall is going to be lessened. Apple, I
think we talked about it a couple weeks ago, has cut productions of their brand new flagship
of iPhones, because nobody's buying them.
Yeah.
Other than people who break their phone, like me.
Yeah, we're idiots like me on the subscription plan.
Right. Well, you're their best friend right now. You're, you're, you're their bestie.
I don't know. I think I'm kind of hoping that this is like a, the dinosaurs take a hit thing.
And we allow the mammals to rise, i.e. people who actually charge for software. Just something
I'm dreaming about. But it's very possible that this is part of just a cyclical decline
and we're all going to suffer together.
I think the ruthless are going to survive. I know that people aren't going to like hearing
this, but this has got to be part of the reason why Elon's going through Twitter like a wrecking
ball.
I still stand with my conspiracy theory. He was super drunk when he said he'd buy it.
He was super drunk when he sent the letter to them buying it. And now he just regrets
it.
Right. And yeah, well, he just spent $44 billion on something that's not worth $44 billion.
And he wants to turn that thing around. And I would imagine if you buy a company like
that, your first 90 days are going to be the most important and you're going to have investors
breathing down your neck. He knows it also is putting Tesla at great risk. So he's got
to move quick and he's moving like a maniac as a result. He's only listening to people
in his peer group. He's not listening to staff. He's only going to listen to other famous
people at this point. And he's just going crazy. Like you just notice it. Like people
say this is a horrible idea and Elon just steamrolls them. And then a celebrity tweets
back at him and says, hey, man, maybe you should rethink this. And he says, OK, all
right, cool. It's not $20. We'll do $8. What do you think of that? You like that that better?
And then that's what they do. They do $8. It's it's wild. You're just watching like
you're watching the man's process go down in public. And it's got a lot of people uncomfortable.
The other thing I realized, too, is a good percentage. Maybe the majority of people are
just really freaked out by chaos in general. So when anybody injects chaos, they immediately
respond badly to it. But to me, it seems like Twitter was horribly broken. It's a dumpster
fire that causes harm. I've been told that many times. And so if Elon were to actually
destroy it, then that would reduce overall net harm in the world.
Chris is like, let it burn, baby. Yeah, let it burn. And if he and perhaps he makes something
out of it. So, OK, so my problem in this is apparently I have no morals. I just look at
the business problem of Twitter was never worth $44 billion in reality. Right. He walked
in arguably 20 to 30 billion in the hole. Right. A paper loss. Yep. How are you going
to make that kind of money when your product is Twitter? I sort of feel like this is like
a Greek tragedy waiting to happen. And I will admit that I am super addicted to Twitter.
I keep trying to to wean myself a little bit. But I'm paying the eight bucks a month because
I know I got some crap for that. Oh, are you? I haven't done that. I am. Well, for the simple
reason again, it's just a business choice. Do you know how much I've paid for ads on
Facebook, Twitter, other places in the past? Sure. Yeah. So even if it does like gets me
one or two meetings to like try to do an Alice sale or something. Eight dollars a month.
This might be the most affordable marketing campaign. In fact, no, this is the most affordable
marketing campaign I've ever tried to run. And if it doesn't work, I just stop paying
it. Right. It's it's really like to me, it's kind of silly not to try, given that you really
can't do anything with digital advertising below a couple thousand dollars that if you
want it to be effective. So the other thing that has worked for me is podcast ads. And
I often will buy them or YouTube or ads because the problem there is you need to usually make
a video which can be quite expensive for a good one. So eight bucks a month, not a lot
of money. Good for me if it works. Actually good for me even if it doesn't because I just
lose eight bucks a month right for a little while. Not going to get you $30 billion though.
That's just not enough money. And I, I, I will say, like, I do not share the doom and
gloom about, you know, like Elon's evil or the political crap. But Twitter has become
like weird recently. And I when I say weird, I mean, like a little more unstable for me.
And I mean, I mean, technically unstable, right? Like slower, whatever. And I don't
know how he plans to, you're not going to make up $20 billion by getting the customers
to pay at this point. The biggest the people who spend drunk money on advertising are the
auto manufacturers who you are their direct competitor. So I doubt they're eager to write
you a check. And you kind of destabilized your core business, which is Tesla. Because
you got mad at who I think is probably one of the best CEOs of our generation agarwal
because he literally did nothing. It is going to make $312 million, which let me tell you,
he is going to get that money. Galloway has a good thing about this about firing people
for cause I have a very similar story. I had a guy send a customer neo Nazi propaganda
because he got mad at him and he got loaded and he did that. I fired the kid for cause
he took me to court I had to pay the New Jersey. Stupid labor court because they're all you
know, geez, let's just say there's not a lot of elephant judges there. They they don't
give a you pay pay the unemployment no matter what. So agarwal there's no like even legitimate
cause depending on where you are and in the Soviet Republic of California, you're paying.
So no offense to California. But it's just something I think you're right though in Texas
he wouldn't have to pay right in Florida never pay right it's just you have to understand
that he's crazy like he he's not done losing money on this. No, no, he's going to keep
going. Yeah, I would probably be a much mentally healthier person if Twitter kind of just like
went away. Clearly one of the worst mistakes in history. He claims he's working 70 hour
to 80 hour work weeks. I don't know. I I think if you if you think about what's motivating
think if you just if you just solve for what's the fastest way to do something and solve
it. And I think when it comes to these technical breakages that people are noticing, I'm not
saying it's the right thing to do, but I think his whole attitude is, oh, let's get and find
out. Let's just find out around and find out. Let's just see what happens. And when it breaks,
it breaks and we'll fix it. Then I'll bring in somebody who knows how to fix it and they'll
solve for it. I saw him on Twitter. I think it was yesterday morning or this morning talking
about, oh, yeah, sorry, that was down. The guy that wrote this just, you know, did a
horrible job. And then, of course, the developer who wrote it chimes in on the thread. Yeah,
I saw that the Android app was like, what are you talking about, idiot? Oh, my God.
It's so embarrassing. But that's to me symptomatic. You know, it's more embarrassing firing someone
and then having to call them back to rehire them because you realize you shouldn't. Yeah,
yeah, he's moving fast, breaking things. And, you know, there's there's a bit of only Elon
Musk could do this because because he's rich and because of the crew around him. You know,
when you're in his presence, there's people around him who are captured by him. You know
what I mean? They are there to work for him and they see things the way he sees things
and they are there to enable him. And so he is surrounded by teams of people who are there
to enable him. He is profoundly rich. So he truly has f**k you money. And he can kind
of get away with stuff. He can kind of become this job in archetypal character, you know,
where he is totally just coming in like a wrecking ball and tearing everything up in
the name of trying to make it work and fix it and make it better. And I think where the
jury is out is he could completely burn and spin out completely wreck Twitter, leave it
a dying husk and then somebody else awful comes around and snatches it up. Or he flushes
out all of the entitled employees who were slowing things down and making the place a
worse place to work. And he comes up with a core product that while it has some technical
issues in about three months, things are turned around and it's looking pretty good. It's
possible.
Is it $30 billion possible?
Honestly, it seems like an easier problem than landing hundreds of rockets on a platform
that's floating in an ocean that has wind and waves. And I mean, it seems like a simpler
problem than what SpaceX is solving. And he managed to put a team together that could
do that. And Starlink too. Like it all seems like actually out of all of his problems,
out of all of his companies, Twitter actually seems like the simplest because it's truly
just a staffing problem.
I will concede that if he pulls this off, this is like, wow, amazing. Elon's right again.
Gee, like never question him again, right? Invest with him every time.
But he'll never, all the people that are railing him now will never change their tune. They'll
never give him credit for it.
This is the problem, to pull this off, right? It's a consumer product effectively. You need
positive press, which I don't know if you've noticed, not happening.
True, true.
The people who work for you, you actually do need good engineers and they need to not
all hate you. So that's, I would say-
Yep, you got to have a team that's bought in.
A plurality of them don't like you. You made a lot of weird promises that while on some
level people could agree with about censorship and stuff like that, are anathema to advertisers
right now. So there's one revenue stream down and they piss off the press, who you absolutely
are going to need.
I'll put it to you this way. If he wasn't Elon, the way Twitter would die is, okay,
let's just say somewhat right-wingy guy, let's just say Mike Dominic buys Twitter, right?
You know how they kill it? They just don't cover it, right? No traction. You just go
away.
It doesn't matter. Yeah.
Right.
They make it irrelevant.
His kind of sort of crazy persona is helping him, but at some point you need to generate
the revenue and SpaceX, thank you Defense Department and US government. Tesla, literally
thanks Obama, right? Lots of subsidies there, a lot of help. People are cheering for you.
You're being hailed as a hero, a climate change warrior. In this case, he's a villain and
those same forces that propelled him are actively rooting for him to fail and causing him, like
they're not just rooting, they're in the game.
Yeah. I'd say they're successful so far. You're right. And the other reason why I think you're
right is if you go back to the premise, this whole thing was a lark. It was a intoxicated
tweet that he backed himself into a corner and then he got in a fight with the CEO and
he had to take it all the way. And now he's stuck with the serious problem and he's just
going to continue to behave erratically. The consequences of failure seem pretty dramatic
since Tesla is the most successful EV company. Starlink could change internet for all kinds
of people like myself. There's like a lot of consequences to him screwing this up and
it is going to be the process, is going to be in front of all of us.
It's literally going to happen on Twitter, right?
It's a fiat world, my friend.
Tailscale.com slash coder. That's where you go to try it for free for up to 20 devices
and support the show. Tailscale is a zero-config VPN. You'll get it up and going in minutes.
It manages your firewall rules. It takes care of your NAT situation. Devices connect directly
to each other in a mesh flat network using WireGuard's noise protocol. It builds you
the best VPN in the biz and it's so smart about how it routes its traffic too. I think
you're going to be blown away by that. Even if your different devices are separated by
firewalls and subnets, TailScale just works. Everything looks like it's on a flat network.
I was really grateful for TailScale recently when we had a power outage. Bunch of devices
came back up that were using dynamic IPs that I'd forgotten about. So I did know the IPs
of a couple of my systems, but their TailScale IP stayed the same.
So I just connected to them over TailScale and then figured out what the IP address was
for the local LAN. And again, like I was saying, TailScale is real smart. It routes that traffic
over the LAN. It doesn't have to go out to the internet through like some sort of old
school tunnel. It figures out where it's supposed to go and it protects that traffic with WireGuard.
Devices connect directly to each other after you sign in through your existing identity
provider. So whatever you're already comfortable with. If you want to enforce multi-factor
authentication there, you can. If you're using it in a work setting and you want to be able
to deauthorize employees, you can. It's so great. And TailScale VPNs are always on, on
every OS I always use, so it's always there. They've got a GUI based ACL editor, great
DNS features, and it's just dead simple to use. I use TailScale every day. You're going
to love it. So go try it for yourself for free up to 20 machines at tailscale.com slash
coder.
So in today's version of Never Trust the Tech Press, whenever they're covering anything,
the collapse of FTX and Sam Bankman fraud is quite the headline right now. It's what
all the other tech stuff is talking about. But there's one angle that I thought the coder
audience should be aware of just so they know how this stuff works in the future so they
can sniff these things out. It turns out, Vox, I know Mr. Dominic's a big fan over there
of Vox.
I like the verse, yeah.
Vox took direct money from SBF to basically write puff pieces about what a great generous
billionaire he was. They wrote a whole spiel on him. They basically wrote propaganda for
the scammer who was stealing from people and embezzling money and investing it and sending
money to politicians. It turns out he was also just paying Vox Media to just write positively
about him, about him personally, and I'm sure about FTX as a result.
And I think you have to understand, I'll put a link to the thread in the show notes. I
think you got to understand how this stuff works. And this thread kind of reveals, it
pulls that curtain back a little bit. And I know this to be true. We got three emails
this week offering to pay us to bring somebody on the show and talk about them like they're
an expert and a pro. Three of them this week, just this week.
So I thought with all of this, if you're interested at all with all this FTX crap going down,
I'll put a link to that in the show notes. You can go read it for yourself. There's just,
I think, a real revealing that happens there. And the whole thing is sickening, I have to
be honest. I guess I'm glad to see him caught.
You know the other crazy thing about that? It was like a house of 10 of them, a 30 million
dollar mansion in the Bahamas. And they were all sleeping together, living in this house,
embezzling money between their companies. It was all out there in front of the press,
all of it. All available, all of their family connections, everything was there. But it
just didn't get reported on. And instead Fortune magazine ran a piece back in September with
SBF on the cover saying that he was the next Warren Buffett. This guy who turns out to
be a total scammer and basically issuing paper money. They had billions and billions and
billions and billions in liabilities and a couple million in actual funds. That was the
peak example of tech and financing just getting absolutely out of control.
So, do you remember the tech press of the early aughts? If you want to go really hardcore,
some of the quote featured stories. This is pretty common, right?
Yeah, it's probably been an issue in tech forever, I would imagine.
For a long time, right? Or how about Apple was really good at doing this, although they
didn't pay people. But like Access Journalism, they only talk to people they like that say
nice things about them, which makes a lot of sense. I mean, Fox did disclose this. I'm
not necessarily here to defend them. I am a fan of their work, especially The Verge.
But I will say that it's... So I don't know anything about SBF. We've talked about it
before. I'm not super into the crypto stuff. The thing that's caught my eye is the lack
of actual like tech reporting going on. And I think we talked about this privately, right?
They've really... And I can only really speak about The Verge because that's the one I follow
the most. They've really leaned into this like, these are media company thing. And it
feels a little weird. Now, I tend to believe, but I could be wrong, that there are interesting
tech companies being founded that nobody hears about and interesting devices being built.
Software applications being built, stuff like that. And they're somehow not getting, in
my eyes, as much oxygen as they used to. I don't know that that might be unfair.
I completely agree though.
Well, I just look at the front page and it's like four Twitter stories, right?
Yeah.
And I get it. Elon Musk says crazy crap and that's easy clickbait and it is a business.
But we've talked about this with events too. I kind of feel the tech press is like... The
press is in capital letters in bold and tech is like small size font, lowercase italics.
I do believe there must be innovation going on somewhere. Maybe it's not here, right?
Maybe there's some kid in Shanghai doing it. Maybe there's some awesome Indian startup
that we should be hearing about or some biotech invention in Oslo. It doesn't necessarily
need to be Silicon Valley, but it's just, I don't know. I know that's not the story
you were going with. I just...
No, I think you're right. You're right. You zoom out and I see exactly what you're seeing.
I trace it back to VC funding. I trace it back to VC funding, networking.
Wouldn't the VCs want their stuff being covered?
Yeah, but it's all a game, right? Certain VC firms have a lot of credibility and a
lot of brand recognition. So if you're backed by one of those, then all of a sudden the
tech press is just more likely to cover you. And when they talk about you, they'll write
that as something that gives your project or your company authority. You've noticed
this, right? It's like these certain luxury brand VC companies, when they invest in you
like Sequoia, who also invested in FTX, when they invest in you, it's a big deal.
So okay. So that Springboard documentary that Vox did, I think it's on YouTube. It's on
YouTube about the Palm OS and kind of that first generation of what we now call smartphone,
what we used to call PDAs basically, that didn't take off. That was like old Vox, right?
Old The Verge. Really good. They talked to the principals. They talked to engineers.
They talked to designers. It was a refreshing blast of the past. I mean, even the new homepage
looks like Twitter, which is interesting.
Well, before we move off, I want to read something. This is from Sequoia's website. They were
so proud of this that they actually had this publicly posted on their website as an example
of how hip they are. This is why they decided to invest in FTX. They write, that's when
SPF told Sequoia about the so-called super app. Quote, I want FTX to be the place where
you can do anything you want with your next dollar. You can buy Bitcoin. You can send
money in whatever currency to any friend, anywhere in the world. You can buy a banana.
You can do anything you want with your money from inside FTX.
And then it goes on to say, suddenly the chat window on Sequoia's side of the Zoom lights
up with partners freaking out. In all caps, I love this founder, typed one partner. I'm
a 10 out of 10, pinged another. Yes, with three exclamation marks, exclaimed a third.
What Sequoia was reacting to was the scale of SPF's vision. It wasn't a story about
how we might use FinTech in the future or crypto or a new kind of bank even. It was
a vision about the future of money itself with a total addressable market of every person
in the entire planet. This is the hubris.
Do you think they actually believe that though? See, I think that's just marketing bull.
Well, then it turns out that it was discovered that during that entire meeting, SPF was also
playing League of Legends and they thought that was so great. Oh my God, he's so brilliant.
He can pitch us, which was a three sentence pitch about basically he wants to turn FTX
into how you spend your next dollar. He can pitch us while playing a video game. He must
be a genius.
I hate myself so much right now.
I know. They write, actually, this is actually what they say. Not only that, Aurora says,
but League of Legends is kind of a multiplayer online battle arena video game and they explain
why it's really hard and you got to do gang killings. She says, I was watching over SPF's
shoulder and he answered that final question from Sequoia like, yeah, and this guy is in
there playing this game. It's amazing. And then they write that he must be a genius.
We have to figure out how to work with him. He has clear purpose and well understood deliverables.
That's a powerful combination they write. All he said was, we want to be able to spend
your next dollar and they were throwing money at this guy.
If it was Dota, would they have been less impressed? I'm just saying.
There you go. So that is the state of VC and finances and tech and this is the kind of
crap that it leads to.
Okay, so the funnier part of the story to me is if you look at this guy, like just take
a look, knowing nothing about the business, he is the young Mark Zuckerberg mold. He literally
is the stereotype. Went to MIT, physically looks like a Zuckerberg clone, right? Different
hair, but you know, same. Like so much for diversity and inclusion, right guys? We would
just want the rich little white kid who went to MIT.
He played this character well, you know, because he'd wear a hoodie or a t-shirt.
My hat's off to him. Good job.
He pretended like he only drove a Toyota Corolla and that was like the point of when he drives
a Corolla. Of course, it turns out he also has like a garage full of very high-end sports
cars. He lives in a $30 million mansion.
Well, that's part of the character, right? You have to pretend like you actually live
to code and only care about the technology and have this great vision.
And his whole thing was something about just being ultimately altruistic. Like their goal
as a company, his company goal for FTX was, is to make as much money as possible so they
could do as much good in the world as possible. And that's why they were paying off Vox and
others to create this bulls**t image about the most generous billionaire in the world.
And it was all fed into this whole hype image. And the idea was to basically make this guy
the face of the crypto industry. There's reports that he was working with the SEC to do that.
And who knows, man? But it's just a very gross situation. And a lot of people got wiped out
as a result.
And they're playing around with their own stupid crappy token, paper money. And they
used their paper money as collateral. And their collateral was based on their customer
deposits. And when their customers did a bank run after their balance sheet was leaked,
their collateral became worth nothing. And so all of their loans got basically margin
called because the collateral wasn't worth enough anymore and FTX just started collapsing.
And then they suspended withdrawals. Then customers couldn't get their funds out. And
then a few days after that, clearly somebody internally had a backdoor. And they drained
$600 million out of customer accounts and stole it.
It's amazing how everything meant to replace the banking system turns out to be like a
really s**tty 1800s version of the banking system.
Well, I think the red flag is anytime they're screwing around with their own currency, their
own token, that's a red flag. That's an immediate no. Don't do it.
Wait, wait, wait, wait. You don't want mad botter token?
Yeah, exactly.
Jar jar coin coming to you.
It's better to wash this stuff out now than when the Fed does start printing money again
and people go risk on and cryptocurrencies start rallying again. Then this guy just would
have been able to cover up all of this. He was trying to raise millions in funding. And
if he would have gotten that millions in funding a week before he collapsed-
Also been lit on fire.
He would have covered all this up. He would have papered it over.
I just want to say you're adorable right now.
Why is that?
You think that by, or you implied that by washing this stuff out now, that the next
time the money printers go burr, these very same VCs aren't just going to do the same
thing. I mean, are you crazy?
Yeah, I suppose they will. Yeah, I guess they would, wouldn't they?
Yeah. I mean, you know, this stuff is just like the new pets.com, right? Nothing's changed.
It is totally, it is, it is the 2008 financial crisis and the dot com bubble in one event
for crypto. I don't know. I think, I think the more I watch all of this, the more at
all, just all this web three stuff is a total scam. It's all a scam.
I don't think it's all a scam. I think the underlying technology for blockchain actually
has some very boring, very boring applications.
I agree. I agree with that. Yeah. But it is not like this universal database replacement
that all of these projects claim to be and their tokens, they're all fake paper money
and the people behind the projects have been issued the token in advance for free. So whenever
the token goes up slightly in value, they, they make a bunch of money and it's all just
a red flag. There's only one true crypto and that is the Bitcoin, my friend.
No, there is one other currency, a boost baby.
Ask not what your podcast can boost for you, but what you can boost for your podcast.
And you tech sent us 250,000 sats this week showing some love for his favorite JB hosts
and show. Mike, you are freaking awesome.
Suck on that stow, which is not around anymore. Those jerks over at Linux unplugged feel embarrassed
now. Thank you and you tech. We appreciate layout. Uh, tack off seven 51 boosted in live
during the show with a 2009 sats. He was trying out a live boost to see if we got it. He's
hacked together a whole system. He's got like Linode in there. He's sending a boost with
web hooks. Uh, he's got a matrix I think to compose it and it landed. So congrats tack.
You built a, you built yourself a system there. I think that's pretty impressive. Strung it
all together and made it work. That's the nice thing about an open network, isn't it?
All right. Elry seven 41 boosted in with a row of ducks, 2,222 sats. So the two factor
stuff hits super close to home for me. A very close loved one of mine, not mentioning who
because I don't think they want to be identified, just went through all of this and even worse,
they couldn't get any cellular connection. So no SMS for the last two weeks. Oh man,
I'm going to send a contact form with more details. He did. And uh, he essentially wrote
a really great blog post on preventing a two factor authentication crisis. But from everything
he learned, uh, from going through his family member and also listening to your journey,
this looks really great. Uh, he really recommends off the two because again of that cloud sync,
which might be the way I would go to if I was going to recommend anything for somebody
who was non-technical, might be offy. If anybody could tell me why that's a bad idea, I'd love
to hear it. Thank you, Ellery. We will link to the preventing two factor authentication
crisis in the show notes for listeners who want to give that a review. I think that's
probably a good idea. Dennis V boosted in with a hundred sats. Finally, I'm back on
track with the show sending my first boost via the fountain app and the ear and sats
while listening. I just want to say I'm using Yuba key for my two factor authentication.
I needed to read, download the Yuba key authenticator and I had to hold my key onto it. I'm currently
driving a harvester in Australia and as a backpacker from Germany and I had plenty of
hours to catch up on all your podcasts. Any recommendations for other podcasts will follow.
Thanks for all the shows. Listen to them while I'm working. Time goes by fast. Hmm. You have
another show recommendation. My other shows are Star Trek shows, so they're very embarrassing.
If you like Star Trek shows, I got a few recommendations. Oh, I think you should just recommend those.
I like business wars depending on who it is. They just did Chipotle and Taco Bell, but
I'm very boring. Mine are mostly business and news and I listen to sections of ATV.
I recommend The Greatest Generation. It's a Star Trek podcast and it's fun. Hey guys,
don't take themselves too seriously. Purple Dog boosted in with 3000 sats. I wonder if
Purple Dog is Alex. He says, I self host all my important stuff because my backups are
in cloud storage and then they're encrypted locally first. The keys are passwords and
the two factor codes are all in Bitwarden. Bitwarden has that two factor authentication
recovery codes and I can store that in my desk with a Yuba key to unlock that. The TOTP
is for my Authy. If my house ever burned down, I lost everything. I decided I'd use Authy
because the backup password is memorized and I actually don't store that in Bitwarden.
So he's kind of got a mix. Like he's got basically his access to Bitwarden is in Authy and then
he has his other two factors inside Bitwarden. So he kind of has like a disaster plan if
his house burns down using that Authy sync, but he doesn't use Authy for everything. That's
a clever idea, dog. Purple Dog continues with another 2000 sats. You know, I actually kind
of like Chris's ad read voice. It makes it much easier to skip. I already use Linode
Talescale in Bitwarden. That is intentional, I will say. If you use it already, then just
let a friend know, you know, spread the word. Send them Mike's way too sometimes. You know,
there's always more places to visit. That's true. I love this next username. Hybrid Sarcasm.
Boost in with 1024 sats. Coming in hot with the boost. Here's a tip for memorizing the
wife's phone number. Change her name or alias title in the contacts app so the phone number
is what you see always instead of her name or their name. Only took me a few weeks and
I have that number down pat. Five years later, still in my head. That's actually a pretty
good idea is to put it in the contact information. That's, I think I'll do that hybrid. I might
try that. Yeah, that actually that would help. I, you know, I used to have like a whole list
of phone numbers memorized and then I got a smartphone. Then I got a phone. Yeah. Yeah.
Big dot boost in with 1701 sats. The enterprise boost. Make it so we recently gave him advice
to check out TNG and then last week we mentioned perhaps strange new worlds. He says I definitely
want to watch strange new worlds. I want to watch rings of power first though. I got a
few friends who like rings of power and I don't want to enrage them too much. Also,
I don't watch TV series on a regular basis, so I mostly only watch them every few months.
So what I do is I watch the first season of each show first. Whoa, this is a, whoa, this
is wild. I, I don't know if that's allowed. That feels weird. So he doesn't just binge
it. Yeah. Also, I feel like, I feel like I got to give an honorable mention to lower
decks. It was a solid season. If you like the fun, I hate fun. If you like fun and funny.
Yeah, it was a good solid season. So if you've got like, you know, 13, 14 year old kid around,
it's great. It's great for that kind of thing too. And then I'm going to give up, I'm going
to give a longterm plug once you get all done their peg to the expanse because that will
make your life better. So I got, I got it. I got it. I got to give that. I got to check
it out. That's on my list. Yeah. You got to give it at least five episodes too. I like
we recommend shows, but we're like, and the first half is terrible. Sometimes you're right.
You know what? You know what? Sometimes that's how it goes. That takes them a little bit
to get their feet. Like our first hundred episodes, probably not so high. It's like
going to bed with me. It's all terrible. No, I'm kidding. Actually, I don't want the review.
No Yelp reviews, please. Okay. Dave Jones, the pod sage boosted in with those big set
of enterprise sats 17 double Oh one sats. Dave says the fourth season of TNG is pure
magic. The cast and the writers just gel together to form something truly new and special. Shut
up Wesley. I agree, Dave. However, I actually think it, it really starts in season three.
There's spots in season three, like offspring and a few other episodes that are just so
good. I like the, I like the cringe of season one though. I don't know. And I technically
say part one of best of both worlds is probably slightly better than part two. And part one
takes place in season three, Dave Jones. So is that the old one? That's the mirror universe
one, right? No. Best of both worlds is when Picard gets assimilated. Oh yeah. Who does,
first of all, wouldn't it be nice to be assimilated? I feel like that would actually solve a lot
of problems. Not to mention you'd live forever. And no more food bill. No more food bill.
No more having to think about nothing. No more having to worry. Talk about a uniform.
You want to talk about a uniform. Chris's uniform becomes part of the Borg high five.
Problem solved, dude. Problem solved, right? So great. Oh, I love it. All right. Thank
you everybody who boosted in a Hannegan, a Hannegan, 4,000 sats. Thank you everybody.
New podcast apps.com. If you'd like to boost in, you go grab one. Sats are cheap right
now. They're probably going to be cheap for a while, especially if a 2023 ends up being
a recession. So don't grab a lot, but grab enough to send a boost in. Why not send a
little extra in since they're cheap right now? We still love them. They still mean something
to us. Strike if you're in the U S blue wallet, if you're outside the U S cash app is also
really great. And if you want to challenge RoboSats, if you've got the tour browser,
our Coder QA members keep us going. They invest in the ongoing production and the Coderly
is coming together. It has been a wild, wild quarter. Q4 is a hard one and I blame Halloween.
It threw everything off. I do. Oh, and I want to thank you all for taking the survey I posted
a couple of weeks ago regarding languages and frameworks you're using that is going
into the Coderly.
You can support the show and get an ad free feed at coderqa.co or do it for all the shows,
get all the shows ad free at Jupiter.party. That's how you do that over there. And then
of course we're live on Mondays. We do it at a 9 a.m. Pacific noon Eastern over at Jupiter.tube.
And then we've got the matrix chat room going during the live show, but it's really going
all week. Mike and I pop in there throughout the week. Details of that coder.show slash
matrix. You know, we we could have for all these times we mentioned the matrix, we could
have had like a Keanu Reeves soundbite or a blue pill thing, you know, whatever it is
this whole time. We've missed out on that. Oh, you don't want to say red pill. I get
it. Oh, oh, is it? I just never remember which one the blue pill is. Well, although blue
pill, you stay in the matrix, right? Right. Don't you want to be in the matrix? Yeah.
I mean, right now I'd love to be in the matrix. Let's call it things. I know now about how
gullible VCs are. Just send me back. Right. I want to do a what is it? Time with that
time. What's the one with? Let's go back. Oh, my God. Not Steve Buscemi. Are you talking
to are you talking about back to the quantum leap? Oh, no. I want to do a quantum leap.
I want to go back to like, give me two thousand nine. Just send me back. New York. Two thousand
nine. I'll be like, listen, guys, we're going to make an app. It's going to say one word
and that word is yo. You're going to give me five billion dollars. Amazing. You're right.
And we know for a fact that they would say yes. We should have known with yo. We should
have. We should have. No, I should have just, you know, fired everybody. I'll Elon started
a new company, just went all, you know, all in on conning. I mean, acquiring VC investment.
All right. Do you have any or you want to send people this week? If you've got a time
mission, can you come to me? No, I don't know. Dominic, I'm dot com. I'm trying to find something
more fun than Twitter. But for now, at Dumanuco on Twitter. Yeah, that's matrix for me. It's
my social network. It is matrix. I'm in the matrix all the time. Yeah. At Kota Radio Show
is the is the show on Twitter. If if you're doing that, you know, otherwise you can just
go get links and stuff and just go to our website. That's a good idea. Kota dot show.
This episode would be at Kota dot show slash for 92 links to everything we talked about
over there, including our RSS feed. So you just get that nice edited version by Drew
whenever we publish it. Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of the Kota Radio
program. And I hope to see you right back here next week.