This is KOTORadio, episode 412 for May 3rd, 2021.
Hello friend and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and business of software development, and the whole world of technology around it.
This episode is brought to you by a Cloud Guru.
A Cloud Guru now includes Cloud Playground, Azure, AWS, or Google Cloud Sandboxes on
ACG's credit card.
Not yours.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at acloudguru.com.
My name is Chris and this special edition of the KOTORadio program finds me all by myself
because Mike is out on assignment, but fear not.
I have a special, special episode for you.
I have the privilege of sharing a wonderful chat between our very own Wes Payne and Brunch
Master Brent.
It is definitely a wide ranging conversation.
It's a deep dive into a swath of life, including Wes's approach to learning new things and
his definition of his kind of work, which I think is unique and different, as well as
thoughts on meditation and improving productivity and the importance of context and comprehension
to just entropy and the evolutions of routines and creativity.
I'm not kidding you.
It is a wide ranging conversation and it's a perfect one for our audience who has to
think about work in multiple different ways.
So before we go back in time to that conversation, I want to thank our sponsor, Linode.
Linode.com slash KOTOR.
Go there to receive a $100 60 day credit towards your new account.
And of course you support the KOTORadio program.
Simplify your cloud infrastructure with Linode.
That's how we host everything now.
They are our go to hosting provider and they give us the tools to develop, deploy and maintain
all of the functions we need to operate at the scale we do with the size of the team
that we have.
And I cannot emphasize that point enough.
Linode makes it possible for us to do things way beyond what a small team could normally
grasp.
That's what's great because their prices are 35 to 50% less than shops like AWS, like big
cloud over there at AWS.
And Linode's been around since 2003.
They were the first in this game and they have focused on getting this right since then.
And with 11 data centers worldwide, you're going to find just the right spot to deploy
for you.
And you're going to rest easily knowing that Linode's built in monitoring tools have you
covered.
Just simple things like that, like I get emails when a system reaches a certain threshold
on memory usage or network usage, man, just watching that stuff is a fantastic indicator
about what's going on with your system.
But maybe you want something even simpler, like just beautiful, accessible S3 compatible
object storage in the cloud.
I love Linode's S3 compatible object storage.
What is it?
Well, if you don't know, object storage is an easy way for you to store and access data
without the need of running an entire server, you know, with its whole OS and everything
in front of that.
You can get just URL accessible storage either for yourself or you can flip it public.
It's a great way to run a static website or host some files.
We use it internally as a dynamic way to automatically add storage for our PeerTube instance and
for our next cloud instance.
So we're not constantly battling with storage limitations and accidentally using too much
for a project that we're going to have around for three months that throws everything into
whack.
And this actually solves problems that have literally broken a next cloud deployment before
when I just totally ran out of storage.
It's embarrassing, but I just don't have the time to manage this stuff.
And so using Linode's tools to monitor and manage this and take care of some of these
things, it is such a time saver.
At the price point that Linode is offering, it's just a no brainer.
They're dedicated to offering the best virtualized cloud computing.
If it runs on Linux, it runs on Linode.
To go to linode.com slash coder, receive that $100 60 day credit and support the show.
And of course, of course, try out all the features I've been talking about forever.
It's linode.com slash coder.
All right, like I said, it really is a special privilege to introduce this conversation to
you.
I take you back in time to Brunch with Wes Payne.
Hi, Wes.
Hello, Brent.
How are you today?
I'm doing wonderful.
I see your smiling face.
Oh, well, come on.
That's just because you're so nice.
And it's not always smiling.
That's why I appreciate it.
I think I try to smile in the appropriate contexts.
I hope I accomplish such things.
You don't want a false smile.
So we're doing brunch here and you actually did participate in some brunch.
How was that?
That was lovely.
You made me an excellent, excellent frittata.
I did.
And Chris got a little bit of that down his gullet as well.
It was it was good.
I was a little picky about my eggs from time to time.
But it was excellent.
All right.
Just to warm you up for our session here.
This is kind of neat for me, Wes.
I'm sitting in the hot seat here, which is Chris's seat.
Yeah.
You're sitting in your usual seat.
So this is totally normal for you, right?
But it's cool.
We've had the opportunity this week to hang out with the crew.
Oh, yeah, so much hanging out.
And we had well, tell me, what were the things that kind of stood out for you?
Some food, some some conversations and stuff?
I really enjoyed the ad hoc collaboration and just sort of people mixing and mashing
ideas and all being nerdy about like a ton of different topics, some of them show related,
some of them just like life things.
Lots of music being bounced around as well, I noticed.
And Chris, I think did a good job of trying to show everyone the virtues of living in
the Pacific Northwest.
So well, I did not attend all of those.
I was very glad that other people got to see the beautiful landscapes around here.
Right.
I mean, you're, you're a local.
So you you've already been converted, right?
Or converted by default, shall we say?
Right.
Have you ever lived anywhere else?
Like you've you've been in Seattle, and I know you grew up a little bit further down.
Yeah, I grew up in Olympia, slightly south.
But have you lived in any other cities?
I lived in Bellingham for a while.
And I lived in Everett.
So all sort of in this little corridor here?
Yeah, the I-5 corridor.
Nice.
Yeah.
And so, totally your backyard?
Very much so.
What I-
But there's still plenty to discover, let me tell you.
Yeah, I was just about to say what I really appreciate is when you can sort of become
a tourist in your own backyard.
Yes.
And so I know Chris, we ended up, well, he's never been to those ice caves.
And I don't know if you've ever been?
No, I have not.
Okay.
But that's always fun when you can, like, both be the tour guide and also the tourist
at the same time.
Yeah, right.
Let's go check out this fun thing together.
Well, maybe it's fun.
We'll find out.
Right.
I have to say for myself, moving to a different city is totally eye opening in the sense that
it breaks all your routines and you have to build them all back up.
You got to find all your new places in this new city.
Yeah.
Was that the same for you when you moved, let's say to Bellingham?
Yes.
Yeah.
You know, I really do like that sort of.
You got to work out what new routines and there's whole different sections of the city.
And there's something, I mean, I think about it more on the trail maybe, but it definitely
applies in cities of that when you don't really know what's around the bend and all the like,
it might be terrible, right?
It might just be like a dump that's around the bend and you don't know until you walk
around it.
And that's a lot of the fun.
But you also get all the enjoyment of before you know, all the things you imagine might
be around the bend.
And that's just fun as you continue finding more bends and you know, whatever eventually
map out a new area.
What you're describing also makes me think that you could be describing sort of a learning
journey through, I don't know, some Linux or whatever, right?
Almost any learning journey is if you're excited about what's around the bend or excited enough,
it might take you around the bend and then you're onto a whole other adventure.
That's one thing I like about living in a slightly larger city, living in Seattle, it's
just that, I mean, I haven't been there that long, really.
But there's still tons of places, you know, I mean, neighborhoods, I think I've probably
been to all of them, at least in passing, but it doesn't mean I know anything about
them.
There's a gentleman I saw, it's actually a film that I watched on the way here.
So perfect setup is it was a film that I shared with cheese about a gentleman who decided
to walk every single street in New York, in every, I think he said the five boroughs.
Now, I don't quite know New York that well.
Right, some big subset.
That's it.
And so he decided to do this because he realized much like you that you can go to each neighborhood,
but you kind of have these loop patterns that you follow.
And you may live in a neighborhood, but only go down maybe, you know, 20% of those streets
in your daily routine, right, because of course, we all have routines and that kind of stuff.
So it's the way that I walk, yeah, partly because it's Seattle, and that's the flat
white, but well, path of least resistance, right, right.
But what was fascinating to me about that is, is how there could be a street one street
over that, even though there's proximity, you just never spend any time on it.
Yes, right.
And so forcing yourself into adventure is, I think, a really good tool to open your eyes
to some new ideas, even.
It's funny, too, like you, you have to keep the mindset.
I mean, so like, even just during this, this sprint, I discovered a nice little New Mexican
joint right by the hotel where people were staying up, I've been to the grocery store
in that same region, but I never even considered, you know, it was always either to or from
the studio, I had a mission, I had a job to do, I never thought about just meandering
around looking for goodies.
And it pays off.
It does pay off.
The Mexican was pretty great, you, you grabbed it, and it was great.
Tell me a little bit about how you do that adventuring journey through learning, because
I know you are huge fan of learning new things, and you're, you seem to be okay with deep
dives and just like, collecting knowledge, if you will.
That's an interesting question.
I mean, I probably should know more about how those processes work.
Just in the conversation earlier, we kind of hit on something, something you said, think
about thinking in systems that I think definitely applies to me.
It's sometimes frustrating when you're learning something new, and you know how much there
is to learn, and you know how much you don't know, but you don't know what the most efficient
routes are going to be, right?
And you don't, you don't yet have the systems, and I really struggle more than I think that
I should sometimes to be like, well, I know I could just like follow that tutorial, and
I could go like run the commands, but I'm going to be fighting myself the whole way
through because each step, I'm going to want to go dig and dive around that.
It won't get me near to the goal of what I'm trying to accomplish, but I really want to
know all the theory as or before I'm like trying to do the practice, and that does not
always work out well.
Well, it doesn't work out well in the sense that it's time consuming, and also you might
not have a good idea of where to head to get that knowledge.
Yes.
Right.
Yeah, you're right.
I mean, I would say generally the outcomes are good, it's just not always the most efficient
for the task at hand.
I do think the flip side of that is I'm going to put that much time into something, do generally
learn it very well because I do focus so much on the systems and theory side that, you know,
once you do have the practice, which you need, you can combine those very effectively.
Yeah, you build like these really robust models that if you dedicate to that particular sphere,
and it turns out to be a useful one for you long term, then you've got this amazing base
to work off of.
What I've sometimes run into is not catching myself soon enough, so I'll do these deep
dives and build these really great systems for things I then decide are obsolete or not
actually solving the problems I'm trying to solve, right.
And it's hard to, you know, if you like what you're learning, if you're curious and you're
having fun playing with it, it is really, it takes a lot of willpower sometimes to be
like, no brain, this is not the track you need to be on right now, like go try this
other boring thing that will probably work.
A new rule I tried to implement for myself recently is to try to not learn something
I'm not going to use immediately, which is easy to state and harder to implement.
But for me, learning is such a driver for some of my sort of mental processes.
What do you mean?
In that if I get curious, then I'll want to dive in immediately.
And every new piece of information makes me even more curious.
So sort of compound.
Yeah, which is, which is great, because I think a lifelong learning journey is sort
of very useful.
However, learning itself can be a sort of procrastination.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
And so I can learn lots and be fascinated and very entertained by my learning.
But it may not necessarily be relevant.
You know so much about the Baroque period, I see that you've got it, you've got it.
So how about for you developing models about learning things that you aren't jazzed about?
Because sometimes we need to learn stuff that doesn't necessarily excite us to reach a goal
that does.
Yeah, that's true.
That is true.
You know, I could probably be better at that.
Oftentimes, I've ended up dealing with that either by making it so that I don't have,
you know, whatever my rule or the task at hand is changing so that I can get by with
learning it in a shallow way and not committing myself, or working with people who are better
at not over diving and having them do that part.
So I've had some of the best collaborators I've had have been kind of in like a little
more on the practical side.
I mean, like, okay, Wes, like, you can do a lot of the like, you know, ideating on thinking
and explore random paths and kind of find interesting things that we might want.
And then I'll handle some more of the like, well, I'll test each of these things or you
know, or like, just sort of the boring parts that make it all work, which I can certainly
do as well.
But I've encountered another class of individual who they don't care to this level, they just
don't obsess about it in the same way that we're talking about.
And I find that really nice to work with.
Because they're complimenting.
Right?
Yeah.
They can be like, well, yeah, whatever.
I just like, read the docs and found the little piece that I needed and left it at that.
And then left it.
Yeah.
And I'm like, okay, that's great.
How can you do that?
And then I stopped asking because I'm like, well, the whole point of this is I'm not going
to ask.
Could you then describe yourself as the really good support role in that sense?
That if you have someone driving sort of the direction, then you can do the deep dives
in the areas that are really obviously helpful?
Yeah, kind of.
It can be either side, I suppose.
And it depends on, I guess, how interested I am in the overall because I can write if
it's going to be something that I don't, if I don't have the vision for the overall whatever
task project, right, then I am totally happy to be like, well, whatever, I'll take the
corner that I'm interested in and learn that to the best of my ability.
If I care about it a lot, then I have a more difficult role.
If I really am interested in care, then I have a struggle to not be one, not necessarily
in charge, but at least, let's say, consulted about major decisions that affect that.
Yeah, fair enough.
So it's not, there's not a lot in the middle, I guess.
Interesting.
It's so good to know, though, how you function, right?
I think if, what a gift it would be if we all came with our own instruction manuals.
Oh, man, that would be nice.
It seems like most of our roles is simply to figure out how we function.
Maybe you have really good people around you who are able to give you some feedback, but
most of the time, that doesn't seem to be the case.
Yeah, that's the real gift in some mentors, right?
Some of the best mentors can see your best and your worst and use both of those as tools.
Were there any mentors that did that for you or helped you learn more about yourself?
Hmm, that's a good question.
I mean, surely, yes, there are.
I've stumped Wes.
You're hearing it for here first.
Yeah, you are.
I might have to think about that one a little bit.
Yeah, sure.
I'd like to give a meaningful answer and I would need more reflection, I think.
I was curious about something sort of related.
I'm wondering if you were also afflicted sometimes, you're talking about not learning stuff.
Trying.
Trying, yeah.
I sometimes find that difficult, too, where there's subjects that I am interested in and
would like to know more about, but either worry I would spend too much time doing or
just know what it would take to do it well and just doesn't seem, you know, it's like,
so while I could probably dabble, I don't, and I'm wondering if that's maybe a net detriment
to me.
Like, there's probably areas that I could enjoy doing a little bit, but I don't let
myself do because I think I should do them more.
Is it linked to perfectionism in any way?
Yeah, maybe.
And do you find that to be a problem?
I do have a little streak of that from time to time.
Yeah, I would say actually that that has been both a real guide for me and a real detriment
to me in the sense that a lesson I've learned recently that's very helpful is the B plus
is generally my B plus, my self evaluation of a B plus generally is really good for most
other people.
And I'm not trying to put myself on some kind of pedestal, but having this, like, deeply
set perfectionism can get me really caught up in trying to solve things that just don't
matter for anybody else.
Yeah, right.
And it's hard to replace that in whatever activity, right?
Like, if you don't really care about it, that won't be as good or the flip side, like you're
saying that if you do really care about it, then you probably end up wasting some time
on details that don't matter, but you also catch a lot of details that other people might
miss.
Yeah.
For you, you describe not wanting to dabble in a specific project.
Is there something that comes to mind for that?
I've thought about doing more rock climbing, which is something I enjoy, but and have many
friends who enjoy, but I have not dove in to any serious degree.
That probably also applies to music.
Right because you...
I did music a lot in my youth, but I mean, I do a little music here and there now, but
not really anything.
Yeah, I know that you have a little bit of brass in you, right?
Yeah, I played French horn and trumpet for...
I was gonna say flugelhorn, but I knew that was wrong.
Right.
I did, in marching band, play the mellophone, which is...
I don't know what this is.
It's like a marching version of the French horn.
Okay.
Yeah.
It has a different sound, but it still has that interesting sort of, not quite muted,
but more mellow tone that you think of with the French horn.
But instead of having the rotary valves of a French horn, it had valves like a trumpet
does.
Interesting.
Yeah.
It was fun to play.
I'd never heard of it either, but it was a lot of fun, and it was kind of nice as like
a big trumpet, but with just like a giant bell on the end, but still about the same
holding size, and a lot of the fingerings were the same, so it was really easy to just
pick up and play, and you could make a whole bunch of noise, which is really the best part
about marching band.
You just go out there and just make a bunch of noise.
You're the loudest one, yeah, right.
And so how do you perceive the link between music and math?
Because I know you have a huge interest in math as well, and I've heard often that those
two kind of go together, even though they don't seem that they should.
Well, I mean, there's a lot of rhythms and periodicity in music, obviously, but in a
more fundamental level, sort of belaying all the surface level details, there do seem to
be some similar just sort of like ways about thinking, or maybe it's not even that they
have to be similar, but some of the patterns or styles of creativity needed for music can
apply well to math or tech-related things.
Because I think, you know, obviously people see music as creative, even when it, and it
is, but miss the side of being wrote and played back and recited, right?
And then see that side to math or computing or whatever, and miss the more creative side,
but often those are the more important role.
It's interesting that you brought in tech there because that's often an area that is
not necessarily seen as creative.
Yeah, yeah, that's absolutely true.
And yet with anyone who's doing some pretty deep problem solving in tech, it's a necessary,
right?
Yeah, I mean, there is a lot of value in being a practitioner and being a good, reliable,
repeatable practitioner, but most of the things that end up, you know, at least at the upper
echelons or the more interesting work is you're kind of at the edge.
No one's done that specific thing.
There's no pattern, or there might be some, you know, there are some patterns, but you're
making that specific bespoke thing.
It's a craft.
It's up to you to combine all of the toolboxes you've gathered.
And that's where like really caring about it matters, or I like to think so.
You can totally not, you can just, you know, you can cookie cutter, you can work on some
of the less interesting stuff.
You can just apply techniques that you've learned and move on and solve the problem.
And that's the right thing to do in many cases.
I just can't, I can't operate that way, you know, like, if I'm not gonna really care about
what it is that I'm doing, or like, at least be really interested in some aspects of it
and think about it a lot, wouldn't want to do it.
Since we're talking about mental models, I've built this model in my mind that there's a
range between on one end, there's the technician.
And on the other end, there's the artist or the creative.
And while you can be on either end, there's often this scale.
And that's, for me, easy to see in my own photography is that there are very artistic
photographers who aren't necessarily technically sound, but if they can get to the point where
their technical ability is enough, good enough, they can get the shot that they can get the
artistry through, then that has a certain positive impact.
And you can have technicians, which are really, they're fabulous at the nitty gritty of settings
and, and lighting and things like this.
But they don't necessarily have the artistry.
And there's obviously the whole scale, everything in between there.
Yeah, and I imagine that's much the same for what we were just discussing, which is that
you can have very technical implementers of solutions in tech, and also the artists who
tend to craft the initial projects or the initial solutions, and then someone else maintains
it.
Yes.
Yeah, exactly.
And maybe you can throw like the like research arm somewhere in here.
So you have some ideas spinning out of this idea factory, and then there's like the middle
layer of people that can find good ideas, maybe they don't come up with them out of
whole cloth, but sort of steward, shepherd them, help them grow, evaluate them.
And then maybe there's another few layers of people that you say, yeah, actually go
operate the thing, you know, turn that into a repeatable pattern that gets standardized.
Because there is a lot of value in that, right?
Like you're saying, like you want people that are focused on repeatability and reliability
and just smooth running.
Yeah, I can play that role, but it's probably not my favorite.
But for you, is it more interesting than to, to come in and build something and then hand
that off to someone?
Somewhere in the middle, I guess, I mean, I enjoy a lot of the different aspects.
It can be neat, when you do a little bit of all the flip side.
Challenge of that, of course, is you don't often get to control how what the relative
amounts of each unit of those are fair enough.
Yeah, kind of depends.
But I don't, I don't think I could be happy long term in probably stuck on either extreme
of those, you know?
Too much of anything.
Yeah.
And I think you also need some people, good people in the middle who can talk to both
sides.
Because there's a lot to learn.
And that's been some of the problems, at least in the software side, we've seen that we're
trying to get over as an industry is not having enough feedback between the people making
the ideas and people actually using the ideas.
Isn't that true?
Yeah, for sure.
We're seeing that on the desktop.
And for you, you've seen that in a lot of the infrastructure that you've built throughout
the years as well.
And you just end up with, you know, perverse patterns, not good communication, angry people,
right?
Because you can make it work in lots of ways.
You just need information and communication to flow.
Right.
You know, they say that for relationships, but I suppose that's true of most things is
that communication is is key, right?
If you're if you're working on the wrong problem, then it doesn't matter how fancy the solution
you come up with.
Right.
And you have to constantly evaluate that because as we were talking about earlier, you know,
like, yeah, there's these, there's inertia to some of these ideas to what you want to
work on and what you are working on.
Important to manage that.
Yeah.
For you and some of your previous roles outside of JB, were you working with really big teams
and is moving to JB like a much smaller team or are you generally generally working in
small groups?
I have been part of some larger teams, although most of my previous experience have been about
the JB size, maybe a little bit bigger.
Really embedded in a larger sort of corporate structure, I'd say, or working with a larger
array of other teams that I would work with closely.
I've also been on the opposite side where I've had, you know, one of my longer term
positions.
I was just working basically with one other person most of the time.
Right.
Thankfully, I really enjoyed working with.
Yeah, I was just about thinking that change that can change things.
Yeah.
That's kind of what we're talking about earlier is he really complimented me in that he was
he was very practical, very much happy to just, you know, didn't didn't fuss was totally
willing to just bang something out and not be a perfectionist about it at all.
So we made a very effective pair, I think.
And this was someone who was like, side by side on the hierarchy?
Yeah, yeah.
We were basically a two person team managing a bunch of internal tooling for a company.
Okay.
And was it someone who had the foresight to place both of you together because they saw
the strengths and weaknesses of each or was it just happenstance?
You know, it was organic survival, I think.
You know, because we just kind of found he he did happen to be the person who trained
me.
Okay.
But we worked different times after the training period.
I think it just kind of came together that we both had a, you know, drive to do other
things.
So we wanted to move in from where we were at presently.
And I think I value that he was very competent, you know, just like knew what was wrong, or
if he was writing code that was sloppy, it was managed expectations with clear communication,
like, look, I just did this thing.
It's not perfect, whatever.
Like, I did it to solve this problem.
It's solved.
Do you have input?
And then move on.
And then I think he liked in me that I was willing to spend a little more time with the
ideas that that made sense to and would find, you know, optimizations or other ideas or
total alternatives that he just wouldn't have spent the time to think about.
Right.
So he was more willing to invest in the projects to see them be smoother long term.
So he would call it West work.
You know, there'd be like, shares of stuff where it's like, oh, man, like, I don't know,
like, you deal with that.
And then there'd be the other share, we'd be like, well, that's West work.
And you go research those topics and come back to me with what you think we should do.
That's awesome.
And there were no clashes during the training, because I have often experienced that when
you're teaching someone something, you can have all these different styles.
And I imagine for two people who sort of operate differently in their minds, that there would
be a difference in style.
Yeah, that is true that it can often be very difficult.
Not that I remember.
No, I think I think this individual in particular happens to be very direct.
I think I think that helped and doesn't be I think because of the personality we're describing,
doesn't have a lot of ego tied up in that knowledge.
I mean, if you question his performance or something he was proud of, you know, whatever
normal human operations there, but, you know, it didn't have to be this battle of like,
well, do you know this or not?
And there's no like, right, passive aggressiveness about what you knew or didn't knew.
And yeah, just no, no games.
Sounds like a great collaboration.
Really?
Yeah, it was it was right.
It was time to move on from that job when I did, but that was the hardest part was there's
just never worked with someone so closely because I don't like in school and things
I enjoy collaboration I do and I mean, I suppose I'd have to work in here now.
Fair enough.
Sometimes you know what you're doing.
I love teaching.
Don't get me wrong.
But sometimes you know what you're doing.
I don't always enjoy the rocky road, like I don't mind check ins, you know.
So like, I played around some ideas, come back after a couple hours, meet, discuss where
everyone got but I really found I didn't enjoy more active collaboration, at least in some
domains where I just wanted to be left alone and think and just do it by myself.
So I would often find myself in roles of like on projects, I would just make myself the
editor or whatever, you know, be like, right, you guys go do your things.
I'll tie this up together and make it look nice at the end.
Would you tie that into introvertedness for you?
Hmm.
That's a good question.
You know, I read this really great book called Quiet, which the it's a very well known book
and I forget the author now it's Susan Kane.
Okay.
This was a book that was recommended to me and when I read it, it taught me so much about
my own inner workings.
Oh, interesting.
It's one of those books that enlighten you about yourself.
That's useful.
Which are some of my favorite books.
Yeah.
But it did so in a way that made me more aware of the methods I needed to use in teamwork
to produce the best work because I know for myself if I'm constantly interrupted, or if
I don't have the time to hyper focus, which takes me a long time to get into, then I can
never create my best work.
And it sounds at least I see similarities for you, even when you have a really good
collaborations even with just one person.
Yes.
No, absolutely.
Like, I guess I guess I get tired of sort of like, should we explore this idea or not
and people have different notions.
I don't I don't want to talk about it.
We can talk about if it's right or not, but I'm just gonna explore the ideas I want to
explore.
Yeah.
And it seems to work mostly.
I mean, I find it honestly, I find it very different that the at least in that style,
maybe it's just maybe it's age, maybe it's different subject matter, because a lot of
those interactions around math and physics and a little more not not creative, but a
little a little more right and wrong binary sort of things.
I don't I don't have that experience really at all, I would say working JB at that may
also be the people involved.
There's a lot of variables.
Interesting.
I hadn't thought about it that way.
I do.
I do agree with you, though.
I find myself in the same boat, I do need time to think and while I can operate under
pressure, you're right, I wouldn't do my best work that way, you know, it'd be much better
to just go like, give me 20 minutes, I'm gonna go over here in the closet, and then I'll
come back out and then we'll have your thing that you need.
That sounds so familiar, right?
I'm very impressed by people that can operate in other styles, you know, some, even some
of our team members at JB, it's like, doing all number of tasks at the same time and multiplexing
and I just doesn't make sense to me.
Yeah, some of us can require pressure to perform.
Yeah, that's true.
It is, I found for myself that it is true that same as you, it's true that I can perform
under pressure and quite well when I need to.
But the level of exhaustion is quite high.
So I can do that for a short period of time, right before you just burn out.
That's it.
Or, like you said, if you give me 20 minutes with headphones away from the world, and then
I'll get it done faster.
Nothing like being watched while you work too, you know, just makes it, everything goes
slower.
Someone over your shoulder, right?
Depends on what you're doing, of course, and how well you know it, but there is probably
an aspect to what you're asking, like with the introverted sense, probably some of that,
at least is maybe not introvertedness, but not desiring excess conflict.
I don't think I'm conflict averse necessarily.
But like in that example, I just would get tired of like, I don't want to argue about
this right now.
You know, like, it's just not worth my time to debate this.
Well, and I've picked up on you being quite agreeable as well.
I suppose that's the flip side of saying that.
Yeah.
Right.
So you can, which is a gift, because everybody likes you.
And it can also be a bit of a challenge in that other people's ideas sometimes trump
your own even in your own mind.
I say that from personal experience, because I'm just I'm quite agreeable as well.
And sometimes you put your own ideas on the back burner simply because someone else is
willing to fight stronger for theirs.
Yeah, that is true.
Yeah.
You know, there's a, the fight costs me more than it does to them.
So I have to care more about the idea to make it worth it.
Ah, that's fascinating.
I like that.
This compatriot that I really enjoyed work with, he complimented me there as well.
He's happy to argue about anything just to just to argue about it.
Okay.
So that worked out nicely, too.
Because you just give up sooner and he'd win.
Right.
Well, and I could just let him fight the battle.
You know, I could back him up with with whatever research and as a team.
Oh, that's fascinating.
But he was willing to push a little bit more.
And then I mean, if he's gonna do it, then I'm gonna support it.
Yeah, of course.
It's easy to support.
Yeah.
Nice.
So you're saying I just need to find myself someone who's willing to fight my fights?
I think so.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now, if I had them, I'd be willing to rent.
But unfortunately, we no longer work together.
Do you ever?
I don't think we necessarily struggle for this.
But sometimes if you have multiple agreeable people, decisions, they won't agree or won't
be able to there's not enough care in one direction.
Like if I said, Hey, Wes, what kind of pizza would you like to see that I think I could
decide.
Really?
Yeah, it depends, too.
You know, there's, um, there's sort of like an open and a closed agreeability.
That's true.
I don't worry about telling you what kind of pizza I want.
Because I know that if you you're agreeable, but you're also open enough to the interaction
we're having that you would tell me if you if you weren't interested in that pizza.
But there's some types of agreeable, I think that that's not true.
And then I worry more about that.
And then might not want to suggest the thing because I don't you know, it just gets a little
more complicated.
These internal processes are just fascinating.
And once you start picking up on them for yourself, and also for others, you those interactions,
like those non language interactions that happen between two people trying to decide
what kind of pizza to have can be fascinating.
Yes.
It's even harder when I mean, at least we're talking about pizza, I kind of know like what
pizza like, it's even worse when you take it one layer up, like, what do you want to
eat?
Oh, that like one person's hungry, like, what do you want to eat?
One trick I got from Tim Ferriss that really helped me from his book for our workweek was
to, instead of asking, what does everyone want to eat, especially if you're in a group
of like, three people or more, right?
There basically will be no answer, no useful answer given.
Or you won't even you'll just get on to a different topic entirely.
Quickly derail.
Oh, yeah.
We saw we see that all the time.
Right.
But what I've been trying to implement, and I haven't thought about it in a while.
So either I've succeeded or failed, I'm not sure if I is to instead of asking the question,
what would you like to have is to put out a suggestion, right and ask if that works.
And when I have practiced this, I've noticed a big difference in everyone's level of agreeing
to ideas, and the speed at which these ideas can happen.
So in working with in teams, right?
This could save a lot of time, you know, you're coming to it with solutions instead of just
questions.
All of that, I think applies.
I mean, because the thing about this, you know, creative work, it's kind of the same
like the open closed, because it can be really useful to have someone start even if it's
just a terrible idea, right, but just to throw it out there and sort of get the ball rolling.
But that requires enough openness and trust in the group that you can feel confident that
like, that idea doesn't represent you.
It's just a thing.
You're just saying it right here, which is often true for what do you want to eat, but
doesn't always carry over to what should we title the report.
We're both brainstorming in a sense.
And what's interesting is that everyone has a stake, right?
And so some of the I read a really great book that was given to me by my uncle, who is almost
identical to me.
Like I'm a younger
Is his name also Brett?
Can we call him Uncle Brett?
You could his name is actually Ray Allen.
He's a great, great guy.
But he has taught me he has taught me a lot about my own inner workings in that he's kind
of a few decades ahead of me and has all this experience and dilutes that into what is helpful
for me at my own stage of life, which is if you can find someone like that for yourself,
it is fabulous.
Does it work if I like just try to talk to like a face app aged picture of myself?
You could start there
because I'm doing that already.
Gentlemen I'll sneak in here if I can borrow the studio for a moment and tell everyone
about Data Dog.
Let's go solve some problems and analyze code level performance across your entire environment
and troubleshoot issues faster with Data Dog.
datadog.com slash coder radio.
Go there to get a 14 day trial.
And if you set up a dashboard and use that URL, you can also get a free Data Dog t shirt.
Data Dog is continuous profiler automatically collects profiles from your production servers
all the time.
I'm talking the entire stack everyone like the whole dang thing from the metal all the
way up to the applications.
So you can analyze any of that data you need quickly with minimal overhead and you get
a unified picture of your environment by correlating code performance metrics with your other monitoring
data with these beautiful, gorgeous, fantastic, slick real time dashboards.
You should go to datadog.com slash coder radio just to see the dashboards.
But now they have over 450 integrations that allow you to do tracing and log management
and that continuous profiler all in one platform.
I mean, they're actually talking and analyzing your applications too.
Can you imagine how this enables you to visualize and communicate across your team?
Data Dog gives you the tools to pinpoint the root cause of issues faster than ever.
So go try Data Dog's products for free for 14 days by visiting datadog.com slash coder
radio.
And like I said, for a limited time, if you start that free trial and you create one dashboard,
you're going to get a free Data Dog t shirt, free swag, datadog.com slash coder radio.
Back to this book, this book he gave me, which he gave to me like 10 years before I read
it.
Oh, right.
Wow.
It was the kind of book you're like, I think that's really interesting and yet not interesting
enough to dive into.
But I finally did.
It's called The Six Thinking Hats.
And it's all about simply, it's a brainstorming technique.
And I'm sure we can link to a Wikipedia page that would describe this a little bit more
sensibly than I would.
But the main nugget I got from it is that brainstorming should be a protected area.
You can do brainstorming with other people in a way that is methodical, and yet still
very creative.
And so the process in this book is basically, there's six hats, and they all represent a
different way of thinking.
And when you're in a hat, everyone's wearing, you know, quote unquote, the hat.
And I forget what they are, but they're fascinating if you want to look into them.
And so one of them might be, like, just throw out any idea at all that fits within creativity,
for instance.
And so obviously, you're gonna have some people on the team who are a little bit stronger
at that stuff.
So that's their time to shine.
And yet when you put on different hats, it relates to some other team members' strengths.
But the most important part for any brainstorming, whether you're trying to decide what kind
of ice cream you want, or what kind of pizza or where to take a certain project is for
it to be, like you said, a protected area where you're not sort of chastised for sending
out what are seemingly bad ideas, but might lead to nuggets that are invaluable.
And it's something I've only recently learned to do well.
But that I see it being kind of a challenge, right?
Oh, that's, yeah, right.
And I don't know that we all think about it as much as we probably should.
It's interesting, too, what you're talking about, too, like how structure can sometimes
provide that.
We all know the rules and like how it's happening.
It's somehow a little bit bizarre to talk about structure and creativity in the same
sentence in a way.
That's another part, I guess, like kind of one of the themes in this whole conversation.
We have these words and notions, but we don't, many people do, good books, right, what we're
talking about.
But generally, we don't necessarily dive into it or try to study or bisect, right?
Like, oh, you're just creative.
Brent, how do you take such good photos?
I have no idea.
I'm not going to conceptualize it, but I mean, there is some element of like, well, you see
photos that you want to take and you take them.
That's over simplification, but I'll take it.
But there's both a lot of structure and a lot of whatever inherent creativity, artistic
sense.
So there's this great website that I'm not sure if you know about.
It's called Brain Pickings.
Tell me more.
I believe the author is Mary Popova, and what she does is dives into a lot of literary work
and extracts nuggets.
And one post I saw that always sticks for me is describing the methods that writers
use and some really historical writers use to begin their writing process on a daily
basis.
So that's the juxtaposition, again, of structure and creativity, right?
They have applied this structure to their day that optimizes their creative time, right?
Which probably doesn't always fit in whatever other random society and post structures.
Yeah, fair enough.
But what's fascinating about that to me is that you really need to know yourself well
to be able to establish that structure in the first place, right?
Yeah, no one's going to tell you how to find it.
Yeah.
And do you have any such routines or, well, you were mentioning earlier when you came
in that the Sprint sort of shook up your routines.
That is certainly true.
You know, just changing, having everyone here and doing all kinds of different things.
I'd say I'm reforming some routines because I had routines for a more traditional type
of role or at least hours, and I have a few things I'm figuring out, I think, that I like,
but I've kind of gone back to a blank slate, at least somewhat, and I've been actively
exploring.
I think I do really like sometimes just starting work immediately in the morning, which is
one advantage of working from home is that you can do that.
You do have to then have the flexibility to then, you know, stop at some point and go
do like regular morning activities.
Right.
Like feeding yourself.
Yeah, feeding yourself, your animals, I don't know, maybe going outside, that sort of thing.
Seeing the world.
Uh-huh.
But there's something about this early morning, I'm not generally a morning person, I really
like the morning.
I'm just bad at going to sleep and enjoy being awake at night.
It just seems to be what I gravitate to.
But I love being up in the morning, so if I can't, but it seems to be the most enjoyable
if I've been up the night before, not super later, but you know, I've been working on
the thing, actively engaged, got a good night's sleep, and then I can just like jump into
it because the early morning hours and then like afternoon are probably my best productivity
times.
Okay.
Do you find that, well, wait a second, I'm going to challenge you there because you mentioned
working late night on something.
I do also, late night can work.
That's a little more variable.
It depends a lot on how the day has gone.
I think it was a better time when my job was more predictable.
These days, it depends a lot on what happens in the day, how many shows we did, you know,
whatever.
And so late night isn't always.
If I have the schedule flexibility, and that depends too, I will sometimes do a hybrid
where I'll just go to bed and then wake up at like two and then work from like two to
five and that also can be very productive.
That's two to five a.m.
Yeah.
Wow.
There's just something about the times when like no one else is up, there's no distractions.
I've heard this before.
Yeah, for sure.
And two, it is one of the challenges, you know, with like working from home can be dividing
those like, when you're doing life things, when you're doing job things, how do those
mingle and where's the border?
There's not a lot of board.
I mean, like, you can just define what you're doing, you know, it's a chunk of time that
you don't have any conceptions about.
And so you can just assign it to something.
And from two to five, nothing else is going to demand of your time.
No, I don't have no plans.
Thankfully.
Well, the only plan you have is the plan you want.
But I've so I've recently sort of rediscovered that I knew that, like in college, I would
frequently, you know, stay up late working and be like, I'm just like too tired to be
productive, and then have to wake up early to get the assignment done or whatever.
And I think working a more traditional schedule, I kind of forgot about that.
So I'm rediscovering it to an extent.
There's something to be said about working at your best times for you personally.
And sometimes our nine to fives can really challenge that even though they're there in
place to try to make it easier or more productive for the general populace, but what I've discovered
as many for many of us, especially in the tech sphere, this late night stuff or early
morning stuff is more jam.
Mm hmm.
I don't know.
There's something about like, the late morning that's just not a productive Yep.
So it's either I'm going to like sleep in and you know, stroll into work at like 1030.
Or you might as well I just just let me work from like, you know, six to nine or something
then I'll come in in the afternoon.
Right.
Is there anything then that you've not had a work from a distance or work from home flexibility
in any previous I have, but those the hours were still more traditional, and most of them
were not totally remote, it would be like a hybrid sort of thing.
Okay.
So I was still at least in the culture of the office, right?
Just from a slight distance, just from a slight distance.
Yeah, exactly.
And so this is kind of the first opportunity, at least in a while where I can be like, Well,
if I want to get weird with it, I can.
Let's shake it up.
Yeah, right?
Why not?
And I mean, that happens anyway, right?
A lot of the team is on weird schedules, just because we all live in different time zones.
So we're a little bit all over the world, right?
Mm hmm.
I mean, you look at Joe, and I will ask him this a little bit more Joe has basically set
his internal clock to a completely different time zone across the world.
So I'm very fascinated about that.
For you working late night on a project, and then sleeping and waking up.
You mentioned that works really well for you.
Do you find that there's something about the process of sleeping with an idea in your mind
that
Oh, yeah, definitely.
I'm a big proponent of the one of my favorite people, Rich Hickey, who's the guy who made
the Clojure programming language.
He calls it hammock time, but just just really tries to underscore the value of like, thinking,
you know, and turning things over in your mind before doing.
Doing is important to you.
And that's a separate conversation.
So I value that a lot.
I really enjoy, you know, that time when you haven't quite fallen asleep, but you're not
quite you're not 100% rational, you're not you're lucid, but not totally.
I think that is a great time.
So that can be a kind of enjoyment too, you know, just like taking a break, having been
a little more relaxed, just laying not worrying either, maybe you fall asleep, maybe not,
it's okay, either way.
That can be some of the best times you can resolve or just make clear something you're
trying to work out.
Yeah, there's a real like, freedom of ideas, right without constraint.
And I think we're easy on ourselves in those times, because we're like, bye, we could just
like, that's kind of like dreaming, and I don't need to commit to anything.
Yes, you don't have to follow down, you may not even write it down.
You can just it's a true exploration, isn't it?
Have you done any meditation?
Because I know that meditation can sometimes Oh, yeah, no, I am.
That's one of the things that has been sort of disrupted in my routine lately.
I definitely enjoy meditation.
I could probably stand to do it on a more regular basis, but it is a usual part of some
of my routines.
Okay.
And do you find it useful for you to gain just general clarity or more of an idea sphere?
Um, yeah, I guess I it can it can be both.
The ideas sphere is maybe a more constrained activity, or at least not constrained in what
it is, but constrained in time and place.
But for general meditation, I find it very useful just to set the tone and whatever I'm
gonna call it brain tone, but you know, like the the thematics of how your day is going
and what you're thinking about, because it's so easy to get trapped in like random little
brain loops where you're thinking about something good or bad might not be what you should really
be thinking about or want to be thinking about.
And it seems like one of the more useful tools I have also, especially like with more creative
work or different timelines, trying to bring a sense of priority and understanding to all
of the things that might be going on at a time, like collecting all the things and sorting
them like a triage.
Yeah, but but in a peaceful, you know, not in a not in a hurry way to not focusing on
any of them, but just sort of, I guess I would say it's more of like an acknowledgement.
It's sort of, you know, you're looking around the room and being like, yep, all right, that's
over there.
I see.
Yes, in the corner, too.
And there's no judgments.
There's no as little emotion as you can and just sort of accepting that those are there.
And then when you're done, now you have the time to go engage with the ones.
Right.
I found often in that for me, items that have otherwise been forgotten tend to start floating
up yet I'm not sure where they come from, or who's asking them to float.
But that can really bring to mind some things that in a what I'll call a waking state, but
a non meditative state, I suppose, our everyday state, our usual operating state, it are things
that get sort of forgotten, despite their importance.
It's almost like a scale from importance to urgency.
And what we're aware of immediately is what's urgent, yes, but isn't necessarily what's
most important.
There's a lot of urgent things I have to do all the time then.
While an important part of my life are not something I would think of as an overarching
bigger sort of goal or task or anything.
Yeah, that is true, right?
Because a lot of the themes in your life are like, you know, things you're proud of things
you've committed to things you've built or learned or enjoyed.
But most of the time, those are not the urgent things are the things you have to plan for
or think about a lot to be able to actually do and probably takes time to look back and
actually appreciate.
Right.
And the rest of it's all like, well, the trash has to go out.
Someone's got to do it.
It's gotta vacuum again.
Yeah, we don't have robots for all that stuff yet.
Well, some of us do.
Well, I'm with you.
Do you find for yourself a real challenge in seeing some of the ideas that you've implemented,
you know, some of the technologies you've implemented, even in the studio here?
Do you find it a challenge to see them constantly evolving, like the entropy that tends to work
its way into projects?
Is that tricky to see something you've built needing to be changed all the time?
Or do you get excited by that?
I think I struggle with it less in a technical sense or a work sense and more in a personal
sense.
Like an emotional sense?
Well, just in personal matters, I guess.
Like I find myself building more routines, having more of those sort of structures in
my regular life and being more exploratory and looking to change in a lot of like technical
work things.
So I kind of enjoy that.
I mean, again, there's a lot of value in reliability and sameness and all that, and I'm a big proponent
of such things.
Right.
But I do enjoy change and evolution.
And I like those things in my personal life as well, but it's a little more of I have
to remind myself of that or I guess it's more of my brain wants to seek routines and then
I have to remind myself that like, yes, you found this, but that's going to change soon.
Like it's good.
Keep doing it.
That's good.
It's working.
Like I said, pinging you being like, well, you're probably going to have to move or it's
going to be winter and you can't do that anymore or whatever.
Do you find it's easier for you in the technical world in that you have a collection of tools
that you can use to help you move through those changes and then your personal world?
Yes.
And more control.
Oh, in what sense?
Usually in the technical domains, I at least have some, I'm usually somewhat involved in
the implementation or this is decision making process.
So I can decide how much I care, but I really have to care a lot about my own personal life.
And I could go live a life where I had more control, but like living in a city and currently
renting and doing things that involve other people, a lot that can change without my input
at all.
I guess there are more external factors.
There are more external factors.
Yeah, exactly.
Do you find to bring us back that agreeableness has an effect there?
Like in terms of lifestyle, do you tend to shape your lifestyle for how it works for
others?
Definitely more so than other people, than some others do.
Yes, that's probably true.
I don't think in a bad way necessarily, at least not all the time.
You never said it was bad?
No, yeah, right.
That's true.
That just is what people think of in that role.
It's the general perception.
Right.
Yeah, exactly.
I mean, I'm not like moving to Tahiti right now or whatever, like I need to do this.
And I do have some of those things, but I would say it is more of a balance.
I would place more weight relative to other people, some other people on whatever, my
friendships or established relationships or how that would affect the people in my life.
That sounds so familiar for me because I'm, as you know, traveling quite a bit.
And so my friend circles have sort of evolved from being in a certain city to being a little
bit scattered, you can argue, all over North America.
Oh, you can argue even further than that.
And so what I'm exploring these days is the difference between what I generally really
struggle with is trying to decide what is best for me and myself emotionally.
Just you alone.
Yeah, versus what should be the answer or what others perceive is the best path.
A logical course.
Yeah, and so that's true of friend networks and family networks as well, is that while
I know I'm traveling lots and I can see all these people as I travel because that's how
this all got built up, there's still some weird sense of needing to choose home.
That currently I know is maybe not optimal in the way I've set it up.
But in choosing a new home, that's one of the life decisions I find to be one of the
most challenging.
Right, especially when you have so many options, right?
It's not like, it's not like you got it.
And I guess that that's another aspect to you know, if, if you're going to go pursue
some new degree or whatever, like you would have a limited set, but you could keep doing
whatever you're doing, right?
I suppose that's a challenge with having such a free lifestyle as well, is that, okay, well,
while I absolutely love my lifestyle, it has freedom, in the sense that I can choose to
do whatever I'd like.
And that is, while that sounds lovely, and is mostly, it also has the challenge of not
having any particular direction or any default.
You got to choose, you got to make each of those decisions all the time.
So that's something I generally struggle with.
And I know you're, I think you're looking for a new space to live in, and that can bring
a lot of those same themes, right?
Is that how in the world do you choose?
It's funny this this time to like, I got the news a little bit suddenly that I was gonna
have to relocate.
And I've moved a ton.
I'm like, it's not it's not really that big of a deal.
And I honestly, I enjoy the process of moving, not part where you have to lift heavy things
a whole bunch.
I mean, that part's fine, too.
It's mostly the rush of having to move all these things really fast, right?
It's just a stressful thing.
But I really enjoy the like, considering new aspects, I think I am building more of a,
at least in a particular domain, of a sense of like, what I like and spaces and ideas
and that sort of thing.
So that's all very fun.
Some of it like the suddenness, and I think playing on that aspect of control, like this
one, I think it was also just like it happened at an inopportune time where I was busy and
stressed out about other things.
But I found that it really like, ungrounded me in a way that I was surprised by.
So you're trying to collect yourself?
Yeah.
So I'm trying to collect myself.
And it was, I mean, I was kind of at a, you know, I moved into the city proper because
that's where all the work was, right?
And that's no longer what I'm doing.
So you have different inputs now or different filters.
Right.
And so while I had been sort of refining this, like, well, I know what it like, looks like
to live in the city, I know kind of what my options are.
And I still have to make some tough calls about like, what do I want to do next?
Now I suddenly found myself being like, not only do I not have the nice luxury of time
to go like, fart around and think about these ideas, which you require, yeah, right, exactly.
But I also suddenly have a giant swath of other options that I hadn't previously considered.
So that's still exciting to, but it definitely took me a little bit out.
And it was like a day or two where I was like, why, what am I, why am I feeling like this?
Like, what is like, the facts don't add up to how this is making me feel.
So you had to pause and be like, oh, yeah, right.
This is what's happening.
And I think it didn't help to that I kind of really like my current place.
Your place is great.
Yeah, for sure.
I see kind of a link in moving house to traveling in the sense that it sort of puts a break
in your everyday routines.
Oh, yeah.
And forces you to sort of look around, right, and reevaluate and have an opportunity to
change things.
And that's what I love that aspect and that it's so interesting, comparing how you live,
you know, because we're all I mean, we're all living, we all have have lives and do
things and make constant decisions every day and not in like a judgment way.
But just in a I think I heard it.
I think I heard this quote on like, remember the show, what was it like a seventh heaven
or something like a religious?
And I think the dad said something like, you know, you're like, life is basically just
like a sum of all of the choices that you make.
And I like that idea, even though I think the show was obviously terrible, and I was
just flipping through channels or whatever and heard this, but it just stuck in my mind.
And so it's just interesting to, you know, as you compare each little choice of like,
well, when do you push yourself?
When do you not?
When do you move?
How do you place yourself in the world?
What's the sum you want to get to?
It's a good question.
I have some ideas.
It's very much a work in progress.
As we all are.
One thing I struggle with is the difference in paths is that if you all of a sudden choose
one fork in the road, I struggle with trying to accept that the other fork is now no longer
possible.
You just cut that off.
Which is not always true.
You can always sort of reach for alternatives later down the road, but they're necessarily
going to be different.
They're going to be different.
Right.
Do you have any techniques you use to deal with that?
Hold myself closely and cry.
Right.
Cat cuddles, maybe?
Cats help, certainly.
No, it's something I've struggled with that I don't know that I've found the answer to
for myself.
And there is some perfectionism in that.
You want to make the best choice, right?
You don't have all the information because you can't.
But sometimes both options are equally good only for varied reasons.
And so then my toolkit is empty of tools to help me deal with that.
Right.
And so I can be very slow at making those types of decisions.
Choosing home, I guess, fits into that realm a little bit.
It is, you know, I think it's hard to there's, there's probably an element of whatever agreeability
and logicalness, you know, it's like, some of those bigger ideas.
It's hard if you aren't falling in love with them, you know, because if it is one of those
things, you're just like, Oh, my gosh, yes, like, I was driving to this place.
I love this town.
I'm already working remotely.
I want to live there.
I'm gonna go do it.
If you can fall in love with this idea so much, then everything's easy.
I mean, you might still have a lot of problems, but makes it easier.
There's so many things in life that just aren't, you know, it's like, okay, I gotta make this
choice.
I know that it matters a whole bunch, and we'll have a bunch of outcomes I can't foresee.
But it's probably both are fine.
Right.
What do you do?
I mean, you flip a coin, I guess, at the end of the day, but the coins are really useful.
That's for sure.
I never really trust what they say.
So
I flip a smartphone, I think.
I don't know that we have coin money.
That sounds a bit more expensive if it all goes wrong.
There's someone I really love named Derek Sivers.
Do you know him at all?
I don't think so.
He built CD Baby.
Oh, okay.
But one thing he, I guess it's a concept that he's sort of spread around, which is he calls
hell yeah or no.
Which boils down to either you feel very jazzed about an idea and you say, hell yeah, I want
to do that, or you should just say no to it.
And while that seems really simple to implement, I've actually noticed that it's profound in
that for those of us who are agreeable, and tend to go along with what seems like okay
ideas or okay paths that others set for us or convince us to follow or what it may be,
it's almost like a preset filter that allows you to tap into how you feel, you know, just
ask the question, well, how do I feel about this?
And often I found that pause is enough to convince you of what you actually feel instead
of what you're sort of empathizing with.
And maybe related thing that just makes me think you're talking a little bit about friend
circles and other, and I feel like that applies a lot to like, there's the difference between
like, being around people, friends and like, more meaningful friendships, and both are
fine.
I mean, you know, there's nothing, nothing wrong with that.
But it just thinks a lot, you know, like, sometimes you have those moments where you
finally ask that question, and you're like, I mean, like, why am I, it's not that it's
bad, right?
But you're just like, these aren't my people, or this is not my venue.
And I don't have to be here, right?
But that can sometimes be a difficult thing is saying, wait, I'm, I don't feel like I
should be here.
And therefore, I will leave.
And I think it'd be hard to if you don't necessarily, you might not have an immediate replacement
to it, right?
So it's like, well, come out and do this thing with us, or do nothing.
I mean, not, you probably won't do nothing.
But at the time, it feels that way.
So maybe we should all have our own defaults.
If we're doing nothing, we can just do something that we really love or find really useful.
I'm trying to do better at that.
I mean, because I've had both, your quote made me think of the opposite advice, which
I think is said a lot of like, just trying to say yes to more things, which is, I think,
applicable in different scenarios.
And it probably depends on what phase you're going through, because that can be really
good if you've just moved or exploring something new or need change in your life.
Like it's tied to a sense of adventure, as opposed to a sense of not being so busy or
optimizing the tasks you do have time for.
Curious.
I've mentioned a few books, I think.
Are there books you're reading recently that really get you jazzed?
I am rereading because I read it very quickly and wanted to read it again.
It's a book, getting the name of the author right now, but surely we'll have show notes
or some such.
Yeah, we can come up with such a thing.
I imagine we have the technology.
It's called Why Buddhism is True, which is a ridiculous title, but is very much a book
about the more, I don't want to just say like science-based, but more secular side, I guess,
of Buddhism.
And I think hits a lot on some of the topics we've talked about and just that.
It ties it a lot to, because the author has a lot of theology knowledge and psychology
and twists those ideas together and points out, here's some of the things that Buddhism
teaches and here's why these make sense once you understand how your brain works and why.
All of what we are is the image painted from our brains as it's exposed.
The brain creates our understanding and view of the world, of course, and you should know
that it doesn't, you know, wise is maybe too strong of a word, but it has other incentives
and programming built into it than just what we are or as part of us, however you want
to conceptualize mind, and you should be aware, you should be thinking about that.
But I really liked it, too, because there has been a lot of Buddhism and Buddhist teachings
that I've enjoyed, but I struggle with some of the more mystical elements of it.
It just doesn't strike my, not that I don't appreciate some of the history or culture,
but as practical advice that's just not my jam, I want like science.
So I found this book really nice as a way to A, learn more about Buddhism and B, I just
thought it had a lot of good practical advice.
Yeah, it sounds like it leans a little bit more towards what you can implement and yet
not necessarily have the depth of spirituality that sometimes is required for some.
Yes.
And yeah, so there's like, that was actually what first got me meditating, too, because
it's kind of like the author describes an experience of like going to like a whole meditation
camp and then like coming out at the end and talking a little bit about their experience
of figuring out how to actually get that in their day-to-day life and the things that
did matter and didn't matter to them about that or what they actually took away and sort
of interesting case.
It was like, yeah, okay, I see, I see what you're getting at here, but I don't need a
shaman to, you know, sit with me in a very hot room for hours.
I mean, you're assuming the room is hot.
Maybe if we take the right drugs, but otherwise, no.
I have found in the same way this exploration of those kind of the desire to understand
your own mind, to then optimize it for the tasks that you generally have to solve, be
it technical tasks, but also tasks such as choosing what to work on and choosing how
to work on it, gaining knowledge of how your own mind works, while this general schooling
we're exposed to doesn't really dive into those topics.
And so I found that same curiosity of like, well, wait a second, like I know my mind is
all over the place and that it can also be hyper-focused and how do I understand the
difference between those two and guide it in the ways that I need to when I need to.
Yes.
And I think a lot of like what tools we are provided by whatever traditional society,
they're all wrapped up in like judgments and shame too, right?
Like there are all these like prescriptive things like you shouldn't do this or, you
know, that's a bad idea just because.
And like there is, yeah, that probably is a bad idea.
We know like history shows us that that doesn't work, but it's a bad idea just because, you
know, you should know because your brain works or at least be informed so that you can be,
you know, make different decisions or be more insightful as you go down whatever path you're
going to go down.
Right.
When someone tells you if that you should or shouldn't do something, do you find yourself
needing to understand the why before?
Depends on the situation.
But yeah, generally, yes, I'm a, I'm a why kind of person.
So like definitely like the best, you know, managers or bosses or whatever have been able
to do that.
It's like, you know, really, it's like I like to separate those because if I've agreed,
there's multiple concerns here.
So there's like the imposed authority sort of situation, which let's put that out the
window for you.
In the situation where I've agreed that I'll do what you say for money or whatever, I'm
okay with that pre-arranged agreement as long as A, I can tell you if I think what you're
doing, telling me to do is dumb, I'll still do it.
If you make me make, you know, ask or whatever.
But the other side of that is I want to know why regardless just because I want help, like
I want to do it the best I can.
And if I don't know why, I can't do that.
I find that to be a real challenge for me too, is that if I don't know why, then I can't
optimize the task at hand to create the best outcome, because none of this stuff is really
linear, right?
And it's all within in situ, you know, there's context around that if I don't know, like
you just can't, can't anticipate.
And sometimes maybe you can't know.
And that's okay as a temporary sort of answer, but at least get that far.
Yeah, context is a great word for that.
That's a way simpler way to explore it for me is that I need some context to understand
the path.
I was listening to a really interesting interview on the way up to the studio today, talking
about some issues in language education and young children, and how a lot of the approaches
today kind of focus on, like separating things so that, you know, you learn how to learn,
which is good.
It's not that that's bad.
But like, you remember those standardized tests where you have like a bad nonsense passage,
and then you have to identify like, what are the points and what are the three or what's
the main topic?
What are the three supporting arguments in here?
Yes.
And while that is useful, all the studies then went and showed that like, while that
it can be good, like if you have kids who are either good, you know, scored on some
like reading comprehension scale, and then you present them passages about different
subjects, what really matters is how much they know about that subject, you know.
So like, if you don't know anything about the subject, even if you're great at trying
to understand it, you might get farther, but you're still going to do worse than someone
with quote unquote, poor reading comprehension who knows even a little bit about that subject.
I just thought it was interesting, especially hearing discussions about this with adults,
how much context in the world we take for granted and just don't talk about and kids
don't have that.
Wow.
And many times we don't either, right?
If you're traveling or in a new situation, but it's almost impossible to see if you already
have it.
I love this.
In travel, because you mentioned travel, you can easily clearly see this if you travel
to a place for the first time, it's total chaos in your mind trying to figure out all
the pieces and how they all fit together.
There are no systems.
No.
And then, but if you've ever come back to that, let's say you travel to the same city
for the same reason three months later, and you've already been through the path, you've
got all this context to figure it out.
And so if you're throwing some curveballs, it's like, well, I've already figured out
80% of this.
So I can deal with this curveball far easier.
Wow, I can see how that could apply to much more than just the education.
Yeah.
Right.
Aspect.
Fascinating.
Do you remember what the podcast was called?
Well, it was on the local public radio station here in Seattle, so I can certainly find it.
I don't remember the name of the author's last researcher.
That's all right.
We'll see if we can link it.
I think we can.
We have the technology.
Well, Wes, thanks for chatting.
I admit I wasn't sure where this was going to go, but it's gone in all sorts of fascinating
topics.
Everywhere.
Let's do this again.
Super fun.
Thanks so much.
Next time, right?
We'll see about that.
Thanks, Wes.
Well, I hope you enjoyed that chat.
I absolutely loved that conversation.
The brunches are the best.
You can find more over at extras.show.
You can find this show's website at coder.show.
Links to what the guys talked about today is at coder.show slash 412.
Thank you to our Coder QA members who helped make this show possible.
You do have a new coder lease, so go grab that.
You can also find our contact form as well as our RSS feed and everything else over at
our website.
And we'd love to have you join us live for the Coder Radio happy hour.
Live Mondays at 5 p.m. Pacific, 8 p.m. Eastern over at jblive.tv.
It's a lot more fun when you watch it live, but we appreciate everyone who downloads too.
Thanks so much for tuning into this week's episode of the Coder Radio program.
We'll see you right back here next week.