This is KOTOR Radio, episode 491 for November 7th, 2022.
Hey good buddy, welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
My name is Chris and joining us every single week, hopefully fully caffeinated, it's our
host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
Damn, skip it Chris, I'm a pot of coffee in and I have a steaming cup of hot matcha right
next to me.
In.
Yes!
Cause I'm, you know, I'm no pleb.
In a mad-botterer cup.
Ah, very good.
A mad-botterer coffee cup, yep.
You know, I'm still loving that KOTOR robe.
Still loving it.
Just rocking it the other day.
It's all I wear when the mailman comes.
You know, I really genuinely had the thought the other day, like, why don't I just wear
this all the time and nothing but this when I'm just going to be home all day?
It doesn't happen very often, but my God, the two things together are so glorious.
So, so glorious.
We are gathered here today mostly, I think, to hear about your two-factor nightmare and
looks like you went deep into Swift again.
So that's going to be, I think, the bulk of the show today.
However, since we gathered together last week, there has been a tremendous amount of news.
So we're going to do a little hangover watch for the economy, pour yourself a cup of coffee.
Yeah.
I found a new site that I wanted to tell you about that is shocking.
It's called layoffs.fyi and it's currently tracking 755 startups with over a hundred
and four thousand layoffs in 22 so far.
And of course you can jump around, you can look at the charts.
They've got, they're doing some really interesting ways of tracking it and showing different
waves of different, I guess, phases of layoffs since COVID-19 really hit.
And the list is, it's kind of depressing to see, honestly, but the news has been unbelievable.
Today before we started recording, Apple announced an update on the supply of iPhone 14 and
iPhone 14 Pro Max.
I haven't seen one of these updates since about 2008 or 2009.
They say that, they say due to COVID-19 restrictions in China and the concern about the health
of their workers, they are going to miss the supply and that they will have more shipments
than previously anticipated that will experience longer wait times as they will be producing
fewer iPhones.
And we've seen rumors about less iPhone demand.
And I had speculated that that would be an early recession indicator is all of a sudden
a thousand dollar phone looks a little ridiculous.
When times are good and the money's flowing, you can buy a $1,100 phone.
But when the price of gas is going up on a monthly basis and the price of food still
going up, $1,100 phone is kind of silly sometimes.
And I think Apple's feeling, they're blaming COVID-19, but they've also been moving more
and more manufacturing to India and Taiwan and other places.
So I don't know.
But I think that's a big indicator there.
Also today's the day that Elon set the deadline for Twitter Blue and it seems to have worked,
remember?
He said they have until like the seventh or they're fired.
Yeah.
Well, they're fired.
And they're rolling out the Twitter Blue.
They're rolling out the new membership stuff.
I think they, although yeah, a lot of them are fired.
You know, I've been thinking about this too.
Imagine what we're going to see here after, if Elon pulls this off even somewhat, and
if the metric is going by ruthless CEO standards in the market, not going by human standards,
if the metric is profitability, he might do it.
I mean, if he gets thousands of people to pay eight bucks a month and he lays off 60%
of the staff, he might get it.
And if he has verified accounts, advertisers are going to eat that up.
I mean, right now you're seeing advertisers pause, but once they know that that's a genuine
human who's been verified and that they know exactly what kind of things they like, that
in terms of an ad buy, a person who is a knowable, verifiable person is worth substantially more
than an anonymous number.
Right.
Than an impression on a page or a CPM or anything like that.
Sure.
So what if we're seeing an extreme recession model be created here?
You'll see other tech companies essentially go on sale.
They'll have some CEO that buys them out ruthlessly, comes in, fires half the staff, brings in
their own people, basically carves it down to an MVP, takes it private, does all of this
work, because you wouldn't do it when it's a public company, does all this carving.
It's kind of the Romney strategy of past, you know, the bank capital strategy, only
it's for tech companies now.
And it's by tech CEOs.
And I think if he pulls it off, and I'm not saying this is a good thing.
If he pulls this off, I think it's going to be looked at as a model for the next two years,
because we're going into a multi-year recession and there's going to be a lot of businesses
on sale.
And I think this is going to be the play, is the idea is you go in, you clean up, and
then you turn it around.
And by the time the market's picking back up in 2024, 2025, you bring it public again,
you make a bunch of money.
Yeah.
I mean, I think Twitter itself, I mean, that could be a model that generally works.
I still feel kind of going along with what I said last week, that Twitter itself has
some unique problems.
One, I mean, I don't know if you've noticed this.
I know I'm much more active on Twitter than you generally are.
My Twitter feed is basically worthless now.
And I used to get a lot of good tech news, dev news, follow a bunch of open source people
or people at Microsoft, stuff like that, because it's everybody just being mad about Elon.
And I understand that it's just strange.
The things I've been saying are the Magic the Gathering 30th anniversary event and Elon
hate.
So I feel like he's somehow got to get a handle on this.
Now, of course, the Internet's attention span is like that of my dogs.
So maybe, you know, maybe he just needs to ride it out for another week.
Yeah.
I mean, I think inevitably, once we get past all this, right, and I think this, I don't
really want to go on about Twitter, but yeah, I think inevitably, people just, they freak
out, they have an absolute panic attack.
And then in six months, they pretend like it never happened.
That's our current state of the world right now.
Right.
I mean, as far as like the way I like to use Twitter, other than like trolling and like
memes or whatever, I still feel like Google Plus was a much better like techie social
network where I got more valuable data than I ever did with Twitter.
Right.
Like I had different circles for perfect example.
So Google Plus, I had like an iOS dev circle I was in and I had your whatever the JB one
was right there was like, I don't know if it was official by you or what.
Yeah, yeah.
Yep.
It was like the JB circle.
You could have like the, Hey, I have this problem with like UI table view conversation
and avoid getting the, you know, sometimes friendly, sometimes less than friendly trolling
from the Linux folks, right?
And then you could have the Linux conversation about, you know, whatever open source.
I think at the time I was like trying to help out with Geary or something like that.
It was better, right?
Than just like scream.
I feel like Twitter in a lot of ways is, you know, going to the Empire State Building and
just shouting at the top of your lungs.
So I don't know, I, maybe I'm just retroactively assigning more value to the Google Plus than
there really was.
But I felt like I had more serious, deeper conversations that actually produced you know,
mutual value.
Right.
Oh, absolutely.
Mastodon is seeing a big boom right now.
So some people are moving over there.
I want to keep going on the Hangover Watch though.
Apple also warned investors they predict a substantial drop in Mac revenue for the holiday
quarter.
Tim Cook made it clear during the earnings call with investors that the company is subject
to impacts of the macro economy, which has been affected by the war in Eastern Europe
and as a consequence of the pandemic.
In other words, the supply chain and inflation is going to cost them.
Well, and they sold a ton of MacBook Airs, right?
The MacBook Air, see, I know our audience, we're all like MacBook Pros, you know, or
the Linux folks, whatever.
They sold a lot of those and those buyers are your average Joe and Jane.
They're buying maybe every three years.
So and there was huge pent up debate.
I worry that if the iPhone is being paused in production and they're predicting a quote
substantial drop in Mac revenue, which Apple is usually very accurate about these things.
I think we're going to see dark Apple.
I think we really are.
You know, there is also since we got together, developers have discovered that recent changes
made to the App Store ads sort of raised some serious privacy concerns.
It seems that the App Store app on iOS 14.6 and up is sending every tap you make inside
the app everywhere to Apple.
We that could be exploited.
There's some uncertainty is that if you have analytics on or not, right, or is it by default?
I wonder, though, you combine this with the recent gambling ad stuff.
And that's that, of course, you know, they they they just knocked the knees out from
meta for app tracking and a bunch of other advertising platforms.
And they've only been turning it up on their own platform.
And it's this, I think, is pretty alarming.
Because if their hardware sales are going to go down, then they're just going to have
to push even harder on services.
And they just raised the rate of Apple one.
They're all in subscription package.
The level of details in the video that they show here is striking.
Gruber says Apple ads are going wild.
Even Gruber is not on board.
Jason Snell, also very concerned, like long time Apple commentators feel like we're starting
to see dark Apple develop here.
And I just got to imagine a recession with hardware sales is just going to make the situation
even worse.
I think Apple is becoming more and more of a threat factor.
It sucks because the M1 hardware, the M2 stuff, I'm sure is going to be great.
Like the M series is fantastic.
But Apple is a company, I think, not good.
We mentioned the Twitter layoffs.
Jack Dorsey came out playing cover for Elon Musk, said it's his fault.
They hired too many people.
Facebook has announced they are planning, quote, large scale layoffs this week.
Stripe is cutting its head count by 14%, readies for, quote, leaner times.
Lyft to lay off 700 employees in a second round of job cuts.
And Lyft has been having just a bear of a time for a couple of years.
Amazon executives confirm a hiring freeze.
Additionally, the scuttlebutt in my local town is they have a ginormous Amazon facility
by the studio that's going to bring 2,000 trucks a day into my area.
And it was about 95% finished, and Amazon hit the pause button.
And they're not going to finish it until proceeds go up, because they don't know if there's
enough demand for another warehouse in this area.
So they're just going to leave it at 90% finished.
They're going to have to keep security on it.
They're going to have to keep the lights on.
And there's a lot of homeless around here.
So if they're not constantly guarding it, it's going to turn into a ginormous homeless
encampment.
Oh, my god.
It's really going to be something.
And it's wild, because it's just this huge building that blocked my view of the mountains
and just totally took over the skyline.
And they're just hitting pause.
I mean, we've been saying it for months now, right?
I know.
It's going to be an icy winter.
So why do we talk about it?
We talk about it not because we want to watch the economic porn.
We're not talking about it because we want to scare you.
We're talking about it because these macro trends are going to impact developers.
They're going to impact client jobs.
They're going to impact employment.
They're going to impact your negotiation abilities.
There's a real world impact that's going to hit the development community.
And they're going to be hit hardest because this is specifically going after tech.
Investors are pivoting from growth stocks to value stocks.
They're literally transferring money out of tech stocks, like another trillion dollars
in tech stocks was drained last year or last week, last week.
And they're putting it into other places, assets and other stocks that are like value
stocks and things like that.
And the tech companies are getting hit the hardest because the tech companies were the
biggest recipients of the easy money for the last decade.
And so now they're getting hit the hardest and it's going to directly affect our community.
And we've been talking about it, but now it's actually happening.
And it just seems like the pace is picking up faster and faster.
You got to wonder where we're going to be in a couple of months.
A couple of months.
Right.
We're going to see more layoffs.
I agree with you on the multi year thing.
I think this actually doesn't hit the depending on how you want to look at it, the peak of
pain or the trough of misery.
Right.
It's going to be a maximalist destruction probably for another whole year.
You convinced me of something last week and I was thinking about it after the show.
I don't think that unless you get a sorry, Europeans, this is super America, United States.
Our Canadian friends don't like it when we say America, the super U.S. focused.
But unless you have a Republican sweep in Congress, there is no way Biden is going to
not turn on the money printer.
He'll tolerate it for maybe a year, but not if this isn't going to be five years because
they'll never win another election.
It's just unfortunately, the whole the whole economy and the populace as a whole is now
addicted to printing money.
And everything runs on printed money now.
Everything runs on.
You know, you take a look at the housing market, which is going down somewhat.
But the prices are still unattainable for your average, you know, your average 20 something
coming out of college, getting married, whatever.
Where if you go back to the halcyon days after World War Two and let's even say like the
60s, 70s, that was much more doable.
And not only that, that was the normal, very attainable path.
So same thing for wages.
This is not one that you'll see in the Wall Street Journal, but I think it's interesting
that we effectively lease everything now in terms of all these services instead of actually
owning anything as something that's been on my mind.
Like I paid 10 bucks a month to listen to the same maybe 30 albums when I could have
just bought.
And I, in fact, do have many of them either in iTunes purchased or CD or whatever.
The universe that happens if they just let this burn is a total realignment of the economy.
And probably that's actually good if you're a little guy, if you can survive it.
Because I don't, I think tech businesses, particularly software businesses are gonna
sober up a little bit and go back to, hey, we actually have to be a business where we
sell or license a product and actually make money.
Where I can tell you one of my big pain points has been, and I've talked to other people
in similar positions, VC backed companies who are just a drunk on the free money, find
out you're a competitor and they're like, oh, they're charging 8,000 or 5,000 for a
license or whatever, we'll do it for 500, right?
They just literally kneecap you and effectively bleed out your capital, right?
Cause you're bootstrapped.
So that might be my hobby horse, but I think it's bad that all these people are losing
their jobs.
Obviously I feel for them on a human level.
But these businesses, and I'm thinking less of the big, big guys and more of like the
VC companies that are trying to kind of edge their way in.
They need to be real businesses, right?
Even it's funny, you mentioned all these big dudes.
Apple in a way was on this list, the only traditional business that when it started
had to actually make money.
Go down that list, Twitter, Facebook.
My thinking though is if it hits these big guys, it's gonna be even harder on the small
ones.
Well, what's gonna be harder is I think consulting could become harder cause you're gonna have
a bunch of like ex Facebook engineers who are like, screw it, I'm gonna go 1099 it out.
And you know, that's very sexy for the, you know, the marketing agency hiring an iOS dev
for a contract or something.
Sure.
But yeah, I mean, it's bad overall.
Don't get me wrong.
I'm saying there's a slight silver lining, but this is a bloodbath and it shouldn't have
happened.
It shouldn't have.
But just to touch on the human moment just a little bit, because we often talk about
it from a business owner, CEO kind of market perspective, but regular everyday people are
paying the price for policies that led us here.
And last week I watched Chair Powell's update on, you know, another rate increase.
And he signaled he's going, he's gonna go for a while.
Pedal to the metal, baby.
Yeah.
And one of the things I love about the mindblower is so there are 12 members of the feds open
market committee that vote for these rate increases.
And one of them is Esther George.
And she is the president of the Federal Reserve Bank of Kansas City.
She's on this 12 member board that votes for the rate increases.
And she did something really unusual.
She had an interview with NPR.
In this interview, she says they're basically going to keep going until American savings
account are drained.
Quote, we see today that there is a bit of savings buffer still sitting for households.
That may allow them to continue to spend in a way that keeps demand strong, she said.
That suggests we may have to keep at this for a while.
Because regular Americans have too much money, they're gonna have to keep at this for a while,
because they can afford the inflation for a little while.
And then, you know, you look at what Powell says is he says employment's too high.
The employment market's still too hot, is his term.
They need to cool down the employment market.
There's still too many jobs available.
There's not enough people unemployed.
So you've got a clear, like they want to raise employment and they want to make Americans
spend their savings buffer so that way they can lower demand, which will lower pressure
on the supply chain, which will then fix inflation.
So they're talking about like fourth order effects they're going for here.
And the experiment is being done on the middle class average workers, while the people that
are rich will be able to just buy up assets that become super cheap as a result of this.
Distressed assets.
Yeah, and they'll just totally blow up in value when the market returns and they'll
make a ton of money.
And meanwhile, the American people, the average people will be left with less sales and a
higher standing unemployment, which is going to bring the quality of life down for everyone.
And that's their stated policy.
Yeah.
I mean, we should get off the doom and gloom, but I think I also saw her on NPR.
I think it's actually slightly worse than you describe it.
I think there's a thing you kind of missed.
It's not just savings.
It's spending power, which is a euphemism for credit.
So what is likely to happen, and we've seen this before, right?
2008, remember that, it's a good time.
Most households are not going to immediately cut their standard of living.
They're going to, yes, burn through savings, but they're also going to leverage every bit
of credit they have.
And at the end of this, you're going to have a lot of bankruptcies.
And what will happen is the people lucky enough to own modest homes, this is going to be a
party for BlackRock Capital, right?
You're going to have a lot of foreclosures because people use home equity credit if they
have any.
A lot of just bankruptcy is caused by straight up credit card debt.
And yeah, you're going to see payday lending is going to go up, which you should never
ever do that, by the way.
In a weird way, this is going to be, since we're using the addiction analogy, right?
This is going to be, okay, the Fed's cutting off your legal opioid supply.
Now you're doing street heroin.
The history proves it out, and I am 100% sure it will be the same this time.
People aren't just going to say, I'm lowering my family's day-to-day standard of living
significantly.
They're going to whip out that capital.
Not until they're forced.
Well, when they max everything out, right?
But it's not just savings, right?
It's not capital.
It's also debt.
Yeah, you're right.
Yeah, so.
Yeah.
So I think people that can focus on doing more with less, people that can focus on building
a minimum viable product value are probably going to have the most success.
And there's going to be a correction in other places.
That's not true.
The super-rich are still going to have the most success.
Well, that's true.
If you bought Apple in 1995, you're in great shape.
No matter what, right?
Linode.com slash coder.
That's where you go to get $100, and it's a great way to support the show.
You get $100 on a new account for 60 days, linode.com slash coder.
Linode is quite simply the best place to build your next application, host your infrastructure,
or run a personal site or a gaming server.
Linode has a really easy-to-use dashboard, and they have one-click deployments for things
like Joplin, Git Tea, Focalboard, which is sort of like a Trello system that you can
just self-host up on Linode, and when you have our $100 credit, why not?
It's like if Trello and Asana had a tacit affair and had a baby, that would be Focalboard,
and you can deploy it with one click up over on the Linode dashboard.
So many great things in here.
I mentioned Gaming Server 2, one-click deployment of the Minecraft Java edition, actually several
game servers, several, including, you know, adult games.
I'm talking about development stuff like Node.js, Nextcloud.
That's my form of gaming, at least.
So they have the one-click deployments, and they have a dozen data centers around the
world, and they're adding another dozen throughout 2023, so they just keep moving from strength
to strength.
They started almost 19 years ago, and they just had to survive on a great product, and
now here we are, standing on the shoulders of generations of development.
It's really quite nice.
I had an opportunity recently to deploy one of their GPU systems, 96 gigs of RAM.
It had an RTX 6000 GPU, three times over.
Unbelievable, and it has a 40 gigabit connection to the network.
Their systems are screaming fast, regardless of which build you go with, because they are
their own ISP, so they all have 40 gigabit connections.
They have NVMe PCIe storage.
They have AMD EPYC processors, if you want a rig that has really fast processors.
They have high memory systems.
This is one thing I've never really needed.
I do have a system that does have 96 gigs of RAM, our matrix server, but they have systems
where you can get like, you know, 300 gigs of RAM.
And because Linode has the best support ever, if you've got a question, you get stuck, or
you want to talk about a custom plan, they'll work with you on that as well.
365, they pick up the phone, they answer your questions.
Because again, as a business, they had to survive on the merits of their product, and
support is part of that product.
And it just reflects throughout the entire Linode product.
They have so many great things over there, like object storage, Kubernetes support, databases
as a service, and a lot more.
So go try it out, support the show, and get $100 on a new account.
You go to linode.com slash coder.
One more time, to support the show, it's linode.com slash coder.
So I get the sense you've been deep diving into Swift, but before we get there, I want
to chat about your recent go about with losing a device, and how I think you almost lost
access to everything, at least based on the chat we had.
One way Apple gets device sales is people who are forced to.
My iPhone 12 Pro, whatever it was, had an unfortunate trick-or-treating accident.
So I got it kind of working, but of course, it was shattered.
It stopped working completely.
In the time it was working, I thought it was going to be OK, and I had failed to take off
my Google Authenticator from it.
Oh, yes.
Oh, my gosh.
Yep.
Been there.
So OK, I have no phone now, which is super not viable for running a business.
So I march my little butt over to my local Verizon reseller, because for some reason,
you can do Verizon's back to doing the two-year thing, and I've had Verizon for like 10 years.
So I go, I get me a handy new iPhone 14 Pro Max, which I can tell you, if I didn't smash
my 12 Pro, I would not have gotten, because it's just not that different.
It's a little bigger.
It's more purple.
Which I like, but it's not worth what it costs in terms of upgrades.
No wonder the iPhone 14 isn't selling.
Yeah, they say the camera's better.
I can't see it.
That might just be whatever.
I really could not tell much of a difference between the 12, 13, or the 14.
As you know, I'm on the upgrade plan.
I got my 14.
It's fine.
So was the 13, except the device-to-device transfer did not transfer everything like
I had been told it would.
And they've added a new screen after you're done doing device-to-device transfer.
On the original device, your old device, they now come up with a screen that says, would
you like to erase this device?
Because I've been led to believe everything was copied over in a moment of lapse of judgment,
I said, yeah, go ahead and erase it.
Oh, no.
Then the password prompt for my iCloud account came up, and it says, you got to enter your
password before we can erase this device.
And I thought, OK, yeah.
I don't feel like doing that, because I got to go look it up on Bitward, and so I'll let
me log into my new phone.
So I log into the new phone, and I realize it's like doing that download from the app
store and restoring stuff, and I launch a few of my apps, and they have none of my state,
including my two-factor app.
So I pick up the old phone, and I go hit Cancel.
I'm raising my finger to tap the Cancel button, and before I can hit Cancel, the password
screen clears.
Oh, god.
And it begins the wipe process.
And it wipes my phone.
Oh, so you feel my pain.
Yeah.
So tell me what happened.
All right.
So I'm super, so I get the phone.
I don't know what goes on at the Verizon store, but it always takes an hour and a half to
get out of there.
But sure enough, it took an hour and a half.
I think it's the eSIM.
They just had a hard time activating the phone.
I think they just have a countdown timer on their point-of-sales device, and they just
come up with a reason to keep you there for an hour and a half.
Maybe it's like, baby, get paid by the hour you're there or something.
It was weird.
But so whatever.
I get it.
Then I realized about the Google Authenticator.
So I'm like, crap.
So I'm desperately trying to get my other phone to unlock while I'm sitting there waiting
for this dude.
Won't do it.
Won't turn on nothing.
Dead at DOA.
Gone.
Luckily, I had diligently saved my override codes.
I can't say this is the first time this has happened.
Something like this, especially because I've been using 2FA for a very long time.
On one service that I will not name, I only have two override codes left.
So it got me thinking, after I had spent roughly an entire afternoon unlocking and re-2FAing
everything, what happens if you just run out of override codes?
Do you know what happens?
I would imagine then it's going to depend on what their support policies are.
It's going to be per platform.
With the exception of Facebook.
The only one who will override 2FA for you is Facebook, and they require you to send
them your driver's license.
Yeah, you know, I could see that.
They're probably dealing with boomers all the time that are losing their account.
No offense.
Listen, get off my lawn.
So by the way, we are boomers.
Look at how we bitch about the economy, right?
We're down with it.
I am literally considered a millennial.
Yeah, so am I.
You're on the edge.
I'm on the edge.
I'm on the line.
So it turns out that the answer to my question is, you're hosed.
There is no, for almost every service, there is no way around that.
Yeah, get a new account.
Get a new account.
And in the case of Matrix, message Chris and have him just reset it for you.
Thanks, Chris.
Right?
Thanks, Wes, really.
Thanks, Wes.
I asked Wes.
You asked me.
So I have a couple ideas here.
One, what I'm doing now is I got rid of Google Auth completely, and I'm just using my phone
number.
Oh, OK.
Which in itself is problematic, right?
It's not as good.
It's slow.
There's a problem with their Twilio integration, which is probably what most of them are using.
And there's a good amount of documented public hacks where somebody got through because they're
using SMS two-factor.
Well, right.
And it's just SMS, not iMessage.
I propose that as Apple wants to conquer more of the known universe, they should make an
iMessage-specific 2FA system, like a Google Auth that runs through iMessage.
That if you have access, because think about it, Apple has your biometrics, right?
In my case, they have two fingerprints, a couple face scans.
Well, I think they scan your face like every five, 10 minutes, but a bunch of face scans.
I have multiple passwords.
They have my phone.
If you're also wearing the watch, the watch is on you, and they know how close it is to
the phone, which is just another data point.
So why couldn't that be the override?
It seems like a system, and I know some of our InfoSec listeners are going to be, well,
every override is an attack vector.
That's true, but I fear, and I've always pushed 2FA, I just fear that even me, who knows what
he's doing other than destroying his iPhone, people are going to have this experience like
I did, but be a little less savvy and not know how to get around it, or frankly, not
save their override codes, which I think is probably super likely, super common, right?
And they're just going to stop using 2FA altogether, which is a bad idea, to be clear.
So I don't know.
I mean, it was a nightmare.
It wasted most of a day.
Discord was surprisingly hard to recover.
And I only use Discord for Patreon things that I follow.
I don't particularly care for Discord.
If I didn't know better, right, I probably wouldn't have re-enabled 2FA on anything,
because it was such a pain in the ass to get stuff back.
And I think about things like, my Discord is the perfect example.
I support a bunch of things that I follow, like Unfilter, even though Chris won't give
me any new episodes because he doesn't love me anymore.
I can't remember Shannon Morris's channel, a bunch of Magic the Gathering stuff that
you people never want to hear about because you don't love Magic the Gathering like I
do.
Of course.
But I have tons of content that I can only get in that Discord account, right, that I
like to watch.
Right, right.
Yeah.
So what would I have to do?
I thought about it.
So what if it fails?
Okay, well, I have to somehow get a hold of Shannon Morris, who probably has some pretty
aggressive filters, I would assume.
So actually getting in touch would be challenging.
I have to get all these random YouTubers who play Magic, again, who I have a feeling have
some pretty aggressive, you know, filters up, to individually respond to me, believe
me that I am one of the people paying their Patreon, and then somehow let me just give
them another Discord handle that they can give the access to.
There's an entire manual process that I would need about six people to do.
Many of them, I'm pretty sure, never read their DMs, nor should they.
So that would suck.
I imagine this is what life also feels like, say, your Google account gets turned off.
It's a very similar thing.
There's a gentleman we could ask about that from a month ago, right?
Yeah.
And I also use my Google account to authenticate to several services as well outside of that.
Well, I do too.
For all my work stuff, because I use G Suite, it's all Google.
Like I can't use my, if I lost my Google account, I could not use GitHub anymore.
Because I have the SSO thing.
So you know what saved my bacon in this situation, and I'm not necessarily saying you should
do it this way, but what saved my bacon was I use Authy, which syncs your two factors
across your different devices that you have Authy on, and I happen to have it installed
on an M1 Mac Mini desktop.
The M1 saves the day.
So I could do my two factor when I was sitting at that machine from the desktop, and so I
was able to pull it up on that device and then resync my new phone.
But it took me two days before I remembered that because I don't use that Mac Mini very
often.
So I was like for two days, genuinely depressed that I had f that up so badly and that I knew
what a, because everything has two factor and I mean, hundreds of different services
and sites I have just for JB alone, not to mention all my personal stuff.
Like I was mourning the loss of my two factor codes, and then I remembered it was on that
machine.
So having that sync, I don't think it makes it as secure and it makes Authy, you know.
It seems like Authy is the obvious attack factor then.
Yeah.
Right.
Is it syncing the actual generated codes or is it syncing the overwrite?
Yes.
Okay.
That's actually pretty good.
You know, don't do like I do, but that was that worked really well.
Bitwarden can also be a tool in this bitwarden.com slash Linux if you want to support our shows.
This is an awful experience and the other thing that's really challenging here is if
you're trying to go from iPhone to Android, some of the stuff doesn't move over either.
Yeah.
If you're with an all Apple solution, you'd be tied to Apple and they'd have a lock on
that.
So I just, but you wouldn't want Google to do it either.
I wouldn't want any of these major companies to do it.
Well, the problem is if, you know, security now, right, TNO, trust no one, but that includes
yourself.
So if you're doing a true trust no one security set up, it is totally possible to screw yourself
these.
I feel like our rough areas, technology needs to work out and as we have more and more digital
assets that we place value on, this just becomes a bigger and bigger problem.
Like your photos, you know, your email, cryptocurrency, pictures of like JPEG monkeys, I don't know,
like whatever people think is worth something, like you have this problem where if you want
to secure it and protect it, you also make it possible to lose it if you lose access
to it.
It's a genuine problem that humanity really hasn't fully sorted out.
We don't have photo albums like we used to just, you know, we don't have that anymore.
It's all on the computer.
It's all digital now.
Yeah, it's all digital now.
Figure it out.
For some reason I thought you ended up on an Android device during all this.
I briefly was using a pixel test device that I have.
What era of pixel?
Pixel 3, 4, no, pixel 4a.
Okay.
Yeah, I have a 3 and that's getting pretty long in the tooth.
It was pretty slow.
Like I tried, I bought a couple like games to try on it, just to see how it ran.
It was pretty, if I was to stick with Android, I might have to get a new one.
But you just got out of there.
You just were like, no way.
Well, so this is unrelated, but turns out all my contacts are in iCloud.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
So like I had to ask my wife for her phone number.
Yeah, I would have to as well.
Yeah.
I was just thinking the other day I should memorize that.
I did a little bender on Android about a month ago.
I went with Graphene OS and my whole thing was not to use Google services.
So I had the same problem with contacts.
I'm like, what the hell do I do for my contacts in my calendar?
And I'm not saying this is what everybody could do, but I have the option and I did
this is I was able to put a little wedge in there basically that lets me send all that
to Nextcloud.
So I became my own contacts in calendar sync point.
And then I had that available in Nextcloud as well.
That was really nice.
I had to roll that whole solution myself, including unlock the phone, reflash it with
ADB, set up, you know, find this app.
Thanks to Jeff who gave me an idea where to find it, get this app so I could actually
sync to Nextcloud, get all that configured.
I already had Nextcloud set right.
Like it was just this massive amount of work.
If you were starting from square one, I was starting from like square three, but it was
possible on a modern ish Android device to have a clean Android install with no attachment
to Google and still have like cloud syncing stuff.
If you want to build it.
Yeah.
But do you want to build it?
I guess some people do.
It depends on how bad it gets, I suppose.
Yeah.
All right.
We've been teasing it.
You got you got into like the Swift again, something you smell a little swifty.
Maybe that's the Swift UI that's extra ripe.
I'm not sure.
But I think you've been doing a deep dive.
Yeah, I I've been playing around with Swift again for a while.
It doesn't matter.
He's six.
He doesn't listen to the show.
I was giving my kid for Christmas a Pokemon, a digital Pokemon trading card binder in Swift.
Yeah, I might throw it on the app store because people always ask, do you have anything on
the app store?
But I figured if I'm going to do it, I'm going to do it right.
So it's using the latest, the greatest version of Swift, which I think is five point seven
because I didn't put that in my notes.
Pure Swift UI.
None of my safe space of, you know, interface builder or her good old UI view or any storyboards,
anything like that.
I'm doing I'm using the relatively new async await features in Swift.
And and this is what I think is the interesting part.
I'm actually doing de-serialization the Swift way, not the Objective C way, which is just
doing it by hand.
Where to begin?
Xcode always has the best error messages.
This is something other IDEs need to think about because at one point I opened Xcode.
It's like I can't open this project.
It's from the future.
Closed it, open it again.
It opened it.
Fine.
Incredible.
Good stuff.
Like Doctor Who.
I crossed my own timeline.
Amazing.
Yeah, nicely done.
It is far more stable than it used to be.
All right.
That's good.
Still, Swift UI, I don't know how much RAM you need, but it wants all of it, all the
RAM in terms of the preview view.
But it's still pretty nice.
Just kind of laggy, kind of slow, whatever.
My first takes working in it were, so Apple just sat back, watched like the whole Angular
React thing happen and was like, we're going to do this, but we're going to make it better
because we're Apple and we only care about one platform.
Cool.
This one class, async image, which you can put on any Swift UI major components like
a V stack or an H stack.
Those are a vertical stack and horizontal stack, respectively.
I had to write a whole library to do this in old iOS.
And the this is, you have a view.
You have a URL to an image.
You want that image to load asynchronously and show a progress bar and not block the
UI.
It is one line of code in Swift UI and the performance is really good.
That sounds nice.
It is super nice.
I mean, I'm super jelly of the new iOS developers because this is easy mode.
Async and Swift, it's like they took async in Python, but married it to the bitchiness
of Rust.
Okay.
We've got a lot of try catching going on.
I mean, it demands.
So this is something I guess I had forgotten about Swift.
Unless you slap those exclamation points everywhere, which is the rough equivalent to slapping
unsafe everywhere in Rust.
It makes you catch everything.
But you know, and by the way, this is coming to C sharp as the default now and the dot
net.
I think it just came in six and seven comes out soon, too.
So enjoy.
You could have question marks everywhere and exclamation points.
Beautiful.
I actually think it is beautiful because I'm catching stuff at compile time that basically
once I get the damn view to be buildable, it pretty much works.
Yeah, fair enough.
Might as well catch it then.
Yeah.
So far, device scaling Swift UI, I think does a fair job of being device agnostic with the
big caveat of I have not yet decided to try it out on landscape.
Things that I don't like.
I get it.
And I have this problem with Rust, too.
I get that you want to be absolutely correct.
But you know, sometimes it's weird, like the Xcode makes you feel just like Rust does.
It makes you feel dirty when you're like overriding its warnings or it's, you know, checking stuff.
A lot of it's just feels unnecessary.
I know I've read the forums, I've read the subreddit, I may have posted on Reddit and
gotten yelled at by the Swift people that, you know, things should be safe, you need
to know the types, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Fair enough.
I've been doing too much Python.
It is very clear to me, and I'm not sure that maybe this isn't bad, but that Apple is going
to shove Swift UI down your throat.
So if you're clinging to, you know, storyboards or it's probably only storyboards at this
point, right, unless you're doing, I guess you could do individual nibs, but I think
you need to change.
I wrote a couple, about a year and a half ago, a blog post on bringing over zibs, which
they're called nibs, by the way, from UI kit into Swift UI.
I almost think that's basically misguided now.
And it's in this weird transitional state of so far, if you stick to just the, it's
not, it's unfair to credit slash blame him, but like the Marco Arment style of app development
where you're basically just using Apple's components with very little styling, then
Swift UI is super fast, super efficient.
The minute you want to go a little custom, things get rougher and it's tempting to drop
to UI view, because you can wrap it in a Swift UI component, but I, having tried it both
ways, I almost think it's one, a matter of time before Apple just, you know, makes it
more robust, right?
You get more robust controls out of the box.
You would hope so.
Well, from when I tried it last time to where it is now, they have, right?
They totally have, you know, WWDCs in June.
Yeah.
If they're trending in the right direction, that's a good sign.
But the point being, I think it's almost misguided to not just embrace the glory that is Swift
UI.
And I know I like T-Swift.
This is really good.
I mean, working on this Pokemon project, I'm like super missing iOS dev.
And I do some for clients, the, we have an app from 2010 that is written in no memory
managed objective C, but that's more archeology at this point.
It's not like new dev.
This is like fun to work in.
In particular, you can monitor your app's health and tail scale.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
That's where you go to try it for free for up to 20 devices and experience the best mesh
VPN you've ever, ever tried to set up.
You get it going in like, probably two minutes on a device.
If not that I, I'm not even kidding you.
It takes me 30 seconds to get a system on my tail scale VPN mesh network, and it's all
protected by wire guards, noise protocol, the encryption is solid.
And the other thing is the performance is incredible and the system is smart enough
to know if you're trying to communicate with your tail scale network, or if you're trying
to communicate with a general internet or something on your land, it's also smart enough
to figure out that if you're talking to another tail scale device on your land, it'll just
stay on the land.
It doesn't rat out to the internet and come back in.
We had huge storms here in the Pacific Northwest this last weekend, 70 mile per hour winds.
Power got knocked out at the studio.
And one of the things that I love is in the tail scale dashboard, I can see the last time
a node was online.
So I knew exactly when the power went out at the studio.
So I knew how long things were down.
I set up a ping.
I just started pinging the tail scale IP of one of the devices here.
And sure enough, it came back online when the power came up and I knew to come down
and fix everything because it was a bad one.
I just love that flexibility tail scale gives me to just, you know, I can use it in so many
different ways, but the thing that really became handy was, this is my bad, but more
systems were using DHCP than probably should have.
So a bunch of my boxes got new IP addresses and like my node for Bitcoin and where I checked
the boost, but also some studio systems, but their tail scale IP stayed the same.
Same tail scale IP.
So I was like, oh yeah, wait a minute.
I can just connect to the tail scale IP and I'm fine.
It just was like, wow, this is even on my land.
This is just so freaking great.
And tail scale SIN is like airdrop for all my devices, including my Linux boxes and my
mobile devices.
And tail scale SSH is absolute fire.
You can log into your system using tail scale through SSH, it's absolute by you're going
to love it.
There's so many great things.
And they've recently made DNS even better than ever on the tail scale network.
So go try it for yourself for free for up to 20 machines and support the show by going
to tailscale.com slash coder.
I think this is going to blow you away.
You're going to wonder why you hadn't tried it sooner.
tailscale.com slash coder.
Now that's not all.
I know you had a continuing journey and have discovered strong opinions, some pushback
and perhaps even a few demons.
Yeah.
So this, this is actually really cool.
So I said I did the JSON deserialization for my Pokemon card structs the way that Swift
wants you to not the old Objective C way of like just passing in an NS dictionary and,
you know, manually parsing the keys, right?
And yes, kids, that is how we used to do an Objective C. Yes, I know it's bad.
You guys have no freaking idea how easy you have it.
So I don't want to hear about it.
Go to your room.
Okay.
Is he in his room?
Good.
We're going to call him just some like 13 year old developer and just yell at him.
That's what we do on the show now.
We're going to call him Tim and we're just going to yell at him all day long.
Dang it, Tim.
You are disappointing us.
Tim, what, what do you mean Java?
Java has functions.
That doesn't have functions.
Everything's like objects.
Java one.
That's all you get.
How do you not know who Duke is?
Go read Wikipedia.
Go to your room.
Then the problem is me and Chris go to the bar and we get Ubered home because we're crying
about somebody named Scott McNeely and son and the 20 year old bartender has no idea
what's wrong with these two old dudes, but she wants them away.
At poor little Tim, he's just looking at his Coda radio dads and he's just wondering why
do they always cry when son comes up?
I don't understand what's wrong about the son.
Every day at sunset, we just sit on the, on the veranda drinks in hand, tears streaming,
openly weeping.
I mean, it's really terrible.
But things that make us happy.
The codable protocol and Swift, first of all, if you're going to name protocols, I love
this thing.
Yeah.
In fact, Swift, you guys get a robe.
This is robe worthy.
Yeah.
This is better than coderly.
Ooh, painful.
We got to do that.
It's codable.
I know.
So I linked the documentation.
It's so baller that it's really a type alias for two protocols, not one decodable, which
does exactly what it sounds like to codes, a Jason object into your class, an instance
of your class, or I'm sorry, struct encodable, which does the opposite encode your, you know,
your data type into Jason and now it has some opinions on how the Jason should look, but,
and this is what saved my butt.
It is possible to do custom decoding and still keep all the other benefits.
So if you have one, let's say easy example, you have like one type that's like a weird
type of Jason.
It's some kind of weird like string that they encoded instead of using a real data type.
You can just have like a custom function that decodes that as long as it decodes back to
one of the basic Swift types.
Hmm.
That's handy.
Right.
But if it is a, if it's an easy map, so like a Jason array to a Swift array, it just does
it.
You just tell it it's an array and it does it.
So you don't have to follow its specific output that it requires.
You can, there's room for fudging it.
It expects camel casing, but if you don't have camel casing, you can tell it that it's,
it actually has built in enums for like other crazy casing, like snake casing.
Well, good.
I'm glad you're not compromising on this.
Well, no, I like my snake casing.
Okay, good.
I'm glad it accommodates you.
What's wrong with snake casing?
Nothing.
Hmm.
Sensing a disturbance.
I just, what I find quite humorous is you going out of your way to just not have to
change.
Like I would just be like, okay, machine, all right, I'll do it your way.
You're like, no, let's see if there's a.
It's not my API though.
I don't control the JSON.
Oh, that's fair.
Yeah, fair.
Right.
You're not, yeah, you're not necessarily controlling the input.
Yeah.
I suppose that's fair.
To be fair, the API I'm using is camel cased and I did have it hit one of mine that's snake
cased and you know what snake casing is the right casing.
Although my Swift code, I am, I am being a proper Swift developer and doing it camel
case.
So there you go.
I hear it tastes like chicken.
It tastes like a, it does taste like chicken as a bird.
I thought for, I think chicken, I think like Raptors great grandson now and I'm very scared.
I had hot wings.
I'm like when the dinosaurs come back, they're going to be so pissed at me.
You could just look at them and kind of see it, right?
You can just see it.
It's surprisingly fast.
It can even handle cases where you can do the question mark thing and say it's an optional.
And if it's not there, it just accepts it.
You can nest different codable or decodable types within a kind of a overarching type.
So for instance, I have a card result type, which in it has a card and in that has the
card has a set so it can decode the set.
And within that you have like all kinds of crap, right?
Like Pokemon attacks, blah, blah, blah.
Now I know the.net developers are like, we have this too.
You do.
It does it a lot better because I think what they did is just rob your ass.
I'm feeling a lot of the Swift stuff is just ripping off good ideas from other places.
It's like we have the strictness of RASP.
You can throw an exclamation point in there if you don't want to listen.
And here's all the.net MVVM kind of stuff.
But we're going to make it a lot simpler and a little, you know, more I want to say forgiving.
I wouldn't say that, but more almost like you can Voltron up your own.
You can more easily than I found in.net Voltron up your own custom.
Whatever data structure you need, right?
It seems like a good strategy on their part that actually does.
Why not look?
Why not see what others are doing like.net in this case?
For sure.
Yeah, good strategy.
Yeah, I would say the closest analogy is probably like a couple of who I think is a Klingon.
Swift does something similar, which I think is ironic.
Also Microsoft who ripped off C Sharp their own thing.
So I feel like C Sharp being early with the stuff kind of.
You know, it's got some baggage.
So I'm going to go on a limb here.
Swift is enjoyable.
Just think if I had a time machine right now.
Don't worry, Alex.
Alex will find it.
I have perfect faith in him.
I think he's kind of been.
He's kind of moved past it by now.
He's like a 200 now.
Yeah, he's in the.
I can't believe he's I can't believe you.
It was 2016, I know it was one ninety something.
OK, OK.
It was such a wild episode for me on my end where you rage quit in the middle of the show
because so short version is we were doing the Apple event live and now it's Swift and
then we go to record the show to get the reaction and Mike's reaction is just rage on bridled
rage.
And then he leaves the show and I'm like, all right, well, thanks for coming, everybody.
It's like a twenty five minute show.
Yet one of our most listened to shows.
I just I'm pretty sure I keep people keep sending me stuff about it.
I feel like.
Swift has made a big journey since that episode.
Oh, it's a I would argue it's a completely different language to like even from where
Swift one point started to Swift five point seven.
I'd say it's more like rust than anything else.
I think it's been trending this way because it seems like each time we check in, you're
like, OK, this is getting better.
I like this.
This is getting a little you know, I like where they're going here.
So it sounds like this is it's really starting to come together for you.
Codable protocol.
I like it.
I mean, I kind of wish Apple wasn't so vampiric with the App Store, but, you know, I since
I'm doing this Pokemon card thing anyway for the kid, I may as well throw it on there and
charge ninety nine cents, which guarantees I will get one download or you can make it
free and do a nine dollar in app purchase for something really basic.
You know, and then Apple will spotlight it because it's free.
Just not what your podcast can boost for you, but what you can boost for your podcast.
We got a ton of great support for last week's episode.
Thank you, everybody.
Zurno boosted in with twenty nine thousand nine hundred sats.
Keep the change, you filthy animal.
It was spread across a couple of boosts because he was bailing out of Breeze.
I've also sort of stopped using Breeze myself.
Fountain has done recent updates and they've added CarPlay support and they just did an
update yesterday to fix a couple of stability issues.
I got to say, I'm still I'm really liking Fountain Podverse.
But Zurno says, OK, Mike, every time you say GitHub Copilot produces terrible code, I wonder
I've heard on other podcasts that it seems to produce code based on the user's previous
work.
Does this mean your repository is filled with bad code?
That's not quite how it works, right?
It doesn't just go on your code alone.
No, it doesn't.
And I would even challenge firms.
I don't say it only produces terrible code.
I would say that when it produces bad code, it's really funny, but it it doesn't produce
bad code.
Right.
Like if you're for example, if you're just doing a jQuery form or a Python WTF form,
it will do that and it will be fine.
Right.
It'll do it in context and it it'll scan.
I think it scans a collection per language.
I think it's actually per platform, too.
It can tell like if you're doing flask or fast API, for example, or rails, it will produce
code for, I don't know, most common cases.
I don't think it's all terrible, but how valuable is someone generating a form for me that I've
written 400 times?
GitHub says on their site, languages with less representation in public repositories
may produce fewer or less robust suggestions.
But they say, for example, JavaScript is well represented in public repositories and is
one of GitHub Copilot's best supported languages because there's so many examples of it.
So you can kind of imagine how that would probably work.
The more there is of something, the more source it has.
Also on the topic of Copilot, a lawsuit has been filed.
Oh, Lord.
It's basically along the lines of what we've talked about, a class action lawsuit in a
U.S. federal court in San Francisco.
You know the details and we'll follow it.
We'll follow it quietly and we'll update everybody if there's anything worth really discussing
there.
But I think it's interesting that that process has now kicked off.
It's probably wasn't and we probably should have, we probably could have had a bet on when
it would happen, not if.
Yeah, I have a little fascinating thought.
I mean, I still hold what I said a couple of weeks ago.
It would be a shame if legal chicanery got rid of Copilot.
Maybe not get, you know, the idea of a Copilot like tool, right?
It's funny because from the first, from Zerno's message, I would actually prefer to be able
to tell Copilot only to look at my repositories because then I could actually use it on client
work.
I think you can with like the private version for Visual Studio, but I'm not sure.
Isn't there some way to do that privately?
There is some way.
Maybe there is.
I just turn it off when I'm not working on my own thing, so.
I would, you know, if I was going to be selfish, if I knew I could go use Copilot and it would
be a pretty good aid and if there was a way I could somehow trust its results, maybe I
could just do that through peer review.
I'd probably be more inclined to write my own stuff and do my own like little side projects
if I knew it was actually going to be a good guide.
If you're writing like a very mainstream, you know, node with an Angular front end or
node with a React front end, there's just a ton of examples that Copilot can pull from.
It's when you get more domain specific, you're going to, yeah.
Which I probably would.
Yeah.
All right, Nomadic Coder 5 boosted with 5,555 SATs.
I recently started using my iPod Touch just to listen to podcasts and music, but with
Apple's latest money grab, I'll have to switch to Fountain on my Calix OS phone in case Apple
starts taxing boosts.
With every announcement Apple does, something that drives me further and further away seems
like it drives me further and further away from them.
I agree.
Yeah, they are going after like in-app advertising, although with like Fountain you don't buy
the SATs, so there's no transaction happening, thankfully.
That's why.
They know.
I've talked to the folks behind both Fountain and Podverse and they're very much aware of
Apple's shenanigans.
They're very careful.
They try not to even play in the gray zone.
They go by the letter of the law.
No, I got to say, like if you're doing an iOS app, I've learned this for many years
of complaining about it on this show, don't even go in.
It's like the neutral zone with the Romulans.
Don't just stay the hell out.
Don't go there.
I agree.
Sam Squatch comes in with 16,180 SATs.
Hey, rich lobster.
Oh, shit.
I'm buying a car suite.
I know.
Like I said, we've got some great support this week.
They say, so I absolutely think Twitter is likely pretty bloated, but the metric of code
is a bit of an odd choice to go by.
I agree.
People have been tossing around how much code.
Bad management.
Yeah.
My experience as my career has gone on and I've gone through to become a principal engineer
and now a manager, I write less and less code.
I spend more time reviewing other people's code, catching bad decisions, overseeing early
design plans, et cetera.
Effectively, I try to be a force multiplier.
Does that mean by Elon's metric, I'm a bad engineer?
No, I mean, I don't know if we have any data to suggest that.
I did see an article that said they actually are trying to reach back out to some of the
people that have been fired so far and rehire them.
Jackass.
That's embarrassing.
That is, that's just, I tell you what, I don't know.
It's going to be wild to watch that.
I think his best shot, just to touch on it one last time, is to make his changes and
get the hell out of there and hand it off.
Yeah.
I don't think you should take Elon super seriously when he talks about the management stuff or
basically anything else because I'm pretty sure he's playing a caricature of himself
at this point, right?
It's like when I go and decide I'm going to complain and make fun of the PHP people.
I don't actually hate PHP people.
I don't even think PHP is that bad of a language.
It's just an act, right?
And to his detriment at this point, I would say, he's playing a caricature.
There's no way he is sitting there reading printouts of thousands of lines of code.
No, they didn't even do that eventually.
There's been some bogus reporting, but...
Yeah, it's just bull.
Yeah.
Anyway, moving on.
I think he is moving quick and ruthlessly because he just spent $44 billion on something
that's probably worth a billion dollars.
Well, maybe more, but anyways.
Okay.
Noob Steve Boostin with 48,600 sats.
I hoard that with your kind covet.
Now he's listening to episode 483.
I think he's responding to something he said in episode 481 about subscriptions in Adobe
Cloud, which kicked off a series of discussions.
He said, sorry, guys.
I didn't really mean to kick off an S-storm, as he puts it.
I promise I'll never mention those who shall not be named again.
Please accept my humble boost as a formal apology.
Also, congrats, Mike.
Sorry, you're having to deal with green bubbles right now.
I lasted less than a day, don't worry.
That's amazing.
That is amazing.
Who was the not to be named?
I believe it was Adobe and Creative Cloud that kicked off.
Oh, yeah.
Noob, you can correct me, but that's what I recall.
So Ham boosted in with a row of ducks, 2222 sats.
This old duck still got it.
All right.
Brace yourself for this one.
Capitalism requires the funny green line profit to always go up.
The catch, the earth and humanity is a finite resource.
Infinite growth is simply not possible.
Apple really has no choice other than to become a bully.
Can you really blame them?
This is I agree to a sense here.
It's like if we are serious about wanting to protect the environment, then we can't
have unlimited everything.
We have to be real about some of these limited resources like, honestly, lithium.
There's a new OPEC being organized around lithium now, which is just going to recreate
the same problem we have with oil.
And the number one producer of lithium is China.
And I hate to think what the labor standards are.
It really is quite a conundrum.
I don't know because I think capitalism is really just human nature.
It's trading and creating value for things.
I think that's human nature where obviously as it gets at a certain scale and certain
amount of control and influence, it tries to get perverted and now it's become something
that seems very sick.
But I don't know if you can take trading and selling out of humanity.
So we just have to, I guess, have a way to do it sustainably.
Let us know if you've got an idea for that.
Also, shout outs for Boost CLI.
Whoa.
Yes.
You know what you get?
That's just for you, Soham, for using Boost CLI.
All right.
Trevdev boosted in with some leet sats saying, inflating your downloads, we're talking about
people that have been buying downloads, is a whole industry in third world countries,
he writes.
It boosts your placement on the top podcast list in the Apple Podcast Index.
That artificial inflation of your popularity gets you a real audience.
That's a good point.
That is true.
That actually does make the transaction worth it.
As an example, when we get big baller boosts into the show, we go to the top of the Fountain
FM list.
Koda Radio is like in sometimes the top four podcasts when people give us big boosts.
And that's a serious signal.
People are spending real sats.
That's a real signal of quality and we've been picking up new audiences as a result
of that.
LUP too.
LUP's been benefiting from that as well.
Pegdot boosts in with some enterprise sats, 1701.
Make it so.
This is our last one.
Hello, Star Trek Radio Show.
A few weeks ago, I asked which series to get started with, with Star Trek.
We remember.
Both of you recommended The Next Generation.
I started yesterday with Encounter at Farpoint, which is episode one and two, and I'm continuing
today with episode three, the one where everyone gets drunk and horny.
Really enjoying it so far.
Thanks for the recommendation.
P.S. I tried the Lord of the Rings series yesterday too, but I like Star Trek better.
That's great.
I thought TNG was a little risky just because that first season, first two seasons, they
have some gems, but they also have some rough spots.
But if you're enjoying the drunk episode, I think you're going to be all right.
Yeah, I was in the drunk episode is one of the worst episodes in that season.
So yeah, there's also that one where the king of a planet like captures Tasha to make
her his love slave, and then they have to fight his current love slave.
You have to have the original series sexism reboot, right?
Well, it's funny you say that, man, because that's the drunk episode.
That episode, a lot of the season one and two episodes were old scripts from the 60s.
Yep.
And they just kind of put the 80s lipstick on them, right?
Exactly.
80s hair and lipstick.
Season three, The Next Generation kind of gets its own identity, although if you want
the one true Trek, and I will stand by this, I'm rewatching Strange New Worlds.
I just love it.
It's funny you say that.
I was reading this boost with Wes yesterday, and he and I were talking about how TNG was
kind of a risk.
And I said, I think the other way to go now would be Strange New Worlds because it's good
Trek with modern production values.
I think it's a good introduction possibly.
So, if you can enjoy TNG, it gets so rich because then you can move into DS9 and Voyager
and then Enterprise and just work your way up.
And that is quite literally years of TV watching.
I started doing that with my wife when we were dating.
And we're now on season two of Enterprise.
And so we started with TNG, and we've been married for like six, I don't know, I don't
know how long.
We've been married a couple of years, but we've been dating for a while, it's been years.
And we're just now in Enterprise.
And so it's literally years of great television.
And you can store it locally and there's no ads and it's just, if you get into it, it's
pretty great.
All right, enough.
Enough.
Big shout out too.
I really want to say thank you to those that boosted in.
Some just send in some sats without saying anything, few send in some notes.
We don't put them all in the show if you can believe it.
But we did get 109,999 sats from WM, who went on a little bit of a boosting spree for our
shows and Coda Radio was a big beneficiary there.
We got 100 sats from jmac217, who says no one in his real life circle is using Twitter
in central Illinois.
Twitter is just not a thing in his neck of the woods, he says, in the real world.
And we got 3,000 sats from Agania or Ahagania.
Thank you guys very much or appreciate you very much.
You're doing a good job.
If you'd like to send a boost into the show, go get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com.
There's a whole suite of options there from a whole new podcast app to just using tools.
And if you're in the U.S. and you want to grab some cheap sats, the Strike app or the
Cash app is fantastic outside the U.S.
I like Blue Wallet a whole bunch.
And of course, you can invest in the ongoing production, the real nuts and bolts of the
show by becoming a member, codercua.co.
I got an email, I got a nice note from one of our members, I think we both got it, from
one of our members over the week who says, this would be my boost would be, but since
I'm a member, I'm just going to send it to you directly.
Totally fine.
We love hearing from you.
And as a thank you, you get an ad-free version of the show and a coderly report, which we're
going to get together.
We will.
Oh, my gosh, you guys, you wouldn't believe how busy the world has been, but we'll get
it together and send it out to our members as a thank you, codercua.co.
I don't know, you feeling like you got anywhere you want to send the people this week, Mr.
Dominic?
You know, as always, I'm at Team Unuku on Twitter, but why don't you all sign up for
the Matrix Room?
I usually hang out in the Coder Radio general Matrix chat room.
Yeah, we got two Coder chat rooms.
There's like a feedback specific room and a general chat and we link to the general
chat at coder.show slash matrix.
That's a great call because that's also what we put up on our live stream.
And so you can find out when we're live just by being in there or you can just review the
chat if you're listening to an episode and you're curious to know what the chat room
said.
It's all there.
And of course, yeah, both Mike and I are hanging out and they're pretty much every day from
time to time.
I'm popping in at least a few times a day.
So join us over there.
We got links to what we talked about today at coder.show slash 491.
How about that?
And you can actually watch how these shows get made over at Jupiter.tube.
It's live 9 a.m. Monday, 12 p.m. Eastern.
And then the archived version stays up there for playback because why not?
It's our own YouTube.
I can do whatever I want.
Is that not a great laugh?
I'll work on an evil laugh, though.
I'll get that together for the next time I talk about it.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio program, and we'll
see you right back here next week.