This is KOTOR Radio, episode 453 for February 14th, 2022.
Hello everyone and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
My name is Chris and joining me with a gold podcasting mic, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello, Chris.
How are you today in beautiful Kyiv?
I like to call it Kiev.
I'm old school about that.
Well, there's two pronunciations.
Something I learned in the breathless coverage in the wonderful Morning Joe show this morning.
Yeah, man.
You know what?
I've actually decided to just turn off the news for the next couple of days.
I'm taking like a news diet.
I can't.
The love of my life, Victoria Nuland, started me on this path.
Yeah, you got to make sure.
And I'm really just trying to glue this thing, Chris.
That's all I'm trying to do.
I'm trying to glue it.
That would be great.
We could just glue this thing.
I think it's going to be a pretty fun, you know, for her, it's going to be a pretty fun
experience.
She's going to hand out sandwiches again.
She's going to be great.
So don't you worry about her.
I think she's going to be like, told you so.
It's the Pacific Northwest that is in absolute chaos.
And if I wanted to take a news diet and I was a Mazda driver, I would have zero choice.
But to listen to the news every moment I was in my car as news of this scandal made it
to your shores.
No.
What's this?
What scandal?
A brilliant software bug has struck some Mazda drivers in the Seattle area.
Oh, yeah.
That listen to our local NPR affiliate.
Now their head units are locked into that NPR affiliate.
No matter what they do.
They can't.
This infotainment system doesn't boot up enough for them to turn it off, to change it to a
different channel or even see their backup camera.
It is always playing NPR.
This programming is possible thanks to listeners like you, whether you like it or not.
You're listening to NPR.
You're done.
Welcome to the quiet storm.
Yes.
Now, initially the response was now Mazda is going to take care of people, but initially
the response was you're going to have to go schedule it with a vendor with a service repair
area and you're going to have to spend fifty hundred dollars on a new head unit because
there's no way we can fix this problem.
We just have to replace the whole head unit.
Can you guess what kind of software bug?
What could have conceivably caused this?
The initial speculation was 5G.
I'm not kidding.
OK, so so the bug is I'm in my Mazda as one is and I am being tormented.
Now did I have to tune to the NPR station myself?
Yes.
Yeah.
You you had to be a listener originally for this bug to occur.
This sounds like a really funny hack.
Are we sure this is a bug?
It is a bug, but it's a ridiculous bug.
OK, don't let me tell you.
I'll just tell you.
You're never going to guess it.
Of course, the radio station uses this third party intermediary company.
Oh, God.
That supplies metadata to the radio.
You know, the radio head units that show the channel name and the song you're listening
to.
Yeah.
Like the guy's picture or the girl's picture.
Sure.
Apparently, yeah, they can do pictures now.
And this third party company included a JPEG that didn't have the file extension.
Yes.
Yeah.
And that broke the head units forever.
I think that's the best.
I feel bad because it sounds super frustrating actually driving around for a few weeks with
like no control over your radio.
I don't think I'd drive the car.
So I'm just wondering what kind of system this Mazda head unit must be.
A lot of those head units are actually what is like Q and X.
Are you thinking of Q and X?
Q and X.
Thank you.
Was to say it's the cute thing, right?
Yeah.
The Q and X systems don't give a crap about file extensions.
I mean, it helps, but I've done it.
You shouldn't do it.
It's such an edge case.
You can kind of understand why they wouldn't test for it, although you can understand why
they should, but why maybe they didn't think of it.
I think it's just perfect that it's NPR.
I know.
It's like probably the most chill, frustrating radio station you could probably listen to.
Because if, you know, say you want some music that day or nothing.
You have a long trip with like a little kid and the poor little guy's got to listen to
like, today we have him on Quiet Storm.
And all the Bluetooth was dead.
Like you couldn't play anything from your phone.
Your phone call stuff wouldn't work.
I'm assuming you're just locked.
Like you can't plug in an iPhone.
Yeah.
You're just done.
Yep.
Daddy, can I listen to the Wreck It Ralph song, which is called Sugar Rush and is burned
into my very soul?
No, no, you cannot, my boy.
You're apparently listening to this book review about some lady growing turnips.
Or you know, the Ukraine, which perhaps you're trying to take a little bit of time from right
now.
Me?
No, no.
So the Super Bowl was last night.
Very important to a lot of people.
I was rooting for the Bengals, Los Angeles one, saving me roughly eighteen hundred dollars.
I was going to buy a System 76 of the Bengals one.
I saw that.
That's hilarious.
That's great.
Because my son was mocking me for using a MacBook Air, which I find out, Chris, how
he got a premium fee to J.B.
We're going to have a little talk.
Let's just say we took care of him.
Yeah.
Oh, he's already like, where's your cool computer?
Like, dude, you're five.
God.
He's like, well, OK, you know, I was on Matrix this morning talking like, stop it, kid.
What are you doing?
No.
And that was an exciting game if you're a sports fan, but there is no greater game.
I call it Newland ball.
I am so in on this Ukraine stuff.
Are you?
I have not been this excited about the news since an orange man descended.
What is it about it that has you so gripped?
I do notice that they're talking about it an awful lot.
Well, I'll tell you what it is about it.
There's two things.
One, any time Joe Scarborough gets on his gets the vapors, I think it's funny.
I actually like Joe Scarborough.
Yeah.
You guys are both fake conservatives.
Oh, damn.
The worst part is the second time I was called a rhino today, weirdly enough, by my ex-mother-in-law.
You totally derailed me.
That was amazing.
You know what?
They have to put you on Fox News to just go after the apparently my people.
I just I just I'm impressed that you're so captivated by it, because I would imagine
a lot of us are just like, I mean, maybe I'm wrong.
All right.
So you know what the difference is?
You can see I'm not to cut you off, but just answer your question.
You can actually if you go back far enough to that beautiful phone call and even a little
before.
This is like watching the play, but being able to see behind the scenes to behind the
stage to there is that element.
And it's like watching something that's been playing out for for a while kind of come to
a head.
I agree.
I have just felt like because there's nothing I can do about it.
And I don't really know how it's going to directly affect me either way.
I just sort of just I'm just going to wait for something to happen and then pay attention.
I think I'm not sure.
I waffle on it.
I mostly just try to stay focused on work.
But every now and then I think about it, it freaks me out.
It's never going to be World War Three.
Not not for not no offense or Ukrainian listeners, but not over Ukraine.
Sorry, guys.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, let's get to the emails.
Casey from Austria asks about the maintenance dance.
He says so at the mad botter, how do you structure ongoing maintenance for your client project?
Care is rarely finished, and even if it's feature complete and the bugs are squashed,
often there'll be ongoing costs for hosting backups, etc.
I've been self-employed as a software engineer for over a decade.
I've been relatively lucky that my clients usually have some kind of sysadmin or ops
team that could handle these ongoing costs.
However, recently I found my client base shifting to clients who don't really have the capacity
to manage the hosting themselves.
So I'm in a situation where I need to have a solid story for how I take care of the client
after the main engagement wraps up.
Do you sell retainer contracts?
Are those based on hours or something else like do you sell fixed hosted plans?
What would they include?
Any horror stories to share or any tips to pass along would be great, too.
Thanks and cheers from Austria.
That's a lot.
There's a lot in there.
Yeah, I do try to sell maintenance contracts and I almost never succeed because in truth,
it's my experience.
People willing to buy maintenance contracts usually want additional development, too,
when you end up spending a lot of time separating maintenance from development.
So yeah, we just do it, you know, as applications change over time and that requires, well,
changes that's poorly put.
For Alice, it's a license for a year, right?
Basically it's not really assessed, but it's getting there every day, closer and closer.
And just, yeah, the ongoing maintenance is part of that license fee.
And that's probably the closest to a pure, but part of the conditions of that are like
we spin up the instance, we control it, you keep your grubby hands off.
I kind of do get the impression from his email that he's getting asked the question because
he says, I need to have a solid story for how I take care of the client after main engagement
wraps up.
So maybe he is getting asked.
So it seems like maybe having a maintenance option is a good idea, but I don't know if
you need to leave the initial sale or any of that with, with that.
The thing that becomes complex is deciding what is a maintenance quote, you know, issue
that you just fixed for that flat fee and what is effectively a modification.
So if I were to do that, I would probably just say you buy it like a lawyer, right?
You buy or retain for hours.
I've done that in the past.
It's fine.
That's definitely approached like by a four hour package.
It kind of depends on what you're maintaining.
If you're maintaining server infrastructure for them, that might be a little more straight
forward, you know, cause Mike's right.
If you're maintaining code, doing maintenance updates or fixing things or adding support
for new importers or something like that, that's a whole different cost structure versus
running a VPS that your sub license leasing to them or a system that you have in a data
center.
And then there that's pretty straightforward to figure out the cost for that.
You just look at your costs.
That almost sells itself.
If that's what they're looking for.
Yeah.
I mean, if it's something you control, then you should know your costs and you just do
some number greater than that.
That makes sense to make it worth it for you, right?
If it's just like pure custom dev where they're going to end up hosting it themselves and
like there are some admin on their side that is, you know, gets to pick what he or she
wants and how they want to go on.
That's a little trickier, right?
You know, the more uniform your systems are, the presumably right, one hopes the more efficient
you are at maintaining it.
All right.
Listener Mike is freaking out.
This is OK, I was listening to you guys talk about VR recently that was beyond gaming,
which is the first time I really thought about that much.
And then I recently had an experience at a friend's house with an Oculus 2 and I was
pretty impressed with how far it's come.
Then when I heard you guys talking about virtual meetings and maybe even using VR on the plane,
it really clicked for me and my mind was blown.
At the risk of sounding like the dad in the room, though, are you guys at all worried
about the possible addictive nature of VR?
The small amount of VR I did was so immersive, it was so honestly disorienting to come out
of it.
Well, I'm old enough to remember a world before smartphones and now we're all just seemingly
hopelessly addicted to them.
So what's VR going to do?
I'm reminded of Jeff Goldblum's quote in Jurassic Park where he says, your scientists were so
preoccupied with whether they could, they didn't stop to think if they should.
What are your thoughts?
Yeah.
I mean, if you've ever read your William Gibson, this is a problem, right?
I don't even think it's a possibility.
I think it's a certainty once it gets good enough, if it gets good enough.
And we know this because people get addicted to things like World of Warcraft.
Oh, for sure.
Yeah.
So I think this is in a lot of ways, I just not even an opinion.
This is absolutely true, right?
People Robin Hood, the, for those who don't know the, what would you, I would call it
a gambling app, but I don't feel like getting sued.
So we'll call it an investment app.
Yeah.
Stocks for retail investors.
You know, there was a couple of young men who destroyed their lives.
One young man killed himself because it is addictive, right?
Yeah.
So, you know, we have a casino not too far from the studio and I have gone in there with
friends on occasion and I see people who are basically just sitting there rotting away
on those slot machines.
Yeah.
It's definitely a bad, it's a bad human behavior.
I mean, just think about it.
Think about like an MMO in like an Oculus five, right?
Like a really souped up, you know, few generations out and you feel like you're, you know, a
wizard or whatever.
Flying.
Oh God.
How cool would it be to fly around an open world?
Yeah.
I mean, I, I have a buddy who has a, a home built a flight simulator that is annoyingly
better than mine and I can't wait to get over it.
Yeah.
I was just talking to my buddy Alex about using flight Sim and VR cause he just got
a VR kit and he says it's just, it's blow away good.
Like he flew over a campground that he stayed in as a kid and he could recognize it in the
flight Sim.
I agree.
All these are things are problems.
I don't really see what VR is changing about it.
Like I'm sitting in front of screens, one, two, three, four, five screens right now and
I sat in front of four screens all morning while we worked on things this morning.
So like I already spend probably 10 hours a day in front of a screen and then sometimes
after I'm done with dinner and whatnot, I sit down, I turn the TV on and I watch TV
for a bit too.
So I'm already living that world.
I'm just doing it with a crappier resolution and a crappier experience, right?
And at least with VR, there's going to be things that get me up and moving where right
now all of it's done on my butt unless I electively choose to stand there and stare at a screen.
So I actually think in some ways VR is going to improve the situation because some of those
games are actually quite a workout.
And so there's, you know, there may be a positive aspect to it.
Yeah, there's going to be a lot of negatives to the right.
Think about the adult industry.
I mean, we've all seen the next generation Star Trek, right?
How many episodes are there about some poor bastard?
Barkley.
Right.
Just like in the holodeck.
He can't get it.
He's just like so hooked on it.
I mean, yeah, I suppose.
But the real thing's always going to be better, right?
Like you're always going to have a better experience eating a great meal in the real
world or sex or meeting somebody.
Like the real world thing is always going to probably because it's a touch and feel
thing as well.
I don't know.
You know, the more I think about it, the more I think it's really just going to be as bad
as it is now.
I really don't.
I mean, it's just going to look dorkier because we're going to have these things on our head.
Don't worry.
Multi-billion dollar corporations have for a very long time been working on addicting
you and screwing with your dopamine already got you.
Have you heard of Van Heuser Bush or, you know, all the cigarette companies?
I'm just saying lots of things were addictive.
So Dinesh writes in looking for some wisdom.
He says, Hello, guys.
A regular listener of the show here over the past few weeks, I've been enjoying hearing
about Mike's experience with Python being a Python developer myself.
It's always interesting to see people speak the serpent language.
However, one thing's got me thinking, given Mike's experience with a few different languages,
is there a template or process which has followed that I think it means you follow to make
decisions about the tech to use for a specific project?
Or is it just about trying out new things and, hey, maybe there's a chance it works?
I'm curious to know about the architecture choices and how they're made.
Thanks for the great content.
Cheers.
Yeah.
So it is not just about trying new things.
That's the easiest one to start with.
I kept getting requests for Python and we got one pretty substantial request that we
had been doing it here and there a little bit.
So in terms of that type of development, i.e. web applications, mostly a Ruby shop, that
is now all completely reversed, mostly Python and for a couple of years now.
I try to keep up, I guess, like I have a practice where I do like what I've talked about them
years ago.
CodeCata is like a little programming exercise and I think it's Coding Hero is the website.
But now I just there's a Reddit for it, too.
I just do them from.
I can't say that I always pick up the new thing, right?
I mean, when node was the new hotness, I spent probably a year here just bashing the crap
out of it.
I still stand by all of that case, like last week where I've changed my mind a bit.
Swift, right, where I understand why you would want to use Swift even over Objective C. But
that's mostly because Apple have become difficult about, you know, putting things in Objective
C.
Why Python particularly?
Well, you know, that is a question, right?
So one of the challenges, in fact, we had a meeting on Friday is Python's not exactly
performant.
Neither was Ruby, but for and make sure I phrase this right.
Most of the time, the client, you know, development work for hire stuff.
They're more interested for us, at least the kind of things we do and just getting it done
at a reasonable performance.
And we're always speaking performance as we go.
Yeah, sometimes, like right now with Alice, we are hitting some some walls that I'm starting
to look at, you know, more like Rust, you know, Rust modules or C++ modules, because
straight throughput is becoming a problem.
You know, I won't use anything that I have to pay for, right, like any proprietary, like
weird stuff.
I don't know.
I try things that look interesting.
Like I like Rust.
I think in the last few years, the new quote language that's excited me the most is Rust.
Although there's a lot of chaos over there for reasons that I still don't understand.
But in fact, Chris, we kind of just dropped that story completely.
The whole kerfuffle.
Yeah.
Well, they aren't giving us much.
You know, there was some more departures, but they claim they were not related to the
recent community stuff.
I'm watching.
But that group has traditionally been very tight lipped.
You know, you don't talk about Fight Club.
You don't talk about Crap Club.
Linode.com slash coder, go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
And you go there to support the show.
Linode is fast and reliable cloud hosting.
It's how we host everything.
And you got to try it for your next project, especially now that Linode has been rolling
out upgrades to their storage, MVME PCIe storage, and it's crazy fast.
We're currently experimenting with the idea of moving our matrix database over to MVME
storage and the back end database for our Castablaster system, which manages all of
the encoding and metadata and processing of our shows up on Linode.
Yeah, we do all of that stuff up on Linode too.
Our editors submit a final flack with all of their amazing skills applied to making
the show sound great.
That goes up to a system on Linode and in it, it does all the processing from there.
It pushes it out to all of our different endpoints on different social media platforms and RSS
feeds and all of that.
And we're looking at our different workloads and thinking, okay, well, what should we move
over to their S3 object storage?
What should we move over to MVME block storage?
That's our math right now.
And if you're a performance hound, Linode's the way to go.
They've got screaming fast CPUs, screaming fast disk, and a screaming fast network interface.
They are their own ISP and they got 11 data centers around the world.
You're going to find something close to yourself or your clients.
And Linode's been doing this for almost 19 years and it just keeps getting better and
better all the time.
They got new stuff they're working on and the stuff they've rolled out, they nail it.
What they've learned is to focus and do things right.
They're not trying to lock you into some sort of crazy complex proprietary hyperscaler platform.
You can use industry standard tools like Terraform and Kubernetes or their straightforward API
or even just their beautiful dashboard.
It's all straightforward.
You're going to get started in no time and it's a great way to support the show.
If you've been thinking about doing it, now's the time.
It really is great.
Linode.com slash coder.
Big congratulations to everyone who's ever worked on.NET and all of those of you who
took a bet on something crazy for Microsoft.
It just hit 20 years.
.NET Framework 1.0 came out 20 years ago, February 14th, 2002.
That makes me feel old.
You know, I was looking up news clippings from that time.
It was a different time.
First of all, I just got to say it.
What's.NET?
I thought it was called Jsharp.
I thought it was called.NET Core.
I thought it was called Mono.
No, actually, you know, I was looking, I was trying to look back at the timeline because
that there are like big moments in all of this timeline and definitely it was in 2016
when Microsoft billed, when they announced the whole like Mono was coming in as part
of the.NET Foundation.
It was going under an MIT license.
I mean, that also followed acquisition of the Zmarion or Xamarin.
Yeah, I mean, that was 2016, which I remember doing the show then.
At least I seem to recall we were doing the show then.
We were.
Yeah.
And I seem to recall having a very skeptical take on how this was all going to go because
we really were, that was really at the beginning of wrapping our heads around what Microsoft
was doing with the development community.
And that was really around the beginning of this big shift internally, I think, on their
approach to open source.
You know what?
I need a Decker King.
Yeah.
You want to tell us a little story?
Is that what you're saying?
Oh, yeah.
Stay a while and listen.
All right.
Our younger listeners, I am going to make some statements that you are not going to
believe, but here we go.
They're all true.
In 2002, not just Microsoft, not just Sun, and let's all pour one out and cry a little
bit.
The entire industry, more or less, and mainstream business press believed that Java was the
terminal point of all languages, right?
Java was going to take over the world.
There was a breathless email from Bill Gates freaking the hell out about Java, right?
That is why you have.NET.
It was originally Microsoft's answer to Java, so much so that they implemented Java and
called it J-Shark.
That didn't last too long.
That is some good history.
You're right.
In fact, when Gates freaked out about it, a lot of people freaked out about it.
It was everywhere, right?
Java was going to be everywhere.
It was going to be in your...
What would we call them?
We called them Micro Edition.
Remember Java Micro Edition for like your, quote, what we call an IoT today?
It was in mobile.
Those crappy flip phones ran Java.
Some people, when they were young and needed the money, wrote Java.
They're very, very sorry.
Don't forget, too, about those horrendous, horrendous cable set-top boxes, that whole
industry.
DVD players.
Remember when this DVD and Blu-ray first shipped with Java apps on the Blu-ray player?
This was a seismic, like- Horrible.
It was like their Sputnik moment over at Microsoft, because it was truly, right?
Most developers at the time, your mainstream developers, a lot of them were doing either
like VBasic, not VB.net, VBasic, or C++.
And Java was such a, how would you say, less of a pain in the ass than C++, but more powerful
than...
I'll say more powerful than VBasic.
I know people will fight.
As we talk a little bit more about where.NET is today, keep the context in your head that
this was effectively a defensive rearguard action at Microsoft.
Because Sun, beautiful, sweet, never learned how to make any goddamn money, Sun, was so
threatening to them.
Go on, Chris.
Where are we today?
I was just thinking, now we're in a world where you kind of exert your control through
open source and foundation participation.
Back in this era, they also started working on their Flash competitor.
So they were fighting this fight on multiple fronts.
And what was that called?
Silver something, right?
Silverlight.
Yeah, Silverlight.
.NET obviously didn't turn out like Silverlight.
.NET turned out to be a very wise investment, but it is so fun to revisit the original motivations
there.
And now here we are.
Sun is no more.
They have gifted us a file system and left us.
It'll always be too soon.
True.
They had some seriously cool hardware.
And some seriously bad businessmen.
But some great ponytails.
Maybe the ponytails didn't help.
I'm just saying.
Especially back then.
You know, congratulations.NET, 20 years.
Yes, you helped kill one of the most interesting, you know what?
We're not going to go here.
How's Oracle now?
Actually, one more thing on the Microsoft thing.
Datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
Go there and sign up for a free two week trial and get a free t-shirt.
Datadog is the SaaS monitoring and security platform that enables full stack observability
for developers, IT operations, security, and business teams in the cloud age.
Datadog's platform, along with its 500 plus vendor backed integrations, allows you to
correlate your metrics, your traces, your logs, and security signals across your applications,
infrastructure, and third party services in a single beautiful pane of glass.
These capabilities combined with the drag and drop dashboards and machine learning based
alerts help teams troubleshoot and collaborate more effectively.
This prevents downtime, it enhances performance, reliability, and your communications.
So we got an exclusive offer to Coder Radio listeners.
Sign up for a two free week trial at datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
That's how you support the show too and get a free Datadog t-shirt.
How great is that?
That's datadog.com slash Coder Radio, all one word.
Get that free t-shirt and happy monitoring.
Microsoft's playing 3D chess and I think Apple is still playing checkers here.
Microsoft not only has been pulling the strings with the Epic lawsuit, but now Microsoft has
published a set of principles that will guide their app store.
Except the one they make money on, yes.
In light of the process starting around the regulatory oversight of the Activision Blizzard
purchase, Microsoft wanted to make it clear that they are committed to an open app store.
One that allows game makers to make revenue directly.
Microsoft said, we have developed these principles in part to address our growing role and responsibilities.
We start the process of seeking regulatory approval in capitals around the world for
our acquisition of Activision Blizzard.
This is coming from Brad Smith.
And the effort is really to paint Microsoft as this open player.
Microsoft's strategy is really a long game here against Apple.
Because if they can break Apple's 30% cut of Microsoft Office and Xbox games and anything
Microsoft related that gets sold on the iOS app store.
If they can break that cut, then it's worth no profits from the Windows app store because
they don't make any money now anyways.
They're essentially offering to make no money in a platform they already make no money in
exchange for Apple losing everything.
I think it's pretty wild.
You know what?
If Microsoft can pull it off, maybe it's better for everybody.
Maybe it's a good thing.
But I think it's really interesting to watch them play this chess game while pretending
like the good guy and appealing to the regulators with promises of their open Windows store.
Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, you know, I'm always excited to roo over Apple on this app store stuff.
But this doesn't, this seems like weak tea to me, and I don't think this is gonna work.
I don't know.
I think it might.
At least in terms of getting the Activision Blizzard deal passed.
Microsoft, you know, like Dave Jones, he sent us a boost from his new podcast app.
And he said, what Microsoft learned from their antitrust tobacco is that they need to up
their DC lobbyist game.
So now they have one of the most effective lobbying machines in DC.
That's why you never hear their name mentioned in the halls of Congress anymore, despite
their size and behavior.
Like, so they figured out how to lobby, how to basically own the representatives they
need to own, and now how to appeal to the world, to the rest of the world regulators,
by claiming that, you know, we're willing to be a totally open store that doesn't need
a cut.
Yeah, but only where we don't make significant money, because they explicitly say the Xbox
is still going to be the way it is.
If I were Microsoft and I were talking to some lawmaker who had questions, I'd probably
have some huge number that was like derived from the sales of Office that get downloaded
through the store and claim that the store generates, you know, $400 million a year.
Add in those team subscriptions too while you're at it, right?
Yes.
Yeah, right.
So you could see how they could cook the books to make it look like it's a pretty big sacrifice.
I mean, great.
I love it.
Mud in Apple's eye, right?
But I feel like what really happened here is Apple continues to, for whatever reason,
be super, super petulant about this.
And as a guy who has been known to be petulant, I get it, but they're just not like, like
they just got slapped again by the Dutch authorities.
You know, if Jobs was alive, we'd all be saying this is Steve's fault.
This is Steve.
He's so pigheaded.
You know, he's so stubborn.
He's so vindictive.
So everybody would just claim it's Steve Jobs' personal decision.
But now that he's dead, people are looking for all these explanations and it just has
to come down to this.
Apple's looking at how many iPhones they sell.
They're looking at what the potential market size is and they're looking at the lifetime
of these iOS devices, especially things like the iPad and Apple TV, and they're looking
at the app store revenue and they're thinking this is our 50 year moneymaker here.
You know, I listen to other podcasts and a lot of them seem to be putting like the Apple
execs on the couch.
And I kind of feel like maybe that's partially fair that like, you know, it's Apple culture
to be kind of a jerk about things.
But they have to know, right, these aren't dumb people.
They have very fancy lawyers.
They have lobbyists.
They have to know that they're going to have to compromise.
And I think they're just doing the classic New Jersey style business negotiation of I'm
going to start at the most insane position possible.
And then I'm eventually going to concede at the last second and give you what I was already
going to give you anyway.
Yeah.
And if you project the entire time, like you're in the right, you know, like it almost weakens
your hand if you start capitulating at all, because it sort of shows that you know you're
in the wrong.
So it's like, who is going to enforce a Congress to pass a law?
Maybe I don't necessarily think that's super duper likely.
I know they're trying.
How about some regulators?
So would that be the FTC?
All right, so the FTC sues them.
Apple's like, we're one of one of if not the richest company in the world.
We can do this forever.
Well, and there needs to be some kind of law they're breaking.
So there has to be something that changes that they are then in violation of.
Yeah.
And maybe, you know, as a fake conservative, I sometimes play one on the interwebs.
Maybe I just don't think Mitch McConnell particularly cares about this and therefore it's not going
to happen.
And maybe I'm wrong.
Right.
Who knows the reason people keep saying the show is turning into like unfiltered to nobody
says that.
Do they say that?
I say it to myself in the mirror every morning.
I mean, you don't want to give people fuel.
They'll run with that.
I like that is because these companies are so big and powerful.
The only entities that could actually maybe stand up to them also happen to have Davies.
They're trillion dollar plus company.
Yeah.
It isn't like a bunch of like, you know, fun companies with some young folks and we're
all chillin.
It I love system 76 because it's nostalgia.
But when they eventually take over the world and join Microsoft Activision Blizzard, Vivendi,
I'll be sad to write.
It's like we yearn for just a small, genuine, independent business these days.
Like when I talk about Linode in the ads, I mentioned the fact that they are independent.
Yeah.
Like that's a huge deal, right?
It's not it's not very common anymore.
And it's a mistake I made for a bit.
I had to go through the process to fully appreciate the repercussions.
I hear you.
I mean, let's do a bacon competition for a minute.
How does this end in your mind, this all this app store stuff?
Well, it feels like Microsoft is four steps ahead of Apple, right?
Like Microsoft has known it was going to end up inevitably at this point.
And they've been getting things lined up to grease the wheels for this Activision Blizzard.
They've known for a year what direction Blizzard was going in, right?
We established that recently.
That in itself is horrific.
But yeah.
So they've been watching.
They've been circling Blizzard for a year while the stock dropped 50 percent in value
and their founder was engulfed in or their CEO was engulfed in controversy.
And during that time, they supplied Epic with documentation and legal time to go after Apple
and possibly some money, too, it seems, while also planning to grease the wheels around
the world with the regulators.
How Apple was clever about the M1 transition, Microsoft is very clever about this Blizzard
Activision acquisition, right?
They have been laying the groundwork for at least a year, probably more.
I don't think I can convey how savvy this move is and how alarming it is to me that
Microsoft is still very dangerous.
You are like warming my black little heart here.
Really?
I am like full on nihilism here.
Like I don't think Apple is just making a mistake.
I think they know they're going to basically win because the government of the United States
barely functions.
Yeah, it could be.
They are extremely legally savvy.
They have a pretty strong case.
Like we can't really put a finger on what rule they've broken.
They set the terms for their own store and Epic clearly violated those terms intentionally.
Well, even by the most aggressive, let's say politicians, right, the political critics,
you know, like a Klobuchar, her remedy is to pass a new law.
Sure.
Can you do it?
Right?
Can you do it to the point where it is in fact, you know, it's a wolf with some teeth.
Can you be a wolf warrior?
If you get that reference, I'm very sorry.
Or are you going to be like a little chihuahua that maybe nips them in the heels?
Because I just don't see a law with real teeth getting through both houses of Congress.
I see maybe some kind of Mickey Mouse rubber, you know, like slap on the wrist.
I don't know.
Like people are talking about there's some bill to do sideloading or to mandate sideloading.
I'd eat my hat if that happened.
I just it's never going to happen.
The issue with these bills, too, is unfortunately they're not really written by our representatives
or their staff.
They're written by industry groups and then given to our representatives.
So number one, that probably means any anti-Apple industry group is probably not as savvy as
Apple's team is.
But it's hard to say.
Their D.C. game isn't the best.
Or they're Microsoft's lobbyists, right?
That would be who would do it.
Right.
Microsoft's lobbyists, yes.
Microsoft's D.C. game is clearly superior.
It's fascinating because, you know, Apple's had to resort to Tim Cook personally calling
representatives and the White House.
Like that's desperate.
Microsoft has institutionalized their D.C. engagement, right?
It is a active part of the company.
It's on the balance sheet.
It's something they staff for.
Apple is I mean, yeah, they participate in lobbyist groups.
Don't get me wrong, but they don't have the savvy team that Microsoft does.
Really you are filling me with hope and light today.
IBM is in a lot of trouble right now.
You don't necessarily hear this very often with when it comes to controversy, but it
is striking.
I didn't even know they were still there.
IBM apparently labeled older workers, quote unquote, older workers that are 50 and up
as dino babies.
Wow.
Did they hire Mike Morhaim?
Is that what happened?
This sounds like this does sound like like a comedy almost.
I'm sorry.
I'm thinking might not Mike Morhaim, Bobby Kotick.
So documents were released in the age discrimination case that appear to show high level discussions
at IBM about paring down the ranks of older employees.
IBM executives were directly involved in discussions about the need to reduce a portion of older
employees at the company, sometimes referring to them as dino babies.
And they've released a trove of documents in federal district court on Friday.
Jesus Christ.
I know.
Here's a quote.
We've discussed the fact that our millennial population trails our competitors.
This is one email from an executive at the time.
It goes on to say, the data below is very sensitive not to be shared.
But I wanted to make sure you have it.
You'll see while Accenture is seventy two percent millennials, we are at forty two percent
with a wide range of mini units following well below that average, speaking to the need
to hire early professionals, which I guess early professionals was a company's term for
somebody who is like new, didn't have much experience.
I see.
The problem is, is they needed to, quote, accelerate change by inviting the dino babies
to leave.
It's Blade Runner and make them a, quote, extinct species.
Whoa.
Oh, yeah.
A third email refers to IBM's, quote, dated maternal workforce, which was an apparent
implication to the older women at IBM.
And it said, quote, this is what must change.
They really don't understand social or engagement.
Not digital natives.
A real threat for us.
That's like the hat trick.
All they were missing was something racist.
They got misogyny and ageism in one.
What's incredible, too, is this was a group of probably, you know, 50 to 60 year old men
and women.
Right.
As I say, the upper level executives at IBM, they have to be older dudes, mostly.
Honestly, you and I know this.
This is how a lot of companies speak internally.
Yeah.
I have been at a client of mine where I was consulting them because of an acquisition
and they wanted to speak to somebody who knew their infrastructure.
And one of the things they just openly spoke about in this meeting and this is a local
company here in Washington that nobody ever hear of, but I was shocked, is they knew the
numbers of people that were on antidepressants through the insurance program.
They didn't have the names of the people, but they knew exactly how many people were
taking what drug.
That seems not good.
And they had the open conversation of like, do we have too many people at work on antidepressants?
And I couldn't believe what I was hearing.
Now, this is probably 2009 or 10.
So this is a little while ago now.
I'm sure companies still have this.
This is the way these companies think and speak, right?
Humans that work for them are a resource that they move around.
That's why they have human resource departments that they have now given new euphemisms.
The other thing that strikes me here is there is actually a bit of truth to all of this.
I have also been at places where the older staff don't get it.
They don't get the internet.
They don't get the expectations of a younger generation.
They just don't get it.
And so they have been a bit of a challenge, but you don't work them out.
You find the work, especially at a company the size of IBM, right?
There's going to be a position there that works for them.
It's ruthless because you've got to assume some of these people probably worked there
for 10, 15, 20, 30 years, right?
They gave a massive portion of their life to this company and then they get to a certain
age and the executives who are their same age have to get rid of them because they're
a quote, real threat for us.
Thanks.
Don't let the door hit you on the way out.
I don't even know what to say.
This is just, I know it's gross.
It's gross.
Yeah.
We can argue about the app store stuff.
There's, you know, there's multiple perspectives.
There's really not two sides to this.
This is just like, you guys are a bunch of dicks.
I want to make it clear that this was years ago.
I couldn't tell you the exact date because I've apparently I've looked at the new yorktimes.com
too many times this month, so I no longer get access to information paywall because
that's the link I grabbed, but I want to say it was like 2006 or something.
It was a while ago that I guess when the documents happened or when it went down or something
like that, that makes sense too because that would be, it's just gross, right?
Well, the funny thing is now here we are.
Some of the older millennials, they're hitting their forties, right?
So these millennials that they had to hire to save the company, some of them are only
about 10 years away from the age where they were trying to, you know, call the herd.
It's just kind of wild.
It's nonsensical.
I could work with these people.
It's just, it's gross.
Well, I don't even think the premise is necessarily true, right?
Older, I'm assuming these people must be managers by now, right?
Like older managers don't necessarily need to know the new shiny, just, I don't know.
It's like if you just maybe communicated with them or had like a ongoing, you know, improvement
plan like many other companies such as Accenture, their main competitor who's kicking their
ass has.
Right.
Well, a lot of these times it's probably just, they don't appreciate the value of learning
something new.
So you just as a, you know, your mission is to do outreach and demonstrate the value.
Okay.
Is it also just cheaper to hire young people though?
Cause this, this sounds a little, now that I'm reading, I just brought up the New York
Times.
I'm thinking, I bet these older folks have also been getting their, you know, end percent
raises every year.
They've accrued a lot of perks, right, a lot of time.
Frankly, the mention of the older women is, there's probably a lot of not a good stuff
there.
Yeah.
You know, I've, I've heard gross conversations of people being like, well, we're going to
hire this woman.
But you know, she's like, she looks like she's in her early thirties and then what if we hire
her and we have to pay a maternity leave?
And it's like, people are scumbags.
I have heard that conversation as well.
So I don't, I think the folks suing them should eat their lunch and IBM should not do this
kid.
Well, I don't think they will.
Optimus Gray got the date.
It looks like it was in 2018 where these, apparently things happened.
Oh boy.
It was reported that IBM fired about 20,000 American employees over the age of 40 back
then.
So 60% of its total US job cuts.
Ah, so this is, this is connected back to that big layoff they did in 2018.
Oh, but didn't they also offshore a bunch of that?
Offshored.
And it looks like the majority of the people they laid off were the older folks, quote unquote
older.
Yeah.
I'm going to go with money.
That I actually, at the time, remember, I remember specifically people on Twitter that
used to work there making that exact point that this is about money.
So you might be onto something there.
I just wanted to mention before we wrap up, I did on your recommendation, sign up for
the Xbox streaming service.
Oh.
So I could get like the ultimate one, so that way I could do the web streaming thing.
It's only a buck for the first month, so I'm giving that a go, but they don't tell you
this when you're signing up.
It's stupid obvious now, but when you sign up and you go to launch your first game, you
have to have a supported controller, which I have, but didn't have with me.
So I didn't get to try it this morning.
So I'm going to try it out later this week and I'll tell you what I think next week.
But so far the experience feels smoother.
I have to say that I do have an Xbox controller, so I'll hook that up.
I did think it was kind of slick with Stadia.
When I signed up for Stadia, they gave me a package that included a controller and a
Chromecast that showed up and then you just, you knew you just had something that worked
out of the box with the service and that was really kind of nice.
Whereas with this service, I'm probably just going to have a mix of different controllers
depending on what computer I'm at, but I'll give it a go.
I'm actually, the more I think about it, skeptical that this is even going to work for Microsoft
because I would propose to you, people that are really into game streaming are people
who are casual gamers and the most expensive aspect of running the service is going to
be spinning up the VMs and allocating the resources and creating the machines for a
game session.
And I often play for 10-15 minutes and then bail and try another game play for 10-15 minutes,
see if it's the right fit and then bail.
And I've been getting throttled on Nvidia's service because I think it's too much resources
to spin up these machines.
And I wonder if that isn't always going to be a problem because if you were super serious
about gaming, you'd probably have the hardware or you're going to be on the other end where
you're just like logged in streaming and running the service all the time.
It just feels like they're going to have a hard time getting that balance right.
Yeah, I think, you know, I don't think you're going to be playing Halo multiplayer on this.
I just don't.
I don't know.
Whatever.
I'm going to try.
That's exactly what I want to.
I want to try.
It's not going to be an experience that's going to be on par.
Why?
Latency?
Latency.
That's what I'm thinking.
You know, I would agree if it was a keyboard and mouse game, but when you're playing controller
based games, I don't know.
Maybe.
Oh, I see.
Okay.
There's a little bit of a...
Yeah.
That's right.
Okay.
So I see.
So if you were playing a real first person shooter, it would be a problem.
Yeah.
If I had real controls.
Like, you know, like not a baby game.
I'm just saying.
No, I mean, I love it, but yeah, like, you know what, I basically exclusively play Marvel
versus Capcom and like various indie stuff that they put on there.
And those indie games, I mean, these guys haven't left the SNES color palette or, you
know, game mechanics for the most part.
And they run just fine in Chrome.
Right?
I don't know what to say.
Yeah.
Okay.
I'll keep that in mind.
I'll keep...
I'll try some of those games too.
I'll make sure I try to try out both sides of the spectrum.
I'm looking forward to it.
Well, I'm also going to try it on my Starlink setup.
You know, that's the ultimate test is can you game stream?
I remember it's a streaming game service over a Starlink connection.
We'll find out.
If you're a member, I just wanted to say thank you, if you haven't become a member yet, maybe
consider it.
Go to coderqa.co.
That's where you sign up.
And then you get a tighter episode, something that's just a little bit shorter because we
cut out the ads.
It still has all of the full production from Drew, but you just get a nicer, shorter production.
And you can support the entire network by signing up at jupyter.party where you get
access to all the shows ad free.
It's pretty sweet.
It's a nice way to support us as well.
Then you get access either membership program to the Coderly report.
And we just put out a new one recently.
Mr. Dominic, is there anywhere you'd like to send people before we get the heck out
of here?
Check out alice.dev and at Dumanuco on Twitter.
Yes.
The power move.
Why don't you join our matrix survey?
If you got matrix set up, it's colony.jupyterbroadcasting.com or we got a telegram group if that's your style.
That's at jupyterbroadcasting.com.
We'd love your feedback.
It's a big part of the show.
We need more of it.
It's at coder.show.com.
And you can subscribe to our RSS feed and get it anytime we publish.
That's at coder.show.subscribe.
Last but not least, links for this week are at coder.show.453 and you can join us live
on Mondays.
We do it at noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
Thanks so much for joining us.
We'll see you back here next week.