This is KOTORadio, episode 324 recorded August 29th, 2018.
Hi everyone and welcome to KOTORadio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and business of software development and its related technologies.
This episode is brought to you by our two great sponsors, Linux Academy and DigitalOcean.
I'll get you hip to them sponsors later on in the show.
My name is Chris and joining us every single week, like the wise Yoda in the swamps, but
instead of like some weird planet.
No, no, it's Florida.
Hello Mike.
Hmm, you said not been to Florida recently.
Yeah, I guess that's what I was thinking when I said that I'm like, well, it is kind of
a strange planet.
But you know, I know now that I'm sure we're that you're based out of Florida.
We probably have a hardcore Florida fan base.
I would just imagine true.
That is not well, I didn't want to upset the one or two of them as it might be, even if
they are family members.
I didn't want to upset them, Mike.
We are gathered today to do a little makeup for the audience last week since I've been
sick.
Yeah, we wanted to we wanted to make another episode for you.
We wanted to give you something a little more something later in your week, a little more
coder in your life.
And we've got a good smattering of topics that we like to put together on these kinds
of episodes, some some that are really just for me to troll Mike really, to be honest
with you and others that I think we'll get into pretty far.
Maybe we should start with what you teased in our last episode.
And that was you breaking your phone, because that's probably the one everybody's expecting.
So they'll not have any idea what's coming next.
So let me let me set the stage thousand dollar iPhone 10 with face ID, no home button, all
glass screen.
Is it in a case?
In a leather case, it is.
Yes.
Oh, I have the leather case, too.
So the leather case did not prevent this disaster failed the test.
So did it fall like on a rock?
Like how did you get past the bun the bumper around the edge here?
So it landed directly on his face on quote unquote artisanal.
Yeah, basically uneven tile, right?
Like tile that's intentionally uneven to feel whenever at the Brandon Mall.
Thank you.
It was great.
So so the irony is there's a crack in the screen.
That's not the worst part.
I can no longer hit buttons on the top nav bar.
Hmm.
So it's like pretty much unusable.
Yeah.
Oh, Mike, you know, you're supposed to wait another couple of weeks because we're like
we're like probably what seven, eight days away from announcement.
I know I could literally buy a new iPhone.
I get it.
Yeah.
So I've had this happen to you know, not not exactly a destroyed phone, but my partner
hadia her phone is a is like a six s I'm not sure the seven I don't know seven maybe I
don't know but it's a it's a it's a standard iPhone.
It's not the it's not the eight and it has a lightning port like all iPhones do hello
and when she plugs it in regardless of charger or cable or if it's like a car charger or
an Apple brick it'll say charging you know boom and it's a little icon will light up
that it's charging and you're good to go say it's like 20% you come back an hour later
and it's like at 18% it goes down it's going down even though it's showing that it's charging
it's got the little lightning bolt icon the battery is discharging and sometimes if you
like unplug and replug it'll start charging back up again won't necessarily get to 100%
but sometimes it does and then sometimes it stops at like 50% then you got to like pull
the lightning cable out turn it and plug it back in again tried multiple cables multiple
power adapters try to DC adapter.
It's always exhibiting this issue and I'm like babe you got to just keep this thing
going for like three more weeks you got to keep this phone going I'm not I'm not going
to go buy you a brand new iPhone seven or whatever eight or whatever it is just weeks
before so naturally the only solution is to buy an Android phone right.
I've done nothing so far oh are you tempted to go with the Android route I was until I
found out there's no comparable Android phone to buy the now the Samsung S8 is coming out
shortly but there's nothing and here's the problem I'm traveling to Utah in a week and
a half what from the date this will be out with no phone no you got to get a phone no
I need a phone that works like this phone okay my iPhone 10 works if I'm very concerned
like it's basically a dumb phone now that I have to be very sensitive and how I touch
it yeah I'm living in a nightmare you could just get a feature phone you know just for
like a couple of weeks although when you're traveling also slip my wrists in a bathtub
you need maps and oh man yeah cuz I'm driving in Utah let me tell you Utah it's not a friendly
state to me have you have you met Mormons and by the way we're once again brought to
us by Malfoy gin I'm just saying Utah's not where I want to be lost Salt Lake City is
not bad I tell you what I've had some good times in Salt Lake City have you cuz I've
had some rough times in Salt Lake City I did get stared at a lot I did a lot of are you
okay sir yeah I got a lot of that I got a lot of I got a lot of weird looks and I don't
know exactly why cuz I wasn't doing anything oh I can tell you why why cuz of me cuz cuz
you and I do we stand out yeah we're well how it stands out is it is it the hair what
is it have you ever seen the movie have you ever seen the movie Monsters Inc it's my it's
a Disney movie kids love monsters my son's current favorite yep oh man it's a good time
when they get you and I are effectively hairy blue neon green monsters and yeah in Salt
Lake City yeah and we're sullies is what you're saying we're walking around as giant sullies
we're giant sullies and sometimes I'm Mike Wazowski like it's not what you want because
I don't know I I fear Mormons and and I have relatives who've converted to the Latter-day
Saints Church which is Mormonism yeah I'm terrified of them because my nightmare is
a Mormon cop actually like that's things I'm afraid of it does sound scary it does sound
scary I'm wondering I'm wondering if there's a show title in this somewhere but it does
I follow your point I do follow you Mike fears Joseph Smith right right like yeah I mean
so you you and I have ever okay can we talk about water down beer for a moment yeah okay
have you ever had tap your beer in Salt Lake City the worst beer okay in the United States
that is the it is it is so disappointing but to drink you know why law it's a lot like
they think they have a hard cap on the right there's a municipal ordinance right on the
alcohol content of beer right yeah how producers I actually think Utah is partially responsible
for America's bad rap for beer because we have we have fantastic beer here in the States
we have a massive microbrew culture with really good beer Tampa has 70 breweries yeah like
we're yeah but we have that we have that dysfunctional situation in Utah where beer manufacturers
have to make these half-assed one-cock versions of their beers which just tastes horrible
I can't even describe the taste it's and it's almost like it's like just a water it tastes
like this like it tastes like sadness right there's a really cuz like because there's
no reason to drink it because it tastes horrible and it's like shitty soda yeah it's not beer
it's not soda it's something awful in between yeah yeah I was shocked I mean I know about
it but I was shocked when I die and frankly go to hell because yeah I will end up in Salt
Lake City like that so like I'm not enthusiastic about this trip I'm pretty unhappy you know
as long as you don't drink the beer I think Salt Lake City is pretty great you know I
think it is yeah what are two martinis and wait till the cops follow you around yeah
I'm just saying yeah yeah yeah it's just hostile territory we should move on from this all
right so uh so your phone broke and Mike's an alcoholic but we give you yeah yeah those
are the two two major points here yeah now here's the one that I don't know if we shared
with the class is you and maybe you told us but I don't think you've given us the review
yet recently picked up a new workstation a new portable workstation a galago 2018 you
bought the original galago uh 4k had some fan issues had some temperature issues so
I was surprised to hear that you went back to the new galago but from your initial impressions
it sounded like they had made some revisions to the model that were pretty good so now
I'm curious now that you've had them for a couple of weeks what's it been like using
the new galago yeah so I got the new galago um I got the 1080p not the 3k version okay
or rather 4k version apologies um and I have to say matte screens are the way to go ah
the 1080p screen is matte part of it's because a lot of linux apps just don't have awesome
4k coverage yeah and it's a lot more computer to drive that display too right and and just
like matt is prettier the battery life is better than the 4k version is this you're gonna is
this gonna be your utah rig no and I like the entrapment I like the entrapment so why
is that because the product I am unveiling at utah is a windows-based product oh my mac
my macbook will be my utah rig because it has a windows partition you know that tickles
me right yeah that tickles me in the words of my my distant cousin bain necessary evil
so this is like your office daily driver this is what you're like you know what fuck it
I'm just gonna go for it all right we're gonna talk about the cute company for a moment oh
oh boy I spent months writing this product in c++ to run on linux it was gonna be a huge
thing for us we were gonna veil on quit radio was gonna be fabulous it was gonna be great
I was gonna give you some money you could have done some ads on linux yeah that sounds
good I like all those linux action news it was gonna be awesome and then capitalism oh
not that again those dirty dirty money grubbing money they yeah yeah but I'm hoping to make
some money yeah yeah not they want to make more money per unit than I was gonna charge
per license right like I would literally owe the money every time I made a sale like what
the hell is wrong with cute so you were you're buying this galago and you're thinking this
is my future right here this is it like we're gonna build linux and windows cross-platform
software because you know we're in the aerospace industry so yeah ignoring windows is is effectively
suicide right or you got a choice that's what your customer that's what your customers run
the future is going to be linux right okay like the future's next even microsoft knows
that so right so I'm thinking okay we'll write it in cute for linux and then we'll like effectively
back the work to windows all right and I spent three days in and we talked about in a previous
episode in dll hell making it all work yeah and it worked it was fabulous right everything
worked we have a fully functioning binary that written in cute that's awesome feels
good business deal with the cute company just like it was basically if I can channel my
new jersey roots here and forgive me itunes go get your fucking shine box kid we just
don't make enough money for them to even care to deal with us yeah it's it's crazy that
is an old saying go get your shine box kid that is so jersey it is very jersey I like
how you cleaned it up so we ended up in this position where while linux is the future windows
is a requirement for right now to go it seems like that's yeah we're already committed we're
already we're already like married to the show I can't back out I'm I'm hooked yeah
man so rewritten in dot net it was what do you think about windows 10 dual booting on
the galago I haven't done it yet I bet you it works better than it does on the macbook
you know I wonder why you say that because it's because it's garbage on the macbook first
of all the camp isn't that terrible it is it is like the fans are crap like this your
macbook constantly is way too hot it's because there's no thermal management under windows
until you start getting to the really critical stuff it's just never has felt right it's
just like the bootcamp drivers are trash they're just the worst software you gotta you gotta
run that one single executable to install everything and they're all garbage and at
the end of it you get a machine that's got like a somewhat less functional trackpad poor
thermal management it just feels like forced on there but the galago I mean that's just
standard Intel hardware with a standard thermal system and a standard fan management system
like it's all just Intel spec so Windows 10 would just work with natively with all that
stuff you know because you know there's models of that galago sold by other OEMs that are
running Windows you know so I so so this is the sick irony of this whole problem I would
have bought a galago with a bigger hard drive had I known true right right right I do recall
you kind of got a smaller one because you didn't need a big one but but you asked me
about the galago and I decided to go on a rant about cute those money-grubbing pricks
from Boston the literal worst place in the United States other than Salt Lake City so
we should continue on so you're liking it though for what it is I'm liking it you keep
pop on there did you switch off pop what's going on I'm on pop I am running basically
an environment that is effectively as close to the stock as you can get and I want to
hedge that a little because I've done some changes hmm I did get really drunk one night
sure and mess with your computer install Katie I installed plasma oh Chris I installed plasma
yeah it's tempting I know and let me tell you something oh plasma is not just tempting
plasmas leave your wife and kids and never look back yeah you can lose a lot of time
you couldn't yeah plasma is nice I I question the wisdom of pot being based on no after
looking at plasma you know I had a I had a I had a back and forth on Twitter with a journalist
at Forbes who's been today before we go to the show that has been trying out a bunch
of different Linux distros and he just popped on plasma and loves it too and I'll tell you
if you if you try it and you like it it's it kind of behooves you to install kabuntu
or another spin that is plasma first so that way it's a little cleaner like you know terminal
launches the right call you know the cute version of it and all it is it is a great
desktop system I agree it is nice you throw that on there you got a nice screen you got
a good keyboard that's a it's a good setup it sounds like how's the heat how's the heat
and fan how's that so this is where we get into some conversation so I still have I was
able to repair my damaged original galago now it's slightly damaged still so we can
take this a grain of salt my subjective analysis is that the fan on the non-high dpi new galaco
comes up much less frequently that makes sense but it does come up oh and the battery life
while being better is not like macbook good or macbook pro good it's it's good enough
right that's what I would say I follow that's a little disappointing but I follow it yeah
it's I'm happy with the machine I'm not in love with it you know if I put it against
my 50 I mean it's unfair to put it against my 15 inch macbook pro with a designated graphics
card but it like it's weird it has a better keyboard for sure but the battery life definitely
suffers and I was wondering so would you say so I know you you kind of you bought a pretty
reasonable one for me because I would want some storage for multiple distros and stuff
like that for me in fact that price is mine like a 2161 dollars do you feel like that's
a fair price for the rig would you would you spend that kind of money on it for more storage
and an i7 it has the i7 with 32 gigs of ram is that is it a 2100 computer it I think it
is it so so this is a you're getting to a fundamental problem I'm having of should laptops
be a main development computer or not and what I'm realizing is you know maybe Mac versus
Linux is not that important I mean Windows is garbage because it's Windows but I'm just
kidding folks like let me give you an example I put like right now I'm broadcasting on my
MacBook Pro right the minute I plug it into my monitor eight down clocks so and I mostly
work in clamshell mode plugged into a monitor or monitor mode using the laptop screen as
a second monitor it and that's not a Mac problem at most computers do that I think the Gallego
will do that so is that a reasonable computer I guess if you intend to use it as a laptop
but I would almost question and more question myself than you do you need does your portable
computer need to be that powerful like have we approached this question in the wrong way
I think the assumptions always been more powers better see battery life is becoming a bigger
and bigger issue for me I feel like my dual core XPS 13 is way too slow these days web
pages are not loading fast enough electron apps are too laggy like a booth still fine
shuts down super fast like the disk seems fine like doing updates packages installing
all perfectly fine but I do feel like I'm getting leg in the UI on both Chrome and Firefox
a lot more these days to the point where sometimes it makes it a little annoying to use and even
to the point where sometimes I've even seen input delay when I'm like filling out a form
or something like that so that is not fast enough and so that's why I've decided to get
a ThinkPad T 480 myself it's ordered now it is ordered and I think it's gonna take him
like three weeks to make it because it's a custom order and that's gonna be a 14 inch
screen but with you know pretty high-end components because I was trying to get the most out of
this XPS 13 I could but it really has just felt too slow and because I'm pushing it so
often the fan has been going so much now that it sounds like that the fans starting to grind
like the fans going out it's only got one fan in it so if it goes I don't know what's
gonna happen that's that so that was sort of my threshold you know I didn't have like
a like a metric I was trying to figure out a metric to measure some benchmarks or something
that I could get some data around and I couldn't I never got there even on unplugged I asked
the audience I'm like what do you guys use like what tools and I talked about open benchmark
and how you could use that but it just didn't really work it was at the end of the day I'm
like this computer just doesn't feel fast enough I'm waiting around too often for this
computer and then part of it is because the web applications the damn electron and web
apps have just gotten bigger and I'm not really doing anything different other than just running
more complex online applications it's yeah so I and yeah so that I went with the t480
although I was I did consider the galago for a bit it's a it's also a great machine so
and I'm glad to hear that it seems like it's better overall I would be curious now how
Windows 10 works on that thing yeah I might have to do I mean that the problem I'm facing
is my dogs also hate the cute they're barking at you right now yeah like I don't want to
like badge on cue like I said last episode I have invited a rep from the cute company
come on and they have not responded I there is no reason I should be doing major WPF
done that development other than as a small business I can't afford their license right
they sort of forced your hand on what tool you're going right they gave me no choice
because I'm already married to the show we talked about it I think last episode in Utah
or was it this episode I have no idea in my sadness with their water down there yeah it
it seems weird to me that we don't have a first class completely open source Windows
slash Linux cross platform software development platform well I guess we do supposedly it's
just not the one you wanted it's the hero you needed but not the one you wanted which
one is it that I want done well you wanted to use cute but dotnet is offering you a solution
it's just not the one well and this is the irony and this is where I want to take this
conversation ironically the Xamarin right now you can compile to GTK sharp and one on
Linux yes right right so the answer to my question is actually dotnet yeah it feels
weird like it feels like a cringe you know I get a little nauseous it feels it feels
odd because I think about Q and I think that's like so you know that's the KDE project that's
in the Linux ecosystem but it turns out that they're like more hostile to a small development
shop that wants to be Linux focused then Microsoft which is like weird you know so I'll pick
up on that a sec but I'll say this just as an aside is I have always heard rumblings
of the licensing around cute it's really strange it's something you'd look into it's a concern
and I never really got any specifics on it until this event and I think I think so I
know it I know this it has a rep but it's really always been very vague and it turns
out you don't really find out let me take it for you exciting and there are two types
of licenses there's a straight commercial where you pay per developer which is expensive
but kind of reasonable it's like taking a merchant advance loan it's really expensive
but you get how they got there yeah the problem I hit is that they felt and I was cringing
at the developer license is that they felt what we were doing and I'll in a few weeks
so I'll be talking about the product on the show they considered it an embedded product
even though it's running on you know straight Debian and straight Windows 10 they considered
it an embedded product which they have a per unit license fee plus an initial cost which
was completely unsustainable for sure and they considered using it in this manner was
an obvious violation of the LG PL no matter how we do so that okay that does that does
clear it up so that that left us and it because people have been tweeting at me that left
me in a position of if I went forward and just like a sort of the LG PL yeah you know
I can't go to court against Q right in win because I don't I just don't have the capital
I just don't have enough money my whole product that I've been working on for months would
be open source and I would just like not be able to sell it philosophy aside that's just
not the model I'm working on yeah yeah so yeah I mean if that I mean feel free to ask
any questions you want Chris I mean that but that's like the long and short of it well
I'll do this let's take a moment and thank digital ocean and then I'll come back and
ask do dot co slash coder that's where you go to sign up for a $100 free credit for new
accounts over digital ocean and then you can try out the platform for 60 days with that
$100 credit try out one of their mix and match droplets where you can set up the different
resources that you need for your specific application one of their high CPU or high
memory droplets that's why over a million developers trust digital ocean because they
make it so easy and so quick to get started which means you go from hey I got an idea
to it's actually up on the web and ready to test in five minutes and that kind of compression
of time means you actually get to do it you actually get to try it and you build momentum
so quickly with these projects it really makes the difference and you can get started with
a $100 credit at do dot co slash coder they have industry leading price to performance
an example my favorite rig three cents an hour beautiful four gigs of RAM two CPUs 80
gigabytes of enterprise grade SSD three terabytes of transfer and you can get it going in less
than 55 seconds you can do an entire deployment of an application stack or you can just deploy
the base system and get started plus they have a lot of really good documentation to
help you get even further with digital ocean just a couple of days ago they posted how
to use node.js and github webhooks to keep your remote projects in sync you could get
this running on a digital ocean droplet take care of this for you and man this is nice
looking and one of the beautiful things about digital ocean just real gorgeous number all
over there is their tutorials really well crafted well put together not only I mean
not just from like a structure standpoint but from a formatting standpoint to to really
make it clear this is code this is something that needs to go to config file and then it's
all itemized out to it's the best documentation on the web so try it all out by going to do
dot co slash coder and a big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the coder radio
program so I guess my question to you is this how big of an oh shit moment did you have
when all this math comes to okay this is why I bought the galago shit now I can't use that
oh crap we've already committed to present at this show in Utah and now that the demo
app that we have built we can't use and we got to come up with something else and we
have a couple of weeks to do it like how big of an oh shit moment was that for you let's
just say those those boxers will never see the light of a lot of poo came out yeah it
was a bad situation I mean and it was yeah oh man that must have been a really stressful
couple of days I imagine it was rough I'm sorry dude I can only cheese and my coder
therapy sessions were canceled I know right right so it was but the whole application
got rewritten and it's frankly done now in dot net so you bet how much writing of dot
net have you been doing on Linux itself some okay a little bit so how much so just a little
bit well so like back in logic is back in logic right the the places where you get into
trouble is the user interface I imagine that is very much the case actually yeah yeah yeah
so like yeah so you you tease me with some large-scale WPF development I'm assuming then
that this is all part of this this is part of this yes the application it's a WPF application
which you know we had platform UNO on a few weeks ago they do not currently support WPF
the irony though is in parallel to all of this Xamarin the little the little busy bees
over there have been working on a GTK sharp compile point and a WPF file point compile
point rather so this may all be able to be rectified by simply refactoring a bit from
WPF native to Xamarin okay that's not like you know it's not terrible yeah it's not like
writing yeah that's that's recoverable you know this is another way to put that the C
sharp code goes into the garbage I mean start the C++ code from Q has already gone into
the garbage which is kind of disappointing I think I hear your MacBook over there working
hard right now my MacBooks real upset you're not running Windows on that thing are you
I'm not it's just running Firefox and Chrome one Chrome tab like I hate I hate computers
right now I can't even you know all I have to say all laptops kind of suck right now
yeah yeah it's the best machine is the machine down on the on the floor with a monitor and
keyboard like attached to it yeah I have to say it's you know I know system 76 supposedly
is coming out with a desktop their manufacturing Colorado yeah Apple in 2019 may or may not
have a Mac Pro right I think those are gonna be the two machines I looked at I'm just getting
real tired of worrying about thermals I mean yeah yeah battery life and just you know what
like get a Chromebook get 12 hours of battery life and that's your expectation I just I'm
so there and maybe this will finally solve our problems that we've been having with these
things like I'm here recording I'm thinking to myself you know I my best machines in the
studio have been these desktops because they last for like five or six years to running
24-7 laptops don't hold up to that and these things never get a break they're always going
they're always on always ready to record and they're still great they're still reliable
and they still feel fast no I I I I mean my laptop dream and I can hear my fan through
my headphones I can hear and it's a Mac it's not even the Galaga yeah I can't even say
it's like I know has a bad thing it's the fricking MacBook yeah yeah it's that Chrome
tab the Chrome tab eats up the CPU it's the one tab I'm running with you to do the show
right like yep yeah it's there's there's so much wrong with the way things are right now
I don't know no but but at all all kidding aside right like I am deeply disappointed
that the that the stuff with Q didn't work out yeah man I could only imagine like I mean
you got you know not only do you have like this this like like the sensation oh man I
bet on the wrong horse but also like now you got it you got to do this whole like what
are we gonna do now how long did it take for you to sort of refactor was it was it was
it a was it sort of an a B thing as in well we have no other choice but this or was there
some sitting around thinking what do we do can we LDL this thing can we there was it
yeah there there so a lot of things happen in parallel there was an initial version of
this written in Xamarin actually ah okay and it was well do we just do we just embrace
Xamarin right it's a Marion whatever you want to call it right that that got effectively
vetoed by me because splitting average garbage yeah right like well Xamarin is not garbage
I take it back but like Xamarin for the high performance error space use case is a tough
choice right now so we ended up going with WPF taking some of the C sharp logic over
for the Xamarin version and that was purely a practical decision of our potential end
customers in this industry ultimately while they're moving to Linux they ultimately initially
care about Windows and WPF is a technology like we looked at Avalon rather Avalon UI
which is an open source UI project to bring a UWP to all the platforms we looked at platform
Uno but ultimately as a small company working in a big space I felt that I very strongly
that I need to mitigate the fear right to sell our product come back to the mic come
back to the mic so yeah you fear of the team or fear of the customer fear of the customer
right okay so the customer look at that sideways and go what the hell is this right so we ended
up rewriting the UI and WPF ah so to make it safer essentially to the customer nobody
gets fired for buying a WPF app right oh man that's true yeah so we ended up going in that
direction huh seems pretty rational it seems sad yeah a compromise I would have preferred
to even go UWP to be honest you know I feel like in some way not that this is the double
episode of picking on Q but Q is somehow like ignoring a market that would be willing to
pay them several hundred dollars a month yeah I have also heard that sentiment from others
yeah like I would have been much happier coming on the show today and saying we are a Linux
shop we're running C++ yes we cross compile to the windows and yes we you know 90 percent
of our customers are using Windows devices but you know we're a Linux shop but in reality
the licensing fees were just unacceptable I'm curious as to what you've heard I've definitely
heard that they could come up with something that is way more compelling to small business
and solve a lot of this that is that is a sentiment I've heard from people at conferences
a lot where I've gotten a lot of the side by grousing that never was quite clear to
me until we've had our conversation I'll tell you man I'll take the liable liable suit yes
I'll tell you know things can change but it sort of doesn't matter like the window of
opportunity like let's just I was just thinking like maybe down the road they'll come up with
some sort of like small business competitive offering but because you know really the reason
why I think that'd be great is cute is stronger as a platform the more of it that is out there
the more the more people that are shipping cute apps the more people that are developing
cute software the larger the community though just what is the right word to put it it's
a it's a it's there's a tangible benefit that's probably the way to put it there's a real
tangible benefit to the cute company for more people to be shipping cute apps so it would
seem like if the opportunity came up for them to say okay here's a small business here's
a small business package that would be a very compelling offering that would probably get
a lot of traction but it's it's too little too late for you isn't it well it's a done
deal right I mean I I'm going to demo the software in a week and a half now and we're
by the time this is on the RSS feed probably less than a week so it's yeah I mean we're
married to dotnet we're married to C sharp you're already going to the event as far as
it's concerned really I mean you're right I mean even if this product fails it would
be hard for us to go to Q and and frankly I think this product is going to do okay well
I hope so that sounds from what I've heard off air it sounds pretty cool I'll take a
moment and I want to thank Linux Academy they have something really cool going on starting
on September 4th and I think it goes till the 27th of 2018 September 27th I'm not totally
sure they'll have details though starting September 4th on their website they're offering
a massive discount full year subscription for $299 which is a fantastic deal it's the
best deal I've ever had and it's it's a great value so I wanted to let you know about that
go to Linux Academy comm slash coders that's got an S on it to get that you could sign
up right now for a free seven-day trial get an idea of what the platform is what's available
to learn on there and then when that promo comes out on September 4th you could jump
on it and you could lock it in for a year at $299 which is such a good deal so check
it out Linux Academy comm slash coders also stick around on their YouTube channel excuse
me Linux Academy comm on YouTube you know Linux Academy comm on YouTube go search for
Linux Academy comm on YouTube subscribe to their YouTube channel there's gonna be some
stuff on that channel that I think will be applicable to our audience specifically in
the next few weeks YouTube comm slash Linux Academy comm and then go to Linux Academy
comm slash coders on or before September 4th and you can grab that $299 promo I believe
it runs until the 27th of this month but again details will be on their website and you can
sign up right now for the seven-day free trial and just start to get a taste for the platform
and then next week get the deal Linux Academy comm slash coders big thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring this here program so if you ever you ever fantasize about like what if
you're in a totally different field and I have yeah yeah what's yours what would be
your like if like you know a universe be version of Mike that never becomes a developer you
know what would your teacher school teacher school teacher poetry wow school I could do
teaching definitely I I feel like I worry for me that it'd be something like sales you
know like I get into sales or something because I think you do have that voice yeah I sell
yeah yeah yeah you're a seller that's so I mean it would just be horrible like no offense
to salesman because a good salesman is a very valuable thing no a lot of offense to salesman
cause I have not yet to meet a good one keep going you're talking to one no I'm telling
you like I worry that's what it would be but I think it'd be like a like a used car salesman
or something horrible if I had a fantasy we're like it would never work out it would be running
my own barbecue you know like a like a hole in the wall slow-cooked pit barbecue where
I just have a like a stable customer base that comes in on the weekdays for lunch and
I only serve lunch and dinner and then and then maybe start doing a little breakfast
do you have a liquor license I mean I think I do in this fantasy yeah well then I'm there
baby I'm your best customer I think I would I think I would run a pretty good barbecue
place I'd only have a few things at first you know keep it real focused real narrow
and nail those products that's my fantasy but I got to tell you I think the reality
is I'd be I'd be like a software engineer sales lead or something it's like the worst
job on the planet because I already went into IT so I've got to avoid that but you know
and I'm already in broadcasting now and so I got to avoid that so it'd have to be I mean
that's you know that's a couple of that's a couple of my go-tos that I can't choose
from so you could tell us audience what you think our alternative universe careers are
by going to coder.show slash contact and if you got a good one I'll try to read it on
a future episode of the Coder Radio program our record schedule is gonna be a little funky
for the next bit because you heard their mics traveling and doing this thing and it's a
long event and he's gonna be gone for a bit so when we get an opportunity we'll do some
doubles and we'll keep the feed going so go to coder.show slash subscribe for all the
ways to get new episodes.
Now before we wrap do you have any like tools or like tool chain stuff you want to cover
because we always tend to do that when we do these doubles any new I mean we mentioned
scoop last week so we can't use that mentioned scoop last week any tools you've been working
with in this process or anything like that yeah kind of so geez I don't even know if
I want to mention this but I took a quick look at a oh geez what did get pod or oh yeah
get pod.io that's what it is I'll drop a link in the show notes yeah drop a link they're
in beta yet yeah I've heard about this yeah they're one of these cloud IDEs and I looked
at it in the content let me give you some context again I have an 11 year old brother
now and I and he's interested in learning coding so you know but he's in New Jersey
I'm in Florida so you know there's some challenge there right like working with him on assignments
this is a cloud IDE that integrates directly with github it seems pretty powerful I've
played with it some it reminds me a lot of remember cloud nine we featured a few years
ago yes yeah it seems like a cloud nine on steroids the catch here is they only support
so many languages okay very few actually so javascript java python go php rust ruby
c and c++ json docker and obviously html and c it says they don't support much else but
they they directly tie into a github get flow workflow yeah that's like their key feature
really yeah so so to me I mean this is not how they build themselves and I would love
to have someone from get pod on the show to explain it to me but to me this is the ultimate
teaching tool for a oh you know a child like like my brother sure huh yeah so it's it's
it's tightly integrated with github it's where you start actually with this you have to use
get up right it's it's you have no choice yeah and then they have an enterprise version
that you can host yourself but that's you know this is pretty cool though how's the
how's the ui all that stuff it's pretty usable you know it reminds me of vs code like it's
okay honestly i we've experienced some latency issues my brother is running a older macbook
that i gave him uh like a 20 oh geez let's say a 2014 macbook pro 13 inch uh with a kick
as a ram but you know he i give him my hand me down he's doing like it works for him fine
yeah he's right you know he's right you know how you mean you remember kids right i'm sure
you have dylan you know they're writing their little games right whatever it's you know
yep yeah yeah they're fine with it his laptop is not a performance machine at all and he's
fine with it i mean yeah i'm sure as he gets older he'll want something faster but yeah
this is nice and so it's got an integrated chat too and it makes it yeah it doesn't make
it clear who's working on what portion and whatnot it does i find it works significantly
better in chrome than firefly uh-huh i've had a few of the little yeah which is a little
annoying to me but other than that it's it's a uh i mean it's pretty powerful my brother
and i like i can't speak to the go support or the java support we've been working mostly
in ecma script slash javascript um but yeah and also it supports python so any of the
other parents out there i know 99.99 percent of our listeners are um frankly corrupted
by the snake and love python so yeah does not support ruby though somehow uh oh right
it does oh oh it doesn't support it partially supports ruby yeah i have uh i have been i
have been using chrome more and more again because of several applications and sites
that i use that just seem like they slow down the firefox ui the whole browser ui gets
all laggy i've been having since i've been working on my mac for this wpf project because
yay visual studio for mac and vmware um i've been having stability issues in firefox because
of just like certain applications seem to just require chrome and and it it reminds
me of ie6 i don't i don't i hate saying that because it feels very old manny but i mean
come on chris you remember like what's best than i yeah yeah like yeah oh yeah oh yeah
i do oh yeah i do yeah i'll give you a couple of tools that i've been using just really
quickly um i guess i'll really one um but i've been using it to use multiple tools and
uh you may know about it but i'm going to remind you in case you've forgotten it's called
nata fire nata fire makes any web page into essentially an electron app um oh sure yeah
but it's great because so you know you can point nata fire mail.google.com and i can
have multiples with different icons and different logins and in their own individual windows
which i find really great for managing multiple gmail accounts or whatnot and it's just really
simple because it pulls down like their uh web app icon so you can you know you can actually
use the official logo icon for the application and it works on uh i think all the platforms
i mean i've obviously been using it on linux but uh i yeah their github page shows it on
a mac and it's nice it's simple sounds like you've probably heard of it before mike and
it just essentially wraps up websites and electron which i know that's everybody's favorite
thing but if it gets a heavily used web application out of a tab in my web browser and lets me
have my own set of credentials in that window and all of that it's a win for me so yeah
i'll link to that too yeah sounds yeah no that's really good in the notes it'll all
be a coder.show slash three two four is this which which episode is this yeah three two
four two four they run together yeah so i've been i've just plugged in like a few different
google apps into that and a couple other things that i just i find that to be intensely useful
there's a couple others out there we talked about another one on linux unplugged this
week but mr dominic i that was my tool um i don't really i don't really have much others
other than grousing about firefox which i i could do for a whole nother episode but
yeah i want firefox to be better than it is yeah yeah i just want it to be great because
i want there to be that strong competition and i want a company like mozilla to be putting
a product out there where their primary motivation is an open web and not commercial dominance
of the internet so google frankly scares me yeah yeah and their and their leverage of
chrome is one of the scarier aspects of google right now so it is a big problem oh too bad
it seems to i mean it just seems to work better for me and i find that intensely frustrating
i feel that way about mac os oh oh oh i'm sticking with firefox for now but when i'm
on other platforms other than linux i tend to use chrome more i don't know all right
mr dominic uh give somebody something else to go get if they want a little more mic in
their life during the week uh go to add to my twitter and at the mad butter.com hey how
about that you can follow me i'm at chris las the whole network is at jupiter signal
and of course we have the subreddit coderadio.reddit.com try to check that before each episode and
our main show site at coder.show thanks for being here see you next week