This is Kota Radio, episode 358 for May 20th, 2019.
Hi everyone and welcome to Kota Radio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show
taking a pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development and
its related technologies. I'm filling in for Mr. West Payne this week who's off in
Barcelona, Spain. It's a Kota classic because joining me as always is our host
battling the Gators in Florida. It's Mr. Dominic. Hello Mike. Hello, hello Chris.
Hello, it feels good right? It's back. You know it's like my
ex-husband came back to me. This is beautiful. I love it. I just had to send
him to Spain you know then finally could be you and me again. Just the two of us.
That's an expensive way to do that. Hey I'm a VP now. Listen, that's right.
That's right. You got that corporate job. Actually this is funny. Elle put it all
together. I don't even think Linux Academy is paying for it. I think because Elle
is such a contributor to the community that they like please come. I think this
I might be wrong but I'm pretty sure like it was like all expenses paid trip.
Although they do have to volunteer and do work. I don't know if we told them that
yet but he'll figure that out pretty quick. Surprise. Yeah I know it's good to
be with you. It's good to be with you. Especially on an episode where we've got
like a good mix of hoopla, a good mix of feedback. The only thing we're missing
is like a classic pick or something. Yeah. Maybe we can randomly come up with
something. Like the Mac Pro we could talk about? Sure yeah I'm good with that.
Oh that's not a pick. That's not a pick. That's a dream. That's a dream. All right
so I was just gonna go through some of the feedback and see what you guys have
wrecked while I've been gone. But you know because the universe hates me my
markdown preview tool took a dump right as we started the show today. You ever
had one of those? Happens all the time. I'll tell you what. I tell you. I tell you
what. So anyways we're just narrowly avoiding too I should say. Narrowly
avoiding the whole WWDC thing. Now I think you and Wes are gonna have to
cover that next week right? Is it like it's the week after? It's very soon. It's
June the 3rd? The only reason why I say we're narrowly avoiding it it's not that I
mind the show talking about it it's just that if if I came on the show during the
WWDC week. You'd buy five HomePods. No I'm gonna be too busy buying the HomePods to be on
the show. Now everybody would assume we're talking about it because I'm on
the show. Not because it's WWDC week but just because I'm on the show. Well let me
explain something. Okay. If there is a Mac Pro launched we're gonna have to
rename the show. Why was that? You think you're gonna get one? I have wanted one
since I was a wee lad. Although I probably can't afford one given what
they charge for the iMac Pro. It starts at like five thousand maybe six thousand.
Oh I think five is generous. I'm thinking like eight. Really? Yeah I think
it's like I think it's kidding aside I think it's a 10k plus purchase for most
people. Which sounds insane to me but you know how Apple is they're gonna make it
they're like you know this is our Tesla right mm-hmm yeah you wanted this fine
pay for it that's what it's gonna be here's what we did we took a Dell case
we laminated it a few times and we multiplied the price by 20 and ran Mac OS
on it all right so let's get into some feedback from last week's episode three
OS is one GPU Tom wrote in and he says Google has contributed a ton to Linux in
the open source but at this point it's no comparison to what Microsoft is now
doing they've got a lot of developer mindshare as a result of that but
Microsoft's has spent a lot more on acquisitions and developer relations and
has simply made some great moves since Nadella took over you have VS code
github and typescript which are all crushing it now and it sure looks like
2019 will be the year that Microsoft took over the software development scene
he says by the way your analysis has been right all along all roads do lead
to Azure Google was busy trying to pivot to the
enterprise with Google Cloud Microsoft came along and snatched up the hard one
dev mindshare right underneath them Google blew it by not buying github and
I admire how Google tends to prefer to spend on engineers but in this case
Microsoft outflanked them he's right only in that at all of the major events
in the last couple of weeks I have seen people talking about a lot of Microsoft's
tools Satya Nadella was up on stage at Red Hat VS code was on the slides at
Red Hat it's huge right now what they're doing with github and the private
repositories that they've just announced or public repositories as well it's it's
um I don't know man it's like it's like Microsoft has has realized that they can
be the the like the development platform for the for the web and Google is trying
to still trying to like get like their infrastructure to be a legitimate
product like they're going through a renaming process right now yeah they are
actively trying to solicit businesses I've gotten a couple of notes from
listeners that have gotten offers from Google to come in and write them a check
to move off of AWS like they're they're really scrambling right now someone told
me something like that I sort of didn't believe it I've got three different
stories really that I can't directly share on air one that I have very very
very familiar knowledge with and two others that I got very good
descriptions of what the offers were yeah I mean there's so much there just
with the AWS stuff and Google like if you've ever used Google App Engine and
you've also used AWS or digital ocean and Docker Google it's just not a
pleasant environment to work in it's not that it's bad it works right I mean I'm
not trying to but yeah they're there's they're somewhat behind I mean I would
say from a DevOps perspective my preferred solution is just do and doku
my way to glory but if I have to use one of the big clouds AWS is uh although
honestly Azure cuz yay click to deploy and I'm lazy you know I feel like what
what Google Cloud had going for it was we can be sort of the neutral cloud
provider we'll work with Kubernetes early on before anybody else would you
know if they were that was that was their big well one and I shouldn't say
they're big but that was one of their big value ads is that they were more
vendor neutral they would work with multiple different vendors and clouds
yeah and it turns out that wasn't that hard for the other vendors to implement
it didn't take them that long to figure out a way to provide Kubernetes services
and things like that and that's on my mind right now just because our crews at
KubeCon like Wes but that sort of changed the game and I think it removed
some of the value proposition of Google Cloud not all of it in fact there was a
tech snap episode we did towards the beginning of the year I believe with a
training architect from Linux Academy Matt you Lason who is brilliant and
really knows the Google Cloud platform and was able to clearly clearly
articulate reasons why it is a good product and so that is you know fair
enough to them it is if they've built something there but it seems a little
too late and I think that's really Tommy Tom's point in the feedback what do you
think about this emax romance er wrote in hadn't really crossed my mind let's
just chew on this for a sec for a second he says isn't in theory the Windows
subsystem for Linux a version one more interesting from a technological point
of view sort of more like how wine but it was in the opposite direction whereas
WSL 2 is more like a tiny VM that's just running a Linux kernel in hyper V so
it's not as tech like they were trying to do something technically really
interesting with WSL 1 it didn't quite get there but in a way isn't it
actually a more interesting technological experiment when you're
doing that translation instead of just doing a big old VM I mean interesting in
terms of was it more interesting to read the Microsoft research papers sure was it
more practically viable well it's hard because WSL 2 isn't really out in a 1.0
form yet yeah fair enough my bets gonna be no day-to-day like like you know we
were talking a little bit about like my assertion that Windows 10 might end up
becoming the most popular quote-unquote Linux distro yeah I mean it I I just
have a feeling that from a practical boring perspective of getting crap dumb
WS 2 is going to be the way to go but certainly there's an alternate universe
maybe where I definitely get us a point where the work being done on WSL 1 for
lack of a better term that kind of translation strategy might have actually
bled into services like wine and stuff like that although we have a lot of
stuff like that now right we have proton we have wine I almost feel like weirdly
enough the odd man out here is Mac in terms of being able to kind of like
cross-pollinate between the you know the ecosystems the systems right operating
systems I do get his point and it did make me smile I think I kind of agree
doing that translation is maybe more interesting but when it really comes
down to it and you're just trying to get work done especially when you're trying
to develop software the practical nature of having the entire kernel it's just
matters so much more that that functions that I think at the end of the day I
think we will not even really give it a second thought it doesn't matter moving
forward speaking of Windows I was just reading this feedback from mangas I'm
sure I'm getting that one wrong and he's he's pointing out a tool that makes me
realize something if I were to spend like a solid year or to three years like
just getting my head into Windows 10 I bet you I could make it a killer
workstation OS he says hey Mike I wanted to point you to a little tool that you
can use to update your Windows machine from the command line one of the
features is it will do a reboot loop between updates meaning you just run
something like this from a fresh install you come back a couple hours later with
a fully updated Windows machine we'll have a link to that in the show notes
ABC update I believe is what it's called and I bet you there is tons of like
tools like that that if I could learn how to use those on Windows I could
probably get by pretty good yeah I mean that would have saved me just so much
time yeah that first the fresh install it's such a bad experience on Windows
like it just really sucks it's weird to me that no one unlike the Windows team
is like hey this is this is terrible can we like fix this right right and the
excuse is always that this is the go-to the go-to excuse is well most Windows
consumers never experienced that Windows they experience a Windows that they have
pre-purchased on a PC yeah you know what those images are always like six to nine
to a year out of date right six nine months maybe if you're lucky that they
still have months worth of updates firmware updates and driver updates and
all the individual applications with their individual install wizards and
their individual update wizards are all gonna run it's no good but I like that
feedback I lose really good feedback that was all from the subreddit this
week I was gonna do a deep dive into the email inbox but there were so many great
comments in the subreddit I stopped there and I left the email for you guys
next week I didn't rob Peter pay Paul this week
coder radio dot reddit comm if you want to jump in on that or if you would like
to send an email it's coder dot show slash contact well it's kind of a lull
this week cuz last week was Red Hat summit and it was the Python conference
and it was build and Google IO and a few others this week it's like there's some
hoopla but it's not like gonna change your world hoopla but that gives us an
opportunity to kind of chat about a few things that are more retrospective and
introspective and there's a post that you was it you that sniffed it up you or
West sniff this up and we've been chatting about it in our slack this
looking back at an app that somebody wrote like six years later where they
took a really hard line stance about something and then you know six years
later had some reflection and realized not everything is as black and white
we'll link to the whole thing in the show notes but six years ago he writes I
wrote one of my most popular blog posts on logic in a rails app in which I
debate some of the critiques about extracting code from the controller but
to summarize his argument was that rails is just a UI layer and business logic
should be put in domain objects instead of keeping them somewhere in the model
view or the controller he says to give you some context he writes it was a time
when I was starting to grow as a rails or Ruby developer I was reading a lot of
blog posts on the topics and I started to have very strong feelings as to how
rails code should be written fast forward six years I'm back man I'm
bringing I'm bringing everything it's all the classics and he says a lot of
things have happened in my career as a software developer my experience has
gotten more rich I've launched more projects my day-to-day work has changed
I've climbed the company ladder and frankly he's gotten more emotionally
mature which thankfully has prevented him from writing a few more
controversial blog posts so what do I think about the post now he writes well
it's really about the trade-offs and the personal preferences if you found a way
to keep all the logic in the controller while your team iterates fast and does
not make silly mistakes code is easily digestible new features can be added
without pain then good for you it doesn't really matter what any other
person says he writes that and I wonder this is really what I'd like to get your
thoughts on too it's very hard to maintain a productive discussion on the
internet about the right approach for building software because that may be
very similar to just discussing religion for some people there's no much there's
so my says there's so much hidden context that you might as well just
respect the other's decision and focus on their personal insight instead oh my
gosh that's beautiful that is that is my philosophy right there in words I've
never been able to put it and I'm curious what you think about that I think
that's pretty fair I mean I his original argument from six years ago isn't kind
of that compelling to me either way because I just sort of don't think it
matters it's weird though right like I had myself have been going through this
kind of his enification process you sort of have to at some point just because
like you're gonna end up dealing with a lot of systems and a lot of
integrations now don't I'm not always perfect in this right it's a journey
right it's it's a journey where you have to accept things that are maybe like
violating what you consider to be principles of good engineering or
whatever but yeah I mean I think it's interesting that this is a rails
developer same as Andre Lisnick rails was known for being quite shall we say
strict when it was originally launched way back in the you know the bad old
days of what is it 2006 2008 oh yeah now rails is legacy and people are
basically doing whatever the hell they want right having said that I'm not sure
I'm ready to shave my head and join the the Hare Krishnas quite yet I mean the
definitely are things that are just bad right like there were such a thing as
wrong not everything is relative I pass it to Chris all right I think you well I
don't really think we do I think we don't dwell on it I think you're
probably right and it's it's it sort of tracks my evangelism for Linux when I
was younger I built a career around convincing people to switch to Linux
sure both you know as a contractor and as a podcaster and it was a everything
should be on Linux everybody everything all Linux as I got older my mind shift
has changed to Linux is a great solution for me but everybody has a reason to use
the tools that they need to use and I don't understand all of the context of
it and I think in part it has been I've been doing something that on the surface
seems simple and people think they understand what's involved with making
something and then when you actually learn what's involved you understand
there's there's so many there's like what the words he uses here perfect
there's so much hidden context there's so much hidden context that I cannot
appreciate or understand that I just need to trust in their personal insights
if I find that if I find someone to be intellectual and seems to have their
crap together then I just tend to trust their insights and don't get judgy about
the tools or the platforms they're using and I think that's a similar transition
the author went through here and essentially yeah and I yeah I think
there's also like there's the extremes here right there's full-on Buddhists and
and then there's what is in my opinion far more common like reddit rage right
yeah how much do you want to bet those people either skew young or they have
something else going on if they're if they're I bet there's not a lot of
people raging on reddit above 40 that don't have a complex set of
circumstances speaking of complex circumstances I know right and the other
and this is something we didn't get a chance to talk about a lot last week the
Python language summit like I just alluded to earlier was going on and true
to form we have pulled out what may be what some consider the most quote-unquote
controversial talk it was by amber brown from the twisted project and she shared
some of her criticisms about the Python standard library I thought maybe for
some context if you're not familiar the twister project just a really short
version it's an event based framework for internet applications so you know
HTTP events SSH events IMAP events DNS events it something happens it triggers
something yeah it's like an it's a networking library it's a very fancy
networking library yeah it's great and boy she had some things to say and I
just thought I'd read just you a couple of highlights we won't have to like read
it all but she says Python claims to ship with batteries included but
according to Brown without external packages it's really only marginally
useful for example async IO requires external libraries to connect to a
database to speak or to speak HTTP the SSL module requires monkey patches to
connect to non ASCII domain names etc actually she looks like four different
examples other standard library modules are simply inferior to alternatives on
pypi the HTTP dot client documentation advises readers to use requests and the
daytime module is confusing and compared itself to competitors such as arrow and
default till and moment but there's also just poor quality lagging features and
obsolete code she says the batteries are leaking she thinks some of the bugs in
the standard library will never be fixed the batteries are leaking yeah yeah
that's pretty good isn't it that is pretty good
savage savage yeah and even when bugs are fixed pypi libraries like twisted
cannot assume that they'll run on the latest Python so they must preserve their
bug workarounds forever Brown identified new standard library features there were
really too little or too late leaving users to depend on back ports to use
features that were in Python to she's got several examples like socket dot
send message and she says twisted is forced to ship its own C extension to
use the send message in Python 2 even though pythons 2 is nearly at the end of
life she says it's going to be until like the end of time they're going to
hey she says quote distributions like Red Hat and others will keep Python 2
alive until the goddamn end of time 100% true she says so we should set the same
state here right cuz I think folks who don't work in like a Ruby ish Python
world won't understand there are many reasons to dunk and make fun of Ruby
developers and our defense is always how's that Python 3 transition going
because it's not right right so there's a huge current schism between Python 2
and Python 3 and like yes if you are doing a new project of course you just
use Python 3 if your organization allows you to which spoiler alert many
don't and you're fine but the truth is the transition just hasn't gone well
it's caused like if you ever want to laugh it just go into a Python forum and
say need help upgrading from Python 2 point insert version here to 3 and just
like watch not that we should troll each other's communities that's wrong I mean
I want to take a moment and just say Python I have a soft spot for Python so
I got to defend my Python love a little bit here it is it is complicated but I
don't know if the solution is to cram everything into the standard library and
rip all the code out and to criticize it for for some of these things I think the
flipside could also be argued you could argue that by developers like the
twisted project continuing to use Python 2 code and encourage users to use the
older Python stuff that you're slowing down the overall Python ecosystems
yourselves and that if they were making users move forward the overall
ecosystem would be in better shape so the blame goes both ways here I got I
mean I just gotta defend Python a little bit yeah no I'm not actually against
Python right so it's funny because I have kind of the opposite thing coming
at this from someone who when given the choice between Python and Ruby went Ruby
years ago I'm kind of jealous of the standard library like one of one of the
annoying things for me is every Ruby project there's always like four or five
gems you always have to use and in addition to rails right which is in
itself like 30 gems it just seems crazy like like that model of architecture
always makes me a little nervous because you have all these like literally 20 or
30 external dependencies at least where in Python most of that basic stuff is
kind of just built in batteries included hmm yep I think the challenge is and
this is where this is where I think amber has has a great point is that the way
the transition has effectively gone down from 2x to 3x I'm not gonna use
individual versions because it's just too hard has basically created two
pythons ah yes and you have to look at it from her perspective she's not a
Python app developer you know we're like writing scripting or doing me she
may be all of those things in addition but in her talk she's primarily
representing her open source project which because of just their users
demands right twisted is not a small project has to support both let's call
it both the streams of Python which I don't know man I've been hearing about
the Python 3 transition since before we started the show at some point I mean
you had a you know last year they got rid of the benevolent dictator for life
my why can't the last act be yeah and by the way we're just not supporting
Python 2 which I know is destructive and bad and there are recordings of me
complaining about things rails has done that like destroy stuff I was using and
maybe rewrite it but it seems like there's some Delta between two
relatively incompatible versions and you know we just blow things up every time
you we have a change right like it seems like there's got to be a middle ground
maybe like three years you know I think there's a handful of projects and I
believe pythons one of the top three that really moved red hats hand on
introducing a new feature to rel called app streams or in fedora it's called
modularity and this is an idea where you can now have virtual software
repositories that are outside of the version of your main distro so you can
install rel 8 but you could install the rel 7 version of Python if you need old
Python and when rel 9 comes out you could be on rel 8 and you could install
the rel 9 version if you needed a newer version of Python or PHP or whatever it
might be and it's then it's just all through your software package manager
and it's all gets updated as long as it's a supported version that you know
rail makes available and it's projects like this that have forced the software
distributions the Linux distributions and others to come up with these kinds
of creative solutions and you know that's probably you know it's also it's
these kinds of things that have led to the rapid adoption of containers yeah I
would think so because in that case you could have a container running the 2x
stream the 3x stream and hopefully be okay okay so um there is also what is
being quoted this is according to the high found blogspot article that we'll
have linked in the show notes the most controversial comment that Brown made in
her speech you know again and we're not criticizing I think good on her for
bringing up these issues so I want to make that clear and that was adding
modules to the standard library stifles innovation by discouraging programmers
from using or contributing and completing pi pi package or pi pi
packages I don't want sounds weird when I say it out like that is the naming
that I never quite understood why they named it that but yeah yeah that's that's
some that's some bacon I I don't know if I buy that I could I could kind of see
it I guess they're worried about essentially being Sherlocked would be
the concern I guess but the standard library is never gonna move as fast as
an individual project oh obviously right and if there was ever a community where
that was true maybe Cole balls a little slower and I you send your email to Alan
at Jupiter broadcasting I mean I don't know I did at one point author and
support an HTTP library and objective C long long ago and like you know NSH TP
did exist right but yeah you could do like a get request in one line and at
the time that was you know new for iOS with my library why why wouldn't that be
true in other languages I'm just actually it is I'm using a library called
sucker punch in rails Ruby on rails that does I think it's what is the hell is it
delayed jobs but it does them as like it's just an abstraction right it does
them as simple you know it spins up the workers all that fun stuff for you it's
just a nicer interface I I do wonder if it's a more of a cultural thing in the
community that Python developers are just used to turning to the standard
library first maybe it's maybe it's because you know it's a lot of that you
always know you it's available kind of kind of situation I think can I zoom out
here for a second zoom out while you were talking and you're touching on a
couple of these things like my community my community guy hat slipped on and I
started thinking what's obvious when you read through the event and it happens a
couple of different times in a couple of different ways the core team and some of
the major developers on some of these projects are essentially just they're
talking past each other and they have different sets of core concerns in fact
in her talk Brown even kind of pointed out a little bit she said that few
Python core developers are also major library maintainers so essentially to
the core Python developers a library author complaints are devalued or
ignored because you know it doesn't affect them there's not there's nothing
that they're working on it's not they can't be their problem she said there's
that issue there and so looking at this I think to me it's clear that people are
talking past each other and then I also take Brown's point here that if nobody
has any skin in that particular game they may not take it as seriously as they
take their part of the job and so you have an empathy problem as well yeah and
also you know I keep making analogies to Ruby one thing Ruby does not currently
have that Python does is Python's being asked to do a lot of stuff right a lot
of different domains with different I'll use the word stakeholders and different
types of developers where let's be honest if you're right writing Ruby
you're writing Rails right so for instance maybe the data scientists group
who uses Python maybe the ML people all have different concerns compared to
let's say you're a flask developer or Django developer and there's this weird
Ubuntu guys running desktops app in Python to boot yeah are they still
around anymore GTK is that a thing no I thought I thought I was using Vala now I
thought that you've been drinking Cassidy's elementary OS Kool-Aid I see
sometimes I tell you what sometimes it's just so pretty okay you know before we
go I wouldn't mind since I haven't talked to I wouldn't mind getting like
an update on on your Linux setup right now you run in Linux and is it still is
it elementary is it Ubuntu is it pop where you are right now so things have
calmed down my desktop workstation is the Mac Mini with Mac obviously oh yeah
Mojave right yes you have to on those newer ones you don't have a choice you
do you don't know choice how is the sound level on that thing well I have it
plugged into the LG monitor so is it quiet though like you hear any fans no
much less than yeah no it's the quietest machines yeah that's nice the
laptop is the daughter which is running pop night I just updated it 1904 yeah
1904 which is fine right pop is very Mac OS like in that it just works and every
once in a while I forget which OS I'm on in Ruby mine and I get the wrong command
the wrong key commands when you put the Mojave in dark mode I think it looks a
lot like no Michelle yes it's also terrible though I'm liking my Mojave
light these days just because there's always that one app I use that like
doesn't respect dark mode and it's like whoa blinding geez we run an old stuff
geez I'm sorry I will not pay for Photoshop again and then and then there
must be a Windows box in this mix now yeah there's a there's a Windows there's
a Windows laptop that's just used for demos and testing and there's Windows
VMs basically everywhere are you are still WSL spelunking I am I'm liking a
penguin quite a lot once WSL 2's out I'm probably gonna take a very serious look
at it really yeah it's shipping a lot of things on Windows I mean most things
it's weird I say that most things you know by volume and just by time worked
we're are shipping on Linux because most of this technology is like web and
server technology so it's all like back end anyway but the front ends more and
more are just becoming like Windows I wonder if I bet you out there must be a
build of that new terminal floating around out there I know you can build it
from source right now but there must be a pre-built one I'm telling you it's
compelling it sounds like some of the WSL folks that are involved like the
penguin developer and some folks from canonical were treated pretty well by
Microsoft around this entire thing got some information we're at the event at
build if they could make it that seems like Microsoft did right I mean weirdly
enough going into WWDC I'm actually looking at Microsoft saying okay what
can Apple show for developers at WWDC which is allegedly a developer
conference during that little keynote it's gonna be the year of marzipan no
doubt right I hope it's not I hope in marzipan isn't the ace they think they
have up their sleeve it is the answer is don't worry about all this other crap
just develop for the Apple ecosystem it's simple it's clear this is how you
build the application for both platforms this is how you'd sell it I
mean it's it's a complete story it's an end-to-end story I mean for me it's just
not a practical story no no for many I don't think it is I think that's their
issue that's their gamble is is it practical for enough or is their
ecosystem big enough that makes it forces some people to make it happen but
yeah when you look at it it just marzipan and it just doesn't seem as
compelling if it can't run on other platforms it's funny because when I
think desktop software that I like professionally have to support it's
always Windows now if you could write a marzipan application that would run on
Windows and Linux like electron does dad let me just fantasize for a moment okay
that they create some sort of super fast electron competitor you know just a
screw with Microsoft it's not gonna happen but then it would at least be
somewhat compelling right but if it's just you could your iPad app can run on
the latest version of Mac OS that's a tiny tiny market there's hardly any iPad
users and there's hardly any users of the current Mac OS like okay yeah all
right I'll target about what is that about 300,000 people and how many of
them are actually willing to pay me which is the other thing we didn't even
cover this week the Apple Supreme Court app store pricing thing yeah I just
don't even know what to make of that you know I think it's not gonna matter
really yeah I mean what they're gonna lower 30% to 20% I mean what do you what
do you think is gonna happen I don't know so for those of you that don't know
this essentially opens up the possibility for people to sue Apple for
monopoly practices with the App Store both both users and developers just
yeah yeah and you could really see how a group of developers or users could come
together and put a hell of a suit together there's gonna be some lawyer
that love to go after some of that Apple money yeah but I mean I've heard
everything from Apple doesn't have an issue here to Apple will have to enable
sideloading of applications like they'll have to do gatekeeper for iOS I would be
amazed if that happens but I know but the idea would be by default it only
runs applications from the App Store but you can download applications but you
have to run them in a certain way where the users authorizing them or something
like you know I you know how like gatekeeper works on the Mac yeah yes I
do I disable it yeah yeah I don't know it's hard to say with these kinds of
things it really is we're going into an interesting place I mean I think you
know just do a quick prediction I think this year's WWDC is either going to be
one of the most interesting because they do something really really cool with a
Mac Pro which really cool for Apple would be just do the obvious simple
black box or like I have this concern I know people are gonna be mad the Apple
Action Show but I have this concern that they think a Mars up hand is a really
good idea and that it's like super cool and people are gonna be thrilled and
like all the longtime developers were leaving for like Linux and Windows and
moving on to web technologies all of me and a bunch of other people throwing the
whole like Mac Exodus time are gonna just like come back and do Mars a pen
which scares the crap out of me because it says there it suggests they're like
missing the boat completely right it's definitely not a play to reclaim
developers right like I I don't know I would be interested to hear from the
audience yeah are you out there are you psyched about Mars a pen and if so why
what like what do you is it that you already have a successful iPad app and
you just like to kind of spiff off some sales for Mac which makes sense I mean
okay I'll give you an example of this you know because you're saying like you
know you run on the Mac mini what if as a result of bars a pan slack rebases
their Mac app off of their iPad version and it uses half the amount of RAM it
launches twice as fast it's only two gigs okay yeah I mean what if like what
if what if that so there's an example of where developers from those companies
who are already producing applications for both platforms can now save time and
money and build for one and gets them off of electron possibly I doubt I
actually seriously doubt slack would do it they have so much invested in their
electron app now but it's a great example of one that would be a great
opportunity I mean I kind of I almost feel like slack is the perfect case to
do it right because they're their Mac app is notorious widely used and like
notoriously crappy compared to native Mac apps but that that's just it's such
a limited use case right so you already have to be big enough on Apple's
platforms including Mac OS which is like just a very small platform for that to
be worth it right what if you have a new project you're starting Chris are you
really starting in marzipan no no given like Xamarin exists electron exists
flutter exists it's more about you're starting you're gonna make an iOS app
and now you can also make some Mac sales I think that's what it might be oh yeah
it's gonna be shovel we're central to right like yeah yeah yeah yeah basically
I'm thinking about it from like games to where the UI doesn't have to be very
Mac like like those Altos Odyssey type games yeah I could see that if that
would seems like that would just be a no-brainer for those shops it's gonna be
a lot of crap man it's gonna be a lot of crap it's gonna be rough it's the Mac is
going to such an interesting place right now with with marzipan and arm on the
horizon and Apple's focus on iOS and the Mac Pro lingering like there it's it's
it's interesting times for them right now and I feel like it's funny because
just as a quick aside like my Linux world is more rock-solid than it's ever
been like I'm the ThinkPad is still really really really working for me and
I've been stupid happy with XFC it's just a very simple desktop environment I
just really need my apps I don't need anything more it's stupid quick the
thing wakes up faster than a MacBook this ThinkPad with all open source
graphics drivers and XFCE like it's legitimately before the screens even
like halfway up it's awake and ready to go it's really great and so I'm looking
back you know from a very detached perspective now because none of my gear
is dependent anymore on what they do where when we were doing the show just a
couple of years ago there were some pieces in the production pipeline that
were Mac machines and very critical I just I don't know it gives me a very
different perspective now and I can't help but just chuckle a little bit
because it's just fascinating to see where they're gonna go you know for
people that depend on it for their day-to-day work tool who I say you know
you look at Windows 10 the thing that they really have going for is not only
is the surface line pretty decent Mike but then you do have a bunch of other
vendor options if Microsoft ever screws that up and that's the Windows and
Linux advantage I know I harp on that but I just think you look at it where
there's just so much uncertainty right now on that platform and where I'm at I
feel like I have more certainty than ever I've got more hardware choices than
ever my desktops working better than it ever has I don't know it's just a really
weird position to be in it's weird I mean and for those of us who are like
somewhat tethered to the Mac ecosystem because we my case you know have to
compile iOS apps and deploy them it's it's interesting like just ten years ago
Apple I felt really had a good like firm grasp of the developer market right and
now it's just like maybe it's the relative society see we I mean we can't
really post more to it but it just seems like okay like I okay he cards on the
table I'm terrified that they're gonna like release this Mac Pro and then in a
year or two you know there will be lots of excited people who've been waiting
for a Mac Pro who will spend lots of money right like this is a type of
machine people are going to finance seriously no yeah and then they're gonna
like switch to arm in a year or two right with their own chips I know that's
what I was saying right which which is kind of like holy shit like you can't do
like it's a huge risk it's a huge risk and it's it's so weird to me because if
they had just like not been stubborn and made a simple black cube called it a Mac
Pro and everybody would have been happy years ago I certainly wouldn't have gone
down this primrose path here right like you it would have been fine right or put
this another way wouldn't marzipan be a great opportunity for Apple to come out
clear they're on the stage of WWDC they name this thing whatever it's gonna be
finally called and they say and by the way this is the technology we're using
to move the Mac to the ARM platform so that way you just knew straight up right
then because there's a very good chance at the second half of the marzipan story
is prepping the Mac for ARM and I think this is a great opportunity for them
just to be straight up all right you want to depend on the Mac platform you
want to plan for the next few years this is our intention and this is their
opportunity this year at WWDC to be clear about it otherwise you're buying a
$10,000 machine or what our $5,000 machine if you get a deal on an iMac Pro
with a ARM transition looming on the horizon that you have no insights on yeah
absolutely I mean and they have done stuff like that before without the
telling you part remember the several years ago when they changed X code to
compile not to native code but to bytecode which is there and why well
because they had the Apple watch in labs but they didn't want to announce it and
they needed to compile down to that architecture or whatever it was right I
don't know and that was a good move you know it's made it it's made like the
Apple watch transition to 64-bit lickety-split yeah I mean I mean the
question is if you're a developer what tools are you using that exists on Mac
OS that don't exist on Windows 10 or Linux and unless the answer is I
develop iOS apps it's kind of like just do whatever you want and probably don't
choose Mac at this point yeah and you're gonna get a taste of it because I
believe then so Mojave is the last version of Mac OS that supports 32-bit
applications well that's the other thing bunch of people have a bunch of like
internal legacy Mac apps that are just gonna break yeah so that'll be a good
test of the markets resiliency how how many people hold off on upgrading how
many people upgrade and have things break or how many people upgrade and
it's flawless like I have a suspicion I wouldn't have very much trouble I think
a couple Adobe things I have are 32-bit and I don't really care about those too
much so yeah that's what that'll be an interesting testing of the waters
because that'll be out in the fall I would imagine yeah it should come out in
the fall yeah yeah which is probably when the Mac Pro will ship too it'll
ship in the fall with the new OS so does a Mac Pro ship do you think I think it
does not a WWDC of course I know maybe they announce it then pre-orders open up
like in October or whatever you know and then when the OS ships the Mac Pro ships
and it ships in the week or two around the new OS with the OS pre-installed
that seems like their style doesn't it because they'll satisfy everybody if
they just announce it they don't actually have to ship it it'd be I mean
they should because they're so far being remember that I think the trashcan was
released and I might be wrong but I think was released in 2013 yes it's just
just ask John circuit so he'll give you a hour by hour so they may not even
release this thing they probably will not release this thing at WWDC and right
now as we record this episode the current Mac Pro ladies and gentlemen
yeah December 19th 2013 Wow December of so it was it was basically probably
started shipping early 2014 yeah so 2020 if you pre-order one on day one happy
new year second week of January and you know it's great to you know it's so
great about Apple it's so it's so great because a product is a product and it
costs a certain amount of money right and it doesn't matter you if you go to
Best Buy right now or you go to the Apple Store or wherever you go there's
still the same prices that they launched them with in 2013 of course they are a
3 gigahertz late 2013 model with 16 gigabytes of RAM and a 256 gigabyte
hard drive and a single 8 core processor you know instead of a dual processor
$4,000 for a machine from 2013 like I love that I love that about Apple it's
like you know that the price is the price and it never changes you know what
I wish I could negotiate like Tim Cook man that's like no just cost what it
costs 1978 days since the last update well mr. Dominic it people don't have to
wait that long for a coder radio in fact no it's every single week often on
Mondays you can get it over at Jupiter broadcasting comm all the links
subscribes all that stuff we have a dedicated site coder dot show go check
that out coder dot show and of course the live stream calendar is Jupiter
broadcasting comm slash calendar mr. Dominic where can people find you on
the Twitters throughout the week at Dumanuco on Twitter I'm at Chris
LAS the network is at Jupiter signal the show is at Coder Radio show how about
all that huh hmm how about all of them Mike you'll have to join us on the
Friday stream soon new show where the crew gets to just hang out and meet meet
the audience do I have to wear pants no get that camera ready drinks are allowed
no pants required yeah yeah it is all on camera yeah for sure love it hi
everybody thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder
Radio program and Wes and Mike we'll see you right back here next week