This is KOTOR Radio, episode 470, recorded June 9th, 2022.
Hello friends and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
My name is Chris and joining us in his podcasting position, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
You're here.
Yes, you are.
You are.
And honestly, that's 80% of the battle, my friend, maybe even 85.
You know what I mean?
That's what I'm sticking with right now.
I sometimes overdo it and I'm in denial about overdoing it until my health starts to fail
and then I zoom out and go, oh, I did it again.
You know, I did it again.
Boy, I am so damn busy and I've been thinking about it.
Why is it?
As a podcaster, you know, why is the guy who's doing podcasts, why am I so effing busy and
I just keep getting busier and I have ways of gauging this, like, you know, when like
you got emails in your inbox that are like about sales and closing a sale, but you just
like haven't gotten to it for a week because you just haven't gotten a chance to get to
your email.
It's kind of weeks, weeks, I'm having weeks of that right now.
And it's like, I thought when I restarted the indie thing, I'd take all these things
I learned and I'd avoid this problem all together again, you know, I'll do better this time.
No, it's way worse.
It's way worse.
This time will be different.
No, it's worse.
And you know what I realized?
A, I went from having a big team to a real small team, but B, I repeated a critical mistake
that I made last time, an absolute critical mistake.
And this is a bit of wisdom I want to pass on to people out there thinking about starting
a side hustle or doing their own gig, only do one job.
I didn't realize it, but I gave myself two jobs.
We got a whole slate of shows over at jupiterbroadcasting.com and that running those shows and creating content
and going through and all the follow-up that it requires, all of the work that, you know,
when you have four or five shows, that's more than a full-time job, my friends.
But then the other thing I did because I was the best candidate for it is I'm also the
ad sales guy, right?
I'm the one that communicates with the sponsors.
I go out there and essentially with ad sales, you're always selling because you're always,
these deals take sometimes six months to line up.
You're always following up your every, you know, every opportunity you get, you're jumping
onto a video call or doing a meeting.
You're always replying to questions or modifications.
It's a full-time job itself.
And both of them never end, right?
There's always a show within a couple of hours that within a few hours that needs to start,
I need to start working on.
I always have to be working on the sponsor stuff, always.
Because if you stop, then like three, four, five months down the road, all revenue stops
coming in.
It's like, it's bad, right?
And so, I think it's a super common mistake in new media that a lot of people that start
their own new media company think it's a really common mistake.
And then I think what happens is most of them burn out.
Like they don't make it 15 years, right?
They make it five, 10 years at most, and then they burn out.
But I just keep going because I'm in denial about it until I like look around and see
like all the rubble around me of things that I have failed to do or forgotten about or
didn't get to.
And I'm like, oh, I've done it again.
And then I start realizing, oh, my health's kind of, I'm kind of falling apart.
What's going on?
Oh, I'm such an idiot.
And I can't believe I find myself here like almost once a quarter at this rate.
It's so frustrating because I'm just so helpless apparently.
Do you just, you know what I'm looking?
I'm looking just to just tell me you struggle like this, too.
I just need to know.
I need to know.
It's not just me.
Between, you know, IT infrastructure, dev, sales, I mean, I don't I don't know how you
avoid not having two or three hats, though.
Right.
Because there's the whole infrastructure side of things, too.
Thank God I get help from Wes on that.
And Alex, you know, Alex has been really helpful there, too.
Those guys are great.
But yeah, there's a lot there.
So just my bit of wisdom that I am my lesson I have learned from this is when you're creating
a job for yourself, try to give yourself just one job and then try to delegate all that
stuff you can.
It's really hard depending on the niche you're in.
Sometimes there isn't the revenue to delegate.
That's always the number one feedback that always comes in.
Oh, Chris, you just need to learn to delegate.
All right.
Well, send that with a with a hundred thousand dollar boost and I'll hire somebody not delegate
in the meantime.
I'm going to have to figure it out on my own.
Well, we got we got a bunch of feedback, people who are working in remote virtual desktops,
something you and I brought up recently on the show.
And I wanted to get to some of this.
Alex Gates wrote in.
He said, my last gig, we configured a medium sized Azure virtual desktop environment and
it was really good.
Anyone that got it pretty much ditched their laptops.
This is primarily because limitations for budgets on new hardware, of course.
Big, crappy company laptops over a powerful remote system.
That makes sense.
The virtual desktops are all RDP based, like I imagine most dev boxes would be.
They did end up having a lot of engineers using the environment with 3D accelerated
CAD setups even.
In a gig like that, I take a virtual remote desktop over a local one any day of the week,
assuming it was on an RDP based system.
And that actually seems to be surprisingly the maker or breaker is what is the what is
the remote connection protocol being used?
Citrix and RDP seem to be the favorite of the audience, and then it kind of goes downhill
from there.
And that just can make all the difference with the latency of the connection.
Kind of on the same line.
Patias shared the joys and the sorrows of running their dev environment on the Google
cloud infrastructure.
They write, I'm a dev ops person for a web hosting company here, and I got some sorrows
and some joys of remote VMs, the joys.
I have easy access to support developers and see what they are seeing in real time and
deploy the same automation on the same OS as our staging and prod environments.
All right.
I've done remote support.
I acknowledge remote supports way better there.
And the staging stuff.
This again, I think, is an area that comes up where people want something they can easily
stage, easily deploy to all the developers.
The biggest issue is resource consumption.
VSCode has a bunch of useful extensions like Live Share and IntelliSense and our devs love
it.
But sometimes it can use one gig of RAM for each remote session.
So resource consumption issues can also run us out of memory.
That can be a problem, though.
This seems like a common issue with any sort of virtual desktop environment, at least ones
that I've run into.
We're planning on moving back to local dev environment based on Docker, but that will
also mean another platform that needs to be maintained since we need to replicate any
changes from our current VM and Ansible based setup in Docker.
There you go.
I mean, that was really, I think, the highlights of it.
We got a note too from Summer Evans.
They love the remote setup.
They say, when the pandemic started, I was working as a.NET developer at a Windows desktop.
We weren't allowed to bring home our desktop computers.
So I ended up remoting into my desktop.
It was horrible at first because of bad internet.
But now that that's been fixed, I work at a company where I work on open source now.
And I have a VPS set up on my own with TMUX and a remote in there for most of my daily
work.
I like it a lot.
I can switch between computers quickly and resume my work at TMUX is way more lightweight
than anything graphical.
I see.
I wonder how that holds up if the internet connection is crappy.
That's definitely where it goes sideways, huh?
Yeah.
So that's getting better, especially, you know, a lot of home connections are wired.
I don't know.
Right.
I mean, have you ever heard of Comcast?
Oh, yeah.
No, I mean, we know.
We know just doing this show for years.
There's some days where things are just bad and there's nothing you can do about it.
Squirrely Dave wrote in to say that he works in Citrix when remote.
And then when he goes into the office, they issue him a Chromebook, which he says, I mean,
that's fine because, quote, I don't actually get any work done in the office.
I mean, but I like it.
It was a jab at you.
It totally was.
It was right on the chin.
Right.
Yeah.
We got more feedback and we'd love to collect some more.
We're recording another episode on Monday in our regular time.
We're doing a special recording right now, a special.
That's right.
Coder on a Thursday because we're getting ready for some travel.
So some extra feedback would be great.
Go over to Coder dot show slash contact or grab a new podcasting app and send us in a
boost.
A quick mention about the London meetup coming up in August.
There's been a day change.
So be sure you're going to meet up dot com slash Jupiter Broadcasting and you've joined
the meetups.
That way, you know all the deets because there are some flight changes.
So there's a slight day change.
Everything's over at meetup dot com slash Jupiter Broadcasting because, yes, Alex from
self-hosted will be in London in August and there is a meetup getting organized.
Mike and I won't be there.
Well, at least not this time.
But when we land that big Ford EV sponsorship and we got, you know, big Ford money, maybe
we'll go do a show in London.
I got that big Ford energy.
I like it.
Tail scale dot com slash code or go there to get a free account up to 20 devices.
I love tail scale.
It is a zero config VPN installs on any device in minutes and not a week goes by where I
don't see multiple community members lives change because of tail scale.
Not exaggerating happened this morning before I sat down to record.
Maybe that's why I'm super hyped right now.
A great conversation our telegram group about a user who was transitioning from a really
kind of brittle open VPN setup to tail scale and then using ACLs and exit nodes to really
complete the picture for them.
It's so great.
You see, devices connect directly to each other using WireGuard's noise protocol encryption.
You build a mesh VPN network powered by WireGuard.
You can quickly create secure ACLs to to share one machine with somebody.
It'll bust through carrier grade net.
I can attest to that.
I have been in like I'm not even kidding, like triple net deep and tail scale still
works.
That's how I keep all my family's computers connected so I can do remote support when
my kids aren't at home with me.
It's super handy for getting into my work systems, prepping for a show when I'm on the
road and you'll get it running on just about any.
I've got it on Raspberry Pi.
I got it on my iPhone.
I got it on an iPad.
I got it on my Linux boxes.
It's part of my basic NixOS configuration.
Now when I deploy a NixOS box, it deploys with tail scale.
Seriously.
So go try it for yourself for free up to 20 machines at tailscale.com slash coder.
This is the modern way to do VPNs.
Every other VPN I've ever used feels so old after I've switched to tail scale.
Go try it for yourself, tailscale.com slash coder.
Well I got my HP dev one since we gathered together last time and I know you've been
going all in using it as your daily driver since we last chatted.
I think this is worth talking about more.
In fact, I think this is going to be a big topic of conversation in the Linux community
over the next few weeks.
Yeah, I think so too.
You go first.
I've been waiting for your feedback and you have been quite the tease.
I have been saving it for the show.
You coquettish bastard.
Sorry.
I just wanted to kind of get your live reactions out there.
Capture it raw.
I feel like this is potentially a laptop that is going to fill a very critical space in
the Linux ecosystem.
So traditionally, I can tell you that we have been lacking just something very simple.
When somebody comes and says, hey, I'd like a great laptop to run Linux, what do you recommend?
You have to need a chart of are they a ThinkPad person potentially?
Are they going to be an XPS person?
Should we be sending them to system 76?
There's all of these potential avenues you could go down and you have to ask them all
of these questions.
And there's not just a go to this website and order this configuration.
And that is exactly how it is on the MacBook world.
Pretty much anybody could go buy a MacBook Air M2 now, whatever model they want, even
the base model, and it's going to be good enough for 90 percent of people out there.
We haven't had that in Linux.
We've had all of these variables.
And so I have felt for a long time that Dell was so close to cinching that if Dell just
made it a little bit more discoverable, a little simpler, a little less of a Dell experience
to get the XPS, and if they just kind of leaned into it a bit more instead of kind of fade
like they seem to be, the XPS could have really kind of grabbed that Linux king crown of laptops.
In fact, today as we record a brand new XPS 13 has just been announced, not the Linux
edition, but a new XPS 13 that Linux edition will probably be based on at some point in
the future.
That's been announced and it's more in a direction I'm not a huge fan of.
I mean, it has a new Intel processor in there, it has a smaller motherboard, it has better
battery life.
Those things are good, but it has one USB-C port on each side, two USB-C ports total.
It has a butterfly style chiclet keyboard, right?
It's going the wrong direction in other areas and it's also based around an Intel platform,
which for some of us there's just less enthusiasm about these days.
So it just kind of wasn't quite getting that king status.
And you'd really like it to be a piece of hardware that comes from a tier one OEM vendor
that can ship, that has scale, that has deep supply chain connections, that kind of stuff,
especially these days.
And the HP Dev 1, I think is the best candidate for the king of Linux laptops crown that we
have seen in a long time.
And it just took them getting the formula right.
You can tell where they decided to take risks and you can tell where they decided not to
take risks.
And the risk that they decided to take here was to make a Linux focused laptop.
And then they didn't take a lot of risks with the hardware design.
It's not really anything exceptional, but it's also not below anything you'd expect.
It kind of just got it right there in the middle with the hardware design.
Do you agree with that?
Yeah, I think it's good.
It's definitely, if you're looking for like a wafer thin MacBook Air, this is probably
not for you, but if you're looking for a more practical is the word that comes to mind.
With a slightly better design look than say like a ThinkPad, right?
It's got that magnesium alloy chassis, which at first I thought might be plastic.
I couldn't tell because it was so light.
I actually thought it was plastic.
So then it really kind of came down to how does it work for me?
And I'm still planning to throw like a bunch of synthetic benchmarks at it and a lot of
scenarios which I haven't done yet.
And I haven't still gotten a good grasp of its battery life capacity.
But I do feel like I have a very good grasp on how it works for my kind of maximum workload
scenario.
It's like when I sit down and I set up a laptop for the first time after I've reloaded it,
I will have Steam downloading and installing a game in the background while I have apt
or whatever DNF whatever installing packages while I also have flat pack installing like
30 packages and I will have all of this going while I'm also browsing the web, probably
watching some YouTube.
I have a matrix chat open.
Absolutely.
I have telegram open.
Probably have slack open as well.
I probably three or four desktops virtual desktops deep while I'm doing this or I'm
doing all that.
If I'm not downloading a Steam game, I'm precaching the shaders for like, you know, the performance.
That's generally how I work.
It's a very ADD style where I have a lot of things going on at once.
And so if I can install a flat pack and a dead package at the same time, I will.
And why not during all of that, which I was doing for a solid three, four hours, the fans
never kicked up that typically almost that just never happens on a Linux laptop.
Even during the precaching of the shaders for my games, the fans did not kick up.
The performance never lagged.
It never it never missed a beat.
I was very impressed.
The only time I heard the fans actually go on was when the game finally started.
Even then, the speakers are so damn good that it was absolutely no issue.
And even with the fans going, it's still quieter than every other laptop I have once the fans
kick up that maybe maybe aside from the MacBook when when I had that experience.
I started getting a little more serious about the laptop because I was like, OK, I just
threw a lot at this and then it loaded my frickin video game.
And then I played my video game on this thing.
That's a big deal, because if I've got a thousand bucks to spend, if I've got twelve hundred
bucks to spend, I game very rarely.
But when I do game, I want to be able to do that.
And that's getting better and better on Linux than ever.
In fact, it's an area where the Linux desktop is significantly more competitive than the
Mac desktop.
And so that's an area where if I'm going to have a Linux box, I want to be able to play
video games.
But on my ThinkPad, where it's all an Intel configuration, the Intel graphics are just
not powerful enough.
And on other systems where I have a Intel and Nvidia, it's a real pain in the neck to
manage that.
And it makes it harder to flip between distributions like a maniac.
This it strikes that balance because that built in integrated AMD GPU is good enough
that I was playing Halo last night on it and it was totally playable.
How new for you, though?
Let's get to the heart of them.
Oh, I haven't played Halo since like the early Xbox days, man.
So it was rough.
Yeah, I tried.
I tried some infinity myself.
It wasn't a good idea.
The other game that I threw at it, which is always very complex, and it sort of it murders
every other system I have, unfortunately, for whatever reason, is Star Trek Online.
It's not even that new of a game, but maybe it's just not super optimized.
Star Trek Online, say you.
Mm hmm.
So like a 10 year old MMO.
Okay, I was thinking, what was I thinking, Stowe?
Yeah, it's Stowe.
Yeah.
Yep.
You know, they've they've kept it going.
It's there still.
It's still going, man.
And so I loaded it on there, which I have.
I have legitimately like 10 years of experience of getting this game working on Linux.
So it's like a great test for me in that regard.
It's so frickin flawless now.
And I'm not a big, big gamer, obviously, but I absolutely felt like this laptop would accomplish
all of my gaming needs, which is a nice box to check for this thing.
And on top of that, I feel like this is not like a blow away trackpad, but it's an above
average trackpad.
It's better than probably every other trackpad out there on on a Linux machine.
This probably has the best speakers of any Linux laptop shipping today.
What was your impression of the speakers?
So I was surprised that I could easily do slack and zoom calls such as the one we were
on, which some pro plugged the show because, you know, you got to have that going without
like a headset or mic or anything, and it was pretty good.
You know, I start off iffy and then I fell in love with the machine until I might as
getting sent back for a replacement.
Oh, oh, yes.
So tell us what happened there.
The USBC charging has just stopped working.
So after a good hustle by the system, 76 people to try to figure out, you know, what was the
software, it was concluded that it's actually a hardware issue.
Could have shorted out whatever.
So I will unfortunately be HP dev one list.
I do have the review unit, but it's such a pain in the butt to kind of move into a whole
system just to have to wipe it, knowing that if I wait till like Monday or Tuesday, I'll
have another one, according to HP.
So super good support, though.
And other than that one issue, I would this was is going to be my daily driver once I
have the repaired unit.
And the reason I care so much about the USBC, are we allowed to talk about that little meeting
we were in or no?
Yeah, I think we should mention it.
You and I were on a call with HP and system 76 where they're kind of giving us the background
deets on how this all came together and whatnot.
Yeah, one of the things I had mentioned was like, okay, so if it has USBC, and it has
power over USBC, because at the time of the call, it was still working, it like died like
two hours later, theoretically, this could be kind of the ideal, you know, I'm just sometimes
your home, sometimes you're on the go, just plug in one cable, and you'll have your whole
workstation ready to go.
Yeah, that port that USBC port does do power delivery and display.
So when that you know, when it works, you know, let's talk about this for a second.
So you know, when you're looking at this, what what makes this like a work machine?
Like is this a is this a viable ThinkPad competitor?
Is this a real work machine?
And there, there's a couple things that we learned in that call.
And that is is that system 76 and HP kind of have a ongoing contract of some kind, you
know, some relationship
Yeah, and Carl, the CEO of system 76 in that call said that system 76 is doing quote, indefinite
q&a on every pop OS, kernel release, every firmware release for the dev one, system 76
and HP are both doing q&a.
And then then they ship it upstream with just with with pop OS, just all other pop OS stuff.
So there's not like a special repo or anything for the dev one users.
But in that conversation, Carl said that the first couple of prototypes they got just arrived
as parts in a box, not even assembled, and that they actually assembled the first one
that they got to play with themselves, they put it together, and they brought that up
to mention it's you know, there's real serviceability here.
In fact, the the the HP laptop, the original HP laptop that this dev one is forked from
has a 10 out of 10 on the iFixit repairability score.
So these are things that I think about.
If I'm thinking about a work machine, right, if I'm thinking about like, I'm thinking about
Brent, right, I'm thinking about Wes, I'm thinking about our our hosts like Mike and
like Alex.
And I'm thinking about what if JB got to a point where when we start working with somebody
just to make sure we had a really good setup, we just sent them a machine pre configured
ready to go to connect in this is your podcast laptop.
This would check those boxes for me, it would have the performance, it would have the noise
profile that I'm looking for in a machine I record with.
And it has the support HP has dedicated support staff just for the dev one line.
That's a big deal.
Like that's a real commitment from a company side.
And I'm curious what you picked up on this, but they won't come right out and say it obviously.
But I think they intend this to be like something iterating on like they do another dev one
in a year or so like this could be a multi product line kind of thing if this first one
is successful.
Yeah, I mean, I think you kind of tried to hold their feet to the fire a little bit.
I think in our call right where it's pretty clear that this is not a one time deal.
I'm curious if they stick with the AMD infrastructure there.
It seems at least to my you know, off the cuff testing, it seems super fast.
And that's just what the base 16 gigs of RAM I mean, I was playing XCOM and getting my
ass handed to me just with fantastic fidelity, though.
Again, this isn't a paid.
This is not again.
Yeah.
Nobody's paying us for this.
Nobody's paying us.
Mike bought his own.
I literally Yeah, that's why.
That's why I can get a return.
And I'm you know, I will I will do the same if at the end of my review, which I think,
you know, I'm trending that way right now.
I haven't thrown like a lot of my media and coding jobs that I haven't done a lot of that
stuff yet.
But one of the things that's giving me a pretty good sense that it's going to work out and
another reason why I think this is a good work laptop is it's an open source driver
stack in there.
And ultimately, when it comes to Linux laptops, that's usually when things start getting a
little buggy on you is somewhere in the driver stack, something isn't working.
As Mike knows, as Mike has run into over the years, Mike is god damn you Qualcomm.
This is one of the reviews, one of the strangest ones I've ever done in that usually I fall
in love when I open the box, because I'm easily bribed by stand ups of robot guys.
But then I start to like see all the flaws, right, the fan kicks up, I get moody about
it, I get a decimal reader, things like that.
This one I was kind of like, okay, well, actually, is that not a plastic?
The battery life is actually pretty good.
Look at it adjusting the screen based on the content on the screen to try to minimize battery
usage, but keep the same relative level of brightness, which I don't know if you've noticed
but it does that if you leave that on.
Yeah.
And it's a hell of a screen too.
I mean, Visual Studio Code still thinks I'm 16 and have like, you know, vampire vision.
So I got to go got to do the command, whatever it is the command shift plus there that's
zoom in a little bit.
That's that's that's just VS code.
I have literally been working in it nonstop.
In fact, I'm probably up until today when I you know, I wanted to like see was a software.
So I did the restore thing, you know, the boot into recovery restore.
It's not software, but it's now wiped and ready to be returned.
Thousand Nits.
I ended up turning it down because it's stupidly bright.
But when I'm sitting in Florida on my porch working and it's Florida, it's super nice
to have it not be completely washed out.
I do tons of video calls.
I look like a potato, but that's not its fault.
If these AMD Ryzen chips keep going the way I think they're going, and if system 76 and
HP stick with that platform, this could be a super viable.
And I think it even is today.
Superviable MacBook alternative.
Plus you get all the games.
And I mean, I'm not.
All right.
So like XCOM 76.
I downloaded Age of Empires four, but didn't get to play it yet.
And Sonic Mania.
So I'm not like, you know.
Super gamer due to, you know.
So I'm sure like for the serious newer stuff, you need the GPU.
But if you like indie games or just kind of puzzle or strategy games, this is just fine.
Also, did you try their insane mouse?
Not yet.
No.
It downloaded the app, the mouse configurator.
If you were like a real gamer, I have a feeling you could do all kinds of crazy.
I don't know if this is still a thing, but like Starcraft macros.
Yeah, it did seem like that mouse has support for essentially little mini macros.
Well, it has programmable, I forgot what they call them profiles or context, something like
that, in that app that was written by system 76 for that mouse on that machine.
Yeah.
It's an interesting bit.
So HP has decided to complete the picture of this.
You can add a system 76 launch keyboard and their mouse, which they are they're actually
pretty proud of this mouse.
They actually dedicate a little bit of their presentation to the mouse.
And you know what?
After they talked about it, I was like, oh, oh, that's why that's why they like it so
much.
They call it the HP 935 creator wireless mouse.
It's an 80 dollar addition, but they boast 12 weeks of battery life.
It does a USB-A dongle or it'll do Bluetooth.
Like Mike said, it has four different profile supports.
And then system 76 made that custom GUI for it.
They're trying to complete a whole picture here, but you notice there's kind of a hole
in this picture they're trying to complete.
Yeah, I did.
I think I believe I brought it up that they really should have some calibrated HP monitor
that's calibrated like that panel in the laptop that is USB-C and it's just optimized to be
the plug in workstation.
Yeah, something that it's like consistent across the two screens.
That'd be perfect.
And apparently nobody else thought of that on the call.
Maybe that's for Gen 2, right?
Because if this thing sticks around, you get the sense that things like Core Boot are going
to be part of it.
Core Boot was on the list.
We asked them about that and they just ran out of time for version one is what they said.
The highlight of the call, I think, would be my fondness of liquor coming up as a quality
assurance metric they have.
Amazing.
Actually happened.
Nicely done, Carl.
Nicely done.
Michael Dominic, I understand you were going to do some spill testing.
But yeah, so that actually happened.
They mentioned it and it does supposedly have a spill proof keyboard.
I tried to get them to really get specific and they were like, well.
Well, you know, yeah, I'm like, well, and then of course I had to tell them it was broken
and the first thing I have to say, I did not spill anything.
Of course you did.
I had to open with that.
I said it's just got to start.
Of course you did.
Yeah, because they know you, man.
They know you.
They know me.
I'm still kind of getting acquainted with it, but I, like you, had a very similar experience
where I took it out of the box, I got it plugged in, but I am so damn busy that I didn't even
power it on for probably, you know, the next day.
I just didn't get, I didn't even get to it because, you know, I don't know, I got a lot.
And so I fired up, I have set up so many laptops over the years that I can start to get a sense
of a machine pretty quickly and get an idea if it's going to be making a lot of noise
and if it feels hot and okay, you know, those, it's passing all of those things.
It's doing a really good job.
It wasn't until I wrapped up the workday and I just kind of, I put everything away and
I just stayed here at the studio a little bit so I could take advantage of the bandwidth
and I just started throwing everything at it because I was kind of in a rush.
And so, you know, I was using it in anger as they say, although, you know, not angry,
but just slamming everything at it.
And that's when it started to impress me.
You know, when a machine can take everything and still has, you can tell it still has more
to give, I like that a lot.
And you can upgrade this thing to 64 gigs of RAM.
So if you need more headroom than 16 gigs, you can do it.
I just don't think you can do it at time of configuration.
But I get the sense too that you could probably replace other components in there as well.
I'm tempted to open up my review unit and see just how serviceable it really is because
they did stress that.
I don't know.
I'm tempted to say this thing is a contender for the crown of king of Linux laptops.
They are in it to win it.
They really are.
And we did ask them, how did this relationship come to be?
That was a question that was asked, which they weren't going to touch on.
And it sounds very much like HP got serious about wanting to get into this segment and
realize they needed a topic expert.
And my observation on that call that we had is that HP intimately understands the hardware,
the supply chain and the relationships, like relationships with AMD.
But System76 truly intuitively understands the Linux community and shipping a product
for that crowd.
And so I think those two things are actually working pretty well together.
It sounds like HP realized they needed that topic expert.
HP reached out to Carl, took a little bit of time.
They started talking.
They kind of realized, OK, actually, there is some things that kind of work here.
And specifically, Carl said, at the end of the day, this is an opportunity to reach more
Linux users on a tier one hardware OEM.
And they didn't build Pop OS to only run on System76 hardware.
They built it for anyone to use.
So it gets Pop OS out there, too, which is a great thing for them.
But I feel like they actually committed.
When you hear that they just kind of banged out a GUI tool to configure HP's mouse and
that they're doing a definite Q&A and they have dev ones in-house that they're testing
firmware releases on and kernel releases on, it seems like often when System76 does something,
they really go all in on it.
So I'm interested to see where this product line goes and when I can get my monitor.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
And it's a great way to support the show.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting.
Everybody in this audience eventually has a need for that.
And unlike those crazy, hyper-complicated duopoly platforms that want to lock you into their
esoteric interface with their esoteric names for everything, Linode is classic hosting
where you have full control.
I mean, don't get me wrong.
They got a great dashboard.
They make it super easy to do one click deployments and manage your DNS and set up VLANs and work
with whatever infrastructure management tools you might have, like Terraform, Ansible, Kubernetes,
etc.
But also, if you just want to stand up some infrastructure, if you just want to take advantage
of some really fast, really reliable, really well-supported hosting, you want to run something
on Linux, you want to build a project, Linode is great for that, for an individual or for
a business.
Like I run my family gaming servers on Linode.
I've mentioned this before, Starbound, fun little game, right?
Minecraft, kids love it.
Why not create a safe space for them on the internet on my own Linode or like my own Sync
thing server, stuff like that.
But we use it on our backend.
In fact, we're using it more than ever and pretty soon it'll be powering so much more.
And to that end, Linode has just upgraded their managed database services.
So earlier it was just MySQL.
And they launched that in May.
And that's been super helpful because Linode knows how to do this stuff.
They know how to do hosting.
They can take care of that.
Well this week they've added Postgres and MongoDB.
Well we use Postgres for several things.
And Wes and I are already talking about migrating to this.
Why wouldn't you, right?
Outsource the responsibility of that maintenance and monitoring.
All the burdens that make running a database a pain in the butt.
Outsource it to Linode.
Let their experts do it.
I am so hyped that they finally launched this and I can't wait to switch some of our backend
stuff over to it.
That's just great.
I also love their object storage.
I think you'll be blown away.
I think you'll be really impressed.
Go try it.
You'll get that $100 and support the show.
What you do, right now in your browser, you go to linode.com slash coder.
That's a vote of confidence for the coder program and it gets you that $100 for 60 days
on a new account.
Linode.com slash coder.
Well we have a little bit of leftovers.
Just brief leftovers from WWDC and we have some text editor news, drama going on I suppose.
So let's start there.
GitHub has announced they are sunsetting the Atom text editor and the original creator
of Atom has announced that he's introducing Zed, a collaborative code editor written in
Rust.
He's going out like that?
That's right.
He's coming back.
Yeah, although Zed was announced first I believe in the order of events and then the sunsetting
of Atom was announced and you caught that.
You were like, this is weird.
The Atom guy just announced a new project.
And of course it's built in Rust because everything is built in Rust these days.
There's a better way to write code.
Mission critical tools should be hyper responsive.
Real time collaboration products are better software.
Conversations should happen close to code.
Oh yeah, it definitely needs a chat client.
I was just complaining to my wife that ultimately every tech product evolves to have a chat
platform.
Every tech product ultimately has a chat platform.
No, no, no, no.
Honestly I'd give it a go.
I'd give a Rust text editor a go.
I will too just because it's not Electron.
Yeah exactly.
Any thoughts about Atom sunsetting?
I mean it was inevitable, right?
You know, VS Code exists, they were under the same parent, right, GitHub effectively
because Microsoft bought GitHub.
So only one could survive, I don't know.
How many Electron editors do you need?
Just saying.
Yeah.
Yeah, I agree.
I agree.
It feels a little sad because whenever something gets replaced and killed, you know, it's just
but it is the right call.
I happen to know there's audience members out there that love Atom.
Yeah, you hear from them every once in a while every time VS Code releases a new feature
that's tied to Azure.
They're like, ha ha, see, we warned you.
But alas, they also owned Atom.
I think you're right.
Get off my bridge.
All right, little WWDC leftovers, just a couple of things that didn't make it into our show
because I don't know, I was moderately disappointed with our coverage, mostly things I didn't
mention because I was in such a rush.
But then again, I listened to some other podcast coverage and they get so drunk on the hype
that it's embarrassing.
I was going to say, what are you disappointed in?
We managed to stay like not Apple high.
I do think we did a good job there.
We did not get crazy.
We did get a follow up from Apple.
Stage manager on the iPad does require an M1 iPad.
Only the M1 iPads have that virtual memory space.
We suspected, that's right, so speculated, but Apple confirmed.
Also didn't mention it in our coverage, no tease of the Mac Pro, which seems late at
this point, and no hints at all about AR or VR, even though that was massively hype before
the event.
There was nothing there that kind of implied that.
But I think the big thing that we didn't know at the time we recorded, but we now know after
the fact, Apple has created a binary for x86 Linux boxes that's Rosetta.
They've created Rosetta 2 for Linux that'll work on any modern ARM processor, any ARM
processor that meets the 8.2 spec or later can run this Apple Rosetta binary.
Now you got to get your hands on it and the way you get it is pretty ridiculous.
You have to be on a Mac using a hypervisor that's probably Apple's and then you have
to mount a directory inside your VM to get access to it.
But assuming, and I believe it's already happened, the Linux community just figured out how to
extract that and I think that's already happened.
You can throw this conceivably in an x86 container and then go run it on an ARM 8.2 or newer
CPU.
Doesn't have to be a Mac box in theory.
Rosetta for Linux, an actual Linux ELF binary.
That seems like a big deal to me.
That also seems to signal that Rosetta is going to be around for a long time and we're
going to be able to run x86 apps on Macs for a long time.
Yeah.
I mean, I think this is going to be important for some developers.
Rosetta has got at least five to 10 years, right?
I guess the difference, although I don't know, I just was reading speculation, I guess the
difference was Rosetta 1 contained a lot of code licensed from IBM and Rosetta 2 is an
Apple creation.
So they own it all so they could just run it forever and definitely if they wanted to.
Then why not?
I mean, maybe not forever, but also just a side note, not really relevant to the show,
but we didn't really understand at the time, but Apple announced a buy now pay later service
and Apple is actually going to be the lender in that situation.
Apple has just turned into a lender.
I believe they're working with Goldman Sachs again on this.
They will handle the lending themselves for a buy now pay later offering using Apple pay.
How dystopian is that?
It's a long way from the kids with the rainbow apple and the pirate flag.
That's for damn sure.
Wow, man.
Wow.
I mean, we're talking asset trips and ashrams to, we're in a deep partnership with our good
friends at Goldman Sachs and we're now a bank.
Also just to kind of round this out, Intel CEO Pat was talking big at an event, you know.
The word you're looking for is drunk.
Yeah.
I think he might've been drunk or at least delusional.
He said in a quote, in an interview to Axios, he said that they think they can win Apple's
business back.
He says, quote, Apple decided they could do a better chip themselves than we could and
you know, they did a pretty good job, so what I have to do is create a better chip than
they can do themselves.
I would hope to win them back, to win a piece of their business as well as many other pieces
of their business over time.
Now, in other news, I just got this text message transcript, Tim, I'm sorry.
What did I do?
Please call.
No reply.
Tim, I miss you.
Now it's, now, wait, wait, now it's 2 30.
The bar has closed.
You know what, Tim, if you like that M1 so much, then you can have them.
Next day around noon, Pat, you're starting to scare me.
Please leave me alone.
It's over.
I have my own chip engineers now.
All the best.
I wish you a happy life.
Oh man.
Your friend, Tim.
Pat wakes up three hours later at 3 30.
Tim, you're killing me.
I miss you so much.
Have you heard about Gen 12?
Question mark.
Happy face.
No reply.
That is probably exactly what happened.
I think you nailed that.
I think I just got it, right?
I got it.
You know, I watch sometimes the CNBCs and the Intel, Pat comes on, he comes on there,
the Intel CEO.
It's so sad.
And, and they're like, boy, looking at the numbers, Intel is sort of set for like devastating
losses in the latter half of the year.
And he's like, sure are.
I'd be, oh wait.
No, no.
He's like, no, no.
It's going to be great.
There's going to be a big surge of computer purchases in the fall.
And have you heard of Ohio?
Ohio, right?
Yeah.
Oh man.
Like he's just, oh anyways, they're so screwed.
They're so screwed.
But Qualcomm though, they, they are bullish.
They're going to nail this.
Qualcomm's chief executive said on Thursday, they believe the company actually will have
the best chip on the market soon with help from a team of chief, with help from a team
of chip architects who formerly worked at Apple, but now work at Qualcomm.
That's how you do it.
Qualcomm's like, we're not even going to pretend anymore.
We're just going to bribe a bunch of dudes from Apple.
Let's go.
That's pretty impressive.
That is.
For the record, if you guys like the sad breakup text message of tech executives, I have many
of those in the bank.
I feel like it could be a series right there.
We did have a couple of boosts come in, but the show, as we record this year's show, I
think our show has only been out for like 12 hours, 13 hours.
Yeah.
We're like back to back.
But the golden dragon sent us in 222 sats, missed a duck, minus one duck today.
So I can get through a week on these sats.
Glad to hear that the dev one is a great system to dev on.
Maybe one you should go full inception on and dev on the dev one using the dev one Linux
distribution.
Whoa.
He sent that in live to the show.
Very sneaky, Doug.
Damn.
All right.
Very nice.
I feel like you get a special boost, Yale, for sending that in live.
Boost.
We also got a thanks from Cos Peeland.
He sent in his classic 3690 sats.
And then we got one in here that I think is going to get you fired up.
I almost don't want to read their name.
See if I can find it.
Because I don't want to read their name on air.
It's Egon?
No.
I'm pretty sure if you don't, we're just going to assume it's Egon.
Yeah.
No.
No, it wasn't Egon.
I know there was one more in here.
Here it is.
Here we go.
All right.
So this was actually a pretty generous 5,000 sats boost from Crashmaster 18.
And he's asking about an app that smells a lot like Alice, and he wants to know if you're
familiar with it.
But I don't even want to give them a plug on air.
Oh, I've not.
I will PM you the name of this.
Here, I'll put the boost in here.
See if you've recognized that name.
Now you tell me.
Anyways, Crashmaster wanted to know.
So I'll pass it along to you.
You go get them, you know?
I hate to see you go into war on the air, but Crashmaster wanted you to be aware.
Mm-hmm.
I'll take a look.
I do not.
This does not look familiar.
All right.
Well, I also want to thank our members.
Thank you very much.
We get offers to do things that you would be surprised.
We have gotten offers to do paid hardware reviews.
We have gotten offers to do paid interviews.
We get approached by all kinds of sponsors that are kind of probably not the sorts that
you would probably prefer to hear from.
And you've created chip executives.
Well, I would take that sponsorship.
I would take that and tell money like that.
Would I use the Intel machine?
No, but I would take their money.
I would love that.
But no, you notice how we don't have mattress sponsors, right?
Or like a Squarespace, like these ones that, you know, come on.
Have you noticed a lot of the higher end podcasts are now offering you, shall we say, sausage
pills for male enhancement?
Isn't that fascinating to watch?
Also having a membership feeds let us do things like avoid dynamic inserts on our back catalog
to monetize the back catalog, right?
It's just the membership is it's it's like a real key pillar to how we do the show.
So thank you to our Coder QA team at Coder QA dot co.
As a thank you, get an ad free version of the feed.
I am working also on a live version of the feed, but it's going to take a little bit
of tech back end work and you get the Coderly report, Coder QA dot co.
I think we should also mention that you and I will not be live the week of the 20th, Monday
the 20th.
You and I are traveling and there will be no Coder live that week, but we will have
one in the feeds.
So we should clarify we are traveling, but because of the laws of physics, we are not
traveling to the same place or together or at the same time in the same space, because
that would right.
That would be you can't have two atoms share the same.
Oh, can we just do a quick Star Trek update before we oh, oh, yeah, totally.
You got a strange already.
You got a strange worlds update already.
I continue to like strange worlds and I have once again finished the original series.
Oh, season three could be the trickiest to get through.
I just finished it.
I've tossed.
Yeah, I just finished it.
I know that can be a little tricky.
It's not that's not the best season.
The last episode is super weird, but I'm at a I'd say a fork, but it's more of a trident
in the road.
The obvious choice, I think, is next generation, but that's the one I've watched the most.
Yeah, I'm a big fan of bald dudes who pretend to be French, but are definitely British.
Yes, they try to retcon that in Picard, by the way.
Do they really?
Yeah, they do.
They try to.
And then, of course, there's like, well, should I give disco another chance because, you know,
Star Trek with good effects is actually kind of cool.
And then there's the one I keep neglecting because I just it's enterprise.
I mean, I was hoping you were going to say that I've never really given it a fair shake.
So that's I just finished season one of Enterprise and I'm just starting season two this week.
Probably this weekend.
Season two, and I initially didn't love Enterprise, but I watched all of it when it aired.
And I have to tell you, rewatching it now, if it's been a while since you watched it
rewatching it now, it is so much better than I remember.
And I think in part because Discovery and Picard have changed my perspectives a little
bit, this this is the last Trek filmed in the traditional Trek style with the character
actors that spanned multiple series and the some of the same production crew.
So it has a very familiar style, but it has the best effects of any of the Trek series.
And the other thing that is extremely enjoyable is everyone is competent at their jobs.
And and they're ahead of the audience most of the time.
Like, you know, when you're watching something, I mean, the characters, not the actors.
Yeah.
You know, like when you're watching something on Discovery and you're like, well, you know,
if they would just do X, Y, Z, this problem would be solved and it's not really a big
deal.
And they don't do that for like three episodes and it drives you crazy in Enterprise.
Right as you start going, well, you know, if they would just they do it, they do it
because they're competent and they're smart.
And it's it's so much better than I expected.
It's so much better.
And it has been very enjoyable to go back and rewatch it.
And if I'm enjoying season one this much, I can't imagine how much I'm going to enjoy
season three and four, because I remember season one and two being the rockiest of them.
And I was just looking at Rotten Tomatoes, you know, now has an audience average score
of seventy nine percent.
And the actors who play Malcolm and Trip, they've recently started a podcast called
Shuttle Pod One.
I believe it's just based on their episode.
They did overcast.
Yeah.
And it's it's on YouTube as a video production, too.
And they've been bringing on former directors and their costars.
They just did one with Rick Berman and they just did a two parter with Brandon Braga.
And you know, they were the people running production at the time.
So you get like I just started watching Enterprise again and then they launched that podcast
and then they're bringing on people and they're talking behind the scenes about the first
few seasons.
It has been so neat.
It's a you got to go Enterprise, man.
You've got to do it.
You got it.
Can I throw two curveballs at you?
Oh, yeah, of course.
I have never completed all of Stargate, but I love Stargate.
OK.
And if I want to be a deep nerd, although I don't know that I have the stomach for this
one, Babylon Five, man, I have tried Babylon Five.
I can't get through that.
I feel like I should like it, but I've never made it past.
I can't get through that first season.
I've tried so hard.
I just watched a YouTube or recap the Babylon Five series and it did make me want to watch
it.
But Enterprise isn't going anywhere.
Right.
So you could do a little bit of deviation.
Have you done The Expanse yet?
No, I have not.
Is that a comedy or is that Orwell?
That's Orwell.
Whatever.
Yeah, that's Orwell.
Oh, boy.
I used to just watch TNG over and over again.
I'm freaking out.
Oh, God, Mike.
Oh, God.
I would kill to be you right now.
I am so jealous that you haven't seen The Expanse yet.
So where is The Expanse available to me?
Amazon Prime.
OK.
And I took three passes at the first few episodes because I didn't like the character it initially
focuses on, but that character isn't the main character of the series.
And by the time I got through the first season, I was really into it.
In fact, if a wizard came out of a genie, a genie came out of a bottle and they said
to me, Chris, you can have one wish in the world.
It wouldn't be, you know, rich.
It wouldn't be that I live forever.
It wouldn't be any of that.
It would be make Star Trek like The Expanse.
It is.
Oh, you're writing some checks.
So good.
It is so good.
It's it's what's going to be our future.
What The Expanse.
It's almost it's almost it's almost inevitable.
It's if humanity just kind of spread out into our solar system, but we never go beyond our
solar system.
Right.
Because when because this this show actually takes place with the use of the limitations
of space.
Right.
Because they don't have like crazy technology that wouldn't actually exist.
Combat is incredible because it's like it really, really would be in space.
And they nail the realism so well.
They make such good characters, such good storytelling.
And then on top of that, the books are incredible.
And it's one of those rare things where the books don't really take anything away from
the show.
They just add more context.
You could watch the show and never read the books, or you could watch all of the show
and then read the books, or you could read the book and watch the show together.
Like I've done all of that.
Oh, my God.
Sold.
That's what I'm doing.
It's so great.
And the audiobooks from Audible are some of my favorite audiobooks of all time.
You know, you got to go look up The Expanse series.
It's kind of hard because there's like a lot of those books.
Only the first six books are really where the TV show takes place.
Some of the best television ever created ever.
And just give you an idea.
So the show started on sci fi, but it was so expensive to produce that sci fi shut it
down.
But the fans love the show so much they freaked out.
And one of the fans was Jeff Bezos.
So Jeff Bezos just bought the whole thing and moved it over to Prime.
Yeah.
Thanks.
So good, man.
I.
We're so spoiled.
I'd love to watch that again.
All right.
So.
So with apologies to Captain Archer yet again, that seems to keep happening every year.
The Expanse it is and I see that there's seven seasons currently.
So this will take a while.
Yeah.
But they're not too long.
They're so good.
So, so good.
Oh, oh, oh, oh.
Oh, so good.
Oh, man.
Anyways.
I got it.
I got to go lay down now.
I'm so excited.
Let's let's wrap this up.
I'm I'm I'm for Clempt now.
Is there any way you want to send people this week?
Go to Alice.dev.
Nice and easy.
He's at Dumanuco on the Twitter.
We'll have links there.
I'm at Chris Ellis.
The podcast is at Coder Radio Show and the whole network's at Jupiter signal.
You know, there's a whole network of shows.
We did a breakdown on that Rosetta story, the details of that in Linux action news.
And I'm going to do my Linux user's perspective review on Linux Unplugged of the HP Dev 1.
I'll throw some benchmarks at it, really push it all the way in Sunday's Linux Unplugged.
So check that out.
Links to what we talked about today at coder.show slash four seven zero.
That's where you'll find our contact form and our RSS feed.
We'd love to hear from you.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio program.
We'll be right back here next week.