This is Coder Radio, episode 402 for February 22nd, 2021.
Hello friends and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and business of software development and the world of technology.
Now running for nearly 402 years, my name is Chris and joining us every single week
perched in the perfect podcast position, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
Hello, sir.
When the Jar Jar does it, it's legal.
Oh, I get a shiver down my spine.
It's legal?
That wasn't my best Jar Jar voice.
I'm going to take that again.
Missa back bitch.
Oh, well.
Right off the top.
Here we go.
One of those episodes right off the top, send your angry emails to WestPain at JupiterBroadcasting.com.
I thought we were starting those to Alan still.
You know, Alan doesn't take the bait.
Alan's like, yeah, whatever, Mike, just yeah, that's true.
You know, as you know, he still wants to make everybody happy.
I know.
Wes is always helping.
We love Wes.
Wes is great.
He's helping right now.
As we, as we fixed your, cause you had, okay.
Surprise topic, Chris.
Okay.
Why are you moving my cheese again and changing our recording technology?
Listen, you know, I'm going to be real gentle with you, darling.
You know, I appreciate that you're sensitive to this kind of stuff.
I hate this kind of stuff.
You know, I know.
You know how I get.
I know.
That's why I understand.
That's why we're testing it real good.
I promise.
Wes was right.
But you know how Wes gets.
He finds real good stuff sometimes.
Get out of here.
Why can't we just run like Skype?
Isn't that what we started with, with Skype?
I think so.
I think it was Skype.
That was awful.
That was bad.
I know.
You know, every now and then there's new tools that come along.
Tools that are not trapped in a web browser.
Tools that are dedicated apps on the desktop that solve problems.
Wait a minute.
Desktop apps?
Yeah.
Can we run on Linux?
Yes.
Of course.
Mac?
Yep.
Windows?
Even iOS and Android.
Mm-hmm.
What about FreeBSD?
FreeBSD.
Of course.
I thought you were running Windows 10.
How is that journey going still?
Are you still in the Windows 10 land?
I've been doing a lot of.NET development and yeah.
Yeah?
You just want to jump right into this?
You want to do this?
I think if I ask you for a few weeks straight, eventually we're going to get to the point
where Windows is really starting to grade on you.
And I don't know if it's this week or if it's next.
I'll put it this way.
Visual Studio is a dream come true.
Yeah.
And if the entire operating system were like Visual Studio.
Right.
It would be great.
Alas, it's not.
See, what I want is Mac OS without the creepy, you know, I'm going to tell you what you can
and can't run on your computer stuff with Visual Studio.
And please don't send me Visual Studio for Mac.
That's just rebranded mono developer Xamarin Studio.
No.
We've been there.
We've done that.
But like Windows 10, it's...
Okay.
You do this to yourself.
All right.
32 gigs of RAM does not go nearly as far on Windows 10 as it does on POP or Mac OS.
I completely agree.
And I'm not even like saying the Apple Silicon magic.
No, I'm not trolling.
Right.
It just doesn't get you the same distance.
Like when people have Windows boxes with 32 gigs of RAM, I understand why.
So I bought this Lenovo ThinkPad, a Yoga X360, I bought it on a President's Day sale.
And it's a lovely piece of hardware.
I love it.
It's great.
I finally get the ThinkPad love.
You all were right.
But I did not know that I needed more memory.
And I really need more memory.
Yeah.
It's slow.
Like my typing seems laggy in Visual Studio.
Yikes.
It says I'm only consuming like 60% of the RAM, but somehow things just sort of like
the start menu.
I hit the Windows key and it's delayed.
I don't get it.
Like Mac OS is fine and does not have these problems.
Well, isn't this kind of the problem with the Windows OEM model is that there's no one
that says this is the minimum bar that these applications.
I'm just going to play devil's advocate because I don't think I actually believe this.
But let's get in the headspace of Apple for a minute.
They have a pro user work group that validates these different machines can run different
workloads and they won't ship a MacBook Pro that can't do a certain kind of workload.
I'm not trying to defend Apple here.
This just seems to be my observation from the outside.
I think you could probably say the same kind of thing for system 76.
They're going to sell a laptop at a certain category of user and they won't sell a laptop
that can't meet the certain requirements that they have with and they're looking at it from
an application level, an OS level and a hardware level.
But Lenovo, not so much because somebody else who buys that yoga that has 16 gigs of RAM
and say they're only running Edge and Outlook, it's going to be completely sufficient.
So Lenovo doesn't really have like this kind of baseline that they're going to guarantee
is going to work well.
They're just kind of targeting a real rough demographic, I feel like I don't know.
This is not a cheap machine.
True.
I mean, granted, it's last year's model and granted I got it on sale, but it's I don't
know.
I mean, I have my lemur.
Is it a lemur?
Is it a darter?
I always messed it up.
You mean lemur.
Lemur from Carle de Shell at System76.
Rochelle.
Rochelle from Paris.
Sorry, Carle.
So sorry.
And it's like, granted, the battery life, not great, but it's fast and I don't feel
like PyCharm is lagging behind.
The Mac is literally the platonic ideal of perfection because of Apple Silicon.
I have nowhere to go from that statement.
It's bold.
It seems like 16 gigs of RAM should be enough to me.
Well, my diagnosis is then that the paper cuts are beginning to set in already.
Well, it's just annoying.
But like Visual Studio is a masterpiece.
Now devil's advocate, maybe the things I like about Visual Studio are just so heavy and
so memory intensive that that's actually what's causing me issues.
Anybody who's trying to run a workload like that is going to have performance issues.
Like if you were trying to do Premiere right now, you'd be having you'd be having the same
problems, my friend.
Not with my Xeons, baby.
So having said that, I solve all problems being the Democrat that I am, which is ironic
because we don't talk about that anymore.
I bought a very or a somewhat expensive Lenovo monitor.
Oh, really?
It has a built in camera and mic, huh?
Because I am going to hook up the Thaleo again as my daily driver.
Good call.
I saw pictures on your Twitter of the Thaleo opener.
Are you swapping out components again?
Los Siento, Carl Los Siento.
I may be modifying the fan to make it quiet.
You have one of the early models, and I think that's an area that I have.
I have one of the first models that has the it's a little loud.
I mean, we did the decibel test with a year and a half and I was like, Mike, you can't
use that to podcast.
You're like, Mike, go get your Mac and shut up and just pretend like you're running Linux
because we need the clicks.
It's no good.
Like right now, I'm an iMac Pro and you know what you're not hearing?
The iMac Pro because it I'm not even sure it has fans.
I mean, I know it does, but yeah, I think they've come on twice.
Having said that, you should totally buy a Thaleo.
The new ones do not do what mine does because they I guess they fixed it.
I am elated to hear that you're coming over to the workstation master race.
I think it is the superior performance choice.
I would watch the term master race these days.
I'm just just saying, yeah, but I'm labeling you, not me.
So fine.
Oh, so I'm the Nazi.
Great.
I am blonde hair and blue eyes.
Let's just keep going.
I need that as a soundboard clip.
Just pointing that out.
Anyways, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
All right, fair enough.
I actually I was on Newegg and for a for a lull I was looking at the price of video cards.
I don't know if you've gone down this rabbit hole, but it's comical, it's comical like a modern video card.
If it's in stock, a great deal would be seven hundred dollars right now.
It's ridiculous.
It's so bad that Nvidia is coming up with this cockamamie scheme where they're going
to have mining only cards and then they're going to artificially limit the gaming cards
so that when they do mining workloads, they're cut in half via the driver.
Wait, this is real.
Yeah.
This is such a like using the software driver to limit the hardware.
It really pushes my buttons.
AMD is having trouble making theirs.
There's a global chip shortage that's impacting everybody.
So I was looking at it and I thought this is just not the time to try to upgrade my
workstation.
But, you know, that'll be my next thing by the end of the year is I'm going to try to
refresh my desktop workstation into something that's pretty powerful and I'm going to start
with a high refresh rate monitor and work my way out from there.
I decided I guess I don't get it.
Why are they discouraging people from buying their cards?
They are having a hard time making enough to meet demand.
Gamers aren't getting access to these cards.
That has a knock on stagnation effect for the rest of the gaming industry.
But also, it means that neither customer is satisfied, neither the miner who wants to
mine some cryptocurrency, nor the gamer is satisfied.
And you have a bunch of miners who when they can are buying up a whole bunch of these cards.
Yeah, but their money's good, too, right?
I know.
And here's the worst part, Mike, is these mining only cards can't be used for gaming
later on.
So when the miners move on, they just go in the landfill.
They're not going to go on like eBay.
This seems like the dumbest way to solve this problem possible.
I think Nvidia realized that they're going to have a problem, that you'd have the use
market come along and dump a whole bunch of cards in a year or two undercutting their
market price.
And so they decided to make this move, which is just it's cold.
You know, it's a cold move.
And you know that that driver limitation is going to get bypassed in under a month.
As I say, you know, there's like 15 guys in Eastern Europe ready to get around that at
any point.
You know it.
And you know, they're sitting there in their coders.
Oh, Jesus.
Go ahead, Chris.
I'm muting.
I'm muting because I know I'm not supposed to swear on the show anymore.
Just do it.
Well, you know, time is running out for the coder.
That's right.
The Coder Radio robe.
It's almost it's almost gone, folks.
At the end of the month, eleven fifty nine p.m., we're done.
It's true.
It's you know what you could say.
This is the final countdown for the coder.
OK, the fact that you made this happen just drives me crazy and the fact that every single
day on Twitter, someone has to tell me, hey, Mike, hope you're having a good day.
Look what I just bought.
I mean, at least you're getting a robe out of the deal.
I even bought one myself because I I sincerely didn't believe that this would be successful.
The only way is through, Mike.
It's the only way out.
I get it.
This is the battle of the bulge.
I just have to shoot and shoot and shoot and like fight.
Right.
And you know, we'll see.
We'll see what happens because I can't guarantee that the robe is gone forever, but I think
this is the only one.
I don't know.
You know, so this is a special moment in Coder Radio history right now.
If everybody who has tweeted at me has actually bought a robe, we should never stop selling
rooms.
I know.
You know, I know.
Unless they're lying.
But I don't think we've even I don't think we've crossed the 150 mark yet.
I don't think so.
That's you know, but it's all it would really take to make this viable, assuming we don't
die in the international shipping.
If the international shipping ends up being half the cost of the robe, I'm going to have
a problem.
But we'll find out.
The Coder dot shop and then the next thing I'm going to tackle after this is figuring
out how to do multiple sizes and colors for some other swag item.
Can I recommend just this is just me trying to help the audience for the same people in
the audience, which I know there's only five of you left.
There is a poster, a Coder Radio 400 poster.
Mine came today, actually.
Oh, do you know if we did a video show, do you know what my backdrop is?
The last one.
It's the 300 poster framed, the old one with the green Emacs logo.
Yeah, this one looks really sharp with the new logo.
Really happy with it.
I'm going to get it framed and I'm going to put it up on the wall in the studio.
I'll have to do the same just out of pure jealousy.
But you know what I will always do now?
Hmm.
So, you know, I'm starting an OnlyFans, right?
I've been waiting.
Hey, the fact that you laugh, you know what I'm saying?
I'm waiting.
You know, I've been thinking this is the way to go.
I'm thinking, you know, we have the Coderly report, right?
Yeah, yeah.
This is the only fans where I dress in the Coder robe and I code in whatever language
the audience picks, which I can already see the PHP coming because many people have tweeted
it at me because I tweeted this idea out.
So just so I'm clear, what would be the product would be, would be you, a grown man in a robe,
complaining that people keep choosing PHP over and over again and then having people
pay for that.
Well, it doesn't have to be PHP.
I mean, if there are particular status in the audience, they could be vBasic.
I mean, vB6.
I mean, I don't know.
Okay.
I actually think now I think I'd pay for that myself, actually.
Now I see what you're saying.
I know for a fact Wes would get in there because he did this to me for free.
Right.
About a year ago.
Yeah.
I think this is something we should do.
So please comment on the show if you would like to torture me.
This could be a new platform for developers to raise money for their project.
Yeah, it's going to be me and a bunch of dancing girls, let's say.
Right.
And you know what I love about it is everyone's wearing a robe.
Yes, I will wear the damn robe, okay?
So go get it now, thecoder.shop.
I will never forgive the audience for the robe.
I'm just letting them know.
This really is, they're the ones that encouraged me, you know, with the emails.
How did this?
You know what?
Let's just move on.
Okay.
All right.
The robe is a thing for me.
The robe is very triggered by the robe.
Let's just keep going.
It'll be a thing, but we'll heal and we'll move forward.
I'm willing, of course, to make money off the robe.
All right, well, it is a special time to mention that a Cloud Guru has a 20% off business plans
promotion going right now.
If you use the promo code SPRINGINTOCLOUD21, you'll save for your whole team.
You know the cloud's growing.
In fact, 82% of companies have ramped up their investment in cloud computing as a response
to the pandemic.
So a Cloud Guru has a spring sale right now.
It's the perfect time to plant the seeds for your digital transformation.
Fast-track into the cloud with the most effective and comprehensive cloud training platform
out there.
That's a cloudguru.com.
You go over there and use the promo code SPRINGINTOCLOUD21.
96% of customers saw improved results within six months when they surveyed 400 users.
SPRINGINTOCLOUD21 at a cloudguru.com.
We have some email.
Should we do email?
Maybe we should do email.
That might be best.
Can you send me a robe email?
I don't know, actually.
No, the first one's actually about keyboards.
That's classic.
That should make you feel better.
All right, fine.
Notjohn writes in.
He says, can we get an update on the Keychron mechanical keyboard that Chris ordered?
They're on my short list of options, but I hear they're a bit tall and usually require
a wrist rest.
So I have the Keychron right here.
I've talked about it a little bit on the show.
It's been a few weeks, though, so it's not a bad time to update.
It's the Keychron K3, and it's just this tiny little 65% keyboard, and it's USB-C or Bluetooth,
and it has really low profile keys.
And they even sell a little baggie that I have linked in the show notes.
This is a perfect portable keyboard to go in your bag.
This would have a no impact on my bag, weight or really size.
It's lower profile than a normal keyboard, so you have to be comfortable with that.
The lighting options are really cool, and it has a switch to move between Mac mode or
Windows and Linux mode.
And I'll link to an iMore review, which I pretty much agree right up and down with their
entire review over there.
I think it was Christine Chan that wrote this.
Essentially because of their low profile keys, it's a little bit harder to swap out some
of the keys on this than a typical mechanical keyboard.
So that's a bit of a downside, but it's lightweight.
It's compact as heck, and it does have hot swappable keys if you need to.
It has Bluetooth connectivity or USB-C, and it has a lot of nice backlighting options.
It's gray for the keys with kind of a soft glow white that comes through the keycaps.
I like that part a lot.
And then the other thing I'm a big fan of is some of the other keys like Tab and Capslock
and Shift and Enter.
They're a darker gray.
They stand out more.
It's a different color.
And then the Escape key is red.
It comes with a different key, but I like it red, and I have it lit up.
So it looks like the Escape keys, like the abort key on a spaceship or something.
It types real good.
I mean, this is me kind of banging on it.
And I think it's a great keyboard, but because it is so low profile, it's not quite as satisfying
to type on as I would ultimately like.
If I was buying this to work with an iPad or another sort of ultra portable machine,
I'd be very happy with this.
And because I'm using it here in the studio in a kind of a tight space, it works tremendously
well.
So if I was going to get a Keychron for myself at home today, I actually would be a little
bit boring and I'd probably go with the K6, which is about a similar size, doesn't look
quite as modern, but has a more traditional depth and size of a keyboard.
It's not quite as thin.
That's the Keychron K6 wireless mechanical keyboard.
That'd be probably the route I'd go instead of this one.
I don't know if I'd buy this one again, but that's just for my use case.
If I was throwing this in a bag, absolutely this would be the one I'd get again.
And I really like it.
It's been a nice improvement from what's in here.
So I will link to both of those, the K6 and the K3 in the show notes.
The K3 is sold out right now.
Keychron man, they have travel pouches, they have wood wrist rest.
I don't feel like this needs a wrist rest.
In fact, if anything, I'd say this is lower down to the desk than most keyboards are.
So I like it a lot.
You're super fancy.
I still like my WASD code keyboard.
Yeah.
Yeah, we actually have had people write in too with good comments about that.
Yeah, I like the little one, but it's not as little as your mini, but we're ultra slim
rather.
And it lights up really cool.
I really like the way it lights up.
Anti-hacker Mike wrote in and he has been in a situation and I'd love to hear what you
think about this.
He says, hey guys, love the show as usual.
I can't, oh here, this is great.
He says, I cannot wait to be listening to it comfortably in the coder.
There it is.
Good job.
Mike, what are you doing?
He worked it in.
We've talked about security a few times here on the show, but he wanted to get our views
on a controversial practice that he has seen on the rise.
He says he's referring to the idea of bug bounties, but not bug bounties like you know
it, where a company basically invites people to hack them and then pays the hacker for
what they find, which is common, you know, Apple and Google and Microsoft and lots of
companies, there's bug bounty that do that.
It seems, anti-hacker Mike writes, that it's becoming an entire career for people where
they essentially bang on stuff and then they come emailing.
He says this all seems well and good until it happened to my web service.
Yeah, a hacker was able to find a small hole in our security and then was able to exploit
it.
He emailed us with screenshots asking to be paid for finding this bug.
While it sounded like a question, it didn't really feel like a choice.
It felt more like blackmail.
Extortion is the word you're looking for, but yeah.
Yeah, he goes on to say we did end up agreeing to hire him to test the whole site and then
report his findings.
He did, and then we fixed those issues.
But then, a couple of months later, he came back saying he'd found more things and that
we'd have to pay him again to see them.
I can't help but see this as anything other than a hustle.
We haven't agreed to anything yet, so I'm not sure what will happen next, but what are
your views on this type of practice?
On one hand, it is a service, but on the other hand, it feels forced and not morally right.
What are your thoughts?
Gather round, children, and let Uncle Mike tell you about New Jersey for a few minutes.
Oh my gosh, that's amazing.
I understand.
I think last week we had a nice conversation about Texas.
Yep.
Well, it's time to talk about Jersey.
Tell us a little bit, Mike.
I want to make sure we have our glossary of terms.
Okay.
Extortion.
Uh-huh.
Give me money or I will do something bad to you.
Blackmail.
Give me money or I will share information damaging to you.
Protection racket.
Give me money or I will hurt you.
Right.
Usually it's phrased as, hey, that's a nice website you got there.
Be a shame if all the user data got leaked.
Right.
Now, I am a pretty mild-mannered guy, which, I mean, Chris has hundreds of hours of evidence
to the contrary, but, you know, we just got to let that go.
The first thing you learn when you're in preschool in New Jersey is if somebody shoves you on
the playground, even if they're right, you punch them in the face, no matter what.
You never admit fault.
Chris knows this from dealing with me.
You're sorry only transactionally, right?
You're never really sorry.
Because your mistake in this case, what's the listener's name again?
Anti-hacker Mike.
All right.
I'm calling you Vinny.
Vinny, your mistake is you paid this jerk, and jerk is the modified.
You know, we need to do a New Jersey feed of the show where I can say what I really
think.
Right.
This guy's never going to leave you alone until you get even.
Now, I'm not telling you to break any laws because we don't do that on Jupiter broadcasting.
We do that on Telegram in encrypted chats.
I'm telling you, you got taken for a sucker.
He came to you.
You paid him, which was not smart.
Now he's coming back for more money.
This is this is mafia tactics right here.
This is the same bullshit people try to pull all the time.
Do you know how many?
Okay, let's go back to classic coder.
I got sued for code journal when it hit the top of the app store.
Like I think it was literally like eight times.
One of the lawsuits, my favorite one, was because I had syntax highlighting.
Remember when that came after podcasts for like playlists?
Yeah.
What was it?
I also got hit with the in app purchase one.
What the hell?
What was the name of that company?
Wow.
That was forever ago.
I remember that.
What the hell was it?
I don't remember now.
But whatever.
These are like gangster tactics.
And the mistake you made, Mike, I won't call you Vinny because that was kind of mean, is
you gave in.
Yes, you may have legitimate issues.
But this person, the way you have at least described him or her, is not behaving like
a security professional.
They're behaving like honestly, like a damn gangster.
Like they're extorting you.
Yeah.
And the minute you lay down to extortion, you're done.
And I've made the mistake.
I have settled lawsuits for bullshit patent stuff that I didn't need to settle.
And you know what?
If I could go back in time 10 years, I would tell younger Mike, you know, eff them.
Don't pay a thing.
Fight, fight, fight.
Because let me tell you, all these jerks are paper tigers.
And what are they going to do?
They're going to write a mean tweet.
They're going to write a mean blog post about you.
Who cares?
People can say whatever they want about you.
This is straight extortion.
Don't give in to it.
And if the guy doesn't leave you alone, honestly, call the FBI and tell him you're doing it.
Because this is a crime.
I know some people in the infosec world will say I'm being too harsh, but this is bullshit.
Yeah, I think you could get him for breaking and entering at this point.
You could get him for for felon abuse.
What is it?
The 1980?
Mm hmm.
What the hell?
You know the law better than I do.
The telecom?
No, the Computer Fraud and Abuse Act.
Right.
That he did not have consent.
So there are real security professionals have get consent to do penetration testing.
That's exactly right.
This is bull.
You're being extorted.
Even if he's right.
You don't lay down to this.
Yeah.
You could.
You definitely should be talking to a lawyer.
There's no there's no doubt about it.
Yeah, I would be talking to a lawyer and the district's attorney at this point.
I this is nonsense.
You don't have to put up with this.
And then at the same time, you could engage with a legitimate firm to start, you know,
helping protect and investigate so that if he does leak something, but a legitimate firm
would not do this without your consent.
Right.
Absolutely.
You're being attacked.
I have been the sales engineer in those calls and we get stuff signed.
You get stuff signed off before you begin any of this for legal reasons.
And I have been on that end of the transaction.
And by the way, I've been the customer for this stuff.
One of the things that is in the contract from the security firm nondisclosure.
Oh, yeah, absolutely.
So the security engineer who finds a flaw in your system, you know, trademark New Jersey
has to keep their damn mouth shut.
They can never say anything.
Once you sign on the dotted line, you you know, you agree to the terms and in there
is going to be a nondisclosure.
It's absolutely part of the standard practice.
And that's why I say you could engage with a firm now and have them start proactively
working on this.
So that way, what this guy knows is an outdated set of information while you pursue legal
options here.
I mean, it's a hell of a situation because, first of all, it angers me because it delegitimizes
an area of I.T. that I think is critically important and something I used to act I used
to I used to do work in.
And, you know, I took it really seriously.
And so that makes me angry.
But additionally, on top of that, like you could see how people could just stay home,
do nothing and just poke at WordPress websites and then extort small businesses for money
all day long.
I am going to say one thing, but like the MadBotter.com is a old WordPress website that
has nothing of value on it.
So.
Well, absolutely.
But, you know, you go into like some mom and pop hair salon or some shop that has.
Well, and they've got their customer info in WordPress.
That's a mistake.
And I think you could scare people enough.
People don't understand that a compromised website on their GoDaddy colo doesn't mean
that their credit card point of sales app at their local LAN has been compromised.
They don't get the difference there.
If you come in and say, I've owned your website and I've defaced it.
Now I have access to your customer records.
They would believe you.
Well, that's why the I mean, I know I'm on pretty aggressive ground here, but I I consider
this stuff extortion, especially when it's small businesses.
I've never gotten the pentest thing because I mean, this is maybe too inside baseball
for me, but we're required to do audits and I have to hire them anyway.
It puts you this way, but the professionals, when they find something, don't threaten you
with it.
Right.
And they actually fix it for you most of the time.
Yeah.
That's how you know this guy's not legit.
This guy's not legit.
You're being taken for a ride.
This is like, I don't know.
I mean, go watch the movie The Untouchables.
This is the guy who goes to the bar during prohibition that's selling soda.
And then when the guy won't buy his illegal beer from Canada, puts a bomb under it and
kills the little girl.
That's a that's a deep Sean Connery reference.
Sean Connery.
Oh, let's can we pour one out for the only true James Bond?
But yeah, seriously, Mike, do not lay down to this.
Yeah.
And that is the most New Jersey way I can put this right.
And I don't care what he says.
Let him say.
Let him say what he's going to say.
This is you.
You are the victim of extortion and it's time to not be a victim.
You got to fight back.
It's no different than if you give in to ransomware, just enables them as well.
It's a exactly, exactly.
It's a bad racket.
You got me all fired up.
All right.
Well, Timer Mike writes in different Mike, my brothers.
Yeah, they're all coming together today.
He when he was listening to the last episode, I mentioned that I was still having an ongoing
battle with RSI and he realized that he has adopted techniques in general to sort of mitigate
and manage this.
He also picked up on you mentioning that you use a Pomodoro timer app when you're on Gnome
Shell.
He said, I'm not really sure when I came across the technique, but it's become a regular part
of my development process for the last 10 years.
I imagine Mike can have a detailed definition of the process for Pomodoro, but for me, this
is how I use it.
I try to distill my tasks into simple sentences that can be definitively marked as done when
they are in fact done.
So like an example would be account record update when Cognito user is updated and sentence
tasks should just be completable in 30 minutes to an hour and no more than two hours long.
I try to keep to this, but I often lean towards the two to three hour side of things and work
time comprises of 25 minute focus, distraction free efforts, followed by five minutes of
something entirely different.
This is where I've been able to improve my RSI health significantly, giving my hands
and body a five minute break from behind the computer seems to make all of the difference
in the world.
When I'm under time pressure, I'll sometimes abandon my break and keep cranking.
When I do this for long, I inevitably find that my hands and forearms become sore.
Over the last year, I started creating a to do today sheet where I list out my distilled
tasks along with the day's date.
I use the leftover space as a doodle pad for ideas and notes.
And at the end of the day or often at the start of the next, I make a journal entry
on the back of the sheet, summarizing my thoughts on the work that was done and what needs attention
next.
I now have a year's worth of these sheets and I fill that with a three ring binder.
I doubt I will ever go through and read every one of those sheets.
But when you work with intangible goods like software, it's nice to see a stack of something
accomplished in the real world.
I've tried various software timers over the years and they've all had something that
made them difficult to stick with.
When I start blaming those timers for not allowing the technique to work, I decided
just to toss them and go old school kitchen timer from Amazon.
It's not great, but it doesn't crash nor does it stop ticking when my OS crashes and I need
to reboot.
I think there might be a J.B. Swag opportunity for the quote, coder countdown put me down
for three.
God damn, no.
I congrats on 400 shows.
What do you think of that, a coder countdown, it's, you know, I think that's something
right there.
He ought to call himself Merch Mike because I think he's onto something.
This is interesting.
I have been experimenting with a daily brain dump at the end of every workday of what I
think my to do's are for the next day.
And I've actually found what works best is just a text document on my computer that I
just leave running that I just leave up on my screen.
So the next day I come in, it's right there.
Get out of town.
We do the same thing.
I have just like a little text document that I pop open on my desktop and that's it.
I have from time to time done the physical, write it down on a piece of paper, and I do
like that.
And then I would cross off something when I got it done.
I like that crossing off thing.
There is something to when you work on an intangible good to have a tangible good that
represents some accomplished work does feel good because there are every now and then
there's days that I have.
There are always off air days where I feel like I lost an entire day to slack and telegram
and email and I feel gross at the end of the day.
Like what have I done with my day?
Like every day all my time is so precious.
I have so little time to get the stuff done and then I spend an entire day replying to
people and I have nothing to show for it at all.
And so that's where having it, I can look back at a to do list and go, oh no, that's
right.
I did fix that issue we were having in the studio and I did get so and so contacted about
this and I can look at the list of things I actually accomplished.
And then while I'm thinking about it, okay, but I still need to get all this done.
That's when I do the brain dump for the next day doc.
I could definitely see extending this though and taking some of these breaks that Mike's
talking about here, doing like a focus 25 minute session and then taking a break.
I do need to play around with that a little bit I think.
Pomodoro will change your life.
Yeah.
I've been doing it for years now.
Little bit of an error here, Mike.
I no longer use the Gnome Pomodoro app because Gnome extensions are fundamentally broken
because Gnome extensions are poorly engineered.
Hey guys, sorry about that.
I keep doing that and I'm sure Eric's pissed off.
I do it on my iPhone because I actually once sold a Pomodoro app and I still have an old
copy of it that I have made run and do not currently sell and it works much better than
Gnome extensions.
Chris, did I miss anything I wanted to insult today?
I don't think so.
I mean, you could, I mean we could throw shade at Chrome or Android.
We haven't done that in a while.
No, you know what?
We don't throw shit at Android because Google, no, I feel like Fuchsia is going to do it
for us.
I feel like Chrome OS overtaking Mac OS, like just like dunked mercilessly on Android.
Oh right.
I mean, somehow Google is its own worst enemy in like the weirdest way.
Yeah.
That Chrome OS becoming the second largest OS is kind of remarkable audience.
This is how it happens when my kid's not here and we no longer have structure to the show.
I have a bone to pick with you.
Oh, all right.
With the audience or with me?
You personally.
Oh, okay.
All right, good.
Okay.
All of the audience, the rogue thing, guys, if he makes a timer, we might take another
couple of month hiatus here because I don't know if I can take it.
You guys got to stop.
Martini glasses, sure.
Coffee cups, yes.
I've noticed certain Linux commentators.
I'm not going to name names, Chris, Chris, Chris, counting Chrome OS as desktop Linux.
Is that what I heard?
What I thought I heard?
Hmm.
I may have in some context.
I kind of waffle on that.
You're a little pussy footed on that.
I could say.
I mean, what do you what do you consider?
It's Gentoo under the hood.
Is it Gentoo?
I mean, I know you can run devs.
I mean, yeah.
And you can run some Linux desktop apps as well now.
Gooey ones.
I know.
But it feels like when people used to claim Android installs as Linux installs.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, maybe.
Yeah.
Like it.
Here's the problem.
Here's the thing, Mike.
It's like what what slice of Linux are we talking about?
Are we talking about like desktop Linux?
Because then, yeah, I don't think it's actually fair to count Chrome OS at all, actually.
Oh, we're talking desktop Linux, right?
Servers Linux wins, right?
IOT Linux wins.
I sell everything on servers and IOT is Linux.
Fine.
I'm with you.
I change my wallpaper background every 30 minutes and that feels like a problem.
Oh, man.
You know, it's I feel like Chrome OS is it's closer to a Linux machine than Mac OS is to
a Unix workstation.
What?
You got a vape pen there?
I think you're nuts.
Are you joking?
No, no, because you can get a Linux command line.
You can run Linux, gooey applications.
That itself is based on Linux and it runs a Linux kernel.
Hang on.
You said Unix, not Linux.
Right.
Yeah, because like Mac OS, while it has it has a BSD user land, it has its own wackadoodle
kernel.
It doesn't have the entire BSD user land.
It has its own init manager, whereas everything on the Chrome OS side, it's Linux kernel.
It's an open source init manager.
It's got the Linux user land and it runs Linux desktop applications.
And they're even converting the sucker to a Wayland based display system.
So it's like.
Yes, because Wayland was always a good idea.
My point is, it's a lot of the Linux stack there where the Mac is their own proprietary
UI, a good portion of the BSD user land and their own kernel.
Hey, whoa, whoa, wait, wait, let's take a breath, OK?
First of all, the Mac kernel is amazing.
Darwin is amazing.
You're fundamentally wrong in every possible way here.
All right.
Yes, the Mac user land is a little schizophrenic.
It sometimes thinks it's an iPad and doesn't know what it's doing.
Like for instance, I was texting a person and it decided that it forgot who she was
at some point in iMessage and sent me the same notification 10 times on my phone because
I sent it from my iMac.
Sure.
Still, I would say Mac is more BSD than Chrome is Linux or Chrome OS is Linux, I should say.
I don't know, man.
I don't know.
Have you seen BSD?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, it's great.
I mean, we know people who run BSD and they pretty much won Windows 7, is my understanding.
You would be correct.
I would be correct.
I know I'm correct.
So I don't know.
I mean, I think we should all run Pop OS and Carl, I don't know why I'm in love with Carl
today.
I don't know.
All I want to do is change my background every 30 minutes and not have my OS crash.
He's got your back, you know, because-
He really doesn't.
This one issue-
His team's making their stuff in Rust and TypeScript, so you should be happy hunky dory
there.
I was with you on Rust and I'm judging them harshly on TypeScript.
Oh, hell, okay.
I thought it was a, I thought it showed a progressive move on their part.
I think, and I don't mean this to be flamey and I know some people will read into it and
it'll be controversial.
I think the gnome team should just apologize for extensions, RM tack R the entire repo
and start over with KDE.
Oh God.
And I don't mean it to be controversial.
No, of course not.
No, not, no, obviously not.
Again, Noble pain on Twitter is where you want to send your feedback.
Right.
Or Alan at JupiterBroadcasting.com.
Alan never replies.
Alan's no fun.
It's because he's smart.
He knows.
He's on Windows 7.
He doesn't even, he can't even get the messages.
Linode.com slash coder, go there to support the show and get a $100 60 day credit.
Now I got to check this, Mike, are you slipping a hundred, a hundred dollars into this?
That doesn't seem real.
How can they afford to do that?
I thought it was just a champagne room.
I'm sorry.
Nope.
It's true though.
$100 in, uh, in account credits for 60 days when you create a new account at Linode.com
slash coder.
I spent everything up on Linode now.
Like everything.
If it's a game server for my kids or if it's the backend infrastructure for a community
chat system, I spin it up on Linode.
One of the things that we run right now is a piece of software that has replaced Google
docs for me completely.
It's coming along.
It's had a few name changes, but I really like where they're, where they're going with
it.
It's called hedge doc.
It's a self hostable real time collaborative text editing Markdown editor.
It's like everything I needed in Google docs, but it specializes in Markdown and you can
host it yourself.
That's something that we put up on Linode.
So our team has a URL they go to, and that's where our hedge doc instances and it works
great for that.
When we're done with this, we're going to upload these files to a system running on
Linode that our editor drew will download it from, and when he's done, he'll submit
it back up to a Linode system that will encode it and then publish it out to the web.
We do all of that on Linode.
So if you're if you're brand new and you just want to get started, Linode has great plans
that are totally accessible price wise and UI wise.
You can get started right away or if you really know what you're doing and you can mix and
match different technologies like their object storage and their cloud firewall and of course
their GPU or dedicated CPU systems, you could really build an infrastructure that's just
unmatchable to anything you could have done years ago.
Linode has been around since 2003, so they have followed this market very closely.
But they were in this, I think, before we were calling this cloud computing, right?
They started before AWS.
They started before Google or any of the enterprise cloud providers got into this.
Because of that, they've been able to really focus on a few things and do them extremely
well.
And they're 30 to 50 percent less in cost than the other enterprise cloud providers
while still having incredibly great network connections because they've been in this.
They can network.
They've been in this for a long time.
They know how to serve this up for an end user and make it super accessible.
They know how to check all of those boxes and do it really well.
And they're my server provider of choice because of that and a lot of other reasons.
But I encourage you to just go check it out.
There's only so much I can really tell you in the show.
For the rest, you just got to take a little time and try it.
And that's why they're making this $100 offer right now.
Go to linode.com slash coder, go over there, sign up, support the show and just try some
of it out and see what I've been talking about.
See what you can do.
You can deploy it for infrastructure that's client facing or for back end stuff for yourself
or your community.
And they have 11 data centers to choose from.
So you can find something that's close to whoever is going to be using the system.
Try it out at linode.com slash coder.
I just want you to know the monsters that listen to the show live have been tweeting
me purchasing coder robes.
You know what, Robbros, I appreciate you out there.
I need you this week, Robbros.
I hate every single one of you with a passion that only equals the memory leakage of Swift
versus Objective-C. I completely made that up, but most of you don't write Swift and
I could have totally passed that off as a fact.
Robros includes ladies and also children.
Robros also includes dogs.
That'd be amazing.
So maybe before we get out of here, maybe we should impart people with some wisdom.
You found a really good article about starting a niche, finding your niche and starting in
one.
And we will link to this in the show notes.
It's it's wow.
This is the week of mics.
It's also written by a guy named Michael.
So many of us.
We are leeching.
This is getting weird, man.
This is the like the third or fourth mic-ception.
That's wild.
But anyways, he starts with the most popular products don't become mass or popular overnight.
It's a process.
Usually their popularity is uneven and they're known in some niches, but not very popular
in other niches.
When you start a product, sometimes you know that niche already and you can easily define
and target that customer.
But in many cases, you just don't know.
And you try to find the niche and the miraculous niche market fit that will work for your product.
One of the most common mistakes is to ignore niches and just try to attract all kinds of
customers going just for that general customer.
But I tell you, it's essential to find one or two ponds to start from and then expand
to the other larger, more promising lakes and oceans later.
And then what Michael does is he goes through here and lays out some classic technologies
that started as strange niche products, but now are huge.
The telegraph, the telephone, the photograph, the car, the radio, the radio was immediately
adopted by the British Royal Navy.
They thought the radio could speed up communication between ships and they were right.
Really, it took a lot longer until others adopted the radio.
So radio was introduced in 1895.
In 1912, the Titanic sent a distress signal, but the radios were turned off on the closest
ships because they just simply weren't using them back then.
Well, they didn't have the Windows Vista patch.
Yeah.
Which meant you had to reboot or else your router and radio service were down.
With apologies to Paul Thoreau.
VisiCalc also, you know, Excel's predecessor that launched in 1979, classic, first adopted
by accountants, businessmen and analysts joined the party much later on.
Accountants saw the value right away in VisiCalc, but the others in the business stack took
a lot longer before they realized what spreadsheets would be used for now.
Now entire companies run off of Excel.
And I thought this just, it really was a really wise article that you found.
I set it aside to read it and I read the whole thing and he really makes the case for how
you have to find a niche.
You have to focus on it.
He says, how do you find that niche?
You can use Conway's law, which you can look that up, but he said it's only a partially
a joke.
You review a couple of the alternatives, you look at what you know best, you select that,
and then you execute as best as you can.
In a way, startups are kind of like an experimentation facility that hypothesizes, executes, and
then measures their results.
And the startups that are successful are the ones that find the right niche.
I mean, I have the sense just from doing this for, has it been 400 years yet?
I mean, are we older than the country?
Right.
No, actually, if you check, if you look at the map this week, it's 402 years.
True.
And I believe that the title should be payment required because I know my HTTP error codes.
And by the way, people are going to look at that and they're going to go, what?
No, they're going to look at it and they're going to buy a poster.
You understand what I said?
And more importantly, what I did not say, no, but seriously, buy a robe.
It'd be a shame for something to happen.
You should buy a robe just to be careful.
Let me explain something to you.
The Thaleo has been a flight simulator for a long time.
I have been working on drones for a long time.
There may or may not be some sort of interference with the robes where there are chips in them.
And then one day you're all going to get painted with the worst possible thing I could think
of, Swift stickers.
I have to say a supply chain attack on the robes would be the ultimate long troll.
That would be pretty good.
You know what?
The problem is you have weirdly aligned my incentives with yours.
Even though I don't think it's a secret that the robes, I thought you were joking and I'm
really surprised that there are actually robes.
I say this every week because I'm not over it.
Like I got to be honest.
I, what were you smoking?
Inspiration.
You know, the creative inspiration.
You did give us a hint at your niche there a little bit, you know?
I did.
How long did, I mean that, that going back to that point, that wasn't just an obvious
for, I mean, it seems like it took you multiple years of getting screwed at different things
before you kind of landed on that niche for a while.
Aviation niche.
Yeah.
So this is the thing where longtime listeners are going to be like, I heard it before.
In the beginning, Chris, in the beginning, there was darkness.
Four hundred years ago.
And then, you know, a guy named, oh my God, I can't remember the guy's name who created
Java and I feel like a jerk.
Gosling?
Gosling.
Right?
Oh, I'm right.
Gosling.
I wrote Java applets because I needed money.
That's a good reason to do anything.
And then the iPhone came out and I had a Dutch uncle who helped me because I was still young
enough to need help and bought me a very cheap MacBook.
I'm not denigrating, but he, he, he hates Apple.
He still hates Apple to this day.
Got like the base model.
He got like the MacBook, right?
It was like whatever.
And this is, we're going back a long time, so whatever, it's not even like comparable
to it.
Like my MacBook Air could like buy and sell this MacBook four hundred times without using
like one core.
Right.
Are we like talking like early, like the first Intel kind of thing?
I think we might be second or third.
No, I think it's second.
Those early Airs were, they were a special kind of slow.
Yeah.
I had a Dell that I was running Ubuntu on at the time and it was bad.
Like until snow leopard came out, it was bad.
I mean, it was just not a good mission.
I cannot believe you just got a snow leopard mention and I just can't believe you till
the day I die where you sell the company again, whichever, you know, either way, I think they're
going to be about the same.
So same.
Yeah.
I don't think you'll ever.
So yeah, I came up in the, uh, the iPhone app gold rush.
I did the code journal thing later on the Mac app store.
That was kind of how I got this guy with the good hair's attention.
And then how long, how long did I ride the iPhone ride for?
Cause you were around for that.
I mean, for as long as you possibly could, I went down hard though.
I messed up.
I, I held on too long.
Yeah.
I mean, I, I mean, have you ever fully let go?
Let's be honest.
When Swift came out, I think, I mean, I think you have it on tape.
I'm pretty sure I let go.
Yeah, that's for sure.
Yeah.
That was rough.
I was pretty upset.
Then there was the, the price bottom dropped out of the market when that's the thing that
is a little bit distant now is it wasn't the norm for an app to be a dollar 99 or to use
a subscription.
Well, right.
When I, when I started, right.
It was totally reasonable.
Like code journal was originally like 10 bucks and then I put it to five, but like that was
cheap and I did it on purpose because I was trying to get like attention, right?
Like I was trying to, for my consulting business.
But like people were selling iPhone apps.
I mean, I think most of our listeners will not believe this, but people were selling
iPhone apps for like 20 bucks.
Yeah.
Like it was just like, it was a real, it was a thing.
I remember there was no one app purchase.
There was no, I ads, there was no, like it was a piece of software and then that changed.
If you really want to know, you can listen to all my moaning and complaining on the back
catalog because I, I, yeah, right.
I went through that like, Oh, I lost 40 grand on windows eight.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
Windows eight.
I admire your restraint and not mentioning that.
Oh, you know, I got it.
I got a jab at you in episode 400.
So I thought I just good for a little while.
And then I tried to do all the cross platform stuff to lower consulting prices.
Did you discover the current that there are not current, but the, the, cause you know,
there was some bot time in there and then you really did focus in on aerospace for awhile.
Did you land on that niche by networking at events?
Kind of.
So this is where, where I have to love up a brother Chris here.
So the first aerospace client came from you, right?
From the show.
It's one of your Linux hippies who doesn't really run Linux.
They bought a Thalia and put windows on it.
So sorry, Carl, Carl, it's been a rough, it's been a rough night for you, Carl.
I don't know what to say.
Sorry, man.
I mean, the other day he's still selling the box.
So yeah, he still sells, sold a thread ripper unit for a amount of money that I could have
bought a car for.
So you know, whatever.
And then yeah, then it was events that they recommended and it turned out, and it took
me a long time to figure this out, like longer than it should have, cause you're right.
I was in love with the whole consumer facing software idea that this niche is people are
willing to pay for stuff and like not fight you about a, you know, $4,000 bill.
They just pay.
Yeah.
They're, they're willing to pay consulting fees that actually pay your bills.
Right.
And like you have to travel.
I mean, COVID, COVID is, I can't say it's messed things up cause we're still up year
over year, but it's, I am very good at podcasting.
No comment necessary, Chris, cause I know I'm terrible.
I am very good at trade shows.
I'm very bad at phone sales and zoom calls and email, which you would think I would be
able to do zoom calls cause it's just like podcasting.
But I had a zoom call and I know, I know he listens, but another listener of the show
who's also a fellow podcaster who I won't name because I don't have permission wants
to hire us for a job.
And I find something disorienting about zoom.
Yeah.
Like I'm, I feel like I'm confused.
I feel like I don't know what I'm doing, but on a podcast or in person, I'm totally cool.
Right.
Like I'm, I'm fine.
I got it.
Not a problem.
I have a similar phenomenon that I experienced and I don't know exactly what it is.
I find zoom calls to be kind of exhausting, not to sound like a wimp, but yes, no, I mean,
I need coffee afterwards.
I'm like tired.
Yeah.
I got a caffeinate before and I got a caffeinate afterwards.
Where here I have literally been live for two hours and 26 minutes and I feel great.
I've been on the live stream for two hours and 30 minutes and I'm totally fine right
now.
Yeah.
I don't know why it's a different, it's a different muscle and it totally is exhausting.
And I, I, I have a couple of times even.
I will admit to convincing the participant to let me call them instead.
And I do a little bit.
Well, I do a lot better.
I feel like over the phone even than I do on a zoom call because I get up and I walk
around and I put like, or you know, earphones on wireless ear pods and I walk around and
I, I gestate like a moron and I, I wouldn't gestate.
Is that the right term?
I don't think so.
Gesture.
And oh, I thought you were pregnant for a minute there.
Yeah, I do.
I gestate ideas like a moron.
I gestate ideas like a moron, but I gesture around and I walk and I pace.
That's exactly what I do.
I pace on speakerphone.
Yeah.
Yes.
And when that's taken away from me, it's, it's, yeah, I'm not as effective.
I was, the reason why I asked is I was having a quasi meeting this morning and we were going
through like sources and material and we were looking at it and like we have, we have a
lot of great people that we know in the community over the years.
And I'm, so I'm not taking away from that, but we haven't really added to the list this
year.
Like our little black book of people, we can, we can email up and say, Hey, tell me the
insight scoop on this hasn't really expanded.
And that's the first time ever that we haven't added people to that list.
You just had like a guy from NASA on, on like Saturday.
Yeah, that was great.
I know that's the, I was going to say, that's the exception.
I was going to say like, come on man, what are you talking about?
That, that, so that was a nice feather in the cap for sure.
But the networking has just dropped off like in terms of what it typically would be, you
know, where I was getting at is if you look at like Alex on self-hosted, he came on board
because I met him at a Linux fest in Texas and we started discussing like our shared
interest on stuff and realized we had a bit of a chemistry and you know, hit it off.
And then he became, you know, he became one of my co-hosts and I just haven't had that
for a while.
I don't mean to bring it back to that again, but I just was wondering if that was pretty
influential on how you got to where you're at right now or where you had been.
I don't know if you're still focusing much on aerospace.
Is that still the case?
Uh, well, I mean, might as well open the kimono all the way, I guess.
Ooh, hello, sir.
You mean the robe, open the robe all the way.
I am aware that I'm getting money off these robes, but at some point dignity matters more.
I know, I know, I know.
Don't worry.
We'll do a mug soon.
You know, I have to tell you the odds of me not loving this robe and wearing it all the
time are zero.
Cause you know what?
I am going to love this robe, right?
I'm going to be like, there will be some tweets of me in the robe with nothing else that will
probably get me banned for a couple of days from Twitter.
Right?
Like that's gonna get you canceled.
I'm going to get, ah, listen, my ex-wife would love to cancel me.
It's all right.
I already, there's already a bunch of them.
Ooh, got the bell, the bell, bell and Carl are getting a lot of work today.
You know, it's a good, that's how, you know, it's a good episode.
Hey Carl, where's my keyboard, right?
He's not going to talk to me anymore.
We should work out a deal.
I'm saying because I think we could sell some keyboards, you know, you know, it's no robe,
but he's going to pack in a robe.
Carl don't do it.
Yeah.
Bundle.
Right.
There you go.
What would you do if system 76 stole your robe idea and just like through their little
robot Zoe, right?
That's Zoe.
It's their robot, the character that they developed for the Thalia.
They should do that.
No, honestly, the world needs more robes.
They should do it.
They should work the idea.
No, the world needs more COVID vaccines, green energy.
Yeah.
But like number four on that list, right?
It's robes, right?
I mean, I can keep you on for another five hours telling you things before.
That's what you want to do.
And I don't even remember the question you asked me.
Hold on.
Cause we were getting to the Komodo about, so I asked you if you're still focusing on
the aerospace or yes, but we accidentally, cause that's how things happen, fell into
food production because of COVID.
So it turns out we had a person reach out to us doing food production over in Canada.
And it turns out that they reached out before like COVID was a thing, right?
But I also live in the state of Florida.
For those who don't know, Florida is famous for alligators, Florida man and Disney world,
but also like a tremendous amount of agriculture, like a shocking amount of agriculture.
But COVID, when you have a bunch of workers living in basically barracks, uh, that's
a problem, right?
Because one guy or girl gets, or one guy or gal gets COVID and potentially 50 of them
have it and your entire farm is, uh, screwed.
Of course.
If you can embed, God damn it, Python, sure.
Ruby is better.
If you can embed Python into, uh, let's say IOT devices and you can run a Python flask,
big web servers, and you can have like smart.net based UWP tablet apps for the form.
I'm going to use the word Foreman, but all these different companies have different names,
but like supervisors.
Yeah.
It turns out you can basically minimize your manual labor, therefore your risk of COVID
exposure while keeping your crop yield up.
And I don't want to get too much into agriculture.
One I've had to learn a lot about it in the last year, but it's one of those things that,
you know, Chris, I'm sure you go to the grocery store, you buy some lettuce, you buy some
strawberries, you know, raspberries, raspberries.
Okay.
Well, we're, we're, we're based in plant city.
So strawberries are the main crop, but, uh, we actually have the strawberry festival,
believe it or not.
You don't think anything of it, right?
But there's actually hundreds of people working on that farm, right?
Our whole shtick now is we're minimizing that work.
So basically on the aviation side, we're killing people on the other side.
We're feeding people.
So I don't know where that leaves me.
I mean, I got to tell you when, when, when I die, St. Peter is going to be like, I don't
know, man.
Got a lot of stuff here.
Yeah.
You know, so you can point, you know, you can say, Oh, I answered some questions on
a podcast.
That might, that might've been some good, like I told the truth.
He's like, yeah, you weren't supposed to do that either though.
So
Datadog.com slash CoderRadio, this episode is sponsored by Datadog, the unified monitoring
analytics platform for comprehensive visibility into your entire stack.
If you have on-premises, if you have cloud, if you have a hybrid, something in between,
maybe multiple clouds, get a unified view into all of it, quickly analyze the performance
of your Linux servers in real time and get dashboards that you can move around and build
to get the information that you need.
If you're creating an application, if you're trying to monitor something in production,
wouldn't it be nice to have analytics that are easy to understand and share with your
team.
So that way you can communicate your needs to them.
That's what Datadog does for you.
And they help you troubleshoot issues in seconds with these unified metrics and traces and
logs.
You can look at all of the environment in one snapshot, look inside a container, look
at the Linux server and look at the application performance as well.
And then additionally, they have over 400 integrations, just turnkey integrations to
get Datadog insights into your application.
You combine that with the server metrics, your performance, and you get it all into
a customizable dashboard.
And you can take actual action on what you see.
But you got to get started.
So go to datadog.com slash coderadio.
If you set up one dashboard, you now qualify for some free swag, a Datadog t-shirt, but
you got to go to datadog.com slash coderadio.
This is a tool to allow you to communicate.
I say that because that's how Datadog started, as a way for the developers to communicate
to the sysadmins.
That's such a quintessential problem, communication.
And to have a tool, analytics and data base that you can use to communicate with your
teams, that's worth its weight in gold.
So just get started, just see what it can do.
Go to datadog.com slash coderadio.
All right, Mr. Dominic, one last thing for you before we go.
You mentioned this at the top of the show, does the release of.NET 6, which is getting
closer and closer, preview one is out, I think today as we record.
So it'll be a few days by the time people hear this.
It's out, it's close, this is it.
This is like them bringing the last several six years or so of work together.
So it's the promise of taking a lot of the, what is it, Xamarin, X-Marion, the X-Marion
tools bringing a lot of that and actually bringing it into.NET and creating something
that's actually usable for desktop, web, cloud, mobile, gaming, IoT, Windows, Linux,
Android, iOS, Mac, even Apple TVs on the list.
I mean, this is it, it's here, at least in preview.
I'm just kind of, I don't know, curious to get your take on.NET 6 and their new preview.
So I'm trying to be a little careful here.
I have not tried the preview yet.
It's going to be a big like asterisk on this.
You know, I have scars from the Java applet days and I do worry that.NET is getting a
little too cross platformy, but I have no evidence of that.
Like I have no reason to think that other than just.
It seems like they're promising the impossible.
Well, it seems like they're promising a lot and not showing much yet, right?
So it's almost a premature, I mean, all right.
One of my concerns just to kind of put the cards on the table is at some point does it
become too fractured in a way, right?
Where there is, it's this big unified framework, but there's all these little asterisks at
all, but are you on iOS?
Oh, but are you on Android?
Oh, but are you on Windows?
Oh.
It's really a bunch of different tools that have kind of been relabeled and brought together
is kind of like a crockpot of different stuff in.NET.
It feels an awful lot like the old Java promises of write once run everywhere.
Yeah.
Only this time it's coming from Microsoft.
Well, sure.
But like, you know, anybody could promise you anything, right?
I mean, yeah, I'm just saying like, yeah, yeah, no, I do agree.
I was always reading through their announcement because it, yeah, like I said, it came out
just as we're about when we're recording.
And you know, they go through all the standard stuff, but they say our unification efforts
offer something for all.NET developers.
If you're a desktop app developer, there are new opportunities for you to reach new users.
If you're a mobile app developer, you'll benefit from using mainline.NET tools and APIs while
targeting iOS and Android platforms.
If you're a web or cloud developer, it will be easier to expose services and.NET mobile
and apps that share code with them.
I mean, they're really pushing on that.
And I think we've had a good sense that when.NET Core came out and they started working
towards this, this was the ultimate scenario is taking these tools that they've invested
in over the years and bringing them in there.
I mean, even WebAssemblies in this mix, it's all encompassing.
Unlike you, I kind of have a little bit more of a positive take on it.
It seems like Microsoft has taken really a decade to kind of sift through all of this
and pull it all together.
And then what's really happened now is.NET 6 is really kind of like it's like an umbrella
of this stuff that you can do now.
And so when you're a.NET developer, it's going to mean a whole bunch of other stuff
all of a sudden.
And then on top of that, they have the pipeline, right?
They have the tools on the desktop.
They have the tools in the cloud.
They have GitHub.
I think in a way, I am more bullish on what Microsoft is doing here than I have ever
been on anything I have seen them do.
And I can clearly see the hallmarks of how this benefits Azure.
I can see how this benefits their GitHub platform.
I can see how this makes more Microsoft developers.
I can see how this sells more Windows licenses and Visual Studio licenses, like check every
box.
All right.
But what do they want?
Like, this is my whole problem with Microsoft right now.
What the hell do they want?
Are they trying to get you to use Windows or trying to get you to pay for Visual Studio
Pro?
Are they trying to get you to?
This is a respin of an idea that I think I rolled out on the show a while ago.
So it's been a couple of years, but I've thought about this.
And this isn't the right analogy, but I think this is the only way to state it where it'll
click.
It's like they want to recreate the magic of Windows, but they want to be Windows for
developers.
They want to bring all of this stuff together, and they don't care if you're targeting Android.
Have at it, Haas.
If you want to make TVOS apps, have at it.
But you're using a Microsoft editor to do it.
You're using a Microsoft developer platform to put a repo to store your code.
And you're using.NET as the back end, and you're using the.NET SDK and tools.
I just think it's Microsoft wins for every Android device that uses this or every TVOS
device.
They don't need you running Windows, but if you want to run Windows, it's going to be
great.
And I think it's so clever it's devious because they're creating something that's useful.
It's competitive in the market.
It answers problems that developers have and corporations, especially enterprises, while
also kind of ensuring that they stay relevant in the game even when people are done with
the desktop entirely.
Like this, essentially, what I think this.NET umbrella does and combining it with Azure
and GitHub and everything else, sorry, sorry, sorry, but it's just going to have to be said
over and over again for a little bit.
When they're all done, they don't even need Windows.
They don't even need Windows at all.
Windows can just fade away, and they're totally good because the world will be developing
for IoT, for the web, for mobile, and for the desktop using their tools.
And even if it isn't totally market dominant, they're probably over time going to be able
to carve out a nice, sizable, long-term percentage, which will include a ton of businesses and
enterprises, dark matter developers, and people on the front lines like yourself that are
just building shops around this tool chain because it's all there.
Every piece of the pipeline is there for you.
You can build a shop around all of these tools.
It's all there for you.
And you can just start executing.
I guess.
I mean, I know months ago, or, oh my God, like over a year ago, we talked about, it
was all about that sweet Azure manna raining from heaven.
Mm-hmm.
But...
They've got to om-nom that Azure manna.
Om-nom.
I guess.
All right.
I guess I'm with you.
I sort of feel like I want Windows to get better, and everything you've described is
it's not really going to get better.
They don't need it to now.
And I think they...
Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, it's deviously clever, I think.
I'm very impressed with the strategy because you just don't normally see it.
So you don't normally see a company be able to shift like this in such a clever way.
Usually it's just a large ship, and once it's set up and going in a direction, it goes in
that direction forever.
Maybe I'm wrong, but...
No, I think you're right.
I mean, I think that's the whole thing is they don't care, which I mean, we're going
way over.
If you're a.NET developer today, should you be scared?
I mean, I don't think so.
Look at what they're trying to target.
That's everything.
They're literally trying to...
That's every platform that exists, from WebAssembly to IoT.
Right.
That's the thing.
I kind of worry that they're trying to be everything to everyone, and it's just not
going to work.
That sounds like Microsoft to a T though, and it will work well enough for a large chunk
of business, for a large chunk of the market.
It will do the job, and it will do the job well enough.
The Surface tablets, we do sell development for them at TMB, at the bad botter, because
they make sense.
But the only reason they make sense is because Android tablets are hot garbage.
Please send your emails to alan at jupyterbroadcasting.com, and because Apple is just a pain in the ass
about enterprise distribution, right?
If Apple would just not have that policy, I would much prefer develop for iPads.
Have you heard of our friends over at Google with their Chrome OS?
Thank you for listening today.
I'm at Jumanuku on Twitter.
He's at Chris Lass.
All right.
Yeah.
Also, thanks to our members.
We should say...
I don't know if we said it last week, but thank you to our members over at coderqa.co.
We appreciate our members.
Thank you very much.
Go get your coderlies.
Yeah.
At the bad botter, Inc.'s the company.
Anything else you want to plug?
I have a book review coming up for Jay LaCroix, a friend of the show, and we met him at System
76...
Or I met him at System 76 a couple of years ago.
He's mastering Ubuntu Server, so that should be up this week.
Cool.
On dominicm.com.
Great guy.
Linux podcaster.
Linux YouTuber.
And sounds like if somebody is administering an Ubuntu server, a very useful resource.
Our links to the stuff we talked about today, you'll find that at coder.show slash 402.
Surprisingly, there's a lot of great things over there at coder.show.
You can find our RSS feeds for all the different ways to subscribe.
You can get our contact form if you'd like to send us in some feedback.
That's a huge part of our show, and we really appreciate that.
And of course, links to previous episodes all over at coder.show, including this one.
I'd encourage you to hang out live if you have some time on a Monday evening.
We do this show starting around 5 PM Pacific, 8 PM Eastern over at jblive.tv.
I'm usually dorking around on the stream, and then Mike shows up about the half hour
mark and we kick off.
And it's a Coder happy hour.
Share drinks and hang out with friends at jblive.tv on a Monday.
But thanks for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio program.
We appreciate every single one of you for downloading this here podcast and sharing
it with your friends, and we'll see you right back here next week.