episode 42 the title can mean only one thing yes it is a hitchhiker's guide to the galaxy reference
oh and i didn't bring my towel oh well don't panic
chris in the badger mornings all right let's go let's go let's get up or whatever you happen
to listen to it i guess on self-hosted dot show oh we're bringing that back are we okay cool
i'm going in with this i love this we are the week i think you and i would have a great a.m
morning show we need to lean into that a bit more yeah we do we'd be doing the traffic on the 15s
and uh we'd also be taking people's tech questions and uh discussing the news of the day and we'd
have a movie review segment and a tv review segment i know you're going to give us a uh
surprise tv review later in the show yeah i might have interrupted an interview with
an impromptu movie review yes it just makes me laugh i love it alex but you know i think
we'd have a great morning show and we'd have our friends on right like we'd call alan on and we'd
give him a hard time about freebsd that'd be pretty great yes that would be rather awkward
at the moment wouldn't it yeah yeah we'd ask him if he's got wire guard set up so that way we could
do we could do it over at wire guard uh we should put a link in the show notes so people don't know
what we're talking about oh yeah quick too long didn't read wire guard nearly got merged into the
bsd kernel and the code was of questionable quality so if you have any questions about that
there is a link in the show notes to jim salter's ars technica breakdown of this you will probably
come away rather salty with bsd just full warning so um yeah enjoy that but in the meantime i want
to say thanks to a cloud guru for sponsoring this here episode they are the learning in cloud linux
and other modern tech skills hundreds of courses and thousands of hands-on labs get certified get
hired get learning at a cloud guru dot com but speaking of that post over at ars technica you
also had a new post over at ars technica and this is a brilliant one how to achieve smart home
nirvana or home automation without a subscription also very clever were you stuck between two titles
alex and congratulations also on your first post at ars technica thank you yes that was rather a
life box ticked last week it was a war of two titles wasn't it it was actually i was working
with their editors and they had about six titles to choose from so we ended up picking two halves
of two different titles that didn't belong together and then kind of like munging them
together wow could you imagine having people like help us come up with titles like you and i like
have to like call each other up after the show and be like what are we going to call this one
we completely forget we walk away and don't even title the show we do yeah all the time
hey so did you see in the news this week that nvidia have finally seen sense and unlocked their
gpu drivers for pass-through i did see this in the news i didn't go too far into it because i
figured i'd pick your brain this must be a shot in the arm for virtualization i'd say so yeah
to recap you know the high level of why this is a big deal nvidia previously locked down their
consumer graphics cards from being air quotes supported are on gpu pass-through so they would
show an error code 43 an infamous error code 43 in the windows device manager rather than loading
and just working as normal so what you would have to do is hide the fact that the vm was running as
a vm from the vm which has some minor performance implications uh only only minor and but what this
does from from nvidia is it basically says yeah okay guys cool go ahead and take our consumer
level graphics cards pass them through to you know guests and do gaming and what have you and
you know go nuts i don't even know if i have a rig to try this on these days alex have you
had a chance to try this i don't actually run pass-through very much these days uh i ended up
basically giving up because you you and i talked about this a long time ago on linux unplug 308
and we talked about all the different rigmarole that surrounds pci pass-through and all of that
still applies even with this nvidia news all of that still applies um so you're going to need a
way of switching your monitor inputs of switching your keyboard and mouse inputs and all that kind
of stuff and i have 144 hertz gaming monitor in front of me here and trying to find a kvm switch
that can support that and thunderbolt from my macbook pro it it just it's just a pain in the
bum so i ended up uh just dual booting these days you know i when i want to do some windows
stuff i reboot and when i want to do some linux stuff i reboot and it's it's it's fine it's a bit
of a pain but it's fine so yeah there is a line where you have to go how much is it worth
virtualizing versus just dual booting i i totally get that that's a line i don't really often cross
like i'm legitimately at a loss of of even i don't know why i'd install windows right now i don't
think i've i don't think i've installed windows i definitely haven't installed it in 2021 and i
don't know if i installed it i must have at least installed it once in 2020 but maybe that was it
i really have over the years just sort of i'm not this is not a brag i just it's because i have in
other places used max for special tools that other people probably would have used a windows box so
it's not like i have some superpower but it's just i have over the times just kind of migrated
completely away from windows yeah the only things i really use it for is fusion 360 so 3d modeling
for my my printing stuff which i can also do on the mac as well so i don't really need windows
there i use it for blue iris as we often talk about on a separate system i could see that
in terms of the desktop yeah i mean vs code takes care of a lot of my coding stuff wsl
2 takes care of a lot of the ssh type stuff and the new windows terminal is actually quite nice
so i mean i spend a lot more time in windows than i think i admit to myself these days even though
it doesn't really feel like windows anymore because they've basically shoehorned linux onto
the side of it okay i feel like there's also an elephant in the room this week you and i have
talked about ubiquity gear a bit on this show and they have been in the news in a bad way some
serious security potential leaks i guess according to someone that brian krebs spoke to on his blog
he writes that a cyber criminal gained administrative access to ubiquity's aws databases via stolen
credentials uh perhaps like an employee's last pass account it looks like and then got root
admin access that's what they say to the aws accounts s3 buckets application logs secrets
for single sign-on cookies all databases including databases that include user credentials
there's even according to some people who've come forward supposedly been backdoor software that
they found that ubiquity it staff found um that the the situation is so serious that certain people
have been fired there's there's a lot going on and i'm wondering how you feel somebody who's
i think running a fair amount of their gear i certainly am yeah i have three access points
in this house i have uh half a dozen that i manage in england for my family across two or three
different you know houses and you know that from that perspective having a centralized controller
where all of these devices talk back to that runs on linode is is for me very convenient and so far
as i understand it anyway there is no risk to people who self-host the unify controller
right if however you're running one of their cloud keys or a dream machine or something that requires
you to authenticate with their cloud you may well want to change some passwords and possibly even
consider you know not using ubiquity stuff in that manner anymore because you know the manner of the
breach was that an employee's aws s3 bucket key was compromised so yeah we have to assume that
the attackers got access to everything stored passwords i mean they won't may well be hashed
and salted but we can break passwords with enough compute you know um application logs databases
uh database credentials all of that stuff that's in there even just ip ip records it's all bad it's
all really bad alex and that's kind of where i was going with this is i quietly for the last couple
of years have been progressively more and more disappointed with ubiquity while my friends like
you and others around me have seemed pretty solid with them i've been wondering if things haven't
been getting a little sour i don't feel like their latest batch of products have been that solid
i have not liked some of their answers around the controller limitations uh and some of their
solutions and it just seemed like a power grab in some circumstances and it seems like this is an
indication that not all is well in hq the qa has for sure been declining you know there's been
several firmware upgrades for the actual ap's themselves as well as the controller software
that have nuked people's databases and history and stuff like that so i wonder if maybe just some
original people left the company a while ago and it's been in decline or if their prioritization
has changed but where do you go to like what what do you change to well i actually asked jim on
twitter what he thought and he's been recommending there's a bunch of tp link devices and uh tom
from lawrence systems just got a bunch in to review on youtube so if you're interested in some
ubiquity alternatives they are out there but i'll tell you what worries me the most about this
breach it's not necessarily that it happened because unfortunately these things are going to
happen at some point to every company what matters more is how a company responds and ubiquity is
and ubiquity tried to basically cover this up they didn't deny i suppose is more accurate they
didn't deny these claims and it took them several days more than a week to admit responsibility and
basically inform their user base that some of their stuff might be boned yeah and on top of
that it seems like it's taken some insiders to come out and leak information to well-known people
like krebs to get the complete picture which is disappointing yeah i think i think you just hit
the nail on the head there is disappointing i mean ubiquity made their name through
basically making people realize how crappy consumer grade gear is and uh you know they're
providing cisco grade ideas and hardware for consumer sort of grade prices but with these
kinds of breaches and and behavior as a company i'm i'm struggling i mean the access point that
i'm looking at behind my monitor here i first installed into a house that i lived three houses
ago uh six six seven years ago and it's it's not mr b it still works perfectly it's had all the
firmware updates and that kind of stuff but there was that one issue with the controller a few months
ago where i ended up having to completely rebuild my unify controller because of poor software qa
it's critical infrastructure in my house okay it's not a hotel it's not a commercial setting
where a lot of people do deploy unify gear into but if it happens to me it's going to happen to
those people as well and it only takes one or two or three incidents before your your brand name is
completely trashed and people are already talking about just going back to consumer grade stuff like
mesh networks like aero and you know all these other you know not as technically accomplished
solutions that have you know poe backhaul and stuff like that in favor of something that is
possibly even more leaky because it requires more cloud connectivity i don't know uh what's
the solution i'm probably just going to wait and see how this turns out for the next six months
but my next ap will probably not be a unify one wouldn't it be something if the community stepped
forward and built something that we could flash again mesh networks be amazing oh it'd be cool i
tell you what if somehow we could open these devices up these unify devices we all already
have and then put like a tasmota style completely divorcing ourselves of unify of ubiquity sorry
you know own the hardware i keep banging on about this don't i but own the hardware it's
not dependent on a cloud service then it does seem like that is exactly what we need it's
something we could reflash and load a common os on that has a common set of standards and interfaces
and a web ui like you used to do with the old linksys routers you know those things are still
being sold today those old linksys routers open wrt yeah we just need a newer version of that
something more powerful with different hardware options essentially like the ubiquity options
because you're right it's you need something that for folks that want to run poe and and then you
know plug a plug a ap at the end of a barn somewhere at the end of a building somewhere
and they can only run one cable like you got to have something for that solution i think your
use case too where you've got several buildings and you want to manage all of the ap's with one
interface is also totally legitimate and extremely common it's so useful when my dad rings me up and
he's like oh my wi-fi is not working in the bedroom i can go in and see the ap has dropped
from gigabit down to megabit for example and i can oh we just need to reboot the the ap and
and we're good to go but there's a way to do that alex you know and get that central
dashboard i know you don't use it much but uh something we should talk about at some point on
the show i maybe is cockpit one of the things i appreciate about cockpit is they have come up with
a way to allow you to manage multiple servers you go you can go to one ui though log into one one
web server and you can you can select all your servers and manage them and it has to be set up
in a special way and there's some security precautions you have to take but it's it's a
very secure setup and so maybe something like that could be done i don't know maybe somebody
out there in the community knows maybe so i found out this week that a device i purchased nearly two
years ago on some black friday sale you know i i bought it thinking oh yeah this is this is going
to solve all my problems with my fans because um quite often when you buy a server grade motherboard
the fan control headers are designed for server grade fans which spin at crazy high rpms and draw
crazy amounts of of current and stuff like that and so when you put a consumer grade fan on one
of these motherboards it kind of goes uh ramps up and then ramps down and ramps up and ramps down
because it's not getting enough of a signal to think it's got enough rpms anyway it's this whole
thing so i bought this device called the corsair commander pro plugs into a usb header on the
motherboard controls led lighting it controls um fans and uh has some temperature probes attached
to it but the downside was this device was windows only to my surprise and absolute delight six
months ago this device has been added to the linux kernel there's been a driver added to the
linux kernel so you can now natively control fans via a usb header on linux i love it when that
happens yeah and you're always surprised like my little thing the little thing that i care about
that's coming that's always the best feeling so i wrote a small blog post about it it doesn't
require an awful lot of elbow grease to get set up but you do need to have the 5.9 or later kernel
and then you need to make sure you've got lm sensors installed and then there's a couple
of other instructions in the blog post about how you configure the pwm profiles
and then once you've done that you just enable the fan control service i mean i'm using a very
tiny tiny little archvm on my esxi host it's i think it's using 256 megs of ram for example
and four gigabytes of disk perfect use case for arch because i don't want anything else
and i want a modern kernel and and that's exactly what arch gives me there lino.com slash ssh go
there to get 100 and 68 credit towards a new account and of course you support the show 100
and that's a lot you can really try out linode and you support the self-hosted podcast that's
like a win-win for everybody linode is our cloud server provider when we're building or
any any kind of testing that we're doing we do it on linode and because the price is so great
it makes it possible for a small team to have killer infrastructure that's one of the things
that i feel like is our secret sauce here at jb is we we can have access to infrastructure that is
crazy fast 11 data centers around the world really fast network connections really fast machines
their dedicated cpu rigs have those amd epic cpus in them and they have been independently
verified as some of the fastest cpus in cloud computing but one of the things i think that's
great about them is when i'm building or testing something they have a ton of distributions to
choose from basically all the distributions you'd want to deploy and even some i'm not sure you'd
want to deploy in production arch but are there and i extremely appreciate that but what i what
i really get about linode is their love for linux that's what got them into this that's why they
started in 2003 is because they were in love with the technology itself they saw where it was going
what virtualization was going to bring to the market and so they got in before aws or anyone
else they started so long ago and yet they don't do like a million things they're not like a bookstore
and a movie platform they really just focus on doing the absolute best cloud computing possible
and they're independently owned even today and they're dedicated to offering the best virtualized
cloud computing if it runs on linux it runs on linode also check a link on our show notes we'll
have a link to their top docs talk that's right top docs talk and they have one about the benefits
of using infrastructure as code and you know that's something we're big fans of so check in
the notes for that linode.com slash ssh go there support the show get 100 in 60 day credit and of
course check out all the features of linode linode.com slash ssh well a few weeks ago i
promised something along the lines of a self-hosted community deep dive you know every so often we're
going to have somebody from the self-hosted community come on and chat with us and sort of
talk about the apps they run why they run them you know what they what they wish that they set up did
that it doesn't currently do and a lot of hopefully discussions about why they made some of
the decisions that they made hopefully it'll be an interesting portal into some of our community
members for you and the first volunteer or the first glutton for punishment is the orange one
from our discord server hey jake how you doing hi yeah i think i feel like maybe the correct term
for this is victim um yes yes yes but yeah no it's it's great it's great to be here it's
it's gonna be good well it's been interesting trying to schedule three different people in
three different time zones so thank you for joining us at i think what is 10 30 p.m uk time
yeah it's 10 30 i've got to be up in nine hours for another seven and a half hours of work that
used to be your life alex yeah pre-dad life huh sleep is a distant memory all right so why don't
we dive in with the first question then and let's talk a little bit about your hardware setup so
specifically talking about the stuff you have at home and things like that talk us through some of
the stuff you've got there most of my setup is at at home the sort of self-hosting life is very much
i run everything on on my lan sort of as normal um most of my setup is a single uh single machine
because running things over the network is a bit a bit funky my main rig is a ryzen uh 3000 series
3700x is the sort of beating heart of it yeah various other parts it runs proxmox because
virtual machines are great do you use vms for a lot of stuff because i know you're into sort of
the one big vm we often have this discussion on discord about the one big vm versus lots of smaller
like lxc containers and docker containers and things like that what's uh what's your philosophy
on that if i'm running a hypervisor with vms i'd rather not do that i'd rather have sort of
everything nicely containerized to fully uh take advantage of vms in their sort of
natural habitat of what they're good for so i think my setup is currently six vms or so spread
most of the different uses there is still one single lxc container which runs docker which has
most of my docker applications in there's probably 10 or so containers running under that besides
that i've got a separate one for um my monitoring applications that would be prometheus again your
advice grafana i've got a separate vm for home assistant which runs home assistant os couple
other ones one which deals with uh ingress coming into my house which is an interesting setup
because i'm sure we'll touch on later and yeah various other little things the other place i've
diverted away from what you've previously done is i've also moved the storage out of the one
big vm and so storage is handled directly on the host why is that then the main reason for that is
i tried running true nas in a vm and it it installed great it i could access all my files
the issue was that performance was horrible absolutely horrible um i just got latency spikes
everywhere next cloud ground to halt uh sq lite over nfs is a really really bad time i don't
recommend it to anyone so talk us through that a little bit more than you know uh performance was
was bad were you passing through a disk controller to that vm or or what were you doing so from some
advice i got from i'm sorry i can't remember who it was on the self-hosted discord uh suggested
using uh an lsi xba that xba i then passed in through regular pci pass through into true nas
from there uh regular mounted a very small two drive zfs pool exposed via true nas's built-in
nfs sharing which was super easy to do which is great mounted that as normal through etsy fs tab
and then from there just pointing my docker containers at it as if it was a directory
in that container thing because it was running entirely over the internal network inside the
machine latency wise it was absolutely tiny you're talking like fractions of milliseconds but for
some unknown reason it didn't like it now that might be because i went a little bit insane and
decided to run true nas scale rather than true nas directly so this may be a performance regression
with true nas scale because at the time i ran it was in alpha and we know full well don't run alpha
software but i did anyway just to try it is scale the bsd one and core is is the linux one or is it
the way around i can never remember other way around so scale is the linuxy one which at the
time was in alpha so i tried it it didn't work great yes i have some thoughts on bsd this week
after the whole wire guard kernel merge thing but let's let's not derail your yeah that that's not
a fun discussion it's all embarrassing after i tried scale out it it didn't work too well for
me and i didn't want to try uh porting over to the actual core version of true nas because
keeping going with that process it meant i had to deal with issues where that one storage vm as it
were would have to stay up and alive sort of all the time and if i needed to reboot that machine
that vm even i would have to reboot sort of everything in the entire machine which felt a bit
like a faff and eventually i concluded well if i want high performance i want things to be easy
then if i move the storage on to the actual host hypervisor under proxmox proxmox has built-in
support for zfs because the os is on zfs so just works it means latency is nice and low and because
the majority of my applications live in lxc there's the nice benefit of rather than using
nfs to mount all of my data i can use bind mounts and bind mounts are you have no network latency
because it's just passing directories into containers in much the same way that you give
bind mounts to docker containers there's no extra latency extra overhead extra complexity
around that it just works so sounds like a lot of a lot of different application uses and it
sounds like you have a pretty distinct line between what is a container and what should be a vm when
i see complexity like this i start to wonder like what's your backup strategy looking like
my backup strategy at the moment is on that one docker lxc there is a single instance of duplicati
which backs up because eat that lxc specifically has access to my entire zfs pool i can just take
the entire pool compress it up with duplicati and push it up to currently there's a mixture of back
blaze and s3 for various bits depending on how much i care about it i intend at some point in the
maybe not too distant future to switch parts of that out to restic ah good man i was just about
to ask you about that duplicati is such a pain in the ass sometimes and it you know it runs fine
for weeks and weeks and then you log in and have a look at it and in the intervening time stuff's
just broken for seemingly no reason and it breaks silently and can only configure it through the ui
which you know how much i love that so restic i think is something i'm really going to be looking
into a lot in the future with uh minio with the s3 back end as well so you can you can use restic
with that so you use backblaze and a little bit of s3 so is that amazon s3 uh yeah wow made of
money boy there's there's like a couple hundred meg in there just because oh okay then i was
testing stuff like this was before when i was only backing up like the tiny bits and i concluded
well if i'm just backing up the tiny bits i might as well back up everything well object storage
is perfect for that exactly 100 let me ask you this then because i'm picturing the audience
somebody's out there building their backup strategy right now if you were going to start
again today start fresh how would you build it better what would you do differently what message
would you send a past version of yourself past version would definitely be installed backups
sooner um i'm very glad that i've never had a case where i've had to actually restore from
an off-site backup i had one case where i had to restore from an on-site backup
which i still think is sort of a bug in docker where i was messing around with some weird
dockery stuff and i went to log into nextcloud a few hours later and the entire nextcloud bind
mount was empty completely empty no app data no files no nothing just gone i have no idea
why it happened fortunately that morning i had done an on-site backup to a disconnected hard drive
so a few hours of syncing files back i lost as far as i'm aware no real data because i'd not
made any changes but that that was not fun so definitely anyone listening i think alan jude
says it best if it doesn't exist in three places it doesn't exist at all oh you had to go and
reference alan huh yeah i kind of did but it's also it's such a good point is that now my data
exists on my server it also exists using zfs send to a random shuck hard drive sitting on my desk
good man and then as well like i say back up to backblaze which has been absolutely great i did
for a small amount of time decide hey what if i roll my own backblaze would not recommend it uh i
had a ten dollar machine from kim sufi which are a very cheap dedicated server host out of france
they're a subsidiary of ovh and we all know how ovh are doing right now yeah i hear their business
is on fire at the minute oh alex too soon too soon too soon hey i thought it was funny yes i
tried running that and minio and it worked fine but once i realized that i was backing up a server
i owned to a server i owned it was great but it was the kim sufi box was a bit finicky it was
low powered minio as tiny as it is it's much more resource heavy than i would expect it to be so
should we talk a little bit about some of your favorite self-hosted apps top three maybe oh so
i'd have to say the one i definitely use the most is uh ttrss which is an rss reader my rss reader
of choice i do most of my content consumption via rss all of my youtube consumption is entirely via
rss because youtube's algorithms and suggestions and things like that are just quite frankly
terrible that's amazing i think um more people should do this because i watched a film the
other night called the social dilemma which talks about how insidious those algorithms are in
controlling what you see and what you eventually what you think and what you believe you know the
ultimate conclusion if anybody's on the fence as to whether you know facebook and google and twitter
and what have you are forces for good in the world or not uh i recommend watching the social
dilemma it might change your mind anyway as you were that's definitely one for my watch list as
well um yeah so ttrss is definitely way up there what clients do you use for that i actually just
entirely use the web ui mostly cool it's easy and it works other than ttrss i would have to say next
cloud is currently quite far up there that's been a really nice tool for just accessing files it's a
little bit heavy for my needs but it is the plugins are great it's fast enough and the sync
clients when they work they work really really well see everybody always says this like oh the
syncs a bit hit and miss i know chris you've had some actual experience with it losing data for you
but i've used it now for i guess three years solid and it's just next file's just been really really
reliable for me so i've only had two issues with it one is that it doesn't do uh partial syncs
so if you modify a small part in a very large file it will sync the entirety of the large file
i don't deal with large files but i suspect if you guys are pushing around very large mp3s or mp4s
uncompressed media yeah then it can be really really slow the other issue i've had or i did
have which i haven't had in a while is it would keep forgetting who i am oh no big deal right
i know who i am but it just forgets and it gets very difficult to sync anything if it just
forgets who you are it'll just keep logging me out i'd love to see them add land sync too
because that's a fantastic feature when you when you power up a laptop and it hasn't been on the
internet for maybe a week or more if you can sync from other nodes on the network directly it's
way faster and it reduces the demand on your internet connection i love that feature about
dropbox also i think dropbox has some intelligence about the order in which they sync files and what
operations sync first versus what operations can be queued where nextcloud's c sync subsystem
doesn't seem to support that so we've had situations where the nextcloud server is kind
of like processing and sinking down some directory cleanup that we've done and maybe it's a significant
amount of like just reorganizing or something and the client has to process all of those changes
and operate all of those file system operations before it will process the sync command to send
the new files up to the server and so we've literally just had editors on the other side
waiting for files and so that stunk but what we did is we just changed the way we operate we don't
make those kinds of changes on any kind of show day anymore we you know we wait and we make sure
we do it like with a couple of day buffer and we've adjusted the way we operate and it's we've
made it work now we've been using it for uh i mean i don't know alex do you remember since the since
the sprint in 2019 right yes and since i appeared yeah roughly yeah right since we brainstormed and
started this show so and and uh it's been running but yeah it isn't ideal so what's your last pick
then it's a project i've been involved with a little bit in sort of contributing and writing
content for uh which is probably also going to be a bit of a sore subject for some people uh it's an
application called plausible plausible is a self-hosted google analytics alternative it's
backed by a company there's a hosted offering it's really really nice the ui is beautiful
it's fully gdpr compliant so it only tracks the data that it needs to do to do its job it doesn't
track things around various other places it's entirely self-hosted so i run my own instance
which tracks my own websites it doesn't track anything else and what that means is i can see
which pages are getting the most traction which ones aren't where people are coming from and
that's about it that looks great yeah really nice it's really nice i highly recommend it
to anyone that's got a website especially if they're running google analytics and want to
sort of take back some of their control from google and various other companies like that
uh-oh ding dong you said it take back control my that's a trigger phrase for me
something something brexit anyway oh it says the guy who's immigrated to the states to the
guy who's still over there incredible uh-huh awkward one final question for you though jake
and it's the one everybody's been waiting for it's the how many terabytes on your land question
oh yeah oh so this is going to be an interesting one i'm going for the opposite record to what
people are probably expecting um to have from guests on here i'm going for the lowest result
possible so my current pool has four terabytes in wow i love this idea because why the headache if
you don't need it right it's two four terabyte seagate drives they've been working pretty well
for my use case there's only 200 gig on the pool so i've got ample storage space i've got ample
space to grow it's been working absolutely flawlessly there is an additional single six
terabyte drive which currently houses all of my media i need to get that into a pool of some kind
as quick as possible because i can see alex's face physically pained as i say that perfect media
server.com yeah i know where to go it's motor fs snap raid are two things yeah reasonably high up
on my list of things to do when i get a free second but yeah four terabytes is exactly just
about enough for my needs and i don't really have any intention of growing that anytime soon so i'm
sticking right here at the bottom of the list so far okay well there's no shame in that i mean you
could be like the michael gambon of uh terabytes huh uh that's an old top gear reference for some
people that don't know what i'm talking about so thanks very much for coming on jake it was
really nice to talk to you and please let us know from from the audience like if number one you
would like to be you know one of these community spotlights that we're going to do what you thought
of the segment let us know as well if it's something you'd like to see us do more of let
us know if it's something you didn't like well maybe keep that opinion to yourself wow is there
anywhere else you'd like to send people jake you know twitter or your personal blog that i know
you write a lot of yeah i believe you described me as a quote prolific blogger and many people who
hang out on the discord know i write quite a lot uh my website is theorangeone.net which i'm sure
will be in the show notes uh my twitter account as well is at realorangeone which i suspect as well
will be in the show notes well jake thank you a quick thank you to cloud guru for sponsoring
this episode and i'd like you to know about their powershell core for linux admins course
it's an intermediate level course and it teaches you the concepts of using powershell core with
linux this could be game changing if you're in a multi-platform environment and the course includes
of course administration installing docker working with the sql server even managing azure instances
as well as integrating all with visual studio code there's a lot there so you'll have to click
the link in our show notes that'll be at selfhosted.show slash 42 and you'll see the
powershell core for linux admins course and thanks to a cloud guru for sponsoring this episode and of
course a big thanks to our members over at selfhosted.show slash sre you can go there to
support the show and get a limited ad feed we often talk as well in the post show about some
little knickknacks in our lives and things that are going on uh so you get a little bonus show
little bonus extra content yeah selfhosted.show slash sre and you can also find the contact page
at selfhosted.show slash contact that's the place to get in touch with us i'm on twitter as well you
can get me there i'm at chris las and i'm there at ironic badger and don't forget the show at
selfhosted show so thanks for listening everyone that was selfhosted.show slash 42