Alex I'm checking my email every single day right now because my Starlink kit is on its way
There's gonna be a game changer for me. I think so. Yeah, like you've unlocked a
Level like you've one upped life if you've got Starlink, you know, it's funny as I started thinking, you know
Like now I need to get serious about a home PC setup
I can always like my work laptop will do or or an iPad will do
But if I'm gonna have like real internet at home now, I got to have like a real PC to connect to that. So
How's it gonna work? Cuz my understanding of Starlink is reasonably limited. I watched a couple of Jeff Gehrling videos
I think that's about as far as it goes
Don't you have to tie it to a specific?
Grid reference so that they have enough satellite bandwidth for you to talk to like it won't work if you drive 50 miles west or something
Right. Yeah, I think it mostly turns out to be like a 30 mile
Area around your service address that you've put on your account is where it's functional. I don't I don't know yet
This is something I'm gonna play with but it sounds like it's pretty straightforward in
most cases to just update your service address and then like it takes effect in like
15 minutes and then you can start setting up in your new location
I imagine that's actually not as smooth as it's going to go
Like I'll try to do it to be like too many users in this area
I recall I was watching a guy on YouTube who was an RVer and was proclaiming that he had
Hacked the Starlink algorithm to let him use it anywhere in actual fact. What he was doing was he was pre staging his
Location in the Starlink app before he got there
So the systems had time to catch up or if where he got to didn't have connection to update his service address
I mean I could see that cuz I generally know where I'm gonna end up parking at, you know before I go there
So I could plug that in before I arrive. The other tricky thing is is I think the little dishy takes like
150 watts pretty much consistently once it's up and running. That's a significant amount of power
In fact, it's like running a whole PC. It is pretty much isn't it and they're not cheap either
So there was the $99 deposit, which I felt was fair. Okay. All right fine, and then there's like a
Separate four hundred and eighty five dollar fee to get the kit and the kit is everything you need
It's like the router Ethernet the PoE injector the dish all of it
But every time I check it just says pending
So you're six hundred dollars in the hole for this thing then and then the monthly service, of course as well
Oh, what does what does that cost? I think it's gonna be in the hundred dollar range
When you don't have good solid bandwidth almost any price that you can conceivably afford to pay is worth it
Yeah, slow internet is worse than no internet
That's what they say. And then once you get that good internet head over to a cloud guru
They are the leader in learning for the cloud Linux and other modern tech skills
Thousands of hands-on labs hundreds of certifications and courses and free cloud sandboxes on their credit card
Not yours go to cloud guru comm get certified get hired get learning
I can only imagine how having decent low ping internet. Do you have any any sense of?
The Starlink kind of ping times yet. I have done a little bit of meta analysis of the reviews and also to their credit
The Starlink folks kind of give you that information in the signup process when they're like, hey, this is a beta
It's gonna go down sometime
You're probably gonna get ping somewhere in the 40 millisecond range is what they kind of warn you for and I that's kind of what?
I've seen from the meta analysis of the reviews. I have seen some reviewers get it as low as 20
Something in the 20 to 40 would be great because 40 is about the best case
I'm ever going to get ever on LTE is about 40 milliseconds
and I know from having done these shows with you now for a long time an LTE connection is
workable, but we end up stepping on each other quite often and
Makes life for our editor more difficult
So lower the ping time for us certainly the better and also I would imagine although we'll see I'll get a sense of this
Is it would hopefully I know it drifts, but hopefully it drifts either less or more consistently
Than LTE where LTE is kind of all over the board depending on all the other users that are in that area
Are there any constraints around the amount of bandwidth you can consume because with LTE that's a big concern, right?
And as far as I know, there's no limits either
I don't know if eventually when they go public if they'll have tiered plans, but that's a huge deal. No, no, no, no
No, I know I know
Even with my quote-unquote
Unlimited LTE plans. I'm really kind of in the doghouse after 300 gigs and around 400 gigs
They're looking at what I'm doing and you know
I get the prioritized and all that kind of stuff and that is like on the extremely high end
Like these are elite rare plans where I can even get that far along before they start getting mad at me
That's crazy. Where are staying last week at my mother-in-law's in rural Norfolk. The only decent internet that she can get is
Through 4g LTE from EE in the UK and she gets 200 gigabytes a month
Bandwidth for her home internet and for me that was a real adjustment, you know dealing with that ping time
Dealing with that lack of bandwidth availability. Welcome to my world. I honestly don't know how you cope with it full-time
I know I know that's why I'm really excited about Starlink even though
there's the downside of putting more junk up in space, which is a serious problem and
These may actually be visible from the ground and maybe you know, there's we're not gonna be happy about that long term
But it's so obvious that at least here in the States
we need a solution to this because my other options are duopoly cell providers or a
monopoly cable provider
That's my options here and it just isn't is it is not long-term
Sustainable or tenable for something as important as our connectivity
Which is how I organize manage and run my entire business and most of my personal life is all online now
And that's true for probably nearly everyone listening to this show and so access to the internet just is so critical that I think it's kind of
Necessary that we have something like Starlink as an option and if they can get these prices down to below what I'm paying for these
ridiculous LTE plans I
Mean that's gonna make it more available to more people and you know, eventually to folks like Alex's mom
It's gonna be a game-changer for a lot of people
There are remote mountain properties that you look at these days on Zillow or rightmove or whatever and you think I'd love to know
It's gonna have to make a DSL. I can't I just can't even consider it, you know
So yeah, and I think ultimately Alex it's gonna make something like my end dream building some off-grid
Property a lot more feasible because all of the areas I've looked at in the Pacific Northwest that I could even begin to remotely afford
That have water or something like that. They're all outside a cellular range. There's nothing around there's no services and the idea
That I could go out there with my solar-powered RV and set up a little dishy and get a connection to the Internet from space
It's just amazing. I mean, it's huge dishy. What an adorable little name
Did you see that home assistant had a release this week? It seems like a big one
you know you it's hard to tell from the outside like
Which ones are kind of just the minor updates and which ones are the big ones?
And the one that came out as we're recording is the October release that came out on October 6th
There's a big thing in here Alex. They got official tuya integration from the folks at tuya
The people that people that organize all the tuya devices and run the tuya infrastructure have now created an official integration for home assistant
So here's the thing about this. I mean, I think it's awesome that we're starting to get actual vendors
Yeah, looking at home assistant and going yes, I want to support that
but also, you know, we've got stuff like cloudfree.shop and mylocalbytes.com and that kind of thing and
There's other things coming along with with pre-tasmota flash devices said that this becomes less important to me
Well even more so because this is the cloud
Integration. Yeah, they worked with the cloud API team not with like this the firmware team
And so this doesn't work for local integration. This uses the cloud connectivity. It looks like it's doing a really good job
In fact, it's much better than before much quicker all of that
It's what you'd want and it's official, but it does require their cloud API, which means it requires an internet connection
Which means it's a disqualifier for me. Just like you said I'd rather get a device I could control locally
In fact, I'd rather get a device that's not on Wi-Fi. What's your preferred poison these days?
Are you a Z-Wave or a ZigBee type of chat? If you go by the number of devices
I have it'd be it'd be Z-Wave
But if you go by where I plan to go to it'd be ZigBee and matter because that's gonna be one of the same
I think eventually yeah matter
I think is really kind of exciting because if a vendor adopts the matter protocol
Then there is a local API if you use matter
Then you've got a local API and like that to me is like well, that's a no-brainer
But right now I invested pretty early in Z-Wave and I've been very happy with my Z-Wave devices
In fact, I'll talk about that in a little bit more but for me Wi-Fi
It's just I like to be able to reboot my access points and maintain control of my devices
I don't like putting that load on my Wi-Fi network
And if it works with Z-Wave or ZigBee, I almost am guaranteed I can make it work somehow with home assistant
That's very true the stuff I talked about in the last episode at my dad's house that the ZigBee buttons I put in here
He's been delighted with them the the little IKEA trad free buttons. I think it's what they called
They're working great. So you get a plus one on ZigBee from me
Anyway, I'm gonna hold out with my Z-Wave devices for now
And then when the matter stuff settles I may make a transition but Alex with the release
they had a live stream kind of like a release party with the developers and they brought on the
Some of the developers from Tuya and they talked about some stats the opt-in stats that people can can get into and then send their
Information off anonymously. They said that for the people that have opted in they now show
90,000 active home assistant users
That's just since April when they launched this statistics package and the people who have opted into it
Also, the data shows that a lot of people have not updated since that April release. Oh
Oh
Boy that's a lot that's a lot of updates since they're doing a monthly now
Also, their analytics show that 40% of home assistant users have a Chromecast
40% is a huge huge number for that kind of thing
Home kit also shows as quite popular and the most popular hardware
Was the Raspberry Pi?
Followed closely by running home assistant in a VM like you do now
Do they take statistics on how many of those Raspberry Pi users are you?
Very fair very fair those all those stats are public at analytics dot home dash assistant dot IO
Or we'll put a link in the show notes
This is also the release for us Z wave users where it's time to migrate to Z wave JS as
Of this release it now supports s2 which is the improved security model and it's short for security to surprise surprise
besides improved security
Devices are also more reliable. They provide greater battery life and less latency compared to the original security mode
That was supported by Z wave JS
Integration will now automatically pick the best and optimal security method available
They have a whole new wizard for adding new devices and it looks sharp
Oh and speaking of wizards
There is now a migration wizard to migrate you from your old Z wave setup to the new Z wave JS
Which is what I was waiting for
However, when I go in my home assistant, it actually still asking me to migrate to open ZW or whatever it was
I don't know why but I'm still getting a migration offer to open ZW and I I don't know if I'm supposed to install
Z wave JS first or or what like they don't give you any information on that
But if your system isn't wonky like mine, they're saying go ahead and make the migration now. It's been pretty refined
It'll walk you through what it's gonna do and what's gonna change and then Alex the developers in the stream kind of doubled down
Which made me feel good about using Z wave. They said this Z wave JS integration is well written
It's well built and it is well maintained and they think it's good code. And so it's solid. It's good
It's a good in fact, they're gonna go for their thinking they haven't said they're gonna do this
But they're thinking seriously about going for official Z wave
Certification from the Z wave group because they're so proud of how this has turned out. Oh, really that'd be a huge success
I bought a Z wave smart door lock on some kind of sale on Black Friday
And it's been sat in a box ever since because I couldn't ever get it to pair
So maybe now is the time I can with that new s2 security support that's in there
Maybe I should give that another go
Yeah
And it gives you a little more information and it's a little more clear about when you should go hit the pair button on
The device like all of that whole process is a little smoother now
It looks with Z wave JS. They did a little live demonstration of a migration on the stream
I just remember it being frustrating as anything, you know when I tried it
Yeah, it feels a bit like a black box, doesn't it? But no, I think I think they're doing they're doing good things
So if you are a Z wave device user, which you know, I just I have I probably have somewhere
I think I have like a dozen Z wave devices
It's not it's not like an unbelievable number that I can't eventually migrate off of but I'll be using them still for a while
All right. I've got a low-key genuinely awesome feature that's come to github. I think in the last two or three months
load up a github repository right now you can do this live and
Open a repository. You just need to be logged in. That's the important thing
When you have that page open press full stop the period key on your keyboard and watch what happens. Oh
That's pretty nice. Oh, look at them
Yeah, all right straight into VS code web suddenly electron doesn't look so bad now hard does it?
It's that repository opened up in VS code, isn't it? Right? It better be. Yep. Oh, that's slick
Okay
impressive and then you open a file you make an edit you press save and it then is because it's part of git the
Git plug-in in VS code. You just commit it directly in there and boom you're done
Oh my gosh, if you're opening a third-party repository though, and you make a change and you save it
It asks you then if you want to fork it and then automatically helps you with the pool
Merge request model at github has Wow, it is so cool in the browser
When did they sneak this in? I don't know
I mean I first found it someone on our discord told me a couple of months ago about it
I think of course, but I've been using it a lot for my notes in the last few weeks
actually, I've got a private repository on github I use for notes and
I've actually just ended up using VS code in the browser on github.com. It's not very self-hosted is it but it works very well
And I want to mention our friends at a cloud guru have a course on the Linux kernel
It's a standalone course, but it's also part of a learning path to prepare you for the LPG 201 exam
You learn how the Linux kernel provides an interface between hardware and software
you'll compile a kernel from start to finish and of course, you'll cover kernel runtime management troubleshooting adding removing modules and
Modifying the modules on boot. We'll have a link in our show notes or you can go to a cloud guru and search for the
Linux kernel
So we were just talking about Zigbee and Zed wave and all that kind of stuff
So I was really excited to see that the home assistant has a new hardware project out
Yeah, and it's been funded the home assistant amber, which is based around the compute module 4
With their own board. It's got an SSD connector. It has Zigbee built-in
In fact the devs on the stream said no SD cards. We hate SD cards
So you can either use an SSD or it'll come with a MMC built into it. They're gonna chip it with a transparent case. I
Think maybe in part for radio
It's plastic for radio transparency and then they they have a whole post on why they chose transparent
Some models will come with a POE hat as well
It's pretty nice-looking. Although I don't know if it's gonna be as fast as the home assistant blue. Well, no, I mean my only concern
about this box and let me just preface everything I'm about to say with
the fact I think that these kind of projects from home assistant themselves are
Wonderful, and I'm so happy to see that they're doing it
My only concern is that putting the compute module 4 into a product at this stage in the Raspberry Pi 4's life cycle
Feels like we're getting towards the end of the Pi 4 cycle
Maybe are we going to be able to upgrade this to a CM 5 one day? Probably not. Will there be a home assistant?
Burnt sienna instead or something. I don't know but that's my only reservation. Everything else looks great
Yeah, perhaps that could be an issue
I don't know if we know for sure if there will be a compute module 5 this may be a you know
Once every few years. That's a good point Christopher
the other thing that holds the Raspberry Pi 4 back right now is
Absolutely the IO situation and they solve that with emmc or an SSD
you know, I mean it's no x86 box, right like
I've got jobs where I need more powerful systems, but
I am doing more than ever with my Pi 4. I mean now it's doing MQTT and it's doing
energy metric collection and and graphing and
It's still just chugging right along like it's just oh and also for a short period of time
I even ran the wise bridge on it
It was still doing just fine
Oh that thing chomps the CPU only with two camera feeds. Let me be clear and I turned it off
I did turn it off, but it was but home assistant everything was still working like it still has a little bit of oomph to spare
It still has a little bit of oomph to spare and uh, I could see the compute 4 module being enough machine
For most people until you get into more advanced logging and graphing and stuff like that
So what does this mean for the blue then moving forward? Well, it seems like the blue is kind of gonna phase out over time
Uh, I think the words used were we're gonna take the lessons learned
And we're applying that to the amber one thing about the blue that
Was noted by the developers is that it's a board that they took that already existed
And then, you know, they flashed home assistant onto it
but if you want zigbee or z wave or matter support you got to add a dongle and
It's it's not really flexible in that regard where uh, this is a device that they kind of control the board that the compute module
Is going to sit in they can integrate things like zigbee. They can do things like poe
Poe and it seems like when you look at also their hardware stats
We talked about earlier and you see so many so many users are using the raspberry pi
It probably makes sense from like a software
End user reliability stability standpoint to base your core product on that same platform if you can
Because then improvements you make there are going to benefit everybody else also using the raspberry pi that isn't running on an amber
They're just on a pi. Yeah, I hadn't considered that angle. That's an interesting one and alex if you if you'll allow me there's one small
Update in this october home assistant release that I wanted to talk about
It wasn't initially going to cover so I feel kind of embarrassed but it's icons
They updated the material design icons to version six. They've added 400 new icons
and
um
if you haven't done this yet to your home assistant update, I know all this has been very homeless assistant specific, but
I tell you what. It made me love my dashboard a little bit more when I went in there and just tweaked the icons
For all the different entities. So they all have unique individual icons that represent what they are and rumor has it based on
What the devs accidentally said on the live stream. They're going to include in the
lovelace
Wizard a new icon picker soon that lets you easily pick from these icons. Oh good because the mdi
Mdi website that you pick the icons from
Slow is the slowest damn web page to load on the entire freaking internet. I swear so slow so bad. Yeah
I i'm glad they have it but it's so slow
Yeah, so they're gonna have an icon picker. It'll be built in
And these these material design icons are in home assistant
There's so many for your different devices that just kind of give you a nice visual indicator what it do. Mm-hmm
You gotta know what it do
Lino.com
Slash ssh talk about people who know what they are doing. They've been doing this since
2003 one of the very first companies in cloud computing that's
Knowing what you're doing and 18 years later lino
It is the largest independent open cloud provider in the world with 11 different data centers around the world
So it's lino.com slash ssh you go there to get
$100 in 60-day credit on a new account
And of course you support the show this show is made possible by you taking advantage of our sponsor offers
We're an independent operation a couple of guys doing our thing here and you taking advantage of something great like this lino.com
Slash-ssh man, that's the circle of life for us
Plus you can go in there and just see how great it is
It really is a fantastic service with great performance and they've really invested in the dashboard and the hardware and the networking and well
The whole stack really like if you want to switch over from zoom to jitzy
They got a one-click deployment for that and it's like a great opportunity to take advantage of our $100 credit
They really have the best in class experience because they've been focusing on making this great for the last 18 years
Their mission has remained unchanged
Making cloud computing accessible affordable for all and once you get in you'll see that they have things like s3 compatible object storage
There's so much you can do with that
They have bare metal servers
If your application load requires that ddos protection vlan support a powerful dns manager
And if you like to do your infrastructure by code, they've got terraform and kubernetes support to help you
Well integrate with everything else you're doing and with pricing 30 to 50 cheaper
Maybe it's a great opportunity to go multi-cloud. Why get locked into a single vendor?
Leno can help you spread that out
So you're not just dependent on one hyperscaler and as we've seen just the week that we're recording sometimes
Sometimes they go down and if you ever get stuck linode has the best customer support in the industry
They really have amazing 24 7 customer support by phone ticket or social
And then they back all that up with hundreds of guides and thousands of tutorials
Linode is dedicated to offering the best in virtualized cloud computing if it runs on linux it runs on linode
Sign up today at linode.com
Slash ssh get 100 in 60 day credit on your new account and you support the show lino.com
slash ssh
Now what were you doing earlier in the week you weren't you know messing about with bgp routes were you
No, no, i'm not pushing out changes to remove dns entries
Uh, just you know
Of course listeners are probably picking up on the fact that this is the week that facebook went down
And alex and I are watching this with popcorn going. Oh, could you imagine what it's like to be on site right now?
Where they can't even badge in let alone figure out why everything's down
What a nightmare or send each other an email. That's the thing like, you know, bob at facebook.com would no longer work
Would it man if uh, if uh, if I didn't know any better, I think somebody probably lost their job
Well, I mean the conspiracy theorist in me wonders. It's all a little fishy that it happened on the exact same
Week as the uh testimony the whistleblower thing
You know
Is it a deflection tactic or is it just genuine genuinely a screw up? I I don't know but
You gotta wonder sometimes. I don't think it was a deflection tactic. I mean it was if it was that was a very significant self-inflicted wound
Yeah, true. I actually saw one of my neighbors sharing on facebook today
10 facebook alternatives for 2021. I thought that was so funny
Yeah, and telegram saw a massive rush of new users, you know, i'd buy an insider
Job before i'd buy an intentional screw up, you know like rage quit kind of thing. Yeah, maybe
Maybe the zuck didn't give somebody the smoked meats they were after
I've been a little too distracted to really pay attention though. I got I got sucked into the rabbit hole of energy monitoring, right?
Yeah, because you're you're back home now
So you've actually got some free time instead of just driving all day
And home assistant while I was on the roads
I didn't have a chance to really look at it added energy monitoring support where you can actually like get some
Good stats and whatnot in home assistant. Mm-hmm
And identify batteries and utility sources and and even like, you know fuel consumption costs
If you want to monitor that
So I thought okay, I got to try this
And I have a couple of z wave smart plugs that do energy monitoring. I've never really used that
So that is sort of the route that I looked at this like well, why don't why don't I try to see if I can?
get my existing
smart plugs to work
And for listeners that don't remember I have I have two setups. I have a home automation setup in my rv
Which is pretty extensive and then I have like a mini version at the studio
it's like a smaller instance of
of uh home home assistant it runs on the home assistant blue
And in a way it's it's often kind of like a good testing ground because it's so much simpler
there's just there's less entities to go through and all that kind of stuff and
I noticed after the update
To the home assistant blues version of home assistant, which is comes out at the same time. Everybody else does
that
I just had energy monitoring like my belkin wemo plugs that I happen to have that I only use here in the studio
We're just reporting their energy usage and home assistant had like a little
Diagram of where power was going and how much power had been used that day and I thought
Wow
That looks great. I'd love to have that at home where I actually care about my power and all that kind of stuff
I thought to myself
So I go home and I don't have any of that
My plugs are monitoring their draw. They're seeing how many how many watts are being used
But home assistant couldn't care less. It's like if I bring up the sensor. Yeah, it knows how many watts are being used
But when I go to configure an energy device, it's just
Whatever bro. There's no devices giving you any stats for some reason. I've just got this picture of home assistant being like
this
Uh beavis and butthead style character sat on a couch in the corner with a backwards baseball cap and a cigarette in the other hand going
Whatever bro. I don't care. Yeah, you can't have that. I don't care and it's so to me
It's like okay. There's something wrong. Obviously these devices are like not giving home assistant the information you need
But when you go into the developer tools and you look at the state attributes and the states it's sending back
It's clearly saying this is the amount of power being consumed
It's in the watts format and it is this many watts like it's easily readable by the human eye and i'm thinking to myself
What's going on here? Why can't I see this power draw?
And I want to I want to not only get an overview of my power draw
But I want to start building automations that say
Hey, hey when two appliances when these two smart plugs because I can just say these two together
They're on one circuit. I know that so when these two smart plugs both have a draw over 500 watts
Turn off the heater smart plug always turn it off
So that way the wife can turn on the toaster and when it starts drawing a thousand watts
It turns off the heater that's drawing 800 watts
And that's that's essentially what I want. And if anybody has a blueprint or a good advice on how to set that up
Please let me know
Ultimately, that's what i'm trying to get to I haven't gotten there yet. But what I did do
Is I managed to get my damn energy monitor and it took quite a journey. I have to say because of ultimately
You have to get the data in the format that home assistant wants
So first you got to have home assistant 2021.8 or newer
And you need a smart plug or an energy monitoring device like one of those clamp devices or a shelly
That reports in kilowatt hours
all my plugs
report in watts
As in watts currently being consumed
Home assistant wants kilowatt hours and then it'll do all the math for you from there
So what you have to do is you have to get an integration
called
integration
It's a math integration
Which will take the watts and convert them into kilowatt hours for you and then produce a new sensor
That shows that energy information in kilowatt hours
I have a configuration.yaml entry example in the show notes
Then once you have that
The new energy utilities that are built into home assistant will see this device as something it can pull stats from
And we'll start giving you your usage. So I have to go through for each one of my smart plugs
And I have to do this. I have to create this
like this template sensor that takes
information from the state of my smart plug
And formats it in a way that home assistant wants and I have the examples in the show notes
But I had to go deep because I had to learn a little bit of how templating works
I had to I had to learn about
creating new kinds of sensors
It was it was really quite the journey
I I naively expected to just do the update get energy monitoring and see my smart plugs report in there
Boy, was I wrong. Sometimes we get a bit spoiled with home system. Don't we it picks up so much. It does so much and then
Occasionally, we actually have to break out some uh davinci code to find out what we actually wanted
I think this is one of those examples and I felt like there was so much out there that
Didn't apply since the new energy monitoring was introduced. So like a lot of the help
was old and no longer relevant and
Because my smart plugs I guess aren't as common. Um, there's not as many people that have solved this problem
So just yeah, it was I felt like I was searching
Niche resources and it took me a while to even just try to figure out the language
I need and figure out what the requirements were of home assistant and all of that
That is a real problem with with projects like home assistant that moves so fast to see it a lot with kubernetes at work as well
is
that kind of uh
google entropy of of stuff like
A post, you know google will think a year old post isn't too old to surface as the top result
When in actual fact in home assistant land that may as well be 10 years ago
Yeah, that's exactly right. Um, and then you know alex when I got it all kind of done
I realized it's okay
It's pretty basic at this point because I don't have all of my battery and solar information in there
It really wasn't worth the journey. I actually like the dashboards I created myself
Better and i'll have a few links in the show notes it it involved uh setting up a history stats integration
So I could collect historical information about my power usage and then I used a utility meter integration
and that let my
Virtual energy monitors i'd set up that produce kilowatt hours show up as a utility source now
That lets me do all kinds of things like now I have a dashboard
That shows me
if today
My heaters are using more power than they were say three days ago. I have a three-day window
On my power usage of my heaters
And I can kind of tell
When i'm kind of using more power and maybe
I can make adjustments based on that if I want I actually haven't decided to take any action on that right now
I'm, just collecting the information and collecting historical information
And so when summer comes around i'll have a totally, you know different set of data
And then when the whole year is completed, I think the information is going to be pretty fascinating
And i'll probably be able to overlay it with temperature information and all kinds of stuff. So I brought together
the history stats integration with the utility meter
Integration and I have again an example of what that looks like in your configuration.yaml linked in the show notes
So now what that's done is it's created these virtual sensors that i've built dashboards around in home assistant
They give me all this information that I think that's where they're going with the built-in energy support
But I like my version better that I built myself
It's not too bad actually 17 lines of code to do all that history stat stuff. It's not
Unreasonable and it's very readable like it all makes sense when you read it. You can see what i'm doing
It's there's nothing tricky about it. Yeah, that's very true. Now something else we've talked about on the show previously is
de-googlifying
I'll be honest on whilst i've been in england. I haven't been paying much attention to that
I've just been getting on with the business of traveling
however
You mentioned in lup this week, uh linux unplugged dot com slash 426 a tool called tube sync
Yeah, think of tube sync as a pvr for youtube you give it
channels and playlists or if you're familiar with sonar it's like sonar for youtube
And then it goes out and pulls down the videos and it gives you a dashboard to tell you
How many video sources you're pulling from?
What's coming up next exactly like you might expect from something like sonar?
It's a pretty advanced ui and there's a docker compose that gets most of it set up for you, too
Alex including the elastic search stuff. You might need now the reason I brought this up on this show
uh is is this isn't linux unplugged extras, but uh,
Uh, I actually found something called media cms dot io and this is essentially
a youtube front end clone. So what I was thinking about doing was
Originally anyway, I was going to use tube sync to download the videos from youtube just as an archiving
type
uh utility
Bring them into plex maybe because there are some people on the plex forums that have youtube metadata agents and that kind of thing
But I think what I might end up doing is using this media cms. Ios to self host my own kind of
Pseudo youtube instance thing. Have you seen this? Oh, this is neat
Yes, and it it is obviously inspired by the youtube ui but good on them. They've taken the best elements in this
And I think it looks really solid. They got dark mode. They got light mode
And it could really end up making a perfect curated youtube and wow
I could I could see it being a lot of work for what you want to do
Man, this could be a slam dunk for parents
This could be a great way
You could take tube sync and pull in the approved channels that you're comfortable with your kids watching
Have tube sync pull it down to the file system
And then point media cms right at that and it's a curated youtube
I wonder how they handle video transcoding because obviously youtube has
A whole bunch of stuff when you upload video to it
It transcodes to all the different formats and then you just switch on the fly the the quality that you're streaming does
Does this have any function for that? I don't see any quality options in the playback. Oh, yeah. No, it's under the settings
It's right there and it says it has multiple transcoding profiles same defaults
It says for multiple dimensions from 20 from 240p up to 1080p
Experimental support for remote workers. So I guess there's a stuff a bunch of stuff. We could figure out there
That's this could be a fun project. That's something to put on our list after I get done solving energy
Yeah, and then world hunger and world peace and uh
Covid as well. You got to solve that one, too
And then and then we'll get on redoing jb.com
But we do have one thing we can solve for people if they are an icloud
Slash iphone user and you got your pictures up there. You came across a really handy tool
To help pull all of your icloud photos down locally to your machine. Yeah, we were talking about this
Where was it in the jupiter broadcasting telegram chat actually?
Someone was asking, you know, how do you back up your iphone?
Pictures and stuff like that because of the way that ios has very restrictive background api kind of it
kills anything in the background that's
Going to drain battery unlike android. That's a lot more permissive
It means you can't run stuff like
Resilio sync or sync thing very effectively or there's another one on android called folder sync
and so
This neat app is actually called gimme-i photos, which is kind of a funny name
And this sidesteps all of ios's problems
With backgrounding api's and on device, you know
Image management and stuff like that
Because it hooks directly into icloud
The only caveat being is you got to be okay with putting your photos up in icloud
But I think what alex is driving at there
It's like that's the only one that's really going to work reliably with the way the iphone backgrounding works
If you want them off the phone reliably automatically, it's going to have to be icloud photo on an iphone
So that's why this is so great and because it's python
You don't have to be on a mac. You could run it on a linux box or a windows box, too
Yeah, I ran this just on a normal linux server. I think I ran it out of a container because i'm
That's just who I am
The really nice thing about it and I didn't expect this at all
I didn't even think about this until I tried it
It uses a python library underneath which actually supports the icloud two-factor authentication
mechanisms
So when I brought this up for the first time a little pop-up appeared on my mac to say hey
Someone's trying to log in as you back in rally. Is this you and here's your two-factor code and I was like, huh?
Did not expect that
Yeah, that made me feel a little bit better that it was kind of legit about how it's authorizing against the icloud servers
It seems to be using like an official apple api for that
And I think it's great for running on your nas. If you've got a nas box that you can shell into
You could go into your directory of choice on your nas and execute this thing and it's just going to sit there and download
Photos all day long and I think for me the absolute killer
Use case are like my parents phones, you know a couple of parents use android a couple use
ios
And the ios ones i've really struggled to get the photos out of icloud into anything
Meaningful off their phones into anything meaningful like next cloud even is a bit of a crap shoot on ios
And this just solves that problem
Altogether i'm not the only thing i'm not totally certain on is how long that two-factor authentication token lasts for
And I guess time will tell but uh, i'm going to set this up for my parents this week whilst i'm here and then
report back when it uh
You know in six months and let you know how it's how it's gone. And are you thinking just cronit?
So it just runs automatically every night or something. Yeah, exactly
Put it put it on a timer and then let it download every day every week. Whatever. Yeah
Yeah, that will be interesting to see how long that two-factor authentication
If it is it I bet you it must have some time expiration
So you'll have to check back in and see if either a it generates a new prompt or b just breaks quietly
Backblaze.com
Backblaze.com slash ssh go there to get a free trial. No credit card required. Just get peace of mind
Knowing your files are backed up securely in the cloud with backblaze. It's seven dollars a month
No gimmicks you get unlimited backup for your mac or your pc your movies your music your photos your videos your projects
All the data and backblaze now has over an exabyte of customer data backed up and counting with 50 billion files restored for their customers
You can do web restores
If that's how you like to roll you can restore files by the app
If that's how you want to get to files on the go
I don't know how you do and they also offer restore by mail check this out a flash key or a hard drive that you
Can grab from them ship to your door overnight with your data restored to it
But here's the best part if you send the hard drive back within 30 days you get a full refund
Now that's some peace of mind if you lose your data and you've got a lot of things you're going to need to recover
It's nice having a physical hard drive mailed to you overnight by fedex
And if you're worried about accidentally deleting files for an extra two dollars a month
You can increase your retention history to one year
Their mobile apps mean you can get access to those same files when you're out and about on the go
And of course backblaze has been recommended by new york times by macworld by tom's guide nine to five mac and many more
But why not go see it for yourself? You get a free 15 day trial at backblaze.com
slash
ssh 15 days means plenty of time to upload and download some files and get a real feel for the service
And you know backblaze has been around for a while
They started 14 years ago to create a business that's equally fair and good for its customers partners employees
investors and the greater community and since
2013 they've been publishing their hard drive reports
That's a report
We make sure to never miss and it's a real value to the entire industry too because of the amount of disks
The real scale that backblaze is working with they can get some genuine insights and now after 14 years
They have over 500 000 customers in a hundred and seventy five countries
Backblaze.com slash ssh no credit card required get started on a free 15 day trial
And start backing up your data start getting some peace of mind
backblaze.com slash
ssh
Now I mentioned tail scale in the last episode which was a brand new project to me
But it turns out a lot of you guys had already figured this one out well ahead of me
And zahid writes in hello. I was just listening to your latest episode and heard about your love for tail scale
Not sure if you're aware, but there are synology packages available for it as well. Keep up the great work. Cheers zahid
Hey, that's handy. Yeah, it really is
I mean that was actually the only reason I ended up looking at uh tail scale in the first place was
I was futzing about with that synology naz ready to put it at my mom's house and uh, I was like
What's this tail scale thing? I'm pretty sure i've heard of it
and then I did a bit of research figured out it was wire guard and was like
I'll just give this a go
And then within 10 minutes i'd built out everything I was trying to achieve with wire guard for several days prior
So no kidding huge fan of tail scale and it you know real success story
My mom took it back from my mother-in-law's house where she you know came to meet my daughter and stuff like that
Took it back to her house plugged in one ethernet cable the power cable pressed the on button on the synology
And within a couple of minutes it had booted and tail scale had registered it. I didn't have to do any dynamic dns
No, firewall changes. It was just magic. I swear. It was awesome
That's why we've been seeing so much love this week erno writes and i'm beyond ecstatic
I listened to episode 54 self-hosted on my way to my morning mountain biking and as soon as I came home
I had to try tail scale
It was pretty cool based on alex's explanation. But now that I tried it, it's even cooler
They make it super easy to set up. I think i've been setting up wire guard for weeks
But this well this just takes care of all of it for me
I have it installed on my phone kabuntu desktop and my linode server
I plan on installing it on my o droid running in armbian and i'm planning on setting up some kind of sync thing
We'll see but so far. I am super ecstatic. Thank you so much for your mention of tail scale
And chris glad you made it back to washington alex. I hope you're enjoying the motherland sincerely erno from virginia
I think I weigh at least 90 of fish and chips now good for you having been back here for a month
That's what I do, too. I'd have to fish and chips and curry
So taylor writes in thanks so much for the amazing show that is self-hosted every two weeks
I'm refreshing my podcatcher like a madman
I was just catching up on episode 54 and could relate to alex's remote access woes
Tail scale is a solution that seems to be popular on reddit and irc
But I wanted to mention something that has been working really well for me and that is zero tier
Now zero tier is a distributed wan solution that essentially creates a global overlay network
Kind of like nebula does
It's open source and self-hostable
With nas packages third party web management guis and so on
They just released a dns solution as well
Which sounds very similar to the tail scale magic dns offering?
And I just wanted to give you guys another self-hosted option. Thanks for the show
I definitely want to give head scale a try
that's why i'm kind of waiting to replace nebula with tail scale is I want to see how
Viable it is to use head scale and uh self-host the server component of tail scale
But that also looks really great. It does there's so many options. I just had to give a plug for nebula, too
now the only thing about zero tier that
Kind of gives me it's just a one or two percent pause
Is that the protocol is custom whereas the tail scale protocol is based around wire guard. So
I mean who's to say one is better than the other but uh, I love me some wire guard
If I were a betting man, alex, I know which one I would bet on
It's not it's not one that's been made up. Uh, I really I respect the wire guard project immensely
So that's just clearly like the one I would put my trust in if my data was was truly critical
I want to mention uh, thank you
Everybody who went to self-hosted dot show slash contact and sent in their question
We also have the discord community self-host dot show slash discord, which is always popping off
And our matrix community is also growing. There's a good conversation of self-hosters going on
You can find our matrix server. We have a jupiter broadcasting dot com matrix server and
Probably the easiest way to just get like a quick guide
Is to actually go to linux unplugged dot com slash matrix. I haven't put that up anywhere else yet
But there is a community growing out there in matrix land of self-hosters. Oh chris. What have you done?
You've invited another set of notifications into my life. Thank you so much. Oh, oh, I know alex. I know so well
But you know i'm i'm trying to assemble the troops because i'm so close to getting this automation bliss where
You know, my my goal is to make it so my wife no longer has to worry about blowing
A 15 amp circuit if we have a heater going and she wants to run the toaster
I want home assistant to figure it out and I know uh, like our guest matt and others out there have done this
But I could use some wisdom
So the matrix server is a great spot to let me know
Because i'm i'm trying to drop in on the matrix from time to time the discord's also really great or telegram
How have you solved this particular problem? What should I do?
And will my z-wave devices update fast enough because it seems like there's sometimes like a 20 second lag
All these things show your wisdom
Let's get this energy monitoring figured out because I think this is going to be big in the self-hosting community
And as always I want to give a big thank you to our sre subscribers. You make this show possible
You can go to self-hosted. Show slash sre to support the show and you can find us on twitter
Alex is over there at ironic badger. I'm at chris las and the show at self-hosted show
At self-hosted show and as usual, thanks for listening everybody. That was self-hosted. Show slash 55