Since our last episode I have been just every single night building something new trying something new for my home server setup
I feel like I've I've really rebounded from the death of my Raspberry Pi and now I'm just like trying out different setups
I'm really just going out having fun live in life experiencing different things
I'm not getting committed to any serious configurations or setups. I'm just dabbling and experimenting and really enjoying myself
Sowing your seed in the field of Linux. I take it
Absolutely, and things were just going really great
Until last night. Oh
But we'll get to that we'll get to that in the show
There's so much to get into today that I want to save it for a little bit because I know you've been at an event
Recently, we also have been thinking about doing a little shout out to the community trying to get somebody who might be a discord
Bot wizard to help us come up with a title bot for the show
So there's a lot to cover today plus towards the end of the show. We've got some great feedback some good questions
I've got some new hardware updates. So I said, well, I'll tell you about it later. Okay. Oh, it's such tease
I think I'll stick around see see what see what's been happening. Stay tuned and find out Alex
Exactly. Well very quickly. Let's just cover the title bot first shall we very simple requirements
We want something that you type, you know bang, you know
Exclamation mark start show and that starts the timer running and then ideally publishes any any bang suggest
Titles to a little web page which we can rank by a number of votes
I can add a voting thing if you've been with JB for a while
You remember JB titles comm something like that that we used to have in IRC
but for the modern age in discord would be
Bang tidy. Yeah, cuz we've been live streaming now for weeks over at Jupiter tube every other Wednesday, and we put our discord up there
we've got a live chat room in our discord and
The thing is we've been podcasting for so long our title making happeners are broken and we just cannot title these things
So we need to crowdsource that and it gives people a chance to participate live and come up with a title if you want to
Help us build a bot reach out and let us know. Yeah, if it was up to me every episode would be called
Linux and stuff
Our buddy Joe's approach and just drop titles all together. He convinced me to do that with Linux action news best thing ever
Yeah, well news is kind of yeah, that's what I different. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right
So I'm a little jelly you've been at all things open today
I have right on my right on my doorstep a great big open source for
5,000 person open source conference right on my doorstep for four to five thousand. Yes
That's what I've been told. Yeah, I kind of almost feel like maybe this is the new Linux fest. Am I right?
Is it worth going to should I travel to this? Give me your take well, it's a sort of semi
Commercial conference. It's it's in a bit of a weird spot. If you ask me it's not like
Linux fest Northwest which is completely hippie and free open-source love fest and it's not something like kubecon
Which is just almost entirely sales pitches. It seems to be to be somewhere in the middle
like it's it's mostly commercial sponsored stuff and there's a handful of talks given by real people and
The rest are given by employees of companies who would like you to go and use their service mesh
Implementation for example, or whatever it might be but on the whole the quality of the sessions was okay
I think probably about half of the sessions I went to were good and the other half were really not good
What made them really not good?
Were they sales pitches? Yeah, a mixture of stuff like that. Like it was clearly just I mean a
45-minute long infomercial or the presenter was an intern and had never spoken to an audience before
Or you know that those kinds of things really so maybe the bar was a little low on who was accepted to speak
Yeah, well, I mean the reason I was interested in going was because Jim Salter was down to talk about ZFS
And who doesn't want to go and listen to Jim
Say how bad every other file system in the world except ZFS is, right?
Poor guy wasn't feeling terribly well though. So he pulled out at the last minute and
We were left hanging unfortunately, no Jim Salters ZFS lovefest. You got to get your updated ZFS talking points
What are you gonna do? Yeah, I know. Well, what I could do instead is talk about WSL 2
Scott Hanselman who is a Microsoft employee
I have to say was probably the best presenter that was at the conference and he did a great job
at the conference and he just had this wonderful way with him where
He was funny and actually engaging and obviously clearly knew that the subject he was talking about extremely well
And he did a very slick demo of how WSL 2 and github and vs code and windows
are actually
the perfect developer platform these days
And who would have thought who had on their bingo card 10 years ago
that Microsoft would nail the developer experience
on
Linux on windows and just make it all work seamlessly together. I mean
mind blown
well
Yes, and no, I mean they have I I think actually to give credit where credit is due
I think Microsoft's pivot to focus on
Linux open source and I would say broader
Development tools and development platforms, which I think is really what they've done. That has been very impressive
They deserve all the credit. You very rarely see these empires these
massive corporations make these huge pivots
a lot of times companies just get locked into a way of doing business and they just
Only have tunnel vision and they fight everything else to try to protect that business model
Microsoft figured out that they had to sacrifice a little bit of windows
And adopt and embrace a little bit more Linux open source and things like that to that to that end
I give them total and absolute compliments. I think they've done very well
And I think it's legitimate in a lot of ways
But I think the Achilles heel to this dream fantasy that they're saying where you can have windows with your compatibility
And your corporate integration and you have WSL and you just using github and vs code and everything's great because edge is based on chrome
So let's have fun
the problem is
It's still windows. It's still got the registry. It's still using NTFS
It still has an onion layered approach to the control panel and all the legacy stuff that comes in there
It still does all of the things that windows does it's still
Absolutely subject to the corporate tax strategy of Microsoft and whatever thing they're pursuing for that particular release cycle
for that particular release cycle windows is absolutely still influenced by it and as a user you have to put up with it and
Wait for the next fad so they can swap it out and put the other thing in there
I mean like right now right they're bundling in teams or the bundle in Cortana or they'll put ads in the start menu
It just doesn't matter because they're always doing something else because one of the fiefdoms in Microsoft
Has finally gotten their chance their moment and they're going to get the numbers and they get something built into windows and you will always
Always have to put up with that corporate strategy tax with the windows workstation
And despite what they say the driver model on windows still blows the printing subsystem on windows still blows
The disk io subsystem on windows still blows
The windows ui is still bloated old and has lots of legacy if you go just one layer below their new lacquer
And so yeah, you can you can run a linux kernel in a really great hyper virtualized environment good for you
And vs code is a pretty good product, but I could run vs code on linux
I could have a real linux subsystem with a real linux kernel that has real file systems
And doesn't have all that windows legacy bullcrap. And so it's close. Yeah, but your your audio wouldn't work though. Yeah. Yeah, right
I mean you're right and there are absolutely there are situations where like linux doesn't cut it and I acknowledge that
And that's why I think it is really great. The wsl is as good as it is
Because there are people that just have no choice, too
And I have to use windows and for them the subsystems there
Well, if I want to run flight sim, there is no other way for me to run flight sim than to run windows
Yeah, and there's uh, you know, like, uh, I can't remember the name of it
But there's some game that my son dylan loves and so he's you know, he's snuck in a dual boot into windows now
so that way you can play that one game and it kills me, but I have to acknowledge like
If you want to run that application, you got to have windows. So it absolutely has its place
But this utopia that they're painting for developers
You know, I just can't I can't I can't subscribe to it. I can't say as I disagree with anything you said
but uh, they did they have solved an
Absolutely huge problem, which is encapsulated development environment. So
Uh scott in his talk showed us something called development containers
And these essentially are a json manifest of all the requirements. You need to develop a specific project in his example
It was uh, an oh, oh my posh
Power shell kind of candy looking to a terminal pretty fire thing
And he downloaded the he cloned the git repo
Vs code automatically picked up the json file that was stored in the correct folder
It pre-installed all the dependencies in the container a docker container on windows running in the linux subsystem
For windows or whatever the hell it's called. Yeah, and uh,
Within, you know a minute of cloning this repo. He was working or well hypothetically presentation working
You know what? I mean that that does sound really slick. I gotta be I mean that does sound slick
I mean a good part of my master's degree sort of five six seven years ago was
Trying to solve this encapsulated development environment thing and that was what led me to docker containers back then and uh, you know
We were looking at packer vms and and you know sending q cow two images around to people and having like a special
university version of linux just for this, uh computer science course and
God damn it microsoft went and figured it out microsoft. It's crazy. They did
Uh, it's pretty legit and I have to say too like they recognized they needed a better terminal
They absolutely did they created the windows terminal. They made it an open source project
And it seems like it's a pretty good terminal like directx accelerated terminal. I mean, it's crazy. Yeah
That's so funny. It really it truly is it's I have to mention that this is something my buddy
Michael dominic and I have been talking about for a while on coder radio because we often talk about the tooling for development workstations
And he's kind of been through this whole journey
mac to windows
Wsl and like the mecca that that opened up for him and also of course vs code and also integration with azure and just like
He went all in for a bit
And now he's actually back on linux as his primary development workstation. And so the whole journey
I I think has been really interesting at coder.show if you are interested
But I want to hear about the meetup. I know you had a chance to
Go say hi to some audience members you guys coordinated in the matrix chat. It sounded like it went pretty well
Absolutely. Yeah. Well, I I bumped into a couple of listeners
Throughout the the day who somehow recognized me from my voice like it's distinctive
Uh, so we've got a little clip from a couple of listeners that we met up with for lunch
So i'm here at all things open with reed and john. How are you like in the conference so far john?
It's been pretty good learned a lot. Uh been to a bunch of different
sessions and
Gotten to meet some cool people and meet up with uh, the the jb crowd here
Yeah, and we've been working on a lot of stuff. We've been working on a lot of stuff
uh and getting a lot of people and meet up with uh, the the jb crowd here
Yeah, and we use the element
To jb matrix to kind of have a little mini meet up in the lobby of the conference. Didn't we?
And uh reed. I know you've been listening for a little while. How are you liking the conference as well? Oh, it's great. Yeah a very
wide range of people here from uh, community to corporate uh, and and lots to learn lots to
Lots to see and lots of great people to meet.
Any standout sessions for either of you?
There was a beer brewing with IoT and JavaScript
that I knew almost nothing about any of those subjects.
And now I know a little bit about all of those subjects.
You're at the Dunning-Kruger effect style moment, right?
Where you don't realize how little you actually know.
You feel vaguely competent.
Completely.
How about you, John?
There was a great, it was half of a two for one
that was on burnout.
And it was a really good just kind of think
about not burning out and ways to kind of handle that stress
and take breaks and things like that.
Yeah, very good.
I've certainly found burnout myself at times
can be quite challenging to deal with,
particularly during the last couple of years.
So it's very good.
Well, I wish you all the best for the rest of the afternoon.
And I hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.
Thank you.
I do hear what you're saying in there, though,
that it's a pretty wide range that All Things Open
is trying to cover.
Although I like the idea about having sessions on burnout.
And who doesn't like a session about automating beer brewing
with Linux and open source technologies, huh?
So the nice thing was the Raleigh downtown
is a pretty small little place if you've never been.
And Red Hat Tower, as we call it, The Tower,
is only two blocks from the convention center,
a short five minute walk.
So I was able to meet up with these listeners, Reed and John,
and take them to lunch at The Tower today, which,
as we record, is Wednesday.
Oh, good, did you get more sauce while you were there?
Alex likes to pick up a little extra sauce
while he's at the Red Hat Tower.
So I think what Chris is referring to there
is Boar's Head, you know the sandwich company?
You think.
You know what I'm referring to.
Make this absolutely delicious, gourmet, spicy mayonnaise,
chipotle mayonnaise style thing.
Yeah, no, it's great.
It is.
And I cannot get enough of it on turkey and provolone sandwiches
when I'm at home during the day.
So what I used to do at The Tower before COVID
was any time I went in The Tower,
I used to go in and buy a bottle of this sauce off the vendor
for, I don't know, like $10.
To put it in context, a tiny little tub of this stuff
from the supermarket is $5.
But a commercial catering size bottle of this sauce,
he gave me for $10 a time.
So I used to just slather this stuff on.
Whereas now I have to treat it like gold dust
because we've got different vendors now after COVID.
That's a bummer.
OK, all right.
So lunch at The Tower, that's awfully nice.
That sounds great.
Yeah, it was nice.
We also met up with Jay from Learnernix TV.
Not going to mess up the creative process.
I'm here with Jay from Learnernix TV.
Hello, Jay.
How are you?
Doing well.
Yeah, I went to your talk yesterday on RetroPie
and how you're saving retro gaming from oblivion.
Yeah, so basically my setup is such that sync thing
syncs all of my RetroPies together.
So if I'm on my handheld RetroPie or the one on the TV,
I could play a game, save the game, then go to the couch.
And it's the same save file.
The ROMs and everything all sync to each other.
So it's just like this thing where my save files just
follow me around.
It's just one of the amazing things
that you could do with technology that you might not
think about right off the top of your head.
But if you put your mind to it, a little bit of creativity,
you'd be surprised what you could come up with.
Turns out if you try hard enough, you can, huh?
Yeah.
You're one of the few people on planet Earth
that's got their hands on the CM4 module, right?
How's that working out for you?
What are you using that for?
So actually, I have a Turing Pi.
So I have four of those in there.
And then I have one in the handheld RetroPie.
So it's actually working out really well.
And the one that I have in the RetroPie,
if it wasn't for Jeff Gehrling, I
wouldn't have it because he actually
messaged me on Twitter like, hey, they have inventory over here.
So if it wasn't for him, I wouldn't have it.
But I actually got the first ones before they got hard to find.
And then later on, like right now, what are they going for?
Some crazy amount of money?
I dread to think.
I haven't looked.
But it's more than double, I think, MSRP.
It's ridiculous, especially the people
that just want to have fun, set up something in their home lab.
They have to navigate scalpers and everything
just to work on the fun projects that they want to work on.
I think that's terrible.
We just want to have fun with our technology.
So how are you finding all things open?
Is this your first one?
Very first one.
So it is very fun.
We have a lot of cool people here.
System76 is here, Red Hat, AlmaLinux,
like a bunch of open source projects.
There's GitLab, Moodle, like countless others.
It's just so much fun to just network with people,
especially you.
I haven't met you in person until this time,
until this event too.
So I'm meeting really cool people.
And I wouldn't trade it for anything.
Yeah, there's something special about an open source
conference, is there?
Well, thank you very much, Jay.
And enjoy the rest of your conference.
I agree with Jay.
SyncThing for the win.
Absolutely one of the MVPs of the last few years for me
has been SyncThing.
Just my background ambient file system sync.
I have Dropbox.
You know, I have Nextcloud.
I've tried these different things.
I think of that as active, persistent syncing.
You see it.
It's got a status.
You know it's happening.
You can bring up the app.
You can look at what's synced.
I kind of look at SyncThing.
You can do all those things with SyncThing.
There's even system tray icons you can get.
But I kind of think of SyncThing as this ambient background
sync that's actually syncing file systems around.
And it doesn't care where you store something.
It doesn't have to be in a particular directory
like Nextcloud or Dropbox does.
It can be anything, anywhere on your file system.
It's pretty cool.
And Jay was using it to sync his Steam Deck emulator
progress with his RetroPie TV emulator progress.
So that no matter where he was, his retro games
were in sync, which is pretty cool.
That's a great idea.
That's a great idea because you don't
want to lose progress when you move between devices.
So maybe next year, I'll see you at all things open.
And in the meantime, keep an eye on the Meetup page
at meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
lino.com slash SSH.
That's where you go to get $100 on a new account
and support the show.
lino.com slash SSH.
We were just talking about events.
That's how I discovered Linode.
It was at a Texas Linux Fest many years ago
in the before times.
And I could tell Texas Linux Fest was special
because it was small, but the signal was very strong.
You know what I mean?
The talks were by heavy hitters who knew their stuff.
They were passionate about their projects.
But the vendors weren't taking it very seriously,
except for Linode.
Linode had a real serious setup.
They were clearly participating.
They would swap so somebody could be at the booth
while somebody could actually attend the sessions.
You could tell they were into it.
And that's when I made a mental note.
I need to check out Linode.
That's almost four years ago now.
And now here they are, right?
They've been sponsoring the self-hosted podcast
from the get-go because it's just the perfect combination
of performance, features, price.
I mean, 30% to 50% cheaper than all the hyperscalers
out there.
And if you like to go to events, and I know you might,
if you're gonna go to the Web Summit,
November 1st through the 4th, Linode's gonna be there.
IT Nation Connect in Orlando, Florida,
the 9th through the 11th, Linode's gonna be there.
There's actually a whole list of events
that Linode's going to.
But try it out.
Even if you're not going to an event, try it out
because it's great performance.
They have systems with super fast CPUs,
MVME hard drives, 40 gigabit connections,
and they're spinning up like a dozen new data centers
next year, so there's just gonna be more and more choice.
So go get the $100 and actually kick the tires
because with that $100, you can actually try it.
You can really see what works and what doesn't work.
Like, you really can try any feature you want
with that $100.
So go with just about, I would imagine.
I don't know.
If you're out, you could probably come up with a way
to spend that $100 in like one day.
But you could also stretch it out for like 60 days.
So go to linode.com slash SSH, sign up, try it out,
and support the show.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Rumor has it that the HA Yellow is in production?
It's here, Alex.
It's here, it's live, and it's glorious.
The Home Assistant Yellow finally arrived
about a year after I crowdfunded it.
I decided, when I saw that it was shipping,
I decided to order an MVME drive for it.
Mine came with a CM4.
I could have sworn I ordered it without a CM4,
a Compute Module 4, but it came with one, which is okay.
My CM4s have eight gigs of RAM, but whatever.
So this one only has four, but that's fine, or maybe two.
I don't know what it is.
It's not enough, but we're getting by.
I hit that, but the first thing I did
is I put that MVME disk in there.
I powered the thing up and discovered very quickly
that it was just running off of the built-in eMMC
and wasn't using my MVME disk.
And I thought, well, now, what am I supposed to do with this?
Just throw it in the garbage.
Get rid of it.
Bye-bye.
And I was digging through the system settings,
and I go in the storage area,
and in the hamburger menu, there's this migrate option.
So I hit that, and it says,
we're gonna move your data over to another disk.
What disk would you like to use?
And the only disk I had available was the new MVME,
about a terabyte.
It says, okay, well, this will take about 15 minutes,
and then we're gonna reboot, and we'll see you then.
So I say, okay, go ahead.
I hit that button.
Little thing starts spinning.
And I just couldn't watch it.
I couldn't, it was too stressful,
because I didn't know what it was doing.
Because again, when it's all like web UI and their own OS,
I have no idea what's happening.
If they told me to go like, you know,
repartition a disk and format it, mount it,
and then update your configuration file
to point to the new mount point,
I'd feel like really solid.
Like, okay, all right, I know I'm done.
But you know, that's not gonna work for most people.
They wanna make it all a gooey option.
So okay, I'll try it.
So I go to bed, and I wake up the next morning,
and I go to the storage area in the settings.
Everything's working, by the way.
I go to the storage area in the settings,
and now it just says like 900 gigs free.
I think it moved everything off of the eMMC,
and it moved everything to the MVME.
I'm not sure exactly what happened,
because it's kind of, it's all kind of abstracted for me.
But the performance is so much better.
And I have to say, I am very happy with the results.
I could not ask for anything better.
And I also decided to just start fresh.
I went clean, I did not restore my backups.
I didn't try to import my old settings.
I just said, I'm gonna burn three or four days straight,
and I'm just gonna reset it up.
And I literally probably spent three days resetting it up.
There is a good argument to, you know,
nuking and paving systems every now and again.
I remember back in the day,
I used to nuke and pave windows every six weeks sometimes,
you know, because it was just that crusty.
You still have to, hasn't changed.
And then, you know, when I get a new phone these days,
still out of force of habit,
I'll start from scratch with a new phone.
But I don't know, like my MacBook here
has got the same install on it as when it came with it.
Like, I don't feel the need to do that anymore.
But Home Assistant, huh, there's so much stuff in there
that I've painstakingly created.
I don't think I could do it.
I had a couple of moments, I think, that saved me.
One was, I downloaded my old backup
from the Raspberry Pi that died,
and I extracted it manually,
and I opened up my configuration YAML,
and I kind of grabbed a few key things
that I knew I wanted, like my generic thermostat stuff,
all of my integrations for my cameras.
I just grabbed that stuff.
So I didn't take the whole config file,
but I just took the bits
that I didn't want to have to recreate from whole cloth.
That was one thing that I think helped a lot,
is I still used my old config file quite a bit.
But the other thing was,
the Z-Wave migration turned out
to be a lot easier than I expected.
The Z-Wave controller had everything
on the network paired to it.
And so when I took that USB dongle,
and I plugged it into the new Home Assistant Yellow,
all of the nodes were still paired to that controller.
They all showed up as brand new devices to Home Assistant.
But all of the networking was already done.
All the node order, all of that was already done.
And so Home Assistant, just using the new integration,
just said, oh, look at all these Z-Wave devices you have.
This is incredible.
And so the only part that was a pain in the butt
was I did have to sit there,
and this was one of the seriously labor-intensive tasks,
and rename every entity, every device entry,
just sit there and rename them,
because it just generates these stupid-ass names.
You know what would be really great?
Imagine if Home Assistant had this paperclip in the corner
that popped up and said,
hey, I noticed you've got some new devices.
Do you wanna set those up?
I mean, super helpful.
I don't think anyone's done that before, have they?
Just something that said,
hey, would you like to just say what you wanna call it now,
so that way you don't spend the next two days
renaming all these things?
Because of course, my sensors,
every single one of my sensors
has eight different entities that it puts in there, right?
All of my power switches
have three or four different entities
that they put into there.
So it's just so, so many items.
That's a good point.
The onboarding workflow of a new device,
I think, could actually use some work in that respect.
Some kind of a wizard or something.
I should say.
So that's my criticism, but I should say,
wow, it has gotten so much easier to set up Home Assistant.
There's so many more UI options for stuff now.
Like scripts, when you're writing a script,
you know, the script thing.
You can just reorder items now.
Oh God, I used to have to rewrite the script
or I'll do it in YAML in the past.
Now you can just reorder items.
It's incredible, the stuff,
just the friction that they, over time, have smoothed out.
It reminded me of like, if you've been playing an MMO
since it launched, like say, Star Trek Online,
and you've been playing it since it launched,
and you've been playing it for like 10 years.
And so like, you're just at the end game
and you've been at the end game for years.
And then you decide to go create an alt account
and you start over from the beginning
and you realize they've completely redone
the beginning of the game.
A totally new tutorial,
a totally new introduction to the game,
a whole new story arc.
And you're like, wow, this is so much better
than when I tried this years ago.
That's where Home Assistant is at now.
It is so much easier to set up.
Interesting.
Well, maybe I should do a new compave.
Just in the interests of science and the show
and stuff like that, huh?
I feel like it was a lot simpler.
I mean, yeah, I had to go through the whole rename thing.
Here's the other thing that's been a lot easier
this time around.
As of right now, I don't have a single automation.
You look smug about that.
Why do you look smug about that?
Oh, I don't know.
My last box, I probably had like 15 automations
and now I don't have a single automation.
And I mean, if you think about it,
I'm sure I will have one eventually.
It's so much simpler.
So I have used the scheduler card custom component
that lets me schedule things in a UI
that is so much more intuitive than using an automation,
that controls the lights and the outdoor stuff,
so much simpler.
And then I've gone all in on thermostat.
So I use the generic thermostat,
which combines a temperature sensor with a smart plug.
So the temperature sensor is used as the thermostat data
and the smart plug gets toggled on and off.
And I just set the temperatures
using generic thermostats now, it's so much easier.
My first pass, they didn't have generic thermostats.
And so I was doing automations based on temperature ranges
and sensor data and it was all manual.
And now it's just so smooth.
And so that made it a lot easier too.
Not having to like rebuild my automations
was a huge time saver.
And so using the scheduler card,
which I will link in,
it's not the scheduler integration,
that's something different.
You want the scheduler card,
I'll have a link to that in the show notes.
And the generic thermostat,
that is just something built into Home Assistant.
Those two things together saved me a ton of ache.
And because the scheduler card allows for things
like presence detection, sunset information,
those types of things,
I was able to avoid creating automations
for things that I used to do all the time.
Nice.
Yeah, oh, it's so great.
It's so great and it's so fast, Alex.
Well, that's what happens when you have real storage,
like an NVMe disk.
Home Assistant is making a lot of little transactions,
which an SD card or even something hanging off the USB bus
just isn't optimized for.
It didn't feel like a problem,
but now it's so fast that like,
have you ever had that thing
where you accidentally like double tap
or something like that?
Like you just kind of like have a finger spasm
and you tap twice when you mean to tap once
or something like that?
Yes.
It's so fast that like, it'll hit it.
It'll boom, boom.
Like when I do that double tap spasm,
light on, light off, just boom, boom.
It's incredible.
There's just, there's literally no delay at all.
And I am so happy with the Home Assistant Yellow
using NVMe storage.
I don't even mind that it's running
its own operating system.
I'm all in right now.
And it's been funny watching my snapshots
as I've configured this thing
when I first started like a 300 kilobyte snapshot
and then a megabyte.
And then two megabytes.
And now my snapshots are like 60 megabytes, right?
It's just as I keep building the system out,
like the backups keep getting bigger and bigger.
I love it, but you are such a nerd.
On my old Pi, I think like the Home Assistant backups
were like 1.2 gigabytes.
And now they're like 70, 80 megabytes
or something around there.
They're just totally, it's a totally leaner, meaner system.
Well, there's a lot of advantages to that.
And I had to take some remedial action
with one of my shellies this week.
My Shelley 2.5 that Brent, the wonderful Brent
helped me install whilst he was here,
that controls my outdoor rear floodlights.
We were down at the fire pit
and I had the lights on the back of the house.
So it was lighting up the yard a little bit.
Every 30 to 60 seconds, they would just turn off
for a second and then turn back on for 30 seconds
and then turn off and then turn back on.
And I'm like, what are you doing?
That's not good, no.
So I go in the Shelley app and then for some reason
the device is rebooting and resetting itself.
So I have to catch the Shelley app just at the right time
where the device is on the network
to even get network connectivity,
to get it to load in the app properly
before it resets itself.
Turns out it only did that when it was under load
with the lights on.
So my guess is there was some kind of a threshold
of maybe temperature, I don't know, being met.
So I did a bit of research and this led me to
something I've done in the past
on a couple of my other shellies,
which is replace the stock firmware,
the Mongoose OS that comes on the Shelley
with one of the more open firmwares,
Tasmota or an ESP home.
There's a link in the show notes,
but essentially the gist is this.
The Shelley is shipped with non-standard
Dupont pin-sized, I don't know what you call it,
jumper pins, where you see you can connect them over USB
with a serial device and reprogram the Shelleys that way
and manually flash the firmware onto them that way.
But this Shelleys already in my wall neatly tucked away
and I don't want to be pulling it out
and doing that kind of thing, really, if I can avoid it.
So I thought I'd try and find a way
that does it over the air.
And in the linked blog post, there is a tool called MG2X.
And this thing allows you to put Tasmota
directly onto the Shelley,
just by using an over the air firmware upload.
And within about 45 seconds, I'd replace the default OS
with a single command in my browser.
That's great.
Is it using a built-in tool or is it an exploit?
I think it must be.
There's no, you know, we've talked about
two-year convert in the past,
which basically created a man in the middle
for these third-party updating things,
which then spoofed the update server.
None of that stuff is needed
because the Shelleys are a lot more open than that.
So I think all it was doing was just providing through,
you know, when you go to a website
and you have like the question mark
and then a few parameters after the question mark,
essentially what it was doing was providing the URL
for the update to this custom firmware, minimal firmware,
to the over the air URL update feature
built directly into the web server of the existing Shelley.
So no weirdness, no hackery going on.
It's just a really cool project.
I see the Shelley plug S is supported.
I actually wasn't really planning to say this,
but I have noticed my least reliable device
in my new setup right now is my Shelley smart plug.
I've just had it go offline a couple of times.
None of my other devices have done that.
And I wonder if it isn't the OS
because the hardware seems pretty solid.
Well, I thought I'd put Tasmotor on there
because it has a temperature monitoring.
And that was, you know, where my mind went to originally
was well, is this device resetting
because there's a temperature limit set in the Mongoose OS
that Shelley ship on these things.
Uh oh, is my house about to catch fire and burn down.
Don't ignore this.
And when I, you know, throw both the light switches on
and put all the juice through this thing,
the maximum temperature it gets to is about 50 Celsius.
So it's totally fine.
It's nothing to worry about from what I can tell.
I don't really have anything negative to say
about Tasmotor on this thing.
I think my original goal was to actually put ESP home
on the Shelley, but I like Tasmotor so much,
I'm just gonna leave it there.
Yeah, why not, right, if it works.
Sometimes you compromise.
I did that.
There was one device that I completely forgot about this,
but it did happen.
There was one device I just had to toss out.
It was a HomeKit device.
It was an LED light strip I bought
that worked with HomeKit.
But you know what the issue was,
is I lost the HomeKit pairing code.
Not only did I lose the HomeKit pairing code,
but I cannot figure out for the life of me
how to get this thing to try to like reintroduce itself
to the HomeKit network.
And I just, I didn't want Wi-Fi, ZigBee, Z-Wave,
and HomeKit, right.
Like I just don't need all of it.
And so I went over to Amazon
and I picked up the Zengled ZigBee smart LED light strip.
It's a 16.4 foot smart light strip.
Now I know guys, I know, I know.
There are ways you can build Z-Wave or ZigBee devices
for pennies on the dollar compared to this.
I understand that.
Here's the situation.
I deployed my new system and the kitchen light strip,
this is the one that my wife uses
while she's cooking to get a little extra light,
wasn't working.
Cause it's a HomeKit one.
And she wanted something fast.
And the wife approval factor was declining
with the new server quickly.
So I snapped up this Zengled ZigBee smart LED strip.
I don't know if I'm saying it right.
It's got LEDs in it and it's got smarts in it.
And it says it's for Alexa and Google.
It's just a ZigBee device.
And so you just, if you have a ZigBee controller,
you just get it, you know, doing the ZigBee thing
and you can control it immediately with Home Assistant.
It picks it up.
You can control the colors, the brightness,
everything works, talks to it natively.
It's 60 bucks from Amazon,
but it is one of these things that you can just buy
and pair immediately natively to Home Assistant.
And we got it up and running in 15 minutes.
And man, did that solve the problem.
And now she's a hundred percent in on the new system.
So I just wanted to give that a plug.
If you're looking for an LED light strip
that you can hook to a ZigBee network
that works with Home Assistant,
I can vouch for this guy
and I'll put a link in the show notes.
It also comes with a remote, which I have not tried yet,
but I believe is also a ZigBee device.
It's just an on and off and brightness.
So it's a little physical remote
that you can mount anywhere.
And I would imagine once you tie it to Home Assistant,
it could control anything.
And the kit I got from Amazon for 60 bucks includes that.
It also includes a ZigBee hub, which I do not need.
Well, tell me about your jellyfin exploits this week.
You've been a busy boy.
Oh, geez.
Oh, geez, you wanna hear about this?
I mean.
Well, I don't know, do we?
You tell me, you tell us, let the audience be your guide.
All right, so it was going real well.
I mean, I thought to myself, here's what I'm gonna do.
I got this whole no container theory.
I think this is gonna work really well.
I'm gonna just install everything natively on Nix.
I'm gonna use the Nix package manager to manage everything.
And I wanted to get a sense of what this would be like
before I actually deployed it on my Odroid,
because I was waiting for an SSD hard drive
and a power cable for that hard drive,
which was a custom order piece.
So I thought in the meantime,
I'll deploy it on my HP dev one,
which already runs Nix OS.
And I'll just start reconfiguring that dev one,
like I would configure a home server.
So I took a external SSD that I had
from the old Raspberry Pi, and I connected that.
So that way I'd have some storage to work with
for a little bit, because it's just an experiment.
And I got that all mounted,
set up with ButterFS like a gentleman,
and set up Jellyfin on Nix OS,
set up Infuse on the Apple TV,
and I was really, really in a good spot.
I tried out Infuse this week because of you.
Oh yeah.
We went to the mountains last weekend
and LNE did a bit of entertainment in the car on the way.
So I thought, oh, well, Chris recommended Infuse on iOS.
So I downloaded a few YouTube videos
and copied a few files across.
Infuse is great.
Oh, you like it, good.
I really like it, yeah.
It's nice.
It is so nice.
And for me, it was a big, I felt like this was a,
this was my best shot for a Jellyfin adoption,
because we're using Infuse on Apple TV for Plex.
And so if I just changed the backend out to Jellyfin,
it's the same exact UI for the family members.
Like nobody would probably notice, right?
And now I could be using Jellyfin, right?
Ooh, you're a smart cookie.
I set it all up on the Nix box.
I got it all working with Infuse.
It was great.
Then one night, we spent one night out in the woods,
just recently, just like a couple of days ago.
We had one night to spend out,
just the wife and I in the woods,
between Halloween and other things going on.
And we get it all set up, candles are lit.
We had an excellent dinner, shared a bottle of wine.
We go back in the bedroom, turn on the television,
decide to watch a little TV.
I launched the Jellyfin app, and it auto-discovers,
like it has on all my other devices,
auto-discovers my Jellyfin instance.
I select the Jellyfin instance.
The wife looks over at me,
appreciating my hard work on setting all this up,
thinking how great I am.
I say, select that server,
and I get back an error message that says,
incompatible server version.
Now I'm in the woods where there's really no cell signal,
so there's no streaming.
I've got the room in romantic mode.
The wife's back there, she's thinking I've done great
getting this whole system rebuilt,
and I cannot get anything to play.
And the Jellyfin app just says, go screw yourself,
your server is out of date.
Because of course, and this happens every now and then,
Nix is really pretty much a bleeding edge
rolling distribution, but it depends on maintainers.
And Jellyfin is just currently out of date on Nix OS.
It's close to getting updated.
They have the next version in testing right now,
as of two days ago, it's really close.
I could technically install it if I wanted to right now.
But you know, if I wanna start playing with goodies,
like skip intro,
well, I'm gonna have to play with plugins,
because Infuse may not even support it if I do,
but Jellyfin doesn't seem to really have native support,
so I'm gonna have to get a plugin that does intro detection
and then automatically skips it server side
and then just streams that to Infuse.
I gotta like hack it around to get it all working
and to do that, I also need their fork of FFmpeg
and I also need everything
to be the absolute latest version.
All of a sudden, I'm pretty much just looking
at like the Linux server IO Jellyfin container
and thinking, why don't I just deploy that?
I'm right back at the container situation.
I'm right back where I began.
And then on top of that, I kinda missplex.
Like the skip intro stuff, huge for me.
I'm watching Star Trek Enterprise right now and I refuse.
I refuse to watch that intro.
I will never watch that intro again, ever.
I've watched it twice in my life,
when it premiered and when I played it for my wife.
And after that, I will never watch that intro again,
I refuse.
And the third time when you loaded up Jellyfin
and there wasn't this skip intro button.
Yes, yeah, oh my God, I came running across the room
for the remote, I'm like, no.
Yeah, and I had to fast forward like an animal.
And so, like I missed that.
Also, if you're using the native apps,
and I think you'll agree, Alex,
the Plex app is way better.
It's not perfect, but yeah, it is better.
Just the layout's better, the design, everything.
It's a shame.
If you're using Infuse, it's exactly the same.
But yeah, so I realized that this NixOS package
is gonna get updated.
And this won't be an issue for much longer.
But it could be an issue again.
And sometimes the TV breaks at absolutely
the worst moment possible.
And that's what happened to me, you know?
You know, and that's why I adopted Plex
and the Nvidia Shield as kind of like
the default media setup in the house.
Most of the time, and I would say more than 95% of the time,
Plex and the Nvidia Shield just get the job done reliably.
I am enjoying the real-time updates of Adia's face
in the Discord chat, are you enjoying that too?
They're having a good time, aren't they?
For the listeners, there's a picture of a lady,
it's not Adia, but just pulling a completely straight face
of, I asked him to put on Netflix.
He glances at me and starts fumbling
with some weird cable on his TV and laptop.
We sit there while he does something on his laptop
with a trembling finger and mumbles something
about torrents.
This one's hitting close to home.
Yes, it is.
Yeah, yeah, oh man.
Yeah, so, you know, the ironic thing is,
I mean, I do follow what you're saying,
but the ironic thing is, if we were watching
on the Apple TV with Infuse,
it wouldn't have been a problem,
but because we are on the Nvidia Shield
and it had auto-updated the Jellyfin app,
I just got this incompatible error.
But I will say, every time I try Jellyfin,
it gets a little bit better.
Of course, Plex is moving on as well at the same time,
which doesn't help.
But, you know, I think in the next year or two,
the tipping point will come.
We're really close to where Jellyfin will be good enough
to have that Chrome, you know, like skip intro,
that, you know, those little things that I really value.
And once we're there, I won't look back when I switch,
you know, when it's ready, it's gonna be amazing.
I think it's there for me now, we're using Infuse.
And so my plan is to absolutely deploy it
at home and then keep Plex at the studio.
So I'm like not giving up Plex,
I'm gonna have Plex running here at the studio
on the studio server where we have like,
JB Media, My Archived Media, we share it with people,
like that'll be the core Plex setup.
But then at my home setup,
that I'm gonna keep with Jellyfin.
And I haven't tried it yet,
but there is a plugin that lets you scan and skip intros.
It has a couple of limitations, but I think it makes sense.
The intro has to be within the first 25% of an episode
or the first 10 minutes.
And the intro has to be between 15 and two minutes long,
15 seconds and two minutes long.
And if it meets those criteria,
supposedly it can detect it and then mark it.
And then on the setting side,
you can just tell the Jellyfin server
automatically just skip it.
Don't even ask the client, just skip the intro.
And I think that'll be fine, that'll work for me.
And if that's the case,
then overall I'm very happy with Jellyfin.
I think it'll be good.
A lot of the work that Plex did
with their sonic fingerprinting
and all that kind of stuff to detect the intros
was extremely impressive,
but I think just given a bit more time.
And Jellyfin is not a commercial project like Plex,
of course, so they are gonna be in a different class
of speed of development and polish and all that kind of stuff.
I'm willing to accept those compromises
for my media library being air quotes free.
And perhaps not monitored.
I mean, I can't make that claim.
I don't know if Plex is gonna monitor,
but I could see how commercial interests
would persuade them to, but also just that aside,
Jellyfin works a little better offline than Plex does.
And I am ultimately always trying to build this system
to operate as seamlessly as possible
with no internet connection.
And with Plex, that sometimes falls down.
Well, like we talked about with Rune last week,
for you, where your internet connectivity comes and goes,
something like Rune where it just has zero minutes
of guaranteed offline playback is just not an option.
I didn't renew my Rune.
I didn't buy Rune after my free trial, by the way,
in case anybody was interested.
I thought about it long and hard after the episode,
but in the end, I just couldn't do it.
Yeah, Jellyfin is just that, it's like, what was it?
Kodi, XBMC, it's like what that project could have been,
you know, turned into, it's like the modern version of that.
And I'm so happy to see it's moving
from strength to strength.
Jupiter.party, if you'd like to support the entire network,
invest in the ongoing content creation
and get the shows ad-free,
you can get every single Jupiter Broadcasting production
at Jupiter.party.
Become a member and get the shows ad-free
like Self-Hosted, including the Self-Hosted post-show,
only available to our members at Jupiter.party,
and of course, our Self-Hosted SREs.
All right, time for some feedback, I think.
Julian F. writes in via matrix,
I was excited to hear about the Mycroft Mark II,
but then discovered Mycroft STT service
is a proxy for Google's STT.
I think that means speech to text.
Has anyone found a comparison of various home assistants
and how relatively good and private each system is?
I noticed there's a Mycroft integration
for home assistant, but is it any good?
This is a tough problem.
The voice assistant stuff is kind of necessary in my house.
Like that's how my kids prefer to interact
with home assistant, and honestly,
I'd say my wife probably 50% of the time-ish,
somewhere in that range,
she likes to interact with home assistant through voice.
You guys know my solution has been the HomePod.
The downside there is HomePods require internet
to do the voice transcription,
and they're doing it on Apple servers.
The upside is that once it figures out what you're saying,
it executes that over the LAN,
where some devices use like an API
and a cloud system and all that.
I don't know if that's same for Mycroft,
other than it sounds like they're using
Google speech to text, which that's not ideal.
Do you have a sense of this one, Alex?
There are zero voice assistants deployed in production
in this house, because as we've talked about several times,
they are just getting worse and more annoying
and more naggy, and hey, by the way,
did you know that you, no, no, shut up.
I just want to know what the weather is,
or I'm not interested, okay?
I've never really played around with it
until just this most recent build,
but when you subscribe to Nebuchadnezzar Cloud
for Home Assistant, one of the features you get
is their text-to-speech service.
I don't know if you've tried it,
but it sounds better than Google's.
I did a little A-B comparison and had the family say
which one they liked better.
They all picked the Nebuchadnezzar text-to-speech service,
and I mean, it's on their servers,
so I don't know how, maybe they're just
proxying somebody else, but I've been using that,
so I have nighttime scripts,
like we've talked about in the show before,
and now, when the script kicks off,
it uses the Nebuchadnezzar text-to-speech service
to play on all the HomePods that the bedtime mode
is starting, and everybody's got 15 minutes
to get their ass to bed, and it sounds great,
but it's not local.
I imagine it's more private than using the Google one,
I'd love something local.
It's something that could tie into a speaker.
I don't care if I have to build the device for it,
a little microphone.
In fact, in a way, I'd prefer to build my own device
because I could build it with badass microphones
positioned right where I need them.
That's the key, isn't it, local, local, local.
Yeah, absolutely.
We did link to the integration for Mycroft
that Julian also included.
If you know, let us know.
If you've seen a comparison of Home Assistance,
if you have a little bit of experience you've done,
or if you have a Mycroft that you've tried
with Home Assistant, let us know.
Selfhosted.show slash contact,
or you can send us a boost with a new podcast app,
and speaking of boosts, Gene Bean came in this week
with a really generous 20,480 SATs,
and Gene has a question.
How do y'all back up your Nextcloud?
I'm running the snap version on Debian for now,
it's just simplicity, but I'm totally game to change it
as I have to migrate servers at some point anyways.
So how do you back up your Nextcloud?
Well, all of my containers,
and I run Nextcloud in a container, of course,
is they're all backed, all of their app data,
which is what I call a kind of persistent data
of these containers, they're all ZFS volumes,
and then I just replicate those across the world
to various different servers that I have.
I've got one upstairs, so my main server's in the basement.
I use ZFS Send, which is wrapped in Jim Salter's
Sanoid and Syncoid tooling, to send it to a box
that I have under my desk up here,
which has just got a couple of 10 terabyte drives in it,
as a full ZFS replication of what's in the basement
in case of a pipe burst or something,
and then I don't have to rely on the internet
to get that data back.
If this house blows down for whatever reason,
then I've got stuff on the other side of the Atlantic
that I can recover from.
And then as a third prong to that backup strategy,
I use Autoresstick as a wrapper around RESTIC
to send my stuff over to Synology as well,
and that does all the app data on a file level
as opposed to ZFS's block level.
So I've got kind of a two-prong approach
to how I back up that data.
I'm wondering what people do when they want to back up
like 25 terabytes of data.
Well, the only option realistically
is to either pay through the nose for Glacier
or something like that with AWS,
or to build a server and stick it at a friend's house.
I mean, once you're getting above the sort of 20, 50,
100 terabyte numbers, the monthly payments on that
would pay for a server somewhere else pretty quickly.
I think you're right.
GeneBean also sent another 2048 SaaS just
to say that he's really been enjoying the random live feeds
over at jupyter.tube, and he's looking forward
to deets on the Odroid.
We don't mention it all the time.
I hope we've mentioned it frequently,
but if you don't know, we have been live streaming over
at jupyter.tube, which is our own JB self-hosted instance
of PeerTube, which is like a YouTube in a box.
We mostly just use it to just record
how we make the live show, or how we record
the shows live and all that.
But you could use it if you are an open source
project, or a church, or like a city council,
or a school district.
You could use it as your own private YouTube instance
with playlists, and accounts, and all that kind of stuff.
User 9014, using Fountain, hasn't set their username.
Boosted it with 1,200 sats.
Tinkers will be tinkers.
I'm trying to boost thing with the Fountain app.
So far, I'm not really a fan of the app.
I love the concept of value for value,
but the app coming from Pocket Casts, to me,
it's just not the same.
Maybe it's just me being an asshole Android developer.
I'll keep trying the other 2.0 apps.
Thanks for the shows, though.
I love them all.
Sending love from Spain.
Una Cerveza, por favor.
I agree, it's an uphill adoption.
I'm not going to lie to you.
It took me a solid month to wrap my head around Fountain.
Really, what made Fountain stick for me is I started discovering
new podcasts through their clips feature.
And then I was like, I was on board.
But I've been hearing from some people,
they'll stick with their favorite app,
and they'll use Podverse.fm, the web app,
to boost into the show.
User 1692 wrote in with 1,500 sats.
I just wanted to let you know that the Rune Lifetime used
to only be $499.
The CEO has threatened to pull it at some point,
as it's not sustainable.
And so I buckled and bought the Lifetime.
A one-off purchase for me is way better than $10 a month.
I just thought you'd like to know.
I'm a bit more inclined for that kind of thing, too.
I mean, $499 is a little rich for my blood.
Well, it's $699 now.
Yeah, and sometimes every now and then,
those things have a Black Friday sale.
Probably not Rune, but $500 for a Lifetime, I'd have to use it.
I'd have to use it for at least five years consistently for me
to start to at least.
In the time since the last episode,
my free trial has expired, as I mentioned.
But the feature voting section of the Rune forum,
re-enabling offline grace period for the server
has become their most requested feature ever
in the space of a week, which I just think is amazing.
That tells you something, doesn't it?
It does, and it will be really interesting to see
whether they listen or not.
And that will dictate, for me, the posture of the company
and the product moving forward.
Huge signal.
Depending on how they react to this
will depend as to whether I become a customer or not.
Yeah, you're right.
This is a defining moment for them.
It really is, yeah.
I'm really grateful DexSword boosted in with 901 SATs,
because I probably heard about this five times
in this last week since I started
talking about the Odroid.
He says, have you guys looked at the Ximura board?
I've been tempted to get one instead of a Raspberry Pi.
I think we've talked about this on the show before, Alex.
We've had some feedback about it, definitely.
It's one of those boards that just looks really cool,
but I don't personally have a use case for it,
so I haven't bought one.
But the more of you becomes SREs,
maybe we can think about buying one.
How about that for a plug?
There you go.
I am just too skeptical to spend my own hard-earned money
on this thing.
I don't know, I think I've been burned too many times.
It is a Intel quad core based system
that is wrapped inside a, like it
looks like it's a ruggedized case that has
a heat sink that's built into it.
And so it's almost something like you
could install in a vehicle, which
I think is one of the reasons why people have hit me up
so much about it, because it looks
like it's meant to be installed in a vehicle,
because it's so ruggedized.
So a company like Odroid has a track record,
but the Zima people, Z-I-M-A, I don't
know anything about them.
I don't know if they're going to be around.
It doesn't seem like many people have this.
And if this thing isn't successful,
does the company begin and end right here?
Like I have so many questions about this device,
too, in terms of performance and storage.
And I just don't trust it enough to spend my own money
to try it.
I agree, it looks perfect for somebody like me.
And it does have a PCI slot, which I would love.
It's really strange, isn't it?
So it's got a PCI 2.0 X4 PCIe slot, and two SATA ports,
and two gigabit LAN ports.
Yeah, it looks really good.
So it would make a pretty good NAS kind of brain.
I agree.
It's just that the Odroid looks like a complete solution that's
ready to go.
And to this, this just looks like it's a Kickstarter.
But I know it's not.
Well, it was.
Yeah, it was.
It was, but it's been fulfilled now, I think,
which is not guaranteed with Kickstarter, is it?
I've just been burned so many times
to spend $120 on something like this.
But I really like the look of it.
If the Odroid wasn't a thing, I may be tempted.
It is close to that.
But now, it just feels silly.
I don't need it.
And yeah.
I mean, with a PCIe 4X slot, you could do quite a lot
with this thing.
You could stick a couple of extra SSDs in there.
You could put a 10 gig ethernet in there.
I mean, you could do a lot of cool stuff with it.
It's a bit of a weird form factor as well.
It's kind of like got a heat sink built into it,
and then the PCI slots hanging off the side.
And what form factor is this designed for?
It looks a little bit odd in that respect.
But it's certainly something I'm keeping an eye on.
All right.
I'm going to try to move fast because we
got some great ones.
But I want to give a mention to MG boosted
in a row of ducks, 222 SATs.
So they've been very happy with LMS and Squeeze Light
running on Pi's.
So there's some more feedback there.
J Cube sent their first boost this week,
and they just started the show at episode 73.
That's amazing.
Neve came in with 2004 SATs.
2004 is the year of NGINX.
That's when it was created.
Ubuntu's first release.
I didn't realize those two things.
Gen 2 was not for weirdos at the time.
That was the year Neve's car was built,
and the first time they ever saw a terminal emulator.
And they just wanted to share.
And then Acorn wanted to know your favorite terminal app.
They say they like Lazy Docker Project, Htop,
those types of things.
Do you have a terminal app that's
one of your go-tos, besides the obvious Emacs?
I think it must be Hollywood, that kind of one
that makes me look like a legit hacker
in the background with some of my live streams.
That's a great answer.
We got to put a link to that.
Hollywood snap.
I'll put a note right there.
Check it out.
There's a snap for it that makes your computer look
like it's doing amazing things.
That's a great answer.
Bashtop is also a really great one,
just in terms of just visualizations and whatnot.
And then Thumbs comes in with our last boost, 10,000 SATs.
Do you guys ever have memories of what you were listening
to at a specific place?
I just pulled into a parking lot I haven't
been to in a couple of years, and I
was taken back to the moment.
I was listening to episode two with Wendell.
Thanks for the years of memories and great content.
I'm a network member, but I thought
you deserve some extra value for that memory.
You know, for me, I can think of a JB memory.
This was when I was doing my computer science masters
back in 2015, 13, 14 period.
And I was listening to you and Mike on Coda
talk about whatever nonsense it was you
were talking about at the time.
And I thought, you know what?
I actually know a little bit about this stuff.
Maybe I should get a career in it.
The funny thing about Coder, that
might have been around the time we were interviewing
the two co-founders of Docker before it was called Docker.
I remember, yeah.
And that is an old, if somebody can find that in the archives,
that's a great, that's a really great old interview.
Before it was even called Docker,
I forget the name right now.
Yeah, Mike always remembers.
So that's my job is just to remember
that we did the interview, and then he
remembers what they called it.
But they didn't start with Docker.
It's fascinating, too, because we asked them
a little bit about their business ideas.
People are still asking some of the questions we
asked them in that interview.
Thank you to Hannegan, or Hannegan, don't know,
sent 3,000 sats, 5,000 sats from a Ninja Mort.
No messages with those.
They just sent them in when they were listening.
We also got a few other boosts in there
that didn't quite make it to the show,
because we got to keep it tighter.
But I just want to say thank you, everybody.
It's a big motivator.
It really is a nice boost to morale,
and it's also a great way to show value.
Go get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com,
or become a member.
You can go to selfhosted.show slash SRE,
and invest in the ongoing production.
A boost is a great way to say good job,
or get a message on the show.
And the membership is a great way
to invest in ongoing production.
Selfhosted.show slash SRE.
We should probably mention The Matrix.
I mean, we do have a Discord, too.
That's been rocking the whole episode
at selfhosted.show slash Discord.
But maybe honorable mention for The Matrix,
because it was useful for the meetup.
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Matrix for deets on that.
Thank you, Alex, because I know early this morning,
when the OpenSSL patches went out,
you got out and got the JB infrastructure all updated.
So thank you for doing that for us.
By the time this comes out, people know about that.
Yeah.
Well, there was a big vulnerability released
this morning in OpenSSL.
Only the second ever, I think, critical marked CVE,
something to do with remote code execution.
Actually, it turned out I didn't have to do a whole bunch,
because I had already set up unattended upgrades
in all of our Ubuntu boxes that we use.
So by the time I'd logged in, it had already
gone and done the unattended upgrade
for the security patches.
It was just an example, I suppose, of good sysadmining.
But I went on to check anyway, just in case.
You heard it here.
You heard it here, everybody.
Alex recommends using Ubuntu systems with auto updates.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, it's still good to have it done, so thank you.
If you'd like to send us your feedback, like I said,
new podcast app or self-hosted.show slash contact.
And you can go and find me over on Elon's latest play
thing at Twitter.
I am at Ironic Badger.
I'm over there at Chris LAS.
And the podcast is at Self-Hosted Show.
$44 billion for a toy.
Can you imagine?
For a pain in the neck.
Yeah, crazy.
Anyway, thanks for listening, everybody.
That was self-hosted.show slash 83.