Are you getting tired of the thunderbolt single cable promise? I know I am.
I thought you were going to do an ad. Well then friends,
I have something special for you. It's the super thunderbolt cable promise.
PetsOvernightInTheBox.com.
No, seriously, I just bought a CalDigit TS4 a couple of months ago.
You know, it's plugged into my MacBook with Thunderbolt 4 as well.
So, you know, the signal chain is extremely simple so far as Thunderbolt goes.
This thing is frustrating, very frustrating, because when I wake it from sleep, my MacBook,
I mean, nine times out of 10, I have to unplug and replug every USB device from the dock.
So I go over to the CalDigit website and I think, okay, cool, there must be a firmware
update for this thing. Turns out a Thunderbolt 4 dock marketed primarily at Mac users,
they don't have a Mac-based firmware update utility. It's only for Windows.
No, no, that's ridiculous. That's embarrassing.
Seriously, it is embarrassing. I totally agree. So luckily for me, I have a ThinkPad T480S,
which has Thunderbolt 3 on it. So I wipe the thing. I put Windows on it specifically
just to update the firmware on this dock. Get all the way through the rigamarole of
installing Windows, which is still a pain in the ass. And then I go to update the
firmware on the dock and it says Thunderbolt firmware mismatch. Thunderbolt 3, isn't it?
Oh, no.
Right. So you can't update a Thunderbolt 4 device from a Thunderbolt 3 device?
Oh, no, you can. So I got in touch with CalDigit support, which took me about a week and a half
to get through the hoops I needed to get through via email. They then informed me that my firmware
on the T480S was out of date and I needed to use the firmware update tool to update the
ThinkPad's firmware. And for some reason, it wasn't working from Windows. So I wiped
Windows and I used FWAPD on Linux to update the firmware on this fricking laptop.
You could have just used a live image, Alex.
Amazing. I love this.
Oh, Brent, I could have, couldn't I?
Yeah.
I love this so much. You must have been like in a fugue state. You were just trying to get
this done.
You know, I was losing the will to live slowly, but surely. Anyway, long story short, eventually
I got the firmware update done. It took way longer than it should have done. We're talking
like two weeks to finally get everything, all the moon and the stars aligned correctly
to make this thing happen. I go to open my laptop today to record this show and guess
what? The USB devices didn't show up. So it was all for nothing.
Ah, this does confirm my personal bias in that I think CalDigit makes the worst Thunderbolt
docks. And I know some podcasters out there, big talk CalDigit, but I've never liked them.
And I have owned one CalDigit and I never went back. And I've owned two OWC Thunderbolt
docks and never had problems. But I don't know if they've been Thunderbolt 4 docks.
They might have been Thunderbolt 3 docks. But I also think the OWC docks look better.
I think they're better looking docks too. So there's that. I'll put a link in the show
notes. I swear by my TS3+, that thing has been extremely solid for me. I had a bad experience
with the TS3 Pro, the smaller one from CalDigit, where it caused a broadcast storm of packets
on my network and literally took out my entire LAN until I unplugged the thing whenever the
Mac went to sleep. So, you know, out of the three CalDigit products I've bought, only
one has functioned as advertised so far. It's not going so well.
Alex, can I ask why you thought you should upgrade to the Thunderbolt 4?
Well, I need, you know, in my house, I have a home set up like in my family room where
I sort of hang out and record podcasts and stuff. And then I have a home office downstairs
and work provided me with a MacBook. And so I thought, oh, wouldn't it be great if I just
had a Thunderbolt cable in each place and I can just plug in whatever computer I have
and I'm good to go. This TS4 has 2.5 gig Ethernet as well. So I thought, hmm, that's a tasty
little upgrade.
I also love the idea. I've had some success, but again, it's all Thunderbolt 3. I know
this sounds weird, but I really love Thunderbolt and I wish it was more widely used. There's
definitely some uptake in the PC side of things, but it's still predominantly a Mac tech. And
it's so much better than USB.
It's just too expensive. When it works, it's fantastic. But, you know, you look at how
USB is with USB hubs and switches and all that kind of stuff. I need all that for Thunderbolt
2, however technically difficult it is to implement. And I need it to not cost $300
or $400 every time I want to buy a peripheral.
It reminds me of Firewire back in the day.
It is very much. Same, same like, I think they're cousins. Same kind of lineage. Alex,
I know that you've been continuing to de-Google like I have. This trend has not slowed for
me. I am so far Google Photos free once again after getting sucked back in a year ago when
they got me some free storage. And I have yet to delete the photos, but I have a full
side like secondary system that's working all the way. It's backing up. I'm trying Storage
J for the first time. I don't know if you've played around with those guys, but it's pretty
cheap decentralized S3 compatible storage. And I'm using that with Duplicati to do backups
like I'm making moves, Alex. The de-Googling thing is continuing even while on the road.
Next step is I'm going to try out Graphene OS on my Pixel 3. Not there yet because I
had to find the Pixel 3 first.
That's great to hear. I've been looking at Photosync on iOS this week, which also supports
S3 storage backends. I'm not quite ready to talk about in the show yet. Like I'm still
figuring it out and making it work as I want to.
You figure it out.
Thanks.
Figure it out.
We didn't we didn't welcome Brent to the show yet. Hello, Brent. How are you?
Oh, hi. I'm doing well. I'm being reminded that almost exactly a year ago we were doing
the same on the road trip. I was sat in this very seat doing a self-hosted with you both.
And we were talking about de-Googling. We talked about maps. So it's kind of our yearly review.
And the maps thing is stuck. You know, since then I am still Google Maps free.
Wow.
However, I realized kind of recently that I do use Waze on occasion. And that is actually
a Google product. So there's that. But I don't use it actually for Nav, you know,
but I just use it for the police stuff.
Apple Maps is surprisingly good these days.
Yeah, I've had I've had I'd say I've had a 90% success rate.
That's impressive. I mean, I can't say that I've given up Google Maps yet. I want to.
But maybe one day. So any talking about the de-Googling side of things, I was focusing on
audio for the last couple of weeks, really. And I have, for some reason, I've got about
feels like a nearly a dozen Google Home Minis dotted around this house. I got for like $5
offers or free or I've just acquired an unbelievable number of these things over the years.
Also a couple of Chromecast audios. And so I've been using these things in home audio groups or
speaker groups, I think is the Google phrase to create a whole home audio solution. I haven't
been 100% happy with it, but it's honestly just been good enough. And, you know, sometimes
when you just want some tunes or in the shower or something like that, or just, you know,
tidy in the house, you just want the same song playing everywhere. However, as you all know,
Google are not currently flavor of the month with me or Chris. And the goal was still is
whole home audio in sync through multiple different amplifiers and different speaker
types and all that kind of stuff. And so in my family room, I have a discreet amplifier
plugged into a pair of passive floor standing loudspeakers. Downstairs, I have another one
in the kitchen area. Again, it's just a normal amplifier, no smarts to it, no network
connectivity, nothing like that. And I've really struggled to integrate these into home
assistant and the smart home in general. And so I went on a bit of a mission this week to try and
solve that. And a few pieces of the puzzle had to fall into place to make this happen. So first of
all, I thought I would tackle the audio playback side of these things, because there's no, you
know, network jack on these on these amplifiers. So I needed to use some other hardware to act as
a Spotify Connect endpoint and Airplay endpoint for when I'm using Plex Amp. And I came across
a bunch of feedback from a couple of years ago when I was talking about doing a similar thing
whilst I was drumming, and allowing people in the house to listen to the backing track that I'm
playing along to through the speakers throughout the rest of the house. I never actually acted on
much of that feedback back then I just sort of stuck with the Google Home thing and the Chromecast
audios. And it, like I said, it sort of worked good enough, but we are where we are today. And
so I tried a few things this week, one of them that's still on my to do list that's very high up
there, I just haven't got to eat yet is called snap cast. So if you're about to write an email
telling me to check out snap cast, don't worry, I'll get to it next time. The first thing I tried
was something called pi core player. And the reason that I wanted to use this was because I've
got a couple of Raspberry Pi sat in the drawer behind me. Well, actually, they're deployed now.
So they're out of the drawer and actually in use, which is amazing. But pi core player primarily
for me was a vehicle to run the Spotify Connect software, the share play, the share port software
for AirPlay one compatibility, and something called Logitech media server. I don't know if you
remember this. It's a really old piece of software. It's about 10 years old or so. Does it do basic
DLNA? Is that what it does? Well, I think back in the day, Logitech made a piece of hardware called
the squeeze box. Do you remember that? Oh, I do remember the squeeze box. Yes. And it was their
kind of vision of what the smart home smart media world should look like. But they were just 10 years
too early with it. And I'm not exaggerating with that. No, everybody, you're like the whole idea
was rip your CDs and get them on this thing, right? They were just before Spotify. It was before
music in the cloud, really. Yeah. And you had this kind of piece of hardware that sat on a coffee
table or was like a small like little touchscreen, almost like a tablet, but before touchscreens are
actually any good. This media server kind of sat behind this thing and indexed your files and
connected to internet radio was the was the sales pitch back then. Of course, now internet radio is
Spotify and Pandora and all that other stuff. You know, it kind of created its own cloud in a way,
which is sort of what you needed back then. I suppose that the idea, thinking about it now,
is kind of a fun one. And if you've got one out there, you could sell it for a decent price,
for a decent price, depending on how good the condition is. What? Yeah. Yeah. Like a decent
decent condition one's going for 400 bucks online right now. Because it's like a museum piece,
right? I don't know. Because people love this stuff. I don't know what it is. But you know,
the idea is pretty great. So this thing can run the indexing back end or what Alex, the receiver?
Well, so this there's two things at play here. This Logitech media server, which is the
has has been abandoned by Logitech now, as I understand it, and taken up by the open source
community and kind of improved over the years. Fundamentally, though, it's still the same old
piece of crap underneath. And I don't wish to be rude about it. But I guess I kind of have been
already. It's just not. It's just not a modern application. But Alex, it has an iPod aux in
in back when they had audio connections, right? Yeah, back when they had audio ports.
So I was using pi core player to actually host LMS. And pi core player is pretty cool. Actually,
it boots fast and it runs entirely in RAM. So it doesn't write to your Raspberry Pi's SD card,
unless you want to save any settings. And it can stream from all sorts of services like Spotify
and Deezer and tidal and BBC music and a bunch of other stuff. And it was a pretty simple setup,
you know, typical pi stuff, you just flash an image to the SD card. And five minutes later,
you've got a working system. Trouble is, the interface once this thing loads up looks like
it was written in about 1984. And it's got lots of little tweaks and buttons. I'm sure the
developers of that interface know exactly where they are and which dials to tweak. And it's just
it's not an interface written by humans for humans. You know what I mean? Yeah. And it makes
it not only is it a challenge for you, but forget spousal approval, if you ever want to know, man,
you know, well, my goal for spousal approval was simply to have it appear as a Spotify Connect
endpoint. You know, when you list the devices, and it says, you know, here are speakers that support
like, like a Chromecast list or an Airplay list or something like that. My goal was for her not
to actually ever interact with this thing. Just except from like, on her phone, maybe it's one
of the available output options. Correct. But I've got to interact with it and try and figure this
thing out. Unfortunately, pi core player, I don't think is quite it. I couldn't get the speaker
groups set up as I wanted or configured correctly, whether that was my fault or the interface or the
hardware I've got. I don't know, it just took up an entire evening of my time. And I just got by
the end of the evening, I got quite frustrated and gave up, frankly, were you able to get it
working at all? Like, did you get any piece of it working? It's still running behind me. It's
booted on the Raspberry Pi that's on my desk behind me. And it's still sat there providing
a Airplay endpoint. But what I ended up doing was actually pulling out my Raspberry Pi two out of
the drawer, probably the oldest Raspberry Pi I have. And I threw another project on it called
rpi audio receiver. There'll be a link to it in the show notes. And this is a simple lightweight
audio receiver with Bluetooth, Airplay one and Spotify connect built in. I couldn't honestly
believe that within one minute of it booting and configuring a couple of things from the command
line, there's a script you install on Raspberry Pi OS, it just worked. That's nice. After my whole
evening futzing around with Pi core player, this thing just worked within a minute. I was like,
is that it? Oh, great. Cool. Isn't that what you'd expect to really, because all of these things are
just using like broadcast DNS and stuff to just discover each other. So you just need to get it
on the network, I would imagine, right? You must have had to give it what DHCP, there must have been
some sort of network config info, and then it just boots up. Yeah, well, so it's a Raspberry Pi two.
So I just installed Raspberry Pi OS on it. And then you clone the Git repo, and you run the install
script, which sets up Bluetooth, it sets up Shareport sync, and Ross Spotify, which is an
open source Spotify client for Raspberry Pi. And then once you've configured it via the script,
asks you for a couple of credentials, you're good to go. Wow. I mean, I guess setting up
Raspberry Pi is not too bad. Raspberry Pi OS doesn't take too long. But it is a step.
What took the longest was the Raspberry Pi two installing all the packages. I mean,
oh, I slow I bet that took about 45 minutes to run the script. I think I couldn't believe how
slow it was. I think I was texting Brent at the time saying, Oh, yeah, this thing is just one step
away from junk. But yeah, it's old. But I mean, it doesn't need to be that fast. It does the trick
for playing audio. And one thing I can't say was the case for pi core player. Sadly, one of the
biggest issues with it beyond the interface was that audio just kept skipping. Oh, and that's just
no good. These days, you'd think and that was running on a pi four as well. So for anybody
that thinks it was the pi two that couldn't cope with it. The pi four couldn't cope with streaming
a Spotify stream through pi core player. Okay, so that's no good. Yeah, I have a question, Alex,
why did you decide to like downgrade to a pi two and not just switch over to the pi four? I was
trying to do too many things at once. I think just, I happened to have that one in the drawer.
I knew that I wanted to deploy two of these things to both amplifiers in the house. And I only had
one Raspberry Pi four and one Raspberry Pi two. So I knew that the pi two was going to have to be
used at some point. I kind of figured out the pi core player wasn't where I wanted to be fairly
quickly. But even though I kept at it, and so I was googling for other stuff in the meantime,
whilst it was doing its thing. Yeah, I've been there. You've already got you've already burned
a pie. It's working on another version. I got I got to put this on a different one. That's why
you got to just have so many pies, Alex. Now you understand my problem. I know. There you go. I'm
I'm inducted. So the last piece of the puzzle was figuring out how to control these dumb
amplifiers. And for that I turned to IR blasters, which is the technology that I've used for many
years with the Logitech Harmony Hub system. But Logitech again, they're turning into Google,
aren't they with deprecating products. They stopped supporting the Harmony Hub, which I still
have one, but I don't want to deploy a new piece of hardware in the house. For starters, I only
have one of them. And secondly, I don't want to deploy a piece of hardware. There's already end
of life. I bought a Broadlink RM4 Mini. And this is an infrared blaster that I can use to program
from Home Assistant, infrared codes from my remote control to change the inputs on the amplifiers,
and then couple that with Home Assistant to detect the source changes on the Raspberry Pi media
player. And it will automatically change the inputs on the amplifier based on what's happening
in the real world right now. It's it's not perfect, unfortunately. So there's a bug, I think,
in the Broadlink integration where I will need to toggle between the three inputs I have on on the
amplifier in a random order, in order for it to actually end up on the correct one eventually at
the end of it, like it just doesn't send the right command. And I can't figure it out. So I
just spam the inputs and eventually it gets where I want it to be. That sounds a bit annoying. It
is. And ultimately, that's why I hate infrared blasters is because they have no knowledge of
what the end result, you know, was their blasting successful? Well, they have no idea. Yeah, that
does sound a little rickety. A little brittle, I guess. The trouble I've got though is both of
these dumb amplifiers don't have an RS232 port. They don't have any other way of controlling them
besides infrared. So I'm kind of stuck really, unless I buy two new amplifiers, which sounds
like it's going to be expensive. What's your sense of the reliability so far? When it works,
it works. When it doesn't, it doesn't. Hmm. Hit and miss. Yeah. Yeah, about 80%
just is not it's not high enough. I bet you there is some sort of some sort of solution out there
for this. Somebody out there listening has solved this problem. I solve it with HomePods. I admit
it. I'm a filthy iOS ecosystem user. And I just solve it with HomePods. Well, Alex, since you're
not satisfied, what's your next step? Well, the trouble is, both of these amplifiers are sort of
audio file grade amplifiers, like the one in the family room powers those beautiful big floor
standing Kef speakers that I've had for forever. And it I am super happy with the sound profile of
these things. And I don't want to replace it. So I don't know if you have a better idea, maybe
an infrared blaster that's more reliable than the broad link that you could recommend me and
I could try out. Please let me know at self hosted dot show slash contact. Linode dot com slash SSH
go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you get to support the show while
you're trying out something really awesome shows made possible by folks like you taking advantage
of our sponsors offer. And Linode is one that we can enthusiastically endorse. You know, they started
in 2003 as one of the very first companies of what we now call cloud computing. And now nearly 19
years later, they're at the top, man. They are like the best the cream of the crop in performance,
pricing, support, flexibility. I mean, you just name it. They got 11 data centers around the
world. They are their own ISP. They've invested heavily and continue to do so in high performance
hardware. So they just make cloud computing simple, affordable and accessible. And as a
self hoster, I love the control I get. I have several in nodes that I have just nuked and built
from the metal up running. One of them runs Nix and one of them runs a super crazy custom VPN Linux
and Linode works with you to do all of that. They're not trying to prevent that kind of stuff.
What other provider out there combines that flexibility with pricing that's 30 to 50% cheaper
than the major hyperscalers? And then they wrap it all up with great support because that's how
they've architected the business. And they always have the latest Linux distros ready to go. They've
got Kali Linux if you want to do some remote auditing of your land. They have fantastic
documentation if you just want a deep dive on a topic like I don't know, maybe Ansible or
Kubernetes. And if you need some great backup or maybe you want to do a static website, they have
S3 compatible object storage that just screams. Then their VLAN support that lets you bridge
multiple different data centers together creating one flat virtual Linode network. And of course,
their powerful DNS manager makes it easy to manage your domains. I could just go on.
I think the best thing to do would be to try it for yourself. That's where that $100 comes in.
That's where the $100 comes in. So go to linode.com slash SSH. Get that $100 in 60 day credit on a
new account. And it's just a great way to support the show and try out my favorite way to run
applications in the cloud. It's linode.com slash SSH. Now, Alex, when I was there last,
I remember you were fussing with some hard drive issues which had existed when I was there the
time before. Me? Never. Many months ago. So did you ever solve that? Because it wasn't solved
when I left. I'll let you know. I've taken some steps to try and solve it. I tried all sorts of
stuff to fix this. So what was happening was I had a hard drive niggle that's been hanging around
since April, as you just said. And since then, I've tried new power cables, new data cables,
a new HBA card, even a new hard drive and still just random stuff just keeps disappearing. Like
you text me, I think it was the other week saying, I'm sure you had more episodes of Final Space
than that. Yeah, it's true. Yeah, some stuff is just vanishing randomly. And the trouble with
that is that it screws with all sorts of stuff like the Plex library reindexes every night,
just as a scheduled job that I have. And so when the drive comes back after a reboot or something,
Plex thinks, oh, goody, here's a whole bunch of new content for you. And it just screws up so
much stuff. It's both the most amazing feature of merger FS, and probably the most frustrating in
this specific scenario is that it supports drives disappearing, like a USB drive disappearing would
be no issue for just silently. And it doesn't tell me that a failure has happened. So I haven't
figured out a good way to alert on this particular issue, simply because it just it's so random when
it happens. Anyway, I took the decision that I got fed up of messing around with cables in the back
of hard drive bays. I'm using the Rosewill LSV 4500 for you rack mount server case. The version
I had did not have the hotswap hard drive cages in it. And so to make a change to the hard drives,
I had to pull the server out, lift the lid off, reach down inside in the dark with my phone torch
and like a caveman I know I know. So I finally bit the bullet. I bought three new hard drive cages
that take four three and a half hard drives each hotswap bays. They look amazing. They've got
beautiful sexy blue LEDs on the front and they they flash when activities happening like a real
server. I can only fit 12 hard drives rather than 15. But actually, I found the 10 to 12 ranges about
the sweet spot anyway for my needs, particularly with density going up as it is. And so the way
I tried to solve it is just by making it easier to do maintenance, trying to reduce the number of
cables being unplugged and re plugged and going to a backplane based solution instead of cables
directly into the drives themselves. That does sound like a really good setup Alex, even if it
doesn't necessarily solve the specific problems, it is going to be a lot easier to maintain,
which will probably reduce problems overall. I do hope so. We'll see though time will be
time will be the tell. Maybe by the next time I visit, we'll have this solved.
Maybe by the next time you visit matter might actually be in existence. Did you see the update
from powerless this week? Now hold on. I thought this was I thought this was my gig on the show.
I thought I was the matter hype guy and you were the guy saying matter is never going to happen.
It doesn't matter, Chris. Oh, man, it matters so much, though. I am really hopeful. I know,
you know, almost as much as Paul is the founder of Home Assistant. He really seems to be like
one of their biggest fans out there. He says he tweets matter being open source is what gives
this standard a chance to be a success. Google, Apple, Home Assistant and any other controller
will all run the same code to control the devices. The device themselves will also run
a standard matter SDK supported by the chip vendor. I expect a wave of new controllers
because with this multi admin setup, you can now have multiple controllers for your home.
Manufacturers that focus on just devices might add a hub. Home Depot will be back in the game.
I expect Sonus to join in to maybe you. He's very hyped. He doesn't think it'll be a success from
day one, though. I don't know. I just remember that XKCD comic, you know, where there are seven
standards and they create a new standard. And now there are eight standards. And I just fear
that's where we're going to end up. But it does sound too good to be true. Doesn't it matter?
That's that's my fear. It does. Every experience I've had in my life in tech tells me this is too
good to be true. But then at the same time, we also kind of have this situation that is a little
unprecedented in tech. And so maybe a new solution is required here. No one vendor has just totally
dominated home automation and the networking protocol and the standards that go with that.
Nest didn't do it. Ring didn't do it. Apple hasn't done it with home kit. Microsoft doesn't even
have anything really, except for like the Xbox ecosystem. And Amazon hasn't successfully done
it with the echo. And Google hasn't necessarily successfully done it with also the their home
assistant and all that stuff along with the nest. It's just kind of like this really kind of mix.
Everybody has a small little chunk. You have a bunch of ten percenters that have ten percent
of the market, ten percent of the market. You know, and so there's no one vendor who's leading
in this space that can declare Victor and and everybody must follow it. So they kind of need
to all come together and just declare a Victor because none of them have won. And it's been years
now. It's a very good point. And I think maybe that's driven in part, at least by the proliferation
of cheap Chinese clones of everything that gets made that's had proper R&D on it. So maybe this
is the conclusion of that and a way to try and prevent that and try and keep the Western companies,
shall we say, in the game in the long run. And the thing that Paulus was really excited about
is that version one dot o seems to have hit the project chip GitHub repo. You know,
I feel like we don't really need to speculate when is matter going to hit the market. I know
with absolute certainty when it's going to hit the market as soon as I break down and replace
everything with Zigbee devices, matter will come out and it'll ship. It's obvious. So you guys just
have to wait. The question really is, yeah, when's Chris going to get his Zigbee devices? That's
really the question we should be asking. Hurry up. OK. All right. When I get back from the trip,
that'll be one of my projects. Have we mentioned, too, that Brent and I are here in southern
Oregon? We just did our first meet up. So, yeah, we're on the road right now if we sound weird.
But yeah, when I get back, I'm working on that. Yeah. This time next week, I think we'll all be
in L.A. together warming up for JPL. Mm hmm. That's I am getting so excited. Yeah. I've been
watching videos, reading docs, getting like all the JPL knowledge. But the videos you've been
watching are like historical. Awesome. They are very the US military needed a very special unit.
You know, that kind of stuff. Well, I'm sorry to derail your space fun, but I did find a pretty
cool project related to ESP home and home assistant this week. We actually mentioned iPods
a little earlier in the show. Well, here's another reference to them. Remember that click wheel style
navigation on iPods as it used to have back in the day, kids? Of course. Yes. Yeah. There'll be
some kids around that don't remember that, which just makes me feel very old. But anyway, take a
look at this link that's in the show notes and tell me this isn't the coolest home assistant
remote you've ever seen. This is better than an iPod touch because it doesn't even have a housing.
So it looks really cool. But it's a little bit smaller, too. But it's essentially like a click
dial attached to an ESP home with a display, a little LED display mounted on it. And you can
just toggle your way through the various home assistant menus. You know, and the nice thing
is, is a toggle wheel actually is a pretty good UI when you're doing things like turning up
brightness or turning up audio up and down like the toggle UI works. Yeah, it does. And, you know,
before touch screens, it was the way to go. Have you have you heard that there was some
like at one point or like there's some mock up of the iPhone, but with a click wheel,
they actually for a short period of time were doing two projects at the same time. There was
one camp that wanted an entirely new OS that was re based on Mac OS. And there was one camp that
wanted to take the iPod OS and bring it to the iPhone. And so they ran both of them simultaneously
until obviously the one based on OS 10 one out. Fascinating. I did not know that, you know,
a little iPod, an actual legitimate little iPod might not make a bad little home assistant remote
if you just wanted a couple of toggle switches on there. I could see that. I was watching some
videos the other day on YouTube. People now are taking the old iPod classics, removing the spinning
hard drive and putting SD cards in them instead. And because the SD cards require, you know,
a tenth of the power of a spinning hard drive, the battery life on these things is measured in
months, not hours. That is incredible. That's such a great idea. I love that. I'm going to I'm
going to experiment with different tablets and stuff, you know, use stuff. I want to find really
cheap ones because I want even more screens. I want a home assistant control screen in every
room. I would say again this year, it's been great for me to come to the studio and also into
JOOPS and have those screens as someone who doesn't know, you know, all the control voices,
the voice commands that I can use here. Just having those screens is great. Bring them up.
And I was able to eventually figure out how to turn the lights off before I went to bed last night.
You did it. Was it hard? Was it hard to figure it out? I would say the icon set on that particular
one, trying to figure out which one was going to control, you know, which one was going to
represent all the lights. I got tons of information about other systems that got me really curious.
But I eventually got there and it's pretty straightforward. Yeah, because the icons really
mean something to me. It's the bus icon, right? The bus icon. Yeah, I never saw the lights. I
never thought that was going to be a correlation. Yeah, that makes sense, I suppose. And that
screen, the tablet that Brent was using, it defaults to the climate control when you load up
the when the screen wakes up, because that's what my wife wants access to in the morning when she's
like managing power or something like that. She wants to be able to just toggle on or turn up heat
and so that's what it turns on to by default. But you can toggle to the other dashboard pages, but
then the then the tablet on the other side of the door that's in the bathroom, that tablet does
default to that bus page with all the buttons and stuff. So go figure, right? So does she use one
for one function and go to back if she needs to turn the lights on? I don't think so. It's just
because it's it turns out, you know, there's like a lot of times there's just different things going
on out here that there are in the back. And so you just want two different controls. And I want
even more. I'd like one by the door. So when you get in, like I just have one that just has like
big buttons for lights, hit up one big button, just lights on. Would you like can you put something
like a stream deck instead? Yeah, or you could do like a, you know, just a regular little wireless
button. There's all kinds of you could do an actual physical button. Yeah, I think for the door,
I'd probably do a physical button. Look, even I'm getting excited. You know, you can buy the old
NVIDIA Shield tablets for like $60 on eBay right now. Oh, those are great tablets. All right. All
right. That's a good hot tip. I'm gonna go look that up before somebody listening buys them all
up. How many ads are gonna be on them? Well, no, I don't know. You think on the video shields? Not
really. I mean, they're running Android. So you know, that may or may not float your boat. But
I wonder if you could flash them with something newer. I would I would imagine it's a well
supported device by the likes of lineage or that that that sort of stuff. Oh, you're right, Alex.
Look at this. Oh, also the iPad mini two is 75 bucks. How would that work as a home assistant
screen? Well, you see the thing about the Android based stuff is you could use fully kiosk browser,
and then you have it, you know, use the camera to turn on and off when you're nearby, which for you
with a limited power situation is probably what you want. Yeah, I think that's a good idea.
Probably what you want. Yep. I use that now. Actually, I do that same thing. There you go.
When you approach the tablets, they just auto turn on. Heck, I might have to pick one of these up.
Look at this thing. I know. That's what I'm thinking. That's great. I'm great. I'm getting
one because I'm looking for a new tablet. There you go. You see, you're you're going to see me
just spend money right here live on the show. You shouldn't watch that print. It's just not
it's not gentlemanly of me. humio.com slash h c e go there to ingest and view all of your logs
in one place. humio is a centralized log management and observability platform. The
company was founded by developers in Denmark in 2016, as an alternative to the legacy logging
solutions that make it cost prohibitive to ingest and search data volumes that you see in your large
infrastructures today. But I think the real beauty of humio is that it can take logs
from any source and then make them usable and you don't have to constantly massage the format.
It doesn't need the schema ahead of time. You just pump all of the logs in there and it has them when
you need them and the dashboard. It's great. This platform is crazy. Humio's index free architecture
means that it can ingest over a petabyte of data per day and search that with sub second latency
and humio is 80% cheaper than the competing platforms like Splunk or Elastic thanks to its
reduced hardware footprint. But really, if you're going to ask me, the best way to get started with
humio is the humio community edition. humio community edition is the largest no cost data
ingestion offering on the market today, allowing you to ingest up to 16 gigabytes per day with
seven day retention. It's not a trial period, you get it for the long haul. This is perfect for
self-hosters who want to ingest their home logs and get a single view of everything happening
in your environment. Rather than having to go to separate places to look at your logs and every
component in your home, humio gives you the ability to bring them together and correlate them in one
place for easier troubleshooting. You can have it do things like monitor your voltage and your
energy or take data out of home assistant and then generate alerts in real time to take action.
You can protect your computing infrastructure that way. When it's your hobby, you want it easy
and quick and usable. You don't want to have to turn it into a job after you just got home
from your job. So go get started with humio community edition today at humio.com.
Well, it's meetup season people. I'm sure you are totally not fed up with us talking about meetups,
but Chris and Brent are on the road on the way to LA already. If you'd like to get details of all
the meetups that are happening along the way, go to meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting.
Where's your next one going to be, gents, after this airs?
Sacramento on Friday. Really? So the day this comes out will be. So if you're listening the
day this comes out, I believe it's Sacramento and we have all the details up there. And then after
that it's Southern California and then shortly and that's a couple like a week later. And then
after that there's one more and that is in Portland. And there was actually an issue
where we had accidentally limited the RSVPs for a couple of the meetups. So if that happened to
you, if you tried to sign up and it said sorry limit reached, that was a mistake. That was
that was a meetup.com. You know, I'm getting rid of meetup. This is the last trip. I swear.
Well, actually I can't swear because sometimes we just don't get to it, but I would love to get a
self hosted meetup replacement. So if you had any problems, go sign up. There's still spots
available. Also, if you have any suggestions for a meetup.com replacement, we're all ears.
We did get some emails. People went over to self hosted dot show slash contact. Dr. Pepper
Shaker says he has some great Z wave light switches he wants to tell us about. I wanted to
give a shout out to the zoos. That's what the Z at the end zoo with a Z Z wave light switches.
I was chatting with the folks on Discord. Some Shelly was recommended and I was really just kind
of worried about having 40 plus Wi-Fi devices because he wants a lot of these things. And I
agree. You know what? He's got an ISP mandatory provided router AP that he has to use. I bet that
thing doesn't handle a whole bunch of Wi-Fi devices very well. So he wired up his whole
house with these zoo Z Z wave light switches. The Z wave network is working great. He says he got
them on sale for Labor Day for $24 each. Nice. What a score. What a score. All right. That's
definitely something to check out, he says. Thank you. And he loves the show. Well, thanks, Dr.
Pepper Shaker. We love that tip. Yeah, they're on at $28 right now. So I mean, even outside of the
sale that they're not particularly expensive compared to, say, a Shelly or something like
that, which is typically in that, you know, for the Shelly 2.5, it's typically in that $25 range
anyway. But these look really, really interesting and they get fantastic reviews. And a friend of
mine actually moved house last weekend. And one of the jobs that we went around to help him with
was pulling out all of his old Shelly's out of the walls. And ah, putting putting Shelly's in
is not difficult, but it is also really difficult trying to reverse engineer which wire goes where
and what's a traveler and blah, blah, blah, blah. Trying to reverse engineer the Shelly's when you
take them out in someone else's house is also just as much of a pain in the ass as well. So
I think smart switches with the smarts built into them versus a Shelly is something I really
think I need to investigate strongly moving forward. That makes a lot of sense. It seems
you're right. I had not given a lot of thought about removing them because honestly, if I was
going to sell a house, I just leave them in there and say it's part of the package. But no, dude,
no one else cares about your smart home stuff. And if you've got, you know, 1520 of these things,
that's, you know, four or $500. Why would I leave that for someone else? They're never going to use
it. They're never going to set it up. It doesn't add any value to them. It just adds complexity.
It's probably a negative for most people. Unfortunately, when was the last time you
moved into a house and took the light switches apart just to see what was behind them? Like
never. You always find some surprise in my experience. Yeah, that's you guys are just
adding to that. That's true. Yeah. But building it into the switch does seem a lot simpler from
an installation, a removal troubleshooting if it dies. That's a great point. All right.
Another check in the box for Z-Wave. We keep now that I've committed to switching to Zigbee,
we keep finding all these awesome Z-Wave devices. I'm going to have both. One thing I should note,
though, about these Zoos switches is that they some of these switches nowadays don't require a
neutral. So in older houses, they didn't always include a neutral wire. These ones do require a
neutral. So please make sure you go and check before you spend any money. Sue writes in and
we got a lot of opinions about hosting your own email server because we brought that up. We read
that article where the author was very frustrated, said that it's basically just only for big tech
now. Sue says, you know, maybe it was a bit of a country based issue. He's in Barcelona. I have
been self-hosting email and web service since 2011 across three states in the US, and I've only ever
had one undelivered email. And that was actually a misconfiguration on the far side. If you get a
business connection, yes, it costs more. It's about double. I have two hundred and fifty dollars for
gigabit symmetric. Oh, oh, man. Today we have been fighting bandwidth issues. We've been struggling
for a few kilobits a second. That sounds glorious. If you get at least one static IP, the same day
customer service, and then there's generally no bandwidth caps. Not to mention, no one is going
to eat everything into the sun from a business block IP space. That's true. They're not just
going to write off a whole business block of IPs. I realize that there are some for whom this is
impossible, you know, awful you or the crypto bro, musky starling types, but the crypto. Yeah, we
call it Elon link, Sue. That's what we call it. That's what it's Elon link. But you know what?
I kind of get the I kind of get your point here. It's like if you set it up right, if you have the
right kind of connection, if you don't get your IP in trouble, you get a good ISP, you can still host
your own email. I get that. Also, Sue mentions that they're a big user of unread 186 terabytes
and running for 12 years. Yeah, that's solid. I mean, the unread stuff. Unread has been around
a long time. And, you know, I think I've been interested in an extra sort of seven or eight
years at this point. And it was it was pretty old when I got involved in the unread community. So
good on you, Sue. Sue also gives you a shout out, Alex, for lots of assistance over the years.
Thank you. Thank you. Now, on the flip side, we got a boost from I'm going to say a Hannigan,
a Hannigan. And they write, I actually agree with that blog post on the self hosted email.
I have done it since 2003, but found out it's increasingly harder to get my mail delivered,
especially sending to Gmail. I ended up switching to fast mail last year.
Here's another benefit of using a real email provider. And I use I use real email provider
to be slightly provocative, only slightly. Bitwarden this week actually added alias support
for fast mail. Yeah, that's so sweet. So for those that don't know what that means, you know,
when you sign up to a website and you put your real email address in an alias through Bitwarden,
that user generation stuff, that username generation stuff they added fairly recently,
you can now also generate a username with an automatic email forwarding alias going via your
fast mail account. They also support simple login and non Addy and Firefox relay email services.
So essentially you can mask your real email address from these services automatically as
part of the Bitwarden generation. And it interfaces with the fast mail API to actually
add that alias into your email kind of universe within fast mail, which I just thought is amazing.
I hear so many good things about fast mail to so many good things from the audience.
A Hanukkah Hanukkah sent 5000 stats. Froze there also sent in 5000 stats. Just wanted to mention
Podverse is great, but I wish Podverse had sats streaming. It's a more fair way to give value
for value. I wanted to give Podverse a plug here on the show, because I think the self hosted
audience might be really interested in it. It is a slick cross platform web, Android and iOS
podcast player, and it sinks between all of them. I love that because it means I can listen to
something and then finish it at my desk using the web player. And it also means that when I have my
flings with Android, I have all my podcasts on there. The other thing I really like about Podverse
and why I wanted to mention it on here is because it's GPL and you can embed it on your website.
We've done it on Jupiter broadcasting and I've talked to the lead Dev Mitch several times.
In fact, he's messaging me right now as we're recording and they're working on all kinds of
stuff, including sat streaming so you can just send the sats as you listen and they and will
receive them. It also supports a bunch of the other podcasting to features like live streaming
chapters, transcripts, host information and a bunch of other things. They've also been really
great collaborators on our new website as well. Yeah, we solved a lot of issues on both ends
with adding their player embedded on our website. And it was really neat because we had, you know,
found a few bugs in their player and they were happy to fix them pretty quickly. And it's been
great to see those two communities come together. Yeah, that's one of the really neat things that
Mitch told me is now that some of their best contributors to Podverse are Jupiter broadcasting
listeners. That's that's so cool. Yeah, it is really neat. So check out Podverse if you haven't
podverse.fm also shout out to Prozac who sent us a row of ducks just thanking us for the pragmatic
cloud discussion in Episode 79 and a young dookie who just got a house and is looking to build a
full home assistant set up going all in. It's such an exciting time. So congratulations, young dookie.
Keep us posted on that. And then shim. What do you think there, Brent? Schmitzfeld. Schmitzfeld sent
two sats just to see if it was possible to send two sats across the Internet. And it was. Yeah.
And then we got 10,000 sats from Silver Snake. No message. Just send it into the show. And I just
want to give a special hello to main Hippo, who sent their very first boost this week into the
show. Amazing. Yeah, I think my favorite thing about boosts is the fact that we're kind of
rekindling the bizarreness of the IRC Nick and all these names. It's fantastic. Yeah, it's a
yeah, it's a struggle for me to read some of these. But that's my favorite part. When I get it right,
it's a win. And when I don't get it right, they can boost in again. Tell me I got it wrong. It's
also a win. Yeah. So go check out a new podcast app. Go to newpodcastapps.com and grab one that
works for you or grab Breeze if you don't want to switch or boost CLI or, you know, try out Podverse.
I think it's pretty great. A little bit of self promotion isn't the right word,
but you know what I mean? I'm looking to sell my old dual Xeon motherboard. It's a gigabyte
GA7 PESH2. It's the dual Xeon LGA2011 board. There's a pair of E5 2690 v2 CPUs in there.
I've also got 128 gigabytes of DDR3 ECC memory in that system. I just don't use it anymore. And I
figure it should go to a good home. There's a couple of 10 gig NICs on the board, which have
been a little flaky recently. So I've been using an Intel NIC card to go in there. So just be aware
of that. If you're interested in the board, let me know via Discord or Twitter if you would like
it and we'll come to some arrangement about how to get it to you. Maybe it'd be a good start for
somebody to build a home lab box. 128 gigs of RAM in those CPUs. You could run some VMs. That would
do the job. I paid $250 for those CPUs four years ago and they're worth about 20 bucks now, but they
still crunch, man. They still crunch. I'm impressed by the old Xeons. I have to say, I mean, I have
that old super micro box. It's like seven, eight years old. And I threw Photo Prism on there the
other day and yeah, it lit up every single core, but sure enough, it did the face detection and
it did the object recognition at a pretty reasonable pace on an old box. So you never
know. And those CPUs are slower than what you're talking about. So you never know. You could get
quite a bit out of that stuff. 10 cores and 20 threads per CPU is quite the thing to observe in
HTOP, let me tell you. Yes, it is. You know what? I'd say it's a thing of beauty, Alex. It is
beautiful. Also, our members are beautiful. Thank you for supporting the show. If you'd like to
become one of our SREs, you can go to selfhosted.show slash SRE. I really think of that as an
investment in future content generation. You know, people can boost in and thank us for the episode
we've made and get a message on the show. But our members are investing in the ongoing day-to-day
research production and just honestly help keep us focused on making our listeners happy,
making our audience happy as one of our biggest customers. You can become a member at selfhosted.
show slash SRE and you get an ad free feed as a thank you. Just a quick thank you to Brent for
joining us today. Thank you very much. Where can people go and find you good sir? Oh, I think
Twitter is a good one at Brent Jerva. If you can spell it, you win a prize. Don't forget that other
show that we make called Linux Unplugged as well. Yeah, I mean, he forgot to mention that part,
but Alex got it for your brand. Thanks, Alex. Yeah, I did actually get a new computer and that
episode is going to come out this week. So we talk all about it as a big day for you. That doesn't
happen very often. Yeah, you were there last time that I got a new computer and you and I Frankenstein
the whole thing. The x 250 was the x 250 x 250. Yeah, we put a new screen in it and a bunch of
like hard drive and memory upgrades. And you know what I did? Chris and I spent basically three days
running a bunch of benchmarks on both the x 250. And the new dev one that Chris and West bought me
those sweethearts. And we can now say also the brand new Thalia that was just released today
as we're recording. That's true. Yeah, that's why it took three days. We had a lot of fun.
We were doing some major shootouts. It was pretty great. Those guys over at system 76,
they do some cool stuff. Speaking of which, actually, I got word today that one of our
old friends of the network cheese bacon is going to be at all things open in Raleigh at the beginning
of November. I will try and be there as well. Certainly, we'll do a micro meetup in the rally
area. We'll post some details on the meetup page in the element room as well to get the details on
that one as well. But if you come into all things open, it'll be great to see you. Maybe we'll go
out for an evening of debauchery and fun. I don't know what we'll do any trivia, Alex. Maybe some
trivia. Maybe, maybe. Yeah, go get in that matrix room and do the meetup spaces. We have more and
more all the time details are at Jupiter broadcasting.com slash matrix. And of course,
we always love your feedback. You can send that in at self hosted dot show slash contact. That's
where you get in touch with us. I'm on Twitter at ironic badger. I'm over there at Chris ls and the
podcast. Well, that's at self hosted show, obviously. Thanks for listening, everybody.
That was self hosted dot show slash 80.