Rumor has it a new TV has showed up in the Alex household a wild LG appeared. Oh, really?
Did you happen to get one that has a web OS and home kit? I certainly did
Yeah, I remember when I was at palm I think had web os back in the early days
And LG bought it and everyone was like what they're going to do with this
And then they turned it into I think one of the best smart TV interfaces around
I've only tried it in a limited capacity, but I was pretty impressed
it's it's actually
I would say good enough that you might not even need a set top box hooked up to it
Are you going to keep your shield hooked up? So I have the shield right now and uh Brent is staying with me right now
And we watched uh last night. So this this is um, let me rewind a little bit. This is an LG C9 OLED TV
Last year, um, I was looking at buying a new TV after I emigrated
and I was looking at the OLEDs really closely, but they were they were about three thousand dollars, which is
Let's let's be fair. That's a lot of money for a TV
um, then the black friday deal started coming through for this year about a week ago and I was on slick deals and
Best Buy came up with the
LG OLED for about two thousand one hundred dollars, which is again still a lot
And then another deal came up on ebay. That was like seventeen hundred and I was like, oh
Okay, now we're talking. It's got super fast
processor in it because
you know i'm coming from the shield which
That thing hardly ever stutters like it's just ridiculously overpowered for what it's trying to do
It's the set top box performance benchmark. It really is. Maybe maybe the apple tv is is parallel to it
But it's very good. But the thing about the shield is it can run kodi it can run plex
It can run iPlayer because it's android. It will also do open vpn, which is important for me to get iPlayer working
Oh, I hadn't really considered that I think it's also worth mentioning not only does it
Play plex, but the shield in some capacity can also act as a plex server
And if you only are streaming to one or two computers or tvs in a house
You actually could just have your set top box be your plex server and it has some units have built-in storage
And some units have external storage. I suppose at this time everybody knows about the shield though, right?
I feel like you and I are such fans, but we've we've been fans for so long and they just released a new version too
Mine's the original 2015 version. So, uh, it's getting quite old now, but it works just great
um, I had an issue with the power supply on it about uh,
Three months ago and nvidia, you know considering it's a four-year-old device at this point full credit to them
They shipped me out a new power adapter. No questions asked no proof of purchase even required. So oh, that's good
I've heard some people complain. Those are hard to get so you just gotta know who to ask
They just sent it to me for free, you know, so
Really great experience there from a customer perspective
So the thing is about using um the built-in smart tv stuff
I've always been a proponent of I want my screen to be dumb. I just want it to be a really good quality panel
I'll handle the content. Don't worry about apps. Don't worry about anything else could have a five to ten year panel
And then a set top box you replace every couple of years
Potentially depending on price. Um, now the downside to that is that you need to make sure that everything every link in your chain
Between your set top box and your tv
supports
The audio formats the the video resolution so 4k and things like dolby
Dts master audio is pretty well supported. But there are some others that are slightly more esoteric that sometimes
Don't get full pass-through support. So
Brent and I ran into this last night. I was like, oh my god
so Brent and I ran into this last night actually, so
There we are watching the matrix
A full-on uhd blu-ray rip that I have stored
um on my plex server
And we're watching through the nvidia shield through my denon avr
into the
lg
We got halfway through the movie and it started buffering for some reason
I think there was several people watching my plex or something
Um, so I started looking at some data and it turned out it was actually only
Playing at 1080p on the screen because my receiver doesn't do 4k pass-through because it's old
Okay, so I now need to upgrade my receiver great, but then I thought hmm. What if I use the plex app built into the tv?
Turns out because it's built into the tv it not only bypasses my receiver
Um in terms of that 1080p limitation, but it also supports hdr which my receiver didn't
So brent and I are sat there and there's that lobby scene where they're, you know, shining flashlights in the matrix
You all know the scene and um, you know neo and trinity are doing the cartwheels and shooting each other and all the people
It's a classic. Yeah, there were moments in that scene where both of us were sat in a dark room where it was like so
bright because of the hdr stuff we're just like
Oh, that's like, you know when someone shines a flashlight in your eyes in real life. It was genuinely like that from a tv
astonishing
I actually think i'm probably going to ditch the shield for the majority of my content now because
The lg thing has this magic wand remote you can wave around and it's it's like a I guess a wee a wee nunchuck remote type deal
um
It's fantastic. And you've sort of simplified too, which is kind of nice because really all of the hard work's being done back on your
Plex server. You just need a front end to stream the hd64 stream
And you need it in the right colors in the right sound channels direct play all the things but so having uh plex on the
Tv leads to an interesting issue that I hadn't even considered getting sound to your speakers, correct? Yes
So I discovered last night and this is quite an old technology, I think but I discovered audio return channel last night
There's a hdmi port on my tv that has an arc
Thing and there's a hdmi port on my receiver that has arc marking
So it will take the sound from the plex app or any sound from the tv actually and then it will use hdmi. I think cec
Protocol to actually turn the receiver on
Send the sound to the amp. Um, and then I get the full surround sound passed through coming through the amp
That's so much fun getting something like that. And it sounds like you got a really good one
Um, and did you say you got it as a black friday deal too? Yeah, I love early black friday stuff
I'm looking for storage. You got a tv lots of good deals to be had at best buy on storage
Those uh easy stores are still 12 terabytes
470 180 bucks something
I love it. You i'm in a telegram group that brings out a bunch of stuff
I'm in a telegram group that broadcasts when there's great deals on hard drives. Have you seen this telegram group?
There's a server builds.net one that's pretty good for sort of an used enterprise gear that i'm part of
That's even better. That's a great one. So, um on the opposite end of that is my home assistant setup, which is
Uh running on raspberry pi 4 in a docker container and then I have another one
I have two I have another one here at the studio, which is running on a much larger x86 box
and home assistant
Is probably one of the open source projects. I am the most passionate about now
What I love about home assistant is it allows me to take all of the different quote unquote cloud connected smart devices
And control them with one interface over my lan with no cloud connectivity required
Home assistant works off of these integrations
And these integrations enable additional functionality home assistant is underpinned by very simple easy to read yaml configuration files
And it's got a default ui that's built around something called lovelace, which is pretty easy to customize or you can just throw it all out
Uh, I am not as long of a home assistant user as you are though
I think you've probably been using it for probably twice as long as I have it was january that I started
Uh, it was the smart led project that I talked about at linux fest northwest
You know just I i'm a huge proponent of solving real problems to get yourself excited about something
And for me that was lighting. It's a great way to learn
It's like the way for for me to learn really
It's a very low risk way to learn. So if if you're let's put it this way. So if your lights don't switch on
Nobody's going to really get hurt or you know something
It's not going to cost you a huge amount of money or something like that. Whereas if you're automating
Like the the locks on your house instead, like you might be locked out if you screw up, right?
And that's that's obviously a bit more of a a big kind of risk
Um, so for me lighting is a really great way for people to get started. It's uh, it's fairly cheap
You know, you can either just buy off-the-shelf bulbs from
Philips hue or lifex or any other z wave compatible or zigbee compatible kind of brand
Uh, I think ikea even makes some stuff now
Or you can make it yourself, which is what I which is what I did
I had a lot of pre-existing smart products
Because I initially went for speed and ease and I went and I tried
the uh google smart stuff the alexa smart cancel. Sorry everybody the echo smart stuff
And um
I also went pretty deep into home kit because I really liked that home kit was over the land. No like cloud api stuff
And so I ended up with a real hodgepodge of devices and it wasn't until I got this project off-grid mandate to say no
Cloud I want all of this stuff that i've learned to like and love in some cases to work when I don't have internet
And that's when I really started to refocus on home assistant. So not the longest user
But I have gotten so much out of this
It has it has become a quality of life project for me. Like it's improved our quality of life
so much so that um, even as recent as this morning
And this is this we've had this conversation several times now my wife and I have been discussing how it has improved
our quality of life in the rv over
the fall and into winter and then something you touched on there too alex is
Sometimes things can go rough at work
You can have a couple of losses in a day at work and you're not feeling that great and if you can go home and
accomplish something
it sort of
Softens the blow of what happened during the day at work and it gives you a sense of accomplishment that you can you can enjoy
so this landed really at a great time for us because i've been
Really experimenting with how lighting can change our space
and putting in light strips and light bars and um
just kind of experimenting with different lifex bulbs and seeing how changing colors and adding light essentially painting our home where I
I looked around and I said, where is it really kind of dark? Where's the light falling off in this space?
and then I put warm different kinds of lights in there that shine lights on walls and ceilings and
tying all of that to the sunset and the sunrise
and morning and wake scripts
It's really made it feel homey. How cool does it feel when you're just sat on the couch watching tv?
You haven't thought about it. You haven't even noticed it's getting dark outside
And then suddenly your light switches on just gently and it's like I did that
I mean, okay home assistant did that but I thought to write that automation that did that
And home assistant has sunrise and sunset as a trigger, which is just fantastic. So it does that figuring out for you
And then you just say when sunset occurs fade these lights on for me
And it's wonderful. Another thing I love about home assistant are the the
Metrics that you can use to figure out what's going on
Are the the metric s ton of integrations that it has
Looking at the website home hyphen assistant dot ios slash integrations. They have at the time of recording
1492 different integrations
And so what can you do with some of those things right now?
Um, I don't live in london anymore
But when I did, um, it would have been quite useful just to have some kind of a visual indicator in the morning
Not another notification, but just like some some kind of visual thing that says hey
Your train is going to be delayed this morning
What I have done is I have used one of the many things you can do in home assistant besides integrations
But just something the lovelace ui allows
Is I pull in traffic cams from all of the major intersections around my home and the studio. So I have one tab
In home assistant. I get a snapshot of the weather
The temperature at the studio the temperature at home and all of the driving conditions. Very cool
the thing that I love most is the fact that it's a single pane of glass for
every single iot type situation that you have so
You know in london you're taking the tube somewhere and you know, let's say your your tube line is delayed
There's a london underground integration
So it will go and pull the london underground api and say the circle line this morning
It has massive delays. So I could change my route based on that maybe
And because it's a sensor home assistant has a bunch of different constructs in it
And one of the things in there is a sensor
So that could include stuff like a water sensor for you in your rv to check that something isn't leaking
It could be a light sensor in the window to check the ambient light levels
So if it's a particularly gloomy day, it will turn the lights on in your house
Or in this case, it is an api call that this integration makes to the london underground
Api to say hey, this tube line is screwed this morning avoid and that status
Access sensor input to the home assistant system and so then think of it a bit like if this then that but on your lan, right?
So you have a sensor
that triggers
Something so again, you have another another construct called a trigger
So a sensor triggers an automation and so an automation can be anything that you can think of
It could literally be changing a light bulb from 50% red to 50% blue number one impact on our quality of life
Has been what I have done with our heaters and our water system because they actually make living in the rv possible
RVs are not super well insulated and ours has three slides and where the slides are at air can pass and so it can be a challenge
To keep it comfortable when it's 30 and 20 degrees fahrenheit outside
So I have a series of sensors and i'll link to my sensors that I just absolutely love
That report into home assistant constantly every couple of seconds
So I also get data I get chartable data on my temperatures, but we'll get to that
so I have an automation that gets triggered by this sensor data that says if it's
between 7 p.m. And 9 a.m. And the temperature in this room drops below 67 degrees
Turn on a heater until it right rises to 72 degrees
Now the thing is in an art that sounds great, but in an rv
You can lose temperature so fast that you either a can't keep up with the demand or b as soon as you turn the heater off
The room starts to get cold
I have solved this with a oil heater that is very low slow
Ambient once it's going it just sort of radiates heat and small little 500 watt space heaters that will kick in in the short term
As the temperature begins to climb up the short term 500 watt heater kicks off and the oil heater finishes the job
And then we have the same thing if the temperature begins to drop too rapidly
The little 500 watt space heater will kick in to shore up the gap and keep it around 67
68 degrees in our bedroom all night long. That's not a problem
67 68 degrees in our bedroom all night long. That's nice. It's it's changed our lives. We sleep so much better
and my wife is particularly sensitive to the house not being comfortable for me, you know, it could be
60 degrees i'm fine, right throw a jumper on yeah, exactly
But she does not want to have cold toes. No cold. She has a no cold toe policy alex
So i've really gotten a nice quality of life improvement out of just a couple of sensors and
Just different smart plugs activating oil heaters or space heaters when you add things to the system
They all become data input points. So when you add a camera, it can also be a motion sensor
A lot of these also offer motion sensing and humidity sensing and this is all information you bring into home assistant that enables you to make
Different decisions and different actions. I'll give you another example
It's very possible for our water to freeze this time of year our water comes in from a hose into a water bay
Now water bay is outside the rv. It's in an enclosed space, but it's low and it gets colder than the inside of the rv
does
I have a temperature sensor. It's a z-wave device. It runs off of a little tiny lithium battery. It runs for a year
And it's 3m taped to the inside of that bay
And it measures the temperature constantly
When the temperature reaches 37 degrees it turns on a traditional incandescent light bulb
That light bulb in an enclosed space is enough heat to raise the temperature up above 40
Even when it's freezing outside and when the temperature reaches 40
It turns off the light and that prevents my water lines just that that simple little tweak prevents my water lines from freezing
Doesn't take much does it and uh, sometimes those those really small jobs add up to a
cumulative
massive impact on your life
You know for me a couple of my favorite automations are around a bedtime routine. So in my house. I'm like, hey hockey puck
It's bedtime that that starts off like a 20 minute routine in my house with the lights doing a certain dimming pattern
Um, so that I don't have to reach for any switches when you know when you're lying in bed and you're comfortable and you're ready
To go to sleep. The last thing you want to do is reach over and actually turn the light off
Um, I don't have to do that anymore. But the other thing and this is a really weird fringe benefit is that
Archie my dog has learned to recognize that particular phrase of bedtime
So much so that as soon as I say hey
g
uh bedtime he'll jump up from his bed and go and stand by the back door and wait to be let out, you know, so it's
I've automated my dog
You know what I stole that idea from you when I when I visited you I saw that and so I went home and I implemented
a bedtime script
And a good morning script now scripts are not the same as automations
Scripts are when you just want to manually execute a series of things and you can program in and what you did
Which I totally ripped off from you
Is you programmed in some delays and some dims?
So when you kick off the sequence, it's sort of a cascading shutting down
Of the lighting in your home and they ratchet down their brightness and then they turn off completely
And there's kind of like it's it
Over a month or so of using that it builds in a routine. Like it's you know
I'm really going to bed now. Like the house is shutting down. I I can't just stay up and just do what I want
I got to go to bed now. I've kicked off the routine. I supplemented it a little bit because we have kids and we're sometimes when we're
When we're moving we're sometimes in noisy areas like rest stops
We have placed a couple of white noise makers into smart plugs
And so my bedtime scripts turn those on as well lights start to dim the noise makers come on when those noise makers come on
That's leafy's cue to go get in bed as well. Same thing. I've automated the dog and in the morning
I hit that it turns off the noise makers and it does a soft lighting
So that way not everybody gets blasted with lights a couple of small lights come on and then over a 10 minute period
They come up to full brightness. So
Some of these automations and stuff do require quite a lot of thought to get them right and tweaking when they're longer
Yeah, tweaking and stuff. This isn't something i've done yet, but I want to investigate something called node red
Which allows you to basically have um, I don't know the terminology but you have boxes and lines that you draw between things
To basically create a automation flow chart
So you say, you know if this then that but on a graphic level you can basically draw a flow chart
And that but on a grand scale
And it can do stuff based on presence detection, which is something i've not really investigated much
But it's a huge part of home assistant really
There's a bunch of sensors that can detect when your phone is on wi-fi
You could use a service like life 360 to detect when you're driving
You and I both have the automatic obd2
Things in our car obd2 ports to read. I don't know like engine statistics and mileage and all that kind of stuff
And you couple all of those data points together and then home assistant can actually have a pretty good picture of whether you're home or not
And so a lot of the problems with things like phillips hue
Is that it has a gps thing built into my phone and it uses that for presence detection on the lights in the house
Well, what about if my wife's home and i'm not
That the logic is just not smart enough to deal with that kind of actually pretty basic situation and very common
Not to mention the privacy implications, too. That's going to their cloud service
Yeah, and a lot of this other presence data doesn't leave my lan in the home assistant world. So
There are just huge huge benefits that it does take a bit of you know, effort to to get started with home assistant
But once you do boy and you can start with simple just turn one or two things on and off with this cheap smart plug
If you want something dead simple a couple of devices I can just recommend off the top of my head
Is there's a fantastic tp-link integration with home assistant if you have a one of those casa smart plugs
You can use them immediately with home assistant
Nearly all home kit smart plugs that just speak the home kit standard protocol
Will work with home assistant. So that for me was huge because that covered everything I had also the I know for sure
Like I have a few in production kind of like um recommendation
Recommendation the I home smart plugs, which are home kit will work
I've the reason why I mentioned home kit a couple of times is
It's a pretty solid protocol
Does not require any ios devices on your network when you're using home assistant and it's all over the lan
The company you bought the device from never even needs to know it's online so you can take advantage of economic
compact
wi-fi capable smart devices over your lan and that for me is huge because
That means anybody can get started with home assistant
I like the tp-link ones because I buy them in a two-pack for 30 bucks
And that's not even the most economical way. There's even cheaper ways to do smart plugs
Especially if you go the diy route like you do alex. Yeah, one of the first projects I did was
Again, like lighting was a very low risk one, but smart plugs again are quite low risk. They're very
Easy to to do and very low risk if they go wrong
And so I ordered a four pack of something called the tekken sp20
And these guys are 100 to 240 volt compatible
And they will support a maximum load of 16 amps
now inside these guys is
essentially an arduino
And what some very smart person
Figured out was that the firmware callback that this makes when you first connect it to your wi-fi
Is trying to connect to tekken to do a firmware update
So what they did was they reverse engineered it and performed like a man in the middle attack
So using my raspberry pi its wi-fi chip and the ethernet to basically
Be the man in the middle
My raspberry pi turned into the tekken update server
Provided a bogus update file to this little white box in my hand
And so I was able to flash it with the tasmota firmware, which is completely open
I will never so long as I own this physical piece of hardware
Ever be beholden to tekken and their business model
And so I now own this piece of hardware
Completely there's no other business model at play here other than I paid 10 bucks for this piece of plastic
Okay, now let's get to the more advanced stuff because we keep mentioning voice control. However home assistant
Doesn't provide home
Automation via voice control out of the box. It's an actively developed project
Maybe it will one day, but how have you solved that problem? Because there's really two routes with home assistant google assistant is
Supported as is the the one that begins with the letter a it's supported
But it's really you have there's two routes you can take on how to actually make it work and you and I have gone
Very different ways on this. There are two routes. You're correct
There is an automatic setup via home assistant cloud and the other one is a manual setup
So I I went through the manual setup. Um, my home assistant is exposed through
A reverse proxy and there are some security implications to exposing your home automation system to the internet
If you're not comfortable with those then
Don't do it
And so if you don't go the manual route, you can go the home assistant cloud route and home assistant
partners with nebuchadnezzar
to provide essentially a
Way to run or control home assistant from anywhere
Without you needing to really understand or configure your own port forwarding or reverse proxy
So I can speak to that a little bit because that's the route I went for another reason
For another reason and that is I am behind some carrier grade double net
There's just no way I could punch a hole through even if I wanted to
plus I have taken it on as a challenge to just
Not allow anything from the outside to this network and I just assumed I would always use a wire guard vpn
but
Not ideal if you want some quick remote access or you want voice assistant integration. So this home assistant cloud is
Is you have partners? Maybe they're connected like it's it is a commercial arm of some of the people behind home assistant
and they seem to be
Essentially proxying and mirroring a home assistant setup in the cloud. There's a slight delay using the system, but it's not bad
and I decided to
pay after the trial because
The way the proxying works
I never have to expose my network to the outside system
But I can still get in I can still view my cameras. I can manage it as if I was at the land
It's 100 like i'm at the land
And by doing that I also get one button
click
Publishing to the echo or the google assistant
Which solves that which you had to kind of build a system including stand up some software on your server to enable that I believe
yeah, and then an nginx reverse proxy is is how I did it and then you have to go into
To the actions section of your google account console
Create a new smart home card a new smart home recommendation and build an action and it probably took me an hour or two
To get it working in the end. Uh, it's not been a hundred percent reliable either
Like quite often I will say
Sync my devices to the google assistant
It will just say i'm sorry has is not available right now
Even though I can go straight to the has url and it's perfectly fine
I have actually had really great results with the home assistant cloud and the other thing it gives you which i'm not utilizing yet
But it gives you a public webhook url
So anything that can be triggered by a webhook can be given a publicly accessible url
So you can send data back to your home assistant
System from anywhere in the world without actually having to expose it to the internet itself
And that's really handy for collecting data outside my environment as well
um, but
Same time I could understand why people wouldn't necessarily want to pay five dollars a month and they might not necessarily want somebody else
hosting a instance
I don't know what they're doing
But the setup process takes a bit like they're building a system behind the scenes and it seems to be its very own
Instance that's dedicated to you and they seem quite confident in the security. I I did look into it a bit
But once you've done either what what alex has done or this route you can then pair it with a voice assistant and it will
Integrate to some effectiveness enough that we can turn our devices on and off which is really all we want
I just want a dumb simple way to start off routines or automations or scripts or whatever. Yeah
Yeah, it's nice when your hands are full or whatnot or when you're in bed
So, okay, so that's that was one of my kind of more complicated ones
The other one I want to ask you about
It's going to come up as soon as you start digging in very far, especially in the home assistant communities
Mqtt there's a lot of answers on the internet that will be well, you should really be doing this with mqtt
You could get a zig beta mqtt device and bring it into home assistant that way
And I know you use mqtt for even those tasmota devices
You were talking about explain this to me because what i'm familiar with is like from the mainframe days
Mqtt is a message queuing transfer
Protocol I don't know what mqtt itself stands for but message queue is pretty much all you need to know
And I know it allows for publishing and subscribing to certain messages from devices
You can subscribe to something and always get updates on it once you have that set up, correct?
So if you're familiar with something like kafka
Or any other situation where you're sending a message into a queue to be processed by something else later
That's pretty much where you're at. Now. There's a few key
Uh concepts to be aware of you have as chris said the publish and the subscribe thing
But you also need what's called an mqtt broker
And in this situation you can enable that inside home assistant with one single line of configuration
And so where that becomes useful is let's say you have a sensor in my case. That is
These techin smark plugs that I talked about
these guys are
publishing to a topic
The amount of voltage the amount of amps being drawn
the
total cumulative kilowatt hours consumed et cetera
They're publishing all of that data to an mqtt topic
now until that topic gets subscribed to
It will just sit there and be
in the broker
So when you're writing your automations you want to consider that maybe you could subscribe
To a topic which is essentially like a push notification at that point
When you subscribe to that topic, you're in a situation where you're not having to go to the end device and say hi
What's the latest amp draw? What's the latest voltage?
the sensor is publishing that data to the broker and then
Maybe you have an led strip that will change color
based on the contents of that published
Topic. Yeah, like you were saying that the traffic was really bad on the tube
You could have a light strip turn red
You wouldn't have to look at your phone or anything
If that light strip is red, you know
You need to take your alternate route that day and the way it does it is through publishing usually a json payload
so, you know, you'll have key value pairs in there which you can
reference in pretty straightforward to write arduino code and then using
Off-the-shelf microcontrollers. You can do some pretty cool things. You can turn on ac you can
Stop a 3d print if the room's got too hot or something
You could turn a light on and off you could I don't know launch a locket to the moon if you wanted to
So if i'm following you in this case the small little lightweight iot device it it just gets its data off of it says
Here's my information. It sends it to the broker
The broker collects it home assistant itself is not a broker home assistant subscribes to the broker
Then brings that in as a sensor data point, which you can then build automations around
Yeah, there's so you can run an mqtt broker as a separate
Container on your system if you want to and just have a dedicated standalone mqtt instance
And do you use a particular one? No, I just use the one built into home assistant because it's stupid simple to enable
It's literally mqtt colon and then it's enabled in your config. That's it. I know other people use what is it mosquito?
I think is one that people use i've heard that's a pretty popular one
That's why I thought maybe you were using mosquito. There are performance concerns. I've never run into any
Let's say you've got I don't know a hundred of these smart plugs in your house and they're all
throwing updates every couple of seconds plus all of your lights plus everything
you know, you will end up in a situation where
Um, you might want to start considering an external broker, but for my needs the internal one has been absolutely fine
I think maybe in my setup being raspberry pies my home assistant pie does the most it does several other it runs like seven other
Containers that are kind of busy. So it has
Sort of the highest workload next to my shinobi pie, but my pie hole
Raspberry pie is just sitting there not really doing much. So I was thinking making that my network services
Pie and putting mosquito on there and putting
Grafana on there because I know grafana is another thing that I could get down the rabbit hole to get really good long-term pictures of data
How does grafana which is a incredible graphing?
Application, how does that?
Tie into home assistant because i've seen a lot of people do that. Yeah, so you can enable the influx db
Output from home assistant which writes pretty much every event that happens in the home assistant
database to the influx db time series database, so
you end up with a
a time series database in influx of
Every single event that happens. So every time motion is detected in a camera or every time you turn a light on and off or
Every time your thermostat detects the the temperature is changed by half a degree. It will write to a home assistant event log
That then gets pushed into influx db
And then grafana supports a bunch of different time series databases influx is one prometheus is another there are there are lots
And you can then create queries which will graph your data out and make it look pretty
It's so neat because i've just done some graphing with the built-in stuff in home assistant
And I really feel like that combined with the event log
I get a I get a real complete picture of what's happened with my family and my home throughout the day in one single day
Home throughout the day in one spot
And I can kind of review it and see when things got cold and how things all respond and what levels of tanks were at
and for me, it's
It's a really nice way to kind of wind down in the evening
It's just see what my home was doing all day while I wasn't there doing the research for this episode last night
Um, I was talking with you after lup about the different integrations at home assistant has and I came across my electric supplier in
North carolina duke energy actually have a home assistant integration
So these guys have an api available for the smart meter on the side of my building
that must have a cellular modem in there to
Send my meter readings back to them every I don't know every day or whatever
um, so I turned that integration on last night in about 10 minutes and
now I have all of that meter data for my electricity supply in home assistant
In home assistant, I could do automations based on that. So let's say my energy usage has gone bit gone above a certain threshold
In a certain day, I could say right that's it. No more electric today turn everything off
More realistically what i'm going to do with that is take that data feed it into influx
And then create a grafana graph so that I can more accurately track my monthly and daily energy usage across the entire house
Not just where each of my smart plugs is at that's so cool
I plan to do something very similar because a future electrical system
I plan to get for as part of project off grid feeds off all of that information via bluetooth
So i'll capture it that way
This is an area where we could go on and on for hours
We could talk about
Z wave and zigbee and wi-fi we could talk about integrating motion and security sensors
Or we could talk about crazy great integrations and automations. I'd love to hear what the audience is doing
With their setups and what they'd like to know is possible. So go to self-hosted dot show slash contact
And let us know or of course, there's always that hashtag ask ssh. So I think that'll do it for today
I'm on twitter at ironic badger. I'm at chris las and the show is at self-hosted show
And as always you can find our show notes and all the rest of the information about this show on self-hosted dot show slash seven