I said I wouldn't do it until it was at least 10,000 miles old, but here I am at seven and a
half thousand miles. I just tuned my Golf R. Okay, now when you say tune, there's like a couple of
different ways to interpret that when you're talking about the Golf, because they have several
levels of tuning, there's software tuning. You got to break it down for me. It's weird, right? So
people say, oh, I've gone stage one, I've gone stage two, all this kind of stuff. So I've gone
stage one with an equilibrium tune. I was at a car show at the weekend at the local tuning house
in Raleigh, Black Forest Industries. I took the R32 down there and exhibited that off in their kind
of main like exhibitor area. And I took the R down there as well. And nobody was interested in that
one because it's too new and too common. But I got talking to a few guys about tuning options and
stuff like that. And someone was selling what's called a cob access port. This is a tiny little
cell phone sized computer that you plug into the OBD2 port of your car. I then paid $175 to a
company called Equilibrium Tuning to purchase a staged tune map. So what they do is they go into
the ECU and they remap all the valve timings and injections and all that kind of stuff. And so it
takes the car from being a 280 horsepower car to being a 370 horsepower car with no hardware mods
required. No way. It's insane. That's remarkable. I did something similar to my RV and I think I
got like a 10 horsepower improvement. 10. These four cylinder, two liter turbo engines that are
in the Golf, it's the same engine as is in your GTI. The only difference with the R is there's
an uprated turbo. It's a bit of a bigger turbo. And the R is all wheel drive versus your front
wheel drive. I tell you, if you've never got into tuning and you want to talk to someone about it
and you've been thinking about it, I would love to talk to you on Discord. I won't take up too much
more of the show about it. But just to say I'm giddy with excitement with the possibilities that
this has unlocked for me. Yeah, that's amazing. And so can I flash my GTI with a software update
in theory and see some sort of improvement too? Yeah. Oh, man. Oh, boy, it's getting dangerous.
I think it's just about as much horsepower as you'd want with a two wheel drive car. But of
course, what do I know? But to me, it seems like it seems like if you get much more, I'd want to
go all wheel drive. That's so awesome. I remember when I flashed my RV's ECU, it was a drive that
you were driving a bus. It felt like I was driving more of a truck. That was a nice improvement just
because the biggest change for me was it meant I could get on the on ramp. That's just it. Yeah.
Yeah. At speed. And you know, I just had her checked. It's been flashed for probably three
years now. And I just had her checked yesterday and she just passed all her checks. She's a
excellent, healthy as can be. Yeah. Made it back from California in one piece. Yeah, we did. And
now it's weird because we basically moved out to get some work done and I had to rip out the Wi-Fi
network. And of course, my, you know, my Raspberry Pi server died. So all of my services were down
and I had to shut down my Pi hole. And it's just strange. It doesn't quite feel like home anymore
because I don't have control over everything that I want. Home is where the Wi-Fi is, right?
Yeah. I don't have Wi-Fi. I don't have internet. It's so strange. So after tonight's episode,
after we're done recording tonight, I'm going to go home, I hope, and get like the Pi hole
and get the Wi-Fi back online. Well, I couldn't quite believe it when you messaged me this week
and said that your home assistant Yella has finally shown up. It's ridiculous. It's here
at perfect timing. It's perfect timing, right? Because the Raspberry Pi died on the road trip.
I get home from the road trip and the yellow's there on the porch waiting for me. I saw the
shipping notification. So I also ordered a one terabyte MVME stick. So I've already opened up
the yellow once and I've installed an MVME drive. I have a quick pile of hardware here, Alex. Before
I get to the yellow, I want to mention what I was going to use. This is a really cool piece of
hardware that's been ruggedized, industrialized, can get into super hot conditions. And it's an
Intel Atom system with QuickSync that's out of a Tesla solar wall that I picked up on the road
trip from a listener. It's decent. You could even run a full Linux desktop on it and it only takes
about five watts idle. So this is where I was considering going. The only problem with this
box, and I'm probably still going to use it. I love that it's DC too. And it's got two COM ports,
which is amazing. Is that an XT60 connector I see on the power cable? Yeah. Now I know who gave it
to you. Yeah. And I'm probably going to use this for something else, but it's such a cool little
box. I thought, okay, I've got an option now, right? So this was one of my options and it's
an X86 box. Good power draw. Then the yellow arrived. Now I have to say I'm very impressed.
I think the Home Assistant team did a good job with the case. I've taken it apart a couple of
times. It goes right back together. I can get access to it really quick. They have the logo
for Home Assistant ingrained in the casing. Laser etched up there. Yeah, it's nice. Yeah.
And all the ports are on the back. The compute modules just popped right in. My MVME popped
right in. I think this is going to be how I will do Home Assistant in the RV is on a dedicated
machine. I'm going to have a dedicated machine for Home Assistant and I'm going to have an
application server for all my other stuff. So Home Assistant yellow will run all of the
automations and jupes. And you know, she's got this yellow has got EMMC for storage for the
primary OS and they've got MVME expansion. I don't really know how you use that, but it's in there.
So it's going to give me, I think I expect at least five years of runway with that device.
But then on your encouragement, and I didn't expect this for like a month. I also picked up
the Odroid H3 Plus that they announced shortly after our last episode. It arrived today
just a little bit before the show. It's still in the packaging. You went for the plus, huh?
Of course. Of course. Who am I talking to? Sorry, I forgot myself for a second.
Now I'm showing Alex on the camera, but I'll describe it to you. But check this out,
Alex. Here it is. It's got two Ethernets. It's got four USB-A. It's got USB-C, DC barrel power
connector. It has audio out ports, including optical audio out, and it has HDMI and Display
port. Plus it has an Intel chip on here. It's got a pretty meaty heat sink on it. And on the bottom,
it's got two slots for RAM and a slot for an MVME disk. And the killer feature for me,
two SATA ports on the board. That's massive. That's a game changer for me because I've been
using USB storage forever. Welcome to the world of real hardware, dude.
I'm so excited. I'm so excited. I'm so pleased. I think it's going to be perfect.
So this is what will replace my Raspberry Pi 4. And I'm going to run all my applications and more,
right? Because I've got more horsepower here and it's got quick sync as well.
I got to get some RAM ordered for it. I didn't expect it to arrive this soon. So I haven't
ordered anything for it. What type of RAM is it? Laptop style, the smaller stuff?
Yes. Yeah, it's the small stuff. I think it's DDR4.
Do I recall reading that thing will take up to 64 gigs of RAM?
Yes, I believe that is the case. I should have grabbed the specs before the show.
I'm so excited. It's funny, right? Because when the Pi 4 died, I was like,
crap, I don't know what I'm going to do. I have nothing I want to replace this with. I'm like,
I guess I could build it around another Pi 4 again, but then I'm going through all this work
and I'm not getting a performance upgrade. And then this thing shows up just a little
bit after last episode. Yeah, it's perfect timing.
They actually shipped it. I got it. I can't believe it. I can't believe it.
I think what I want to do is first is I want to load desktop Linux on here just to see
what it's like. And then I'll wipe it off immediately and start building,
I think, a NixOS server. I mean, it looks amazing. And I shared it
with you for this exact reason. It's got a passive heat sink on it. So, you know,
it can run completely, completely silently, which is perfect for a small space like the RV.
Yes, totally. The only thing I would change about it, and I don't have one,
but the only thing I would change about it is the fact that both of those Nix are
Realtek 2.5 gig Nix. I would have preferred two Intel Nix, just simply for better hardware
compatibility reasons. In a real text, probably fine. But if ever I've had a Nick issue in the
past, it's been not an Intel, Nick and a quantia or real tech or something like that. Whereas Intel
Nix just work and it takes all the problems away. But anyway, I'm nitpicking. Otherwise,
it's a fantastic looking board. I imagine they'll be fine, but I also 100% agree with you.
I would also prefer that, though I'm just excited to have a Nick that isn't on the USB bus. So,
that's good, too. I don't think it was for the Pi 4, but it is for most of the Pis. And
if you wanted to ever add a secondary Nick to the Raspberry Pi to like use it for a firewall
or something like that, you would be doing that over USB. So for me, it's like, okay, at least
they're on the PCI bus. And then it would be nice if they were Intel, but I'll take on the PCI bus.
So what are you going to run on it? Proxmox and then virtualize like Home Assistant that way?
Oh, I should consider Proxmox, huh? Well, you know, I'm still kind of subscribed to the no
container theory for a lot of this stuff. And NixOS would be really good for that. But it does
make a lot of sense to have Proxmox sitting on there. And I shouldn't have any problem passing
quicksync through, right? That should be fine. So what would you need to pass it through for?
Plex. Yeah, I mean, we'll come on to this topic later in the show because it's actually been
coming up quite a lot in Discord lately about LXC versus Docker versus VMs, all that kind of stuff.
We'll come to that later. Please remind me if I forget. But in the meantime, I also saw another
update in the news feed this week that I thought would make you a happy little bunny. Apple with,
I think iOS 16.1 are actually shipping. It's real. It's really happening, people.
They're shipping matter. This is my week, man. This is my week. It's all coming together, buddy.
And the thing is, they're shipping it on the HomePod. They're updating the HomePod to support
matter. And they just announced today as we record a new Apple TV and the fancier version
that has Ethernet also supports thread and matter. So they're, I mean, surprisingly going all in
for Apple, at least. I don't really know if this changes what I'm going to do hardware wise in
terms of sensors and devices yet, but I am curious what it means for accessibility of Apple's remote
control features to Home Assistant. When Home Assistant gets their hands on this, maybe I'll
have remote integrated control even better than I did before without even having to use HomeKit
at all or something. That would be nice, wouldn't it? Yeah. Yeah, maybe not. What's important about
this update coming out now, Apple being the first mover, I think, in actually shipping,
you know, provider level support for this stuff. It's a very strange place for Apple to be.
But anyway, you've already got HomePods. You've already got Apple TVs. So for you, you could just
purchase one or two matter devices and kind of dip your toe in nice and early and get a feeling
for it without having to spend hundreds or thousands of dollars on all new sensors and all
new whatever. And you can just do a couple of things and kind of drip feed this stuff in as
support lands in Home Assistant and that kind of stuff. Which is probably the best way to go,
right? Because I guess if history is to be our teacher, it's very possible that the Rev1 devices
could be kind of so-so and this thing takes a couple of revisions and... No. The first iPhone
was perfect. Yeah, right. Right, of course. And the first wireless communications protocols are
always perfect, too. Yeah. I'm seeing the reaction to the H3, the Odroid H3 that we just talked about
in the Discord chat. It's probably a good job you got one because I think half our audience are
about to buy one. I've got to imagine they would be because it seems like the perfect device for
what we do. I mean, low power but performance where it counts, MVME storage instead of an
EMMC or SSD, and of course, having those two SATA ports. I have a request for you. Could you
do some energy monitoring for us and compare what a Pi draws versus this thing? Because my argument
to you for all these years has been, look how much more powerful x86 is for the same power budget.
So I'm curious as to what that in reality is. Is that true or not? Yeah, that's a great thing
to check. I will. I'm also wondering, should I figure out what my power budget is? I've always
just kind of played fast and loose. Three, four Pis down to two Pis. So if I look at that, what
would four Pis have taken versus having everything on just two devices? The yellow, which I expect is
going to be, you know, what a CM4 takes plus a little bit more. And then now this H-Droid or
O-Droid, H3. I'm expecting somewhere around five to six watts idle and then who knows when it's
ramped up. We'll find out. You just got to figure it out, eh? Figure it out. lino.com slash ssh.
That's where you go to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account. And it's a great way to support
the show while you're checking out a service. It's frankly awesome. We run everything we've
built for the last few years on Linode, including our brand new shiny website, jupitabroadcasting.com,
which is kicked off and rebuilt on the regular on Linode. And we are super impressed with the
speed. We've integrated it overall with our infrastructure management tools. And you can
too. Terraform, Ansible, Kubernetes. It works with all of that. But maybe you're brand new. Maybe
you've never done any of this stuff. Linode has what they call an app marketplace. It's basically
like one click deployment for a lot of really great open source applications. And they just
recently refreshed their whole approach to Nextcloud. It's got a new feature in the marketplace.
They're working with the project. You hit that deploy button, you get a properly set up Nextcloud
instance on Linode right away. This week, I'm also just playing around with their GPU instances
with a little bit of AI image generation because they got GPU machines. And I'm not going to go
build a crazy huge Nvidia box just to play around with a project, right? But I'll go deploy a Linode
for a couple of days. And you can too. With that $100, you can really kick the tires and try just
about everything out. From their backups, their S3 object storage, to those powerful CPU or GPU
rigs. Or maybe you just want a gaming server, a blog server, or a Nextcloud instance up in the
cloud. Well, you'll have full control with Linode and you'll be super appreciative of their support
if you ever run into any problems. I'll guarantee you that. So go try them out and get $100 while
you support the show. linode.com. That's linode.com. I thought I'd continue my journey down the whole
home audio rabbit hole exploration, spelunking exercise that I've been doing recently.
Lots of people write in, give me lots of excellent recommendations of different things to try.
Volumio is still on my list of things to try. However, I thought I would try out the big dog
in the room in the Rune. The big dog in the Rune. I see what you did there. Terrible. I tried out
Rune this week for all of you lovely people. I love it. I didn't want to because it's so damn
expensive. Yeah, but Rune bills itself as the audio file player for music fanatics.
So essentially you run a piece of software on a NAS or a computer or a server like I have,
and it goes through and it catalogs all of your FLAC files, all of your audio. So it can be lossy
stuff. It can be lossless, whatever. All right. That sounds great. I've got about a quarter of
a million files I've acquired over the years. A lot of them have ripped actually of CD rips. I did
a decade plus ago. I went before I donated all my CDs to the charity shop. The performance has been
fine. It indexed that quarter of a million files in, I don't know, six hours or so, maybe three,
four, five, six hours, something like that. Is this running on a Windows machine, Linux machine,
Mac? I'm running it in a Docker container on my Linux server, but you can run it on a Windows
machine too. So they do offer it as a Docker container. Yeah. Well, I don't know if they
officially do, but it's certainly possible because it's just a Linux app. The real issue with it
though, is that to run this server, they charge, I can't believe I'm going to say this, they charge
me $10 a month for access to my own files. Yeah. Okay. It's bring your own streaming service,
bring your own music streaming service, essentially. It does have a couple of nice
features like it integrates with Tidal and Cobuz for high res gap filling in your library. So let's
say you're missing an album or a new album came out that you haven't bought yet or something like
that. It will automatically go to Tidal and Cobuz if you have an active subscription with those two
services and pull it in and fill in the gaps for you, which is just really nice. And it tries to
automatically prioritize the highest quality version of a track available. So let's say I had
an MP3 in my local library, but Cobuz has a high res, you know, high res mastered version of it.
It will play the Cobuz version, which I really liked. Yeah. That does seem like the way you'd
want it. And I guess that $10 is going towards the access to the licenses to stream that stuff
automatically. I guess so. But Roon's killer feature, and I say this genuinely out of love,
is the way it presents metadata. So you end up with this kind of like magazine view
of an album. So let's say I'm listening to some Led Zeppelin or something and it shows me Led
Zepp 4. That's the best Led Zepp album in my opinion. And so I go in there and I look at it
and I click on one of the tracks and I can see on the credits, you know, all the different people
associated with a specific album and you know, who produced it, who did the mixing for it. And
if you're a proper audio nerd, you can go down the rabbit hole really deep, really fast, because
each of the names and each of the albums mentioned in the description about this thing is a link.
And that's powered on their server side. You know, for example, Stephen Wilson is one of my
personal musical heroes. He's in a band called Porcupine Trees and a bunch of solo stuff as well.
And he is probably the most famous musician you've never heard of. Like he works with all,
he does mixes film soundtracks and all kinds of stuff. And so when I dig into Stephen Wilson's
Stephen's profile, I get to see everything he's associated with and everything he's worked as an
engineer on and worked as an editor on. And before you know it, you found 10 new bands you didn't
know you liked because it's got some of your favorite influences in. So that's amazing. The
way it presents metadata is genuinely Rune's killer, killer feature. The other thing that
I like about it is the fact it does multi room audio much in the same way as like a Sonos does.
You have a little icon in your playback client, and then you can just check a box and suddenly
you've got two devices playing in sync. That doesn't sound too incredible until I explain
the scenario that really blew my mind. So Rune has this thing called Rune Advanced Audio Transport
RAT that runs on anything that runs a Rune ready or a Rune native client. So certain amplifiers
and amplifiers have been certified by Rune and by Marantz and Denon and all these big guys.
They pay Rune a small fee and they embed the Rune ready receiver software into their
network streamers. You can also run a RAT ready device on a Windows PC, a Mac computer, an iOS
device, a Raspberry Pi. And so you can cast effectively, it's not quite casting, but you
can stream music to any RAT ready device in sync, no matter what iOS it's running. So
just paint this, I've got my iPad out on the deck where I'm grilling some meats.
In the lounge next door, I've got a Raspberry Pi plugged into a HiFi running Linux. In the room
next door, I've got my laptop running Mac OS and all three of those devices are playing audio
perfectly in sync that I'm controlling from my iPhone with a single checkbox.
That is pretty glorious.
That's the dream, isn't it?
Yeah. All the machines, all the speakers, all the OSs.
The catch, and unfortunately I think there's probably some technical limitations here at play,
is that you can only stream like that to devices that are part of the same kind of ecosystem.
So I can only group devices that are RAT devices. I can only group Chromecast devices together. I
can only group AirPlay devices together. I can't stream to an AirPlay and a Chromecast
device at the same time.
Do you have any idea why? That's a pretty interesting limitation.
Well, I mean, AirPlay, the way it buffers the stream is quite different to how Chromecast
buffers the stream.
So it's using their native protocols. It's not using like a client on that. Oh, yeah. Okay.
That makes sense.
Well, that's what the RAT stuff is doing. So the RAT stuff is running a native client on the
specific device, iOS or whatever. And that's why you can't group them together. And I was a little
bit deflated to start with when I found that out because I had this magical vision of all the
Google Home Nest mini hub things I have around the house and all my computers and everything
all working perfectly in sync. And unfortunately, that isn't the case.
What if you bought the Nucleus Plus, which is their $2,600 server that you can buy from them?
How do you know this service is aimed at audio files, huh?
How to tell, right? I mean, it's a cool looking case. I'll give them that.
It's a beautiful ecosystem. Yeah, they've got, so you can run this rune core,
this server software. You can run it in a Docker container like I am. You can run it on a Synology
on a computer. But rune also sell this thing called the Nucleus. And Chris is showing on the
stream now something called the Whirlwind, which is a rack mount version of the same thing.
It's so great. That one's $4,500.
Yeah. And you know, what's funny is if you actually dig into the specs page on these pages,
there is zero information about what CPU is in there.
There is a page where they just say they have on their partners page,
they say they have partnered with Intel. Yeah, that's it. I mean, who's to say whether
it's a Celeron from 2003 or whether it's an i7 12th Gen. I mean, I imagine it's neither,
but we don't know. And that's the point, right? It's a black box, literally.
Yeah. And when you're dropping that kind of cash, I guess, you know, and of course,
the answer is they're selling this to a market who couldn't care less. We realize that.
But it's still it wouldn't kill them to put the specs on there.
If you go by the ports, it looks like it's a knock in there. I have to say.
Yeah, I agree. So, I mean, if we can get over the price of this thing,
because I mentioned the monthly price. I didn't mention they also offer a lifetime pass for $700.
I mean, if you really stuck with it and they stuck around, you know, you got somewhere between
five to 10 years out of this and it had high spousal approval. Maybe. I mean, I could see that.
So Rune as a company was founded, I think, in 2015. And so if you bought into Rune in 2015
and paid $700, you would only just be breaking even on your monthly subscription.
Just put that into perspective. Seven years is a long time for an ROI on that kind of thing.
Yeah. And I wrestled with this pretty hard before I actually tried Rune out. You know,
I wanted to hate it because it was expensive. I wanted to hate it because it was closed source.
But then I thought, well, so is Plex, isn't it? And you like Plex just fine. And so I kind of
came to terms with it and got over myself and thought, yeah, you know, it's fine. You can try
it out and you'll hate it anyway. I don't. I love it. The trouble is just as I've been doing this,
they've made a big release. They've just released the 2.0, the version two, which if you're a Rune
aficionado is a huge deal. But to me as a newbie, it's just unstable, right? So you're familiar
with Plexamp, right? The app that lets you play your Plex music remotely. Love it. Rune have just
released an equivalent app called Rune Arc, A-R-C. And this lets you access all of your Rune music
outside the house. As it stands, the Rune desktop and mobile clients that already existed only worked
if you were on your LAN and directly connected to your Rune core. I couldn't get it to work over
tail scale remotely. So Rune Arc kind of bridges that gap for a lot of people. However, this brings
us to the cons section of my document. I don't really know how else to say this, but Rune with
2.0 have shot their, they're kind of eating their own face. Okay. And the reason I say that is
because firstly, they're charging me $10 a month for access to my own files, plus the metadata,
plus the integrations with Tidal and Kobuz. Okay. However, it gets worse. They guarantee with the 2.0
update zero minutes of offline playback. If the Rune core cannot connect to the internet,
Rune's position is that they guarantee zero minutes of playback. Because they don't want to
have to pay out when somebody's wifi goes down or their router takes a crap, something like that,
you think? Well, according to Johnny Darko, who is the source of this information, he spoke to,
I think his name is Danny over at Rune about this. There's a link in the show notes to this video
because I couldn't quite believe what I was watching. And Johnny Darko is a proper audiophile
and I trust his opinion almost implicitly on an awful lot of audio gear. And I like the way his
videos feel. I like the way he presents information. He's a British guy living in, I think, Berlin.
We've got to stick together, you know? But what's interesting is Johnny is clearly not a techno guy
like us, right? And listening to someone who's operating on the edge of their understanding
about how some of these technologies on the server side of things work, it's really interesting
because it shows you actually that I think Rune are just trying to pull the wool over people's
eyes. And I don't say that lightly. And the reason I do say it is because the Rune projects say
they're doing this always online connectivity thing for the server because they want to move
a lot of the processing to the cloud and to move the product forward and all that kind of stuff.
So a lot of the local processing that currently happens on the Nucleus, on the Rune core, on my
local network is moving into the cloud. And they say that they'll be able to batch stuff up and
make it more efficient and kind of, you know, de-duplicate a lot of, you know, template matching
and all that kind of stuff, which I get, which I understand and does actually make some semblance
of sense. However, we're talking about this through a lens of self-hosting, right? That's
the name of the podcast, right? Just imagine a situation where your internet goes out for half
an hour every day and you suddenly can't play back the files on your NAS under your desk in
your basement. You know, it's just unacceptable on a huge number of levels for me personally.
And I think despite how much I love Rune so far and, you know, the 2.0 release has been a little
buggy and, you know, not perfect, a little rough around the edges, I just can't adopt a product
that costs this much money and compromises on such a fundamental capability like that of an
offline self-hosted type product. It's just, I just can't. Yeah, that's a fair point,
especially when you consider there's people out there that maybe they're on Starlink and they're
having a bad day or they're on LTE and they're having a bad day. Or they live in the third world
and the entire island is connected through a single satellite type people. That surely is
not a big part of Rune's core audience. Starlink customers, I could see the Starlink customers.
Starlink people are out there, you know. You know, the thing is, it's sort of taking away
one of the biggest advantages of you collecting all that stuff locally for so many years and it's
just... At that point, why not just have a Cobuz subscription or a Tidal subscription? What value
is Rune adding if I can't even, let's say, you know, one of my friend's dads was out of power
for like 8 to 10 days with Hurricane Ian a couple of weeks ago, you know? Yikes. It's just no good.
It's no good. You know, for the pricing, especially if you were looking at server hardware,
you could almost just afford to just buy sets of speakers for every single room and just
put a dedicated hardware device on them and just call it good. Yeah. It does sound like it was
really nice for a moment though. The alternative is Sonos, really, that's got this level of fit
and finish and polish and all the rest of it. But Sonos is just hardware and as we talked about
several episodes ago, when Sonos decided that a device is no longer supported, suddenly that
perfectly good speaker cone and that perfectly good amplifier unit become a brick, thanks to
their business model, you know? And that's a thing. It's frustrating. So I think that the next one to
look at is probably Volumio, although I've heard mixed reports about that and I certainly don't
expect the level of fit and finish I've seen from Rune. The other one to keep an eye on is Plexamp
Headless. There's been some pretty good movement over there lately. I think they're working on
multi-room audio stuff, but it won't have the Rune audio transport stuff, so I doubt it will
be quite as polished again, but who knows? Who knows where this will go? But that's my review
of Rune, people. Fascinating. Thank you for updating us on that. We've been getting a good
series of feedback on multi-room audio. It's something people are trying to solve and I know
there's got to be somebody out there that's like, just get a Pi Zero, you know, or something like that,
but who do you really have time? Well, Rune, sorry to come back to Rune again, but I'm running one of
the playback devices is a RU-P, a Raspberry Pi running the Rune server. Right, okay. So I am
using Raspberry Pi as part of this as well. So, you know, maybe one day I'll find the perfect
solution, but I think until Rune guarantee, I don't know, seven days before the server,
the core has to phone home again, it used to be 30 days. The grace period, by the way,
with 1.8, which was the previous release, used to be 30 days and now it's zero minutes.
It's just a hard sell. Yeah, especially when you're paying 10 bucks a month.
Feels like you, you know, when you're paying for something like that that's using your own media,
they should give you grace periods like that. 30 days sounds about right. That's about it.
You know, I'm going to be buying new gear soon. Cloudfree.shop is where I'll go to check it out.
And you can too if you use the promo code SSH. I think you get like a buck off. Light switches
coming soon. Cloudfree light switches. Light switches is definitely the way I want to go.
And after we get to the feedback today, I think I'm going to be doubling down on ZigBee. I'll
tell you more about that later, though. Cloudfree.shop. Promo code self-posted.
Yeah, one of my Shelleys just failed actually in the, in the garage. The actual switch,
the relay part still works. But when I flick the physical switch in the wall,
which in the garage you do all the time, nothing happens. So I've no idea what's happened with that
one. Bummer. It's kind of apparent they're about to take it out. Yeah. Well, I'm looking,
I was thinking about getting one of those zoo switches that we talked about last episode,
but I don't want to go just Seawave just for a few light switches. I'd like to stay
within the ZigBee universe. So if you have a good ZigBee switch recommendation, please let us know
at self-posted.show slash contact. Speaking of feedback,
Docker versus LXC versus a VM. You teased it earlier in the show and it's been a point of
conversation recently. Yeah. Monkey Angst and I were talking on Discord and he wrote in saying,
I'm trying to decide between using an LXC or another containerization technology.
What are you using these days, Alex? And why? Well, the short answer is
Docker and Docker and more Docker plus some virtualization. And I think that's a, oh,
and I suppose in the cloud too, there's a couple of things up there. Most of that stuff's running
in Docker too. And I'm just going to preface everything I'm about to say by saying that it's
a personal choice. And there's more than one way to skin a particular cat in this arena.
The way I do it is I run everything in Docker because Docker Compose is awesome.
It's a great way to manage your personal systems. It's a great way to separate without really having
to do much anything, separate out the application and the data. And just from a system building
standpoint, that is a great design practice and Docker just gives it to you as a general practice.
And the other thing about LXCs to consider is that the benefits of them is that it gives you
an init system. So for those that aren't familiar, an init system is something like system D
with a typical Docker container or some kind of other Linux container. What happens is the main
process inside that container gets given PID one, process ID one. And when that PID dies,
the container dies with it. The same, by the way, is true of your Linux server or your Linux desktop
or whatever you're running Linux on. When PID one dies, the system dies. And typically that PID
one is system D these days. In an LXC, what happens is you get an init system like system D.
My biggest gripe with LXC generally, and there's two really, one is that it's an extra layer of
complexity that not that many people are using. Some people in our self-hosted community are
using it, but generally it's on the fringes compared to the number of people that are using
Docker containers. The second thing is that running more than one process in an isolated
environment like that is a bit of an anti-pattern. And the reason I say that is because containers
are designed to be this black box almost of just a single block with a single purpose.
And if you start trying to run more than one service inside that container, so let's say
system D plus a web server, on the face of it, you're only running one service, right? A web
server, but actually you're running two, you're running an init system plus a web server, which
is a whole bunch of overhead that you A, don't need and B, technically speaking is like I said,
a bit of an anti-pattern. And so the other thing it gives you is some issues, well not issues,
it's not the right word, but added complexity around passing hardware through. So like QuickSync,
for example, which I think is what we talked about earlier in the show. If you're running
QuickSync in a Docker container, it's a couple of lines to pass through the render device.
To QuickSync running in Plex or whatever, it's no big deal. With LXC, there can be some
compatibility issues. It's a similar thing, you've got to pass it through, but I can never remember
if it has a distinct lock on the GPU once you pass it through to an LXC or not. So somebody
in the chat could update in real time, I'd appreciate it. But then the other thing you've
got to consider is if you want to run multiple services in one isolated environment, that's
exactly what a VM has been designed to do. The tooling around VMs is extremely mature at this
point. They're very, very well understood. And I don't know, LXC for me fall into this awkward
middle ground of not quite knowing who they're for. It's not to say they're a bad technology
because I think LXCs do have their place. They just don't in my world personally.
Yeah. Well, and I think they're also a little more popular in the Ubuntu ecosystem as well,
which is probably just not as prevalent in the North America area. So I think there's that
element as well. I like what you're saying about VMs, just to step back a little bit there. Your
point about the VM sometimes the right tooling, people shouldn't feel bad about it, I think is
underscored by the fact that VM performance, it's like it's not your grandpa's VM anymore.
On modern hardware with modern virtualization software, VMs can be extremely performant,
way better than they were when we were emulating the entire hardware stack. Because these days,
not only do we have pair of virtualized devices, but there's also just been a lot of plumbing in
the kernel to get virtual driver requests to the physical hardware so much faster than they were
even four or five years ago. Exactly. I mean, you think about all those cloud servers that are
running virtualized stacks, a lot of that investment trickles down to us mere mortals.
A lot of those improvements end up in the kernel one way or another. So yeah, the other thing we
didn't talk about at all yet is Podman. I know being a Red Hatter, I should probably be a bit
more pro Podman, but for me, the tooling's just still not quite there yet. I rely on Compose all
the time for interacting with all of my services. I know Podman Compose exists and I've tried it
several times, but it's still just- It's not 100%.
It's not quite there. Yeah. It's like 90% or so, but it's not 100%. I have the same opinion.
I feel like Podman is a better design system architecturally. It feels cleaner. It feels
more native as well. But then again, you have like monsters in our chat room that are running
Docker in LXC. Oh my goodness. Well, you can run Docker in Docker in Docker in VN.
Right. These are the people that show up to our live streams.
Yeah, right. Say the tip of the iceberg.
Yeah, there you go. Very interesting. I'd love also to hear other people's opinions on it too.
So do feel free to go to the contact page or send us a boost. There was discussion going on
on Reddit that I wanted to just kind of touch on because I have a lot of thoughts on this,
but I had something I think is actionable. And the question is, and Alex, I liked this question a
lot because it's being honest with themselves. And I think it's something all of us self-hosters
should think about. How do I prepare for a time when I'm just tired of tinkering with
Home Assistant? That's the question that was on Reddit. And I love it because it's like,
this guy writes, I've used Home Assistant for the last six months and I've had a blast
tinkering with the platform. I've got a hundred plus devices. Everything is working as intended.
And I know from experience there come a time when I just don't find home automation as flattering
anymore, but I'll still need my lights and whatnot to function properly. So how do I prepare for this
day? This is really, I need to take this advice in as well. Now I've always remained pretty
fascinated. Home Assistant moves quick. The community moves quick. It hasn't lost my attention,
but things have. And as geeks, I think we're just kind of prone to the new shiny sometimes as well.
Do you have any hot tips on how to prepare your infrastructure for when you are bored with it?
Do you have anything off the top of your mind?
Don't get bored at the time where it's broken.
Yeah.
I don't know. It's such a hard question because I'm aware that the raindrop of inspiration
in the desert of computer, you know, there's several things have to line up in order for me
to be interested enough to tinker with something. I have to have enough free time in my mind and I
always underestimate how long something is going to take. So if I think it's going to take four
hours, I know I've got to estimate I've got to have a whole day free. And if it's quicker than
that, great. I mean, that's often not the case with Home Assistant, but sometimes it is. Probably
the best advice I can give, and it's not terribly wisdomful, but is just try and break down the
things you're trying to accomplish into small tasks, small batches of stuff. Let's say you want
to get a specific room behaving a certain way, or you want to get just a couple of new lights added
or something and try not to leave anything half finished when you go to sleep or something like
that. I know it's not always possible because, you know, I'll wake up tomorrow and my interest
will be in cars tomorrow, not Home Assistant or what, you know, how it is. And for me, leaving
stuff half done when I go to sleep is the enemy because, A, I've loaded it into context, like in
my personal RAM buffer or whatever, and loading it back in again is going to take a long time,
typically. Sometimes going for a walk or whatever, you know, can be the solution.
We've also got to get the motivation program running again, too. So it's not just the context
and the data and the state, but it's also you've got to get motivated again.
Also, the caffeination station has to be fired up, too, you know. So, yeah, you know,
essentially just break things down into atomic blocks, really.
Yeah, and complete it one room at a time and complete it as much as you can. That's a great tip.
Yeah, and I find that helps with motivation, too, because if you actually think,
right, I've done that, and it works as intended, next time, you know, you'll be like,
oh, well, yeah, I actually achieved what I set out to do, and it can be a self-perpetuate,
self-fulfilling cycle of improvement.
I think that's probably how I should probably attack, like, the rebuild of the sensors and
all the switches and stuff and dupes. It's probably just one room at a time, and it'll,
you know, it'll go quick.
Also, you are your own worst enemy. Write this down. Document your crap, because you will forget.
You think you won't, you think you remember it, but trust me, you won't.
You've got to write it down. Absolutely agree. Absolutely agree. I have one bit of wisdom from
my whole, my home assistant's been unavailable, and this is what this guy was worried about.
Like, it would crash, and he just wouldn't have the motivation to fix it.
This is something you can do in Z-Wave, but I read how to do it in ZigBee,
and this seems like the thing to do. It's called device binding.
So, you can bind a light switch to a particular light, for example. You can bind two ZigBee
devices together, so they can control each other without the central coordinator. So,
they, as long as they're both on the network and both devices support binding, you can have them
operate without home assistant even running. And this is incredible, because it means, like,
all of, like, your switches and buttons and those types of things continue to work,
even if your server's crashed. And so, this is definitely something I want to look into for at
least a few core devices. Like, switches to turn lights on and off, those always need to work. And
I don't really have the flexibility to, like, open it up and, like, install a Shelby in the,
or a Shelly in the wall, because my walls are, like, two inches thick. They're thinner than
the Shelly is. So, I have to go with the soft button route, which means when home assistant's
down, no light switches, which is crazy. Just absolutely crazy. And so, something like binding
would keep it working and give you the time to continue to operate your stuff without having to
actually get the server up and running. And they have groups and all kinds of stuff. And I've read
that people also get this working with their Philips Hughes, so you can use binding with the
Hughes lights as well. I'll have a link in the show notes for more information about binding.
A dot technologies that you own the firmware of, you know, Tasmotor is a great example.
Don't rely on a cloud-based service, you know, buy the right hardware, all that kind of stuff. Try,
try and buy with the idea that you want it to just keep working until the hardware physically
stops working would be a great idea. I like the chat room. Serverless IoT. Nice. It is kind of,
isn't it? You're right, Aaron. That's pretty cool. We got some boosts into the show. Check out this.
Yerero? I'm so sorry, dude. 135,000 sats was sent into the show this week. He says it's not a moly.
I know. In fact, I'm going to buy a boat that put us on the hot list. So in Fountain, you know,
highly boosted shows, I believe it was this boost put, put self-hosted on the hot list and
then new people find the show. So when you send a big boost in, it's where we, the show trends
and the people discover us. It's really great. So Yerero writes, it's not a million dollars,
but these are all the sats I have. I am currently thinking of automating the lighting around my flat
and unable to pick between smart lights or smart switches. What are the pros and cons of each one?
Thanks, Alex, Chris and Brent. Fairly easy answer, actually. Switches mean that your bulbs stay
powered all the time and you can, so you can control the switch, you retain physical control
of the switch and you also gain the ability to control that switch remotely as well. Whereas if
you just go for a smart bulb and someone turns the light switch off, uh-oh, you're out of luck.
Yeah. And it's also just way more approachable by every other single human on the face of the planet.
And so if you have anybody else that's going to be in the space with you,
what I literally have on my switches here in the studio, I have tape over them that says
no touch because like people just flip light switches all the time. And it still happens when
we have a meetup here at the studio, inevitably like a listener will just walk out of the studio
and they'll just instinctively flip the light switch off, you know, they'll even flip it right
through the tape. Read the FM, huh? What? What is it? Hearty FM. Oh, even if it's just a bit
of tape on the light switch, you know, you've got a hearty FM. Yeah, that's true. Read the tape.
Prozac boosted with 1200 sats. Just thanking Alex for sharing your secret sauce. And so I thought,
just in case people missed it last episode, we should probably put the Badgerstack link
in the show notes for an overview of Alex's setup. People have been liking that. PA or PageDot
boosted in with 3333 sats. Hi, please take a look at the FunkWhale project. It's a federated music
service with a great GUI, active development, a subsonic API, mobile app, and financial support.
I use it without the federation for my personal library, but I really like it because they really
managed to keep me up to date and involve the community in their decisions I just wanted to
make. So I went and looked at it, super quick, and I'm going to put this on my checkout. This
and Jellyfin, which I realize are not quite the same, but Jellyfin's, the jelly amp app that
people are working on, and this FunkWhale, I think could be great solutions for my music use, because
I'm not so much looking for a whole home sync so much as I am just looking for something that could
expose a local music collection to me in a way that I could consume when I want to listen, mostly
in the car or on home pods. FunkWhale's really nice. Funkwhale.audio. Are you familiar with it,
Alex? I tried it out once a few months ago, and then just for some reason it didn't stick. I can't
remember why. If I might interrupt the boosts for a second, we're having a live question in the chat
room. What is the boost address? We've got jupyterbroadcasting.com slash boost, but then what?
So you need a new podcast app because it's an RSS feed-based thing. So the boost address is in
the RSS feed. So you get a new podcast app, and that reads that RSS tag, and then automatically
adds a button to your playback screen. There's also a browser extension, which I was actually
going to suggest to you after the show, Alex, called ALBY. And that lets you do it in a browser
based environment. And the reason I was going to mention it to you is they've launched a new
platform called Saturn. And I think it's like, I don't know for sure, actually. I have to look
at it, but I think it's kind of like having your own node, and then you could get a copy of the
messages and a split of the SATs with Saturn, I think. And then I don't think you have to set up
a whole node, but ALBY is an open source project for a Lightning wallet in the browser. I don't
generally like it because I don't like stuff built into the browser, but I had a chance to talk to
the co-founder and ask him my questions about security and open source practices, and I actually
walked away with a pretty good opinion of where they're at. So ALBY for that. Then you could boost
from the website using our new player on the website. Otherwise, it requires a new podcast
app at newpodcastapps.com. And then one day, soon, one day, Alex, I have a dream. Jupiter
Broadcasting will be generating all of our own RSS feeds independently. We use a service provider
called Fireside right now. It's very common practice to have a service generate your RSS
feeds or like a WordPress plugin or something because you never want them to screw up.
So like people have just like specialized in that because it's like your radio signal.
But right now we don't generate our own RSS feed, but we want to. And then we'll start taking
advantage of even more podcasting 2.0 features like transcripts and host information in there,
like, you know, guest, more guest information, richer context around that kind of stuff.
And a big one that I'm really looking forward to, I don't know what we'll use it for exactly yet,
alternative enclosures. So like maybe like an MP4 file or an Opus file if people want an Opus
version or I don't know. But it's so your podcast player will just it'll see the entry and then in
the player, you'll just choose like which format you want because we can just specify multiple
formats in one RSS feed entry with podcasting 2.0 in the past. And you've probably seen JB has like
so many different RSS feeds because any variation of file type, you had to do a whole new RSS feed
because that's just how these players worked back then. So it's a whole new generation over there.
Very excited about it. I think it's going to be big for podcasting. And I think it's the way to
keep podcasting decentralized and self-hosted because the other big trend in the podcasting
industry is consolidation with Spotify and players like that. And then they do dynamic
ad insertion. They do the hosting. They manage your RSS feed and the podcaster doesn't have
any control over it. And I think decentralization is key to keeping podcasting healthy.
And I think self-hosting plays a big role in that. Fundek Hermit boosted in with 2,346 sets.
Hey guys, I wanted to mention an amazing newish feature of R-Clone. You can now use a Docker
plugin to mount the local or cloud storage directly as a Docker volume. That's great for
host isolation and separation. That is great. R-Clone for the win.
Yeah. So I guess you could use, you know, like Google drive as a Docker volume. I wonder what
the latency is like, but that sounds amazing. I mean, if you're just writing like an encrypted
tar file or something. Yeah. For something like my smoke ping, you know, history or something
like that, that might be nice that I would like to keep around, but I don't really care
that much about it. Maybe I'll investigate. That sounds pretty cool. Thanks Fundek Hermit.
Last couple of boosts for this week, although we did read all of them. We only feature some
of them in the show. Soltros boosted with 9,000 sets. I recently got into Docker after refusing
to let go of my VM obsession. Welcome. Are there any tips out there for use case scenarios or cool
project I can run at my home on my Ubuntu home server? Right now I have Nextcloud, Plex, and a
few other odds and ends. Well, over at PerfectMediaServer.com, I have a list of my top 10
recommended apps to run on your new media server. So I'll put a link to that in the show notes. And
if you have any other recommendations, let us know at selfhosted.show slash contact.
Look at that. And you know, just keep listening to the show because as you listen, you'll hear us
mention our favorite apps over and over again. Like Alex just namedrop smoke ping. That's a great
one. It's a classic. Yeah, it's funny. I got smoke ping from Linux action show back in the day way
before you knew me. And then I wrapped it up as a Docker container on Linux server.io. And then
now it's a thing. I know. And then I grabbed it one day. I'm like, hey, it pings Jupiter broadcasting.
That's awesome. Yeah, that's why that's why I put you in there, bro. And it really is a great
example of like an app that probably should be in a container because it's kind of super old and
legacy in a lot of ways. And you don't want it on your whole system. Our last boost of the episode
came in from bronzewing, who boosted nine thousand and one sets over nine thousand. There's another
option called Mood M O O D E moody, perhaps that runs on a pie and says it can do multi room audio.
And we have a link in there to mood audio dot org. It's free and you can get a hi fi Barry
amp and put speakers on that in each room controlled by a Web interface. And that interface
is mobile friendly. I hear it's actually better than Volumio. It could be the complete solution.
Worth checking out. Does look nice. Yeah, I think when my rune free trial expires, which I think
I've got another week left on, I think I'll probably have to give Volumio a spin next and then
move on to this mood thing after that. But I'll be honest with you people. I'm getting a little
fatigued with the music situation and I'll probably just go back to Spotify for a few months
whilst I just calm down again. I'm just going to ship you like six home pods and you'll be good.
Yeah, I know it's not what you want. I know. I know. I also want to say thank you to John A.
who sent 2000 sats. He's going to be switching to Podverse. That is one of those new podcast apps
that is totally GPL, Web, Android, iOS. And it's an F-droid. And I really appreciated that when I
switched to graphene. And then Schmitzfeld, who Brent appropriately pronounces. I mentioned that
it was recently his first boost ever that he sent into the show. And he also is a big fan of
replacing the Raspberry Pi with a small, low power PC. He's had great results, he says. So
I will let you guys know how the O-Droid H3 Plus works out. I'm super excited about that. And then
that old Powerwall or Solar Wall device. I have a couple of ideas and I think I have a couple
outside the box places where I could mount that because it is so rugged too. All projects for
future episodes. That H3 is the type of device that I'm trying to think of a project for.
But I don't already have a solution for. Like, I want to buy one. I just don't know why,
what I'd use it for. I want one though. I mean, maybe you'll get lucky and your server will die.
Oh, we can hope. Hopefully not, dude. Hopefully not. Thank you to our SRE subscribers. Those are
our site reliability engineers. You guys make the show possible by investing in our ongoing
content production. And as a thank you, we make an ad free version of the show and every episode
gets a little extra content for the members, a post show. You can become a member at self hosted
dot show slash SRE or support all the shows get ad free for everything at Jupiter dot party.
And as you know, self hosted dot show slash contact is the place to go to get in touch with
us. You can find me over on Twitter at ironic badger. Oh, do we want to tease all things open
at all? Any updates there? Oh, yeah, we could do coming up around Halloween all things open in
Raleigh. If you're going to be in town, keep an eye on the meetup page. I don't know if we do the
official Jupiter broadcasting meetup or just the Raleigh room, probably just the Raleigh room on
matrix could do either way. Myself and cheese bacon longtime friend of the network will be there.
He's supporting a booth for system 76 at the conference. So I'll be at the conference too. And
we might go out for a drinky poo in the evening after one of the talks. We'll see.
Now I want to go. I really wanted to go to all things open. It's too much traveling, but I really
want to go next year. Remember Halloween, Raleigh and you'll I think so. I think so. Also, I'll
mention we have our discord server. You can find that on our self hosted website. And we also have
a couple of self hosted matrix chat rooms. That's a Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash matrix. And
then the podcast itself at self hosted show on Twitter. I do really mean it. I don't know if
I say this every single week about thanks for listening, everybody. But genuinely, if you made
it this far in the show, thank you very much for listening. This is self hosted dot show slash 82.