So far, I think I hate Shinobi.
Oh, no.
I thought I was going to love it.
Yeah.
No.
I think I hate it.
You're supposed to love it.
I know.
And I went and I bought all the cameras before I even tried it.
So I got five Wwisecams.
I reflashed all of the Wwisecams to the RTSP firmware,
so that way I could just stream directly from them over my LAN.
I got a Raspberry Pi 4 dedicated to the Shinobi installation,
set up the Shinobi DVR software.
Or I guess it's not technically DVR.
It's whatever the term is for a closed circuit recording system.
Got it all loaded up.
And I'm just not thrilled.
First of all, by default, it doesn't support motion detection.
That's a plug-in, which is broken right now on ARM.
And it, just three cameras, is slamming the Pi,
maxed out all the cores on the Pi.
That's a real shame.
I mean, I've used Shinobi a little bit.
I'm not an expert.
I've got three Wwisecams feeding into it here,
and it's running on my big Xeon downstairs.
But the interface is a little bit confusing,
I've found at times, right?
So when you're trying to pull in the feeds,
you have to set all sorts of parameters.
Yeah, and I think I may have some finessing to do there.
And I probably should also mention the big caveat
that I did.
I broke my own rule with using the Raspberry Pi 4
in production, and I did not put Raspbian on it.
Because I'm not super comfortable with Raspbian,
and when it does big updates and stuff,
I don't have experience with it to trust it.
I'd rather use, like, an LTS Ubuntu or a CentOS,
something that I just have more faith in.
And I let that doubt get to me.
And I loaded it with a community build of Ubuntu 18.04 LTS
that swaps out Ubuntu's kernel and puts the Raspbian kernel
in.
And I thought, maybe this will work pretty well.
Maybe it'll support all the drivers, but maybe it's not.
And so today, I brought the Raspberry Pi in with me,
into the studio.
I'm going to reflash it over to Raspbian,
reset up Shinobi on that, and then
see if maybe I have better GPU acceleration,
because I need to pull in more cameras than three.
And so if it can only do three cameras,
I don't think I'm going to do a Pi for every three cameras.
I think I'd have to go to x86.
Yeah, that's a bit expensive.
Are you running into issues when you load up
the UI, the web interface, or is it just constantly slammed?
It's definitely worse when the web UI is up,
but it's still very slammed, even when I don't have the web
UI running.
The other thing is, is in Shinobi,
I'm seeing more frame loss, like chunks of the video
go missing, like with encoding errors.
I do not have that same problem when I open up the same video
stream and just pass the URL to MPV or VLC.
Opens right up, no problem.
Yeah.
If I had a tiling window manager,
and I could just put eight versions of VLC,
that might work well.
So you know what I've done in the meantime,
and it's not great, but I've pulled the RTSP
feeds into Home Assistant.
Oh, how's that working?
Pretty good.
I get real time.
I don't get recording.
But I now just have a tab in my Home Assistant dashboard
called Security, where I've put my motion sensors,
my outside cameras, and my inside cameras all on one tab.
I tap that, and it pulls them all up.
So it's really nice just to get a look
at the state of things, that it works really well for that.
We haven't really touched on your camera setup much yet,
and I think we'll probably get to it
in a future episode of the perfect IP camera,
the perfect POE camera, if such a thing even exists, right?
Oh, totally.
Yeah, we can totally do a dedicated episode.
I'm holding on to this why stuff just for a little bit longer,
because I'd really like to figure out
how to make it work for people, because these
are $25 cameras that you can put RTSP support on.
And they make for such a great addition to your home security.
And they support person detection, motion detection.
They have two-way speakers and a microphone, obviously,
for $25.
And you can completely run them offline
on your own local LAN.
So I'm going to stick with it for a bit,
see if I can't tweak my Shinobi config, because I'd
love to come on the show and tell people
how to get it all rocking on a Pi with Wyze cams.
Because for $100, you could have a full camera security system.
For the price of one, not even one Nest Cam.
Yeah.
The other thing is I was not able to get
Shinobi running in a container.
I've had, like, that's the first application
where I bailed on the container approach
and built it on the host.
Bro, you should hook up your container expert over here.
No, I thought about bugging you, actually.
But I thought you were dealing with your own container
issues at the time, so I didn't want to bother you.
Oh, probably, yeah.
Actually, interestingly enough, so I
mentioned stat ping in an episode recently.
And Joe Ressington pinged me a few hours after it aired
and went, Alex, your stat ping is down.
And I'm like, no.
I thought I'd been DDoSed by the show audience or something.
But it turned out I'd actually just been a bit honey badger
with the updates.
The ironic badger goes honey badger.
Right.
So I have this.
I use Docker Compose to do all of my container management.
I just log in randomly and just do Docker Compose pull,
Docker Compose up.
And that's my update process for updating my apps.
It's as simple as that.
I probably should script it, right?
I should probably have DigitalOcean do a backup,
or what's it called, a snapshot via the API,
and then do the updates, and then have some kind of sanity
checks afterwards.
But I'm not doing this for business.
I'm doing this for my own personal pleasure.
You do know better.
You're just choosing not to do it.
I just couldn't be bothered, yeah.
All the config is in Ansible.
So at least I have it all stored in Git somewhere.
So I'm not going to lose it overnight.
But anyway, the interesting issue with this one
was I logged into the droplet.
I was actually in a hotel room in Florida at the time,
connected via my slate, WireGuard VPN,
the little travel router, connected back
to my house in Raleigh.
I'm ordering another one of those slates.
We talked about it recently, like two episodes ago.
But this is a little OpenWRT powered box
that has WireGuard support and CAPTCHA support.
So you can throw it on a hotel Wi-Fi,
VPN up all your traffic, and that
becomes the access point for every device in your room.
I'm traveling mid-November, and I'm picking one of those up
for the trip.
Good shout.
I swear I should be on commission.
I think I've sold about 15 of those devices since then.
Really?
Too bad they don't have an affiliate deal or something.
Yeah, right.
So anyway, I logged into the droplet via SSH,
and I looked at the logs for the container,
and it said, schema error.
You're now running Postgres 12 instead of 11.
Statping was running against Postgres 11.
So it was just a case of going into the Docker compose file,
adding a tag, because currently I didn't actually
have any tags specified, so it was just pulling latest.
And so it rolled back from version 12 to version 11
in about eight seconds.
When it pulled the old image down again,
I pressed Docker compose up, and lo and behold,
Statping came straight back up.
Isn't that amazing?
Oh, it's so good.
Are you able to fully appreciate how much better that
is than the old way of doing things,
where if you installed everything via package,
it would have spewed libraries all over your system,
and it would have been a massive uncoupling to walk back,
especially if other components or applications on the system
were dependent on that package?
Less than five minutes from diagnosing the issue
to having it resolved.
I mean, luckily for me, the database
hadn't updated its schema itself automatically
or anything like that, but just rolling back
the image of the database was super duper easy.
So if you want a sales pitch for why containers
are great, that's definitely up there.
Containers today on the self-hosted podcast.
That's the container corner segment for today.
I have another thing I need to admit
is my current storage setup is already
starting to fail me because I'm starting
to do multiple disks attached directly
to the Pi, each Pi, which is now three of them.
Via USB?
Yeah, USB 3.
I don't have super high performance requirements
because I'm accessing these mostly over Wi-Fi, so.
It's just a reliability thing.
I've just seen USB devices drop off the bus for no reason.
That never happens with SATA.
If you run a machine for 100 days,
I would way more bet on a USB disk disappearing than a SATA
just wouldn't disappear unless the disk fails.
The other thing is I don't have enough storage for the cameras.
I don't need a lot of disk, but I'd
like probably at least three solid days worth of storage
so I can go back if something happens.
A week would be ideal.
But also, I need to accommodate things like Plex, which
holds my books, my audio books, my music, my videos,
about a terabyte of local media, and some pictures I
need to accommodate, some notes.
I've also got things like Docker configs
and the containers-related data that I all need to store.
And I don't know if I should.
What I've done so far is I've got,
when on sale, these Samsung MV and E
drives that are bus-powered over USB 3.0 and they're tiny.
I'm holding one up to you now on Telegram.
I've just sent you a picture.
That's the SanDisk one you have there, right?
It's not even half the size of a credit card.
No.
And it's ruggedized.
It sort of has a rubber coating.
And it's also very well-rated in terms of performance
with the Raspberry Pi.
I just recently went through some disk benchmarks.
Here's the other thing that really, really
is a tricky thing for me in the RV.
Is whatever disk solution I implement
needs to be able to withstand a level four
earthquake on the Richter scale.
Because when I drive, that's essentially
what the conditions inside the RV is, is a level four
earthquake.
And so the disks, ideally, could stay online while we drive,
because I might have the children on board
and they'd like to watch television or use the services
while we're going down the road.
Man, that would have made road trips so great as a kid.
Can you even imagine just having, not just,
you know, I mean, when I was a kid,
we used to play games in the car like,
count the number plates that start with the letter L,
you know?
Right.
Meanwhile, they've got Wi-Fi with internet.
And they've got a Plex library of their favorite shows.
And they have a total blank check to marathon them,
because what else can they do?
Kids these days don't even know they're born, Chris.
I know.
And so I need to accommodate all these different factors.
So it kind of seems like I need to go solid state.
Yeah, you probably do, right?
And solid state's getting there, you know?
Linus Tech Tips did a video not that long ago
about a new 3.84 terabyte.
I mean, it's four terabytes to all intents and purposes.
SSD released by, I think it was either Samsung or SanDisk,
probably Samsung.
But they're still $500 a pop.
Whereas these one terabyte ones that you're talking about,
the ruggedized ones, they're about $100 a pop or something.
I mean, it's not cheap, but it's enough now that I can move.
So my use case for the little SSD that I have
is my photo library lives on here for each year.
So every year, I'll rotate my photo library.
When I'm traveling, I just have everything
that I've shot this year with me physically,
and everything else is at home.
And generally speaking, that works pretty well.
So at the end of each year, I'll rotate my photos.
And drone footage is an exception,
because it's so much bigger, but just images
fit just fine on here.
Do you only keep the year's images on that disk,
or do you also store them somewhere else?
Oh, so yeah, I mean, I'd be a loser
if I only had one copy of my photos from this year, right?
This wasn't clear.
I was getting upset for a second.
Yeah, no, so generally, whilst I'm traveling,
my use case is quite straightforward.
And I actually did a post about this on my blog
very recently about my photography workflow.
And I talk a little bit in there about how my backup situation
works, and how by the time it's all said and done,
I've probably got about six or seven copies of this data,
all automatic once it hits my server back in Raleigh.
It just then all sort of spiders webs out across the internet.
We should put a link to that in the show notes
to that blog post, because that could also
help answer the ask SSH we're going
to get to in a little bit.
Yeah, OK, I mean, so the way I look at it is,
I have a couple of options here, is
I could just hang a terabyte disk off of each Pi,
so about $300 worth of disk.
That's not the end of the world when you're
talking about a network storage solution in terms of price,
but it's not very elegant.
Then I'm wondering if it's just ridiculous and crazy to buy
yet another Raspberry Pi.
Probably.
And then make that thing an iSCSI host for the biggest
disk or the most amount of disk I can attach to it.
Can't you just get a 512 gig SD card these days?
Yeah, so the way I tend to use the SD card and the Raspberry
Pis is just the root file system is on the SD card.
Because I'm just so paranoid they're
going to just die on me.
Yeah, I've had a few do that, especially
in power loss situations.
That can be a real issue.
So I kind of feel like, just like a lot of times in a server,
I'll have a small internal SSD.
Yeah, I'd do the same.
Yeah, the array is on a pool of disks.
So I had thought about taking a Raspberry Pi 4,
attaching like three or four disks to it,
and then sharing that out over Samba NFS
and making an iSCSI target as well.
And you know, we talk with the developer of MergerFS
in an upcoming Jupyter Extra that will probably
be released the week this episode comes out.
And MergerFS could potentially be a solution here.
There's a lot of ways I could go with this.
So I'm kind of hoping you can give me
some of your thoughts on just disks in general.
If MergerFS maybe would be a good use case for me,
especially since I'm dealing with more limited amounts
of RAM and hardware.
And I know that you and I have been talking offline a lot
about your storage setup.
So give me an advice here, Doctor.
What's your prescription?
Well, over the years, I mean, I've
talked about on my brunch with Brent,
I talked about how there was a 1.5 terabyte hard drive that
failed.
And that's kind of what led me down this rabbit
hole of self-hosting.
And I've bought a lot of hard drives over the years.
I was trying to calculate it.
But I think I probably bought somewhere
in the region of 30 to 40 three and a half inch drives.
Just this is my personal purchase history.
Yeah, I hate to think how much disk
I've bought over the years for the JB Productions.
Oh, so I've got a few rituals that I follow.
I've got a few thoughts.
I've read a lot of posts on Reddit, on different forums.
And this is just my personal experience
over the last five, six, seven years of doing this stuff.
I appreciate some people have different opinions,
but these are mine.
And I think a lot of it boils down to several key things.
And I cover a lot of this stuff in the perfect media service
series that's on the linuxserver.io blog.
There's a few things you need to take into consideration.
First of all, what are your requirements?
Are you running high performance databases?
Probably not if you're self-hosting.
But things like Plex take a surprising amount of I.O.
So if you're going to put your Plex metadata directory
onto a spinning Rust drive, you'll
notice a significant speed bump if you then
put that onto an SSD later on.
So there are just different use cases,
even within a home setup, that you might want to consider.
Also, I think it's worth mentioning
there are ways you could even set up spinning Rust
to get pretty good throughput.
You may miss out on data integrity or protection.
For example, forever, for editing,
I will use a bunch of as fast as I can get spinning Rust.
Usually 10,000 RPM is what I go for.
I know I can get slightly faster,
but I go for 10,000 usually.
So not as fast, I should say.
The exact opposite of what I just said.
And I'll put those suckers in a RAID 0.
Fantastic performance.
Then I make sure that the disk pool is labeled scary RAID.
I call it scary RAID.
Good.
Oh, I like it.
So for those that aren't familiar,
RAID 0 is striped across both disks.
So if either of those disks fail,
or any of the disks in the RAID 0 array fail, you're boned.
Yeah.
And so that scary RAID label always
reminds me, don't trust anything on that array,
because you could lose it any time.
Now, when you're working on a video project, in theory,
you have your source materials still either on the camera
or on the OBS machine or however you were doing it.
And so if my array were to go away during a project,
I would just have to redo that project.
But I think a lot of this stuff is a little old school
in terms of thinking nowadays.
SSDs, terabyte SSDs are in that $100 sweet spot.
And we're not talking that long ago.
We're talking two, three years where a terabyte
was $300 or $400.
And that's just not realistic.
I'm not going to spend that much on that price per gigabyte.
Which leads me nicely on to my other consideration.
You need to decide what the capacity requirements are.
So if you're working on video, like Chris,
you're going to be needing hundreds of gigabytes
for a single project, potentially.
It is funny, because when we switched to primarily doing
audio, all of a sudden, I had to do this huge shift on it.
We had so much additional storage,
because we had projected for the next couple of years
using video.
And then we made a transition to audio.
And then all of a sudden, I win a year
without having to buy disks.
It was beautiful.
And now, in the RV with my limited options,
I think about storage in a different way.
I think, what do I need immediately available,
versus what can I store in a colder storage that's
remote and slower to get to?
So I kind of even break it up to,
what do I need as hot files versus cold files?
And so the hot files, I'll put on the SSDs.
And the cold files, I'll store on spinning rest somewhere.
Like here in the studio, we have plenty of spinning rest
storage.
So the other thing to consider is
that there's an article by a chap called,
and I'm going to butcher this name, Laurentius.
And this is from January 2016.
And it's actually been something which
has influenced my strategy in how I've purchased hard drives
pretty much since then.
It's like a thought model, huh?
Yeah.
And this post is entitled, The Hidden Cost
of Using ZFS for Your Home NAS.
Now, I want to underscore the last two words,
for your home NAS.
I'm not talking about small business.
I'm not talking about your use case here, Chris.
I'm talking about people like me that
have a media server which has five, six, seven, eight, nine
disks in it that stores media that is written once
and read a few times.
Things like drone footage, ripped media, music,
that kind of stuff, right?
The performance is not critical.
So a lot of the benefits that you get with ZFS
kind of pale into insignificance.
But the thrust of his blog post here,
and I totally agree with this, is
that when I'm expanding my NAS over the last few years,
I tend not to buy more than one or two drives at the same time.
I tend to buy one drive every, if I know I'm expanding,
I'll buy a drive every month or two.
Generally speaking, over the last couple of years,
I've bought a drive every six to seven months or so.
Now, with ZFS, that's just not going to work,
because you need to preallocate your VDevs and your pools
and all that kind of stuff up front.
So you need to have drives that are the same size.
You need to ideally have drives that
are the same brand and firmware model
so that there's not some kind of random problem
occurs at the hardware level there.
And so for me, it really makes the ZFS kind of sell
a lot more difficult, because purchasing multiple drives
at once is not realistic.
Now, then I moved to America, and I had access to Best Buy.
And they have this wonderful thing
called the Western Digital Easy Store.
And this has really changed the game for me.
So I now have access to 10 terabyte hard drives,
10 terabyte drives.
Just one drive is 10 terabytes.
My entire array used to be 10 terabytes.
But anyway, for $160 or $170.
The caveat is it comes in like a USB enclosure.
So it's like an external hard drive.
But you can pop those bad boys out
of those cases in 10 minutes flat.
And then you have, to all intents and purposes,
a white label Western Digital 10 terabyte hard drive.
They're generally of decent quality disk, too,
because they don't want them popping and then having
a consumer RMA.
There is also like a slight electrical bit of work
that has to be done to the disk once you deshuck it.
Well, that's an interesting one.
So I think you're referring to the 3.3 volt mod
that you might have to do.
That's what it was, yeah.
And this is actually in the SATA spec, the SATA power spec.
I read a post on this a few months ago,
so I might get the details a little bit wrong.
But the gist is this.
Enterprise Gear uses the 3.3 volt rail
to reset failing hardware.
So if you're a hard drive in a data center,
you don't necessarily want to have to be power cycled
physically by a human coming in and pushing a button
and all that kind of stuff.
Data centers need a way to reset hardware
without physically being present.
And the way in which hard drives do that
is on the 3.3 volt rail.
So in a server situation, if that disk
receives a signal on the 3.3 volt rail,
it will reboot just that disk.
Now, most consumer power supplies over the last decade
have either omitted that rail
or just not followed the SATA spec
for trying to save money
because nobody really uses it for power.
They just use it for that use case.
But some power supplies do respect the SATA spec.
And if yours is one of those,
you need to do one of two things.
The first option is you can either just cut
the 3.3 volt wire, which is what I did.
I actually made some custom SATA power connectors,
which omitted that wire altogether.
You can buy, I think it's a one to five SATA power splitter
thing on Amazon.
And then you can use the DIY SATA power connectors
and just sort of pull the cable down inside it
and slice and cut the connectors for you.
It takes about half an hour to do five the first time
and then you get quicker after that.
Just be careful you get the wires in the right order
because if you put the 12 volt rail on the five volt thing,
you're gonna let the magic smoke out.
Not that you would know.
No, I actually don't, but yeah, thankfully.
I was very careful when I checked with a multimeter
that I got it all correct.
The other thing you can do,
and there are plenty of videos on YouTube on this,
is you can actually get a piece of Kapton tape
or something like electrical tape or something
and cover a couple of the power pins on the drive itself.
So that's a very, very non-destructive mod.
And that will just prevent the drive
from being able to receive that 3.3 volt signal
and it will just work as you would expect.
That's not so bad.
I do agree with your overall assessment
that if you're going to implement ZFS,
you need to go into it knowing
that when you wanna add capacity,
you'll be buying multiple disks at a time.
And this for me is the beauty of merger FS.
So we spoke to Antonio during the JB sprint.
Drew and Brent and I had a chance to sit down with him
and ask him some questions.
I've worked quite closely with him on a few things
like some of my blog posts, for example,
like I've submitted them to him for review
and made sure that it's all technically accurate
and that kind of thing.
But where merger FS comes in and the magic of it really
is you can have any number of mismatched drives,
any file system, it could be a USB drive,
it can be a SATA drive, it could be a CD-ROM drive,
it could be an R-Clone mount point,
and you can combine all of those different things
under a single mount point.
So I use slash mount slash storage as my pool mount point.
And under there, I have 12 different disks
combined and an R-Clone mount point
and the ZFS stuff that I have on my system
all in one place.
And does merger FS manage the parity as well?
Does it keep things, like if a disk fails?
No, merger FS is just a fuse layer user space file system
that combines all of those mount points underneath it.
If you want parity, which is the thing
that lets you rebuild from drive failures,
I use SnapRaid for that for my media
and then ZFS for the really important stuff.
We'll cut a SnapRaid later, I think,
but in short, it takes a snapshot of the state
of the drives at a moment in time
and calculates the parity data for those drives.
I think in terms of the other options that you've got
that do have similar functionality,
UnRAID will support multiple mismatched drive sizes as well.
The advantage of UnRAID is it has real-time parity
calculation instead of snapshot.
Downside is it's not open source.
So, you know, and you have to buy a license.
So it depends on what floats your boat there.
Open Media Vault will support merger FS
and SnapRaid out of the box,
but you'll have to go through the GUI
and configure it yourself.
I like that for you, that's a downside.
For some people listening, they're like,
oh God, it's got a GUI, thank goodness.
Yeah, well, I'm the sort of guy
that puts everything in Ansible.
Yeah, and if you just take the time
to learn the configuration syntax,
it will last with you forever.
And it is simpler and quicker and easier to back up.
Somebody was asking me in the JB Telegram the other day
about how to configure Samba.
And I just dropped them in my Samba config file.
I was like, there you go, done.
You know, it's 30 lines worth of text and it's done.
Right, it's worth recapping for a moment.
There's a lot to consider.
How fast you need the disk to be,
how much storage you need,
what other kind of usage requirements you have.
Then you have how much storage you plan to add to it,
how much it will change and what your budget is.
You have how critical the data is.
Is it okay to put it on one disk?
Maybe if you got a really good backup,
but you need to consider what your options are
if you need to go with a RAID.
One is non-CRS.
Right, one is none.
And then you have other things to consider as well,
like ZFS versus a different file system,
if you have enough RAM, I mean, there's a lot to it, Alex.
So how do you really get to any of these answers
without being really intimately familiar
with what your setup requirements are?
Like for me, I'm sitting here parsing this thinking,
well, what should I do for my storage solution?
Because I have all these weird use cases.
One use case is camera recording, which is fairly high IO.
The other is notes, like I have this huge spectrum
of like super low IO and super intense IO.
I want everything redundant
and I don't have a lot of backup options either.
So other than offsite,
which I won't always have connectivity.
And I also have that whole problem of a level four earthquake.
Yeah, I'm a massive MergerFS fan boy.
I tried dozens and dozens of other things
over the three or four years,
previous to settling on it in 2016.
And I've just, it's just been absolutely rock solid, right?
And I actually hate it when people use that phrase,
rock solid, but it's never missed a beat.
I haven't ever had to go in and tweak it.
There's not been any random hidden files created
like with MHDDFS, for example, is another one I tried.
It's just been flexible, right?
So anything I've needed to bend it to do,
I've been able to get MergerFS to do it with no data loss,
no having to copy files and have,
you know that slide puzzle you get
where you've got to move the little cubes around.
Yeah.
If you're migrating from one ZFS pool to another,
you actually have to play that game
with your data sometimes, right?
Where you're trying to re-architect a VDEV
that you built knowing what you knew at the time
when you built it,
but it turns out three years later,
oh, oops, that's not the most optimal thing to do.
It's not the most optimal way to do it.
True.
That is a bit of an issue I'm having now
with the storage here at the studio.
I feel like it's less of a problem
in a more static environment
where things don't change as much.
Like for example, ours is architected
for these huge, huge like storage requirements
around production video.
And we just don't have that anymore.
And now I'm looking at it going,
oh man, I think I need to redo this.
Flexibility, man.
That's where MergerFS really wins out.
Yeah.
I really don't want to have to deal with that.
I really don't.
But at the same time,
I feel like if it's super important and critical,
I'm still going to end up dealing
with these limitations of ZFS, if you will.
But the thing is, right,
so MergerFS, the reason it wins out so heavily for me
is it supports any file system underneath it.
So if you want to have ZFS on a pair of drives
and then pool it with a bunch of other EXT4 drives
or XFS drives, MergerFS will just handle that
absolutely fine.
And then using the policies that MergerFS has,
you can say only write this data to a drive
that already has that existing directory.
So the way that I do it
for all of my Docker app data, for example,
is I tell it through the file system table, the FFSTAB,
only create that directory on that drive.
So it's existing path, most free space.
But you're not allowed to create that directory
on a drive where it doesn't already exist.
The operation should just fail and you'll alert me to that.
So I'm not going to end up with files
scattered around multiple different disks.
Here's the other thing that really, really wins
on MergerFS for me.
I can pull that drive from one system
and I go and stick it into any other Linux box
and it will just be able to be read.
It's just a disk with files.
Yeah, right.
Unlike a ZFS array,
which I have to bring the whole pool over
and then import it
and it now belongs to that operating system.
And you have to hope that you've got the correct ZFS version
and blah, blah, blah.
You're kind of winning me over,
especially for my home setup use case.
It's just flexible
and it will support hot plug of USB devices.
You know, this, like whatever I come up with
may not work out
because it may be a bit of a roll of the dice.
I'm not even sure if I'm going to stick
with Raspberry Pis long-term.
I mean, I really hope it works for my use case.
It's very low commitment, right?
And for those of you with commitment issues,
you know, it's a really easy,
really easy thing to get started with.
Yeah, I think step one will be listening to your interview
with the MergerFS dev when that comes out on extras.
And then step two would be for me to get you
to send your config over.
So I can just read what that looks like.
It's one line in your FS tab.
I'll try and see if I can get it in the show notes.
No, your merger,
there must be a merger FS config file somewhere.
Nope, it's in my FS tab.
I'm literally SSHing in now.
I'm going to put it to you on telegram
and send it to you.
Oh my gosh.
One line.
All right, I got to check this out.
So do you think this would be ridiculous?
Raspberry Pi four with two, two terabyte SSDs
hanging off of it on the USB three bus.
And then on the USB two bus,
a parody disc, like a one terabyte.
Can I do that with SnapRaid?
Can you have a separate parody disc?
That's what you need to do, yeah.
So, okay, we're going to get into SnapRaid now.
Okay, you made me do it.
Well, let's do a brief lick
because we should do a whole episode once I try it too.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So SnapRaid, the parody disc has to be as big
or larger than your largest data disc.
Okay, okay.
That's a lot of discs everybody.
That's the requirement.
Okay, all right.
But SnapRaid will support up to six parody drives
if you are really paranoid.
I think people should let me know at Chris LAS,
am I crazy to set up a Raspberry Pi storage server
with disc running off the USB bus?
Is there a SATA hat for the Raspberry Pi four?
Because I'd love to get a Raspberry Pi SATA hat.
So I think to me at this point,
you're pushing what the Pi is really suitable for.
Damn it, I know, I know.
I'm wondering if you shouldn't just build
a hundred dollar used X86 system.
I built for my PF sense a little while ago,
an i5, I think third gen system for a hundred bucks.
I mean, maybe for the storage, I could see it.
I just, if I think if I did the storage over iSCSI,
all the Pis are ethernet gigabit wired in.
And on the Pi four, it's on its own bus now.
So, and it seems fully capable.
Here is the reason why I'm being resistant
to the idea of going somewhere else.
They're disposable at 25, $35.
They're inside a seat, they're inside my dinette seat
and it gets hot in the summer in there.
I mean, they might just burn up over time,
but all I have to do is pull out the SD card,
pop in the SD card into a new replacement Pi
and I'm out 35 bucks.
If I have to replace them once every year or two,
that's pretty reasonable.
Plus the way I've done it is I've Velcroed them
because they're so little.
I Velcroed them to the wall of the seat inside.
It's a wood, how would you explain this?
It's a dinette seat, but people don't know what a dinette is.
It's a booth, it's a booth.
It's a booth seat with a hollow inside
that you can take the cushion off
and take the board off the top of the booth
and it's all empty inside.
And praise be to Thor, this is where they decided
to install my subwoofer for the sound system,
which is on an inverter.
And to power this one small subwoofer,
they ran an entire AC outlet
into the inside of this booth seat.
So there is an AC plug on the inverter
that runs off of my house batteries.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Doesn't the Pi run on DC power?
Yes, that's for a future episode, Alex.
Okay.
Once I go solar, I've got to get everything on DC.
But right now I just have, I have a surplus,
well not a surplus,
but I have 200 amp hour lithium ion batteries.
So I can get about 12 to 18 hours
of using the RV off battery power.
I wonder how long you could run
just a Pi four off that battery for.
Years probably.
Very, very long time
because a 3800 milliamp battery
supposedly will run it for like 16 hours.
So there's a plug inside this booth seat
and I have every,
so I have installed all of my equipment
inside this booth seat.
I have my switch Velcroed to the wall of it,
my router, all three Raspberry Pis,
the discs that are attached to them,
their USB hubs, everything's Velcroed in
really nice and secure and snug,
but don't call it Velcro, it's loop and hook.
And so I'd hate to go away from that.
Yeah.
You know, you have a very unique set of requirements.
I don't think most people need to drive their data
down the road every week, but you know, if you do.
I think you'd be surprised.
Digital nomads are a bigger and bigger,
bigger work demo.
People who, because really what I'm doing
is I'm trying to build a system for anybody
who needs to work and travel at the same time.
Mine's gonna be at a larger scale,
but the concepts are applicable to anybody
who works and travels.
And so I am trying to solve these in a way
that is low power, works off of maybe solar
and is as best as possible noiseless.
I don't know, you might be right though.
I'd like to hear what the audience thinks
I should do for my storage setup.
Yeah, you can use the hashtag ask SSH.
Now, speaking of the hashtag,
Matty McGraw wrote in through JB Telegram,
for data security, I want to do mirroring
of my data does, directories.
Is ZFS the best choice?
I don't have tons of RAM.
You know, I recently did some testing
that shows that if you have even like 16 gigs of RAM,
you'd probably be all right
with certain storage mounts in reason.
It really kind of scales to how much storage
you have with CFS.
I think in the old days, the recommendation
that I certainly recall,
and maybe we should hit Alan up
for an up-to-date recommendation,
was one gig per terabyte.
I don't know if that still holds true now or what.
Ish, I think is the old recommendation.
But I think the other question
that is embedded within the question is,
if you want data integrity, do you have to go with CFS?
Let's say it's like pictures of the family
and you know, they're just irreplaceable.
Does that, is your only option using ZFS?
I don't know, I think after our conversation today,
it might not be.
Let's take the MergerFS SnapRaid situation, right?
SnapRaid does checksumming.
So every time it calculates parity,
it is checking the integrity of those files
at the file level, not the block level,
which is where ZFS wins out.
But what's interesting is that
you can do your SnapRaid scrub,
which has much the same kind of connotations
as a ZFS scrub, which again, just checks the checksums
and makes sure that the file integrity is there.
You do get things like compression with CFS,
you get encryption, and obviously you get bit rob protection,
which is one of their favorite things.
But really that just means it's checking the data.
And you get other things that are more advanced
that can be really great for backup,
like ZFS send and receive.
And data sets, I'm falling in love with data sets.
Yeah.
However, if this is not, if everything,
if the words we just used do not excite you,
it may not be the file system for you.
That could just be the measure you use.
And I am such a big believer in using systems
that you are comfortable administering
and keeping up to date and secure
if you choose to self host.
This is why I took FreeNAS off of our storage server
here at the studio.
FreeNAS is a great product.
I am not the right type of user for FreeNAS.
When I have a problem with my system,
my troubleshooting technique is to get a command line
and look at the logs, look at the output of the system
and start troubleshooting and start fixing.
That breaks FreeNAS.
You need to use FreeNAS through the GUI.
It's not my use case.
I also, I'm not as familiar with FreeBSD as I am with Linux.
And if it's my super valuable data,
I want it to be on a system that I know how,
like Alex said, I know how to rip the hard drive out,
put it in another system and get to that data.
I gotta know how to do that.
And what ended up happening is once we flipped that thing
over to Linux, I used it a hundred times more.
We've now got so many applications on there.
We've got backups, we've taken care of things
like getting properly signed SSL certificates.
Like it just went, it went much further than I was expecting.
And once I switched to a system I was comfortable with.
So Maddy, that's my number one advice.
I know you've got some experience with Linux.
So I would recommend maybe not doing FreeNAS.
I would also recommend maybe looking
at something like SnapRaid.
You don't need mergerFS to use SnapRaid
if you just want the snapshotting
and backup capabilities of SnapRaid.
And then look into getting that data offsite.
So this is an important thing to focus on,
which you're looking at right now.
But like we mentioned earlier in the show, one is none.
And two is not enough really.
No, no, it really isn't.
But the other thing to consider, right?
Let's say that he went really simple
and used something like rsync just to copy data
from one place to another, one server to another,
one directory to another.
It doesn't really matter, rsync doesn't care.
What you've got to think about is let's say
that you have some kind of, what's that?
Is it crypto malware or something?
Oh yeah, sure enough you mean, yeah.
Crypto ransomware, ransomware, thank you.
Thank you, Brain.
So let's say you have some ransomware situation, right?
Where the files on your source of truth,
your main system get encrypted
and you don't know how to unencrypt them
or you delete something or you just generally screw up, right?
If you have a script
which is automatically overwriting data
at the other end every time, like rsync would,
you're also going to sync the encrypted copy
potentially over the top of your quote unquote backup.
Or a damaged file or deleted files potentially,
depending on how you have it set up.
There's a lot of ways that it could break.
So this is one of the things where ZFS send
would come into play
because you'd have data sets to play with.
And you could just roll back to the old data set
before the ransomware happened.
But is that a common problem?
I mean, the deletion thing is probably quite common
for people, but there are tools like our snapshot
that will do similar sorts of things on a non ZFS system.
There's a lot of options to be honest.
Alex and I both like to use duplicati
as a way to back up some of our server stuff.
Yes, how did I forget duplicati?
Yeah, I use that every day and it just works.
But it suffers from the same situation, right?
If my source of truth here gets encrypted
or I delete something,
it's going to also delete it on the other end.
The nice thing about applications like duplicati,
another one that's super great for local backups
is backup PC, been using it,
I think since like 2008, 2005, I love it.
Backup PC and duplicati will support revisions,
which is really nice.
So you can revert back.
You can also have it configured not to do that.
So that's why it's important to go through it.
When you decide to self host,
this is going to be like my soapbox
for like the first 10 episodes.
When you decide to self host,
you're taking on a little additional responsibility.
You got to check these things.
Do I have revisions and stuff like that?
But here's the thing, when it breaks, it's on you,
not some massive data breach like Equifax
or something like that, right?
Like it's your fault.
And I actually kind of appreciate the honesty of that.
There's also the reality that you're not nearly the target
that Equifax is or Amazon, right?
You're almost in some ways enjoying the obscurity,
I would say.
And I kind of like it to be on me,
because it is my stuff.
It's just a digital version of my stuff,
just like the security of my home is on me.
So I prefer it that way.
I'd rather not outsource the security of my house
or my RV or the studio.
So yeah, I think it's a little more stress,
but it's also very gratifying.
Like when my setup,
when this stuff I'm doing in the RV works,
like with Home Assistant, it genuinely gives me joy.
Like it just gives me so much joy.
And I feel like I know I've done a good job,
like with the wire running for the cameras,
I'm proud of that.
Where I mounted things,
how I've done the pies are mounted
and run the wires for that, I'm proud of that.
Like I've put craftsmanship into it.
It's given me an opportunity at the end of the day
to come home and work on something for an hour or two
that gives me genuine satisfaction.
And it also improves our digital wellbeing.
So there you are, Matty.
I'm sure we've just completely made that
even more complicated for you
by giving you 15 more different options.
You see, why wouldn't everyone want to hashtag ask SSH
and get their question on the show?
Exactly.
So you can get more of the show at selfhosted.show.
I'm on Twitter at ironicbadger.
I'm at Chris LAS.
The network is at Jupiter signal.
And don't forget extras, extras.show
with our merger FS interview coming up,
probably already out by the time you're hearing this episode.
And also a plug for another brunch
that was excellent recently
was the Alan Jude Brunch with Brent.
So, you know, he talks more about ZFS of course,
cause it's Alan.
Yes, and his free BSD stuff.
And yeah, that'd probably be a fun episode
for people that are into self hosting.
Great, great point.
Yeah, check out Brunch with Brent and Alan.
That was a good one.
And then one final JB plug is techsnap.systems.
Yes, talk about getting simple explanations
of how these complicated ZFS things work.
Jim Salter is a master at explaining ZFS.
He's really good.
And particularly techsnap414 is all about ZFS.
And I really enjoyed the snapshot discussion.
And 415 is gonna be about benchmarking,
which should be really interesting.
Absolutely.
So thanks everybody for listening.
That was selfhosted.show slash five.