Is there some sort of universal law that states that your infrastructure is going to fail
whenever you're not around?
Because I seem to always be subject to it.
There I was, down at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, actually the night before, dreaming
about what we might discover, thinking about what we might learn.
I decide to check in on my Intrepid RV, about seven hours north of where I was.
I pull up the Home Assistant app, and it just isn't quite loading, and I think, hmm, that's
strange.
So I fire up Tailscale, and I pull up the web interface, because the web interface always
works when the app doesn't work.
And it still doesn't load, and I think, huh, I wonder if something's wrong with Home Assistant.
And a few days go by, and I finally make it back to the RV, and I discover that my Raspberry
Pi home server, that runs more than just Home Assistant, I mean it runs my Plex instance,
my SyncThing instance, my Duplicati instance, my Smokeping instance, my Markdown notes instance,
and Home Assistant, dead.
Just dead.
Dead as a doornail.
Just totally dead.
Uh-oh.
And you know the worst part?
I don't even know why it's dead.
What do you mean you don't know why it's dead?
I don't even know what happened.
I mean, we've been on the road, and I've been trying to figure it out, but I just haven't
had a chance.
I haven't even hooked up an HDMI screen to it.
Oh, I see.
I did the hardware swap thing, you know?
Yeah, so what was your plan with that hardware swap?
Because it seemed like a brilliant plan at the time.
Well, thank you.
I mean, I bought a duplicate Raspberry Pi, same thing, Raspberry Pi 4, 8 gigs, in the
same case, forever ago.
Just ready to go.
I swapped everything over, hit the power button, and nothing.
And I looked at my dead Raspberry Pi, and I realized, oh, there's an SD card in here.
I think it might...
This is like the first one I ever set up.
I think maybe it was using that SD card for, like, slash boot.
I can't remember anymore.
But when I first did this, it was kind of a workaround to get Ubuntu running on the
Raspberry Pi 4.
It was before official support had landed.
And I think maybe the SD card was used for grub or something like that.
But I don't know why it would have died while it was running.
So I'm wondering if something more significant happened, but I just don't know at this point.
Maybe there was an unintended upgrade.
Maybe a live patch.
You know, I did the whole reboot thing, and of course, I'm trying to SSH into it.
I can't ping it.
I can't ping it on the tail scale IP either.
It seems gone.
And the worst part of that is it runs a lot of automations in the RV, like all of the
lighting, the heating, of course, the cooling, a lot of the outdoor stuff.
It's all managed by Home Assistant on this stupid Raspberry Pi.
And so it's like we're running things like animals with switches.
Yeah, this place went from a five star to about a three and a half, I think.
Wow.
You let this guy into your home, Alex, you know?
Indeed.
Well, this seems like an appropriate moment to introduce Brent again.
Hello, Brent.
How are you?
Welcome back.
Thank you very much.
And what about you, gentlemen?
Well, actually, we had some feedback at the meetup in Pasadena that we don't introduce
ourselves anymore.
So let's just take a moment for anybody that hasn't worked out that I'm Alex and the other
guy is Chris.
Hey, Chris.
Hello, everybody.
Thank you for being here.
Okay, good.
Now that's out of the way.
Welcome to episode 81.
Yeah.
Now that's out of the way.
I want to ask you if this has got you thinking about deploying some real hardware in the
production system?
Ooh.
Throwing shade.
Fair enough.
You know, Listener Jeff was really the MVP of our West Coast road trip and he sent me
home with an atom based unit that only draws five watts and it's got two cores, but four
gigs of RAM.
I'm tempted to just build a dedicated home assistant system out of that.
Why not?
Well, I just got shipment notification about my home assistant Yellow.
I should be receiving it this week.
I did.
No, you didn't.
I've got UPS, I've got a UPS tracking number and everything.
Where's it coming from Guam?
I think they landed in Texas and then some some distribution place in Texas is sending
them out from there.
Right.
Okay.
It's so exciting because this marks the second crowd supply thing that I've ever backed that
I'm actually going to receive.
Very excited.
And so the home assistant Yellow is supposed to arrive this Friday.
The only thing was I kind of wanted to go something more powerful.
Yeah.
Well, I'll tell you what's got me thinking is you often run into these issues when you're
on the road remotely and that kind of thing.
Yeah.
Almost exclusively.
Oh, it's so annoying.
I think you need to embrace IPMI of some description.
I think that needs to be a requirement for you.
Oh, interesting.
Oh, you know, I thought about that for the studio and I agree, but I had not thought
about it for the RV.
Well, of course, there's the Pi KVM project for x86 boards that don't come with a BMC
chip built in.
But, you know, you could probably build a server that does everything.
How many pies do you have deployed in in dupes right now?
Well, come on.
I pared it down.
I pared it down to only two.
I'm not I'm not saying this to be a to be a, you know, a phallic object.
I'm just saying this out of love, like genuine question.
It was four.
It was four in production, and over time I pared it down to two.
OK, so if we allow a 10 watt budget per pie, give or take right now, it was 40 watts.
It's now 20 watts.
You could build a very capable x86 system that does everything all of those pies do
and has a BMC built into it, you know, given the power is it's not you're not quite as
limited on power as the Mars Rover is, but you're not far off.
It's true.
Every watt does count, especially watts that run continuously.
What about heat consideration?
That is a thing.
That's a big thing.
I've been really trying to do the math on that, too.
When I build the next one, I'm trying to think, do I want to build it in a booth or do I want
to go somewhere else and just drill holes?
The Raspberry Pi and maybe that's what finally killed it was heat.
I don't know.
But the Raspberry Pi has done a remarkable job of holding up to intense temperatures
over long periods of time.
My bet really is what happened is there was some kind of a power brownout that was enough
to make the Pi reboot and the SD card was toast in that time since it last rebooted.
I don't obviously have any data to back that up, but that's what I suspect probably happened.
So in total, I spent $169 on the Home Assistant Yellow and I was watching their live stream
today as we record and I don't think they're going to make many more of these because they
can't get their hands on the compute module.
So they finally got this thing shipping.
In fact, they don't even have the POE one sorted out yet.
They have the non POE one shipping and they may not make many more just because you can't
get them.
That's a real shame.
I mean, but on the flip side, it's not a good look for the project, is it?
Charge people money for something and then not ship it for a year or two.
I know it's not their fault, but yeah, I ordered it mid September and now we're here in early
October.
It was just over a year ago that I ordered it.
That's a long time.
It's a very long time.
I mean, if you look at what Valve did with the Steam Deck, I know that Valve orders of
magnitude got more buying power than Home Assistant, Nebuchadnezzar as a company, but
I paid Valve five bucks to sit in a queue, essentially.
And then when the time came to actually ship my hardware, that's when my credit card got
charged.
Maybe something like that could work for Home Assistant.
Yeah, I think, too, the tricky thing here is they based it on the Pi compute module
and that became one of the hardest things to get your hands on in bulk right now.
The Raspberry Pi stuff is like still impossible to find.
I was just doing a check recently and the most common thing you can find at the moment
is the Pi 3.
Which from what I'm learning, isn't that useful for anything.
Did you see that Jeff Gehling did a video just last few days where he talked with the
founder of the Raspberry Pi project about availability and things like that and how
there's no end in sight.
They're making 400,000 of these things a month and something like 95% is going into industrial
use cases.
Wow.
95%?
Is it even really meant for industrial use cases?
I noticed, because Jeff also does an accompanying blog post, and I noticed that one of the comments
on Jeff's blog post was sort of giving a different version of this story.
They claim, I don't know how they would know, but they claim having inside knowledge and
that Broadcom is actually a bit pissed at the Raspberry Pi folks because they're going
commercial and essentially like the whole deal for getting a super cheap chip from Broadcom
was that you were creating this educational device for kids and now you've announced your
intentions to IPO and make a commercial company out of all this and now you need to pay the
commercial rates and you're going to be lumped in with our commercial clients and not our
educational clients.
And so they're also getting slower supply from Broadcom, according to this commenter.
But I have to say, it kind of seems like it checks out.
I think the Raspberry Pi Foundation, much like all of us, are kind of being caught off
guard by just how ubiquitous it's become.
And I think it's a perfect example of how if you influence the right people, the nerds,
the engineers, the people tinkering, if you influence them, they will then go into work
and say, hey, well, why don't we just use a Pi?
If I, you know, I remember my last job we had on the wall, we had TV screens showing
build statuses of all the different CI processes and each one of them had a Raspberry Pi running
because one of the development team in that sprint team was like, well, we need to monitor
the status.
Why don't we just get a Pi because it's only 35 pounds, stick it behind the TV and jobs
are good.
And I think not only has the Pi Foundation been caught out by the success of their product,
but so it sounds like has Broadcom.
Perhaps that would make a lot of sense.
It's tricky because I actually think if they don't figure something out, the M1 platform
is going to make a pretty worthy successor for home labors.
If imagine for a moment, if you would, Alex, there was decent Linux support for the M1,
which we may be only nine months, 10 months away from.
And that includes Thunderbolt support because right now I'm hanging USB disks off a Raspberry
Pi.
But if I had Thunderbolt support, I could have real actual PCI attached storage.
And if I had an M1 CPU, I would have something that has built in HD 64 decoding and encoding
like a Banshee.
And if somehow Plex could come along and get support for that, then we'd really be cooking
with gas.
Don't you just wish that Mac OS server wasn't terrible?
Is Mac OS server even a thing anymore?
I think they might.
No.
I don't even know.
I know.
It's really sad.
And honestly, I feel like Docker desktop isn't good enough on the Mac for production use
the way I would want.
I want something headless.
I want it to be Linux.
I mean, Asahi this the last couple of weeks released preliminary support for GPU acceleration
under Linux with the M1 chip, which is a huge, huge milestone.
Yeah.
Using a Rust driver.
A Rust driver.
I mean, that's amazing.
So maybe, I mean, maybe it's not too far off, but it's not going to be within the time that
I need to build my next home server.
I think I'm going to have to just out of practicality base it around this yellow, it would seem
crazy not to, you know, showing up on my doorstep as I'm returning back in town and I need a
new server.
If you need an appliance, it sounds like that might be it.
But let me ask you this.
If money was no object, what would you do in tubes?
The trickiest thing is storage.
If money was no object, I'd spend a lot on storage and it'd be solid state storage because
I have to go down the road.
So that's where I'd probably blow a lot of money.
You're not going to believe this, but I mean, for 90% of the time I have found the Raspberry
Pi 4 has been fast enough.
The pages could have always loaded faster in Home Assistant and I'm on a couple of versions
behind now.
Home Assistant could have always been faster.
But Plex and Sync thing and like my Markdown docs, I forget the name of the Markdown docs
website thing.
Those all always ran totally fine.
I was surprised.
I was shocked that I got by with a Raspberry Pi.
It was just Home Assistant that could be a little bit faster.
But you know, a lot of that might've come down to storage technology.
That's why I think the M1 would be perfect, you know, 10, 20 Watts, a lot of horsepower,
fast storage.
Just don't want macOS.
Well, if, if power was no object, I know we, we made money, no object just then, but I
think power is probably your biggest limiting factor as well as maybe space.
You can't have a big 42U rack in there, can you?
Like if power was no object, would you do the same thing?
If power was no object, I think I'd be tempted to build a rack unit into one of the storage
bays, you know, and go with like a big x86 box and probably do a lot of hosting in dupes
just because that's, I like the idea of it's, it's truly decentralized.
I can move it, I can take it with me and I'd rather have the source of truth here as long
as I had a good backup.
Right now I hold the source of truth and everything at the studio.
So I'd probably build a rack unit if I could go crazy, but I don't need it.
You know, I didn't lose any data.
My server is down, but I didn't lose any data.
So the setup is working as I need it to.
Well, the obvious thing that comes to mind for me is the Intel NUC, that kind of tiny
mini micro thing.
I don't know if you've been following serve the home at all over the last few months.
They've been doing a series called tiny mini micro where they get these four, five, six,
10 liter micro, essentially thin client machines designed for business applications.
And they've got powerful chips in them and 32 gigs of Ram and you know, all the rest
of it.
And they are the size of two or three CD cases stacked on top of each other.
What about something like that?
That is pretty tempting, especially if it's got, you know, reasonable horsepower and it
can do decent video decoding.
That would be and networking and connectivity because I always need to add more storage.
I think what you'd be looking for there as your silver bullet for video decoding would
be quick sync support, which does limit you to Intel.
But you know, speaking from experience, quick sync uses anywhere from four to six, maybe
eight watts to transcode a 4k stream.
And it's hard limited at eight watts.
Like I've never been able to get it to go above eight, eight to 10 watts is about the
maximum I've ever seen.
So even if you're doing multiple trans codes at once, which in an RV I find very unlikely,
quick sync is the way to go.
That is the nice thing is I only really need to build for like two televisions.
Three is the max.
Well I guess there's always tablets, but very unlikely that we'd have three TVs and a tablet
going in the RV.
But you could negate the transcoding requirement entirely just simply by using something like
Tedar or Handbrake to pre encode the media.
And you can automate all that stuff, you know, into the correct formats for the TV.
You know, actually I think for the most part, I mean, for the most part, most of my stuff
doesn't need transcoding because it's either an Apple TV or an NVIDIA Shield and it's H264
and AC MP3 or AC3 audio for the most part, not 100%, but I'd say, I'd say 85, 90%.
How many terabytes do you need here in JOOPS?
I'd love four.
I'm getting by with two, right?
I would love to do more even.
I mean, ideally I'd love 14, let's be honest.
But I get what I do is I, I batch over just the stuff we're watching, like a couple of
series for the kids, a couple of movies that are for Hadiya and I, a couple of movies that
are for the kids and a couple of movies that are for family and just a few TV shows.
And I just kind of keep like what the current season is that we're watching of a show on
there.
And I don't need to keep everything because I have a larger storage at the studio.
I have no idea how reliable it is, but I just looked on Amazon just to sort of see how much
a two terabyte SSD costs these days.
The brands you've heard of, Samsung, Crucial, et cetera, they're all in the 160 to 200 range
per two terabytes, but there's a brand here I've never heard of called Levin and these
guys make a two terabyte 3D NAND SATA 3 internal SSD for $99.
I mean, you throw a few of those in a raid, what could go wrong?
You throw a few of those in merger FS and what I'm thinking is before a trip, right,
you take one or two of these into the studio, sync across what you need to through a USB
interface that's much faster than a network interface and then you throw it back into
your hot swap bay in dupes and you're good to go.
Yeah.
And then you just keep it topped off with a little sync thing action, you know?
Yes.
Yeah, that could totally work.
What I'm kind of picturing is like a board, right?
Like a removable, almost like a piece of plywood that has the yellow mounted to it and the
disks mounted to it and the Zigbee and Z-Wave antennas mounted to it and I can just insert
this board into dupes and I can pull this board out of dupes.
And if I need to work on it, I just remove the whole componentry, all of it, put together
as one piece, I take it to the studio and I work on it and then I bring it back into
dupes and I just reinstall it and reconnect things.
I love that modular approach.
I'd love to add into that mix your new mixer plans too, that would be kind of fun, huh?
Oh, imagine the ultimate setup, right?
Like server capacity, media capacity and production capacity and just slide them all in.
You have, you know, like eight XLR inputs on the front of this thing for all your mics
and what have you.
And then on the back, you've got a couple of network jacks and a power cord going in
and that's it.
That would be pretty cool.
That sounds really sweet, actually.
That'd be pretty, pretty, pretty great, pretty, pretty great.
Let's work on that then.
But speaking of upgrades and stuff like that, I assume you saw that Paulus from the Home
Assistant Project has been very, very excited that Matter finally hit 1.0 this week.
Damn it.
Can you believe this?
You know what that means is that they're beginning to pull it into Home Assistant.
They're beginning to build in Matter support into Home Assistant and an actual device shipped
in the last week, a light bulb with Matter.
It's actually happening, but you know, it's really still like probably six months to a
year out before just general devices are available.
And of course, of course, I'm doing this rebuild right now.
Of course, my server died.
I couldn't hold out.
You know, I was holding out for Matter.
You know, that was what I did.
That was my entire intention all along was to hold out and just replace my devices with
Matter devices.
And just as it becomes official, just as the first device ships, my system dies and I'm
going to have to either go all in on Z-Wave or ZigBee.
ZigBee is very well tested, though.
I wouldn't imagine Matter is going to be stable, properly stable for another, I don't want
to say five years.
That might be a bit pessimistic, but you know, at least two or three before we've got, you
know, the ubiquitous level of devices we have now in ZigBee land.
I pulled the trigger and I pre-ordered the Home Assistant.
I think they call it...
iLink?
What do they call it, Alex?
SkyConnect, I think.
Yeah, SkyConnect.
It is a ZigBee radio.
It has ZigBee and Thread, and they promise they'll do a firmware upgrade and add Matter
to it.
So Home Assistant SkyConnect is their own hardware ZigBee radio, which seems like, okay,
so Home Assistant's clearly going all in on ZigBee.
This is a clear signal from the project.
ZigBee is the future of Home Assistant and Matter, but then they made the announcement
that they just full-time hired the Z-Wave integration guy.
And now the Z-Wave integration guy is a Nebuchadnezzar employee.
Mixed messages, it sounds like.
I'm so confused as to what direction to go right now.
I think what they're saying is, whatever you want to use, we're going to support and we're
going to try to support it really well, but they haven't like just clearly articulated
that to me.
So I'm trying to figure out like, well, if I'm going to buy one device, should I buy
ZigBee or should I be buying Z-Wave or what?
It's like, I'm probably going to have to replace some of these devices because some of these
things are probably not going to unpair very easily with my dead system.
Or are they saying that when you buy this in a year from now, when it actually lands
on your door, then they'll be supporting it full-time?
Yeah, it is a pre-order and it is quote, available soon.
So just as I'm finally receiving my yellow, we'll see how long it takes me to get my SkyConnect.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account.
It's just a great way to support the show while you're checking out something awesome.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting with the best support in the business.
Real humans every day.
It's how we run everything we've built in the last few years in the cloud, like our
brand new website.
Got to go check it out, jupyterbroadcasting.com.
We use it in our personal environments.
We use it in our testing environments and we use it in our production environments because
Linode's tooling makes it really straightforward to do all of that.
And Linode was built nearly 19 years ago and they just added better and better things.
They've improved.
They've refined the service over the years.
So now, like, we're riding on top of years and years and years of investment.
We get all of that as just part of the product.
And Linode is still 30 to 50% cheaper than the hyperscalers that want to lock you into
their crazy platforms that are just secondary to their main business.
And on top of that, I think Linode has the best performance out there.
And independent testing is also showing that.
And right now, today, Linode has 11 data centers for you to choose from.
And that's a whole bunch all over the world.
And coming soon, there's going to be more than a dozen new Linode data centers firing
up across the world.
That's just going to be insane.
You're going to have so much choice.
And you know, Linode really is just the perfect balance of support, performance, and price.
So with that $100, you get a chance to see it for yourself.
That really is an opportunity to kick the tires and try it.
So go build something, go learn something, go experiment with something, and support
the show.
Try it for yourself.
Get your $100 at linode.com slash SSH.
One more time.
That's linode.com slash SSH.
We're trying to review an app that I've actually put in the show notes more times than I can
actually remember.
We just never quite seem to get to it.
This time, finally, Invoice Ninja has made the cut into the show.
So I thought it would be good because I know, Brent, you do quite a lot of freelancing stuff
with your photography and other things, you know, podcast related stuff.
So you're always sending invoices to people.
So I thought whilst we had you on the show, it would be a good time to discuss Invoice
Ninja.
Now, this is a piece of software that allows you to create customizable and nicely designed
invoices and quotes.
So essentially, whenever I do a piece of freelance work for somebody, I create a customer in
the Invoice Ninja software.
And then I create a product, you know, like a podcast episode, for example, or something
like that.
And then I put in there, you know, what the product is, it could be a physical thing,
it could be a service, whatever.
And it has a rate attached to it, a standard rate, which I can go in and customize if I
want to.
But typically, it doesn't change that much between clients.
After that, it automatically generates the invoice based on my information and the client's
information.
And if you get fancy and set up email with it, which I've never done, I always just download
the PDF once it's generated the invoice and stick it in my email manually, but it can
actually send emails directly from the Invoice Ninja software to the client, which is a really
nice feature.
Alex, you're right to include me because I have a lot of questions.
Okay, far away.
Okay, you've been using this for how long now?
I think it's been like two years if I remember.
Two years plus however long it is since I set you up with your instance that is probably
dead by now.
You did send me a backup.
So thank you for that.
Okay.
Okay, good.
Yeah, Alex, you you shared with me invoice into I think when you first found it, or maybe
you were a few months in and you were crazy excited about it, and I did get the chance
to try it.
Yeah, it's it's years old in my workflow.
Now at this point, everything you described your introduction just there is not something
that I think is unique.
I'm curious from your perspective.
What are the things that you're really loving about this?
Is it that?
Is it the fact that you can self host it really easily?
Is it the fact that it's really responsive?
Is it the interface?
What is it about it that really grabs you?
Yeah, I didn't touch much on the actual mechanics of hosting this thing.
The invoice ninja project actually has hosted options which you can pay monthly for.
However, I don't do that I have a fully self hosted version that lives on my server.
This thing requires three containers.
So there's the app container, there's a database container, which in my case, I'm using my
sequel.
And then there's a front end, which in my case, I'm using nginx, which I then proxy
through traffic.
So I tell you what I like about it just as a piece of software.
It looks nice.
Yeah, I'll agree with that.
I like the fact that when I create an invoice, it gives me a little chart that says you're
owed $500 this month.
And then until you mark that invoice as received or paid, it will show you a pending number
versus a last 30 day number versus a, you know, 90 day number or whatever you want.
So I could see this being very useful for people who are actually sending hundreds of
invoices every day, less useful for me who sends maybe one a month or two a month.
But it's still nice to have a record of everything I've ever sent in one place.
The other thing that I like about it too, is that I can tweak stuff.
And I feel like I'm using a really, I'm driving a really powerful sports car.
And I'm okay, I'm only puting down the road at 30 miles an hour.
But it's nice to know that it's got all of that other stuff there should I ever need
it.
Yeah.
And I think too, it's it's pretty quick that the pricing on a lot of the hosted invoicing
can get really expensive.
You know, I have been a customer of FreshBooks for a long time.
But I think I'm paying some somewhere near 50 bucks a month or something like that 60
bucks a month for the package, well, JB does not me, but it's actually kind of a good deal
for a lot of these things.
People pay astronomical prices for QuickBooks and the invoicing components.
So there's that aspect of invoice, besides the UI, and besides the self hosting and tinkering,
there's the cost savings too.
In addition, it does a whole bunch of other stuff.
So I can set up things like recurring invoices, if I want to in a separate area from individual
invoices.
I can record manually all the payments that come in and attach those to specific invoices
if I want to.
I can also do things like quotes and proposals and set up specific projects and attach different
things within invoice ninja to different projects and what have you which, you know, if I was,
I don't know, let's say running a home improvement company, that could be quite useful to have
different quotes for the same person within a single project, for example, something like
that.
I can also do things like track different vendors.
So I can say, well, this vendor, I've sent them this money for this product.
And like I say, it's, it's an incredibly powerful piece of software that I'm really only scratching
the surface of by pretty much only using the invoice portion of it.
But it has the ability to run some pretty sophisticated reporting as well.
So again, if I was a bit more of a serious small business owner or something like that,
which I'm not, I could, you know, let's say give me the last, you know, every invoice
this year to a specific client or something like that.
And it'll just show me all those things in one place.
Now, Alex, have you used anything else for invoicing or is this kind of your first foray
into this style of software to help you accomplish things?
I used to just have a Google sheet that I've, you know, manually changed and filled out
things for a long time.
Which is also very powerful.
It can be, but it's also, you know, you don't really have a record unless you do a new sheet
per invoice or something of what you've done.
But this is the first kind of invoicing suite, I guess, that I've used.
Because many of the features you described are, yeah, they're great.
They're not unique.
But what I have found when I used Invoice Ninja was that they're very well implemented.
And like you mentioned, they allowed you to really tweak a lot of things.
I have been using for many years a piece of software called Invoice Plane, and it is far
more basic.
It is self-hosted, and I have some automated emails and stuff sending out of there.
But I do find after having used Invoice Ninja, thanks to you, that I feel it's lacking now.
And every time I use it, I'm like, oh, God, I really gotta switch over.
I gotta change this.
So I think you made probably a really nice choice in choosing your first piece of software
because often, the hardest part is taking all that information out of these pieces of
software and switching to something new.
That's one thing I really struggle with.
And so have you investigated at all what the importing and exporting parts of this database
might look like and what that's like to port to something new, if you so choose?
Well, I just, whilst we were talking just then, exported a CSV report of every invoice
that I've sent this year.
So let's just take a quick look at that.
All numbers, of course, is gonna be a real fun time.
So the CSV is exactly what you'd expect.
It's just a bunch of this client, this date, this invoice number, this amount, status,
all that kind of stuff.
And so if you can get it out to a format that you own, like a CSV file, there's no QuickBooks
or FreshBooks kind of proprietary license required.
That's a huge thing for me, given I just do this as a spare time thing.
But yeah, I think CSV seems to be pretty good.
I haven't actually done anything with importing though.
Well, I have another question for you.
I overheard when I was at your place last that your wife, Catherine, has been using
it as well.
Did you get any feedback from her using it in her business?
Yeah, I think it's massive overkill for just invoicing a few music students, parents, but
she likes it.
I mean, she has her own login.
You know, has a shortcut on her browser's bookmarks.
She just logs in and just does the thing and like I do once a month, I guess, and just
sends the invoice out and it's all good.
I've just found the import data pane, by the way, and it supports a huge number of different
formats.
You've got CSV, JSON, FreshBooks, blah, blah, blah.
Invoice plane is one of them, I would just say.
There's about 10 or 12 different options for importing and exporting is CSV, XLS or JSON.
Sounds like you've got me hooked.
Yeah, there's no downside.
I can see.
Next.
Yeah.
And even if you try it and you don't like it, it sounds like it's pretty easy to get
out.
So it's no real downside to trying it.
I know a lot of people listening to this show probably love their Yubikey.
I've heard from some of them.
And it sounds like Cloudflare is going to work with Yubikeys.
I didn't know they didn't tell us all about this one, Alex.
Well, the first thing about Yubikeys, we should explain what they are for those that don't
know.
They're a hardware two-factor authentication token.
So essentially what that means is whenever you log into a specific login portal, website,
piece of software, whatever that needs 2FA, that six digit code or whatever, it could
be an alphanumeric string in the case of a Yubikey.
You have to physically plug in a USB device into your computer or your phone via NFC.
The two-factor piece is stored in the hardware of the Yubikey.
That has a few benefits, obviously, unless someone has physical access to my hardware
two-factor token, they can't log in.
The downside is that includes me.
And what I found when I got a free Yubikey back at DockerCon in 2015, I think, because
they were doing some push to get people to sign Docker images back then.
So I tried it for a while because you can load SSH keys onto this thing as well.
Secrets can include a private key, all that kind of stuff.
Even your Bitwarden two-factor authentication token can be stored and set up to work with
a Yubikey.
The trouble is my Yubikey is always at the wrong end of the house.
It's always at the opposite end of the house from where I am.
And so whenever I want to log into something, I'm like, damn it, I have to run from one
end of the house to the other or just have multiple Yubikeys.
I feel like there's some universal law about two-factor and the device you're using is
always at the other end of the house.
Yeah, that's true.
I remember our friend Noah wears it around his neck for that very reason.
I mean, so it's not to say that they're not good because they're incredibly useful in
the workplace.
For example, you want to give someone access to some privileged secrets.
You give them this hardware token and at work, typically that's the most common use case
for it, I would say.
And so what Cloudflare are doing is they're running a promotion with Yubikey to provide
these security keys at air quotes, good for the internet end quotes pricing and they start
as low as $10 per Yubikey.
Now typically these things are 30, 40 plus each.
So actually that could be a huge boon if you've been looking to get involved with the YubiCo
Yubikey stuff, sign up to this offer that's in the show notes with Cloudflare, it's not
sponsored or affiliated, it's just a Cloudflare thing and get yourself a cheap Yubikey.
Good for the internet pricing is adorable.
I thought we're supposed to hate Cloudflare, but I can't help but think this is a good
idea.
This is truly good for the security of the internet.
You know, Chris, I did find a Yubikey in your closet one time.
I think the last time I was here, um, Brent, you're going through my closet?
No, no, I just, well, we'll talk about it later.
You know, there used to be lots of reasons not to use Yubikey's laziness, being at the
wrong end of the house is one of them, but they didn't used to make a USB-C specific
one that was low profile for like MacBooks and stuff.
They fixed that.
That's now a low profile one for MacBooks.
They didn't used to work on mobile devices, but they now do through NFC.
So really there's no real reason if you're curious not to try one at a $10 entry price.
That is a really good point.
I've looked at these keys many times, both the Yubikeys and alternatives, and I've always
hesitated to pull the trigger on price because actually you kind of need two of them.
One is your main, one is the backup.
But the other reason was always that I couldn't quite figure out all of the different features
and you know, which, is it Fido that I need to support everything?
It's like, it seemed like 12 websites use this one proprietary way of doing it, and
the other 12 use this other method.
So I always got lost in all of those details and complexity, and I hope that maybe that's
been solved recently.
Do you have any sense of whether they're easier these days than they were maybe five years
ago?
I think they're more mature and they support a lot more stuff than they used to.
I don't know whether that makes it simpler or more approachable though.
If anything, it makes it worse because there's more options.
That's where I kind of debate, like maybe the, maybe the sweet spot is like an authenticator
app on your phone, but I do kind of, I love that idea of you plug in a hardware device
that does something and it feels like you'd really want to combine a two factor code on
an authentication app with a hardware device with a password potentially.
Or as a backup, you know, when places do SMS phishing attacks and stuff, that's one of
the most common attack vectors is people steal your SMS access, send a two factor code there
whilst they have the temporary access before you notice.
And this would completely negate that as an attack vector.
But only if supported.
Only if supported.
This takes me back to a few years ago where the company I worked at used Yubikeys and
in Slack multiple times a day, different people accidentally touched their Yubikeys and put
in their, you know, 40 character long string, most of the days.
I have seen that.
I see that in our chat room sometimes too.
I did it one time.
And Alex, you've, you've sent some of your passwords to GitHub if I remember correctly.
Oh, well that's, that's different.
That's just me being, being an idiot, but that's different.
What's the difference?
Well these strings aren't useful on their own because they're attached to a specific
service and they're time limited and all that kind of stuff.
So if you happen to know exactly what service I'm logging into at that specific moment in
history, maybe it's useful for about the next 25 seconds, but otherwise it's useless.
Well I want to talk about something you came across that really piques my interest because
I'm often using Reddit as a way to discover topics that seem like might be worth discussion.
And you found essentially an automatic archiver for Reddit.
I did.
I haven't actually tried it out yet, but there's a piece of software in the show notes linked
called Expanse.
And this builds itself as a fully self-hosted multi-user web app, which allows you to externally
store Reddit items such as things you've saved, created, upvoted, downvoted and hidden.
And this bypasses Reddit's 1000 item listing limit, which I didn't know was a limit.
And so essentially there's a quick demo in the GitHub repo, short YouTube video, and
that was enough to sell me.
I'm hooked.
I will set this up the earliest opportunity.
Same.
What the video really demonstrates is it creates like a mirrored environment of Reddit.
So you kind of create some of the same categories of saved post, upvoted post, downvoted, submitted,
commented.
You know, that same kind of thing you get from your Reddit history.
It mirrors that UI in a cleaner way and just presents all that information to you.
And it just continues to just suck that information into your own local instance as you use Reddit
like you normally might.
You don't have to do anything special.
Pretty much like Pocket for Reddit.
Yeah.
Like if, but like if everything you read just automatically went to Pocket or something,
because it's everything you do on Reddit just automatically gets backed up to this thing.
It's kind of brilliant.
I wish I had that for all the services.
Yeah.
Can we get that for Hacker News?
Well, we can give you that.
We can give you anything that's really like all the services for everything.
Have you heard of RSS?
I see you found out that Bitwarden has integrated Fastmail email aliasing.
So that way, when you sign up now you can generate a fastmail unique email address for
a service.
How great is this?
Well, this is amazing.
know that Google supports the plus delimiter in their email
addresses. So you can say, Alex KTZ plus Twitter at Gmail or
whatever, and it will send every email that Twitter has to that
specific email address. The trouble is it relies on the
service that's in question Twitter or whoever, to respect
that. And then also when they sell that information to third
parties at whatever point Elon decides to in the future, they've
also got to include that plus in there because everybody knows
that plus is just a delimiter. And so the real email address is
just a bit before the plus. What this fast mail integration
allows me to do is set up a genuine email alias. So you
know, becomes two or three random words and a couple of
random numbers instead of my actual email address being semi
obfuscated. And it's built directly into the Bitwarden
clients. So they have that generate password feature. If
you if you look at the checkbox, the next one down is now a
generate username box, which we've talked about before. But
if you look just a little bit further down than that, there's
three or four services in there and one of them is now fast
mail. And so just by creating or generating an email address
alias in the Bitwarden client, it will go and talk to the fast
mail API create the email alias. And then from that point in
history, you have a routable email address that is not your
real email address, but is the alias. It's it's brilliant.
You know, it feels to me like we are creating a huge void between
two worlds. We now have, you know, most of us hopefully, who
are well educated about passwords using password
managers, you know, you mentioned YubiKey earlier, all
of these things that are really great, but then I feel like most
people are just not even anywhere close to using a unique
email address for each service. I think we need to figure out
how to bridge that gap.
Well, the tooling helps, you know, building the tooling to
do it. I think that's what this I think that's what this is
trying to do, isn't it? Mm hmm.
Yeah, I think you're right. Yeah. Okay, you win. I've been
I mean, this is not a sponsored thing. I've been trying to get
Brent on Bitwarden for weeks. The man loves his key pass.
You know, what I like about it is that it's worked for the last
15 years, and I don't need to question it. And but I've been
trying to find that key reason that will make me switch and
maybe this is it.
I think the key reason will be when you decide it's time. If I
know anything about about you, Brent, it's that you have to
decide it's a good idea before you'll do something.
Shouldn't that be all of us?
Yeah, technically, technically. I think it might be time for some
feedback, gentlemen. What do you think?
Bring it on. We've been getting a lot of various tail scale
alternatives sent into the show. And at first, I was like, okay,
okay. But what's coming a couple of times has been net-based
and I don't know if either one of you guys have seen this, but
netbird is trying to check all the boxes. And I hope the tail
scale team takes this as a compliment because this is
clearly an indication that they're on to something that all
of these open source projects have cropped up. And I suppose
for a lot of folks, headscale has not been sufficient, I
guess. But the netbird folks are attempting to get as close as
you can to a WireGuard based mesh network. They're supporting
single sign on and multi-factor authentication like tail scale
does. They have some simple controls. I don't think they
have the install down quite as smooth as tail scale does, but
really, who would right? But you get a lot of it, you get a lot
of the advantages. But you know, it's 100% a well, it doesn't
have to be actually, they're also offering their own hosted
implementation as well, of course, which then I'm not even
sure why it's even better than tail scale. But they do have a
by default, a host implementation, but they make it
really clear how to do all your own self hosting if you like.
This is why we were also excited about WireGuard being put in the
Linux kernel a few years ago. It legitimized the project. And we
hoped at the time that it would lead to this proliferation of
solutions based upon it for VPN stuff. I'm so pleased to see
that that's coming true. Aren't you?
Yeah, absolutely. And it looks like, you know, we're gonna have
a spoil of choices. So I wonder if we'll go through a period of
some of these sort of proving themselves out and tail scale
will probably be a leader for a while. Because they got a huge
start. They have a commercial entity behind them that has some
money. And they got a good product, right. But so now
you're gonna see a lot of, I'd say, kind of not clones, but
this kind of kind of what they are, right. And we're gonna have
to see which one kind of wins out. And I think that's going to
be interesting to see which one wins out. And which one ends up
being the most popular in the community? Will it be tail scale
and headscale for those that want self hosting? Or will it be
something like netbird? So if you tried something like this
out there, let us know send us a boost or go to self hosted that
show slash contact and let us know your thoughts. I am just so
happy with tail scale. And now that I'm doing subnet routing,
and all of that I I'm really, I'm really quite pleased. I don't
really see any particular reason to switch. And I'm also totally
in managing some of the authentication and some of the
connecting that's fine for me because I want this to work like
a rock. We talked a little bit about the subnet routing at the
Airbnb in Pasadena with our questionable Wi Fi situation.
That's generous. And it's fascinating. I use the heck out
of the subnet routing. It's amazing. Oh, it's so handy,
especially for devices that aren't PCs or Raspberry Pi is
that you something you can't install software on like my
Victor on solar equipment and battery equipment. I can't
install tail scale on that it's an appliance. But I have tail
scale on my Raspberry Pi that's on the same land and I have
subnet routing on. So now I'm like checking the solar when
we're at the Airbnb making sure jupes is doing okay. And then
you know, I wanted to check the temperatures at the studio. So I
have tail scale installed from hacks on Home Assistant with
subnet routing turned on. And so I'm checking the temperatures in
the garage to make sure the server is okay. And I'm just
using local IPS for all of it. And I'm pleased to say that I I
did hope one day that this would exist that this world would be
real. And so I preemptively set the RV network to a 17 to 16
subnet. And the studio is a 192 168 seven subnet. And so the two
are very different. And that has made life like so just made it
ready to go. Yeah,
when Brent was here, I had to completely re change my retool
my cider my IP range in the house because there was some
overlap between my house here and my dad's Starlink network
because remember, I moaned in an episode, I couldn't change the
ACP range. So I had to completely retool. So that's
some good foresight from you there, Christopher. I tell you
what,
the old days, the old days of VPNing like an animal building
flat networks. But let us know if you try out netbird, I'd be
really curious to hear how it goes.
Yeah, same. And I think in a future episode, we might do a
bit bit more of a deep dive into the subnet routing that that I'm
doing and the split DNS between different sites, because I think
that'd be of interest to folks. So if you're interested in that,
let us know at self hosted dot show slash contact.
I agree. Having chatted a little bit about it at the Airbnb, I
think it would be a great topic. We got some boosts into the show
two and have boosted in with over 9000 9001 sats. And we also
got 1024 sats from Amar, who's having some trouble getting
their audio whole home audio working. So these are these are
our whole home audio boosts that I wanted to follow up on. So
we'll start with Nav and he writes, whole home audio as a
concept has existed as long as human history. So there are
plenty of solutions moving around. Rather than getting
fancy with software, I might present an alternative he
writes, pulse audios, network streaming, and Cody. Now why
Cody, because Cody has a rich app ecosystem for remote
controls and a web GUI. Plus, it supports Plex jellyfin MB, and
even aircast. This solution I have been using for years now,
I would never have thought of Cody, would you know, and I
think it's probably worth a mention because a lot of people
love Cody that listen to the show. And pulse audio network
streaming has been around for years, and I never think to
mention it. But I constantly hear feedback from the audience
that it works pretty well. Just anything with pulse audio gives
me PTSD, I think rustic as diverse boosted with 2000 sats.
And he echoed a sentiment we heard from multiple people out
there. What about vol milio or volumio? Sorry, I'm butchering
that. But it acts as an Airplay Chromecast endpoint. He says if
you want a lot of them synced, you'd have to pay but it's a
good projects was worth paying for. I had a couple of
recommendations for volumio. Actually, the pricing doesn't
put me off too much. I don't mind necessarily paying for the
right solution. I mean, the alternative would be just giving
up and going for a Sonos based deployment, right and that that
ain't gonna be free, is it? So the other thing that came in as
a recommendation was there's a chap on YouTube called Darko
that does he's got beautiful production quality on his
videos. He is a hi fi audio file nerd. And he talks occasionally
about how he streams music around his house. One of the
recommendations I had come in was something called rune audio.
It's not open source, I don't think. And it is paid does cost
quite a bit per month. But you know, this will support along
with volumio multiple rooms based off of Raspberry Pi and
that kind of thing. I'm still stuck though, on how to actually
automate the speaker component. The Raspberry Pi bit I think is
actually the easy bit. I mean, there's a few options, you know,
snapcast is another one out there. It's just controlling the
speaker component. That's the tricky bit. The Broadlink
infrared emitter blaster that I talked about in the last episode
sort of kind of is behaving itself. But I've ordered the
components to build myself a blaster based off an ESP device
as well. See if that's any better than the Broadlink stuff
because it's not, it's just not reliable enough. Yeah, thanks
for the recommendation. I'll take a look at volumio a bit
more seriously over the next next few weeks when I'm not
traveling to LA.
The shame to hear you're having some trouble with the IR blaster
because when you're doing the music stuff, and you just you
just want to hit a button and have it go, you know, you want
it to be a really kind of chill experience. That's not, it's not
when you want to do the troubleshooting.
It seems to me like the intersection of two very
different worlds, you know, the the hardware button, audio file
grade box that's sitting, you know, next to your TV or your
entertainment system feels like maybe high end technology of a
very different era. And you're trying to kind of marry the two.
So I understand there's clearly some some challenge there. But
wouldn't it be great if they just made friends?
Quick code wanted to know if anybody has any tips on content
request systems for music, you know, how there's things out
there like overseer and other tools for like books and stuff
like that. If anybody has suggestions for music, send them
into the show. And then drew oof, or Dr. oof, boosted in with
5678 sats. And he wanted to give a plus one to the zoos z wave
switches, specifically the 700 series. Thank you very much for
that detail. He says I've been through a bunch of different
brands of smart switches over the years. And the zoos have
been that zoos have been the most reliable, affordable and
configurable to date. I'm a network security engineer by
trade. And I've an enterprise grade Wi Fi throughout my house
and property for different APS. And even that can't keep up with
my smart switches. Interesting. My house is long and narrow. So
it just turns out 900 megahertz mesh network works better than
Wi Fi. Thanks for the great podcast. I do love 900 mega
hertz. I love 900 megahertz radio so much. I wish we could
have stayed there. mega strike three boosted in with 3000 sats
Hey, Chris and Alex love the show. I picked up an IKEA ZigBee
light bulb. As I begin to build out my smart home. Any
recommendations for a home assistant ZigBee router?
Currently, I'm looking at the con be two thanks, as always.
Well, he's already got my recommendation that can be I use
the really cheap sewn off one to start with. And it was it was
not good. It was just not good. But the con be two has been my
favorite phrase rock solid since I installed it.
You know what, though, I agree. In fact, I don't even have like
mine hanging off a dongle. It's just like hooked up right to the
back of my home assistant blue in the studio. And I'm talking
to devices that are on the other end of the house. I will also
link to the Zalesh ZigBee 3.0 stick that cloud free.shop sells
because I would imagine if cloud free is selling that that's
probably a pretty good device. But I to own the con be two USB
ZigBee gateway and have been very happy with it and home
assistant just picked it up right away. So that was really
nice.
Don't forget, we still got a coupon code over at cloud free
dot shop. If you put self hosted in there, you'll probably get a
dollar off whatever you're buying.
At user 3513 boosted in with 8192 sets. I'd love to know how
Alex is running Proxmox and Docker on a systems. Are you
running an Ubuntu VM on top of Proxmox? Or containers? Did you
use a bare metal Linux and then somehow hack the packages to
install Proxmox onto it? Tell user 3513 Alex,
you know,
this question has been coming up in discord a lot in the last
month or so. And it's like something has changed and people
just need to need to know exactly what I'm doing to copy
it, which I don't understand.
They can't buy pies anymore. So they're finally giving in and
buying x86 systems and going Proxmox.
They are very sensible people, you know, they should, you know,
you should you should consider doing that. Perfect media
server.com would be where I'd send people for actual
documentation on what I'm doing. I put a new page up there in
May, I think badgers stack in in May, just to just to tell
because I got was getting so many questions. What are you
doing, Alex? What are you doing? And I'm like, well, okay, here
it is. Here's the hardware. I'm using the exact hardware, the
CPU, the the OS, all that kind of stuff. So in the original
perfect meter server guides, I used to recommend virtualizing
Ubuntu, and then passing through all of the drive
controllers to those virtual machines. That was in the days
before I was an absolute quick sync snob. And if you recall in
the show, a long time ago, also, I've written blog posts about
it. And it's on perfect media server.com. I was I was trying
to do something called GVTG to split the quick sync GPU, the
IGPU up between multiple virtual machines and pass it through
and all that kind of stuff. It just didn't work. The
performance was no good. And the complexity was off the charts.
And you know how it goes. So essentially, I decided at that
point, I've got no option if I want hardware transcoding using
quicksync, rather than having my Jules Eon box pull 400 watts, I
only want to pull four watts when I'm doing a transcode. And
who wouldn't want that? I've got to run Plex on the host. And
that's it. That really drove the next wave of my builds, which
I've been doing now for about 18 months, I would say. All of my
containers run directly on the host. Home Assistant itself
runs as a has OS VM, or whatever they call it these days. That's
the only VM I have in Proxmox is literally just Home Assistant.
It's a bit of a waste. I mean, occasionally I spin up a, you
know, an Ubuntu thing for testing or fedora thing or
whatever, just literally for testing. But in terms of
production, everything's on the Proxmox host. It's all done in
Ansible in my GitHub repo, which I'll put a link to in the show
notes as well. And it's just really simple. It's just an
install of Debian with Proxmox installed on top of it. I used
the Proxmox documentation to achieve that. There's not much
to it. It's just Linux, really. It's very boring.
I think that's a good thing. I was we were talking before we
hit record. I'm like, you know, there's a lot of things about
Linux are getting boring, but that's what you need when it
becomes like this layer in the industry. It just needs to work.
So that's great. And we'll have a link to Alex's high level
overview in the notes, including some links to also, as Alex is
adding them right now to documentation on how to get
Proxmox running on Debian 11.
The Badger Stack.
Well, it can be confusing because Proxmox provide an ISO
directly so you can install Proxmox directly from an ISO
just, you know, from the project. Or you can install
Debian and then install Proxmox on top of it. And that can
confuse some people. Either route is completely valid. One
is slightly more hands on there than the other. There's no real
preference in my mind as to which one works better. Just do
whatever makes you feel warm and cozy.
I'm wondering how you feel about this next one, Alex, John A
boosting with 10,000 SATs. And he after listening to the last
episode is yoloing into setting up his own email server. No.
Yeah, yeah. He also was checking out pod verse, which is awesome
new podcast apps. And we also heard from P4 P4, John, who
says, I've started self hosting my own email server this year.
I got a business Comcast connection with a static IP. And
I'm using, you know, host. It's going great. We're somehow when
we say, I don't know if it's a good idea. People are like,
thanks, guys. I'm doing it. You guys are crazy.
I don't think it's a good idea to send us a million dollars.
That would be an awful idea, don't you?
Oh, yeah. Yeah, definitely a bad idea to know. So I see, you
know, I just think it's interesting.
So John, you can send us an email from your shiny new email
server to tell us how it's going, huh? And if we receive
it, we'll let you know. Right?
Yeah, definitely. Also, let me know how the pod verse
transition goes, John, I'm gonna expect a boost from pod verse in
the future. Also, I just want to give a quick shout out. We got
5555 sats from soul trust, sending in just some love for
the show just wanted to wish us well, I thought that was nice.
And then, right, you got this one right. Schmitzfeld, I think
it was mitzvah, he says that he just want to send us a series
of ducks, Huey, Louie, and Dewey. And we got 3000 sats from
four legged emu, who says he's loving calyx on his pixel. So
we get it. I switched to graphene. And now I'm hearing
about calyx constantly. I heard you were testing graphene. So
maybe you need to switch and text calyx. Maybe I should just
go back to the iPhone because this is just it's too much. It's
too much. But we do love the boost. We read all of them. We
only feature some of them on the shows now just to keep things
tight. But we do appreciate everybody who sends one in. If
you'd like to boost the show, you can grab a new podcasting
app new podcast apps.com. Or if you don't want to switch
podcast apps, you can use breeze br ez. technology and keep your
dang podcast app. I think probably Albie deserves a
mention as well. Albie is a way to do it from the web. If you
don't want to use a mobile app at all. And the Albie team seems
to be really solid. They're creating some great open source
code. I had a little call with one of their co founders. I
really like where they're going a l b y for that. Can we give a
little pluggy pug to office hours dot hair? Yeah, it's
something about plugs and hair but office hours dot hair.
Lucky episode 13. I think it was we covered our our some of
the shenanigans on our trip. And then in the most recent Linux
unplugged, we covered our JPL trip to which how great was the
JPL trip? Alex, that was the JPL trip. I just can't process it.
Did that really happen to us? Like we're just normal people.
Something like that doesn't happen to normal people. Does
it? It was so cool. And and to see the clipper to see them
working on the next mission. The Europa clipper. Oh, so Chris
last night to tuning into the live cam that you can get for
there. Oh, cool. Yeah, on YouTube. Go look up the if you
look up the Europa clipper stream. It's on there. I've
checked it several times. And they've added a lot more to it
since we saw it. Wow, that's, that's so cool. I'm just so
grateful. I know I put a little clip in the next unplugged for
you, saying how great the audience is. And it sounds like
a cliche. But genuinely, I think you said it that it's amazing.
We had, you know, 20 people show up for the tour and about double
that for the meetup. Not one person got lost. Everybody was
on time. Everybody was friendly. They brought stories
they brought, you know, I was just like, does any other
podcast network have such an amazing audience? I don't know.
But ours is pretty great. I don't think so. How could they
because we took all the good ones.
True. I also learned so much just by chatting with people.
Alex, I know you were fascinated, but basically all
night because I was kind of hanging around you and learning
a bunch of stuff. But Chris, you were having a great time. And it
was almost like 10pm.
Yeah, oh, we went for our meetup went for five hours
strong, and I still didn't get to everybody. But let's, let's
be clear here, Alex saved the night. Because our guest of the
night, Tim can from JPL brought a very exclusive little device,
he brought the computer from the Mars Copter, like that, you
know, the earth version, the test version, the prototype
version, he brought that for show and tell. So we can all see
like just the parts that we don't recognize. And so you
know, it's in this bag, and it's like secret top, or it's like
private property of NASA and JPL, like it's, and then it's
inside like this sealed case even, you know, and it was like
really a big deal. And Tim bless his heart. You know, I think
with everything going on, he got up, walked away, left it on the
bench. He left it on the bench.
We very nearly had our own iPhone four moment, didn't we?
Very nearly. Yeah, you tapped him on the shoulder. And you're
like, I think you forgot something. And I think he was
extremely grateful. A little bit of history right there. Yeah.
What a lovely guy. What a lovely guy. Yeah, it was really nice of
him to help us make all that happen. And then to make it to
the meetup as well and bring a little show and tell for
everybody. Just so cool. Really, really a great experience
something you'll never forget, you know? Yeah.
Huge thanks to Tim. Huge thanks to everybody at JB. But of
course, thanks to Linode as well for enabling us all to go down
there and take the tour, you know?
Yeah, absolutely. They, they really came through for us. And
you know, we had some great swag, we got to give away swag to
people who came to JPL and came to all the meetups to Linode
gave us an updated shirt for the road with the new route on
there and all that and brighter, bolder colors. So awesome. You
know, we got to meet some members while we were down there
as well. So thank you to all the members who make this show
possible. Self hosted dot show slash SRE if you'd like to sign
up. You are our site reliability engineers and you can support
all the shows if you want to get an ad free version and all their
special features for the whole network at Jupiter dot party.
The very last meetup is on the day that this episode airs. So
if you're a very keen listener, you've still got time to catch
Chris in Portland on his way back north. 6pm Pacific time on
October the 7th.
Yep. And if you missed us future meetups, meetup.com slash
Jupiter broadcasting. Well, I do think we've we've done the
meetups pretty heavily for the last few months. I will say if
you're going to be in Raleigh around Halloween at all things
open. I'm going to be in town obviously because I live here.
But so is cheese bacon longtime friend of the network. I think
system 76 are sending him over to man a booth for the
conference. So we may do an informal meetup. Keep an eye on
the matrix rally room. And we'll talk about any stuff that's
going to happen in there. I mentioned in the shows too, of
course, but the details will be in the matrix room.
That's gonna be fun. All things open always seems like a good
one to go to. Now we do love your feedback, your questions,
your topic ideas, self hosted dot show slash contact is the
place to go to get in touch with us. And of course, you can
find me on Twitter. I'm at Chris LAS.
And for now, at least until Elon closes the deal. Finally,
I'm at ironic badger.
Yeah. And I'm at Brent Jerba.
We might have to revisit the whole Twitter topic again. In
the meantime, there is yes, there is a also a show account
for some reason at self hosted show. Follow it.
What a ringing endorsement that is. And thanks for listening
everybody. That was self hosted dot show slash 81.