We're doing something fun for episode 69
We're doing our first self hosted live stream and we have a whole bunch of people hanging out with us live while we do the show
This is your crazy idea Alex. I know right SSH 69 and we've bumped up the recording date by one day to make it on
420 I mean we couldn't pass up that opportunity could we so joining me today? Obviously we have mr. Fisher. Hello Chris. Hey there
Also in the room with me is Brent. Hello. Hello, and we have cheese bacon from Denver. Hello there
Hello bacon. Welcome back to the show cheesy. Thanks, man. And we have 40 plus crazy people watching us on the live stream
Hello live stream. Hello. Jitsi room, although they're all muted Alex. So they're all not gonna chime in
Well, that's that's a technical hurdle. I need to understand still
If you are watching live and you want to suggest a title
We're doing a whole lot style thing. You can bang suggest in the IRC room today
That's right, and we'll pick something. That's fun
We thought I don't know we've never done this before
But every now that it'd be kind of neat it also I think it'd be a lot of fun to do a live stream
Maybe on like a project day
We work on something and then we do an episode and talk about it
And maybe we do part of the build or the configuration on the live stream. We got ideas
We got all kinds of ideas. I have a drawer full of ideas behind me
I
Have been collecting my ideas in a box that I store in my closet in the RV so
We both have like to-do boxes of stuff, but you literally have a nice light out drawer
Box or drawer of shame, whatever you want to call it. I just can't get to it
I've been I've been creating new shows. I've launched office hours dot hair. It's a new podcast
sort of a podcast for the Jupiter broadcasting community and
One where I can kind of talk about things going on with JB the shows
Community events podcasting in general. So I started a new show
It's but now that I've got that out of the way, I'm planning to get back to some of my projects
But go check it out
It's office hours dot hair
Now of course
This is the first episode since our big East Coast rally meetup rally thing that we did a couple of weeks ago
We had about a hundred people show up. So great job and hello to anybody that we said hi to on that day
Yeah, we had fun. We had some feedback from five who wrote in. Thanks Alex for conjuring the meetup
I had a really great time and I would definitely come out to the East Coast from Minnesota again
The barbecue the brew pub and the park were all superb
I was curious about what drew you to North Carolina in the first place
But after meeting the friendly people and enjoying the beautiful trails of Raleigh, I get it. Oh
Oh, that's nice Brent. You've been living there for a hot minute. How do you feel about that live in the East Coast life?
I feel as though
It's maybe a month ahead of the season where I'm used to so this is like a vacation super great and Alex and I have been
Doing projects galore which has kept me very interested very busy and learning a bunch of new stuff
Yesterday he turned up with a pickup truck bed full of
Materials we're gonna build a roof under my deck tomorrow to store my lawn tractor and all sorts of stuff. We're having a good time
Your lawn tractor. You're so American now. It's a terrible
you know when in Rome darling when in Rome before we were even like
24 hours after the meetup the folks in Raleigh were already talking about holding their own just because there is such a crowd there
There's more tech there than I realized that's what the meetup really showed me
Is that there's a lot more tech in Raleigh than I then I even probably
Appreciated and they're really motivated to keep going. That's something I not to plug the show game
but that's actually one of the reasons I'm launching that new shows to help organize community meetups because I think
people could just start doing these on their own even if we can't make it and maybe from time to time we drop by because
We had we had over a hundred folks show up at this one and it was cold
The weather wasn't really cooperating with us and it was kind of vague where to even find us
Right, and we still had over a hundred people show up
We actually covered in full detail in lup full 53
We had a bunch of interviews with the folks that we met on the day and stuff like that
So if you want more information about the meetup and you know our initial reactions because we recorded it the day after the meetup
Linux unplug.com slash 453
Now tell me about the open mower thing here because I'm picturing you building a robot that mows your lawn
I mean, that's pretty much what we're talking about here
I mean, so I was looking at I have a push mower and I have like about half an acre to mow
It's not too big but it's big enough that in the North Carolina heat in the summer that I'm just like
Nah, this is this is too much like an hour sweating late in the evening. No, thank you
So I bought the lawn tractor in the end, but what I really wanted to buy was one of these autonomous
Mowers, but they're too expensive for the moment
Then came along this open mower project, which I just think is the coolest thing in the world. It uses like open-source software
to do like GPS traces of the mower in your yard and
for those in the jit see room Chris is playing at the video from the github page and
essentially this thing is
It's like it's like the autonomous mower
But actually smart the old ones like the kind of I say old like the current generation ones
Just sort of bop around the lawn in a random pattern until they're done
This thing actually uses GPS traces to figure out the most efficient pattern and then zips ups back across the lawn
Of course, my question is does it work with home assistant? It really is. It looks like a Roomba for your lawn
It looks like while training it. He's walking it manually with almost like an RC controller that's wired to it
That's teaching it the the way he would mow the lawn. So it's essentially repeating
his
Lawn mowing technique right? It's just memorizing it. I mean he's basically saying to his lawn mower. This is the way
Right. This is the way
Previously other lawn mowers, right?
The automated lawn mowers would have like a wire or something that you would like embed in the ground
Which would then say hey stop here. So to see this open and the fact that it operates on GPS is pretty rad
Yeah, this one specifically calls out in the github page. No
No perimeter wire needed
Hmm I like that you could I mean with the walking it technique while that means one time you have to walk this thing around
You could also give it really specific routes
So if you have like a patch of gravel somewhere you'd want it to avoid or stumps and roots and stuff like that
This is a really simple way to just avoid the thing from screwing itself up
And then of course I go to like well, could I then get metrics?
What kind of metrics can I get out of this and what could that tell me about the state of my yard?
Well, and maybe maybe you could you know learn how?
More efficiently you could mow your yard if it was operated in different patterns, right?
like the kind of like Google gives you the recommendation of
The most economic or eco-friendly path to your destination versus the shortest route and stuff
Well, you know what actually thinking about I could give you an example is the things monitoring when it's raining or not
So that way it doesn't run during rain
It would be actually now I think about it. I'd really like something that specifically told me for my yard
When it rained how long it rained when it stopped raining all of that
So if anybody has a recommendation something that I could pull into home assistant
Send a boost into the show or email me Chris at Jupiter broadcasting comm because that actually I could geek out on you need a weather
Station right, but which one aha Alex I'm interested in the hardware that's running this thing
Is it like a do-it-yourself kid or are you taking something off the shelf and reflashing it or something?
well, unfortunately this project has been shared a bit too much and
several of the components in the
Hardware bill of materials have sold out. I mean, we're all used to that at this time of the
Pandemic right, but the trouble is the specific stepper motors that is using are
Out of production or out of stock. They're not even sure if they're still going to make them like he bought maybe the end of
the batch or something
Coincidentally, so unfortunately he's saying to people make sure you look up before you invest in this project
You can actually find all the parts because it's not a given
another thing he said that's really interesting though, is that it looks like
in terms of the robot mowers that are already on the market, there's a bunch that may
Share a similar main board across rebranded different manufacturers. So
he's gonna try and target that one and
hopefully make that one open and then you could just buy a
Clone of this mower and then flash it with his firmware. It's like the pixel of a lawnmowers
It sounds pretty awesome
Hmm. Well, I guess we'll stay tuned and if anybody tries this let us know
So this week we had we had one of these stories that was kind of the inspiration for the podcast
And it's just a shameful story. You may have heard of insti on well
It looks like they're gone and the entire company seems to have just abruptly shut down before the weekend as we record here and
That broke users cloud dependent smart home setups with no warning
there was no official word ahead of the shutdown no advanced warning to users and
It's sort of like salt in the wound style. They have a
Craptastic status page that's obviously manually updated because when you go to it, it says all services online
Right. Yeah
Clearly that monitoring doesn't do jack. I hate that. I hate that so much
Yeah, so instant is or more likely was a smart home company that produced a variety of smart home devices
They did something along the lines of Zed wave or Zigbee with their own proprietary protocol
Which has thankfully been reverse engineered. So we're not completely up the creek without a paddle just mostly
And yeah, like Chris says they went out of business
some point over the weekend and their CEO has scrubbed all mentions of the company from his LinkedIn page and
Basically all of the devices belonging to insti on are now paperweights
With the exception of their wall switches, which are electrically connected as part of the circuit
So that the worst case scenario that happens with those is they're still mechanical switches that will operate the the lights at least so
There is some silver lining. It's a small one
But it's there
This is horrible
and whatever you do do not factory reset your hub, apparently it has to contact their servers as part of its setup and
That's gonna fail now home assistant have actually
Updated a documentation since yesterday to say it's now possible. You don't have to worry about that anymore
So if you do actually factory reset it they now have a workaround
This is really a shame to see and they also had their own proprietary networking protocol, which actually looks like it was kind of neat
I mean, it's 900 megahertz, which is usually pretty good
It also could coexist with power line networking, which is kind of neat and it supported local control, but it was
Proprietary and patented and you know unique to them. So that's just sort of gone now
See not only are your cloud services gone, but the whole protocol that has been created is essentially now invalid
It's still usable, but nobody's they're maintaining supporting
Shepherding it
We just see this happen over and over again
and it's these kinds of stories that really got Alex and I thinking we should we should do a show about this because
When you take this kind of stuff over
Like if you go to cloud free dot shop or you reflash something or you just get it working locally and you get all working
Home assistant, you no longer need an account or you know a cloud login
There is a so there is a sensation of self-sovereignty that you get it feels really good to have
control over this stuff like it feels better than you'd expect and
I think it's because we keep seeing these rug pulls
Essentially from these companies and you buy these things and there's sort of this implicit
promise that they're gonna keep the service running, but they never actually
Commit to it. And there's no warning to the average consumer
that
The discontinuation of the online services invalidates the product, right? They don't understand that they don't get that our audience understands that but
People that are buying these things from like Home Depot or whatever. They don't understand that. I
Mean the obvious answer is to just use home assistant and never worry about it again
You know use devices with open firmware like TAS motor, you know, not the ones from cloud free dot-shop
There are some other options, of course, you know, there's a home kit compatible stuff
Which is all local only
It's not quite as good as like a fully open firmware, but it's it's close
Open hab and what's the other one Dom a titch? I'm never quite sure how to say that one because in tight. I
Mean it's just a shit situation, isn't it?
It is because I feel like you're kind of giving the typical answer of oh
You don't like what the carrier flashed your Android device with well, you can always put lineage on it. Yeah. Okay. Well, I'm
Maybe but probably nobody else in my family, right? It's I mean the reality is they have just created a
huge amount of e-waste
In yeah weekend. I was just about to touch on that exactly
100% yeah, I'd like to see some kind of legislation from
governments from the EU from these bureaucratic bodies to say you have a duty of care on the
life cycle of these devices whether that extends to how people sunset devices and say right we're going to
The Sonos that we talked about last year at some point the v1 hub or bridge or whatever it was
Why didn't they rather than just saying you've got to buy the new one?
Why didn't they provide a firmware to say for the v1 devices?
Hey, you can put this open firmware and I can do what you like with it, you know
Make it this open device and give it another life. We've been doing that with laptops for
Two three decades now, you know
We take old crusty Windows laptops and throw Linux on there and give them a new lease of life
All I'm proposing is we do the same thing with embedded hardware
Yeah, absolutely. That's it. That's a great idea
So, you know you had kind of mentioned Chris about Home Depot and you know possibly picking these off the shelf and and I don't
know, you know where
These were sold at retail, right? And then, you know, Alex mentions about the e-waste which I think is a very significant problem
but how many of these devices do you think are still on the shelves and
Retail, you know at retailers and consumers are just buying with the intent that they're going to work as soon as they get them home
Maybe this is their first smart device ever right as soon as they get them home
Now it doesn't work. It doesn't connect to the cloud server
Here I am trying to go through some work around something. I don't know
Here I am trying to go through some work around something. I'm not technically inclined. How do I get this flashed?
How do I get this to work with something else?
You know, imagine being that teenager that's finally convinced your dad to buy a piece of smart home gear, right?
He gets it home and this happens. Yeah, exactly bad luck
exactly
You know, it's not an isolated case either. Um, my father's dealing with this right now
He bought a few d-link cameras and water sensors
For a few rental properties that he has in his home as well. He gets some flooding there
Just as a security blanket and this is a perfect example of a really great use case for these devices, right?
Um, luckily he got an email maybe at the beginning of the year in january saying oh d-link
We're gonna stop supporting our protocols and all devices will stop working at the end of the year or in september or something like that
But it's I think what's troublesome and I chris, I think why you suggested that
The whole premise of this show started was that this is not an uncommon situation
We see it, you know time and time again multiple times a year with various devices and it's just really saddening
Luckily, I looked it up and of course they're compatible with home assistant. So i'll be doing some homework there
Now for those of you that are already home assistant users
They just put out a blog post for insteon users detailing all the little ins and outs of how you can get the most out of
Those devices moving forward. We'll put a link to that in the show notes
Linode.com
Slash ssh go there to get one hundred dollars in 60-day credit on a new account and you go there to support the show
Now this is a way for you to host things under your control on linode's incredible infrastructure
They have 11 data centers around the world
They have super fast systems with amd epic processors if you want to go with a crazy fast cpu system
They have pci mvme storage if you want some really fast storage. And of course they have systems that are just
Real budget focused if you just want something for you a friend
maybe a real basic gaming server the whole whole gamut and
Unlike the hyperscalers that want to lock you into their esoteric complicated platforms with their own language and their whole
entire own ecosystem
Linode is real old-school servers built with a modern infrastructure
And people that really know what they're doing and of course you could do a one-click application deployment if that is your bag
You just want to hit a button and spin a server up they got you
But if you want to build something from the ground up you can do that as well
And that's why I think it's perfect for our audience and with pricing 30 to 50 cheaper than those major hyperscalers
It's going to work for a personal project or for your business and everything we've built in the last couple of years
We've built on linode. It scales up to demand
They have s3 compatible object storage, which I use all the time
ddos protection vlan support a powerful dns manager
Kubernetes and terraform support if you want to integrate it in with your overall infrastructure and so much more and at the end of the day
The audience tells me over and over again. They have the best support they've ever experienced
that's the number one thing I hear from the audience is whenever they run into trouble with their site or
They hit the wrong button or they just don't feel right about something. Linode has answered their questions
They haven't escalated them to a different tier. They've remained on the line and got it solved 365 even during the holidays
And that gives me the confidence to use them for my business
Even though I've never had to I love knowing that they just have the best support in the business
So go check it out build something try something learn something take advantage of that 100 go to linode.com
dollars go to linode.com slash ssh
Now I've still got brent staying with me after the meetup and
He is quite the phos advocate. I tell myself. I'm a phos advocate, but this guy lives and breathes it
And so we watching something on plex the other night and it was just an offhand comment about plex. I can't remember what it was
And it made me think well, I should probably try out jellyfin again. It's been a few months
And so I thought well i've got a bunch of watched status in plex. I'd rather not lose
And so I started investigating how I could sync the watched status between plex and jellyfin
And I came across this plex tracked sync plugin. So t r a k t for tracked
And this thing is awesome. Essentially it scans your media in plex
And adds it to a tracked collection. It will do things like sync the ratings and the watch status as well between
Different plex servers that you run this thing against
There's a config file that you can edit which will let you know which things you can and cannot sync
You know, you could exclude certain libraries like home movies, for example
It doesn't require a plex pass or a tracked vip membership though. Of course if you're going to be hitting the tracked api a lot
Consider supporting those guys. They do a great job over there. Um, the downside though is it was
It wasn't difficult to set up but it wasn't easy either. Um, so I ended up running this thing in a container
Just a one-liner docker run file
Uh docker run command and then I set it to run on a cron job every four hours or something like that
Um, I mean it worked fine. Uh, there was a couple of um gotchas with a pin you had to enter between
Tracked and the command line in the correct order to get things to link up correctly
But overall worked as advertised
well, this is you're doing the lord's work here alex because uh, this is this is powerful stuff here because the other thing that this
clearly would be useful for is
If you have a couple of locations and you have some of the same plex media content, right?
And you watch them in separate spots like sometimes cd and I will watch something here at the studio
And then i'll go home and watch something and I have to like manually mark things red like a damn caveman
And this could solve that problem. This is huge for that
And i'll tell you what I felt during this whole process that the next stage was to was for me to load up jellyfin
I still had my config directory. So I just had to redownload the container and set it up again
Which took all of 30 seconds
Don't you love docker for that?
Uh, so once I got uh, jellyfin up and running the first thing that struck me it remembered my library
It was like a time capsule of four months ago when I last tried it, but the first thing that struck me was how quickly?
Everything loaded because there was no cloud communication going on. I was logged in instantly my media loaded instantly
It was so refreshing. Yeah, and i'll note
It's real nice
If for just some reason you're trying to watch tv and you don't have an internet connection that night jellyfin just you know
It doesn't mind at all. Um before you go too much further. Can I ask you you're not having to like
Modify the plex container or put this put any software like a plugin into plex or jellyfin
It's just all running as separate containers that are
Speaking via api or what plex speaks via the api I think and uh, it runs on your local system
And you authenticate against the plex website with your username and password. It also supports 2fa, which is pretty cool on the plex side
Uh, but on the jellyfin side, it's even easier. There's a plugin right there in the store built into jellyfin
You know three or four clicks. It's all done in the user interface. No wacky container stuff
And it adds itself into the scheduled task section of jellyfin itself
This is perfect. I do have a question on the initial
Setup to sync between how long do you think since it was local? How long do you think it took to to sync these watch status?
And the the stars and stuff like that. It's a good question
The first run of uploading it from my plex library to tracked took about 16 minutes
I've got about a thousand movies and I don't know 150 tv shows or so about 60 terabytes worth of stuff. That's really reasonable
But jellyfin on the other hand pulling it down was about half that time
About eight minutes or so. So it's pretty quick process really and honestly once it's running as a scheduled task in the background
As long as it doesn't take three days. I don't care how long it takes
Well, this is uh, absolutely a will do after the show, uh thing for me, I love it when you have these ones that's great
I love that that's I've thought I've thought how am I going to solve this problem because it's not a huge
It's not a huge issue, but I also like you
Have contemplated moving to jellyfin and I know this seems stupid
But one of the things that brings me back to plex is we're in the middle of watching a couple of series
And or the kids and I are watching like a movie. That's like a trilogy or something like that
And we just want our watch status
It's silly, but it's been a real problem. So this sounds like a real way
I could sync to track it and then sync track it to jellyfin and I could just start there
And this also could solve the problem between watching things at home and watching things at the studio alex. You're solving problems for me today
I'm here to serve
Now the only thing that still has me pausing about jellyfin is the android tv client
It's still not quite as reliable as I want it to be. It's pretty close
It's really getting there, but there's just some nice things now, particularly plex have added this
Uh, what do we call it?
Like the discover feature where you get some extra little ratings and some extra little things about which sort of
Some extra little ratings and some extra little things about which servers it's on and qualities and stuff like that
That plex have done that. I think jellyfin could probably add as well
Um that would you know, just take the interface just to that next level
The the search aspect of that discover feature where it shows you all of your friends servers is is actually really nice
Yeah, but the beauty is you know, you could switch between plex and jellyfin at your heart's content now and everything will stay in sync
That's a good point. You could also just get rid of android tv and use a good tv platform like apple tv and run infuse
Which works great with jellyfin?
Oh you now I also wanted to have a look and see uh, if I was going to drop plex completely
Um, it needs to do a couple of things for me
I use prologue on ios to do audiobooks and I actually shared this with your good lady while she was here chris
Uh, so I can see she's been listening to a lot of my audiobooks since then
and that's one of my favorite things of the trip alex is we exchanged audiobooks once again, she exchanged some of her audiobooks and
uh, she's like
she she I think is probably
In heaven right now because she's kind of been on a bit of a dry streak with audiobooks and i'll be honest
I have not been super happy
With how I was doing my audiobooks prologue helps a lot though that that's been nice, but it's really only best on the phone
The downside to that is there isn't really a good solution to audiobooks and plex on android
And so with brent staying with us, you know, we've been talking about books and stuff and we thought well
There's got to be a better way. My wife has been using book sonic for many many years
Which is a java based application based on top of the old subsonic base
It's fine, I guess I mean it it's pretty reliable until it breaks because it's a java app
You know, there's some memory leak somewhere or something just doesn't quite work and it crashes
so I actually have a job to restart book sonic every day because it's
Not the most reliable application
So I saw on reddit the other day. There was an application called audio bookshelf had been released
And this is a self-hosted audiobook server for managing and playing your audiobooks still early days
The first commit the first release actually, sorry was only in september 2021. So it's not even a year old yet
Uh, and I don't know if you remember the old ios like ibooks application
That was like skeuomorphic with like the wooden bookshelves and all that. This is what this thing looks like
Yeah, the best version you mean? Yeah, I remember that I loved it. Were you and scott forstall good buddies back then?
Nice callback, dude. Yes. I like the skeuomorphism. Why not? You got that high resolution screen. Let's make it look good
Yeah, it's got the wood shelves. It's got nice big bold book covers
This is great
Well, it looks great and I think it's got a lot of potential but it's sadly not quite ready for prime time yet
So I tried out the ios app which I had to install that test flight thing because it's not properly in the app store yet
It's like like the application is is in beta
And let me tell you it's most definitely in probably alpha stage right now
I had two versions across the last two days where I was testing it
The first version didn't load any of the audiobooks from my library at all
So even though I had a few hundred books in the library, it just said library empty
Okay, that's a bit that's a bit of a problem. Luckily. There was an update available
So I pulled down that update and installed it from the test flight app
Um, and then I tried to do it found the books this time
But I tried to test the syncing of playback positions between the browser on my laptop and my phone in my hand
And it worked ish
So if I started playing the the book on my phone and skipped to a certain chapter
The browser would update in real time as to where I was and it would save that status if I close the browser and come
Back, it would remember it if I close the ios app
It would just start at the beginning every time
So there's obviously some work to do. It's not it's not quite there yet, but it's extremely promising
Hmm. Okay
Yeah, i'd like something that I could use reliably on the desktop and on mobile because sometimes I want to sit down
I want to listen on my desktop speakers
um, and I need something that's really
Really usable by the wife and she likes prologue quite a bit. I also set it up for my son dylan and I used plex collections
to create just a collection of books for dylan and then um, you know when he signs on on prologue
He just sees he goes to the collections tab and he just sees all the books that I've already picked for him
And so over lunch we were talking with brent about how to get him access to my book sonic because it's behind my firewall
Typically, I just give my wife my uh wire guard access
access
I love brent, but I don't want to give him full access to my lan. You know, I can't trust his phone
That's literally about to catch fire
You know the one i'm talking about. It's literally the battery's popping out the thing
I can't believe you're letting him bring that in the house. You have a family now. You got to get that out of there
And so I was looking at tailscale and they actually offer a way to share a specific server as an exit node
With someone else with a tailscale account. So what i'm thinking of doing is sharing just my
Uh media server with brent as an exit node and then he should be able to access book sonic that way. Oh
Now this is excellent
Tailscale.com slash self-hosted, you know alex what we ought to consider is playing around with that for helipads
So you guys can see the boosts?
because I have my uh bitcoin node on tailscale
And that's how I read the boost that people send in from anywhere i'm at on my phone whenever whenever I need to pick me up
I'm not even kidding whenever I need a pick me up. I pull up the boost page
And it just always puts a smile on my face
So if we could figure out a way for you to read those I'd probably do the same for you
Now if you don't know tailscale is a zero config vpn you can install on just about any dang device you've got I mean
any device a mobile device an arm device a raspberry pi an x86 server to help you manage your firewalls
And it works from anywhere. I found the coolest thing today in the feature request section
They're adding android tv support. Can you believe this i'm so excited
This is going to make me keep a shield. I have one shield left and this is going to make me keep it
Think about this for a second think about how amazing this could be when you're traveling
And then you reconnect to your home network and it just discovers your media server like you're right there on your land
Or you have family members or maybe there's some content you want to get access to this is next level stuff and tailscale is in this beautiful
Beautiful sweet space where they're just created this amazing tool
With just enough infrastructure to make it work like you need and they use wireguards noise protocol for the security of it
Which you know is great and they support your single sign-on provider
If you're a corporate user like you could use whatever you want and for me
I'm using my google account with two-factor authentication, which just gives me a little bit extra peace of mind
And the best part is wherever i'm at if i'm at alex's house
If i'm on the road if i'm back here at the studio
I just use the same ip for the devices. I need to visit all the time
It's one flat wireguard network and you can put a dns server in there and you got name resolution
There's acl support. There's exit node support like alex was talking about
It's such a like take my work to the next level kind of tool. I am thrilled
They are sponsoring this show because I can completely enthusiastically endorse this because this is making house
This is making how I do my job better. And I think it would really be a great tool for you, too
So go check it out. Try it out
support the show and get a free account for up to 20 devices when you go to tailscale.com
slash
Self-hosted that's tailscale.com slash self-hosted
Now I want to take a moment to say thank you to our site reliability engineer subscribers
You make this show possible over at self-hosted.com slash sre
Now as many of you know and you love to write in and tell us we're wrong
We'll get to the feedback shortly, but you can write in at self-hosted.com slash contact
and also
this week
And also we have a discord server over at self-hosted.com slash discord loads of great conversations
But this week there was one that really took the sandwich
This week we found out the origin of the pseudo logo. This thing is so cool. Have you seen it?
No, I waited. I saved it right now for this. Um, the have you seen the xkcd comic of sudo make me a sandwich?
Make me a sandwich
Well, the logo for sudo is
a sandwich
That's great, I love it
Is it though? No, it is it's great. It is great. It is
Well, I think it's great because if you look in the corner of the actual logo, it says influenced by xkcd 148
That's pretty impressive. That is pretty great real world change being affected right there right there. That's that's fantastic
Um, all right. We I know we have a couple of quick tips
We wanted to bust out is this a thing we do now we do quick tips on the show
Uh, it is this week because i've been using the crap out of docker stats, which is
It's like a top for your containers
So if you if you ssh into a box right now and just type docker stats
you'll get like a live print out of the cpu memory disk io network io usage of each container one by one broken out and it's
It's legit pretty cool. That is oh, you know, I think i've seen this tool before but I think I completely forgot about it
So, thank you
All right. I think it's time to get into feedback. Don't you?
Yeah, we got a boost coming in from remaking eden one week ago 2000 sats. This is hello from manchester, england
Hey, that's where I met my wife. Hey as a listener since episode one
I wanted to tell you that self-hosted has changed my entire home
And helped shape my it career. So thanks so much. That's awesome. I have three wise style cameras
I think they're actually rebranded yaomei cameras. Um, oh, okay interesting. I didn't know why he sold them
He says in the uk the most popular seller seems to be neos. I immediately
Um reflashed mine with the dfang hacks firmware
I use the rtsp feed straight in home assistant and frig it and they've been flawless for years
I was wondering if you looked at this as an option seems like they're not yet working on a v3 camera though
I didn't even know these were essentially rebranded wise cameras
That's fascinating
Remaking eden. Thank you
Alex go buy some
Brenda if you still got that credit card, you should go pick a couple up. I think I know where he keeps it
I know where you sleep at night. Is that
That's creepy
Yeah, so I actually tried this to fang hacks firmware on my original wise v2s
It was probably two or three years ago now
And honestly, it was a pain in the ass, uh trying to get it flashed on there with the sd cards
I had a real time getting it on there, but thankfully they released the official rtsp firmware some time ago now
So for me the use case for the defying hack firmware has kind of been diminished somewhat
Yeah, and also with wise bridge
um
It's even kind of simpler now to just use the default firmware get all the security updates and still capture the video locally
So that's kind of the route that I think i've been suggesting people go anonymous boosted in
He says I meant to get the name. I apologize for a thousand stats
I found you guys through the fountain app, which is a fountain.fm a new podcast app
Because you have the podcasting 2.0 tag set up
So I want to take a second and just break this down because you may be seeing this if you're in our community more and more
So podcasting 2.0 is a set of new specifications
For podcasts to give them more features like chapter images well chapters to begin with
transcriptions
links that are
At a particular time code all kinds of other features including a value for value tag, which includes the boost that you hear us talk about
And you can grab one of these new podcast apps that supports these new standards at newpodcastapps.com
And we'll have a link in the show notes
That takes you to the ones that specifically support the boosts
But alex, I know we also just got a whole bunch of traditional emails this week, too
We did and i'm gonna make use of having brent sit next to me and read the long one
You just want to hear my voice, don't you? I do baby. We all do we all do
It reads. Hey chris and ironically named badger
I was listening to your segment about what to do with syncing certificates to multiple servers using something like s3
And I have some comments, please for the love of god, don't do this
Firstly because the certificates are the keys to your kingdom
A leak of those removes all security on your services and lets anyone in the middle snoop on whatever it is you're doing
Self-hosted or otherwise certificates are massively important and shouldn't be stored anywhere. Other than where they're absolutely needed
Secondly because it's just not necessary
If you're not using wildcard certificates
Then just creating certificates for each domain is totally fine
And they can be stored and managed wherever the domain needs to be served from if you are using wildcards
There's nothing which says only one can exist in the world
My servers each have their own wildcard automatically managed and renewed by trafic
This way there's neither a need to store their certificates anywhere other than the servers nor to set up some secure storage or communication method
I don't even bother backing out my certificates anymore. That seems crazy to me
Let's encrypt or more specifically acme makes provisioning certs insanely simple
Let them deal with the security side of things. We can just use their tools to create all the certificates. We want
Wherever we want. Thanks for reading and keep up the great work your friendly neighbor orange
Thanks for writing in jake. Now. This is jake of episode 42 fame who came in on our first community spotlight
Also, we had kevin write in who told us that we're actually trying to over complicate the management of ssl certificate management
He says I get the desire to use a wildcard cert, but it would be much easier to generate machine-specific certificates on each vm instead
I manage a few dozen servers and use dehydrated to generate let's encrypt certificates on each host
That way the private key and the certificate don't need to be distributed and they never leave the vm
It uses a plain text file to configure the host names and generate certificates and it makes it very easy to add extra names that way
Thanks for writing in kevin. You raise a very good point. And uh, yeah, I don't know why we missed that
It's a really obvious thing. Just run
Just run acme or cert bot on each machine problem solved. Well, I do this is of course
easy for me to say now, but I remember specifically on the pre-show that we were
Not streaming. We we thought this guy isn't doing this, right and we did start talking about this
But then we did we just dropped it and we got to the business of actually recording the show
We have this thing don't we where we're always having a pre-show conversation and all the best versions
Of our problem solving comes out then and we're like save it for the show and I guess we just forgot to save that nugget
Yeah, and it is absolutely our bad
So, um, thankfully we have an awesome audience who helps us with that kind of stuff and we have no qualms at all about making
Corrections and fixing that sort of stuff because it's all about just getting the best info out there
Now I was hoping to solicit some feedback from the audience on my next next video
Back from the audience on my next networking upgrade. I've currently got a gigabit network everywhere
Which like most people I did because it's cheap, you know, I can buy a five port switch for 15 bucks at best buy
And every time i've looked at going
More than gigabit so, you know 10 gigs probably the next logical step
I'd look at the switch prices and they're like two three hundred dollars per switch and I think oh
I'll just wait for the prices to come down a little bit and they never seem to
And jeff geerling, you know who was also on the show previously just did a video on a microtik switch the crs
309 1g 8s plus in
That name rolls off the tongue doesn't it flippin. Yeah, nice smooth
So we basically questions for the audience if you've done 10 gig i'm really curious to know how you did it
Did you run fiber in your house? Did you do it with cat 6a?
Thankfully, I ran cat 6a on the trunks in my house when I moved in three years ago
Or am I shooting for the stars with 10 gig is 2.5 enough for my needs right now
That's a fair question. I'm curious what you're doing right now. That makes even gigabit insufficient. Well, i've got gigabit
WAN so sometimes if i'm pulling something down from the internet and then trying to stream something to
Plex, uh, you know a high bitrate movie or moving some files around from my desktop to my nas, for example
Uh that can sometimes cause issues. Sure. Yeah, especially when you're you're you're you know
Not working with like cisco switches there at your house, right?
So that also makes a difference that makes I mean i'm i'm never going to stop a guy from going as much performance as possible
I'm, all about it. Uh, I I think that's a great question is two and a half gigabit enough
and
And is it worth the leap to 10 gigabit? I have to tell you alex
I feel like you're the kind of guy that appreciates the value of doing it once and just doing it, right?
You know, like you could do 2.5 gigabits and you could probably get away with it for a couple of years
Probably even five years
But there's gonna be a point where you're gonna wish it was faster because you're just that kind of guy
And so and you know, it could be better too. That's the other thing
You are totally spot on now lucas writes in in the live chat
I impulse signed up for two gig google fiber and realized almost nothing. I have can distribute it across the land
Oh, no
Who thought we'd have wan connections that were faster than gigabit, huh? Yeah
I mean, I would love to have that problem. I'm still stuck with 300 megabits here at the studio
That's what i'm with you chris. Yeah
They're i'm not even joking. There are days when the starlink in the rv performs better than the comcast here at the studio
Yikes, I know although
although
We did get a letter saying that fiber was in the area and would be available soon
So things could be looking up boys. Things could be looking up. Oh brent will attest to this
We're driving around my area at the moment and there are just trucks rolling running fiber
Everywhere around me but not in my neighborhood
Good
That does sting very it's very frustrating and it's
They're also hard to miss their giant rolls of orange
Beauty so alex every time we're out driving. He's like there's another one fiber
Yeah, yeah, I will say that I agree with chris here on that though that
You might as well go ahead and do 10 gigabit and you know, we were on the topic of e-waste earlier
Right. What is it going to be like 2.5 for five years until then you upgrade to 10?
It just seems like save yourself the time and the effort do it once and do it, right?
I agree completely and that was why I ran cat 6a when I moved in was because I had one eye on that in the future
But I was talking to abstract vector who is matt adventurous way who was also on the show a few episodes ago building the house
He's running fiber in a conduit from the road to his house
Which is like a three four hundred foot driveway or something
Uh, but then he's also running fiber between all the buildings. He's building on his land
And so he's looking at all the different switching gear. He's going to need for that kind of stuff. So you would too
Right. I mean wouldn't you at this point? I mean, absolutely
I would love to do that. Yeah, we should have him on at some point and see how it goes how it's all working
Yeah, we need a six monthly update from matt on his house build
But he was doing he was doing 10 gigabit over two and a half for his home build
We'll have to ask him
Okay, I bet if he's running fiber in conduit. Yeah, you might as well right?
You know what?
I want to find out we'll talk to him. Maybe he can let us know in fact
Let us know what you think two and a half. Should he go all the way to 10 gig? How would you do it?
How have you done it go to self hosted dot show slash contact?
That's the place to go to get in touch with us
Give us some feedback or send us a boost get a new podcast app your boost go to the front of the line
As always you can find me on twitter at ironic badger and i'm over there at chris las
Cheesy you got anywhere you want to send people? It's been a while since you've been on anything to plug
Uh, no, nothing really to plug per se, but uh, i'm glad to see that you guys are still healthy
The show's still doing great. Sorry. I missed the meetup this time
Hopefully i'll get to come out next time when we're not in the helm buying process
Which is just a nightmare in and of itself right now. Um, yeah. Yeah, that's a whole podcast
When you do get a place and it's time to tech it out. You got to come back on the show
We'll talk about that. Oh, absolutely
Absolutely, we'll drop into a helicopter in and do some ethernet pools with you or something
Well, yeah, you know now that i'm here at the apartment like I brought all of my unify gear with me
Though I can't really it's like just sitting in the closet right now. Like I can't really use it
You must be already daydreaming. You must be thinking about absolutely every house we look at dude. I'm like, hmm
Where could we go here? Oh, I like this crawl space plenty of place for me to get around here. Um, right
But yeah, you know, it's great to see that you guys are still uh, chugging along doing great in the the the turnout
You know 100 people that's that's pretty phenomenal
Um and that people are already talking about meeting up there individually. That's I think that's just a
A great thing for the community as a whole
Um, and you guys kind of kick starting that's pretty pretty amazing
Um, but yeah, if you want to learn any more about me if you want to get in contact with me
If you want to slide into my dms
Uh, you can get me on the twitters at cheese bacon at chcbaco in
Very nice. And of course brent you're our frequent friend these days, uh, and frequent flyer
One place they can of course find you is on the linux unplugged program anywhere else you want to send people?
Yeah, I think you guys are all doing the twitter thing so people can find me there
I'm at brent jerva and I think you should look for the link don't need to spell it. Oh, there you go
Also, he lurks from time to time on our matrix
We do have a self-hosted community on our matrix server. Our matrix server is colony.jupiterbroadcasting.com
But you can also follow the show on the twitters if that's your thing I understand it's at self-hosted show
Big thank you from me to everybody that came to the meetup
It's the first real public meetup that i've i've been to I know we went to denver
But this one was kind of initiated as self-hosted. Yep show
There's your crew there. I know it's like my my bros all came to say hi
So it was great huge. Thanks from me personally to everybody that made it. Uh, I had a blast. So thank you for coming
Also, thank you for listening everybody and those of you that joined us live. Hi welcome
We might do this more often because we had a pretty good turnout today and this was self-hosted dot show slash 69
420 edition