Coming up on today's show, Chris talks about industrial grade LTE.
We have a philosophical debate on cloud versus local,
and I experienced full blown Americana this Halloween.
It involves golf carts.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Alex, and this is Self Hosted.
Well, this is an awkward one because it's just after Halloween
and just before the election.
So there's a lot going on.
How are you doing, Alex?
I'm doing very well, thank you, yes.
We don't really celebrate Halloween very much in England,
but it's a big deal over here, isn't it?
I actually had my, I think one of my biggest Halloween wins as a dad,
and it just came on accidentally
while the kids were out doing a Halloween activity.
I had the realization in a moment of clarity
where nothing else was going on,
I realized that basically 90% of the lights in my house are smart lights.
And I always have them at just a warm white,
but I actually could change their colors.
And so I went around, well, inside Home Assistant,
and changed all the different colors of the lights to Halloween colors
and then turned on the Halloween sound effects on the Home Pods.
Oh, cool.
And then the kids got home and opened up the door to Lady Choops,
and it was like a Halloween festival inside.
It was like a nice smart home win moment
because everybody looked around and went,
oh, yeah, right, colors.
You can do that.
How is it going for you, though?
I mean, Halloween's one thing, but of course, the election's coming up.
There's got to be a lot of new, a lot of America in your face right now.
Well, yeah, I think the most American thing I've seen since I emigrated
is a family trick or treating on a golf cart.
Oh, that's next level.
That's a good idea.
You know, I mean, you don't want to have to wear yourself out getting your candy.
You don't have to walk.
I mean, and even this year, because it was all, you know, corona,
everything was socially distant.
So people just placed the tables at the end of their driveways.
And the kids, they literally drive along on the golf cart, hop off,
take three paces to the nearest driveway, load up the bowl of candy,
and then off they go again.
So it's a minimum viable effort trick or treating this year.
I lurk on a lot of the communities that share their ring footage.
This is a thing on the internet, by the way.
People that share their ring footage.
And so many, so many videos this year, a lot of them have made it to Reddit
of full-fledged dudes like adults just coming up and wholesale stealing candy out of bowls.
I just can't even with these people.
People need to do something better with their time.
Like get certified.
This episode is brought to you by Cloud Guru.
Are you looking to make a high paying career move into the cloud?
Well, there's no better place to start than getting a certification.
ACG has helped more than 2 million people skill up on the cloud.
AWS, Azure, and Google exam preps, you're covered.
Just get going at a cloudguru.com.
I'm so excited.
I saw on the road outside my neighborhood last week,
the AT&T techs were fiddling around with a ditch, which running fiber up the road.
So I might be getting fiber soon.
Oh, I was thinking maybe they were running down infrastructure for the towers for 5G.
Oh, it could be.
Yeah, it could be.
You've got to get that Corona in somehow.
Right.
You got to get in every town in every neighborhood.
Well, I mean, either way, though, you're getting an upgrade, right?
So fiber would be great.
Speaking of backhaul, though, you have been
going crazy with this industrial LTE modem setup.
Tell me about that.
Oh, my gosh.
I have achieved LTE nirvana, I suspect.
I mean, early days, big, big upgrade for the RV.
So super quick recap.
For those of you who maybe are new or don't know,
I choose to live in a Class A RV, a 40-foot bus, basically.
That's what the Class A is.
A baked bean tin on wheels.
Yeah, carry on.
And it's sometimes loaded up with kids and dogs and tons of podcasting gear.
And it has to accommodate working from home and school from home now for three kids.
And my wife, who has transitioned some of her practice online, so she's doing video calls.
You forgot one important thing that it carries as well.
What's that?
Your poops.
That's true.
Lady Jupes carries my poop.
So I call my RV Lady Jupiter, named by the audience, live on Linux Unplugged one day.
And for short, Lady Jupes.
And you might not think of this initially, but it's really tricky to have a solid,
reliable internet connection in a mobile vehicle, especially if it's not just a car.
Because there's some booster solutions that you just throw an antenna on the roof of your car.
They're pretty straightforward.
But I needed something that could accommodate a family, that could accommodate work,
and that could accommodate multiple cellular scenarios.
Because some areas have better carrier coverage.
In fact, it's just how it always works.
There's some areas that are stronger with different carriers.
And through research, I had come across the PepWave Max Transit by a company called Peplink.
The Max Transit is a purpose-built modem router unit with two LTE modems,
each with two antenna ports.
And you can do redundancy, you can do combination here.
I'll get into that a little bit.
With optional speeds on the modems.
So to really learn all this, Alex, it was actually really kind of fun because I had
to learn a lot about LTE and LTE modems that I never knew before.
And I didn't know or appreciate that there were multiple categories of LTE modems.
And each category is sort of translatable to an expected best-case scenario speed.
Well, I know there's lots of different bands available,
like different frequencies, effectively, is what that means.
Right. There's that as well.
Oh, that's different.
Yes. And also very important.
It's so crazy, Alex, because you have networks like AT&T, and they have this super hodgepodge
network where they have got different bands in different areas, and it's very uncommon.
And then you have a carrier like Verizon, who in comparison has a much more kind of streamlined
network, a more maybe custom or intentionally built network.
But no, the category of the modem, to really kind of just make it just super approachable,
think of the category of a modem like how many antennas it has.
And each category you go up, you get more antennas.
And antennas, you could think of those as listening ears and sending ear and mouths
to the tower.
And the more antennas you have, the faster the connection is.
And it could be really common for a cell phone to have two or even like four antennas like
in the iPhone 12 now.
And in certain scenarios, you can utilize all those antennas at once.
And each one of them could be potentially 20, 30 megabits.
So I needed something that was pretty high end.
I had to find that sweet spot between ridiculous money, because this is something you could
spend ridiculous money on, and something that was performant enough that I could actually
notice a difference when I went through all this hassle.
And so I ended up with something that's called a category 12 modem.
And that has somewhere around a maximum transfer speed on LTE of around 603 megabits, potentially
if your LTE network could handle that.
So you could go as far up as a gigabit with some of these modems, but the cost just exponentially
grows.
So I went right there in the middle.
Some systems have what's called a category four, some have all these different categories.
At the end of the day, you have to kind of pick and choose.
And when you start getting into this, you have to start learning what these terms mean.
So I wrapped my head around all of that, and I got myself a dual cat 12 modem.
So I have two cellular LTE modems, each of which are capable of around 600 megabits,
given the proper LTE connectivity.
So do those things support GSM and CDMA?
GSM and CDMA are a different set of technologies.
This is all LTE.
And then within LTE, like you touched on earlier, there's a ton of different bands that you
could get that have their various pros and cons.
That's interesting, because when I unboxed my OnePlus 8T last week, I put my Verizon
SIM into it, and it said this device is CDMA-less, and I'm like, uh-oh, and then it just activated
just fine.
So does that mean that CDMA is not really a thing anymore?
Right.
Yeah, Verizon was the bigger CDMA carrier, and they've transitioned to LTE.
Fascinating.
And of course, 5G is just around the corner, right?
So there's also that math.
I had to look at getting a technology that was sufficiently performant, but was sort
of established and reliable enough that I felt comfortable putting it in my RV.
I sort of treat the RV like a boat, and I don't always go for the absolute crazy, latest
and greatest.
Like when I put my lithium and solar system in, I got a really nice system, but there
are crazier, newer, higher-tech systems that are coming out now.
But I kind of go for one generation back that's gotten really good, gotten a lot of market
adoption and really worked out a lot of the bugs, and then I put that into the RV.
And that's what these transits are.
This Pep Wave is built for public use on transit, on a bus, in a plane, where you have maybe
even up to 100 people using Wi-Fi off of this thing and then using its LTE connection.
And it is this particular line, the MAX line for these transit devices, are ruggedized
for harsh environments.
They're built to be going down the road bumping, and they're built to be powered directly off
of DC or AC if you need.
And so they're like for a home use, they're just up to the line of overkill without actually
being overkill for my particular use case.
So I'm just looking at this picture you have in the show notes of the device itself, and
there are lots of antenna holes and serial and console and power inputs and Ethernet
jacks and all the rest of it.
So what do you need to put on the outside of your bus and stuff like that?
So you can hook up antennas directly to the ports that it comes with, and you're going
to get something that's way faster than any Wi-Fi.
You're going to get something that's screaming fast, and that's how I use it right now.
But in about two weeks, I'm going to get the seven in one antenna installed on the roof.
I'm going to have to drill a hole, which I'm very nervous about through my roof, and that
will bring in external antenna into this guy, and I'll take off the little antenna that
I have installed on it, and I will hook up the wires from the external antenna.
That'll give me even more performance because it's outside the metal box.
It has multiple antennas in it, and it'll probably give me about a 5 dB gain in cellular
signal, which is huge.
That's a massive gain.
So your before speeds were what, and what are you hoping to get with this new antenna?
So right now, with the current setup that I have where I'm just using the built-in antennas,
I'm getting somewhere between real world, it depends on the carrier, but 60 to 90 megabits,
which is pretty great.
That's good.
Yeah.
I'm pretty happy with that.
It's enough where you combine it with some of the other features this thing has, and
it's really freaking cool.
Let me tell you about the really freaking cool stuff.
So I guess one other disclaimer is you've got to pay for the LTE, right?
So I have an unlimited AT&T SIM in this thing, and I have an unlimited Verizon SIM in this
thing.
And then I have a Google Fi data-only SIM, which are awesome, by the way, if you're a
Google Fi customer.
You just get a data SIM and just pay for its usage.
I have that as a failover device.
Oh.
Yeah.
I'm going to do that.
Catherine has a Pixel with Fi.
I need a SIM card for my iPad.
I didn't know you could do that.
Yeah.
You've got to be a current Fi customer to get it.
Well, she is.
I'm going to do that.
Thank you for that tip.
It's pretty great.
So the peplink itself runs their own OS.
They put a super nice processor in this.
It's very fast.
I have no complaints about performance, which is not an easy bar for me.
I'm pretty sensitive to slow-loading admin pages and whatnot.
But one of the things that pushed me over the link on going with this setup versus what
I had before, which originally was a travel slate router, and then I kind of replaced
that with a Raspberry Pi 4 that was doing kind of a bonded VPN sort of, which worked.
But I needed something that was 100%, something that I could rely to run a security system,
something that if I'm not home and my kids are home and they're doing school, I don't
have to get a frantic call from my wife saying the internet's gone down again and I walk
her through rebooting a MiFi.
I wanted it rock solid.
And one of the things that they build into this, you have to pay for it, but it's what
they call speed fusion technology.
And it is a bonding VPN that very, very cleverly bonds your two LTE connections.
And it's aware of the data going over both and it's aware of the individual performance
characteristics of each connection.
And it will intelligently balance and bond these two connections into one.
So how does that work with stuff like cookies and things like that?
Because I've often run into this issue, well, this used to be something I did when I was
back in college.
We used to flash a couple of cable modems with a spoofed Mac address and we used PF
Sense with multi WANs and that caused loads of issues when it did a round robin balance
between different connections, different WAN connections.
Does this kind of have like a sticky feature?
Well, the way it is really working is what it's doing is their own custom source VPN.
So your endpoint is what all of the client websites and services see as your IP.
Oh, that's smart.
Yeah, I like that.
The downside is you have to either pay them to host it, which they offer multiple servers
across various VPS providers that they've abstracted throughout everywhere.
There's also other companies that are now around that just offer VPN endpoints for these
routers because they're pretty common in industrial use.
And so there's a good amount of enterprise customers out there that are willing to pay
$200 a month for something like this, which is mind boggling to me because it's really
just a VPN.
And you've got these people that are charging $150 to $200 a month for the service.
They do allow you and they have different licensing options.
Some are more affordable than others to just self host as well.
That's very cool.
What's the VPN tech they're using?
Is it WireGuard or OpenVPN?
I wonder if it's OpenVPN.
I haven't dug super deep into it.
I did grab their self hosted VM image and I am in the process of testing that so I may
be able to figure that out.
I don't know if I will.
They layer a lot of their own like signaling tech on top of it.
So whatever it is, it's unique in that sense.
Like for example, they have this technology that they call WAN smoothing, which duplicates
packets, which sounds like it would take bandwidth, but stick with me for a second.
And they call this forward error correction.
It sends additional reserve packets, which can be used to mitigate the effects of packet
loss via interpolation.
The actual practical use case of that is your video calls are rock solid over LTE.
And so I'm doing video calls, I'm using this connection for, I went off into the woods
and there's a spot that is on a farm that is, you know, at least a hundred acres.
And I don't know what it is about this spot.
Well, actually I do know is on the Hill above, I actually saw it this trip.
This is the third time I've been there and I finally found the cell tower and it's just,
it's a beautiful line of sight cell tower to the camping spot.
And I get 90 megabits on LTE.
And it's just it, when you have a device that can handle very high performance LTE and it
can handle 30, 40 wifi clients, which is what I actually have.
And it can, it could manage all of this intelligently and it can determine, well, if you send something
to Verizon and you're waiting for it to come back, I'll use the AT&T line.
Like it figures all of that out for you.
It's really nice.
Man.
I need, I think I need that in my house.
I mean, spectrum is just rubbish.
So I put a link in the show notes.
It wasn't fantastic.
It wasn't, it wasn't amazing that I could still, I could still see some compression,
but I played Red Dead Redemption over Stadia in the woods on an LTE connection.
Wow.
You are living in the future.
That's fantastic.
It was really good.
I mean, there's some latency issues time.
And every now and then I got a message from Stadia saying your connection is not that
great, but it, you know, it works pretty solid.
I don't think you are probably their target market when they, when they invented Stadia.
No, no, I don't think so.
The other thing that's just absolutely been brilliant and it was one of those why factors,
you know, I do this change and she's like, yeah, it seems faster, right?
But you're like, oh my God, like I put all this, I put all this time into research and
spent a fair chunk of change on this thing and did all of this work to get it installed.
You know, I had to switch over our DNS, I had to switch up our DHCP.
I had to take out devices, you know, replace my SSID.
Like I really, you know, put a lot into this thing.
And her first response was it's kind of faster until we sat down and watched YouTube.
And you have to understand how this works to fully appreciate this.
On AT&T, YouTube gets slammed to 480p.
It basically puts up a wall and the client, the YouTube client just smacks his head into
that wall until it finally settles on 480p and then it streams you mud essentially.
And it's annoying because you just sit there and the YouTube video player just spins while
it has this confrontation with AT&T and then you get your crappy result.
That's one of the reasons I love YouTube DL because I just download this stuff and watch
it offline.
Love YouTube DL with all this hoopla going on.
I have faith.
Yeah, me too.
But I'll tell you what, when you're going over the bonded VPN, AT&T has no idea what
you're doing and YouTube doesn't care.
And so the video starts immediately and it's full 1080p, beautiful, crispy, just boom.
And so the wife and I were sitting there on the couch and we pull up YouTube to watch
some of the creators that we follow and we hit play on that video and she goes, whoa,
it's like we got a brand new TV.
The picture quality just skyrocketed and that she noticed.
And that, you know, when you're doing that once or twice a week, three times a week,
whatever you're doing, like that kind of thing, it's like a quality of life improvement that
she noticed.
And then that kind of built on that and then she started noticing other things and now
she loves it.
And the very clever thing that this thing does, Alex, is it sets the bonded VPN on its
own SSID.
So you get a new wireless access point on your LAN and you join that and everything's
the same.
You're on the same LAN, same IP space, same DHCP server, same DNS, except for your default
route.
I'm not sure how they handle DNS in this case, but your default route gets set to the bonded
VPN.
So you have these, you have this new AP and you can put certain hosts on that AP and they
go out the bonded VPN and everybody else just goes out the balanced connection, which that
just automatically balances.
So you just put the televisions on the bonded VPN and boom, streaming is just magic now,
buttery smooth.
It's so great.
It reminds me a lot like when we did the solar and lithium battery upgrade last year and
it just changed everything because now all of a sudden we always had power and all of
our outlets, we went from having three outlets that worked when we were on battery and having
two lead acid batteries and then two lithium batteries.
Now we went to 600 amp hours of lithium and solar and it just changed everything.
We could leave our smart lights on the automations and home assistant could be completely changed.
It was a massive quality of life upgrade and it feels similar to that.
It's just another huge improvement and for the kids, it just means everything works just
like all the outlets work and we always can turn lights on and all of that and we can,
we can leave a TV going if we want.
Now the internet just works because if AT&T is having problems, it just switches to Verizon
and Verizon's having problems, it switches to Google Fi and it just sorts it all out
without me ever having to touch it.
You have such a wonderfully unique set of problems to solve in an RV, don't you?
What about Starlink though?
Isn't that going to change the game in a year or two?
I hope, you know, I really, I hope it's maybe in a year.
I don't know.
We'll see.
I imagine the last thing they're going to support is RVs because right now if you're
a Starlink beta customer in the EULA, it says that you have to use the Starlink service
where you signed up and I don't know if they're doing like geo checking or not, you know,
maybe they sure could be and so in there it says you use it where you signed up and I
think, I don't know, maybe it's, maybe they don't have the tech right on repositioning
the satellite when you move or something like that and the other thing to think about Starlink
is it won't be usable while you're going down the road or if there's a lot of tree coverage.
So I think this will still fill those gaps in even once Starlink arrives.
Have you ever gone outside and watched the Starlink trainer satellites go over?
It's pretty cool.
I have never seen it.
Every time I look on a night sky on my phone, it's always underneath me.
It's awesome.
I'll tell you what, we went out a few weeks ago and every, you know, 10 seconds or so
there's another satellite goes over and they're just all in a long line and it's just, it's
amazing and you think to yourself, well, okay, now I've got visibility of that satellite
for maybe a minute as it goes over and then you know that they've got like some kind of
mesh network between them and communicating so that they're doing some kind of like zero
handoff type style thing between the satellites.
It's very cool.
Crazy cool.
They're doing a lot of beta testing here in Washington state.
So I've been getting little bits of information and you know, people are seeing decent speeds
20 millisecond ping time, which is doable and a hundred megabits on a, on a good night
of unlimited data.
Yeah.
My, my, my worry really is that, you know, satellite is very, very easily disrupted by
weather or trees or something like that, you know, so yeah, a cable is always going to
be better, but you know, it could open up possibilities for new economies of, of people
moving to rural Montana and stuff and working, you know, for a Facebook or an Apple or a
Google or whoever or a red hat.
Oh, it's my dream.
It's my dream.
Yeah, man.
Me too.
Like, I mean, I live in Raleigh right now, but you know, there's no reason besides the,
you know, social things that you can do here.
Like you can go to the cinema and well, not the moment, but anyway, you get the idea,
right?
Like we live in cities, but there are also reasons to kind of think about that fully
remote off-grid style lifestyle, but there's also that kind of middle ground of I'm going
to live within half an hour's drive of a town and then, you know, have a few acres to myself
and, you know, I think I would love that.
I would love that.
I just spent Thursday through Sunday off-grid, you know, it's funny because when we started
the show, I, the, the RV was just not off-grid capable, right?
And you remember I launched project off-grid and yeah, and now I'm living it.
We went off into the woods and it is, it's about 45 minutes from town.
It is very remote.
It's you don't see another soul.
It's a giant forest you can walk around in and there's, you know, there's wildlife, there's
bears and there's, there's things like that to be aware of.
But when I'm out there at this, this time, it made me realize, I think I could pull this
off on an ongoing basis.
Like, I think I could buy a chunk of land that didn't have utilities and I could live
there.
I would probably build a little shed with solar and some additional supplemental batteries.
So maybe I could double my battery capacity while I was there and I might need an extra
large propane tank for the winter.
But outside of that, I have, as long as I have cell signal now and it's reasonable to
get into town or Starlink, right?
It's getting really close.
It's happening.
I saw an article, I don't know what website it was on, maybe New York Times or something,
where Bozeman, Montana is seeing, you know, 16% year over year real estate price growth.
Yeah.
I went to Bozeman just a few months ago and I go every year, I went twice this year and
it is just, even during Corona with lockdowns, it has, it has changed every year significantly
and it's going through major growth.
I talked to a real estate agent at a pizza place, of all things, I'm sitting there eating
pizza and I'm talking to a owner of a business at the pizza place and I'm talking to the
real estate agent and he said, the thing he said is that people are getting these places
and they're just kind of doing the off-grid lifestyle and they're doing exactly what you're
talking about.
And you know, I am thinking, you know, it could happen.
I mean, a year ago I was just figuring out how to even use solar and now I just basically
spent nearly a week off-grid loving it.
So it just has to have connectivity, but with Starlink it changes it.
And I really debated, should I build this towards 5G?
Because that's an example of a decision where I could have gone a little more cutting edge
here and because you could build a 5G system that's still fully LTE capable.
And this speaks to what you said a few minutes ago of, you know, you're using the version
of the tech that is, you know, not the latest and greatest that's got all the bugs worked
out and that's what LTE is right now.
Yeah.
And it's got the most durable gear, the stuff that's built to go into industrial grade operations.
The reality is if I could start getting ideal LTE connectivity, if I can start getting a
hundred megabits on LTE, you know, and the system's capable of dual 600, but if I can
get even a hundred megabits, that's plenty really.
It's just the cost of those plans, right?
Yes.
Yeah, exactly.
And maybe that changes as time goes on, you know, you go down the road five years from
now when LTE will still be around, but the majority is now everyone's on 5G just because
that's what all the phones have that are in operation.
Maybe they, maybe they stop being such jerks about data usage on LTE.
Maybe they don't really care.
That's what happened with the edge network for years.
Like edge went on for a decade and they just started letting people have full access to
the edge network.
And you started seeing all these little devices, little tracker devices and whatnot show up
that used edge with unlimited data.
And maybe that could happen.
And then, you know, be a perfect, you know, three, four or five years from now would be
a perfect time to upgrade the system.
Linode.com slash SSH.
You go there to support the show and receive a $100 60 day credit towards your new account.
This episode of self-hosted is sponsored by Linode.
The world's largest independent cloud for developers.
Simplify your cloud infrastructure with Linode's Linux virtual machines and tools to develop,
deploy and scale applications easier and faster than ever.
I've been using Linode for over two years.
I started right after I sold Jupiter broadcasting and I wanted to just separate work stuff and
personal stuff.
But then as we started to go independent again and I needed a lot of infrastructure fast
and I mean, really it was a serious undertaking, Linode was my obvious choice.
They started in 2003 as one of the first companies in cloud computing.
So they really know what they're doing.
That's three years before AWS.
And they're independently owned and founded that entire time.
And you know that this is a good sign when it's a company that got into this business
because they saw the technology that was being built into the Linux kernel and they knew
what they could do with that and they started a company around that.
I think that's really something special.
And they've built such a manageable and usable system now with their cloud dashboard.
I'm not going to spend hours and hours learning how to manage these systems.
I can go in there and it's really easy to use.
You don't have to have a very high skill level.
But if you want, you can do everything through SSH.
You get full access unlike entry level hosting services that lock you into their platform.
It gives you full back end access to customize and control your server.
So if you want it, it's there.
And if Kubernetes is your thing, maybe you want to centralize your management a little
bit, Linode's managed Kubernetes engine is simple and the pricing is simple.
You only pay for what you use.
And there's no management fees like AWS charges for their Kubernetes implementation.
And with Linode's 99.9% SLA, you know you're going to be set.
You know you're going to be okay with your infrastructure.
That's why I run everything on there.
And if you're going for something that you want that's customer facing, you've got a
lot of great options from node balancers to object storage, different tools you can use
to really make your performance super fast.
Or maybe you just want to build something for yourself or for your family, an online
gallery or a blog.
Linode's got plans that make that really easy to starting at $5 a month.
But if you go to linode.com slash SSH, you're going to get a $100 60 day credit.
I'd encourage you to play with something with some horsepower.
It's a great opportunity to learn too.
Go build a website just as an experiment.
Check out their stack scripts.
It's a great way to get a really nice base WordPress setup up and going.
And they've got a couple of options depending on if you want NGINX or Apache, and of course
you've got all the different distros to choose from.
So go check that out too.
It's a great way to get up and going.
And with 11 data centers worldwide, you're going to find just the right spot to deploy
something that's going to be either close to you or close to your clients.
So go over to linode.com slash SSH.
Receive that $100 60 day credit towards your new account and support the show.
And simplify your cloud life.
Linode's been around since 2003, and they're dedicated to offering the best virtualized
cloud computing.
If it runs on Linux, you can run it on Linode.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Big thank you Linode for sponsoring the show.
Go get your $100 60 day credit, linode.com slash SSH.
And with some feedback, do you think?
Yeah, it's been a little bit.
And now that we're in our early thirties, we got to start paying attention to these
kinds of things.
Alex.
Early thirties.
Sure.
Wink, wink.
Squirrely wrote in.
He says, uh, this is on discord by the way.
I have six, eight terabyte drives at the moment, but I just picked up two 12 terabyte drives
on sale.
Nice.
What are some options for how to incorporate these new drives into my environment?
I have the eight terabyte drives protected via a single snap rate parody set up right
now, but I'm curious as to whether this is still the best route in 2020.
The vast majority of my stuff on my NAS is replaceable via media.
So I was thinking about putting the truly important stuff on a mirror or something that
will also get backed up with something like Backblaze.
What are your thoughts, gentlemen?
Interesting question.
Yeah.
So we had this discussion a little bit on, on discord, but I thought it was going to
be useful to relay this to the audience as well.
And there's a few different routes you can go.
So you're already using snap rate and the process of adding new disks to snap rate is,
is quite straightforward until you start to mess around with drive sizes.
Like you have here, you know, you had six, eight terabyte drives and now you've changed
and added a couple of 12 terabyte drives.
One of the requirements of snap rate is that your parity disk has to be as large or larger
than your largest data disk.
So currently your parity drive is an eight terabyte drive.
You're going to have to swap that out to be one of these new 12 terabyte drives.
So what that means is that you're effectively giving up a little bit of space to parity
in the short term, but as you expand and buy more 12 terabyte disks over the next year
or two, you'll be able to add those into the snap rate array for want of a better word.
And that should just work just fine.
So that's an important consideration, but the last part of your questions is, is about
should I put stuff on a mirror or, or have something backed up with, with backblaze what's
important to remember is that raid or snap raid or any kind of parity system, whether
it's ZFS or whatever, is no replacement for a real backup.
Raid is not backup.
We've pushed this mantra for years as a community and I just want to implore you to, you know,
remember that parity is not, raid is not a backup.
So having an offsite is, is absolutely something I would suggest, you know, you could do the,
the G suite hack, although there was some news about that is changing the terms of service
with G suite stuff is changing.
So we'll dig into that more in a future episode, but you know, backblaze do offer some really
competitive prices for backups.
So that's a really good option as well.
There's, there's loads of other backup services as well, but make sure you have an offsite
backup would be a recommendation of mine.
Then the other option that you've got is to do what I do, which is I have a kind of a
JBOD array of disks with merger FS, which are all of, you know, eight to 10 terabytes
in size.
And then I have a pair of drives, which are ZFS, which are mirrored.
And then I combine that mirror into the merger FS pool of, of drives using a, a specific
mount point.
And as a blog post I've written on this, which is in the show notes.
And so essentially what it allows me to do is keep my photos and my drone footage and
the stuff that I can't reacquire that stuff stays on ZFS and is, you know, using a Sanoid.
I mirror that to my parents' houses, stuff like that.
And it gives me huge peace of mind.
As I said, a couple of episodes ago, when I woke up and my ZFS array was blank, I was
just like, Oh, she's annoying rather than, uh, I've actually lost data.
So that's an important thing to consider as well.
But when you're looking at the number of drives you have, you know, you've got six eights
and two twelves.
If you were to do a ZFS mirror with the two twelves that you have, if you do the math
behind it, you're actually going to keep the same amount of available usable space by doing
it that way.
So my suggestion certainly to start with would probably be do a mirror of ZFS, free up some
space on the, uh, the eight terabytes by moving some stuff off of that onto a new mirror that
you've created and then, you know, uh, add drives as you see fit to the snap rate side
of things.
For my perishable data, it's like inconvenient to lose, but not going to wreck my life.
I accomplished this through Butterfess.
For better or worse, I find Butterfess to be a great way to manage this and you can
just add mixed sized volumes to an existing mount point.
You just plug it in and you add the volume.
It's a really simple, straightforward process, but there's no redundancy there unless you
do underlying rate.
Tasty too.
Yes.
Very much so.
So let's talk about a ZigBee future because Chris L wrote in about something that's been
on my mind.
He's been listening from the start, he says, and it's rich in all sorts of fabulous ideas,
but ones that you've actually worked out, not just ones that you're theorizing about.
To some degree, there's a little bit of both, I'd say.
He said, I wanted to comment about episode 24, open makes sense.
There are some discussion in there about Z-Wave.
I think Chris commented that Z-Wave is used less and less as embedded devices have switched
more to Wi-Fi.
While this may be true, I thought I would share comments from a man who fitted the smart
meter last month at my house, which is currently being rolled out across the UK.
He goes on to say the different meters like gas and electric and the monitoring station
all talk to each other on ZigBee, the open standard cousin of Z-Wave.
And the central point he made is that the SIM card sends the data over a mobile network
to the energy supplier.
The main point being the Zmesh technologies are not being used less, but more as these
meters are battery powered and expected to survive in service for a long time.
Thanks for everything.
Looking forward to the next show.
Also, he didn't mention this, but the new round Amazon Echo, I think has ZigBee built
into it as well.
Is that part of being a central like home automation hub type thing?
Yeah.
So it can control the ZigBee devices.
I agree, and I have ZigBee abilities on my home assistant.
I even got a little ZigBee to MQTT adapter, which is pretty rad.
However, in actual practical production, I found Z-Wave to work better.
And you guys know me, I'm always going to go with the open standard first.
That's why I went the ZigBee to MQTT route first.
But having several devices, I have found Z-Wave to be iron clad, rock solid.
Like I can have devices that have been missing from the network for three or four months,
come back online and it sorts itself out and rebuilds the mesh network and everything's
just working.
I love it.
And I would love to see ZigBee be just as good and reliable.
And maybe as more vendors get serious about it and start to use it, that just happens
over time.
I don't currently have anything on the Z-Wave or ZigBee trains besides my Hue lights, I
don't think.
Right.
Yeah, they use ZigBee, don't they?
On the back end.
There are things like that, that are consumer, quote unquote, products, but are actually
just using ZigBee.
The other notable new addition to the smart home communications world is Thread, which
the new HomePod Mini support and Iroh Wi-Fi access points support.
And Thread is another industry standard, open, low power communications technology that has
been around for a while, just like ZigBee has, but more and more recently seems to be
getting adoption by the mainstream vendors.
It's a weird world out there.
So there may be more to come in low powered communications outside of just Bluetooth.
Good.
Just what we need, another standard.
Yeah.
So Michael wrote in and asked us to explain our view on local versus cloud.
He says, you focus on privacy and self-hosting, but you also seem comfortable with Alexa,
Google, and the Ring doorbell.
Can you take a moment to explain the balance on a future show?
Interesting question.
We could get quite philosophical here if we were not careful.
I generally speaking try to self-host first these days, obviously being a host of the
show that's clearly now a part of the job description.
But when I'm talking with family members and people at work or just generally people on
the internet, I don't always suggest self-hosting because it comes with the overhead of you
are the admin.
Like when it goes down, as we've talked about in the last few episodes, when there's a problem,
you're the one that's got to fix it.
And sometimes that can be jolly inconvenient.
So you've got to really weigh up the trade-off that you're going to make of your time and
money and convenience and privacy.
You've got to trade all those things off against each other for the particular use case that
you're talking about.
And lighting is quite low risk, but quite rewarding to automate.
But the doors on your house, for example, if you screw up the automations there and
you get locked out or locked in, let's say, it could be even worse.
There are different situations where the cost of stuff going wrong is higher.
So when you look at the privacy angle, you are just a single data point in a sea of noise
to Amazon and Google.
So you could argue that actually it doesn't matter if you are saying to your Google homes
this, that, and the other, or your Alexa's this, that, and the other.
You could argue that nobody's listening because you are one of X number of million people
doing this.
But at the same time, there is a microphone always listening in your house and you don't
know they say what they're going to use it for.
We don't know necessarily what it's going to be used for.
So there is that to consider as well, I mean, there isn't one right answer to this question.
It's it's you have to evaluate your own risk profile for these sorts of things and figure
out what works for you and your beliefs and values.
Yeah, it's like so many things in life.
It comes down to getting the balance right.
And that balance is different for each people.
It's like dieting.
It's just different people.
A balance of intake and exercise is generally that you got to get that just right.
Yeah.
Pizza a day keeps the doctor away, right?
That's the saying.
Right.
And I think it's the same for not just cloud services, but privacy and security in general.
So there is some areas where for me, it's just it's a no brainer.
I always run a local DNS server.
The benefits of that is literally everything I do on the Internet just is just that tiny
bit faster and it feels private.
And it's something I know how to do intrinsically.
Now it's I know the ins and outs of it and I can get it going in 15 minutes.
So obvious one.
I have not hosted my own email in a decade.
It is just something that I feel like the risk profile is higher.
The attack surface is high and then the pain in the arsonist is extreme because of spam
blacklisting and all of that crap that you end up having to deal with.
And so that is something where I've made a judgment call to outsource.
Same with cloud backup.
I think it's good to have your own backup regime that's local that you can have immediate
access to.
But it makes sense to also leverage cheap cloud storage that's off site that protects
you from natural disaster, et cetera.
There is an obvious kind of balance to be had there.
And I kind of look at all of these things.
Let's to address like the ring one, for example, I think this is one where we kind of we kind
of get lost in the story a little bit and we hear stories about cops doing subpoenas
and getting a block's door camera footage and that being bad and privacy invasive.
So the reality is, is that somewhere in the middle there is a process when you have a
ring doorbell where they can request access to your footage.
You can deny or approve it via the app.
You can determine if that's a good thing or a bad thing.
And there's the privacy aspect of a third party hosting those videos as well.
And you can determine if that's a good thing or a bad thing.
And I think it all just kind of depends on your sense of the company, their risk profile
and all of that.
And that's, you know, an always moving target as well.
So if I think if you choose to host, like, say, a doorbell or something with a company
like ring, you have to continually assess the risk.
It's not something you can just look at once and continually assess.
So there's downsides to it as well beyond just the privacy aspects of it.
There's that overhead of always needing to be cognizant of what's going on and reassessing.
But the balance for me, I tend to be a little more practical, I tend to be a pragmatist
when I look at these things.
And I don't get overly concerned about the privacy story around some of these things
like others do.
But that's just different for each of us.
The other thing as well is that companies change, like Chris says, you know, look at
Nest with their works with Nest API situation, and then you end up with nine months, nearly
a year where there is no API whilst Google figures out what they're doing with Nest and,
you know, companies get bought and acquired and closed down and change priorities and
focus all the time and, you know, you've just got to bear in mind that if you buy a product
now that is subsidized with a cloud subscription or something like that, there is no incentive
for that company, unless you're paying them money every month to keep offering that service.
And sometimes even if you are paying them, it's not enough to be sustainable.
So well said, the only constant with your self-hosted home is going to be that things
are going to change.
Yeah.
I mean, I think it's like you said earlier, it's always preferable if I can, if it's
something that my business relies on or something that is really critical to me, something I'm
really concerned about the privacy, like my internal cameras to my RV are completely disconnected
from the cloud.
I think that's where self-hosting can play a really significant role, especially for
businesses.
I think that's something businesses should think a lot about.
Yeah.
There's no reason the internet needs to see Chris walking around in his robe, is there?
No, no, no, there's not.
And the other thing too is the other line I sometimes consider is, would I deploy this
if it wasn't all like a cloud provided service?
If, you know, they didn't take care of all of the implementation details, would I ever
get around to doing this?
And that's something I consider as well.
Datadog.com slash self-hosted, today's episode of self-hosted is sponsored by Datadog.
The unified monitoring platform for real time observability and detailed insights into Docker
performance and more.
Enhance visibility into container orchestration with live container view and easily detect
clusters that are consuming excessive resources using auto-generated container maps.
Out of the box, Datadog will collect critical metrics from each Docker container so you
can get immediate visibility into aggregated and dis-aggregated service level traffic.
Try Datadog today, starting with a free 14 day trial and receive a Datadog t-shirt after
creating just one dashboard.
Visit datadog.com slash self-hosted to get started, get that 14 day free trial, support
the show and get a free t-shirt, datadog.com slash self-hosted.
I actually still have a Datadog t-shirt from DockerCon Europe 2015, I think.
That's great.
I've definitely picked up swag from the Datadog booth at a few events.
You know, I've used Datadog just from a keeping track of systems and metrics standpoint, but
I like this new stuff they have for containers too.
So go check them out if you haven't tried Datadog before, datadog.com slash self-hosted.
So following up on a previous episode where I talked about the new Chromecast with Google
TV, they've released an ethernet adapter, which turns out is a bag of crap.
Oh, really? Because it looks so slick.
Yeah.
Well, I was watching a YouTube video yesterday, so I haven't personally tested it out.
It's just based on a YouTube video, but the ethernet speeds are capped at 100 meg.
Stop it.
Not even gigabit.
Yep.
Apparently so.
I'm looking at the specs.
You're right.
Now in reality, is that going to be an issue?
It's 2020.
Why are we putting up with a device that isn't gigabit?
It probably saves Google a few pennies from using a gigabit adapter instead of a megabit
adapter.
What they've done here that's super neat, though, is it looks just like a standard tiny
white USB-C power adapter, but on the side of it, it has an ethernet port.
So you plug the ethernet into the power adapter and then it all comes back up one USB-C cable
to the Chromecast.
I also saw a guy doing like a USB-C hub and it had a power delivery because the Chromecast
needs 7.5 watts.
You have to have a power delivery-supportable hub to put that much juice through it.
And the gigabit speeds were not capable of gigabit either.
So I don't know if there's some performance limitation on the USB bus inside the Chromecast
because he was getting about 300 megabits from his Wi-Fi connection using AC Wi-Fi,
but then he used ethernet through USB-C, not even the actual official Chromecast adapter,
and he was only getting something like 180 to 200 meg.
So it was actually slower in both cases being wired, which is just wrong.
It just dawned on me that we just assume it's USB 3 because it's a USB-C connector in there,
but maybe they saved money and put USB 2 in the thing.
That's got to be it, hasn't it?
That's got to be the answer.
It could be.
Oh, Google.
Let me ask you this, though.
Seriously, is a hundred megabit wired connection not still better though than Wi-Fi for what
you're doing with this thing?
Yeah, I guess it depends.
I mean, Google have engineered this thing to be on Wi-Fi.
Ninety nine percent of customers will use it on Wi-Fi, haven't they?
So I don't know.
I've not noticed any performance difference between my wired shield and my Wi-Fi Chromecast.
It's right.
It's like if you're not going to get gigabit, then might as well just keep using N. It's
pretty good.
Mm hmm.
Yeah.
I will.
Bart writes in with potential pick replacement for you, too.
So this is our last email and it also is going to be a bit of a pick.
He says, hello, friends.
Thanks for the show.
It helps me get a great deal of home automation ideas for my home.
I've been looking for Chromecast alternatives, though, and lo and behold, quite recently
someone came up with this beauty.
It's called Nymphcast.
Seemed right up the self-hosted crowd alley.
I for one certainly am going to build it and take it for a spin with my Pi zeros I have
in a drawer somewhere.
So this thing is essentially a build it yourself using Raspberry Pi zero stream audio and video
anywhere around your house using any Linux system.
Kind of like a universal DIY Chromecast.
That is super cool.
I think we've needed something like this for quite a long time.
Yeah, I like this because it's not just something that's like figuring out the Chromecast protocols
and using that.
But this is a full fledged open replacement and it seems surprisingly well thought out
and further along than I would think.
It's really in-depth.
It's an alpha stage right now, but you can download the server binaries from GitHub.
Yeah.
I've designed Linux images too, so I could see this being really easy to container up
if it isn't already and just have the server running as a container on your media box.
And we'll have a link to that in the show notes at self-hosted.show slash 31.
And I want to say thank you to our self-hosted site reliability engineers who keep this show
online and going.
They also get a limited ad feed and they get extra content every episode, a post show.
If you'd like to support the show, help us stay independent and be choosy about who sponsors.
Sign up at self-hosted.show slash SRE.
Yeah.
Big thank you guys.
Thank you very much.
Yeah.
As always, you can go to self-hosted.show slash contact to get in touch with us.
You can find me on Twitter at ironic badger.
And I'm there at Chris Elias and the show is at self-hosted show.
Thanks very much for listening everybody.
That was self-hosted dot show slash 31.