Coming up on today's show, I give you my thoughts on the new Helios 64 Ultimate Arm Powered NAS.
And Chris has a huge sack full of your feedback.
Okay, I'm Chris and this is Self Hosted 33.
After last week's episode, everyone got the impression that both you and I
were iOS users exclusively, but that's not actually the case.
I am a whore to different OSes, Chris.
I use Linux, Mac OS, Windows, Android, iOS on a daily basis.
So I think I don't think I fall into that camp of being pigeonholed as an iOS user.
I'm trying not to be offended, but it's hard.
Well, you know what it was is because we were talking about audiobooks
and we didn't mention any audio players for Android.
We only mentioned them for iOS.
That was just that was my bad.
I'll tell you why that is.
It's just simply because booksonics been so reliable for my wife that
I didn't feel the need to try anything else.
But there's some really good options that some listeners have sent in.
Yeah, we'll link to those in the show notes for the for the Android
ones that got at least a couple of mentioned via the email.
I also have an Android and iPhone, but I do.
I do mostly mostly use the iPhone, but I do love my pixel three.
It is time for an upgrade.
I'm just not in a particular rush, but I am in a rush to tell you about a cloud guru.
This episode is brought to you by the all new cloud guru.
The leader in learning for cloud Linux and other modern tech skills.
They have hundreds of courses and thousands of hands on labs.
So get certified, get hired and get learning.
Go to a cloud guru dot com.
I feel like our roles have reversed this episode.
This Helio 64 hardware you're about to tell me about seems like something I would have bought.
And it like would have been the natural upgrade from a Raspberry Pi
four days to something a little more hardcore.
So I'm extremely interested to know what your experience has been like with the with the Helio 64.
And is it.
Cobal, is that how you say the company?
Cobal, I guess.
Yeah, like the element.
Yeah, this this thing builds itself as the ultimate arm powered NAS.
And Cobal is the name of the company behind it.
You can find them at cobalt dot IO and they have a couple of products.
But the one that I picked up was the Helios 64.
Now this thing purports to be, as it says, the ultimate arm powered NAS.
It has five hotswap SATA 3 bays.
It has an M2 SATA port.
It supports hot plug for those drives.
It's got two gigabit Ethernet ports, one of which is two point five gigabit USB-C.
It's got a micro SD card slot, a couple of USB ports,
and it's no bigger than, you know, your average Synology type box.
OK, so it's about Synology size.
I was just going to ask you that.
It also has eMMC for storage.
And then I understand it's a hexacore processor,
but I don't really know what that actually means in terms of real world performance.
Yeah, so I'll come on to all that later.
But six core system on a chip arm.
Wow.
System four gigs of RAM.
The eMMC is 16 gigabytes.
You know, Alex, if this thing performs half as good as the specs sound,
I'm going to be pretty impressed.
We'll get there.
One feature I thought was just unbelievably cool and just shows the power efficiency of arm
is this thing has a built in UPS.
It's got a pair of 18650 cell batteries in there.
You don't know how cool this is.
You just you have a NAS on your desk.
You unplug it from the wall and the thing just stays running for 15 minutes.
You pick it up and walk around the house with it.
I mean, that is that is great.
I mean, I'm not going to do that because I need a network cable and stuff.
But in terms of money, I mean, you look at how much you could spend on just a UPS.
That's easily a hundred or two for a decent one, you know, and to have that built into this unit
for the ticket price of $295, which didn't include shipping.
I think I paid about $330 for it to be shipped overall.
The proposition is great.
It also has a direct attached storage mode as well as a USB type C display mode.
So in the promo materials, at least, they show it hooked up to your TV running Kodi,
which I thought was a really interesting use case.
That could be nice if, you know, the budget only allows for one machine.
Yeah, absolutely.
Now, I'll come on to my impressions in a second.
But first of all, I wanted to let the audience know that this thing is it's a little DIY.
So when it when it arrived, it was a kit.
It was a box with baggies full of screws and drive trays and stuff.
It's not fully assembled and the assembly took me about two hours or so.
And that's on top of about a three month lead time for ordering it.
So I'd waited, I think I ordered at the end of August and when I ordered,
it told me it was going to be delivered in September.
September came and went and I looked on the website and it's silently updated.
To October, October came and went and silently updated to shipping soon.
And then it went on the slow boat from China.
So it took literally like felt like forever, you know, left China.
And you don't hear from it again for weeks.
And then suddenly this box shows up at my door and I'm like, oh, yeah, I ordered this thing ages ago.
Yep.
And if you go to the website right now, it doesn't say buy, it says preorder.
So it's like another batch is coming.
Yes.
I think they're sold out of the batch that I have here, which is, I think, the first one.
Now, what I will say is that the machined aluminum housing that it comes in is gorgeous.
The outside, the look of it, sat on a shelf.
This thing looks really premium.
I love how it looks.
The downside to it, to them being a, an upstart in the kind of case manufacturing world is there's
a lot of rough edges and I mean, literally it drew blood in the odd place because there
are so many sharp edges to just to catch you.
It's like building a, a computer was 15 years ago before people like Fractal came along and
really stepped up the game.
So absolutely the outside looks great.
And you know, sat on a shelf, which is where it's going to spend 99% of its life.
It's, it's a huge thumbs up, but they have cut some corners in several very important
areas. If you look at the product picture on the website, the front IO panel has what
looks like a laser etched, you know, um, power button and reset button and, you know, HDD
number one through five with little leds for LAN and USB.
That looks like it's a laser etched led kind of front panel, right?
It's a sticker, isn't it?
It's a sticker.
Yep.
Yeah.
And it's on this flimsy little PCB that's held in with a couple of small screws and
if you push too hard, the entire thing, the sticker is stuck to kind of flexes and moves,
which makes this ultra premium, beautiful aluminum chassis feel like it should cost
a fraction of what it does.
So that's disappointing.
The same is also true of the rear IO panel.
There are stickers there that go over the, um, the panel there.
So in future revisions, I would love to see actual laser etching because I know that stuff
doesn't come for free, but I think that is going to make a huge difference to the overall
quality of the product, just the fit and finish.
If it bumped the price to another 50 bucks, would it be worth it too?
I'm not sure.
I mean, I'm going to come onto the price at the end, I think, um, once you've heard the
overall impression, you're just teasing it out.
I got you now.
Another thing, uh, that is a bit tricky is once you finally got it assembled, which as
I say was a bit fiddly and took about two hours, they do have fantastic documentation.
I just want to say that upfront wiki.cobol.io is built around MK docs, one of my favorite
self-hosted wiki solutions and the quality of the documentation and the open schematics
they have on there for all of the, you know, SATA controllers and the way that different
things connect to each other and stuff.
It's great, you know, um, and I'm, there's, there's a lot this company have done, right?
So I want to just preface everything I'm about to say by saying most of it is good, but there's
just a few other problems with it.
So let's go on to installing the operating system.
This isn't simple.
So you have to flash the OS to the eMMC via a USB-C cable, uh, which you do using, you
know, Balena Etcher or something like that.
That's not too difficult, really, but it could be easier.
It could be a USB key that you flash, which we're a lot more used to.
They are making use of the direct USB-C attachment to do that.
So once you've got the drivers installed into windows, which is what I was using, it's not
too bad, but I can just imagine trying to talk my family through it over the phone or
something as that's not going to work.
The next thing is that once you've put the OS onto the eMMC, you think to yourself, right,
I just press go and it's going to also configure and appear on the network.
Well, not quite.
You have to use something like PuTTY to connect to a serial console and do some initial
Ambient configuration before it will boot and get a network IP address.
Can you give me an idea of what kind of Ambient configuration you have to do there?
That's getting in the weeds pretty quick, it sounds like.
Yeah, if you've ever installed a Raspberry Pi one or something, you know, back in the
day, you know, a lot of these things had wizards that you followed.
I mean, it wasn't difficult to do.
It was just stuff like set host name, set a time zone, you know, what do you want your
boot order to be, that kind of stuff.
But it's an in-curses kind of walk you through it wizard style?
Correct.
Yeah.
And it's over a USB-C serial console.
So it looks straight out of the movie hackers or something.
You know, but once it's booted, it's very nice.
It's very quiet.
The fans that are in there are, I think, fairly cheap, Chineseium PWM fans.
So I replaced them with a pair of Noctua fans and noticed a reasonable drop, not a seismic
drop in noise, but definitely noticeable.
Now, the fans are controlled using a fan control program, which is linked to CPU temperature
right now.
So that unfortunately leads to the fans going quite a lot as you, you know, run a particularly
heavy, you know, while you're doing apps update, install, whatever, the fans will go bananas,
even though the CPU temperature is only at about 60 degrees and the hard drives, which
are the important thing in there, in my opinion.
Right.
Have moved not at all.
So one thing I would like to see them address moving forward is have that temperature control
or the speed control more accurately, I suppose, for the fans be linked to kind of overall
chassis ambient temperature or take an average of the hard drives and then divide it by five
or whatever and then do the fan curves based on that.
I think I found a forum thread that said they were going to do that, but I couldn't find
it researching for the episode again.
So the fan noise isn't too bad, but it's just really when they ramp up and down that you're
going to notice it.
Now, it has been on the entire time we're recording right next to us.
So it maybe it's maybe two feet from this microphone, which is a very sensitive one.
So it is quiet when you're not doing anything with it.
But I had a real problem trying to get ZFS working, which is you can imagine is
is a problem for me because my primary use case for this box was going to be a local
ZFS remote replication endpoint.
It's going to just sit in a in a closet quietly getting on with its life.
And it was just going to be a ZFS target.
But because it's running Ambien because it's an ARM CPU and not full on Ubuntu, the ZFS
modules aren't in the kernel, and then that leads you down the road of having to do DKMS
and worry about specific kernels.
And after about two or three hours last night, I just gave up on to throw my laptop at the
wall because, man, I hate DKMS.
Yeah, it's always that, oh, right moment when you're doing your updates and then you
realize, oh, I'm going to have to wait for this.
Oh, I hope it doesn't break.
I just couldn't get it working.
I mean, as well, I say that I had it working and then the kernel upgraded without me
noticing.
And then I just haven't been able to get it to work since.
So there's a pair of drives in there that are ZFS ready, but I just can't get the the
module to load.
So maybe I'll get it working over the next few weeks.
But but right now it's a pain in the ass, to be honest with you.
And that's a real shame because they actually bill and this was a learning for me.
I was speaking with Pope on Twitter over the weekend for those of you that don't know,
Pope works for Canonical, so he knows a thing or two about Ubuntu.
And he was schooling me on the fact that even though on the Kobol website it says it's
a focal fossa image, 2004 image, it's not Ubuntu, even though it says Ubuntu and has
the Ubuntu logo, Ambien is not Ubuntu.
So you live and learn.
You're telling me on their website they claim it's Ubuntu?
So if you go to wiki.kobol.io slash download and take a look at the images there, Chris,
and tell me what you think.
Is that misleading or is it just me being an idiot?
It is.
It's like they have they have Debian 10 Buster and Ubuntu 2004 listed is essentially what
is they have both.
It looks like it's hard to say, though.
It's hard to say when you click it.
I'd have to actually down.
You're right.
It is it is a little vague.
I'd have to download to actually to actually determine.
And so then if you scroll down that page a little further, you get a bunch of known
limitations regarding some of the hardware things.
So one of the issues that I ended up facing was I plugged my gigabit LAN switch into the
two point five gigabit ethernet port that's on the thing.
And I ended up getting horrible.
I'm talking like 10 or 15 megabyte out of a thousand.
Right.
So very, very slow performance.
And it turns out it requires a hardware fix.
I'm going to put a link to this in the show notes.
But if you're interested, go and take a look at what their proposed fixes.
It's to solder a wire on the back of the PCB.
Are you going to do it?
I am.
I mean, that's almost that's almost your kind of thing.
I am because I'm comfortable with it because I've been doing, you know, building racing
drones and stuff for years.
I'm quite comfortable at soldering small stuff.
But this wire would be maybe two centimeters long if that and going on to very, very tiny
surface mount components and a small pin.
So if you screw that up, I don't know what the warranty would say about that.
They don't really mention anything.
And, you know, the final conclusion at the end of this post is we will, of course, fix
this issue in a future revision of the board.
But what they don't say is what they're going to do for everybody that has current boards.
My assumption is nothing.
That's perhaps it shows some wisdom in choosing to do these in batches because they realize
that they're going to have kinks to work out.
Perhaps I would like the option to send mine back for a replacement.
Yeah, I could see that seems seems reasonable.
They may not be too excited about offering that because they don't even have probably
devices to replace yours with.
Sure.
But if you're a company offering a product, I think maybe a refund something, you know,
I don't know, because if I screw this up, which, you know, with a soldering iron on some
some components that are that small, it's very possible.
Sure.
What then?
Am I up the creek without a paddle?
Then you've got a really nice looking piece of equipment.
Yeah.
Now, I think if if these guys had marketed it such that here is a kick ass aluminium
beautiful machined case that you can buy that, by the way, also we sell a kit that fits inside
of, I think it would be a completely different proposition.
But they didn't.
They tried to go full Apple, do the OS, do the hardware, do the software.
Right.
And for me, they've just fallen short in enough key areas that it's really taking the
shine off the product for me.
Another example is and again, this is my fault because I can't read.
Apparently, the M2 SATA slot that's built into the motherboard disables SATA port one.
So you suddenly go from having a five, three and a half inch drive capacity.
You put an M2 drive in there and suddenly one of the bays is useless.
Why not spend the extra few cents on a SATA control that can do six devices?
I just don't understand why they would cut that corner.
It's just really annoying.
And then I suppose the other thing that kind of tripped me up was the USB-C cable that
ships with the product.
I actually had to cut some of the rubber off the outside of it to make it fit in the port
properly.
They have a Wiki article about that.
There's just a lot of rough edges literally with this product.
That said, all of this said, and I'm aware that that all sounds a little bit negative.
The reality is, I bought a product, it shipped, it arrived eventually, it sat on my desk next
to me working and pretty much as advertised.
The hard drive hot swap caddies are a little bit hard to get in and out because the manufacturing
tolerances.
I spoke with Gautier at COBOL about this and he said that it's only during mass production
that we can start to see what really needs to be improved because at the prototyping
stage, different factories will always show us their best in terms of tolerances.
That's an interesting insight.
They do say they're going to rework the backplane for the drives, which is my other major complaint
with this unit.
So the backplane for the five SATA drives are these little plastic things that convert
the ketchup and mustard cables into a SATA power and SATA data connector.
And they've got these really very, very small, thin plastic tabs on either side to mount
them to the chassis.
And I bent a couple of them just by inserting a drive slightly misaligned, which was enough
to make the power pins on the drive have contact.
So when I was putting the drive in, I could hear it spinning up.
So I'm like, okay, cool, the drive seated fine, but it wasn't making contact with the
data pins.
And it took me a couple of hours to figure that out.
Oh, I bet.
So yeah, once I took it, I basically had to take the whole thing apart again, saw that
I'd bent the tabs, I guess, just by having to push so hard to get the drives in because
the tolerances were so tight.
It actually shaved plastic off the drive caddies as I did so.
I guess I just bent the connector at the back.
You're super tough.
Yeah, yeah.
You're strong.
The drive caddies themselves are not tool-less.
You need to use four screws to mount drives into the caddies and then two screws to secure
the caddies into the drive bays themselves as well.
So, you know, it's not perfect.
And I think for the price of 300-ish dollars, I look at what we could get from Synology
or QNAP, and I'm having a hard time with it.
What would be the advantage here?
Because the Synology products and the QNAP products, they offer a lot of features.
So what do you think the Helio 64's biggest advantage over those would be?
Well, we didn't talk about performance yet.
Uh-huh.
I know.
Oh, I know.
I'm waiting.
Basically, if you want to do transcoding, forget about it, of anything.
Oh.
It can handle direct play just fine.
It will just about handle transcoding a true HD audio track, but not much more than that.
And even then, the CPU is going bananas trying to do it.
So I'd like to see some hardware circuitry, a bit like, you know, Apple Silicon is doing
to get some of those crazy numbers with the M1.
Some hardware decoders for H.264, H.265, that kind of thing.
Maybe some kind of quick sync of some sort.
Well, yes, that's the other elephant in the room, isn't it?
I mentioned Synology and QNAP because they are off-the-shelf, ready-to-go products that
you could send to your family and say, right, just shove a couple of hard drives in it,
and I'll do the rest remotely.
You know, you could, and over at serverbuilds.net right now, actually, they've been linking
on eBay this UNAZ chassis, which can take a mini-ITX motherboard and run whatever OS
you want on it, and you have full control over everything, which I think is the primary
advantage of the Helios 64 over a Synology device is that you own it, right?
It's not, you're not beholden to whatever Synology decide to do with DSM moving forward
or who knows.
Right.
And the fact that they offer both Ubuntu and Armbian is rather nice.
You have some choice there.
You could probably put Arch on there if you tried hard enough.
But I think the other thing, the other story with these ARM devices, and for some of us,
it matters more, is power usage, and the Helios 64 may have them licked there.
30 watts at full load.
Whoa, really?
That's pretty impressive.
With all the drives spun up.
Right, right.
Compare that to my dual Xeon system in the basement that's pulling 300 and something
at idle, you know?
So there is a real benefit to having these low power devices.
You know, the fans that I mentioned run at zero RPM most of the time.
Yeah, I'm really glad you checked that because fan noise and power draw, I think, are the
big part of these ARM devices in a review.
You got to look at that because that's where they're going to be most competitive.
So it does seem like as far as noise, because you're podcasting with it right now,
and as far as power draw, it may beat what those other products have to offer, maybe.
It might, as long as you're aware of all of the caveats going in, and the fact that you
are basically a beta tester for this product, as long as you're fine with all those things,
then go for it.
You know, I was hoping for a bit more of a finished product, like, particularly from
the software perspective, there's lots of things in Ambien that on the Helios 64 forums
users are talking about fan control being one of them, and there's a few other things
as well.
If you look at the known issues on the download page in the Wiki, you know, you can see that
some kernels will let you monitor the internal battery, some kernels won't.
Suspender RAM is not supported because of some issue with the USB host controller.
Some kernels have kernel panics on shutdown, and some don't.
So, you are very much a beta tester, and I think for the price it's a bit hard to swallow,
but it is a beautiful physical thing.
That it is, and it needs to start somewhere.
These devices will only get better over time.
They'll be able to add things like accelerated hardware, accelerated decoding.
It may even be possible with the SOC it has, maybe it just hasn't been enabled via software
yet.
Yeah.
So those things will improve.
They'll be able to address things like the wire harness approach I mentioned for the
backplane.
They're going to move to a PCB backplane on the next batch to address issues exactly like
the one that I faced.
So, you know, they are going to improve things over time, and if all my $300 has served to
do is enable them to eventually build the ultimate ARM-powered NAS, then it might be
worth it.
And I think ARM is the future, Apple are showing us that, you know, just the sheer power on
offer with that M1 chip.
I mean, I've been watching the benchmark videos over the weekend, and wow, I mean, it's fast,
that thing.
Yeah.
And I have to tell you that 30 watts is extremely appealing to me.
I'm sure it is.
Yeah, Mr. I run on batteries in the middle of the desert half the time.
Right.
So that to me is something where it's like, okay, I want to see where this goes.
But you know, your review here has made me appreciate something I don't think I've really
thought about when it comes to pre-built NASes, because I think traditionally both you and
myself have done it the more like complicated way where we build an x86 server and it has
a bunch of disks, and like my case, I went to a Unix, or I think it's Unix Surplus, is
that what it's called?
And I got myself, you know, a whole chassis, and I have big disks slided, and then that's
how I do a NAS.
This is it, these smaller NASes, these product NASes, like the Helio 64 and like the Synology,
they're a category of their own.
And the point that you made about how things like the battery detection and the thermal
sensors and those things not quite being worked out, because right now they're not upstream
everywhere yet.
In a couple of years, it'll probably be universal across Linux distros where that stuff is supported.
But with something like DSM, they're building it for that device to support that specific
device and their other ones.
And so they can purpose load hardware and software to make sure everything works together
so you can get something that runs DSM and have a pretty, you know, as long as you've
looked at the specs, it's going to do hardware decoding of your Plex videos because they've
got the chip and they've got the software and they're going to support it because it's
one package.
So if you're going for these one package products that are everything from the chassis disk
to the OS, it seems like that might be the more appliance like strategy where you know
you're going to have better long term luck.
And I mean, I have I think I don't know, Alex, it it actually could be a six year old, seven
year old Synology at Angela's house.
And it's still running today.
And about a month ago, I logged into it and did a bunch of updates.
And it's still running 24 seven out in a garage for I mean, may even be seven years.
Yeah, you buy these things to be an appliance.
You shove the disks in, turn it on and off you go.
And that should that should be the end of it.
That's that's the last thought you should give this type of device, in my opinion.
I did note on their website that they have adapters so you can put two and a half SSDs
in there, which is probably what I do for vibration resistance.
But they're about six bucks a pop.
So I'll in it, I'd probably be close to $400 if I was going to buy this thing.
If I was interested in power savings, if I didn't need hardware accelerated decoding,
or if I felt like maybe it's going to get fixed, would you recommend it to me?
Because I may be the target audience for this thing.
It's a tricky question to answer.
I think, yes, but with the caveats we've discussed, you think the price is right.
As long as you go into it with your eyes open, then definitely maybe it depends on you.
It's not for it's not for everybody.
That I think is my answer.
It's not for everyone.
Linode dot com slash SSH.
Go there to receive a $100 60 day credit towards a new account and support this here podcast.
Linode is our cloud hosting provider.
Any time we're trying something that has a cloud component for the show that we can self
host, we spin it up on Linode.
The back end infrastructure for the JB podcast network, Linode, my personal sites, Linode.
If you need a simple personal server for a blog or a portfolio or maybe a game server
or a VPN server, Linode has you covered.
And if you get $100 credit, you can try out some serious systems, too.
I mean, you'll be cooking with gas because they have rigs that start at $5 a month.
So you've got a lot to play with there.
And if you need to scale your business or maybe something you're doing goes popular,
gets viral, they can help you there, too.
It's a really fantastic cloud hosting service because they've got the network to really
back it all up, 40 gigabit connections coming to the hypervisor.
Plus Linode's been around since 2003.
So they've been able to secure some super great long term relationships in connectivity.
Plus on top of that, they've got native SSD storage for each of the hosts, 11 data centers
around the world, and Linode costs 30 to 50% less than the major cloud providers.
They've been around longer, they're independently owned, and you can support the show.
Linode.com slash SSH.
Turns out our listeners are the target market for audiobooks.
Who'd have thought, Chris, people that like podcasts also like audiobooks.
Yeah, I guess when you put it that way, it does seem kind of obvious.
But man, did we get a lot of feedback about audiobooks.
So I collected, like I mentioned earlier in the show, some of the apps that people sent
in.
But I also thought I would just cover a couple of the more clever ways people are consuming
their audiobooks once they have freed them from their DRM or acquired them in some other
means.
And Phil wrote in and he said, stop thinking about audiobooks as some special thing you
need a specific player for.
Audiobooks are basically identical to podcasts.
Just use a podcast player and publish your audiobooks via an RSS feed.
We got like eight different versions of how people are converting their audiobooks into
podcast feeds.
It seems to be really popular.
Phil here, he's written a Python script that generates an RSS feed given from a folder.
He put that behind some HTTP server with basic authentication.
And then he says, with that, I build a Docker container that hosts my audiobooks in an RSS
feed.
And he just has that and he subscribes to that in his app.
He says, I'd actually be happy to release the script and container to the community,
but they aren't really ready for public consumption yet.
It would be great if I could get a few spare cycles from someone in the community to clean
it up before releasing the code.
Maybe you can help facilitate such things.
And Alex, we got a couple of people that have come up with clever scripts on how they convert
things or do what.
And they often ask, should I share it with the community?
And it got me thinking, maybe we could use our GitHub for that.
Because people won't know how to find individual GitHubs for all of this.
Maybe there's a way for us to use our GitHub as a jumping off point for people's Ansible
scripts and cool Python scripts and other stuff.
Several things came in.
So let's you and I ruminate on that, because that might be a way we could facilitate some
of this.
And then you combine that with the Discord, and it could be cooking with gas again.
I like cooking with gas these days.
We do have that Wiki that's been sort of languishing a little bit lately.
So maybe we could have the best audio book playing Wiki page on the internet, something
like that.
That'd be pretty good.
Turns out, though, that there's not a lot that you can't do with FFmpeg.
I know.
Yeah, including convert your Audible books, turns out, Phil.
And actually a couple of others, and this probably is what OpenAudible is just doing
on the back end, really, has a FFmpeg script to check and convert.
One more podcast trick.
This one comes from James.
He says he uses OpenAudible to download his purchases to his home server.
And then he has a PHP script and a cron job to auto-generate RSS feeds for any book that
appears in the audio books directory.
I have another tiny script that then creates an index of all the RSS feeds.
When I want to listen to a book, I just add the feed to Antennapod.
It's super handy, and it takes care of all of the offline syncing issues and lets me
choose if I want to listen to a whole book on the go or a podcast here and there in between
chapters using Smart Shuffle.
It's basic, but maybe I should publish my scripts.
Would anybody want that?
Where could I do that?
Well, you know what they say, sharing is caring.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, we'll get that going.
So yeah, there's several that came in, but it was interesting to see people using different
tricks to convert them to podcasts.
I don't know, Alex.
It's not my jam, I got to be honest with you.
Something like Booksonic or an audio book dedicated app still kind of seems to be more
my speed.
That's the beauty of this kind of stuff, though, in the self-hosted world is that there's not
really ever a right or a wrong answer to this kind of stuff.
True.
Once you have your data, once you control your data, you can serve it up to yourself
however, wherever you like.
And that's one of the advantages of it.
So Luck wrote in, and this is a tip that goes back to our discussion last episode, where
we were experimenting with a Google Photos replacement.
I don't know, do you still have that going?
I probably do, but I haven't opened it in two weeks.
Yeah.
Well, one of the things we were talking about was what would be the best way to get the
photos off your phone and into a directory where this tool could index and do all of
the object recognition.
And Luck wrote in to say, check out Photosync.
It's photosync-app.com.
It's available for iOS and Android, and it supports tons of ways to transfer from like
all of the typical cloud services, but it also supports S3 uploads, NFS uploads, web
dev uploads, Samba, et cetera.
And we've got a couple of people that are trying to do their uploads to S3 and then
having that app, which I'm drawing a blank on the name of it, analyze the photos.
And so this app supports S3, NFS, web dev, so there's a lot of ways you could get these
up on your home server to then point Photoprism at it, photosync-app.com, if you want to
check that out.
Now our next bit of feedback comes from Draw, D-R-O-R, I'm sorry, I'm going to go with
Draw.
You said that about your podcast a couple of weeks ago, and I'm on a marathon catching
up with the previous episodes.
So far, I'm enjoying it.
Many thanks for all the tips.
Thank you very much.
Now I'm stuck in a wanting mode where I pretty much know my needs, but I'm failing to actually
make purchases.
We've all been there.
You're in the research phase, Draw.
Too much choice is paralyzing you.
Yes, definitely been there.
So storage backups NAS wise, I'd like to start with decent storage for my media, but I'm
far from being a hardware and network guy.
Where would you recommend to start without diving too deep into learning all this stuff?
Would a couple of my book, Western Digital Hard Drives, work and what would I connect
them to?
Regardless, maybe you might discuss it later.
But what about Mycroft as well as a self-hosted Google Home replacement?
So this is a great email because this is maybe the candidate we were just talking about for
the Helio 64 versus something like a Synology or QNAP.
Yeah, I think so.
And you know, to get started, a Raspberry Pi with a couple of USB hard drives connected
will do just fine.
Yeah, you know, don't be shy when you write in.
Let us know what your budget is and let us know what your comfort level is, like your
DIY comfort level, your budget and your DIY comfort level.
Because Alex and I are totally happy making recommendations anywhere on the spectrum.
So you could go with Raspberry Pis, like Alex was saying, and hook up a couple of USB disks
and you'd really be off to the races as long as you're comfortable configuring Samba or
something like that, or maybe even going something with like Cockpit.
And what I would say as well is that over the last several years over at linuxserver.io,
I've been writing the Perfect Media Server series.
Go and take a look at that because in that series, I cover Docker, MergerFS, which is
an awesome bit of software, with SnapRaid as well for drive parity to protect you from
drive failures a little bit, that kind of stuff.
And I talk about the overall kind of decisions you've got to make.
And hopefully, when you start looking against your requirements versus what some of this
software can do, you'll start to narrow down your field of decisions a little bit and it
should make things a bit easier for you.
I don't cover hardware.
There's plenty of other good pieces of journalism about that.
So Brian Moses writes a really good blog every year, I think, on the perfect NAS build.
Of course, there's serverbuilds.net as well, which is always a great resource.
But yeah, I mean, just feel free to let us know what your budget is or drop into the
Discord.
We have a hardware channel.
I'll add to that.
And you were touching on it there, Alex.
I think what he needs to do is figure out what his primary app or use case is and then
build for that.
I think maybe that's what he's lacking.
Because he may also be a good QNAP or Synology candidate and where he wants to, instead of
struggle with the networking and OS aspect of it, he'd rather learn at the application
level where he could deploy the applications using a UI that they provide and learn the
applications.
And then maybe from there, get a passion, get rolling, get enthusiastic about this stuff,
and then go more towards the DIY route.
I think that is really common for people is they have an application or a use they build
for that.
They kind of take the easiest route possible that is sustainable for them.
And then when they go hardcore, they just start going even deeper.
And that may be what happens to you.
So consider maybe one of those Synology or QNAPs, like we were talking about earlier,
that will make it a lot easier to just get going with the applications, but still give
you a good, solid base to run everything from.
A really expensive requirement to ask yourself about is, do I need to transcode?
So with Plex, if you want to watch stuff on your phone or on your TV or anywhere really,
it will go ahead and transcode on the fly.
So it will convert the video that you have to whatever format the device you're watching
it on can play back.
It will also reduce the quality.
So it will take a 1080p quality file, for example, and convert it all the way down to DVD quality
or something like that, if you're on limited bandwidth.
But that requires some very specific hardware choices around CPUs or GPUs and that kind
of stuff.
So I mentioned API earlier, but that wouldn't be the best choice if you want to transcode,
for example.
So lots of options, but it depends, like Chris says, on what you want to do.
And our last one today, although we did get some other emails in, so we will cue those,
but also do please keep sending those in at selfhosted.show slash contact.
We have a form there.
You fill it in, and it lands in our inbox.
And Russell writes in with our last one, and it's a bit of a workaround for you OpenHAB
users out there.
Alex and I are obviously deep into Home Assistant, so we don't have a lot of OpenHAB experience,
but we do like getting tips.
And Russell writes in and says, to my knowledge, OpenHAB doesn't have anything built into it
that detects dawn, dusk, sunrise, sunset, et cetera.
So I wanted to set something up myself, and I turned to Python.
But every library I found that used calculation-based time had an issue where, after a year or so,
the sunrise and sunset times would be wildly incorrect.
He goes on to say there's a couple other libraries that were just very out of date.
So to make it work, I got myself a free API subscription to ipgeolocation.io.
The free developer subscription allows for 30,000 requests per month with 1,000 per day,
which is way more than the two calls I use, one to get the sunrise, sunset times, and
another to get UTC offset.
That's how you can also handle daylight savings, which, nice catch, Russell.
He goes on to say I use a cron job to call the Python script, which retrieves the times
every day and then runs an at command to schedule the sunrise, sunset triggers.
It works really well.
And the documentation is easy to understand.
I highly recommend it for anyone looking for sunrise or sunset solutions.
He needs a good way to share that script, though, because I think people could take
advantage of that.
Cheers, he says.
Well, good work around there.
OpenHAB might not have it built in, but he came up with a way to make it work.
And that's all it really takes.
My tip of the hat to you there, Russell.
All right.
So coming up on December 13 is the Home Assistant Conference.
It's to attend will be $1, which they're going to use to cover the cost of the platform.
Obviously it's a virtual conference for obvious reasons.
So it's Sunday, December the 13th, and that is at 10 p.m. Pacific Standard Time, which
I think is 7 p.m. Central European Time.
So hopefully with it being on a Sunday, that should fit most people's schedules.
Interesting.
I, of course, signed up.
I got my ticket.
I'm all in.
I'm going to go.
And they will have it just on YouTube as well, I think, from reading their website.
You don't have to sign up.
And I'm going to keep my eye on the conference.
And if there's some really great audio, I may grab some clips.
You know, I may.
It could happen.
I'm particularly looking forward to just seeing how different people work with Home Assistant.
You know, there's a couple of sessions around improving YAML workflows.
There's one here which might be interesting for you.
On the main stage, managing an off-grid vehicle with Home Assistant.
Stop it.
Are you serious?
Uh-huh.
Somebody's doing my bit?
No.
That's great.
I should like pick them for all the knowledge they have.
I did not see that.
As well as reverse engineering a 433 hertz megahertz RF protocol.
I did see that one.
That could be useful for, you know, hacking some of the little remote controls you have
for like garage door openers and that kind of thing.
Well, I want to thank a Cloud Guru for sponsoring this episode of Self-Hosted.
And they do have their Black Friday sale going.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
We know the cloud is growing, and so is the demand for skilled cloud professionals.
82% of hiring managers say cloud certifications make a candidate more attractive.
Well, ACG's Black Friday sale is your last chance for low prices this year.
Keep up with change and develop the skills you need with a Cloud Guru.
Developing cloud fluency can be hard, and it's even harder to keep up.
So they make it easy by providing an engaging way to learn, retain, and stay competitive.
Get the best price possible by using our Black Friday link in the show notes.
You can get that at selfhosted.show slash 33.
And thanks to a Cloud Guru for sponsoring this episode of Self-Hosted.
You know, speaking of Black Fridays, Alex, I'm going to do a Black Friday sale for the
Self-Hosted SREs for probably a couple of weeks.
So if you want to support the show and get a limited ad feed and get the extra content,
the post-show, go to self-hosted.show slash SRE and then use the coupon code blackfriday.
And it'll work for as long as I leave it active, and that'll take $2 off, which is like basically
nothing for this show because since it's only twice a month, we have a lower membership
fee already.
So that's a ridiculously good deal.
Crazy Chris is blowing off the doors with these crazy prices, but you know, I never
really have had an opportunity in the past to do a Black Friday sale because I never
really had anything to Black Friday sale, so I thought it'd be fun.
So yeah, if you want to support the show and get a great deal, go to self-hosted.show slash
SRE and then use that coupon code blackfriday and you'll get that deal.
Maybe by next Black Friday, we'll be able to have a merch sale.
Wink, wink.
I know, right?
You know what?
I just was looking at badges this morning.
Self-Hosted badge would be pretty cool.
So as usual, you can go to self-hosted.show slash contact to find more ways to get in
touch with us.
And you can find me on Twitter at ironic badger.
Yeah, I'm there too at Chris LAS and the show is at self-hosted show.
Don't forget the network is at Jupiter signal.
Thanks for listening.
And that was self-hosted.show slash 33.