Well, I'd like to extend a congratulations to Sir Lewis Hamilton on his 8th world driver's title this this past weekend
Wow
I've only got two. I mean technically he didn't actually win because of some oh utter shenanigans in the formula one management camp
But that's probably saved that's probably best saved for a rant down the pub sometime
Oh, I know it was rough alex. I saw your twitter feed and it was going to be a rough recording day for you
Yeah, man, you know, I followed formula one since I was
Six seven years old so a long time
And what went down on sunday?
Ranks as the most corrupt fixed thing i've ever seen in sport. I think possibly ever
If you're not a formula one fan, you have no idea what i'm talking about
but if you are hopefully you're in solidarity with me and lewis because it was uh
Yeah, it wasn't cool
Your faith has been shaken. I can tell. Mm-hmm. Yeah. Oh
Why do I bother getting emotionally involved in something where they can just change the rules in the last lap? That's the
that's the crux of my
of my beef
Hmm, I hear you
I hear you see I get
I get really upset when uh
When I just watch sports
I generally just I either get like really super sucked in in any kind of sport or I cannot pay attention at all
It's one or the two for me. And so it's not generally a pleasant experience
I mean i'm used to disappointment. I have been an english football fan my entire life
And I am used to not winning major tournaments or going out at some highly tense moment
But at least the rules of engagement are followed from end to end. However, corrupt fifa may or may not be
uh, but the fia man who that was some
Grade a horse manure on sunday
This will never be forgotten. This will be the day never
and i'm i'm sorry, I mean, you know max Verstappen he is a worthy world champion, but
This is his first and it will forever in my opinion be tarnished. So, uh
unfortunate for him, but
It's the way it goes sometimes
anyway, should we talk about something that is a little less morbid and uh, well depends on your point of view I suppose this uh,
This aws outage this this past week
It's a little rough for some and once again, I don't know why but this is maybe my favorite part
AWS is a big old outage you go to their status page. Everything's green. It's all good. Alex. Nothing's down
Meanwhile, the services you depend on are just totally not working
And now amazon just said that network devices got overloaded. That was their essential
Basic statement on the problem like oh quite the post-mortem there. Okay network devices got overloaded. All right
Why why didn't your status page work that kind of stuff? That's like saying, you know, i've just crushed into a tree
Well, why did you crash into a tree alex? Well because I didn't turn
My wheel enough to stay on the road. Yeah, I mean technically that's accurate. Why didn't you turn your wheel enough? Oh, I don't know
Yeah, that's true. Uh, they do say they're gonna work on trying to get the uh status page working better though
But along with this we've also I mean this is a trend we've talked about before it's like everything goes along
It's working great until there's an outage
And so a lot of things quit working that are associated with this
Some of the services we use to produce the shows quit working
Uh, and then kind of unrelated to this I believe wise also had an api outage so you couldn't get access to your wise devices
And as they expand into door locks and other things like that motion sensors and whatnot like that matters a lot
Absolutely does. Yeah, I mean i'm not
I'm not party to any of the internal amazon discussions
That uh, you know is to root cause analysis and that kind of thing
but what I do find interesting are the
butterfly effect impacts to smart home users and things like
Right, right
We've put a few links in the show notes that I just got from twitter by typing in smart home aws outage
And I found people whose christmas lights weren't working whose robo vax weren't working whose smart plugs had stopped working
All because the cloud in us east one had had stopped working
And I mean, you know stuff like my home assistant nebu kasa
That stopped working for a few hours because that must have some reliance somewhere on amazon and
You know, you look at the the way in which aws telly to architect your systems, you know, they
Pioneered the availability zone concept. They pioneered the multi-region concept
The trouble is certain core services like root 53, for example their dns service
Are based out of us east one
So if that site goes down doesn't matter how highly available your system is you can still be impacted by outages like this
Yeah, and there's so many things that you
end up using they
They're either services applications or devices that become dependent on something like amazon
And you don't even know it until it's out
Like I didn't realize some of the podcasting tools we were using
Actually, we're on amazon and we're using that particular data center. I found out though. I found out the hard way
It makes you really stop and think about the homogenization of the internet in general really, you know stuff like cloudflare and amazon
Uh to some extent google, uh, although I don't think their compute is terribly well utilized
Or i'm probably way off base with that given how big google itself is
Uh azure as well, you know, you know, there's five or six companies that control the lion's share of the internet's traffic
And if one of those companies has a problem then we all do which makes me question
What's the point in architecting for high availability and spending all these hours spinning our wheels on kubernetes clusters and all these other
complex abstractions on top of
these sandcastles effectively of cloud architecture when
When no matter how much work I put in to keep something available
Something completely beyond my control somewhere else down the pipe is going to cause a blockage
yeah, the other thing that drives me kind of crazy about it is we're really not taking advantage of some of the strengths of tcpip and
The way the internet can be routed around
It it really lends itself to a decentralized internet and what we've done for convenience and quality of service and whatever
Is we've centralized and we're ignoring one of the key original design strengths of the whole network by doing so
And I don't I don't know if the solution is is all of us, you know, we just self-host even harder. I mean that definitely
helps isolate us individuals from these outages
But there are circles of the internet that are talking more on and more about
Decentralization and ways they can they can become more available and and less of a single point of failure
I was just talking with dave jones who is behind podcastindex.org
And they're using ipfs for some of their file storage trying to prevent any single point of failure for a server outage
Really makes you stop and think like
The mars rover or the mars copter I think is uh vulnerable to this log4j vulnerability
Like there's just so much there's so many libraries. There's so much abstraction
Between us and the hardware these days
It's really impossible for a mere mortal to keep track of where all this stuff and where all these dependencies are going to lie. So
You know, I don't know what the answer is
with regards to aws because clearly they are the dominant force in cloud computing, but
So far as i'm concerned in my own personal
Fiefdom of my house
Uh, I you know, I didn't really notice a huge amount on the day-to-day
Except for the nebucasa stuff when I was at the supermarket. I wanted to just turn the heating down a bit
Uh, because I thought we were coming straight home and we weren't you know, um
Besides that I didn't really notice a huge impact
Yeah, and that's because I use things like wled and for my smart lights and vale tudo for my robo vac and tasmota
For all my smart plugs
all of those things are
Basically disconnected from the internet and I fully own those pieces of hardware now
So that no matter what happens to those cloud services
i'm good, and this isn't to say, you know local good cloud bad because sometimes there are benefits to cloud services, but
Uh more and more. I think the layperson is beginning to understand maybe a bit like the privacy argument
There's there's just been enough times it's happened now where they're thinking. Hmm. Hold on a minute
Maybe there is something to this metadata collection. Maybe there is something to this internet of shit type stuff
Maybe there is yeah, that's a good point
It's like it is maybe each outage is kind of pushing it into a new wave of people that are recognizing
The problem I kind of just have this general philosophy too. It's like for an application to be whole
I prefer as much of it to be on my land
in part for security and privacy, but also
You know, I I started using the internet in an era of very limited bandwidth
I sometimes still have very limited bandwidth and I don't like just extra chatter going out over my internet connection that doesn't need to
Every packet matters in my opinion and why?
Why send spammy little packets that are just maybe like messages back and forth for what i'm typing when I could run all that
on my land so that definitely
is a mindset of mine that sort of
Has kind of I guess paid off
Over the years, you know old man doesn't want to use up his modem bandwidth
But you know as the as we just modernize and more things go online
There's also just things you have to use that are cloud-based. There's no way around it sometimes and
Yeah, it does go out
I I have yet to have it cause an actual genuine issue for me, you know
It's an inconvenience mostly maybe a show goes out a couple hours later, but in my it life
I did have lawyers as clients and there would often be like
This extreme time pressure to turn around a contract that has something to do with, you know, some 10 million dollar deal
And we did have a situation where the exchange server went down
And it was like red alert all hands on deck get this thing back up as fast as possible
We've got to get this email out because everybody's self-hosted back then and so you can also sometimes have these outages
When you self-host and you know in like i'm sure this is probably happened to everyone who's listening to self-hosted for a while
It's going to fail when you're on vacation or something like that
You know like my server here at the studio, which had been running fantastic, of course
Crashed while I was on my road trip and I was stuck in tucson and I couldn't get back here for a week to check
On what was going on
So that stuff happens when you self-host too, and you know, it's all on you to fix it
Speaking of I know I mentioned briefly that log4j vulnerability in the last bit
The linuxserver.io team have posted an info notice. I think this is a new thing
They've started doing over at info.linuxserver.io about the log4j vulnerability
Essentially, this is a very critical vulnerability in java
Which leads to denial of service and remote code execution in java apps
It's in java version 11. So it's quite a recent version of java
I think you and wes did a full breakdown in this week's land didn't you?
Yeah, we got all the details in there and the steps you'd have to go through to actually trigger the exploit
But spoiler is yeah
You could actually even get this thing to remotely connect to remote urls and pull down shell script and run it
So it's not good. It's not good at all. And ironically it was found by minecraft users
Who figured out they could take control of the minecraft server because most developers and for totally reasonable reasons
Are logging
The commands their users are entering into the shell so they know what the user was doing
And if you take advantage of that, well, you could probably guess where that leads
So there's a lot of minecraft servers out there that people have set up for themselves that are self-hosting that have to get updated
And you know what? I say good on linux server ios for uh going through and kind of letting people know what's up
I think that's also pretty nice to see
Just because I use a lot of their containers
The main one that stood out for me was the unify controller as being vulnerable. Obviously that's got some pretty
Pretty good network level access to your stuff. And so if there's a vulnerability there you want to be on top of it pretty quick
Um, there is a version released now with a workaround applied as well as an upstream fix. So if
You're running unify from linux server in a container go ahead and pull down that update. There's a few others on the web page as well
Yeah, I know some of our listeners use uh airsonic and that's one that's currently vulnerable as well
So watch out for that
Now i've been in the market to buy guitars in the last couple of weeks joe and I have been talking endlessly about guitars lately
and uh
A lot of that has involved me
A lot of that has involved me f5ing a lot of websites to try and you know
See what's coming up on the use market all that kind of stuff
And so I thought there's got to be a better way to monitor these web pages and I came across an app pick
Called change detection.io
This thing bills itself as the best and simplest self-hosted open source website change detection monitoring and notification service
cool
This looks really good. It gives you a little dashboard and shows you when a page was last checked
When it last changed and then gives you buttons to check the difference to recheck it. Mm-hmm
This is so neat. It's really nice and some of the examples they ship out of the box are for things like the covid
UK government page for example
So, I mean if you wanted to know when the guidelines change for that for some reason
Uh, you could have this send you a notification with the diff of what changed so you don't even have to go to the website
And look it up
I have mine pointed at the gibson demo shop, for example, and you know for me it just lists
It just looks at the guitars that are on there and every time a new guitar gets added
I get a push notification through apprise to my phone with the link to the website so I can just click on the link and
Go and have a look at that new shiny guitar that I can't afford
Linode.com
Slash ssh and linode has done the work to make sure that log for shell is not going to be a problem on their infrastructure
It's where we host everything. They're so dang fast and they got 11 data centers around the world
We got a testimonial from deckbot recently says hey chris in the badger
I recently moved homes and in the process I knew I needed to put a home server into storage for about a month
The server is my samba server on zfs, but I also had two cores and eight gigs of ram dedicated to a minecraft vm
Knowing that they would still want to play while we were moving to the new house
I set up a five dollar nano to install the minecraft server and upload the world using linode's game server how to as a guide
Testing it though. It showed maybe things would work. Okay, but I saw crashes that we started to use it more and I realized
Minecraft was ram constrained
But linode's single click upgrade to the next nanode was fast flawless and fixed the service performance needs right away
Best of all the single core two gigabyte nanode on the cloud was beating the performance of my locally hosted two core
eight gig vm
You know what deckbot I see that all the time
Like I say, I used to do things in vms
But this is what linode does they build and manage servers and they've been doing it for 18 years
So they know how to make these things fast
And on top of that they got a great dashboard and they have the best customer support in the business
It's where I test things. It's where I deploy things. It's where I learn about things
So go get a hundred dollars and try it out for 60 days kick the tires for yourself and support the show
linode.com slash ssh
New month new home assistant update. They just released their 2021.12 update
And along with that there was also a three-hour live stream. Uh, the big state of the stream project
Yeah, it's the end of the year. I think they're gonna just do this now all the time
Um before we get into the details of what they announced
Did you see the vr thing that they showed that how they do their team meetings now? I did it felt very uh,
Like a rudimentary version of ready player one or something like that, you know, yeah. Yeah
Yeah, uh, well paul has filed up on twitter and he said we at nubukasa, uh are doing all of our meetings in vr now
It feels more like being together compared to just a grid of webcam feeds, especially for our collaborative sessions
It's a big win
We use horizon workrooms on the oculus quest 2 which is the standalone headset that runs android
They don't connect to a pc or anything like that
And he says why it's better for them is number one reason is body language compared to webcam
Your hands and fingers are now included on the call so you can point to things you can gesture
You got emotions you can draw on a whiteboard
Spatial audio actually lets you know where people are and makes it more immersive. But here's the other thing I didn't consider
And this made me go, huh?
It's faster
Vr is faster because webcams you're actually doing like an h264 video stream or something like that, right?
Or vp8 or whatever
But in vr it's audio and then it's just the data
For the movements and stuff the updates for the movements and they're not actually sending the video feed of it
They're just sending the data feed
And so what you get is you fix this like oh, no you go. Oh, i'll go. Oh, can I oh
Uh, uh, uh, like that's gone now because the latency is so much better plus you can see people are like
You know gesturing with their hands and whatnot
Actually kind of made me think here's what I kind of clicked for me. I thought to myself this sounds so silly, right?
until then I thought
Well, what if we use this for podcasting? Like what if you and I were doing this right now?
Right
That'd be pretty cool. That would be interesting
I'd I'd need to invest in some vr gear and obviously if I tell the wife, you know
I need to buy vr gear for podcasting, which is an audio medium
And I need some kind of expensive video headset. I think that I go over really well
Yeah, yeah, because really you're going to want to get like the upgraded strap and you're going to want the controls
Uh, so you're like 500 bucks on amazon and then like to get good headphones that plug into it easily
That's like another hundred bucks
So you're almost to the price point of the of the style that you can plug into a to the pc
And it actually has good graphics almost to a price point of a ticket to come and see you
Yeah
That's true
Yeah, oh, yeah. All right. Well anyways, uh, the other thing that they just kind of slipped in there
Maybe I missed this because I haven't been following this super closely
But you know the home assistant amber their little hardware device that they had crowdfunded. Well, I guess now it's called the home assistant yellow
So
The change in the name is still based on the pi compute module for still got that m2 expansion slot in the zigbee module
And gigabit ethernet
Uh, and it's still available to order
But uh, yeah, it's going to be a little bit I think before it's shipping and now it's called the yellow not the amber
well, like anything this year, you know, I think you just got to accept the fact that
You know, for example the 1080 ti that I have in my graphics card as in my gaming rig
I'm fine with that. I mean if I could have bought a 3080 or whatever at retail
For msrp i'd have probably done it but
You know, I think in in 2021, we just got to accept the fact and and 22 now that these shortages are going to continue
I think I was watching a
A jay's two cents video the other night where he was reciting some insider information that he has from his contacts at intel and nvidia
who
said
That the shortages at the end of 20 were going to continue through 21
And now they're saying the same thing at the end of 21. They're going to continue through the end of 22. So
Eh, it is what it is. We've all just got to end up being a bit more patient. I think
well, you know, I
There's a lot of negatives to it in the rv community. It's a massive problem parts are super short
and now there's rumors of a def a diesel exhaust fluid shortage, which
The diesel pusher rigs need to go down the road
So they're like the shortages. I don't want to make light of it. It's really bad
However, one silver lining that I would love to see out of it is people repurposing old pcs like i'm doing this
i'm kind of thinking like how can I just sort of spread stuff out a little bit or take advantage of stuff and
Instead of going with something new
Trying to refurbish something old and I think that's actually a good way for us to be thinking absolutely more
Yeah, I mean all of the systems in my house are based around the eighth gen
Intel cpu socket i've got you know, my backup server my desktop my main system
my desktop my main server
And my work desktop. They're all you know, all four of those systems have uh, my blue iris system five
all five of those systems have eighth gen cpus in them so that if anything fails in there
I don't even have to think oh what generation of cpu does that specific motherboard have no
It's eighth gen it's done right and you know if you do the comparisons between an eighth and an eleventh or an eighth and a twelfth
Okay by you know four generations there might be 10 or 15 percent difference
But is it worth the thousands of dollars to upgrade at this point?
No, and I remember, you know, I remember like 10 years ago when I went from a core two duo to one of those uh, lga
1366 i7 960s
Oh that was like that was like lightning that thing and I think it coincided with getting an ssd for the first time
For the first time as well. Oh
Yeah, it's a sweet upgrade
We just don't have leaps like that anymore. I mean, I know mvme is a lot faster
than sata and
Ssd are a lot faster than spinning rust, but I think a lot of the main
speed generational bottlenecks
Between you know an eighth and a twelfth gen cpu. Okay. There's pcie gen four is a slight change but
On the daily i'm never really thinking god my computer's too slow these days. I
Think you're seeing kind of a big leap over in the apple side right now
And I was just thinking about this this morning, man
I was just thinking i'd really like the asahi linux project to just come along a little bit more so that way I could try
Out the m1 mac mini as a home server in the rv because the damn thing takes 28 watts at max load and that's at max
load and it takes a lot less down to like six or seven watts at low load, which is just I can't
I can't even fathom that I can't I've seen the numbers and I still don't believe it
And it makes for me like the perfect home server if they just if I could just get macOS off
My MacBook Pro that i'm using to record this episode right now
According to iStat is using eight watts to drive a 4k monitor a 1080p monitor and the laptop internal display
Plus all the USB audio processing that it's doing and eight watts
So it's nice to see that kind of shift but yeah as far as like gear i'm using for my home systems and servers right now
Yeah, the older stuff is is plenty plenty fine
I mean i'm running i'm still running home assistant on the home assistant blue and on a raspberry pi
And I did do the new upgrade. I did the because on the on the blue, you know, i'm using their OS
So now i've been upgraded to their new OS
And to the new version of home assistant. It's got that brand new configuration panel. It looks a lot better. Yeah, I don't like it
Really? No, I think it's cleaner. You know, it's more organized. It feels I don't know more like how it should have been probably all along
Hmm, maybe but it's you know
Commodity over here. It's changed for changes sake it feels, you know to get to my supervisor panel. It's an extra click now compared to what it used to be
True. Yeah, uh, I did. I did see some grousing online about that. I had to downgrade as well
I had a bunch of my automations stop working, uh, particularly around zigbee stuff. Oh, no, so I actually I went to uh,
Dot 12 dot zero, I guess
Uh, and then I upgraded to dot one
The zigbee stuff still wasn't working. So I was like, right i'm going back to dot 11 then
Uh, so there I will stay for a little while and see what happens
Crap I uh, I have not upgraded the rv yet. I've only upgraded the studio. That's how I do it
I do the studio first and then if the studio passes i'll do the it's no big deal with home assistant os and the
snapshots that you can take
so you just put them in google drive and then you just download it and restore and it's as if nothing happened, you know,
So my biggest fear is somehow some update writes something to my z-wave controller or something like that, you know
Don't hurt the z-wave network. Just yeah, I could see that. Yeah
So there was a new configuration panel. What about what did you think of the button entity stuff?
I like it. I've been waiting for something like this because
My wife likes to sometimes use the physical buttons on like a led
Light strip or or a smart plug. She'll sometimes if she's just there. She'll just use the button and that's great
But every now and then home assistant does lose state sync
And so it'll show off or on when we've pressed the button physically
And so now I think i'm just going to replace those with this kind of button, which just makes a lot more sense
just it's just
A switch you press it has a state on or off
But it doesn't move back and forth. It's just a switch that you press
It has a state on or off, but it doesn't move back and forth indicating what its state is. It just says like press
I think that's clean
I like to see this feature users can now be created that are able to log in only from the local network
So, you know if you want just a purely local user you can create that
I'm also pleased to see for you the new jellyfin integration
Yeah, how great of timing is this?
Yeah
um, the only problem is
currently
limited to music only
Which is not great. I'm sure they're going to get there, right?
But it's a good starting spot. We'll see
I would like to see of course video and all of that
Also nice that the hue integration now supports the version 2 of api for the hue lights and hue devices
Which means they show up a lot faster. That's good to see and I have a pie hole
I know you don't use pie hole
But I have pie hole and that integration has been updated to indicate when pie hole needs an update which is nice, too
A few integration changes one thing that came up in the presentation from powerless was some of the work that's been done
In the esp home project that's been upstream to other projects
Yeah, I actually tried setting up for my christmas tree. I did a bunch of
Led's for my christmas tree with running wled
connected to an esp8266 and
Back in the day. I've done a live stream with you actually a couple of years ago now
Yeah, where we had to create an arduino sketch and then upload it and then do all this esp tool-based flashing
Now you can just do it all in the browser and it picks it up in the browser
Oh man, you've got to try it. It's amazing
I love seeing that. Yeah, they give it they give it as due on the live stream now, too
Now that they're all part of the same family. That's good to see
And so I did do the home assistant os7 upgrade. I mean, there's not a lot in this one
Uh, the broadcom and atheros ethernet drivers got updated. That's good to see and this brings the linux kernel up to linux 5 10
8 3
The reason why that kind of matters is linux 5 10 is an lts kernel that will be maintained through the end of 2026
Um, and so if they're going to be rolling their own os
Which i've always kind of been hesitant about but i'm warming up to more and more as time goes on
When I see things like they're using the lts kernel that to me shows that they're making some good long-term thought choices
They're about like how to build something that's going to be potentially run on an iot device for a while
And I that made me feel a little better when I saw they're doing that
So I went ahead and did the upgrade first. I do the os update first. Well first I do a snapshot
Then I do the os update reboot everything and then when it comes back up
I do the home assistant update and uh, it all went pretty good for me. I I don't have nearly the
depth of automations here at the studio that I have at the rv or likely you have at home alex, so
I'll probably wait another week or two before I upgrade the rv just to make sure nothing's going on with zigbee and just to make
Sure nothing's going on with z wave and just to make sure my automations are okay
I mean look I know what's going to happen is if I post in the forum saying I had this issue someone's going to say
well, you've been ignoring this thing in your log files for the last six months this deprecation notice and
I don't know. I just can't be bothered to deal with it. So I downgraded for now
Anyway, speaking of which I think it's time. We did some feedback. Don't you?
Yeah, we wanted to do a bunch for this episode. In fact, we were going to mention it earlier. It's episode 60
It's a feedback special
Indeed 60 episodes. Wow. That's a that's a lot of episodes
When in fact if we've been doing weekly we were 120 by now
Whoa
You see my maths there was it's uh, that's quick pretty quick
Anyway red asks. Do you guys have any naming conventions for your home assistant automations?
Oh, that's a great question
I should I if you were to look at my automations right now, I think i've
I think i've tried three different naming schemes
Uh, you know over the couple years that i've been running home assistant now
It's kind of embarrassing
You are an xkcd comic personified. Are you? Yeah, it's kind of embarrassing
I mean i'm trying to do something like I try and group them, you know button dash
office lights toggle
button dash toggle music room lamps, whatever it is
Uh climate dash
Up and downstairs set to 18 celsius that kind of thing at 8 a.m
I try and make the titles as descriptive as possible starting off with you know, the type of event first, you know
Integration I suppose first. Mm-hmm
Uh, and then if that doesn't work i'll do things like notify dash
So I just have like a single word and then a hyphen and then an explanation of what it does that seems to work. Okay?
Yeah, it's pretty close to what i've i've pretty much landed on
Mine's a little more rudimentary. It's just like if it's if it's a heater and it's being turned on it's heat on dash
Name a heater heat off dash name a heater, but i've pretty much retired all of those now that i'm using the generic thermostat
I used to have a whole bunch that started turn on turn off this turn on that
And when you're looking through a whole group of stuff
You kind of want to group things together a little bit like you want all the bedroom automations to be together
You want all the kitchen things to be together?
Yeah, and so, you know, you've just got to find a logical grouping that works for you and stick with it
That's how I would do it to
Do it so that way all the same areas look all in the same spot
When you're looking at the damn list
All right, alex
Our next one comes in on how to approach a company about building a home assistant integration based on their api
So this is a tricky one a listener of ours
Ran into um, and they have basically
Created an integration that they realize may actually get them in trouble. And so
They're wanting our opinion on the best way to approach companies. It's a european company. Um, they're big in this space
So should they open source the library and just hope for the best should they try to contact the company and get permissions?
What are your thoughts on how they should approach them?
Well, I think it depends on the company. Um, so I mean in the question which is linked to in the show
Notes, there's an awful lot more detail. But essentially this one revolves around reverse engineering token generation
So, I mean if you were to contact this company and say
Hey, I have been able to achieve this result
You will end up in one of two situations one. You'll end up in the swedish school
Voting app situation. I don't know if you saw this uh this in the news a little while ago a couple of parents
A couple of parents, um, basically reverse engineered their school district's app to allow parents to talk to teachers and all that kind of thing
So that they could access the api that was publicly available
and then
Build another app on top of it that was better
So you might end up in a situation that they did
Where the government the local government comes after you and starts issuing cease and desist letters and say hey stop that you're hacking us
Blah blah blah blah blah
Because they don't understand that the publicly available api data is just that it's not hacking. It's just it's available
That is how an api works. Yeah, or
You'll end up in a situation where the company is receptive and you might end up with a job out of it or some kind
Of situation where they're open to people
Willing to work with things like responsible disclosure and all that kind of thing. So yeah
Yeah, don't go posting it all over reddit and twitter as your first port of call
talk to the company first if you're worried it's going to get you in trouble and see what their response is and
Then you can start going down the responsible disclosure routes and all the rest of it
yeah, I think that's all probably pretty good advice you could also try to
You know, maybe go a little linkedin spelunking
See if you can find some people that might be in the right areas of the company for you to reach out to
Uh, if the company has a forum that they run sometimes some of the employees are active in there and you can kind of get a sense
Start get an idea who you're dealing with
This has got to be a wider problem, you know, even when you're not cracking tokens and whatnot
There's a lot of crap out there that could do with some home assistant integration and they just need somebody to come knock on
their door like it
It is a crime against humanity
That the victron, uh folks that like do my inverter and my charge controller and manage all the power in my rv
It's a damn crime against humanity that they don't make a home assistant integration available
Not only does the victron system support mqtt
But it also supports modbus over ethernet and tcp. So there's like two
Really straightforward ways that they could build an integration to get that data
Which would be life-changing?
Life-changing and i've talked to people who built all their own solutions for this stuff
But it's just a great example of like you can find people out there that are reverse engineering it right now for these victron systems
But really what it needs is the company to either document this stuff or come out and do it or or
Enable a community to build something right? That's what we need. And I don't know how we start changing that culture
Because when they're looking at how they're going to spend their engineers time and resources
You know, it's a it's a hard thing to pro and con
It looks it just looks like a waste of time when you're doing it on a pro and con list
I wonder how many more sales people like victron might make
If they advertise the home assistant integration
That's perhaps the angle that you have to approach is is the business angle
To get the product owners interested in spending those development tokens on
What we want them to do. I think it was frank. I think frank on the live stream for home assistant
Said that vans and and mobile applications are actually a very
Large use case for home assistant which blew my mind. I'm like, hey, that's that's me like but that's actually like something that
is a big enough use case it was brought up on the live stream and um, yeah, when you're looking at the energy monitoring capabilities and
Logging and long-term logging now available in home assistant
Uh, yeah, that'd be powerful
Well, james writes in
In defense of portainer after last week's character assassination. I think we gave it. Hey guys
I just listened to 59 where y'all talk about portainer whilst I do love ssh and docker cli for most of my personal life
I think portainer is great at two things at my company
Number one it provides discoverability for new users
We're slowly dragging our company into the wonderful world of containers
But it is slow getting everybody on board
Having a nice gui to show all the options for docker run and to easily store things like docker compose stacks
Or private registry credentials where anyone can access them is a huge benefit to us
Number two, it also provides some level of access control even in the free version remotely
While we could just set up os users for everyone on our big docker test server
It's much easier for me to just let portainer handle it and somewhat lock it down
Especially when it comes to things like the qa team who don't really care about how things work under the hood
They just want to click a button update a container and do their testing. Thanks. I love the show james fair enough
Yeah after we recorded and I was chatting about it with wes
I it did kind of dawn on me. Oh
Right when you got a team of people that might need to poke in on these containers
I start to appreciate a tool like this a little bit more like we have more systems
in the cloud on linode than we probably should without some sort of tool like this because there's a lot of containers out there that
We have running and you know, you've got some and wes and I have some running
I've got some that only i've set up wes has some that only he's set up
We've got a lot of applications that are running in containers up there
I could see how portainer would be nice to manage all that
I think we're probably pushing what you could do with the free version though
I mean don't forget I work on a daily basis with open shift and that really is the value add proposition of open shift
I mean, there's a few more to it when you start getting down into the technical weeds
but really it's presenting a
Cohesive single pane of glass across different clouds
That's really the value out of open shift the hybrid cloud thing that you hear that's that's what it's doing
Is it's giving people a standardized interface to access the underlying abstractions, which in this case are containers
You know and and james who writes in does make a valid point that you know
You can use gooey's to solve that problem. I would argue that also you could use just simple bash aliases and some good documentation
But you know, I worked with some qa teams in the past that really don't care how it works under the hood. They don't care if it's
The perfect technical solution. They just need to close their ticket and move on to the next one. Well, and that's why often
especially
Internal projects you'll go to a web page and there's a button and that button, you know, it's just some hack script
That's just doing something to like, you know
Check something and check something out and put them in the right spot for the qa like it can get real hacky
But they don't care
I'll tell you what I would like to see for jb and this is my own personal wish list that you don't know what I'm
Thinking yet. So this is a voyage of discovery for you here chris. Ooh
Uh, you've been talking about this new server in lup where you want to do tumbleweed or something
Crazy with susa. I don't know what you're smoking over there, but the audience voted
I'm, not i'm not convinced in the legitimacy of the results, but we're proceeding to maintain faith
Well, I was thinking why don't we look at something like k3s, which is like a lightweight kubernetes from the rancher team an open source
thing
That is you know based around kubernetes, which is an industry standard deployment mechanism that we could
Adopt as a network, you know, hmm. Hmm for the on-premise and cloud systems
Perhaps yeah, I mean it's a lot of work for me, but uh, i'm not afraid of a challenge
Hmm. Yeah. Okay. Yeah, we should talk more about it. We should have like a little powwow with west and like, uh, you know brainstorm
I mean there's a bunch of problems to solve like dns and load balancing and
you know access control all that kind of stuff, but
For me when we had that hedge talk outage a couple of weeks ago, it just for me
It was a red flag to say hey chris doesn't have access to this box. Hmm. Perhaps you should fix that alex
Perhaps we should have a more centralized
Way of managing all the jb core services that we use to do the production of these shows
Backblaze.com slash ssh go there to get a free trial. No credit card required. Yeah, it's backblaze
Yeah, it's backblaze. That's right unlimited computer backblaze
That's backblaze. That's right unlimited computer backup for your macs and pcs just seven dollars a month when you go to backblaze.com
Ssh you can restore files from anywhere
You can directly download them from the web
Or I mean if it's a lot you can even restore them by mail you purchase a disc
They'll overnight it to you and then you can just return it to them when you're done for a refund
They also give you access via their mobile app. They've restored over 50 billion files for their customers
Can you believe that?
So go try out a free fully featured no credit card required trial at backblaze.com
Slash ssh. Yeah, that's right backblaze.com
Slash ssh
You guys know about backblaze. This is the opportunity to try it out and support the show
Get a full featured 15 day free trial at backblaze.com
Slash ssh go there play with it and start protecting yourself from a potential bad day start today at backblaze.com
slash ssh
Okay, so five writes in with a science fiction self-hosted vision this is a bit wacky so bear with me
All right, get in story mode
Stay a while and listen
Okay, so I perceive my data as captives on a titan class closed system ship
Some of the captives are treated quite restrictedly
Whilst others might be provided with what seems like paradise with ample food and simulated sunlight and fauna and so on
As we know what appears to be too good to be true typically is too good to be true
There's no telling when the captors decide to unleash a vicious creature or deadly virus on the captives
I envision projects like home assistant jellyfin and matrix as emergency life pods liberating the captives
It would be suicide to take on the whole armada at once, but we are able to rescue a few captives from each platform
Once our libre starship is prepared for their arrival. The captives can adjust to the stable lts systems
And these systems could also be stable container-based systems. Look i'm not judging after the freed captives are acclimatized
We can fly off and break free the next victims behind proprietary space jails
Keep the jupiter broadcasting beacon illuminated for the wayward souls
Okay
I want whatever he was having when he wrote that in that's great
It is true though. I kind of you know, like last episode I was kind of grousing about hosting matrix
But I do feel like it's a bit of a hedge I I totally admit
That discord gets more engagement has a way bigger network effect
It's way simpler for users to get going on and from an administrator's perspective. It's so much less work
but
matrix is ran on my own infrastructure, you know and
Like the I I like that I can have an at jupiter broadcasting account on there. It's a like my domain
And so I feel like it's a bit of a hedge from when it seems like eventually discord's going to turn into like a piece of crap
As all of these social platforms tend to eventually do and so we keep it going, you know, and I also
Like the challenge of figuring out how to manage something like a synapse server, which is a constantly growing and and changing beast
It's just a it's an interesting infrastructure challenge, too
Charles writes in he says i've been listening since episode one
I have an idea for discussion on the show that i'd like to hear you guys chew on
What about self-hosting git? Is it worth that over using something like github? I see so many people in the community
often open source software users
That are just up on github when we have solutions like git lab and get tea and of course, there's just plain git
I'm, not a developer myself, but i'm trying to move my self-hosted services to get based docker
Compose files. Thanks as always so charles wants to know
Your thoughts on like running your own git lab or just using github because I know you use github quite a bit for stuff
Doesn't have to be
An exclusive relationship with github. So that's the thing right? I mean I run a githy server at home
And I mirror every single git repo that I have on github
Using their mirroring functionality built into git tea to my local instance
so I generally go with github on stuff that I know other people are going to see or want to see or
I think they might find useful just simply for that network effect and then everything else, you know
Like my personal wikis and stuff like that
That I don't want sachet to have access to
I keep them in my local githy instance and they never leave my land. You know, it's just
It there are different classifications for different types of data in my opinion and you know
You just got to figure out which one which service works best for that particular piece of code or whatever it is
Man, if that doesn't just sum up
How I kind of weigh the pros and cons of what I cloud host versus what I self host right there actually
Because you're using git for your notes system, right? So that's you know for that reason. Yeah, i'm still figuring that out actually the obsidian
Mixed with drone ci and uh an engine x based container running mkdocs
I am still working on that blog post, but I don't know my you know, since i've become a parent my time just evaporates
I just can't get the blog posts out like I used to I am still working on it and I am still using it but
Maybe i'll get it out before the end of the year, but we'll see
Pew pew pew. All right. It's our last one. Pew pew pew pew and we'd love to get your feedback
Uh, we try to get a couple in every episode and every now and then for a special version of the show like additions
You know like these 60 milestones. It's great. Thank you. Thank you
Like these 60 milestones, it's great to have your feedback so we can just go through all of these
So please send us your thoughts your questions your ideas
Your cool builds whatever it might be at selfhosted.show
Contact and deck bot takes us out with the last one
saying I often hear comments like infrastructure as code as well as
Sentiments like your servers are cattle not pets. Well as a linux system enthusiast
I disagree with that premise my servers are pets. They are special in my heart that said
Once a decade when I finally get around to replacing the hardware i'd like to spend less time potty training them
He goes on to say is there a recommended guide book or a primer for ansible or some other such tools
That would be good for us hobbyist admins. Thanks for the show
It always gets me to try new things kind regards deck bot
I mean, there's a huge bunch of content around for ansible, uh, jeff gehrling friend of the show
Uh, he's got an absolutely amazing ansible 101 series on youtube
Uh, there's a book I read a while back called infrastructure as code by keith morris, which i'll link to in the show notes
As well, um in that book he lays out an infrastructure
framework for defining every part of your infrastructure as text files
Um, and sometimes as we call it code so infrastructure as code. That's what the phrase means
And essentially, you know my take on infrastructure as code is it's actually helping me be less stupid
Because I can't tell you how often I set a system up manually
Even if it's a very simple task like installing one or two packages
uh, and then a year or two elapses and I come back to that server and i'm like
What did I do that for how why? Mm-hmm. And so for me, it's just a case of saving myself a future self a bunch of time
Yeah, I think the other thing I would really like out of it and one of the reasons why I want to get into this
mindset myself is uh, I you can build on things you've figured out before because the
The code is a documentation of sorts you document your infrastructure there
So you can go back and review what you figured out and you can build on top of that for future deployments
Which I like that a lot, but I I am with you deck bot in that. Um,
My servers like my home server in the rv and the server here at the studio
They have real special places in my heart. Like I
I have inappropriate
feels for both of those rigs
but
I get with what the sentiment actually is going for when you treated this cattle. The idea is it's
It's something that if it had to be replaced if its life cycle was complete
It's easy
To replace it's easy to swap out the more I think about the analogy. It's kind of gross but
It I get the idea because if you adopt that that mindset then your data tends to be protected and isolated your
Configurations tend to be off the rig and you're actually in a much better place should there be some kind of hardware failure or other
Disaster just adopting that mindset and kind of deploying things like that. So even even if you still have like the real inappropriate man
Feels like I do
It's still probably a better way to manage them and keep them
And it's getting to the point now where i'm kind of feeling like what alex was alluding to earlier is just like
wiping a clean slate
Redeploying everything and doing the whole thing from the ground up that way, but it just is such a massive project. But
Of course if we ever do it, I think we'd probably document the journey here on the show. Yeah, and you know, we do have an infrastructure
Repo for the show as it stands at github.com
Self-hosted show slash infra which i'll put a link to in the show notes
There's a bunch of terraform in there and ansible in there that I use to deploy all of the show infrastructure that that I manage for
chris
um
But you know, even if you're only implementing a few principles
Within the infrastructure as code kind of ethos
You'll still have a lot further down the road and a lot of people that don't even know what that phrase means
So, you know ten percent of of something is ten percent more than zero
That's right, I like your math today dude, you're like your math whiz
You know, I feel like I should mention
There's there is a possibility. This is going to
Get cancelled because of the news out there, but I feel like I want to mention that
If things go, okay, you know, uh corona wise we are going to have a meetup at the studio january 2nd
And i'm trying out get together because get together is a meetup alternative that you can self-host
I'm trying out their hosted version right now to see how people like it for this small event
And it's get together dot community
Slash jbhq or i'll just have a link in the show notes if you'd like to join us. We're going to have a new server christening party
On january 2nd, assuming I can get everything done by then. I actually haven't even got the things powered on yet
I've been so busy
And then there's also the whole corona thing so it's all up in the air
But if it happens that's where you'll find out about it, even though it says it's at 3 a.m. For some weird reason
Also, i'd like to mention that we've now launched based on popular demand
A network-wide membership
And if you sign up before the end of december, it's coming up quick
I'm taking two dollars off a month for a year
So it's less than the price of two membership two show memberships
And you get access to all the network goodies every show's special features and goodies
And any new shows we add and it's also the only way to get linux action
News totally ad free and of course it supports the network. It gives us that flexibility
To be picky with the sponsors that we choose
It lets us do extra little things like get togethers every now and then and of course it gives us a runway
To make sure that while we are working on developing relationships with sponsors or whoever it might be
Show production continues
That's critical. So jupiter.party if you'd like to join us, you can sign up for the link in the description
That's critical. So jupiter.party if you'd like to sign up for the whole network membership
There's also a gift option right there
And of course you can maintain your self-hosted membership if you'd like to just support the show
If this is your favorite thing that's what you listen to selfhosted.show slash sre
You get our special post show and everything like that. Even if you can't support us with a membership though
We still really appreciate you listening downloading and maybe sharing it with a friend
And the question we've had a few times actually is once I am a member. How do I get access to the member feeds?
So, um, you can log in
at any time to the member area
But right after you sign up it'll actually redirect you to a feed page and it will generate a feed for each show
and um
If I add a show down the road you log into the membership area and you just go pull that new feed
And then you just got to go pop that in your podcast player. That is
It's a custom dynamic feed created just for each member
And we do we do make it possible to subscribe to just the ones you want to listen to so maybe you don't want all
The shows I mean, I know it's wrong with you, but maybe you don't uh, then you can just pick the ones you want in there
Well, very good. Thanks for supporting the show if you're an sre already and good work chris and uh, and wes on that membership
Something that's been in the works for a very very long time. Yeah, you know what?
You know what? It was like we had to connect multiple platforms together, uh three
And then there was like contract stuff because now all of the shows which I didn't say earlier
But this is kind of a big deal too. It's not limited ads anymore. It's ad free
Unless like unless I didn't like manage to get all the ads and I was supposed to
Which shouldn't happen but uh, that's also been a big thing
We've been working at the same time so we could kind of do an upgrade because it's now been a year of memberships
And so we wanted to go from limited ads to no ads
Uh, because you know, and you know what else I hear from some people they don't mind the ads
That's fine. Like you know what? Thank you. Really?
Because we need people listening to the ads too. It helps that way as well
So it works out both ways and it I like having that mix
Because it kind of gives us the flexibility to to be kind of picky to you know, you get these
You almost get like these spam level sponsors that just want to blast all podcasts
You hear them all the time. You probably can think of a few of them off the top of your heads
And that just doesn't serve our audience, right? So that's why I think the memberships are great
You mean you don't want a new mattress in a box every week?
Yeah, there's a lot of those uh, we'd love your feedback like I said earlier self-hosted show slash contact and uh,
You can also find there is a self-hosted. Um, besides we mentioned the discord
There is a self-hosted discord self-hosted show slash discord, but there is also a matrix room
On our jupiter broadcasting matrix server at colony
dot jupiter broadcasting dot com
Rumor has it as well. We're stopping twitter plugs for the foreseeable future now that jack's out
I mean i've been rolling back. Yeah, I feel like if jack's out. I mean do you do you love twitter?
I don't love twitter. I use it. I like it for replying to people. That's what I like twitter for and that's about it
You know
It's nice, you know, I put out a post the other day saying has anybody got any old hardware?
They're looking to get rid of or to sell because I want to benchmark a whole different bunch of quicksync cpus
Um, which i'm working on an article for that
And i've actually had a listener send me a fourth gen cpu who lives in charlotte sent it over
So i'm going to borrow that for a few weeks and do a benchmark. Was that a connection made by twitter? Is that weird?
Yeah, yeah, yeah through twitter. Gotcha. Um, so if you have an old
Old quicksync motherboard you're no longer using let me know via twitter at ironic badger
And uh, I still plugged it. It's just happy. That's okay. I mean, I still like the interactions I have with people on there
I've just been thinking like
If they were going to follow us, they probably have done it by now
So now i've been thinking like maybe i'll plug the matrix
We also have a telegram channel at jupiter broadcasting.com telegram
But you know i'm on there at chris lass
If you tweet at me i'll tweet you back
And if you want to find all of our show notes, you can go to notes
Jupiter broadcasting.com for a searchable archive of the jupiter broadcasting show notes
Uh, and so all that's left for me to say is thank you very much for listening everybody. That was self-hosted.co.uk