I went to the dentist this week for the first time in about 15 years.
Oh, that sounds rough.
It was not pretty. No, no, I came home with a fat lip or a pair of fat lips like a flowerpot man.
I want a selfie next time that happens.
I took a funny video, which I might share with you,
but it's definitely never to be published to the public.
I definitely would never do that.
Yeah, I don't know. So I had this horrible like cleaning procedure done. It wasn't that bad,
actually. I'd psyched myself up that it was going to be awful. And in the end, you know,
I was laying back in the chair and there was a TV on the ceiling and I watched some like
Dwayne the Rock Johnson skyscraper movie and I don't know, it wasn't so bad.
You know, my daughter recently went in and they gave her like goggles
to have video screens in them.
Yeah, what are we doing here, boys?
We need goggles. Hold your breath. No, they got like screens in them and she's like watching
a movie while they go to town on her mouth.
That's the way to do it.
I know.
If they just gave me a little happy gas while I'm at it, we got ourselves a deal.
That's VR, happy gas. I'll be in that dentist seat anytime.
Don't know how I haven't told you this. I bought a Valve Index last week.
You what?
And I haven't told you.
You what? Have you hooked it up?
Speaking of VR, yeah. Yeah, I have.
What's your first impressions?
Beat Saber is my new favorite game. Have you played Beat Saber?
No, but if I got VR, I would. If I got a Quest, which I know is not nearly as awesome,
could we still hang out in the same places? Is that a thing?
I don't know. I mean, I run the game from Steam on Windows.
Yeah, I think anything on the Quest runs from Mark Zuckerberg's bedroom,
but I'm not sure about that.
Well, including the building access systems.
Right. Oh, too soon. I got big dreams, though, of us hanging out in a virtual
studio while we're doing these shows. Something really sweet. The coolest studio you ever saw
on MTV Cribs or whatever, virtually, and then we'd have this ginormous stadium that
the live audience could hang out in. All in VR.
Well, Steam VR has this... It's sort of like the holodeck brought to life. It is awesome.
Awesome. So you load up Steam VR and you put the headset on and you're stood in this kind of
feng shui room with concrete and wood and glass and birds flying and you're on the top of this
mountain and you just feel like you've just transported yourself. It's a bit like that
scene in The Matrix where they open the door and suddenly they're in a completely different
part of the world. It's pretty amazing and the immersion is very, very impressive.
So the Index has a couple of headphones that kind of fold down. They don't touch your ears,
but they sound really pretty good. It's like a pretty solid set of open back headphones
that you're wearing. And the nice thing is it means my wife and I, we can share the headset
without needing... Because I prefer in-ear headphones that go in my ear canal. She prefers
AirPod styles that don't. And so we always had to have two sets of headphones if we wanted to
share before, but with the Index we don't. And you just hook it up to your PC and
does the rest, huh? Yeah, a USB port and a DisplayPort is all you need.
See, I'm trying to, if I get into VR, I'm trying to figure out if that's the route I want to go,
or if something like the Quest is the route I want to go where there's, if I want, there's no
PC at all and it's portable, which might make it easier for the kids to use too. You do need a good
amount of space for the Index, you know, sort of six feet by about 10 feet. Oh yeah, sure, sure.
Yeah, so that would sort of be a studio device, whereas the other one might be better in the RV.
Yeah, I could see it, you know, in the room behind you in the studio. It would probably
fit in there just fine. I mean, you know, mostly I just want to play Super Mario,
so if I could just get Super Mario working on these things, I'm set.
I did have a moment though where I loaded up Microsoft Flight Sim and I was sat in the cockpit,
I've got a joystick, several years ago, Flight Sim in VR and I'm flying and I came into one of
these scenarios they set up for you, like a sightseeing scenario, and I was transported
instantly to this plane flying over Loch Ness in Scotland. And I looked down and I thought to
myself, I stayed in that caravan site as a kid. Wow. And I then looked it up on Google Maps
afterwards and I was like, holy crap, I was right. That was the caravan site. And you know,
there was the Jacobite steam train going along the bottom of the campsite and all that.
So the graphics in Flight Sim are truly remarkable and I was quite struck by it because I remember
thinking the first Flight Sim I played was probably MS 2002. I think Concorde was in that one. And I
remember, I think it was just before Concorde was retired. And you know, I lived in the south
of England and Concorde used to fly over my house every day. It was awesome. And I just remember
thinking back then, oh, these graphics are amazing. How could they possibly get any better?
And then I was struck wearing the VR headset as I flew past Ben Nevis, you know, at the same height
as Ben Nevis, the tallest mountain in the UK. And I sort of looked to my side and I was like,
huh, there's a mountain there and there's the campsite there. And I was sort of moving my head
around in real time thinking, wonder where we'll be in 20 years. Oh, no kidding. I've heard that
I've never seen it, but I've heard that the team also really nailed the Pacific Northwest because
obviously Redmond, their hometown area. So if you want to fly around my neck of the woods,
I guess it's supposed to be pretty accurate. Yeah, they use this photogrammetry thing,
which is based on the famously good Bing maps, although actually it is pretty impressive. Like
the 3D modeling and stuff of certain cities is truly spectacular. There's a few things like
bridges over the River Thames, for example, that are definitely in need of some work, but they're
issuing patches all the time and it's improved hugely since launch. So, you know, if you have a
VR headset, you're thinking about buying one, I would say Flight Sim is probably a must play.
Well, now you really made me want one. Alex, you do that. We do these episodes and I'm like,
I got to get that. It's easy to spend other people's money. I'll tell you that.
You know, I think we have a theme though today that could save people some money.
But I was about to say, you know, we're on the topic of gaming and a listener wrote in with a
project called RetroNAS. And I thought with the Steam Deck coming out soon that we might see
a resurgence of handheld gaming, of retro gaming, you know, people playing Mario Kart on handhelds,
as well as, you know, Grand Theft Autos and all sorts of cool stuff. I know the Steam Deck can
play some AAA titles, but I doubt that will be the primary use case for a lot of folks.
Oh, really? Hmm. Okay. I do like the idea of getting some of my retro games on the deck.
So you're right. I would I will be getting like a Super Nintendo emulator on that one handheld
device that can play Nintendo games, Sega games, PC games, anything you can think of pretty much
because it's just a computer, right? It's just a laptop, essentially, in a little handheld
switch size device. And once you think within a short period of time, the Linux community is
going to have respins of SteamOS with emulators baked in and whatnot. The community for this thing
is going to be bonkers. You think how big it is for the Switch. Now, the Switch is a lockdown
platform. Think how big it's going to be for the Steam Deck that is free and open and running
Linux, baby. I mean, how cool is that? It might be the most exciting thing that's happening on
the Linux desktop at the moment, period. Yeah, it could be, you're right, because it's also a
plasma desktop. So anyway, we were talking about RetroNAS briefly, and this is a project which
allows you to use any kind of Linux computer, so a Raspberry Pi, an old PC, a VM, whatever it might
be, as a network storage device for different gaming consoles and emulators. And at first,
I was like, isn't RetroNAS basically just Samba? What is this project doing that a network share
wouldn't do? And it turns out, actually, it's doing loads. So a lot of these older consoles
require things like Samba version one and Apple file protocol and all sorts of stuff that's been
a long time deprecated for security reasons. And so what RetroNAS does is it very clearly states,
we are doing stuff that is insecure, here be dragons. But what they're doing is they're
actually serving games up over the network using all these old protocols to all these old game
consoles. And one example, we have several links in the show notes of the project founder, his
YouTube channel, Dick Freaks. There's one example here where he's actually loading up games and
ripping ISOs from his PlayStation 3, storing the ISO on his NAS, and then streaming the ISO back to
the PlayStation without the disk in it to play it offline and basically DRM freeing the game forever.
Oh, that's the dream. You know, when the very first Xbox came out, I got on board that hacking
train as fast as possible because you could get the games on the hard drive and avoid having to
fetch the disk and the load times. This sounds like the sweet spot because you could get a
Pi-powered NAS and then you could go pick up a used PlayStation, like a PS3 right now,
how much could that be? And you could basically have trouble-free appliance gaming.
100, 150 bucks, something like that. Yeah. You know, it's funny, I don't even think retro.
When you say retro gaming, I think even older than that, but I guess that is retro.
PS3 is 10 years ago? Maybe more? So the list of consoles that's supported,
there's quite a few. So MS-DOS and clones, like FreeDOS and PC-DOS, Windows 95 and up.
We've got Apple GS and classic Mac systems. Atari ST is supported. Amiga's the Nintendo 3DS.
So it's pretty cool to see a Nintendo console on this list. The PS2, the PS3, Xbox 360,
as well as many more are planned in the future. That is pretty neat. You know, I know I'm a bigger
retro gamer than you are in part because I've just never really moved on. But also I like retro
gaming for the exact reason you don't like it, Alex. I so rarely have any time to play.
And games like Mario are so easy to pick up and play for 15 minutes and then put down again.
And so I've kind of been biased towards some of the older Marios because I can load them up on
low-power devices and they're great for road trips. Yeah, I mean, I still play an awful lot of some of
my favorite older games, retro games, but I've always been a PC gamer first rather than a console
guy. My kind of god tier list of games is Factorio, Open Transport Tycoon, or the original
Transport Tycoon I did used to play before Open TTD. Rollercoaster Tycoon, Sim City 4 is great.
I'd say those four are probably my top ones. As far as PC games go, I've always, always preferred
games that support some kind of LAN play. I don't generally finish games, but if I can co-op or group
play a game, I will finish that thing all the way to the end every time. I love that kind of stuff.
And I've done some of these early games that required IPX. I want to say the first Starcraft
I played wasn't over TCP IP on a LAN, but I want to say it was over Net Buoy or IPX or something
that's just totally not even supported anymore. Showing your age there, bro.
I know! You're right, actually, right? Do people even know the struggles that we had to deal with
with Net Buoy and the pain that Microsoft inflicted upon the networking world back in
the day? No, nobody even cares. I don't even remember a time before TCP IP, I'm afraid.
Yeah, and then WINS came along. WINS was just supposed to solve it, but they had to have their
own thing. They couldn't choose to use DNS. Oh my goodness, you got me all upset. The very first
game, I think there's two that come to mind, the very first games I ever played, there was Stunt
Car Racer. My nan had a computer with a five and a quarter inch floppy bay in it. That was on a,
I can't even remember what the OS was. There you go, it was that long ago. But then the next one,
the first game that I ever had really of my own besides Lemmings at school was Monster Truck
Madness. Oh, okay. The first game I really saw take off, oh my God, I'm doing it again. This
is your fault. It was Oregon Trail. Oregon Trail was really big when I was in school. And we had
just green screens, green and white monochrome type screens, but it was green. And I remember
playing Oregon Trail on that to the point where, and there was a buddy in me and we'd play on it
and then we'd leave it on and it burned in on the school screen. The CRT guy, Oregon Trail burned
in on it. Oops. I remember seeing that like betting screens in the UK used to have like
CFAX pages. I don't know if you know what CFAX was, but it was like a version of the internet
before the internet, but it came through the TV. I don't know a better way to describe it than that.
It was kind of fun. Like everybody knew their favorite page number. Like a 606 for me,
for example, was like now and next on the TV channels. Like it came out with a little
like end curses style display. It was pretty cool. Now I think about it. Yeah, that sounds
really rad. But anyway, all the betting shops, they used to be like sports scores on CFAX as
a whole section. And they used to have these CRTs burned in with these CFAX logos and stuff.
Oh yeah. Yeah. The CRT burning thing was real in the library and the school too.
Um, and of course the other game that was a hit back in the day was Where in the World
is Carmen Sandiego. It's coming out on- Yes. Oh, I do remember that one.
Played that on DOS all the way into Windows. I played that from the text era into the graphical
era. I was so young. I didn't really know where any of the places were or how to even pronounce
like Budapest. I remember I was like, where is that? Well that's miles away. It's Hungary.
Goodness me. You know, it'd be fun to fire that up again though. The nostalgia factor
helps make up for the lackluster graphics. I don't mind a game with low graphics because
I can play it on a computer and the computer won't turn into a ball of liquid metal on my lap.
That's nice. True. Yeah, very true. Linode.com slash SSH. Go there to get $100 and 60 day credit
on a new account and you go there to support the show. Just think of it like this. Linode is fast,
reliable cloud hosting. You just, you got to go try it and that's why they're giving you $100
to really go kick the tires. That's like Linode just showing you that they're confident that when
you go try it and you really get a chance to use it for a bit, you're going to stick around.
And I think you'll like it. They have a good mix of performance. They have 11 data centers
around the world. They have customer support that's going to help you when you need it.
They're available 365. They've been upgrading their infrastructure. So a little bit ago,
they started rolling out bare metal systems. Of course, they have invested heavily in their
networking over the years. So they are their own ISP. And most recently they're rolling out PCI
and BME storage on some of their systems. And not too long ago, they upgraded their
Optron processors and some of their high-end CPU rigs. I mean, they're just, they're constantly
trying to make sure you get the best performance for your buck. They got a great UI. And if you're
ready to kind of get fancy, they also have an API that it's pretty straightforward to use. It's
well documented. And they have a command line client that you can get on any OS. I have installed
on my systems. And you can do simple things like take snapshots and reboot. You can create systems.
You can upload files to the object storage, all from the command line. And that's kind of like a
power way to use Linode. We have just about every critical system we've built with the exception of
a rig here at the studio that runs a few things in the last couple of years. We look at it as a
balance of like some things we decide to self-host and a lot of things we decide to manage ourselves
on Linode's cloud. Because it strikes the balance of security, performance, and ownership and control.
I love all of that. Plus, I also like taking advantage of the backup options. Before we go
make a big change on a server that's in production, I'll go take a backup on Linode. And I have
automatic backup set too. And the thing that's great about it is you can easily review where
they're at, when the last backup was, and all that kind of stuff. And you can also use that
command line client to initiate a quick backup if you want to go that route as well. And having
those kinds of tools there, plus things like S3 compatible object storage, they've brought a
small businesses game up to like a next level that we couldn't have achieved otherwise. And
the pricing is 30 to 50 percent lower than the big hyperscalers that just want to lock you into
their crazy complex platforms. So go try it out and support the show and see what 19 years of
working on something is built. That's Linode. And you can get it for 60 days and $100 and
support the show. That's like a trifecta of awesome. Linode.com slash SSH.
All right. So our very own, the orange one, is going to be hosting this weekend a matrix
setup party. So for those of you who aren't quite sure what matrix is, we're talking about the
messaging system, not bullet time, bullet dodging, dodgy reboot, matrixes, matrices, matrix I
matrices, matrixes. I like matrices. I think that sounds better. OK, well, if you're not sure what
one of those is in the chat context, come along this Sunday, the 13th of February at 12 p.m.
Eastern, and we will take you through or certainly the orange will take you through
how to set up matrix and elements and all that kind of good stuff and try and figure out exactly
what decentralized chat is all about. I mean, that's pretty exciting. You know,
matrix has so much damn potential, but it needs more users and the chat clients just need more
time. We have a matrix server at Colony.JupiterBroadcasting.com. And one of the things
you can do is you can self host your own matrix server at your own domain, and then you can come
join and hang out our matrix server using the account from your server. You also could just
create an account on our server. We have that open to the public as well. But I kind of love it
because I can go hang out like I'm in a Red Hat matrix room and I'm in there as Chris at
JupiterBroadcasting.com. Right. Everybody knows it's me and it's my domain and it's all I love
that aspect about matrix. It's also it's it's a slack killer. It integrates with Jitsi and it'll
do video conferencing and screen sharing and you can have individual channels and you can have
spaces that are groups of rooms and and and individual channels all in different kind of
categories. So we have like a self hosted channel. We have a couple of them in our on our matrix
server and we have a channel for each one of the shows. We have even have a channel for
cryptocurrency all on our matrix server. That's sort of like how we do it on Discord as well.
And then the last thing I'll just say about matrix and the orange one could probably tell you way
more. The last thing I'll just say is they offer this technology called bridging and it's hit and
miss. But one platform it's actually pretty good bridging with is Discord. So you can bridge some
of the rooms and this is how theoretically we may want to do it one day. We could bridge the SSH
feedback room on matrix with the SSH feedback room on Discord. Right. You just bridge like
couple of the rooms together, not all of them, but like a couple of them. And that's totally
something we might be able to do one day. And matrix has bridges for lots of other services,
pretty much anything you can think of with various success and hosting a matrix server that has lots
of users is kind of a complicated thing that we're always tweaking with. Even just this week,
Wes and I are troubleshooting a few things on our matrix server, which has always been an
educational process. So I would totally say it's worth checking out because even if you don't do
anything with matrix, it's probably something you should know about. That's just it. So I came into
the chat room a couple of weeks ago and said, Hey, I want to go to the FOSDEM talks because
they were running that through matrix this year. What's an element? What's a matrix? Like, what's
a riot? What's all the, how do all these different things plug it? It's really quite confusing,
to be honest with you. So yeah, this Sunday, 13th of February at 12 PM Eastern, ironically enough,
we're going to host this on the self hosted discord server. I thought so. Okay. Hey, you know
what? I totally acknowledge discord is way simpler and has much simpler onboarding too. So it's easier
for the admins and the users. Matrix is just, it's self hosted and it's decentralized. And I find
that extremely appealing. There'll be a link in the show notes. Don't worry too much.
Now, did you see this week that NABU CASA have increased their prices by 30%?
Yeah. So, hmm, this, I have mixed reactions because, uh, I have been recently going through
a period of reducing all of my subscriptions and trying to minimize how many subscriptions I have.
And they, they've gone and raised the price right as I'm doing the math on absolutely everything.
Um, I've decided to stick with it because, uh, I think they've already made some of the
infrastructure improvements that they claim the money's going to go to. I think that's already
been done and I've already noticed things are better. And, um, to be honest with you,
I almost feel like I should be giving them more money, you know, because I use the hell out of
home assistant. So what they're doing is they're taking the $5, the optional $5 a month subscription
for home assistant that you can pay to enable some cloud features, remote access, that kind of stuff.
They're taking it from five to $6.50 per month. They've also introduced a new annual tier of $65
a month, $65 a year. I mean. Right. $65 a year. And these prices all seem really quite fair to me.
And if they had another tier, I may even, or, or if they had some sort of annual donation drive or
something like that, because I get utility out of home assistant in my RV and in my studio, and I,
I use it here in the studio to help control and manage lighting. When I get here and I get to work,
home assistant manages that and home assistant manages the lighting in my office as well.
Like you say, I don't really want to see the price go up, but also now I stop and think about it and
talk through it with you. I sort of think. Yeah, $6.50 for the amount of money that you're going to
I sort of think. Yeah. $6.50 for the amount I use something. I mean, every day, multiple times a day,
I'm opening that app or doing something and it's, it's a huge part of my life. And I think, um,
future houses, like the, the house, my dad's buying, I mentioned on the last episode,
we're talking about temperature sensors and lighting and, you know, it's going to be the
heart of everything, you know, around houses and RVs and yeah, I do for the next 10, 20 years. So
I want to see this project succeed and stick around. And yeah, if $6.50 a month is the price
to do that, then make it sustainable, then great. You know what, if they had a plan that was
nine bucks a month, that let me connect to home assistant instances, because that's a problem.
Like, how do I do this when I have two different home assistants in two different locations? And
I'd like them both to be on the cloud, but I don't want on the Nebuchadnezzar cloud,
but I don't want to have two different Nebuchadnezzar accounts. I just don't really
bother with one of them, but yeah, exactly. Exactly. Also noteworthy, they've hired two
more individuals, um, working on different aspects of a home assistant, including ones
are going to be working on more like YouTube channel stuff, uh, and some home assistant front
end. Um, I'll be frank with you. It's probably the old man in me. I have been doing internet
content for 15 years and I never like it when projects directly get into content creation.
There is a space for it in terms of how to's and guides, and if they're done correctly,
I think they're useful. But, uh, a lot of times it creates an echo chamber and it's a hard thing
to kind of wrap your head around, but there's a long-term effect when the project sort of becomes
the source of the content creation. It kind of has a knock-on effect, a kind of an ecosystem effect
on the places that cover it, usually for the negative, unless they get it just right. We'll
see. It's a weird use of the funds too, but we'll see. What if rather than directly putting out
content under the home assistant brand, this person almost becomes a consultant for other
YouTubers to reach out to directly. You know, if they want to create a video about a certain topic,
they reach out to this person and say, how do I have all these sensors average and connect to
a thermostat or something like that? I would just adjust that slightly to just say media outreach,
because you've got a lot of people writing about home assistant. You've got a lot of people
podcasting about home assistant. I would, I would open it up beyond, you know, what,
now that you say this and again, we're talking through this, it's, it's the limitation on
YouTube. Like the YouTube community creates a distorted reality of the user base. It does this
to Linux. It does this for any project. The YouTube audience doesn't reflect the entire user base.
And so you want to get out to other media outlets as well. And there's going to be a lot of people
as home assistant grows, they're going to want to learn and start writing about it or start
podcasting about it. And so I think if they had somebody who was there to help those people get
that stuff right, because a lot of times it happens to somebody will come along. They're
going to start covering home assistant for the first time. They'll get something wrong.
They won't understand why, what, what decision, you know, three years was made. And so they'll
interpret something that happens today and they'll get it wrong and they won't have the context.
Because they're still learning. And that's just what happens and doesn't prevent people
from making videos. And so if there was somebody at home assistant that had the time, the bandwidth
and the skillset to interface with those creatives and help guide them in the right direction,
I could see that being useful. That could be a good use of time and money.
Now, the other thing we should mention about the subscription price increase is that those changes
don't come into effect for existing accounts for three months. So you get three months
grandfathered in at the old price before things start to go up.
And just a last couple of notes about this home assistant release that came out along with the
announcement on February 2nd about the price increase. They now show the size of your backups
in the backup view. That's a nice little tweak. Apple TV users, the integration has been updated
to support OS 15 and now can also launch apps from home assistant.
That sounds kind of cool. If you think about like some automations or something like, you know,
set up TV time and have an auto launch plex or infuse. Yeah, because that extra click is real
difficult. Oh, come on. Come on. You would be trying it if you if you hadn't got rid of your
Apple TV. Come on. Oh, maybe, maybe. I mean, I've been able to do it on the shield for years and I
never have. So maybe not. I'm moving in the new house, Chris. You know what I'm saying? That's
true. I do know what you mean. Google Assistant integration can now be set up to use local
fulfillment. Hey, oh, I am still waiting, though. I was just telling you before we started the show,
I'm still waiting for updates on the home assistant yellow or amber or whatever they want
to call it. And like when we could kind of expect that for those of us who threw some money in,
because I'm looking at my home assistant setup and I'm thinking that's probably going to be the
time I redo it is when I get that home assistant amber and or yellow. And I just love to kind of
know what kind of timeline I should be thinking of the home assistant burnt sienna 2042 edition.
That's what it will be. Tailscale dot com slash self hosted. Go there to get a free personal
account for up to 20 devices and it supports the show. Tailscale dot com slash self hosted. I
probably don't have to tell you about tailscale because you guys probably already know and just
have been waiting for an opportunity to try it out. Well, this is it. You can get it set up on
any device in minutes, manage firewall rules, and of course it'll even bust through that dreaded
double net. I can tell you from experience, your devices connect directly to each other,
not through tailscale, but directly to each other in a mesh wire guard network. It's so slick. And
Alex and I are both daily users. I often will connect back to lady jupes and manage something
from the studio now, like getting in over a VPN was like the thing that was super hard for me to
solve with my carrier nat. And now it's like I just pop on each one of my boxes, get things started,
get things thinking. It's so awesome, Alex. And that mesh network portion is so cool. So,
you know, picture this, right? I wanted to back up about three terabytes worth of data to England
across the ocean to that Synology box that I took back there to my mom's house a few months ago.
She has a BT home hub, which is a famously crappy router. And you know, I don't want to do port
forwarding in there. I don't want to have to talk her through anything. So what did I use? I've been
using tailscale for this for the last few months and it's just been absolutely perfect. Every time
I fire up restic boom straight through the tunnel, it does the script. I have tailscale up. It connects
through a dedicated IP address on a specific subnet and using the magic DNS feature that's
built right into tailscale. I don't even have to remember any numbers or anything like that. It's
just boom, boom, boom, done, simple. And it's, it's been so reliable. I almost forget that I'm using
it. It's always up. It's always on. And I like the fact that every machine now essentially has a
static IP in my brain. You know, it doesn't matter where I'm at. They all just have a static IP I
connect to. I threw it on my iPad. I connect to LTE. I can get on my system super quick. I'd love
it. You got to check it out. If you've been waiting to try it, this is your opportunity. You're going
to be shocked how fast you're going to get this up and going. I mean, I, I even have it running
on my raspberry pies. It's so great tailscale.com slash self-hosted. Mike writes, I've been loving
your show so far. You guys seem to have some pretty elaborate setups, which brings me to a
question as someone just starting out in the self-hosting world. How do you balance progress
and perfection? I frequently find myself at a roadblock in my setup because I feel like I need
to be doing something the optimal way the first time. And as a consequence, I just never do it at
all. Hmm. I can feel that for sure, because, uh, when we, when we decided to start the show, I also
had been working on this concept in part from a conversation we had with Wendell about craftsmanship.
And I had decided that I wanted to take real craftsmanship in my self-hosted stuff that I do.
And so I, I really got in my head with that forbidden also sort of struggled with perfection.
And that saying is so true that perfection is the enemy of the good enough really. Uh,
and here's what I came to. And I wonder if what you do, Alex, in this case, but what I realized
about myself is that I'll get into something deep. I will become I I I'm so smart, Alex,
I a galaxy size brain here. I will become so informed on a topic. It's unbelievable. And then
I know all of it now. And I, I arrogantly assume that I will remember all of it. And then six
months later, I have forgotten 98% of everything I learned. And I am a total smooth brain idiot.
And that, and I realized that about myself and now have decided that I must document while I'm at
peak knowledge. So I must document. And then I have also, if I hit a roadblock and I don't
implement the perfect solution, I document what I thought I wanted to do and why I couldn't do it
and what I did instead. So I can always work back if I, if I ever want to revisit the project and
get it right. Yeah. That was why I started linux server.io was it was actually just my personal
blog writing down how I compiled that kernel where I think I was doing unraid on top of, uh,
arch or something back in the day. And documentation is just so important, but, uh, I was
laughing so hard whilst you were saying that, like I'm the world expert on this topic. And then six
months later, I can't remember any of it. It's so true. Yeah. And you just gotta like, you gotta
like learn that about yourself if that's how you operate. And like the guys that are probably, you
know, like really a level above us are the ones that retain it all right. Those people, I don't
know how people like Wendell do it. And you mentioned him in your, in your little bit and
like he can just rattle off model numbers and cereal and, and, you know, specific kernels and
builds. And I'm like, how do you remember all that stuff? I can't even remember, you know,
I bought a bag of pumpkin seeds to put in my banana bread this morning. I can't even remember
where that is. It's been half an hour. How do you remember anything? Um, it's really impressive.
So I think if you document where the shortcomings were in your setup and then you just, it kind of
gives you permission to proceed because like, it's like, okay, I've written it down. I've
captured my thoughts. And you'll also find that you think through things a little more clearly,
at least in my case, and then you move forward. There is a phrase, isn't there? And this doesn't
just pertain to it, but it's analysis paralysis. And you know, you can go down this rabbit hole
with anything, you know, buying a car, buying a house, building some infrastructure for your home,
self-hosted needs, whatever it might be. And at some point you've just got to stick a pin in it
and say, right, this is the way I'm going to do it. It might not be the best, most optimalist way
to do something, but at the end of it, you will have built something and you'll have gained some
experience along the way of doing it. And, you know, in six months time, you may well decide,
well, actually I shouldn't have exposed that particular service over the internet without
a password. For example, maybe I should put it behind a VPN or put it at least like a rough
lesson. Right. Exactly. But I mean, you know, I've admitted on this show before I ran remote desktop
open to the internet and the password was two, two, that was it. The numbers, two, two.
What could go wrong? What could go wrong? Bizarrely nothing. But I mean, a lot could have,
you know, and nowadays it makes me rather scared. I did that for as long as I did that. But anyway,
oh man, so many things, so many things back in the day, Alex, so many things, you know,
the internet was a different place back then. It truly was. Now, Mike, you've got to think about,
is there any value in just sitting there, twiddling your thumbs, thinking about stuff?
Yeah, some, but there's going to be a lot more value in making mistakes. You'll learn to fail
faster. You'll learn that, you know, this particular building block doesn't fit with that one. And
actually I need to do it this completely different way. And you'll just learn so much more by doing
it. So my advice, such as it is, would be start small, solve a real problem that you have, and
then just start building on top of it. Maybe write a little bit of automation to do it as well,
if you want to, once you've done it a few times manually and kind of got the hang of it. And
after then you'll be surprised within, you know, a few weeks just how quickly these things start
to snowball and start to build on top of each other. You know, to tie it all together,
if you wanted a project, if you've been wanting to get into something like this or take your skill
set up to the next levels, you mentioned automation there. And the orange one is doing that get to
no matrix session. There is a super popular deploy matrix on a system using Ansible going around
right now that does a pretty good job. Wes and I were taking a look at it and we think we may
actually use it in the future. And so that could be a great opportunity to combine your peanut
butter and your chocolate and, you know, learn a little something about Ansible, learn a little
something about matrix. I ate my first PB&J this week. Your first? First one. I'm not even shitting
you. Like I've never had one before. All right. Okay. Okay. Tell me. Okay. Hold on now. Hold on.
Tell me about the bread. I got it. We got to start at the beginning. What kind of bread was it?
Where was it? Was it at home? Homemade bread. You know, after the pandemic, I'm a bread bro now.
I'm a world expert on bread, you see. What kind of peanut butter? Jif. Okay. Crunchy or smooth?
Crunchy. Yeah. All right. Now, did you have any problems tearing the bread?
Tearing? Why do I need to tear it? Well, sometimes when you apply the peanut butter,
the bread can tear if you're new. It's proper bread with a good gluten structure, dude.
Tell me about the jelly. It was grape jelly. It was very nice. Although the English people
are probably sat here going, jelly. It's actually jam. You know, it's what we would call jam.
I mean, grapes are right. Grapes are right. It's okay. So how thick is the bread?
About the thickness of a finger. Okay. All right. So not too thick. Chunky. Not too thick. Nice crust.
Now, what's your ratio of peanut butter to jelly? I just did one slice covered in a reasonable
thickness of PB and then the other slice covered in a reasonable thickness of J. Slam those bad
boys together. Now, I need to know what a reasonable thickness is because I actually
go a little heavy on the jam. Oh, about 37 microns. I don't know. How do we measure this?
Were they equally proportioned? It's important because you need slightly more jam to get the
moisture ratio right. Oh, I see. Okay. Yeah. We don't have a standardized jam measurement
system in this country though. I mean, you like to measure things in feet and inches.
Maybe we should say I scraped my jam in eight elbows thickness. You measure an American. What
you do is just put some on there and then put a little bit to where it seems like too much.
And then that's just right. Okay. That's how you do it. Okay. So what'd you think of it though?
Consider it a beta, but don't consider it the final word on peanut butter and jelly because
let me tell you, you can really take those things up to 11. Like there's some toasting
techniques you can do and stuff that'll really take it up a notch. But what'd you think?
It's a delicious, delicious sandwich. It is a beautiful mix of sweetness and gooeyness. And
oh, where has it been all my life? Budget-friendly, quick to make. You could take the loaf
and the peanut butter and the jam and you can just bring it to work or bring it with you. I mean,
just the port, it's just, it's great. Kids love it too. So anyways, moving on. I just,
that's amazing. Thank you for sharing that. That was great.
I'm still trying to assimilate into your culture.
Yeah. I mean, I don't know what you haven't done yet. That's a big one. I wish I could have been
there for that. I didn't know. Had I known, I would have been there, but I'm sure we'll find
some others. Well, I've never bought any tactical pants. I've still got to do that. Okay. All right.
That is something. You're going to love tactical pants. It's all about the phone storage capacity.
Okay. You ever wanted to have your wallet in your pocket and not even feel it? Tactical pants.
Well, my wallet is about the thickness of three credit cards as it is. So.
Oh yeah. Yeah. You've worked on it. Good. Good. All right. Well, Luke liked it last week when
we talked about self-hosted music options, but he says, I just wanted to add one thing.
The subsonic compatible clients are a lot more polished than the jellyfin ones. So he says,
check those out. There's some shims that let you use the clients with jellyfin on iOS or Android,
and gives us a couple of links that we'll toss in the show notes. You know what? I have good memories
of subsonic and I know that that's gone a couple of different directions over the years, but for
just a brief period of time, I had subsonic downloading all of my podcasts and then I was
streaming them using apps from the subsonic server. And so I could kind of keep my play
position sync across, synced across all my devices using that. It was so great.
Now, Sam writes in, and I think this is a question for you, Chris. My partner and I are about to
embark on our first ever week-long road trip around the North coast of Scotland, the Scottish 500.
We've rented a van conversion for it and we'll be out of reliable cell service for much of it.
I've got about three weeks of time and a drawer full of raspberry pies and USB hard drives.
Do you have any recommendations for a quick and dirty mobile media server
to keep us entertained in the evenings after a long day's drive?
Hmm. So you're going to need a mobile power. So you're probably going to want to look at like one
of those Yetis or not Yetis. What do they call it? The blue Yeti.
Jackery.
Jackery is another one. Yep. There's several of those portable power units. You're going to want
something that is easy for you to charge while you're driving. Like you could plug it into the
cigarette lighter while you're driving. And then I assume they have them over there and then you
just run it over, you know, you have full charge and you just run it while you're parked. And then
I think you're also going to want a LTE router like the, I can't remember what we recommended
before. You probably do Alex, that little slate router that we've recommended before that you
can actually use to do Wi-Fi and also manage the LTE connection.
The GIO Inet.
Inet. Yes. Thank you. Cause you're going to need networking. And then you could connect
the Raspberry Pi directly to the TV using HDMI out if you're adventurous like that.
Or you could get something like the fire stick or some of the other, or maybe if you already have
a set top box at home, you just bring it with you. And cause you'll need something to get the
picture onto the TV. And that's it. So you'd need power, networking, and a way to get it on the TV.
And then for the Raspberry Pi, what I would recommend, since you're only going to use it
for a road trip, right? It's not like it's going to be like your setup for five years,
load the thing up with some USB storage on a hub. It works. I know it's crazy, but you can,
you can take a USB hub, you can plug a couple of like one terabyte disc or two terabyte discs in
there. And then like a maniac, what you do is you just use butter FS on those because it's
Raspberry Pi. You're not going to want to use CFS, trust me. And you can just join those two
discs together as one volume. So if you got to say, for example, two, one terabyte external disc,
I recommend SSDs. If you're in a van, it'll show up as a two terabyte volume and you could get those
off Amazon or if you maybe already have them, something like that. And that'll work great.
What about even more simple than that? Just a laptop.
Yeah. And especially if you don't have a TV in the van, right? Or a tablet.
It's got speakers. It's got a battery in it already. You won't need any networking.
If you got an iPad too, you could do like the Plex sync thing.
Yes. Plex sync. Does the iPad support playing videos back from USB storage?
But imagine it will, right?
You could use Infuse on the iPad to do that.
Yeah. Lots of options.
Yeah.
And the speakers on the iPad pro are particularly good, I must say.
Yeah. Really depends on what you already have.
Depending on what you have, if you've got the Pi's, I mean, really, if you've got two Pi's,
you could have one be the NAS and you could have one set up as, you know,
connected to a television playing the videos.
Not everybody's a double Pi wielding maniac like you, Chris.
Some of us are. Yeah. Well, he says he's got a drawer full, actually, right? So are she?
Say they've got a drawer full.
He does, in fairness, say that in the question.
In the question.
So I actually kind of feel like I might consider then
setting up like a Kodi or something like that on a Raspberry Pi.
I mean, unless you already have a set top box, then I'd probably go that route.
Thanks for the question though, Sam.
Lots of feedback this week. So thank you all very much for writing in.
Several more of you wrote in about the East Coast spring meetup that I kind of floated
as a vague idea in the last episode.
So enough of you wrote in. I think we're actually going to do this provisionally.
I'm thinking somewhere around the start of April in Raleigh.
I'm not entirely sure when what type of food we'd have, probably like a brewery where we can
always go and get snacks and beers and that kind of thing and be outside.
So it's all safe right in these times.
And yeah, so just keep an eye out on the meetup page for that.
I'll obviously announce it in the show as well and see if I can't convince a certain
Mr Fisher to fly out as well, maybe.
I imagine it's pretty, pretty nice there in April, right?
Apart from the pollen, the pollen can be pretty bad, but it's...
I don't know if that gets me too bad.
It's beautiful weather.
Yeah, like a self-hosted fest kind of thing, which normally in April, like I'm gearing
up for Linux Fest, but there's no Linux Fest this year.
Yeah, that's what I'm thinking. We need our Linux meetup in April.
Yeah. Well, thank you to our members, our SREs who keep the show going.
You help keep it independent. We get to be choosy about the show.
We get to be independent. We get to be choosy about our sponsors.
We truly like and use Linode and Tailscale.
So we can wait until the right sponsor comes along and pick to work with the sponsor we
think is a good fit for us and our audience.
Our members give us the leverage to do that.
And when you sign up at selfhosted.show.com you get an ad-free version of the show and
an extended version of the show with a post-show at the very end.
You can also support the entire network and get access to all of the network shows,
at jupyter.party.
And as you well know by now, selfhosted.show.com is the place to go to get in touch with us.
You can find me on Twitter at ironicbadger.
You can find me on Matrix at ChrisLAS.
Boom! Oh! I think.
I don't really know how you find me on there, but join me on there and say hi.
And as always, thanks for listening, everybody.
That was selfhosted.show slash 64.