Coming up on self-hosted 12. I'm back from the forest and Oregon was solar on board
Alex has gone nuts and installed wikis for two weeks and then he'll tell us about his robot vacuum
That runs a bantu. I'm Chris and I'm Alex and this is self-hosted
So you're back from Oregon now. How was the the epic road trip? It was a bit epic. It was pretty great
it was it was a lot of everything including some dad kid time and
Some husband-wife time because it was two different trips
And of course getting the solar system and the electrical system installed in the RV
Went pretty good. Actually, I'd say best-case scenario. The audience was right. They were riding in they said Chris
That's not enough solar
If you're gonna do it
You got to do it right and go for more solar and I got down there and I was looking at the draw of my
Refrigerator and all that kind of stuff and they were right
So we went with a total of six panels on lady jubes because you've got this big-ass
Normal house refrigerator in your car on wheels
It does pull a lot it's I didn't really appreciate that when I bought it, but yet it's so much space
So we have we have somewhere in the range of one point two kilowatts of solar
Potential power now on the roof that goes into six six hundred amp hours of lithium-ion
Battery storage from battle born and then we got a victor on 3000 watt inverter all installed rocking
We spent the night there at in their parking lot
They let us stay in their lot, which I thought was pretty great because if anything were to blow up
I wanted to be right there. Yeah
Because it's a big job, but I went pretty good. It's thrilled really with the results thrilled
So has it been everything that you dreamed of I assume from your thrilled word that it is
It was a little bit more. I mean honestly all said and done. I didn't quite
fully
Realize all of the changes it was gonna mean for us. I'm really kind of still in the fate than the testing and learning stages
It's a really complicated system, but I am documenting it
I launched a podcast that just sort of dedicate all that stuff around the RV at work life and RV podcast work life and RV
comm and I'm
right now in the learning phase then I'm gonna go into the testing phase and
Try to just get my head wrapped around it because it's pretty complex
but it's also
Super great for future work like projects where we go somewhere to a lot and we're working at a place like we did at
Dell or like we've done at Intel or like we do at Linux fest every year Linux Academy
We can go in the parking lot and we'll be able to hook up and or just run off solar or it's good
It's gonna extend our project time immensely
It's really I'm really excited from how much it's gonna kind of give us flexibility in that regard to
Say you originally spec'd out. What was it 500 watts of solar? Yeah. Yeah, you've gone to every doubled that
Yeah, yeah, we did and what's pretty nice about that is
When you have I mean, this is so obvious, but when you add more solar panels, even on a darker day
You're you're collectively drawing in a little bit more power. And so even on kind of a overcast Pacific Northwest
raining
Snowy kind of day. Seattle's not known for being gray. Is it? No, never never never
I'm still pulling in enough power to cover all of my home automation system
all of my home servers like the all the Raspberry Pi's my storage and
All of the smart lights are all running off the solar because a kilowatt doesn't really sound like an awful lot
You know, how much is a microwave a thousand watts, right?
When you're running a microwave, it's drawing a thousand watts. I guess so
Yeah, or a hairdryer is around 900 watts a heaters around a thousand watts
So that kind of gives you an idea of it's not like it's um
Unlimited you're gonna leave something in the efficiency though, right? Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. Absolutely. Yeah, you lose like 40%
I think it's in some cases. It's it's pretty abysmal. Okay, so if I have a kilowatt array on my roof
I want to budget I'm gonna get no more than five or six hundred
Actual usable watts out of that then do I depending I mean, it's pretty great
If what you're drawing from it is DC
So if you can move some of your load over to DC and there's a lot of things that are DC
In fact almost everything we have that's electronic is DC
We just convert it to AC either in a wall wart or in a box inside the computer
Speaking of AC the other kind the the one that keeps you cool in the summer that must draw a lot of power, right?
Yeah, and one of the things this is an area where you asked if it was what I expect and I said it exceeded it
This is an area just because so much was going on including the trip down there that I forgot to properly
investigate how to run the air conditioners and the big issue with an air conditioner is
And this is true for a home air conditioner or a mobile one or a one that goes in your window
Its biggest draw is when it's first powering up and that compressor is going and that fans spinning up
it really spikes to its maximum load and
Then it kind of drops down and it settles and it just has a running load
which is still a lot but it's not an unbelievable amount a bit like a jet engine where they have the maximum like takeoff thrust and
Then just just cruising is is easy almost. Yeah, once it's in its groove
So they have these things called easy starts or soft starts that help. I don't know shave that load down
So it it will start the fan up and then it'll wait a bit and we'll start the compressor up and it'll do it in
A stage start process and so with those installed which they caught even though I neglected to catch it
The installers caught it. We can indeed run the air conditioners off the battery bank quite quite. Well, it works quite well
Do you have any idea what sort of runtime you'll get from that on battery?
I'm not yet. My my first pass at it is somewhere around six to fourteen hours
Depending on how hard they're working. That's not bad though. That's pretty good
it's not bad and really probably running for 15 20 minutes just to get the temperature down when you just get home and then
Switch to fans and whatnot pretty exciting pretty exciting, especially if you consider in Seattle
You're only gonna need it for two or three hours a day. Anyway, realistically guy confess something to you
Mm-hmm, something I did not expect to be as hard as it was for me was shutting down the whole home system all my
Servers my remote login. Okay. I have I have one SSH tunnel that I have set up that I can bounce into something goes down
It's my only remote connectivity that goes down. Of course. I can't get to home assistant
I can't check the camera and everything's offline and it was like that for a week and I have built up just habits
During my day if I get a minute, I'll just go check on how the hell are the temperatures doing?
How's this or that doing it? What's the draws, you know?
I'll just check on that kind of stuff throughout the day and it was like it was missing
It's hard having my servers down home automation addiction calm
No kidding. No, it's for sure
It's the thing that was I was surprised by by Friday when we were going down there
Hadeah had to step out to take care of some business work
And so while she was out of the RV job one was I got all the raspberry pies booted back up got the Wi-Fi network going
Got the net you got the internet connection back up
You sound like me when I moved into this place the first job that I did was ran ethernet
Well, everything needs it everything needs it even the clocks. I swear the internet and can I just register a complaint Alex?
Can I register this?
Can can think just stop assuming they know my location because of my Wi-Fi network and then just not check again
I'm trying to get traffic on Google Maps and it's like oh, you're on your Wi-Fi network at home
So you're you're at your home base
I don't need to look up your location and I'm driving down the freeway
And I couldn't get my dumb iPhone to just redouble check my location. I toggled airplane mode
I closed at Google Maps reopened it it just
Insisted I just had to set it down with Wi-Fi turned off for like an hour
And then I picked it back up and it had sorted itself. I think you might be what they call an edge case there Chris
I know I know
Did you see it was on Hacker News?
I think this week a guy has a little you know children's toy trolley and he filled it up with 99 Android phones
And he created a traffic jam in Google Maps
I did see that I you know
What's cool about that is I'd always wondered had that ever crossed your mind
Like if you just got a whole bunch of Google Maps devices and yeah
How many people does it take to make the road turn yellow or red or whatever?
You know what impressed me about that is that the phones could get the signals in and out in that pile. That's
That is really impressive from my radio engineering standpoint
I mean if you think about a double decker bus or something like that
You could have 50 to 100 people on that pretty easily true
It's a bit bigger than a little children's toy trolley admittedly, but yeah, these are all stacked on top of each other. Hmm
Yeah, that's pretty nuts. It's been a huge transition for us. It feels like in a weird way coming home. Very very thrilled
I I'm so excited about it that my wife and I wrote two blog posts about it and we recorded a podcast about it
It's like I said, that's it work life and RV comm the podcast though is good
I mean, I'm proud of it, but the blog posts have the pictures
So if you want to see the gear, that's where you go is the blog post. There's some good stuff in there
Well, thank you. So you have a little note here that we should talk about
SSH remote file edit for Visual Studio code. This is one of my favorite plugins. Oh, yeah
I don't know why it didn't occur to me sooner that VS code might have this functionality
I wanted to edit one of my home assistant configuration files and for some reason the web UI wasn't working but SSH was
So I just looked in VS code on a bit of a hunch and there it is
So remote SSH file editing plugin you can essentially load any
Directory on a remote system as if it was on your local system via SSH and you know what the chocolate to this peanut butter is
the Docker compose plug-in for VS code that
Visualizes the the yaml layout so if you like me make one space mistakes and screws up your entire yaml config
It catches that which is nice when you're saving directly back to the server
I love this plug-in because it's it's
Functionality that I had on a really old Mac app called BB edit a hundred years ago
That I had a hard time ever finding replicated functionality for it. This is it
Did you note though that it only works on Linux this remote file edit plug-in only works on Linux you have to be
On oh, oh, I'm sorry Windows 10 if you're using the official open SSH server now
You can you can use it on that now. That's a surprise
It doesn't work on Mac OS because they use a very similar SSH type setup to what we do on Linux
That's what I thought and now I'm not positive
I suppose it could work on any client, but it's the server that it's expecting certain SFTP features
There is a lot going on with this plug-in and it's just a real signal to me
That VS code is just going to be the editor that sticks around for the next 10 years
Atom was good
Sublime was good
You know, you can argue that VM or Emacs or whatever are good in their own ways
But for me the thing that makes VS code so so good is I can run it on any platform
You know electron. Thank you for that and I can even run it in the browser
You know home assistant has a one-click plug-in to deploy it as part of home assistant
You can run a container that runs it, you know in an isolated space on any system
It's just great
I realized that I was really liking VS code when I had a realization that if I had ever switched away from the Linux desktop
I would still use VS code on whatever platform I ended up on it
But let's move quickly beyond that and talk about wikis
You dropped the wiki bomb in the last episode and you didn't sit around and do nothing about it
You went off and installed a whole bunch of wikis and I'm really interested to see what you learned because if I remember Alex your requirements
Were a fuzzy search and I added on to that something that might even be spousal
Approvable. Have you ever had that worry about what would happen to all your systems after you pass on?
I have and I've seen it come up in the community a little bit too
Like what do you do you write a wiki? I think just just some basics, you know a wiki
Okay, not a will no no no the self-hosted podcast recommends you write a wiki folks
Okay, I'm with you. I'm with you though. I follow you
Maybe my wiki could constitute my last will and testament, right?
I mean you could be it could be in there right written in markdown. No doubt. Yeah in markdown. Yep
Well, there is that saying that goes around that my biggest fear in life is that my wife will sell my computers for what?
I told her they cost
I have not heard that but yeah, that's good. You can apply it to anything so guitars cars
Okay, but so the reason I wanted a wiki was not to document my last will and testament believe it or not
the reason that I wanted a wiki was to just try and
Descatter my documentation. I have some stuff in a git repo from when I tried to do it that way
And I think it's on my github called today. I learned to till TIL. I've got some stuff in Evernote
I've got some plain text notes in a folder on my server that aren't in git that are in next cloud
I think
I've got maybe five or six different random
Things that have tried and failed over the years and I wanted to try and fix that problem
I'm just sitting here nodding my head. I'm thinking yeah add Dropbox to that list
iOS notes to that list
Qo notes on that list of Google Keep. Mmm. Yes got a key things in Google Keep too
This needs to stop here. The line must be drawn here. And so when you look on
Reddit and you know, it's generally my source of inspiration for self-hosted stuff actually
There's a few different options and loads of people espouse bookstack as being the gold standard
it has this concept of
shelves and books and that and chapters and that kind of thing and
It kind of tries to divide up your notes into this kind of logical structure
Which not every single note kind of follows
but you can kind of make it work for what you need so you could say have a book for
Computer hardware and then a shelf for servers and then a chapter about each of your different servers
For example, sounds like you're spending a lot of time though figuring out how to get your information to fit into its structure
Yeah, that's kind of what I found and also another pain point that I really couldn't get past and I admittedly probably spent
20 minutes trying to figure this out. So if you know the answer, please let us know self hosted dot show slash contact
I found that image uploads were a real pain in the butt
I couldn't upload any images that were over a certain size and I think that size was like
900 by 600 pixels or something
Oh, you mean image size not necessarily file size and do you know where you're using the s3 back end or I think both
And bookstack wasn't using s3 to my knowledge
It was just spun up as a you know using a volume on my server with a container
Yes, right then you can use an s3 back end with it, which might change that aspect of it
Well, maybe maybe but in general, I just wasn't quite feeling it
You know
You can spend half an hour with with a tool and just generally get a feel for whether it's going to work for you or
Not and I think a wiki is going to be a highly personal thing
So I know there's gonna be some people listening to this going. Oh, I love bookstack. Why doesn't he like it?
It looks really nice. I mean the UI looks pretty great. It's not bad. You know, it's a solid option
It just didn't quite work for me because I want this to be an Evernote grade kind of experience
I want it to look as nice as feel as nice and just not have to
Manually convert images to the right size to fit into that thing and it images is a real pain actually in this
In this whole sphere, what kind of images are you doing screenshots? Are you taking pictures of stuff?
Like for me, it's business cards notes that kind of thing
Yeah, both like instead of writing down the specs of a system
I'll just do a neo fetch to get the specs of a specific box and then just put that screenshot into the system page
As well as you know photos I've taken on my phone of serial numbers of things and all sorts of crap. Yeah
Yep, same over here. Now. The next one that I tried was wiki.js. Now this thing is
Gorgeous. Yeah, this is even better looking than bookstack
It has a really nice easy to follow and understand layout and looking at this it it appears. It's it's a node.js app
So it must set up its own web server than you pointed out a database. I
Started out with my sequel. I say I started out
I continued until the end with my sequel, but you I used my sequel to start with and
It also supports obviously Maria DB
Postgres as well as MS SQL or SQLite 3 as well. It's a node.js application and
Version 2 is build a stable. There is a legacy version 1 which I didn't try
I tried the new version 2 and in general, I really really like this application except for one really fundamental thing
It didn't feel finished every time I went to click on something. It had this little coming soon banner
Partner dust which is fine
I guess I wish I could turn that off in settings like I don't want to see coming soon all over the UI every time
I'm using something and
One of the things that really got me was sitemap is coming soon. And that's one of the key things that I wanted to have
I love looking through a git repository that has a folder structure that makes sense for me
I need my notes to kind of fit into that
hierarchical structure
Almost like files and folders do and if possible
I'd like to be able to tag something with multiple tags and have it show up in multiple places potentially because it's
So often the case that you end up with I don't know
Let's let's use a bash script as an example, but that bash script is about Docker
So you might want it to show up in your Docker?
Note section as well as your bash scripts note section. I couldn't find a way to make wiki.js quite mold into my
Situation. However, I will say it is stunningly beautiful
The search worked pretty darn well
And I think it is definitely one to watch serious contender. Yeah. Yeah, it definitely will be it's gpl3, too
As well, I believe which is pretty nice. That's nice. Yeah, I like the fact that on their website
You know, there's three ways to host this thing your AWS digital ocean or self hosted and I love the fact that
These guys are putting that front and center. I think it's I think it's perfect, you know
So give it time. I think it will be the wiki gold standard moving forward and and certainly the screenshots
You can see on their website, which is wiki.js.org
You can get a good sense for just how beautiful this thing is and it's it's so close to what I want
Now an honorable mention for another tool that is not self hostable and is not open source
Unfortunately, because if it was it would be a slam dunk is gitbook
Now we actually use that over at Linux server to host all the documentation over there
And it's it's got that beautiful fuzzy search that I was after it will show you words within the documents as well
Mmm, that is nice
You can not only just search the titles
Because I don't about you my brain files stuff based on the odd
Keyword or stuff like that with with which I know is in an email or is in a note somewhere
And I can spend hours looking for that one keyword, which I know is in there
But the search algorithm isn't looking deep enough. And so all that led me finally towards tiddly wiki
One other one. I should actually just mention briefly is mkdocs
Now I really did like this one as well
It's git based and that wasn't quite what I was looking for in this situation
But it was really close between mkdocs and tiddly wiki in the end by this point
I tried out half a dozen wikis and I just wanted to start actually documenting stuff
So I just went with tiddly wiki and it's version 5 and I must say I've been super duper impressed with it
It's not the prettiest. I mean, it's not ugly by any stretch. It's just
functional just gets the job done gets out of your way shows you the information that you want and
Each note that you create is called a tiddler
I'm loving the names and each tiddler can have a tag it can have multiple tags and guess what?
When you tag something with multiple tags, it can show up under multiple categories
Which means that I can have that
Wonderful esoteric system that molds with the weird-ass way in which my brain works
Oh that is perfect for you and have stuff stored in three different categories all at once
It sounds like maybe you did find your perfect wiki then. Yeah, maybe so I'm curious about the setup side of it
What's it like as a server piece of software to get going? Well much like all the other wikis
I ran it out of a container. So it was up and running in a couple of minutes flat and
If I look at my stats on my server at the moment, it's currently using 90 megabytes of RAM
So we're talking about a very lightweight application here
If we look at smoke ping, for example that uses 40
Plex is using
2.5 gigabytes. Oof
Nom nom nom. I think cheese might be watching a video right now
But well, I mean it's it's doing a very different job than your wiki is so that's understandable
So tiddly wiki the name didn't put you off. It actually has made me wince once or twice
Yeah, yeah, it could have a better name
And now image uploads again were a bit of a pain point
you have to upload the assets as a separate tiddler and then sort of link that in to tiddly wiki and
Creating a table of contents is a bit of a thing and you have to follow documentation
I mean it it takes 10 minutes
But I don't know why they don't just have it like that out the box
Or a checkmark box that I can click and have it do do it that way
I mean, there's lots of stuff that makes it great
But equally I think there's definitely a lot that could be done in the user interface side of things to improve it
But I'm really happy I found it
I think I'm gonna stick with it for a little while and hopefully it doesn't end up like the XKCD comic of
We've got 13 standards. We need one standard to rule them all and now we have 14 standards. Mm-hmm
I'm sure it will but I hope not. Let me ask you a question
Would you deploy this for a community or would you choose a different one for a group of people to work with?
Because this sounds like it very much works with your kind of mind and thought process and way of retrieving information
But what about a group of people? Well, the search is great for a start
And I think for a community search is the number one thing that you need to work. Well
The next thing you need to work well is kind of moderation and users and that kind of thing for a community
Which leads me on to something I wanted to talk to you about really we can do this meeting live on air if you like
It's a little production meeting right now. Yeah. Yeah. Sorry. Come on in here in my office. I
Get maybe half a dozen messages a day from people saying how do I do this or did you hear about this or where did?
I find that link or yes, and I love it. I don't I don't mind. This is not a negative
This is not a negative thing whatsoever
but I think it would be good if we as a community could come together and
Start building a central repository of where to find all of this information
Because it is scattered across the web and there's a lot of smart people listening to this podcast
I know because you email me and you tell me lots of amazing stuff
So if we can all get together and try and build a wiki of some sort
To be the ultimate self hostable
Self hosted wiki on the internet and we can self-host it ourselves
Then I think we're eating our own dog food number one, but number two when people are
Trying to get into self hosting stuff
They will discover this wiki and they'll discover the show and they'll start falling hopefully down the rabbit hole and we can just bring a whole
bunch more people into the fold and
Hopefully end up being the one-stop shop for this kind of stuff on the internet. You never know
I tell you what. It's a big vision Alex. It's a big vision, but I actually think it's
Pretty great. I'd get down on that. I'd probably even look at seeing what some of my personal documentation
I could convert to a wiki to help other people. I probably have some stuff. I could contribute right away
So how would you run something like this? I think you need some community help with that as well
Well, I've had a couple of people on telegram already tell me that they're up for it in terms of
Moderation and helping me build the thing out
I think we'll probably be looking for three or four volunteers just to spend some time with
Me and Chris on on telegram in a private group just to go through some stuff
Figure out how to actually set this thing up and uh and get started. So if you're interested send me an email
At self hosted dot show slash contact or you can tweet me on twitter at ironic badger and uh, we'll get that ball rolling
I like it. We'll do a update in a future episode. That could be a nice resource
I remember back in the day for last we thought about doing something similar
But there were so many other resources that came along. It wasn't really necessary
unfortunately
the resources I use are pretty much project github pages and reddit and neither one of those are great because reddit is
It's like a river. It's changing constantly and you lose stuff and github pages can just sort of be
Really hit and miss in terms of details and documentation
So I would love to see something like this
Out of all the wikis that I tried the one that I think's most likely to fit our needs is that mkdocs one?
Oh, really not tiddly wiki, huh? Because it's been a long time since I've seen anything like this
Tiddly wiki, huh? Because it's based around git and we can then use github's pull request model to accept
Stuff coming in and kind of filter it and curate it that way going back to the community slash team thing
That makes a lot of sense
Yeah, it's very easy to do git blame and figure out who modified chris fisher's wiki page
I love that you're already planning trolling
You've got to it's the internet
You just exposed it though right here right here on the pod. I'm calling it a pod now the self-hosted pod
It's so horrible. I mean if you want to sound like a douche be my guest. Uh-huh. Okay. All right
Meanwhile, you're the guy with a robot vacuum. So let's talk about that for a little bit
I'm the guy with a robot vacuum running a buntu darling what? Yeah
What next you're gonna tell me you have a working with home assistant then i'm just gonna quit life. Oh, yeah, no
I bought a robot vacuum and it's a it's a roborock s5 now roborock are owned by
xiaomi the chinese company, so i'm well aware that
You know, my data will be going off to a data center that contains coronavirus. Oh, geez too soon
Is it still connected to their cloud service running ubuntu does it come running ubuntu no
So it comes out the box with um a me home app that you pair it with
like much of their other stuff and like light bulbs and and what have you
And out of the box, it works just fine
It has a little lidar thing on it that maps the room out and you know, it's it's pretty cool to humans detected
Yeah, assimilate
The robot vacuum is just the the room mapping is particularly creepy to me
But I I do kind of also appreciate the utility of it
Well, it's nice if you think about it because you can say to the robot
Go clean the kitchen or go clean the toilet or whatever not the inside of the toilet
Obviously, but you can say like different zones. I would buy that robot though
Yeah, I would too
And so naturally if i'm going to buy a gadget
I want to make the most out of it and I want to try and integrate it with home assistant so that when I
Leave the house I can have my robot vacuum start cleaning and when I come home it can go back to its dock
So it's never running when I'm at home
When I come home, it can go back to its dock. So it's never running when i'm here
um, that's the simple use case or it could be like, uh, you know
It's cleaning time where i'm doing some hoovering of the stairs for example
And then the vacuum is doing its thing as well
And if we're having a cleaning mode, it doesn't matter if it's churning away. So do you have a cleaning mode?
Is that something you've done? Yeah, it plays blink 182 full volume through my stereos because that's peppy enough that it gets my energy going
And then uh, yeah, we start doing some washing up or and then the robot vacuum deploys all the lights turn on the humans deploy
and
Yeah, and it it turns the lights on for 45 minutes and we have to keep going for that 45 minutes
That's a neat idea. And then at the end of that 45 minute period the lights
Dim or turn off on blink 182 stops playing and we know we're good
You need to have some wine deploy somehow that would be the next level at the at the end. Oh
Yeah, that would be good I guess you could always automate yourself to do that
Yeah, I wouldn't have any issues with that
That would be pretty easy and I and you automatically get the benefits of the location awareness when it's communicating with home assistance
So that's nice as well and you can integrate with all the other automation. So there's obviously advantages to doing that
So is there some sort of project out there designed to flash robot vacuums? Are they that popular?
Yeah, believe it or not. I love the community. It's so amazing
So to start with I discovered that I needed to obtain something called a xiaomi home access token
And the documentation on the home assistant website was a little bit out of date
So I submitted my first ever home assistant pull request. Yay
And so if you use a specific version of the me home app an old one by the way
You can actually go into the file system of your android device and retrieve the access token that way
It's not too difficult, but it took me probably an entire weekend to figure it out because the documentation wasn't up to date. So
There you go. I saved you some time
And then so once you have your token you can enter that into home assistant and use the xiaomi home assistant integration and it just
Just works
But I wanted to go a step further than that. I wanted to root my vacuum. I wanted to put ubuntu linux on my vacuum
And to do that you use something called a valetudo
Now valetudo is an open source firmware that you flash onto your robot vacuum and this thing uses the robot's wi-fi access point
to
Basically pretend to be the xiaomi servers
You then flash the valetudo firmware onto it. This is all done over the air
You don't have to plug any cables in you don't have to do any soldering
All the documentation is on their website and it it's actually really straightforward
And within a few minutes you'll have ubuntu on your network. You can ssh into your vacuum if you want to that's great
I love that so much
But one of the really super cool things that it enables as if a robot vacuum running ubuntu isn't cool enough already
is you can
now use mqtt
So you can bring the map into home assistant using mqtt
So you can have a card on your home assistant dashboard which uses the lidar sensor on top of the vacuum
To actually map out your house in home assistant it updates in real time and tells you whereabouts in the house
It physically is which is so cool. That's super high tech
All right, okay, you're selling me on this now now
You just got to build one of these and pre-flash it and ship it to me. That's all
I got it on black friday. It was
$160 this vacuum. Well, i've seen some of the I can't I can't remember the exact price
But the one I saw was near 800 for a different name brand. Yeah, they get pretty pricey
Well, you know what's next for you man is solar
Power all this stuff with solar i'm telling you it's next level. There's so much to learn
I I really am enjoying it if you and I know you do if you enjoy digging and researching and discovering new things and new tech
It's right up your alley a little solar panel on the roof telling you
I just need a bucket full of money to do it. That's true. Yeah, but then you could charge your robot vacuum from solar
Oh my god
I think if I buy an electric car, which will almost certainly be my next car purchase
then uh
Solar on the roof because I saw the uk is actually banning
gasoline and diesel car sales from 2035
That's pretty soon. I think it would be
next level awesome
To drive around a car that was charged by solar from at home. I mean that just
I'm feeling pretty good having my whole home server systems running on solar right now. I'm feeling like hey, look at me
But yeah, that's next level
Tell people about the blog give give a plug for the old blog because you got some good stuff on there
We don't mention it too often
I have a personal blog over at blog.ktz.me where I try and document as much of my personal
Shenanigans as I can. Yeah, and you also often take really great pictures over there
So that's something that I appreciate about you and something i'm trying to knock off from you is i'm trying to try to
do that same thing is put some good pictures on ours because it
Not something we get to play with a lot in the audio medium
So that's why I like to mention the blogs because it's like every now and there's a little extra stuff there
You've documented a lot of these projects over there fair warning. My latest post was about brexit, but uh,
Now we mention it
my latest post
Aside I quite often talk about all the projects i'm up to and you know how I do 3d printing and
When I switch to ios for a week and you know, just that kind of stuff really. Yeah, that was an interesting week
I just launched a blog chrislast.com and I did an episode little audio episode about the max vista moment
So you should check that out. I know you're not a big catalina guy over there
But you should give it a listen. My macbook is still on the one before catalina. You seem like a big mac guy
Yeah, like you're really into it. Am I no i'm giving you a hard time
All right
And of course the show is at self hosted dot show and we'd love to hear from you self hosted dot show slash contact
And links for the wikis or the blogs or all the stuff we talked about today are at self hosted dot show slash 12