Coming up on self-hosted. I'm slow cooking some servers Alex has self-hosted some AI with a nasty gotcha and a damp basement
I'm Chris and I'm Alex and this is self-hosted 22
I've got a 13 pound brisket in my fridge the only man I know who has hooked his barbecue up to home assistant
Almost almost so I bought a signals below or something now
They make a couple of products and I wanted to try and get this particular one hooked up to home assistant
They have another more expensive model, which does work with home assistant. And so this one I tried to decompile the APK and reverse-engineer the
Firebase database calls that it's making but no luck haven't been able to get it working
So I just have to cope with using their crappy app, which it's fine. No, it's no good
but this needs to be an obvious priority clearly we need to have you set everything else aside and
Get this working
There's no other option. It's really nice. So when you want to cook a big piece of meat in this
In the Kamado Joe you have to you know temperature is everything when you're coming to barbecue and
Keeping a nice stable temperature to get that lovely smoky flavor. That's really important
I had lessons from Carl, you know, so, you know, it's important, you know, we'll get to this
But that's what I'm doing is I'm just slow cooking my raspberry pies in the RV
I'm not it's not a thermal getaway issue. It's a it's a slow cooking and it plan
I don't know what you're talking about. Ooh, could you use them to do sous-vide?
You absolutely could you just put some meat in a bag in my server in my server booth and and let it go
that is unless I have to
Deploy my current fix which I'll tell you about shortly
but one of the things I did for this road trip that I'm on down here in Texas enjoying myself some barbecue myself was
shut down my
shinobi
Home camera system, so I have no recordings right now. Everything's just
streaming into the wind I guess and
Before I fire things back up
I think you may be changing my mind on what software I go with because while shinobi did the job
I kind of had issues with it over time. I'd have to reboot and for those of you not familiar shinobi is a
Closed-circuit capturing application. It's a web-based app
It's a little strange to use but it gives you an ability to pull in all these RTSP feeds and camera feeds into a single
Application. I have a sense Alex. I have a sense you may have found something better
I was watching a video by the hookup YouTube channel and he
Really piqued my interest in blue iris now blue iris is paid software
It's $75 for a proper license, so I'll just get that out out the way up front
You know, it's not free like shinobi in terms of cost, but it is self-hosted
It is self-hosted, but it's not open source either. So, you know, there's a couple of trade-offs to make
it's running fully offline fully on my LAN, you know, it's a
local NVR software and
What really piqued my interest was he
set up
artificial intelligence
motion detection really now
This is super cool AI motion detection
In other words, the software is aware of what's in the picture and it's using image recognition to make that determination
Correct. So when I first watched the video, I thought there's no way this is all local
He must be leveraging some kind of a cloud API
sending these photos off, you know to who knows where and
I'm not interested
but then I watched the video and realized that he was using deep stack AI and deep stack you can run in a container on
your LAN and
so what this thing does is you submit a JPEG to it and then it will apply its
What you call it? I don't know what
object recognition because from what I could see in there, it seems like it can determine the difference between
Faces dogs all kinds of common objects that would be in a camera feed
There is a list of objects it can detect and you know a short list of useful ones is stuff like car truck bus
Person dog bear that kind of thing bear
Bear is on the list. That's good up in the Pacific Northwest. Trust me. It's just funny
And so I thought this is gonna be really hard to get working, but I'll give it a stab
I'll set aside an evening and I'll get going. So JDM who was on the last episode, you know, the server builds dotnet guy
He hooked me up with one of those HP
Z I
Can't remember the model name a HP box anyway, and it cost me about $100 and in this thing
it has a dual core seller on and
And most importantly it supports Intel quicksync
so this $90
x86 system with 12 gigabytes of RAM and I bought a very cheap NVMe SSD. That's like
60 gigs to put in there. So it was not booting off the spinning rust drive. It shipped with I
Have an NVR system now that can support five cameras for $90
Whoa, and how much storage like how long can you keep the footage with this? Did you have to add disk?
Are you using the network storage? How is that part working? I have a USB 4 terabyte hard drive
That's been sat in a drawer for about three years
And I thought well may as well use it for something useful
So I've just literally plugged in a USB hard drive into this desktop system
There is room inside for a three and a half inch hard drive
So I was kind of tempted to go and buy an easy store and throw it in there, but use what you got, right?
Yeah, especially for something like this and then you could always build on it later
well, we're talking about storage one of the things that impressed me when I was digging around and learning a little bit about blue iris and
The hookups videos. He also mentions this it would seem that if your camera supports it
You can do two types of video storage a low resolution
maybe 15 frames a second 640 by
You know 480 or whatever some really low-res video that you can store indefinitely forever
You have that but then when the AI
Detection kicks in and it notices something that is recognized
It will flip over and keep a 4k copy or whatever your camera support of that particular moment in time
So your stuff that has the action is in full glorious resolution
And then your keep forever stuff is lower resolution and lower frame rate. Is that how you are using it with this box?
Yeah, pretty much. They're called sub streams. So, you know, I have a 4k camera pointing at my driveway
There's no reason to record 4k 24 7 that's just honestly stupid and a waste of energy
but these cameras have hardware chips in them, which do the
Video encoding in real time. So you actually get two streams out of this camera
You get the 4k stream it can be either h264 or h265
Which is great for file size and then you get a second sub stream as well
which again comes out in h264 or 265 depending on what you set up and
The resolution as you say of the sub stream. The second stream is much much lower
So the SD stream is what we'll call the low-res stream. The SD stream is running pretty much all the time
It has motion detection turned on so that's what's looking for motion in the frame. So
What happens is motion is detected. It takes a JPEG still of that frame
Sends that to the AI detection software
The three pieces of software at work here. You've got blue iris
You've got AI motion and then you've got deep stack. So deep stack is what does the image processing AI?
motion is what reacts to the JPEGs coming in and sends the images off to deep stack and then
Obviously blue iris is the CCTV NVR software. So AI motion
Which is a small app which was written by someone the IP cam talk forums. I think his name is gentle pumpkin
This app you can figure what you want the deep stack AI to be looking for
so, you know cars bears trucks, etc, and
Then once it detects a certain type of object in the frame, it will then and only then tell your
Cameras to record the HD feed and you can set a pre record buffer of 5 10
30 seconds if you want to so if you were sat there thinking oh, well
Maybe it takes a bit of time for the images to process
Am I not going to lose in the time it takes for that to happen up?
Am I not going to lose the pizza guy coming down my driveway? No, you won't because you get the pre-record and it's all fine
And it all just works, you know, that's the amazing thing about it. Is it just works. So
one of the big things I missed after moving away from nest when I moved into this house early this year was
You know that that really super simple interface of just swiping back through the timeline to see events and stuff like that
And with blue iris, I have that again now and it's it's great. I've really missed it
Yeah, there's a couple of cool modes for capturing stuff including what looks like a really nice UI for reviewing those motion events
Pretty efficiently. Have you found that?
Okay, I downloaded an app on my iPad that has been the best way to do that kind of stuff
but one of the
Better bits of blue iris is that it has a web interface so I can just log into you know
IP address of HP server
Colon port whatever and bring up the web interface and I have access through wire guard to my LAN
Of course so I can just connect through a wire guard tunnel and do it that way wherever I am
That that works really nicely, but I do have a bit of a confession to make about blue iris Chris
It only runs on Windows
Wait a minute, but doesn't the deep stack stuff run in a container on Linux? It does. It's a Windows Linux mix
Yes. Yep. Well, I don't know if I want to deploy Windows just for that but at the same time
It does look significantly better than shinobi. That's would you say maybe it's biggest downside for those that don't run?
Oh, I mean, I don't know some people that it's not a big deal for sure. I'd say it's the biggest downside. Yeah
the reason I ended up going that route in the end was
Because of the fact that you want direct hardware
Support for things like quicksync to make the the video transcoding or stuff like that
You know not to CPU intensive
You're gonna have a dedicated box for it. Anyway, let's say I wanted to put it on my server in the basement
I would have either needed to buy a dedicated graphics card and pass that through to the Windows VM
So that that can do the transcoding using envy ankle or whatever
or I would need to buy a more modern CPU and put that in my server because I have
Some old Xeons that don't have quicksync or I can spend 90 bucks put Windows on this thing and just forget about it
Yeah, you did Windows 10. I have an old Windows 8
Product key that I bought back in like 2013 or something
And I just typed that in thinking this ain't gonna work and it did so, you know, I've got Windows 10 Pro for free
I was getting pretty hyped, but that is a bummer. Yeah. Sorry about that
Do you think deep stack would work with shinobi deep stack will work with anything that is a JPEG
So all you need to feed to deep stack is
an image
Doesn't really matter what the problem is. The rest is shinobi
It's a good it's a good app, but I just yeah
I when it came time to reduce thermal load in the server booth. I thought yeah, this is one that has to go
Well, there are a couple of others that perhaps you should try out, you know in the interest of science
There's motion. I and zone minder. Yeah, I have looked at them. I
Definitely need to give motion. I another fair shake zone minder
I'm less impressed with but maybe it's improved recently. Yeah, I mean the worst thing about running Windows is that
It's Windows and I don't really like running anywhere and I don't mean to come across as a you know
A typical Linux kind of, you know, four legs good two legs bad sort of guy, but I just don't
Feel the need to run it anywhere
That said if I'm throwing it in a closet and forgetting about it the whole time
Does it really matter probably not probably not no and if you were in the commercial space out in the you know
real world with that at businesses running
CCTV systems if they weren't appliances running Linux, they would be applications running on Windows boxes
So you do see some of it out there in the real world? Yeah, there's nothing really better in the small to medium
NVR space in my opinion. Yes, there's the unified thing
But again, that's a proprietary ecosystem that you need to have their cloud key dream machine, whatever. They're calling it this week
That's super expensive and the prices of their cameras are outrageous
They might be good quality, but they are super duper expensive
So, you know 70 bucks for blue iris supports up to 64 cameras and for me, obviously, I'm you know
I'm only in the house. I'm not gonna get anywhere much much above 10, you know, and that's pushing it really, you know
I bought one of those
Doorbells, we had Morgan review a couple of weeks ago, but I bought the easy vis branded version of it
Must say picture quality is fantastic on this thing and it plugged into blue iris. No problem with the RTSP feed
So another vote for that doorbell really so who needs a ring when you can get an easy vis, huh?
well an easy vis with a
24-7 Windows box talking to a 24-7 Linux box running an artificial intelligence model to
Decode your images apart from that. That's what we're all about here
Right is taking something that is a commercial offering and enrolling it yourself
And in this case you bought a commercial app to do it
But you're still able to run it locally on premises, which I think is when it comes to video camera footage
It's just so critical. I'm trading my time and effort for my data and convenience
Yes, but this in particular is visual data of activities around your home and that to me
Like yeah, I'll tell you like when I'm walking around in my house in the buck naked
It crosses my mind when I see a camera out of the corner of my mind. I think to myself man
I'm really glad that's not cloud connected right now
Ain't no one gonna see that
Right exactly just go ahead and delete that footage
So easy vis is the maker of the doorbell you got and that does RTSP
So you could in theory pull that into home assistant as well
If you just wanted a Lovelace car just showing you the front door. Yep
I can pull it into Lovelace and I do it works great. The the camera is like a weird like fisheye lens thing
So that's kind of a trip getting used to that
But I mean that's no big deal
At least I can see whether those packages on my porch now without actually having to go and physically look
Yeah, and I it sounds silly but when you're traveling like I am right now
I have a camera at the studio at the door on the door and
I love being able to just pull it up and check on it from time to time that particular camera, too
I've intentionally made it possible for me to view when I'm away
Yeah, I just love this at the studio that way when I get a package
I know it's there and I can I can call up West I can say hey Wes
Will you go grab that package for me?
Now before you left you were really quite worried about the heat down in Texas, you know melting your pies
How's that been? It has been tricky. In fact, I'd say it's been trickier than I
Appreciated because it really starts with the solar system. I've gotten some good experience and I've learned a few tricks
So I can run my air conditioning off of solar which feels like a hack
It feels like a cheat code for nature
But what I discovered when I'm running my air conditioners off of solar is when you invert
That much of a load it generates a lot of heat
so I'm already dealing with a heat issue in my server seat and now my electrical system is
Struggling to stay cool as well. So the very system that powers the entire RV which I did not expect to be an issue
But when you start inverting a huge load
There's safety mechanisms that kick in when the gear reaches 110 Fahrenheit and it starts an auto shutdown procedure where certain things
Ironically, it wasn't the air conditioner, but certain things start shutting off
How much load does your AC unit pull in how when they're both going it's it's about 2,200 watts
It varies that's the same as to what my entire house uses for AC
Well when they're both going full bore and I really mean, you know, like it's 100 degrees out. It's hot
It's hot. Yeah when it's Texas heat. Yeah
If I run just one and it's not I don't have it on high, you know high power mode
I think it's around 700 watts. Okay. Well, that's still a lot but not you know
2000 plus it generates quite a bit of heat. So I've come up with a human solution to this problem
I've trained the boy on which bays of the RV to go open to create some some venting
Hey Dylan
Ventilation bays go open the ventilation bays and he runs out so you have to do when you're stopped obviously can't do it going
Down the road, so he runs out. He opens up the bays and I kick on the air conditioning
I had visions of some Keanu Reeves style speed stuff of hanging out the window
Yeah, I'm holding on to his feet. He's hanging down the side of the RV as we're going down the road. It's tricky
It's trickier than I expected because the batteries are near the drivetrain and so the drivetrain gets hot plus it's 100 degrees outside
So there's just a lot of thermal pressure on everything and the server seats
very warm during the day if I don't get ready for this get ready for these numbers if I don't
Implement a cooling solution for the server seat
I have seen the temperature in that booth get as high as 97 degrees Fahrenheit for the ambient air temperature
For all the components in there, so I've been following this very closely
Of course, I'm bringing all this data into home assistant and then I'm reviewing it each day to kind of see how bad it got
I now have like five of these
six in one
multi-sensor from
Aotec AEO tech they're kind of expensive. They're like almost 60 bucks each, but they track light UV motion
vibration temperature all that kind of stuff and it has a cool temperature sensor where it's actually like scanning using
infrared
So it actually it gets it's it's a really cool way to get ambient temperature and the pies themselves
Start to throttle when they reach 80 degrees Celsius and they don't really
Go above 85 degrees Celsius without shutting down
Amazingly, they continue to function everything continues to work even transcoding and watching video
All that stuff is still working and I have implemented another human solution here where I have tillin crack the booth
he just he
Removes the cover on the top of the booth and creates a little bit of airflow and that cools it down
But then we have to seal it back up to turn it into a bed every single night
So then if the temperature builds back up each day and then we crack it to cool it
Have you thought about a vent in the side of the thing or something? Yeah, we're looking right now at ways to vent it
It's tricky because it's wrapped in cloth and it would be really gaudy and it's also right as you enter the RV
So if I put it right in the side of the booth, it'd just be right as you walk in you'd see it
Very ugly. I am looking at other options. I've just got visions of Dylan going to sit down and you've been like, nope
Sorry, son. You can't sit down today. The servers have got a breathe. It's a hot seat. Yeah
It's so bad, so I ended up scouring the internet to find
The various ways to take the temperature of a Raspberry Pi
Because a lot of the built-in things like LM sensors that you would normally use on a Linux box
They don't work on a Raspberry Pi
I got a little script and I'll link the the details in it
but essentially if if you just cat sys class thermal thermal zone zero slash temp if you just cat that file you'll get back a
number and it'll be like
54,530 and what that actually is is the temperature of your CPU. So when I ran it it was
Fifty four thousand five hundred and thirty was the number that came back. Well, that is fifty four degrees Celsius fifty four point
Five degrees Celsius and so I know that right now as we do this
My pie is just a little under sixty degrees Celsius. So it's not in the dangerous throttling zone yet, and I just keep an eye on that
Basically, I'm running it on the red line
During this entire trip and I have a few ideas about relocating or using ventilate ventilation when I get back
I mean, this is production mode, you know, the real solution here is just don't go to Texas in June. No kidding
This was a non problem in the Pacific Northwest
I'm only here for a few more days and then I'm making my way north again
And it shouldn't be as much of an issue and then I think when I do eventually make it back to the Pacific Northwest
And get to my home base. I will probably retool this setup
And move it to a different spot that has ventilation because you had a spare Raspberry Pi ready to go and everything like that
I did. Yep
I was gonna be surprised if it was the pie that went first, you know
Not a power supply or you know switch or something instead, but I think I think that's a very fair point
In fact, that was the realization I had as the temperature started to rise as I realized
Oh, you know, it's gonna pop first will be the power bricks or my firewall or my Wi-Fi
That's what's gonna go first not the Raspberry Pi
I mean if you look at you know, any Intel system these days, you know any Intel laptop
They'll go up to 100 Celsius, you know almost instantly and so the I mean these things can cope
I mean a pie isn't probably built to the same tolerances as a high-end Intel chip
But you know these things can cope with some heat the circuit boards and stuff like that
They're not they're not gonna melt or anything like that, but power supplies. They really really don't like heat
Yeah, I'm a little nervous to be honest
I have to give a hearty plug again for these AO tech multi sensors. I've talked about them on the show before
They're not the cheapest z-wave temperature sensors. You can find out there, but I have these now
I have one in my water bay. I have one in my electrical bay
I have one in the bedroom one in the living room. I have one in the server booth
I have one up front where I drive and I all of them
flawlessly
Report into home assistant and what is fantastic about them is you can run them with continuous power with with USB
It's just you know, like super low voltage and then you get continuous one every second reporting if you'd like
Or you can pop a like a Duracell lithium ion battery, you know those little removable lithium ions
It has a spot for one of those you can pop in there and you can adjust the update interval by default when you run off
Battery, it's much slower
It's like every 15 minutes to save battery life and then the thing runs for like a year off one of those batteries
Nice. I really like these things you do have to have z-wave, but they're just fantastic
What I'm thinking is I'd love to put one under my deck or something outside that somewhere kind of vaguely sheltered
Just to get you know an outdoor weather station going or something
Are they suitable to go outside or are they indoor only?
I mean, I wouldn't be surprised if you could but on their box now they think about it
Does it does say indoor use only I don't know man
I mean once you have the power in there and you seal it up
It's they're pretty simple if you had it under your deck where it was out of the rain
I think you'd probably be fine because I have two of them in my outside bays and one of them is my water bay
Which is frequently exposed to the elements because I have incoming, you know hoses and stuff
So you might be like get away with it cuz I'm I'm doing it
Basically, it's pretty great and I just want to give them a hardy plug
So I'll put it in the show notes. No, you know, I get no affiliate or anything like that
But boy have they just worked really solid for me
What I learned is you can use motion sensors for a lot of the things
I was using cameras for for presence awareness and and automations. It's pretty great
Well, particularly in your world where you know one footstep probably shakes the entire house
Or at least I'm running kids, right?
Like I I see a future where when several of these sensors are reading a certain vibration level. I just automate
Something I I started playing with this for a brief period of time where if there has been motion or or not motion
but vibration
Disable all of the automatic lights and heater stuff because one of the tricks about home assistant going down the road
Which I've been dealing with on this trip. It does not automatically update its location
In fact, nothing does nobody builds these home products for a home that moves the echo product doesn't update Google stuff
Doesn't auto update its location. You think you have a smart tube on your on your counter and it
For the life of it still thinks I'm in Washington
but also home assistant doesn't update its location automatically and
Heaven forbid you've ever specified it via the YAML file because then you can't even update it in the web UI
So I've had to go through and like every time zone change. I have to go through and fix that stuff
So my automations for sunrise and sunset and all that still work, right? That really is a first-world problem, bro
Yeah, who you tell it I know
Doesn't mean doesn't mean I don't enjoy them, you know, it's it's these little challenges that kind of make this fun
I mean, I know you you were kind of playing around with trying to get it right in your basement recently because you got a wet
Basement. Yep, when we first moved in actually one of the first episodes where I was in this house
Around the turn of this year. We talked a little bit about how I was monitoring the temperature and humidity in my basement
now it's not a finished basement, but it's important to me because that's where my primary server, you know with the
15 or whatever is
13 spinning hard drives in is down there
So, you know if it's you know, sitting at 90 plus percent humidity for a month. I want to know about it
well, the rainy season has started here in Raleigh and
unfortunately the
Basement at Casa del Crech Mar is getting a little bit humid
Got a wet basement
How bad is it? Like when you say a little humid? Is it like yeah 90% plus?
Oh, so there could be even moisture like collecting in areas and maybe mold starting to develop
Yep, you can actually correlate in Grafana when I when I put some of the six month views into the discord
I was talking with some of the guys in there about it and
You could correlate storms
with
Spikes in humidity in my basement. Obviously is the ground around the house gets wet
It's got to come up somewhere, which I just thought was super interesting
And so I went on the Costco's website and bought a hundred and fifty dollar dumb
Dehumidifier as in dumb as in it doesn't have any Wi-Fi enabled nonsense or anything like that
And I've just thrown it down in the basement forgetting about it
But I didn't really want it running 24 hours a day because it's quite loud
It's directly underneath where my home offices so I could hear it through the floor. Oh, that's annoying
Yeah, and so I just thought hmm. I've got the technology to solve this haven't I I found one of my tasmota smart plugs
I wasn't using I
Threw the dehumidifier on there and then I put a home assistant automation to run the dehumidifier between 7 p.m
And 7 a.m. And that's worked great. Have you thought about getting a
Sensor for humidity and then just running it when humidity is at a certain level
that's how I know the basement was at 90 plus percent was because the
The temperature sensor I have is one of those esp8 to 66 d1 minis connected to I think it's a dht22
Which just monitor temperature and humidity that's all they do and that just reports back into the home assistant API
I flash that one using ESP home a little while ago
Which it just works really really reliably really really well. And so yes, you know in time. I will have the humidifier
The dehumidifier, sorry, I will have that only come on. I mean it has its own
Sensors built in once it detects the basement is you know, like 45% or whatever your target is
It will shut itself off, but I also only want it running overnight when I'm not anywhere near it. So
You know for me, I think
That's the best of both worlds the dumb appliance has been made vaguely smart to fit my own personal requirements
And then it uses its own thing inside itself to turn itself on only when needed. So hmm
Yeah, that is a nice combo a way to use some of its built-in sensors
I really whenever I can now and I'm buying something like a fan or a heater or a dehumidifier
I just look for something that just has a dumb switch on
That I can just leave in the on position and then really power cycle it with a smart switch. Mm-hmm
Speaking of smart outlets some of the designers at github have obviously been a bit bored recently
Oh, I got to admit I didn't realize they'd done a design change
I mostly just interact with github from the command line
So and also I don't think it's as bad on my screen because I'm on a laptop screen
It's quite a subtle change, but it was I think the same day as Apple's keynote where they announced the big sir
You know the the big design refresh with the rounded corners and the transparency and the magic
yeah, then comes the github theme change and it's
It's it's a very subtle change, but I use github every single day
So for me, it's like one of the most important websites on the internet and I hate it. I just hate it
there is
the issues and the projects and the wiki thing the little bar above the repo is now over to the left and the releases tab has
Moved from being a tab to being this weird
Micro sidebar on the right and oh you're right. It's a fully adaptive website now and it I
Mean, it's probably better in some ways. I'm just checking it out right now. Oh my goodness. You're right. Oh
Hmm I kind of like it
You really are an apple sheep well, no, it's just I'm on a smaller screen
So it feels like it's a little tighter, but I could see if I was on a ginormous
95 inch screen like you are it would be a lot of wasted space 95 darling. It's only 38
Well, it's bigger than my 14-inch think bad, yeah, yeah
So, I mean I do generally work on an ultra wide all day
So I'm probably not the target market the designers had in mind
When you move github to be, you know
A third of my screen width or anything like that
It looks like it always used to and for the most part the changes are largely
Fine and benign
But it's only when you start to get that wider screen where you've got elements all the way to the right and all the way
To the left and in the middle. It's like guys it was fine before you've just made it worse
You're taking a mouse road trip just to click on a UI element. Yeah, true now the good news is that
That pushed me. I mean, it's just something I've been using kind of not super seriously for a while
But in the last couple of weeks, I've taken it a bit more seriously and that's get tea get a yeah get tea
I think get tea. I've always called it get tea a self-hosted. I want to say github clone
That's probably not necessarily fair. Although it's very similar feature set to github
They call it a community managed lightweight code hosting solution written in go and it's published under the MIT license
It's really nice. It lets you mirror any public repositories that you want to so if you know
You want to mirror every single thing you push to github locally just automatically
Get tea will do that for you. It supports multiple organizations multiple users pull requests
Forks all that kind of stuff, you know everything you're used to really with github
Obviously the downside of self-hosting something like git is that you don't have the community that's there
You know, I often think that when I see big projects moving to git lab even which is obviously a next level up from self
hosting your own
Git server again, so, you know just bear that in mind when you're making that choice. I think that's fair
I think if you're a project that's trying to
Draw in as many contributors as possible. You've really got to do the math on this
However, if it's for yourself and some friends or for a work project
I don't think there's any real downsides to it if you've got the storage and the means to keep it running
I assume you probably deployed the container version of get tea. I do. Yes, and then it backs itself up to a ZFS
Dataset which is now remotely replicated between my server and my other server in England
I finally finished a six terabyte upload to England which took eight weeks
How often were you checking in on that thing the trouble was
Whenever I was uploading and my dad wanted to watch I player it kept buffering
So I had to keep going in and turning it off and then I'd lose a night because I'd forget to turn it back on again
Did he complain Alex? My my internet's just been so horrible. I don't know why yes, he did
Sorry, dad. Did you say? Oh dad. Sorry about that. I
Don't understand because so here's here's what I'm doing. I'm running from ZFS in my basement
I'm doing a wire guard tunnel through my open sense router
directly to the endpoint, which is a
Ubuntu
2004 LTS the box. I did the remote reinstall on a few episodes ago
So if you want to know how long this uploads been going for go back to that episode
And that was when I started the upload so it was a while ago
Wow, he was having stuttering
Downloading I player which is going to be a couple of megabits of most I would have thought
Made let's say 10 and he has 300 something down and I have 35 meg up here with spectrum
And it's like how can that possibly be causing buffering on his end? No kidding. You would think that your remote connection
That's over a transcontinental link
It wouldn't be able to mess up a download that he's doing this probably as near local as it gets
And the only thing I could think of and this is just a pie-in-the-sky theory
Is that there were too many connections open or something?
But then it's going into a pf sense box at the other end which has you know a pretty large state table
So it's not a cheap ISP router or anything like that, you know
So I'm a bit stumped to it is as to what was causing it
So if you have any ideas right in and let me know please. Yeah, that's tricky. It may not be a bandwidth issue
It could be could be a device issue that was causing it but six terabytes
I mean, I must feel good to have it all done now and backed up
Yeah, and now I just do the incremental backups, you know
I did my app data back up this morning and it took about 20 minutes instead of
Six weeks. That was nice when you're self-hosting boy
Have I learned this lesson recently that kind of peace of mind is necessary because you know when you're when you're deploying something like get
to yourself
You don't want to lose that data. That's gonna be really embarrassing and I am so grateful that the recent data loss I had
the vast vast vast majority of it was all recovered even though my backups had broken because I had that data stored on another system which
like you're doing now too and I
Just really really got to double down on that. Like if you're gonna do this if you're gonna host this stuff yourself
take the time because
Boy, did I learn that one the hard way recently and that's even knowing this, you know
Even having said this and preach this stuff over and over again, like it can still be an issue. So
Congratulations, sir. That must be a nice piece of mind. It must feel good. Yep. Yep. Yep. Yep
My grand vision is I'll have the the ZFS
Replication at his house which will then itself replicate to the PI 8 gigabyte. I bought a couple of weeks ago at my sister's house
So I'll have three full copies of everything. I care about in a ZFS reachable location
On top of that. I have everything backed up to Google Drive that I care about and also Glacier
So between those five different points, I think I have it covered. You're set unless it's a meteor strikes the earth
Yeah, unless something takes out North America and Europe at the same time. I'm fine. I
Think you probably have other problems at that point. Maybe maybe we'll see if you're lucky
So thank you very much for listening. That was self-hosted 22. You can find the show at self-hosted show on Twitter
And don't forget the discord self hosted show slash discord. Oh, yeah, it's really kicking up over there
We've got over a thousand users these days. It's a it's a really great community. It is my social media platform now
I mean, I'm still on Twitter at Chris last of course, but I've been really getting a lot out of discord
So go check that out. We'd also like your emails your feedback your questions your ideas self hosted a show slash contact