Coming up on Self-Hosted 16, we're getting to some network basics and tips for solid
Wi-Fi connectivity.
Plus, we make the biggest compromise in the history of the show. I'm Alex, I'm Chris,
and this is Self-Hosted 16.
Hello Alex. Staying sane while staying indoors, I assume?
Doing my best. Yeah, I realised I haven't actually left this building in four days.
You're such a nerd though, because you sent me a screenshot of a new home assistant card
you have that tracks your quarantine amount percentage-wise. You were like 99.4% at home.
It's QuarantinoMeter. It was on the Home Assistant Reddit page. It uses my Life360 integration
to calculate how many hours I've been at home in the last seven days. Turns out I've only
left the house for three hours in the last seven days, which is fine. I know as a community
and as a society, we all need to be doing that. But when you see the data presented
to you, you think, what was I doing for three hours? Okay, I was grocery shopping for somebody
that had just come down from New York, and they were self-isolating. So I was doing a
good thing for the community, and at the time I was out walking my dog. But you think to
yourself, well, actually, I could probably do seven straight days. And then here I am
on day four, and I'm going slightly mad.
I feel like I could do it. I love it. Something about it. For me, it's like, I love being
all in there and cozy and working on stuff. Also, it's given me a great chance to hang
out in our new Discord, which has been amazing.
Yeah. So we've launched a Discord server. We have unfortunately fallen into the traps
of a non-self-hosted chat platform. I know that's what you're thinking.
Within 20 minutes of launching it last week, we already had people giving us a hard time.
So we've definitely gotten it. Should we just address why that elephant is in the room?
Because even going back to episode one, I think this is something we flirted with, but
this is the first time we've really, this and maybe Plex.
It's like the whole GitHub versus GitLab self-hosted argument of, yes, each organization, each
project, whatever, could host their own chat server. You know, a Mattermost, a RocketChat,
an IRC server, whatever it is this week, a matrix thing. But in reality, you have to
go where the communities are. And if you look at the purpose behind why we've launched this
Discord server, it's to give people a place to hang out and talk about everything relating
to self-hosting. Not necessarily to be a self-hosted platform itself, but it's to enable the community
to grow and, you know, build relationships and stuff like that. And whilst the Telegram
group that we have is fantastic with, you know, 1700 people in it and growing still,
and Telegram isn't self-hosted either, by the way, conversations and threads get lost
in that number of people sometimes. And I think it's going to be really great for people
to have an area they can come and just talk about a specific topic without blasting it
off to 1700 people every time.
Trenton Larkin Absolutely. We'll have a link in the show notes
at self-hosted.show slash 16. And I'll also try to remember to put a link at the top of
the website for the Discord. I want to underscore something here because I want to make it clear.
It's not a decision Alex and I came to lightly. It's something that he and I have literally
been discussing since episode zero when we were just brainstorming. And while we almost
always default to self-hosted, it is in a few exceptions where we don't. And there's
other areas, too. I'll just admit to it right now. I use Twitter and I use YouTube and I
don't like it. I actually don't like it because I don't host them. But that is where the audience
is. And I think for a lot of people it's all a balance. Some stuff is really worth going
on to the top of the hill and fighting to your death. And some stuff is just easier
to go with the flow and just get collaborating. And I think that if this Discord server leads
to more people collaborating and trying out more self-hosted software and technology and
building out more self-hosted infrastructure, then it's a net win.
Trenton Larkin Yeah, couldn't have said it better myself.
Let's do some follow up from last episode where we talked about Grossi, the toilet paper
stockpiling inventory management system.
Josh Birk And batteries.
Trenton Larkin And batteries. There is a really cool thing
that you can get called Barcode Buddy. So one of the pieces of feedback I had was it's
quite laborious to enter all of your stuff into the inventory system. Well, with Barcode
Buddy, there's a link in the show notes. With Barcode Buddy, you can actually scan using
an app on your phone, the barcodes of, you know, tins of beans and all that kind of stuff
and actually add it to the database that way. So I thought that was pretty cool and worth
sharing with you.
Josh Birk That I actually would do. Not so big on the
manual entry, but the old scan and go, I'm okay with that. I think that's a nice little
addition. I love that.
Trenton Larkin Right. Shall we come on to the bad news of
the day?
Josh Birk Okay, I'm ready.
Trenton Larkin It was announced this week that Dark Sky have
been bought by Apple.
Josh Birk Yeah.
Trenton Larkin Sad trombone.
Josh Birk This is a bad one because it's super popular
as a tool in the home assistant community. But I've discovered based on the now daily
messages I'm getting from audience members that a lot of other projects are using it
too for their backend information. This is an example where a hosted project maybe wasn't
the best solution. And I don't know what your answer is here for weather other than it did
get me thinking. Is it time for a weather station in the junkyard?
Josh Birk You could easily do it with an ESP8266 board
and you know, maybe $15 worth of parts.
Trenton Larkin Yeah, you think?
Josh Birk Yeah.
Trenton Larkin Okay. All right. Sounds like we got a project
for next time Alex visits Washington.
Josh Birk I've been meaning to do this in my backyard
since I moved here. So I will do it. I will do it.
Trenton Larkin I'd legitimately be interested to see how
it goes.
Josh Birk Don't tempt me.
Trenton Larkin This is a shame though. Apple bought them
and you know, it's not unusual for when they make an acquisition like this for them to
either shut down or just change the game completely. The good news is if you already have API credentials,
it sounds like it's going to remain on until maybe some point in early 2021.
Josh Birk Yeah, that is air quotes good news. New users
cannot get API keys anymore. So even once Apple integrate this into whatever product
they have in mind, presumably the weather app, right? They're gonna be doing API calls
under the hood anyway. Dark Sky is a paid service. I think I pay 79 pence or $1 a year
or something for Dark Sky access through my phone. It's such a small amount of money that
I can't remember exactly how much it is. But you know, the point is, is that Apple could
maintain the existing product without necessarily really affecting, in my opinion, whatever
integrations they're trying to do. Now, obviously, I'm not, you know, Scott Federighi. I don't
exactly know what plans they have for it.
Trenton Larkin Craig Federighi.
Josh Birk Oh, Scott Forstall, wasn't it?
Trenton Larkin Yeah. You know, I follow you. I think they
would brand it as like iCloud weather or something like that, and then nobody would want it.
I think Apple looked at this and they say, well, this isn't enough money to be worth
our time. Let's just keep our competitive advantage. And we'll just internalize it.
So not only is it probably not a moneymaker, even at $1, as you say, a year, or a month,
whatever. I think that combined with the competitive nature of them being the exclusive holder
of this information is probably worth it. I mean, for me, the thing I loved about Dark
Sky was that super hyper local rain information. As you can imagine here in the Pacific Northwest,
I check that thing daily.
Josh Birk Almost like it rains a lot where you are.
Trenton Larkin Almost like that.
Josh Birk One time I stood outside a pub in London with
some colleagues and I got Dark Sky out and we were having a pint stood outside. You know
how it is in London. If you've been there, there's the little tape on the floor. You
have to stand inside. And so we were stood just outside the tape, outside the canopy,
and it started to absolutely throw it down. And I said to people, right, this rain is
going to last for three more minutes. Three minutes later, it stopped. Bang. Dead on.
Trenton Larkin Yep. Same thing. I was at a meetup and we
were eating outside and we checked Dark Sky. Is it worth going inside? Because there was
really no tables. What would we do? Look at Dark Sky. Yep, it's worth going inside. It's
going to be raining for an hour. It was really nice. While we're still on the Home Assistant
topic, what are you going to do in Home Assistant to replace Dark Sky? What is do you have an
option right now?
Josh Birk I don't know. I'm hoping to solicit feedback
from the audience. Quite honestly, self hosted dot show slash contact.
Trenton Larkin While we're still in follow up and on the
topic of Home Assistant, the last episode, I think it was, you made a very, very strong
pitch for me to switch to what I refer to as has IO, which is just now Home Assistant.
But it's the whole OS stack, where you get the supervisor with official add ons and third
party add ons. And then it's very easy to add hacks, the Home Assistant community store,
and get even more integrations. And you really kind of piqued my interest when we did a live
stream. And I thought to myself, I got to do this at some point. It all went south though,
when my Raspberry Pi Raspbian install started kicking up a bunch of errors, package errors,
about the Linux image package, which that sounds really bad. It also kicked up a bunch
of errors about my time zone information. And I just don't think it's going to survive
a reboot. So I thought, well, I recognize the problem better do something about it.
So I bought another Raspberry Pi four. Only this time, I put Ubuntu 2004 LTS on that sucker.
And it's running from an external SSD, not off the SD card. It screams, screams, Alex,
I can't believe the performance I'm getting on this thing. Everything's faster. And then
what I did is I grabbed Home Assistant's installation script. And I ran that on top of 2004. It
pulled down all the containers after I had Docker set up. And now I'm essentially running
what I would have traditionally called has IO with custom themes. I got hacks installed,
I got everything reset up. And really, it wasn't as bad as I was expecting. I drove
home dreading this because my Home Assistant setup works so well. And it is actually responsible
for quite a few things. Now. I was dreading it. You told me it wouldn't be so bad. And
you were right. Thank you. Two tricks I'd like to impart upon the audience. The thing
I was most concerned about was moving over my Z wave devices. I have some Zigbee and
Z wave devices that I use for temperature, light, motion, security, base data is battery
based at it's like all kinds of Z wave devices, and outdoor plugs. And I just didn't know
like what what how do you move a Z wave network over. But I shut down the old Docker images
of my old Home Assistant core install, export it out or went in on the file system grabbed
all of the Z wave configs. I shut down the Home Assistant install and has IO move those
Z wave configs over inside the container, and then plugged in the adapter started it
up and all of the devices just moved with the controller and all started reporting they
lost all their names. So I had to rename everything which was a real chore figuring out what was
what? Let me tell you. That can be a pain in the ass. Yep. Yeah, yeah, it was. So one
of my tricks was is I just cranked the heat in the room and then just waited to see which
one registered. So that was the other room. I opened all the windows. It was a mess. And
then the HomeKit devices were particularly hard because once they're paired with something
that can't be repaired with and a lot of them just have a general reset defaults. They don't
have a way to unpair them by holding down keys. So I had to go around to the HomeKit
smart plugs, reset them, rejoin them to my phone, then remove them from HomeKit and then
add them to Home Assistant one by one. So I got rid of those. Now, I will say last thing,
if you want a really easy smart plug that isn't something you have to flash, I still
think the TP links were a good purchase because they were automatically all redetected. And
the names I had given them were actually written to the device. So they all showed up with
the names I had from the old Home Assistant install, auto populated, clicked right in.
The easiest part was the TP link. And they're the smaller ones that only take up one plug.
I think if you're going to get a smart plug that isn't something you reflash, that's still
the one to get. Just works immediately with Home Assistant. It does require an app.
You know, it's even better than the TP link ones. This is a point where I talk about Tasmota
again.
No, you're right.
When I rebuilt my Home Assistant instance, the DNS name that I use for my MQTT server
meant that I didn't even have to reconfigure the plugs. It just picked up the MQTT server
again and
Oh, that's even better. You're right. See, what I appreciate about the TP links is I
could get them in two packs for like $35 from Amazon. And then they just plug in. You use
the app once to configure them. You never have to use the app again after they're on
your network, though.
Yeah, it's not too bad.
It's not too bad. But one day that app will probably go away.
Yep, it will. Don't know when, but it will.
Yeah. In the meantime, it's not so bad. Just how I'm on the fence like with those kinds
of things.
You know, I think there is a real value in doing a Nuke and Pave. When it's a new thing
like Home Assistant, it's relatively new. I think back to my early days with Windows
of Linux of even Mac OS, the way I used to learn the most was when I was rebuilding those
systems, rebuilding those automations, whatever it might be.
It's like a trail. You're re-stamping down the grass and the weeds. You're making that
trail. You're working it in. It took me, what, a week or two the first time, and it took
me an evening this time. Maybe it's not 100% done, but in other ways, I have more functionality
now with the add-on store hacks. Now I have snapshots, themes.
Additionally, this time around, I thought, well, why not set it up more with their Nebuchadnezzar,
the Home Assistant online services. I decided, let's turn on the Echo integration. I'd never
done that before.
Jason Valee It's pretty great. I can kick off automations
and scripts via the Echo. Now that's money. If I say Echo, run bed time, which we call
last call, from anywhere, and then I can say Echo, good morning, and it just, from anywhere,
it's really nice. Via the Echo, I can set brightness levels. So I can just say Echo,
set kitchen strip to 10%.
Jason Valee Again, that speaks to the whole...
Jason Valee...compromise. Yeah, it's a compromise that those things are not self-hosted. They
are reliant upon Amazon and Google and Apple to some extent, and for me, an internet connection
as well, which is not always guaranteed. But the way I look at it is that remote control
is just the beginning. If you can turn something on and off remotely, that then opens the door
to be able to link it in with all the other devices, and this is why, in my opinion, Home
Assistant is doing such a great job. It allows a single entity, a single instance where it's
just got a record of everything that's in your house or in your RV or whatever, and
it's all in one place and it's all aware of what everything else is doing, and then you
can kick off automations based on that. For example, in my garage, I have a light switch
with Shelly in it. Shelly is the thing we talked about a few weeks ago that is a smart
switch kind of like add-on. This is the size of like an Oreo cookie and goes inside the
light box.
Right, turns any regular switch into a smart switch.
Correct. And then I have on a separate light circuit, a separate pair of lights in the
back half of my garage so that I would normally have to walk over to the far side of the garage
and flick a separate individual switch that's on a completely different circuit. But because
these two lights are on the same Home Assistant instance, I can flick one switch and I have
an automation that's always listening for a state change. And if either of those switches
gets toggled, it knows to turn the other one off as well. And once you start thinking about
how you can convert dumb switches into smart switches, oh boy.
Very much so. And I also kind of look at the Echo stuff and even the Nebuchadnezzar or
whatever it's called, remote integration as layers on top of a core. And if that were
to go away, no big deal. I have a tablet mounted to the wall. That's actually my main control
for my Home Assistant is the tablet mounted to the wall, not the Echo.
What do you use? Is it the Fire?
Yeah, I know a lot of people will like reflash it or set up in kiosk mode. I find none of
that necessary. I just got one app to keep the screen on all the time. And then I just
open the browser in full screen mode and just leave it up. And it works all the time.
As you see in the latest Home Assistant update, 1.0.7 is the latest version, there is a new
dashboards feature. So you can actually have different home screens for different devices,
not different pages. It's like a different kind of interface all based off the same Home
Assistant instance.
That's definitely something I'm going to take advantage of because there's an interface
that works well on that tablet, but that doesn't necessarily look good on my desktop browser.
Yeah, tablet, you want big fat buttons for your big fat fingers.
That's exactly what I did.
On a desktop, you want tiny little toggles because you have a mouse, right?
I did exactly that. I did really big buttons with sliders and just to make it really easy
for one spot for them to touch. And then I did like individual smaller toggles for myself
and using like the new temperature cards and stuff like that, that all look very nice.
So visually to the family, it looks like dad just did a big upgrade to the thing that they
use.
Good job, Chris. Well done. Nice effort.
Little do they know, I was like, oh, God, I don't know if I'm going to pull this off.
But I'm glad I did it now. And I'll be playing around more with the stuff that's built into
it. One of the things that works significantly better with this load is my Wyze cams. I pull
the RTSP feeds into picture elements or media elements into Home Assistant. I just have
one security tab where I can get a real time feed of all of my Wyze cams. Works much better
with the new load. That is unless I take advantage of this new firmware they've released.
Yes, with the new work from home movement that seems to be gripping the world by storm
right now, Wyze have enabled a webcam mode.
This is a weird one, but it involves manually installing a firmware onto your Wyze camera
like you would to get RTSP support. And then after that, the Wyze camera no longer communicates
with the Wyze app. It just stops talking to their cloud servers. But you can plug it in
to your machine and it'll power it over the USB port and act as a USB web camera for them
Zoom calls you're making.
You know, I have a top tip if you want a webcam. Probably don't use your Wyze cam. Go to eBay
and buy a Logitech C920 for $40 used.
Yes, great tip. The nice thing about that, too, although probably the Wyze as well, is
that it does H.264 encoding in the camera. So it takes less CPU load, which is always
a good thing and still a pretty good picture. I don't think this is something I would use,
but I do appreciate the flexibility of these $25 cameras. That's kind of fun.
Well, I'll tell you what's great. My wife is a music teacher and she's had to convert
all of her students and teach them through Skype or Zoom or FaceTime or whatever. And
her iPad is getting a real workout at the moment. And if for any reason that went down
and stopped working or whatever and then one of the three laptops I have in the house stops
working and then one of the three other webcams I have in the house stopped working, then
I might use a Wyze cam as a webcam.
And you decide not to just do it from your phone for some reason, which probably has
a better camera.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah. There's a lot that would have to break in my house before I got to
the Wyze cam, but it's not the case for everybody.
However, if you just want to buy one $25 camera, it will do it all, which is, I guess, nice.
We have not dug a lot into home networking yet, but it's something Alex and I are talking
a lot more about. So we thought we'd cover a little bit of home networking basics today.
With this whole working from home business, there's been a lot of calls appeared in my
calendar of people that normally work in an office that are missing that kind of social
contact. Now, for those of you that don't know, I work from home 100% anyway. So for
me, not a huge amount has changed on my day to day, besides obviously the world ending.
And I think that listening to a lot of these people, you know, quote unquote normies talking
about Wi-Fi and firewalls, and I've just referred to other Red Hatters as normies, didn't I?
I know. I just love where this is going. Now, to bail you out a little bit, 100% of my meetings
this week have people working from home dealing with Wi-Fi trouble. And then people like going
from the nice room that they've set up where they've cleaned up behind them to like progressively
having to just move closer and closer to the router. And pretty soon they're like just
in their closet so they can make the call work. Let's preface everything I'm about to
say about Wi-Fi with the caveat that a wire is always better, significantly better for
real time video calls as well. The machine I'm doing this call with you wired in right
now, I would never do this without it being wired in. And so you have this initial spot
with a lot of people's home networks where the Wi-Fi network just by its very nature
because it's radio isn't as solid. And so that right there introduces problems regardless
of the rest of the network infrastructure on your LAN or your internet connection.
Yes. And another thing that a lot of people don't think about is the ISP provided routers
often have Wi-Fi hotspots built into them. You know, your ISP will rent you a router
or sell you a router or maybe just give you one for the duration of your contract. And
quite often they are what's called a combination device. They do all the routing into and out
of your network. So every webpage that you visit, your traffic goes through that firewall
outbound. And then when you request that webpage to come back, it comes inbound through your
firewall that way and then out through the Wi-Fi that's also in the same device. So sometimes,
especially when you have a house full of, I don't know, half a dozen children and, you
know, a dog and everybody that wants to stream Netflix all at the same time, you can end
up quite quickly in a situation where the routing tables in these devices, they're very,
very cheaply made Chinesium type routing devices and they don't have a lot of memory in them,
a lot of these cheap ones. And very quickly you can exhaust the tables that they have
available that will fit in their memory. And that can manifest itself in a number of different
ways, poor performance, slow latency, pages just not loading for no reason, crash, crashes.
One of the things that I did probably four or five years ago that's helped my Wi-Fi experience
the most more than anything else was to separate my ISP modem or my router from the Wi-Fi hotspots
that I use for everything else. Now, I will also say that putting everything I possibly
can on an ethernet cable helps a lot as well. You know, like my Nvidia Shield is on ethernet,
my PlayStation 4, my 3D printer is on an ethernet cable, all of my desktops, my laptop is on
Wi-Fi 90% of the time, but at my desk where I spend most of my day, there is an ethernet
cable there ready for it. So if I can avoid Wi-Fi, I will. But sometimes you just can't,
you know, with a phone or a tablet, for example.
Or in my situation where we have ethernet everywhere in the studio, I go to the RV,
I can't run ethernet at all. It's just literally not an option. And so I have to have extremely
robust Wi-Fi.
And so by separating out the firewall from the Wi-Fi, that gives you a few benefits.
Firstly, if you have to reboot the router, all of the devices in your house will maintain
their Wi-Fi connection. Chromecasts won't decide that they need to now turn into a hotspot
and take a few minutes to figure out that the Wi-Fi is available again. But the same
is true conversely as well. If there's a problem with your Wi-Fi, you can reboot just the access
point and then your internet connection will stay completely stable and solid.
So there's a few benefits to doing it. And the company that I've used for the longest
time now is Ubiquiti, who make the UniFi line of devices.
I think probably most people listening at this point must be familiar with Ubiquiti.
They are extremely popular in our segment. And I think the number one thing I've heard
is they have really sophisticated management. And generally, there's just the one downside
brought up and that is the controller software. But even that doesn't necessarily sound like
it's the end of the world. You just have to be willing to host an application and it has
to be able to talk to the internet.
I was talking to somebody on the Ubiquiti broadcasting telegram just this afternoon
about hosting the UniFi controller out of a Docker container. Linux server obviously
make one and I've used that for years and it just works. Now I have two, I've just recently
added actually a third access point in my house. And all of these devices talk back
to a UniFi controller that's running on a DigitalOcean droplet. So it's not even running
in my house. I wrote a blog post last week, which there'll be a link to in the show notes,
about how to adopt an access point, a new access point with a remote controller. Now
for most people, they're going to be running their UniFi controller on a Raspberry Pi inside
the firewall or...
In a container.
Yeah, something like that. And it's not going to be an issue. It's just going to appear
through magic in the controller. You can adopt it and then configure it that way. It gives
you a lot of flexibility in some ways. It did feel, I will admit the very first time
that I did it, like a bit of a, why do I need, why can't I just go to the IP address of the
access point and do it that way? That's the way I've always done it before. But the advantage
of having a centralized configuration system is that if for any reason I need to reload,
I can back up all my configurations to that central system, wipe the access point and
then just reload the configuration from there. And what it's meant is that I've had now a
stable Wi-Fi configuration and network that's transcended four, five different houses, multiple
different ISPs. And that's another point I didn't actually bring up is if you separate
your Wi-Fi from the ISP provided router, every time you change ISPs, if you move house or
whatever, you don't have to reconfigure all your Wi-Fi devices. You've still got the same
SSID, the same password.
So I've got a couple of questions for you. Are they aware of each other essentially?
Do they balance their signal because they're aware of each other's location? Is that also
a benefit of the centralized controller? I had presumed it was when I had seen enterprise
deployments. Is that true in home deployments as well? Or is it not really applicable for
you?
I don't know if that's because of the centralized controller, but the Unifi gear itself does
have this zero handoff feature, which allows me to roam between different access points
in the building. And I just don't know slash care which particular access point I'm connected
to right now.
Yeah. So have you tested the performance of it?
Yes. Yes, a lot. I use that Libre Speed app running on the server in my basement to test
the throughput of the Wi-Fi. And I actually identified that one of the ethernet ports
on my Unifies was slightly dodgy through that. And I used a bit of hot glue to really jam
the cable in there and keep it there. And so I went from sort of round about 100 megabits
on that one up to pretty much full gigabit speed, not through Wi-Fi.
The reason I asked, and I think this is really important to underscore, is I've been to Buddy's
houses, I've been to a shop, and I've had one set up here in the studio that are all
Unifi Wi-Fi networks. And in those three anecdotal experiences in which I have gone to, I had
some of the worst Wi-Fi experiences like devices not connecting, horrible performance. And
I think what it just sort of underscores is if the rest of your network isn't really up
to shape, it doesn't matter what access points you put in. So like for these guys, their
DHCP server was running on a piece of crap that was so slow that it would time out before
you know you can get an IP. So that was the issue on one of them.
There's other aspects to a network that make it... It's not just the access points, but
I do think that it is more important than ever that Wi-Fi be as close to wire grade
as possible.
So I don't care whether you use Ubiquiti, Microtech, whoever. It really doesn't bother
me whatsoever. The point is that you separate the Wi-Fi from the firewall. And that will
in itself just enable easier troubleshooting. It will also mean, like I just said, that
you can transcend different houses with the same Wi-Fi gear.
Right. And the nice thing about the Ubiquiti gear is that's easy for you to do. And it's
not so easy with a lot of the mesh solutions that are out there now, like the Google one
and the D-Link one and the Eero one, which I've had good success with, but it wants to
be a router.
Now in the Eero solution, you don't have to use it as your main firewall slash router,
but in some of these you do. And I very much like Alex, am a big proponent of separating
those two tasks. I actually reboot my firewall on a somewhat regular basis because I'm often
switching between multiple networks. And I just want to clear things out every now and
then. And it takes like 15 seconds to reboot this little slate that I have. And so I just
toss off a reboot. And I know that all my... What? You like tossing off a reboot? You like
that? I toss off a reboot from here to there.
Tossing off in England is slang for...
I know what it's slang for. I just wasn't going to call it out. So I toss off a reboot
and I just wait a few seconds and the device is reconnected and everything's good. That's
my pro tip.
Who doesn't enjoy a good toss off?
No, especially when it's a reboot. It just feels good. So there's definitely some solid,
solid rationale for separating those two devices. So if you are looking at some of those mesh
networks that do offer some nice advantages, just be wary of that. Separate those functions
if you can.
There's a huge amount of stuff that if you want to hear about, let us know through selfhosted.show
slash contact or find me on Twitter at ironicbadger. And let us know if you want to hear more about
the UniFi. There's a bunch of features in there which we could cover.
Yeah, I would like to get that feedback because we are definitely not done talking about this.
We want to talk about switches and firewalls soon. So it's your chance to get your feedback
in the Discord. That'd be a great spot to just engage with us on this. And it's a spot
not only are we watching really closely, but where we could kind of have a ongoing conversation
about it. So be sure to join us there.
I need to upsell you on PFSense or OpenSense or one of these others.
You think you could run on a Pine64 board?
You're a madman.
I know, I just ordered one and I'm trying to think of, you know that thing's got a PCI
slot, Alex.
Ooh.
Yeah, I know. And I know if I'm thinking about it, thinking about it. But let's wrap up today
by spending a little time talking about a really cool app you can load on your rig to
get really good information. In fact, you can even use it to monitor multiple, it's
called NetData and it's a Westpane special. He loads it on all of our systems here at
the studio.
If you've never tried it, netdata.cloud, it's kind of amazing. So it provides real time
metrics of pretty much everything that's going on in your system. And it's really quite
beautiful. It just runs in the background. You won't even know it's there. It uses very
little resources. But if you want to know, for example, which of your hard disks is being
completely trashed right now and causing your machine to stutter, load up this NetData thing,
go and look at the disk IO section and you'll figure out, oh, it's this one over here. Maybe
I need to move this workload over here or do something else with it.
You can also monitor network traffic. It's a really good way to test, you know, you'll
see quite often in Linus tech tip videos, they're monitoring network speed through an
unraid server and they're using NetData to do it. So there's a lot of different use cases
for this software and it comes highly recommended.
Like you said, it is also very pretty, which I appreciate the way it visualizes everything.
We keep it running here on the systems like I was talking about. And it's just a nice
way to just check in on the health of them to get an idea of what the workload is. And
you will spot weird problems watching these graphs. You will notice something's taken
a long time to wait on X. Maybe it's like Alex was saying, a disk. I found what seemed
to be a wonky Nick. And how about that? A wonky Nick. And we replaced it and it immediately
looked better. It just was one of those things you could immediately visualize the improvement.
And that's kind of cool too. Plus it stores all that stuff and then you can add your other
rigs in there and switch between them. I don't think it stores them on their servers. It's
all local. So they all have to be able to have access to the internet if you want to
be able to jump around.
It's all local. Yeah. Do you want to know the icing on the cake though? What is that?
I discovered a Home Assistant integration for it. Stop it. Link it up. I got to see
that. It's in the show notes. No, no, no, no way. So you could run net data on all of
your pies and then have it show up various stats in Home Assistant about each of those
pies. I do run it on my pies. So I will be doing this. That's great. Home Assistant is
so awesome. This is ultimately why I had to go to the more HaasIO style setup because
I realized there's such a great community around it and it's just getting better. And
so you got to have access to all these cool things people are doing and that's just the
best way to get it.
Absolutely. Now I was on Reddit this week and I saw a post about somebody saying, everything's
gone. All of my stuff is gone. And they'd accidentally exposed one of their services
to the internet and some bad actor had come along and deleted all their media. Oh, that's
so sad. Now we have an Ask SSH question from Seb Couture. Did I get that right, do you
reckon? Let's say yes. I don't know why I'm asking you. You're horrible at pronouncing
stuff. Yeah. I would have said SebCulture or something. And Seb writes in on Twitter,
would you open your Home Assistant behind a reverse proxy? Is it safe? What do you think?
Well my previous answer was no. And then this time I signed up for the Home Assistant cloud,
which is not quite what he's talking about, but it is a form of remote access.
That security through obscurity though almost with the URL's really long string of random
characters.
Yes, it is. And then you have to have authentication and there's those elements to it. And I opted
to do it this time. In the past I required like a wire guard connection to get to it.
And I think you've kind of opted to do the same, haven't you? You've set up a reverse
proxy for yours. So you have kind of made that same sort of call. Again, it's a compromise.
I run a few apps on my reverse proxy, which are public and internet facing, but they all
have at minimum some kind of authentication. The mistake the guy made on Reddit was that
he had no password for anything set. So if you just guessed the URL or the port number
correctly, you could log in and delete whatever you wanted with no password.
I don't think I would expose any of my media server or media collection applications to
the web. I would only expose applications that are explicitly designed to have public
facing features. And I know that just because some of these apps are web apps, it seems
like they're designed for that, but they're not. They should only be used on your LAN,
I think, or with a VPN.
Right. And that was going to be my point, you know, with WireGuard making it into the
Linux kernel now, which is amazing, incredible. There's no real excuse these days. And perhaps
when we talk about firewalls in an episode or two, we'll talk about why I switched to
OpenSense and what that has to do with WireGuard. But I think, you know, once you're on the
VPN, it's so easy to pretend with DNS or whatever that you're on your LAN anyway. I mean, maybe
five years ago it was different, but nowadays with WireGuard, it's so easy. I don't really
see any excuse to open much to the internet anymore.
I look forward to talking more about networking. That's been Self-Hosted 16, and we'll see
you on Discord.