well i've made it down to southern oregon to get lady jubes ready for a summer road trip and she
had a little bit of work she still needed done from the last road trip so i'm down here i might
sound a little different might sound a little off because i'm actually like just in a parking lot
i'm just i'm not like in a studio i'm not in some nice place with good signal and quiet sounds nope
i'm just in a parking lot while i get some work done but the show must go on alex and what could
go wrong with that particularly with the starlink situation you've got right now yeah my starling's
busted too the motor the dish works so i can rabbit ear it you know i can i i've done this
i've gone out there and tried to point it at the northern sky and try to figure out where the
satellites at and it'll work for a bit but finally after about like a week and change maybe a little
almost two weeks they finally got back to me they're going to send me a replacement that's
good good don't forget to buy an ethernet adapter if you're getting the square one now right i think
i probably will i'm going to go from the round dishy to the square dishy i went shopping today
while i was killing time while they were working on the rig i haven't gone to best buy since the
pandemic started i just haven't had a chance to go in so i was curious what are they doing
for their home automation gear now and they're they're really big of course on the amazon
ecosystem and the google ecosystem huge on arlo and a lot of the video lights that you can attach
to your house that have like motion detection they sell a whole bunch of those like i said i haven't
been in a long time and i'm sure a lot of people listening know this but i didn't really realize
or appreciate that they're doing e-ink displays for all the prices and stuff for most things
have you seen this you've probably seen this because you've probably gone in more recently
than i have it's pretty cool isn't it it works right some of them are a little hard to read
but i like it i think it's a nice touch it's cool and then the one device that really impressed me
out of all the stuff there that i saw i didn't pick it up but the pricing on the lenovo smart
clock stands that have google assistant built in it looks like an alarm clock but it has google
assistant 29.99 for this thing yeah that is nice open box 25 bucks and then they have one with a
screen that has the google cards on it and stuff like that for 89.99 i was at best buy just this
week buying a new hard drive but let's not let's not spoil the show oh yeah yeah yeah it was good
to go in there you know do a little shopping get a sense of where the pricing's at and honestly
doesn't seem like the the tech pricing's really changed much everything's going up in price except
for a lot of the tech stuff still seems like it was priced it was a year or two ago i feel like
walking into best buy is how like harry potter must feel walking out of diagon alley or something
like this is this is how normal people live this is like how muggles live i would have loved to
have seen the starlink kit at best buy i mean i knew it just wasn't going to happen but imagine
if i could have walked in there and bought a new dish tonight with a working motor imagine this
imagine if starlink made a dish that was repairable oh whoa like maybe i could open it up
and replace the motor no and then i could just carry spare parts on board and then like install
them when it goes wrong that's just that's crazy alex it's so frustrating you know it's going to
be like a three dollar part that's broken yeah i'm actually a little concerned about how i'm
going to transport it in the future because as far as i know it was just transporting it going
down the road maybe the jar a jarring bump something broke the motor and uh so now i'm
thinking about when i do get a replacement dish like do i need to get like a case for this thing
like a pelican case like i don't know i'm curious what the audience might do if they have a starlink
and they're transporting it are there starlink cases for safe transport is that a thing we'll
build you a wooden crate between me and brent i think we can make that happen there you go that
looked pretty nice what we're live tonight somehow i don't know how the cellular signal is mostly
holding on i've dropped 6 000 packets so it's not perfect but it's holding good enough dude we've
got folks in the discord the self-hosted discord is going like always at selfhosted.show slash
discord hit a milestone recently we did we just passed 4500 members which is crazy that is so
great you got to admit it was a little awkward when we decided to go with discord since it is
not a self-hosted chat platform but you can't deny the networking aspect of it well i just
look at the uh palava that you and wes have been through on linux unplugged with your matrix server
and i just i feel completely vindicated in that decision yeah you might be right you might be
right the matrix server has been a real learning process i like to think of it as a long-term
investment right something like that something like that now speaking of long-term planning it's
not that far away but i'm going to be in the uk in august early august so i'm kind of floating
the idea of a uk meetup because several people messaged me when we were talking about the rally
one saying that they were jealous the vague very vague plan at this point is uh the weekend of
august the sixth somewhere in london so that people can fly in from ireland and europe more
easily somewhere in london we'll have a meetup maybe a pub maybe a community center something
like that i don't know we're going to figure it out but if you're interested send me a message
on the discord or hit me up on twitter at ironic badger uh i want to go so bad i bet august is a
great time to be in london too it could be it could be a good time or it could be snowing and
raining sideways in august who knows i mean no maybe not snow but i mean honestly it could be 35
celsius or it could be 10 who knows do you want people to send you uh suggestions via emails maybe
the contact page contact page anything like that if you've got a venue in mind i was i was thinking
we did a few events for redhat consulting when i was in london at brewdog those pubs are quite
hip and trendy and modern they've got like a whole area upstairs that you can kind of rent out some
some of them so maybe something like that would be nice because they're sort of half open half
inside type thing so kind of hedge our bets on the weather that's probably a pretty good idea
let's be honest man i'm so jealous please take pictures i want to i want to see it maybe one
of these days we'll get you out there huh maybe uh fosdom i'd love to definitely on my list it
kind of got set back the last couple of years but it's definitely on my list this is one of those
episodes we have them i think about every other episode i'm gonna have a bunch of work after uh
this this episode i just i just know it i know it and it's gonna be it's gonna be because my wife's
gonna demand it you have come across something i i feel like either you talked to me about it before
off air or someone did it just doesn't seem right that we haven't talked about this on air yet well
a couple of weeks ago the tandoor project a self-hosted recipe manager released version
1.4 so they've been in in development for a year plus at this point so it's very possible you've
seen it on reddit at some point before yeah maybe but the 1.4 release has got some notable changes
in it there's a whole new shopping list feature built in which is pretty darn cool and so just
to be clear this is a recipe manager that you would run on your own system where they offer
a self-hosted version and if we if we haven't talked about on the show before we should have
well we've talked about chow down and i'm fairly sure we've talked about mealy before if we haven't
i use both of those equally i still love chow down because it's a simple markdown based system
there's no database there's no craziness it's just a stupid simple markdown plain text files
but having a database gives you some nice features like in tandoor for example
when you import a recipe you can then add it into a meal plan so you could have a
family-facing meal plan dashboard take it one step further the app knows which ingredients go
into those recipes so you can say excuse me tandoor could you please add that to my shopping list and
then pull that shopping list up when you're at the grocery store and just buy everything you need for
that specific thing now what i saw in reddit as a particularly interesting idea was some kind of
like self-hosted hellofresh someone suggested to the developer that he integrates with instant
carts api with those recipes to order three green peppers and some chicken and whatever else you
need for that that recipe so you end up with this like self-hosted hellofresh type thing which i
thought would be an amazing amazing thing no kidding brilliant idea this has another feature
that you're probably about to touch on but i just have to talk about because this is what won me
over and it is one of the newer features they just recently implemented and it's this really slick
import feature where you can give it the url of a website that has a recipe i threw one of those
one of those like essentially a blog post where they tell you their whole life story just to give
you a recipe and they have pictures and oh i hate those so much i found like the worst one man where
it has like slide over javascript and just all kinds of junk and i i i gave the url to tender
and it actually processed the page it pulled out all the individual steps all of the individual
ingredients and it itemized it all just perfectly i threw some simpler ones out it did great too but
i was really impressed that it got that that really complicated one and so it's like you just
take this really really long three-page post and condense it down into just a good block
information you need and then you add it to your database and now you got that recipe it's amazing
it will import the images from the website it will also pick out keywords yes yes yes it will
figure out the steps you need the ingredients uh everything so the the import stuff is really slick
and you can do one recipe at a time or you can just give it a list of urls with a line
a new line per link and it just it just works i mean that's the best kind of works right i had
the wife use it because she was just yesterday talking to me about how you know my grammy used
index cards and when i when i first started cooking i created a binder she said and i had all
my recipes in this binder that i'd printed out but that's gone now and she wanted to start collecting
her recipes again and so i had her sit down and input a few of them into this and i'd say within
15 minutes she probably had four recipes added and she was testing the shopping cart feature
to see how that works and then she was visualizing okay well how would this work if i'm
if i'm at if i'm at the grocery store and i have my phone with me how would the ui look so she like
resizes the browser to see if it works okay on mobile it totally did it looks like it's going to
render just fine and so she had herself a list that she could just go down the aisle and check off
as she buys and she experimented with seeing what happens if multiple recipes call for the
same ingredient and if it gets the right amounts correct in the shopping cart and it does it just
does a really good job with all that and it supports markdown for your cooking notes that is
cool yes i was going to touch on the comment feature at the bottom there's also another option
to log a specific cook so i'm thinking for my barbecue grilling like if i put the brisket recipe
that i use in there i can link things like the youtube video but then i can also give myself a
rating out of five and a specific date and time that's in there and then tie that into a specific
comment on a specific day to say i let's try say i tried a new technique that day with uh with
grilling it's a serious business don't you know you got to make sure you get it right and if you
got if you nailed it you got to note down what you did or if you mess it up exactly exactly now the
the other thing that i really really like is it has a servings option at the top of the page with
like a plus and a minus and in the ingredients thing here let's say you've got two pounds of
chicken in your recipe and it's four servings i can just hit the plus button and double that to
i don't know seven let's go with seven servings now i mean the mental maths isn't too difficult
on that one but how many times have you had to do some weird fractional maths on a cup of flour or
something weird like that and and the servings thing in here it works flawlessly yeah and it's
again that's also nice when you're using it to generate the shopping list so you know how much
you need of something in there the other thing that i didn't get a lot of time to use but i think
was really interesting to my wife was it has a meal planner in there and uh you get a calendar
and you can plan out your meals of course you can use you can select the recipes that you've
already input to the system then if you would like it will actually export you out a calendar
file an ics file or whatever they are and you can import that meal plan into your calendar
app of choice so you have it somewhere outside tandoor as well which i thought that was a really
nice touch now for hadia's thing there is a whole cookbooks feature so you could kind of group
recipes you know like grandma mom wife whatever you know for me i could have a barbecue cookbook
for example that would be pretty cool there's so many features in this thing i feel like we could
spend an hour on it almost but if you're interested it's obviously free and open source software over
on github there'll be a link in the show notes it's at tandoor recipes recipes in github yeah
definitely worth checking out i mean when's the last time we get this excited about a recipe app
i mean maybe we just like recipe apps but this is a whole management suite but what was the process
like of getting it installed because i tried their online demo since i'm on the road i didn't want to
get go through all the process of loading it up but i think i'm going to have to do that when
i get home so give me an idea of what i'm looking at it's not too bad three containers there's a
database so postgres there's the app itself which is a jango based application and then there's an
nginx front end i mean you can switch out the nginx front end web server if you like with
your web server of choice personally i would prefer if the developer shipped the tandoor
application with a simple web server built in the g unicorn stuff that's built into the app that
ships is not really fit for purpose in terms of public hosting and he mentions that in the
documentation he's very clear about that and that's why he suggests people spin up nginx
but i'm a fairly experienced docker administrator at this point a container guy and i got a couple
of my file paths wrong so some of it's on me admittedly but it took me about an hour to get
this going simply because i had to link three containers together and make sure everything was
just so and there's an environment variables file and all that kind of stuff it's not too difficult
honestly if you don't copy paste the wrong paths but it could be easier if it was just an all
self-contained app like for example plexus i understand there's a bit of a debate there
some people have the philosophy you just do the core application and then you do one instance of
nginx and one instance of your database and maybe whatever else you might have and don't run multiple
copies of that software in a container and i definitely think that's probably an appropriate
setup for production you know anything that's in a business or enterprise or anything that's going
to scale beyond a dozen users probably worth considering but for this sort of scenario the
one that you're talking about now where you're going to run it on your home server it's going
to be you and your wife and maybe me and maybe brent they're going to use it total right and so
there it does make a lot of sense to just have something that is maybe just a single docker
container you pop it on your machine and you go particularly it's not a super heavy application
right it's a small dango app and an nginx web server like that's that's very tiny also i mean
i know this is easy for me to say but wouldn't be impossible to have two types of containers one
that's just the application core and one that includes maybe the full suite of everything you
need yeah so mr developer man vabine 1111 if you're listening that's pretty much the only
feedback i have for you really the application's great the stuff you've done over the last year plus
improving this application is to be commended truly but the setup process i know i saw in reddit
that you don't understand why people find it difficult i hope just what we've articulated
there helps a little bit of me on that particular bone it's it's just linking different things
together in people's different setups you know some people are running unraid some people are
running true nas i'm running docker compose through an ansible templating thing that i created so you
know there's lots of different strokes for different folks and anything you can do to reduce
that deployment complexity is going to increase your adoption it's as simple as that definitely
well said and i'm looking forward to getting this running this is going to be something you know the
wife and i are really going to going to enjoy but i don't think i'll be setting it up on my proxmox
system not yet but i am planning to build one soon and it sounds like we've got a brand new release
that looks great we do 7.2 now the headline feature for me besides you know fun stuff like
the linux kernel getting a bump and qemu and lxc and zfs and all those things getting bumps to the
latest versions is support for the accelerated vert io gl display driver i know it sounds
thrilling right but hear me out the this particular display driver is in software and i went from
about 13 frames per second we all know what that feels like that's what the traditional vm in a
browser has felt like for a decade i went from about 10 or 15 frames a second to over a hundred
hey whoa really just changing that feature and there was no drivers required on the guest i had
to install a couple of packages on proxmox itself but it tells you what they are in the documentation
and it was that was it i was done and suddenly i've got 10 times performance improvement how
often does that happen that's huge i can tell you i've experienced that on parallels on the m1 max
when they added support for the m1 platform they added vert io and vert iogl for the graphics
pass-through and it makes the desktop on linux responsive like it's on the metal it's really
really great and so how are you accessing this it through proxmox is it is it through the web
console through the web browser yeah nothing crazy at all so there's a spice client that connects
to the vm's console in the browser there's no hardware pass-through going on here i want to be
absolutely clear this is all in software you know traditionally we did a whole episode of linux
unplugged a long time ago now on gpu pass-through and how much of a bitch it can be to get the right
hardware and get the right software and everything all lined up just tickety-boo it's a lot easier
these days now nvidia have kind of capitulated there but i digress this is all software and
you know i can't overstate like just a 10x performance improvement right in front of my eyes
and so now i've gone from needing a spare laptop to test linux desktop distros to get the feel
right to get that high frame rate feel of what a new gnome release feels like what a new kde plasma
release feels like i can do this now in the browser from proxmox and it's so great that's
awesome i'm oh i've decided proxmox is going on the studio servers we put a pull out to the
audience again and said what do you think of a proxmox with nick's combo probably some open
suits in there too just to make the lizards happy and uh we're gonna have three systems and at least
two of them are gonna be running proxmox gonna start with 7.2 out of the gate so we're gonna
get this feature out of the gate proxmox is a great choice there's uh it's a debian user space
with a modified ubuntu kernel which means that you get zfs support as well no dkms
nonsense to mess around with it's just there and you get a nice little gooey on top to manage your
vms i mean there's some other stuff too like they've got a pretty slick backup server and
you know the community around proxmox is really starting to gather steam i've really noticed in
the last i would say two to three years it's gone from being a kind of niche project it's
it's really up and coming right now you know they've been consistent they've delivered over
and over and over again with it and i think that makes a difference i've i've just seen their
reputation get stronger and stronger you know if they're ever looking to sponsor hit us up
we basically just gave them a pretty good plug right there for free huh i know they're good for
a while aren't they one other thing i want to point out that i thought was pretty cool and this
is a very minor annoyance but if you're a proxmox user you will appreciate it you can now send
it you can now set your default vm id range so when you go and click the button that says create
vm it normally assigns a three-digit number like 100 102 whatever and it'll just do it sequentially
based on the next number that's available a bit like a dhcp reservation now i can select start
that range and end that range of the auto kind of like vm id dhcp requests for one of a better idea
i can select a range to put those numbers in and i can have my kind of normal vms sit at the top
where i see them all the time and then my more ephemeral stuff sits at the bottom out of the way
where i use it for testing linode.com slash ssh go there to get 100 and 60 day credit on a new account
and you go there to support this here show that's right it's made possible by you taking advantage
of our sponsor and of course linode is one that we enthusiastically endorse they started in 2003
and they have been building the best service to run applications on linux since and you can also
use as part of a multi-cloud strategy like i do this i have some servers on my lan and i have the
bulk of all of our audience facing systems on linode and we also have some of our work systems
on there too so i kind of pick and choose based on the workload and what i love about it is they've
got pricing that makes that really accessible so some systems they start at just five dollars a
month other systems they have a lot more options like amd epic processors we have one box that has
96 gigs of ram right i mean you can really max this stuff out 48 cpu cores in that box mvme hard
drives they're great and then of course they have 11 data centers for you to choose from so you're
going to find something close to you or your customers don't know how you're doing it they've
also got a great dashboard they got the best support in the business we hear that all the time
the other thing that we hear from the audience all the time is that they'll deploy themselves
a server for just like their family for like a gaming server or next cloud or photos or whatever
it might be uh recently and i never really thought about doing this but recently i heard from an
audience member he runs piehole up on linode and then he points all the systems to that even his
laptop and stuff and his family member's laptop so when they're traveling they're always using his dns
system and they're getting the filtering up on linode that's great and when you get a hundred
dollars you can play around with stuff like that see what sticks see if the value is really there
and it's a great way to support the show and learn something so go to linode.com slash ssh you go
there you get that hundred dollars you go deploy something you go learn something you support the
show it's a win-win linode.com slash ssh now after my buddy brent went home the other day
i was sat in my basement by myself billy no mates we did a shot of my server just doing some
tinkering around because we did some electrics down there and i wanted to automate uh something
that we put in with one of the shellys in a light switch and i was sat next to my server
and i could just hear oh no i was like oh no dead disk turns out it wasn't the cable people
oh right last time you thought it was the cable oh no it really was going it really was the drive
so quick trip to best buy the next morning bought a new 14 terabyte easy store ripped that bad boy
out of the case and it's now in my backup server doing my whole like pre clear ritual testing
burning thing no data loss no luckily i was able to just copy all the data from the failing drive
onto the rest of my merger fs array i actually had more than 10 terabytes free so i was lucky
there really i could do that i just removed it from the array and copied everything across with
rsync what do you think it would take for a new file system to work its way into your life for you
to find a new love for a file system um just say hypothetically like bcash fs comes out
it's so great it's xfs meets butter fs meets cfs and it's just next level performance too
what would it take for you to switch would it be would it be a matter of years would it be
something you'd start experimenting with sooner than later i don't know as i have a need for
anything new my needs through merger fs have been met so comprehensively back in the day that if you
look at the perfect media server kind of blog post series you can kind of see my transition
over the years from i think it was a ufs to mhd dfs to md raid through zfs even for actual media
files and then i ended up with just ext4 and xfs on the drives themselves uh kind of bridged with
merger fs on top it's just been so reliable for what six or seven years when i don't even know
when i wrote that first post it was a long time ago i don't know like i felt the need to add zfs
into the setup for data i truly care about mostly for replication ease and stuff like that but i've
kind of solved that now with uh restic as well so i've got a couple of ways i back stuff up for the
important data but for media files that are right once read a couple of times probably merger fs
does everything i need what are you uh what are you hinting at there chris well so the word on
the street although we'll see if this really pans out but the word on the street is that we're going
to see bcash fs hit the linux kernel in about the next six months or so maybe a little bit longer
but it's nigh and the developer kent overstreet recently said that his goal is to essentially
make a file system that does just that it kind of replaces or it offers uh the advantages of xfs
which xfs is a very solid very tried and true file system and with some of the benefits of butterfs
like copy on write snapshots stuff like that that's pretty cool he was asked recently who's
using bcash fs is anybody using it in production and he said well i do know that a lot of video
shops that are dealing with multiple 4k streams are using bcash fs and it made me think like i
think every time i've switched a major file system it's been to solve a performance problem or a
scalability problem like i i really finally gave in and tried butterfs for real when i needed to
solve storage issues on a raspberry pi and i just wasn't going to use the fs i had no choice so i
had to learn butterfs and then i learned that i actually liked it quite a bit but i only did it
when i was trying to solve like a new problem and i just wonder you know like bcash fs is going to
come along one day it's going to be great no doubt about it but i i i'm kind of of the uh
school of thought that when it comes to my data i like to give that stuff years you know years of
cooking years of people other people using it in production that's just one area where i'll
i'll kind of tap the brakes a little bit and that's why it took me a while to come around
about our fest to be honest that's really what i love about the zfs i know it has a bit of a
learning curve and a bit of an aura around it but are you laughing an aura i think a bit of an aura
is a funny way to put it yeah it does i mean just listen to you and alan back in the day on text
snap like you made it sound like this massive complex beast and actually it's not it's just
two drives in a mirror right i mean it's that's it that's what i use anyway yeah it does it can
be very complex but yeah um that's not so bad really so i'm glad that you got it found i'm
sorry there was actually the drive and not the cable though that does stink well so this presents
an interesting opportunity for content actually so this will be the first shut drive i've had fail
on me i don't have the plastic casing anymore i chucked that out as a matter of principle
so i'm really interested to see what happens when i send this 12 terabyte drive which is only about
15 months old back to western digital it came with a two-year warranty and there's apparently
something called the magnuson moss act i think that's what it is if they try and play funny
buggers with it i can quote them and say that and apparently then they'll just capitulate and send
me their replacement reconditioned drive because they can't prove that my shucking it broke it or
something let's talk a little ansible one of our favorite topics here and i think maybe one we
should should probably share a little more on the show as brent begins his journey down the ansible
lane but in the meantime before we go down ansible lane maybe we should stop off uh on uh bit warden
drive what do you got here what about if i put some peanut butter with the chocolate yeah that
sounds perfect for me and bring ansible together with bit warden how about that right that sounds
good actually there was a chat happening on discord i think it was this morning where orange uh jake
who was on the show a little while ago was talking about how he uses ansible vault crossed with bit
warden there is a reference to one of my favorite bash.org moments where the part his demo password
is hunter 2 those that know know about that one and but essentially what this allows me to do
is use bit warden as my credential store for my ansible vault encryption password so all of my
secrets remain encrypted using ansible vault with 256 bit blah blah blah as a file that i store
version controlled in git what i'm doing now is rather than having a clear text file sitting on
disk to decrypt that file i am now using the bit warden cli to connect the vault password that i've
now put in bit warden to unlock that uh encrypted file in ansible this feels like it could be pretty
powerful i think i'm understanding but um so essentially as ansible is setting up a machine
if it needs to deploy software that needs some sort of secret password or key instead of having
to put that somewhere in the ansible config or whatever there's now an option to have as ansible
is deploying use the bit warden cli to look that password up and sort of insert that password as
it's being deployed is that right you could do that using the lookup plugin i think but the way
that we're doing it right now at least is using a so you can actually this is a really neat trick
that i didn't know until this morning you can put in your ansible config the vault file location as
a script and in that script you can actually have it do the bit warden cli export lookup thing of
the password and then it returns it as a string which then feeds into the the rest of the process
so all i'm doing i haven't moved any of the secrets themselves out of ansible out of the
vault in ansible but i've moved the vault password from a local text file on my laptop
into bit warden and now i've connected the two together using oranges post very nice we'll have
links to this so you can follow along we'll have links to this in the show notes of course at
self-hosted dot show slash 71 i thought it'd be really difficult but it turned out to be about
a five or ten line change there'll be a commit in the show notes if you're curious as just to
how easy it is easier than getting the recipe app going much easier uh we love you tandoor we love
you we've been having a lot of fun on the discord over the last couple of weeks with ansible and
infrastructures code talk as you can probably tell from how much of it's in the show one of
the things i decided to do when brent was here he just flippantly asked me can you do dns from your
docker compose generator and i was like sure knowing full well i couldn't but how hard could
it be right turned out to be quite the operation it took me about two or three days with the help
of about four or five people on discord to write possibly one of the most i dare i say over
engineered ansible tasks ever this thing essentially takes a traffic label strips out
strips out with regex a bunch of stuff surrounding the bit of data i want which is you know the host
name of like test.jupyterbroadcasting.com that's the bit i actually want but i had to find a way
to iterate over all the labels in the nested list that i have in ansible and then extract them and
do what i need to do and then only act on them when the item in the list was set to active equals
true there's a lot of logic in there anyway the upshot is we can now specify for all of the
self-hosted jb infrastructure simply by adding a container with a traffic label into our compose
definition file we add the dns record automatically into cloudflare hmm that is pretty damn slick so
just by having the label for traffic yeah it figures out from there what the what the host
name should be and all of that absolutely yeah that's it and what's particularly fun is you know
let's say i wanted to spin up an nginx just to test for example i just copy and paste that in there
and if i put test. as long as the domain's in my cloudflare account or i have permissions like
you've given me yeah delegated permissions on jb.com i can add something into that git repo
and we could then theoretically have a continuous integration github action that would pick up that
change and deploy that new container and also the dns records in cloudflare automatically for us
that's what i'm talking about alex that is awesome it's really cool that is awesome and
that is such a great example of we recently were talking about nix and nix packages and managing
nix os and all of that being a deterministic system and how it compared to ansible and this
is such a great example where you can go much further with ansible you can go much beyond just
just what you can do with nix very exciting and it makes me pumped to kind of redo some of this
infrastructure stuff and do it like this from the beginning because like down the road it's
just going to make future deployments so much simpler right that's that's really when you spin
up a new show or decide you're going to have a garage sale or whatever it is it's all automatic
that's so great yeah and done once and now it's done one of my favorite tricks in this particular
task and there are a couple one is to use json query to create a dictionary that i can then
split and join and what have you within the task itself the other one is to use what's called a
ternary operator now ginger which is the templating language that ansible has is is pretty amazing and
you can do a lot of cool stuff but i was running into an issue where my item dot active contents
was either true or false and the ansible module was expecting the phrase present or absent now
you as a human can work out that true equals present and the absent equals false computer
is stupid you have to tell computer this thing turns out with the ternary operator we can actually do
that so if we pass in a true or false statement into the ternary operator and then specify just
a couple of other values present and absent in this case we can have true or false actually be
any other string that we require very simple very cool tailscale.com slash self hosted go there to
get a free personal account for up to 20 devices and you support the show tailscale is a zero config
vpn you get it on any device in minutes it'll manage your firewall rules it'll help with
double carrier grade crazy nat all of that i'm using tailscale right now in fact alex and i
were using tailscale earlier today as well in a way that i haven't really used it before tell
me about the fanciness that we were doing share share it with the people actually well i span up
tandoor on my lan and i thought it'd be pretty cool if i could just share this demo instance
with chris because you're having some issues with their public demo so i went into my tailscale
dashboard and i click sharing settings got a link to share one of my specific hosts my docker host
with you you accept a couple of things in your tailscale dashboard on your end straight away
you've got access just to that specific host but you could also use it as an exit node as well so
let's say you have a friend geographically in a useful place for you you could ask that friend
to share just that vm or whatever it is and you won't have access to the rest of that person's lan
only to that specific host and only as an exit node if they permit it yep it is a superpower
and it's something that just makes collaborating with people so great and the way tailscale works
is it uses wire guard's noise protocol to create a flat mesh network between all of your machines
and if you've got two machines on the same lan and you're talking to their tailscale ips
it figures that out and it actually will just go over your lan it doesn't like need to go through
some central proxy or anything like that they have a authorization backplane that they use to
proxy the connection to set everybody up to get them established but then you're talking directly
to each other after that they also work with your single sign-on provider which means they also
support two-factor if you've got that going you got to go try tailscale because once you have it
set up in a couple of minutes you've got an always on vpn protected by wire card it's so slick and
i've got it running now on my family's machines as well as my raspberry pi's my servers my vms
it brings it all together and you can try it for yourself for free for up to 20 machines at tailscale
dot com slash self-hosted that's where you got to go to support the show and try it out for 20
machines for totally free at tailscale dot com slash self-hosted scott writes in looking for
chip shortage alternatives with this continuing on through the foreseeable future and raspberry
pi's becoming the new unobtainium i would like to hear some ideas from you both as to what to look
for in alternatives i'd also love to hear from other insiders what they're using through feedback
of their own specifically this is a problem for me since i like having dedicated systems for
certain tasks for example a pie hole is a dedicated appliance for me and i want my dns to be reliable
i just want stuff to work with minimal administration i've got loads of other
hobbies and i don't want to spend all my free time being my own it admin as they're always
overworked underpaid and usually grumpy after business hours can relate scott can relate
he may be right about that got to admit you know scott the first thing that came to mind for me
and this is something that i've already done once is low power cheap used laptops on ebay
often they have more horsepower than a raspberry pi some of them even have features like quicksync
so they make it great for plex the only real challenges that i've run into and why i haven't
really talked about it a lot on air is because i'm almost always hitting some kind of ios limited
some kind of ios limitation that just drives me crazy maybe it's usb or ethernet or something
like that but depending on what your needs are like if you get if you could find a laptop
like some of these thinkpads that support two discs and maybe you're okay with just that amount
of storage you can actually make a laptop work pretty well in place of a raspberry pi what do
you think alex you got any ideas well something like an old thinkpad you can have pretty cheap
like i've just had a quick look now t450 which is fifth gen intel 100 140 depending on the spec and
how much ram and disk and have what have you that's in there but we've also been talking
about this on the discord a fair bit recently with the uh like tiny mini micro stuff that kind
of stuff like um serve the home i've been doing a whole series on this stuff now they typically
buy the higher end stuff the newer stuff or they get sent it anyway we've been talking about the
kind of the lower end of that market there are some old thin client boxes that have been knocking
around for a long time i i think it's is it wise spelt w y s e these guys uh they do thin clients
for enterprise so they they've got boxes knocking around by the thousand and you can get them super
cheap on ebay and often they've got ethernet built in and usb depending on the model you go
for you might be lucky to get one with some sata space in there you know maybe you could have a
sata ssd in there or an m.2 if you get really lucky uh so that's the i'd probably go yeah we
looked at a couple of those recently and um those could be really awesome too for low power i think
like the biggest bottleneck there was memory on those units like they're usually pretty but
depending again what you're doing that might not be that might not be an issue just kind of depends
on your workload these wise boxes are about the size of two or three cd cases maybe so they're
very very small and they're very very cheap they can be had for as low as 15 20 something like that
some of them don't include memory at that kind of price but some of them do and they're x86 they're
atoms right i mean they're you could just run anything some are atom some are amd all right
well oliver writes in he says hi guys thanks for the show i've been listening from the beginning
and i've learned a lot i've been struggling to find a great self-hosted podcast solution for a
while now audiobook shelf has recently blown up and it's been really actively developed and the
podcast feature is probably the most excited i've been for a self-host application for a long time
but there's still some work to be done it's amazing what's been accomplished already though
it's now my primary podcast listening app i wonder alex have you played it all with podcast and
audiobook shelf i've still got it spun up from the episode we talked about it a couple of weeks ago
did you try a podcast in there i haven't done any podcasts but we could do a live we could
do a live test right now if you like oh all right let's oh that's exciting i know this is a common
question that comes into the show is hey how can i can i self-host my own podcast and i never really
feel like we have a super great answer because i think a great aspect of podcasts in my opinion
is that now i know not everybody does it this way but for me is that the mp3 file is actually locally
on the storage device of my phone and so i can listen to a podcast without using data or when i
don't have signal or when i just don't want to use much battery life either and so i really like
having podcasts locally on my phone so that's why i've ended up trying to use podcast apps at sync
but i yeah i don't love any of it i found it so i have to create a new library so i've just added
a new folder to my um audiobook shelf container so i'm going to have a dedicated podcasts folder
okay that container is now spun up so i'm going to just load up audiobook shelf add a new library
select podcasts from the list i've got to give it the correct icon that's very important now
interestingly enough the metadata provider is itunes so even though it's a self-hosted podcast
um server for want of a better word still using uh internet-based metadata that's a real shame
you know they could be using the podcast index and they could also use pod ping and they wouldn't
even need to use the index that's a bit of a shame oh i see so i can have a oh i can put an rss feed
in there all right so where's the self-hosted rss feed self-hosted.show rss rss yep it's real simple
all right let's put that in there let's see what happens when i click submit oh that's pretty cool
it's found the album art it's got the genres correct it's got the description auto download
episodes check add podcast all right hmm let's see what happens all right all right that doesn't
seem too bad i gotta be honest okay this is pretty great yeah this is the this is the way you know
you're just saying you don't have a great way this is it i think anyway okay all right all right
maybe we got to give this more serious go then because this would be nice to just have a solution
for people because they're writing all the time okay thanks oliver i'm gonna gonna try that out
i think that'll be pretty great we got some boost into the show first one came from x thumb sx who
sent us a boost using a new podcast app 5000 sats he mentions that there are silicon wedding bands
that solve the issue of like uh i think we were talking about getting them in the cases or getting
them uh you know problems with working with electricity he says this is also great when
installing smart devices they don't dig into your finger when gripping tools or sports equipment
that's pretty awesome i didn't realize they made silicone wedding rings i'm such an idiot
i never even checked you know it's not something that occurred to me i just took mine off and
didn't think about it yeah cosp land sent us a boost for 3690 sats he always comes he always
sends us in like numbers that i think mean something and he says yes the numbers are tesla
numbers and he also wants to know if we have any sue servers do you have any sue servers i do not
hmm all right i didn't think so not surprising really uh i have uh one in production and i have
one on a on a raspberry pi cm4 so not a lot but i have some for 500 sats gin for matique writes in
hi chris i just stumbled upon a french blog discussing about podcasting 2.0 the article
is translated to english and here's what they did as podcast lovers for over two decades we have
founded ad auras a u r e s a ruse a ruse yeah my french pronunciation is uh poo poo shall we say
anyway they're aiming to build a fair and sustainable ecosystem for everyone in the
podcasting industry they've developed castopod a free and open source solution
for hosting your podcasts in order to facilitate access to podcasting 2.0 for everybody yeah
castapods actually pretty neat there's a there's another one out there too that's being created
and they're supporting all of the podcasting 2.0 spec out of the gate which means things like the
alternative enclosure tag transcripts uh clips and um things like that and the idea is is that
you could just kind of use their out of the box solution i mean if you're looking to start a
podcast right now and you want something that's kind of like an all-in-one back end package like
a hosted fireside that's what castapod is and i've looked at it because it is enticing it'll
support clips it'll generate video clips and it supports the podcasting 2.0 namespace stuff for
that it does the value for value stuff so you can do boosts and it supports the transcript stuff
there's a lot in that spec and they're one of the like premiere places that are supporting it so
that's pretty cool i haven't tried it myself because we're already you know we already have
a whole system built out but if i were starting today and i didn't have anything i'd be pretty
tempted to try castapod i have to say toxic safety 89 wrote in two days ago with 3333 sats i feel
like that's a lucky number all threes that's got to be a lucky number thing i swear to god
my alexa and siri are getting worse and worse at understanding me i love the home pods like you
chris but it's a 50 50 hit rate these days do you guys have these problems is there anything better
out there well i can't tell you the number of times i have to put on a very bad american accent
in order to make my google home understand me oh really it is have you tried changing the voice to
the british voice i have in fact when brent was here we had a good giggle because we were doing
some youtube searches and i searched for something like tool danny carey drumming videos or something
and it came up with something completely random and i was like cool drumming danny carey videos
and it just worked first time so that's your american that's so great yeah it is say what
you will but that's my american accent what of it bro i have to be honest i feel like the echo the
amazon devices their hit rate for me remains the same but their annoyance rate has skyrocketed so
i don't have any echoes in the rv where i'm at now and i don't have any anywhere else except for in
one spot and that is in the studio proper like the main studio the jb one studio where i'm
live streaming anyways i don't care if there's an echo in there and that thing is inserting ads and
by the ways and did you knows and would you like all the time now it's so frustrating that i've
stopped using it by the way did you know you can ask for groceries in nine different languages
yeah okay great cool it's not what i asked for and then on the flip side with the home pods
which i too you know i like them i like them like you toxic but the thing is i swear to god
they're getting stupider i agree with you like i i don't know what it is but the hit rate is so
bad these days that i stop i enunciate really clearly i speak directly at it and it used to
be one when i i swear when i got the home pods and set them up i could just bark into the air
no matter what noise was going on and they would hear me and it was such a neat parlor trick i
would show it to people like we could have it super loud in here and i would say something
quietly to the home pod and it would still hear me and everybody was so impressed and now i would
never dare doing that i i swear it's gotten worse so um i'm in the same boat as you toxic if anybody
out there is using another system besides one of these commercial systems that are doing a cloud
dictation and all of that please let me know how it's working for you and if the hit rates are any
better real time feedback in the discord one of our australian buddies tells me that almond and
ada powered by home assistant are some good alternatives so maybe we should give those a go
but how how accurate like that i hear that i don't know but how are the hit rates compared to
the commercial ones that's what is it is it a downgrade because when you're the dad and you've
deployed all this stuff and then your family goes to use it and it fails them you always i take it
personally every time i'm embarrassed for the home pods when they fail to recognize what the wife is
asking for it's embarrassing send us a boost and let us know if you'd like to send us a boost
get a new podcast app a new podcast apps.com good news sats are on sale especially today they're on
sale as uh as we record and you know the great thing is you can buy them cheaper and they're
still the same great sets what is bitcoin these days what's it doing i mean not that i'm watching
but twenty eight thousand nine hundred and fourteen dollars not that i'm watching oh yeah i know but
like i say you get really get more sats now for your money i don't care it's still you send it
you can still send us the same three thousand sats it's just you got them for cheaper uh and you can
loan them up in a new podcast app in a few years time we'll be laughing huh yeah really new podcast
apps.com go grab one also if you want a web one if you want a web player that syncs to a mobile
device i think i was podverse i was just trying this out this is an interesting one so their whole
thing with podverse is a full featured web client that syncs to a mobile device client so that and
it also supports it doesn't do boosts but it supports all the other podcasting 2.0 features
which is pretty great been playing around with audiobook shelf whilst you've been talking a
little bit there and uh it's it's the way to go you can specify a specific date like in the self
hosted back catalog i wanted to download everything from may last year and just in the time we've been
talking there which is what five or ten minutes it's gone and downloaded all those episodes in
that time it doesn't do them all it only does the ones i asked for which is oh chef's kiss that's
nice all right boy another one of these episodes where i've got way too much stuff to do afterwards
now don't forget we're still uh working with cloudfree.shop over there the coupon code
self-hosted still gets you a dollar off per plug and also mylocalbytes.com if you're in uh if you're
in europe or the uk same deal over there one pound off one of those plugs too coupon code
self-hosted yay go help our friends out they're selling you stuff that's ready to work it's been
a while since we mentioned them but they're still going strong and uh particularly mylocalbytes all
of the affiliate revenues we get off that it's very very small amount a few cents honestly per
plug we're going to donate all of that to some open source projects upstream coming up soon
we'll do an announcement about that soon but if you want to support open source as well as the show
head on over to mylocalbytes.com yep and cloudfree.shop oh i think cloudfree might be
listening he's just written in the discord how fun is that hey he's just launched an eu shop as
well he tells us which is exciting oh really well there you go what's the name of it eu.cloudfree.shop
that makes sense if you can believe that that's creative naming right there well thank you to
our members our sres you guys are the engineers that keep us going you give us the runway to work
with the sponsors that we want to work with not just all of the ones that ask so we appreciate
that you could become a member and as a thank you you get an ad free version of the show
and you get a bonus post show self-hosted.show slash s re this week we're going to be talking
about my brand new soldering iron the pine sill pine sill i think that's what it's called i was
going to say pine sill 64 i'm not sure if it's the 64 or not but version pine sill version one
yeah it's a pine sill soldering iron so if you want to hear more about that subscribe and i'll
be in the post show today and we always are making our best efforts to do this show live
every other wednesday we did it live on may 18th so you can do the math on that but we also are
listing it at jupiterbroadcasting.com calendar where you'll get it converted to your local time
come hang out with us we're also chatting with the discord as we do the show now don't forget
if you want to let me know ideas about the london meetup august 6th is the provisional date go to
self-hosted.show slash contact and if you enjoy an episode of this show share it with a friend
word of mouth is the best way to share a podcast with someone it really is now thanks for listening
everybody that was self-hosted.show slash 71