We're doing the show from Cheyenne Wyoming and Brent is here in Lady Dupes with me Alex. Hello Brent
Hello guys, I brought him with you know, he's been with us the whole trip Alex. We're in for such a treat tonight
I have two of my best friends in the whole world
My one of my favorite beverages and a self-hosted podcast. This is this is gonna be a perfect episode
Wow, wait a minute though. What's the favorite beverage? I feel like you gotta gotta give us more information
Well, this particular one is non-alcoholic
It's an import. Okay, so I've gone to a lot a lot of effort for this particular beverage
Import from Canada or somewhere further the British people in the audience are gonna laugh their faces off in a minute
It's it's Robinson's squash
You know what that is? No, I gotta look it up. Tell me about it. Okay, so it's just flavored water
Essentially, it's a bit of it's a bit of sugar
with
Apple and blackcurrant flavoring in it and every six months or so
Someone in my family sends me a care package with a few British treats in so some you know
British style Kit Kats because the Kit Kats you have over here a garbage. Mm-hmm. And then also a few of these Robinson's squashed
The this the word squash with an apostrophe and D after the end these little you know
Water flavoring packets you can get and I end up with a you know, the taste of home
It's it's just a little treat. I have every now and again that does sound kind of nice
We have we have we have some some things just like that on board today
Actually, the kids love to drink it while we're going down the road. We've been off grid and to killing it
In fact in some ways, I think I've been not in some ways in every single way. I've enjoyed our off-grid
Random spots that we've stayed along the way more than any of the campgrounds
Some have been forced and some have been planned, but they've all been good
you know there was there was a time where we had to pull over for a bit and
You know, the power system was great. Although we were a little we were a little short on water
The mobile internet system has been killing it though. It's been fantastic
We've had connectivity the entire time everywhere. We've went sometimes better or worse connectivity like here in Cheyenne, Wyoming. We have kind of
Moderate connectivity right now
but even with moderate connectivity you can still use a cloud guru and become a
A cloud guru go over to club guru comm the leader and learning for cloud and Linux and other modern tech skills hundreds of courses
Thousands of hands-on labs get certified get hired get learning at a cloud guru comm
So Alex with our special guest in studio as it were do you have any questions for our our exclusive?
Access to Brent. I mean, when's the last time we've had a chance to sit down and ask him a question
it's been too long for those of you that don't know Brent is the host of
Brunch with Brent which you can find over extras dot show
Now I wanted to ask you Brent you spent a few days now in lady dupes with Chris and the fam
He often goes on about
Accessibility of the home assistant interface and how he's got these
Tablets mounted to the wall and how easy it is to use and blah blah blah
I was curious as to how you found using someone else's automation system
Well, as you know, I don't have an automation system at home
So I'm pretty fresh when it comes to experiencing these things
However, I will say my experience on day one started actually in the studio
He very kindly set up the exact same tablet system in the studio as he did here in lady dupes
So night one I slept over there and had to figure it out. He gave me a 37 second tour
But actually that was enough. It had a familiar enough
On off switch interface with very kind labels that were identical to the voice commands
and so I was able to play a little bit actually I could sort of
Run over there and go see the tablet and what things were named and then use some of the voice commands
And I guess learn myself
The other thing I did is I got one of those wall mount socket mounts for the HomePod mini
So it's plugged in and mounted right there at the wall socket. And so it's in that guest room
So once you learn the names, you can just ask the HomePod to turn things on and off
I do remember when my mother-in-law came to stay once a couple of years ago now
I was just in the throes of doing home assistant, you know, the first few months
Everything I could possibly put behind automation was behind automation including, you know, the light switches the light switches no longer worked and
I just remember hearing through the wall. Hey Google turn off the sodding lights. Yeah
Yeah, you got it the memorizing the names is the hardest part I mean
My wife's been using the automation system for a couple of years now
She still has some troubles with the verbal syntax and in part that's because I've tried all the different
Assistant tubes and so they sometimes have various different syntaxes, but the real systems in the RV
That's like the bigger system. Mm-hmm. I feel like that system in the studio was really the training. It was like
step one
To the system in the RV. And so what was nice about that was that getting here into the RV?
It was like, oh, yeah, you know this tablet thing
It just has a heck of a lot more on the screen, but the same kind of systems apply
and so what I appreciate I think the most about that interface is its simplicity and
It's categorization. So Chris has the systems categorized by either living space or
what their use is and
So the first few nights I would walk all the way back there just to turn the lights on but these days
Feels a lot easier now, you know the names and they can just bark it into the air
Are you tempted at all to retrofit the cabin that you live in with with any of this stuff?
That's a very good question. So that hadn't quite hit me yet
But now I'm beginning to realize all of the advantages
So for instance Chris has shown me, you know, he gave me the geek tour and he's given other people the geek tour
So I've been on it a few times and there are sensors in various bays on the RV
That give temperature and in my home
I'm got these thermometers all over the place
But I got to actually, you know go up the stairs into my loft to go check out if the fire is too hot up
There and like an animal
So, yeah, I know I could see now
The two systems in juxtaposition where I could really gain some
Some currency there because we've talked a lot about how you in particular
can dip your toes into more self-hosting stuff and I feel like you're
Curious and you want to do this stuff, but you just don't quite know how to break down that first barrier and kind of
Get going. I think if I had to pick the very first barrier that's keeping me from it the most it would be the server side
It would be getting in there and creating a server that's stable enough and safe enough that I feel like
I'm not getting myself in more trouble than not. Mm-hmm
This is where I think the home assistant blue or something like it eventually is gonna be it's such an easy
on-ramp for a guy like you because you know about home assistant now you've you've seen my home assistant setup and
The fact that there is a an official home assistant device that runs the whole stack
That's that's pretty compelling
I don't know if the price points right yet or you know if it's quite the right device yet
But I could definitely see that being a good starting spot though, you know
I think that maybe you guys are on to something I have
At least two very good mentors who can walk me through some of the glitches if any but it sounds also like these days
You know, I've been hearing you guys talk about this for years, but it sounds like these days things are pretty solid
So I feel like for me, maybe then that was a nice time to jump in
Yeah, and you could always start small
Um, you'd be surprised to how many things homo system might just pick up on a LAN automatically and suggest integrations for and it's never
Been a better time to take local stuff. Seriously
I mean
I don't know if you saw the Apple news that broke over the last week or two about their expanded protections for children
In other words, they're going to scan all of your pictures for kiddie porn, right?
and it always starts this way and I I really hate this kind of
Insidious way that big companies will roll out
Overreaching egregious things like this in the name of you know, child porn because who could possibly disagree with child porn
The other thing about those integrations. It feels to me like it is
Affecting many people to solve the problems of few. Absolutely. No wonder about that
Yeah, I mean so as Apple put it our goal is to create technology that empowers people and enriches their lives
We want to help protect children from predators and those who use communication tools to recruit and exploit them and limit the spread of
CSAM, you know child sexual abuse material
Obviously, that's a laudable goal and we can't legitimately sit here and say that that is not a laudable goal
However, the way in which they're doing it. I have significant issues with so
What they're doing is they're taking every photo that you have on your iPhone or iPad that is linked to an iCloud account and
Scanning it on your local device and this entire announcement has been extremely complicated and confusing because they've really announced three things
They've announced iMessage image detection for child accounts in a family plan. They've announced iCloud
Photo library scanning on your local device
In other words, if you have iCloud photo library turned on locally on your device
It will scan and check for matches in the CSAM database. And then the third thing they've announced is they're also going to start censoring
Results in Siri search. So if you search for something like child porn and it matches that stuff series going to block that and this is all happening
Using that new neural processing area in the Apple processors that they love to break so much
It's accelerating this and I find this to be an extremely extremely slippery slope
And I know that the other side of the argument is is that child harm is real
So one interesting stat you've probably seen this floating around is Apple reports a couple of hundred incidents of child porn and iMessage a year
A couple hundred a year and Facebook Messenger because they are already using the CSAM scanner reports 20 million
It's a huge difference and you've got to figure people that are using Facebook are probably on iPhones or Android devices
So there's probably a lot of iPhone users if 20 million Facebook messaging flags have happened
Whatever that is whatever that metric is there's a good chance that they were using iPhones and that that stuff's on their phone
Now the thing is is it's not going to matter if they don't turn on iPhoto library
And if you are a big child porn collector I wouldn't imagine you're probably using iCloud's photo library feature
You probably wouldn't be auto uploading your child porn to their server right
I think you might be surprised actually I bet you there's a lot of people out there
Using technology just with for the bare minimum just to get what they need done and not understanding like we do the underlying principles
And yeah I guess and I suppose it's so easy to turn that stuff on you turn on iCloud when you get your phone
You don't realize every picture you're taking I suppose especially if you're taking the pictures with the phone
But an important thing to realize is the CSAM detection is only looking for images that are in the database
It's not doing like some sort of flesh recognition algorithm and detecting 80 percent nakedness on a 10 year old like it's not doing that
It is looking at a hash that has been provided by CSAM which they then only look for those images
And so it doesn't really feel that effective if you combine the fact that people can just turn off iCloud photo library
And it's only looking for the CSAM photos that exist today
It seems like a limited reach, limited return for a massive increase in surveillance on people's devices
And Alex I think it sounds like it bothers you that it's actually happening on device
Like you'd almost be more comfortable if it was happening up in the cloud it sounds like
I think I would and for me this feels like a capitulation to wider pressures that are at play
If you're Apple you probably get a lot of requests from different governments, different organizations
To put back doors into your end-to-end encryption algorithms
And for me I think this is their way of saying no we're not going to do that
But what we are going to do is say we have some protections in place for the stuff that you say is actually bad
As opposed to terrorists or whatever the next excuse is going to be
Right, you say you need a backdoor for child porn so we are going to build a system that automatically detects it
And then your excuse for a backdoor goes away, it's nullified
And then you have to move on to the next one
But what bothers me most is there was an ad campaign not that long ago that says
What happens on your iPhone stays on your phone as part of their privacy message
This feels to me like it crosses a line because the scanning is happening on the local device
I don't necessarily opt in quite as obviously as I would if say my stuff was being uploaded to a remote server
Like Facebook is a good example, if I upload something to Facebook in my mind I consider that now public domain
Whatever the privacy controls that Facebook say is there
And it was an implicit action as well, you're choosing to upload to Facebook
It's a manual action you're taking where iCloud photo library is kind of a built-in default
You have to be an iCloud user and you can go in there and turn it on and off
But if you sign up for the whole shebang you're going to get iCloud photo and every photo you take goes in there
Like you said it's just a very, very slippery slope
This year it's child pornography, next year it's terrorists
In 20 years time it's monitoring a social credit score because you said something bad about the president
That's what I worry about
It's also true that these are only the things that they're saying they're scanning for
We don't know about the things they are not saying
Right and if you go by the docs that Apple has released they don't even have input in that CSAM database
They're basically just being handed a list of hashes, here put this in your database
Now I have to say I am actually more comfortable with this being on device
I think because it limits the scale and scope of something when it's on device
A big database update or a feature like this is going to have to come through a software update
Where if it was a cloud service they would just push the update and one day I would be subject to it
So I kind of prefer those aspects and I think it also does help with the privacy aspect
They're not having to unencrypt everything on iCloud to do this
They're doing it on your device that already has access
And then they're pinging Apple with a hey we think we found a match here
Apple then has to have some sort of human interact with that alert
There's various descriptions of what kind of alert they get
And then Apple flags the authorities
And it does seem like they've taken a lot of steps here
They've limited the way they check this, they're looking for specific fingerprints
And then they have this cryptographic signature that they assign to it when they think they have found one
And that's what they send up to Apple
Then it's reviewed by a human
It's happening on your device instead of at cloud
And you can turn it off by turning off iCloud photo library
Is this a reasonable compromise if the platform, let's just say for the sake of argument
Is really being used for child abuse at some massive scale because of the popularity of the platform
Is this a reasonable thing for them to do?
Do they have some responsibility as a platform owner with a billion devices out there
To take some action to try to maybe stop something like this?
Well I look at that 20 million figure that you came out with for Facebook
And divide that by 365 and that's 55,000 flags a day
Who is reviewing 55,000 flags a day?
That's just a crazy amount of signal to noise ratio isn't it?
No kidding
Well and can you imagine when they turn this on
The initial, if this is going to be a thing and it's a real big problem
You would think they're going to have just this massive deluge of alerts
And I just wouldn't want that job
Well I've certainly been on the other end of logging overload or alert overload
You just stop looking after a while
And you know the other reality is several cloud providers
I think many, I don't want to name them off the top of my head
But I know Facebook and Microsoft are already doing this scanning
They're already doing this
Apple was one of sort of the holdouts here
So it really comes back to if you're not comfortable with this
You really have to self host
And you have to advocate self hosting
Because that's the only way you can avoid this kind of content scanning
And if you're worried about the slippery slope of what could be added to this database
Then I think people should really be, I don't know like
When you can, self host
Like invest in self hosting, use it, make an audience for it out there
Absolutely and on that note actually
I thought we might try doing a new challenge in the show
The de-Googlification challenge
I need to come up with a better name than that, don't I?
I don't know, I actually kind of like it
Because I know what you mean immediately
Yeah, so the idea is
I'm not going to be able to just cold turkey drop Google from my life
Because I use Gmail and I have done for 15 years or however long
I've been using it a long time, since the beta anyway
I use Google Photos a lot
I use Google, you know, it's going to be tricky
I'm not going to pull any punches
It's going to be very difficult
But the idea is, one day a week
I am going to go completely cold turkey from Google
That's DuckDuckGo
That's a self hosted note service
A self hosted photo service completely
No Google photo backup etc etc
No Gmail
And no Android
Well, technically I'm going to be using LineageOS
And I think the only thing that I will allow in terms of de-Googlifying
Is the micro Gapps thing through
So for the very first iteration of this
It will probably be in episode 53
This is 51, just because I'm going to Denver next week
To see you two fine gentlemen
And I probably won't have time to do the full research on this
But I have an old OnePlus 6 in a drawer
I'm going to designate that as my de-Googlify device
What do you think?
I mean, I love this idea
I have an Android device, it's a Pixel 3
But I've always struggled with replacing the ROM on there
Because the reason I have it
Is to kind of know what the Google experience is like
But I'd be down for it
I'd give it a try
I'm trying to run through my head
My biggest area where I worry this is going to lead to
Is I use Google Apps for Jupiter broadcasting
For like email and calendar and stuff like that
And I think it's kind of a decent service
I hate to say it
Oh right, calendar
I'd forgotten about calendar, I use that all the time
Even stupid stuff like contacts
You kind of forget that they're just managing my contacts for me on that
Oh gentlemen, you guys are so behind the times
Oh, oh what?
You all in our next cloud over there?
Well, I ran through this very experiment many years ago
I'll have you know
Could you sound any more smug right now?
Well, it's only because you guys are both
Typically far ahead of me in most other realms
He's enjoying this moment too much Alex
He's enjoying this
Well good, I want to hear it
I did a similar challenge
I didn't have anyone else to challenge
I just challenged myself
And I will say it's been actually a few years now
I think two, two and a half, something like that
And next cloud I will say is the underpinning of most of it
Most of the hard stuff which was calendaring and contact syncing
You know when it comes to file syncing
I can figure that out in a whole bunch of different ways
But I will strongly encourage you both to take it pretty seriously
Because on the other side is a fairly liberating feeling
To know that you have control of all of your own deeply personal information
I mean something like contacts
If you think about the people you know
And the sensitive information that's in there
It's a little bit surprising to think about what might happen
If that got into someone else's hands
That would like to mix up your life a little bit
Well you heard it here first ladies and gentlemen
Brent is our de-Googlification referee
Yeah, he'll be our correspondent in the de-Googled universe
Reporting live from an alternative universe
So the thing is, I mean there's so many things to this
There's maps, Google Maps is so priceless
Maps? Oh no
I know
And you could, like if you're on the iPhone
You could use Apple Maps, you could
And in the RV I've got a Garmin
But I tell you what, when I get to a new town
And like legitimately has happened several times on this road trip
I trust Google Maps to have the most up to date information
That's going to be really hard for me to kick
I really haven't thought this through, this is going to be so hard
Well I can give you a few pointers based on what I've gone through
Are you not using Google Maps?
Well, so that's a really good example of I think the concept I'm about to explain
And so I'll start with saying that I use the exact same concept with my dietary choices
So when people say, oh how do you eat Brent?
I say well, I'm like trying my very best to eat as vegan as possible
But that never always works out
So what I would say for you both in de-Googlifying
Is you'll never likely get to 100%
And you need to be okay with that
Because if you can do it even 80, 90, 95% of the time
And only rely on Google in certain instances
Maybe when Maps in Google has the only updated information on this new ring road around your city
And nobody else does or something like that
Then I think you're already making a massive difference in your life
And you shouldn't feel bad about that 5% or whatever it may be
Amen, yeah absolutely
So the idea behind this challenge is to do exactly what we've just done
Pick a service, in this case it was Google as a whole
But let's take Maps as an example
Discuss what would be required to drop that service
Figure out in the intervening two weeks
Some options we could use to try and replace it with
And then in the following episode repeat that cycle
Pick a new service and report back on how the old one went
I mean I kind of feel like if I was going to do it
I could try Maps while I'm on the road
Like this is an opportunity to try alternative mapping and routing
I know there's a few apps I could give a go
Maybe I'll try, this is going to be crazy, but while I'm on the road trip
I'll try for the next two weeks not to use Google Maps
See how that goes
Go for it, yeah
I have a question about your choices of alternatives
Will you try to make them free and open source
Or just try to be an equivalent replacement?
What's the name of the show, Brent?
I'm thinking like for mapping, I don't know what would be even equivalent
I think it's not so much equivalent, it's about just core functionality
There's always MapQuest
Yeah, and I feel like switching to Google Search to look things up
Isn't an alternative that I can accept either
So I'll have to give it some thought
I will have to give it some thought
I'm going to look into a couple of different apps for it
And I'm also going to look into how Apple Maps works
And see what the privacy situation is there
Because that's also already on my device
That's a factor too
It's like you're saying, I love your point about
You could just reduce your footprint at Google
If that's the goal, I think that's something I could get behind
But it doesn't necessarily mean I want to increase my footprint somewhere else
So that's the math I'm going to have to do
I don't mind taking two steps forward and one step back
With this over the next few years
Because that's how long I genuinely think it will take
I just worry, you know, you see people like Apple
Who were genuinely supposed to be the privacy first people
Rolling out stuff like this CSAM protections
And you just think, yeah, it's never going to get any better
It's up to me to take control
It's up to me to host this stuff
And if I take my daughter, for example
I think there's one photograph of her on Facebook
One in the last six months
And I want to keep it as low as that
One every six months
I mean, why does Facebook need all of that data to mine on her?
So it's not her choice
She can't make that choice yet
Because she's six months old, you know
When she's old enough to make that choice for herself
And understand the implications
Then fair enough
But it's not really my place to share her pictures everywhere, is it?
Linode.com slash SSH
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account
And you go there to support this here podcast
You know, this show is made possible
Independent content like this
By our listeners taking advantage of our sponsors' offer
And Linode is one that we can enthusiastically endorse
We use it, we love it
It is powering our live tracker right now
As we go down the road
Linode started in 2003
As one of the very first companies in cloud computing
You know, that was 18 years ago
That's like a whole other internet
And the entire time they've stayed competitive
They've increased the capabilities
The performance
The smooth slickness of the dashboard
Over time, they became their own ISP
They've built out to 11 data centers around the world
Super crazy fast systems
They're always investing in the disk I.O.
In the CPUs
In the network connections
And now, they've got nearly a million customers
And businesses around the globe
But yet, Linode's core focus remains
They're making cloud computing simple
Affordable
And really accessible to all of us
If you're a sys admin that's been doing this for years
Or if you've never set up a server
You can get started at Linode
And I think that focus has really led to the best-in-class
Dashboard
Speed
And more importantly, customer service
When you do need it
They've got the very best in the business
And then, as you start to use Linode
Or something you could use that $100 credit to check out
Is some of their nice features
Like the S3-compatible object storage
Think about all of the software
Like the backup software you have
Or different ways you can mount file systems
That support S3-compatible object storage
Start thinking about what you could do with that
Not even from like a server standpoint
But just like a cloud storage standpoint that you control
You encrypt
And then you upload
Plus, they have cloud firewalls
VLAN support
They support a very powerful DNS manager
Block storage as well
I know some of you still prefer the traditional disk
They've got that
And then they also support things like Terraform and Kubernetes
If that
Kubernetes
I say Kubernetes
If that's the direction you're going
They've got all of that
And you combine that with the fact that you can get $100
And support the self-hosted podcast
Well, what kind of maniac wouldn't go to linode.com
Slash SSH
Get that $100 60-day credit on your new account
And you support the show
And by the way
If you're coming to our Denver meetup next week
Linode will be there
They're going to be giving out prizes
Linode credit
Raspberry pies
I mean, Linode is going all in on our road trip
And they're helping support it
It's great
And we'd love to see you at the meetup
That's linode.com slash SSH
To get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account
And to support the show
Linode.com slash SSH
I know you've got this whole road trip prep ritual
Where you update things a couple of nights before
In critical systems the week before
And all this kind of stuff
What did you upgrade this time?
You are correct
And yes, I did do some updates
This time, you know what I wanted to do
Is I wanted to try out the new Pi-hole
Because I was sniffing around
Pi-hole is one of these things
For those of you who maybe are not familiar
Pi-hole is
It's like a nice DNS manager that can block ads
Maybe block adult material
Has a lot of advantages
It's also a DHCP server
So it can hand out addressing
And then give your systems on your network names
And it gives you a beautiful dashboard
To see everything on there
It just checks all my boxes
And you can run it as a Docker container
Which is what I'm doing on a Raspberry Pi
And I have version 4 on there forever
Since I talked about it on the show
And it's just been running
I don't even mess with it
But I thought
You know what I want to do on this road trip
Because I'm an old man
And I go to bed, as Brent could attest
Really early
Quite
I've had to change my schedule
When do you normally go to bed?
Well, if left to my own devices
I drift deep into the night
But that doesn't serve most people around me
Yeah, we're doing like what?
9, 10 PM at the latest
And so I don't want the kids up much later than that
Browsing the internet
Because they can just get their devices
After dad nods off
And start browsing the web
Or watching YouTube more likely
Let's be honest
And so I wanted to be able to pause their devices
And I had read that you could do that in PyHole
But I logged into my PyHole setup
And I had just done a Docker poll
So it should be totally up to date
And I log in
And it's several versions behind
And I'm looking at my Docker compose file
And I see it's using the latest tag
You know, for the latest image
And I think
Okay, well, why aren't I getting that?
I'm starting to think
Maybe there's some compatibility problem
So I start looking into it
And it turns out
No, I'm using the wrong tag
I was supposed to be using PyHole Master
Arm64 Buster
Because I'm on a Buster-based Debian
And so I set the right tag in there
I get the right image
I pull down version 5
It's like version 5.3 or whatever
Working great
The upgrade goes super smooth
You know, congrats to the PyHole team
For making that easy
And yet I can't pause the devices
Like I read like I should be able to
I grouped up the kids' devices by Mac addresses
I go into their group
I say disable
And I think what I'm just doing is disabling
The PyHole filtering
I don't think I'm disabling their internet access
So I went through this whole rigamarole
Getting this whole system updated
So that way we'd have the latest PyHole
While we're going down the road
Because my theory is
Let's block the ads at the network level
So that way I'm not wasting network bandwidth
You know, because we have limited network bandwidth
Anything I can do
So PyHole, it's working great
But it's not giving me the results I wanted
I wanted to be able to pause the kids' internet
When I go to bed
And I cannot do it
If anybody out there knows a way
To do this with PyHole
Or a relatively straightforward way
To just accomplish this
That doesn't require a specific router software
Or whatever
I'd love to know
Selfhost.show.com
But the upshot is
Upgrading from PyHole 4 to PyHole 5.3.whatever
Super smooth
Totally flawless
Once I got the right tag in there
I have a question
Would you be able to tie that into your
Home Assistant Goodnight Kids recipe?
Oh, I could imagine
I do pull in Home Assistant
There is a PyHole integration
And so I do pull into Home Assistant
The amount of active network clients
And some DNS stats for the day
And I graph them in Home Assistant
On the dashboard
Just for my own fun
And I don't know
But I bet you
There is a way you could totally do that
When I run that script
It also would pause their devices
Right
Have a look in your Telegram
I've just sent you a picture
This is of the AdGuard home interface
And just look at all the different services
That you can toggle on and toggle off
And then also look at the top of this page
Where it says
Select the tags that correspond to a specific client
You know, the tag being child or whatever it is
Doesn't this do what you need?
Ah
Yeah, you know
The only thing that's
The funny thing about it is
It felt like
This approach with AdGuard
Because I actually gave AdGuard
About a 20 minute try
It didn't have like
Just turn off everything
You can go in and block individual services
Like eBay
Hulu
Discord
Amazon
Instagram
Facebook
Telegram
Twitch
YouTube
All which actually would basically do the job
To be honest with you
If I just turned off YouTube
That'd do 90% of it
But I just want
Turn off internet access
Like just
Don't route them
Could you send them to a dud DNS server?
I was wondering about that
You know, it would
It would have to be a pretty short DHCP lease
That somehow switched
Around bedtime
Or something like that
I don't know
Or maybe reboot the Wi-Fi access point
Then every client
Gets a new IP
And at that point
They all get routed to like
Nowhere
I mean, I think the AdGuard solution
May be just simpler
Because if you turn off
It's funny that Cloudflare
Is one of the services in here
I mean, if you turn off Cloudflare
You're going to break
A lot of the internet
Right there
And then if I turn off YouTube
That's going to do pretty much
The rest of it for them
Yeah
So maybe I'll go back to AdGuard
I think I liked the DHCP server
Setup better in PyHole
When I was looking at the two though
One option might just be
Throw them on a different
Wi-Fi network
And switch that off
Yeah, that's true
I could have a kid Wi-Fi network
That's the one, Brent
The simple solutions
Are always the best
Simplicity, gentlemen
I, you know
I do need another Wi-Fi network
In this thing
I've got like six or something
I don't know
It's ridiculous
But yeah, that would probably work
Huh?
If you have a better idea
Let us know at
self-hosted.show slash contact
Now, in the meantime
OnePass would have been busy this week
And released version 8
Yeah, version 8 of what I used to think
Was one of the best password managers
Out there
And they recently released
A Linux desktop version
And they announced that the backend
Was written in Rust
And I thought, hey
Isn't that just fantastic?
But version 8 is switching
To a subscription-only service, Alex
And I think there's kind of
A big loss in functionality with that
Three dollars a month
To manage your passwords
Why do we need a password manager
To be a subscription service?
Not only that
Why do we need a password manager
That can no longer handle local vaults?
My mind is just blowing out right now
When I read this news this week
I just couldn't believe
They would make such a dumb move
And then I saw that they took
A $200 million Series A funding
Late in 2019
And suddenly, all became clear
Oh yeah, okay
That does kind of connect the dots
Doesn't it, unfortunately
I hate to see it that way
But that's...
That's pretty tough not to see
And then when you combine
The changes they're making
So that Linux Electron app
They created with the Rust backend
Surprise!
Turns out to be what they're
Switching everybody to
So now the new Mac version's
Also Electron
And the Mac users are pissed
Because 1Password started as
Kind of an exclusive to the
Apple ecosystem
With native applications
That was what 1Password
Was special for
And so now
They switch over to Electron
The Mac users are just pissed
And I don't mean to laugh
But Linux users
We've had to live with that
For a while already
But it's two whammies at once
An Electron Swaperoo
And the removal of a local vault
That's just...
Well...
That's game over right there
I have 1Password installed
On my machine because
I was playing around with it
To compare it to Bitwarden
And they just disqualified themselves
I remember 1Password
I think was the first
Password manager I used
It must have been...
Because I was still working
At the Apple store at the time
So it was 2013
I want to say
And at the time I thought
It was absolutely crazy
The idea of putting
All my passwords in one place
I thought
How could that
How can this possibly be
More secure
Than me remembering
The password in my head
Yeah
I remember that
I think I thought that way too
Very early on
I was very skeptical
Yeah but over time
I mean my
Approaches matured
And everything now lives
In my Bitwarden
And I do mean everything
Wireguard configs live in there
Bit of a tangent for a second
We had a right old chat this week
About encrypted storage
Vaults on Discord
With a couple of the guys on there
One was talking about
CryptoMator
Which I'll talk about
In a future episode
And another one was talking about
VeraCrypt
And both of those are great fun
But honestly nothing beats
The simplicity of Bitwarden for me
Just you can store files in there
You can do all your
Two factor stuff in there
And all your passwords
I mean if you know
My master password
I've never said it out loud
Good for you
Well done
I mean you deserve to crack
Some of my stuff I guess
Bitwarden should totally
Sponsor this show
Because I am a big
Bitwarden fan now too
They totally won out
In my test
And the fact that there's that
Rust implementation of the server
That's super easy to get up
And running
I'm just all about it
Have you tried Bitwarden?
You know I will admit
I haven't
I got onto password managers
Even earlier than Alex
I will admit
And
Wow he's really taking
This opportunity Alex
You don't have me on the show
That often
So I got to take it all
I love it
So I landed on
A great many years ago
On the key pass databases
And I will say that
They are simpler
And I have to sync them myself
With some other solution
However they've been solid
And my father thinks they're
His favorite application ever
And that says something
So everyone I've shown it to
Has enjoyed their simplicity
And hasn't needed to think about it
Much more than that
So I think Bitwarden
If I was getting into it today
Would be the perfect solution for me
But I don't really have
A reason to change
Keypass and keypass
Was it XC?
I think
Very popular options
But you touched on the reason
Why I won't consider it
And that for me is the fact
That you have to sync it
With Voltwarden
Which is a self hosted
Bitwarden server
And the hosted service
That costs $12 a year
I never have to think about it
And for passwords
When I have way too many devices
In my life
And I have often
Got more than one phone
And a tablet
And a laptop
And a desktop
And a server
And wife's phone
And blah blah blah
I just don't need that extra
Complexity in my life
Systemd has been around
For a while
And a lot of us
Can muddle through
But our friends at a cloud guru
Have a course
In systemd management
For Linux
That will take it
To the next level for you
You can get an idea
Of how the components
Work together
How to configure
This rather important
Piece of system software
It's a course that's designed
To help demystify
The sometimes difficult
And deep topic
Of systemd
So go over to
Acloudguru.com for that
Or we will have a link
In the show notes
For systemd management
For Linux
At acloudguru.com
And you're all familiar
With cloudfree.shop
At this point
You can go over there
And use the coupon code
Self hosted
To get $1 off a smart plug
The version 2 smart plugs
From cloudfree
Have just launched
With built in energy monitoring
But some good news
For the British people
In the audience
One of our other listeners
On the other side of the pond
Has launched
A similar store
In England
This is at
Mylocalbytes.com
And to start with
He has launched
A couple of Zigbee devices
As well as a
Branded smart plug
For Localbytes
Again you can use
The coupon code
Self hosted
To get a pound off that
But if
For all of those of you
That have been asking me
About cloudfree.shop
Shipping to
The UK
Well here's your answer
At mylocalbytes.com
Wow that's so great
Now we have no affiliation
With them other than
They are listeners
But this is incredible
They even have an LED
Light strip thing there
What a cool idea
Mylocalbytes.com
And I love that
There's some Zigbee tech
In there
I've been thinking
More and more
I think I'm going to
Quit getting wifi devices
I'm going to go
Z-Wave and Zigbee
On stuff
We got an email
In about
Two weeks ago
We got an email
In about
My usage
Of wall panel
The linux trucker writes
I was listening to
Your last episode
And heard you talking
About wall panel
Although it is
Great software
I feel there is
A better option
The fully kiosk browser
Does everything
That wall panel does
Including motion detection
Auto launch
And will even function
With the home button
On android
However
For use with home assistant
It takes it
A step further
Fully kiosk
Will connect to
MQTT
And send battery
Temperature and some of
The other information
To the home assistant
I'm using this
In combination with
A smart outlet
To cycle the battery
In hopes it will
Last a little bit longer
Man, I've been talking
About doing that
That's awesome
Linux trucker goes on
To say
It also gives you
One more device
You can use
For automations
And tinkering
In home assistant
This is a very small
Five dollar fee
To unlock all
Of the features
And I don't mind
Supporting great software
That I use every day
Give it a look
Before you settle
For wall panel
The linux trucker
Is saying
Hi Chris and Alex
I recently bought
My first apartment
And construction
Will take about
Two years
My wife is going to
Focus on the kitchen
The living room
And the bathroom
Whilst what I'm thinking about
Are the tech parts
Of the project
Of course
I have many things
I'm wondering about
And I'm not entirely sure
What to prioritize
I mean
Laying cables
And other electrical work
Is probably going to be
One of the more important things
But I'm already wondering
For example
Whether POE
Is the right tech
Or not
A totally different topic
Is IOT
And home appliances
You can buy
Washing machines
And ovens
And all sorts of things
With wifi built in
These days
But some of this stuff
Is going to be in a basement
Where wifi
Might not be
The best choice
I am hoping
That there is some compromise
For all this
Can you help me?
This is an opportunity
Because he is so early
In the stage
Of planning
He can run
Cat 7
He could run
Fiber if he wanted to
I mean
He could really go
All out
And he could also run
Ethernet
To wifi
Access points
This is how you get
Your wifi
Rock solid
By the way
Is you have multiple
Wifi access points
That have ethernet
Run to them
And that stuff
Just works like
Nearly like
Ethernet
I won't say
Like ethernet
Because nothing works
But it's pretty close
And if you're in this
Man if you're in this
Stage right now
Anonymous
You are
You are in such
A great position
Two years before
Your house was even
Finished building
Like you
What a great
So many choices
But what a great
Position to be in
Well it's the ultimate
Conclusion of being
A self-hoster
Isn't it?
Is to be a self-builder
So
I think in my life plan
At some point
It might be
Ten years away
But I really want
To build my own house
And do all of this stuff
And make all these decisions
And to that point
Another one of our
Listeners
Is
Embarking on a similar
Journey himself
Up in Vermont
My name is Matt
And they have a YouTube channel
Called Adventurous Way
There'll be a link to it
In the show notes
They've literally only
Just closed on the
40 acre plot of land
Up in Vermont
And currently Chris
They live in an RV
So you know
There's a lot of stuff
A lot of synergy
Between his approach
To stuff and yours
Right now
So I'm really curious
To see what they're doing
I've just watched
A video tonight
Where they're cutting back
All the trees
On the land for example
So they're doing it
All themselves
Pretty much
Right from the very beginning
And man does that
Give me some excitement
I think
In the future
I've just
You've got to do it
I've just got to do it
I feel the same way
I feel exactly the same way
So I'm definitely going to
Check out their channel
I could see parking
Lady Dupes on some land
And building from there
I think that'd be the ultimate
Final destination
For Lady Dupes
If I could
It'd be some piece of land
That we park her on
I can imagine a JB
Commune right now
Brent
In his little
House in the corner
Totally
Yes
Yep
Yeah
You'd be there
It'd be great
Yeah man
You know I've retrofitted
Many homes in the last few decades
With the technologies of the day
And I think
Part of my advice would be
To look at the cost
Of laying a bunch of cable
Versus what you think the future
Might bring in the next
Even five years
Because
Some of the homes that
I've lived in
That have been retrofitted with
Ethernet to every room
Actually
My parents home right now
We didn't do this
Because there's
Ethernet run to every toilet
You know
Just in case you need
The best
Speeds possible
I don't know why
But I love that idea actually
I see nothing wrong with that
That seems reasonable
But it turns out
They never get used
And nothing ever gets plugged in
Because the wifi
Even in the basement
Is good enough for
Most of the activities
That ever happen in that home
So I would use some imagination
And think about where
That's going to be
In the next
Five to ten years
And think about
If the cost is worth it
I know there are people
Tapping in their keyboards
Furiously right now
Run conduit
And I think that's probably
The best future proof
Thing you can do
Is to make sure
There's plenty of conduit
So you can upgrade
The cables later
Without having to
Fish through walls
Jonas writes in
Along the same line
He says
I know you guys talk
About networking a lot
We're renovating our house
We ran Cat 7 cables
Almost to every room
But we've discovered
To Brent's point
We're still using
Wifi a ton
And so now I'm looking
At what are the right
APs and switches
To use here
I heard you guys
Mention recently
That you don't think
You'd recommend
Unified gear anymore
So now I'm kind of stuck
Do I go with cheap stuff?
Do I do unmanaged?
Do I do managed switches?
You know I'm looking
For stuff in the range
Of maybe a thousand dollars
Somewhere in there
Slightly professional gear
But not too crazy
And he wants to know
If we have any recommendations
This is a good point
Like what do you do
If you want really
Great Wifi right now?
I mean the reality
Of the situation is
I bought the Unifi access point
I'm looking at right now
From my desk in 2015
And it has just done the job
Extremely well since then
Despite all of Unifi's wackiness
With their policies
Over the last year or two
The hardware and the performance
Of what I put in
Has just been great
I can't really fault
The actual device
So with regards to
Would I purchase it again?
I'm already in the Unifi ecosystem
The pragmatist in me is going
Yes I probably would
If I needed a third access point
In this house for example
Just to make sure it all meshed
And talked together properly
I'd probably just buy another one
I know that TP-Link
Makes some good devices
And Jim Salters written about those
On Ars Technica a little bit
There are lots of people over
At smallnetbuilder.com
That regularly review this stuff
So if you're looking at
What the best mesh system is
Or the best Ethernet backhaul system is
That's where I'd go for all that advice
Rather than listening to what I know
Now I won't pretend to be an expert
But I do know some people who are
And I will notably say
My older brother Chris
He very, very, very strongly recommends
The microtik hardware and software
In this area
He's explored a bunch of it
And he has been very happy
Over many years
With just how powerful their software is
But also how it can be simple
If you need it to be
And the software that's available
Is their professional software
That gets sent to all of their devices
So even if you buy their low-end hardware
You get the same software
So I would recommend looking into that
I can't make any specific recommendations
But when I asked him
That's what he told me
So passing that along
This is an area I'd love to hear
What people are using
What are you actually using out there
And how has it worked for you
Because I'm also trying to find something else
And there's so many mesh options out there
But so, I think all of them
If I'm not mistaken
Require cloud connectivity
Or some sort of cloud account
And I just don't want any of that
Unifi, I feel like I've already made
That concession once before
For the stuff we have in the studio
So okay, that's already a concession I've made
But I'd love some tips
And if you're sticking with Unifi
I'd love to know why too
Selfhosted.show.com
Did you see that the Grand Tour
Aired an episode this week in Scotland?
We watched it on the road actually
As a family, we all sat down and watched it
And had a great time
It was more of like a classic episode
I felt, Alex
Did you get that sense?
Yeah, for my stag do actually
A buddy of mine and my dad
We rented three cars
And we did our own mini top gear road trip
From Edinburgh actually
We started in Edinburgh and finished in Edinburgh
But in the intervening three or four days
We went up to Inverness
Drove down the side of Loch Ness
Out to the Isle of Skye
And then back through the Trossachs
Oh man, I tell you what
Scotland has some of the best driving roads
Not cliche
In the world
It was just a phenomenal trip
And to watch that episode
Feeling as homesick as I am
At the moment
You know
Ah, dude
It was just so perfectly timed
Yeah, they really made it beautiful too
Yeah, those had to be some of the same roads, right?
Some of them were, yeah
And I tell you what brought me onto this topic
Was
I've been looking at mechanical keyboards lately
And I came across a podcast
Named Top Clack
You know, like Top Gear
I just thought that was fun
TopClack.com if you're a mech keyboard enthusiast
Oh my goodness
There is a podcast
Are you kidding me?
Of course there is
Why am I surprised at all?
Why am I surprised by that?
I shouldn't be surprised by that
Almost everyone we've met on this trip
Has had a podcast
That's true actually
I was listening to your podcasting adventures
About concrete in Idaho, so
Yeah
We did a couple of micro meetups
And we had a group of five at one of them
And literally every single person there had a podcast
Then we did the Salt Lake City meetup
And there was a handful of people there that had a podcast
It's the influence you both had
I don't know
I don't know, but it was pretty crazy
And Brent joined you for episode 418 of Linux Unplugged
Where there was an absolutely excellent rundown of WireGuard user interfaces
Yeah, and not only the tools to manage WireGuard
But big news for people that want to use WireGuard on Windows
There is an alternative to that user space implementation
There is now a kernel space implementation
And the performance difference is huge
So Jim Salter from Ars Technica and Two and a Half Admins
Joined us to talk about that on Unplugged 418
At linuxunplugged.com
That's huge with a Y at the beginning by the way
Yeah, that's going to be a big deal for people that want to have
Interconnected Windows and Linux machines
Or just Windows to Windows machines
And to be able to use WireGuard too
You feel like this is probably going to take WireGuard up to the next level
In the enterprise
And you're going to see adoption now just across the board
Once they get this code done
It's early days, it's still experimental
And Jim goes through all the details
Also, we want to say a special thank you to our members
Who support this show
And to our reliability engineers who sign up at selfhosted.show.sre
You are very special to us, in my heart
Remember that? You are in my heart right now
And I say thank you because as we're out here meeting people
And we're doing a road trip like this
And all of it, oh and we're also
This is the other big part, is we're almost at a year now
Of being independent again
And all of this stuff about how critical our members have been
And all of that has just been on my mind
So thank you very much and if you'd like to support the show
selfhosted.show.sre
And don't forget if you're an SRE to listen to the post show
There's going to be an exclusive discount code in there
For the merch that we launched last episode
The Chris and the Badger t-shirts are flying off the shelves
And just to make sure that everybody that wants one gets one
We're going to keep that up for another couple of weeks
And then we're going to retire it
And then after that it might make some future
Special edition appearances, who knows
But if you want one, make sure you go over there
And pick one up now
Because who knows when it will ever come back
So we're going to extend that discount code
For two more weeks
And come say hi to Chris, Brent and myself
In Denver at the meetup
Go to meetup.com
Slash Jupiter Broadcasting
And I've mentioned a couple of times, it matters a lot
Your feedback, selfhosted.show slash contact
That's the place to get in touch with us
You can follow me on Twitter
I'm at Chris LAS
And I'm there at ironicbadger
And this here show is there at selfhosted.show
And I want to extend a big thanks
To everybody for listening
To selfhosted.show slash 51