Think we have something like 70 people signed up for the East Coast meetup so far
69 baby nice
You know, it's gonna go up from there too because it always kind of goes up a few ticks in the last day
Now the question that I I have is this barbecue place gonna have enough meat
Well, I've been emailing them back and forth and it's a little bit complicated
Like we don't want to have to charge everybody like tickets and admission and that kind of thing
but you know a barbecue restaurant they make a certain amount of food in the morning and
Well the night before and once it's gone, it's gone. So yeah
There are a couple of things that we can do to help kind of mitigate that you can pre-order on the website
so, you know when you turn up to the spot you can walk into the restaurant and they'll sort of
Carve your food while while you wait in there without waiting in the normal line
The other thing that we were thinking about doing but we're not sure of the logistics and how it would work is giving them numbers
Before hand so that we can actually make sure there's enough meat for everybody. Well, the way that would work is if people sign up
On the meetup page. Yeah, so it is critical if you are coming, please make sure you sign up on the meetup page
So we have a really accurate idea of numbers and equally if you aren't able to make it, please unsubscribe
Please saying you know, you're not coming anymore. That's really important, too. I love that. We're running into this problem
And this is just a great problem to have we are thrilled to have this problem and we want it to be an even bigger
Problem, so if you can come on come hang out with us on April 9th in Raleigh, North Carolina
We have all the details of meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting and don't worry
We're gonna bring some snacks too. So and they're not gonna be meat snacks. So if you're not a meat eater
There will be something for you. You know, I think we're bringing a Brent with us
So we've at least got to take care of him, right? Right? He'll be our vegan advocate
You know, he always stands up for the non meat eaters because he's about the only one in our crowd
I
Was browsing the old hacker news the other day and I came across a docker.com blog post
About a speed boost achievement for docker desktop in 4.6. This is fascinating story Alex
Yeah, I think so too and the performance of docker desktop particularly on the m1
silicon Apple silicon max has been
Bad enough that I have literally stopped using docker on my Mac
And I just SSH into a server and use it there and do all my builds on a remote server
Yeah. Oh
Okay, so, you know, we're gonna talk today about how I'm looking at ditching containers
so we thought we should probably have a little bit of container good news and
This is a neat little happenstance. There was a discovery by the Asahi Linux team Hector Martin
Who's trying to port Linux to the m1?
Discovered that Apple's MV me drivers are really really great
except for a particular function called the f-sync and
Depending on how this is called and when it's called. It's
Horribly slow on Mac OS so Hector discovered that
Talked about it publicly. They've submitted code upstream the Linux kernel to solve it on on Linux
But it isn't necessarily solved on the Mac. And so a docker user noticed this
We'll have a link to the github issue and said hey, by the way, this might help performance
I've done some testing here and I've noticed that if you use the same fix that Hector Martin found and you apply it
You're gonna get this kind of expected performance increase and you know
Just one of these great examples of community helping, you know
Really improving a product like this the docker team took a look at the suggestion and said yeah, you're right
Let's implement it and and now they're saying some operations are like 98% faster
Well, they were pretty slow beforehand. So I mean
They had plenty of headspace to improve that. Yeah. Yeah, it's interesting
And you know as we record the Asahi Linux team just released. I think it was you know a few days ago their first alpha
right and
I'm gonna give it a go this Sunday by the time people are hearing this it'll be just like
probably
The weekend this episode came out, but we tried it at first and there's a there's like some
File-system typical problems you'll fall into that just sort of trap you it's like I don't know if you ever played that game pitfall
You know, yeah, you're running along and also you just fall into a pit
That's what it's like right now trying to get Linux on the m1
but if you solve file system problems
Or you don't have any file system problems and you're trying it on an m1 Mac like like an air or a mini
it seems to be pretty straightforward and
Early benchmarks are showing
Pretty good performance as long as you're not hitting that GPU
Yeah, you know what's interesting is Jeff Gehling released a video this week talking about his experiences with the new Mac Studio and
in that video he did some power comparisons between a recent Ryzen system that he built a Linux gaming PC
compared to the Mac Studio and I
Couldn't quite believe what I was seeing but then at the same time having used the m1 MacBook Air and my m1
Max MacBook Pro god, that's such a stupid name. I
Just called the MacBook max
Okay. Yeah, well, it's still a stupid name. But yeah, who thought max Mac was a good one
Anyway, I know, you know, there's just nobody to say no anymore. Is there anyway, that's a bit of a segue bit of a tangent
bit of a tangent
Yeah, the power draw was a lot better though. You're right the like the wasn't the Ryzen something in the 40 watt neighborhood?
That's right. Yeah. Yeah, the Ryzen was about 38 40 watt something like that and the Mac Studio idle was 6 watts
It's the same as a Raspberry Pi. Yeah, and in the context of Docker desktop, too
you really got a you got to figure the majority of the use case is for development testing and
So this f-sync change doesn't really impact things much other than you know improves performance
I think I'm not sure Alex
But I think there's an argument to be made that it might be slightly less safe the way the way they've changed this operation
but it kind of feels like
You know again for a development Docker setup
It doesn't it doesn't really matter if it's slightly less safe because you're not running your production
Server on this thing. Yeah, it's a similar type of operation to when you make a bunch of rights to a USB Drive, right?
After you've written some data
You need to sync it and make sure that those rights have occurred and the file system tables all been updated that kind of thing
So as it turns out Mac OS actually cheats as you said Chris on Linux f-sync will both flush rights to the drive and ask
It to flush its right cache to stable storage
but on Mac OS f-sync only flushes rights to the drive itself instead they provide a
f-full sync operation to do what f-sync does on Linux
Aha, so you got f-sync and you got f-sync full sync
Now on the laptops I can see why they would do this, right?
Because essentially the laptop has a built-in UPS if you yank the power cord on a MacBook
It's gonna keep on trucking right but on a Mac studio same on the iPhone right same on iPhone
Yeah, absolutely, but on a Mac studio or some kind of other desktop
Once you pull the power cord your toast
So this leads me to wonder what would happen to you know data integrity on a desktop Mac that doesn't have a built-in battery
Yeah, you got to figure Apple must have done the math
But there is that sort of cynical voice in the back of my head that goes well, you know
They may have just designed this for mobile devices because that's their primary device now
And you know when they sell max the the number one Mac they sell are the laptops
So they're probably designing for that, you know
I got that's the voice in the back of my head when I hear that and I think to myself
Maybe APFS needs a few more years before I give it the old production grade for any kind of serious data storage
I mean that said I've experienced zero issues with APFS and the migration was flawless and I
Really give them credit for the migration. I also give them credit for
the really kind of
low-key
But consistent rollout they did over three versions of Mac OS to sort of slice and dice the way that volumes are managed on
APFS like they really executed well on that transition. I'll give them credit there
that that doesn't change the fact though that we haven't seen a lot of
Production server grade edge case uses out there for years, right?
And I don't mean to be the old IT guy in the room
But for me for a file system to really be production grade safe for like server data
I want to see other people
Banging on it for a few years in production in the way I'd be using it
So if it's containers or or whatever it might be, you know, like yeah, they've did they've done
Well, and I think that sets the ground for a pretty good file system that I can trust
But it's still like for it to actually be considered safe in my brain
I got to see people using it the way I'm using it and I got to see that working for a while
Yeah, so with all that in mind, okay. I really hope that Asahi Linux
Works well in a couple of years time and you know with the market is flooded with these cheap
M1 Mac minis that are now obsolete from Apple software and we can all run low power
Linux Apple silicon
home service
Leno comm slash SSH go there to get
$100 in 60-day credit on a new account and you go there to support this here show. Yeah, that's right
This here shows made possible by you taking advantage of our sponsor when it comes time for you or someone
You know or someone you're working with to deploy a server go to Linode comm slash SSH
It's what I use for anything that I deploy in the cloud for like the last two and a half years and it's so much
Nicer than those hyperscalers that just want to lock into their crazy complicated platforms
You know Linode started in 2003 and they've just been moving it forward iterating on making it better and better and now
It's like nearly 19 years later
That's wild Linode is old enough to vote. That's crazy
And they've really just iterated on and making something super great and that's why they're willing to give you $100
$100 is like a confidence statement
They're saying we trust that if we let you actually kick the tires with this thing
You're gonna like what you see and it's just such a great way to support the show, too
So it's Linode comm slash SSH go deploy something go try something go see why they are the absolute best
They make cloud computing simple affordable and accessible to all Linode comm slash
SSH
Now this is a mixture public service announcement slash app pick I think we've mentioned paperless on the show before
It's a document management system that helps you transform physical documents into a searchable online
Archive and I've used this to great effect for my wife actually when when we're traveling and stuff back to England
She does a lot of Skype and zoom music teaching lesson
she's a music teacher and
What we actually did was scanned all of her students music into paperless and then using the OCR that's in there
We can actually search for the specific bit of sheet music that we need when she's in England on my server back here
which is just
Super cool. So anyway for the longest time I've been using paperless dash ng
I think it stood for paperless next-gen not entirely sure to be honest
I like to think the next generation. Yeah, like make it so
You got it
A chap called Jonas Winkler actually took over the original paperless project, which itself had been abandoned now in the last few weeks
There's been a new project come along called paperless dash ng X
next generation X
something like that
And essentially what the community have done is the ng fork of the original code has seemed to go unmaintained
There's actually a github issue which we'll link to in the show notes
Where there's a bunch of people talking about how much value they get from the software
And also how much of a shame it is to see it kind of go to waste
But obviously open source being open source, you know
This discussion thread went on for you know, the best part of two three weeks
Before eventually the community just went okay this Jonas guy. He seems to have fallen off the the radar for now for whatever reason
So we're just gonna fork this thing and call it ng X. Yeah, I sure hope he's okay
You know, I hope it's just a case of burnout
and it is good to see something like this you wouldn't this wouldn't happen with a
Commercial service right when a cloud company is shutting down for whatever reason
The products just kind of gone
but when you have something that you can self host that's open source software
there can be a
Escape hatch when the project kind of starts to fade now this first version doesn't seem like it's introduced a ton of new stuff
They drop support for Python 3 7 so they're kind of moving that forward
They've updated a ton of the docs and the scripts and the containers and the branding
They also had to drop support for ansible playbooks, which is definitely a bummer to see that
But they are hoping maybe somebody would want to help them support that it seems like maybe it's just an issue of things getting out
Of date and the dev team not really having the skill set to manage it
So long as they continue to support Docker, you know, they're all they've got my vote
What's interesting though is if if we look through the the issues on their github, there is one
specifically talking around moving the organization in github forward and
You know, so that right now is probably a really good time to get involved in the project
If you're looking to do any kind of open source contributions, you know clearly they're looking to improve the the project
There is an issue in here
1632 which again will be linked in the show notes where they're talking about how you can make your membership official of the project
It's 100% a community project and they will gladly welcome
contributions from anybody member or not
But you know if you're a member of of it
You can start to have a bit more say over where the direction of the project goes and that kind of thing
Interesting. Yeah, I wish them the best right? This is one of those projects that I think is
Probably not mentioned enough
If you look into it, it's such a no-brainer
I'm I'm implementing this in the future probably at the end of summer
I'm gonna I'm definitely putting this into action and it's amazing there. There's just no way I'm gonna do another year without this system
So paperless ngx go check it out. I'm gonna my plan is to have something set up by the end of summer. So that way I
Know me a big talker right now, but that way at the start of 2023
I could just just use paperless from the beginning of the year. We'll see
I'll tell you where it's really useful is tax season
You know, you get all these 1099s and w2 forms all this kind of crap coming in, you know from yeah all over the place
you just take a picture on your smartphone with one of the scan apps and
It then you can share it from there with paperless, you know, like through the share sheet on iOS or a similar thing on Android
that will basically then upload the file into paperless and then it does its
Optical character recognition OCR on those files and from there
All you need to do when it comes to tax time is search
1099 or tax or whatever it is and you'll just find all the forms boom boom boom boom
Even cooler than that though is you can set up a bunch of ingestion rules
So what we did for the sheet music for example
Was we look for certain keywords like bassoon or piano or that kind of thing and add certain tags to each file
So in our case we added sheet music as a tag or any time I get an email from Google with my Google
Fi bill in it. I have that send the email automatically forward it to an address that will put it into a specific folder and
Paperless will scan that folder ingest the file
Automatically tag it and so when I come to expense my cell phone bill through work
All I need to do is I don't need to log into Google Fi and then spectrum and in all these different
Systems, I log into paperless search for my little keyword to bring up my personal
Internet bills boom just download the PDF done. That's so
Great. I love it. I really really love it. I've been struggling with that very thing today
That's what I was working on earlier today
It's just been one bad news after another including the one that I probably heard from
The most from the audience since our last episode and that is that the matter group has announced a delay
For the matter standard. Yes, that is the one announced in
2019 by Amazon Apple Google and Samsung
The idea is to take ZigBee and make something they could all use together that has a few base
things that could all agree on and of course Alex the industry is trying to
Spin this like the Nanoleaf CEO said quote. I think the three-month delay might actually be a good thing
I feel that now that there's more certainty across the industry. We'll see unity at the time of launch
Yeah, it's a good thing because we can't get enough chips right now
So we'll just push it out and then sell the same amount anyway
Right. Sure. Yeah, I mean it's his job to say it's a good thing, right? I gotta say I'm not too surprised
Um, it really is funny though. Cuz like anybody who like doubts matter. It's like they they took this newsman
They just they were on with it. They like they they sent me the link, you know
And you know, I agree my confidence is slipping
But it just it's so obviously needed that I I hope I hope I hope that this delay
Doesn't throw this whole thing off
track, but it has sent me into a bit of a
Death spiral with my whole home set up now Alex. It's just a disaster
Well, I blame you
I mean we had that feedback a couple of episodes ago saying
should I wait for matter or should I get into Z wave or Zigbee or whatever right now and
If I recall the advice was if you need something now buy it now and I think that advice has just been proven
Right, you know if you need a new smart home widget today
buy
What's on the market today and hope for the best?
Yeah, and for me for me it it sends me into this whole spiral of okay. Now I've got a problem
Because I've got a network of you know
30 Z wave devices and
They are integrated throughout the automations and you know everything from temperature display widgets to
Scripts and automations. I have a Z wave device in there. And so the migration to Z wave JS
Which I've tried in the past for me
Went horribly bad. Nothing worked
I essentially had to just retouch everything in home assistant
And you know one of those things where you load your dashboard and like everything's aired out and not working, right?
Oh, yeah. Yeah, that was my situation
And so my thought was screw it. I'm not gonna migrate to Z wave JS
I'm gonna hold out and just move over to matter and I'll just
Low-key replace the devices over a year and call it good and
That plan came crashing down a couple of months ago when I discovered or a month ago when I discovered that the next release the
One that comes out in really probably a few days from the release of this episode
Will totally disable the Z wave integration that I'm using so I'm kind of stuck in time
With home assistant and now that matter is delayed. It's like a whole nother complicating factor and
I've realized that if I'm going to do this Z wave JS migration
That it's gonna end up being so much work
That I might as well take this opportunity to just redo everything, you know, have you reached that point?
We're like, yeah, okay
This one this one job is essentially so much work that just nuke and paving the entire infrastructure
Is only a minor part of the overall work. I
Feel that way every time I think about implementing a VLAN set up in my house like at the moment
I just run a flat network and I think I would be cool if my cameras are on their own VLAN and then all my
IOT stuff was on its own but you think
I'm gonna have to touch every device here and I just can't be bothered
Let's just stick it in a slash 16 and forget about it
Tailscale comm slash self-hosted go there to get a free personal account for up to 20 devices
And of course you support the show and you can sign up for tail scale tail scale comm slash self-hosted
It is the zero config VPN it installs on any device in minutes. You can manage firewall rules
You can work from anywhere. I have really taken things to the next level
I have recently started adding a couple of my VMs to my tail scale
Network now stick with me here for a second now, I can SSH into the VMs
I have running on my machines here in the studio where I'm working on projects from home. It's so
Great. It is so great. Also, I can confirm that it is
Stupid simple to set up tail scale on Nix OS more details on that in a moment
And what I love about tail scale is it supports two-factor authentication
You're single sign-on and underneath all of it. They're using the stuff that just makes WireGuard
So great the noise protocol and they do a mesh network. So that way it's one flat network between all your machines
It's so simple to get started as well
And they really have installers for like every distro even ARM Linux distros all that kind of stuff
You'd be amazed how fast you can build out a WireGuard network
That's mesh peer-to-peer in just a few minutes
I love it. And you know after you get everything signed up. They all have their own IP
And so I've started setting bookmarks. I have a I have a tail scale folder in my bookmark bar and
All of the different web services that I hit that I have a tail scale IP for now
So from and I of course that syncs across all my Chrome instances
So from every machine I can get access to those web apps and it doesn't matter what your machine is
Every machine I can get access to those web apps. It doesn't matter what it could be Dylan at home
It could be something at the studio. It could be something in the RV. It could be something up on Linode
It's just super powerful
So go try it for yourself support the show and use it up to 20 machines for absolutely free by going to tailscale.com
slash
self-hosted
In the dock, I see a very tantalizing little sentence that says I have a new direction for dupes the no
Container theory. I cannot wait to hear your logic on this
I want more control with this next go-around and I'm looking at what my options are
With any kind of setup that I might redo and maybe to kind of help you understand. I should recap what I have now
So right now I have a couple of Raspberry Pi 4s that are running Ubuntu 20
04 right the previous LTS and
Back when I set that up Alex you could still get
a setup script for home assistant where you could install supervised home assistant
On vanilla Ubuntu, which I don't think they actually support anymore
But in my world
This is the ideal setup because I have home assistant running in containers
But a fully supervised setup so I have access to the add-ons. I can get the hack store
All that kind of stuff. I get the backup manager snapshots, etc, etc
But it's on an OS that I manage
That I update because that's how I prefer to do things
That is no longer a viable option and even now it's kind of
fiddly
Home assistant will often say that I am in an unhealthy state and so it won't let me update add-ons or update the system
And I have to reboot and then it's all of a sudden in a healthy state again
And then I can go about updating things
So it's it's already not perfect and I don't want to go the direction of where I was trending
Which is an x86 machine that would be more powerful
Ideally like a laptop that supports quicksync
And then I would put proxmox on that
And I would run home assistant in its own dedicated virtual machine as just an appliance
And I would just swallow the fact that I am running their OS and I don't really want to do that
But you know what?
It's fine. I told myself
But as the asahi linux team started getting linux on the m1 closer to a reality and I started realizing
that a headless mac mini m1
running
Linux could be a viable home server
And maybe I don't want to go this proxmox route. Maybe I want to go a
Linux host that is running these applications
But then I started thinking
What are my two main problems that I would like to solve with this next round?
Like if I besides performance because that's a given
If I were rebuilding my entire home setup and you got to think about this yourself probably sometimes
What would be the next step
And I realized I would love to solve
reproducibility
Because a year or two into this I don't
Really remember how I have it set up. I have it set up
In a way that it's pretty obvious to figure out
And I do have some documentation, although I haven't touched it in about a year
So I don't really have like a game plan to like rebuild this thing should a rabbit
So I don't really have like a game plan to like rebuild this thing should a raspberry pi crap out
I mean I could probably do it in a couple of days
Then the home assistant stuff would take longer
But you know, it's not ideal
And I started thinking about what I could do to solve this problem
And I started thinking about your favorite ansible, of course
Perhaps like, you know, this was an opportunity and my moment in time to learn ansible
I'm sure you think that's probably a great idea
Well, you're not going to hear anything
Bad about some kind of config management from me. No, no, I think ansible is a
laudable goal
So instead I did a hard right and turned from that and and went down the path of nix
And the reason why I got to nix is I wanted god damn it. I wanted I know i'm sorry. I know it's so close
I wanted something that was
reproducible from the metal
So I could essentially just recreate the same exact setup by just dropping in some config files
And building the system
And that's what nix provides
and then as I start to
Use nix and nix os and I tried nix os versus just putting nix on top of a distro
and really it's just a
it's kind of like
It's a matter of how far do you want to be able to control the system, right?
Are you good with setting up a base distro and keeping its package manager going and then putting nix on there and then rebuilding everything?
Or would you like to build everything from the ground up?
user accounts groups permissions
Everything reproduce everything and that's the route I want to go and that's why I went more than just nix the package manager
I went to nix os
and the nix os way of doing things is extremely compelling because you can
with very simple syntax you can say I want containers and then
You build the system and you can test it before you deploy it and it's reproducible
And it's so great, but you build the system and if you tell it I want containers
It it the nix system figures it all out man
It figures out the software dependencies the services that need to be installed you can make declarations in there for firewall stuff
It's a lot like dr. Compose
But for your entire os it's honestly how linux should be
For a lot for basically every use except for the desktop
This is how linux should work for every container for every server for every iot device out there for any system out there
I'm telling you this as somebody who's used linux for probably almost 25 years
This is how linux should have worked forever. Now. Nix has actually been around for a little while
I'm, just finally getting around to try it
And so what I have discovered alex while using nix is if you can use the nix package manager to install stuff and manage stuff
You've essentially documented your entire system with the config file and made it reproducible
so anytime you could like deploy home assistant through the config file or
A sync thing or plex or you know, whatever
You can essentially run a command on another box and rebuild and recreate that entire system to the exactly how you had it
And you can do that in a rolling way
So what happens when something isn't in the nix way that nix ethos
Yeah, like an example of this actually is paperless ngx. Like I don't think that's been packaged up yet, right?
You can totally do containers and nix like totally is great for that
It's great as a container base and it is great as a container host
And uh, you can do podman and docker on the same system at the same time. Like it's really powerful
And um, I think a lot of listeners that are hearing me right now are probably thinking no chris
Just run the container on nix os. It's so much easier
And that may actually ultimately be the way I go
I may still end up running a few things in containers, but what I have realized is
the benefit
of the way nix manages everything is that I can come back to a system
five years later
And not only will it be fully up to date
But if it just has any problems a super easy to roll back and be super easy to reproduce
Just like done. How often do you do that though five years as your example?
Often I mean usually I don't use hardware past that right? So i'm touching on i'm rebuilding nix
stuff every few years usually I mean speaking about myself. I prefer to
Change stuff every couple of years
So the chances of me sticking with the same system for five whole years is is quite slim
Have you have you ever had like an arch desktop that you install and then like three years later?
You realize it's the same install and you've just been reliably updating it
My arch desktop actually is the one that I installed in london and it travels to the US
It's the one that I installed in london and it traveled across the ocean in a container, you know
I love it, right?
And when you think about how like some desktop linux users, especially mint users
They they actually like reinstall every major for every major version. I know they have it's crazy, right?
Nix is that for everything to the next level and I can pin versions if I need to I can roll back
It's the kind of distro
that you can install it and and
And you can actually reliably let it auto update because it's so simple to recover
It's very compelling and I'm I'm still kind of new to it
So I'm struggling to really put all of it into words
But it's got me excited in a way about deploying software on linux
That essentially docker compose did for containers and I I really don't have a major problem with these
With running these applications in containers, but if I'm being totally honest
I do feel kind of weird about
pulling down like
Essentially an entire software os environment to run sync thing when it's just like, you know
Some binaries and some config files
And I don't really need to run all of that in a container. I don't need to manage the network
I don't need to have like these virtual network interfaces
I don't need any of that. I don't need to like mount storage volumes or any of that
I don't really need it
If I can still get all of the manageability benefits that I got with the software as a container, you know
Being able to pull down specific versions being able to stay current being able to roll back
Being able to isolate data and application stuff like I get all of that with nix without actually having to have in a container
That's compelling to me and it also means that I could probably really eek a lot of performance out of an m1
And the great thing is is there's already people working to get nix os running on the m1 mini
That's running on the m1 mini. So like by the time i'm ready to do this the work's going to be done
Can I play devil's advocate now? Are you done?
soakbox, uh
So so in summary
Boo containers. No. Yeah, go ahead
Why
learn a
Slightly unusual bespoke
Soak deployment configuration system, which is what nix appears to use just from a quick glance. I'll be honest
I'm, not super familiar with it
Uh, and I really you know, I have I have no real opinions
Let me preface everything i'm about to say with no real opinions about nix os at all. I haven't looked at it super closely
but
Devil's advocate time if I am learning ansible
And I want to run it against ubuntu or centos or arch
or mac os or any other system that ansible supports
I've learned a skill that's transferable not only between multiple different operating systems
but also different
Jobs and ansible has been hugely powerful for my career
You know as a springboard where I could start operating at a level that was much higher
Than actually if i'd just been doing everything like a caveman on on the command line
Right simply because people smarter than me had abstracted away a lot of the complexity
And so I look at nix os and I I see their configuration language looks
Pretty easy to understand. It's you know, it's just a standard sort of json type looking configuration thing, right?
And some of the things you said right you you wanted reproducibility
okay, so nix os is clearly that because of the whole ethos of the project, but
Let's say you wanted in five years time to redeploy a specific version of sync thing for whatever reason it might be
You could do that with a container on ansible. You could go through your git commit history
Look up what tag you are running five years ago
Pull that down from docker hub assuming it's still there
But the same is true of nix os, right?
And then deploy that container and you've got everything as it was on that day in history five years ago
And it's all in git. So it's all version controlled and it's all reproducible
I wouldn't be surprised if the more common way of using nix isn't
Ansible deploying like a centos or a rail system or an open to system with the nix package manager installed
uh, because I think the other thing you I don't know if you mentioned it necessarily in there, but
Learning ansible would also be a much more employable skill
You know if you're ever looking for a job, it looks good on the resume
It looks good on the resume. Um, so I actually don't think it precludes me from wanting to learn ansible because I think that's still
Time that would be well spent. Yeah, I do
what I have kind of felt about using nix is um, okay, this is going to be kind of a controversial statement, but
Uh, this is the future of linux and this a lot of what they're solving. It just should be done at the os
anyways, and it doesn't necessarily mean you don't still also need something like ansible maybe for some small scale things, you know,
You're if you have a few boxes maybe with something like nix you could get away without something centralized
But if you have any kind of scale, you're you're obviously going to need tools to manage that
But I I honestly think when I use nix I look at what rail is doing and I don't know how they're going to get there
But they're ultimately going to end up here
And same with what canonical needs to do with ubuntu
uh, and it's so in some ways I like using it because it's just
I I think it's how i'm going to use linux now for the future
When i'm not deploying a desktop system and i'm not even convinced
It may actually ultimately end up using it for a desktop system as well
Especially like a system here in the studio. That's pretty static
I think the counterpoint to that is what redhat for example. I know it well are doing with the uh, redhat core os
Core os operating system at the minute fedora core os if you want to try out the uh, the upstream version
Everything is configured
Declaratively up front, right? So you say I want this nick to have this ip address, right?
I want these storage disks to be configured to this mount point that kind of thing
Uh, that's all done through an ignition config file. You supply that to the vm or to the
The machine when it boots up and it then configures itself based on that
instantiation kind of request
And it seems to me like nix is operating in a similar space where the the operating system is almost like read only
And everything is kind of given to it. It's like this blank canvas
Onto which everything gets painted straight away
Nix os itself managed to make base arch feel bloated. It's really nothing. There's not a lot going on there
So what happens when you need to do a rollback, uh, for example with my home assistant vm
Uh running on top of proxmox
If an upgrade goes sideways
all I do is roll back a specific snapshot which on the zfs backend storage that uh proxmox uses is
Simple what's uh, how does that work in nix? Do you know yet?
See you probably wouldn't quite go through the same scenario
So what i've what i've run into so far is uh, there's two ways you can you can yolo it and just build and deploy
But you can also do like a build
Dash dash test and that does everything and it'll uh, you know, that's where it'll fail out
So they have this sort of switch command that you add. So once you verify that everything's saying the config works and
Like like what software building when it fails to build it'll give you errors and it'll tell you where in the config file
There might be a problem and stuff like that
Um, and then once you've resolved all that you do the switch command and it actually then deploys that as your production system
Um, but by the time you've deployed it, you already know everything works. So there's no, uh, you can roll back but there's
It doesn't really you don't really need to because you just don't it doesn't it doesn't actually switch over unless it actually successfully
Everything works
I mean, that's interesting. Uh, obviously there's a paradigm shift there that I
I and you and we perhaps as a as a show need to go through and kind of figure out
What the future looks like if nix is is the way to go because you're certainly you're certainly peaking my interest as we talk about
I think it is kind of for me. It's a discovery thing, too
Um, i'm thinking about making a nix chat room on the matrix server because I think we have some nix nerds
In the audience, uh, just to kind of wrap this up, uh, alex
What I was thinking is uh with using nix, I would keep things under very tight control
And then I think I kind of want to and maybe you could tell me if i'm on the right track here
I think maybe I might stick with home assistant core. So it's going to be a pretty minimal home assistant
I'm going to get like the minimum viable home assistant rebuilt
And I I wonder if I shouldn't and maybe you could talk me off this ledge consider going with node red
For my automation. So i'm doing all my automations in something separate something else outside of home assistant again kind of
Building these data silos
Um, and i'm also thinking and I don't know how I would even manage to pull all this off at this point
But this is really the time to transition everything to mqtt like anything I can get over mqtt do it including
Like z-wave js to mqtt and all of it
So do you think i'm on the right track is node red too far?
Or is it just like I don't know i'm just if i'm going to redo all this again
I don't really want to have to do it a second time
node red is brilliant for extremely complex automations where there are lots of uh,
tre
If this then that and if this condition is true, then do that, you know, all that kind of really complicated almost like programming logic
Um where it's I think complete overkill is just a simple turn light on at 6 a.m.
Type thing turn heater on at 6 a.m. Whatever it is. Sure. Sure. Yeah, um, and I
I tend to have in my mind as soon as I go beyond like three or four or five kind of steps in an automation
I find the uh home assistant yaml based or the interface based automation is quite cumbersome and that's when I reach for node red
I could see like 80 of our automations wouldn't need to do that
I could see like 80 of our automations wouldn't need that
but there is a niche there like
If so-and-so hasn't been home for so long and so-and-so is this far from here then turn these things off
and then additionally
I hope at some point i'm gonna have
Over mqtt all of my power information from the victron system feeding in and then I would be also looking at solar input
And battery charge level and possibly doing automations based on that as well
Mqtt is just so lightweight and
It's all you it does all you need it to do in a really small
Little lightweight package. So I got an idea. So here's what we're going to do is you and west come out
We'll fly you out for episode 70
And we'll do a bro build at the rv
We'll rebuild everything over the weekend. We'll record it for the show
You know, we'll go do some fancy driving
We'll make a whole thing out of it because I just don't know if I want to take all this on like we got to
Get linux. We got to get nixos going on in m1. I got to
Get everything rebuilt. You got to get all the individual docker services restored got to migrate data
And we got to get everything using mqtt got to get no red going
Just talk about my daily rate, huh? Yeah, I mean, you know, you know, maybe I could pay it in like sandwiches delicious burgers
Oh, i'll tell you what is good in the pacific northwest. There's a little asian place just across the road from the studio
Which yeah, I love that place is good. That's when noah comes in to visit
That's the first place he and I go and if we don't have time
And but I know he's coming i'll order ahead for him
So I remember this is a very old linux action show where he was waxing lyrical
I think about panda express and you're like dude. It's a chain
He does love his chinese food though. I don't know we just think about it
We gotta do something for episode 70 and i'm just saying you come out here. I mean, you know, jb will put you up
Yeah, it's not long is it? It's probably what sort of may june sort of time. Yeah, maybe we'll see
Watch this space
We need to issue a correction on the show
Samuel g writes in about the argon aeon four bay raspberry pi nas case that we covered last episode
Hi guys, I love the show. I think you might have read the argon aeon announcement wrong
You referred to the base model as seven hundred dollars, but I think that's actually an hk money
Uh in u.s. Dollars, it's only about 120 which is a pretty good price if you if you look at it
So yes, thank you for writing in and letting us know that uh, we we can't do currency conversions
No, you know what? It was my bad because I grabbed it and I put it in the dock, but I didn't note the currency
And so I just assumed it was us because it was like, you know had been a couple hours because i'm a dummy
Also samuel sent that in as a boost
With a value for value podcast app
Uh, that's pretty cool very and um gene sent. Oh, I meant to bring it in the studio with me alex, but gene
Uh gene heard about the temperature issues. We've been having in the studio garage server room
Over the summer and he built a wi-fi sensor for me to put in there. That is so cool
I meant to bring it down here for you
Uh, so that way you could look at his handy work. So i'll i'll show it to you, uh after the show
But of course it's using esp home. So it should be uh, no problem to get it working
Uh with home assistant here in the studio and we'll be able to monitor the temperature out there
Which i'm going to get this installed once we have the rack in its final position
So thank you gene for setting that in he sent that in a bit ago and um, the plan is to deploy that soon
Yeah, I mean if I come out there we should do that and deploy. Oh, yeah deploy a fleet of sensors. Not just one
Oh, man, if you actually came out here. Yeah, it would be we'd have a lot with this probably like a dozen things we could do
Um bearded tech sent in something so
Rad and I say rad ironically awesome. I got I got feedback that I should stop saying rad. No
No, I will not
Uh, anyways bearded tech has written this piece of software called fever
And you got to look at this alex. Go look at uh, go look at his github page there. It's a uh,
Frigate event video recorder. Have you seen this?
Yeah, I only because you put it in the dock and it looks awesome. I am going to be uh,
Adding this to my frigate arsenal pretty soon. Yeah, so it lets you store video independently of frigate
But it also has some home assistant integrations for notifications. Um, you can get frames in home assistant
It makes browsing it really easy. He's been working on mobile support. So if you got
One of them internet phones like alex does you can still look at it. Yeah
You can look at your vidjas in the uh web viewer
Like an internet phone is a special thing these days I gotta give you gotta give you crap I guess I don't know
You know have you seen the prices of the coral like the little ai kind of usb sticks that work really well crazy
Yeah, so I paid I think like
$30 or $40 over msrp. They're going for over $200. Oh my gosh, like more than double. It's it's kind of crazy
So, uh bearded tech has a github page up with this fever app on there and it's super cool
He's also got a docker compose
If that's how you you know, if you're still using containers
I mean, I don't use containers anymore. But if you're still using containers, he's got a docker compose good to go
You know, what's interesting is I see in his config file that he's got a whole tail scale section. Oh, yeah
Yeah, he's been he's been dropping me hints about stuff he's working on
It's really good and it's gpl too. So nice. It's free. Yeah, so go check that out
We'll have a link to that in the show notes
Well, very good. I uh, I hope to see lots of you at our meetup on april the 9th in raleigh
Uh, like we said, please make sure you if you are coming your updates are updated
Uh, like we said, please make sure you if you are coming you update the page so we can get a you know
Accurate idea of numbers so we we don't order too much meat or too many uh,
Too many other treats for you
Right, and I want to put the word out there alex
I'd like y'all to join me including you on march 31st at jblive.tv 4 p.m. Seattle time
7 p.m. Alex time 11 p.m. London
We're doing an ama and any of the hosts are welcome
I though nobody's actually said they're showing up but we're gonna do an ama we're gonna help people get set up on matrix and
the big thing
I'm giving away some bitcoin. I'm gonna help you get your value for value podcasting app
So i've been talking about fountain on some of the other shows
It has a little boost feature in there, but the hardest part is getting set up
So i'm going to give away some bitcoin to help people get set up. So that way
they can try out boosting boosting their favorite podcast creators out there and maybe one day free software projects because
the bearded tech
Who's working on fever is integrating lightning payments so you can send a boost to his project to support it. I think that's so cool
So join me ama matrix setup
Bitcoin giveaway and I have a special guest joining me
Do a little interview on the live stream. So it's march 31st 4 p.m. Seattle 7 p.m
New york 11 p.m london at jblive.tv
And for all the ways to get in touch with us, you can go to self hosted dot show slash contacts
There's a form over there. You can fill in and and get your message on the show
Pew pew pew pew you can also hit us up on discord
We got information about that at self host dot show slash discord and the self-hosted matrix rooms at colony dot jupiter broadcasting
Dot com and of course this here podcast is at self-hosted show on twitter
As always, thank you so much for listening everybody. That was self-hosted dot show slash 67