Coming up on today's show we cover our favorite last-pass alternative
We talk about why more boxes might be better than one and we confess our undying love for arch
I'm Alex and I'm Chris and this is self-hosted 39
I too I too Alex have been worshipping at the altar of arch recently after experimenting with various different distributions
I like that I can set up a minimal system and I actually have been enjoying using arch as my base
Application server. I don't run apps directly on arch but in containers or VMs
I find it to be a fantastic platform been doing it for a while now
This comes hot off the heels of this week's Linux unplugged where I think it's fair to say you got in your soapbox
And preach the arch gospel. Oh, I don't know
I think what I what I got in my soapbox about was it's become kind of a joke or a meme
Oh arch users people are just trying to flex and talk about how elite they are
When the reality is that's not it at all
I simply just want something that makes it really quick to get software deployed or up or running and maybe have the most minimal Linux
Installed before I run an application and I find it great for that without sort of all of the upfront work
That's something like gen 2 or Linux from scratch takes a broke broke broke. I run arch by the way
Yeah, well, that's kind of how it started and then it became you kind of grew from there, didn't it? It did
Yeah, I definitely feel the shame like when you say to people I run arch
It's not because you want to flex or at least I don't want to flex it
It's because I I love it so gosh-darn much and I think other people would too if they just gave it a chance and well
Why is that? I think we should talk about maybe just really briefly why it is
You love it so much because it's not it's not the forums, right? It's not the arch. It's not the arch user base necessarily
It's the practicality of it, right? It is I am
One command away from pretty much any piece of software that I want
yay, dash s
Everything literally is you know, the AUR is is arch is secret source
Think of anything think of a custom kernel, you know, the FIO stuff is is pretty complex to get into
There is a custom kernel already compiled or there's a package build to compile a custom kernel already there for you ready to go
You want some esoteric piece of software that on Ubuntu would be a PPA or on Fedora would be a copper repo
I don't have to worry about any of that. It's just yay, dash s install and and off you go and
Besides that, you know as a new user when I was getting into Linux in
2013-14 sort of time period the arch documentation
It's just the best around and it's crowdsourced
It's not always completely accurate and always completely totally up-to-date, but it's good enough
That even an idiot like me can pick it up and get going when I knew basically nothing and at that point
That was when I should just transition to system D. So I kind of credit arch and system D
And docker as being the three kind of pillars of what got me into Linux and being able to get me over that initial
New user not knowing what I'm doing hump those three things together for me would just
Game-changing there really is a Linux for every type. Obviously, there's benefits to running something like Debian or
CentOS or Ubuntu LTS on a server that make just a ton of sense for most people
I'm the type of user. I don't mind logging in at least once a week doing a package update and
Seeing what needs to be installed. I I don't always have time for that
I don't I don't always get to do it weekly
But I generally am able to do it at least once a month if not twice a month and that
Seems to be all it's taken for me to keep these systems up and running and the benefit that I get from
A self-hosting standpoint is my operating system is continuously updated. I don't I don't have this event that comes up every few years
Where I kind of brace myself and do this massive upgrade
I instead I take my medicine kind of on a weekly basis and it kind of stretches out the changes so that they're just more
Minor, they're more frequent, but they're more minor
I I prefer that and then when you add something like Alex is saying the AUR
with the package management system I can get something up and running in moments on arch that would take
A bit of fiddling around maybe adding a package repository following a guide to add the keys and all that kind of stuff
To a machine and then I have the joy of watching that repo go by every time I do an apt update or a dnf
Update and not a huge fan of that system. It works and for some people it's not a huge fan of that system
It works and for some people it works really well for me
I just like to have it all integrated with a single package manager single set of updates that I do and it's always
Guaranteed to be at least close to guaranteed it
I should say the latest version when I install something
So I know the security stuff's taken care of the feature stuff that I've been reading about online
I know it's already landed and then anything that's more complex than a basic system level tool
I'm already loading in a container anyways, and those are often based on alpine or ubuntu, etc
And it kind of doesn't really matter what the host os is running as long as it's secure and up to date
I kind of view arch a little bit like
Stock android, you know like on a pixel phone or well not oneplus anymore, but definitely on the pixel phones like
It has no opinion. There's no opinionation really in how it does stuff. It just gives you stuff and lets you figure it out by yourself
And for that reason it makes a really great minimum viable server
It also makes a really great workstation
It could make a great cloud box because you can only install very very minimal numbers of packages. So from a security perspective
There's a smaller attack surface
The downside is that the industry and I use air quotes around industry
In the cloud at least does seem to be settling on ubuntu like if you look at market share and stuff like that
so you are kind of
trailblazing your own path by going with arch but
I would argue that what distro you run doesn't really matter that much anymore
I mean, I I do feel pretty strongly that you know, all my systems will just run arch
You know if it's a laptop or a desktop or whatever, but if it's a server
I'll probably put ubuntu on it
even though everything we've just said because
It has canonical behind it doing a bunch of testing
Especially when it comes to zfs and the licensing there. That's a tricky one even on arch
Just a bunch of stuff bunch of testing and things like that mean that I don't run arch absolutely everywhere
Just most places. I have found that for the cloud i'm sticking with ubuntu lts for the most part
I find that works really well and for my raspberry pies that are at the rv on an lte connection
I'm also running ubuntu lts there in part because they've done a really good job
with their pi support, but also
Less updates is a feature when you're on cellular. Yeah, and i'm already updating my laptop enough as it is
So there's those those elements of it
But when I have an opportunity to run local physical hardware like I do here at the studio, it's all arch
It works fantastic. I do have one arch box up in the cloud that is like an example of arch in the cloud gone wrong
Where the vendor tried to pin to a third party
Vendor tried to pin to a certain version of the kernel
And of course that just doesn't work very well with arch
So I think it is a little trickier in the cloud and it's not a hundred percent solution
and what I was just advocating now, I guess here and in that episode of linux unplugged is
let's
Not mock people for their choice of distribution
There's functionality behind everything and like perfectly good reasons to run susa as well
My buddy on coder radio mike
That's what he prefers to run. He likes susa in the enterprise. He runs pop os on his desktop and susa
In the rack and that works really well for him
It's not it's not like we're trying to create a this distribution is better debate
what we're trying to say is let's include everybody in the conversation and not mock people for their choice of distribution and
As a couple of counter narrative guys, I guess we happen to find arch actually works pretty well if you're willing to maintain it
Linode.com slash ssh go there to get a 100 60-day credit towards a new account. Yeah
$100 in credit to play with and of course your support in the show by going to linode.com slash ssh
That's where we set up all of our infrastructure for jb 3.0 if we're playing around for something like ssh like segment work or something
Yeah, we do that up on linode and speaking of arch
One of the great things about linode is they let you pick just about any distribution you want they have arch
They got I mean they got everything alpine debian
sent off susa
Ubuntu's of course, I mean they got like everything up there even some fedora for you crazy kids out there
You can run it up on linode. They've been in this game since 2003
They've learned what works and they've learned what doesn't work and they were doing that years before everybody else
and they've really managed to modernize it with a beautiful cloud dashboard that makes it approachable to somebody who's brand new to servers or
Or maybe you're like a longtime pro. You're gonna love the way this dashboard works
Of course, they have native ssd storage 40 gigabit connections coming into the machines
It's all super fast and because they've been around since 2003. They've got some great locations
Like think about that, right?
They can leverage their experience their relationships in a way that nobody else can because they've been in cloud computing before it was cloud computing
11 data centers around the world. We got an email into the show from james
He said I wanted to set up an smtp relay at my previous
vps provider but
Because they were kind of you know
Trying to be competitive in the market
They they ended up with not the best ip reputation
And they ended up getting blocked by microsoft. And so then he spun up another box on their system and that also got blocked by microsoft
He's like I couldn't even find them on any public blacklist yet microsoft just started
Blacklisting all of these ips. So I decided I'd go over to linode and try a try a linode over there and support the show
So he goes to linode.com
Ssh he spins up a system on linode and he discovers. Oh
Linode has a policy where they block all smtp related ports by default
Oh, well, I guess i'll email support and see what they say
So he sends off a quick email to support he gets a prompt response later and they open up the ports and everything is working
Perfectly he goes then a few days later
I finally got a response from my original provider with some canned email that didn't help it at all
I reply to that. I got another canned email response and that was it
I just gave up and i'm moving everything over to linode. They're genuinely just great
And i've gotten so many notes into the show that talk about linode support
It's not an aspect. I touch on a lot, but it really matters once you get up and running
Especially if you've got some important infrastructure on there, so go check them out linode.com
slash ssh
Now I know you covered some stuff about last pass in linux unplugged this seems this is like linux unplugged plus this episode, isn't it?
But uh last pass have been doing some shenanigans with their free tiers and stuff
I think we've all been expecting this for quite a long time
since uh, they were acquired
now they are limiting
the
access to unlimited devices of one type so to clarify what that means is you can access last pass free
On an unlimited number of computers or an unlimited number of mobile devices, but not both on their free tier
I say enough. I say that stinks and we have a recommendation for you. I agree
I mean the price right now is kind of reasonable. It's like what four bucks a year or something
It's not outrageous
for a year, I mean
But it stinks the way it's going about
And I agree it it's time to look at an alternative and this is the self-hosted podcast
And I think both of us landed on bitwarden pretty quickly
I have some trepidation here though. Hold on a minute. I think last pass is 27 a year
It's two dollars up two dollars 25 a month billed annually
Oh, you're kidding me. Yeah, huh? Oh geez, okay
Uh-huh. Yeah, you're right. So that's that's not nearly the deal. I thought it was that's a bad deal
Especially when bitwarden is only ten dollars a year. That's if you buy an annual plan
But if you don't even want to do that, you can self-host the bitwarden server, which is just so cool
Yeah, I really love seeing this and I know it's a little complicated. I think it requires sequel among other things
So the community has come up with an alternative. Yeah, there's a a project called bitwarden rs, which is written in rust
Where's where's when you need him?
and this is a a
A bit warden server that can run in a container that will essentially perform the same role as the ten dollar a year
Hosted service the difference being is you own all the data. It remains on your servers or your vps or whatever
So there's a couple of ways you could go about doing this the first and most obvious way is to spin up a linode
Or something like that and throw a bit warden on there
And just call it good and because it's your password manager. I would probably caution against
Running this on a shared cloud vps, you know, if you if you're hosting a ton of websites
And it's a very public, you know vps
I probably wouldn't put your password manager on that same system. I would put it on a separate system
Just so you're reducing the blast radius of any bots or anything doing something crazy with the web servers
The other thing you can do is run it on your lan and I think the
running it on a separate system becomes less important when it's on your
Network and the idea of of running it on your lan, of course
Is that your data never leaves your house, right and and that will hopefully
Reduce the risk even further now the downside of running it on your lan
Now the downside of running your own password manager backend is you've got to configure secure access to it
So that could be using wire guard
Or some other kind of authentication through ssh or something like that
But ultimately you're going to want to be really careful and really sure you know what you're doing from a security perspective
Before you start going and storing all your passwords on a public system
That's where you could make the argument that it could just be worth paying for their hosted service
And this is where i'm currently experiencing my trepidation. I I 100 know I could self-host it
Uh, and the nice thing about this rust version of their server is
Really minimal resources so you could really run it on anything
So I could run it on my raspberry pi or I could run it easily here on the server at the studio
But I i'm not sure I want to you know, there's something about the the master password vault
It's such a sacred responsibility
that
I almost trust an organization like bit warden to be more focused on securing that platform than I am not that I
I really have no concerns about our security really
But there's something that still gives me pause
They got one job to do right and i've actually paid bit warden the ten dollars a year for
Two or three maybe four years at this point. I've been very very happy. It just does the job
I never have to think about it. All the auto fill stuff on android and ios just works fantastically. Well
You know ten dollars is that kind of?
Screw it amount of money when it's spread over an entire year, you know
It's less than a dollar a month and yeah
To just not have to worry about it and to just not have to think about it for what 80 90 cents a month
That's worth it for me. It reminds me of why I kind of like
Like supporting nebuchadnezzar and how supporting nebuchadnezzar goes into home assistant development makes home assistant better
By subscribing to bit warden you're helping them come up with sustainable business model that encourages them to make the password manager better
And keep their service secure
So it incentivizes the right things and on top of that. It means I don't have to host it myself. I haven't actually made my decision
Because I I have kept a lot of business stuff in last pass for a while. I know I like bit warden
So i've always thought that's what I would jump to
And so I went over to their to their subscription pricing page and they also offer team plans
For as little as like three dollars per user and that's still pretty reasonable
So I think that might be the direction I end up going i'm going to research more about how they host it first
Because I know a big use case for me a really big use case for me is mobile access
It's such a crap shoot with me. I don't just connect from one machine
I could it's just ridiculous, especially when you bring in like traveling or setting up family member systems or and hosts
yeah, it's just it's it's ridiculous so I
I kind of like the idea of something where i'm not handing out wire guard connections to 15 different people
So that way they can access the central password database
And don't forget as well
Generally the time when you need bit warden the most is when your device is completely brand new or empty
Right, and so you've always got that awkward first 10 minutes where you're getting, you know, your two-factor auth set up again
And your bit warden whatever set up again
And once you've got those two things you're good to go generally
But yeah, I can see you don't want to be handing that out to randos
If you do want to self-host it though alex like somebody in our audience who may have a different use case
It's easier than ever now because the bit warden rust server has a docker image fully up to date
Um as of like 19 hours ago as we record this it's like uh, the old proverb
If if something isn't dockerized at this point, does it even exist?
Now another nice thing that I do with bit warden is I actually share passwords with my wife
She has a bit warden. I don't think she pays the premium. I think she just has the basic free account
But we created an organization and when you create a particular login
You can assign that login to an organization and share it with that organization
So certain passwords for us like amazon ebay, you know stuff that you want to share
It goes into that shared, uh area if you like that shared organization and we've both got access to it
I find that really useful. There's of course other solutions out there
Another beloved one in the audience is key pass and key pass x and
There's several solutions to this
But bit warden is the one we both landed on I think in part because of the ui the browser integration
The ability to self-host and the quality of the mobile apps all kind of come together to make it our favorite choice
So whilst we're sort of kind of on the topic of security
Why don't we discuss the plex hoopla that's been going on as well about this?
Botnet thing that's been amplifying stuff across the internet
Distincts because you know, you you got a plex server going you've opened it up to the internet
So that way you can share it some scanner finds your server
Indexes it and then some botnet author figures out a way to take advantage of a vulnerability and plex to amplify
by a factor of five
Their ddos traffic they kind of corral all of these different plex installs together
To kind of do this amplified attack against a single source and just happened the last week as we're recording this
Net scout said that there was a ddos for hire service that recently turned
Misconfigured plex media servers into amplifying attack servers
Yeah, not only does it suck up all of your bandwidth and attack somebody but it also runs your server like crazy
It's just it's bad. Yeah, what really kind of
I don't want to use the word scared me, but I suppose so, you know gave me cause for a concern at least was
just opening
port 3 to 400 that 32 400
On tcp just opening that port alone is enough to be vulnerable because it's such a common port
People will scan it and find it and then be like, oh this guy's running plex. Yeah
so what i've done since this vulnerability to kind of remove myself from the
The risk factor is i've closed that port in my firewall and I have started to define a custom
server url in my plex server settings
And I set a dns entry in cloudflare
That then points to my wan ip
From there that then points to a traffic instance that's running on the same server as plex
And from there it does a standard reverse proxy thing and just does the remote access as if I was going through port 3 to 400
Like I was last month
Very easy fix and I highly recommend you take a look into that. That's a great idea because netscout said that after a scan
They conducted they found about 27 000 servers on the internet that can be abused this way
So if it doesn't mean you have to shut off remote plex, but it it does
It does mean you should probably take some steps to protect yourself. Yeah, just put it behind a reverse proxy
I mean doesn't have to be traffic. It could be nginx could be whatever but uh,
Just don't open any ports in your firewall. You absolutely don't need to which actually brings me very nicely onto a very very
Quick bit of follow-up about the wire guard rant. I had last week on uh open sense
Uh turns out like an idiot. I uh, I set a slash 16 subnet in my dhcp server
Now for those that don't know what that means is every address from 192.168.0
All the way up to 192.168.255
Was within my dhcp range. So I had 65 000 or whatever dhcp address is available
Uh, the the upshot of that was when I was trying to route through wire guard. I was doing a 192.168.13
subnet and so
The remote servers were hearing that were receiving the commands from my laptop or my phone or whatever
But they didn't know how to route back to the client device because so far as they were concerned the slash 16
Overrode everything and it just thought everything was on the land. So
What I did was I changed the subnet of the wire guard vpn to a 10 dot something
So it was a completely different subnet and I reduced my slash 16 down to a more manageable slash 20
So i've only got a few thousand like four thousand addresses now instead of having to go through the subnet
So i've only got a few thousand like four thousand addresses now instead of 65 000
I think that should tie me over for a bit. Right nicely done. I definitely always suggest if people can
Different subnets for the different vpn and points makes it so much simpler
uh, you know and i've tried i've tried to do that myself so many times because it can solve you just a few
Simple problems and keeps it a little clearer in your head. Like I know that the studio is dot
4 and home is dot 7 and the wire guard network is actually a dot 10 network. It's all separated out
Yeah, so I just wanted to be absolutely clear that the problem was the user not open sense or wire guard
It was totally my fault
And uh, I I owe a huge debt of gratitude to one of our listeners who reached out to me on discord
and uh
Did a screen share with me and walked me through it for half an hour because he works in uh,
security down in charlotte in north carolina
And he sort of taught me some new stuff about you know networking and triage and that kind of stuff. So that was pretty cool
So huge. Thank you to to that listener sounds like somebody we should uh buy a beer for when uh,
community events happen again one day
Yeah
Well, if you'd like to learn networking or anything else acg has 20 off annual plans right now
We'll have a link in the show notes or just go to a cloud guru.com when you sign up use the promo code
Spring into cloud 21, you know, the cloud is growing. There's lots of new services and systems more every day
It seems and that also means the demand for skilled cloud professionals is growing, too
82 of hiring managers say a cloud certification makes a candidate more attractive
So go grow your skills with hands-on labs and learning keep up with change and develop the skills
You need with a cloud guru to get that 20 off sign up for an annual plan and use that promo code spring into cloud
95 of learners say that a cloud guru's tools and content directly help them advance their careers spring into cloud 21 link in the show
Notes or go to a cloud guru.com
Ryan writes in with an igpu question. Hey there friends. I'm a big fan of the show
I currently i'm in the process of building an off-grid house in new zealand. Oh, oh, that's the dream. No
Right amazing. Can we come visit?
self-hosted on tour
Power power consumption is key. So I want a small box to run basically everything I need which thankfully isn't going to be that much
My question is is it possible to run a linux server and pass through an igpu to a windows vm for blue iris
While still using the igpu for containerized applications like plex
I can't seem to see any problem with this in theory, but wonder if you have any ideas. Love your work ryan
What do you think about this one? I have also contemplated. Is there a way I can have my cake and eat it too
When it comes to an igpu and a low power system, I thought i'd solve this problem
I thought I had the answer and it was a technology called gvt dash g which is a virtual
graphics card kind of slicing
Thing that basically lets you take a an intel
Gpu built into your cpu and slice it up into two slices and give one to one vm and one to another so
The obvious use case for that is to give one slice to a windows vm for blue iris
And then give the other slice to a another linux vm for plex and then keep the host as clean as possible
Yeah, however, and i've written a blog post about this this week
unfortunately, the performance of gvtg is
is horrible
I found it to be anywhere from 58 to 82
Slower than quicksync being run natively on the bare metal host. Holy smokes. I did not expect that at all
Yeah, so my test that I did was it was pretty unscientific
Um, but it was a very real world use case for me. So I used the
Plex sync for offline playback feature and I chose a high bit rate. So about a 38 megabyte
A second. Um
Was it megabit? I always get confused
video file encoded with mpeg4 and h264
um with a dts
master audio soundtrack
And I used the four megabytes a second 720p sync for offline playback option within plex
And I did that on an ipad, you know, that was the client. I don't think that it really mattered too much
But I did a few different tests. So I did a software render. So this is using the
intel i5 8500 cpu
I picked that up for about a hundred dollars used on ebay. So it's a pretty good value four gigahertz
I think 4.1 gigahertz six core cpu
With cpu rendering only I saw a 1.1 times speed
The best I saw running it natively in quicksync on the host was 10.2
And then on a sliding scale between those two numbers of one times and 10 times
with the gvtg stuff
Set into two slice mode
I saw only about a 1.8 1.9 times. So it was faster than cpu
software encoding, you know twice as fast actually
but it was
80 what something
82 slower than running it on the bare metal host. So
The other problem that I ran into besides, you know, leaving 80 plus percent performance on the table
With stability, unfortunately
That wasn't a great story either the problems I ran into were so I was running proxmox as the base os
because the
Proxmox wiki actually has a really great entry about enabling gvtg and
Quicksync and pass-through and all that kind of stuff and it was really painless to get going
It only took me an hour or so to figure it all out and get it get it going
But the stability was just not there. My evidence is only anecdotal though
Because of the instability I couldn't really get the log files that I needed
Because the system either had to be hard reset or it was just hanging and processes were just hanging or I was getting kernel panics
it was just a mess and
You know at the end of the day just not not something you could just let run and and just not have to think about
It no, unfortunately, it wasn't and you know things worked fine until I powered on the windows vm
that was running blue iris and
That system has six 4k cameras going into it. So it's got a decent amount of load
Now I know for a fact that the i5 cpu can handle that load because it's been running in my hp290 slim
For six months just fine handling everything perfectly
But for some reason when it's in the the gvtg mode
it just I guess because it's the performance is so poor with the
Emulation whatever they're doing to slice the gpu up. However, they're doing it in the intel drivers
It just meant that as soon as I powered up blue iris
within 30 minutes the whole proxmox system was just
Unhappy, you know like the web ui wouldn't load sometimes or you actually go and reboot the system and you'll see
System d printing out waiting on kimu guest to shut down for like 30 minutes and
So it wasn't just guest stability issues, but the entire host. Uh-huh
Oh, yeah, that's that's well, that's just a deal breaker
Oh man, alex at the end of the day you want it to be on and functional and yes, this is a hobby and I do enjoy
Messing about with servers, but there comes a point. It's not a full-time job
No, exactly. There comes a point where you're like this s just needs to work now
Yeah, and it just didn't unfortunately
I think you cross the threshold of devoting more time to this than most folks quite a while ago
I mean even taking a pass at the different encoding options. That's good insight and it really shows you that you're
I mean, yeah, it's almost twice as fast if you use gvt
When you consider the stability issues
stability issues I would rather just use cpu encoding cpu encoding with quicksync because that's only pulling down about
10 watts when it's doing a full 1080p stream and it's running at 10x real time
So actually, you know in terms of performance per watt is the best thing out there
I actually also just for giggles use my 1080 ti to run one of these trans codes
So quicksync is running at 10x a 1080 ti which is pulling down 18 times
The amount of power is running at 17 times. So 10x versus 17x. Wow
It's a good way to see the performance discrepancy between intel's gpu
And the nvidia gpu right there, isn't it?
You can really and then of course cpu with its measly 1.1x. Yeah
Performance per watt of the nvidia card was just hilariously bad. Well, sure sure
So what i've ended up doing actually and this is to go back to ryan's question now is i've ended up splitting things back out into
Physical boxes the blue iris box is uh an hp290 slim. I already had
I've put the i5 back into there and I bought another i5 to put into my server. So I have two now
Which is a shame but hey ho
Um, I was doing some testing on the hp290 for average power usage when I say idle
What I mean by that is blue iris is running with its normal sort of load. So
At average sort of use power usage I see on that box is anywhere from sort of 10 to 25 watts depending on what it's doing
Which for the performance i'm getting, you know, that kind of power usage is is fantastic really
And then my main server is pulling it anywhere with you know, it's got I think 12 hard drives in it anywhere from
40 to 80 watts
Uh at idle so, you know, it's all pretty good pretty low, you know to have all that performance for under 100 watts at idle is
I'm pretty happy with that. Yeah. Thanks for sharing the details with us. You mentioned the blog in there. Well
Sam actually writes in with our next question
He's a new listener and he says i'd love to hear more about what alex uses for building his blog
And if you've experimented with any other options and what you thought thanks for the great show
Well several years ago when I was launching linuxserver.io
I actually had a personal blog blog. Katie said dot me that got turned into
Linux server's blog and eventually the linux server website and that kind of took over and became its own thing
So we used to use wordpress and then we moved to ghost and linux server and this would be
I dread to think how long ago like five years ago
Um, we moved to ghost and it's been so solid
I then ended up spinning up ghost for my own personal blog to do like travel writing and all that kind of stuff as well
So I use ghost almost exclusively for blogging
Um, and then the perfect media server website is written in mkdocs
I live vicariously through you on ghost. That was the route I thought I might go if I were going to set up a blog again
And uh, i'm going to put a link to that in the show notes because I think that's worth checking out
Although they've changed their model a lot since I first originally found them now
They seem like they're really focused on them hosting the blog, but you can still post self-host and all that
Self-host out of a container. Yep, and i've actually got a custom theme
So I spent quite a bit of time before the perfect media server
2020 edition came out making sure that my blog had search and a few other different, you know
Like fav icons and and social media icons all that kind of crap. So
You can customize the theme relatively easily and all of that stuff is open sourcing github. So
You know, I have no complaints about ghost at all. It just does exactly what I need. It looks pretty good and
You see it all over the place on the internet really. So I think that's kind of uh,
You know proof is in the pudding. How how how many blogs do you see that are in in ghost quite a few?
So yeah, it must be okay
All right, so I think our final question for today tarmo writes in about user account management
Hi guys, i'm a new listener and this show is perfect for me. I started at episode one. Well, thank you
I was wondering if you have done a podcast about how you manage different servers and user accounts
Do you have ldap or some kind of centralized authentication?
I'm finding creating unique user accounts for every server and saving their credentials every time to be a bit of a pain in the bum
I was wondering if you have any thoughts
Looking through the episode descriptions. I didn't find anything about this. Thanks
Tamo good question because it's been on my mind a lot
recently
linux distributions like fedora and ubuntu added checkbox active directory support to their installers and
That got me thinking
Yeah, almost almost wouldn't mind having like an active directory set up here on the land either either actual active directory or some samba
frankenstein version of it, but
truthfully
I what I have landed on is standardized accounts
So we have a standardized studio account and I have an account on all the systems
And the people who work here at the studio, we know those logins and then for our server logins. We use ssh keys
But I do long term have my eye on systemd homed as a potential way
To solve this at least here on the land at the studio
uh, and i'll have a link to that in the show notes, but essentially it
It takes your home directory and all of your user information and puts it into json
And then you can drop this home directory bundle into a systemd homed enabled system
And not only does your home directory show up there, but you also then become a user on the system
That's obviously me giving you the short version, but it has some potential so you could see here in the studio where
Perhaps we'd keep our master homed directories on the server and then rsync them down to the studio machines in my workstation
I don't know every hour every 24 hours. I don't know. I haven't really looked into it yet
But if we did that, it would also sync down our user credentials
Early days just something that's on my horizon kind of keeping on my radar as a possibility because I don't need something too advanced
I've managed large ldap single sign-on installations in the past as part of my job and
It worked surprisingly well for a long time, but I just don't really have an interest in doing that anymore
I mean you could spin up ldap. You could do free ipa
You could do a lot of things, but could do active directory kind of sounds kind of fun. I don't know
Yeah, but I don't know about you, but i've got to the point over the last decade where i'm managing so many different
Systems some of them are in different houses or different cloud providers or stuff like that that
Having them sync back to a central
Authentication would just be so complicated. I've kind of got I feel like half decent at context switching
Between the different servers and knowing. Oh, right. I don't have that particular
Set up on this one and any files. I do need to sync between various things
I have my nas and I just mount that via samba
And I I don't really worry too much about the home directory anything that's in there as in my opinion at least is
Ephemeral it goes in git or it goes in samba or it gets lost. That's kind of how I treat it
Yeah, I I think in part it's because I have
in full disclosure
I've accepted a security practice on the land of the studio that
Probably you shouldn't do and that is we don't rotate passwords very often
Maybe once every couple of years, but then again, it's convenient. I'll give you that
Yeah, and as far as physical access goes it's a lot easier to do that
It's not like a organization with an office of 20 here. And then for this for the servers
uh, it's it's pretty much all down to
ssh keys and
All remote login is usually done with that any access to the lan is done with wire guard
And that has its own set of keys
So there's some layers there every now and then I still think it's a fair question. I still think to myself
I could do this on my own
I still think it's a fair question. I still think to myself I could do this a little better
And I I do fantasize about a future where I deploy everything
Pragmatically and then everything has central sign on and central storage
But I think i'd have to i'd have to like clone myself to get there
But this goes back to the point at the beginning, right?
You use arch because you just want to get stuff done and I think we don't use a central authentication system
Because we don't we just want to get stuff done. Like we don't want to spend the week or two figuring it out and
Setting it up and then every time we reinstall a box
Attaching it to a domain controller or whatever it is, right? I think it's just pragmatism, isn't it?
That means we're lazy and don't do it
Maybe that's a bit of it. We've gotten old what we need is a young ssh
Ssh intern to come into the studio and whip us together and get a single sign on going. Yeah, maybe maybe
Thank you to our members over at selfhosted.show
Sre, thank you for supporting the show as a thank you
We supply you a limited ad version of the show and you also in that feed get extra content
The post show. Thank you very much to our members at selfhosted.show
Sre we're gonna have a little bit of a 3d printing
Hoedown in the post show today. I think yeah, I look forward to that
And I also have a bit of a confession to make just a little bit of business before we go
Everything we talk about is over at selfhosted.show
As always you can go to selfhosted.show slash contact for all the ways to get in touch with us
And you can find me on twitter at ironic badger. I'm there too at chris elias and the show
At selfhosted show on discord. I'm at alex ktz
Thanks for listening. That was selfhosted.show slash 39