Coming up on this week's show we discuss how listener Morgan was almost outsmarted by a not-so-smart doorbell
jellyfin makes Alex's prediction dreams come true and
I try out QO notes
Again, I'm Chris and I'm Alex and this is episode 18
Well, Chris I went and did it. I bought myself a smoker. My Americanization is complete
This truly is the completion of a journey that has been a multi-year journey. I'm so so proud of you Alex the
Culmination reminds me that American Pie moment. You remember where the coach is on the field? I
Don't want to take this from you, but Alex, you know, you got to automate this
We got it. We got to integrate this somehow into Grafana. I got expectations, you know, it's coming
I want to see average cook time built into graph on it something like that. What about average temperatures that you use?
I want all the data average temperature per probe. I think is really the sweet spot per probe
How many how many probes are we talking about? I don't know. This sounds like an episode of South Park
Doesn't it where Cartman's getting probed or something?
But I don't know you like for four probes is a good number of probes
Have you looked into it though the possibilities what I have and actually joining us on the show
This week is a friend and colleague of mine Morgan Peterman. He works with me at Red Hat
he's a technical account manager working on OpenShift and he has an extensive home lab and
He was the benefactor of a certain doorbell that you ordered Chris without researching it properly
Yeah during the show actually I ordered a smart doorbell. So Morgan, it's great to have you here and how is my doorbell turned out?
Thank you so much for having me. Yeah, the doorbell actually worked out pretty good
Once I finally got it set up wired properly and connected running on Shinobi
It's a little difficult
especially if you watch their YouTube video and then you see that they use one application and then you go to their website and
They recommend a completely different application. So that was a lot of the hassles that I went through
I I spent quite a bit of time using the easy viz app, you know
It's standard scan the QR code it connects to the Wi-Fi and ad hoc mode and it's supposed to work connect
Configure Wi-Fi and then you get your video and it didn't do that
I had a series of texts that were getting progressively more and more frustrated over the course of what six hours
You were installing this thing. Yes. It took a couple hours to get it working. I
Replaced the transformer because I didn't know if it was a power issue
I changed the wiring cleaned up some terminals and in the end
It just came down to the fact that the application was just awful. So I went to the website I found out
That they offer a batch configuration tool
So I downloaded the batch configuration tool put it on the Mac loaded it up found the you know
The camera and I couldn't configure it
So then became the hunt to find a Windows machine in my house
That I could actually tolerate long enough to get the batch tool on. Oh my goodness. That was the easiest for me
you know again, there's
Easy viz guardian vision and then there's their actual batch tool the easy viz
Did not work at all. They just could not connect couldn't configure and this is after I created a new SS ID
Just something simple. I called it IOT with a password a password still couldn't connect
Guardian vision wasn't working at all for me and ended up using the batch tool. The batch tool was great. I found it
It's gooey based, you know on Windows. You configure the SS ID in the password and it connected instantly and I was up and running
And then I found out that my doorbell didn't work had to go over to Home Depot stood in line for about an hour to get
into Home Depot
Came home hooked up the doorbell and then it was a fun game of picking which one of the 16 songs
We wanted to hear whenever the doorbell rang. Does this thing trigger a built-in doorbell that's in the house already
So if you had something installed it'll trigger that
Yeah, so what I found out was my old mechanical doorbell was actually broken
One of the springs had popped and it just wasn't worth trying to repair it. So I had two options
I had a regular mechanical style doorbell or that you know
The 16 song doorbell is standard off-the-shelf from Home Depot came home wired it inside of the easy vis app
Which is what you want to use after you get a configure this very important after you get it configured
You want to keep the easy vis app because it is the best app of the two that they recommend you just go into the settings
you configure it you tell it you have a
You have an electronic
Doorbell and then you're set
So whenever you come up you push the button your doorbell rings and what's nice is you can configure it if you want it to
Be two seconds or ten seconds. You have you have configuration options just to be clear
Does it require like an account or a service?
Any kind of any kind of login that you have to go into a service to get this thing to be configured or functional or?
Anything you have to pay for so no you do not need to sign up for an account to get it to configure it
You can download the batch program the batch tool off of their website and you can get it configured
But if you want to use the easy vis app
From my for what I found you you do have to log in so I use my standard Google account
And if you're an iPhone user, which I am you definitely want it when somebody comes up and rings my doorbell
I get a phone call. I answer the phone call and it's audio you hit the easy vis button and then it does
Video so I can actually see them and I can talk to them and it's a great app
It's not a hundred percent self-hosted
But it's it's a good option that they give you
so I
Also configured shinobi. It's view only or watch only I configured my motion detection
and I had to toggle a little bit with the audio detection because
It was too low and crickets were setting off the recording and then obviously if you set it too high, it doesn't pick anything up
So again, I used shinobi. I got it set up. I got it recording. I
Caught myself mowing the lawn picking up the grass, you know
My neighbor at 830 in the morning revving his motorcycle wanting to wake everybody else up. So it works great with shinobi
I was really happy with it and that actually didn't take very long to get set up
All right, and to be clear, we're talking about the Nellie's security camera that was on Amazon for around $130
It's currently not available, but there's different iterations of it
I bought this back in January while we were recording the show and I had a sense
It was a project and so I never I just kept putting it off and then I realized I didn't have the proper wiring
So Alex suggested we ship it to Morgan and so Morgan did all of this testing did the whole install
but the one thing we haven't asked you about on this Nellie security camera is
How's the picture quality? Does it actually do the job and give you a clear picture of what's going on around your porch?
So the picture is actually really nice
I took some videos and I sent it to Alex so he could see and it was super clear
one of the issues I did have with it is
It's more of a fisheye style lens and they advertise this as a feature
So you get the full height of the individual standing in front of the camera
But that also distorts the image just a little bit
So for example, if you're a little little big around the belly, you're gonna look a lot bigger in the video
But the the picture is crystal clear. The audio is actually really amazing
I was quite surprised how well it picks up audio
Especially for conversations if you're if you're not standing directly in front of the camera for $139
I would definitely recommend it to any individual who's looking for a good camera and you want to get out of the ring
You know or one of the ones that maybe comes with Comcast, etc
Have you tried the ring doorbell? How does it compare to that?
So I had the ring doorbell when I purchased this house and it was transferred over to me
My big issue was the fact that I was paying monthly for it
You know, there are some features that ring has is really nice
But I didn't like the idea of a reoccurring monthly payment
And as you guys know monthly payments always go up every year
They adjust it and the total cost of ownership for these doorbells just skyrocket on top of that
It didn't look very good. That's such a 2020 sentence the total cost of ownership of this doorbell
Yeah
Unfortunately, you're right and and the fact that we're even considering does does your doorbell have a subscription service?
one of the upsides that I really liked about the Nelly was
The fact that it's hardwired. You don't have to worry about a battery, you know, I know people that bought
rings and then they were charging their doorbell battery every couple of days, which is ridiculous, you know
The Nelly is hardwired, which is nice. It doesn't offer a battery as Chris, you know
The downside to it though, and this is something I mentioned to Alex. It does get very hot
Whenever I was just plugging it in just to test it
It got to the point where I couldn't hold it for more than a couple seconds to the point where it could burn me
I don't know if this is gonna affect overall longevity of the device, but you definitely don't feel it if you touch it
It's only the back where the camera and the electronics are but that is something to consider obviously
You know as longevity is how is the heat going to affect this device over multiple years?
Particularly for you down in Florida where it's you know hot
Always so you now have it going into shinobi and then in there you're using
the
Plugin system to do motion capture. So it's only it's always streaming but it's only recording when there's motion capture
That's correct. And then what's really great since it uses
RTSP I have VLC running at all times, especially when I'm expecting an Amazon package
Because what I've noticed is shinobi doesn't pick up
The real quick toss of the box that most Amazon deliveries do, you know, ups and FedEx are really nice
They seem to always ring my doorbell
but I get Amazon who stands just outside of the view of the camera and they toss it on my on my
On my porch so with VLC having it streaming at all time
I can see that nice camera land the same thing with Amazon
I can see the Amazon truck drive by and the video stays connected. It doesn't drop. Yeah, I haven't had any issues
I've actually had it running for two days straight without even realizing I had it connected and it doesn't use a lot of video
I use unified to track how much data it uses and it's not very high cool
I mean
so it sounds like if you're willing to wire it and you're willing to deal with some half-baked apps for some of the initial setup and
configuration changes which can be sounds like a little frustrating the end result is you still have something you can
RTSP stream on your LAN without any cloud service required and what happens if
Nelly go away because you found some you know generic clones of this thing, right?
The only difference between every other one of these clones and Nelly is the fact that Nelly sells it
There are some comments on the internet that they run different firmware
But from what I can tell all it is is a clone of the easy vis camera
And that's why you use the easy vis application. So if Nelly goes away, the only thing you lose is support
What's great is it's not necessarily connected to a cloud
They give you instructions how to remove it from being connected to the cloud
So you can set this up with the batch tool never connected to the cloud and use home assistant
You can use shinobi
I'm sure blue iris would work as well. And that's what's great and it stores everything right on that SD card
so if you're not streaming it to a
You know a DVR or an NVR you can still pull out
You know the guardian vision app and view the data without ever logging into anything
Morgan I'm sure you didn't do a full penetration test analysis
But did you get a sense of what the security is like on this thing if you're comfortable with it?
So one of the things I actually did do was I completely disabled it
Internet access so it could not go out. I set it up
So it had no internet access and it still worked great internally in my land now
Obviously the phone home version of the easy vis application wasn't working
But shinobi still works RTSP still works. I was still getting alerts
Through those applications, but the easy vis application wasn't working, right?
So then I guess that would mean you wouldn't get the push notification video sent to your phone if somebody was at the door
Correct, correct
But you could still have the VLC stream up watching the door all the time and it could be over your land
No cloud service required. So that checks my box. One of the other options is
Motion eye and home assistant which was shared with me by Alex. I did not get a chance to set it up yet
That's my next project
But to get alerts via telegram bot and or a discord bot
So there are options out there where you can set up an alerting service
Again, since this is a doorbell app, I would keep it available to the internet just for the easy vis
Application because I want to be able to answer the phone from my couch or from my bed and see who's there
All right. I don't want to get a video sent to me that may be delayed
it's nice to have a communication and we actually use that on Sunday morning whenever a
You know the Jehovah Witnesses came by thanks, but no, thanks. Have a great time
It was a lot better than waiting for a notification on the phone then viewing the video to see who it was
Yeah, absolutely
Yeah
the real time when someone's at the door like that really makes a difference and that does seem like a great way to
Politely say thank you, but no, thank you and not get stuck in a conversation. I just blame coronavirus these days. That's the general go-to
Well Morgan
I'm really glad that we sent it your way so that way you could give us the full test on it and it it sounds
Like if I had if I could have wired it in which I couldn't do in lady tubes
But I could have essentially gotten the functionality I was looking for
So I'm gonna keep an eye on this category because if they make one with a battery
That could be the route I would go. Yeah, I agree. It's like I said, it's great application. Thank you
I really appreciate you giving me the opportunity to test it out for you
Now before we let you go Morgan
You have an embarrassing data loss story. You want to share with the class, don't you? Oh, no as Alex mentioned
I am a Red Hatter and one of the great options that Red Hat gives you is the ability to
To install the full stack and I love home labbing and as a home labber, you should really practice good backups
Because if you're supposed to be replicating what you do at home for your what you do at work
You should practice what you preach. I unfortunately ran afoul of that this weekend installing some new SSD drives. Oh
Oh popped open the the home lab install some SSD drives configured the raid and I initialized the long
raid array
system reboots
Can't connect a vCenter can't connect to my VMs
Login to the ESXi hosts and all my VMs just have VM dash number and they're all gone
Oh, no, and then I realized instantly what I did that I just wiped out all of my data
How awful did that feel cheese, but it's okay Morgan because you and I were talking and you wrote
loads of automation to rebuild this stuff right and you put it in git was fine, right
Alex has been hounding me to document the entire process to automate everything and I took his word for it
I love ansible ansible is a great tool and I wrote
Thousands of lines of ansible playbooks to replicate my entire environment outside of ESXi in vCenter
To the point where I actually deleted a bunch of my VMs and I redeployed them
Unfortunately that was in my git lab server, which was on my home lab that I erased
Right. I mean, I'll be honest. I laughed pretty hard when he told me the story the first time. Yeah, cuz it's not you
Yeah, I mean I've done that. I've wiped out three terabytes worth of stuff
Numerous times probably but wiping out data and the VMs is like a double blow
But I've never not had my configuration in github as opposed to it local git lab. So yes, I learned
So once I redo all that work, it'll all be stored externally
So a nice little tip for you if you've heard of git t that is a self-hosted local
github server clone thing and
Git T will automatically clone any commits you make to github
So I have a local copy of all of my github stuff is locally saved by git T
Now the motivation for that was what if they get bought out by some evil company? Oh wait, they maybe did
What if they did something crazy with my data?
but obviously the same is true in both directions if if I accidentally initialized the wrong SSD array and
Wipe my local
Git server, it's all in github too. So yeah, so I spent Saturday night rebuilding the most important VMs
And I'm sure sadly it won't be the last time I accidentally delete everything
But I'll make sure that this will be the last time I delete everything without proper backups
So your post-mortem is off-site off-site off-site. Do you know what you're gonna use? I have not looked into it yet
Back please is obviously one that I do like, you know unlimited storage the downside of I've used it before and it does take
A long time to pull everything down. We've got gigabit symmetrical internet though
So, you know the actual upload part, which is normally the problem. You've got that licked. Yeah, I have symmetrical one gig
So it's pretty nice. But most likely what I'm gonna do is write some scripts using PowerShell that'll export the VMT case
Except for you know, the things that I can easily download quickly
And then I'll just zip those up and set them up to back place and just have that like on a 24 every 24 hours
That'll go that's what I actually used to do in my previous job is a site consultant
But you know
As I said, you're supposed to practice what you preach and very rarely do we practice what we preach and we end up
You know with egg on our face. Amen to that. Well, thanks for joining us Morgan
It was a lot of fun and I'll see what other free stuff I can get you in the future
Pleasure. Thanks a lot guys. Have a good one. Thanks Morgan. I have a data loss story of my own this week
It's not quite my fault. Although it could be I'm not sure it is though
I was using Joplin and I've started work on the 2020 version of perfect media server
And I was writing away one evening for about three or four hours and I went to bed
I just finished a huge section which I was really pleased with and I thought I'd gone through it
I'd proofread it and I'd edited it and I'd tweaked it and it was I was really happy with it
And I came back in the morning to my desktop and it was gone gone
I was just like what the hell has happened here?
And it turns out that Joplin had decided that the version of the note that was on the server
Was more important than the version of the note that I just edited and I overwrote it
mm-hmm, then I started going to try and look through the SQLite database that Joplin has and
It's gone. It's too late. It's dead Wow
So you and I were talking about notes and I think Joplin unfortunately was so close
It was really good. It's been working well for about a month
But you found an alternative for me. Yeah, you know funny enough. It's one that you and I have used before
But I just I kept coming back to it. And so I wanted to share it with the class
It's it's a classic
It's Q own notes and I think it holds up to be the biggest and best
Contender to Evernote that I can find there's a couple of fundamentals that I really like about it
Number one all of the notes are stored in plain text files markdown files. You can just go cap them on the command line
You can also you can put notes in multiple folders
You can have them one in Dropbox one on your local file system one on
Same thing another one in next cloud
It also will use the own cloud next cloud API to actually take advantage of the notes in next cloud if you have that and then
That gives you a web viewer for your notes, which is really nice
It can also integrate with some of the calendar stuff there. And then the one that you
Sounded like you were kind of excited about this isn't something I've played with before but I think I'm going to now is I
Realized it also supports get versioning. Yeah, that's a game changer. I mean I use get
Version manage all of my code. So why not version manage all of my notes and
normally the process of doing a you know a git add git commit or whatever every time I get to
You know a new paragraph would be a bit too cumbersome
Sure, but QO notes seems to handle that for you on on the most part and I've kind of written it off as being a bit
Ugly and a bit clunky, but I really started to dig through some of the menu settings today, you know, I was wrong
I think honestly, it's it's a really great looking app and this speaks to a larger principle
I think you and I have been kind of circling around with notes for quite a while really
We're going to use next cloud to actually sync the notes between devices
So, you know between an iPad and a Linux server and a MacBook and a you know an XPS whatever running
Whatever flavor of Linux this week. We're using we use next cloud to handle the sync and then on each
System, I mean QO notes runs on Mac Windows and Linux but on mobile we can use whatever apps
We want to edit those files where QO notes doesn't exist. And I think that's the key really is it's a bit like Wi-Fi
Really you're separating your firewall from your
Wi-Fi you're separating the sync of the notes from the editing of the notes and I think hopefully
Hopefully that's going to result in a really reliable robust solution. I've been playing around with it. I have
I a writer on iOS on the iPad with the new keyboard and I use that to edit some notes
And then I go back to my desktop and it's right there in QO notes. I really like that so far. It's worked really well
I do think maybe eventually I could see some sort of conflict, you know
Maybe I have QO notes open and I added a Dropbox directly. So I'm gonna wait and see how that plays
We'll see eventually if I create my own problem with that one or not, but so far
It's it's worked and QO notes also has support for adding an external editor
So you can double click a note and now it opens in VS code, which is my preferred markdown editor. Really? Oh
Didn't know that. Mm-hmm
Yeah, and it's pretty nice because then if you have some more complex stuff or some just things the VS code does that you want
To do in your notes really simple to do that now and then the other little tip
I'll pass along is if you rock a dark theme like I do if you play around in the settings for QO notes
It's not enabled by default
But they have a dark mode that they call it and you can turn that on and it just looks a lot better
It just simply it just looks a lot better
But also if you're running a dark theme, it's more usable. Some of the stuff won't show up unless you turn that on
Yeah, it's it's much better than I remember. I used it maybe
Was around the time I was emigrating
I think because that's when I was getting into next cloud big time for the first time and
Then it just sort of faded away and I stopped using it for some reason
Yeah, all of the kind of controversy surrounding snaps at the moment. Like I can't quite put my finger on
What it is. I don't fully like about them, but I never end up sticking with them
I couldn't give you a concrete reason why but it just sort of happens and the same thing happened with QO notes before
so hopefully this time is different now I've dug into the settings a little bit and
We'll see I guess, you know, what I think it might be for me is I changed
next cloud servers a couple of times and I sort of hit the reset button on my notes and I wanted something that was
Separate from that and not really wrapped up and I didn't really appreciate the QO notes
Doesn't even need next cloud at all to function using what like sync thing or something like that. That's what I'm thinking
Mm-hmm. Yeah, I mean I actually have next cloud now, so I'm just using that
Yeah without without the API and just using the file sync right now
and then I have another folder that I think I'm gonna keep as like a backup copy and then
Maybe I might eventually throw sync thing at that
I want to do an episode where you and I talk about sync thing a little more because I'm using that for a lot
Of things I never really expected. It's kind of in a way. It's become like a global file system for me. It's it's really cool
Oh, that's interesting. I'll look forward to that one
I've used bit torrent sync since you were using it on the young filter show years ago now called Brazilio sync
But I'll be interested to hear about sync thing. Yeah, it's different definitely different
It's and it's not like a torrent like protocol. It's its own protocol. I was just the other day
I was reading their comparison of the two and
They assert that their security is superior sync thing does and they also point out that all of their code is open source
Yes, well, we can't argue that one
The open source angle. Anyway, that's just a fact
All right, so last episode we talked a little bit about Plex amp and I gave it a bit of a rough review
I'd like to change my assessment slightly. I had a lot more time to play with it over the last week or two and
Fixed some issues with my Plex library that were causing it to act out if you remember from last episode
I I put on heavy metal radio and it played tool and then M&M
One after another which was not right and it turned out that actually the slash temp directory for my Plex media server container
Was not writable and that is why I was having these issues. So if you're having lots of
Random weirdness when you're scanning your library, for example when I was going to do
You know fixed match for you know, a really mainstream album like Green Day American Idiot
It tried to tell me it was by the Beastie Boys
And you're telling me this is because your slash temp wasn't writable correct
What after we talked to Elan in one of the earlier episodes of self hosted from Plex
he invited me to one of their internal slack channels where they've been doing the development of Plex amp for the last six months and
So I reached out to him on there and said hey, I've got this really strange issue
That's preventing me from using Plex amp. So he and I spent a couple of hours going back and forth on slack
Trying to debug this thing and I learned a lot about all the different log files that Plex keeps
When Plex does a scan for a media file it writes something to temp very very briefly for less than a second
And so he was asking me to try and capture that file and in the process. I just tried to do a touch test
File in that directory when I was exacting to the container and it wouldn't work and I'm like, well, there we go
Temps not writable
Did a change mod and then it was fine. So I just removed the mapping altogether
I don't even remember really why I had that volume mapping in my container, but
Anyway, I removed it and it worked and I've just been in love with Plex amp. It's great. It's beautiful
It works really really well it
You know handles the caching of the tracks ahead really well. I found the recommendations now
I've got temp working to be really quite good, you know, so
I'm sorry Plex amp. I was rude about you to start with
But I kind of love you now. So a little more time within you're liking it, huh?
Isn't it interesting that the recommendations aspect of it seems to play a pretty central role for you
Yeah, I mean that's what kind of what I use
Spotify for really is I I go to a particular artist and I'll search and I'll just play the top tracks or whatever
Most of the time and then I look for you know recommended artists or a discover weekly playlist that uses like machine learning to generate
Who it thinks I'm gonna like but of course with your own music library
Most of the time, you know, what's in there? You've generally curated it to the point where you know
Most of the tracks on an album because you've listened to it at least two or three times
And so what I found the most interesting was when I was scanning the
albums to
Plex in the first place
I was going through metadata madness trying to fix it trying to make sure that that green day American Idiot album was absolutely
Pristine it had the correct cover. It had the correct tags
It had everything was perfect in the metadata of the files and it still thought it was the beastie boys
So I started looking at ways to make sure the metadata was correct and I used a program called beats to do that
Now there's a post over on the linux server blog written by josh stark
And he covers a bunch of interesting stuff about beats in there, which is a it's a command line
music metadata management tool
And that's it. I mean it can import music from a download directory or a ripped cd directory or whatever
and then goes through and tags it against a whole bunch of databases and
It's very command line driven, which means it's scriptable. So if you want to do some automation around the imports of your
Music you can do it that way
But that led me on to another
Uh problem I was hitting api rate limits of one a second on the music brains api
Which meant that beats was running really really really slowly
I'm talking
It would have probably taken several days to import my entire library
So linux server also make a self-hosted music brains mirror
So i'm now running on my server a local mirror of music brains, which is kind of cool
So then you just point beats to that local mirror
And you can rate limit to you know, 100 requests a second instead of one so it goes much much faster
Oh, that's really cool. I didn't even know you could host that that is a rad little discovery alex
Isn't it interesting that you can do that?
That is a rad little discovery alex. Isn't it interesting the rabbit hole you ended up going down for this?
Just trying to fix metadata to get plexam working
anyway, it turned out it was slash temp and all the metadata was fine anyway, so
There you go
I wonder why people use spotify. I wonder hey while we're talking about you going down rabbit holes
traffic 2.2 came out back in march
And I think you just recently had a chance to deep dive
But I didn't hear how that went the reverse proxy of choice in the kretschmar household for the last
Several years has been nginx
Um, I don't know sometimes I get itchy feet and I think to myself. Oh the grass is greener over there
What if I just use traffic with its super cool?
Labels and and I could just define everything in my docker compose file and not have to worry about nginx configs
It works great in the studio and it was it was working really really well. I was having a great time until
Until and i'm afraid to say until because this is going to be a showstopper for me
Until I went to use any container that was in host mode
Soon as I did that
The container is no longer on the docker network, which is what traffic uses for internal, you know dns
It's what it uses for internal communications
It's actually on the host
Network so hence host mode
So docker basically can't see it anymore. And as such you can't route any traffic through traffic to the container
Which unfortunately means it's no good to me. How many containers are you running in host mode networking plex being one
Mostly for some of the upnp stuff it does around the hd home run
Yeah, I mean when possible I suppose it's best not to use host networking, but I guess on your lan media box
It's not really the end of the world. No, I thought I had more than that. The only one is plex apparently
so maybe I should just expose a bunch of individual ports instead of
relying on host mode it might not be worth it, but there are a lot of nice advantages to using traffic and
If that's all it took I did really like it
it took quite a bit to get my head around the kind of concepts of their front ends and back ends and
How to get the labels just right specifically
An issue I ran into was because v2 only came out in autumn last year
An issue I ran into was a lot of the documentation is around v1 and when you're googling for stuff you find syntax
for v1 rather than v2
That's obviously going to improve with time and it's not really a fair criticism of a project that it's you know
developing and changing and improving but
what really drew me to traffic was the
kubernetes kind of
Cloud router of the future type sales pitch that they're going for at the moment, but I must say it's it's pretty cool
you know five or six labels in the compose file that define how the traffic gets routed and
It's all in one place and you know from a quick scan. I can see exactly what's going on and
I really like that concept. It's just
Don't know. Maybe I should try to give a bit more of a try chris
I'd be curious to hear what you think. I think it'd be interesting to follow up on it. It's also sort of I think good
Market research for a guy in your day job position
I did see that caddy v2 had a release today as well. So I might go check that out this week
Maybe i'll do a little reverse proxy round up next week. Okay. Yeah, that would be great. Totally
I would I would be I mean, it's we're nerds, but I'm totally down for that
But before we go speaking of new releases pretty excited to see that a roku app
Has landed for jellyfin. We'll have a link to that in the show notes
I'm super duper excited because this is my second jb prediction that's come true this year
I predicted number one that wire guard would be back ported to the
Colonel that released with uh, ubuntu 2004. Yep. You did indeed
I predicted that jellyfin and mb would start upping their app game and start shipping on some major platforms
And I think this is evidence of that so
It's down to the referee, you know, i'm not saying i've won the race yet, but it's looking good
Well, if you want to be impressed by future alex predictions
You can be impressed directly by checking out our discord at self-hosted dot show slash discord. We have a growing active community over there
Also, you get just a little
Additional things that go along with the show information notices. Sometimes alex will drop a great deal
For hardware in there. So self-hosted dot show slash discord if you'd like to send us an email
We'd love to get your emails at self-hosted dot show slash contact and then subscribe
The show is fortnightly and you can find it at self-hosted dot show slash subscribe. And if you want to get more
Pictures of my delicious barbecue meat smoking adventures. I'm on twitter at ironic badger. Yeah, and they are
Very tasty looking I am at chris las
Oh, I didn't mention it in the show, but this entire episode is solar powered completely off grid
I have a little bit of just enough cell connection to do this
And we're watching all of our offline media on my local raspberry pies
It's happened gretta thunberg somewhere is is really happy with you. Good job
I know project off grid is a resounding success even with an overcast sky
We're generating enough solar to top off our battery bank by the end of the day. So no generator
Just solar 100 percent. It's so awesome. So i'll have to maybe i'll post a picture
Up on twitter. That is really cool. I want to buy solar so bad
It's just expensive, you know solar powered self-hosted. So I am at chris las and the show is at self-hosted show
On twitter. Thanks for listening everyone. That was self-hosted 18