This is Linux Unplugged Episode 81 for February 24th, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's in it's time machine and
ready to go in the way back machine to look at some of your favorite topics.
My name is Chris, I'm flying solo this week because it's a disaster here at the Jupiter
Broadcasting.
I'm actually in the bunker right now, you didn't know this, but we have a bunker underneath
the Jupiter Broadcasting Studios.
A hatch opens up here in the studio right about where I'm sitting and I just kind of
fall down into it, it closes and then that's the bunker.
And down here we can only do limited things.
Unfortunately the bunker was installed a while ago and we just have a Tetris arcade machine
in there.
So I can't do a podcast, no actually what it is is that we're just on reduced staff
this week.
So we're going to do a look back because we've been collecting these clips.
Back when we set off to do a best of, we got a whole bunch of your submissions for what
could be a best of Linux Unplugged episode and we only got to use like a super small
handful of them.
And so we've been kicking around ideas of topics we wanted to revisit and look back
at.
So this week I'm going to join you on a journey into the way back machine, we'll look at some
of those topics and revisit some of the classics that you submitted from the audience and we'll
share a few anecdotes together, unbutton our pants towards the end of the show like we
normally do and have a Diet Coke.
Right?
Isn't that what you're doing?
That's what I'm doing.
By a totally impromptu live stream who doesn't even, I don't even tell anybody we're doing
a show right now.
So thank you guys for being here.
I mean, I don't know what the hell you're doing here.
Shouldn't you be at work or something?
What?
Bunch of slackers?
Anyways, we should get on with the show.
So we're going to take a retro look back and I'll join you from time to time to talk about
things.
And we start of course with a classic.
Okay, but this one comes in from Bob.
It's safe territory.
We're not going to get anybody too upset.
He says, hi guys.
Just a quick note, Chris mused that maybe the day is near that you could run with a
machine without a swap partition.
Well this intrigued me and for the last year I've been running my eight gigabyte laptop
with no swap partition and have not noticed any issues even when giving it a pretty thorough
workout.
In fact, it worked so well that I honestly forgot about it.
One thing that had bugged me though was that the Hibernate hasn't been an option on Ubuntu
for me.
I just assumed that it was a config issue or the hardware not being supported.
I found out I could run pm-hibernate command but it would just simply not Hibernate.
My frustration boiled over today and I went digging for clues.
It looks like it may just simply be a case that a swap partition is required for Hibernate
to work as where the memory image is written out before the machine shuts down.
I goled, that's groaned out loud, when I found this out.
I'm not yet, I cannot yet confirm this issue but I thought I'd share experiences for the
benefit of all.
Bab.
Yeah, that is true.
That is true.
That is the downside to running without swap.
And you know, I have a swap.
All my machines have swap right now.
Do you do swap partitions still?
I do.
I mean, and honestly, it's just a legacy habit.
I mean, it's like, it's almost like building machines and putting a floppy to drive in
it.
You do something like out of habit.
It's like, why the hell am I putting this thing in here?
Or actually, Matt, I don't mean to age you but it's now CD-ROMs, Matt.
It's not floppy drives anymore.
What?
It's CD-ROMs now, yeah.
Well, I've got my cassette tape drive sitting right here.
That works.
Magnetic media is the future.
Why hibernate when you can just either suspend or boot?
I mean, what kind of system takes that long to boot anymore?
I don't know.
I'd put it out to the mumble room if anybody in here has a strong feeling on swap partitions.
Anybody in the mumble room running swap free these days?
Yes, kind of.
I use swap files instead.
Yeah, okay.
Can I jump in quickly?
Okay.
You only need swap if you're using a laptop and you want to put it into hibernate.
If you've got more than two gigs of RAM, you do not need swap.
Swap is only used for hibernation.
Well what about crashing?
That's not true.
Yeah.
That's completely incorrect.
Here we go.
And it's on.
Basically-
Yeah, okay.
So let's say you've got three gigs of RAM, what is swap used for?
I use a swap partition in order to compile my kernel.
Usually I don't have like five or six gigs partitioned or put on my rig so I use a-
I knew this would be a hot topic.
But I have 12 gigs of swap.
Even on machines I have 144 gigs of RAM.
Yeah, I do too.
If you have no swap at all, the only negative thing I add is you can't hibernate.
That's it.
No, there's no negative things.
First of all, if you don't have any swap space, as soon as you're out of memory, the kernel
either has to start killing random processes or panic.
There's no other option.
Okay, but you've got four gigs of RAM.
It's not an issue anymore.
Yes, it is.
If I want to gig the swap, I think should be enough.
Just as a safety, I mean if I want to gig, you only have a boot partition or a swap file.
Yeah, exactly.
Oftentimes you'll make the swap only 512 megabytes or something, which is just enough so that
really inactive stuff can get out of your way because any free RAM is wasted RAM.
So you use as much of your RAM as you can for your file system cache and things like
that.
But if the program is completely idle, why have it wasting memory that could be being
used for cache if you could swap it out?
This is my philosophy too.
Yeah, just to be safe.
Having even just that little bit means that a program can be swapped out.
Yeah, but hard drives are a lot slower than RAM, so you want it all in RAM.
Right, but if the program is always idle and its memory is not in use, then it's even worse
than just wasting it.
So you may as well just write it to the disk even if it's slow.
It's not being used.
Who cares if it's slow?
But the important thing is that a lot of applications will adjust their behavior based on memory
pressure.
For example, the XenFS file system will free up some RAM when there's memory pressure.
But for those couple of seconds, while that's happening, there's nowhere for the program
to go.
Whereas if you have even just a little bit of swap, most of the time if you need a swap,
you'll know that you'll need a swap partition.
Otherwise, you can never...
Right, but your Firefox profile is being used, so it's good that you're storing it in RAM,
right?
Yeah, but I stored it in RAM.
I actually stored my Firefox profile in RAM.
Right, but that's good because it's actually fast then.
But that doesn't change the argument about using swap.
It's not an answer.
It works for you.
You may not use more than four gigs of RAM, but there do exist people who use more than
four gigs of RAM.
Yeah.
All right, there you go.
So you can see, I did that as a pure demonstration that this is not a cut and dry topic, right?
That was Chris making a point right there.
I think there's no total right answer other than you should use some swap unless you're
somebody who thinks you shouldn't, and that's really the way to leave it.
Excuse me, and allow me to interrupt here.
I'm coming in from the bunker again with a quick message from some dear friends of the
show.
That's right, our good friends over at Linux Academy.
In fact, go to linuxacademy.com.plug.
That's where they've made a little spot for you, a little home for the Linux Unplugged
audience because you're going to get the special 33% discount on the Linux Academy subscription.
And Linux Academy is a great resource to further your education, but also to challenge yourself
a little bit, just to kind of see what's new because Linux Academy does such a good job
of staying on top of the latest technology developments.
Things that come along that are honestly something that usually takes most shops a while to kind
of get their head around, Docker, all the changes to the virtualization landscape.
And as OpenStack continues to evolve, and as DevOps becomes more of a defined thing,
they're constantly tweaking and adjusting, responding to that.
And they have live stream courses where you can always ask the instructors questions,
and you'll notice immediately during these courses that these are people that truly care
about the subject matter.
And then that's where you start to get the difference, right?
You start to understand that Linux Academy cares a little bit more than everybody else
about the subject matter, and that closes that 10%.
And you really begin to see the value of the Linux Academy system when you get to take
advantage of things like their step-by-step video courses and downloading that content
that you can take offline and read on your own.
That's material that you can refer back to forever.
That's insanely valuable.
And they spin up your own servers as you're going.
Your subscription includes labs, even on AWS if that's what your course is required.
There's seven plus Linux distributions that you can choose from, and I would recommend
one that I haven't suggested for a little while, but you hear it all the time, OpenStack.
Well, what the hell is OpenStack?
Do you know?
They have an OpenStack Essentials course.
Go over to linuxacademy.com and go figure it out, right?
Have you played with Docker?
I mean, you've heard us talk about Docker, but are you familiar with it?
What about Python?
What about backing up your Linux system?
What about deploying NGINX?
Are you familiar with all of these topics, or could you use a refresher?
Have you done it once under a CentOS box, but never done it under an Ubuntu rig?
Because you get to choose from your distribution.
Not only do the virtual machines change, but all of the courseware also automatically adjust
to the seven plus distributions you can choose from.
So you could experience something on one platform, move over to the other distribution, try it
over there.
And the other thing they do that's really cool is they have scenario-based training.
So you get to actually implement these things in a production environment, actually bang
on them from a public address, and really get a feel for the technology ever before
you've gone out and done something where, you know, your job's on the line, or the contract's
on the line, or anything like that.
The scenario-based training is one of the best ways to get hands-on, real-world experience
under the guidance of an instructor.
And it's, once again, a differentiator that they have because they've built this entire
Linux Academy platform from the ground up to match exactly what their vision was.
It's pretty cool.
Go check out their courses on AWS, PHP, OpenStack, Android, Ruby, Python.
It's all really good stuff.
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged.
Get our special 33% discount.
Go see what I've been talking about.
And go enjoy the community, too.
If you ever kind of bottom out a little bit and you're losing motivation, they have a
really good community that'll help pick you back up.
And a lot of them are filled with Jupiter Broadcasting members, too, so that's really
cool.
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged.
And a big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
Big thanks to all of you guys who also visit our sponsors.
Now we'll be down here in the bunker for a little bit longer.
I think I have a can of olives over there and some really old whiskey.
So I should be set.
I'll kick back and we'll watch a little more of this retro spectacular with you.
All right.
Well, let me bring Michael Hall into our restricted casting room here.
And Michael, welcome to Linux Unplugged.
Thank you, guys.
So you had a really great post this morning on your blog, emhall119.com, and you said
it's a new 80-20 rule for open source.
So before we get into that, I noticed, are you trying to do like a blog a day kind of
a thing right now?
Yeah.
There was some conversation at the end of January about the content going on Ubuntu
Planet.
And I didn't come up with it.
I stole this idea of doing a blog a day for a month.
So you're hoping to sort of populate the Ubuntu Planet with some reoccurring content every
day kind of a thing?
Yeah.
I was just trying to get people to kind of blog more actively on it.
So what do you do at Canonical?
Well, as you mentioned earlier, my official title is Upstream Liaison, but I really haven't
been doing a lot of upstream liaising lately.
I've been doing a lot of app developer focus.
Yeah, I bet.
As you guys are ramping up the Ubuntu Touch effort, right?
Yeah.
And the Ubuntu SDK.
It's really a lot of exciting stuff going on.
What has got you most excited right now?
Everything around the app development and the phone.
I mean, I've got a Nexus 4 that's running Ubuntu, and it's been my primary phone since
August of last year.
And just the workflow using the phone is so much better for me than what Android was.
So is that really...
I mean, the essence of that is, you know, because so many people when we talk about
the mobile market, so many people talk about, oh, you know, Android's there, they're the
new Windows, they're dominant, the market's all locked down.
But you're telling me that you sit there, you're using this thing, you're like, you
know what, this works for me.
And that's what's got you excited.
It's like, I see this fitting into my workflow.
And do you think this is like a whole new generation of opportunity for Ubuntu?
I think it is.
And the thing we have over everybody else in the market right now is that we're running
the same software on the phone as we are on the desktop.
So it's not like, you know, you've got completely different platforms like you do with the iOS
and OSX, or even Windows and Windows Phone.
And of course, you know, Android, there's not even anything on a desktop space with
Android.
There's Chrome OS.
So being able to have just the one platform on all the devices, being able to have the
same apps on all your devices, it really changes the experience of it.
So changing gears to your blog post here, I know you've been active at Canonical for
a long time.
You've been in the open source community for, do you have a rough estimation of like how
long you've been in?
I've been involved with the Ubuntu community for probably six, seven years now.
And so you've had time from that perspective to sort of notice trends as they come and
go, you know, the big hoopla's of the week that sometimes last multiple weeks, sometimes
fizzle out fairly quick.
And I thought, you know, you had a really poignant piece when you wrote here on your
blog, people tend to appreciate it more when you only give them 20% of something.
And then they resent you if you give them 80%.
Let's unpack that a little bit.
When you say people resent you, people appreciate it more when you give them 20%, that sounds
crazy to me.
That sounds like that sounds ludicrous.
What do you mean by that?
Well, it does sound ludicrous.
But what I realized is that at some point past the 50% mark, I just chose 80-20 because
you know, the 80-20 rule is a common thing.
But at some point after you've given them more than half, people start to think of it
as something that they're entitled to or something that already belongs to them.
And so instead of looking at what you're giving them, they're paying more attention to what
you're not giving them.
Oh, interesting.
So it's sort of like what Matt was saying, it's one part expectations and two part what
have you done for me lately?
Yeah, it is.
And as people have mentioned on my blog, there's another aspect of that and that's, you know,
what direction are you changing in?
I mean, if somebody goes from giving 10% to giving 20%, that's better than somebody who's
gone from giving 90% to giving 80%.
And that's a valid criticism of my original blog post is that the direction of change
does matter as much as where you're currently at.
Sure, sure.
But I think this is fascinating in the recent light of Firefox's announcement of enabling
ads on their new tab page.
And part of it, like Matt made a very good point last on Sunday, that part of it is honestly
how they announced it.
And part of it is I think that the phenomenon that you're writing about on your blog is
that, wait a minute, you're telling me I've gotten this thing all this time for absolutely
free, with no ads attached.
You guys are the anti NSA, anti ad tracking cookie organization on the internet and now
you want to ram ads down my throat?
How dare you?
This maybe while it doesn't surprise all of us, Michael, how do you combat something like
that?
Because Firefox has got to make money.
What can Firefox do?
It's really a tough question.
I mean, obviously it's a question that we've been trying to figure out in Canonical also.
And I think a lot of it is getting the messaging right.
But a lot of it is just the community needs to understand that every project is going
to have missteps.
And if somebody has been doing 80, 90 percent right for so long, you have to be a little
more gentle when they have those missteps.
Well, let me give you an example.
So Linux Unplugged, this very show that we are currently recording at this very moment,
is a symptom of this problem that you're talking about.
I knew that I needed to make changes, even just from a creative expression standpoint,
to the Linux action show.
But I also knew that we had a really great product that was firing on all cylinders and
has a ton of runway still.
And I knew that if I changed that product to what this show is, there would be massive
upset.
And so my solution was to create an entirely new product.
Now that has been wildly successful for multiple reasons, but it was exactly this kind of pressure.
And we made the mistake years ago with the Linux action show when we decided to broaden
the scope and change it to the computer action show.
And we basically took a beating for an entire season over that decision because we had changed
the product.
And the problem is, is at some times, at some level, you've got to change the product.
Apple, they changed the product with Final Cut.
They changed the product with the Mac Pro.
Two recent products from Apple that are used in professional industries, completely gutted
and redesigned from the ground up with less functionality, but yet in the long term will
probably be better off for it.
As somebody who uses Final Cut for editing, I can tell you, everybody who uses Final Cut
10 as crap hasn't used it recently.
I just recently went back to the old Final Cut.
It's like going back to the 90s.
It's like when you've been using Gnome 3 or Unity and you go back to Gnome 2, it feels
like you've gone back in time.
And sometimes, a lopping off like this, a major change, implementing ads, implementing
the Amazon search scope is necessary for the sustainability of the project.
The very people who depend on the project are then the ones that turn around on the
project and attack them.
What can a project do, do you think, in your opinion, to communicate that change better
so that way they can sort of preempt some of that attack?
So a lot of it has to do with the messaging that goes into it.
But another thing that I've noticed that I didn't really expand on in my blog is that
there's a difference in reaction between people who are just users of the project and people
who are contributors of the project.
And people who are contributing seem to be more understanding, be more willing to work
out an ideal solution instead of just jumping on the, oh my god, you're evil now bandwagon.
So I guess what I don't understand is why can a company, just using my example I set
up here, why can a company like Apple reboot something, cut away tons of functionality,
and be called an innovator, but if an open source project does the same thing, they're
crazy, they've lost their way, they're evil, they're whatever people are accusing, Canonical
or Mozilla of that week.
It seems to me, Canonical has people that deal with PR, they've got a pretty good presence
online, and yet they have been unable to get in front of this.
Mozilla, same thing, they have an entire crew that works there, and they were still unable
to get in front of this.
Matt, I want to ask you, because I know you've worked in this space before, what are these
people missing?
What is Mozilla missing in this case?
What did they do wrong?
What should they have done before the news came out?
Well, the big difference between Mozilla and Apple is Apple sells experiences, Mozilla
offers a browser.
A lot of people think that Apple is a computer company or a technology company.
They're not.
They're a PR company, pure and simple.
They've mastered this years ago.
They could literally be like, hey, we have this iHome invasion thing where we're going
to come in and basically invade your house and ransack everything you own.
People are going to be excited about it because they can present it in a way that's attractive.
What Mozilla needed to do when they came out with their whole advertising thing for browsers
and what not is they really needed to get in front of this and say, here's our rationale.
Here's how we've been supporting ourselves thus far.
Here's what we're challenged with.
This is what we're planning on doing.
We would like to have an open forum debate about this and actually get all the questions
out in the open and really have a conversation about it, but at the same time, we need you
to understand why we're doing it, why it is or is not a threat, why you should or should
not be concerned, and to quit treating people like they need to be talked at and actually
talk to them.
It's something that historically geekier companies don't do real well at.
Google, Mozilla, two real big offenders in that space, probably Google being the worst.
I see it over and over and it's something that's not really addressed very well.
I've seen other companies do this as well, but I'd say Apple, honestly, as much as I'm
not a big fan of their company, they can spin anything.
Right.
They control the narrative from the very beginning.
Absolutely.
Props to import.
I mean, really.
They know how to do it.
But other than everybody yelling at how horrible Apple is about it, let's look at what they're
doing right.
I mean, the products aren't kind of meh, but as far as their marketing techniques, come
on.
Let's get with it.
So, Michael, what do you think about like, so if we don't have the means and resources
of a company like Apple, these smaller, even Mozilla would fall into the smaller category.
What about being just more direct?
And I'm not asking you as a representative canonical here.
I'm asking just your personal opinion of somebody who's been following open source for many
years now.
Do you think that if a company like Canonical come out and said, hey, we're doing these
Amazon placements in our dashboard results because, honestly, we got to generate a revenue
from the desktop in order to keep it sustainable?
Or if Mozilla had come out, maybe let's take a more recent example.
If Mozilla had come out and said, look, guys, we can't have all our eggs in the Google basket.
We respect our relationship with Google and we appreciate the financing they've given
us so far, but we've got to diversify because this browser is more important than one contract
with one company.
And we've got to implement these ads to come up with a new source of revenue.
If they had just been totally straight, plain English like that, do you think things would
have gone over better?
I think it would have helped.
But I mean, you're always going to have people who would rather see your project go down
in flames than have you backtrack a little bit from their ideal.
And you're always going to deal with that.
There's no way to explain things sufficiently for those people.
But one thing we did do, when we came out with the Amazon lens in 12.10, it just kind
of landed out of the blue with no explanation of why it was there or what it does.
And we're still dealing with that even today.
But then the next release, we came out with the broader SmartScope service.
And we came out first with a public spec on our Wiki.
We held multiple Google Hangouts that were recorded explaining what the feature was going
to be and what it was going to do and how it's going to work.
And the security improvements.
Yeah.
And that certainly helped.
I mean, if you can get the narrative right from the start, that helps.
As soon as the FUD comes in and establishes itself, you're going to spend all of your
time just trying to-
Fighting that.
Yeah.
Just trying to fight that.
Boy, that is a really well-taken point.
And I wish there was a way to sort of reinforce this with the open source community.
Because I'll give you another recent example I talked about on Coda Radio yesterday.
I want to say friend of the show, although he's never come on.
I'd love to have him join us.
But Martin, who is responsible for the Kaywin project, he continues to battle this problem.
We talked about it several weeks ago here on the show, where the media grabs a headline
from the KDE mailing list and just runs with it.
And we inaccurately reported that the KDE Next release date.
But more recently, and because of my lessons learned, did not run it in last, thankfully.
But more recently, Ferronix ran a story that the KDE search system, it was a waste of money
and that it's being abandoned in favor of something completely else, which is inaccurate
in total.
And of course, not everything is being abandoned.
And of course, Recode is going to be repurposed.
But again, they're fighting a battle that you just touched on, Michael, where they're
responding to a narrative that somebody else created for them.
And this is happening more and more for open source projects because, and this goes back
to something else I've been really getting on recently, the coverage in Linux and the
open source space is going downhill.
It's becoming industrialized and it's not original reporting, it's reposting based on
what a corporation wants you to post and it's getting worse and there's agendas involved
and it's getting to the point where not all of the information is coming out and the press
is not giving the actual narrative a chance to get aired out.
The only narratives that are getting repeated by the media are the ones that get created
first.
And this is a massive problem that is plaguing Linux and open source and it affects the way
the entire open source community perceives events, I believe.
And I think it's one of the things that I want to set out to help correct on our platforms
any shows that we have is that I want to try to give the actual real narrative a chance
to get some air time because nobody else seems to be doing it.
And that's why I really, that's why I wanted to bring you on Michael because I really appreciate
the fact that you're, even if, you know, there are some things I could disagree with on your
post here and you've actually generated a very active discussion on our subreddit.
People are taking issue with minimizing the CLA and things like that.
But I want to save the CLA discussion for a future episode.
I'll just say, I want to thank you for bringing this topic out to a broader discussion because
I think the problem really has to be solved with the actual consumers of these open source
projects.
It is our responsibility to consider the long term viability of these projects.
I extend that to our own projects and our advertisers and why we have ad supported media
because that makes it sustainable.
I think we have to consider the software we consider valuable and when they make changes
we have to understand that sometimes they're doing it for their best interest in the case
of the Mozilla project and perhaps even in the case of the Dash Lens results.
And I think in that context your post, while I think there's plenty of things people could
quibble with, it definitely provokes some interesting thoughts.
So thank you for coming on Linux Unplugged today.
Is there anything else you wanted to touch on before we wrap up?
No, I think that's it.
Oh welcome back friends to the bunker.
It's good down here.
It's starting to smell a little bit.
So I think that's Ricai.
I'm not trying to say my ass doesn't stink but that doesn't smell like mine.
I know what mine smells like.
Hey you know what else I know?
Digital Ocean and they freaking rock.
That's why I know Digital Ocean.
They're keeping our bunker online.
They're also keeping the rest of the world online while we're down here.
I don't even know what's going on up there right now but I know my droplets run all the
time.
I've never even experienced an outage and Digital Ocean has some great, great systems
for you to deploy right now that run Linux powered by KVM all on top of the sweetest
hardware you could ever imagine.
It's a thrill just to use it.
You go over to digitalocean.com and I want you to arm yourself with a little bit of knowledge.
Okay?
Are you ready for this?
Because this knowledge is going to save you money.
I'm all about that.
I want you to go play around.
I don't want you to have to pay for it.
So use this knowledge right now.
You ready?
Open the spot up in your brain.
Put it in the vault.
DO unplugged.
All lowercase.
One word.
DO unplugged.
Ten dollar credit over Digital Ocean.
You put that in the vault now.
I'm going to tell you about Digital Ocean and then you remember that's why Chris had
me put it in the vault.
Digital Ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy way for you.
You to spin up your own cloud server.
You're going to have root access to that bad mamma jamma.
It's going to be sitting on top of Linux boxes on tier one hardware.
It's just so sweet with fantastic bandwidth and all on SSDs.
I mean it's great.
It's so great.
You can get started in less than a minute and pricing plans start only five dollars
a month for 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU and a terabyte of transfer.
A terabyte of freaking transfer.
I mean I've got my own cloud up on one of these things.
I never go close to that.
Digital Ocean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam
and London.
They're gorgeous data centers.
As somebody who's put up a lot of really messy data centers that I'm totally ashamed of and
would never want to take a picture of because the wiring mess is absolutely a rat's nest
of disaster.
When I see what they build over at Digital Ocean by checking out their Instagram feed
I'm like oh shoot.
Oh shoot they're showing me up.
Digital Ocean totally shows me up.
Go look at their data center port on their Instagram feed and then check out that interface.
This is really the masterpiece.
This is where it all comes together.
This is like the icing on top.
Their interface is so simple but powerful.
It can get anything done you want, backups, snapshots, redeployments, DNS management,
one click applications, destroying machines, changing the root password, HTML5 access all
the way from post to your login screen.
And the best part?
They have an API you can use and that API just basically replicates all of the function
but you know you want to snap it into your puppet system, go ahead.
You can do that.
You know you just want to write a bash script that'll deploy machines when you need to scale.
Or you can be like me and just take advantage of the tons of great things that the community
already builds.
It's really sweet.
Digital Ocean also has a ton of great tutorials.
Check them out.
They're good for everybody.
I mean it's just Linux commands and they're always adding more as well.
So remember, DO Unplugged.
That's one word.
DO Unplugged.
You're going to get a $10 credit.
You can go try out that $5 rig.
Two months, no credit card required and my gosh what a thrill it is.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go over there.
Try it out right now.
Thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show.
It is keeping the lights on down in the bunker.
Now we return you back to our retro extravaganza.
So I'm going to pull Aaron back down into our private little room here and hopefully
he wasn't in the middle of saying something to the group.
So Aaron, let's talk a little bit about, you got kind of fired up when you were watching
the episode that we did recently in Defense of Gnome and I think you really called me
out on something that I was actually sort of kicking myself for.
And that was sort of the celebration of new and shiny and rebuilt to have a rebuilt purpose.
And you sort of brought up this counterpoint and said, well, what about this methodology
of refinement and evolution and working with something and staying with it for a while
and building on top of a platform, building on top of something.
And that isn't almost in some cases really even respected in the community.
What are your thoughts and share a little bit about what got you fired up?
Sure.
So just to make it clear for everybody right off the top, I'm not wearing my KDE hat at
all here.
This is really me with my free software must rule the world one day hat on.
And it's this exact idea that, yeah, you know, new and shiny is awesome.
And yeah, I mean, it is new and shiny is awesome.
But there's cost to everything that we do in new and shiny.
Every rewrite, every new adventure comes with a cost.
So when you make a bunch of applications and you decide we're just going to redo them all,
you end up with, you know, being able to get the first 90 percent of functionality or 80
percent of functionality fairly quickly.
And then you spend, you know, the rest of the 90 percent of the development time getting
the 10 to 20 percent that people actually need for it to become a reasonable application.
And when we toss these things aside, you know, applications that work and that have reached
this point of maturity, what we might do is we might deliver something with marginally
better visuals or a slightly better workflow.
But in the meantime, our users tend to be left with locations that don't have the features
they need.
And what happens from a developer's point of view, who works on free software quite
a bit, there is a real constant pressure from a lot of people, especially the attention
areas of our community, you know, the media and whatnot, to always be producing something
new and flashy and cool.
And it's more reward for promising something wonderful and starting off by scrapping whatever
you have right now.
At the same time, we also get our feet held to the fire if it isn't stable and if it isn't
performant and if it doesn't have the features that people need.
You're talking earlier about, you know, is the Linux desktop ready for the average person?
Well, it never will be if we keep reinventing things every few years.
And so there's this conflict, right?
These two motivations don't really jowl well together.
And this is both part of what new free software developers coming into it are bred and born
on.
So they come into it with this expectation of, oh, we need to redo things so it's sexy
and cool or go the other way and be hyper conservative.
There's no middle ground.
And meanwhile, those projects that try and hit a middle ground, I think, come under a
lot of unnecessary pressure on the one hand, but also just get overlooked a lot for trying
to be going through cycles of innovation, but then also going through longer cycles
of stability and support.
So just to kind of track this to a level where people would kind of recognize it down to
the desktop, I would say, for me, I do kind of understand what you're saying in the sense
that I look at the GNOME desktop and their reboot has cost them, I believe, not only
untold users, but years of basically progress on the desktop.
I would say that while they've obviously been working very hard, it's really now getting
to a point where I'm comfortable using it on a daily basis.
That wasn't...
I mean, if you look at the years it took to get there, that's a big reset, and it kind
of came at an inappropriate time, right when Microsoft was stumbling with Vista.
There was sort of...
I've always felt like this golden opportunity where Linux could have succeeded a little
bit stronger, where perhaps if Canonical hadn't rebooted with Unity, and Unity was really
quite awful at the beginning, and if GNOME hadn't restarted with GNOME 3, which GNOME
3.0 was really quite unusable at the beginning, we might have had a little more traction perhaps.
So then you look at it now, and these projects are getting to a good state, but one of them
is about to face another reboot.
And I see there's projects where sometimes there'd be value in starting over, and then
there's other projects where I see it almost feels a little sad because so much effort
and time will be lost while they rebuild and retrace things that they have already once
completed and already once figured out.
Exactly, and when these projects get to the point of, okay, finally they're usable again,
I can use them on a daily basis, have they really progressed the technology sufficiently
to offset that cost?
And I think with the wild abandon that we embrace new and shiny with at times, we tend
to destroy that.
I mean, the biggest problem I had with something like PulseAudio, for instance, was not that
we needed a non-crappy audio stack, but that it was pushed onto the user community when
it wasn't ready can be clearly seen by years of troubles that people had.
There was literally a distribution that shipped where the volume slider didn't do anything.
As crappy as the Linux audio stack was, it finally worked for most people.
Yeah, exactly.
And so we seem to be, as you said, picking really bad times to reinvent things and doing
it for what will deliver marginal benefit, if any, at the end of the day.
See here's the thing, it's this interesting culture that's driven, and I feel like it's
more than just one thing that attributes to this, but from a media production standpoint,
like from the Linux action show, people are going to be much more interested in something
brand new that they want to learn about than sort of retracing how great it is that every
application I use under KDE has a proper notification icon on the system tray.
That's an example of how staying stable and just having something and defining the way
it works and keeping it that way for years benefits end users, but it doesn't make for
a good segment in a podcast and it doesn't make for a good article on a blog.
And so I do agree that that is driving the conversation in one direction, but at the
same time that's because that's what the consumers of that content want to hear about, right?
And the developers that are going into these projects, they don't want to work on the old
guys old busted code, they want to come up with their new hot concepts and bring those
on the world.
So that's their motivation.
It's like this multi-dimensional problem that just sort of is maybe human nature.
No, I agree.
And so on the one hand, we need to not reward those developers who just want to come in
with a wrecking ball or at least reward them a lot less for doing that if they're not bringing
any real large offsetting value to it.
The other side of it is, yeah, how do we present mature projects as interesting?
And I agree it requires a little more positioning and thinking and most free software projects
and most people involved in free software are not great self promoters and marketers.
And so yeah, I completely get that new is an easier story, it writes itself.
On the other hand, if you look at, so a product that I've been involved with for years was
Plasma, which most people know as a desktop environment.
And it gets to the point where it's mature enough that we can actually start branching
off and doing things like Plasma Active where we can bring in devices.
And this whole convergence story that has been really exciting for people around Unity
is actually where we were three or four years ago.
Now the question is, why didn't that story get out in a more interesting way?
Why doesn't it keep people's attention?
And I'm sure there's probably things that I could have done differently or better to
make it more interesting.
But on the other hand, I also think that there's a kind of an expectation you can only tell
a story once.
And I think that the convergence story, for example, is one that has a lot of legs if
we can keep ourselves kind of moderately entertained and interested.
And companies like Google, for instance, there's a bunch of people talking pre-show about things
like Chromebooks.
And what we don't realize with these things is that, or I don't think consciously, is
that they bang on the same boring message for like five years before people get it.
And when people get it, it's new and exciting to them.
But you have to bang those old messages through.
And I think that hurts the free software adoption as well because we don't have the patience
to bang the message through.
That usually takes two, three years.
And so what happens is we get projects that are less interesting to people.
And until someone comes along with the wrecking ball and erects the new Shiny that is not
usable anymore, they don't get the attention.
And so we kind of catch ourselves in the spiral.
You also have these companies that some people in the development communities idolize, Apple,
where you'll see Apple from time to time completely reboot a product, even if it's a high-end
product like Final Cut or the Mac Pro, into something brand new and just say, suck it.
You take it or you don't take it, and this is the way it is.
And I think in some weird, creepy way that messages to people that that's an OK thing
to do.
You see Apple doing it and some people hold that in some level of regard.
And so it seems to me too that there is a bit of commercial...
The commercial companies like Google and Apple are also sort of driving this mentality a
bit.
And it takes a certain wisdom to sort of see past that and be still motivated to work on
something that is tried and true.
How do you incentivize somebody to want to do that?
Well, I think that most tried and true software, how do I say this politely, has areas that
suck after a number of years.
Software doesn't stand up to the test of time if you don't change it.
And so right now I'm involved in rerunning one small part of a project that I'm involved
with that's...
It's a rewrite of one small component and it's very interesting and it will bring important
value to the users.
It's not a rewrite of everything.
So I think on the one hand, finding ways to create a culture of you don't have to rewrite
everything.
Make your software a little bit more modular with a more forward looking design, which
is something that we need to teach each other how to do.
And then you can do incremental important evolutionary work where you can talk about
it.
I mean, my blogs in the last two weeks have featured quite a few times this component
that I'm rewriting and people are finding it very interesting and exciting.
And it's done in a very low risk way.
The other thing is that there are tons of topics that free software does not touch,
does not cover.
We don't need to be rewriting the image viewer application every two years.
Let that topic area go and let's find the other 8 million application categories that
we have no answer for and create a new shiny there instead of just chasing our tails.
So maybe that's just me.
Maybe we actually do have a complete software catalog, but last time I checked we didn't.
Well, so I guess if you kind of zoom out a little bit and you look at the whole free
software ecosystem, there's certain aspects of like Linux itself have had pretty even
curved development and stability and also innovation.
The Linux kernel has then been adopted by every company under the sun to power their
product and I think that speaks to sort of what you're talking about when you have a
group of people that just stay at it and keep building it.
Don't keep throwing it all out and restarting again.
It gives people certain assurances.
But because that hasn't happened really at the user space as much, we haven't seen a
stabilizing there.
And so you see these, we had a great thread in the Linux action show subreddit saying
why has Linux on the desktop failed?
He looks at, this was Ersk in the chat room, he looks at the market shares.
Linux is at 1.73% according to NetMarketShare.com and he says, regardless of the distro, it's
at 1.73% while XP is 12 years later still at 29% market share.
One of the reasons this could be the popularity of XP in Asia of course and things like that,
but honestly XP was this quote unquote stable in terms of it's an easy target for developers
to quantify, develop for.
And I wonder if perhaps, remember when Miguel Itacazo wrote that the problem with the Linux
desktop was always changing and always incompatibilities always being brought in.
I wonder if he sort of nailed it in a sense where like what we really need is something,
now I know I'm just going to sound like I'm blowing smoke up the KDE project, but we need
something like KDE 4.x that is just what you see is what you get for years.
Like it's like this for, it's snapshotted like this for years, much like Unity will
be in the current, in the next LTS release.
Does Linux need a little XP-ification right now?
I think so and this can be done without ossifying or fossilizing things either.
Now you brought the Linux kernel, I completely agree with what you said about it and why
it's successful.
The thing, but the Linux kernel is like this massive constant churn, so it's not like they're
sitting still and moribund, they've managed to marry the two.
So a really good example I think of this in the user space is so we've had the whole many
years of Udev, U disks, basically the hot plug and disk management facing the user space
side has gone through a number of revolutions and not always, in fact at each break it was
a radical API change.
So what the KDE developers did was they decided to create an API that did what application
developers could wrap their head around because the lower level user space APIs were also
pretty hardcore for the average person who just wants to write a cool game or something.
So they created a slightly simplified API but they masked what was going on down below
and this yes, it's opened up the ability to port to Windows and Mac and now iOS and Android.
But when the U disk thing came in while other desktop environments like XFCE for instance
had to do a lot of work to catch up their applications and rewrite them, no KDE application
had to line a code, a new backend was written for that framework called Solid and everything
just continued working.
Even more magical, no one got left behind because the people who were using the old
stuff used the old backend and the people using the new stuff used the new backend and
no one was stranded on an old version.
So it is possible to do but it takes forethought and I think that Miguel de Caso was correct
in his criticism or his critique except that we do have projects and communities out there
that do exactly what he said we should be doing.
And the challenge we face is that the community as a whole on the one hand I don't think recognizes
that.
When someone does something like Solid, there's a certain community or group of people in
the community who hurl stones saying you're just writing yet another abstraction layer
and you should be writing to the Linux stack directly and that's the way to go.
And so there's a popular backlash against doing the responsible thing and I think as
a community we need to take stock of what really matters.
And if we do want to get that stable, approachable user land and especially at the GUI level,
we need to start valuing that kind of work that isn't very glamorous but pays off in
the long run and we need to start supporting those people.
And the people who don't do that, maybe we should say look I love you guys and you guys
are doing free software which is freaking awesome but you know what?
We need you to do it responsibly and so we're going to go over here and support these people
that are looking at five, ten years down the road.
And I think if we did that, if we shifted what we value, everybody would start doing
things a little more responsibly and then I think the whole new shiny thing would resolve
itself because people tend to do by and large that which is rewarded.
Matt, let me ask you the million dollar question and then I'll open it up to the mumble room.
How do we shift the end user's value which would hopefully then influence developers
and media coverage, how do we shift the value from new and shiny to tried and true?
Well I think the opportunity definitely lays with XP.
The problem is that the end user looks at XP not realizing the fact that it's going
to be a major problem here in the coming months and doesn't see a reason to switch.
But I think if you speak to the fact that they could potentially continue to use the
hardware they already have without having to invest in new hardware, I think money is
really going to be the sweet spot.
Yeah I think the point you're driving at here is there's a certain class of user that absolutely
values tried and true and then there's a certain class of user, the more sophisticated user
who maybe is a little more on the I want the shiny, right?
Exactly.
That's exactly it.
And I think that it's really hard to hit that nail on the head but I think the biggest problem
Linux has for both groups is they really suck at marketing.
I mean I can't stress that enough.
They have this amazing product that is driven through very much an echo chamber world.
I mean it really is and it's a shame because like I introduce it to people and they're
just blown away as to why the hell they've never heard of this before and they have an
Android phone.
They have no idea.
So it's interesting.
So it's going to be tough to say for sure but I definitely say that it's going to be
the real opportunity for growth that's going to come from the people that are using XP.
I think that's really where it is.
The new and shiny people honestly I don't know.
Maybe they're always going to want new and shiny.
Yeah that's like trying to herd cats.
I don't know about that.
Well I think we can do both but I do completely agree with you Matt when you say that people
who want the tried and true, how do we market to them?
And that's the gap, the marketing bit.
And this is kind of what tweets me when I listen to your show and I'm often like one
or two weeks behind that I've been on the Linux action show to catch up.
And it's what tweets me about it right was it was like you guys are the people who market
us best because we do suck at it, full stop.
And so when I see people who would be our best and brightest in terms of getting the
message out of marketing, rewarding really and for good intentions I think the new and
shiny because you all want to support and push for everything.
I mean nobody wants to be the grumpy guy who goes well you're really putting your heart
and soul into this and I can see that and you're doing this free software but really
no one wants to be that guy.
I get it.
But if we want to succeed there is some level of responsibility that needs to come in and
the people who do the best marketing for us who is not me and the other software developers,
we need you guys and not just you two but the media in general who follows free software
to do it.
And what goes even one step further of pain and heartache is when I read certain people
in the media who cover free software basically going fine, okay great.
The free software projects will never get together and again this is a systems thing
because we've been rewarding the wrong things all along, fine.
And now I'm just going to say that Google with their services are where it will be and
to me that feels like just running the white flag straight up the flagpole and unnecessarily
and I just I'd love to find some way to break that feedback loop so that we can start rewarding
strategically useful behavior and then getting that message out to those people who would
most benefit from it such as the XP crowd.
It's not an easy thing that I realize that's a gigantic thing to take on but I think that's
the path of success lies in that direction somehow.
Very good.
That's a good point.
It's well taken on my end too because it's something that it's definitely on my radar
because I always cringe a little bit when like you say I have that same feeling.
It's like okay it's good that you're doing this and I really appreciate the hard work
and especially in the Gnome case it's like for years everybody's been so hard on them.
Like okay they've finally gotten it to a state to a point that it's okay it's worth talking
about now it's really gotten good but at the same time like in the back of my mind it's
like you know I'm I do understand that I'm sort of encouraging like I called it a form
of consumerism and I'm not generally comfortable with those all those kinds of things.
Oh hey guys.
We weren't.
Rekai put that out Rekai put that out man they can smell it and we weren't doing nothing
down here we're just hanging out.
Oh you guys still watching that retro thing?
Hey well I got you for a second can I tell you about how good the Ting service is down
here in the bunker?
I mean Ting is incredible and Ting is a sponsor of the Linux Unplugged Show in fact you can
get in on some of that goodness by going to linux.ting.com so not only does linux.ting.com
support this here show but it's going to get you a $25 discount off your first Ting device
that matters and it also if you've got a Ting compatible device you can bring your own device
well they're going to give you a $25 credit so you're going to win either way and you
support the Linux Unplugged Show.
Now what is Ting?
My mobile service provider and Matt's mobile service provider Ting is mobile that makes
sense because there's no contract there's no early termination fee but the big one for
me is I'm only paying for what I use it's flat six dollars for each line and then you
just pay for your usage on top of that Ting will just add that up and that's what you
pay at the end of the month so I've got three lines I've got an HTC one I've got an iPhone
5 and I have got my Nexus 5 and on there I usually pay somewhere in the range of 35 to
40 dollars for all three lines all smartphones they're all ready to go with hotspot and tethering
you just turn it on when you want it they have an incredible dashboard that allows you
to manage all of that and they have no hold customer service you can call and talk to
a real human between 8 a.m. and 8 p.m. East Coast time you call them one eight five five
Ting FTW and a real person answers the phone they got a great range of devices value devices
like flip phones all the way up to like the best the best or you can just get a SIM and
just go grab like a Nexus 6 from the Google Play Store and put it in there and the dashboard
really brings it all together they've got mobile apps they've got a very fantastic web
app that's web compliant they've really done a very good job with that and I think the
best thing about Ting is they're also a company that I'm pretty comfortable my money goes
to and I've never said that about a telco before but Ting isn't like a telco they're
they're mobile and they're different and so when I think about Ting I think it's you must
be very challenging being in this industry but yet being so different and they happen
to answer just that very question in a recent video Ryan asks what were the biggest challenges
in creating a wireless company what is the most difficult part of maintaining such low
rates for us the most difficult parts of building a wireless service were finding a good carrier
partner availability to offer the network and being able to initially build the systems
that supported what we're doing you really need a great back office to provide great
customer service so the easy part was conceiving of it imagining all of the bits and pieces
knowing that we wanted to provide a great customer experience you know the hard part
was really putting together the wiring now that that's together all of the challenge
is around getting as many people as possible on the platform linux.ting.com go get on
that platform finally put your money somewhere where maybe it doesn't make you want to hate
yourself a little bit linux.ting.com it truly is mobile that makes sense and I'll tell you
down here in the bunker we can't recommend any other mobile it is the best mobile provider
linux.ting.com also I know is mobile service provider for the Linux action show really
the whole team here at Jupiter Broadcasting has been using it and now that they're going
GSM as well shoot linux.ting.com go join up and start savings and check out their savings
calculator it's linked right there on the front page when you go to linux.ting.com and
that might just finally help you realize the difference also if you're having like a spousal
debate about it this giving numbers like this getting data on your difference you put in
your current usage you compare it to what ting would be and you know then they'll say
over the life of the two years this is what you're going to save and when you see that
number like I did and you see that number it's pretty easy to switch and they also have
an early termination relief program that makes it even better linux.ting.com big thanks to
ting for sponsoring the linux unplugged program I'm going to jump back into my cozy it's honestly
it's not that cozy it actually has a hole in it and I think Rekai spilled some chili
on it but I got nonetheless a sleeping bag I'm going to jump back in while you watch
the rest of the retrospective our last bit of feedback this week comes in from Dakota
Dakota writes in about Linux in schools and says I'm 15 years old I've been using Linux
for a year now I've done stuff from write my own code to compiling a custom kernel on
Ubuntu I think we as a community should start a petition to get open source into more schools
and like you talked about on unplugged with the same other teens I think the school should
actually teach you something useful if computer in the computer in IT classes it's really
sad when there are kids out there like me who can teach the class better than a teacher
you know that sentiment teaching the class better than the teacher which can come across
a little bit like the youngster knowing more than the teacher and you know these damn kids
but in the same sense like I remember one of the reasons I wasn't super spun up about
taking more college level courses is because I quickly felt like I was outflanking my teachers
and knew more than they did and it was frustrating when the teacher would incorrectly cover something
or say something wrong or use the wrong terminology or you know right system D with a capital
D or you know bad example but you know what I'm saying like it it is very frustrating
for these students so and essentially because we got a lot more emails and the ones I just
read on air and a lot of them iterated that point and there's a situation a trend of young
people saying hey you know don't don't give up on our generation we're here we're talking
we're sharing we're teaching others that are willing to learn maybe not the teachers but
right you know certainly other students I'm almost coming to the conclusion that I think
the future of Linux on the desktop in a non-enterprise situations perhaps at home will be with young
people I think that that much like how Firefox had its adoption spread I think it's going
to be young people that make it interesting like mom and dad screwed up the computer let
me replace the OS with something that works just like these two at the browser be like
oh mom and dad you're not using Firefox this is what your problem is let me fix that for
you right yeah yeah you know what you might be right about that Matt I would say too when
I think about this you know looking at these these kids that are really smart I think that
really there's two things that we have to realize is that younger Linux users will find
resources that we have out there for the adults like these shows like these shows like when
we make these you know we don't really have a specific age group in mind but we're definitely
not trying to target a younger demographic but yet they still obviously we have an audience
that represent that they you know they represent a percentage of the audience that's this noticeable
and they are finding the same resources that we create for adults and I don't think we
have to get in this mindset that we have to do something very special for the kids I think
smart savvy kids that are told it is okay self-education is an old is an okay thing
if we can you know because a lot of kids I felt when I was in school I felt the internet
was new right and it was untrusted and there was pushback from my teachers when I would
self research and self educate like I can't rely on that you don't know if you're teaching
yourself the right thing you're not smart enough to figure it out on your own you need
our guidance is really what they were saying and I now looking back on that I resent that
because self-education is a fantastic tool and the internet empowers people to teach
themselves things on their own in their own room don't you think I think that's I think
you really nailed on something there even bigger than just the experiences that you
had I think that the problem is is it was a change it represented the changing of a
guard to where it was no longer teachers who were the teachers essentially and they no
longer were the power player or had all the knowledge that there's this new new thing
of an angle thing that kids were quite frankly more adept to than the adults were I was at
that time when this was happening I was pretty much out of my own and out of school and whatnot
but I witnessed us happening a lot just in society that there seemed to be a real shift
and so I think that that's probably a lot of what you were experiencing yeah and I think
maybe that could still be there could be a little bit of that still in play today because
some of those same teachers are still in and they really are aren't they yeah so I think
you know if we tell these if we tell these teenagers and kids that hey you know dude
and do that it's fine go out there and learn on your own you go teach yourself you don't
have to have somebody's blessing to become educated on a topic I think the Linux community's
pride blinds them from seeing the real threat I think maybe we also still see Microsoft
as the threat but I think the reality is the real competition is Apple I think it's I think
from all they have they have compelling hardware that people a lot of people like not everybody
the fact that they can sell so many computers that ethernet ports blows my mind but it's
a thing apparently and they they offer sort of at least the idea of a turnkey computing
solution and I think that is I want to I want to sort of keep that in mind as we talk about
the overall Linux community's abrasiveness sometimes when it comes to issues that they're
passionate about and Matt you touched on this in an article you wrote for DataMation saying
is Ubuntu animosity misplaced kind of from a high level like what's the concept here
basically I'm looking at it from this perspective I always take the Ubuntu perspective for two
reasons one it's what my editor would prefer and secondly it still covers most of the Linux
universe just by default anyway so it's really a mood issue in that regard but the point
is is that a lot of people come into Linux and people I introduced to Linux they go to
the forums they go to these different places or especially on the social media sites and
they see a lot of real negative behavior I mean it's really unfortunate the kind of stuff
you would expect to see in a Windows form you know you like to think you got away from
I got away from that but in the Linux space it can be really prevalent and for a lot of
people to turn off but also going deeper than that I feel like that so what got these people
to that mindset in the first place and a lot of it does come down to unity other aspects
of Ubuntu as well I mean just really nailed down the list you know you said Ubuntu simply
needed to give unity more time and development for releasing it because of that it got you
know a big backlash from the community simply put you said I believe some folks within the
Linux community felt like Ubuntu was isolating itself with this move to unity I think that's
probably a fair point that caused some hurt feelings and then or you know maybe hurt feelings
is the right way to put it but it caused people to take sides and then you said you know down
the road you had the mirror versus Whalen tobacco which we're very familiar with and
we said when it was first announced mirror was to be Ubuntu's choice for Xorg's replacement
once again the Linux community sounded off at the time I took a stance on the matter
that explaining I took a stance on the matter explaining that if mirror didn't get at least
one additional distro to use to use it as a display option I would wear a monkey suit
for the masses unless well it's 12 months later I've lost the bet I'm prepared to pay
the price initially agreed upon now for the bitter pill you don't want to hear the casual
computer user couldn't care less about the issue so long as the applications work as
expected I suspect we'll be seeing shrugs of indifference throughout the Ubuntu masses
no I see this as a battle of wills between developers and their opposing views and I
think you nailed it there yep and I think if you look at will Wheaton what he just said
he couldn't give two craps about way doesn't versus mirror and he also defeats the thing
that it's only new users that don't care he is not a new user by any oh great point so
I think this is something we've got to appreciate is people you know as their lives get busy
just because just because they might not be they might be technical people but they might
just decide that they don't have time for drama or they don't have time to follow this
kind of stuff and that can be a whole off-putting thing in itself and you say the back and forth
was perhaps even more heated than we'd seen than the unity versus gnome challenges in
the past like the mirror versus Whelan thing was like every time they've had something
that event has been more hotly contentious than the one before it that's true and it
seems like like the animosity is building on itself and building on itself and it's
like this snowball that just keeps rolling and then of course we get into the whole upstart
versus system D discussion which you know canonical and about two more directly involved
in but you say unlike the unity versus mere debate upstart got the attention of a fresh
new crop of Linux users as it directly affected how a Linux distro starts and stops events
and services so even if you're not a system admin or a developer this affected anyone
who uses Linux on a day-to-day basis definitely and I noticed a lot a lot of people that normally
wouldn't care one way or the other about desktop environments or whatnot because they just
use something else this affected them more so because it was under the hood it's gonna
change how they do things and you said of course the CLA at its core the CLA is perceived
as a barrier among many developers within the Linux community you mentioned Linus Torvalds
expressed his displeasure with all CLAs in all forms and you know that's been a real
concern for some developers and you mentioned in your closing thoughts that the Linux community
is passionate involved and sometimes overtly loud when it comes to the direction the platform
is headed in that you say while users such as myself try to be tried hard to remain neutral
and not act as though using our computers as a religious experience the community at
large continues to make their voices heard no matter the cost now what do you think that
cost is I think a lot of times the cost is that we create unnecessary you know contention
between each other I think a lot of times that we become so focused on stupid stuff
that we really lose focus of what's going on in other areas for example like let's look
at the Chromebooks and how Chrome's doing its thing and that you know these things are
selling really well and whatnot rather than focusing on outdoing Apple outdoing Google
outdoing other stuff I feel like we focus on our internal squabbles so much that it
really not only doesn't solve anything it just makes us dig deeper into our own personal
camps well yeah but we ignore bigger bigger issues I think I'm not sure if you're thinking
about it right because I mean there's a lot of things that are huge deals you know like
what side of the window is the close button on oh my god I know oh and the last and how
I used to know I'm guilty of this I used to I used to bitch constantly about the lack
of a minimize button and no I made a big stink about it just and why went on and on and on
and on about it no one cares I mean you know it was my problem not yours right so it's
like why would anyone care but I'm I'm guilty of this as well I'm just as bad as the other
guy Riley what are your thoughts on the unity well there's a thank you interesting about
unity too there's a large user base who would actually use unity on other distros if they
could sure oh yeah people would use unity on ours if they could but since they can't
they just hate on it I actually think unity is maybe the the ultimate example of stuff
that we argue about that actual users don't care about because here's the thing even if
unity was quote unquote the most terrible desktop in the history ever it doesn't matter
if you if you are even slightly linux technically inclined you know how to use a different desktop
and if you're a new user to linux you really probably have no problem with unity because
truth be told it's not that bad especially if you don't come in with preconceptions
and go ahead honestly isn't that bad it's a very pretty desktop especially if we used
it 1204 board right actually halfway stable I don't know what you think I think it's something
that we're general users just don't even know they should be caring about and and if you
think somehow like maybe user choice plays into all of this yes absolutely here's the
thing we keep talking about over and over again linux is about freedom and choice and
it's something that I wrote actually on the subreddit when it comes to desktop environment
use whatever you like the best and works best for you don't let anyone talk you into something
else just because they like it more or have some other agenda good advice yeah yeah rotten
corpse you switched your mom over to a unity desktop I did how to go been using it for
about two years now I guess yeah she has no problem with it the the thing is I I was using
it at this time because I was testing it out and I wanted to kind of like have her opinion
on it and because she's a completely she doesn't really care at all all of the de's and stuff
like that's irrelevant to her it doesn't matter so when I look at unity I find the little
flaws and stuff that I don't like and a few things that I do like the dash I don't like
it almost at all but I asked her what she think about the dash she's like what's that
and I explained it she's like yeah I don't care that's cool yeah exactly well see I've
had so I had my dad running an older version of Ubuntu with unity and he really liked it
he was coming from it was either XP or 7 it was before Windows 8 and he was switching
over and he ran Ubuntu for a little while and what he ran into is kind of what you touch
on here Matt is you say in sort of closing out your article you say my concern is that
newer users have just come over to the Linux side of the fence will be scared away by some
enthusiasts and their misplaced animosity towards Ubuntu will this color how the majority
of newcomers see the Linux community it did for my dad yeah and I've seen evidence of
it I don't just you know I actually have people that I talked about this stuff before I write
this stuff yeah yeah he saw it he saw you know when he was so he had two problems I
think first problem was is he wasn't really clear on where he was supposed to go to look
up problems and like so he wanted to he moved at one point and they didn't have internet
access they didn't have like cable or DSL where he'd moved to and so he wanted to tether
to his phone and like trying to look up and he was at work and trying to do like the googling
at work and then bring that home he got so many different results and so many different
mixed messages on that whole thing that it and I don't I wouldn't blame it all on this
but I think it definitely in when it came time to buy a new rig altogether he just kind
of decided to go get a Mac yeah oh yeah because it's an all-inclusive experience and much
as I'm not in any way a Mac person believe me I really don't like them at the end of
the day they don't sell a computer they sell an a collective experience yeah they really
do and you know they have the whole the whole genius angle to it too so he was able to ask
the guys some questions and I so this article you wrote really resonated with me here because
not only did I see that through my dad's experience but when we were taking the arch challenge
there was equal parts really good advice that I got from you know some awesome people on
our subreddit and things like that and there was equal parts really like hostile bad advice
that I got everything from trying to scare me away from using arch and telling me how
hard it is to use and how I I really have to keep the system maintained and it turns
out to be like the easiest Linux box I've ever had to maintain right that it would be
unstable because you're using bleeding that was another one yep yep and you know don't
use this tool use that tool and it's I and I suspect this happened for you too but it
gave me pause for a little bit where I thought I don't think I want to deal with this right
I know I don't like this this is I don't need this you know and it's even more nuanced than
it is an arch because an arch there's multiple ways to install a piece of software we're
like an Ubuntu like pretty much the end of day every guide is gonna tell you sudo apt
get install right add this PPA like there's consistencies so you can get a lot of different
you get a lot of information but they all kind of tell you to use the same tools and
do the same things not the same thing in arch now thankfully that wiki is very authoritative
and has a lot of good info but when you're just switching I felt like I had a lot of
mixed messages and I can so I'm I think that experience might be what a lot of new people
get when like you know they're reading a common thread and there's just tons of Ubuntu hate
in that common thread I would agree and I and what you said about the wiki the problem
with the wiki is that it's it's it's too good and and and what I mean by that is that the
information in the wiki blows other distributions out of the water as far as accuracy but the
problem is locating and knowing what to search for to find it that's the rub for a lot of
people because you don't always know like when I was trying to figure out the whole
battery life for you know the battery life situation for my netbook I wasn't necessarily
finding exactly what I was looking for to about the third or fourth search and then
I clicked yeah and the information was fantastic but it was finding it so I think if they can
hone that a little bit the information is gold there's no problem there some people
actually suggest people to look at the arch wiki to find the information which is a good
idea but they'll also suggest to people who are not using arch which is right very awkward
now yeah yeah that's true right you were gonna you were gonna say it kind of depends on the
existence of users of Linux to make regular users experiences a little more easier right
I was basically just gonna say that when when people talk about moving people to Linux they
always think about you know hair telling the advocate of why Linux is good and why they
should use it but they don't necessarily make that transition easy like for example with
my mom or my roommate or my neighbor I've moved over I set up their computer to I find
out what they want I put I put the Linux thing that I think fits best for them the distro
I mean and then I put on the different apps that they want like for one of them wanted
Wow so I had to put wine in so then I wow connection and is if you give them Linux set
up where they can have it just how they would just the stuff they want to use and the things
that they would be used to like the way they get Windows but it's already installed if
you do that for them the transition to Linux is almost negligible in as far as like whether
it's hard or not mm-hmm that's true that's true I used to support Linux at a small bookstore
in town north to me and I actually the service calls were well they went from a ton of them
to none yeah as long as I maintain the machine yeah I definitely noticed during I used to
joke you know when when my clients would ask me like so what should we do here for this
desktop and I would tell them you know I I would say I thankfully a lot of my clients
use Windows I'm very thankful for that because it gives me ten times the amount of business
that I would have if they ran Linux and that's not just me like gas and that's like literally
from my experience like I can put Linux in and once things are set up and stabilized
like rotten corpse is saying is I would go in there and I would configure everything
for them right and I would even set it up so it would take snapshots of their configuration
settings and all that kind of stuff and back those up and we could restore them very simply
and webman was a great tool to help some some of their local tech gal set up users and stuff
like that and that works so well that I would literally lose money on those clients exactly
yeah that was that when I switched to Linux full-time is about the time I got out of repair
so now it was going to say our problem here is that we've been conditioned by Microsoft
what's going on there Rick well here let me just go ahead and set the way back machine
to like 1995 when Windows 95 first came out people were up in arms that their programs
were not right there in front of them like they had on the program manager of Windows
3.1 now fast forward 19 years later now everybody's looking for that start menu if they see that
start menu they are up in arms it's just like okay now Microsoft has conditioned us to operate
this way and see that's the thing people are assuming that a desktop environment such as
humanity is unintuitive just because they're not used to it I suppose yeah that man has
earned a ding all right well here you go there you go you get a ding Dave you were gonna
say that maybe we just need to cater to each specific user that's your go man that's your
go right there no that's all right well that's I think what he's gonna essentially saying
I don't know he has a little bit of lag by the way okay yeah it's complicated no what
I was simply going to say is every user has their own sensibility of how a desktop should
and should not be I mean you have people who use Windows 8 perfectly with and without touch
and you have people who see the Macintosh interface and see if that's the perfect desktop
they can't use anything else regardless of of you know whatever it is so every user has
their own sensibility of what a desktop should be and what their workflow should be so what
while we're arguing about what the perfect one is well thinking of a hypothetical magical
user that that doesn't really exist that's me that's exactly that that's what I'm kind
of driving at is that intuitiveness is subjective yeah true yeah and I think so this goes goes
going back to Apple is the big threat here I think that the thing about Mac OS that you
got to wrap your head around is that it's it's not a great desktop in a lot of ways
like when I use it for you know I have several machines here in the studio and you know to
me it feels very old it feels like it feels like I can you know I remember the Macs from
the 80s and I still see a lot of influence there and I don't think it's I don't think
it's that amazing of a desktop I think it's what Matt's saying is that with Apple it's
this hardware good enough software better than of the alternative which is Windows and
that support package and I think when you're somebody like Wil Wheaton and that price isn't
a factor because that's the bit I'd say the number one argument once you take out all
the freedom and the open arguments which if you're not even if you don't even know to
be concerned about that that's not even part of the equation right if you take away that
and you take away the cost barrier because for a huge segment of people that's not going
to be an issue I think I think Apple is a fierce competitor to Linux I think it's I
think it's much more of a threat on the desktop than than Windows is well it is especially
for someone coming from Linux because they can drop down to a command line and do anything
they need to do I mean that's the other thing like look at Megali Dekaza you know one of
the original gnome developers who faint who eventually just threw his arms up in the air
and said you know what I'm gonna go get a MacBook but you could sort of that equivalent
on Linux easily if you go with something like Ubuntu and system 76 I mean they have excellent
customer support magnificent hardware on top of generally they ship on what like LTS is
I think this is an important piece is this is this is why I'm a system 76 fan is because
they they are also creating that entire end-to-end experience but the problem is is we don't
have enough people doing that and it's right you know it's like whereas Apple has this
massively established presence and brand and I just you know we do our part just to spread
the word about system 76 because I think it's a really important I think that whole entire
product package is super important and I think one way we can achieve that today is in larger
installations like at schools and at businesses where you have a person that comes in and
rolls out a system for a whole bunch of people that seems so ripe for the Linux desktop picking
to me it's ridiculous it's just this maybe a few software applications but that just
seems so ripe whereas you know that home user who's you know you know a 30 something 30
something hipster that just wants to go down to the mall and buy a metal MacBook I don't
know if we're gonna be able to get that person but I think schools and businesses and anytime
where you can take the experience and you can build it around the need I think Linux
is such a slam dunk for that well that's sort of already happening now we see Chromebooks
and Chrome OS which is technically Linux based in educational areas all the time now it's
becoming increasingly popular that just makes me sad so I think the formula to the you know
to making this work is the fact that it takes a multinational company make this happen right
what I would say is that what it goes it boils down to the same thing that Matt has said
a bunch of times and that is marketing yeah that's Mac Mac stuff the software isn't is
okay and it's built on stuff that was already there to it was already good in the first
place so it's like if you took LXDE put a dock on it it's very close to way Mac works
or like gnome 3 or you know if you spend a couple hours configuring KDE right yeah you
can have a I really believe you can have a more modern experience desktop that has better
efficiencies it's in some ways can especially I think for gnome 3 can be more user-friendly
I agree I just this is such a this is such a problem that I just kind of want to and
I guess I want to bring this back to how the community can make a difference here and we're
not going to convince everybody to you know lay down arms and embrace each other in a
kumbaya but I have an idea what what if the GNU project because they always want Linux
to be called GNU slash Linux they put up money for marketing to make it GNU slash Linux I
don't know I think it's close I think it's close get a GNU start with GNU slash Linux
well here here's an actual actionable formula of how this could actually be done first of
all you get yourself Kickstarter product project you know or however you want to fund it some
sort of a collective funding process that gets a bunch of advertising dollars together
then everybody in key metro cities goes to the Google AdWords program that allows you
to advertise in your local cable channels take a fiver voiceover of one of those really
good movie voices slap together some great video capture from OpenShot or whatever just
really show off what the desktop can do make it sound like a movie intro launch those in
each one of those metro areas on television stop this internet crap on TV where regular
people actually get their media and watch what happens I think you might be surprised
isn't this part of the problem though is there's no there's no you know Linux Inc. there's
no there's no company that that needs to you know capitalize on this opportunity that could
capitalize there's individual companies that are all kind of scattered about and I think
that's one of the reasons you know Ubuntu has such name recognition is because there's
a company behind that and Red Hat has such name recognition and brand recognition but
there's no one company who's you know got the money and the and the presence to do that
and so maybe let me let me shift the conversation here is this why everybody is so hard over
mobile because it's it's the grand reset of this technical century that we get to start
all over again and you know everybody is everybody is a fresh and new and the possibilities are
endless is that why everybody's so hot on mobile hmm well maybe it's because they have
right now essentially two platforms that they have to look at only and they're so massively
widespread now that it's since it's easy for people who are not computer users even just
regular people who just want a tablet so they can watch something like Netflix Netflix or
something it can bring that so many more people to look at your stuff so people are just kind
of like jumping on the bandwagon of any kind of mobile device of all yeah well I mean and
it's a lot easier to get mobile devices in the hands of individuals around the world and the
fact that you know there's billions of individuals around the world that still don't have a mobile
device that's a huge user base that a company could target well like Dave is saying in the
chat room everybody loves a computer in their pocket but wimpy what kind of tipping point
do you think we're at what you say we're at a tipping point right now well 20 years ago apple
was um in in uh excuse the queer localism it was in the shitter and um you know they've really
turned their fortunes around and and the two companies that are really driving um popularization
of cutting edge technology at the moment are apple and google so I think the tipping point that we're
at right now is that Microsoft is is on a downward trend um they're hanging on to traditional markets
and really not succeeding in that and I I think the tipping point we're at is with with apple
and ios and mac os 10 and then google with obviously android and then chrome os and I
think it will be a battle that's fought out between mac os and linux in the guise of chrome os
well I think the big problem with windows is it's sort of like become a tainted name
like I know people who won't buy windows phones because they think they'll get viruses it's a
black mark yeah I agree I think the windows name is now a black mark on a product and I think the
general consumer thinks it's something old and it's not hip it's not cool anymore I think that's
what's holding back a lot of these windows mobile devices and desktops um and I think that's well I
feel sorry for Microsoft because they can't win they try and be hit and then everyone says oh we
don't have to use metro and then they try and be like old school and everyone has a go at them
for not being different it is kind of bad for them they're trying to be hip again
they're just trying to do it through a bunch of you know people dancing around
holding tablets and that just doesn't work clicking them together exactly because you
know I use a computer I'm always running around my office smacking the monitors together to try
and get it to accomplish tasks I mean really yeah I that's an interesting concept so and I you know
uh the whole idea um is it gonna be is it gonna be macbooks versus chromebooks in the future
and you'll have everybody who wants to save a buck running chromebooks but they'll be
inextricably forever linked at the hip to google and you'll have everybody that wants to drop some
cash we're talking you know large percentages here buying macbooks and uh is linux gonna be
in is the predominance of linux gonna be this bastardized closed down souped up for their
commercial cloud services um client side wait you said commercial software would that honestly be
so bad I mean this is open source people can do people can do whatever with it that they choose
and people can implement it the way they want and if linux adoption requires that companies
like google and whoever change it the way they need to or you know the stabilization of linux
will that be so bad because isn't that sort of the original idea it's negative in the freedom
dimension I don't I don't know uh it's not it's not what I hope for and I think also you know
we can't really have this conversation without keeping in mind that linux will dominate on the
server side too and that's going to be all different kinds of operating systems but it
does make you wonder like what the future holds for these desktop focused distros and uh if
eventually they're not just going to be kind of you know just the ones that survive will be the
ones that are maintained by community enthusiasts yeah I've noticed uh myself like especially and
I don't know if it's just the point of my life I'm at but I see my parents and my grandparents and
you know all these people around me going and saying I don't know what to do anymore you know
they've always they've always had you know go with windows if you want business or you know
go with mac if you want media and now they don't know where to go and you know it's kind of this
weird point where people that you know once thought they knew what they had to do don't
know anything anymore yeah kind of sad it's a weird we're in a weird transition and I think
what we're trying to wrap our brains around on this show is what do we need to change to get
linux in position to sort of be there to catch a certain amount of people who are dropping away
from windows and uh are there things just as a community we could do oh is it safe to emerge
well I think it is safe so that wraps up this week's look back uh we'll have a full crew next
week and we'll be back with a regular show I definitely need to take a shower and rikai he's
staying away from chili for the rest of the month no more chili for rikai hopefully you've enjoyed
the look back at some of the more popular topics they were sent in by you the audience thank you
so much for those submissions don't forget we'd love more interaction go over to linuxactionshow.reddit.com
go to jupiterbroadcasting.com contact and geez join us live won't you we do the show on a tuesday
go to jupiterbroadcasting.com calendar then you can participate in our mumble room hang out in
the chat room it's a good time thanks so much for joining me this week see you right back here next
tuesday
so