Wow, an abominable winter ale West brings us.
World class beer, sustainable, Portland, Oregon.
17 degrees, 70 IBU, 17 degrees.
What is that?
17 degrees, Plato?
I've never even heard of that.
It's like a beer metric, because it's like, it says it's 70, it's got a 70 IBU, which
is International Bitterness Unit, it's got an alcohol volume of 7.3%, those are all things
I understand on the side of a beer, and then it's got, it's one pint, I understand what
that is, but then it says 11 degrees, Plato.
You guys ever heard of that on a beer before?
Maybe I'm, am I, it's P-L-A-T-O, right, that's Plato, yeah, I mean.
It's a beer, come on.
What does that mean?
That means it's degrees proof?
What does that mean, Diddle?
There's apparently a Wikipedia page about beer measurement, which mentions degrees
Plato.
Really?
I've never heard of that before.
No, I've never heard of it either.
Wait, they can increase philosophers in there?
Did you see that this has a beer measurement metric on it, which I've never seen, this
thing is 7 degrees, 17 degrees Plato.
It's got a 70 IBU, and a 7.3% alcohol by volume, and a 17 degree Plato.
Wow.
How many Platos do I want?
I don't know.
I think this is the most Platos I've ever been aware of.
Compared to zero?
I know, I'm like thinking, is this like the philosopher?
Like this is how many beers, this is how many of these Plato would have drank?
Boy, he could knock them back.
Yeah.
Apparently, it's Fritz Plato.
It's what?
Exactly.
German chemist Fritz Plato.
Oh, I see.
The Plato scale differs slightly from the Bolling scale, whatever that, or the Baling,
what is this?
Which is the, okay, the measurement of specific gravity used to determine the dissolved solid.
Oh, wow.
Oh, so you're getting, you're getting like, you get to know how, how they measured it.
So this is like a dish, this is like really, this is for people that are really into beer,
is what that is.
That's, you know what that is?
That's a little nod to like, if you're drinking this beer, you're a beer connoisseur.
So we're going to tell you about, you get to know everything.
Even the Platos.
Interesting.
beerandbrewing.com, I mean, they would seem to be the ones to know.
The Plato scale is used by most brewers worldwide, although brewers in the UK and those using
British brewing traditions tend to prefer to use the specific gravity scale instead.
This is derived by measuring the specific gravity of the wort, multiplying by 1000 and
then subtracting 1000 from that figure to give the degrees of gravity.
Thus a wort is specific gravity of 1.048 is said to have a 48 degrees of gravity.
The Plato and gravity scales can be approximated by multiplying P by four to give the degrees
of gravity.
Well, there you go guys, duh.
Didn't we know this?
See, drink beer and you learn things.
It's some science.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 180 for January 17th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that prepared for this week's episode
by learning more about how to measure your beer.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
It's true fact.
True fact.
We actually did learn a little something about beer today.
I love the pre-show.
Wes, we have so many project updates.
I actually started today thinking we wouldn't have much to talk about.
I know, but people have been busy.
Yeah, they have.
We got some good ones to go through, so we'll start with that.
Then we have a new distribution that says it's inspired by material design.
It's going to create cohesive Linux desktop and apps.
I know, it's a totally radical idea.
I've never heard it before.
So we're going to take a look at a new distro you likely haven't heard about today.
Then there's some crazy kids releasing some crazy assistant on that crazy Raspberry Pi,
the Crasberry.
Raspberry Pi.
Crasberry.
I got one.
Here it is, Wes.
Look, I think I found it.
Right here, I got a Pi 3.
Pi 3, right in the box.
If we had a screen for this sucker and a keyboard and a mouse, I'd say we should try it live
on the show today, but we'll tell you about it and how you can try it out and maybe report
back.
Then at the end, I'll be getting some feedback, so I'm going to address something that we've
been covering on the show recently, and it's generated a lot of feedback in the audience.
Chris has got to get real with you guys for just a minute.
Just a minute.
We're going to take it a moment.
Heart to heart?
Yeah.
Just a little real talk at the end of the show.
Our minds to your mind?
Mind-meld kind of thing.
Yeah.
So that's coming up on episode 180 of the Unplugged program.
Lots of stuff to get into, and more stuff that I couldn't even remember right there
during the intro.
But one thing I can't forget is that Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, Virtual Lug.
Greetings.
Hello.
It's good to see all of you, and I'm glad to have you all here to help us go through
the week's news.
So let's start with this first story, which I kind of think is maybe one of the bigger
stories.
It's definitely an interesting trend that's developing.
It's now possible to use OpenSUSE inside Windows 10 using that Linux sublayer.
Seuss's senior product manager was intrigued by the fact that Microsoft chose to enable
the wrong Linux distribution.
Ooh, strong words.
By default.
So within the Windows subsystem for Linux used by the company's latest Windows 10 builds,
and he decided with his own agenda, he would go off and teach people how to use Seuss inside
of WSL.
And he says, why Seuss?
And this is some really sound, solid reasoning.
Really gets me fired up to go try this.
Why Seuss?
Well, Seuss knows what they are doing because they have been in Linux business since 1992.
Try to find a Linux vendor, or in that case, a distributor, which is older.
You won't.
There aren't any.
That was the senior product manager's solid endorsement for using Seuss, is because Seuss
is old.
Fired up.
You know, I think people sometimes ask Chris, say, hey, Chris, how do you say, is it Seussa,
is it Seuss?
Is it open Seuss?
Is it lowercase O, uppercase O, all uppercase, lowercase U?
Part of the confusion might come from when your own team doesn't even use the right language.
So the product manager at Seuss is calling open Seuss, Seuss.
Which just confuses the general public.
And then the news article is rightfully just quoting the words of the senior product manager,
who's calling another product, open Seuss, the name of his own product.
Which is like, yeah, okay, maybe it works for the people who, like, you're all using
it and you're familiar.
But for any outside observer, it's just, yeah, it's just confusing.
Now, that aside, pretty interesting to see this developing pretty quickly.
The Windows Linux subsystem, or whatever it's called.
Windows Subsystem for Linux?
Yes, I think that's it.
WSL?
WSL.
Pretty cool.
And the instructions do work probably, I believe, I have not confirmed any of this, but I believe
they also work for Seuss Linux Enterprise, so you can also run Sles on there.
I would want to try, I think I would definitely want to, if I was doing this, I would definitely
want to try Sles, because that seems to make the most sense, because if I'm doing this
on Windows, it's probably to match my server environment that I manage.
That's kind of what I envision.
Probably a dev or admin who needs to test stuff locally.
Yeah, you've got Sles servers, and you want to have a common local environment, just so
it's sort of the same, I think, the big draw for having Ubuntu.
So have we seen Fedora or Centos on the sub, I don't know.
No, I don't think so.
I haven't seen it.
We do see, there is a couple of different efforts to get Arch on the Windows subsystem
for Linux.
Here's one I have linked in the show notes where you can get Arch on there, which would
seem to look a little bit like what just needs to be done, you know, obviously it's not that
much if they're all getting it working, I'm sure it's just some dealing with the boot,
maybe getting the, not boot, but starting the user land, getting everything working.
This makes a lot of sense.
In this screenshot for Arch under the Windows subsystem for Linux, they're using your work,
and now if you got access to a lot of the AUR command line applications on the Windows
Linux subsystem, that would be very useful.
I know they're just poking fun, but to say that Microsoft chose to enable the wrong default
distro, I feel like that's sort of the opposite of the truth.
It's obviously the right distro because of the massive cloud penetration, and that's
really why Windows admins want it in the first place and not really why anyone was ever asking
for SUSE.
It's also funny to kind of imply like, well, Canonical jumped at this or worked with them
to develop this.
You guys did not.
It's hard to make that wrong when they were the ones taking some of the initiative here.
Right, that is true, although it does demonstrate that there's nothing specific about WSL to
Ubuntu.
That, I think, is the more promising thing.
Is anybody in the Mumble Room trying this or using this?
I thought about it for a hot moment over the weekend, I thought about trying it because
I saw this story come up, and I thought to myself, I wouldn't mind dual booting into
a system and trying Premiere again, and then using this for the tools I would undoubtedly
need while I'm there, and I could see a use for that, but I just can't bring myself to
use Windows.
Then you have to install Windows.
That's the most painful part.
Yeah, yeah.
The thing is, we're not the target audience for this, really.
It's people who run Windows full-time who want to have an environment in which they
can run Linux-y tools natively just in a window.
Your audience are probably not likely to use it, and not likely to use it on a daily basis,
but someone whose employment demands that they run Windows, but they want to be able
to have a shell.
There's probably a fair amount of people listening.
I see a huge thing for the enterprise where it's like, yeah, your developers are complaining.
Maybe they want MacBooks, but if you can be like, no, here's our already-domained, everything's
in Windows already for everyone else.
Here's your Linux shell.
Go crazy.
That's a pretty big sell and a good compromise for a lot of people.
Yeah, especially if you can offer them a piece of hardware that's attractive, like some of
those XPS 13s and 15s.
If you run Windows 10 on that, and then you put SUSE or ARCH or Ubuntu on the subsystem,
that does seem like just the right mix of enterprise compromise for people that need
to use the rest of the Microsoft ecosystem like Active Directory.
It's interesting to see this developing.
I just wanted to give them a shout-out.
More so than that, guys, if you want to try SUSE out or open SUSE on your Windows 10 box,
there is instructions in this article on how to get it set up, and then the one we've linked
for ARCH, it's a script that does it for you, I believe, and it gives you a minimal ARCH
Linux distro that you can then go out crazy on.
Can we run the show in it?
Do a whole episode?
Yes.
Run from subsystem for Linux?
I don't really feel all that fired up.
I don't really feel too fired up about that, Wes.
You know what I am fired up about, though?
N1 going free.
Now they're calling it Nileus Mail instead of Nileus N1, and they're introducing Nileus
Basic.
I really am excited.
This is my mail client of choice.
I've been trying to very cautiously recommend it because it costs money for the Pro version,
and if you don't want to do any work, you have to run off their intermediary host, but
this is really nice.
So N1 has been renamed to Nileus Mail, and they're launching a free version of Nileus
Mail called Nileus Basic, and by free, they mean also open source.
That's great.
Yeah, I got the GitHub link linked in the show notes.
They're still working on it, so there's not much to see there yet.
So does this mean that they're comfortable enough with their monetization as a company
with their being Pro only for a while, that they're ready to... Because that was one
of the things I was a little disappointed at when they did go Pro only.
They still had the open source, but it felt like there was a lot of hoops to jump through.
They weren't really welcoming that tier, so now that there is a basic tier, does that
mean they're feeling more established?
I think it's the opposite.
They need more people.
They're hoping to sucker people in here.
Well, I don't know about sucker, but I think it didn't work out.
I think, first of all, it's funny.
Having been a Pro user, it was not easy to give them my money, and it was clunky, so
I would not be surprised if they saw not a big success with that.
Plus, who wants to toss a bunch of money at a no-name company, at least a company you
don't know, building an upstart mail client that's Electron?
There's not a lot of people that are going to get in on that when you've got good old
Thunderbird sitting there.
So I think that was an uphill battle for them, and I'm betting this is more of a... Well,
this is a plan B. This is a bit of a pivot.
Interesting.
Yeah, actually, it's funny you asked that.
Daniel from Elementary OS jumped into a conversation thread that we were having in the Linux Action
Show subreddit, where an Elias employee stopped by and said, there's no Linux builds yet,
but we're going to get them out soon.
And Daniel, before I jumped in, says, well, my big question is, what's your funding model?
How has it changed?
How are you going to remain profitable?
Oh, right.
He says, to me, hearing that this service is now free is scary.
Who's the real customer?
Am I now the product?
I think Daniel's asking some good questions.
So I'm excited that it's going open source, but I don't understand how they're going to
fund and continue development.
And I know a lot of you are probably like, I don't care.
I don't care.
Well, that's because you are so wrong about life right now.
It's a really good mail client, and you don't …
And it's nice to see innovation in this sector, like with Thunderbird being installed and
Geary.
Stop it.
It's disappointing that we can't be like, yeah, OK, we don't have Outlook.
But you don't want Outlook.
You want this better Linux product.
And so if there's a good open source client that we can tell people to use, that'd be
awesome.
Here's a fundamental problem I have with email.
And this is something that Nyleas, I guess it is, Nyleas Mail, has made better for me.
Email is a son of a bitch because it allows anybody to all of a sudden create an expectation
of you without you even knowing that an expectation has been created and now being held against
you.
And so anybody can drop any turd in your inbox asking something of you, requesting something
of you, telling you about something, hey, FYI, heads up, any of these things, they all
create a different set of social expectations.
And we all have different internal calibrations of how we treat email.
For me, some weeks, I check my email once a week, maybe twice.
Some weeks, I check it daily.
It really ranges.
But people that email me, I often get emails from people that I work with that expect me
to be responding, not at JB, but outside of JB.
People in JB know.
But outside of JB, people will often send me an email expecting me to respond within
the first maybe half hour I receive the email, let alone the day, right?
And it will be sometimes days before I get back to them, I just have to say, I'm sorry,
I've been busy.
And the thing that now mail does for me is it allows me to take a couple of extra steps
to manage that situation where I can take an email, get it out of my inbox, but then
have it come back later and say, you asked to be reminded about this tomorrow at 8 a.m.
Guess what?
It's time.
Here's that email again.
It's a simple function along with its really sophisticated read-receipt system that's better
than anything else out there before.
It has a great set of signatures and good support for GPG.
And now it's open source.
It is a very good mail client.
It works on every OS you want to use it on because it's Electron.
And if you're an Electron app hater, you're like, I don't want, I don't like the overhead
of an Electron app, that's so stupid.
I understand.
That was me.
I was totally that guy.
And then I got a few Electron apps that are actually pretty good because that's the thing.
There's bad Electron apps and there's good ones.
And this is one of the good ones.
So I think it's encouraging for Electron as an app platform.
It's encouraging for people that are looking for some innovation to make email not such
a life suck that it is.
It's great.
And I just, I don't feel like it gets enough attention.
I'm hoping now that they've gone this route, they've gone free, they've gone open source.
Maybe more people start talking about it.
Hopefully they can be sustainable.
Yeah.
I will say it seems like Electron fits well with your lifestyle where you're maybe distro
hopping or on random computers.
You don't have to worry about being in the package manager.
You know it can run.
Yeah.
It is.
And also it's not like these are 3D games or video editors.
They're not something where I have to have the just unbelievable desktop performance.
And then let's get off our high horse here for a second and stop pretending like Qt and
GTK are these hyper optimized lightweight toolkits that make application rendering lightning
fast that no other.
We all know that's a load of crap.
But the Linux desktop is not the fastest snappiest desktop and part of it is the toolkit.
I mean one thing I hate about using Windows is that GDI system is so crappy and old and
the Windows toolkit, I forget what it's called, is such an ancient piece of crap and then
they managed to throw it all into a GPU buffer now post Vista or 7 even.
It actually like Windows fly open on Windows.
Like that's the one thing Windows is good at is actually opening Windows.
It's funny but that is actually what it's good at is opening and displaying Windows
very fast.
This you often with a super high end machine will still sometimes see parts your UI render.
So yeah we can be on our high horse about electron apps.
I hear that shit every time I talk about electron app.
I get emails and tweets.
The chat room goes on about it.
People watch the show afterwards and then come back in the chat room and trash.
Can't believe Chris is once again promoting electron apps.
People get all their high horse about electron apps.
Meanwhile Qt and GTK are not like they're the second coming to UI speed.
So just give it a shot.
If you have problems with email and for you you struggle with email like I do it's worth
looking at.
And they do have some pretty good stuff.
I've always enjoyed their blog posts.
They do some they have some interesting discussions about how they a lot of their stuff's in Python
and how they package it and that kind of stuff.
So it seems like they're kind of contributing their good upstream people.
I want to I want to give a little attention to something that I see happening more and
I want to I want to also get some participation from the audience to help us with something.
So there is a trend that's beginning to take off and clever projects like the guy that
runs the Ubuntu Mate project have have been reaching out with their community using Patreon
and other funding moments been doing it for a long time to using their own custom system.
A lot of different developers and projects are starting ways to get funded and Patreons
becoming a pretty common one and I wouldn't be surprised eventually people start feeling
Patreon fatigue but what I would what I would like to what I would like to try to do is
use the audience reach of our shows to help promote some of these funding methods at least
for a little bit.
Maybe we spend one episode on it because I have a feeling that that's probably something
the audience feels would be a good use of our airtime would be giving recognition to
like this one I have up on the screen right now is a GIMP developer who is rewriting the
GIMP backend image processing core and if he's successful GIMP will then have high bit
depth support full CMYK support full layer effects and all of it's impossible without
this rewrite and now he's launching a Patreon I think he's got like a hundred and something
patrons this could really change the game and we've seen this actually work now we've
seen some different projects some better than others really pull this off and I think the
audience would feel like it's a good use of our time to give them attention and airtime
but I need their help finding a lot of them I have I know I know about some of the Saudi
developer I can think of three or four or five off the top of my head I but I know there's
got to be more and so wherever you're watching this I'm asking I'm asking at last and I'm
asking in this episode please let me know in the comments or in a tweet or submit them
to the subreddit mm-hmm and so I would just thought maybe they haven't actually watched
this video yet but this is this is some work that's going into GIMP that will eventually
yield and some big big improvements lots of stuff that we've wanted to see in GIMP for
a very long time which could be landing in GIMP to some of it could be landing in GIMP
2.10 I haven't seen this video yet oh yeah okay I have seen this that's right it's just
it's just a video of a giant goat or whatever that is that's what the it's just a I don't
know I guess it's kind of cool to show off what you could do with GIMP I forgot I for
some reason I blocked that out of my memory anyways it's really cool work that's happening
and I guess I'm just I'm kind of saying hey if you think that we should spend some of
our time giving attention to this stuff well then I need your support making it actually
happen exactly Wimpy do you have any thoughts on this topic I currently back a couple of
projects through their patrons that I'm interested in and I'm sure there are others so yeah I'd
be interested to hear what else is out there so that if there's things that I'm already
using or something that I think is nifty then I've got a way to support the project yeah
obviously because patreon has been hugely successful for Ubuntu mate and I would like
to see other developers have similar success yeah I agree and I think one of the nice things
about patreon is once you're signed up it's it's not too much more barrier to then go
support somebody else and you can set limits so you don't overdo it and stuff like that
so it's a it's a system that makes it possible to support multiple content creators without
having to go create an account everywhere they decide to go right and we do need the
scaffolding as in you know in the free open source software community yeah I want to be
able to give back but there's just you need a minimal set of hoops yeah we'll have to
jump through yeah all right so let's brainstorm more we can do more brainstorming too in the
post show if you guys want I want to keep going though because there's a topic that
we have kicked around a lot and haven't gotten updates on a little bit and so now we'll have
one plus the FSF has a new top 10 list that they want you to focus on so first let's take
a moment and thank ting for sponsoring the unplugged program linux.ting.com go there
to save money off your first device or off your service plan depending depending on if
you buy a new phone or bring your own phone and one of the really cool things about ting
that you're gonna love is no contract nor the termination fee and just pay for what
you use just your minutes your messages and your megabytes and six dollars for the line
I love it such a simple system because it means if I want to turn something on I just
pay six bucks that month and then when I get rid of it it's gone that's really nice for
my five for backup my files when I'm traveling it's also been really nice when I've had a
problem and I'm traveling and I was able to use their customer service you get to speak
to a real human being but I've always pretty much gotten done in the dashboard and they
have CDMA and GSM networks for you to use I think the perfect combo nexus device or
maybe a pixel device now I guess I should stop saying you gotta it's dead Chris get
over it I would do this I would get a device from the play store or get an unlocked device
somewhere and bring it to ting because ting's not gonna lock it up they're not gonna stay
in the way of updates personally if you could afford it I would recommend either an iPhone
or a pixel I think that's really the way to go these days if you can go there ting though
they've got all kinds of great options because I know those are expensive unless you get
like a nexus 5x or something I mean you can start at nine dollars for just a SIM card
if you have a device you can get a feature phone for like 20 bucks and then they are
they actually this one by the way the Kyocera Dura they have this one back in stock now
this is like the indestructible phone if you want like a phone that has like a week-long
battery you can hear the ringtone from anywhere in the house and it'll almost survive a war
like Indiana Jones in a fridge check that thing out lots of other phones oh wow the
iPhone 4 is only 87 bucks now from ting wow wow yeah iPhone 591 bucks iPhone 5c and then
they have of course all the other devices like the one plus the motos I think you should
go over there and just see what you might want to get if you don't have a device already
or you want to start fresh you can see the whole lineup over at ting including that pixel
phone or you could just bring one and enjoy the ting savings by going to linux.ting.com
linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program now we
go into the future and look back at last year yes that's right to go into the future we
must look back the future being Mir and Wayland of course and to look back to see how Mir
is doing this was just posted on the insights.abuntu.com blog I guess and they will go over some of
the things in 2016 they say it was a good year for Mir it's being used in more places
as better upstream support and it's easier to use by downstream projects 2017 will be
even better when we see version 1.0 will somebody in the mumble room to find what upstream is
for Mir for me I'm not trying to be clever either I really don't understand what upstream
is for Mir wouldn't upstream just be Mir's project itself nobody knows I don't I wasn't
paying attention so what is what in the context of Mir when they say it has more and this
was Alan Griffiths on the insight blog he says it's being used in more places it has
more and better upstream support and it's easier to use by downstream projects so what
does upstream support mean?
Maybe he's talking about back end support for things like Qt and different toolkits
and what have you and then here's a there was a piece here enabling Mir on Ubuntu non
or enabling I thought this is a good one enabling Mir on non Ubuntu Mesa or Mesa distributions
Ubuntu currently carries a distro patch for Mesa to support Mir work is planned for this
year to update it and and then upstream this patch we've not done so yet as we know there
are changes needed to support current developments such as Vulkan which brings us to the next
thing which I thought was interesting they're working on improving the graphics API to support
things such as Vulkan which requires development of the Mir plugin module and now that they've
actually done the work on getting the Vulkan support in as one of the first major plugins
they've also discovered a bunch of stuff needs to be done to the plugin architecture looking
forward to 2017 they'll see a cleanup of the toolkit API and better support for platform
plugin modules after learning so much from Vulkan I would imagine and they'll be working
to upstream their Mesa patch soon they also have a snapshot of all the progress include
they've been reducing latency and big wins and performance which are available right
now and we're going to complete changes and believe they will see the Mir 1.0 release
in 2017 wow yeah something to look forward to that's been a long time coming that's a
Mir in 2017 predictions book out here Chris I didn't make that prediction I just kind
of was like you know what I just I couldn't do another year of predicting Wayland and
Mir I even though it feels like this would be the year of all years doesn't that say
something I just done West despite that you're just no I couldn't do it nope Wes I couldn't
do it I just I had to put it to bed and because I had to come to a personal acceptance West
I had to come to a peace with the fact excellent forever this stuff is hard West and it takes
a long time and you know what else I realized is even once this shenanigan ships I'm probably
going to be one of those old codgers on X for a long time because I'm going to need
my x11 Forden or I'm going to want V and I'm going to want something West that these new
fangled Vulkan powered Wayland and Mirs from every which browser and desktop environment
maybe I want my clipboard to share contents between all my applications maybe I want my
clipboard to be able to monitor my screen even when I have like my apps stealing all
of my credentials that's why they're there so yeah I figure I figured this wouldn't be
the year to really get excited about Wayland or Mir because it probably won't be the year
for Chris anyways because all of the reasons that we just stated but you can read more
about the post on the quote unquote blog blog where they also have a screenshot of the obligatory
screenshot of GIMP running on Mir which feels like you got to do two things you got to have
a terminal and you got to have GIMP running to show that your new display system works
with legacy applications what should we show I know GIMP's a UI monster let's show that
that's what everybody does it's a monster let's put that up on the screen but it works
mm-hmm yeah I'm gonna stick with X for life you're gonna pull it from my cold dead insecure
hands all hacked so the Free Software Foundation I don't even need to tell you guys this because
I'm sure you all probably check this daily so for those of you that maybe didn't know
about this that don't have this as your homepage it turns out that the Free Software Foundation
has a high priority software projects list now I know you guys all knew that you're checking
it constantly that's how you make your morning prioritization decisions what should I work
on today I better go check Richard's list I know I understand but for those of you that
weren't aware the Free Software Foundation has been working on this since 2005 and they
got a lot of feedback in 2016 from about 150 free software community members the high priorities
projects committee let's just let that soak in for a second is that where my money goes
if I donate to the Free Software Foundation is a bunch of committees the high priority
projects committee what is this a government institution the high priority projects panel
recommended extensive updates to the yeah to the high priority project list the high
priority projects initiative draws attention to a relatively small number of projects of
great strategic importance to the goal of freedom for all computer users this list serves
to foster work on projects that are important for increasing the adoption and use of free
software applications and free software operating systems and here's where my here's where my
issue begins because that is a very fine statement to make if you just did one thing where they
have a period where they say the list serves to foster work on projects that are important
for increasing the adoption and use of free software applications and free software operating
systems instead of a period it should be comma in our opinion man they speak as if they are
the ultimate they're the absolute they're the Free Software Foundation ergo they have
the ultimate authority to declare what is and what is not important what must be our
attention must be directed to and what must be ignored and it's not it's not it's just
some it's something about the way this is framed to me I find it to be slightly sort
of it's almost like that in their mind it's a foregone conclusion you know there's no
element of convincing or storytelling it's kind of just like these are the facts these
are the things we've decided this we are the bastion of your freedom please read yeah yeah
I guess it does kind of so here you ready for it you ready for it this is the list here
are the high priority free software areas a free phone operating system smartphones
are the most widely used form of personal computing today that's the need for a fully
free phone operating system is crucial to the proliferation of software freedom yep
okay accurate decentralized Federation and personal services a software substitute clouds
a little phrase they've got here yeah I like that service as a software substitute yeah
that is good the large and fragmented space deals with increased centralization of web
activities and user reliance on servers they don't control or service as a software substitute
clouds the free software community provided extensive feedback regarding many projects
that follow this initiative also they say this is on their list free drivers firmware
and hardware designs man it's a good thing they got a committee to come up with this
list because otherwise they might have missed some of this maybe our community should come
up with a list and we can compare and contrast real-time voice and video chat so this their
list okay I guess I guess I feel like there is this does nothing there is probably nobody
who's sitting back oh man you know what I got 40 hours free this week and I just don't
know what to do I'm gonna go check Rick's list and see what he thinks I should be working
on I mean the idea is preposterous so instead of their set of my money to the free software
foundation going to actually funding some of these projects or paying a developer for
a week to do this work it goes to creating committees and updating lists from 2005 of
no no shit statements of course we need a free phone operating system no shit Sherlock
of course we need to use WebRTC better no crap yeah we need free drivers people been
working on that for years now none of this is useful what are they doing and it really
feels like it kind of lacks the community aspect that makes a lot of these things important
right like it's not it's not an ongoing discussion it's just kind of like put out
there as a list right so it's not let's work out together what we should work on as a community
bettering things you know it would be great you know it would be amazing if this was a
list of how they were organizing action around these items the free software foundation has
identified these as critical areas to the freedom and so we are organizing groups of
people around these particular items we don't need to sit around and wait for Google Summer
of Code here's their patreon pages go fund them they'll be working on these items here's
how you can help why does it take some stupid podcaster in Arlington Washington going around
go hmm you know I ought to come up with a list of ways we can contribute to open source
developers so they can financially afford to work on free software I can come up with
that idea but the free software foundation can't come up with that idea why aren't there
links to patreon pages on this why aren't they telling you how I actually take action
this just feels like they're preaching from on high to us I don't know why this list offends
me so much but it literally offends me reading this list all right so there you go if you
want to read that masterpiece that took a committee some go ahead is there anyone here
who's donated to the I have recently oh yeah recently last year do you do you get spam
from them yes yeah yeah I wasn't impressed about that yeah so I did I did a talk earlier
in the year which I was paid to do and it was all about you know Linux and open source
stuff and I said to the organizers that I wanted to donate that money so I chose to
donate it to the FSF because why not and now I just get spam from Richard Stallman with
choice photos of him gallivanting around the world and what have you right and the verbiage
is would you like to join our low volume mailing list and receive a monthly newsletter that's
the verbiage when you sign up on it I'm getting a paper newsletter as well from America like
a little pamphlet you know I might if I was getting mail I don't get much mail because
I they have my old address so but I didn't I didn't ask for this I just sent them some
money and now I get email spam and snail mail spam and they you know like the chairman say
well maybe they're not linking to patreon pages because patreon is negative in the freedom
dimension but they'll happily accept you to pay by credit card or PayPal and they'll also
take Bitcoin which is how I donated but they'll also happily accept PayPal so I don't think
it's about some sort of moral reason why they're not linking to developers patreon or bug bounties
and Richard Stallman doesn't have a problem with people making money from free software
so I yeah it's yeah wimpy that there is it's sort of I guess where I'm going with this
and I didn't even realize it is there is a real easy way for people that are creating
something really great to go out and seek direct funding and there does seem to be less
relevancy for this particular function of the FSF not that it's irrelevant but for this
particular organizing and function like this this makes no difference in the community
in the direction of what people work on this is this is them basically shouting into the
wind and pretending some sort of pretense of relevancy here we talked about it there's
like a couple news stories maybe and then that's it right it's done it's in a way it's
an average it's advertising the little bit of sway that they they seem to be lacking
now over the free software community it's sort of it sort of undermines their position
in a way to do things like this I should move on because I'm probably pissing off a lot
of people things to talk about yes including including Wes I have right here in my hot
little boxes a new distro that I bet you've never seen whoa yes never tried oh distro
it is very bespoke it is very very bespoke and I did a little sniffing around under the
hood and I I got a full report if you like going under the hood and then friends I recommend
Linux Academy that's right Linux Academy comm slash unplugged as a platform to learn more
about not just Linux but all of the great things around Linux the nitty-gritty itsy
bitsy details all the way up to the high level stack I mean this is a serious platform with
downloadable comprehensive study guides instructor mentoring content getting updated all the
time a great staff behind it it's legit experiences admin are new to the world of Linux Azure
and AWS OpenStack and DevOps a sharp skill set is an absolute necessity to succeed meet
Linux Academy an online Linux and cloud training platform that uses self-paced video courses
and hands-on labs to give you real-world experience for a wide range of skills trained for your
certification learn the latest DevOps tools and grow your skill set to do better work
Linux Academy is not just a video library our scenario based server labs and quiz system
allow you to learn hands-on we also have full-time human instructors who answer questions and
help you earn that certification or promotion at work we add new training every week so
you'll always be up to date on the latest tech sysadmins of every experience level use
Linux Academy to stay on the bleeding edge of the Linux ecosystem you should too that's
also a great point just to stay current and up-to-date on these technologies Linux Academy
dot com slash unplugged go there sign up for a free seven-day trial kick the tires see
what I'm talking about use the core scheduler for your busy week figure out how these learning
paths can help you lock into a specific type of learning path which help you know in those
moments we like I just got to get this done and I know exactly the type of content I need
to buzz through and instructors have built these learning paths just for your particular
career tasks you might be in this is really a slick system and one of the things I continue
to use it for and I never ever would have thought this in my and I guess is probably
because of the way my mind works is this feature that I thought was kind of silly at first
called nuggets who calls it nuggets good sound delicious actually and they turn out
to be just like these deep dive topics where you can go in get something it's like maybe
five minutes long maybe it's an hour long it depends on the content it's just whatever
the content dictates and you just learn that one particular thing so it's not like how
to do Python on Linux it's not that broad it provides a little like sandboxed area like
okay I'm gonna learn this one thing I can understand this one thing and you come out
of it with a new skill or tool I mean I got 45 minutes yeah exactly check it out linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged sign up for a free seven-day trial and a big thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring the unplugged program so they call it leery l-i-r-i l-i-r-i leery is an
OS and apps built with modern design and features it's available for download right now they
say we're building some exciting features including atomic upgrades powerful notification
support not average power and much much more we're leveraging the latest and greatest Linux
technologies including OS tree Wayland Qt 5 and much more wow they say by utilizing
elements and principles of material design we'll be able to create a framework that incorporates
components and animations that provide more feedback to users additionally a single underlying
responsive system across all platforms to allow more unified user experiences leery
is a mediocratic consensus based community interested in developing an OS and apps with
modern design in mind we believe in the power of open source free software and worldwide
collaboration as we want to build share and improve software together and make it available
to everyone a modern responsive framework based on material design and universal integrated
apps leery ships with a set of modern and flexible apps and the core apps are tightly
integrated into the OS yeah so I did a little sniffing I went to the downloads want to get
a little idea of what I was dealing with here and I something something jumps out at me
you can try leery OS with a live image and eventually install it from there or if you're
already using arch Linux you can add a repository to install the packages and build them for
yourself with the AUR interesting yeah yeah I could just turn this thing up into a material
design desktop yeah now how are they gonna do atomic transactional updates using I don't
know I think it's they probably got they got some distance to travel but so yeah I loaded
it up here and yeah it is a let me expand the size now this feels like one of those
distros that does not really that deserves to be I should put it this way this is a distro
that deserves to be tested outside of VM yeah bare metal they're talking about animations
and I've already noticed some of it it's usable and I just wanted to show it to you guys check
out this cray cray launcher West now for those of you on the audio feed let me I'll describe
it to you you click on what looks like it might be the gnome applications button because
I've got one right I've got one right next to it looks almost just like the gnome all
applications button but when you click it it brings up a what was your window it's like
a modal file manager almost but it's got like a search bar at the top yeah and it's you
type the application name so you put in like terminal there and then okay can't hit enter
but then you click it and it it launches terminal they have a their own terminal window decorations
here they have their own likes bar there that there's a gap between where the applications
are and the launcher is to where the clock is and the notifications are at notifications
slide out on a slide tray same with like network settings they slide out in there and disk
information as well where I can see what this are mounted and the date and time but there's
no calendar in there like you might expect like say from like solace I think it's kind
of interesting it has like built-in share buttons in the terminal window or no maybe
although I'm sorry those are open a new window it has a tab support even though it seems
to be their own application so they are building some of their own apps too which is they mentioned
that do you see anything else in there that looks let's take a look because there's not
a lot of here's not a lot of apps and pre-installed apparently and now all you get is terminal
no I bet here we go so yeah this is pretty much it this is pretty much let's check out
the file manager because that's kind of my my only other I'm betting this is oh nope
this is their own file manager look at that wow it does look like material design it does
yeah it looks very Android it but none of it even scrolls like Android do you see that
yeah I do it's got a little momentum to the scrolling it rolls a little bit after I finish
scrolling but not in a bad way it's not crappy really could be worth oh yeah well that's
that looks right flashback there yeah it looks like an Android dog box but it really I mean
it really could be worse yeah yeah yeah so I don't personally in my life have any room
for another distribution that wants to whole cloth create all of its own apps and its own
desktop paradigm use those X apps every day Chris yeah oh yeah that's right this is using
Wayland that's right it's no good it's no guy kidding what about this as like on a Chromebook
on a Chromebook or as the like desktop component to like a convergent style phone device like
Maru but if instead of like a Debian XFCE it launched something like this I've always
been a fan of a desktop UI that has animations that do that serve a purpose that explain
to you the position of Windows or they explain to you where an alerts coming from or they
show you where an applications land once you've installed it like there's certain animations
that I find actually be they help you in yeah intuitively understand and then there's some
animations where it's just excessive and when your systems under load you're like okay that
looks like crap so you got to walk that line but I actually feel like there's I feel like
there's more room for that kind of stuff in desktop Linux and I like that there is a project
out there that's willing to mess around with that if they're really gonna build some sort
of unified core running on top of Wayland I mean I'm gonna check it back in on it I'm
gonna see how we absolutely yeah we should put it on bare metal one no word yes no word
on touch support I don't see that the governance model seems interesting too for a distribution
like this the leery is a mediocratic consensus based community okay that seems very specific
and they have documents out that describe their governance model so they're like I feel
like they're big about it yeah hopefully that means a constructive good community can form
they have an app they have app rovers maintainers chief maintainers decision makers lazy consensus
decision making typically involves the following steps proposal discussion discussion by consensus
maintainer if consensus not reached and chief maintainer they really got some of this stuff
dialed in like they got some stuff seriously figured out about their about their organization
anybody the mummer have any thoughts on leery building a new distro with a you know new
desktop paradigm creating their own apps again anything like that I'll put it up to you guys
for a moment before we move on no no no I think it I think Wes was right it looks like
it'd be something it'd be good on Chromebooks but outside of that I'm not not sure we need
more of the same when people aren't already doing this work yeah I don't want to discourage
them from doing something cool but it's probably not for me for a little bit it might be fun
to play with if you got an extra machine like when West finally gets a new Sputnik or whatever
he's gonna get totally be cool to throw it on we should I mean I'll throw it on here
I left like half the hard drive here just for distro there's no apps though I guess
if you have the AUR then that's where you are yeah they probably have to pull down all
those GTK you probably I'll make that sacrifice for you guys Wow Wes you know what you know
what else we should try is that where's that what happened that what happened to the Raspberry
Pi story we never covered the Raspberry Pi story should we just talk about it real quick
yeah I guess we should because we forgot to so this week Mycroft released images for the
Raspberry Pi so you can put I secretly use yeah I know I know I know that you don't have
to interrupt the show you can put Mycroft images now on a Raspberry Pi and go all you
know Amazon Echo style using a pie so I got one right here so I was thinking maybe I might
try it eventually what do you think of this West is something to be willing to kick with
kick around and see if that works I don't know if I have an SD card for mine at the
moment yeah that was my limitation maybe I'll order a new one if I can't find one tonight
yeah I mean I'm kind of curious especially after you got the Alexa here in studio let's
see if it can't and there is an element like I played with it a little bit I've installed
like the the desktop version that kind of thing but there is something to be said about
just being able to flash it onto a drive stick it in a pie that really I'm just like same
with you it's like sitting on my shelf I've been waiting for a project to use it on so
I can certainly start talking to it and connecting it to things around my house and it seems
like a very it seems like a platform that's easy a lot of people have it and it makes
the barrier to entry a lot lower yeah that is a huge thing to start playing with I hope
this I would what I would hope for is that this creates some serious adoption because
right now we have this we have this I think we have this really bad habit in the open
source Linux community and maybe general tech community at all as a whole it's probably
not just us where we get all hot and bothered on specs and features and technical differences
that matter to some degree but don't matter in the wider market and that's premature
optimization so we're kind of sitting here like gosh it's gonna be so cool once Mycroft
is about as fast as an echo and can do about half the stuff that the Google home could
or echo can do like it's gonna be great when it gets to that point it's not even at that
point and we're still here talking like it's a possibility that this thing has a chance
in the market but that's only because we're geeks like the reality is the markets already
moving on and I really I mean to that end was I believe that so firmly and I really
I I spent a lot of time on this show like bringing attention to Mycroft and talking
about what important can be and I'd still love to see the project continue I'd love
to see it work on Linux desktops but I really think like the home market I here was what's
in you tell me what's in this box oh this looks new yeah I just came today actually
so it's kind of funny that we're covering the story this is a new brand new inbox Amazon
echo yeah I full one the big boy you know ten speakers and everything yeah I got that
for the RV I you're sold huh yeah yeah yeah it is really it once what I actually like
I actually think it's I know people are worried about monitoring but in some ways it's actually
improved my network security so I like it for that reason alone but how do you feel
about Amazon's platform versus Google well I definitely feel safer about Amazon see
Amazon I think is on the this is why I think really the Mycroft doesn't have a shot is
Amazon has this huge institutional priority to get these things in your homes they don't
have a storefront they can't guarantee you're gonna go to amazon.com when you need to buy
something but if they can get an echo in your house then they have essentially get ready
for a debug term here they've disrupted the store they if they can they can do if technology
can give them a quantum leap over even needing to establish stores although I could see Amazon
opening stores one day but I think this is so fundamental to their long-term business
because it's not just about buying shit on Amazon because having three dots or two that
I use and one for the beard I've never bought one thing from Amazon I don't know if I ever
will buy anything from Amazon using an echo device because it's like a minor feature that's
not what you know what it for you know what I do buy from Amazon is I buy shit that's
compatible with Alexa now so a lot of stuff on Amazon says works with Alexa and it's becoming
a massive at part of their like accessories and technology they're selling related to
the Alexa so there's that entire market then there is the fact a lot of people will use
it to buy stuff off of Amazon that is something a lot of people will and do use it for there
is a massive strategic priority for Amazon to have a device like this in your home and
they don't need it for monitoring your metrics your data your mood they don't need it for
the reasons Google needs it to sell you ads they need it to make their business profitable
and sustainable they need a storefront in your home nobody else needs that like Amazon
does so they have a real incentive to make this thing work with as many third parties
as possible to make the API as generous as possible they have the biggest incentive to
keep updating to give it more features they're going to keep pushing the price down nobody
else even has a multi-device ecosystem now there's like three echo devices you can buy
directly from Amazon dot tap and echo now after CES like a dozen other manufacturers
including frickin Ford in cars has announced echo integration so we're sitting here talking
about mycroft now the conversation about mycroft is going to have to be how can us
geeks incorporated into our homes and our desktops not how is the market going to adopt
mycroft that's that's not happening I found it interesting what you were talking
about about the perhaps market pressure pressure for third-party integrations which I think
is important if we're going down this road of a proprietary semi-documented interface
rightly way better if you could use the echo and use the and use mycroft in the same way
because they integration spoke the same language but probably that's not what we're gonna happen
I would love that but so at least we would need an ecosystem that is right like it matters
less to Google do that than it does Lipsy in the chat room says this is a lot of self-rationalizing
going on that's the kind of tech arrogance I'm talking about where you think well because
it's open source because I could run a lot of devices and people could create plugins
for it and make it extensible it's obviously gonna win one day that's such bullshit like
if that was the case we'd all be using free software on our phones right now that's not
how the real world works anymore it's all about ecosystem it's all about who you integrate
with and all of that integration is closed up behind these stupid API's the world's all
gone to API's well API's mean I control what you have access to that's what an API is and
so that's how the entire world communicates now and mycroft isn't anywhere in the spectrum
unless there's somebody like Hughes or somebody else who just has a general public API they
make available service integration things like that only Amazon and Google and Microsoft
are gonna be able to make those kind of deals and right now I don't think anybody has anything
that competes nowhere near to what the Echo can do that's not self-rationalization that's
I thought this was a joke product for like a year I was skeptical of this thing finally
got one because they put the dot on sale at 40 bucks and I thought alright I'm gonna give
this a go and you know what I've changed my tune I think really have yeah I think it's
a really legitimate product category and it's not just me it's my entire family uses it
when they're like when the kids are here when he is here they're they've all taken to using
it for all kinds of things like it's it gets frequent use by other people besides me I
think 2017 is gonna be a really interesting like I'm really curious to see if if you say
the same thing at the end of this year right now about the family about the excitement
about your uses and then at the same time like is this like first first out there advantages
Amazon just gonna take off with it or are we gonna see some competitors are we gonna
see this as a general enough category who else has the presence they do to it like they
constantly are pushing on every box you get from Amazon it's it's covered in echo branding
they have they have the echo plastered all over their page when you go to amazon.com
every any device or service that works with the echo it says it right there on the on
the product and I agree I mean I think they have all those advantages I only ask because
it's still early days in some ways for this industry I think it's shifted with CES and
a little bit before I think it shifted to a couple I think also people are more the
industry is more willing to get in bed with Amazon because they're already in bed like
selling stuff through Amazon whereas Google is bigger risk and Amazon seems more consistent
right like Google's the often they're like high castle out there doing their thing deprecating
what they want stopping agreements whenever they want they you know like the whole they
bought Motorola just to sell them to Lenovo you can't really trust Google to do except
for their core advertising business right and I I think what I'm concerned about with
mycroft is it sort of the smartphone problem only way worse like the smartphone is sort
of was made like the iPhone part of what made the iPhone successful was the whole ecosystem
of content apps music videos and when Android first launched Google didn't really have that
stuff there wasn't a play store it took Google like three years to really get that stuff
all figured out and dialed in and then now they have a pretty successful ecosystem it's
the same with this only to a higher degree because now it's not just the music and the
videos that you integrate with but it's also all of the hardware products and the home
services and and it's things like alarm companies and and you know business relationships are
being made and if your device can't do those things if you know if if your Amazon device
can unlock your house or lock it when you leave it but the Google one can't then what
are you gonna do you're not gonna relock your whole house now I'm not saying everybody listening
to the show wants those things no certainly not and I think there's for me there's still
a I'm still gonna play around with mycroft I'm still gonna see what I can do I would
prefer that it does everything the echo can do but I'm pretty skeptical at this point
and not not not happily so either I'm kind of bummed out about it I think I think it's
kind of it's kind of a bit of a bad situation and I think that's something to be clear about
too is like you're not saying that you don't have these other qualms or this desire to
use mycroft right but you're you're exploring this in a practical sense of like you have
a studio that you run you need you want something that can help you and to help automate your
day-to-day life and the echo is meeting that need yeah it does it it I think it's it's
hard to describe the value of the product until you have one because it really depends
on your setup and if you don't have hardware to control it's less valuable it immediately
I would I would be 40 bucks asking it things it's like well I can I can do that with my
phone exactly yeah that's not a compelling use case for the kids and others like it I
do not I know I don't I don't do that that's not what I use it for I use it specifically
to automate things in studio and whatnot all right well let's let's move on there's been
something I got some feedback on a lot of people said you know we we've talked a lot
about recent Mac switchers and a lot of people oh Chris you're such a Mac hater such a Mac
hater and I thought there was says the man towards the man who's made how many hackintoshes
and other things well I don't it's just they're just I don't think they're good value propositions
so there's another post that I was posted just after last week's show and I I wanted
to instead of go through his whole why I switched to Linux but it's yet another why I'm switching
to Linux from Mac OS which is interesting in itself but what I wanted to cover was some
of the replacements he came up with for his Mac apps because I thought that would be kind
of interesting so for iTunes he switched to no music for Photoshop he switched again
not too surprising there for sublime text he went to Emacs for Lawrence yeah wow yeah
I know for Lightroom he went to dark table for albatron live which is audio processing
he went to our door for DD he went to gnome disk which is funny that he switched from
DD I know right yeah textual he went to hex chat mailed that app to Thunderbird I cal
the gnome calendar address book to gnome contacts I term two to terminator good choice reader
to feed the monkey Twitter for Mac to just using the website he says I basically stopped
using Twitter so it's not really a big deal he switched from no password manager to key
pass and he uses type talk which I might try out which is I guess it's a it's an app that
allows the computer to read articles to you and whatnot mmm type talk nice I could see
that especially if you're like well I want to read this but I'm you know doing the dishes
or I there is something fascinating about peeking into their experience because they're
looking at some of these applications for the first time say in 10 years and so watch
them evolved for the right years necessarily so to them it's like look there's this contacts
application gnome has a calendar now and me I'm like why does gnome have a calendar and
they're like no mess I can't wait from the coming from Mac like that makes sense you
expect that yeah yeah talks about how this is better than the disk program is macOS now
that's that is true though yeah it's I was just recently experimenting with a hackintosh
and I don't even know how you format things in that I don't I don't just go to the terminal
yeah like I just I was like this is how the disk manager works in macOS now this is this
is that was bad so why did I switch this is the summary this is the part I thought we'd
touch on I think it started with some dissatisfaction about OS 10 and the desire to be at least
in theory able to change things so they would work like I want them this translates directly
to the GPL with its which is the license most of these programs I use is under add that
to the feeling of membership because everyone at work is using Linux and also pride in curiosity
I'm able to look behind the scenes which he likes a lot directly at the code this is not
possible on OS 10 at all and to top it all off with the fact that I use Linux on so many
different hardware my laptop my desktop at work the security cam I'm running in Poland
the Raspberry Pi I have embedded devices in my car on the phone my router and so on all
this together right now is so compelling macOS doesn't stand a chance that's it's interesting
that the the pressure of everything else using Linux is encouraging him to give Linux another
chance to he did try Linux back in the day like he was a mandrake user he was you know
there are a lot of Mac Mac users in that same position like well we tried it we dabbled
with it yeah here was this like beautiful shiny Unix compatible thing that well we were
gonna go with it um it was kind of he's also just a couple other things he says you know
I started off I just love this because because this really fits my prediction I'll be honest
that's really why I love this because because I've been I've been seeing this and so it's
fascinating to see this materialize so this is exactly what I was this is exactly what
I've been thinking because he writes after five or six years of he admits I fell in love
with macOS but after five or six years I started seeing the cracks first small they introduced
spaces and a desktop manager that wasn't working anymore thus I wasn't able to change the speed
which I could change between virtual desktops which are central to my workflow then they
introduced iCloud into a text editor and instead of starting it and then you could save anywhere
on my hard drive I had to take an extra step and tell it not to save to iCloud I hated
it so much that I rewrote text editor myself so it would work like it did before with plain
text and he links to text Ed iTunes started getting out of control accurate yeah he says
and it gets worse and worse with time I wanted my computer to work a certain way and it often
worked that way before then came OS 10 update and made it possible to keep and made it impossible
to keep my workflow so I don't use macOS much and so I don't often upgrade but I have the
macbook pro that you know we installed archon during this show and a dual boots final cut
OS and so I went into final cut OS and I decided well if I'm going to use final cut I should
update the latest version of final cut OS because it's totally free so from the final
cut app store it downloads final cut OS and doesn't install and updates to mac OS final
cut Sierra I don't know and you know what the first thing it does and I went you know
what I wanted to do two different things I wanted to edit my video and go to bed it wanted
to re-index all of the photos on the computer for some sort of deep learning analysis which
pegged my processor cores at 40% so at least they're doing it locally right but that's
why it's pegging your processor I'm like I like and is it not like set as a low priority
like how is it not falling off into the background when I go to use final cut how is that not
a thing they thought of yeah well I actually what I did is I was so frustrated I just rebooted
back into archons and I'll edit later that sucks though it does because you know what
I ended up doing is I just oh yeah this thing so in the morning I booted it up and let it
sit there and do its thing and then just shut it down again so that way it's done so now
you can edit video yeah yeah because I just let it go for a while but I really feel like
I had no domain over that computer I like I guess it's not too unusual after an upgrade
for some backend process to work like that but I don't need my photos I don't use photos
on that Mac I don't need it to do those things there's just probably stuff that's in that
library because that's where stuff gets dumped like I don't need that to be done like I would
just like to go and check that box and I looked around in the OS I couldn't find anywhere
that allows me to turn off that feature it just does it I don't need my photos analyzed
you know right that's the kind of thing it just drives me nuts about that and I feel
like if they were focused on that platform like it was the only they didn't make an iOS
device and it was the only major platform they had to worry about these kinds of little
cracks wouldn't be so bad but they feel like iOS has really especially with how popular
and how much it defined the early smartphone era I feel like it changed the idea of who
their product was right and so that has changed the way that they design products well you
know I mean they send they sell they might sell a hundred million iPhones in a year and
they might sell 20 million racks and no one thinks that an iPhone is thinking differently
right like that that's just it doesn't it's incongruent yeah that's interesting too so
I wanted to move now that we've had that little brief aside unless anybody in the moment wants
to jump in and I thought we'd go something more technical just to sort of refresh our
palates this is an interesting talk that you found I think right building a billion user
load balancer this was at the USENIX conference I think is that right and this was a gentleman
from Facebook Patrick Shuff I think and he gave a talk on that and I just thought I'd
play just a moment before it's very interesting and I'll jump ahead a little bit here into
the presentation single server served all of Facebook so the entirety of Facebook every
request comes in and we're gonna slowly build up one by one layer by layer each of our load
balancing infrastructure pieces so that we get to the point where we have a multi data
center multi-continent load balancing infrastructure to serve all of the requests a couple of points
I want to make here is we use a lot of open source software so almost all the pieces in
this talk are going to be open source there is going to be some custom stuff Facebook
specific to our environment that aren't necessarily open source but all of this stuff is easily
done in open source and I will talk about all of those different projects as well and
lastly my my goal for this talk is for you guys to you know think about the patterns
that we use you know use doing what we do for load balancing might not make sense for
everybody but kind of looking at the patterns and how we evolve our infrastructure and applying
it to some of the things that you guys are building now he does get into numbers so when
people ask me what is a traffic what does the traffic engineer at Facebook do this is
the image that comes to mind so this is a visualization showing all the people on Facebook
and all their connections to all the other people on Facebook our job is to make sure
that no matter where you are in the world when you open up Facebook app on your phone
or you type Facebook.com into a web browser that you connect to our servers as fast and
secure as possible so our job is to make sure that you know we were able to connect the
world you know that is the mission of Facebook is to make the world more open wow so just
to kind of quickly go over the agenda for today we'll talk about the different types
of requests that kind of make up Facebook it's kind of hyperbole but I suppose in a
way it is sort of true like I think most of my family that's not technical uses Facebook
to stay in touch absolutely it's like they sometimes use email for like planning big
family events but mostly everything and since I'm not on Facebook when I show up at family
events I'm like out of the lube on half the stuff and I get the feeling too in that way
where it's like well we used email because grandma isn't on Facebook and but she does
check her email once in a while you know and then you're like so suddenly you're lumped
in a very different technical group I still get the question what is Linux what is what
is Linux and I you can say you know to something that really connects with people it's what
powers huge websites like Facebook yeah lastly I'll open it up for Q&A and you guys you know
can ask any questions about load balancing Facebook production engineering anything at
all all right now here's the numbers I believe so let's dive quickly and talk about some
numbers real fast these are company-wide numbers every month and the month of the month of
September 1.7 9 billion people use Facebook and on average over that month 1.1 out 1 8
billion people use Facebook so these numbers are really cool and you know these are Facebook
numbers but I think about these in terms of a traffic engineers perspective so that means
every day assuming there's only one TCP connection per device and this is you know I think you
guys all know this is probably very improbable you know that means we at least have to terminate
1.1 8 billion TCP connections every single day and serve us from those and also the really
important interesting thing is 1.09 billion are on mobile devices so we have to think
about people who are using high-speed you know LTE or or you know landline cable modems
we also have to think about people using networks like 2g and 3g wow you know all these different
networking environments and we need to make sure when you hear numbers like that it gives
you an idea of how entrenched Android and iOS are when the numbers of mobile active
I want to just make sure these that this didn't go over you 1.09 billion mobile daily active
people they're not even like fudging that it's daily active so it's not like you have
an account but you never log in it's daily active people can you imagine building an
infrastructure for that and that's just mobile that's just mobile I mean it should be said
they probably engineer their apps so that if you ever installed the app that it wakes
up at least once a day to ping their servers but that's still their service right so they
still have to design for it that's probably true oh I like the way you think Wes that's
probably very true that is probably something there to it but damn even if they were they
are responding to those TPC yeah I don't think most people could handle that kind of load
unbelievable so it's just cool like whatever you may think of Facebook and obviously we
both have our qualms there yeah they do either not very much yeah I have an account I have
an account as well I do use Instagram sometimes but yeah I've experimented with Facebook more
as like a means to drive traffic than anything else they do some serious engineering yeah
and that's all laid out in this video well not all of it obviously but a lot of really
good stuff is laid out at least at 16 and you can get access to it usenik.org you can
find more but I would probably just start with the link in the show notes and then go
out from there because that's a big site and that's an interesting talk and yeah like Wes
is saying regardless of your opinions of Facebook the technical feeds and you know what's fascinating
yeah bringing it from just one server to what it is now mind-blowing that is a hell of a
project a hell of a project if you want to get started with your own infrastructure friends
digitalocean.com is the place to do it digitalocean.com use the promo code do1plug it's one word
it's one word it's the best word do1plug unplug digitalocean but not really because I mean
that'd be cray cray because you know what happens a lot of 40 gigabit connections right
just like would you take you all day all day all day and they got data centers all over
the world so you better get prepared to travel and then they'd have one of those talented
engineers from digital ocean just plugging them right back in right behind you you'd
never win they probably could outnumber you yeah that's the thing and if you use the it's
just way easier to use the promo code do1plug go create account apply it to your account
and then get started they got a great interface very simple and intuitive to use five dollars
a month for one of their machines or you can go hourly I love the hourly system so great
for trying out open source projects lots of nice stuff that I'll I'll often just burn
a digital ocean droplet for an hour yeah exactly oh some sense I might count fine yeah totally
worth it three cents an hour okay all right well I can do that I get two cores I mean
this one of the best parts is that unlike some other cloud providers you may have used
they're so upfront about their pricing it's like bam this is what you're going to pay
here you go you know it mm-hmm and it's all SSD based so even at the five dollar one you're
still getting a 40 gigabit e-connection you're still getting SSDs you can still pick from
a data center all over the world you can choose any district you want or that free BSD which
I hear people like digital ocean calm use the promo code do unplugged and by the way
they are doing early sign up like they were with their block storage not too long ago
for monitoring for like metrics very curious to see what it looks like yeah I am too I
bet I mean man so far everything they've released I've been super impressed with the UI to manage
it I'm really curious to see what they come up with really curious so they say they're
launching it soon no configuration required hey damn you can get alerts when problem I'm
signing up to right now I'm gonna do it right now that is that's a that's a no brainer all
right there I've signed up digital ocean calm use the promo code do unplugged in a big thank
you to digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program so you guys I don't think I need to
build the case that I think the Mac books are a bit of a train wreck or that I think
people are switching from Mac to Linux and Windows to Linux obviously but I'll tell you
something that was super disappointing in my test and you might have heard me mention
earlier that I was I was experimenting with a hackintosh over the weekend I tried it on
three different computers just to kind of see what the state of hackintoshing was and
that was following a test I did which was massively disappointing we have we frequently
have a conversation on our different shows about media production under Linux and a lot
of times people say they have a pet project have you tried have you tried Katie and live
have you tried blender have you tried open shot have you tried you know all of these
and there was a question posted on the our Linux subreddit about the current state of
Linux video editing in 2017 and I I just happened to go through another round of this I tried
it on my XPS 13 on the entryware Apollo on the Librem 15 and on my custom build hair
master machine which is a six core i7 with 32 gigs of RAM and all SSD storage that's
with a GTX 9 handsome as you are Chris it's not a GTX thank you well thanks Wes you handsome
devil yourself it's not a GTX 10 series graphics so it could do better there but it is a GTX
9 series graphics so for video editing purposes it's it's pretty capable out of all of the
machines that I used in my testing none of them could even play back my test footage
except for hair master and to do so it took all the six core CPU performance I have which
didn't leave much left over for applying effects and I'm not talking editing I'm not talking
rendering I'm saying just trying to play the footage back that I intend to edit the systems
literally cannot do it so there is now footage that is available in consumer grade equipment
that the codecs on Linux are just not capable of playing back I'm talking things at 4k resolution
not crazy frame rates not well high bit rates but not unbelievably high bit rates and they
just they just do not play they just chop or like in the case of some players they they
freak out and it goes all green or they flip the image and it's two frames a second in
2017 I honestly believe the state of Linux edit video editing is worse than it's been
in a while we have what we have right now are a half a dozen half baked tools that are
almost good enough but not good enough and we don't have a supporting media pipeline
under those tools to make it all connect and to make playback streamless and to guarantee
that if something works in one editor it'll work in another editor like if you won't even
get in there that's an entirely different dimension we are in a we are in a really bad
position if you're trying to do anything with that any if you're trying to work with any
camera that was sold in 2016 or 2017 I was gonna say like is it safe to say that like
we're getting there in terms of like video from 2009 but you know like yeah all right
you've got like maybe 1080 video you can edit that you can do it but any 30 frames a second
you could probably do that but modern video which is not that anymore like the world has
moved on and we are not catching up right and so this guy on reddit kind of had the
same experience he said some of some 4k wouldn't even play back on my machines there were only
five minute clips I recently went through I tried Katie and live PDV blender Lightworks
open shot as my main ones I spent the most time with Katie and live and Lightworks because
those are the ones I always tend to like the most and of all that I like Katie and live
the best so if you have a straightforward project it's really it's but but it's not even Katie
and lives fault anymore like the fault lies in the underlying yeah in the codecs they're
not hardware accelerated and depending on which ones you get they if they are hardware
accelerated they don't support the right resolution and frame rate so they have to fall back to
CPU decoding and we are leaving the world where CPU decoding is impossible it just doesn't
work anymore yeah it took a six core system playing from an MV and then from a fast solid
state storage to play it back the enemy yes thank you and I so the when this when this
question came in about the current state of video editing on Linux this is an area where
it's still it's the thing is is a 2013 MacBook Pro that I have can play this back not only
can it play these files back but I can apply real-time color and I can speed them up and
slow them down and I can apply those effects interact with them I can so like yeah that's
a 2013 MacBook Pro running a system name is a 2015 but hey oh but you get my point exactly
right like and yet you could buy the latest XPS or whatever and not be able to do it on
I mean these are this this is a sky like let alone over here X I mean it's a pretty bad
situation and I maybe it's just not a market we're ever just gonna be able to capture because
maybe the maybe the technology is moving too fast and maybe it's just not possible maybe
there's just certain things that open source isn't equipped to tackle is that I hate that
I hate that be the conclusion I come to but I just and it's frustrating to be in the position
where like there's so many tools right where Windows has the or Mac has the like power
user light option but then you can go to Linux and get the like oh no you're an expert this
is the real power but video editing is not that way right like you the second you go
to Linux you start making compromises you're like well but yes I want to make manual workflows
yes I want to do these things like I don't mind spending a few minutes configuring so
that I get optimal things but those settings are not as good as on the proprietary solution
people listening could will often respond well what about transcoding into an intermediate
codec or what about working with proxy media you know you could do Chris you could do this
with proxy media that first thing no suggested that all takes a ton of time and it it doesn't
allow for sort of a flexible creativity that is when you can take a set of mixed resolution
mixed frame rate footage drop it all in your timeline put your piece of music down and
just start cutting and working with the music with the footage it's an entirely different
process then I'm going to import all my camera footage I'm going to load up this program
that transcodes all my footage into this output directory then I'm going to take this output
directory I'm going to add it to my project folder then I'm going to add this project
folder into the editor and I'll only work with this media and then once I render it
out I'll replace this media with the final foot with the final cut with the final you
know high resolution footage and just hope that all of the color effects and all of the
speed up and all that translates well to the final footage even though it's a different
frame rate it's a totally different codec it just doesn't make any sense and it would
be one thing like if you worked at the local news station or something with the support
crew right but especially with like the the vlogging you've been doing etc like I don't
I don't know if people understand the workflow where like you're on your own you've got like
three different cameras you've got one laptop you've got a truck and you're trying to like
you're trying out experimental shots you need to be able to review that footage right there
on the scene and figure out what's going to work or not yeah it's it's it's this weird
paradigm because we have all of this flexibility with hardware we have all this flexibility
with software but it's left us sort of incapable of answering certain types of workloads and
it's the most frustrating thing because it would be perfect so I'd say for depending
on your workload and depending on your camera footage and depending on the bit rate of your
clips what your expectations are yeah if you wanted to jump in with Linux video editing
and you were working with some pretty straightforward stuff I just went through it again I mean
I've done this on and off for years but I just went through this I think Katie and live
still my favorite I thought I go Katie and live I go with a dark theme I think it looks
really pro it works well it sometimes is a little sluggish the it's weird some of the
effects the way you change the settings are super arbitrary and weird and and not like
any other editor you'll ever use but you know as far as an editor that just works and is
pleasant to use and allows me to have your audio tracks and your video tracks and intermix
and have multiple tracks and it's really simple works in a way that a person who's edited
video would expect Katie and live org we should throw that in the show notes to put that in
there too all right mumble room anybody have thoughts on media production under Linux before
we wrap before we go I know and I also should just say that I don't feel like this any of
this applies to audio production on your Linux no ironically I feel very different yeah I
feel like I feel like if you were gonna only use if you can only have one platform to do
audio podcasts Linux would be it especially with some of the cool stuff wimpy makes some
of the cool open source projects that are out there some of the stuff we've built internally
yeah the script ability and automate ability I think XMN might be right is what Final Cut
is is sort of sort of what you what you get when you control the operating system the
software application that runs on it and the hardware that's the upside the downside is
anemic hardware a company that has an unsure direction that's focused on a different product
and has way too expensive prices I mean that new MacBook is a killer so that's the downside
of the Apple approach just in a nutshell and the lock-in obviously but the upside is for
one particular application this entire stack integration it's all optimized I mean they
know they know their quirks and how to write for it so yeah all right I'll get off my high
horse but I wanted I think part of the reason why I wanted to talk about this with you guys
is we've spent a few episodes in a row talking about how people are leaving the Mac and about
how the Mac is crap and about Mac OS is junk and about how they're switching to Linux and
I just I just also wanted to give you a little bit of a reality check and say it's not all
roses like the the that platform is still viable for a large portion of the workforce
that right now Linux is in my personal opinion fallen behind moron now because equipment
has pulled ahead and so the situation right now is worse in some ways than it has been
in a while because it you now give me the point where Linux isn't even capable of playing
some of these files so I know I've spent a lot of time harping on the MacBook and people
switching to Linux but I felt like this was sort of a counterbalance to some of that and
I'll keep testing and I'm not ever done testing oh no certainly not right none of these are
foregone conclusions it's more of a this is what's the feeling right now yeah this is
sort of like I've gone through around it all up and this is sort of where it lands for
me personally the other thing about it is everybody's workload is different what the
footage you're working with is different the the aspects and goals of your project is your
turnaround time what's the yeah right there's a huge part of it to affect that huge part
of it if I did one two shows a week I might you could do proxy or like whatever exactly
exactly that would be it but if I'm trying to do something every single night totally
different and and during the day to it's not like it's like I do it all day long and then
I go home and I do it at night now as a side project so it's like it's really got to be
pretty tight it's and there's really no time for extra bullshit yeah yeah and so that all
is a totally different thing but I feel like that sort of probably more better my my view
probably is more representative of the larger industry and and maybe less and less and less
of the personal hobbyist and but I think it's probably where the money is where people would
be coming from where the switchers are becoming from and when people are looking for certain
requirements that group I have I think I have a better idea of what that group will be looking
at and I'd say right now we're worse off in some ways right and I guess it comes back
to that story of like you know are you trying to sell someone you're like yeah you should
pick up this new Linux rig and it'll do all your things but if they're the new hobbyist
vlogger can you honestly say that and not say yeah but here's the here's the capitulation
job to me I'd say it depends on how professional you want your stuff to look that's one thing
and it like if you're doing a screencast and you're cutting up the screencast to make a
little bit shorter or take it out a mistake that's that's Kaden live would be great or
you have a New Year's party video that you shot and you want to make a quick three-minute
video and share it around it's gonna be awesome for that you know you even maybe like a trailer
for a Kickstarter project there's a lot of things you could use it for so it really just
depends on what you're doing so that's sort of my answer to the state of video editing
in 2017 and I wonder I hope it's a good question I wonder I'll definitely know I mean I try
it it seems to be almost every other month or so I sit down and I go alright let's take
a project I get all the same footage and I say I'm gonna take the same footage I'm gonna
take I'm gonna try to make the same thing three or four times it's extremely monotonous
but it's the best test I have and I try to create the same exact product as close I can
and you know what in this test sometimes I feel like I end up with something better than
I did in the other editor like because the way it works and the workflow it's better
with the way my mind works I get a little more creative better with your creative spirit
yeah right and then other times I'm like I just basically make doldrums yeah grinding
it out it's the awful and it could all change right like maybe we live in the Vulcan Wayland
open source AMD driver Wonderland in two years but we're not there now many you had a question
before we wrap up no oh sorry many oh sorry sorry right I had you I had you muted I'm
sorry I'm a jerk go ahead talking to me yeah I had you muted I'm sorry repeat what you're
saying so did you do your tests on the X server and Wayland or only Wayland only X server
no way I think that no Wayland do you think that that had that has an influence on it
would it be I mean you know good try are you wondering for video playback yeah yeah I don't
really think this display server was the limiting factor I think the the issue was that all
of the codecs were dumping the decoding job off to the CPU and even on even on like a
Skylake you know system it just wasn't the throughput wasn't there yeah four cores but
not enough to six core system could do it though yeah yeah I thought there's something
else I thought I saw in the chat room but I think I will wrap it up there I think I've
made I've made my pay a piece about it oh yeah that was mr. go go says that the Linux
gamer is a good example someone who will use Linux for video editing yeah Linux gamer and
Linux gamecast yeah exactly there's projects out there that are being done on this stuff
that you can go check out right now they're producing content and I like I say you know
if I was doing one or two things a week and it might be a great like you don't have money
to shell out on a new Mac system totally the most professional editing software but you
want to start making your vlog or whatever like yeah Linux is still great for that yeah
and you got it really to like one of the nice things about Linux is where the software tool
might not be as quick or you got to make proxy media or the the toolkit might be a little
clunky but you could also get like a 12-core Xeon with 64 gigs of RAM and all that like
you can go nuts on that and it'll all work it all yeah so you there are areas where you
could where it's one part might be slower but you could go way faster another aspect
of it and you know the other nice thing is with arch and and and Ubuntu and and and all
of these different distributions having these video editors packaged for them you get just
as part of your package updates already there you get the new you get the new improved editor
which is nice actually it is generally with these it's nice to get that new stuff because
all the new OS that wants to re-index your pictures that's exactly what I'm talking
about that you don't get drug along with that strategy tax and so there's there are huge
benefits to doing media production under Linux I guess my advice is don't ever try Final
Cut don't ever don't don't do premiere don't use premiere don't use it is always easier
if you haven't tasted the you know yeah sweet sweet grass on the other side yeah yeah yeah
don't use what was that what's a Sony Vegas don't use Vegas don't use that don't use it
so don't use that never work at Pixar wait no that works on Linux yeah I know wouldn't
be nice if some of their tools yeah they're down although I thought I feel like their
tools be more like using blender and it's so funny there's people a lot of one of the
number one comments actually I get is Chris have you tried blender and I always my response
is have you tried blender for video editing it you have to create 3d views to just do
this simplest and this is again back to that like the like weird Mac Windows professional
hobbyist type thing right like it's like you're not barking basement you're not beginner you
have some budget for this thing but you're also not like this isn't necessarily your
like $200,000 a year day job thing you fall in the middle where you have serious expectations
you want to get stuff done and it's just not there but you also can't spend 50 grand on
a software license right yeah no and it's it's then and then on the other side of it
you just have a lackluster hardware that cost too much so it's you pay one word yeah that
is Chris's take on the current state of video editing and Linux and thanks to it was glee's
a web for asking that question because it got me it got me chewing on the topic a little
bit discussion it's some it's it's good counterbalance to a lot of the coverage we've been doing
recently all right that brings us to the end of this week's unplugged program would you
like to contribute you can do it several ways you can spread the word about the show maybe
somebody out there that would like a Linux podcast let them know that's a direct way
you can help the show you can also join us live in the chat room and chat as we go over
jblive.tv or hang out in our mumble room and get your voice heard in our virtual lug all
of that's possible just get started going to jblive.tv for the chat room where you can
get mumble information or jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar where you can get calendar
information now don't miss tech snap where you can check out Wes on the new tech snap
that's right that's right and we'll see you right back here next week.
I've never installed GNU slash Linux. Chris I've got a question for you. The other day
you might have been on Laz I think it was in between segments you were talking to Noah
about your laptop and things you like to keep installed on your laptop and you mentioned
sab nzb and couch i think yeah well actually not necessarily on my laptop but yeah on my
on my workstation upstairs uh right now it's uh right well it can be those two right now
my my setup is uh sonar and nzb git but i could also do sab nzb and sick rage couch
potato i care less about yeah i don't care as much about couch potato but uh it's nice
to have because i i made a snap of sab nzbd and couch potato no no really just to make
it nice and easy to install them and it's stupidly easy so how does it i wonder which
others you would use what is the okay so but here's the question what is the mechanism
now for that to get updated like that's kind of that's kind of what my docker question
was about is like if i get a docker image am i going to get behind on sab like what
is that mechanism so the the ultimate goal would be for me to contribute this to upstream
the main project and for them to have their continuous integration system push it into
the store whenever there's a new release and so you would just do you would just do nothing
it would just update automatically in the back end um it's much like like my next cloud
box updated i didn't even realize it upgraded from next cloud 10 to next cloud 11 the snap
just updated in the background and i had no idea and it just carried on working i didn't
do anything so that's the kind of thing but it would need to be update um adopted by upstream
so they would push it to the store that's uh those applications are a good example of
something that's a bit of work it's not impossible but it is a bit of work and if you could have
snaps for it that's really nice it's a great idea that's exact and i signed up for a new
service just so that i could test it because i haven't touched these for a while so yeah
yeah yeah it's it's uh it is a pretty slick um you know it's a pretty slick setup once
you get everything all set up because essentially they're set and once they're once they're
configured and the programs you want to monitor or the movies you want to monitor are specified
you just kind of walk away and everything will find it'll automatically find the content
download the content extract it rename it to a naming convention you want and put it
in the folder you want so that way your media server sees it it's pretty it's it really
is nice i just got the push notification on my phone about chelsea manning's uh sentence
being the book commutes the book the book of the sentence yeah that's amazing that's
great wow well i i might try that out poppy that's that's really cool yeah gimme um i'll
try the others so now i've looked at sonar and do you say nzb get yeah nzb get which
is i guess you know after i talked about i got a note from a couple people like you should
try nzb get chris it's actually a lot better actually i am using it that's what i am using
now uh sabin zb just seems to be the one that has more traction all right well i'll i'll
do these and commit them upstream and see what they say but i mean it may well be they
say no because some some projects we've talked to say no no no we're not interested you know
if you want to put it in the store do it yourself and then you know i could set up a cron job
that will just grab the latest and push it to the store or something but it's entirely
up to them it's their project yeah they can yeah yeah i hope they i hope they take you
up on it so that would be that would be really great