I wanted a good keyboard and there weren't any out there. I figured, well, how hard could this be?
And then we built the best keyboard we possibly could. It's not what you'd expect from a keyboard,
but people love it. Creating a keyboard is kind of a weird thing. It's been an obsession.
All right, Wes, can you master the keyboardio that runs Linux in a beautiful hardware body?
It is the keyboardio, a mechanical switch keyboard, custom sculpted keycaps. It's a dream to type on
and it sells for $329. Wes Payne has it here in studio hooked up USB-C to his laptop.
It has Arduino boards inside. Wes Payne, can you light the keyboardio on fire? What do you think,
sir? Well, it's either going to look beautiful or turn into a brick. One way or the other,
a lot of fun. We'll do it live on this week's episode of Linux Unplugged. Keyboardio,
the only keyboard where you can install plugins that make it look like your keyboard is on fire.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 279 for December 11th, 2018.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's making its list and checking
it twice. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Wes. I'm very excited about today's show.
Not only because you're lighting your keyboard on fire, you maniac, but we're going to share
a WireGuard success story this week. We implemented that brand new Linux VPN in production
here at Jupiter Broadcasting, and it kicked butt. Yeah, Chris doesn't hate it. I mean,
that's how you know. It was really great. And man, is it fast. We'll tell you about our
WireGuard success story. But first, we're going to start out with a big batch of community news,
a little check in on the Ubuntu 1904 development cycle. I'm running it here today in the studio,
and a potential fix for that crazy CPU system D dominating issue I talked about last week that
was wrecking my box. And then we'll finally introduce the name of our automation system
that you voted on. You did it. Not our fault. Can't blame us for this one. We're innocent.
We totally. And then we'll wrap up the show if time allows, you know, because time. Actually,
it's Joe really. If Joe allows, he does. He gets mad. But if Joe allows and time permits,
we have not one, but two fantastic fricking picks this week that are really great. And one of them
that just might bring me back to Reddit. But before we go any further, we got to bring in
that virtual log time appropriate. Greetings. Mumble room. Hello. Hi. Hi. Hi. Hello, Mr. Badger,
MiniMech, Sean, and the silent drifter. It's good to see you. And we have a whole bunch up
in quiet listening to Wes. How are you doing? You feeling all right? You good? You didn't get sick?
Yeah, no, I don't. I think I'm I think I've recovered any any, you know, amount of I was
pretty tired. We got back. Yeah, definitely. Yeah, definitely crashed. But after that,
I was exhausted. I was convinced I was gonna get sick. Wes and I just got back from the Linux
Academy holiday party. And we're now we're like who raw full of team spirit. Really, you know,
they do these things. And I'm like role my team building exercises. I will admit to being
conditioned from some of my past employers to have a very similar attitude. But the game shows
that were hosted by Tom Hazlett were pretty good. And one of the final questions it was like a
family feud. I was wondering if you're going to mention that. How can I not? You have to Yeah,
I'm still going. I am still upset about this. This was like Friday morning. This happened. And
now it's Tuesday of the next week. And I'm still upset. So it's family feud style name Linux
distributions, right. And so like if you surveyed Google or the or people or whatever the scenario
was, these were the top 10 Linux distributions, the top five Linux distributions. And so you know,
first group first table shouts out Ubuntu, you know, because it's their turn,
that family Ubuntu goes up, boom, number one on the board, of course, of course, right.
So then they shout out another distribution. I can't remember what it was. And wasn't on the
board. So you know, they so they so they lose switches to our table, the other family. And
at this point, like it's it's a process of elimination. And it's down to us and them.
And I'm all in. And I'm like, this is my domain. I know what the popular distros are. This is what
you were hired for. Right. So he turns to me, you know, Mr. Fisher, what's your answer? I say, Tom,
Linux Mint, right? Because that's a huge lots of desktop users use. I mean, we don't talk about it
a ton because we don't use it. But lots of lots of new users to Linux use Linux Mint. Ubuntu made
sense. Linux Mint. Not on the list. Not on the list. You know what was on the top five list?
Manjaro. Not Linux Mint, but Manjaro. How can I not be sore about that? How can I not be sore
about that? I tell you what. Now, apparently this was sourced from like Google rankings.
So maybe there's some something there. I'm using Manjaro right now. You are not helping at all.
You know what it is, is that with KDE, though. So it's all fine. I'm just saying, like, would
anybody in this Mumble Room disagree with the statement that Mint is way larger than Manjaro?
No, no, no. Right. I mean, I mean, it's a great distribution. Actually met a Mint user in the
in real life, though. I will disagree. Oh, just for the sake of disagree.
And there's Dar. Dar's made it to the Mumble Room. I'll say this, though. Great fun. There's a lot
of really smart people. We're going to start figuring out how to get some of them on the shows
because these people really think about this stuff a lot. You you made some friends. You were out.
You were really, you know, Westpain. Westpain is a gentleman socializer. I'll tell you,
shucking and jiving out there. Well, I mean, it was nice, right? There's a especially at a company
where most people work remotely. This is this is a great opportunity to get to meet some people.
And yeah, everyone's nice. And they just want to they want to help people learn cool new stuff.
My biggest regret really is that we didn't bring Joe out. Like we're on the fence. We're like,
it's not enough time. We should have given we should have known more. It was just it just
didn't work out this time. But so we'll have to treat him well. Oh, yeah. Yeah. We'll treat him
well. All right. Well, while Wes is hacking away. Do you have you? Are you actually doing your input
over the keyboardio right now? I started to and then it was very, very slow. It's an unusual
way. It's not QWERTY. It's not. No, no. I think I could get used to it with time. But yeah,
for the sake of you know, we have a small amount of time that Joe as we said, I'm cheating a bit.
Okay. All right. Well, we'll check in with you later on the show and see how it's going.
So we had a tweet come in to me and the Ubuntu podcast from crimbus. He says Yo,
at Chris last, I'm tired of depending on our internet to play movies for the kiddo.
I was trying to rip some DVDs tonight using VLC and acid rip in hopes to run them off of a home
server. But either the video ends up glitchy AF, as he says, or there's no audio any suggestions.
Now, I gave him a quick rundown of the tools I use, like make MKV and handbrake. Oh, yeah,
those are both great. If you want full quality make MKV, bring it in via Blu Ray and just put it
you just drop all of the different video files and languages you don't need. And you end up with
a largest file, but it's the exact encoding right off the disk. So it's as good as it's going to be
on the disk. If you need it smaller from there. So like in crimbuses case here, he's making it for
the kiddos, kiddos, you know, they don't care if it's 720p versus 1080p or 4k, you could put it in
720p and upscale it and they're going to be okay. And so you could run it through handbrake, you
know, get yourself a nice small file. Yeah, it adds up if you have a lot of those, you know,
so that was the tools part. But then that the big question is how do you serve this up to the kiddos?
And my answer from when he tweeted this to what I'm going to say now has dramatically changed
in the last week. Thanks to the people over at MB, I was gonna be really derogatory. I'll just
say the people over at MB, who are shattering our dreams of an open source Plex competitor
this week by announcing that they're shifting to a closed source core with open source components,
which is the exact model Plex uses. Actually, in fact, it may be now at this point Plex has
more open source code in it than MB does, depending on where they fall on this whole thing,
where it all falls down. And MB is sort of botching the communication. In their release,
there's some implications that make you read between the lines. And then when people ask for
clarification on GitHub, the project came out and explained in further detail what was going on.
It does seem like communication has been one of those things that the community has not always
been happy with for a couple of years in this project. This is a big shame because this was,
I think, its biggest feature for our community was the fact that it was open source. You could
use it without having to have an MB cloud account if you wanted to. I have it running on a droplet
for ages now and here at the studio, and I like it so much. I didn't want them to change anything.
I became a premium subscriber just to support them. I wanted them to stick around. I did the
same exact thing. The real shame. And it was nice too, right? Because, I mean, it was open source.
It was easy to package. I have like an Arc system that's running it, and it was just
like, install MB and away you go. And it feels like this is still kind of developing,
so we don't have all the details yet. So I don't want to raise the full panic flag.
I want to give them time to communicate better what's going on.
It couldn't have come at a worse time either. The whole Plex community over the last couple
of months on Reddit has been getting slowly more and more toxic. Go figure. It's Reddit, right? But
the Plex clients and UIs have been going through all sorts of crazy... My uncle is in Vancouver,
and he streams from my Plex server all the time. And they updated his Roku this week,
and he's been texting me all week. He's 70, right? He's been texting me all week. How do I use this
new version of Plex? I'm like, I don't know. I don't have a Roku. I can't help. And so now he's
stuck. And so thanks, Plex, for that. So I think there's a lot of people in a similar situation
looking for a decent alternative. And MB is, was, it, but now, I don't know.
Yeah. Drifter, have you run into this with your Roku?
Oh, absolutely. And it's really obnoxious too, because not only did they not really tell you
about it, it just kind of all of a sudden you went to go use it, and it was completely different.
Oh, yeah. It's good stuff. That's exactly what you want on the TV when you watch a show.
That's exactly what you want on the TV when you want to just sit down, turn it on, and chill out.
It's so frustrating. Yeah. I think the problem with Plex is they've been taking their eye off
the ball a little bit, and they're trying to focus, ironically for me to say this, but they're trying
to focus on web media, like podcasts and stuff. And while I'm kind of like, cool, another platform
to distribute our shows on, that's good as the content creator, but like the viewer of me is
like, no. I just want this to work really well. I have a whole bunch of offline media I want to
watch. I've got a USB drive plugged into this machine, and I just want you to index it really
well and keep track of what I've watched and make it possible for me to watch it on my
portable devices. Yeah. And I think in the past, MB has benefited. It had great integration with
Kodi, which I use a lot, and that works very well. So I think there's been some of that spirit,
right? It's open. You can kind of hack on it as you need to. You can make this sort of rich
ecosystem around it. I don't know. I kind of worry about that now too. Yeah. So I use the
NVIDIA Shield, which I know you do too, Chris. Love it. And the Plex Android client has gotten
slowly less and less. You just want to click on something and it just should just work first time
every time. And it tries to transcode everything. So to fix that, I have gone into Kodi and installed
Plex for Kodi. And now everything plays direct play first time every time. So along the same lines
as Wes really, like Kodi, thank God, is the answer. Yeah. That's exactly how I use it now too, because
a lot of times when I'm in the RV, I'm connected via a MiFi. And if it's going out to the Plex
cloud to even broker the connection over my LAN, which sometimes even I'm trying to play over my
LAN, it wants to broker a connection over the internet. Kodi solves that problem every single
damn time. So whatever we land on here in this conversation, keep that in the back of your mind.
Kodi is a great tool for that. So we had a little look around. And Wes, you found a couple of things.
First of all, let's just start with the one-to-one replacement. Jellyfin has been announced,
which is a fork of MB, right? Are you laughing at my pronunciation of it?
No, I was just enjoying it.
How would you say it?
I'm not arguing.
Jelfin? Would you say gel? No, because it's got a... No, jellyfin.
I think jellyfin.
Jellyfin.
Yeah, okay. You're just smirking over there.
I'm just enjoying it. You said it so well.
Thank you. Well, I tried it. If I'm going to mispronounce it, I'm going to try to mispronounce
it with some level of confidence, just so that way it doesn't make people like... It's not
distracting, right? Because if I sit here and I torture myself over it, that's distracting,
like this conversation is. They forked it right at the point before all this happened.
And did you note in here too that they talk about they're rebasing some of it on.NET Core as well.
Hey, that's kind of neat.
Isn't that fascinating? So jellyfin is a fork of MB. The MB crew basically said,
good luck with that. That was essentially their response to it. So I don't see what that means.
How many people will move over? Will there be a new community over at jellyfin?
Maybe, maybe.
All we need to do is these fork guys to actually set up a subscription model. We subscribe there
and we let them see who actually had the good luck.
Yeah. Yeah, possibly. Yeah. But Wes, you also found this StreamServer.org. Is that what it is?
Is that what the URL StreamServer.org or Streama, Streama, Streama Server.org, which is a really
kind of low, low feature. I like it. It's an MVP. Yeah. It's like a minimum viable
streaming system, but it is in fact, a video library organizer and streamer that apparently
also has a Google Play app. I did also notice one feature, which I have not tried, although I did.
It was pretty easy to get running. I have not been able to make it run in a way that we could
actually use it, but it is just a war file that you can execute if you have Java. So that's easy.
It says here, live sync watching. Watch with your loved ones remotely with sync for play,
pause and scrubbing. And if that is true, that's money. Game changer. That's something that Wes
and I have been trying to figure out because when I'm traveling, I have to stop watching
Star Trek Deep Space Nine. And I've been marathoning Deep Space Nine. Nothing makes
it grumpy with that, you know, when you don't get your nine. And now season five is taken forever,
right? So if we could do this, that would be huge. That'd be huge. All right. You got to get that.
We got to get, you got to try that, Wes. That'd be great. And I know you want to try to solve
the same thing. So Streama is the one that may also be an alternative if Kodi doesn't work for
you. I don't know about that though. So what, so it's a, it's a Java app is what it is. It's all Java.
It's all Java. I mean, I guess that's fine. Yeah, no, I guess that's fine. No, I know. I know.
I know. That's true. It's just, I don't know. I don't know why it just gives me pause. I shouldn't,
right? I'm bad. I shouldn't. It shouldn't. It's probably makes it even easier to run it on any
Linux distro and stuff like that. So I guess in a lot of ways it's, it's pretty good. All right. Well,
so I, a little, a little sneaky fact here, even though I already told you, I've been running
Ubuntu 1904 all day here on our production system just to give it a go off of a live,
off of a live USB 3. And I thought maybe we'd do a little disco-dingo roundup.
So disco-dingo is set to be released on February 12th, I think. No, it's a feature freeze. Feature
freeze is February 21st, 2019. And the UI freeze, March 4th, 2019. And the kernel freeze, April 1st.
Wow. That is a lot of specific dates. This is an article that Joey wrote for OMG Ubuntu.
And the release date is April 18th, 2019. That's right. April 18th. Look forward to it.
I'm thrilled, Wes. I'm thrilled. So this is kind of fun to just sort of take a look at where it's
at right now. If all goes to plan, it'll be shipping GNOME 3.32, Linux kernel 5.0 possibly
if it's ready, if it's ready. And a bunch of other little performance tweaks to GNOME. Well,
I actually shouldn't say little. In fact, there's some pretty significant performance tweaks to
GNOME Shell in 1904. In fact, enough that's kind of got me a little tempted to give this a go once
it's released. Not that Plasma's still been doing great, but if they shook out a lot of the performance
fixes, Wes. The call of GNOME. I can see it in your eyes. Well, you've gone mad. The area where
they're doing extensive work right now is in multi-monitor performance and management. And
that is an area in which I am struggling right now, now that I've got that dock with three monitors.
You're in a new world. It's a new multi-monitor world. Who would have thought that's what would
bring you back to GNOME? Not me. Not me. No. Is there anything that jumps out at you about the...
So this is a Phronix article here that talks about some of the performance fixes. Is there
any in particular in this roundup that Michael's done here that jump out at you? Okay, well,
they are working on showing pending kernel live patches via the update manager user interface.
That would be nice. Yeah, because right now you don't get to see that at all. No, and live
patches are kind of a nice feature that you might not get or at least as well integrated on some
other distros. Yeah, I use it on these two systems. Really? On these two on the desk here. Yeah,
that's nice, I think. Of course, you know, there's like latest packages and all the other goodies.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, except for Nautilus. Except for Nautilus. I have been following their Trello,
which is public, turns out, for Ubuntu 19.04. And this is where I started to get an idea of the
level of fixes that are coming into GNOME Shell. I'm not positive all of this is going to be
upstream. I mean, they're submitting it upstream. You never know what's actually going to take you,
right? Yeah, exactly. I'm not sure it's getting accepted. Important question. How much of these
fixes that are being pushed for are advent of IBM acquisition? Oh, no, I think a lot of this has been
in place since Canonical switched to GNOME, because the couple of the individuals, I've met
them at an Ubuntu rally. And while I mean, this was, was this April of last year? Was that April?
That was April of last year. Yep. Where they were talking about how they were going to start working
on fixing performance issues upstream in GNOME. And that they did a lot of that recently, but 19.04
seems when I read through their Trello, it seems like it's a huge list of them. And it just makes
me wonder if maybe it's going to be time to give GNOME another go and if maybe the Ubuntu spin of
GNOME might be a particular performed or performance. I don't know. It's just worth trying,
I think. Well, I mean, and we were coming into our own, right? I mean, it's not that long that
they switched back to GNOME in the first place. So now we're kind of seeing some of the we've
lived here for a while. What do we got to fix? So I've been trying it here. It pretty much right
now looks like 1810 theme wise and look wise. It's got the you know, more updated apps. It's got the
new GNOME shell, including that new GNOME to do list manager, which we were playing around with on
the pre show stream. Yeah, it looks nice. Yeah, it is nice. And you know what it is very quick,
even for running off a USB three thumb drive. It's very quick. It's very, very quick. So it's got that
new fresh feel. So you have to know what you're doing the show here today. No problem. Yeah. Yeah.
The only thing I don't have is our highlights for the for the shows. But I suppose I can probably
figure that out. But yeah, it's not bad. And the GNOME UI itself. I like some of the tweaks,
canonicals done. I really like their doc. And I don't use it a lot, you know, because I'm a
plasma user. So I haven't used their their version of GNOME. It's pretty much since they've launched
it. I was pretty much when I switched to plasma. But it's not bad. It's actually a pretty damn good
implementation. And you combine it with the new GNOME three settings the screen, you know,
that's been around for a while. And it's just I like it. It feels kind of simple. Yeah, simple.
Yeah, it's simple and polished. And the Thunderbolt three support now is also extra
appreciated more than ever, more than ever. West. So yeah, I give it I give it the old
thumbs up here on the Linux unplugged review. I'd say they're in a right in the right direction
stability wise. It's been I've just been running it for the day. So I can't make like a firm like
Oh, yeah, it's it's the most stable release ever. But I'm legitimately in the past I did have no
shell crash on me at this point. Like it didn't take more than an eight hour workday to have
no shell crash on me. And I've made it that far. So that's that's pretty good. That is pretty good.
I'm looking forward to the disco dingo. Gotta play twice, you know, because it's so great.
It's the first thing I thought of when they made amazing. Isn't that great? It is great.
But canonical is also making some news this week in the enterprise space. It is KubeCon.
KubeCon North America is going on just down the street from us this week. And canonical
is making some noise really before the event has even opened its doors. And they've been
working in the Kubernetes space since 2014. But this year, I think they're really trying to say
this is our offering. Yeah, that is right. One of those things that got people talking was
MicroK8s. What? Yeah, MicroKris. Is this already a known thing? A MicroK8? Or is this something
they've made up? As far as you know? Well, it's a new project. It's there. It's there. There's
already, you know, there's already attempts like Minikube to get a system running just for
development. You don't want to play with it on one box. I asked you to set up that Kubernetes
cluster weeks ago and you still haven't finished tying all the string together. That is true. That
is true. Well, now you with the snap install MicroK8s, that job would be done for you. Oh,
I see. So it's like a full, complete, ready to go out of the box or out of the snap.
Kubernetes environment. Yeah, full featured. Includes automatic updates, well-defined
security capabilities, and some of Canonical's open source add-on services such as a container
registry, storage pass through and native GPGPU enablement for hardware acceleration and machine
learning workflows. Yeah, you've got those GPGs. You've got those GPUs. Too many Gs. If you need
to compute those GPGs on those GPUs, then you're set. Oh yeah, in the cloud. And with this now,
like you can see the game they're playing is they're wrapping it up with that Ubuntu
Advantage support as well. So now they're making this an offering for their enterprises and Ubuntu
Advantage subscription. So if you need Canonical support and taking care of managing all of this.
And yeah, a big thing about that, too, is that you can get that support for clusters you've built
with Kube admin. And so if you already built your own cluster and then you want Canonical's help
managing it, you don't have to have it all set up customized by them to get started with that. So
that's a big selling point. That's what a hungry company does. Hungry in a good way. We know this
will be painful. Probably you've done some things wrong that we would have never done, but we want
your business and we want to help. Yeah, and that is a way Canonical, isn't that a great example of
how Canonical can be competitive in a way that IBM can't? IBM will, I mean, they'll come in and
charge you to fix it. But what IBM wants is you do it to the standard, right? That's what Red Hat
wants, too, is you do it to the standard. And if you could deviate from the standard, it may not be
a supported configuration. And what Canonical is implicitly saying here is we'll bail you out and
that that cluster F that you've built will manage it for you and fix it up. And that's a that's a
hungry play. And I like it. Yeah, they were also talking about some new partnerships with people
like Dell EMC and Supermicro. So those are both big names in big server business. So, you know,
they are really trying to get their name out there in that space, which has been kind of
dominated by Red Hat, at least in like the Kubernetes area. Yeah, it has. I kind of found
out I found a really interesting tidbit. Do you know why it's called K8s? You probably do. I only
found out the other day. It's because they took eight letters out of the middle of Kubernetes.
Okay, that's what it is. I could have sworn that when we were, we did an episode for TechSnap,
I did a ton of research. And I think I've unlearned a lot of the things I learned for that
episode, because that was in there. That's funny. That's good. I don't think also, it's no small
achievement here that you can now get a, as they call it a micro Kubernetes setup, with a snap
install command. That's that is, it's a pretty good showcase of what snaps can offer in the
enterprise is you can take this really complicated system, and you can boil it down to a single snap
command. Oh, and by the way, it's also going to get updated. Yeah, right. And you can go poke,
you know, go poke at it, see what's in there, go take a look at the at the YAML file, see how it's
put together, play with it yourself. Well, it'll be interesting to see how that plays out. I think
that's a space they can be pretty competitive in. And just kind of anecdotally today, I think it
was Badger that mentioned when he got in here that DigitalOcean has taken their Kubernetes support out
of beta and made it like an official thing. So you could have Ubuntu boxes on premises,
you could have Ubuntu boxes on different cloud providers, and you're managing all from one
Kubernetes system, like, not to sound too much like you six weeks ago, before you got bought out
but I span up a Kubernetes cluster on DO in maybe three minutes. That's pretty nice. And you only
pay for the app nodes, you don't pay for the workers or anything. So it's kind of like the
GKS or the EKS model, ECS model, sorry. Rumor on the street has it you can still get $100 credit
if you go to do.co slash L and L. That's the rumor. I don't know. I don't know if that's
true or not. But if you still want to try out Kubernetes, if you want to go try out, you know
what? Because the thing is, we're both still users. Were you not using DigitalOcean this weekend?
True. This weekend, I spent up a high CPU drop last night. Oh, last night. That's when it was.
Yeah. Yeah. A high CPU drop. What were you doing? Video encoding? Video encoding, weren't you?
You're doing something with video. High CPU? No, math? You're doing something with math.
You're doing mathy stuff? He's a math nerd, guys. He doesn't talk about it much on air,
but Wes is a math nerd. Oh, you don't want to say. You want to tell me off air. Oh,
okay. Oh, I like that even better. All right. Well, this next story is rather interesting.
Wouldn't this be a cool feature to come to the x86 side of the house? But for right now,
and probably forever, this is a feature coming to the ARM side of Linux, and it's a pretty cool one.
It's energy aware scheduling for the mainline Linux kernel to better handle systems with
asymmetric CPU topologies. Energy aware scheduling is designed to take into account information from
the ARM energy model framework. So you can make better scheduling decisions based upon the topology
of the CPU cores, and the performance and power characteristics, right? Because you might have
this this sort of ARM board that's put together with all kinds of different components. And that
can vary widely depending on is this for a smart fridge, right? Or is it for your Nvidia shield
device? Those are usually different. Yeah, that's nice. And the work for supporting energy aware
scheduling in the mainline kernel has been in the works for months. And you're not going to be
surprised when you learn that Google's Android kernel team has already been supporting this
technology in their core. This, you know, getting this in the mainline means one less thing that's
in the that's in the Android kernel only. So that's kind of nice. Yeah. And if you look at
some of the patchwork, the churn of all the work going on here, it's starting to settle down.
Hopefully, that means it won't be much longer till we say it's in the mainline and energy aware
scheduler sounds pretty neat, pretty, pretty neat. I think that'd be a good a good addition.
You go down the road a few years, some of us might be rocking some Linux arm laptop of some form,
and you can have just fantastic battery life or something like that. That could be really cool.
Unless system D, you dev is eating 100% of your CPU, then your battery life is going to be
horrible regardless of your CPU architecture. And that's what was happening to me last week
talked about it on the show. Short version is after I got this Thunderbolt three doc with a GPU,
and I installed the NVIDIA drivers and then disconnected my system and booted it without
the doc connected system to you dev went crazy eating up 100% of one of my cores constantly
trying to find the NVIDIA adapter connect and authorize it and initialize the driver.
And then when that would fail because the hardware didn't exist because the doc was disconnected,
it would freak out and use 100% of my CPU. And I discovered I could stop and start you dev manually
manually and essentially solve this but I have to do it per boot when I'm not connected.
Oh, that's pretty annoying.
Yeah, it's not great. It's not great. But Mike wrote in with a system to you dev fix.
And what's he doing here with what's he essentially accomplished with this?
I mean, he's basically doing what you were doing on a offhand manner,
making it happen for you at boot time. So you install the new service. And then all
that service is doing is stopping all the various you dev things and the sockets that they listen on
starting it back up. And then the rest of this his article is telling you just how to get that
all enabled so that every time you boot up, that'll happen automatically.
That's not a bad worker. So it's a workaround.
I mean, it's a hack. Yeah, it's unfortunate that we have to you know, that these that
you'd have won't figure it out.
But what I liked about it is I don't have to I don't have to uninstall the NVIDIA driver.
But my question would be what happens when I am connected to the doc?
Don't I want that process to work?
Well, you are restarting it. So I say you should do some research and find out.
And report back to us here next week.
Fair enough. Fair enough. Fair enough. I will. I will. I'll try to figure that out.
All right. Well, before we get in to more like our WireGuard success story,
I'm very excited about WireGuard now. We've been talking about it in the theory sense for a while.
And this travel week was our opportunity to actually put it in production and it freaking worked.
But a little housekeeping before we go any further in the show.
A couple of things we need to let you know about.
This is your chance, Wes, to get some progress on that keyboardio.
First of all, if you want to get a hold of us Linux Unplugged dot com slash contact,
please go there.
Sign us in your app pics. I'm going to try to do more of those in every episode.
And I've got my own feeds, of course.
But if there is a command line app that you've been loving.
Oh, we can't say that. That's command line nervous.
If there is a command line app that you find to be quite swell.
Something you're fond of, you think about at night when you're falling asleep.
That's a whole other thing, Wes.
But maybe Linux Unplugged dot com slash contact.
Also, just kind of fun little heads up.
Wes and I at the end of this week are heading to System 76 to tour their factory in Denver,
Colorado and sniff out the Thelio hardware and just get a sense for what kind of scale
of an operation they got over there.
So I'm really looking forward to that.
I know. Exciting.
Wes and I, after just getting to hang out in Texas, are going to get to go hang out in Denver.
They are flying us out there as well as a bunch of other media.
And they're doing a tour.
And I think I've been talking to them about this for three months now about doing this
and just trying to really.
I mean, I've been a bit skeptical and they know that.
And that's actually kind of what I respect about them willing to do this is I've been
pretty skeptical about Papa Wes.
I mean, I'm still reserving judgment.
I want to give it like three to bake.
Yeah, exactly.
I want to give it like three or so years to really fully realize.
But, you know, I've been pretty skeptical about Papa Wes.
I'm kind of skeptical about a small operation opening up a U.S. manufacturing plant in Denver.
I mean, we're not talking like we're not talking Arizona or West Texas where land where they
basically are paying you to take the land.
We're talking about Denver.
Right.
So I just been I've been a little skeptical.
And so I've been and I feel like they're so important to the Linux community.
There was a conversation at Linux Academy, like we want to add another Linux hardware
vendor.
Who should we add?
And the first name that came into the list was System 76.
And I want to be able to say with confidence, you do it.
So this is hopefully what we're going to find out.
So we're going there at the end of the week.
They're going to give us the tour and then we'll be back next week and we'll report what
we found.
I think nonetheless, we're going to have a great time.
I know that's going to happen.
I know we're going to have a great time.
So System 76 props to them for being willing to bring a critic out there at times.
I try to, you know, I just try to be honest because you guys also know I've been a 10
year customer.
Well, more than that now.
So still got three System 76 rigs.
Yeah.
I mean, right.
I think that's probably an important perspective of.
Yeah.
We're concerned to tell you guys about it.
But also, yeah, we want to we want to buy some of these rigs.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
So that should be good.
We'll have a report next week when we get back.
And we also have the results of our automation naming system.
We've been building a system behind the scenes.
We talked about it over the last few episodes.
I don't know actually when, but it's been we have talked about over a few episodes.
And it's it's pretty fun because it's not only solving some problems here at Jupiter
Broadcasting, but it's given us an opportunity to think about releasing our own open source
project.
And that has been the most fun.
And when I was all said and done, that is our goal is to release something that other
podcasters can utilize to automate production, increase quality and accuracy, and maybe even
eventually a lot more.
I don't want to commit yet, but we have some really great long term plans.
And so we asked you guys, what should we name this tool?
This is a tool that we're going to be running all of our shows through, that it'll be like
a verb.
You know, make sure you run it through X, Y, Z because it's got to get posted today.
Or did that go through X, Y, Z?
And we asked you guys, we put it all out there and we had a bunch of really great suggestions.
We got a decent sample size, even for not plugging it too much, 272 votes.
Nice.
I'll take it.
You'd be surprised.
That actually does end up being decently representative.
Doesn't seem like it would be for the tens of thousands of downloads.
But it actually, experience tells me it does.
So one of the submissions with 8% of the votes was Jupiter Podcaster.
That's not bad.
J Publish was another popular one, also at 8%.
Jupiter Caster, 11% of the votes.
Pod Pusher, which is very close to what Wimpy and Popey have, came in at 11% of the votes.
But the number two suggestion, which is pretty good, which you could, you know, if you're
thinking about this as an open source project, this might be the better name of the, of,
but, but it's not the one that the people decided.
But I like it.
It's called Autopod.
It's not bad.
Autopod.
It almost sounds like a podcast app on a phone though.
You know, like a cloud box symbol.
Yeah.
Running through Autopod.
Sounds to me, one of those, sorry, Tasker, Alto Tools, the guy names everything literally
Alto something.
Yeah.
True, right?
There's that danger.
Yeah.
So that was, that was, that was, that was there though.
That was number two.
But with 26%, 72 votes, 26% of the vote.
And I think we swung it.
I'm going to, I'll, I'll, I'll own that, but it's Casta Blasta.
Casta Blasta, which is a callback to the very first podcast that myself, Brian and John ever
did before we even formed a network.
We did a show called Casta Blasta together, which was really where we learned how to record
our audio edit and all of that stuff.
Just starting out.
Yeah.
And when we launched Linux action show and Radio Revolver and other shows, Casta Blasta
was still on the air at that time.
So it ran for many years of our origin.
So I think it's kind of fun now that we are fitting part of Linux Academy and we've gone
through all of these evolutions over the years and we're building a system that is really
kind of a serious professional system, right?
There's some, there's some, I dunno, there's something sweet about calling it Casta Blast,
which is when we were so raw and amateur and, and ingested beginning and saying really stupid
stuff into microphones that today you could not say into a microphone, you know, you would
not say those things and we said those things and it was just some other things.
Yeah, it was good stuff.
It was, it was really good.
And so I think it's sort of fitting and it's like, you're blasting it out there too.
So we're going to call it Casta Blasta.
Thank you everyone who did vote and look for more about the Casta Blasta project very soon.
We have, we've taken a page from Microsoft's book where they like, they call the surface
three different things now, you know?
So we're, I guess that's the hip thing to do.
You sound a bit like Mark Wahlberg saying that Casta Blaster.
Casta Blasta.
Yeah, yeah.
That's how he used to say it is Casta Blasta.
You put it through the blaster.
And then last bit of housekeeping before we move on with the show is Linux Fest Northwest
last but absolutely not least, April 26th through the 28th, 2019 at the Bellingham Technical
College.
If you're international or you're around the States, you fly into SeaTac, you can get
shuttles up there.
There are carpools that are forming and Bellingham is beautiful.
The Pacific Northwest is gorgeous.
And the Technical College is one of the better campuses I've ever attended an event on.
Been to a few of these now.
And the great thing about the Technical College is that it's that same place every single
year.
And this is the 20th year of Linux Fest Northwest.
So it's a well oiled machine.
They figured out all the issues you run into the first or second time you're there.
We know where our booth is.
You know where our booth is at.
I know right where it is.
You know right where it's at.
And that's just anyone else who's been there in the past however many years.
It's so nice.
And you know what rooms to go to and you know where the food's going to be at.
And because of that, the lug that puts on the plug that puts this on the Bellingham
Linux Users Group that puts this on can focus on all of the other stuff.
You know, the content, the talks, the great organizations they have.
That's so huge.
And this is their 20th year.
They're doing a theme past, present and future.
We're going to be there.
Joe's flying in.
We're going to try to bring as much of the crew in as we can.
We've got to remember to talk to System76 about doing a party.
Oh, yes.
I'm going to be bringing Lady Joops.
Parking her in the parking lot doing barbecue grilling.
Not barbecuing.
Sorry, Noah.
Grilling for everybody.
If you'll let me put my meat in your mouth, you can come there and eat my meat.
Well, I'm in.
All right.
Very good.
So LinuxFestNorthwest.org if you want to check that out and if you're interested in going.
I just say this because I still need to submit talks.
I bet you do too.
We both need to submit our talks.
I'm thinking about doing a talk about Castablasta.
So who can end Castablasta separately possibly or we could do a combo talk.
So we should talk about that.
Yeah, let's talk about that.
And then audio reading on Linux.
You could definitely teach us a thing or two.
Oh, we totally could do.
We could do our Jack segment.
Yeah, that'd be fun.
Why not?
Oh, man.
Because, you know, there's people there.
I already know there's going to be people like how to podcast on Linux.
There's always like two presenters that do that.
And I'm always like, oh, son.
Oh, child.
You know, like I'm always like, oh, yes.
How are you doing?
And I don't mean to be demeaning, but it's always like, no, that's no, no, that's not
going to work.
So we can have a good Q&A session to be so much fun.
Anyways, what I'm getting at is I'm hoping that if we can get enough talks together,
including from somebody that you guys haven't heard of yet and from the people that you
know about on air, maybe we could have a whole dedicated room at Linux Fest Northwest.
That's just the Jupiter broadcasting room.
So that'd be really cool.
Just another reason that this is the this is the year to go.
If you've been thinking about giving talks all day, having a booth, live streaming, doing
a live Linux action news, baby barbecue.
And I mean, it's it's our big get together.
I know it's a big ask to travel that far, but if you can make it and the side benefit
is, you know, even if you end up paying Linux Fest Northwest, which you won't, you won't
know.
Bellingham's great.
The Pacific Northwest is lovely.
So just, you know, you can go on a surprise little summer vacation.
Yeah, early summer.
Yeah.
You know, and come see everybody.
That's always part of the fun is like there's a whole bunch of people there that love talking
about what you're interested in.
And that's just really rewarding.
Anyways, that's all the housekeeping for this week.
So let's move on to our WireGuard in production success story.
So we set up here at the studio on my workstation.
I thought, well, just let's give it a go.
It was one of those projects are like, I'll just I'll just see how hard this is and how
far I can get.
And then I got all the way and I'm like, oh, well, now I've just put this in production
on my workstation.
Oops, but I'll circle back to that.
So WireGuard is a VPN that is built.
Well, is it mainline now?
It is mainline now, right?
In the Linux kernel.
It is now mainline, I believe, in the Linux kernel.
I don't know if it's in kernel 4.15 because you need a DKMS.
You have to build a DKMS module to actually get it to work in 1804.
But I set it up on an 1804 workstation.
There's PPAs available and it just builds super quick and it's installed immediately.
And what you essentially get is the ability to start a new virtual interface.
In a sense, it looks like another network interface on your Linux box and you interact
with it like you would any other interface.
You can assign an IP address.
You can use IP tables to route traffic.
It is like you have another network card in your box.
You create it with IP link and then make a new one and just say, type WireGuard.
Yeah, and then it's up to the kernel to figure out what to do with traffic that's sent and
received to this new interface.
And that's where WireGuard comes in.
And it's so great for somebody like me because I know how to work with network interfaces
and IP tables and all of that.
So within minutes, I had it up and installed.
And then it was like, OK, well, now that I have an interface, I need to route traffic.
So I'm going to set up some IP tables rules to route that traffic.
And it was just obvious.
It was just obvious what the next step was.
That wasn't the hardest part at all for you.
No, no, really.
No, it wasn't.
The hardest part was modifying our Microtech router OS firewall.
That's where I got it.
Go figure.
But no, what I expected to be the hard part was the fact that because I'm apparently a
masochist, I wanted to connect to the WireGuard VPN running on my Ubuntu box from an iPad.
No, well, no, of course you do.
I know.
iOS.
Now, I'll tell you why is so we have the Behringer X32 mixer and it's got a Linux power.
Yeah, it runs Linux.
Our mixer runs Linux.
And it's got a really awesome set of remote control capabilities, so much so that even
the dials and sliders on this mixer are motorized.
So if in software I pull down on a pot line, which is what these are called, the actual
physical slider in the studio moves and they have a touch app for the iPad that happens
to fit the exact amount of channels that we use on the screen.
With real time levels, individual channel control, and if I slide or mute or do anything
on that iPad, it's physically represented in studio.
Oh yeah, it's wild.
It just moves.
Which is great because when you're here sitting in the seat that I normally sit in and you're
sitting in front of the mixer and I'm in Texas, you can actually see me moving sliders.
And you can see me moving though.
Yes.
Both ways.
It's so, so great.
Really nice.
So this is why I wanted to be able to do a WireGuard VPN from the iPad so I could have
touch control of our mixer when I'm remote and I could see everybody's levels.
The mumble room, Wes's, mine, remote hosts, everything.
But iOS is a son of a bitch.
You can't just go to the app store and install a WireGuard app.
That's not a thing.
That's not how it, that's not how.
What do you think this is, Android?
Yeah.
We get a sideload.
You can go screw yourself if you want a sideload.
So the way you have to do it is you have to join the test flight beta for WireGuard.
And there's only a limited amount of slots, but I will have a link in the show notes if
this is something you're interested in.
Get in early.
LinuxUnplugged.com slash 279.
They have been granted a networking stack privilege extension by Apple, where they're
able to do a network level VPN connection.
So it is a true kernel level VPN from the iOS device to my WireGuard system.
And the traffic is then routed to my WireGuard box and I'm able to, my iPad is essentially
on the LAN and it's, I am completely capable of controlling the X32 mixer.
It's just amazing.
It was, I mean, it was really slick when we were playing with it in the studio because
you just, I mean, we just hit like, you tap a button, you tap a button, start it up.
Yeah.
And then it's live and it was latency.
It's so fast too.
Yeah.
It's so fast.
Like the connection is instant and then you wouldn't even know you're going over.
There's like, for what I've done, I've seen very little penalty for the VPN overhead.
It's, it's pretty amazing.
And I think the entire thing took a 30 minute investment.
You know, I asked you, I had to ask you a couple of things because you had done it before.
So I bounced a couple of ideas off of you when I was, what was I, what was I, oh, it
was the remote connection stuff I was troubleshooting.
Yeah.
And once we got that solved with Wes's help, it was just, boom, done.
Wes got router OS into submission and we were good.
There's, there's areas of improvement.
I think, I would like to explore using it for persistent connections between say the
studio in Texas or the studio in Texas and the RV, like maybe a way to like do sort of
like kind of, oh, not a mesh, but almost like a tink style VPN, I don't know.
Yeah.
But like do like a WireGuard connection from the RV to the system in Texas and from the
system in Texas to the studio and from the studio to RV and you know, like do a complete
I don't know, that's something for the future I want to play with.
Also, another thing that should probably happen is I should probably move it off of my work
station in my office.
Maybe pick something a little more permanent.
Yeah.
I was like, but where?
Like I could throw it up in a VM on the free NAS box possibly.
Yeah, that could work.
We also have that dedicated KVM system running CentOS, but it's really old.
It's like when Bitcoin was first released old, that's how old it is.
That's how I measure it.
Okay.
Well, maybe the workstations looking better.
Maybe the workstations looking better and better, but I really and you had it, you were
playing with it off of a droplet.
Oh, yeah, it works great.
The connection establishes so damn fast that I literally do a ping every time just to make
sure it's working because I'm like, how can I connect that fast?
Like I have to like go ping the other machine on the other end just to make sure no way
it's possible.
I was really impressed.
Yeah.
I mean, that's one of the nice features about it, right?
Is the way it doesn't have this kind of older style, really complicated, persistent connection
to do. It's smart enough to just pick up when you when you've got a new one and it picks
up and realizes, oh, hey, you're talking to me.
The public key matches my are you in my allowed IP set?
Yes.
All right.
There you go.
Connection made.
Yeah.
So if you feel like this, I guess it doesn't even there's so many uses for VPNs these days.
I wouldn't even I wouldn't even like put it in any particular box.
But what was the was it Nord VPN that did a commercial?
I think there's several now, but yeah.
Okay.
So it is something WireGuard is something that the commercial VPN providers are starting
to introduce.
So you could play with it that way, too, if you just wanted to mess around with the client
side of it.
But I got to say WireGuard, the WireGuard hype is real and it's pretty great.
And it's pretty easy to get running on a current released version of a Linux distro.
You don't have to wait for it to to show up baked into the kernel.
It's super simple.
How did you guys find that compared to Tink VPN to set up?
Um, it's a it's both simpler and slightly more complicated.
There's a couple things to do in terms of like exchanging keys that it's closer to SSH
and Tink is I guess Tink is about the same.
Does Tink have any GUI front end to set it up?
There might be there might be some I have not used.
Because that scenario WireGuard.
I mean, if there was like a network manager front end to WireGuard, that would be really
great.
I guess I'd have to say it's simpler because it has similar stuff around some of the key
management, WireGuard.
But then you don't have to use the actual, you know, there's no program to run.
You just install the module and then create the interface.
That is really nice.
It's system level.
It's just baked in.
You don't get Tink's magic of, you know, magically making a national connecting peers and all
that stuff.
But it's kind of so in that sense, it's a little more complicated, or it's a lower level
primitive that you could build more elaborate networks with.
I wonder if there could be a like a hosted key sharing system like could keybase, for
example, could could keybase could you add could they could there be like a front end
of WireGuard key exchanging that would make that a little easier because it's got these
it's I like this key system.
I think that's a good way to do it.
But exchanging keys is it's going to be like over email or chat.
And those are vulnerable channels of communication.
So it would be nice if there was like a key base dot IO kind of way to would actually
call fault work.
Maybe I don't know.
I don't know, maybe, maybe I haven't.
That's a good question.
That's sick.
That's that would be interesting.
Either way, very happy with WireGuard.
I'm yeah, I mean, I have a Tink system set up now that all part of it is a backbone from
my parents networks, my home network that I use like so I can get in and troubleshoot
stuff for them.
What do you think you're gonna replace that with WireGuard?
I think so.
Really?
No, why?
Why not stick with Tink?
You know, I wanted to do some maintenance in that system anyway.
And while I've been enjoying Tink, I just don't have that.
I don't have a big enough mesh where I really need that sort of, you know, Tink is great
for creating like one whole new overlay network that you want on top of everything.
But I have more security domains than I want.
You know, I don't want one big one, it turns out.
And yeah, I think WireGuard will be a very low maintenance backbone VPN connection.
Yeah, that's exactly what I think.
Which to be fair, Tink has to I don't ever have to fuss with it.
And it does just work.
But I also see myself using WireGuard more often.
So should I should I need to do any troubleshooting, it'll be fresh in my mind.
Yeah, and it seems like the way of the future, way of the future, way of the future.
I really liked it.
And it's going to be way faster than a lot of the competitors.
And if Apple is allowing it on test flight, then there's a good chance they're going to
allow it in the App Store.
And so there's a really good chance that we're going to have pretty good mobile OS
support for WireGuard.
And I think that's I think that's really, really important.
And the fact that it's so fast means that it's not a big deal for mobile travelers to
just tap it on and go.
Right.
And you've already got stuff like, you know, like a go version of Tink.
Go version, various user land versions.
I heard there was talk about maybe a free BSD kernel version sometime down the way.
No way. Really?
Yeah, maybe.
Maybe.
They already have one imports for the user land stuff, too.
So it's like, yeah, the availability is really climbing.
Yeah.
Well, how about we switch gears and talk about some app picks?
What?
Love the app picks.
Now, I've been I've been on a really slow decline with Reddit.
Like it's been it's been really since.
I don't know.
Two years, three years.
I can't remember.
Like, it's just I don't know, slowly and slowly, I use Reddit less and less.
And I find myself using smaller and smaller subreddits.
So the subreddits that I enjoy the most are the really small ones with like less than
a thousand really focused community.
There's not a lot of room for random trolls to come invade.
Yeah.
When you get above five thousand, I just I don't know.
It starts to turn toxic, I feel like.
But one way that I have been and it's just a visual differentiator.
But one way that I have been processing Reddit a lot easier is on the terminal.
And I've been using an app that's likely in the repo.
I thought you were going to say, I mean, just based on this, you know,
an iPad Pro application, that was the best way to browse Reddit.
No, man, I don't like that.
I don't like the Reddit mobile app.
And I also really freaking hate that when I go to Reddit on the web on a mobile device,
they're like taking up like a solid fourth of the screen.
It's huge.
Yeah, it's very annoying.
A third of the screen, really.
It's a third of the screen.
Almost half of the screen.
They're taking a full screen.
They're taking up your entire screen.
And then there's that annoying nag they put in lately, which is,
do you want to use our mobile?
That's what I'm talking about.
No, no, no, no, I don't.
That's why I'm not using it.
Go away.
That is what I'm talking about.
That thing that takes up basically half the screen.
Three quarters is so annoying and takes up the whole screen where it's come full screen,
full screen, full screen.
It's it's got to go in the meantime, though.
In the meantime, though, if you're on a Linux box, see if you have RTV in your repo.
RTV is a terminal user interface for Reddit that allows logging into your Reddit account.
So you get your subreddits.
I do.
I do have it in my repo.
You do.
Yeah.
And you can use external tools like it will launch your web browser or it can launch,
you know, like a YouTube player.
It's just a simple.
Oh, it's Python.
It's a Python application.
I thought it was something.
It's just a simple Python application.
Browse Reddit has clipboard support.
You can open media links in your preferred media player.
It's got easy navigation through the front page.
You can jump to your favie subreddits.
You can open up specific user pages if you want to, like, go get creepy on a user.
You can browse multi-Reddits.
It's got support for multi-Reddits.
Okay.
And search.
And you can do it all from the command line.
Something about seeing Reddit on the terminal makes it way more palatable for me.
Okay. That was pretty easy.
Now I'm browsing our list from the command line.
Isn't that great?
Yeah.
If you're on Ubuntu, it's in the repo already.
It's on a lot of repos actually.
I think it's in Fedora's too.
So that's pick number one this week.
Now, pick number two.
Pick number two was to replace functionality on a Mac.
The Mac, if you ever dip your toe into the Mac, like we've got, you know,
Final Cut on the Mac here that we used to use, thankfully, that's no longer the thing.
And the occasional Photoshop file.
So, you know, I dabble from time to time.
Haven't had to for a while.
But one of the things that I noticed about the Mac is they got all these little one-off
applications like we have on Linux for everything.
But they're all like pay-for applications.
Of course.
They're all like five bucks, ten bucks.
They've got that healthy app store, Chris.
Yeah, they sure do.
Actually, it's struggling, but they still like to charge for everything.
But on the Linux side, a lot of the stuff is free.
It's something we don't talk a lot about, maybe because, you know, we want people to
make money and we want them to be able to, you know, make money making software.
Like that's the thing we all want.
But there's so much shit that you get for free besides just the desktop.
There's so much stuff.
And some of this stuff the Mac users have no idea about.
This is one of them you can really rub in their face because this is hard to get on
the Mac that's decent quality that isn't at least 20 bucks.
And you may have heard of it, but I got to tell you about it.
It's called Sound Converter, and it's perfect for my workflow.
And Sound Converter is exactly what it sounds like.
It's an easy way to set up a preset.
You drop some files in there, you hit go, and it converts them all to that.
Which, as Wes probably has already guessed, is great for our production flow here because
we can record in a multitrack editor and huge WAV files.
And then I can drop all these WAV files in Sound Converter, it spits them out as mono
FLAC files and sends them off to Joe.
Boom.
Done.
And it's the same thing like if you want to convert a whole bunch of stuff to Ogg Vorbis
or MP3, you just drop them all in here and you hit go.
It saves you from writing out this whole complicated command line syntax.
And the batch support sounds pretty nice there.
And it has the benefit of giving you a GUI to expose all the options you might possibly
use, which is always really nice when you're getting started with conversion of media.
You don't even know always what you can do.
And this has the option of doing resample or, like in my case, dropping it to mono.
It has the option of transcoding to a different format if it can or just copying it if it's
going to the same format.
I like that Opus is a handy default input right there.
Yeah.
And it basically supports everything.
I'm sure it's just using FFmpeg and a bunch of other great stuff under the hood, but
Honey Badger over here, I don't care.
This is just a great way to use it because I can go from the file manager, boom, I hit
start, it puts it right in the directory I want, that syncs up to Joe, and I'm done.
And it's just so nice because there was an application on the Mac that used to do that
and it was legitimately like $20.
And I just see that kind of stuff.
And I'm just overwhelmingly appreciative of how enabling open source software can be
for people that don't have immaculate, huge, ginormous Uncle Scrooge sized budgets.
That's a really good point, right?
Because sometimes we're talking from the perspective of professionals or business or
just high end people at home.
And that's very different from sort of the baseline.
What should you be able to do with a computer for free?
If you just install this, you get that.
And because there's so many options, it's easy to forget how valuable that is.
But when I switched over to the Mac and I'm like, I mean, this is something I could do
for free?
You're telling me I got to spend $20?
This is ridiculous.
And I was incensed by it.
And then it's like, I have lost that appreciation for just how much comes with Linux
that is just totally free besides the desktop itself.
And I feel like the conversation is always around the value of the desktop.
But it's really, it's the entire ecosystem, right?
It's the applications, it's the support, it's all of it that's free.
And that's huge.
So, and this is just one of those great applications.
You can get it.
We'll have a link in the show notes, linuxunplugged.com
slash 279 and go there and get links to everything we talked about.
There's also the contact page there.
If you would like to send us some of your feedback, we have the subscribe link there.
If you want to get this show every single week, and we encourage that.
Just around the corner is our predictions episode and our roundup and look back.
And our future casting is what I'm going to call it.
Where we, if we had a magic wand, if we could just make something happen, where,
we're not constrained by the sad bounds of reality.
No, no, no.
And of course, it's a great opportunity for you to get involved in that virtual lug.
Give us your predictions and all of that.
So we'll do one the day after Christmas, Wednesday the 26th.
Escape your family.
You're tired of visiting with them.
Come hang out with us.
You got a hangover.
Just sit in your chair and chat in our mumble room and future cast.
Eggnog is welcome and allowed.
The day after New Year's, we'll have a show then too.
And you can make your predictions, get it on the record.
And I have been keeping a list of predictions and checking it twice.
And I'm feeling really good about my predictions this year.
I think it's my best year ever of predictions.
So you better get started.
Oh boy.
Don't get, this is, this is tough.
Go get more Wes over at TechSnap.Systems.
Thank you for joining us.
And we'll see you right back here.
Next Tuesday.
The Unplugged Show.
There we go.
$279 in the can.
Let's go pick our title.
And Mr. Payne, without further ado.
How's that keyboard over there?
Uh oh.
It's not quite in flames.
Yeah.
It doesn't look like it's on fire right now.
We're having a little bit of a compilation error that I'm working through right now.
All right.
Well, you got to post show.
But I guess there's a lot of C++ here to go through.
I feel like you do well under pressure.
You'll get this.
All right.
We'll check back in with Wes Payne and how he's doing on getting his keyboardio on fire.
We have to also pick our title.
So we still have, we still have some housekeeping to get to.
Thank you, Mumble Room.
Always enjoy having you guys.
Why are Guardians of the Galaxy?
That is good.
Yeah.
Yeah, I agree.
What does that have to do with anything?
Where'd that come from?
Why, why a god?
Oh, WireGuard.
I see.
Ah, I see.
Come on.
Oh, I see.
You just heard the Galaxy.
I did.
Yeah.
Dar, are you on the Dex doc again this week?
Yes, I am.
You maniac.
Well, I am doing a Tora experiment.
So yeah, I'm like, I'm also using the iConnect headphones.
So, ah, I also like embarrassing and embarrassing.
That's pretty good.
WireGuardians of the Galaxy, those really great.
Man, we have some, those are some good ones.
MB Aerosine is also pretty good.
It's hard to say though.
Micro K8s on Ubuntu.
I no longer MB you.
I like you.
This is, this is the good one.
Oh, does anybody, okay.
All right.
Does anybody have any travel hacks for me?
Doing a lot of travel these days.
You guys have any tips to make travel easier?
Have you got one of those little,
what's it called?
Little, I've got this on my desk here.
It's a little travel router, smart router,
and it runs open WRT or something.
And it connects to hotel wifi.
So you do the captive portal once and then all your devices
are magic, like a Chromecast just works.
It's great.
I have been thinking more and more about that
because I could also WireGuard from that, right?
So that could establish a WireGuard connection
back to the studio.
Yeah.
And that could be extremely useful.
And I could just route the 192 network over there.
So I used it in the summer when I was over to get BBC iPlayer in America.
So I just VPN back to England using that little box.
It's great.
Hmm.
Is it a GLI neat one?
Yes, I have the GLMT300N.
GLI stuff is great.
Realms open WRT right out of the box.
They don't do too much.
They do it their own custom interface, but that's not too bad.
Could you, you should throw a link.
Yeah.
I have like three of them.
Link it up.
Put it in the chat room.
So this is just open WRT have like a capacity for like connecting to my files too.
And what about the double net issue?
Badger, do you have issues with double net when you do this?
It will repeat Wi-Fi just fine.
And double net, I don't know because I'm only ever going outbound
because I'm usually where the thing is.
So I haven't tried.
I'm worried about that too much.
Sorry.
I got to check this out.
We got to link this up.
Because this could be, this could be nice.
The other thing that we were playing with is a little project called iodine.
And this has been fun.
Yeah.
This has a lot of potential.
Iodine allows you to, and correct me if I'm wrong, tunnel TCP traffic over DNS.
Yep.
Try out SSH Shuttle for that.
It's much easier to set up.
It just works over SSH.
I'll look into this too, SSH Shuttle.
SSH Shuttle.
But the nice thing about iodine is it's, it has,
DNS has to work for a lot of these captive portals to work.
So if you're on a network that has a captive portal,
in order for the page to load, DNS is likely working.
And so you can exploit that to get access to the internet
without having to accept the captive portal, which I think has a lot of potential.
It is not super fast.
You can hope for maybe like 200 kilobits per second or something.
Yeah, it's, it's straight up.
Is it, is it Shuttle with two S's or is it?
Yeah.
I just dropped a link into IRC for you.
Okay.
All right.
This is happening.
We're, we're getting down on all of this.
So iodine has the potential to keep me connected in situations,
maybe like when I'm in the air that I normally couldn't be connected
for text messaging and email and IRC and Slack and telegram.
Not live streaming.
No, not for, not for Netflix or anything like that.
Yeah.
I did see somebody trying to watch Netflix on the airplane on the flight back.
Oh really?
How did that go for them?
Cause I phone those connections to vary a lot.
I don't, I don't, I didn't watch closely.
The trick is you download man.
That's why Netflix on mobile devices allows you to download content before you travel.
Maybe they downloaded.
That might be it.
Yeah.
So S Shuttle, is that, is that what I'm looking for here?
This looks.
SSH.
Yeah.
S Shuttle.
I suppose it is.
I've just put some aliases in the, uh, IRC for you too.
So it puts think the paid file up so you can run it as a demon in the background.
So very, very nice.
Yeah.
Transparent proxy server that works as a poor man's VPN forwards over SSH.
Doesn't require admin.
Supports DNS tunneling.
That's great.
I didn't, I've used it for just the regular stuff, but I didn't know it had the DNS component.
DNS tunneling could be pretty, pretty great.
I, uh, it's in the, uh, it's in the repo too.
Hmm.
So it's a pretty low barrier of entry here.
I'll put a link to this in the show notes.
I think this is also worth checking out.
Thank you, sir.
That's a good travel hack.
Yeah.
So that's the kind of stuff I'm talking about.
I like this stuff.
I use it to get around corporate firewalls.
So your mileage, cause you can put SSH on port four, four, three, and then use corkscrew to
tunnel your SSH through on port four, four, three.
So most proxies can't tell the difference between that and SSH traffic.
So right.
Yeah.
And, um, that's the thing about DNS tunneling is like, they can't shut down DNS or else that
breaks a lot of stuff.
So they're kind of stuck.
DNS is sort of essential for all this to work.
So that's what's great about being able to tunnel over DNS is sort of the gotcha, uh,
the gotcha maneuver.
Hmm.
Well, um, I like that.
Thank you.
I'll take a look into all of that.
If anybody else has any travel tips, uh, travel hack tips.
Yeah.
We can all get by better together.
At Chris Elias.
Oh, uh, Badger, it looks like J6 is saying in the, uh, chat room that there's actually
a system D service, uh, for S shuttle too.
So that could be the way to go.
Yeah.
Can imagine there is.
All right, Mr.
Payne, it's the last check-in of the show.
How are we doing over there?
How is the keyboardio treating you?
Okay.
Well, I, I was able to build the clean firmware for the keyboard.
Now I haven't tested it yet, so we can do that.
Oh, really?
So you've rebuilt the entire firmware?
Yes.
Oh my goodness.
And, and you're about to deploy it to the keyboard?
Oh, wow.
We certainly, I mean, that's the next step.
Now it doesn't have the plugin modifications.
Oh, that's going to be the, that'll be the trick after this.
Assuming, assuming this works.
All right, let's do it.
So let's, uh, let's send that new interface over.
So this firmware, by the way, so it goes, the interface is USB-C, but the keyboards
themselves are actually in two pieces combined together.
Look like butterfly wings.
And they're connected with what seems to be an ethernet cable between the two different
keyboards, Wes Payne plugging it in right now, getting ready to deploy the new keyboardio
firmware.
Yeah, let's see here.
Custom firmware for a custom keyboard with beautiful mechanical key switches,
a nice maple wood enclosure and Linux firmware inside the hardware.
All right, Wes.
All right.
Um, I mean, it's kind of anticlimactic.
It is, right?
Well, there's a lot of steps here.
Okay.
You know what, you know, what we'll have to say is, uh, I guess tune in next week to find
out if it works.
Right.
Tune in next week where I'll be exclusively using the keyboardio.
Really?
Do we get that handy dandy music again next week?
Yes.