This is my Geiger counter project I've been working on for about the past year
I decided to build this project as I discovered these cheaply available radiation motor boards on Amazon or Aliexpress and
Although they like as they stand they give you a nice clicking sound like the recognizable sound you hear on movies and TV
They don't really do an awful lot
So I decided to up the ante a bit by connecting this board to a Raspberry Pi
Feeding the data into influx DB and showing it with Grafana, but then of course it needed a fancy case
So I set up on this expedition to build a steampunk style
Geiger counter case
including
Like custom machine brass parts LEDs and nixie tubes. Yeah, it is a beautiful case
The input to the project is of course generated by the radiation detector
this board generates a pulse for every count which is then fed into custom circuitry to drive the LED displays and
Simultaneously into the Raspberry Pi which as he mentioned not only allows the nixie tubes to update which look
Incredible, but that's also how the data gets into the influx database
And it's kind of a neat little trick because the Raspberry Pi is locked inside this wooden box behind
screws and
Adhesives so there's no getting physically to the pie anymore
Thankfully, you know and this is a show-and-tell over on balena.io so of course the author here is using Balena cloud
To handle all the updates they've got a neat sort of framework where it's all still powered on Docker containers now
They've got their own forked version from from the upstream Moby so that it works well for you know iot embedded use cases
but basically means you can just go you know push some updates to your code push a container to a repository and
Then the pie just pulls those updates runs the new container and you don't have to worry about having to go take all the screws
Out pull your thing out to replace the SD card with your updated less broken software
Plus it's all connected with a VPN connection to a public URL so you can get to the dashboard from anywhere
That's my favorite part they might be known for etcher, but they come up with some pretty cool solutions
It's worth checking out the link in the show notes
Hello friends and welcome into 361 of your weekly Linux talk show my name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Mr.
Payne
361 is packed full of community news our look at the new openSUSE elite 15 to that has been in the works and
Crazy drew got his crazy pebble running rebel, and we'll tell you about that experience
We have an app pick and a lot more so before we go any further. Let's say a hearty
Time-appropriate greetings to cheese and drew hello gentlemen hello internet. I'm not crazy. I'm eccentric
Fair enough, and I agree in a good way in a good way drew because now we get to hear about your experiences with rebel
which as a former
Pebble watch owner which has been a while now
I'm really curious to hear how these old devices which I loved mine had the L cars theme on there curious to hear how it
Holds up and also
We have a duty right here at the top of the show a big shout out to our virtual lug time appropriate greetings
mobile room
The force is strong in the mumble room some good voices familiar voices new voices. It's great
It's great, and if I'm not mistaken. I think one of those voices is
Jeff who is joining us from an undisclosed location
I'll say because I actually don't know what it is
And he has a new project announcement this week Jeff welcome to the show or a big update at least yeah
Thank you for having me. I could say I'm from a bunker in New Zealand, but that wouldn't be the truth I
Like it though. I like it a lot, so Jeff
I grabbed a clip or two of you from a video today
But I guess I didn't need to because you're here, and you have a big release
This is an app that I think a lot of us could use it's getting things gnome
Version 0.4 came out today as we're recording just a little bit ago, and it's a big update
It's if I'm not mistaken the first update in a long time with 630 new changes
Hundreds of bug fixes it seems like kind of a big milestone
Yeah, it is and it's an application that I've been using using since what 2009 so it's been a while
I've just decided to not let this application
Go the way of the dodo because it has gone unmaintained for a while, so I just thought this application is too good
it's worth saving and
Now I it's basically the last six and a half years of development packed into one release
So pretty significant seems like there's a lot of focus here on improving the contributor experience
You know with some new methodologies some new structure around how the project is gonna
Go so making you hopeful that the next release won't be in another six years
Yeah, because I'm not gonna try to fix everything under the Sun
I mean that part of the
Part of the way you get to release early and often is to try not to fix everything and just fix the most important things
And then leave all the rest
The that what I call the low-hanging fruit to newcomers to tackle now getting things done
Apps are very popular for those of you that aren't familiar with the getting things done methodology
it's a it's a personal task management system and
I've seen
Hundreds on iOS and Android there's websites dedicated to this
There's entire services and companies like todoist where this is all they do and I'm curious Jeff
What motivates you to make this because it doesn't seem like we're lacking options for commercial offerings
But maybe we are lacking
Really nice well designed beautifully designed. I should say to do apps for Linux. What's your motivation here?
Obviously, I'm biased. I've been using this thing for over a decade
but I do think that getting things gnome has no equivalent on Linux or even arguably on some other platforms and
It's really the I mean, there's maybe one or two other apps including Emacs
That you can use to do GDD on Linux, but it's not the same user experience
It's not, you know built to be not as beautiful as in eye candy
But beautiful in terms of efficiency and terms of workflow
So it has a bunch of little details, you know attention to detail that make it a wholly different thing from your regular to-do list
And someone might say why are you obsessing about something? That's basically a to-do list. But that thing is
You know, it's really easy to make
Grocery shopping list to-do list application. That's basically computer science 101. You hack that in two hours
But making something that is really well integrated and smart and that has all the crazy features that you need to
Do something as advanced as to getting things done methodology or some of the other
Methodologies out there is quite a different ballpark
Yes, it is and you touched on something there that I think is really important for a personal life management app like this
And you said I've been using this for 10 years
Can you talk a little bit about how an app like this needs to be around for a very long time?
And that's why it's kind of risky to go with something like to-do list or a commercial application in this regard
That's part of the reason why I've stubbornly refused to let this app go
completely on maintains is I
Basically invested my life and my my productivity
And I centered everything around this app. Wow
And so you don't really migrate that easily to another app for one thing
You would need other apps to understand the file format and that sort of thing
Those apps usually aren't built to interoperate, you know, especially in the commercial world. Well, they don't really care to
Interoperate I I refuse the notion of
just going out there and paying like a
30 bucks to buy a proprietary application that I I'm not sure will still exist in five years
Whenever the company gets bought out by another company or when they change their terms and condition or they decide to
Stop supporting my platform. That's one of the risks you have with proprietary software
Especially software that you really depend on for your daily life work and play
Is to depend on a system that might not exist next year. Yes. Well put
Yeah, and of course if you switch, I mean all the time spent switching is time wasted
All the time spent switching is time spent not getting things done
Arguably that's also a disease that many gtd practitioners have we have this shiny widget syndrome thing where we
Want to try yet another tool
Um and yet another to do app. Oh and this one promises to be just as more amazing than the previous one
And you spend more time
Playing with the tools than actually using them and this tool. Well, I mean it's good enough it works
So I haven't changed it and I don't want to change it. I just wanted to improve it
I'm curious about the experience of bringing it up to a modern
Gnome application because it it kind of almost looks like an example modern
Gnome desktop app
It's got a lot of the bells and whistles that you see in there and i'm curious
What that process was like to just modernize it. I can't speak for isidor and the other people
Who spent a couple years burning out doing the actual port to gtk 3?
Uh, I just came in and finished the job kind of um by just kind of focusing the project towards a singular goal
or getting the release out and
managing the project properly
But it's more of a technological problem and a problem of risking burnout
Than a design problem
It's kind of special in the way that getting things gnome was kind of so well designed from the get-go
That it was almost a gnome 3 app already in terms of how the ui behaved and everything
Of course, you need to change the code base port to python 3 from python 2 and to integrate things like the gtk header bar widget
To have a nice cleaner ui that is now possible. It was not possible 10 years ago
but the whole design processing that was not the hardest thing the hardest thing is
Getting things gnome done
And getting it out of the door and like so many free software projects
It stands on the work of those who came before you to get some of that work done to get moved over to gtk3
Well, congratulations on the new release
We'll have a link to uh the project page and also the flat hub entry if people want to get the flat pack of it
If you're out there looking for a native local
Task management application either for a beginner or somebody who's fairly advanced
I give this a big hearty recommendation jeff. Thanks for making it on the show and telling us a little bit about it
My pleasure. Thanks for having me
Let's talk about the crazy cats over at fedora now who are just
Working up a whole bunch of stuff for fedora 33 including the end of mod php
and perhaps
more
Interesting to us is no more swap partition fedora normally installs itself with a modest swap partition to take some pressure off
Memory if needed, but a new proposal says to do away with the swap file and instead use a virtual swap device using
Zram the zram device works by compressing memory contents and then storing them back in memory when needed and then retrieving them and
Obviously decompressing when you're compressing and decompressing the ram it's super fast and swapping the zram can
Potentially free up considerable space from a swap file or a swap partition if it's not needed
Yeah, and surprisingly maybe zram is often faster than swapping to a storage device
Even though the cpu has to do the work of compression and decompression, but that's just really fast with modern cpus
Yeah, that'd be interesting to see if that takes off
I could see it especially since I think fedora workstation is really targeted at a lot of laptop users with
Limited ssds. There's also some stuff being considered at the lower levels of fedora
Yeah, some interesting potential changes on compiler policies now long-standing fedora policies are
Fedora policy as it is now says that the entire distribution has to be built with gcc
With exceptions only for packages that cannot be built with gcc, but the plan for fedora 33 is to get rid of that requirement
Instead the compiler used for any given package would be the one preferred by upstream
Well, assuming that upstream has expressed a preference, of course
That would open the way for building a number of llvm preferring packages
Without maintainers having to struggle to get a working build with gcc and that seems pretty great if you want to you know
Maintain good relationships with upstream, especially if you've already been building with llvm and here you go
Just some downstream, you know distro says oh no if you want your package here
You got to use an entirely different tool chain
Yeah, I hadn't really thought about that problem before lwn.net has some great coverage of the reactions, too
Which we'll have linked in the show notes if you'd like to grab that
Jeff law is driving this change and he said using the upstream preferred compiler would make life easier for fedora package maintainers
Some of these proposals have strong reactions
But the one that I think has probably gotten the most strongest reaction is that crazy cat neil who's in the mumble room right now
Has proposed that fedora change the default file system for fedora workstation to butter fs
And i'd say it's seen the whole gamut of responses neil
Ha ha ha you're here. Yeah. Yes. Yes
You sound tired you sound tired it showed up on devil on a friday
And thank goodness. I I had the day off that friday. And so that friday saturday sunday
monday and tuesday
I was responding to things basically almost every other email and pouring over it and trying to figure out
You know what's going on and the feedback the good news is that it's generally been very balanced. It was very the the fedora community
Took it seriously and responded with really useful feedback that helped us
Tune and refine the the proposal and also I want to point out that this is not just workstation
Every fedora desktop flavor is switching
The only variants not switching right now are fedora server and fedora cloud
Those two variants are remaining with their current setup, which is for cloud
I think it's just a single big x4 volume and for server. It's xfs on lvm
And fedora core os also has its like
Strange
X4 based thing, but yeah, that's the change that's just because it reflects the intentions of rel not to make a switch to butter fs
Yeah, it's it's that but also um
One of the primary motivating factors for changing to butter fs is that there's this space contention thing
I know you talked about this on air a few weeks ago
The space contention thing is essentially the biggest driver for this
the next driver for using butter fs over alternatives is that
Anaconda the red hat fedora installer
Has special behavior when it comes to butter fs sub volumes if you wish to reinstall
And you have home as a separate sub volume. It will not make you blow it away because it will just make a new
root sub volume or erase the existing one and then remount the new one that you make and you can reuse the existing roots of
Home sub volume and that lets you preserve your data as you reinstall so you get to have your cake and eat it too
Access to all the space while also being able to reliably preserve data across reinstalls, which can happen
There are for various reasons people may want to reinstall. Maybe they want to switch desktop environments
They want to change some settings or whatever
So like this is about making sure that that's still possible because every other alternative blocks that now on the other hand
There has been some pushback and I think there's also a lot of folks still who are uncomfortable
Around the idea of butter fs. They consider it unsafe, but I remember a time
When the newer versions of the extended file system like three and four were considered a mess
I remember a time when riser fs was a mess
I remember a time when a lot of file systems were rough and they got better as development continued
The file systems that didn't get better just didn't have active development
And I think the big difference back then was is we didn't have all of these platforms to amplify the problems
You didn't have social media reddit and podcasts and youtube videos that were
Just amplifying the issues you were just a person in a data center dealing with data loss by yourself
Maybe bitching on a form or a bbs and it was essentially contained
But now there's an amplification chamber where people who don't really know the cause of the problems
I it seems like if you go by the data a lot of file system issues that butter fs run into today
Are actually caused by crappy firmware on disks
And this is something that's bared out at facebook as well about
five six years ago
Facebook started seriously ramping up towards the next generation storage architecture
And they hired on developers to work on butter fs as their select as their choice for this
And they've discovered over time
That basically things that people expected it to be butter fs's fault
Wound up being stupid things like the storage controller just can't handle massive. Io load and started rejecting drives
Or the ssd just like chokes out because like it just does the wrong thing
And the problem is that butter fs is sensitive to those things other file systems are not
And you know people do things like well, let's intentionally punch holes through the file system and see if butter fs can recover
The problem with that strategy when you compare it against the old system
The problem with that strategy when you compare it against xfs and x4 is that when you do that?
The way that fisk works is that it attempts to repair the mountability of the file system
It tries to restore the integrity of the metadata at all costs
This means that you could entirely have the possibility
Of restoring an x4 xfs file system where the links to the data
Are fine, but the data itself is bad, right? And it just continues on as if nothing's wrong
Exactly and in butter fs's case
And of course you and I both are aware like we've talked about zfs before zfs also does this if you repair the file system
And it does a validation of the data as part of relinking the metadata to the data
And it it discovers that the data is broken. It will loudly tell you so and it will say you've lost data
Good luck. Have fun
My final thoughts on this because I know we've talked about it a lot is essentially in the ven diagram of when to adopt
Open source or free software. I think butter fs is now sitting in the sweet middle
It needs more deployments
But it has now been tested not only in scale with lots of nas products that ship with butter fs
And obviously at facebook that gets mentioned all the time, but also as the default file system on opensusa for years
So we've had a lot of production testing and now we could bring it to even more masses and the reality is fedora and redhat
They're never going to ship zfs as the default file system, but they need a competitive product
They need something that competes with modern ntfs and apfs
Things like snapshot based backups and windows shadow copies
Have been commonplace in the commercial operating systems for a while now
And we will never even get to the point of starting to build those features into things like our desktop environments and our file managers
Or even user land tools until it's shipped developers need the code shipping to use it and there's things
We need to work out too on how to properly ship all the updates and all of that that will only happen
When we start to do it at scale
And it seems to me that if you were to review the landscape of possible linux distributions that this could happen in
Fedora is an obvious case
My old butt remembers a time when fedora was so cutting edge that they adopted pulse audio before everybody else
And they shipped a volume applet in the gnome menu bar that didn't actually change the volume
But they plan to make that work in the next release
And it was important to get pulse audio out in front of end users and make it reliable
and fedora could bring butterfs to a whole new scale of users and
The ideal fedora user from a project standpoint is a sysadmin devops developer type person who's using a laptop
With an ssd in it. That's probably 512 gigs or less and that is such a perfect use case for butterfs
additionally
features like encryption are coming down the pipeline that already use the same mature data pipeline that
Compression uses on butterfs which means it's going to be a solid crypto using a solid proven data pathway
To make it happen and you'll be able to encrypt a single file a single folder or encrypt an existing
Mount point without having to wipe the data and set it up again and that
Single limitation that exists now in linux has forced vendors like system 76 to create installer
Methodologies that wipe and reload your system after you receive it
Which if you think about it is mental that they have to do that because it just enters so many
Possibility of mistakes and errors where it could leave the user with an unusable system
So they have to test the hell out of it
To just work around this problem where they can't encrypt a mount point or a home folder that already exists
So they can't ship you a system that's set up and ready to go
They have to do that work and that's crazy
And it seems like something from the 90s and linux should be a bastion of technical excellence
And we have a file system here. That is gpl. It's free software
It's completely cool and okay to link it to the kernel
And we're just sitting on our hands going. I don't know. I've heard some bad stuff about it
Meanwhile, people are putting in production going actually it's gotten a lot better
Last but not least even though I said, I know it was almost done. But now i'm going on a roll
I was a big critic. I said it was junk and I was willing to revisit that and try it in production again
I even was willing to revisit it after I blew away data because I realized it wasn't butterfess's fault
It was my fault. I screwed it up
I even I will now eat my words and say, you know what? It's gotten better
Maybe it was crap when I tried it and my systems wouldn't boot in the past
But now here I am using it and it's been working fantastic for me
And I just have to implore people to just give it another look because the reality about free software
And this is something that's great is that as long as development continues
It's always improving and if you haven't checked in lately, then maybe your opinion's out of date and
I'm not saying it's forever use case
But the developer workstation with a 256 gigabyte ssd in their laptop. I think it's probably the ideal case
End of soapbox, but I would love to see it happen in fedora 33 and i'm curious neil in your personal opinion
How close is that actually to happening?
I mean is this is this getting dangled in front of me and it's going to be yanked away
I sure hope not. I mean like man i've been working on this personally for a little over three years
Like I i've been doing integration at almost every layer of the stack for a few years now, and it's just
Nobody more than me would be sad if I had to feet from the jaws of victory here
I have no reason to expect it to not be approved and that we would not start going forward with this
Within the next day or so
Basically once it's approved formally by fesco fedora engineering steering committee
Then uh, we will go forward with starting to implement all this
and like I have in my mind a mental road map of ideas of things that we can do to start leveraging these things as we
Validate and test these features and integrate them into our user experience. I'm going through this actually fairly conservatively
There are many things that I am personally using that i'm not even including in this change proposal because I want to make sure
That we have this rock solid as we go forward and adopt features. That makes sense
It's no fun to be the guy who has to say well, i'm sorry
Like your data's gone because like you messed up here. It's neil's fault
He got everybody to use butter fs and you lost your data because of neil. Yeah, no, no
The reason why i'm excited for it is
I like to see this stuff happen
I like to be on the front lines and watch it and then hopefully see developers begin to integrate it and that just won't happen
Because today I could install fedora and I could choose butter fs or xfs and I have
And it's fine, but it's basically as functional as any other file system. There's nothing
Integrated with the operating system. There's no real advantage to it. Um, it's just disconnected
It's disjointed and we can begin to bring that together
If we start to deploy this default and still leave all the other file systems available for people to select you could oh you could
You could put extended 2 on there for all I care
So i'll keep an eye on it neil. Hopefully we'll see it developed now. We are going to be off next week
So if it does happen, uh, I mean we're pre-recorded is what I should say because we never really take a week off
It's the steady beat of lup, but uh, if it does happen, we'll have to cover it in two weeks
Should be interesting
Um, and then actually you know what if it does happen, uh, we'll be talking about it in the lup lug
So why don't we right here? This is probably the best time to do a little housekeeping
So the lup lug happens every sunday at new york time
It happens every sunday at noon pacific the regular broadcast time in our mumble room up in the lobby
I encourage you to join it now. I mention the mumble all the time and I want to let you know how to find it
I should probably put it on the main linux unplugged website
Never crossed my mind wouldn't that be an idea?
You know, I guess we just been around a long time west
We never thought about it because the traditional way is you just go google search jupiter colony mumble
And the setup guide is there you can follow that and
And get it set up in a few minutes, but I think we probably should have something on the main site
So we'll probably do that eventually go google search mumble jupiter colony and you'll find it in there
You'll find the guide get it all set up and then join us on a sunday
And chat with us and be part of a lug. We have 30 folks in here right now
If you think about that in terms of people showing up for a lug meeting, that's a really great attendance
Usually on sundays we usually have around 20
And we're just chatting about all kinds of stuff
So yeah, like I mentioned, we won't be live next tuesday, but the lug lug continues every single sunday
And then the live show will be back on the 21st of july
2020 obviously if you're listening to this in the future i'm going on a little family trip to montana
And then linux headlines will also be off
Back on the 20th because drew's taking a little time off too. That's great. Huh? It's about time. We're finally letting him
Finally, I mean i'm gonna make him set up cameras and wear a tracker obviously
But we're gonna let him take a little time off and then you can always check the calendar
Yeah, put that put that tracker back on drew this ankle monitor is giving me a rash dude
Yeah, yeah, that's what my kids and wife complain about too. Uh, you can know when we're live at jupiter broadcasting.com
Calendar, hopefully we just keep that updated and it's all over there and then you don't have to worry about it
So there you have it. That's it. That's all I got for you in the housekeeping
Nice and tidy around here west doesn't take very long. This is my last uh, my last podcast
Total into from texas. You sound a little sentimental about that. I am i've i've liked my i've enjoyed my time down here
It's so much nicer to drive down here
They've got like side highways west that go along the main highway and then they've got frontage roads
And then they've got toll roads and uh, so you can just zip around here. You just zip. I mean i'm in
austin and it's still
Better traffic than you get 50 miles north of seattle. So I will miss that
I won't miss the heat though. The feels like temperature is 108 degrees fahrenheit today. So I won't I won't miss that
Um, all right. Well, let's talk about open susa leap
15.2 a new leap is upon us
Speaking of uh butter fs based systems. I have not tried out susa in about
275 years so I thought why not give it a go and immediately install the server version which i'll talk about
in a little bit, but uh sus has
leaped again
I don't really know what to say about sus because to me it's this linux distribution
that I try for a little bit and then I end up usually going back to other distros just because
I've never really just gotten in the groove but 15.2 contains a lot of nice stuff
The shipping sway for wayland, which as you know is a drop-in replacement for the i3 window manager
they're also including a real-time kernel for some folks that need that like uh
Embedded devices or audio pros or if you're capturing a lot of data real-time can be
Very important. It's just nice to see this going in another distribution
Of course yas has gotten some improvements as always and the other thing that's interesting about leap is they're
Continuing to support a migration strategy to go from open susa leap
To susa linux enterprise their commercial product
Which I suppose probably happens. Well, right. I mean, you know, you maybe you're testing it out
Maybe you're considering switching or you just you know, you build out your prototype down the road your business does well and you realize
Oh, you know, we we really we can afford support now. We need support now
And you don't have to re-architect stuff. You should just you know, switch on over. Yeah
It's just all those people are using ubuntu. Well, there is that but maybe you're in germany
Yeah, I suppose it's just you know in the ubuntu model and I don't mean to to to to harsh on susa's vibe here
But in the ubuntu model, it's just one ubuntu. You just go get the lts
There's no silly different versions. It feels like a windows thing to do this. Yeah, or I mean it is definitely an older style
I guess right
Not as not a hyper converged, which is okay. I mean that still works for a lot of people. But yeah, I could see it
I could see it being a possibility of try before you buy sort of thing
So let's go around the horn and see what you all thought cheesy. Let's start with you. Why don't we do a
You know the old say what you didn't like and then end on what you did like and so i'm gonna look at this as kind
Of a new user perspective this perspective. I generally like to give someone that that hasn't used a lot of linux distributions
And susa's one of those that's kind of like you said kind of on the outskirts a little bit that a lot of people may not have
Um yas
While cool is still yas
Um and feels a little nostalgic to me. The the installation was a little awkward. I didn't get you know, um,
Like a simple partitioning
Method, uh, it did select the disk that was empty by default
So it was smart enough to know that this disc didn't have any other file systems on it. Um, use that disk
There were also some other little features in the installer which kind of annoyed me. They had uh green buttons with gray text on them
Why would you ever do that? It's a horrible idea
Please don't because I didn't know when to click next was it done? Was it supposed to light up?
You know black over the green button whenever it was done. I didn't know so that was a little awkward
But I mean installation was pretty straightforward. No big deal there
The default installation and version of grub recognized my popos install on another disc
And was fine. I was able to you know switch into either one
however, after I
Updated it for the first time it removed that entry from grub
So, you know not a big deal something I can get through but you know
If you are a user that's trying out multiple distributions on a system with multiple hard drives that might be
Something you come across and then after the first update as well auto login was turned on by default
Yeah, I think it is in the installer too. I think during the installation. Why would you that's no
Well, you know, I I think there are
By far and large my use case is you know the system i'm setting up at home where yeah
I never turned that on but
I imagine for a lot of people it doesn't make sense to have to log in if you have one compute user on the account
And you keep your computer in your house
Especially right now. That's true. But I mean, I I think it's always good practice to have a login
The thing that's annoying about that is then you just have to unlock the keychain anyways, you know
Like kd wallet or gnome keychain still has to be unlocked when you auto log in and so you end up just having to put your
Password in anyways, right? Right. They also use a little bit older version of gnome
Which was good because the the problem I'd had with folders in gnome 3.6 is that you have to have a keychain
I'd had with folders in gnome 3.6 isn't there because they're using gnome 3.4
That does use the 5.3 kernel
And then another thing that was just really kind of awkward to me. I've seen other distributions do this
There were two terminal applications
There were two mail applications by default. So there seemed like a lot of
Stuff they could have cleaned up. Yeah, it's just an old way of doing it, huh?
Yeah, well and it's you know, they just auto populate the the menus and and that's what you get, right?
So, I mean, I I like that it's
Installed by default like having mutt there is cool. But if you're going to do that does mutt really need
An icon in your application menu if you're just going to open up the terminal and open mutt that way
So it seems a little weird in that regard
You know, I would have personally cleaned up a few of the apps and made that selection a little a little better for the end user
But on the good side, I mean it did seem pretty snappy. I know i'm the only person in the world
That's a fan of hot corners, but they were turned on by default, which I thought was cool
The offline installer was super cool. Yeah, I do like that
It threw me back into a little bit of nostalgia right with yas an offline installer. Everything's there on you know, the 4.6 gigabyte
Uh iso reading the release notes as files install
Right, you know, so I mean it was cool. It was cool
And then the the overall selection of default apps were pretty solid apps
I mean they weren't bad, but there were some redundant apps, which is kind of weird but
Overall, I mean, I think it's a good distro. Is it something that i'm going to use
On the day-to-day, you know, probably not at least not right now
But I will review it again in the future as I mean it was the very first
User-friendly distro that I ever ever used. I think I pretty much am right in line with your observations there
It feels almost like a a different branch where there were trying things out and some things have stuck that didn't stick in
The other branch of linux and some things should be adopted that haven't been adopted by the other branch of linux
Wes i'm curious your thoughts on this guy. Um, I think in my opinion
The installer manages to strike that balance of easy to use for the most part
But gives power users a lot of options and perhaps I think it gets there a little better than anaconda does for fedora
You know, honestly, I was really impressed with the installer. It's been ages since i've installed open susa
And yeah, you know, um parts especially during the actual installation
It was a little bit slow for me now full disclosure
I was installing in a virtual machine and then rebooted, you know into the real os afterwards
That might have just been my own internet or you know, whatever mirrors I happened to be using at the time
But the rest of the installation experience really I couldn't have been happier with and I was really impressed at the end
Especially you just got this really detailed rundown of all the options
You've configured and then little clickable links if you need to go adjust that
One that really stood out to me was let's say you want to change, you know
If you're enabling or disabling specter mitigations, you just click on that
Pops you up to where you can go make adjustments to whatever grub parameters are going to get set for your kernel command line
Right there in the installer and I don't see that hardly anywhere else
Yeah, it really felt like it was at home in the enterprise
But it didn't make you go through those things if you're just a normal user and you know
You don't even know what that means
I do agree with you that anything to do with package management feels like your soul dies a little bit
I I just wince when I click on the online updates and it does like the four or five
Prerequisite things that it has to do before it can even execute the very task that i've asked for and it's just
Compared to every other package manager on the entire planet that just immediately gets to work when you tell it to do an update
I find that just soul crushing the transactional server option was interesting
So this is an installer mode you can now select and one of the key features is a read-only root file system
You kind of need that if you're going to go with the whole transactional style, right?
And we've all had especially thinking of upgrades over in the debian world with apt where
Something breaks or maybe it's on arch and suddenly you just you can't change your packages
You don't know what to do and you just wish you could roll that back and try it again later, right?
And if you enable this transactional server support, that's what it does
It comes with a read-only file system
And then when you install stuff it all goes in a brand new snapshot and only if that installation to the snapshot volume goes well
Do you actually go reboot into the new system?
One thing that's different too, you know compared to things like um, like os tree or some of the core os style
You know, there's been a lot of different takes on this idea, but in the open suse land
It's all powered by the same zipper and butter fs
So you don't have to rebuild your packages to support this new transactional style. You just basically get it for free
There's a good example of a distribution that is starting to leverage
The built-in capabilities of butter fs instead of having to create that code themselves from scratch
And it's just an aspect of maturity of shipping butter fs for a while
These things are just now commonly available to them and they can integrate them more and more
And I I think that was a key point I was trying to make earlier with the fedora adoption is they have to adopt it
Now in order for features like this to come along down the road. This is pretty neat stuff here
Yeah, the other stuff I thought was really kind of neat is um, there's a transactional shell feature
So if you'd like after that installation installs into this new snapshot
You can get a shell, you know, basically a cheroot into that environment
If you want to go test some things out make sure your package is installed correctly tweak any of the configuration before you reboot
And I think another sign of maturity. There's a built-in health checker framework
So after you've rebooted into the new server the health checker runs and verifies the state of the system
So you make sure that all the services you need are running make sure that the database you installed starts up
Okay, and it's just a bunch of shell scripts
So it's easy to extend if you know, you're using this to build your own custom application
You can include your own logic there to make sure that your custom app starts up
Okay, and if not, the system automatically rolls back to the previous snapshots and reboots, so you're done
that is
So what i'm talking about
That is really a really nice setup and like you said it just seems like a mature way to do it
It's enterprise grade. Exactly. So check out leap
It's a pretty solid option. And if you're not an old grump like me
Who's stuck in his ways?
It may be a great opportunity to try something that has a lot of unique features and capabilities to it
I think it's something kind of special in the linux world and we don't talk about a lot because none of us are susa users
But i'd love to hear your experiences with it
If you have tried out 15.2 go to linux unplugged dot com slash contact
And write in and let me know how it's gone for you. I think it's uh, it's an opportunity to kind of
Crowdsource
People's results, you know, it is kind of it's been something of a blind spot for us, I guess
Um, and there's really a lot of interesting stuff there. That's that's happening
Especially around yast and the butter fs adoptions
A lot of good ideas and I think we could do a little better job of highlighting that and that's something the audience could
Really help us with linux unplugged dot com slash contact. Okay, so on december 7th
2016 it feels like it was just yesterday pebble announced they were ceasing operations
Two days later on december 9th 2016
The rebel site went live and our very own rebel. Mr. Drew has brought his pebble back to life
Such a rude. Tell me about this process and this experience. It's something i've always wanted to try
Were you still actively using the pebble?
Did you have to dig it out of the drawer and it just happened to still work the very first step was remembering which
Bucket I had put it in and finding out that it was working
Put it in and finding it
The second step was finding the charging cable
Which was not right there with it because I just am terrible at sorting old junk that i've tossed in a drawer
And it's got a weird charger too. Yeah, it's got the little pogo pins and all that
but once I found it it charged right up and
The process to install is a little involved, but it's not terrible
The instructions on the rebel website are pretty clear and they're separated out for if you're on ios or android
And me being on android the number one thing that you have to do is you have to go and get the old pebble app
Which is not on the play store anymore. You've got to download it from apk mirror
And once you do that and kind of get everything connected
Then it's really simple. You just have to go to two websites
two websites and in the back end the pebble app will switch
From the pebble web services over to the rebel web services and you're off and running. How does that switch happen?
You literally just go to auth dot rebel dot i o in a browser
and sign in
And then after that you go to boot dot rebel dot i o it'll reopen the pebble app
And you'll be greeted with the rebel login screen instead of the pebble login screen. That's it
Wow, is it using some sort of software update function to do that? That's pretty simple. That's nice
I don't know how it works in the back end because when I was reading the instructions
It's like clearly there has to be something more to this than just clicking two links
This doesn't make sense to me to my my little brain
how does it um, you know make that switch within the app itself, but
it does and
Once you're in you can download old and new watch faces and old and new apps
Pretty simple pretty slick and it works just the way that you remember back when it was the official pebble stuff. That's pretty great now
Simpler than you were expecting it sounds like oh, yeah much much much simpler than I expected
I thought I was gonna have to be like
Doing some adb stuff or something along those lines. No, not at all. Are they hosting these services?
Yeah, they are and the rebel web services are basically a drop-in replacement
It's all hosted on their end and they do have a premium tier where you can pay 33 bucks a year or three bucks a month
And that'll give you dictation and weather services
But other than that the main reason to do it is just to support the rebel project so that they can keep their servers online
So once you got this thing up and going were you able to do anything cool?
I did try to get the old home assistant app up and running now that i'm a home assistant user
but unfortunately the app was not authenticating properly for me, but
I found another app called HTTP push that allows me to put in custom HTTP
you know get or
push requests
And I set up some webhook automations in my home assistant. And so now on my watch I can launch services
I can toggle lights
I can even set it up so that it will broadcast to my google homes
And let my wife know that i'm on my way home if i'm out picking something up neat
Very modern and all the old health features and everything still work
You know, it still even ties into google fit which I really like and I think my number one feature
The thing that I missed most of all is the smart alarm
Where it will track my sleep and figure out when i'm not in REM sleep
And that's when it starts vibrating on my wrist to wake me up. That makes all the difference. Oh, I missed it so much
It was so good. Yeah, you know, I just did this yesterday and I used that smart alarm feature last night
And I woke up feeling better than I had in quite a while
Is the integration pretty good with your phone OS like music controls or podcast controls work? Okay and stuff. Oh, yeah, totally
Huh, I gave my pebble to my dad
Uh, and he still uses it and I don't know if he did this or not
He may have he's he's just technical enough and it sounds like the process wouldn't be too difficult
Does it integrate in with calendar services and stuff like that as well? Absolutely
And they show up on your timeline just like they used to
And the rebel people recently set it up so that you can push other things to a separate timeline and it'll come down to your watch
So you can do things like set up, um, you know if this and that integrations to
Have like rss feeds and things pop up in your timeline
Which you couldn't do before because that was tied in with the old pebble service, but now they've uh, stripped it out and uh,
Polished it up and made it fresh again. So you're gonna keep using it. Oh, yeah, absolutely. Yeah, really? Yeah, totally
Oh cool. How's the battery? Is it still hanging in there? Yeah, it's doing great
It's as good as I remember it being you know, like eight days of battery life on the model that I have and it's
you know, it's only been a day, but it's uh sitting at
Like 90 to 100 percent. So oh man. I wish something would have come from this
Line of technology because it just makes so much sense to use an e-ink display
On a watch and when you say eight days of battery life
My mouth drops open because i've you know, i've had several newer watches
Digital watches and they get a day maybe two days if i'm lucky. I'm curious drew if you're now going to uh,
Look around at the the old round and the steel and the other series because you should be able to get those for
A ridiculous amount of money nowadays. I mean, they should be pretty cheap
I loaded rebel a long time ago probably in 2016 or something like that on my old pebble, but
I've since put it away and it was okay then but it sounds like it's worth a revision
Yeah, I remember they were really cheap right when the service had just you know
Been announced that it was going away
And they were getting rid of like the old stock and the used market is not as cheap as you would think
I was looking at some time rounds to replace my wife's her old one. She loved it, but her battery exploded
and uh
Haven't been able to you know, get that going again
So now I either have to get a new battery and do some soldering
Try and find one, but they're like 120 bucks on ebay. Oh, wow. Mm-hmm
Well, they're not making any more of them. So I could see why
You hold on to it as long as you can drew. It'll be it's I mean it already kind of is a collector's item
Isn't it? Yeah, totally. Well, thanks for uh, taking one for the team and uh, totally making me miss my my old pebble watch
That sounds pretty cool and sounds like a hearty recommendation if anybody has one rolling around in a drawer out there
Yeah, absolutely. And if anybody has one in their drawer, you know, it's a good idea to have one
In a drawer out there. Yeah, absolutely. And if anybody has an old uh time round that they want to sell to me for cheap
I will take it
There you go at drew of doom on the twitters. That's right
slide into those dms
All right, let's uh, let's do a pick really quick, uh west pane you found
A markdown editor for the 21st century and you know me whenever there's a markdown editor. I want to talk about it
This is a local native application, right? I think well it is electron. Okay, okay
But you've got fedora and debian packages and app images. So, you know almost native
They're making a good concerted effort to at least publish it to the linux desktop. I'll say this
It looks really great. It looks like a solid app and
One of the things it has that seems kind of appealing like a differentiator to the other markdown editors
Is it has a pretty sophisticated research mode? They have a video that explains it and it's just a couple of seconds
I grabbed a clip that talks just about the research mode if you're a professional author or researcher
Settler has all the tools you need to write efficiently
Simply group everything together using the project feature and arrange all your chapters neatly
A mighty citation engine sits at the heart of the app letting you cite your sources with ease
Pull in your literature and choose from over 9000 citation styles
You can even use templates to directly export your paper using the format desired by the journal
The other thing that's kind of neat is it supports exporting to latex as well as other formats and it supports importing
A bunch of formats it has a code highlighting for different languages besides markdown as well
And of course best of all it's free and open source. No. No best of all
No, no best of all it's got dark mode support
But seriously, you know, there's a ton of really great markdown apps out there
But a lot of them kind of just stick to doing markdown and that's good
You know, but there's a whole world beyond markdown and a lot of times, you know
You might use markdown just for some casual notes or a simple document
Settler really lets you take it to the next level and make serious publications do research integrate with citations integrate with latex
It has pandoc integration as well
So if you know you need to pull in sources from word documents or render out to them
It's all built right in it really seems like too
they've taken a focus on helping people collect research either journalists or everybody like anybody that's trying to just
Pull together a bunch of stuff and then cite sources
With a reference manager on sitting on top of it
It seems like that component along with the ui and the import export options do kind of make it stand apart and I
I have now taken it just I write everything in markdown
I just text editor if i'm even just taking notes for something I write it in markdown if i'm making a to-do list
I do it in markdown. So this kind of stuff I find to be pretty appealing
I for the most part just stick with plain text editors
But I absolutely could see busting out settler for a research project or trying to pull something together
Say we're going to do a history of an open source project special
I absolutely could see using it for that kind of stuff and then it keeps it all organized for you in a really easy to
Browse way and you can combine everything into a project. So it's all kind of in one spot
Even if there's multiple files and of course on the back end, it's all just plain text
So, you know if you want to stop using it one day no bigs. I like that too pretty good fine there wess
Pretty pretty good fine. Where can people find links to that and everything else we talked about today
Well in our show notes, of course linux unplugged dot com slash three six one and that does bring us to the end of this week's
Linux unplugged the show is at linux unplugged on twitter where you can get news announcements about the show live stream announcements releases
At linux unplugged the whole network that's at jupiter signal, but if you don't use the twitters, I don't blame you
We'd still like to hear from you though. Go to linux unplugged dot com slash contact
I'd like to start featuring more of your feedback in every episode right around this point in the show
I'd like to be reading your emails and the only way that's going to happen is if you send them in linux unplugged
Dot com slash contact i'm at chris las he's at wess pain
Thank you so much for joining us on this week's episode of the unplugged program
We appreciate you and we'll see you right back here next tuesday
So
Thank you everybody for joining us, uh, it's time for me to head out hit the road i'm gonna i'll be on the road early tomorrow
So that way I can get a solid. I don't know hundred miles in before work
Starts and then i'll work and then as soon as work wraps up
I'm jumping on the road and i'll probably be driving until nearly midnight
But that's not so bad because it's so dang hot down here
That that that kind of works you drive then you park somewhere with a air conditioning you work for a little bit and then
The evening around 8 p.m. It's it becomes nice out again, and then you just drive and drive and drive
So so you've switched to being a night driver. Well, just while i'm in texas. It's because it's a lot neil