Is anybody in here running any docker images in the mumble room?
Anybody use docker?
Well, I think docker is getting pretty popular
Yeah
And I'm worried that we are creating ourselves a bit of a long-term problem with docker
They could give us a bit of a bad name and the BSD guys are gonna give us a hard time about it
We got to get our act together when it comes to docker containers
So a study was just done recently
Showing that over 30% of official docker images in the docker hub contain high priority security vulnerabilities
Honestly, what did you expect?
So what I mean really what did you expect? I mean that is the fundamental trade-off either we have everything is linked
So you have the binary and that links to all these libraries and those libraries are dynamically updated which let's face it in practice
Never works. Well, it well, I wouldn't say never okay fine. I mean it almost never work. I don't know
I think that's a little harsh. It's not harsh eventually
It will cause a problem eventually usually causes a problem
But if you think about it
That is that problem happens the minority of the time because your system works the majority of the time
That's true. So so in the grand scheme of things, I agree with you
However, yeah from the I follow what you say
But it comes to like if you need that one piece of software that one piece of software doesn't work and I have been bitten
By this so many times that I I admit that I am I am like I'm overly sensitive to the issue
Yeah
But well and you're working at it from an enterprise angle to where it's much more of an issue
Right because these companies like I said, they release cut they release software for one version of Linux
Oh, here's the issue though
I mean, yeah, I guess it's not that surprising but we're talking things like these Docker containers are vulnerable to shell shock heart bleed poodle
Etc
And then images published by Docker users not explicitly verified by any authority
Like if you just go to like the general images in the Docker hub, it goes up to 40% of the images having serious
security vulnerabilities over 40% and
a lot of them are old
Mercurial when you look at the official images is the number one source of
Vulnerabilities, but of course when you look at community images ones that are not from the official hub
Then the vulnerabilities primarily come from bash
apt open SSL
File bin utils mercurial rpm like, you know the basic stuff sequel pseudo
HTTP W get like these things are just not getting patched and they're getting these weird vulnerabilities
So now I think you're being too harsh. Really? Well, here's this look at this. Okay, but the numbers Noah are are disgraceful
I mean, we're talking we're talking really well known vulnerabilities that have been taken care of we're talking it
We're talking like you put this stuff into production unless you have taken serious mitigation steps
40% of these images created by the community have critical vulnerabilities and by the way, dude
if you drop from critical down to medium vulnerabilities and you include everything rated as medium then
70% of the images have vulnerabilities. Yeah, but so let's start with this you start with a
Technology that is relatively new right Docker has not been around a terribly long time
He is still they I mean that you people granted people were putting into production before Docker even said
But the reality is it was just last year
I think it was that self when the guy came out and said alright
We've actually fully we actually now support you to put this into production
Yeah, not like it's been out that long to begin with second of all, they're doing something relatively groundbreaking
Runbreaking from the standpoint that we don't really have any sort of cross-platform container that can you know cross distro cross?
Yeah, that's true. Okay, so then you have that working for you
Then add to that the fact that the people that are doing this the people that are smart enough and the people that have the
Resource to do this have other things to do
So they might be able to create this Docker container, but the ability to sit there and maintain it and update it constantly
Yeah, I think I better things to do right? Well, so Corky you think this is just fundamentally
The flaw with having a Docker hub
Well, I don't think we really need it
the whole point of having a hub is to replace what official package repositories if we just
Did what the rocket project is really about just taking the container and then sticking it in package repos
such as the Ubuntu repos or the arch repos and have people
install and
it use
Docker containers from official package repositories, would this be a big issue? That's an interesting approach, you know
I was gonna argue with you. You're right
I mean, I guess you could take the rocket approach and that that and do it at the distro level
I wanted to back up and say is doesn't this actually justify the need of a hub because here's a different approach
What if okay?
So what these guys are doing this this guy at Banny Ops that wrote up the post is they're doing a analysis of the code
They're scanning it. They're checking out these images. They're running a vulnerability assessments against them and they're creating like Nessus reports
or whatever the hell they're using
Somebody at the Docker company could just as easily do this Docker could automate this process
Docker could automate the flagging of images that have known vulnerabilities. It could even rate them with scores
They can say this one is had high vulnerabilities
Docker could do all of this and they could add that as a value add to the Docker hub because I I think there is
A place in the market for the Docker hub, you know, we were talking about
This new that new office suite that's going to be server-side Google Docs competitor
And they're bringing it to Linux for the first time and they're off their option for distribution when they come to Linux for the first
Time is a Docker image because they can wrap their heads around a centralized repository that distributes these Docker containers down to end-users
For server just for server software for server software deployment
It does make some sense have one spot to go for all Linux distros
I don't know if I wanted to be Docker
I don't know if I wanted to be owned by a company
But I think it's interesting to give the market a chance to play this out because you could see a value add by doing that
Automated vulnerability assessment automated checking rating things, you know Docker could staff that up
Almost treat it like App Store reviews without all the dickishness of it and make sure people know
Right now though and almost feel like Docker is being negligent in this matter because these are on their platform because these are being offered
Up to their end-users. Is it not the responsibility to make sure I guess how far do you take it?
Because if you say it's Docker's responsibility to make sure that these things don't have vulnerabilities
Then isn't it also Docker's responsibility to make sure they don't have backdoors or rootkits, right?
I mean, I wouldn't say that what I would say is it's Docker's responsibility if they're going to have a central hub
To give an interface that will allow people to to communicate what they like and what they don't like so take Torrance
For example, right there is a there is a there is a great system in place and it's not mandated by you know
By any user group. It's not mandated by by any committee
But the reality is when you go on to the pirate bay
I can tell you the best torrent to download from the worst
Because that that's all being rated on voted on and if there was some that had that had some some snarky snark
That was connected to that torrent
I would know about that because it would be in the comments or if there's some sort of yeah
So is that really that hard to implement? That's kind of what you're talking about, right?
Yeah, I guess that actually works and even like at the AUR level like I know yeah
Yeah, yeah, I'm going right comments and usually know what's up. Mm-hmm. That's a good point
And I guess that would sort of be a good middle ground for now
And then the other thing is from their perspective all they have to do is provide the infrastructure everything else
It will be provided by the users
Yeah, yeah right now
It's a bit of a it's a bit of a clown show and they need to get it cleaned up
Because it's all happening really fast around them and people aren't gonna take it seriously if it has these kinds of problems
I think and I think you know, there's gonna be competitors out there. They're coming up
I mean canonicals launching their own format. You got obviously the rocket stuff coming out of the core OS project
You got the free BSD guys have had jails and had this fixed up figured out for a really really long time already
Plus they can back it up with a great file system that also provides a lot of advantages in conjunction with jails
Right, and we should just get all that done in just a couple months here. Yeah
Come on I mean like so
July is that about when it came out like officially officially they were yeah when they said
It was when the latest Red Hat Enterprise 7 shipped. Okay, that would have been yeah
So June July somewhere around that was that was and I'm using air quotes here 1-0
Yeah, but 1-0 shipped it shouldn't have been a 1-0, but I think I think they had that new partnership with Red Hat
Yeah, you know Red Hat didn't want to ship a non 1-0 thing in Red Hat Enterprise
And so I think they called it 1.0. Yeah, even though they didn't even have like signing and things like that
Yeah, but yeah, it is new. The thing is the reason but here's what?
Here's where and then we can get off this cuz probably people don't care too much
But I think here's where we would give them a little too much slack
It's new. Mm-hmm, but the technology they're using they didn't invent right?
Yes, they're using kernel features like right the container ization has been around
Oh, yeah
What they invented is the layer that sits on top that does the github like checkout check in the container formats
They came like they the specs they came up with all of that stuff and that's super value-added
That's obviously made a huge difference and cannot be downplayed. But at the same time that's the layer they're working at
I mean obviously they're working with those other layers too because you know
They have coded that layer there there they have interest there, right?
But what I'm trying to say is like this is the area they should be focusing on
This is where their energy should be going. So like there is only so much so much room
I'm willing to give them it's not like they're creating the entire container ization from whole cloth and they have that entire burden
Yeah, so yeah. Yeah. Yeah, you're right. I agree
That's it
Not the trip set or anything. Oh
Also, also why why can I say sorry? Why are people complaining about the pack that?
Containers having vulnerabilities when they can just update them
Vulnerable software in the containers themselves. Yeah, here's the issue and I was just reading I was just reading a blog post about this
Had this, you know, and this is part of what I think gets me a little pissy about this issue. I don't
know if you ever he ever worked with a developer who just really hates the sysadmin like the sysadmin is the guy that slows me down
He's always worried about security permissions
He's always got a firewall rule that I have to go talk to him about guy wants to do updates and it breaks my program
Like they just hate the sysadmin right? Yeah in fairness. A lot of sysadmins hate the developers. Yeah. Yep. Absolutely. All right, and
so one of these guys one of these developers is
Brogging about why docker is so great and it's not because it you know makes it takes care of you know, all the different distros
And it makes a single point of just deploying software through the hub
No, no
The reason why this guy likes docker is because now the sysadmin doesn't screw his stuff up with silly updates and permissions
He just gives the silly sysadmin. He didn't say silly
He just gives the silly sysadmin one file and it's a two-step process to get his creation right up on the server
And then he doesn't in his words mess it up anymore
And the whole idea is and the reason why I'm bringing this up is right
There is a mentality where people are creating docker images and they are creating these things thinking
This is a static world that will never change the world around it is gonna be updated
It's gonna be chaotic libraries gonna change kernels are gonna change whatever but this container everything in this world this Ubuntu
Yeah, 1404 little world in here or 1204 little world here will never ever change. You don't want to know something Chris
I like that. I know but that's an administrator and I like that. That's the problem though
That's because then the things were those processes maybe say like what what do you what for example?
Let's say you put the Zimbra inside a container wouldn't that be you know?
Just get Zimbra in a container and keep it nice and contained on it on a CentOS box
The problem is what if in that container?
Zimbra is using a version of IMAP that gets to be a year old or so that has another heart bleed like vulnerability in right?
Well, then you have to go update that container to get rid of that vulnerability
But now you are doing something that was against the original design of the people that distributed that container
So your only option at that point is to essentially and I might have this wrong, but I believe the container
Well, you you yeah, you essentially not this is the right wrong word
But you essentially like fork the container you copy it and now begin running your own version of you maintain separately
Right than the one that comes from Docker Hub, right?
So there are a couple things one is I would rather have an insecure program than no program
So if my choices are to run something insecure
Are you sure like are you sure like in the in like, you know, like something that could be really bad like that
You know where people can read the memory on your server and stuff like that
I'm I go back to to to a client I had and this was not all that terribly long goes in fact one of the first
things I it's I we had set up them up with the system 76 computer and the
the version of Ubuntu that had shipped with the system 76 was
Newer than the last LTS, but the Intel drivers to get the Wi-Fi to work had to have that that newer kernel
So we ran into this weird issue where the software
Software manufacturer would not give us they didn't have a version that would run on the newest version of Ubuntu
Right, but he didn't have Wi-Fi
So the solution was as crappy as it sounds he bought a brand new laptop and he had to have a USB dongle for a couple
months until and
So if my and I think if that was if that was a wider scale if we're going out to a server something like that
If my choices are there's some sort of security vulnerability and granted heart bleed is a bit of an extreme example
That would probably require us to sit down and talk about if using that software then is really still the best course of action
But if if it's anything slightly smaller than that
I would rather have the software work at all rather than even if it has some security flaws then not have access to that solution
Yeah, I mean I can I can follow that line of thought for especially a class of software and use cases like
word processor or
Anything that doesn't have anything that doesn't here's where I draw the line
Mm-hmm anything that could potentially reveal my user information or other users of the systems information
So like say Jupiter broadcasting had its own mail server, right?
And we were running it very likely if we did that we would be running it on a container on a digital ocean droplet
Right, and let's say let's go back to this timber thing. Let's say we got a compromise. Mm-hmm now
Maybe I wouldn't care so much about my information leaking out because I'd probably have a unique password for that server
And so they just compromise just that account getting my email would suck
But I do have the responsibility of everybody else that log. Yeah, right
And so if you know Rekha is logging in and Alan's logging in and you're logging into it and Angela's like everybody's logging into this
thing
If that thing starts to have a year old see the problem is too is the longer these vulnerabilities hang around things like shell
Shock and heart bleed. Mm-hmm. Those are so well known and there's such low-hanging fruit and some of them like heart bleed can be diagnosed
Remotely that they just get they just get written into into IP scanner scripts
yeah, and then you know, it becomes really almost no effort for them to start banging on your box and reading, you know, what I
It's like because it's so easy for them to do it and because other people are impacted by it
I feel like I have the responsibility to keep it even up to date even if I don't care about my own personal data
Right, so I'm not saying that security isn't important, right?
I'm not saying that we shouldn't have a methodology for updating
I'm saying that the priority level should be get the software to work then let's make it secure and
So that means that the security then falls upon whoever is releasing that docker container
That shouldn't necessarily rely on you
So when something like heart bleed comes out and all this data is leaked
We I think we should just treat docker containers just like we would treat a piece of software
Thunderbird had a had a security for saying the vendor should update it
Right. Well, I'm just saying you wouldn't you wouldn't expect to say well Thunderbird has a security vulnerability
I better log in there and and open the
So shouldn't the way it work is like so say let's go back to Zimbra again because it's like we can both wrap our brain around
This shouldn't December guys. Let's say they're distributing their software by a docker containers
shouldn't they
Test it in a docker container on their network
Certify that the latest security updates work and then publish that version of the docker hub and then have that
Distributed down to all of the people that are subscribed to that docker container
yeah, shouldn't it basically be like a software vendor update because if they can test in a container and
Verify it works and push those changes up to the docker hub and then everybody else is in a container
It's not like there's random library vulnerabilities are randomness or anything like that
They can just overwrite the same files like it seems like the solution here is for the vendor to patch
But then the vendors in order to do that are gonna expect some money like you want us to update your our images
Then you're gonna have to pay us for a support contract
Yeah, there's no there's no way vendors are gonna update an Ubuntu 1404 container for five years for free, right? Yeah
Yeah, that's probably they would I don't know
Maybe they would just maybe they would because that's how people are getting their software. I
Don't know but it's an interesting
It's an interesting world
We're moving into a software over the over the next couple of years on Linux is gonna change a lot
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that invites you to insert your own Monday morning joke
My name is Chris. My name is Noah. Hey Noah. Hey Monday here. Happy Monday. Happy Monday
So we're doing this show on a Monday cuz Noah's here. He's flying out this evening. What are you flying out? Well?
Hopefully tomorrow tomorrow morning or whatever. Yeah, we wanted to record today
Yeah, we say tomorrow morning, but really that involves leaving here at like 1 30 in the morning Wow
Yikes yikes. Well, so that's we're gonna get you now before we have to worry about that coming up on today's show
We're gonna follow up on our fedora 22 review in just a little bit
We're gonna spend some time talking about Gnome 3.18 the upcoming version of Gnome and also Gnome 3.16 victory lap
As of fedora 22. Yeah, I know. I know. I know I'm being a little insinuating
Also, we're gonna talk about the new Google Cardboard how it could work for Linux Dell's perhaps huge embrace of Ubuntu
This is a big deal. We're gonna talk about that
And then also we have a little surprise coming up in the feedback section of the show Noah. It's a packed show
So like somehow even though you and I were just on air less than 24 hours ago doing the Linux action show
Yeah, we just talked about Linux. How is there more Linux to talk about?
We literally just literally been less than 24 hours since we did last yeah, does that blow your mind a little bit
Yeah, it's been like less than 12 hours since last actually got published
Wow talk about a content factory. Hey, so let's get into the catch-up
There's some interesting stories that have actually managed to develop since we put together Linux actions
Even though it's only been a couple of hours
So I want to bring in the mumble room time appropriate greetings virtual lug I'm like is anybody there
Wow, okay, we lost them all so Google I oh was last Thursday
And it was the biggest IO in the history of the world
Which isn't that actually hard of a record to set when you think about there's only been so many IOs and Google just keeps
Getting bigger, but it was a monster
It was like a four-hour keynote, and I am excited pretty much about one thing
I mean, I'm excited about a few things that came out, but hear more my hear more of my thoughts in code radio
but for us Linux users I
Think there's some potentially I think we need to get on board with this you familiar with Google Cardboard
I am yeah, they're VR cardboard that they gave out at last year's
Google IO you know it's funny
I've heard this described a couple of ways some people say this is Google flailing saying they can't come up with any ideas in the
VR market, and so they're just dropping this on the public and saying here figure it out
I am not such a pessimist so they updated their two point
They just a Google Cardboard VR 2.0
And it just supports up to six inch screens now including internet phones if you're a masochist and it is
Completely published as an open spec. There's already websites
That's they're selling an entire kit for like $20 or whatever
Uh-huh and you basically get a fully usable VR environment
When it comes with little glasses that it comes preset in there that are in there
And you just put your smartphone in there, and you have legitimate virtual reality for $30
And there's already apps out there to do this
There's already apps in the Play Store to take advantage of it
And there's nothing that says you couldn't hook it up to a Linux box and create
this could be the avenue for the community to create their the beginnings of their own open source response to the
Oculus Rift yeah, yeah, you know what's neat about that is if that so imagine this
Oculus wants to take this the the quote-unquote high road with yeah with with
Microsoft
Microsoft they make do they make small things well they make that the that challenger to Linux I
Microsoft it's that sounds like a viagra competitor to me
Windows they make Windows you've ever used it yeah, man
It cost a lot of money because it crashes a lot and stuff, but and they break you know like yeah
Yeah, yeah, but they have but it has tiles so
okay, but they
So they're gonna take that road
Imagine this imagine imagine when imagine when this takes off like the Raspberry Pi does and everyone that wants to play
Everyone wants to play with it goes there well
I could get that thing, but I'm locked into the games that they tell me I can play with the operating system
They tell me I can play with and and the SDK that they're gonna
Tell me when it's gonna release and then there's this and it's like I think do it's almost a bigger competitor to Samsung Samsung
Gear VR is essentially this you put a smartphone in the gear VR, but Corky
Do you oh, I'm sorry it was in a go-go in a go-go
Do you think that maybe we're just getting too excited that Google cardboard is kind of a crappy product?
Yeah, mainly the cardboard bit because I I got the last version for Christmas, and it was and by
The end of February it kind of had fallen apart
so
Would it would it make you feel better that there is several different companies that right now that are working on
3d printed versions of Google Cardboard
So it's a much sturdier case you can print it out at home or buy it it comes with the lenses you can get it
In different colors, there's a lot of people that are working on different kinds of moldings for the Google Cardboard, too
It doesn't actually have to be cardboard. It's just the nice thing about cardboard is you can make it yourself, and it's
It's sturdy and it's so great thing about the correlation
Yeah, but not all phones work with it either because some
For what there's one feature that requires a compass because it's like this trigger on the side yeah
And not all phones have a compass
Yeah, and there is definitely limitations there. I know I mean I kind of look at that as like saying well
Not all HDMI monitors. No, no, it's not are gonna work with are gonna work with the raspberry pi
I also look at this as sort of a Model T
That is available to the community to tinker with not like not like a full-on competitor like honestly
We need to start somewhere. It's kind of my philosophy about it is and when you get that price point down
so and this is the thing that was great about the pie, and that's this is what's great about this thing is I
Cannot afford to spend five or six or seven hundred dollars on a computer for a project that may or may not work
But I can spend the I can spend the the money
$30-$40 on a piece of cardboard to to put my phone in to play with it, and if it doesn't work. That's fine
Yeah, yeah, I do agree with you there, and I I look forward to seeing where it goes
Hopefully there's something that comes out of it. It doesn't just fizzle away
I don't think it will but I'd like to see the open-source community embrace it there could be I mean just think about the potential
Windowing environments all kinds of things could be really cool
but
We'll have to wait and see hey Noah. I know that you and I've talked about Dell before mm-hmm
Matt wasn't a huge fan Adele. Yeah
I'm not a huge fan. I I I talk about Dell kind of like I talk about
Cars and things like that like I feel like Dell's like a pretty good choice
It's not always gonna blow me away
But it's gonna get me a pretty good value for the price and come with a warranty so full disclosure
As you know I'm an I we own an IT company, and we are partnered with Dell so
My I'm probably a little biased
Because I've been we've had a very very good experience with Dell and part of that experience
Probably comes from the fact that Dell really values their commercial market
Which is kind of funny because when Dell started they started really valuing that consumer market and somehow
They kind of made that switch, but from a business perspective the nice thing about Dell is as Dell partner
When I want parts they just they ship them to me and to supply them to a client
So my my experience with Dell has always been
pretty solid on the business side a little a
Little adversarial like when doing large server purchases and things like that and then screwing me a few times on things
I didn't really need are selling me like an entire series of bad tape drives an entire series of bad perk controllers
Which was the entire reason for the partner program because now you don't deal with those people you deal with me
Yeah, and I can come on to your site
And I can look and then and I just go into a portal and order that stuff
Yeah, and but you know and but my preferred my preference there though is I mean not to deal with people like you yeah
I'm sure like I actually prefer like the IX approach
Yeah, and that's sort of when I realized where I have the issues with Dell
But if you remove that layer of Dell I like I like things like their service tag set up
I like that you know they have a really good database
And you just really look up all the drivers for your machine and and like they have to be fair like when we have those
Tape drives that just failed one after another they're always very solid about replacing them right
And so I what I've always met ran down with issues with Dell has been in the consumer space and sort of how they like
They kind of keep putting their foot in with Linux, and then they dump it and they're like oh just kidding in the US
Yes in the US because in other parts of the world. That's a very different story
Right and that's what's been very frustrating for me is to see them be committed in other parts of the world and be like why
Aren't you committing here? Just stick to it like you do in other places. Just stick to it. Yeah, and so I was really happy
That when they first launched the spots
Sorry, China China China for China for example, and yeah, and India yeah
I mean so they have they have they have widely push in fact if you go to like the kiosks in the mall here
We see kiosks in the mall that have Dell computers if you go over to China or India
You go into those into those malls
You're gonna see a lot of Ubuntu kiosks
And they're gonna push the computers that that run Ubuntu and the reason for that is is because the market is so much
I think the market is better there
They believe the market is better there to push those open source solutions that they can do that in the US
Yeah, I guess and I guess it's probably partially driven by cost and partially you know other other factors political. Maybe I don't know
but
That has always kind of left a bad taste in my mouth when it comes to Dell's approach the Sputnik program first gave me some
Hope and then the spike and then they then they launched the XPS 13 spotting version which is a pretty solid machine
So I when I saw this article this kind of grabbed my attention like this seems to be
Another pretty big step in the right direction for Dell's commitment to Ubuntu
Check this out Noah. You know of course Dell and canonical have been longtime partners, and they just updated
What was that $200 Ubuntu Dell laptop? Yeah? I just I was just pulling that up
It is the it is the it's it's a 250. It's a 250 $49 laptop
And in fact I have a person in my mind of who might be the first recipient
It's like a week out right right right so what's gonna end up happening is I think I'm gonna start her with a
With with another computer that I have set up, but if it takes off, and she's like you know
I really like this thing just be nice to have it on some newer hardware. It's the inspiron 15 3000
Yes, it's available for $249 and comes pre-installed with Ubuntu and
Specs on it and all there. Yeah, I have it actually right in front of me. It is a
So it's for four gigabytes of RAM. It's an Intel Celeron, which is basically what you expect
Well, so what this is I know I know what this is Chris
That's right, but it's a Chromebook that I can just that comes with Linux
And I think that'll do all right 500 gig
It's a spinning it's a spinning rust drive of course integrated graphics
And then 1366 by 768 by 4 for 250 you could go you go of new egg spend another 80 bucks and put a decent SSD
In there right and the thing is for the people that are checking their email for the people that are browsing Facebook
Editing editing some basic work documents not doing anything too heavy. This is a great computer form yeah
I think that's I think it's a real sell for down. Yeah, that's yeah
That's it so they're playing at the XPS level which is around a grand another playing down at the $250 level
I think the $250 level is I'm surprised somebody else like HP or somebody else doesn't come out and say let's take our Chromebook hard
We're just put Ubuntu on exactly why not what's it up?
What's gonna? Is it off there because they I think that those companies think that there is a bigger investment to be made on
Google's Chrome OS yeah, and I honestly I honestly suspected to that
Intel and Google have been subsidizing the hardware, and I believe Intel is pulling back on that now to a degree yeah, so anyways
Dell tweeted out on the 27th of May
Del's a delcarespro account at delcarespro mm-hmm tweeted out time for a new OS
Time for a new OS why not try hashtag Ubuntu check out our Ubuntu installation guide this is coming from Dell's official
Yeah, verified Twitter account insane time for a new OS check out Ubuntu from Dell's freaking Twitter account. That's pretty cool
I'm gonna check how many followers that maybe they don't have any followers, so it doesn't matter
Well, they have say of almost they have 10,000 followers
So that's not bad. You know there's the Dell's global technical support for business customers
Follow us to get valuable information and support your company's IT infrastructure
And they're recommending people try out Ubuntu, and they've included a link to a Dell support article
Which is how to install Ubuntu Linux on your Dell PC?
Yeah, this is legit look at this article. This is legit. Yeah
Yeah, and you know the thing is there are other things that Dell can push
And you are the chat room is figuring it out that Dell can sell this computer and say listen
You don't need an upgrade for an antivirus it
It's not necessary, so yeah, that's not necessarily a perk for Dell though
Those are those are upsells that don't make money. That's money
That's that's true, but the but Dell also makes money off of selling their computers
And if they can get away with saying this is a more competitive product
Then the then other offerings from other manufacturers that puts a leg up everyone's buying this
$259 computer instead of the instead of the instead of the $300 HP that is at best buy well
If they can deploy Ubuntu, I don't know what their arrangement is with canonical
But I gotta imagine they're probably not paying for every seat of Ubuntu mm-hmm
So no, and I don't really know the details of Dell very well
I don't know maybe you follow them, but are they now a private company? Yeah?
Well, so this may be the result of all this that this is that's a complicated question to the best of my understanding
They are owned by a private company, which is owned by
Actually, I believe it's Microsoft
The company that the company that took that the company that gave them the money to buy Dell back is backed by Microsoft investors
I got an idea so when in doubt you know you know what we do when in jail
We ask we just ask okay, Google
Who owns Dell?
Let's see what according to the Dallas Morning News
Dell Inc. which had grown to one of the biggest computer makers in the world during 25 years as a public company is now privately held
Michael Dell the 48 year old company founder and CEO owns about three-quarters of the company and his investment ally Silver Lake Partners
That's right. Okay, okay, so if you look Silver Lake is some partners. Yeah is somehow in bed with Mike. Yeah
Yeah, I do remember that now. I wonder if okay Google
Who is Silver Lake Partners? According to Wikipedia, Silver Lake is an American private equity firm focused on leverage, buyout, and growth capital investments in technology, technology-enabled and related industries.
Yeah, founded in 1999 it says so that's interesting. That's really yeah
So and I actually said it my Dell rep is very very much aware of my of my strong Linux preference, right?
And so he knows better that he knows better than to ever recommend a product or tell me about a product that I can't put Linux
Yeah, so when this came through I actually called him and I said hey, you know
How is this gonna affect things?
Because right now every Dell I've ever bought I've been able to throw Linux on and it works right out of the box
Is that gonna change with me? And he said no, it's not because you're worried about the Microsoft connection
Yeah, and this seems to be an indication. Maybe you shouldn't be worried. Yeah
Well in his and here's the thing I know you can't actually trust to be quite honest
I don't actually trust everything he says because he's yeah, he's gonna he's gonna sell me the company
So he knows what I want to hear
Yeah, because I made it very clear to him in the past
So I know what he's gonna say even before I asked but I wanted to get it on record here
We are and this is why I brought this whole topic up is because here we are on the preface of like what's Dell doing?
Are they doing some good stuff here? I mean they're shipping more machines than ever with Ubuntu
They're tweeting out to their business customers switch to Ubuntu
They're creating guides on their support site how to switch your Dell machine over to Ubuntu, but then they're owned
by
They are they are owned by Michael Dell Michael Dell got his money from a finance company
Which yeah, but so there are so many steps of removal from Microsoft that the influence may be maybe not there at the end
I'm excited to see where this is going. I'm getting excited. Yeah, are you getting excited about well?
I'm getting excited because I've been excited for a little while because as a Dell partner, that's that's what we sell
That's what we give to customers
So I need to be able to go into those clients and say well you bought your computer with Windows
I want to put Linux on it, and I've never had a problem doing that
And I don't ever want to have a problem doing that right
but the thing that is exciting about this two hundred forty nine dollar laptop is I
Am the kind of person that if I see somebody that is not using Linux
I would like to get them to use Linux and to do that oftentimes that means they're just buy them a machine
What that means I was trying to think of a more graceful way to say it
But the reality is is a lot of times if I come to your house, and you have everything set up
You're not just gonna. Let me erase your computer. Yeah, put something else on it, but you will yeah
Well if I'm like here play with this new toy
Yeah, you'd give it a shot especially if it's nicer, and then once you get it hooked
And I just dealt with this I just dealt with this before I came out here
There was a guy that I had we he actually bought a Lenovo yoga based off of
My recommendation based off what Angela was doing yeah?
And the way I got him to switch was I didn't give him a laptop
But I gave him a hard drive with Linux on it and put it in his existing laptop
And he just didn't want to go back yeah, and then he bought hardware, and yep windows is gone
Yeah, but so this two hundred forty nine dollar laptop is because there's a limit to how much I can do that right yeah
I have a finite budget, but two hundred forty nine dollar laptop brand new
That's it with a warranty. I mean you might go into my cost a little more
And maybe they'll let you customize and put an SSD in there
Rotten corpse you have information about the Silver Lake connection there
Yeah, the reason why there was a connection to Microsoft is because they're like owned inside of a consortium. They owned part of
70% of Skype oh
Okay, oh interesting so when they sold the Skype and they become part of
They like it wasn't completely like there's actually some kind of stuff with like the CEOs of Silver Lake or some kind of connected
As well, but it was it all started with Skype in 2000 I see thank you for the information and Corky
You think maybe we're getting too excited. Maybe there's a much more practical reason for this
I think I haven't checked recently, but Dell has traditionally had a
Banner saying Dell recommends Windows 8 for quite a while. Yeah, that must have been an
Advertising deal and if that's come to an end, and they know no longer a contractually obliged to
Recommend Windows right they might be taking advantage with this could you imagine?
Yeah, because you're right they probably had a they have they might even had a they might had a marketing deal
That was so lucrative and so important to Dell that it might have been something like you need to position your company as
Supporting Windows like your entire company needs to position and then Dell's wiggling these Ubuntu machines out
And then if that deal expires they're no longer. I mean who knows yeah
Maybe the reality is the band in a go-go is checking their sites as the banners are gone
I don't I don't take too much stock in that because the reality is Dell
Doesn't exist to advocate for Linux or open source Dell is has one goal, and I don't make money
Oh for sure well, but so what I'm where I'm going with that is
This idea that if Dell wants if Dell wants to sell
Computers they're gonna sell with whatever with whatever they think the market wants and so if Microsoft says
They want to recommend Windows 8 so be it but if the people that are looking to buy Ubuntu
I don't think that's gonna cut into their sales whether that banners there or not because the people that want to buy a bunch of
Laptop will just know I think what I'm saying and maybe Corky's implying too is that?
That marketing contract we're assuming mm-hmm
would
Prevent them from outwardly positioning themselves as supporting Ubuntu like tweeting it and creating guides and things like that right
I don't I don't but there's
Yeah, huh, I mean Microsoft's in Microsoft's here's what what here's here's the difference between a million dollar contract and a ten million dollar contract
Position your entire company. Here's a ten million dollar contract
So where is the money coming from to position themselves to support Ubuntu selling more machines as that contract expires?
They're no longer getting that money. They just want to sell more machines
Why not market your Ubuntu machines something haven't heavily marketed before also if I was them I'd be hedging my bets
So that so that's my that's my question. Why is it that you think that that?
That they're going to sell more machines by saying we support it, but I like Corky's there Corky
You have a good theory, and I'm totally on board with it. Yeah. Well. I'm just trying to understand. I just Corky Corky
What's yours? Why why would Dell be doing this right now? You think it's a negotiation tactic?
Well, I well, I hope it's a positive thing, but then this is Dell so maybe they're just trying to force Microsoft
to up their bid
with renewing this advertising bid I
The reason why I give that stock right is because I think some of the reasons why they've flirted with the Ubuntu market in
The past of them pulled out is they were negotiating with Microsoft
Yeah, that could be I guess what I'm getting at is I don't see I guess what I'm saying is
I don't think it's going to affect their their their Ubuntu market
To a certain extent anyway if they if they remove all those banners and say we support Ubuntu
Or they don't do that because I think the people that are buying an Ubuntu laptop are buying it for two reasons either one
They know the advantages or they want a cheap computer right well
So then then the banner being gone and that might that that that deal expiring probably won't change their dynamic much unless now
They're promoting it more outwardly like through Twitter and on the support calls and things like that
They weren't doing before we can hope we can hope we can know well
I think what we should do is a little market research yeah
Next time you call Dell you ought to ask him about Ubuntu and see what they say sure well my rep like you said
But he know yeah, yeah, yeah your reps gonna. I mean he's a little different cuz he'll look up and before he even gets on
The phone with me, and he'll say well
This is the latest machine we have that runs Linux and you're you'd be happy to know that we had a client that bought a couple
Hundred of these particular latitude series, and they all worked with Linux flawlessly and all right boys
You know all of a sudden
I'm just arguing like notifications like crazy on my phone today like now Spotify's noting notify me about tracks added to the radio stations
I've listened because you're popular. I guess I want I guess what I need to do
I need to Zen out
I need to go to my I need to go to my comfort zone my my sweet spot my place of
Absolute education and focus and learning that's right my friends
I call it the man cave where I bring up Linux Academy comm and I begin to learn and you can too by going to
Linux academy comm slash unplugged sponsor of the unplug program perfect sponsor, and no I you got to check out Linux Academy
Yeah, I have a membership. Whatever it is a subscription. Yeah, yeah, yeah
Go to Linux go to Linux Academy comm slash unplug to get the Linux unplugged 33% discount and then go check out their features
It's a really great service created by people that are truly passionate about Linux and open source, and they do a great job
They have self-paced courses you can get
All the content you can download it offline and like take it at your own pace, too
Which is great for commuters if you want to read the stuff and they have over 1500 video courses for you to take they have
Scenario based lab so you get a real hands-on like experience
Seven plus Linux distributions and the courseware will automatically adjust to those distros and the virtual machines adjust to those distros
I love that
Have you seen some of the new stuff they've rolled out recently so I went to the when when when rel
Release when rel released rel 7 usually I pay my you know
Whatever it is $800 thousand dollars to go out for two days and get a little refresher course
Yeah, and then they tell me all the things that are new and then I go take the cert
I did all that on Linux Academy this year because Linux Academy has they actually have a course or I
Already have there's there's two courses. There's a course of teach me about Red Hat Enterprise Linux, right?
And then there's a I understand Red Hat Enterprise Linux. I just I've been supporting six. I want to support seven
So tell me what are the what are the headlines?
Give me the bullet points of what if what has changed between six and seven that is so nice
It is because I don't have the time no I know right and you know the thing is training events
The problem is even if the training is really condensed because they do Red Hat does a fantastic job about getting it real down
Yeah, but it's still it's a day. I have to arrive a day ahead of time
Yeah, I have to rent a hotel right the rest of the day after I'm done with the class is blown
So you're probably you're already gonna run a car. I am running a car. I'm paying for meals out
Yeah, there's this huge expense that time suck
Yeah of going to these things and now I can do that on my laptop when I want in my skippies at night
I know and these guys are mostly and this is the best stuff
This is the best stuff around on how to do this and they've got the you can you know
You can get all of the study material. You can bring that with you. They're always keeping the stuff relevant
They just rolled out some new Red Hat stuff. It's really nice
And I think you know and you know what you got to do you got to think about it
They're gonna they're starting to roll out public profiles
So when you're really like your achievement courses and stuff like that on the public profile like you're embarrassed
You know what Pete the Red Hat stuff like if you did nothing with the Red Hat stuff
It's like at least to be all hardcore stuff on your thing
Well, it's one of those things where like I just do things I'm interested in and then I only a car
I only will look at the area you need. Yeah, that's nice though. It is they've got right? Yes
I know you wouldn't want to publicly show that they've got they've really got like so much great stuff
Like are you gonna try out their Python courses actually so funny you mentioned that
So the not being a developer, but I kind of want to look I'm like you
I kind of want to dabble in the idea of development because I like to understand these things
Exactly, and so the great thing about that was I will because my in my mind is so a DD
I'm like, oh I got done with the Red Hat stuff. Well, I'll go start Python
You know what?
I noticed Chris the guy that teaches Red Hat
Lives eats and breathes Red Hat like you can you can just tell by the way he talks
Yeah, the guy knows Red Hat and like he'll make off-handed comments. Like he'll say oh, you know that you know
This particular thing of course back in version 5 this way. Yeah
That's a guy that's been around
Then I go and take one of their programming courses and that guy knows like everything there is to know
You know about what he's like in their true testaments to their profession
And it's not just like they have hired a couple people and said alright
You're gonna sit in this room and we're gonna prepare content and then you present it. No, no
No, they took the time to go find industry experts
Yeah present this stuff and then they have they have you know
Like you've seen that where you can customize the course to do. I just want to learn about this specific
Yeah, that's what they have the new nuggets and there's a ton of them
In fact, you can you can go to Linux Academy comm slash nuggets and just do a deep dive
I love that as a new feat. That's another new feature
They've just rolled out a lot of cool stuff coming to Linux Academy all the time
That's why the membership makes so much sense
And I want you to get that 33% discount by going to Linux Academy comm
Slash unplugged and a big thanks Linux Academy for rockin support of the Linux unplug program. You guys are awesome
Alright, let's get into some emails. We haven't done emails on the unplugged show for a while and we got a bunch
So a Dario are writes in with the Ubuntu CC topics
It's not sure if you guys going to cover this or not
Oh really this one on unplugged or laughs, but I just found this comment on the same site
I really think they'll understand what's going on
Oh
All right, so he's talking about the kabuntu drama
Do we want to talk about this? It's up to you
Does anybody in the mumble room want to talk about the kabuntu community council drama? I?
Mean you can if you want to I mean we I'm not avoiding the topic. I just
Okay. Well, here's what I'll say on it. Um in our feedback thread for fedora 22
You can there's there's a comment thread open and Palasso has the epic comment of all comments Noah
It look at this thing here. He breaks down. What is the Ubuntu community council?
What decision is being made the redaction to the decision or I'm sorry the reaction to the decision
I have light shining on my screen and the aftermath plus closing thoughts and he breaks down some acronyms, too
This is such a solid contribution. I don't know what more we could contribute the comment here
Yeah
And we're this there's really been no development for those of you are not familiar what's going on
Jonathan riddle has been asked to stand down as leader of the Ubuntu community council, I guess
He actually explains it all in here and a lot of people in the project are upset by that
the decision remains at a standstill and
Plasso you're in the mumble room right now. Did you have any thoughts you wanted to add to the coverage of it?
Are you right up by the way? Yeah, you seem to be following it very closely
Did you have any any follow-up to our coverage or any comments you wanted to kind of get on the record? I don't have anything
Than what I wrote, I would like to mention that there were two things two issues
We're asking about on the community council
Right
that were on the dot-com website and it seems that the
The
community members don't know how they have been used and the other that was
mentioned was
the part of the
IP policy of canonical about the binaries
Yeah that you know, and it's one of those things
The the the write-up itself
Explains a lot of that stuff
And goes into it with a little more detail and we talked about it on last
But the reality is we just nobody really knows the whole story, right? Yeah, so it's it's it
We you kind of want to stay away from making present, you know making presumptions
The only information we have is been basically handed to us by yeah one one side of the party
Yeah, so you want to be a little careful on that?
But that's a tough. I don't know if there's a whole lot to add. Yeah, and and I think you know it so the straw poll
We I think it was somebody a corkier
Somebody started a straw poll in the Linux action show subreddit to see do you guys care about this topic?
You know because one of my concerns is do we even should we even be talking about this at all?
Obviously it's getting coverage. It seems to be a popular topic for some people
yeah, and I feel like it seems like we're not paying attention if I
Feel like it comes off that we're not paying attention
If the number one thing in Linux is being talked about all over the internet, and we're like we gloss right over it
Yeah, so right now of 58% of the votes say yes
They do care and 37% of the votes say they don't care
And not only 71 votes of art because it hasn't been a very popular thread, but there's a link in the chat room right now
We'll continue to follow to see if there's been any interesting developments outside of just additional drama like any maybe statements from the canonical guys
Oh and also blast so thank you for breaking down the structure of the Ubuntu Community Council that I was good insight today
I was very good to have because it does seem pretty connected to come out canonical basically
It's Mark Shuttleworth and seven people Mark Shuttleworth likes yeah
Well, but hold on because it's not actually from canonical right yeah, yeah, the name is not in there
So there are currently so here's here's how it goes just for those of you
I'm making fun
But the the Ubuntu Community Council consists of eight people one of them is Mark Shuttleworth and seven seven others are nominated by Mark
Shuttleworth and elected by the community for a term of two years currently
There are two canonical employees Michael Hall and Daniel Halbach and one canonical ex-employee Laura
Kozinski the canonical owner himself Mark Shuttleworth and four others from the community one of the roles of the Ubuntu Community Council is to resolve
issues of violation of the CoC
community with code of conduct okay and community disputes with the participation involved members, so
It does kind of seem like a stack deck a bit, but I mean it was there were elections. Yeah, yeah
I guess I don't have a problem with them saying this is not an official canonical thing
And it's not the official word of canonical
I don't have a problem with that what I do have a problem is
When people want to try and remove it so far as to say canonical has nothing to do with this
I mean, it's not a canonical thing
It's totally separate that is come on first of all canonical controls the branding of Ubuntu second of all
The head of the community or the member of the board on the Community Council is the head of canonical
So there's definitely a connection there. There's more than a passing connection there. I agree yeah
All right, so David M. Wrightson with a question about open susa. He says hi
I'm just wondering why you don't mention open susa as an option
I can understand why you don't like Ubuntu and arch is cool, but it's not for production
I enjoy your shows. I plan on making contribution next penny. Oh, that's nice. Thanks David, so he's asking about open susa as an option and
Do you want to take well the reason the reason actually I put that in there was because so
He says that arch doesn't belong in production
And you know what if you would ask me before I had spent time in the studio
I would have agreed with him I would have said listen I would not put fedora
I would not put arch on on a production machine
I don't want something that I knew I want my I want to treat the production machine
Essentially like I treat my KitchenAid mixer on the face of it. It actually seems obvious
Yeah, I just want it to be in appliance once I get it working
I never want to touch it again unless the hardware fails right and then I will do something right in practice though in practice
The total opposite has proved to be true
Numerous numerous times so much so to the point that even though I really wanted to put a bunch of matte on here
I don't dare open my mouth because because I know
Basically, I know that three weeks after I leave some update is gonna come in here
And even if we try not to update it somehow that stupid updater
You know rolls back up, and then it's something somebody or we have to install something else you have to update exactly something happens
That's something that's updated
Yeah
And then something breaks and now because it's so far gone not just one thing breaks like three different things happen at the exact same
Time and you don't know if they're connected
Yeah, or if they're separate and all of a sudden you've got problems like every time you reboot your sound cards get remapped right?
And so and I've I have argued that perhaps in media production because of the underlying stuff
We rely on needs to be so current all the time that Linux by its very nature just as difficult in these kinds of roles
And so maybe being more current is more helpful. Yeah, so open Sousa offers
You know tumbleweed and also evergreen releases so open Sousa has potentially that sweet spot right where open Sousa could
Fill a role on a machine that needs to be uber current and it could fill a role on a machine that needs to that could
Stay fairly static like say my bonobo. Yeah, and so but you don't use open Sousa in enterprise
You don't use open Sousa in your personal stuff. Why is it not really ever been a contender for you?
So there's a couple of things
I I actually really like the idea of an RPM based distro that I could use in production because really I'm not gonna put
I'm not gonna put fedora or at least
That might be changing now, but got a year ago or so. I wouldn't have put fedora into production on on on a client's machine
However, we tried open Sousa in one client
I was gonna go out and we were gonna do that and I ended up bringing him a test machine
We set it up, but it had this weird thing where it will show the it when you click on
You plug a thumb drive in it will show up as if it's mounted
but it doesn't actually create the mount point and show the files from a from a from a
removable storage and they had some sort of script that that kicked off that did something when somebody plugged a thumb drive in and
It wasn't the script kept failing because this thing wasn't mounting and I worked with it a little bit and I couldn't get it
To work and I said eventually just screw it
We'll just go to a bunch of because the reality was everything else they were doing other than this one tiny little piece of software
Which we could which had both RPM and Deb
Was all being done in the browser, you know, so I just went with that's that's an interesting reason not to use it
Uh Mike's a little more nuanced. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, so I I actually thought I would be sitting here and
I
Thought I thought I thought by this point in time
Open Sousa would be the far-gone conclusion because the build service was so awesome. They have
a tumbleweed they have their evergreen releases
I'm still a fan of yast and yet I sit here and I think I
Don't know still a bit of an unfinished mess rotten corpse. What's your take on it?
I would say that
Open Sousa has like a ton of potential and they do a lot of things that make you are really interested in them
But then they kind of fall short and the actual
Production of this stuff like for example, the OBS is cool
But then they don't have any focus on it and it's very clunky and it requires specific
Files and configurations that you have to know in order to send something to the OBS and then they have like the Sousa studio
Which is cool, but not a very good environment to reuse and they have like there's
One click install that's actually like 12, right or whatever. I very clunky
Yeah, they have a lot of great ideas, but they never actually like they don't all come to fruition
I actually don't think any of them really fully come to fruition and it's just like it's really cool and then disappointing
Yeah, and I think a lot of the changes around zipper and the package manager for a few releases a while ago
Sort of I lost momentum on my open Sousa edge like I had I for a while
I ran Sousa Enterprise Linux in a in a on a quite a few servers
I thought I thought it made and it was so great because you know
You could have it was so easy to make to make a Samba file server with Sousa Linux
Using the asked it would connect to the domain and authenticate all of the users and set up all the permissions and you could set
up extended attributes on all the file systems because Sousa was super easy with riser FS and XFS out of the box back then and
It was just like I could drop a Sousa box in within 10 minutes
I'd have it connected and authenticating to a Windows domain controller and I'd have it all updated in Yast and it was
Beautiful. Yeah, and for a while I even used this program from the Zemarian folks to manage all of the it was called red carpet
And I could manage all of the patches on all of my Sousa boxes from one GTK console on one desktop
And it was so amazing and when they went through all these package manager changes
I just really lost momentum on all of that and and then and I just kind of I kind of fell into
back into apt-get and
Ubuntu for a long time and it just seems like such a more streamlined process to manage your packages then
And and there's so many layers on the open Sousa side. Mm-hmm. And then the other thing that's given me a
little bit of
Cold feet with Sousa is I'm not very comfortable with their parent company and I'm not very comfortable how they've been passed around in the
Last few years and I'm not super clear on what the parent company's priority is for Sousa Linux other than making a distro
That is a companion piece to mainframes type software and I so and I'm sure that's not their purpose and vision
I just I have I feel like they haven't articulated it yet
And so I'm not willing to invest a lot of my personal energy into that
Yeah
The one thing that I see that open Sousa really really digs down on is if I had a if somebody came to me
And they said I had a lot of experience
Administrating a Windows server and I want to switch the Linux server. What should I start with man?
Yeah, it is in it and it and it and and Sousa such a capable distro open
Sousa such a capable distro that I think it has a lot of but you know
Here's the other thing too. If you were gonna use open Sousa, would you not use KDE?
Because it's a really nice KDE implementation really nice. Yeah, and KDE is
Yeah, they have a good gnome one too. I mean they do overall they do good work
And one of the things I like is like Yast is like a Qt UI on KDE and GTK UI under gnome
Like they do a lot of good stuff
It's just it all doesn't really come together to make it super compelling but heavens
I'll give you a chance to give them a bit of cred here
Yes, trying to judge the desktop usage of open Sousa based on their open build service is not exactly
Doing it justice. I do use open Sousa at least in a couple virtual machines just to test and make sure that it is up to snuff
At least in my standards. It is up to my standards in terms of desktop usage
In every way the zipper package manager, even though it is a little bit different from RPM
But in terms of RPM distros, open Sousa is the only one that I kind of like
Yeah, but yeah, I don't know. It's just a monthly for a deb or pac-man kind of usage
But I don't think it has much to... you can't blame it based on its other services
Even though yes, it should work, but one thing, one installation of open Sousa
It should work, but one install package manager or at least one click install packages is useful for users
The package search is useful for users, adding extra repos, especially with GPG based repository authentication is useful
And you know, it's nice
That's not even the problem. The problem is the whole package
Like there's a lot of cool things and they make really good ideas with the package search
And basically everything is on the website you can install from. Really cool
But it's just funky when you actually go through the process
I think I'm done on this topic. No, no, hold on. Let's talk about more in the post-show
Because I don't want to spend too much more time in the show on this topic
Because honestly, here's where I kind of come down on open Sousa
That's why I don't want to spend a lot more time on it
Is despite as much as I wish this wasn't the case
And despite as much as a lot of people in the community who really love this distribution
Wish it wasn't the case and the people who work for the company wish it wasn't the case
I believe the reality is, and I'm sorry I have to say this
This is the final word for this episode on the topic and we can take other
I just need to move on from this. I'm getting orange on the topic. Red, really
But I unfortunately do not believe that open Sousa really makes much of an impact in the market
In the industry, they don't really move the needle when they make an initiative
Nobody really pays attention except for them
They're not super relevant, not like Ubuntu or Fedora or even Arch
Or honestly, definitely distributions like Debian and Slackware even
I don't know, there are just a lot of distributions out there
That I feel like when they say something, it makes a huge, huge wave
Like when Debian decided to switch to System D, holy shit, right?
When Sousa switched to System D, do you know when that was?
No. In fact, I wasn't even aware that they'd switched to System D, to be honest with you
Right, they did a while ago, right? That's my point
And I wish it wasn't that way, and that's why, to be honest with you
As somebody who's an enthusiast about this market
I like to use a distro that's a little bit more relevant
That has a little sway, not a lot, I don't want a lot of drama
But I do like to have a distro that has some solid relevancy in the areas I care about
I just don't feel like that's where open Sousa's at
And that's my final word on it
So, Harold writes in about Angela's Yoga 3
And he says, I'd like to move my wife to Linux as well
But how do we sync an iPhone or iPad to iTunes using Linux?
That's her greatest stumbling block. He also wants to know what spreadsheet program she uses
A lot to choose from
So, it's funny that he writes in and asks that, right?
Because, just like, I think, Friday
It was Friday, we were working on show notes
And you said, hey, while we're working on that, you know what would be awesome?
If you could get Angela's iPhone to sync up to...
She's like, I'm basically doing almost everything on the Yoga, except, you know what?
I take pictures with my iPhone, and when I plug it in, nothing happens
And I thought, oh, yeah, that's right
We never went back around to get that working
We talked about it on the show, and then I just...
I forget that there's still people pulling photos off their phones using USB
I just think when you take pictures, it syncs to something
And she talked about using Dropbox and OwnCloud
But none of them, she takes so many pictures, and they're fairly high resolution
She likes being able to plug it in, have them suck off the device
And then delete them off the camera roll of the device
But the fundamental problem is you have to get the Linux box to recognize the iPhone
And this has got to be a common problem in our audience
Right, so the answer's actually fairly straightforward
There's two or three packages you need to install
We'll have a link in the show notes to them
But they have, once you get those packages installed
What it allows you to do is mount the phone as either an MTP device
Or actually mount it as a drive
Now, we actually set it up so that it mounts as a drive
But it doesn't have right access to the phone
And the reason for that is...
We want to be careful
We want to be careful, and she's had problems in the past where
She does something on Linux thinking that she is just making copies of her photos
And in fact it's moving them
Here there's no possibility it can move them
The only thing it can do is copy them
Now, you can actually set it up so that inside of Shotwell
It looks when a given mount point is mounted
So when slash media slash Ange's iPhone mounts
It will automatically look inside of that directory
And then the DCIM folder to sync up all of the photos
That's not a hard set
No, and so the nice thing for her is she just plugs her phone in
And somehow all of her pictures will magically populate in Shotwell
And she actually likes the idea too that it's in the file manager
So if she just wanted a single photo to post online or something
Right
Or send it to me over Telegram
So that would be mounting it
And yeah, you're right
So she can log in there and just manually copy that photo out
But it actually really took, what?
It took five minutes
And four of those minutes were researching it
And 30 seconds were implementing it
You know, so the Librem is on the verge of shipping
July, I think, yeah
The XPS 13 is very solid
The Yoga is very solid
Dell's got this new $250 laptop
Yeah, Linux is big
Yeah, and that doesn't even count
Like, System76 has their best Bonobo Extreme yet
Like, that thing's a monster
They're shipping the Meerkat
There's a great ton of options desktop-wise for System76
The Galago is amazing
You have like, this is the best year for Linux laptops ever
Yeah
And a lot of these are shipping with very good Intel graphics
There are plenty good for average users
And for those of us who want to have dedicated graphics
Those options are available too
Yeah, but really, if you think about it
The Intel embedded graphics are really what have kind of driven this market so far forward
Because now you don't need to have dedicated
Before, like five years ago, when you bought your original Bonobo
I bet you, like, buying integrated graphics would have been a joke
It was not an option
Because you can't get anything done on it
Not even possible
You can't game
And I couldn't use OBS
And this thing has to drive, this thing has to mirror the display out to the capture machine
So how are you going to do that with integrated graphics?
How can I play any, how can I show any video games under Linux with integrated graphics back then
And then also mirror the display 1080p
Right, and now, and now look at that tiny little nook over there
Yeah, it's doing it
Does the same freaking thing
I know, I know, I know
So yeah, they have gotten, it's gotten light years better
And it's only going to improve
Yeah
In fact, one might even wonder
At least in the mobile sphere where you want a thin, portable, powerful laptop
Yeah
At some point, do we just stop putting, do we stop putting up our graphics on
For the purpose of getting that laptop down a little bit in size and compact
If integrated graphics get a little bit better
That's why I had a great hope for Thunderbolt
I wanted to be able to have an integrated graphics laptop
And then hook up an external GPU and have at it
Yeah
But, yeah, we'll see
Alienware's got something like that
You know, so integrated graphics have been changing the game
For portability on the Intel-based machines
The, you know, the amount of performance you can get it
It's the same thing as sort of in the server space like DigitalOcean has done
That's our next sponsor
Where they've taken something and they've been able to get it to a price that's just unbelievable
Five dollars a month for your own server at DigitalOcean
It's incredible
And when you use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, one word, you're going to get a ten dollar credit
What, what, what, what?
You don't know what DigitalOcean is
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you
To spin up your own cloud server
How about that Noah?
That's pretty cool
Did you know that?
I didn't know that
Tell me about DigitalOcean
It's not like I have like 30 droplets
It's not like I had to email DigitalOcean and ask them to expand my droplet offering so that I could get more droplets
Freaking, that didn't happen
Game freaking changer
That's what DigitalOcean is
I can't even imagine if I was doing what Noah does as a day job and DigitalOcean was around
It would change how my business was structured
I mean, actually
You would have made a lot more money
Well, yeah, absolutely
And in a way, like, now I think about some of the stuff we're doing server side for Jupiter Broadcasting
And how would I have done that before DigitalOcean
You either had rented rack space
Yeah
You would have either had to rent an actual dedicated server which would cost you like a couple hundred dollars a month
Or like go crazy and I could maybe set up a server here
Okay, alright, let's talk about that
But then I got bandwidth problems
Hold on
Comcast
Before you ever get to the bandwidth problems, you got to come up with 2500 macaroons
To get the rig
To get the server
And oftentimes, that's not even going to include
You're going to want to put some solid state drives in there
Well, and if this thing is
Yeah, and these things are
And these things like, so there's a lot of automated backend functionality
If this doesn't work, shows don't go out
So I'm going dual, I'm going redundant power
I'm going to go hardware drive array
Okay
Then I'm setting this box up myself
Now still, you're counting on a couple things
One, you still have the risk of a hardware failure
Even if it's redundant
Yeah
They're still, they're going to be
Or a Comcast outage
Okay, so we haven't gotten to bandwidth
First, the server itself can die
Second, you might have a bandwidth issue
And third, what about your expandability
In two years, in a year, it's dead
And you can't upgrade that thing
Or what if the network starts growing really crazy fast
Then what am I going to do?
Then I'm going to stop that money because I'm going to replace it anyway
What I'm telling you is
And that doesn't even settle the fact that I'm going to probably need to set up like a DMZ on the firewall
Get that all wired in
Get the firewall rules all set up
But even if all that worked perfectly and nothing ever went wrong
Which, let's face it, what's the chances of that happening?
Thanks
Even if nothing, wow
That's because you need us, Rekai and I to come in here and do some wiring for you
But if that happened, it would probably have a decent chance of staying up
Oh
Oh really?
Let's go with that every week
Let's go with that again
Even if all of the hardware functioned for a year or two
At the end of that two years, now you have to do all over again
And you have to set all that crap up again
It's ridiculous
And meanwhile, DigitalOcean's over here
They're going to get you going in less than 55 seconds when you spin up a Dropbox
Five bucks
For $5 a month
You get your 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte of transfer
But it's a terabyte of transfer at like tier one data centers with unbelievable connections
They have data centers in New York, they have ones in San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London, and Germany
It is really nice
And then the best part is, and I wouldn't get this if I rolled my own rig
They have an amazing interface to manage it all
They really have a super intuitive control panel
And you can get all kinds of additional functionality on your own using their API
And I'm thinking like create your machines, obviously destroy them, duplicate them
Make backups of them before you make a big system change with a really nice snapshot system
Full feature DNS management allows you to easily manage your domain
Snapshots are a great function
Now they're not just like backup
These are like full, this is a great way to deploy servers
Like you get a server set up just the way you want, you snapshot, you make it a template
You want to snapshot something and send it off to another customer
Hey, here let me set you up a WordPress machine
Think about this you guys
You could go over there and have a Droplet that you set up with like a perfect ghost installation
All set up for customers
And you could sell it
You could sell that, like make that a service
And re-host it
And DigitalOcean has referral programs and all kinds of things
A really great offering for the customers too
They've structured in a way to incentivize you as well
So go check out some of those options like their one-click installations that make the control panel super nice
And by the way, tons of job openings right now
They've asked me specifically to mention that they're looking for some of the best Linux admins out there
To keep them in the right place
I know
And they also want to get some content editors because they're doubling down once again
They're doing another like big push on their content for their community tutorials and whatnot
They're willing to pay people
And you know the real secret to DigitalOcean is a lot of these tutorials are not necessarily DigitalOcean specific
Like how to set up an SSH key
Look how well this is done
Look how clear this is
That is super nice
That is super clean
And none of this, none of this is specific to a DigitalOcean Droplet
Yeah, that's the super nice thing right
Is that they have those set up as just we want to help people
We're going to set this up and provide that information to you
They look at all of that as like a whole product
They really do
Because when they rolled out free BSD support, they rolled out a whole bunch of tutorials with it
They don't want you to just sit there and have a Droplet
They want you to really get some use out of it
That's really cool
And they have great products built around that API too
Like you've tried out the Swimmer app
Mist.io is really cool
Command.io, you can manage your DigitalOcean Droplets using the command line
You know what's interesting
You're talking about that control panel being easy to use and intuitive
The other part of it is for people like me who I do the same repetitive task over and over again
I'm not using a lot of their features of clicking this and changing that and modify
I'm going to do all that from the command line once I SSH in, right
For me, once I log in, it's like three clicks to get stuff rolling
And then I just, I have the IP address and I throw that in my DNS server
And now I can access that machine
And like you said, I didn't get a chance to show it on Sunday
But the way that you can set it up with SSH keys, they just have a button
So I can check nose lanyard, nose laptop
And then when I spin up a DigitalOcean Droplet
Boom, I can instantly have access to it
I don't have to wait for the email to come through
Do you remember when I had that problem here
And then my email went down so I couldn't get the email
That took me what, 30 seconds to set that up?
It's very nice
Yeah, it's quick, it's easy
You've never had a better experience
Because usually what you have to do is you have to SSH into the computer
And you have to enter this huge long password
Then you have to run all these stupid commands
And copying an SSH key is not as easy as you might think it is
Because you can't have any spaces, you can't modify it
It's just a pain
There I click a button
One button
And now I have my SSH key
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED
One word and I'll get you a $10 credit
Tried that $5 rig for two months for free
You'd be surprised what you can do with it
I have so many things I actually frequently forget all the things I'm using it for
It's amazing how much I've integrated into my life
And how hassle free that is
DigitalOcean.com is so cool to have your own server up there that rocks
And you could use it for so many things
Alright Mr. Noah, I want to talk a little bit about Gnome 3.18
Major updates are coming for Gnome 3.18
And of course we're going to see that land in a little while
But probably the ones we should talk about today is the changes coming to the files
You know the old Nautilus application
It's going to bring numerous under the hood and user visible changes
It also fixes bugs that have been reported by users for a while now
So fix for window focus issues that have occurred with the file manager
Handling the command line options in certain areas
They're going to also introduce a public API for files
To allow for plugins to be written
And a documentation for developers to create those extensions as well will be released
Interface has added some modifications
They've added padding on the window list and views
And things like that
I'm going to show you a picture of it
Oh, they took the picture down
Well good thing I put that in the show notes
We do have, I do have, here's another copy of it
And I'll zoom in
I don't know if you can see Noah, a little bit here
But they're adding some, like when you create a new folder
This pop down area here is new
They've cleaned up this area here and added some padding
And the search area has been changed a little bit
So files is getting quite a bit of attention in GNOME 3.18
No, I'm just, I'm looking and I'm thinking
I kind of, you know, I'm all about innovation
I think that's great
I'm glad that we're always trying to move forward
And I can always appreciate a company that attempts to be innovative
Even if I don't always agree with the innovations
But like, I don't know if I want to create my folder up in the menu
I think I want to, I think I want to create a folder
Like I want to right click and create a folder
Or if I have to go up here and create a new folder
You still build it right click
But yeah, have you checked out Nemo?
No
Nemo is a fork of the Noddle's file manager
Started by the Cinnamon Project, I believe
And it's pretty good
I don't know, Noah
No, I care
See, Greater says, wow, GNOME 3 will bring updated apps
It's incredible, who cares?
I feel like we can be such dicks in the open source community
Like, are we so callous that we have stopped caring
That a desktop that was down on the ropes
That people thought was a failed desktop initiative
Is now coming out with incredible updates that are genuinely impressive
And in some cases, more trend setting than any other desktop on the market
I mean, look at Yosemite
Yosemite and some of the UI changes they made there were direct rip offs of GNOME 3
You look at some of the changes in Windows 10
And the way they're managing virtual desktops and things like that
Very much a rip off of the way they do things in GNOME 3
I think GNOME 3 has been a trend setter
And I think GNOME 3.16 is the best full desktop environment for Linux
I say you stack, Plasma 5 is getting great
But it's still not there yet
It's still not there yet
As far as a full featured, complete modern desktop
I'm not talking about your Awesomes and your Exmonads
I'm talking about, you know, a real full red blooded desktop
Nothing is beating GNOME 3.16
And I think it's a little sad that as a community we don't give them enough recognition
The updates they have made are genuinely reflecting user feedback
They're genuine improvements
And as somebody who has used desktops since we have had graphical environments
Literally, I have been using desktop computing since GUIs were a thing for mass adoption
And I, in my personal opinion, have never used a better graphical environment in 30 years of using computers
Okay, so let me take the other side of it
If only for the purpose of discussion
Why is it that basic things that Unity has are still not implemented in GNOME?
So I'll give you an example
When I open the display manager in Unity
I can choose where I want my launcher bar to be
If I want it on the far right display, if I want it on the center display, left, in my house I have six
I can pick which one of those six displays I want it on
Why is it in GNOME, not only can I do that, I can't set the refresh rate
I can't set...
You can't do that in Unity either
Yeah, I guess that's true
Now remember, Unity's what, had eight releases now almost? Seven releases?
Yeah
So, okay, I'll give you that
So you're saying they're further on? Is that...
No, are you not able to set where that...
Like, I'm able to set where that bar goes
How?
In GNOME Tweak
Okay, well then maybe it's something I'm missing
I guess where I looked for it was inside of the displays I can't set...
Oh yeah, maybe the bar, how about the activities menu?
So what I want is if I have three monitors
I would prefer that the activities menu be on my far left monitor
The reason for that is because when I send my mouse up to the far...
I send it all the way to the end, then I want it to activate the activities menu
The last time I've done it, the way it sets up
The activities menu shows up on my center display
And then when I scroll through my virtual desktops it moves this other monitor
I feel like we're arguing slightly... I think I'm on another level
Okay, alright, that could be
No, what I'm saying is like, I guess don't mistake what I'm saying to say that it's flawless
Right
Because that's not possible
Of course
What I'm saying is...
But you said...
Because what you're talking about is like an esoteric use case, honestly
You're talking about a three to six monitor setup and you want the activities menu to be...
Two monitors, and I just want the activities menu on the other monitor
Well, that's how it works now
Whatever is your primary monitor is where the activities menu is
Okay
So if you have a dual monitor setup and you set activities to be...
Whatever your primary monitor is, that's where that menu is at
Okay
So yeah, you can't say if I have three or four or five or six monitors, I want it on monitor number four
Alright
But like, these are also changes that as the desktop matures, they're going to add these refinements back in
See, and this is the other thing is, the thing that we really crapped on them for was pulling a bunch of features out
But to be honest with you, they are the developers
They know what code has been rotten, they know what code needs to go, they know where they want to take things
And where they need to restart
And at some point you have to trust that they have some more insights than us users do at some level
So if you accept that, then perhaps they can do some reduction of functionality
If you also grant that basically since GNOME 3.10, it's been nothing but adding a bunch of great features that we all wanted back in there
And with GNOME 3.16, we're really down that path
And with GNOME 3.18 now, we're going even further down that path
And I would argue that I also think that we have been way too hard on them for their focus on the touchscreen
Because now that I have had a couple of users try out, I know, I know, I can't believe I'm saying it either
I seriously can't believe those words came out of my mouth
Roll your eyes all you want, because I still think it's also an excessive use
But the couple of users now, and this is super anecdotal evidence, but the couple of users I've had use the touchscreen laptops
They all think it's great
They think it's the, they think it's great
It is, to Angela, the best thing about her yoga is that she swipes that touchscreen up to unlock it
To her, that's one of the coolest features on that laptop
Because these people are primarily mobile users
So the fact that they can reach out and touch it from time to time is almost an intuitive way to interact with the computer
So I could see that if the touchscreen in GNOME functioned the way that the touchscreen functions on mobile
But the reality is I still feel when I touch the touchscreen on GNOME
I still feel like I have taken a touchscreen and plugged it into a desktop
I don't feel like I actually have a touch optimized desktop
Where she's using it is like she touches the activities corner or on the dock launcher or to unlock the screen
That's about all she uses it for
I can see unlocking the screen, that feels normal enough
But even the activities menu is just small enough that I have to like kind of wiggle my finger in the corner to get that to launch
I don't know, it just doesn't feel
My perfect desktop would be exactly what GNOME is today, written in QT
Well okay, so let me take it from another angle then
If GNOME has done such a good job with the desktop, why do we have to apply so many extensions to make it usable?
Yeah, that's a fair argument, but can't you say the same thing about Firefox and Chrome?
Yes, I could, except I don't use any extensions in Firefox, I think it works perfectly right out of the box
You really don't use many extensions in GNOME though either
I don't, yeah I don't, I don't, but that's because I'm too lazy to install it
But it works for you without them
It does, it does, that's true, I'm not saying it's not usable without extensions
I'm just saying that, I guess I did just say that
My approach to the extensions is, I find GNOME irritating to use without them, but usable
With extensions, it's so in that sweet spot where I've got kind of my cool heads up information that I like to have
But it's not at the KDE level where I'm constantly tweaking it because the options are there
It's just that sweet spot
Until you update the next GNOME and then your extensions are going to break
But that's been getting better too, I grant you that as well
But my update from 3.14 to 3.16, I didn't have a single extension that didn't work
Because either the authors were right on top of it or I think maybe I had one extension that didn't work
But it's so minimal that it doesn't really matter
I don't think I could use GNOME without the extensions for a long term
But for a few days after an update, it's not a big deal
Now how do you think that that relates to a new user?
One of the nice things about Ubuntu and Unity is that big dock along the side makes it really, really obvious
They recognize Firefox, they recognize Chrome
So when they see those icons, it's pretty intuitive just to reach up and click them
Now granted, there are certain things that are horrible in Unity for a new user experience
For example, it hides all the menus by default
I think by default, GNOME is a little hard for app discovery
Although, remember when we sat Angela down?
The first thing she did was went up to the corner and looked for applications
Remember that?
And we even asked her
But she's also used GNOME, right?
No
Oh, really?
Well, I mean, she's used it here, but I have the dock
I mean, she's never used that menu before that I know of
And so I just thought it was, to her, it seemed kind of intuitive to go up in the corner and launch an application
But I agree, I think for normal users, I take that dash to dock extension
And I set it to auto expand like the Unity byte
And I think that just makes a lot of sense
No, it totally does
My question was, do you see GNOME as primarily a power user's desktop then?
Maybe not power, maybe that's a wrong term
Experienced users, not necessarily power users
I think it's perfect for experienced users right now
And I think if they could stabilize the extension stuff, I think it'd be a lot better for regular users
Or I think the stuff they just keep adding to it, you won't require extensions
So I'm pretty excited about it, to be honest with you
Because I think they're going in a direction that is great for users like you and I
That have been using Linux for a long time and are comfortable with GNOME tweak
And we're comfortable with installing some extensions
Ironically, those are some of the more hardcore things to do for a desktop that's supposed to be super simple
But if you're comfortable with that stuff, which is pretty much everybody in our audience
I think it's perfect for them
And then if you can get somebody like, if you get one extension on there
Basically like Angela's desktop, she could get by with just dash to dock
And I think she'd be fine
So I think for her it's fine
Yeah, I guess if you don't know what to look for
Or you don't know what you're missing
Or you don't know what is available in GNOME
If you don't know, you could have a Bitcoin ticker in your menu bar
Or a ping indicator
You don't care when they go away
Yeah, 14.2 milliseconds
Yeah, oh really? Really?
I'm at 11.3 milliseconds right now
Yeah, I'm on wireless
Oh, I get the wired advantage
Hello, Ethan
Wired advantage
You know, Mr. Noah, we could go on about this for a long time
We could
But I do want to just take a moment here
And I want to talk about our next sponsor, and that's Ting
And then, my friends, we have got to dig into this stuff going on in Fedora
Actually, there's some really interesting things
One in particular I forgot to mention in our Fedora review
Major oversight, because it's totally changed the way I use my laptop
So we've got to talk about that in our Fedora
I know, can you believe I forgot that in the review?
Well, it's the way you change your laptop
Right before you decided that you couldn't deal with Fedora anymore
And you have to go back to Arch right before the show
That doesn't have to do with this thing, though
Yeah, I'll talk more about that, too
But first, let me tell you about
That's right, our buddies over at Ting
Go to linux.ting.com, please, won't you?
Not only do you get to put Linux in your URL bar
But you get a $50 discount off your first Ting device
$50
Yeah
That's a lot of money
Dude, they have some devices that are nearly only $50
It's almost the whole device
And if you have a compatible device, you'll get a service credit
Now, why Ting? My friends, I will tell you why
Ting is mobile that truly makes sense
Thank goodness
Mobile that makes sense
It's no contract
You only pay for what you use
$6 is all you pay for the line
And then it's just your usage on top of that
It's really straightforward and obvious, too
There's no hidden secrets in there
There's just, like, your usage and your taxes and the line
And the devices are unlocked
You own the device outright
So that's super nice, isn't it?
You can go over there and bring your own device
If you have a GSM-compatible one
Or they have so, so many nice ones to choose from now
And one of the things I really enjoy about Ting
Is I can fully manage it just using my own web browser
I really never have to call Ting
Even though I could
Ironically, Ting is so well-structured for that
If you call them at 1-855-TING-FTW
Between 8am or 8pm, a real human being answers the phone
Wrap your head around this, you guys
It's mobile service with no contract
No early termination fees
You're only paying for your actual usage
And they have no hold customer service
Plus, they have a CDMA or GSM network you can choose from
That's super powerful and a lot of flexibility
For me, it's really nice just from a straight
This probably sounds a little excessive
But see, with Ting, it's very easy to have multiple lines
Because I'm just paying the $6
So Ting now has the Galaxy S6 Edge
I think that's the best phone of the year right now
Yeah, I think many would agree with you
So I also still have my Nexus 5
Which is also a very good phone
The thing I love about the Nexus 5
That the Edge, I don't know if it does
Is that the Nexus 5 can be moved between GSM and CDMA
So when we go to conferences and stuff
I can look up the coverage map
And see if it's stronger to have CDMA or GSM
But on top of that, if I get there
And I discover, oh man, the GSM network is blasted at this conference
I can try switching over to the CDMA network
I just got to swap the SIMs out and stuff
Switch over to the CDMA network
That is such a unique competitive advantage to Ting right now
That blows my mind
And you just pay for what you use
Yeah, and the great thing about it is
Because of their intuitive dashboard
You can shut that phone off
And it can sit in the studio here for six months
You never touch it
Then when you get there, you log in
In fact, you can do it on your Ting app
You can open it up
From my app, that's what I do
I just turn it on and off from my other phone
It's really the way it should be
So you said you thought that it was most of the cost of a phone
You can actually get the Kurosera Dura XT for $47
Now, at first glance, you might look at that and go
Why would I want that old looking flip phone?
Oh, I don't know
You know how I got started on Ting?
I was listening to the Linux action show
And the only time I had to do that was at like three in the morning
So my wife was next to me sleeping
And all of a sudden, I get out of bed
And I'm over at my computer
And she goes, what are you doing?
And I'm like, I got to check this out
I think you can get a phone for like $10 a month
And she's like, do we have to do that now?
And I'm like, yeah, we have to do that now
So I ordered something like this
It was made by Samsung, but it's very similar
It's just a little flip phone
And that was how I got started on Ting
And it was just my, what you were talking about, a Bat Phone
So I gave Sarah the number
And I'm like, here, you're the only one that has this number
Anything really important happens, call me on this
The battery will last a while
And I'll just have this with me
And then once I learned that I made sure that I could get coverage everywhere I wanted
Then I switched over to Hog
So this Kyocera Dura, right, this is a $47 feature phone
It's super durable
They joke here they can get hit by missiles
And it still works
What if they tested that?
Well, it meets the military 801G standard
Which means the phone can take dust, rain, radiation, salt, and humidity
I don't see anything about missiles
No, I don't either
It has Bluetooth
It also has a camera
Now, it's not going to be a very good camera
But you know what this made me think?
If it's rugged, which means it's probably going to handle heat and stuff okay
In my glove box
It has a camera
I could just have this thing plugged into my cigarette adapter for $6 a month
When you get a $50 credit, the phone is freaking free
And then it's just $6
And I could have an emergency phone in my vehicle at all times
That's really nice
You could have an emergency phone in your vehicle
Or I like to spend a lot of time at the lake in the summer
It would be great to throw that in the backpack
And just know that if I ever need a phone and it gets a little wet
I don't have to baby it and stuff like that
Or like I was just out at the lake recently
And I was very, very aware that I just got the S6
And it's out there at the lake
And I'm like if I freaking ruin this phone out on the lake
And it's just like even out in the sun and stuff it bakes
So that would be the perfect day to take my day phone
Now it sounds really crazy to take a different phone with you
Depending on where you're going
But it's so easy to move numbers around like with Google Voice and stuff
And it's so cheap to do it at $6 a month
And when you get the $50 service credit, this phone is free
And the same thing, they have the MiFi adapters
Actually, you know what I noticed?
The phone is $47
So actually, the phone is free
And they're going to pay for half of the line charge for the first month or whatever
They're going to pay the first $3 for the service
I know
It's nuts
How can they afford to do that?
That's what's so awesome about the MVNO structure
They didn't have to dig the dirt and put all of those towers in
So they didn't blow out a billion dollars doing that
So they can focus on the customer service
They can focus on the right devices
They can focus on the awesome plans and making the deals possible
They buy up all the spectrum from these guys at wholesale
And they get a great price on that
And when you remove that layer of having to constantly invest in the infrastructure
And all the techs and pulling all the fiber and all that
When you remove all of that, you can focus on really the customer experience
And that's Ting's secret weapon
And that's why they're always going to be more competitive than the other guys
So go to linux.ting.com
And thanks to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program
Alright, so Fedora 22 came out
The last couple Fedora releases we've gotten a lot of coverage
We've gone from really not talking about Fedora very much
To now we talk about Fedora a lot
And I feel like
Linux action shows are definitely improving
Noah takes no credit for himself there of course
I wasn't there for the other two reviews
I'm just saying the quality of the show is improving
Because you're talking about Fedora
It's for people who like to mess with computers
That is true actually
I would agree with that
Fedora is for people that like to mess with computers
I actually agree with Leo Laporte on something
That's amazing
So we did mention that Fedora 22 marks the demise of YUM
And the introduction of DNF
And does anybody in the Mumble remember with DNF?
Yeah exactly
The quality of Fedora increased as well
What does DNF stand for?
Do you remember?
Does not stand for anything maybe
But here's the one thing that was the miss in our review
That I wanted to follow up on right now
And I also wanted to kind of mention it
Because it's one of the semi-controversial things
About the new release of Fedora
It's not the use of Wayland for GDM
But it's the new lib input
That changes the way trackpads are handled
And for my Synaptics trackpads
I have noticed a huge improvement in accuracy
Right now I'm using it to scroll this page
I can't quite describe what it is that feels different about it
But it feels very good
Like this scroll
It's right on the mouse
It's right on it
And do you notice the difference too with the mouse input?
Not on this piece of crap
But on my System76
Or on my
I have the
Not a Dell
Lenovo
That's what it is
My wife's Lenovo
I was testing it on there
And on those with smoother trackpads
It works
It was very responsive
And I think you made the
You said this
I think Linux Unplugged
Maybe it was last week
And it struck a chord with me
It feels like the cursor is glued to your finger
Yes
It's attached to your finger
Exactly
It's right there
They've really nailed it
It feels like a level of mouse responsiveness
I've never seen in X before
I thought maybe that just wasn't capable in X11
And I was going, okay, I've got to wait for Wayland, I guess
I hope they fix it then
But LibInput's real nice
So DNF, by the way, stands for Danified Yum
Yeah, yeah, yeah
Dandyified, right?
Dandyified Yum
Dandyified
It's amazing how they come up with these names
It's something
Here's what's funny
That is going to be in some sort of corporate brief at some point
The selling points of RHEL 9, RHEL 10 is going to update
An update package manager
You're right
And they're going to be using the Dandyified Yum
Like some guy in a business suit is going to sit there
And have to listen
It's just kind of funny to me
It is
I never thought about it from the RHEL perspective
Yeah
Anybody in the Mumba Room want to share their perspectives
On Fedora 22 before I kind of get into what's coming up
For Fedora 23?
Nobody has used Fedora 22
You're all missing out
Do you know what you're missing?
I've used every Fedora release since one
That's a great release
And nobody has tried Fedora 22
This might be the best release of Fedora yet
Yeah
With a couple of exceptions
I've had some weird problems with Chrome under Fedora 22
A couple of my extensions did not install
Yeah
Which has never happened to me before
And Flash video plays
The Chrome tab shows the audio is playing
But I don't actually get any sound out from Chrome
That's an Adobe problem
It's a Flash
I know, but I've never had that problem before
I'm just kidding
I don't even know if it is
Is it even Flash?
Isn't it rendering in HTML5?
Did we talk about this?
Oh, that's right
I don't think it's
That's right
We tried HTML5 video and it doesn't work either
It's just any sound in Chrome
Yeah
And Firefox doesn't have that problem
So that's
I've had those issues
But for the most part it has been pretty good for me
Chrome is sort of a sticky point
I'd like to get the audience's response
Obviously our virtual lug has not been too excited about Fedora 22
Yeah, well I guess
So here's the thing too
Fedora is not for everyone
And Red Hat acknowledges that Fedora is not for everyone
And I am a diehard lover of Fedora
I acknowledge that Fedora isn't for everyone
Fedora is a great release if you
For one, for a long time
If you wanted to use Gnome
It was a great release to have
Because if you don't want to take the time to put Arch together
Because maybe I just want to install my operating system
And I'd like to have things like a software manager and stuff like that
I think that Fedora fits the bill pretty well
And then like I said, I think the real sweet spot is
If you're a system administrator
And you want something that you can try out the newest versions of something
Before it actually goes into stable production
I wonder too
Maybe not many
I wonder how many people are waiting for Korora 22
The re-spin of Fedora that includes all the codecs
And makes it much easier for end users
So I want to clarify this
So somebody says they want to bring up the comparison to Antragos
Antragos is a great installer
It's a great distro
And I think it does do a very good job of just
You plug the USB key and then I have Linux
However, first of all, there are tiny little issues that do come up with Antragos
Like its installer can be broken from time to time?
Like the installer doesn't recognize the internet
That seems to be an issue
But the other thing too is
Antragos still is a very customized
It's very customized and it's very minute
So okay, alright
Give me like one example
Alright, so when you plug the USB drive in
You have to choose if you want to
You have to choose which desktop
Sorry
You put the CD in, Chris
No, I just like that you're
Like how the desktop environment handles the USB storage medium
Is like a major issue for you
It's like a deal breaker
I was talking about installing it
But you have to choose the desktop environment, right?
And so for somebody that plays a lot of Linux distros
That's super nice
And I think that's an awesome
Sorry, go ahead
I was saying you get to choose a desktop environment
Yeah, that's true
You get to
But kind of the nice thing about Fedora
Is when I plug it in
I can just install it
Some of those things are gone
And in some respects it's kind of nice
Because it's kind of a mix between
This really bleeding edge
And not just having to custom
A curated thing
Pick every single thing
I have a mail client
I have a web browser
So have you tried Korora?
No
Well yeah, a while ago
I haven't tried it with obviously
They don't have Korra 22 out yet
And I think like people in our Mumble Room
If you've been kind of
Or in our audience
If you've kind of been borderline curious about Fedora
But you're worried about it
Maybe not working for you
You could just try straight up Fedora
It's pretty great
Yeah
Korora 22 when it hits though
You know like
One of the things I really like about it
Is it just
It comes loaded again
I know this is always my go to
But it just comes loaded with a ton of stuff that I like
So you get to choose from
Cinnamon, GNOME, KDE, MATER, XFCE
It's got Adobe Flash already installed
Dropbox, Google Chrome is loaded
With the Google Talk plugin
RPM, Fusion repos are already set up
VirtualBox is already
Is ready to go
Third party driver support is set up
And ready to go
Like for Nvidia graphics cards
Steam is no problem to get going
Like it just
It just takes all of the stuff that
You might want
And makes it ready to go
So I guess where I get kind of disappointed with that is
I guess it makes me disappointed
That we have to have
Essentially a fork of Fedora
To get those things
It's a respin
They're using the respin tools I think in Fedora
I would like to get that respin
If your opinion is reflected
On a large user base
And I think it is
I think it would be
It would be nice to see those changes implemented
You know they won't
Because of the legal issues
Right
So this is taking care of a problem
That Red Hat can't legally do
If Red Hat wanted to make the most amazing desktop
Ever
They couldn't
Because of the legality
So you know what
These guys take care of it for them
And the thing is
It follows pretty closely to Fedora
And if you want to use regular Fedora you can
I just think Karora is a great option
Fedora 23 is going to have a new way to upgrade
So FedUp has been around since Fedora 17
Have you ever used FedUp?
Yes
Yes I have
FedUp is getting rewritten
To be totally honest
I would not recommend upgrading Fedora
I've done it
I've done it a couple times
But I've run into issues far more times
Like probably
It's probably not an exaggeration to say
Probably one out of every three times
Something bad happens
Between 15 and 16 was particularly horrible
Because what would happen is
You would upgrade the system
And it would just do this thing
Where you would load
It would load the log in manager
And you would type in your password
And then it would just go right back to you
Asking for the password again
And I could not find a way to fix it
How annoying
Well it's annoying when it's on your laptop
And all of your work is there
And I can't log in
And I'm sitting in front of somebody
And they're going why can't you log in
Then I have to explain that
I don't know why I can't log in
And not only can I not log in
But I can't even log in to find out why I can't log in
So here's what they're doing
Here's what they're doing to FedUp
They say they've come to the conclusion
That the current design is unsupportable
Mostly due to upgrade.image
Which turns out to cause more problems than it solves
So for Fedora 23
FedUp needs to be redesigned
They're going to download packages for the new system
And then they're going to use SystemD
And it's offline updates facility
To install the packages
This is really simple
They say it's going to be a simple enough approach
That probably will be provided by the system packaging tools
They have a proof of concept already up on GitHub
Integrated in as a DNF plugin
As a DNF plugin
A dandy-ified yum plugin?
Yep
This behavior could be implemented by package kit
Which would make it easy to write a gooey wrapper for it
So the plan is to drop upgrade.image
Move to upgrade support into the system packaging tools
And make it a simpler system
So use the SystemD offline update functionality
Bob is indeed your uncle
What do you think of that?
Look at SystemD being an essential tool to do the updates
Do you think that this is another sign
That the Red Hat group is trying to move
Is trying to repurpose and restructure
Fedora to be more streamlined for the workforce?
Rather than just being a testing bed for Red Hat?
That's a, yeah, why do they care?
Yeah, why do they care about being
I mean, blowing away a desktop isn't that big of a deal
I mean, especially if you're using Fedora
Especially if it's for enthusiasts
Yeah, right
So it almost, and you know, look at the wording
They've changed it to Fedora
Now they call it Fedora Workstation
That alone is interesting
The only thing that is missing for me to go
Every client I work for and say
We're done with using this, that or the other
We're going to switch to Fedora
I have to have an LTS
I have to have
I have to have some sort of a locked thing
That's there for three or four or five versions
That is centered around a desktop operating system
And 18 months just isn't enough
No, it's not
And then the other thing that would be nice
I can live without it, but it would be nice
Is if they could offer support
So I could say, pay $800, $900 per workstation
And you can call this company anytime and they'll help
There are clients that would demand that
So if that would be, that would be nice
But I can live without that
We can do the support
So that's not the end of the world
I mean, that is how I make money, right?
I guess
You could turn away as a money maker, I suppose
But I'm still not convinced it's going to be a workable solution
Because the problem, honestly, is
Fedora releases
And I think 22 is an example of this
In my opinion, take a month before they're good
I think it takes a month of updates
A month before RPM fusion is all cut up to date for everything I need
A month before everything in copper is where I'm at
And so what you really get is
So if you're going to turn this around to a client solution
So you're going to wait a month before you deploy it to your clients
But I'd wait a month before I deploy the next LTS
Of course you would, of course you would
But for Fedora, you're going to wait a month
Then you're going to schedule it
So it's going to be two to three months before you actually get it installed
And then what do you really have?
You have a 15, 14, 16 month support window
Oh, as it is, yeah, it's not usable
Even if the day it came out
I could get it installed, I still wouldn't do it
I don't have the time of day, the effort
And I'm not going to tell my clients they have to pay me
You know why we use Linux to begin with?
Because I can set it up one time
And then I can make my money actually doing useful things
And the customer sees value
Because they're not paying me to redo things constantly
If I tell them that
Because you can't wait the actual
The full release
I would probably up it by one
So if the release cycle is, let's say
They release every six months
And then the support cycle is 12 months
I would be replacing every six months
Or this is 15, 16?
Yeah, so I'm going to replace the cycle before that
Because I want to give myself a little buffer time
So even if I could do it the day it came out
It wouldn't be practical
Yeah, if they really want Workstation
And it seems to me it would be so good
For so many of their initiatives
If more people were using Fedora Workstation
The more people that are using Fedora Workstation
Are going to be writing software for Fedora Cloud
The more people that are deploying Fedora Cloud
The more people that are going to use Red Hat Enterprise
When they step up to the next level
The more people that are buying Red Hat Enterprise
Are buying huge fatty support contracts
That milks the cow
So it seems to me
I know at first pass
You can't quite see how Fedora
How doubling down on Fedora
And making it a long-term supportable product
Makes them money
But to me it seems pretty clear
You can put it on a lot of desktops
And plus they're just going to have to compete
With other distros anyways if they don't do it
And the model has been here for a long time
To do stuff like this
So for example, how many times
Do you have a program that you have the choice
Between the unstable and the stable?
Why can't we do that?
Why can't we have Fedora Workstation
And Fedora Bleed?
And Fedora Bleed is the
Every time a mouse moves
Yeah, right, exactly
Every time something moves
We put something in there
We see if it works
And then when it crashes and burns
Oh well, at least we have
Fedora Workstation
And then Fedora Workstation
You take the best of that
And turn that into RHEL
And that becomes a server
That's essentially what they do
But without the support though
Yeah, well kind of
Except not really
Because I still see a lot of
Really, DNF should not be
Well, actually it has worked really well
So I guess I can't say that yet
But I feel like there should have been more
I should have had more of a chance
To play with DNF before
It was in 21
Yeah, I guess
But it was a transition
Actually, DNF was instituted in 18
Oh really?
I started playing with it in 21
Yeah, okay
Yeah, I wanted to give
While we're talking about DNF
I wanted to give Heaven's Revenge a chance
To geek out
I know you and Rotten were looking at
Go ahead, Heavens
Alright, DNF is an acronym for
A SAT Solver Algorithm
As in a Satisfiability Solver
It started up in YUM on OpenSUSE
To do their dependency management
For package dependencies
Yeah
So DNF means Disjunctive Normal Form
It's just the acronym of what the
Class Combining Algorithm is
For how they do the SAT solving
That's geeky
Thank you, sir
Thank you
That's a good way to end the Fedora discussion
Right there
I think, you know
I invited Matthew Miller, the Fedora Project Lead
On the show today
But then we moved the show today
Sorry, Matthew, if you were going to make it
I'm fascinated to see where they're going
Fascinated to see what Fedora 23 has in store
And see what they do with the workstation spin
I have a lot of interest in that
I think that's going to be a big deal
Just a couple of bits of business
We'll be back at our regular time slot
On Tuesday next week
2 p.m. Pacific
You can go to jupiterbroadcasting.com
Slash calendar
To get that all up in your business
We're also attempting to raise some more funds
For the network
Post Linux Fest and events
We are hoping to get some more support
On our Patreon page
Over at patreon.com slash today
We'll have some interesting developments
Coming there soon
And when you go over there
There is a video that Noah and I posted
In fact, if I go to the post real quick
I can go pull this up
Noah, do you remember we did this?
I posted this from my phone
Yeah
A May studio update
Posted for our patrons
Look at your face right there
It looks like I'm calling you out on something
Yeah, I think you were
Yeah, so there I am
Rocking my HTML5 shirt
And Noah and I are doing an in-studio build
Where Noah shows us
Here, look at this shot right there
Look at that
You can see the rig we're working on
And we talk to our patrons about that
We try to do those from time to time
For our
Oh jeez
Don't put Rekai in the shot
There's almost a beard in the shot
That's for the patrons only
Yeah, yeah
Cannot show that on the May studio
See that right there
Is worth signing up to be a patron
Yeah, patreon.com slash today
The money raised there isn't just for the Tech Talk Today show
It is for all of the shows
And Tech Talk Today is the way I thank you for that
And with that
We're going to have some announcements
Of where that funding is going
But it helps us build a little runway and predictability
Without having to increase our sponsor load
Patreon.com slash today
Also, last but not least
I'd love to get submissions from the audience for Runs Linux
If you have a cool Runs Linux rig
Get some video or audio of it
Or pictures of it
And send it to linuxactionshow at jupiterbroadcasting.com
If it's like a YouTube video
You can upload that ass and send us a link
We'd totes appreciate that
And then we'll feature it on an episode of the Linux Action Show
Now, we have a lot of really good episodes in the pipeline
For the Linux Action Show
So tune in on Sundays as well
10 a.m. Pacific, jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
And if you want to make this show better
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Including the feedback thread
To share your thoughts on anything we talked about today
Noah
Yes sir
Is there any place you'd like to plug for folks to check out
For you throughout the week
You can head over to AltaSpeed
There you go
And check out what I do during the day
In fact, actually
I think next week on Linux Action Show
You're going to find a slightly different aspect
Of AltaSpeed
That we haven't really talked about before
Yeah, we're going to have a feature on that
Also, check out my new Twitter account
I've changed
But it's still chrisles
You just have to re-follow it
At chrisles
Alright everybody, thanks so much for tuning in to this week's episode of
Linux Unplugged
See you right back here
Next week!
Alright, JBtitles.com
JBtitles
Let's go
And a last chance to vote
We've got the Fedora 22 discussion in here
We have a lot of topics we talked about today
So, JBtitles.com
And we'll pick that
Disjoint of normal Fedora
Do not Fedora
Wow, Fed up with Fed up
Wow
The year of the Linux laptop
Ooh, that's not bad, Ubi
That's not bad
Carboard container catastrophe
That's not bad either
Some good ones
Dell recommends Ubuntu
Mmm
Crappy desktop environment
Ouch, guys
Ouch
What's a crappy desktop environment?
Well, I don't know
Apparently somebody thinks something's crappy
JBtitles.com
What'd you think, Mr. Noah?
What'd you think?
What are we doing after this?
I'm gonna decode a radio
What are you doing?
Really, really isn't it what you think of this?
What are you doing after this?
Uh, well
Rekai and I are gonna cuddle
Ooh, nice
And, and, and
Burgers, right?
You're gonna get burgers
I have to give him five guys
Cause he, uh
He gets really crabby if you don't give him five guys
Yeah
Yeah, for sure
He comes out and he's like
Where's my five guys?
Yeah, and he hits you
He whips you with his beard
He, that happens
Uh, disjointive, uh
Disjunctive
Disjunctive, uh
Normal fedora
I misspelled it
Can't even
What are you trying to say?
It was disjunctive normal form
And I changed it to just disjunctive normal fedora
Carboard container catastrophe and year of the Linux laptop
Are our top contenders
JBtitles.com
It's a tight vote
It's a tight, tight, tight, tight vote
So, um
You guys
I got a little
I got a little anecdote for you
Wanna hear an anecdote?
I don't know if you would actually
Oh, okay
Cause it's gonna be a rip on fedora
Why would I do that, dude?
I don't know
We just
Do not fedora
Why would you do that?
Why would I do that?
So, uh
You know, uh
It kinda goes like this, you guys
Um
Before, uh
Before Noah came out
Rekai comes into the studio
And he says to me
He says, you know
Noah and I have been talking
Like, they've been talking offline for a while
About what a mess it is in the studio
And about
And about how
They're gonna come in here
And, you know
It's just time for the professionals to come in
And clean up
Because
You know
You know, Chris
You just haven't been able to figure it out
So, yeah
The big boys are gonna come in
Yeah
And we're gonna clean up this wiring mess
And, uh
Make sure that all this is cleaned up
So, if he has any audio issues
It must be cause of that
Well, ladies and gentlemen
I am happy to tell you
As I stand here
The wiring mess is now ten times worse
Oh, okay
Ten times worse
So, you prefer the buzz
Uh-huh
Is what you're saying
I'm just saying
Your audio buzz is gone
I got schooled on my wiring
And how it's gonna be all cleaned up
And then you guys
Look at that mess right there
Yeah
So, uh
I love
You're very good at presenting one side of the story
Oh, am I?
Yeah, yeah
You're very good
So, here
So, here's the thing
First of all
I
The
Here
The cables that I have to work with
Are the
Are the spare ones that are in the box
Because, you know
This is an interesting argument you make
And I like it
So, your argument is
And this is great
Oh, no
The reason
Hold on
Let me tell you what he's about to do
Everyone
So, just so you can appreciate this
This is a destroyable argument
And he's going to do it in
In such a quick and precise manner that you'd think that he sat up all night and rehearsed
No, it's just
It's obvious
Oh, okay
I think it's funny that this is your argument
So, your argument is
If I understand it correctly
Yeah
That this would not be such a mess
If you didn't have to use just the random assortment of odd cables I have
Yes, actually that is exactly my argument
Right
So, my argument is as such
It wasn't such a mess when I used those same exact cables
Yeah, but
I have the same cables
Oh, so
I use the same cables
So, hold on a second
So, what you're saying is
I don't make that mess
But the guy who was in charge of Jupiter Broadcasting was in this room and ordered all those cables
to begin with when he decided that he was going to move his studio from his house over
to this studio over here
Now, here's the thing
Now, that happened
Somehow
Somehow, the same amount of computers is in this room that was in this room before
Right, except
But there's way more wires now
Yeah, and the reason
And the reason for that is
You say it's because they're an eclectic set of wires
Right
Except for when I used that set of wires
Yes
It was not this messy
You did, but you also didn't have stereo in and out of the M-Audio
So, you weren't feeding stereo to the Mumble Room
We don't have stereo return into the
Oh, I'm not done yet
That's just one thing
There are so many things that I've done
Pause, because you're painting a bad picture
Oh, okay
That's a very compelling argument
Yeah
Except for the fact that all of those cables are like three feet long and they're on the
other end of the room
Yes
Over there
None of this mess is because of that fix
All right, all right, all right, fair enough
But, but, so, to get that, so, so, we have, we have improvement, so it's not the same
setup as it was before that
I was destroying that argument independently
But, now, but the reason that, the real reason for that cable mess back there
Uh-huh
That rat's nest
Yeah
That horrible mess
It's in the wrong spot, it knocks the PC over
That, that's happened once
Which actually happened during the show
Twice
So, so, the reason for that is, is because since we don't have actual, enough HDMI cables
to go all the way over here, I can't put the computer where it was before
So, it has to go on the floor so that this, this godforsaken VGA cable, which I haven't
used a VGA cable in probably ten years
Somehow I, I have to use it, because that's the only way that you can see this on here
So, the, what we could do if, if the cable mess bothers you that much is I could go back
and put the nook back in, we could go back to a buzz
Because
But again
The buzz is kind of nice actually
None of this changes the buzz
It does change the buzz, the buzz is gone
No, this PC, if it wasn't for that VGA cable, could be on the other end of the room
Yeah, that's true
Yeah
So, what you're saying is I should go to Best Buy and buy a, a, what do I need?
Oh, you know what, actually, you know what
I don't know
Oh no, I'm about to destroy my own argument
It's not an HDMI cable that we need, it's another HDMI output
Yeah
On the box
Yeah, we do
Well, I could go buy an HDMI splitter
VGA's fun
So
Yeah
So, yeah, so now, and now of course Noah flies out tomorrow morning
And leaves me with a mess
Yeah
But that's fine
That's fine
That can be, that can be
There's a reason that I plan to, I plan for longer, just in case I need to
Well, I wonder what a spectrum analyzer would look like right there
They say in the chat room, it looks like a pit of doom
I have a spectrum analyzer
I should have photoshopped this a little bit and added some additional cables
Yeah, yeah, should you
Yeah
I'll tell you what, I'll come in here while you're in the middle of Coder Radio
Yeah, there you go
Yeah
Good, good
Alright, speaking of that, we gotta go
So, let's see where our titles are
JBtitles.com, JBtitles.com
And I'm refreshing
And our top vote is, ladies and gentlemen, Disjunctive Normal Fedora
Really?
I guess you guys like the clever ones, huh?
Which do you, do you have a preference there, Noah?
Mine is still the year of the Linux laptop
But that's only because I really like the idea that we're gonna have a year of the Linux laptop
What?
We've had one every year for the past 15 years
Yeah, right
No, that's the Linux desktop
Now we're in the Linux laptop
Catch up
I'm on a different level
The desktop, oh burn, the desktop is a part of the laptop
Oh, is that how that works?
Alright, alright, we'll go with Disjunctive Normal Fedora, that's fine
I like it, I like it enough, we can do it, I think that's pretty good
And I like Blaster