a robot yes what are we going to do with a robot well astro follow me yeah who doesn't want an
amazon dog following you around your house for just over a thousand dollars their new
alexa on wheels has been announced today it probably runs linux but i don't know if it
even matters i don't care at this point if it runs linux or not i don't want a robot that
follows me in my home i have too many dogs as it is you do have a lot of dogs that's a good point
i would like them to just actually have a program that connects us to dogs how about that let's
just skip the whole robot thing save everybody money yeah quick short term you know prime delivery
dogs hello friends and welcome back to your weekly linux talk show my name is chris my name is wes
hello wes you're coming in looking great today i love that all purple outfit this episode is
brought to you by a cloud guru the leader in learning for the linux cloud and modern tech
skills hundreds of courses thousands of hands-on labs go get certified go get hired get learning
at a cloud guru.com well coming up on the show today it is time for our server crash post-mortem
it struck at the worst time possible and then it crashed again it's been quite the journey we have
talked about our server on the show a lot and this week the chapter is coming to an end i'm a
bit sad but also excited about where we're going we have a major update for you this week but we
will start out by telling you why our arch server crashed recently and then why it crashed again
even more recently that we haven't told you about and then what we're going to do to get things
right to do the right thing here and get going and what we had to do just for now we're going
to tell you all of it it's a full post-mortem today on the show and then we have at the end
a really kind of a fantastic surprise twist we'll tell you about some really big future plans and
on top of all that in case the server stuff isn't quite your bag we've got some nice thought
provoking community news some old friends stopping by the show and a lot more so there is as they say
a big show today so before we go any further let's say time-appropriate greetings to our
virtual lug hello mumble room hello hello hello that is a good-looking mumble room we got 18 of
you in there nice to see you mostly everybody in the on-air room rocking out with us today
so i want to start by asking the mumble room how they feel about a news story that i came across
just before the show started ferronics has noted that the first sign of linux support for what
intel is calling quote software defined silicon are now landing for linux michael writes there's
been talk of intel moving to offer more license able opt-in features for hardware capabilities
found within a given processor and so we are now seeing the linux signs of support coming with a
driver for the intel software to find silicon to allow for secure activation of such features
baked into a processor silicon but only available as an upcharge option yeah michael larable did
some digging on this and kind of makes it clear the basic idea is that without having to purchase
a new processor intel software defined silicon allow for activating additional hardware capabilities
just by purchasing a license or upgrade unfortunately right now the exact details
don't appear to be public for what these upgrades might actually have in them but intel is currently
preparing the linux kernel driver support known as sdsi this driver exposes a per socket interface
so that intel's user space application can provision an authentication key certificate
which is then written to internal nv ram but it also allows provisioning what they call a
capability activation payload and it also handles the boring stuff of just reading out what
configuration the cpu state is right now oh okay so what we have here is this software defined cpu
that allows these hooks for authentication of various add-on packages initially targeting the
xeon line of intel cpus which i think you could probably understand why i'm curious how people in
the mumble room though feel about software defined cpu essentially a piece of hardware that ships you
buy it and there is features and capabilities in that chip that you just don't get access to until
you pay this is not a new concept we have seen this before but this seems like a whole new level
and you could almost kind of see this taking off in a way you know maybe an lte modem that has
extra 5g capabilities if you license those capabilities as an end user you know in that
purchase just 29.99 a month to activate these in cpu or in chip features i mean i think we've
already seen this to some extent with some of those arm boards right where you gotta get a
license to do some of the video encoding or decoding mini mac we're probably seeing this
because intel is going to target businesses initially definitely i see this as a business
feature so probably it's it's just a must that that thing has linux support i don't think this
is really for private users bite didn't they try something like this with itanium yeah so uh hp had
a system where they want to give the cpu a sort of offload of the processor so moving those kind of
functions to the software the software defining what instructions had to be executed and then the
software could just run through all the instruction needed and so thereby creating a more efficient
processor but yeah and you know what happened with the itanium right i mean this whole thing
i'm sort of sitting here going is this what intel is spending their time on right now this is what
they're worried about is licensing additional features instead of just making the absolutely
most kick-ass processors possible and shipping them as fast as possible but the reality is i
think there's like a cold business calculation here because making these cpus they're producing
these things in these massive quantities and it is cheaper and easier to produce if they're all
exactly the same and then they just turn things on and off via software which is not much further
than we are today where they're all manufacturing like say the cpu they're manufacturing tens of
thousands of them and a few of them a core doesn't light up properly or maybe a couple things just
don't pass a specific set of tests and so they will re-bin that as a lower brand cpu oh this is
the this is the four core version instead of the eight core because maybe one core doesn't test out
successfully so they'll disable them several of them and ship it as a four core instead of an eight
core processor when it's essentially the same silicon i mean that is something that already
happens today this feels like an extension of that but there is something i think initially when i
read these kinds of stories as a long time free software user i have this really like screw
licensing you know what like licensing can get the hell out of here i am so sick and tired of
software licensing i would like just no licenses and everybody just essentially operates as if the
gpl were just cultural practice but that's never going to happen but anyways that's but at the
core of me i just don't like licensing and i don't like it in software and i really don't like it in
hardware well it's a reminder that at the root of these computers that we try to fill with free and
open source software is this black box that we you know we don't really have full control over
and it just feels like a little bit kind of you know we've done this huge shift to services and
this isn't quite the same but it feels like it's kind of in that direction of changing the
relationship of i bought this thing it's static and i know what i've got and that's how i calculated
the cost whereas now that's a little more complicated yeah that's totally it that's
totally it we put all this energy and time and thought into the software stack that we run and
try to get it as free as possible and then we have dozens of black boxes baked into our
dozens of black boxes baked into our motherboard that's absolutely part of it oh there was an
interesting steam deck update this last week we talked a little bit about this on linux action
news you probably heard that epic and battle i have updated their anti-cheat software to support
games under proton on linux actually functioning now there's been so many top tier games that linux
users could theoretically technically play because proton was capable of making that game run but it
would fail to run because of anti-cheat software and as we noted on linux action news this week
that has been addressed by both battle eye and epic however game developers still need to patch
their games but no matter how you look at this this is huge news for linux gaming in this last
week this is ginormous news and it immediately means that some of the most popular games on steam
are now theoretically within reach of linux users yeah personally i'm hoping dead by daylight season
updates soon i suppose maybe now is time to reach out and voice our linux user opinions about games
we like and would like to see these updates although hopefully we do it politely yeah i'd
love to see destiny to get support that's what i would love to see and i think that's battle i
but all that aside for the moment we'll just have to wait and see there was one small update from
valve that seemed to have gotten missed in all the anti-cheat coverage but it's one that we're
kind of excited about in the recently updated steam deck faq there are two new questions and
answers that really did stand out the first asks if the steam deck will support booting from the
sd card which valve answers really quite simply yes steam deck supports boot from micro sd that's
great you're going to be able to boot different distros off of the sd card and there was a second
part of the faq that that backs us up the specific question was and this is a quote from the faq
which we have linked what can you tell us about the bios and does it allow dual boot and valve
answered multi boot is supported you can have multiple os's installed and choose which one you
want to put into users will have access to the bios menu what do i even say to this this is
suspiciously open i mean wow huge this means we're going to be able to see community takes on that
that steam deck experience that will have essentially zero barrier to entry i'm very
excited about this like i just i can't overstate it because it's going to allow a lot of people to
participate in creating a software experience for this hardware what if it's too easy though
you know there's no it's not like hacking linux onto a we or something they're almost begging us
to do yeah so i mean really what we have to see here happen is a couple of things we have to see
game developers update their game to support these new anti-cheat updates it looks like it's crazy
easy epic seems to indicate it's very simple they say quote starting with the latest sdk release
developers can activate anti-cheat support for linux via wine or proton with just a few clicks
in their epic online services developer portal that's from epic battle eye says well we already
had linux support but now we've specifically done an update to support proton that's number one is
game developers are going to have to update the game to support this anti-cheat stuff number two
and i'm not 100 but this looks pretty solid from what we can tell you're going to need linux 5.11
so you're going to need a linux kernel or you're going to be able to upgrade your kernel to 511 or
newer because you need a kernel that supports syscall user dispatch which is some work that
was done to make these these anti-cheat other things that are running in wine communicate
better on linux and if you don't have that support it looks like some of this anti-cheat stuff might
not work i haven't able to test that obviously so i can't tell you for sure but from our digging
around that looks to be the case and from what you can tell that seems like that's probably likely
right neil with linux 5.11 collabora on contract with valve made some changes that were upstream
that called syscall user dispatch which provides a way for user space to to register hooks to the
linux kernel for syscall interfaces and apis and things like that this is particularly necessary
for games because a lot of anti-cheat software work by directly calling windows nt syscalls
instead of using like the standard c library and going through user space the normal way
and they would fail in wine because linux doesn't know what that syscall is and they would just
break so what this does is it allows wine to register a handler in linux for syscalls just
like it does for binary format so like when you load in an executive a windows exe file
linux knows that this actually needs to be run by the wine bin loader rather than the
glibc bin loader and so that same process then allows you to run applications that would normally
talk to windows nt directly to then successfully be redirected back to wine for wine server to
handle and the wine fake nt kernel to give it what it expects so that the applications will
run properly that's what's so impressive about all of this right is like the the long-term work
where we got changes actually upstreamed in the kernel to a better enable playing proprietary
games on linux and that valve at the same time negotiated behind the scenes with these anti-cheat
vendors to you know actually get that working yeah and i think it's it's just nice to remember
that collabra is behind the scenes in some of this doing some of the work making some of this
possible at some of the lower levels and you've had valve clearly pulling the strings now for
about a couple of years laying the groundwork this particular groundwork for the deck and
you couldn't look at it necessarily from the outside and see that's where it's going but
now with hindsight it's obvious they were building towards a device now it's just obvious it just
stands out um so that's probably what you need to know is you're probably going to end up needing
a kernel 5 11 or newer um and uh that's you know by the time the deck shipping and all that that's
that's probably not going to be too hard to achieve so that we'll have links to information
about that in the show notes at linuxunplug.com 4 25 but we need to talk about a little community
news in fact something coming up very soon daniel foray joins us from the elementary os project
welcome back hey how's it going it's going really good i'm curious you know i want to talk about the
hackathon that's coming up because it's just in a couple of days but before we get to that
tell us how version 6 is going because i think it's been about a month since elementary os 6 came
out there's been an update how are things shaking out yeah it's been about a month and a half now
since release so we had um we do updates every single month so at the end of uh last month we
did a smaller updates post and we're packaging up all our updates uh to go out now with tons of new
features for online accounts tasks mail app center like everything's getting lots of goodies and i
being dense because i'm sure it was probably it was probably communicated pretty clearly
but i completely missed that there is like a monthly update cadence thing now yeah actually
we started that um last cycle uh and so we're kind of continuing that over but we wanted to
make sure that we're not just pushing out bug fixes and feature updates like every couple years
because it's not a super great experience we want to push them out monthly because then we can get
that feedback loop really tight where you know people are reporting an issue or they're requesting
a feature and we want to get that out to them as soon as possible so they feel more involved
okay well let me ask you this is there anything that stands out in your mind
today that is kind of different or changed since elementary os 6 0 you know version 0.0 shipped
i guess there been anything behind the scenes that has changed in the last 30 days anything
that stands out i mean i think um some of the biggest things are that we're making a lot of
progress with app center with flat pack we've been working with the wider community on some of the
free desktop stuff like with the dark style support across you know all the apps and and so we're
going to be working more on portals and that kind of stuff we kind of redid our ci and cd system
recently so we're now building our flat packs for arm so we're going to have app center
apps building for arm and they're all flat packs now so we're like we're going to have this really
great collection of apps that you can go run on any distro now if you go to appcenter.elementary.io
you can go download those flat packs for whatever distro and we're just going to keep growing that
and make it super awesome wow that sounds rad yeah very impressive that's some serious work
you're putting in that's really cool okay so let's talk about this hacktoberfest live stream
that's coming up isn't it this thursday yeah so uh what's going on with that is that uh it's a
really great time in the cycle right now because you know we just released so it's not really like
the end of the cycle it's like the beginning of our development cycle and so we have a great
opportunity to get people involved and you know try to talk about like what projects we want to
pursue during this cycle and we have hacktoberfest coming up which is the event put on by digital
ocean and github so we're going to do a stream on thursday and we're going to talk about how to get
involved with hacking on elementary os and working on new features and cool stuff like that and we're
going to try to you know tie that into hacktoberfest so if you've never heard of that and you want to
try to get involved you can come find out how you can get some free swag for contributing to open
source projects on github right on but you know it's fall when hacktoberfest rolls around it's
like a milestone of the year so what is an easy place for people to go to get involved if they're
interested and they have some time on thursday if you want to go to our get involved page actually
elementary.io forward slash git dash involved we have links there for all kinds of stuff but
if you want to watch out for our youtube page we have a link to our youtube page on our website
that's where we do our live streams on the last thursday of every month so you're saying if i'm
already subscribed to the elementary youtube channel i'm good to go because of course why
wouldn't i be subscribed yeah exactly and then you can come hang out and do some little q a with us
we got the whole live chat live stream thing going on great well danny thank you for coming on the
show it is always great to catch up with you and it's great to hear things are moving right along
with elementary os6 and it sounds like the hacktoberfest thing is going to be a lot of fun
thanks for joining us thank you and i'll see all you guys on thursday lino dot com slash unplugged
go there to get 100 in 60 day credit on your new account and you go there to support the show
linode keeps getting better i have been a customer for about two and a half years and i can absolutely
testify to this i'll admit though i was watching them for a while you know when these new like
vc supercharged fly by night vps providers came along and were offering all these different things
i sat back and wanted to see what linode would do because you know they're kind of like the old
timer in the linux community they've been around for 18 years i was like are they gonna fumble this
are they gonna get passed up by the new kids or are they gonna stay competitive
and sure enough they they really really have in fact now they're lapping those kids linode just
upgraded their block storage with super fast mvme pcie storage and it screams you can get
systems with amd epic processors that benchmark faster than any other major cloud provider and
pair it with mvme block storage okay it's amazing and then they have 11 data centers you can choose
from and they have become their own isp so they have secured super fast links between their data
centers 40 gigabit connections coming into the hypervisors and then they wrap it all up with a
beautiful easy to use dashboard that lets you get under the hood when you need and i mean i actually
have a linode that i completely replaced the image that they ship with it like i wiped the box and i
put a custom linux distro from a router vendor to create an lte mesh vpn endpoint and they actually
linode actually let me like wipe it off and set up my own custom box there and now the crazy cats
are launching bare metal servers if you really need like just the ultimate performance and it
doesn't matter if you've never set up a box before because they've got easy one-click deployments so
say maybe you're ready to switch to next cloud they got a one-click deployment for that or maybe
something just like a little more like in between like are you done using zoom and you'd like to
use something you can trust and open source they've got a one-click deployment for jitsi
and there's really no excuse and they're 30 to 50 cheaper than the big duopoly hyperscalers you
can get like a five dollar a month box that runs jitsi that's a pretty justifiable business expense
in my opinion but i i really encourage you to go play turn it up to 11 because you can get a hundred
dollars that and when you look at their pricing that's that's incredible that really is great so
go try it out i can tell you all about it all day long but you need to go see it for yourself and
you can support the show it's an opportunity to go play learn and support the show you can call it
like the trifecta of awesome so just head over to linode.com slash unplugged get a hundred dollars
for your new account and try all this stuff out build something learn something test something
there are a lot of ways you can host i admit it there's a lot of them out there and there is some
big big hyperscalers that they'd love you to just put everything you own into their systems but
nobody does it like linode that's why they've been around 18 years and that's why i completely
recommend them go see why we choose linode every single time by going to linode.com slash unplugged
there's a few things i'd like to mention in the housekeeping section first of all thank you to our
members over at unpluggedcore.com the live stream feed has just been delivering mr roach joined us
in the mumble room and told us about his time interning at pixar and about the linux boxes
there that was awesome we had so many great conversations that's available to our members
in the totally uncut bootleg feed we also create a limited ad version that's the same type production
just a little bit shorter and you support the show at unpluggedcore.com i also wanted to let
you know that our buddy joe has a new show a new member of the late night linux family it's called
linux after dark go check it out it's in your favorite podcast catcher already episode one
is already out i'd also like to encourage you to join our luck plug it happens every single
sunday at noon pacific in our mumble room right there in the lobby you can figure it out at your
time zone at jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar and all of our mumble info is at linux
unplug.com slash mumble and the nice thing is you get it set up if you're ever around on a tuesday
you can come join us and hang out in the show and get your word in on uh your weekly linux talk
show that's linux unplug.com slash mumble for that okay wes i i know we've talked a lot about
the server recently but this is kind of you know it's what's happening right now and there's some
big stuff in the works you think it's okay if we just maybe one more time touch on this subject
well we have to right it's clearly becoming an issue and the audience needs a resolution
we need a resolution too well yeah that too so just in case you haven't caught previous coverage
just super briefly our goal with this arch server that we have here in our studio has been a bit of
a long-term experiment i think you know too often you'll see online reviewers who spend 30 or
40 minutes with something if that and then they go make their video or their blog or whatever
maybe it's just a forum post somebody you know talking smart in a forum giving you their opinion
people speak with authority after they try something for a little bit they kind of they
because they speak with authority to it it kind of gets accepted as maybe expert opinion
and then before you know it it's all over the entire internet as fact
and so we love pushing back against that kind of stuff and we also know that how something holds
up long term is a totally different story than how something is during your first impressions
right i've been like i'm i'm already preparing myself for our fedora 35 review because i've
been running fedora 35 for the last two weeks so that by the time it ships in a month i'm gonna
have a pretty rounded opinion of that distribution and some of it will be you know it's during it's
a beta cycle but some of it's like i'm a forming opinion now about gnome 41 and i i truly believe
whenever we can we try to really experience something as long as possible and when we can't
we come right off and we'll tell you hey man this is a first this is a first
opinion you know first impressions kind of thing with this server we wanted to try actually running
arch in production for an extended period of time and see if we could make a few tweaks to make it
keep running like you know using the lts kernel file system snapshots utilizing butter fs on the
root file system and then using zfs on the large external data pool not that we necessarily
recommend you do any of this but we wanted to test it to see how it would hold up we wanted
to find out so you didn't have to run a rolling arch server in production well and we both had
such good experience with arch you know on the workstation on various machines in our life and
we both knew that it had all the software and kind of got out of our way in terms of managing
it was like a pleasant environment that we were both familiar with to admin so it was tempting
to just see like yeah can we make it work here too and i should have looked it up before the
show but i'm pretty sure we've crossed the year mark running this thing in production in fact we
might even be rounding the second year possibly and it's it's all out there we've tried to put
all of it out there as much as publicly possible so if this thing blows up on her face you know
and you know because that's our our singular motivation is really just to prove if it's
possible and if it's not we're gonna find out for you and the reality is this is a production
server we really do use it so when it breaks it breaks in front of everyone and it hurts
and you know it's out in a garage it's not particularly well thermally protected in fact
it's not at all and there has even been some power outages recently and that's what's led us to some
of the more recent issues initially we had some lockups that we traced back to net data but we
weren't sure right before the road trip about a week before the road trip the server started
locking up the worst timing impossible yeah we got it up and running again suspecting it was net
data we turned off net data and the system remained running for you know a month maybe
then about three weeks into my road trip the server went down i checked in i couldn't wire guard
i couldn't talk to the server at all but i was able to use rust desk to get to a couple of the
studio desktops and using that approach i determined oh power went out for a while and
the funky way we have this thing wired up is one power supplies into the wall and one power supplies
into ups for stupid technical debt reasons and i think when that happened the server got into
a funky state and it eventually lost power then when it rebooted it came up in a bad way and never
finished booting and i couldn't tell why because i was i was gone i was on a road trip and the old
server admin in me was dying i had to know why my server was down plus i wanted my server back up
right i mean here was this situation that we hadn't actually encountered right i mean we've
we've seen it power cycled we've come back into the studio after the power went out and it's
always been fun i mean it takes forever to do so but but it gets there yeah and of course it happens
while wes is camping so i'm i'm gone wes is camping and then moving the whole thing was just
like the worst time possible so we didn't know why it was back up and so like the last day of the
road trip i legitimately just made a beeline for the studio i was just i got lady jupes to her spot
i got lady jupes secured and parked and then i jumped in the car and i ran down to the studio
to figure out what was wrong and i mean i literally i maybe was back in town from the road
from the road trip for a grand total of an hour before i was in the car and headed directly to the studio
uh-oh that's not a good sound
well i've been in town for about an hour and i've already made it to the studio to try to figure out
what's going on with the server
getting a beep
that seems bad
i'm gonna shut her down
seems that the console is locked right now
take it down take it down we did have a power outage here seems like i didn't expect it to be
on i thought it was going to be off
i'm going to pull the power completely it's got a dual power supply
go hug them back up
both power supply fans are working
oh immediately getting the beep
hold on the beep just stopped the red light on the front of the chassis just cleared
still waiting for console it hasn't posted yet
there we go we've got post yes okay keep booting you bastard keep booting and it did and i i was
sitting there thinking man i i expected some sort of catastrophic hardware issue and the entire time
i kept thinking how could i have done this differently let's do a ping check
let's do a ping check yes i am getting ping all right let's check if containers are up
uh yes i think yes yes containers are up
yeah they're definitely up there's a lot going on look at all that okay great
okay i'm gonna go uh applications plunking see if everything's working and it was i mean for the
next 24 hours or so the server ran great we were able to connect in over wire guard it was chewing
away on a backlog of work just like it was supposed to it started sinking out results to
lady jupes it was glorious everything and i was just like god i appreciate this i don't know why
it crashed but i appreciate it so that was you know thursday or so friday things seemed fine
saturday i kind of i got wrapped up in stuff we were doing with the kids and i didn't really keep
an eye on things but wes and i arrived at the studio on sunday to record linux action news
just as we sat down to get started we noticed something wasn't quite right and it didn't take
us long to figure out the server had crashed again let's go check on it server's down we're
going to go check on it we're recording land but we got to stop i got i got fish sticks air frying
we got to see what's wrong with the server oh it's dark out here too
none of the discs are flashing it's not beeping but this is like the state it was in the previously
before my road trip where it would just kind of lock up and then you i could tell immediately
because the fans are low and none of the hard drives are flat it's not working at all and when
you got that many hard drives there's always at least one flashing let's turn the console on here
what will we see i bet you it's just totally locked
just locked it's hard it's just hard i wonder i wonder if net data started back up maybe it did
and what is it probing so we gotta we gotta power it off and we'll start it back up and make sure
net data isn't running hello over the face yeah there's nothing that feels better than physically
powering off your server over and over again like that's not going to lead to problems i recommend
you do it all the time i think it's off i think that's it this is as low as the fans ever go
yeah here we go also i like how all of them light up red that's great really reassuring don't freak
me out at all all right well i think we'll just watch this boot up it's gonna boot up fine i would
imagine and uh we'll make sure net data isn't auto starting maybe i only stopped it and didn't
disable it sounds like you i can't believe it was freaking net data again wes so i had not disabled
it i had only stopped it previously before the road trip i mean you say net data i i surmise
that you know anything poking those might do the same thing right really we have to figure out do
net data as a monitoring agent we want to use something else to scrape the metrics do we want
to just try to disable some of that you know poking the hardware monitor functionality for
the time being i don't know we have bigger fish to fry first but we'll have to solve that down
the road yeah i think you and i both kind of suspect there's some sort of hardware issue
and net data is poking whatever that issue is and causing the lockup because when you get hard
locks like this it almost always ends up being hardware and i remember now i hadn't disabled
it because my intention was after the road trip to come back and fire net data back up and see if
it locked up again and so accidentally we ended up testing that theory and it did seem to hold
so as long as we leave net data disabled the system continues to run and assuming the power
doesn't go out and i don't really know why it was in an air state other than i think one power
supply is plugged into the wall one's plugged into the ups they've lost power at different times and
it just sort of went into this failed hardware state and had that beep you could hear but you
know what we have got some major stuff in the works very excited about this uh it's clear we
need to replace the server we knew that before this latest round uh we bought it used it has
served its term it started life as a free nasbox and then i think it lived life as a fedora box
for a while it has seen some stuff yeah and we have figured out that we really need like a
three-phase approach to replacing this thing so phase one is going to be replacing the server
it's well actually i'm going to flip this west phase one is going to be breaking out wire guard
onto its own dedicated box so that way in the future if our server crashes we can still get
access to the network now we solve that with nebula and rust desk but we'd like to have the
vpn capabilities removed from the server itself and on a different machine the debate there is
and i'm curious where you fall down west we could do it on a raspberry pi like we could have a wire
guard pie or we could replace that comcast router with like an open sense box and do open sense and
wire guard on one box what do you think hmm yeah there are a lot of options i mean i think we have
to decide yeah how many different things we want to administer and and how much i am kind of curious
to see how well a pie would perform and that does have some nice options in terms of you know you
have a whole bunch of pies laying around i do too so it'd be easy to drop in and test and we could
do that real quick do you think a pie would be fast enough to be the firewall like i'm picturing
a linux box with some basic firewall and routing we might just have to try right i don't i don't
know i mean maybe put pie hole in a container for the dns and dhcp and then you know if it wasn't we
could always migrate it to another rig later neil says the pie won't be fast enough for performance
network stuff like almost always you need hardware acceleration for packet handling but we're just on
a comcast connection it's like 300 megabits it's not just that it's about how fast you can push it
not how wide you can go so yes sure like you can blow out the bandwidth of it any day of the week
and that'll also be a problem but like the problem you're going to have more often is that you need
it to be low latency and you need those packets to go out as fast as they can as close to line
rate as possible especially when you're live yeah so raspberry pi would not work this is just why i
kind of want to test it though yeah i i wonder and if the other thing i was thinking and maybe
people could write in at linux unpluged dot com slash contact but like a really low power x86 box
that has ipmi it's like a micro atx itx kind of like tiny box there are a few mini pcs that do
actually have a bmc built in that you can use that might be something to look at as well but so i
think phase one is going to be figuring out our vpn stuff and you can see there's some some stuff
we got to sort out then phase two is replacing the server itself and the biggest challenge here has
become the disc we need about 40 terabyte of new disc to come in that's clearly going to be the
largest cost then the second challenge with a new server is what distro should we use obviously
we've been using arch for a while it's been great and there's certainly a part of me that would like
to just continue to use arch to see like how far can we take this thing before it breaks you know
we already have some more updates on the server i just checked oh man but also i recognize this
is an opportunity for us to try something else as well so in the show notes we'll have a link
to a straw poll and i would like the audience to vote on which server distro we go with next
there are only a few options because we've limited it to genuinely rolling distributions
rawhide's on the list right now but neil brings up a good point that we could have significant
issues with cfs if we went rawhide but not necessarily impossible to solve for so we have
arch nix tumbleweed and rawhide all as an option for you to vote on right now the live audience
has gotten 42 votes in so far these often will indicate the trend and right now tumbleweed is
in the lead with 45.24 percent of the votes rawhide's in second place nix is in third and
arch is in fourth if you have an opinion about this we're going to leave the poll going for the
next week so go to the show notes we'll have a straw poll in there it's a crazy url so i just
tell you what it is and go vote and uh we're very likely i mean like 99 likely unless some weird
reason comes up gonna go with the distro that you guys choose rawhide gives me the most pause
so not saying we're not gonna pick it but it's gonna require wes and i having a strong discussion
if it does if it wins i like that this is the option you're the least sure of what a funny
world but you're right i mean there will be some complications we might have to learn a fair bit
about the internals of rawhide or tumbleweed if the if the trend line continues my friend which
that's a whole new world what have we done using snapper so i guess like in that sense you know
maybe it makes sense but true true there's also the hardware component of the server and i cannot
believe this but the ups tracking numbers don't lie a listener has reached out mr real zombie geek
is sending us some new server gear new to us he's actually decommissioning it but he has in route
right now should be delivered tomorrow at the studio a dell poweredge r820 with and i i just
can't even believe this four intel e5 4657 cpus each with 12 cores four of them with 12 cores
and 384 gigabytes of ecc ram hey yo right i mean this i mean even if like it's maybe it's only two
intel i can't imagine it's four maybe it's only two xeons that's gonna be an amazing amazing amount
of compute for us uh he's shipping it with no caddies or drives so we're gonna have to figure
out what kind of caddies that r820 takes and i'm gonna i'll go on ebay probably and buy like a
whole batch of them so i've got some prep work to do here yeah and then jb's got to buy some
discs right but i mean he's saving us a huge cost and i was considering going with another pre-owned
server anyways and he's had this in production it's been a solid box he's just replacing it and
he offered it to us and i just i can't believe it that's wonderful best audience in the universe
there's just no doubt about it so that'll be the hardware whatever distro you all vote on will be
what we put on there and then there'll be the third phase the third phase is going to be to
set up some kind of remote console we were initially trending towards pi kvm and i think we
still may try try that because i ordered a little pi kvm kit oh look at you but this power edge has
a built-in idrac enterprise which may be just fine with we'll see yeah i'm kind of it'd be interesting
to compare and contrast so with idrac there might be even some fun automation potential that you
could you could work with because like i know that in in rail and centos and i think also in fedora
and it would be in tumbleweed as well there's a lot of tools around integrating with various bmcs
ilo from hpe generic ipmi redfish extended ipmi and idrac as well from dell so there's all kinds
of fun opportunities there if you have like built-in management interfaces like that i love
that yeah i can't believe it i mean what a what a gift to us right now because you know we just
caught back from that road trip so expenses are tight right now so that's a great thing to have
come along and uh should be great to play with and i don't know what i'll i may put the old server on
a test bench and see if i can't narrow down what the issues are or it may just sit there for a bit
we shall see but either way that's the that's the plan we have a three-phase plan to get this server
going and uh wes and i are already beginning to play around with vpn options there's some really
fun stuff out there we often talk about the desktop stuff because it's fun and we love the
desktop but there's so much awesome stuff going on at these layers too so it'll be fun to deep
dive into that and i'd love to get your opinion on which distro we should go with next so go find
the straw poll link at linux unplug.com 425 oh it's time for feedback and hey maybe if you've
got some ideas on what we should do in any of those phases well yeah right into the show but
in the meantime aaron's already done that with a self-hosted location tracker he really likes
now of course we had that set up at colony tracker.live a different piece of software
that we've been testing out for the road trip but aaron has been using a nextcloud app called phone
track this is an app for nextcloud i think i've seen this before yeah i think we just need to
install it on the jupyter nextcloud instance that we've already got running as aaron suggests
although i haven't actually tried it yet i like this as an overall approach to like taking something
that i think a lot of us think is is taboo like user tracking and cameras right having cameras in
your home oh i like taking that and putting it on its damn nose and saying well what if i do the
tracking and i control the data well what if i run cameras but they only work on my lan and they go
into something like shinobi and i record the cameras and can technology that we often consider
invasive be used by me under my control and that aspect of phone track really appeals here because
it's part of just hosting something yourself and if you've already gone to the trouble of setting
up nextcloud you install this app and i think it has an android companion app too yeah you know
aaron hits on that that he'd been on a journey to google fly and that location tracking was
one piece of that and i think it kind of makes sense in some sense to have it integrated with
nextcloud because yeah nextcloud can be a big part in getting off a lot of those popular google
services and for his part he does notice that the phone app has worked pretty well and that
he hasn't seen a hit to the battery life hmm yeah you can have it set so it sort of gets a the
background location update from the android operating system we opted not to go with this
just because we didn't really want to put our nextcloud instance public and own tracks was sort
of perfect for our use case but by ben if i recall you gave this a go for a bit right yeah so i use
it to track my phone and for when i lose it then i can find it again and it works really well it
also says when it's collecting its gps points how many it's already sent how many there are in the
session and it's also a really good platform for example if you've got drivers or delivery guys
driving around you can see it really easily on a map and a nice overview and you see they have
put some thought in multiple use cases but what i also noticed is you really need to get a good use
of these sessions because i have for example one session of my phone tracking and once i pull that
up my living area is just one big red dot about yeah you've been there there are all the lines
and i don't know if it's my amount of data or my setup but the filtering isn't that really great
for me at the moment but i assume they will be fixing that in later versions but yeah you can
select specific sessions you want to record to and you can put devices in there but you have to look
at if you need to select the session from your device itself so that is for me at least question
mark if you can put devices in there from the server side okay that's good to know for people
that might be interested in using it and we'll have a link to that in the show notes if you
want to try it or actually no you know what no you just go in your next cloud you look in the
apps and you just install it right there no link for you no link no link for you i will put a link
to this though because i am on the search for i'd love something that's a server side web app
that i hit up on my land and i paste a youtube url in and it downloads in the background and
puts it somewhere on my file system and then i open up my media player of choice and it's
connected to my nas and bam there's the youtube video and i've been looking for a web app to do
this for a while and i don't know if i found the perfect one but i think i found a real contender
it's called tube archivist it is a self-hosted youtube media server you give it the urls and
then it will archive them and then present you a front end to review all of your downloads kind of
give you like your own youtube um subscription feed but on your own box where it's pulled down
the videos locally oh this looks nice yeah man and it keeps track of like which ones you've
viewed and which ones you haven't viewed and uh it's using that new uh youtube dlp that we've
talked about yt dlp instead of youtube dl oh we made that a pic a couple weeks back right yep yep
so uh this is kind of like taking and putting it all together and then i like this because i thought
i've got a couple of youtubers i've followed that have like put up videos and then pulled them
but i also have a ton of videos i watch on youtube for like rv maintenance stuff and sometimes i'm in
an area where i want to do some work and i'm offline this is what i was hoping for is something
i could throw on my my box and just throw these links in there and then build a little offline
youtube collection the only spot where i kind of got hung up and why i haven't pursued it and
west you're gonna laugh at me but you know you gotta set up like elastic search and do some of
that stuff and i just i didn't want to go that far but i wanted to give it a link so you're saying
you need someone to write you a already composed docker compose file absolutely west that's exactly
what i'm saying and and also if anybody has another tool to accomplish this same thing
do let me know about it however you want to tell me because uh i'm always looking for uh for a way
to do this yeah you know i want something like this but just if it also had some like chromecast
support on the flip side you know it could kind of be the one-stop shop for all the videos uh
that would be nice yeah yeah and for me personally i don't really need a front end that tracks the
watch status because i just would like them on the file system and then i'll throw cody or jellyfin
or plex or whatever at that directory and manage it with my existing media application so you just
want the ingest side ingest and maybe a little bit of sorting you know maybe a folder per youtube
channel and so you know if you download from this youtuber you put it in their folder automatically
i don't know i guess i'm asking for the moon here but it seems like there must be something out
there because i mean hell there's so many there were back in the day when we all watched our
television via a cable there was like a dozen different pvr dvr solutions and there was myth tv
and we just need something for the youtube age so if you know of one let me know and if you'd
like to find our friends a cloud guru on social media they're just slash a cloud guru at pretty
much any social media website the youtubes instagram slash a cloud guru go find them over
there and see what they're up to if you do the twitter thing you can also follow the show at
linux unplugged west you're probably over there i'm at west pane remarkable remarkable the show's
over there uh the network's over there too yep that's true we have a show and a twitter for both
of them and myself it's a lot of twitter accounts really who would have known i'd be managing so
many different logins in 2021 and then don't even get me started on the show mailboxes holy smokes
whoo just bypass all of that come join us live we do this show every tuesday at noon pacific 3 pm
eastern see you next week same bad time same bad station and if you work in the tech industry
or you consider yourself a linux fan don't miss linux action news every monday morning really
sunday nights wes and i break down everything that matters in the world of linux and try to
get you the information in a concise accurate manner that's at linuxactionnews.com keep linux
rolling after that by joining us on tuesday or go subscribe at linuxunplugged.com subscribe
we absolutely love them subscribers and our members at unpluggedcore.com thanks so much for
joining us on this week's episode of the unplugged program it's not a monday it's not a wednesday
no no my friends we will see you right back here next tuesday
so along with their robot amazon has opened an invite only program for their previously announced
home surveillance drone the always home cam that flies around and surveys your home for you
oh man wes oh i think i'm about ready to go move out into the woods it's really just such a shame
because it's like in some sense if i felt like i was actually in control of it yeah maybe i would
want that you know it was open i could i knew where the data was going but of course that's
not what we get that's very much like the philosophy i was just trying to articulate
in the show it's like if if it's cameras that i have complete control over and i can replace the
firmware and it's something i can check and monitor then yeah i'm okay with it but if it's
something that i have no control over that could be easily perverted i find that gets dystopian
really quick and it feels like there's a lot more of the ladder these days well with the dog you
know i was just imagining here you are you needed to sit and then suddenly the connectivity goes out
of just the worst time you