What colors your hair?
Still brown still brown
I think I'm gonna do it at Linux fest if I remember problem is that the the hair dye already got taken from me
So I already had forgotten until you said something taken from you
Every time I'd sit down at the studio. I'd set my arms down and all of a sudden like everything was turning red
It was ridiculous. I was like oh, this is no good
I think if Chris does it he needs to he's to go all the way and do the orchid
I don't know if that's gonna happen
Maybe I also feel like if he's gonna do it. He needs to bleach his hair. Oh, yeah, Chris. Are you gonna bleach your hair?
No, he says oh junk then yeah
It's gonna look no good really why?
Cuz you do orchard what you should do orchard. Why why don't you bleach my hair?
That's that sounds like a bad time. Well, how are you gonna put a lighter color on a darker color? Is it lighter?
Both of them are well think so
Pretty dark hair bro. It's it's not gonna show up at all. Really, you know what they say about guys with dark hair, right?
I feel like we could have not said this on air and then that could have been my out now you guys are just totally
No, no. Yeah, the mistake you made is we want you to do this. Oh, yeah
Well, damn it. See what I think you should do is I think you should make your hair red and your beard organ
It's not actually a terrible idea oh
Oh
My gosh, dude, this is Linux unplugged episode 195 for May 2nd 2017
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's ripped out all of the proprietary software
Replaced it with good old Linux. My name is Chris get it out of it. Wait. No, my name is well, yeah
We're gonna keep it here now. Yeah, we got all the proprietary software adder
We'll tell you a little bit about that later, but that's not what we're gathered here to talk about today
Oh, no, we do have a great show though. Oh, that was really totally
That was great though. I really enjoyed that some new projects
Some of the pretty excited about because Wes has gotten his hands on them directly and he's like, hey, I've been trying this
We got to talk about it. I always love those segments on the show
Then a big big big change has come to all of those encumbered
audio files on your hard drive will tell you about that and then Windows 10 s has been officially announced and it's got
Chromebooks and desktop Linux in the education market
Squarely in its crosshairs. Oh, oh boom squarely. Let's just right in there Wes watch out for that and then
coming up in
Just a few short days the final episode of the Linux action show Linux fest Northwest
live Linux unplugged perhaps I'm okay. We'll tell you all about all of that and
Some of the efforts we've been going into here to get all of the Linux get all of the Linux and maybe if we have time
We'd like to have a very honest and frank conversation
About the state of Linux battery life some tools some tips some tricks from us and the virtual lug
To manage battery life to get better battery life
Wes has a has a story you could perhaps share with the class
from a co-worker who recently tried Ubuntu 1704 and
we'll just kind of hopefully walk away with some tips to have better battery life on our laptops because it seems like it's on a
Downward trend these days under Linux when Mac and Windows perhaps are at their best the new Microsoft surface laptop announced today
They claim 14 hours of battery life. So we'll see maybe can we get Linux close? Can we get close?
That's the question. I certainly hope so. Yes. Yes. So before we can do any of it
We've got to bring in our virtual lug a time-appropriate greetings bumble room. Hello. Hello
So guys
There is there is a couple of open source projects that I thought we'd start with this week that are just really cool to check
out and really cool to see come, you know come to fruition and
The first one is one that the Mac users have had for a while that I I really thought would be great on Linux
And now it's here. It's called open snitch
It's a open source port of the little snitch application
That's pretty famous on Mac and it's an application firewall
But what it does is it gives you graphical alerts about the applications on your system that are trying to take
They're trying to make an outbound connection and then the first time it happens you can take immediate action
You can whitelist that application. You can block it allow deny
It's a cool. It's a cool way to see what's talking to what and sometimes you're surprised. What's talking to what?
Yeah, exactly ever seen it. Yeah, you know
I've used it on I've seen people use it institutions that used it on on Mac OS and it
seemed like it's that like
Last mile kind of thing that we often associate with the Mac or some of the programs for it where it's like, yeah
All right, I could do all of that with IP tables or you know other means command-line applications
But but probably you don't I mean if you do great and there's a lot of cool guides out there to do that
But for like, you know the people who just installed Linux or their casual users or they just want like, um, you know
They don't do it all the time. They want a cleaner simpler interface. They can remember
I think this looks like it could be nice
Yeah
the other thing that's cool about it that I've used a couple of times when I had client max is I was installing a new
Piece of software and I wanted to figure out what I had to punch open in the corporate firewall or I just want to know
What's going on in the system you fire up in this case now open snitch
You run it for a couple of hours and you just get a list of everything that's trying to talk to everything you discover
That this application that runs in the background actually pings this HTTP server every hour, which you didn't know before
Yeah, totally. That's good. It is nice a little bit of visibility
Yeah
Now there's been some people say oh, you know running this kind of stuff through Python probably isn't a great idea
And it probably doesn't have the best performance
So you wouldn't necessarily want to put it on a server that's handling tens of thousands of requests
But if it's on your you know, like your laptop or your your parents computer or something
It might be might be worth a try they do caution that it's alpha quality software
We don't know how good it is right now
I've only played with it just a little bit but something to watch
Yeah
It's officially being entered into our cool open source projects that we're gonna keep track of
Category that we like to have on this show and now in the category of cool projects
And I think you've had a chance to play with this maybe a little bit too
Deb
Simple get it. It's like dead simple, but it's dead Deb simple and I don't really understand because it's like a repository server for app
So it's like your own local repository server. But does it does it not have packages? Is it is that right?
like it says on here that there's
Something about does not require packages or something. I read this on what the hell is this West? What is it?
What kind is a little confusingly described? So I was in position where I just had some
Programs that I needed to modify then build I was packaging up as Deb files
I really I mean I could just download them and install them but it would be nice to have a little repo
And ideally I'd like this to be minimal effort. It was just for some internal processes, right?
Nothing customer facing and it was a little more work to get set up
I mean like, you know an app a Debbie an arc repo. It's not that complicated
It's mostly just an HTTP server around some special files with metadata that you index the packages and that and that sort of thing
Yeah, so there's like some some app programs out there that'll build that for you access it, but it was a kind of manual
I found a Docker container that was like, all right
Well, you run it this way you SCP the thing and I was just gonna say like there must be a Docker
So they're totally are and that that would have been okay
But that was like really if you were making like you had your dot changes file and you were doing it like you're building like
A source package, you know, and I was really just I just wanted that one artifact
And so this is a little go implementation that provides a HTTP API
So it just makes it super simple if I have a new package, you know
It comes out of my build server Jenkins or something. You just post it over
HTTP post that'll add it to the archive and then BAM
That packages is up there supports multiple versions for packages multiple architectures
And it has it has API key so you can kind of control things as well
So be like well this user can up only this user can update new packages
But other people can get them or more granular than that
I realized the limitation that I was talking about earlier was that it doesn't have the ability to mirror existing repos, right?
So this isn't like a full apt proxy type setup, which I've used before but really isn't what I needed
I just wanted my own little simple local mirror for
And and because it's go it was like go get
Get hub dot blah blah blah and then it was running so it was super easy. Yeah
So there's a project that I'm watching and maybe if anybody in the virtual log there has a suggestion for something else
Feel free to jump in but I'm watching this project called hardened Linux
And it's at hardened Linux gnu. I'm sorry old habit hardened Linux github.io and
They say they're a group of free software enthusiasts anarchists and cybersecurity researchers
Long live anarchy the site reads and long live old school spelt with O's. I think they're being a little tongue-in-cheek there
They it's a small step in security hardening and a giant leap in free and open source software. It's a it's an interesting idea
It's a core infrastructure. So you're familiar with like obviously all the different projects out there to secure your system
So what if you brought them all in one spot?
What if you just brought them all together and tried to make a distro based around that?
It's kind of think what they're going for here
They're all they're also big on on that on a bunch of different open source security projects like PACS and GR security and whatnot
So interesting new initiative. I've always been fascinated with the whole
Like really super ultra secure Linux stuff. I've played in the past lockdown
I've played in the past like there's a I came up as I called Bastille
I can't remember
There's a piece of software you spell to load on Linux that would go through and try to harden it to meet all these
Requirements and so they I think they're either basing around like a Debian a Debian base
I don't know just something I came across this week that I'll be digging into more might have a review down the line
Once I get a chance to check it out and and try it out or or learn more about it
At least I was just just sort of digging around when I came across it this week and thought let's share this with class
It started though in 2014. So it's not like it's brand new. Yeah, the group the group's been together for a while
I don't know
I don't know if they're shipping out code or I don't really what they've got at this point
but something to dig into hardened Linux and one of the things too that I
I used to struggle with was I used to have to be able to show regulators that I was taking steps to
Right meet certain requirements and and so if there's certain things that like you if you can come across
This is a question to the audience
If you know one where you can come across like checklist for how to make how do you make a boon to Linux?
Meet these regulatory requirements. How do you make sent us meet these regulatory requirements or are there distros out there?
Or is something like hardened Linux maybe a project to get us there where it's like you you can start with a Debian base
And we've applied all of these
Security packages are all of these standards
I don't really know quite what's out there these days because I haven't looked for a while
But I've had a few questions come into the show. So I thought I'll open up to the audience
So I this is one thing that I've come across to my research, but I'm curious if anybody else
Has anything I think it's I don't know. I don't know
I don't know if this is even really a project that has much legs anymore
I'm not quite sure but it's there's got to be something out there to meet this particular requirement because I've gotten notes from people
They say well we can't really use Linux because there's no way to prove that we're following this particular standard or
For for you know, whatever the reason is whatever the industry is it changes. Yeah, exactly
Would you so let me ask you this say you were going to play a server?
For a company is there have you ever you ever have you ever worked in a company where they where they say when we deploy
a server you must always configure these things and set these settings and
Turn off these services and install these packages and turn off
The root login on this service like do you do you have you ever worked in a company where there's like a checklist of yes
Oh, yeah, okay, and that's just an internal process that they've developed
Yeah, in a lot of cases that that has been the case and then like these days I see a lot of it done with
Configuration management systems or others like you can run you can have roles or recipes that what defines
What what needs to be changed? Like how do you know?
What to secure how do you know like what services should be configured what way like other than just personal experience and like
You know just learning over the years like how do you know you're actually doing it, right?
you see that's where like we have an issue like hardened Linux or something like
That has like a group of people that are experts in the area that can go through and really come up with a common standard
Of how you secure a system how you make it auditable
That that's something that's a little easier to get more
I think larger buy off like otherwise it seems like to me companies come up with their own
Well, we're gonna configure these things to meet our standards and it's sort of their own internal tribal knowledge that defines what all those things
Should be yeah, I mean, I think there's like, you know
There's some best practice guides and there's some guidance from like the actual requirement
Documentations or like, you know when you get compliance tested or that sort of thing
Yeah, that's usually where some of that will come from
Yeah, right, but if you're not an industry that has compliance testing, but you still want to secure your systems
Yeah, in that case then something like this I think would be
Even if you don't use it
It might be a very handy reference like you might also go look at some of those like cookbooks or other things that see what?
Settings they what changes they're going to make. Yeah, yeah, but you're right that it's not always and then I think there's
Even goes above and beyond where a lot of times like, you know
the the compliance things will be concerned about a fact, you know, like goals and end goals and
Real world things and then that doesn't always necessarily a one-to-one mapping back into how you should configure consistent or which way you should
Configure. Yeah. Yeah, that's the tricky
Monkey come you had something you wanted to add
Well, yeah
I mean every time you do a an audit inside of a banking company that does any kind of financial transactions or has any
any international transactions with banks
They always do those audits where they bring an audit a company in to audit your entire network, and they want you to explain
How you're securing these things exactly. That's what I was trying to say
Yeah, and and they don't you know
It all comes down to having good auditing and good practices inside because even if you're I mean we were running puppet
but then somebody goes and installs a bunch of
applications on a Linux box because they want to be able to debug something and they leave them running and so the scan goes out and
You find all these open ports on a server for something. You didn't even know was running on it. And I mean those are the
I think it all comes down to you know, controlling access to servers
and I if that's what they're doing with a hardened install, I just don't see that working because
Most people don't want to use a custom install for for anything
It's got to be something that uses like Santos or Debian or Ubuntu
It can't be like its own custom role distro because you need a lot of industry industry support
You need folks that can walk in off the street that you've hired that have some built-in knowledge
and you need something that in some industries the auditors can recognize like one of the things that happened to us is a
Couple of times we got pushed away from Linux just simply because it was Gentoo and they didn't know what Gentoo was
They knew what red hat was. This is years ago years ago. And yes, I had Gentoo in production
Yes, I understand but I had a Gentoo system in production. I had many of them and they actually dinged us for it as having
Like this they didn't call it fragmentation at the time, but they dinged us for fragment a fragmented
Network because we had we had Windows boxes
We had SUSE Enterprise boxes, which they understood what that was
We had NetWare and we had Gentoo and it was a lot of systems because we were in the middle of the transition
from NetWare and Windows and
And and so they they come in they're like well
These Gentoo things are some weird thing that somebody sit down some one of your rogue IT people has just installed across your system
and they should be replaced with Windows 2000 using Active Directory and because
That was actually a finding that the auditors recommended
the
The way that what happens is it by the next time the auditors come around you don't have it
That's a big deal
and then if the second time they come around you don't have it you lose your FDIC insurance and then the bank goes out of
Business and so we ended up deploying Active Directory simply as a response to that. Wow
So it's yeah, it was it's really been codified in my memory that sometimes you really got to get that stuff dialed in totally
Well, you know, there's another way to learn more
Linux Academy you go to Linux Academy comm slash unplug. Do you support the show look at idea?
I know right learn more it could be like this little command line tools
You need to learn more or it's the big stuff, you know, like the big stuff like the container stuff. We're talking about
AWS Azure all of that stuff you can learn more at Linux Academy go to Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged and you sign up you support the show and you can get a seven-day free trial. I like this graphic
They have look at this Wes
Doesn't that really tell you the state of Linux in the world today?
You got Linux at the core and then off at the different branches
You've got AWS Azure OpenStack big data containers DevOps the whole category of DevOps
And it really is at the center of it all Linux and open-source technology
Totally and Linux Academy has the entire platter covered you want to go in and get an education buffet Linux Academy Linux Academy comm
Slash unplugged you sign up you support the show you get to learn more community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members
Instructors that actually know the material that can help you
They have systems in place for team training if you want to get your whole team trained up and you can do it all
For seven days absolutely free just go to Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged I like the flashcards because they're focused by the community
I like that they spin up servers when you need them
And you can use SSH to log in the courseware and the servers all match. It's so great. It's so great. Um
Our buddy Michael Dominic. Yeah, just started taking some Linux Academy courses
Yeah, it is it's it is so great for continuing education for challenging yourself for staying up to date on stuff
It's just and it's just so easy right like it's it's modern. It's kept up-to-date by Linux experts people experts in all the fields
That they support and so you just know that you're getting a fresh information that you can count on it makes it super easy
You can you can you can tell the passions there exactly yeah, you can join Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program now mr.
Noah joins us to talk about our next story finally Noah after all these ages
We have a brand new version of grub you ready for this. I'm ready. It's grub 2.02. It's gonna support
Experimental 64-bit extended to support it's gonna support LVM UUIDs
It's gonna have proper handling of LVM in general, which I know you're probably excited about absolutely. Here's the thing I'm excited about
ZFS support
Okay, yeah, and it XFS version 5 support for the version 5 format of exit like talk about checking a couple of my box
Yeah, that is awesome as well as support for LVM raid one so does it support?
defaulting to the LTS kernel so
Okay, so a little revealing here a little behind-the-scenes reveal here
We are we're doing a lot of work here in the studio as we've mentioned and where's that mouse hand me that mouse here
I'll give them there for people watching the video version
I'll give you a little behind-the-scenes shot of what we've been doing here. Yeah, we got a new sky cam with and
so a bunch of new equipment in here and
All Linux based all of it even even this big honking mixer this right here. That's Linux what yeah, this mixer runs
I know
It's really something and in a decade it's taken us, you know
but with the qualities there like everything is like we're it's a no-compromise setup. In fact, it's better than the old setup and
That's great. Yeah, and here's what here's what is is awfully funny about it is all of it comes crashing down
If you accidentally boot the OBS machine with the stock arch kernel and not the LTS kernel
One thing it was like, oh, okay
Well this capture card requires a module and that has to be on the LTS kernel
Oh, well actually and I think actually to begin with we have even one more because we had ZFS and that needed the LTS kernel
So it's like there's all these things that had to have the LTS kernel and then you yeah
We just we didn't even think about it
We just restarted the box and like all of a sudden nothing's working
No, the capture working on the audio stuff's working just set it up. Yeah when we'd restarted it before so we were like
How does that happen? Yeah, it is super funny, right and we sit here. We're scratching our heads
We're like everything was working and we're about to start with Koda radio. It's right. Today is a busy day
We've got Koda radio Linux unplugged and texting up all back-to-back
Yeah, and so there's not a lot of time for things to break and we're like what's going on?
What's going on and we guys sitting over there in the chair he goes
Oh damn it had to take the stream down choose the LTS kernel you removed that option now, right?
Well, we haven't we haven't had time yet
I've been recording show right? That's a time to grub right? It's like maybe there's some new cool features that
Also, you're gonna have some network support in there as well as it really at the boot level and some improved support for core boot, too
Really? Yeah, it's a serious release. So on grub. Like what do you mean by network support? I don't know
I'm really excited about this. I'm really excited about this. I'm really excited about this
What do you mean by network support? I don't know. I'm reading this. I haven't I haven't read past that
I just read that I just read down the line. I hadn't read that far ahead
I was so excited about the LVM and ZFS
You know cool it would be if I could get to a point where I could just be like boot off network
Oh man inside of the grub boot menu. Yeah, that's something to get into right? That is really something to get into
It's however, by the way, if you're ever using arch in production highly recommend the LTS kernel. It's a good way to go
It's good. It's a good combo of
Rolling user LAN software, which is what we needed. Yeah a nice level stability. That's right. That's right
Hey guys, you mind if we do a little gaming update just real quick here on the show
There it is. That's I was gonna say you got to have that. Yeah, I got to have that
this is something that
It's a little bit of a little bit of hoops. You got to jump through to get to this
So I'm gonna warn you right now. You got to buy the Windows version
Yeah, and then you got to sign up for the beta but when you do
Under Linux you will get access
To what looks to me like a very very well done mech game you like mech games, you know
Where you're walking around and like in a huge like mech suit, you know, I'm talking about, you know
I'm talking about guys
this is Dark Horizons mechanized corpse and
Gaming on Linux is got good things to say about it
So it was really good like the way the mech moves it feels really good
Like it really really nailed the feeling of walking around in a giant mech suit now
It's it's not yet out for Linux officially, right? The developer is actively developing this software
And he's just kind of on the side started making a Linux version now
This is why I mentioned it because I think this is the time to show some love just say hey
Yeah, there's an intro. There's an audience here that's interested in this
So if you want to check it out, you first have to get the Dark Horizons mechanized corpse under Windows
Or just buy it through the steam web app
Sign up for the beta or enable beta mode and then you can go into your library and pull down a little
So what happens if you just buy it unlike the web store, yeah, that's what you do, okay
That's that would have to buy it under Windows. No, that's what I mean. Yeah, it's just that the only version
Mm-hmm. Yeah, that's what I do is I would buy it on the web
I would do on the website for sure and then you don't even have to go close to that Windows
Yeah, exactly Noah and I did try while we're in the valve section Noah and I did try to set up a SteamVR
This week. Oh, really and so it's it's hit and miss
So there's really two there's there's a two pronged approach to get SteamVR working under Linux either arch or the second prong is Ubuntu
And in arch it's because all the stuff you well here
Let me back up a little bit. You need to be at least on kernel 410 and
You need to have as of this recording Nvidia driver version 375
Dot-x and it needs to be the Vulcan beta edition of that driver
This is where it gets tricky because both arch and Ubuntu have Nvidia driver 375 as a package name
But it doesn't have the beta Vulcan stuff and it's in the regular repo
So if you just try to install it, that's what you get. So under Ubuntu
You have to go get the Vulcan driver version PPA
Then you have to go into your PPA priorities and you have to pin it above the main repo one
And fight that fight or under arch you have to you have to play dependency hell where there's all these different conflicting dependencies
And then once you even get all that set up
It's basically like hardly anything works. So it was a little disappointing. It was so it's still a work in progress
So we haven't really had a chance to really try it out fully because it's sort of
Yeah, but we continue now. It's like halfway set up for when you know, there's more interesting stuff to talk about
Yeah
I mean
I'm gonna keep working on it because I would like to actually do like a little report on the show and and say this is
How the state of VR under Linux also?
I like just you know, we just want to get I just want to get wimpy's head in a VR headset and have them
See how cool it is. He's such a VR hater, you know, and he's gonna be out here for the Linux fest Northwest rumor has it
So it'd be the perfect opportunity to put his head in a VR headset and get his opinion and because I feel like maybe he
Hasn't really experienced a good VR right because I was a big see here's why I say this
I was like VR smear. Come on. Wake me up and we have holodecks, please
And then I got the oculus and I was like mind blow. Yeah, I had a moment
I had a moment and then ever since then I was all I was all in I thought it was pretty cool
So maybe we'll get a chance to get it working if anybody out there has any experience, please pass it along
Let us know what you dig go to the content we could do we could I tell you what here all the speed technologies to
The rescue if there's anyone out there that thinks I could set it up
Just get in contact with me and I'll get you remote it into that machine
There you go fresh nice fresh 1604 install and you just set it up for us
I'll be your remote hands like I'll plug this stuff in for you. Yeah, totally, you know, whatever
There's got to be somebody out keep on dreaming dude. Keep under maybe though, right? Maybe maybe. All right
That concludes our gaming section. There we go. Wrap it up. Yeah, I gotta wrap up
So anyways, you can find that met game link up in the show notes. This could be good news for all of you
Who are struggling with our org feeds that are under repair right now the mp3?
Technology the licensing program around certain mp3 related patents and software has been terminated
Mmm, isn't it one of them of like the four this would be I think the remaining and the reason why I say this is
On the front har website like the actual like patent holders of mp3. I have a post on their website
Basically saying have at it
Really? Okay
They say we thank all of our licensees for their great support for making mp3 the de facto audio codec in the world during the past
Two decades the development they go into the development of mp3
But yeah, they say
They say that essentially mp3 is still very popular
However, most state-of-the-art media services such as streaming or TV and radio broadcasting use modern ISO MPEG codecs such as AAC or MPEG
H and that's what we're making our money. Yeah, and they make higher quality at much lower bit rates
And then they link you to the successful history of mp3 like they're done with it. Here's the history if you want to read about it
Yeah, they say the the the Technicolor mp3 licensing program for certain mp3 related patents and software for Technicolor and Fraunhauer IIS has been terminated
Hmm. I was thinking it doesn't mean it's now
I think this means it's free as in speech and it's freezing beer, but it's not like free like as in GPL code, right?
Yeah, I don't think it's yeah, it's definitely probably not GPL code
But I was under the impression that we still had some limitations on mp3 due to some existing patents. I could be wrong
Well, it's definitely not like just free code
But I think it means it's legit to I think it means it's safe now to redistribute it like straight up one. Yeah
Okay, that's a big deal today. I learned monkey calm
You want to do a follow-up on a discussion that Noah and Ryan had a few weeks ago. It looks like go ahead
Yeah, so I just installed the pop theme. Oh, yeah
Yeah, this is 76 GTK theme. What do you think a pop? Oh, it's freaking awesome
I mean, I know they're just starting out with it. But if this is what the next few years it's gonna handle for that. I
Mean it's they're doing it. They're doing it right. They're gonna get their users
Exactly what they need to have to make gnome a wonderful experience in Ubuntu now
What are they now? Did you also replicate the bar at the bottom like the OMG Ubuntu screenshot has?
No, no, I did mine on the side
You can play around with it, but just the theme itself
I mean, it's known so you can do whatever you want with it
But the theme itself is just really clean all the the icons pop everything looks good. And when you bring up Windows it just
They're making they're laying the groundwork so that when their users have it
They can use the system 76 theme and it just everything looks the way it's supposed to there's no hidden
Weirdness and they're gonna back it. That's the greatest thing about it. Yeah. Yeah, it is very bright
And some areas like the like they have the gnome tweak tool up and the like the remove buttons and the orange checkboxes
I feel like they're hitting me in the face a little bit
But I I also I like I like the shade of color they've chosen there. So it's I don't know
There's a theme. I think it's a great theme. Here's my question you start out on that and then you go to a
generic install
You know the nice thing about system 76 in the past has been you know
If I start if I bought a system 76 machine there might be a couple little tweaks like they turned off like, you know
The the auto logging privacy stuff. They'd shut a couple of those things up
But it the the system wasn't didn't look drastically different if I sat down at an Ubuntu machine
I knew I was sitting at an Ubuntu machine and
I feel like depending on how far they take this especially if it starts getting into the point where they start they put in
A dock or something like that, you know, does that does that then change that?
Essentially, I guess what I'm asking is have they just have they just forked the the time when we all just finally got settled on
A given desktop, right? When you say for it, you mean like the user experience in a sense, right? Yeah
Yeah
yeah, but I think we're talking apples and oranges there because conical supported the unity and
I know gnome has its own support structure, but there's not a commercial company behind them saying, you know
Do we this is what we're going to do? Well, I think system 76 does as a vendor
I don't think you just say here's my desktop whatever they do flies and I'll be okay with whatever they choose next year
Yeah, I think yeah
I'm of two minds of this because my first thought is well, where do you draw the line because I've I've
You know
I've had I've had a big revelation recently about gnome extensions that I'd like to share with the class here in a second
But before I so before I before I defend them
I'll raise you my concern and my concern would be is what we end up with is essentially the
Bastardization that's happened to Android where you've got Samsung skin. You've got LG skin
You've got a moto skin and some vendors have a light skin
Some vendors have an entirely different UI with their own applications on top and it's a real shit show and what everybody pines for is
Just a good clean
Regular Android experience and that's why West has a pixel right there, right? That's where that's that's the market spoke
He said we don't want your customizations. We don't want your cut
We know you think you can add value
But the problem is you can't keep up with the pace of rapid development, right now
Gnome is not Android. Gnome is not developed or modified nearly at the rate that Android is and I gnome is a
product and project of limited means and limited resources and so it's within that context that I look at what system 76 is doing
Not at the so not not
Comparing what they've done to like what Android has done or what other desktops like, you know
Cuz you could also say the same thing about we all know there's some Windows OEMs out there that have just crapped up Windows with
Their own start menu Lenovo and their own their own updaters and they just junked up Windows and nobody wants that either
So there's definitely a risk of that
The thing about gnome though is while it's a great desktop and I just recently switched back to it really enjoying it
Stays out of your way very efficient, but it's not enough
It just the thing is you have to have extensions with gnome
Because the team just doesn't have the time or resource to add everything that everybody wants in an entire world full of geeks and adding
To that what everyone wants is different with every person and you know, you look at the last few releases of gnome solid incremental improvement
But no moving of the gas pedal nothing that's freaking people out no big changes
And so there's there's really no massive progress that system 76 gonna fall behind by shipping their own theme
The risk of divergent user experiences is there. Mm-hmm
And that's I think we just have to wait and see how that plays out
But I think because because of what the reality of gnome is there is room for a vendor to improve on it
But they just can't go too far
And so system 76 like has to walk like this
They are not only gonna kind of create the line they have to walk but then they have to walk it like super tight and then
We're all gonna have the advantage of sitting back and go. Well, they did a good job or they didn't yeah
I don't know. I'm I so I share your reservations, but I almost feel like there's no path forward
Yeah, well the path for an alternative path forward might be we say we go to the gnome team
We say here are the things that we think that would really improve this experience. What do you think about it?
And then, you know collectively everyone that's all that's using gnome
Everyone that makes those decisions looks at it says yeah, we agreed that would be a you know
A way forward and then and then now we've improved it not just for system 76 customers
But for everyone that's using no, I feel like it took him forever just to get wadi updated like it was
Yeah, and I'm like, why do you guys care so much about the rounded corners of your menu?
But you don't care that your default theme looks like garbage like how does that work?
Mm-hmm, and I think their stance, you know what I thought I thought about their stance as well
The themes can be changed and that's why we build it this way
And so they're like building the core of what you need with the expectation part of me. I gotta be honest guys. I
Really hope that Ubuntu does not ship stock gnome in some ways because it's not that great. Yeah
It's really not that like there's not needs a spit shine right on a little bit
Yeah, like it needs a couple of things fixed up
But it you know, that wouldn't kill you to set a decent default background
It wouldn't kill you to turn on one or two extensions
You know really you whatever whatever you got done just in about five minutes of goofing around with numb the thing is what you got
To pretty quickly and you said it best
You just said it's pro you go from what looks like a hack on
Linux what everyone thinks of is like a Linux graphical desktop and you turn it into a
Professional broadcast machine just by tweaking a couple of a little like things, right?
Like the dark menus and the dark windows and the in the smaller window borders and stuff like that
It just makes for a much more pleasing desktop
Yeah, I think if they just even I agree like if they check if gnome if gnome adopted a default theme of like arc or even
Numix or something like that, then I feel like we'd have a totally different conversation then I'd be like
Now I feel like system 76 is just trying to differentiate and you know make themselves, you know brand their desktop
Right, but right now as it stands, I feel like they don't really have a choice
I mean they almost have to in some interesting to see what it would take to get them to change things like the default theme
That's not very good. I
Don't know why it took them so long to begin with. Yeah
So we're gonna have a conversation about laptops here in a little bit
In fact, we had a question that came into the show about the setup you did on the Macbook
2013 so I thought we would get to that in a little bit
I also thought maybe we in the context that we could talk about Windows S and
Microsoft's attack on Chromebooks and all of that. So we have a lot to get plus we still have Linux fest stuff
So let's stop and thank digital ocean for a moment digital ocean comm you go over there use the promo code
Do unplugged one word lowercase you apply that to your account after you've created it and then you get a $10 credit
You know, they're so you don't have they introduced high-memory droplets. You can get like over 220 gigs of RAM
They got block storage
You can attach you can attach like just a block device with a bitsy bitsy tight little bit of storage up to 16 terabytes of SSD
Storage now they're introducing it's in you can request early access right now. It's not finished but
high CPU droplets like
Maximum consistently fast lots of core big boy CPUs like there are some big compute jobs going down
DigitalOcean.com now if you're like me you just want to run a next cloud instance
It's great for that too
In fact, you can get started at $5 a month and you get a machine with 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one
CPU a terabyte of transfer and all of the storage is SSDs all of it runs on KVM for the virtualizer Linux for the hyper
Yeah Linux for the host hypervisor. It's got 40 gigabit e connections into the data center right up to the VMs each VM
I mean we're talking can you imagine that I would love to see them
They actually have some pictures on their Instagram feed and it looks super
Whole thing just the whole thing. Yeah, it's it's so nice. I love I love DigitalOcean's interface too because it makes managing all this easy
We all know how to use it. It's straightforward. And then when we're done setting everything up
we just plug it up to the API and just
Push a few buttons tell the bots what to do after that
Just yell at the bots DigitalOcean.com use the promo code DO unplugged check them out
And also when you're there and you've got a machine set up and you want to do a little more with it
Take advantage of their really great documentation. They have I
Have a tutorial on Grey Log for Ubuntu 1604
They just posted seven days ago very very useful and also a tutorial on how to use the Python debugger
hosting multiple websites with nginx and HAProxy using LXD setting up
Yeah, I know setting up Debian setting up CentOS setting up webman
Lots of tutorials lots of open source projects to take advantage of your droplet once you have it going for experts or total beginners
Trust me, you can make it work go to DigitalOcean.com sign up and then apply our promo code DO unplugged
And a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the unplugged program
So today Microsoft announced Windows 10 s it's not a joke
It is a simplified Windows Store only version of Windows for schools
The s stands for streamlined and performance guys
So jank
But this seems to be actually sort of exactly what valve was worried about why we got steam machines to begin with was this eventual?
Windows Store only
Closed down nature even though the you know
And I thought I thought when the Windows Store failed and that nobody bought stuff there that they wouldn't do this
But even despite the failure, this is what's so incredible about these rich corporations that can just burn cash doesn't matter
It doesn't matter like it. Oh, yeah, our stores been a total failure
Okay
The vision
Keeping the vision and they say that do you get better battery life when you can only run store apps that you don't have weird
Stuff updating in the background. They say it's better security
It's best for schools and they're gonna pair this with some of their hardware partners
They're gonna sell computers running Windows 10 s for 190 bucks
They have to they have to do this right because if they don't do this they are going to get overrun by Google and Chromebooks
Yeah, I'm gonna get over there as a raspberry pies and in Debian
They're gonna get overrun by all of the other all of the other hardware and software
Combinations that exist out there that don't require Microsoft Microsoft's licensing model
And and if they open it up and let people use apps
Then people would be running Windows these Windows s books with OBS and learning how to broadcast and they would be running open office or Google
Docs, so the only way they can prevent that is to force them to buy their applications through their store for their Windows book
That is specifically designed for education. It's really it's kind of a sad thing. Hmm. What do you think Wes?
I mean, it does seem like they kind of they have to do this
I imagine you can you know also sell the the schools on office 365 educational editions or whatever
So it is, you know you you get them in your platform and I do see I mean, it's it's kind of like iOS
I do see something like well, right
There may be some auditing capabilities of Windows Store apps other things. It may be a lower maintenance burden for IT staff
That's possible. I don't know for sure. I wouldn't
Having used Google Apps
You can drill down the management of Chromebooks like you would not believe down to down to what what what?
Icons are available on the Chromebook itself. So can that person go to this given site?
Can they click on this given link? Can they run this given application?
Application, you know down to that. So is there like a potential opportunity for Linux or for yeah
I guess we're like for regular Linux here in that will this make Windows more associated with this limited thing with well
See, here's my worry is it's a it's it's first of all
Probably not gonna be a lot of open source applications in the Windows Store, right?
So probably not gonna be getting GIMP in the in the Windows Store, right?
You're probably not getting Inkscape which would be great tools for schools, right just as an example
So on the low end you've got so much momentum around
Microsoft OEMs active directory Windows management that I could see it doing some serious actual credible damage to even
People that might be putting Ubuntu on library machines
So I'm worried on the low end that it's gonna eat away and then on the high end
They're also doing something else. So it's like a two-pronged approach on the high end
They have the thousand dollar surface laptop now, which is like their new developer machine
They got a big fancy video, but look at the verge and Microsoft has created a real laptop this time
So this is the surface book laptop and one of the things Microsoft's done with this sucker is its cloth on the inside
So they've and they've laser cut out the keys like they've yeah, they've really got they have a pixel sense
Super high resolution 1080p display on the thing. It's light as hell
It doesn't have any ports which seems to be what everybody actually has a couple ports
But you you get my drift. It has like one USB port one mini port dongles. It's got yeah, you gotta have dongles
So what are the chances I can run Linux on that weird cloth bad boy? I don't know honestly probably pretty good
I have an amazing luck running Linux on Microsoft. You try it. You try it. Oh nice. You try it
I feel like I don't want to give Microsoft any money
But I feel like it's gonna be a little bit before it's working but so they got a high-end thing here
They got you know, this is obviously going after your XPS 13. Yeah, you know those kinds of machines your Lenovo's
You're at your galago pros and they're claiming
14.5 hours of battery life if you use Windows S
It'll be great for all those VB developers. Yeah, right and they have integrated a vapor chamber into the aluminum chossy to
Give it better cooling out the rear standard for $9.99 is a core i5 version with 4 gigabytes of RAM
128 gigabyte SSD and it's gonna start shipping June 15th. Nice
4 gigs of RAM. Yeah, that's just that's unbelievably low. Yeah, but 999
So, you know when you get the $2,500 version will be everything you need
So they got you got this two-pronged approach. You've got you've got them going after Chromebooks and students
Oh also, I should have mentioned this Windows S Windows 10 s free for students and teachers
So that coming, you know all that coming have at it though
And I'll tell you what here's I made this prediction on ask no one you're actually seeing the start of it come up
You are gonna see Microsoft pivot to software as a service
And so they they'll give you the student and teacher version for free
And then once you go to the pro version, they're not gonna sell it to you
They'll just it'll be $39 a year
That's coming. It's not we've already seen it start with the high Cal license seats stuff is all subscription based now
so I mean it's
And that's a bad boat for everyone to be in because that's how I feel because here's the thing what you're gonna wind up with dumping
On the market to you're going to wind up with a bunch of people that get sucked in on a free thing before they can
Actually ever do anything interesting with it. They're going to have to pay a ransom fee. Yeah
So and Microsoft that's how Microsoft plans to stay in business
Because they have to sell something and nobody's buying Windows
so
Mumble room anyone there have any thoughts on how free Windows is going to affect student and teacher adoption of Linux
What do you think monkey? I don't think it's gonna affect it. I
Just got I'm working with a school right now and the conversation is how do we get away from Windows and all of their?
requirements just for doing business with them, it's not an
with can you elaborate
well with
With Google, it's a web interface you log in and you basically manage everything remotely. You don't have any
infrastructure requirements
Secretary at the front desk could set up a student where?
With Microsoft, it's not like that. It's just that they're they're they're barrier for entry is a lot higher, especially for small private schools and
That's something that you see a lot with these guys this is Microsoft comes in and they offer a lot of free stuff
But it's not free because you still got to buy the hardware. You still got to buy the infrastructure
And they're getting away they have a bunch of Macs that were donated to them
but they're having to get away from Mac because they put Apple TVs in every office and they and they
Plugged them in so that the teachers could present their take their iPads
Oh really put presentations up and it completely destroyed their entire network because of all the Apple talk and the broadcasts and it
Yeah, the DNS just killed everything Larry's and but see that's how that's how these guys do it is they
They're not delivering a complete solution. Yeah, they're delivering just one component of it
And that's why I don't think that Microsoft is gonna take off as in the schools unless you have a vendor who's
Developing the whole solution and walking in there with a Microsoft solution, right? Right. Okay, that's fair
So I see come more people. So I wanted to go to arm one
He says not much Linux and UK schools to begin with go ahead arm
A lot of the schools in the UK are buying into the Microsoft stuff because of all the office 365
Oh, yeah, so that you can link all schools together and you can easily talk between teachers. What about Chromebooks?
Not much
Well, I've worked at a few schools and never seen one in a school
I mean the last school I worked at they were starting to go all-in on
like just getting dumb iPod the very basic iPods just to use as a it's like just an interface for
Smart boards and things that finding that I was cheaper than doing it any other ways, but you very rarely see like classes of
laptops in UK school sometimes but the school I were for if you know if I want to use laptops
We might have three sets of laptops for the entire school and then you've got you've got a book about whenever you want
Yeah, so you that's interesting interesting dynamic from the u.s. Because in the u.s. Chromebooks are like highly prevalent
Yeah, we just have hearts of them. Mm-hmm. Yeah. No, I mean you go into
You know you go into some of like the PC world see it and this may be maybe for
Old Chromebooks tucked into a back corner. Most people don't even know what they are how they work
and
As far as schools guy, I was having a conversation with our IT guy and saying, you know
He was saying that their head of IT with was looking at maybe Google classroom and stuff
But no one's really got the time to look into what it is and how it works and then Microsoft is saying, you know
I'll take more of our free stuff and we've made this new Microsoft team speak
Bulls, you know just utter crap for that replaces this thing, but we're not going to turn that old service off
So now you've got you've got SharePoint and you've got 365 and you've got this and you've got that and you've got and none of the
Teachers know what the hell is
All right. Hmm. That is very good insight. Thank you very much
I that's good to hear is just even for another perspective Swift
You kind of are on my train of thinking where I'm like, well crap
Is this another market opportunity that Linux could be about to miss out on if Microsoft can come along all of a sudden and offer?
Windows machines for 180 bucks 190 bucks all of a sudden the entire rules have changed. What do you think?
Do you think this is yet another maybe?
Opportunity slipping between our fingers
Yes, I really do. I mean Linux has been around for a long time
I mean we get to the point like with with Vista missed opportunity
We got eight missed opportunity. We got ten again missed opportunity. When are we gonna have our stuff together?
So that we can really compete with the other stuff that's out here
I'm tired of these people with their shiny little Macs and they're pretty little little computers
Just use Linux for crying out loud and do what you got to do and stop paying all this money for the stupid crap that
We just don't have to do like our turn. It's our turn
Aren't you supposed to be giving up already? Give up on this market. Damn it
I'm with you man. I'm with you
I my only my only thought on it is you know
There is such a there can be in some of the schools not always but there can be a tinkering element and that tinkering
element often leads to Linux and open source and right it's it there's something about open source and maybe even canoe and and the
GPL in particular that
Feels very in line with sort of the core principles of continuing education or fundamental education
Like there's something about it that feels like a really organic fit and there's something about
Licensing and proprietary software that to me has the feeling of walling off knowledge and holding not holding knowledge
Whereas open source is about learning and sharing and improving which is what education should be about too
So it doesn't limit exploration creativity. You can do whatever you want with it
So there is like to me it feels like a really fundamental
Fit that is almost long-term too hard to deny
But there's also practical commercial budgetary things that are very real in schools, too. So you just I
Don't know. We'll see where it goes
You know
I remember when Windows 10 was about to be released and the tech press was so
Stinking positive and if you guys recall
Windows 10 was given away to everybody for free initially. Well in their defense
Windows 10 was a drastic improvement over Windows 8
They had a reason to because after Windows 8 it was like met geez the DOS would be an improvement, you know
Yeah, yeah, I guess well both of them you can only have the one app open at the time so
All right. Do you think we should make a video to sell it to like pitch it to the people?
That'd be good. That'd be a good Noah. That'd be a good Noah video. Like oh, yeah
Yes, what AltaSpeed should get into is the education market. Oh, yeah, maybe although that's pretty budget constrained
But I imagine hospitality is too. Yeah. Yes
So, I don't know. I mean once you get in there like you can you know
if you get a right school you can I some of the fun some funnest work I did in some ways was at schools just
Because there isn't the that quite quite the like we have this site has to go live on Monday morning
So we can start taking orders kind of pressure. Yeah, that's not there
But it's still if we need to do a good job
But it's not going to be in the end of anyone's careers if this goes south either
That's a nice environment even if it's budget constrained because you still get a little creative
Linux is a good fix for a lot of that stuff
But there's still scale that you get to play with and there's you know
Really busy hours and there's privacy that you have to take into consideration
So it's still it's still a very challenging and interesting environment to work in
So yeah, I'd be at the end of day you're helping kids like that's that's great
Yeah, so as long as you just give me a little off the top for that recommendation
I think you should totally get into it now. Yeah
Send all support to crazy Jupiter broadcasting.com. Does that work like that? Does it work? Oh, okay three-year SLA
Three years have you ever emailed that man?
You
Know what that is not it is I have actually gotten to emails like they're three years old
I've been like hey, thanks for email, and I'm sorry. I just got to this it came up on a search
And yeah, I've done that before
Boy, when I once I went once I left for Texas the inbox just kind of went yeah
Well, you didn't have many before that so I can understand how they drastically changed your outlook
You know what I got to do is I got to get a really good email program on my phone
Have you seen some of these like there's Google inbox. That's not bad
Yeah
You do I'm a really big fan. I just started using a new one. It's called because you were
Before you were using one that I'd like canine canine. Yeah, yeah now
I'm on a program called blue male, and we have a blue man by far my favorite thing about it
is I can swipe left and mark it as later or done and
That allows me to to archive that message and then come back like that's a task. Yeah, I like blue male
Yeah, yeah, the task angle is is a nice man. Yeah, what I'm using a lot on inbox
I'm Felix. I feel like I'm already using gmail, so it's not like I'm right. It's just a layer on top
Yeah
I like the remind me about this at this day at this time feature because it's like okay
I I have certain days that I deal with this kind of work and so I'm gonna set it for a minder on that day
An inbox you can use with other mail service for us cuz I'm on a fast new new new no
That's why I really like about blue males. Yeah, I use it with fast mail
You don't have to have all the privacy stealing compromises of Gmail right right you know
You know speaking of mobile phones ting. That's what you do
You go there get a deal go to linux.ting.com get $25 off one of these phones
You want to get a new mail app on your phone first got to start with a phone?
That's math guys
That's that is phone math linux.ting.com is where you go if you have a compatible phone
And you just might they got CDMA and GSM
Then you'll get $25 in service credits you bring it over to their
BYOD page you look at all the dirty details, and they'll tell you if it's gonna work on ting or
Or take a shortcut
Call up ting and talk to a real human being and just ask them
They'd be more than happy to work with you the fact that they have CDMA or GSM is big for me, too
If you go on road trips like I do or you travel every now and then huge or heck
You're just gonna move and you don't know what the cell service is gonna be like right go with ting
Yeah, or you know just have fun and experiment like if you get like a Nexus device
I've in the past just let's let's go to an area and I'll activate this one
And then I'll put it in and then I have the other one active and I just switch between them
And you know it's a little bit of hassle, but not bad and on the newer devices
It's even easier and just do a speed test. I offered to give a wimpy a timsling. Oh really yeah for what he's out here
Yeah, he has global roaming, so he doesn't need it, but I was like hey
Hey coming to the US do you need a SIM card cuz I can hook you up, bro
I could hook you up
That's awesome, dude
And they have a really great control panel to the let's you manage all aspects of your account set limits alerts turn things off
So like right now not driving to Texas don't need my team if I on it's great
You know and the other thing is even if I left it on it's six dollars a month for the line
That's it those are the kind of things that are other providers that feel like you're like breaking a rule or doing something shady
But I think they're like no that this is your plan your minutes like just use them when you or you know feeling bad for
Having like a $30 a month device in your not use yeah, but if routine it's six bucks
And then it's just when you use it you pay for the usage just minutes message in megabytes and whatever you use
That's what you pay and six dollars for the line is so simple so straightforward bring a device buy one from ting
They don't care just try them out. They also have a calculator
You can see how much you would save and a blog that's full of good tips even if you're not yet a ting customer
Just go to linux dot ting dot com linux dot ting dot com and a big
Thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program
Big event coming up, and this is almost the perfect representation of how this event works
This know what do you agree if you disagree? I'm sure you'll speak up
me
Really next fest Northwest has the possibility of becoming the largest community organized event in the United States yes
and I
Love these guys, but they really got some problems still right now their websites down. They got a Drupal issue
It looks like they're my SQL server is down
They have issues on the website. They say still on the website say it's gonna be announcing their schedule in the coming weeks now
I'm not saying any of this to criticize. I am pointing out that this is truly a lug run event
It is like an event of the people and there's certain things
They're stronger at right like putting on a hell of a good event, and there's certain things
They're not so strong at like planning a whole bit of it. Yeah
Love about it, dude. We not polished. It's not I mean, but it but it works right as we know it's gonna happen
We're gonna be there, and it's gonna be awesome being in contact. You know from the broadcasting side
We get a lot of behind-the-scenes things that you know we don't necessarily share with a lot of other people and
basically all suffice to say that a lot of things in the Linux landscape are changing a little bit and there is a
Opportunity here for Linux fest to become the Linux fest to go to
So if we could get some of these issues worked out
That'd be really great because and even if they don't work them out to be honest with you. Just show up
That's my answer people ask me. They're like I couldn't register because the just show up
Oh, yeah
Just show up if you if you have trouble just show up and if you if anyone gives you if anyone gives you know
You will not be turned away. You know the sites back up now
So maybe that's good you know, but I've heard
They're getting a lot of traffic
Maybe that's it maybe they're getting you know and they just have it on some like in a little server
And now it's getting a bunch of traffic office
I wouldn't put it past these guys to be running this on about Raspberry Pi
No, there's a kind of thing they would do totally the slackware server x486 there crashed
We bought a restart there was a time there would so you know it's May 6th and 7th
we're gonna be streaming it live at jblive.tv if you want to check it out and
It also be where we record the last Linux action show. Mm-hmm. Wow. Wow, that's crazy. That's wow end of an era
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, and then almost immediately we launched into whole new projects user air comes back the Linux action news show
It's gonna be big Joe and I are getting really ready. We're going through final things now on the show so exciting
Yeah, it is. It is really it is really fun
It's been a long time since I've done something like this and I think it's gonna be a big big hit
I hope I hope people like it. We'll see maybe they'll hate it
I don't know. Well, you'll get some of both. That's just a guarantee. Yeah. Yeah, and then I'll just switch to vlogging full-time
Anyway, so when you have time to edit as yeah as is always as is always the case when the Linux fest is near
We like to punish ourselves. We like to punish our bodies. We like to punish our mental spirit stomachs
We like to punish. Yes, we definitely punish our stomachs and we punish equipment too, by the way, Wes
Sorry, you may have bad lighting for text now
Yeah
Yeah, we have that why you look so good on Sunday. Yeah, we did
We actually did not have the right lighting on Sunday either. So since last Friday
Well, yeah since last Friday Todd has it only been a week. We've been basically so much longer than who he said not
Yeah, not even no, but it's been the Friday before last right? Oh, yeah, that's right. Okay, that feels better. Yeah the Friday before last
It's been a lot of work. We started we ripped out everything in the studio pulled out every single wire
Every everything we were down to the four walls in the ceiling for a while. Yeah, boy, and then we've been
And that was the last time a Mac was in here
And it's just ever knows. Those were the first two things I took out
Like literally I unplugged it carried it out and I was like, okay now we can go with the rest
Just set it in the backyard. Let it graze. I
Was actually nice to it stay on target
Stay on target. No, then we we rebuilt
with a with around around a couple of core ideas
we rebuilt with the idea of
Supporting the production of the new shows and now the existing shows we have so this studio was built for a different set of requirements
And now we essentially rebuilt the studio for the new set of requirements
So that was the first thing then the second thing we built it around was all Linux. So everything's Linux
Even down to our mixer, which is Linux
We we put everything everything around that and then of course, that's really the third thing because the mixer is so huge
which is not a final mixer, but
It's all kind of built around that so we've we've we've made a lot of changes
We've made I can't I can't show it on camera, but we've made additional room for guests
So we'll be able to have guests in studio mic'd up be able to hear everybody. It's way more like clean and efficient
Yeah, it's lots more
My favorite part of the whole studio renovation is after ten years Chris finally found where he wanted his microphone. Yeah
Yeah, actually he's not kidding. So for the first time in ten years really eleven years of brought actually twelve years because I
Before Jupiter broadcasting I had a couple of things
I could never ever every time you buy a microphone stand on a boom stand
It comes with a desk lamp and something that you can drill into your desk
Mm-hmm, and I've never been able to commit to it because you know when video production like I some I'm moving stuff around all the time
And you're almost for every shoot like I have a dive a laptop this time this next time
I'm doing a capture the next time it's two people and so you just can't be static and you can't just lock things down
And so did we or did we not just nail the position of that finally after ten years?
I found the perfect spot. No, I got it drilled there drilled it in my hand actually
with his brown bear muscles and
And then we finally actually mounted a a microphone to the table. It's fixed in place. You can move around. It's great
It's on it. It's on a gesticulating arm. I
Enjoy
So it's an almost perfect position we've got a touchscreen over here for something I'm about to talk about
The all of this is it's really built around now making higher quality productions better better than ever
Wes is at least I hope but to my to my left here. We're running something called caster soundboard
It was a project that was created for a juke for Jupiter broadcasting by a coda radio listener caster soundboard is
Sort of a recreation of proprietary software that's available for macOS to do a production soundboard, you know, we're like we
Fire off sounds like that. This is written in c++ and q5. It's GPL
It's up on github you go to github.com slash Jupiter broadcasting to see it and
It's really close to being perfect
It just needs a few tweaks and we have open issues for what needs to be fixed and we're hoping
We're hoping maybe folks in the community would be willing to work with
That yeah, so I don't know if it shows up on the webcam here
So for those of you watching the video over here, we have a this is a 1080p
21 inch Dell touchscreen monitor and I can I can try you want me to try it?
We have one clip in there
This is this is from the open source soundboard running on Linux using a touchscreen and it's got a little button right there
But let's see. That's dark dirt dirt. Did you not hook up the USB port? Never mind?
No, it is no it is fast looking up the
USB card I was I jumped ahead. But anyways, isn't that look great Wes like from what you know
You've seen my past soundboard setup. This is this is it right here. This is a this is a dedicated soundboard setup
It's got multiple tabs. It's all written and cute. It's essentially touchable. It's not perfect, but it's touchable
Oh, it's muted. There we go. This is from this is it right here
And one of the things that's really nice is every button is triggerable by a keyboard
But what I'd also like is I'd like each tile to be pressable and playable. I'd like it to be
And if the volume slider was a little bit bigger, I'd be able to slide volume and stuff like that
So it's really really close. We don't have the ability currently to save or export soundboard
So if the application closes you lose the entire soundboard, so there's details in there that here's your principal
Here's how here's how here's how he prompts work out of me. This is how he gets free labor
He just he's like a soundboard up yet. I'm like, yeah, you know
Close but he's like, well, I could get a dungu and a MacBook. Go get the MacBook in here
Come on no, you don't want a Mac in here do you?
So we find a developer we're like, yeah
But if there's anyone out there that wants to work on this do we have links in the coder radio show notes?
Yeah, I'll put them in here too. Yeah, and it's you can also just find it
We have it pinned at the top of github.com slash Jupiter broadcasting. Sweet. Yeah, it'd be really because oh, here's the thing Noah
tell me the thing is
there's a few open source projects that we've now been involved with like show bot and a
Couple other things like pod publish and whatnot that I think we can help out and we can you know
And people have like there's like many podcasts now that use some of the stuff
We've written a j-bot sure and they have their own title
Suggestion systems and all that kind of stuff and it's helped podcasters
Mm-hmm, and I think this is another one because it there's nothing that says it has to run on Linux
I mean, that's what we're using it for but other but if it's just an open source soundboard
I think that'd be useful for people in general not just Linux users. Yeah, it could be a very big
No, actually, I would not mind if nobody ever bothered to fork it outside of Linux and we just and that became
Like you want the world's best podcasting sound where you're gonna run Linux. Yeah, maybe yeah, maybe we could get there
I'm not the thing just be and stand on but could just be an AUR or flat pack away or maybe a snap package one day
Either way, if you if you'd like to help us boy
Would we appreciate it because it would basically improve all of the Jupiter broadcasting shows and it's really the last thing that the Mac's better
At in here like I can objectively say in my opinion everything else in here that we've replaced with
Amazing is the only thing the Mac can do is play random clips, isn't that stupid?
But I mean in terms of what you actually say it all out
Yeah, I kind of but if you actually had you ever done it as a living and used to use a soundboard before you understand
It is a very piece important piece of equipment because it's not just about playing stupid noises
It's also how the music's done in the show right intros outro. Yeah, like it's it's actually a pretty critical piece of equipment
So you want it to work right and right objectively?
It's the only piece of software slash equipment that we've replaced that is a very much a downgrade
Everything else has been an upgrade in terms of performance reliability functionality
All of it and then obviously the fact that it's free and open source
Yeah, this would be the one thing that is not quite there
But it's so I'd say it's like 60% of the way
I think it's like 60% of the way and what's amazing is it was put together by you remember the community member guy that he
Was Xerox was it Xerox? No, no, he's the guy that may be working up, but it started with a C
Yeah, I wish I hadn't but anyways, he was so super cool worked with me before and we kind of a couple people work on
We also had a web-based one that was worked on this
We really like this one because we have the touchscreen here. Yeah, you can you can just see looking at that how useful that would be
So yeah
Caster soundboard and when we get it done, it could be something that takes off wouldn't just be for podcasting either
Mm-hmm. Could just be fun to have a soundboard
What you want to go we should probably get going in a little bit
But I wanted to talk a little about laptops and battery life
Yeah, so why don't we start with a question that came into the subreddit by a pursue doof?
I think is he had a question about the setup on the MacBook
Running Linux arts Linux on the 2013 MacBook and I said, you know, essentially system
D boot was what was used to do the boot management. I use the built-in you if I manager the Mac has when you hold
Down the option key to get to that point
and the Linux dash MacBook package from the AUR were some of the bigger like
Important components and so he followed up with a couple of specific questions, and I thought maybe I'd talk to you
He said as you know
Do we see of a way to switch between the integrated Intel GPU and the dedicated Nvidia because I think the way we did my config
Was just dedicated Nvidia all the time. I think that's right
Yeah, so that was one thing he wanted something on so I don't know if we have that don't know that that's worth looking into
You though and then he also and this is one I will toss out to the audience if yet
If you what would you guys do for snapshots?
Would you go with LVM? Would you do ZFS?
Would you do butter FS clonezilla if you want to do snapshots of your system?
My personal take would be clonezilla, but did you have any I would do clonezilla? Yeah. I mean, I guess it depends on how
How frequently what kind of downtime are you willing to support?
What what is your use case and how comfortable are you experimenting if you're okay with LVM?
I think LVM snapshots have gotten a lot better in recent years
If you're okay
If you're already experienced with ZFS then just do that because you'll have a great time with it if you know how to use it
Administer it if not then definitely don't do that and yeah, maybe clonezilla or something where sure you it's not as frequent
It's not like just instant, but you know it's reliable understandable thing
I like about the thing I like about clonzilla is I can store it totally off the machine
To receive I mean yeah, oh yeah, you could do that. Yeah, I would say this though. I
Was also of the mindset that I better have snapshots for this MacBook because I know it's gonna break on me
Just like the pseudo devs just thinking of and it really has been fine. I've done many kernel updates
I think I even I even did an like a complete OS upgrade to Final Cut OS Sierra
And I think it's nothing was affected like I just hold down the option key and choose Linux, and it's just fine
It's great. Yeah, so I I found it to be pretty reliable
I was surprised how reliable it was on there
So you might just give it a go, but I did notice one thing that's definite
It's obvious that the battery life under Final Cut OS
when not editing is superior to just Linux you know just say you're browsing the web and
And Final Cut OS is gonna switch between the Intel and video graphics whereas Linux is always on the Nvidia graphics
right, but the battery life difference is like
Seven and a half hours to an hour and a half to two hours like it's a huge matter
It is a big difference
And I I don't know what is going on with Linux battery life right now because across all my laptops
It's not really where it should be it's not that bad. That's the worst but across all of them
Mmm. It seems like it's have you noticed this have you have you struggled with this?
I know you were saying a co-worker struggled with this recently yeah, you know I did
I did know someone in my life who you know he's done Linux stuff for a long a long time
He uses it at work
You know very good on the command line had no he's like hadn't dabbled that much in the desktop side of Linux
And so he you know got himself a new laptop. I'm not sure which one
Installed the latest Ubuntu on it and just had a hell of a time
You know getting anything like decent bad, but I don't think he did any configuration
But just running out of the gate you know he installed it kind of got us up and running boom batteries dead
Which is not a great first run experience, and he'd already you know when he came with Windows
And we just ran at that it was you know eight eight hours of battery life. Oh easy
And so you know I was kind of like we were I was talking people who are
It's like okay. Well we start giving them some tips about what to do, but it's like okay
Well is there ever are we ever gonna get to a point where you know even?
mainstream distros have some of these changes out of the gate or
Optionally for a couple distros like Ubuntu Mate edition does some decent battery
Loving tweaks out of the box that some other distros don't do so I know that's one of them
But yeah, so there is some distro differential as you might say a distro the diff the distro differential indeed
But it's still I think across the board since I really would say since kernel 4. It's just been shit I
Think it's gone down. I think it's yeah, I think it's been bad since version 4 of the Linux kernel
I don't really think it's ever come back up
And I don't really care so it's not like I talk about it very often because to me
I just need my better to last long enough between where I have plugs
Right you know it's funny. I'm in a totally different boat for me
I need my battery to last only from the time. I leave my house
So time I get back because I won't have plugs usually do you know you get great battery life
Yeah, you know about 16 hours well, but then again. I have there's three batteries in that ThinkPad. You know effectively so
Not the best test. Yeah, I see what you mean there. Yeah, I so does anybody in the virtual log
there have anything that they do to save battery life like maybe TLP or
Powertop because I know those are things you can do with power top for example
You can at least get a sense of what's draining your battery, which is a very useful tool
But that's maybe old-school is there new things people are using to figure out what's sucking down battery life
I'd love to know any new tips because from where I'm at I feel like I have a limited set of tools really track it down
Earlier I'll add it to the show notes architect in the IRC room posted a good link that kind of had a rundown
These days it seems like TLP is the most popular at least what people are talking about the most and seems to be the most
up-to-date or most modern
and
And you know is one of the ones laptop mode tools being the other one where you know you can kind of just install it
And generally forget about it. I think TLP has less config that you might want to do or able to do
So if that might just work for you, and then of course yeah
There's power top which can be very useful especially if you're just trying to understand things you're writing your own
You'd have rules, or you're just like oh. Yeah, it's it's this thing all the time
I'm just gonna disable that hardware or not use that program and
Sandy bridge and was that the was that the Intel release that you hated no I hated
Sky like sandy bridge and sky like if I recall both had issues like with their p-state driver
Where which screws with like the CPU scaling and just burns battery life like crazy, too
So that hasn't helped either and that was an Intel problem
That's not really a mean it's a Linux kernel problem because it's in the kernel right, but it's Intel code
And I feel like we're just kind of getting that solved in like 412
I think yeah
Didn't we just have a new release come out like today or yesterday to of the Linux from I think 411 just yeah
Yeah, and that's not in there. I don't think but I'm not sure did you you did a little rundown of it
Did you see that in there when you were doing it didn't?
No, that's a good question. Yeah, I didn't see it in there when I went I went through your notes
Wested a nice little breakdown of what was in there
We never even put it in the show, but it happened during our show prep period and I saw it in there
It's like okay that might be something worth talking about but that's still not I still doesn't fix it on
Yeah, yeah, you mostly called out LZ for improvements to software raid and sip hash
which
Sounds interesting. Yeah, this is a new hash algorithm that people are
But not a piece a driver fix not a not a really not we'll have to go review the kernel newbies
Yeah, yeah, yeah, maybe it's maybe it's something buried in the details there
But I know that's been that's also been part of what's causing this
I know I know from reading some like of Matthew Garrett's older posts
Remember him talk about you know these days more and more things are being combined not to like one chipset or linked together
Whereas it's separately they used to be you know more separate components
And so now you have to get the power states right on all the components for the group of them to power down sufficiently
So that's not helping us very much. No, that's
complicated yeah
Well, I guess I would say this if you have a great tool for sort of tracking this problem down
Or you if you've solved it on a more recent
Ubuntu or or or distro because one of the other problems I have is when I when I looked I did see some stuff
But mostly what I saw was like really old guides. Mm-hmm. I'm like is this from 2009?
I don't think that's a good idea
so I would kind of like to see something maybe submit a few articles for the subreddit Linux action show dot reddit comm or
You can send them in directly to the show go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact and put it in that way
Maybe I know power tops
I mean so those ones the basics we know but some other cool ways to track it down like one thing I was thinking about
this is really stupid, but like if it's just something you wanted to stay on top of all the time and just sort of
Whittle it down is what would happen if you just put a temperature sensor extension on gnome and just look to the devices
They're running hot all the time and track it down that way like if your CPUs seems like it's running hot or your GPU is
Something hitting that more than it should yeah
I could at least give you an indication that something's working hard because the power obviously would translate to heat somewhere
Yeah, so it might be a way to start mr. Mr. Noah before we go
Why don't you tell the people at home where they can find you and maybe what other shows?
Yeah at Colonel Linux at least for one more week
the Linux action show on Sundays and the ask Noah show 6 p.m. Central jblive.tv and if you're in Grand Forks and
keqq 88.3 o pfm and
Give that number around eight five five four five zero Noah. That's one eight five five four five zero six six two four
That's what I want to do. I want to make that number the thing that people say well. I'm getting started with Linux
Okay, well here here at six o'clock on Monday. Yeah, give these guys a call
You know yeah
You know we should do is for swag wouldn't be awesome if we had like business cards that were like
You have a have a have you know need Linux help call call one eight five five
And we still could it's new it's early so well not I mean for Linux fest
Oh, yeah, that would be good to give out at Linux fest the people hand out
I'm I might I might see what I can do about that
I'm gonna get something printed because it's just basically be like a little card that says need Linux support call what he got
I'm five five four five zero Noah
That's one eight five five four five zero six six two four and it's live on Mondays if you want to tune in and call in
I would be a specific. Yeah, 7 p.m.. Eastern 6 p.m.. Central
The thing is like I started by just doing Pacific time and then the radio station
We're like why are you always giving in Pacific time? We're in Central time
I'm like okay well 4 p.m.. Pacific and 6 p.m.. Central then people wrote in and they're like
Why don't you give it Eastern time really everyone measures in Eastern and Pacific time and I'm like 7 p.m.. Eastern
So I just like rotate between the three
And then mr.. West there's places people can find you outside this show as well. Yes, that's right
I'm at West Payne on Twitter, and if you just stay tuned you'll catch me on the tech snap program
Which is coming up next?
Very well very good, and I'm excited about that and there is some big news this week for the tech snap program
I am at Chris LAS the network is at Jupiter signal the vlog is
Youtube.com slash Chris Fisher tune in live this weekend at jblive.tv for our Linux fest Northwest coverage Wow
It's finally here
That time of year again, and you can also keep up to date on that coverage at Jupiter signal on the tweeters
Even if you don't use the tweeter you can still read the feeds. I know it's crazy. Thanks for being here
If you want to join our virtual lug next week
You'll have to show up live go to jblive.tv for that you put a broadcasting comm slash calendar
And if you want to give us your feedback Linux action show dot reddit comm at least for a little bit longer
What?
I'll leave you with that. Thanks for joining us. We'll see you right back here next Tuesday. See you later everybody
Oh
JB titles calm everybody go to JB titles calm. Let's pick that title good show Wes good job
Good job podcasting now. What do you think? Did you see any titles go by that you like? I actually haven't looked yet
Yeah, I haven't either
I'm excited about Linux fest. I think it's gonna be a good time. Well, it's gonna be a good it's gonna be great
Windows 10 sucker edition. That's kind of funny and gabien was right that I like that too
Windows 10 Titanic edition
Windows is the S
We also have kill dash 9 grub 2 oh
Oh, man, I got the burps right now
The burps wouldn't rub a dub grub. That is money. I like that one. That's good, too. We're system T. That's funny
I where's rub a dub grub. I got to give that about that's going on. That's going up fast
That's going up really fast people like that battery life myths Linux shenanigans a hoppy lup. Yeah, it was that's true
Mm-hmm max unplugged. I get it the max unplugged. That's pretty good. Oh, is that what your solution is?
It's all right, it's good. It's good. It's good. No, that's fine. It's fine. Rub a dub grubs going up there. Let's go with it
I think that's perfect. I think that's perfect
All right, you know what's funny is we got the sky cam in here and that was done like at the last minute
We did that during the show. It was perfect. Oh, yeah, that was good. That's good. I like the sky cam. All right chat room
Thank you for being here. Thank you everybody for listening at home and oh good hashtag blame
Noah's going up on the list. Okay. Now we can officially we can officially in the show