40, 50 years ago amateur radio operators and just general electronic enthusiasts, in fact
the Linux users of like the 1920s, 30s and 40s were into a hobby called ham radio.
If you haven't heard of it, basically it's you take, you build your own radios or you
buy pre-made radios and then you play with them and you learn about them and the federal
government literally takes millions of dollars of frequency spectrum and gives it to amateur
radio operators to play with.
The only real requirement is you have to pass a very basic test proving you're not going
to kill yourself or anyone else.
And as we have entered 2012, 13, 14, 15, 16, technology has evolved and now instead of
buying these physical radios, you still buy physical radio but the radio doesn't have
an interface.
There's no dial, there's no ability to interface to the radio, just a box with a USB plug and
you plug that box into your computer and you can control the radio from software, thus
the name software defined radio.
So what Wes is talking about is this Lua radio and I'm over here at luaradio.io and it says
Lua radio is a lightweight embedded low flow graph signal processing frameworks for software
defined radio.
It provides a sweet source sync of processing blocks with a simple API for defining flow
graphs, running flow graphs, creating blocks and creating data types.
So I'm assuming if I'm reading this right and if I'm understanding it from the 45 seconds
I've been looking at this, basically you're able to go through and piece together different
components of the radio inside of the software.
Am I understanding that right?
Yeah, that's what it looks like.
Have you used GNU radio at all?
I have.
Yeah, it's a real challenge if I'm being perfectly honest with you.
Yeah, and so that's what I was reading this.
I haven't used software defined radio very much but I'm definitely interested in it.
I have a physics background so any kind of like playing with the spectrum is definitely
interesting even though I haven't done much of it myself.
And so a lot of people are saying like this has similar capabilities but is easier to
use, more lightweight and if you're familiar with Lua at all, it's easier to interface
with.
Yeah, man.
Have you ever used XMonet?
You know I have not.
I've looked at it but I have not actually tried it.
So I've been playing with XMonet.
I was on a – I was for better or for worse I was stuck on a very low powered machine
and the way to drag the most horsepower out of that machine was to use a tiling desktop
manager and I chose XMonet and I was super happy with it.
In fact, so much so that I'm considering it making my primary desktop interface but
–
Wow.
Yeah.
I know.
It sounds crazy but here's the thing.
Anyone that – I used to think that I used Nome because I had too much to get done and
I didn't have enough time to worry about memorizing weird commands and stuff but after
using XMonet for a while, I've honed in on this is a more efficient way to work and
to that end, you can configure it up the wazoo with Lua.
I believe it's Lua if I'm not mistaken.
No, buddy.
It's Haskell.
XMonet is Haskell.
Okay.
Which one?
Is it awesome then?
It was awesome.
Awesome.
Okay.
Well, so I guess my point doesn't really stand except for the fact that what I found
was the things that I was going to tweak were already tweaked for me in XMonet.
So the things I wanted to set up were already set up the way I would have wanted them to.
I thought that was – Lua, apparently I confused the two.
I've gone through a couple of different ones but the point – all that to say that
those kind of configuration setups where you just have this big configuration file
in something like Lua is super easy for anyone to just – even if you don't understand
programming, it's a little daunting at first but once you learn what the little things
that you need to change are, super easy to get set up and use.
So I guess what I'm saying is I feel like it would be the same thing in the software
defined radio, right?
Yeah, definitely.
It definitely seems like that.
People are excited that it should be portable, maybe they can use it on all kinds of different
interfaces and devices.
So it'll be interesting to see what this comes from.
It's exciting to see it launch anyway.
Right.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, episode 152 for July 5th, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's taken your beloved host,
shoved him into the back of an RV and sent him trailing across the country to enjoy himself.
Stepping in for the one, the only, the great, the Linux podcaster, hair master, Chris Fisher,
it's me, Noah Chaliya, and – Hey guys, it's Wes.
It's Mr. Wes.
How are you doing today, Wes?
Oh, I'm doing wonderful and it's great to be with you, Noah.
How about yourself?
You and I totally rocked Linux Action Show on Sunday, now we're going to rock Linux
Unplugged today.
That's right.
And we have an exciting, exciting show.
I told you on Sunday the show was going to be so big that we couldn't put a word to
it.
Is there a word to describe this show that we're about to do right now?
Maybe two words, exciting and confusing.
Really?
Well, that got me intrigued.
I think we'll find out.
All right.
Well, let's head on down into our mumble room and welcome our virtual live.
This is a group that meets over at mumble.jupitercolony.com and you can join for free.
Just download the mumble client and participate with us 2 p.m. Pacific time.
Hello mumble room.
Time appropriate.
Greetings.
Hello.
Everyone says.
Oh, those voices.
I love them.
I know.
It's like it's like we have our own little fan club and they and they join us via the
Internet and everyone is welcome.
So if you're if you're listening to Linux Unplugged, you could join Linux Unplugged
next week by downloading mumble and get with the program.
Please do.
It's so much fun.
All right, Wes.
Tell me about our first story.
Our first story.
OK, so containers, all the rage, everyone's talking about them and maybe people are actually
using them.
Right.
Like you were just talking with Michael on Coder about how he's deploying a lot of Docker
containers up on DigitalOcean.
So now if you're if you're one of the people using Docker containers and I know at least
me, I use them on DO, but I also find uses, you know, deploying apps on my local computer.
Maybe I need something.
I don't want to mess up.
We talk a lot about we've been talking about snap packages and Flatpak, etc.
But really, Docker can do a lot of the same things.
There are other considerations.
Right.
Like it's more complicated.
There's it's not quite in the same boat, but it really in the end, you can use it to deploy
applications in the same way.
So now NVIDIA is releasing a plugin that allows you to have GPU accelerated containers.
Awesome, awesome.
You know, that is that takes things to a whole new level on some degree, because if if you
if we could start to containerize games, that that seems like that would be a major game
changer because no longer are you packaging and developing first and you're not targeting
a specific platform anymore.
Now you're targeting a container and if you can if you could take that container and make
it interoperable among all three of the big operating systems, Linux, Mac and Windows.
Now we've really changed the landscape.
Oh, that'd be interesting.
Yeah, it looks like it's first right now.
They're really targeting like machine learning applications, places where you might want to
be deploying these apps.
But you know, inside the container, they're too restricted to get access to the GPU.
So in video, they're working on they're basically exporting, they're adding some hooks into
the user land part and having these user land accessible parts exported into the Docker
containers.
And then you can do like CUDA type stuff right from inside Docker.
Awesome.
So what have you see is this is I this is early days, I assume this is not something
that has that has taken off or have any real teeth to it yet, right?
Yeah, it is early days.
They do have some code up on GitHub.
You know, the info world here does note that like one of the biggest drawbacks is that
CUDA is a proprietary standard, even though but but it also just happens to be the NVIDIA
really is the chip maker that does a lot of the machine learning stuff.
You know, these big clusters, people doing the serious work that usually do not on NVIDIA.
AMD has been opening up, which is really interesting, but really doesn't have the same kind of market
uptake that NVIDIA does, especially in machine learning.
Sure.
DERP learning.
That's right.
We have a term for this guys.
DERP.
DERP learning.
I'm interested outside of so you're saying, are you telling me that at this point in time,
what they're really targeting is really kind of only the whole machine learning thing?
Or is it going to expand beyond that?
You know, the article doesn't mention anything that's kind of focused on the machine learning
stuff.
I'm sure that's kind of what's hot and what's motivating this.
But once you have access to the GPU, it'll be interesting to see what else can be run
there.
Yeah.
Yeah, it really would.
You know, it's interesting because I watched, we went to LinuxCon last year and the way
that LinuxCon works is they always have a sub-focus, Linux is obviously the general
focus and then they have this like deep down focus that they kind of run in on and this
year it was all about containers.
And in fact, they were joking, not joking, the little subtitle was ContainerCon, right?
And I have watched everything in Linux over the last year focus or shift focus to be centered
on or around containers.
And you know, first we saw it happen on the server side and then very shortly after that
we saw that entering on the desktop side and it makes me wonder if the future of computing
in general is not just going to be containers.
Yeah, I know, right?
And it's interesting, you know, having gotten, you've been using LXD in the past, I do kind
of get this, I'll build up a host, right?
And I'll have this main host and then I'll install a bunch of containers on it and I
just love, it's really nice having that main host just kept so clean.
Anything you really want to do, you input in a container, if you're done with that you
just delete it.
There's really, it's very easy to manage, I can see why people are fond of it.
Yeah, yeah, for sure.
You know, I wonder, have you played with, have you played with Flatpak and Snap Packages
and all those?
Yeah, I've been getting my feet wet, I mean, I haven't done anything, any real work in
them yet but I played with them a little.
So I'll tell you, the telegram conversation I was having literally as I was getting on
the area is one of our prized and beloved community members is actually working on packaging
me a OS ticket app inside of Electron because one of the things, so one of the things I
hate is not being able to have a dedicated application when I'm working and I can't alt
tap between things.
It really messes up the window management kind of workflow, yeah.
It does and especially because, you know, things like, so for example, our ticketing
system, I'm basically constantly referencing back and forth.
You know, there's never a time when, you know, no matter what I'm doing, something is either
going in or out of the ticket system and to not have that, it's own dedicated window is
a huge crutch for me and so Sean was working, Sean, Adram was working on packaging this
just because he's a nice guy and sends me a telegram, he's like, here, I got this done
for you.
I'm like, really dude?
And he's like, yeah, it actually didn't really take me on that.
I know.
Yeah, I know.
So I'm playing with that and then, you know, the first story we get on the air, we start
talking about containers.
It's like, it seems like every time I turn around, something else is now possible.
Something else is now happening because of containers.
Yeah, exactly.
Well, I mean, the Electron thing is just because it's web app but you don't even need an Electron
framework to do that.
There's like browsers like Surf which is from the Sucklass project and they have a browser
that's pretty much bare bones, nothing, it doesn't have Chrome, like any user Chrome
anywhere.
And for people who are not aware, that means like the GUI of the browser, not actually
Chrome.
But anyway, so it has the same kind of thing, you have custom cookies for each individual
website.
So you can just load up any web app into Surf as its own independent window and not have
to worry about putting any kind of framework in it.
Really?
Now, have you...
Oh, that does sound very useful.
Have you had any experience deploying this stuff?
Yeah, I actually have like three of them running right now.
Really?
And how have you found it to be?
It works great.
The only problem is that I'm running an older version of Ubuntu base that has an older version
of Sucklass, which the problem with that is only because packages don't update very much.
So once that's no longer an issue, then it wouldn't matter because the latest version
of Surf has the latest WebKit engine, so it doesn't have any kind of weird issues.
For example, I have Gmail in one of them that every once in a while Gmail will say, you're
using an old version of WebKit.
Other than that, it works flawlessly.
It just constantly tells me that I'm using an old version.
But as far as functionally, it works fantastic and all you need to do is create a text file
that stores the cookies and you're done.
It runs just like a web app in a full desktop thing, but web app style.
Now excuse my ignorance, but isn't the entire idea of the whole container thing that it
shouldn't matter what version of Ubuntu you're on and what version of Ubuntu your users are
on?
Right.
But Sucklass is not based on the container stuff.
This is just an old traditional deb thing.
I'm saying like this is a browser that doesn't need any kind of framework to run around it
to be what you want or it's a separate window and everything like that and it has a separate
session so you can have two or a hundred different Gmail clients running at the same time and
they would all be separate windows and it would all be tracked differently and all have
a different session.
Wow.
I could definitely use that at work and a few other places.
Yeah.
I have one for each slack that I use.
I have one for multiple gmails and so on and so on.
Yeah.
That's…
Sucklass Surf is a really good app for that.
Yeah.
It's funny too because for a long time I told myself, I was like, what I'm asking
for, what I need, what I want is so simple and plain and straightforward that I can't
believe something doesn't exist and then I kind of got the idea that the only real
way to do that was with something like Electron and then I'm like, well, I guess that works
but I just I feel like there should be a simpler, more straightforward solution.
I'm finding out as usual it's just a matter of my ignorance, not a matter of the lack
of Linux.
It's also they don't really tell people about, they don't really advertise that
they have this feature that I did just say it's a bare bones browser.
They don't mention that they have individual sessions system.
But it's interesting because all you need to do is run whatever thing you want, whatever
website you want to go to, you just type in surf, put in the cookie file location and
then the website and that's it and it runs how you expect it to.
Nice.
Well, thank you.
I appreciate that, Rotten.
And you know, the next thing I want to talk about or I guess rather Wes wants to talk
about is making his computer more artificially intelligent.
And I'll tell you what, I'll give you two secret surprises.
Secret surprises.
It's not really secret, I'm about to tell you, but it's still a surprise kind of sort
of keep it secret for the surprise.
There are two things.
One is I am desperately trying to get more patrons for Chris so when he gets home.
We have to do it.
You know, so he'll get home and he'll be like, Oh my gosh, Noah and West did not burn the
network down and dad still has a house.
This is absolutely great.
So we are at 650 right now so we've had we have two patrons.
My goal is to get us to 660 now.
I can't tell you quite yet because I'm finalized the details of what it is, but I have something
in the works and I also have a backup plan if that first plan falls through of something
super special and cool that we're going to be giving away to one of the 12 people.
Two spots are taken.
We've got 10 left.
So if one.
Yeah, I know.
I know.
And and so if you have been considering signing up for patron now is the time to do a patreon.com
slash today and if you sign up before Chris gets back so that's going to be it will have
to do it on the Linux action show this coming Sunday.
So has to be before then if you sign up before then you'll be entered into the dry.
I don't know we're going to do.
We're gonna do some kind of drawing and and and pull out names and you'll win something
really cool.
I think it's cool anyway, and it might be even cooler if if if Noah's plan number one
goes through and if not a backup plan number two, okay, that's super secret special thing
number one super secret special thing number two next week's Linux action show if you don't
usually tune in obviously with Chris being gone it gives us we have to fill for his absence
and those are some pretty big shoes to to fill however we think we might have a pretty
good idea of how to do it and I'm not going to tell you exactly what it is but suffice
to say that it is going to be amazing and it may or may not relate to this next story
that we're going to talk about which by the way is that the mycroft AI personal assistant
is now available on KDE plasma 5 what do you think about that was well you know I mean
Chris has just been making everyone so jealous he's using that gnome extension he's loving
it you've got the personal AI Popey's voice right there all the time but he's right exactly
oh how I wish I had that Chris why did you leave and not give me that would you like
so now would you like it I can send it to you because I have yep let's set that up later
I think so so if you are a KDE plasma 5 user rotten corpse you can now have access to the
mycroft AI application which let me tell you know that the thing is I am still in kind
of disbelief that he's managed to get this project as far as he has in the short amount
of time that he has oh it's incredible without compromising on basically any of his core
values you know so we really have a hugely industry competitive project in fact arguably
the only one of its kind right because you have things like the Amazon echo but that's
a very specifically tailored device that you can do very specifically tailored things it's
not a drop it's not an open extensible world right but even so even if you even if we abstract
away from the open source argument even if we get above that there's still no drop in
solution that I'm aware of that you can just take an AI you know software stack and just
drop it in and say okay this is my device that does you know my widget that does XYZ
and I wanted to have AI so here we go I don't know of any other software system that will
lie to do that and so you know he's really he has struck a nerve and I think that in
the long run that's going to work out very very well because it inevitably mycroft is
going to be a more versatile and useful platform than anything that remotely competes with
it right right exactly and I think we've seen like because it's so you know if you become
a business that wants to have the same thing like it's it's open to you sure you have to
contribute back upstream of course but you know it allows the community and people who
really have needs to build the tool that will do you work for them do you have to contribute
back upstream well depending on license so yeah if you make changes yeah yeah but I'm
saying as if you are a project and all you want to do is just is is use that mycroft
AI in its in its form you're not making changes to it you're just you're just using it you
just take it and use it right and totally so I you know that's exciting I think so I
think so and the fact that you we already I'm starting to see you know it I remember
we were at system 76 in November and we were they were still in the launching phase of
this so to watch to go from November to July and have this not be a thing just on gnome
but now they've extended out to KTE you know where's this going to be one year from now
is this going to be on every device I own I hope so I know and I also feel like when
you know like when Cortana came to the desktop and series coming to you just before before
mycroft really had picked up as much momentum as it had now it really felt like it was what
was Linux going to have to compete what was the open source world going to have to compete
we were so far behind we didn't have anything we're not that great at desktop integration
anyway so it really didn't seem like there's possible so really like have to throw a hat
tip out here to Aditya Mehra who seems to be the author of both this Qt application
as well as the gnome shell extension so it's really helping desktop users out a lot okay
so here's here's the here's the here's the I guess here's the thing well I won't say
that I won't say yeah we'll leave it at that we'll leave it on show Noah yeah no yeah right
no that's my thing it's my trademark I take it everywhere but suffice to say that I think
that mycroft is is going to be absolutely awesome and I don't think I think that at
this point from what I've seen what mycroft can do and that's a that's a that's a small
scope right I think it's much larger than that I think that from the very little that
I've seen it blows away Cortana to me is the new clippy of 2016 that's all I feel about
you know you mean I played with it for a little bit it feels like clippy it feels like that
stupid irritating paperclip that bounces around gives you nothing useful and just annoys the
heck out of you except now it's like it's almost like clippy combined with annoying
flash infomercial embedded in the page with super loud sounds yeah exactly and it's like
under your fingertips all the time all right so I see you're wanting to run a podcast would
you like exactly exactly dude that's exactly how I feel about it I think it's the dumbest
thing ever all right well looks like arch has finally caught up to a bunt to zygoon.pl
headline snappy in arch move to community repo and says hey there snappers I'd like
to announce something that you may have noticed during the last update of snapd to version
2.0.10 the AUR package is no longer there instead you can now get an update snappy in
the arch simply by running this one-liner and then he gives pacman attack s space snap
d s n a p d you know it's interesting was I was just talking again I was talking to
adrium right before the show and he was he was in the process of packaging this electron
thing to me and he says well I know that you have a bunch on your laptop now so I'll just
package it as a snap and I said doesn't it really not matter anymore what operating system
I have now if it's just a snap I just you know just start on any of us right or any
distro and he said no actually so turns out it's it's still very much a community thing
so the community distro and arch has it and you know it's it's available in a bun too
and it's available in copper but it's not like widely spread right so fairly wide it
is fairly I mean it's for the fact that it's only been around for two months it's pretty
wide now well I guess my question is twofold the first question is or the first part of
the question is doesn't it kind of eliminate a universal installer if it's not truly universal
throughout all distros and then my second question good yes but it's it's that's that's
only a temporary thing because it's it has to be people have to adopt it to make universal
yeah so what you're saying is eventually we'll get there more than likely I mean the fact
that it's been two months and when it first started two months ago it was in one distro
and then now then it became in every flavor and then it became in like six other distros
now like sent to s has it fedora has it gen 2 has it linux mint has it now like the fact
that it's only been two months and there's already that much support the more and more
distros that adopted and longer and you know the more time we have the more it becomes
universal I think it just hasn't had enough time to get there okay well I guess that makes
sense so it is good point you can't have universality just on the on the get-go or that'd be pretty
hard to do and we will see if we get the critical mass like if you can tip the tip the ship
here with enough distros then it will will you know you'll feel like an outsider if you
don't have it and your user will probably come to expect it yeah I just I every time
this discussion comes up I have to reference the whole xkcd thing problem we have 13 competing
standards let's create one standard to standardize them all problem we have 14 competing standards
I mean that's it's true but that's also kind of like we didn't really have a standard for
universal apps yet so they're all competing to become the standard yeah so it will eventually
we will have a standard because there's there's so many people who are who are behind the
idea of having a standard that it is very likely that will be the one of them will get
it I don't know which one but one of them will and I think the best example right now
is if someone wants to install like next cloud they can just you know install Ubuntu or whatever
that supports snap and then just snap install next cloud and you're done yeah like it's
that simple now like that is that is such a huge change from what it used to be that
I see that this is big this is definitely going to be like revolutionary type of thing
yeah go ahead dar I will claim that it doesn't even matter if it doesn't become universal
as long as the core distribution is implemented what I mean is the distribution concept is
a concept of try different things and see if you succeed at doing and if it becomes
good people adopted the toolkits GTK cute all that kind of jazz essentially for me if
it is good is going to get adopted by the major distributions usually people run mostly
on the major distributions those that are running different things it's probably because
they're looking for different things anyways it doesn't matter if it's not universal as
long as it's in the core ones if you're developing software and you want to ship it heck if you
can have a single binary that it runs that's what matters for your user as long as he can
execute your program and in the end of the day it doesn't matter yeah that's fair that's
fair I guess I guess I you know I started out I mostly took the opposite side of this
argument simply to you know to provide context and because I've been speaking with some developers
and they had some concerns but I think overall if I had any concerns even if they haven't
been those concerns haven't been directly addressed or or squashed I guess they're outweighed
by the by the huge benefits of of what this brings to the table and I guess the only thing
is is it is interesting to me that that something that of this magnitude is still you know is
is in the community repo it's not in the main arch repo although I suppose on the other
hand it is the main arch repo though is it yeah well there's a distinction in terms yeah
it's a community is just a branch it's not officially maintained by arch but the fact
that they're allowing a trusted user to maintain it in the official arch repos it is kind of
like they are kind of acknowledging that it's more than just an AR it is being maintained
by someone in that community gotcha okay well yeah that's an important good that's good
clarification because I was not aware of that so anyway anyway yeah I think it's I think
this is gonna be interesting it'll be exciting this will be my first snap package that I
will rely on you know I've installed telegram but I have you know I've always had the option
of doing it from a PPA I installed you know I've installed other applications but they
they are just it was specifically for the purpose to try out snap this OS ticket desktop
application will be the first one that I've ever that I'll have ever used that is only
available to me in a snap package and because snap package I guess I'll be able to use it
on anything right yeah I'll be really curious to see you know how that goes for you should
definitely when you once you've got a hold of it you should definitely see how how far
you can spread it just see which servers and how easy it is yeah I totally will I tell
you what the funny thing about the snaps is that the most of the things that as like on
the developer side there are certain things that I say that it could be problem but there's
also certain things that I think that are fantastic and but the funny thing about it
is that so far it's since there's only been a couple months the amount of progress that
has been made on the snap side is like kind of amazing just because when the very beginning
there was like two or three problems that were addressed as like being catastrophic
and there's no way it's going to be adopted and then they happened and snap release features
for that and then now there was like the immediate jump was then the shared library issue and
then now snap is basically going to have in like a couple weeks shared libraries are going
to be released so they're like pretty much anytime there's an issue that's not like that
seems like snap is not going to be something that people would want they're going well
okay now if you brought our attention we'll make it huh well that's a good time yeah it
is that's very promising very promising outlook so West you have the chat room up right now
yes I do so I'll tell you something I had I was I had the chat room up on my laptop
and then as it turns out one of the problems so here behind the scenes ready behind the
scenes one of the problems with doing shows from Grand Forks is I'm not usually doing
them from Grand Forks and so when I every show I think I kind of have everything down
and to be fair Kota radio was so much less overhead than last that I literally walked
into the studio I set up in about 15 minutes and then I was like well now what I guess
I guess I'll go have lunch and come back in an hour and a half and do the show and worked
out beautifully well thought I was all set up to do unplugged but the one thing that
I missed was I there's where I didn't do the intro music for Kota because there were some
editing concerns love I've done the intro music before and I was like wow it should
be no problem to knock it out but I realized I didn't have a third computer to play the
intro music on so right before the show starts I'm like well I'll use my laptop so I bring
it over I set it in the middle of the studio plug this audio cable in and run the music
well then I get back here and I realize I don't have access to the chat room that's
a problem right well the great thing about Quasl is it syncs on all of the devices turns
out today is the day that our techs decide they're gonna upgrade all of the access points
so we're going to AC right I have no Wi-Fi in here I have no Wi-Fi what are you gonna
do I tell you what what I did was I have my Samsung Galaxy S6 on Ting and the cool thing
about Ting especially if you use the code Linux or you visit the website linux.ting.com
is they are going to give you $25 off your first device or your first month of service
now my total bill my total bill is $24 that's what I pay every month and that is for a phone
for myself and my wife that's crazy yeah we have two phones and it costs us 24 bucks a
month now the great thing how that's even possible is you only pay for what you use
so I don't use minutes I in fact I hate phone calls if you call me you're likely to get
rejected I only answer phone calls from like three people and other than that the little
ringer thing if by default is set to silent and then there's certain people that I have
set a ringtone for like my wife if she needs something urgently for the most part I just
don't do phone calls so my minutes are zero my messages I hate texting because I'm on
so many different devices that I can't text from one device you just send me a text message
in fact I have those alerts disabled so I check them like once a month for those people
that refuse to join 2016 but I use yeah exactly I use telegram for going over you know data
for everything now we're an IT company so what does that mean that means that we install
IT infrastructure I never have to worry about not having Wi-Fi because if I'm at my office
except for today I have Wi-Fi if I'm at my home I have Wi-Fi and if I'm at any client
location we have a super secret special network that all of our all of our tech devices can
I do that give us admin access to the network and unrestricted speeds and all that good
stuff I just throw my phone on there so I have network access literally everywhere I
go so much so that when I got my s6 I didn't have a GSM SIM card at the time for it because
I still have my other phone activated I want to number two it's a long story but I didn't
have a SIM card I actually used my phone for three days while I waited for my Amazon Prime
SIM card by the way you can get them off of Amazon Prime the ting ones I used it for three
days voice calls through Zoiper SIP texting through telegram and of course all of my email
stuff and I never even really missed a beat I didn't have data while I was in the car
that wasn't really the end of the world so it's kind of like gap coverage and it was
just kind of funny today because it was one of the first times where I was like hey I
actually don't have I don't have Wi-Fi for the first time and that doesn't usually happen
so all that to say linux.ting.com go over there for 25 bucks you should easily be able
to get your first month of service if not if you're single person you might even be
able to milk two months out of that just six bucks per line and you can do a hotspot so
I actually in addition to my my two phones I've also got a hotspot that I use when I
go when we go out to the lake and stuff like that just so the laptops can't get connected
the kids can be there and and whatnot linux.ting.com and a huge thanks to Ting for sponsoring
the Linux unplugged program.
So the next story on the docket is I believe it's this BPKG am I am I pronounced that?
You are dead on what does that sound like to you?
Big B package I mean I know what it is because I got it pulled up here but but is it is it
B package is that how I'm supposed to pronounce it?
Let's go with B package that seems like the most fun so you know you need you pretty we
all love package managers we're just talking about the next round of pseudo package managers
with snap and flat pack and docker and well everyone you know you also have things like
you have your you know your rust has a has cargo you have pip for python now we have
a B package for bash as a developer I hate them all okay tell me why hold on hold on
tell me why okay I will say the following if you're developing python somebody uses
install somebody uses pip yes they eventually fixed and merged both of the package managers
but that means only that now you have software that when you download the repository in the
source code you actually don't get all of the dependencies you need for that program
to to build even though you're just getting source code in tarballs you will get source
code and you will have all git has sub modules but developers seem that they want to use
whatever package manager you have go has the same problem they put the url as an import
inside of the language what that means you download your source code you want to work
offline you can't want to build you can't if the server goes down of one of the dependencies
you're dead essentially it's terrible drunk it's much worse the problem than actually
the problem you end up finding in the distributions repositories because at least you know that
it's your distro they might not support all the packages you're looking for when they
have something they tend to have all the dependencies you need so what would you recommend then
I mean are you are you saying that there shouldn't be that none of these should exist are you
saying that the problem is we got too much of a good thing I think it's because it creates
isolationism and makes it the people using a specific language end up having to recreate
all of these libraries that could be used across and actually have the ability to use
code that already exists outside of their their own isolationist thing I believe if
you want to fix your source code if you're already shipping source code and if you're
already using some sort of version in control it's not difficult to put in your build script
or it whatever your your version of control supports like git has sub modules in and sub
trees use those things please okay so you can avoid so much there's one tool to do the
job okay so you're saying it's unnecessary you're saying it's unnecessary I'm saying
it's unnecessary because let's say I want to I want to use a python program now I have
to have peep is install I have to have a git I have to have the distribution so all of
these packages are spread across not uniformly not all in the same version it's like it's
just a pain as a developer I think it's terrible actually hmm okay Wes do you have a do you
have a contrary opinion well you know I wasn't exactly excited about this I just think it
was interesting to see something like to see these concepts promulgate down even to the
shell level I don't do too much bash I mean I enjoy writing a bash script certainly is
useful but you know there's a get to a certain level where there's enough logic I usually
have migrated to another language that has solved these problems already I did install
it on my laptop here and you know it's working well it was a fast install although they do
recommend the one of the ways install isn't is the curl pipe to bash so there's probably
a theme going on here but you know you can install stuff I've got like an our tail program
for remotely tailing log files so I can see some utility in it and certainly if you were
like a bash developer I'm not sure if that's a thing but if it is a thing maybe you know
it does allow you to have like it will set up local dependencies for you so you can install
things in user land rather than you know needing root permissions just add one small thing
I see nothing wrong with having maybe an index of where you can find the multiple sides the
things that don't get published into a repository if you have some sort of index that allows
you to search code search code website for example you can do that but honestly when
it comes down to the way you distribute your package come on it's source code if you are
building a program that program you're shipping the source code the user expects to be the
user of that source code expects to be able to build and run your program make that work
stop depending on yet another tool to push your code so that all of your collection of
code is available and start dealing with you know last surface a lot of the errors and
issues come exactly from increasing your surface of the area you as a developer can comprehend
all of it perfectly you end up having dependencies and you can see as an example what happened
with node just actually one developer decided to okay since I can't have name I wanted because
of trademarks I'm going to delete it and broke a lot of websites because projects depended
on it was an example that's not a very good example just because node had a very poor
infrastructure it was if no did not allow them to you know remove it any time for any
reason whatsoever that wouldn't have happened but here's the they screwed up not necessarily
like the structure like not the concept of having shared dependencies and stuff like
that it was the the fact that node screwed up or anything specifically actually what
about this and this proves the example that I was speaking about if you are using versioning
control and you fork a repository that you are using as a dependency you can pull exactly
that hash version guess what you can insert into your project as a sub module as a sub
tree and it will be just there okay well well first off I would just point out that you're
talking about an ideal idealistic situation where everything and all source code is open
source but that's not the case and the majority of proprietary software would be a dependency
that you could not do that with so you can't you can't you can have get repositories that
have binaries that are proprietary you can totally do it it's a lame excuse it's doable
we have the tools it's people who don't who are so centric about the code way that they're
used to developing code they don't look at how I actually make my source code something
that just builds and just works they're looking at they complain about the packages issues
but most of the maintainers of the multiple distributions constantly fight okay this package
pulls from pip and this package pulls from easing install and this package puts from
node js which one respects my licenses in the case of devian the maintainer has all
of these efforts to go through if maintainers didn't have this effort to go through they
could just look okay we prefer in our distribution to put binaries in usr bin and so they would
look at where in your package build so in the directory where you build your project
the binaries are generated make it those binaries go to usr bin that actually will simplify
the process for both developers and maintainers but no nobody sees that okay i'm used to
i don't want to be dependent on maintainers to update my applications for the rest of
my life so even if even if your solution is is good in that sense it's still it still
puts it on the maintainers and still means that i can't update it whenever i want so
even if that was a solution i still don't want that for all intensive purposes you can
be the maintainer as much as you want i i don't care i just think that it separates
the concerns between what a developer ships in terms of source code what what a maintainer
ships in in terms of as a maintainer job currently the maintainer job basically is reverse the
process that developer decided to create to build their package understand how he can
incorporate that that into their distro one thing or not that's the process of a maintainer
if i just say that if you as a developer have the care of isolating your source environment
into a location it's actually preferable even if it's you doing the work as a maintainer
it's you shipping a binary or it's someone else coming and picking up on it you know
uh rikai says in the in the in the chat room he made a he made an interesting point i'd
like to get your guys's take on it he says someone point me to a distro that is packaging
a ton of bash scripts as packages because i don't know of any so this argument doesn't
make any sense to me i can see for normal packages but bash scripts and then he goes
on to say sorry i was just gonna say i'm i'm surprised that this is even a thing like this
no not no just that bash has packages i mean i don't even know that like a.sh file that's
the package for bash well i think that i don't even understand i think that's i think that's
what he's saying he's and then somewhere in here i can't find the exact 12 but he says
oh yeah here it is i would love a bash script repository so that makes sense to me but there's
no way to get it elsewhere without just searching get home from code and pulling down from local
does that does that change your perspective at all either rotten corpse or dar devlin
or west if you slightly slightly but very mildly only in the sense that i agree with
the repository i agree that there's not something for it and in that sense maybe distribution
should look into incorporating common bash scripts then you have to make the other question
isn't bash scripts for customization personalization of things and things need to be a system become
their own isolated demon or program if if we look at bash as something to automate things
for our own personal taste and our repository makes sense in the terms of community sharing
not necessarily as distribution actually distributing this it's very personal so i'll
look those things become standardized they become small little programs that end up being
deployed as a package good with my feeling i'll just add in in some ways like it you
know there's also kind of like a weird reverse or perverse incentive where a lot of times
bash scripts i i'll use them where i might not use another tool because you know they're
very portable they're easy to run you don't have to compile them etc so if i'm if i have
to install this secondary tool to then down these obviously you don't you can get them
just through the repo or whatever but you know it makes it like well if i'm gonna already
be using a package manager i might as well use something in python or a higher level
language that i could use rather than bash you know i'm guilty of that and i and i can
tell you firsthand raki is as well i mean fundamentally bash is what is is the quote
unquote programming language that's used to facilitate a lot of things in fact raki actually
shares with me a couple of little out scripts of the way that some of the videos are transcoded
my understanding is that's all wrapped in inside of a bash script i i actually tried
using you know i took a course on linux academy more about them in a little bit but i actually
i tried writing a little bit of code in bash uh and and then i decided i was going to quote
unquote graduate to a higher programming language and so i took a course from linux academy
on python and what ended up happening was i found in python how to write bash like how
i could call bash scripts and so i ended up yeah and so basically ended up wrapping all
of these bash scripts inside of python which made absolutely no sense but you know it's
fun to do but i think part of it is that you once you get you have to be comfortable with
bash to be a linux admin to begin with and so for those of us that are system administrators
and we're not developers being able to get small tasks done or even automated inside
of bash enables us to get the functionality as if we were a developer writing a a program
without the overhead of actually having to learn the development language and quote unquote
doing it properly and in that regard i think that there's that that bash has a lot of power
has a lot of power behind it you know to that point how many people do you know in 2016
that are writing hugely complicated scripts in dos or whatever you know it's just i i
i we have we have i mean our shell is so powerful that we're talking about a package manager
for it that in and of itself is cool i'm going to not without disrespecting anybody i will
say that the fact that once those things start needing a package manager i think is actually
an indication that perhaps those things should be moved outside bash it's just a suggestion
because a lot of things don't contemplate the use case scenarios that are beyond the
you know small automation bash was originally at least if i understand correctly it was
originally intended as you invoke mostly other programs to do but when you start doing manipulation
when you start producing it's a show yeah exactly when you start trying to produce output
maybe it's the time that you need to make a stop in your heart and say really i need
to get this done properly because seriously it actually just damages further because we
then need that bash becomes always there becomes having the issues that other programming languages
already have solved and now we're having to deal with an extra package manager i just
don't believe it's a good idea a package manager might not be good for bash but i i agree that
the uh the idea of a repo would be pretty cool so maybe not practical but still pretty
cool yeah well you guys should all just try it out and report back if you actually use
it yeah yeah yeah maybe that's an idea maybe we could have like a community review kind
of a thing you know i think part of the drive is to you know so one part of the drive is
just that we're familiar with it but the i think the reason that a lot of us especially
a system administrators i don't know about us but the reason that i've become so ingrained
in bash is because i can run it from the command line right yeah exactly and so basically what
that enables you to do is if you have a tool that you fundamentally rely on that requires
a web interface it means that you're only able to access that tool when you have i'm
sorry can i say web interface graphical interface you're only able to access that tool when
you have the graphical interface graphical desktop installed and that's not always the
case in fact a lot of times you'll end up using like all of my servers and i can say
this with 100 certainty every single server i own whether it is a virtual server or it's
a physical box does not have a head on it and it's it actually it provides for some
comical interaction because i'll get calls from clients you know all the servers that
we have installed at client locations they're on a rack and there's no display connected
to it because we administrate everything you know over ssh totally and that that enables
us to get it to it remotely but it'll be funny every once in a while you have a client that
their server goes down or something stops working and they don't want to pay us to come
out so they'll they'll go in there and they're like i'll fix this i'll just go and click
the restart button or well it's all right they're locked as a gang login but they they
have this they have the the cable they plug a monitor cable and they set a monitor up
and i've gotten more than one call where they're like well yeah oh this is so and so from so
and so client and uh we uh we want in the server room something's definitely wrong with
our server we plug the monitor in and it it's booted to a dos prompt and uh it's not loading
windows you know they just they have no idea right but the i think that and the the drive
behind that not only is it lower resources but in it fundamentally enables us to take
those servers if we ever need to and it's happened more than once and move them over
to a vps provider so you have a you have a client and they have a server and all of a
sudden it goes down the protocol used to be 10 years ago here's how that conversation
would look hey i'm really sorry that your server went down i understand that you're
not able to get any work done if you'd like i can go ahead and overnight a brand new server
to you and would have it up and running in about 12 hours if it's super super super super
super super important i can call xyz and they'll go ahead and uh put an expedite thing on it
and i can drive to minneapolis four and a half hours and i can have it up at eight hours
and then you'd be back online today that conversation looks like this hey guys i'm really sorry
that your server went down if you pay us fifteen dollars uh we will go ahead and set you up
an account over at digital ocean which is our chosen vps provider and then we bill them
15 bucks and digital ocean charges us five bucks and so we make a nice little spread
in there and it's a recurring cost because if you're in small business you know that
the most valuable revenue stream that you have is the recurring sources it's not the
one-offs the people that call even if it's a big client even if it's a big job and you
bid it out and it's you know 10 15 20 even 30 000 that money will eventually go away
so it's those it's those it is those reoccurring contracts where they sign up and they say
yeah we want because it's only five bucks we want a main server we want a backup server
and then we want a failover server off-site you know this that and the other okay no problem
i log into my digital ocean control panel i create their main server i create their
backup server and those may be on one data center and then i put another one in like
you know frankfurt or wherever that's totally off-site and it's doing off-site replication
so if anything fails at the main data center or something like that we have the backups
and i can do all of this from my laptop or even my freaking cell phone right on site
and i can tell the customer and i have told the customer hey we'll have this up and running
for you in about 20 minutes because it takes me about 30 seconds to get the server spun
up and working and then it takes me you know the the rest of the time i probably spend
half an hour locking the system down and installing all their applications and stuff like that
the thing is um if you use the code do unplugged you're going to get uh you're going to get
ten dollars off your first linux rig now you could apply that towards a big linux rig and
run a really powerful server for a free month or you could do what i do which is spread
that over over two machines and you can actually run two five dollar rigs now just to see how
far i could push digital ocean a couple weeks ago we did a review of uh virtualization and
i actually virtualized a five dollar droplet to see if i could do it you could actually
get mini droplets out of your five dollar droplet if you really had to so if you had
like a good example might be a web server a small web server that has like a company
portal maybe it redirects to a different site or maybe you just have a couple little company
resources something like that you need just something super super tiny maybe you needed
two of those you could probably get those to run on a five dollar rig i'm not necessarily
suggesting you put that into production because for five bucks a month who cares but i can
tell you this i have there isn't a vps provider out there that i haven't tried and hands down
the zero compromise vps solution is digital ocean so go over there use the code do unplugged
and get ten dollars towards your first linux rig and a huge thank you to digital ocean
for sponsoring the linux unplugged program so wes uh i this next piece here is uh confusing
confusing to say the least linux and open source are powering comic uh massive restructure
am i reading that right almost so uh linux and open source are powering comcast massive
infrastructure i didn't see the wrap there you go okay you know and it's hard that's
a hard one to say for us people comcast is not always our friends i know uh here at the
jb one we certainly complain about them i think that's every day but it's you know you
don't always think about like how much of the open source technology they really do
and have to leverage to compete as a huge isp uh-huh we've had our you know you speak
about uh problems but we have had a a plethora of comcast problems recently so much so that
chris is actively looking to try to find alternatives to comcast the problem is in his particular
area neck of the woods they are not terribly available in fact he was i heard him on the
air last week sometime he was even joking he's like maybe i'll just go do shows from
the road because i probably have more reliable internet yeah exactly i mean that says it
right there okay so dive into this a little bit for me tell me how comcast is using linux
well okay so basically i mean to start with obviously comcast ships a crazy amount of
traffic uh let's see so in 2012 they had 1.2 million gigabytes of data traffic in 2013
that grew to almost 7 million gigabytes of traffic and it just keeps getting more right
so like in 2014 now it's at 74.8 million gigs of traffic so people are clearly picking it
up and they need things that can really scale okay and so so and it's just interesting to
hear the people say so here um here's what their representatives saying comcast like
so many others is a very linux heavy operating system country a company generally speaking
we're more on the open source side of those linux distributions than the commercial side
so they mostly are using ubuntu and centos in addition they're huge open stack users
so they they mostly deploy kvm and then they do all their data center orchestration through
open stack they have a let's say they have roughly a petabyte of memory and around a
million virtual cpu cores that they are running under open stack mostly to pile you know to
run all their web interfaces billing management account stuff the x1 interface the on-screen
interface all that stuff so i really never really thought about it before but it's it's
kind of interesting you know i suppose really what you know the thing is like it would be
cool to you almost to use almost it would be cool to use this as something like a runs
linux on the linux action show but the reality is there they are the epitome of everything
i hate about uh these kinds of linux users and it is it is this in a very short order
they don't care about linux or the community they care about profiting off the backs of
the hard-working people and and the excellent infrastructure that linux offers now i'm a
small business owner i'm not against making money i'm not against making a lot of money
right our economy relies on that yeah but i am against abusing a community and having
zero respect for that community and oracle well and then further is pushing the people
that made that community exist in the first place out of the community because they are
not part of your business model and don't benefit you directly and uh comcast and the
few little things that i've had to deal with them seems like they hit every one of those
bullet points square on the head and i hate it um and so you know it's kind of cool but
let's face it all that to say you can't run a company the size of comcast unless you're
running it on linux i mean windows small business server ain't gonna cut it and and comcast
needs like you know best in class engineers and those people are gonna be using unix tools
and and a lot of linux based tools so here's an interesting twist for you are you familiar
with cumulus networks uh only a little bit okay so cumulus networks had a really bright
idea they said right now in business we have a problem we have network engineers network
technicians and we have system administrators and the system administrators are very good
with bash and are very good with linux and are very good with you know computers and
understand the networking side of linux but anytime we want to do something serious
heavy lifting with networking we go to our network engineers and our network technicians
and those are the guys that know cisco and they know juniper and they know hp very different
worlds you know microtech right exactly um and they they are who provide our network
so if you want to have a high functioning company you employ the best of the best of
the system administrators and you employ the best of the best of network engineers and
technicians and if your network crashes your system administrator notices he contacts a
network engineer and they take care of it and if your network engineer or technician
is there and the the server goes down they don't touch it you just wait for the administrator
to come but basically that means your payroll is twice because you have two equally technically
proficient people but they are specializing in different areas even though the guy who
is running your network engineer guy has to have some basic system administration knowledge
because he's copying files off to and from a tftp server most of the time and your network
engineer has to have some basic your your system administrator has to some basic knowledge
of networking because he's got to get a service to talk on the network and so they said why
not do away with this whole dichotomy and say let's use linux as the network operating
system and just route everything through ip tables and through a custom interface that
they wrote on linux and so how interesting yeah it is really cool dude so basically they
sell this switch and router and you know whatever for you know data center you know we're talking
like 40 gig connection i'm going to move they're not small scale right it's really big stuff
but right isp level that kind of thing but it's all being done on linux and you're using
linux so they're they're they're selling point is train your guys to be a system administrator
they can administrate our networking equipment as well as any of your servers because it's
all one operating system and you interface with it like you would any linux distro and
all that to all that arriving to the point that it seems like that would be a really
great route for some place like comcast who probably has an abundance of people that are
working in networking and now they're trying to branch out and well not necessarily branch
out but they're being forced because cable is going by the wayside to focus on these
video type services which require a huge back end infrastructure of administration seems
like you could really cut your costs down if you could get a network infrastructure
in place that utilizes the same talent as your administrators that are administrating
all this video content what do you think yeah it's interesting it's interesting to see
especially with like you know microsoft's working on their switching linux based thing
dell has their new operating system doing the same sort of thing definitely you know
software divine networking and having these things i will also say personally you know
networking is interesting and i have several friends who have you know cisco certificates
or etc or our networking guys and i work with network engineers and you know we all we get
along on the fundamentals and the and the protocols but it's it's just interesting
because a lot of the professional network engineers are applying practices with very
proprietary equipment you know very locked down they're very following specifications
made and implemented by these vendors it's very different in the linux world where it
networking really has that spirit of just like you know maybe you won't get quite the
throughput or you won't be able to do like you know you're not having a giant core router
or anything but the amount of flexibility and things you can do with the linux networking
stack is i'm i'm continually impressed you know it's interesting too because they they've
literally proven and i mean i'm telling you these are not cheap equipment right you're
looking at 20 000 plus you know totally yeah so i mean but they're selling these things
right and left and they're hugely popular and i think the reason is because in the long
scheme if you're looking at large scale really your costs are going down not up and i think
that i think that alone is hugely advantageous now so i don't mean to sidetrack the conversation
with but have you do you have do you have any networking certifications i do not have
any certifications now have you ever gone to any of the training i've had some informal
training from network engineers yeah so i have sat and passed the some of the cisco
exams right and i made an authentic comment on last i've actually made it more than once
that the certifications for networking are kind of a joke and i didn't mean to say that
network engineers are not talented or that it's not difficult to pass the test or anything
like that totally but what i am saying and i stand by this and after i explained it via
an email guy wrote back and he's like oh man you you brought back some bad memories you
know i thought when i went to sit down i actually i was certified in red hat first and then
i went back and did my cisco stuff because at the time i was focusing on system administration
then i went and branched out my own company this and the other when i went to sit for
the cisco test i expected to sit down in front of a cisco router and they would give me a
computer to ssh or telnet or use a serial connection whatever and give me a series of
tasks to configure the switcher router or whatever right turns out what they actually
have is a little java applet that emulates the router but only the commands that they
think that you should have so right off the bat you know you get used to doing certain
things especially if you're a cisco guy one of the first things that you'll do when you
sit down is uh is show space config enter and then it spits out exactly what the router
is you know doing right now you know or or show int uh you know you can you can you can
put in non-ambiguous terms so it the the full command would be something like show interfaces
brief but i i've never actually typed that out in fact i couldn't even tell you i couldn't
even tell you if it's interface or interfaces i don't remember what i do know is i type
show space int space br enter and it shows me all of the interfaces that are there well
a lot of the stuff isn't working in this stupid java thing and it and it is throwing me off
because i i'm i'm i am painfully aware that i'm not actually onto a router i'm on this
little emulation thing that doesn't feel like a router and nothing feels right to me it's
not testing your ability on a real router no it's really not aside from the fact that
it's super delayed and it's not in guake and i can't draw it's just everything is off to
me and i'm already feeling out of my comfort zone and then i get past the little simulation
things and they go on to these questions where they ask you to calculate subnets now i would
figure if i was writing the test that if i wrote four subnet questions and the person
can answer all four of them then they can subnet and if they can't answer four of them
then they can't subnet and that should be the end of it what turns out they want you
to do like i don't know some absurd thing like you do like 30 of these questions but
they give you the only i'm not very good at math and so i have to i have to do all the
addition basically by hand and they give you a like an eight and a half by eleven transparency
thing and an erasable marker oh man yeah but you can't erase it because they don't give
you they give you like a kleenex but they don't really give you like anything they don't give
you an eraser so you didn't wear your best clothes they're not kidding dude i'm like
spitting on the thing because there's no water and i'm like i use up my kleenex in like the
first 30 seconds and then the rest of it like it's all over my arm and i'm trying to find
places that it's just a mess right well that was in stark contrast to doing my red hat
sir which was you sit down at a linux box they give you 25 things to do and you do them
and you restart the computer and if the computer does all of the things then you pass and if
the computer doesn't do all the things and you don't pass it is it's a really straightforward
thing so i am looking at my certifications coming up for renewal and one of the big things
i was concerned about was red hat 7 because that's we've made this you know this big change
gone to we've gone from rel6 to rel7 and i have to go sit for this test and so i was
a little concerned because things have changed and i know i'm not i'm i know i'm not necessarily
in in the swing because i'm i'm no longer focusing on you know knowing you know when
i did the six test i was focusing on learning all the things for six now i'm focusing on
learning all the things i need to do to get my job done well turns out linux academy was
able to help me out there i went over to linux academy and signed up for an account by going
to linux academy dot com slash unplugged got a huge discount and actually did all of my
rel7 training there so i think that is awesome i feel perfectly confident i have gone i have
done both ways guys i have done it both ways i have paid the like it's like a three thousand
dollar class fee and then you go for a week and there is there is an advantage to that
i won't lie there is an advantage to sitting in a classroom and being surrounded by other
people that want to learn linux and spending nine hours a day you know with an hour break
and right it's like a boot camp no yeah no real coffee you know you have some coffee
but it's cold and sometimes smells aren't great as smalls are not great because you're
sitting in front of other it people and it's somebody else's computer and it's their uncomfortable
chair sometimes and they frown upon you bringing your own laptop which means you have to do
things at their pace but there is some advantage to that but the bigger advantage is going
to linux academy dot com slash unplugged and signing up for an account it'll cost you
pennies on the dollar literally like one one hundredth of the cost about that actually
and then on top of that you decide when you want to train so if i work best between the
hours of like 10 pm and three in the morning that's my like power zone i can get almost
anything done in those hours partly because my phone isn't constantly interrupting me
but also because i'm just i'm the most awake and the most focused right about that period
of time well this academy works great for me with that i curl up in bed i take my laptop
i take a course did red hat seven uh also did um python you can learn just a ton of
things on these on these you know e-learning sites and the other thing is and i talked
about this on the linux action show these instructors are not your average these aren't
the guys these aren't the people that are here for money they're not the people that
they needed a job and they couldn't actually administrate linux so they decided to teach
it and you wind up with some of those people sometimes these are people that are genuinely
passionate about linux and teaching other people about linux and i said it on linux
action shall say it again on on on linux unplugged if you're not making seventy thousand dollars
but you understand what is going on in this show then you need a new job and you need
to go over to linux academy dot com slash unplugged sign up for an account show your
support for the linux action show and pick yourself up a new skill get a certification
the red hat certification to take the test is like two hundred dollars to take the class
is like three thousand that's a crazy difference it is it is and the and so if you can do the
learning part of it if you can actually pick up the learning over at linux academy for
pennies on the dollar and then go take the test for two hundred bucks you'll wind up
in the same boat that i am in you'd be able to i think if you're if you're one of those
people that are that are working at like a help desk for thirty thirty five thousand dollars a year you could
double your income in just a couple of months by going to linux academy dot com slash unplugged
they'll hook you up and a couple of people after saying similar things on the linux action
show have written in and asked me some small business questions and hiring questions by
all means do that go over to jupiter broadcasting dot com click on the contact link and choose
linux unplugged from the drop down menu i'd be more than happy to address any specific
questions of course you can always email me no at jupiter broadcasting dot com i have
some experience in that area and i'm more than happy to share it with you so wes i want
to talk about uh let's see here local wire uh let's see here which which i'm sorry where's
the next story i got lost set up uh core on a bun too is that right the local wire one
yep okay okay good okay uh local wire dot pl headline set up dot net core on a bun too
and then subtitle microsoft loves linux dot net core 1.0 is here and it's great and it's
a great opportunity to start playing with not only the windows platform not only on
the windows platform but also on linux today i will show you how not only to set up dot
net core but how to set up the whole development environment for developing dot net since one
of microsoft's goals was for multi-platform to support let's take a look at how to dot
net core on a bun too why a bun too well it's popular and easy and doesn't work right i
added that uh also microsoft uh used it as a platform for the choice for their bash and
docker support so windows for windows so the decision seemed quite straightforward to me
we'll be working with a bunch of 1404 lts good choice as it's the most widespread version
at this time you can also try out other platforms as i did specifically red hat enterprise
yeah which is totally free at developers dot red hat dot com for developers they also support
dot net on rel and as part of the dot net foundation quite rock solid backed isn't it
in fact he misses it but i'll inform you that you can actually do the same thing on centos
in fact that's what i totally that's what i would actually recommend because they're
not gonna they're not gonna cut you off rel is really if you got money and you want to
pay for it um i know they offer you really need that support yeah if yeah exactly that's
really what you're paying for um i am a big fan of uh i'm a big fan of centos when it's
either for me or for personal or even if it is a even if it is a a professional you know
production environment if it's not a large company that doesn't depend on support i'll
oftentimes stick them on centos just because i think it offers you know you get basically
the same thing for less money but you know this is super exciting especially because
it seems like there is a lot of disagreement on exactly what dot net core on linux meant
um exactly you know and the big thing was was i have directly been told by people much
smarter than me that you could not develop dot net on uh on on linux it had to be done
on windows and this specifically says otherwise so i think there's a lot of fud going around
no it used to be it used to be true like the dot net core thing is it's pretty much brand
new but like there are certain things you can do in linux there's certain things you
can't just like you can't use visual basic on linux that kind of thing okay i guess i
can i can talk a little bit about this as i've looked into actually using it on linux
because there was a need for a customer that uses windows and i just wanted to make it
on linux deploy it i see essentially when it comes down to this is a lot of the things
that you would rely on to have your dot net application built and shipped on windows that's
kind of the appeal is you wrote it in your linux environment you ship it there it's actually
non-existent so the wpf the windows specific stuff it's not available so you can't even
call it call it with dummy functions that would allow you to then deploy and test so
you can't really do that develop in environments on linux for dot net are really not curated
so that experience also sucks and it's a language that benefits a lot from all of the existing
code base of the dot net framework but without that it becomes kind of like useless most
of the times you better go with c++ use kit or something like that for making your application
at that point essentially then there's also these others thing that is actually helping
a little bit of its adoption in the linux platform which is everybody has seen what
oracle has tried to do with google in terms of apis and copyright so even though google
won fair use it was fair use in the google's case doesn't guarantee your case is going
to be fair use and you're a little bit scared of that but let's face it microsoft is also
a proprietary developer company they've had these clothes done for longest time they're
famously to being able to copyright to patent out software so if you're scared about litigation
you might not use it so in that sense we already have a curated environment around other languages
that provide those features and then you say but at least with dot net i can develop it
for mobile platform well you have to pay about five thousand dollars to have a zamari account
which is the only development environment which is based on mono developed i supposed
to support the iphone and android so then you look at your options around and you say
just no essentially this is why i think it hasn't been the explosion was intended to
be it's like basically you lack a consistent environment to work on on the platform so
essentially makes it useless for most people i would claim yeah there are definitely a
lot of usability limitations i'm just kind of curious because i know there's a lot of
people who like and they they kind of grew up in like c sharp is very popular some people
really like f sharp and i wonder for certain like server side things if there are people
who were kind of bound to windows and were comfortable in those environments and were
okay with a minimal environment but they still wanted to use the core of those languages
if they could find a find a use case here essentially they lack the tooling to support
them in their use case they probably could do but they lack the tooling so they don't
have visual studio as they are used to they had that they probably could do the switch
but now they still can a mono developer is very good is the best choice you have when
it comes to c sharp in linux but it still mostly sucks honestly sorry point well taken
you know i i guess i'm watching this with interest it is from all angles the world is
getting to be a smaller place now we're developing for containers rather than targeting specific
distros i just talked with michael dominic on monday code radio great show you should
check it out he was talking about how he pushes clients to develop for html5 because they
can move from device to device and it becomes platform agnostic and now we're looking at
you know bash coming to windows and we've got passion windows and dot net is on linux
and it's like it's very confusing it was i i don't know if confusing is the right word
or if or i guess i shouldn't say the right word wrong word but is not the word i would
choose but the the it just it seems like the walls are falling down and we're all gonna
find it we're all gonna look up and realize that we're all standing in the same room with
the same same things regardless of what operating system we're using that couldn't be exemplified
more sorry go ahead so the same thing will be linux i've already did this prediction
in and unplugged before microsoft will use the linux kernel that's why bash and linux
exist that's why they bottom a lot of android developers android companies basically to
get the the developers and they will move into having a proprietary desktop on top of
linux people won't even notice they will just suddenly swiftly change the underneath and
since every program is already running on linux linux will be what we've seen as the
tron operating system dude do you want to know what i would use it i would use it exactly
i would use it if if tomorrow i tell you what if tomorrow microsoft came out and said you
know what windows is a terrible you know we have destroyed the windows name we have destroyed
the windows brand and we are sick of windows and windows 10 is a total failure because
it sucks just a little bit less than a which sucks just a little bit less than vista which
suck just a little bit more next be the the the we if if that happened tomorrow and windows
says okay we're done with windows we're going to do the next thing called microsoft next
os which is our next version of windows are into the future and stuff like that and basically
because we have done all of this stuff and we're trying to drag these developers off
their macs and we're trying to drag them onto windows we have implemented bash and we don't
want to make there's no point in maintaining the nt kernel anymore because now we could
just maintain we could just let the linux community which we're already relying on for
the bash stuff and basically everything at the developer level all that stuff is we're
pulling that in from the open source community and hey we love linux why not just use the
linux kernel okay that's all right so here's our new windows version and it's kind of like
windows except it's running a linux kernel and we have the traditional windows desktop
that you all know and love with the stupid idiotic start menu which by the way we patented
because start is such a unique and signifying word we're going to take that ui and we're
going to stick it on top of linux and now all you developers don't have a reason to
go anywhere else oh and by the way because we're microsoft and we basically dominate
the pc market space everyone will now develop for linux because we have the linux kernel
if that happened tomorrow i wouldn't when i buy a new computer i wouldn't bother reinstalling
linux i just use what's on there because frankly even if it's a proprietary desktop am i super
excited about it no but if it saves me the trouble of having to reinstall the operating
system if i get support from the oem i can run all of my software because all i have
to do is maybe i install the snap whatever and i can install the snap packages on top
of the existing abuntu base which is probably what they're basing off of it anyway do i
really care if it's a proprietary desktop now i can live with that i think that would
be amazing and i would take i wouldn't take back but i would significantly reduce all
of the microsoft bashing i've done over the years that would be like that would be like
noah's dream come true because instantaneously america switches to linux basically overnight
if that happened and i realize i'm pipe dreaming you know no need to send me an email tell me
how crazy am i what it's not gonna happen a half past since my since my prediction two
years and a half happened bash on windows happened a linux distribution on the server
side happened they bought a lot of android companies to smart my words it's only two
years and a half since my prediction i did a total prediction of five years i said this
in the show i'm saying it again stick to my word do you know how do you know how happy
i can't i don't know what i will do the show naked i will show up and do the linux action
show naked if that ever happens i will yes the camera only goes waste up but i'll just
i don't know i don't know what i would do i'd be so happy you wouldn't i just words
cannot describe i don't know what i do i do something crazy that's how excited i would
it'll never i don't believe it's going to happen i hope so who did that whoever did
that amazing whoever did that should be shot no i i don't think i don't think i i don't
think i'm i'm really not uh i'm really not i hope you're right i so hope you're right
i have a hard time buying into it but our next story kind of exemplifies why you might
actually be right turns out you can run i3 on windows so it's not exactly what we're
just talking about because it's still the empty kernel but we're running an open source
desktop on it wes tell me about this yeah you know this uh brian kettleson here you
know he he kind of goes out and kind of talks about why you know he feels mac os is slipping
he really isn't quite comfortable enough on the linux desktop i know you and i would both
have a lot of things to say there about improvements you know but but for him he really appreciates
that he deploys to the linux environment server side he appreciates you know the the niceties
of linux desktop but he also has certain things he needs for windows a lot of people embedded
in you know larger enterprises they they're hooked on outlook or compatibility with other
issues uh and again i'm sure we wouldn't say like hey you know you could probably just
virtualize that but uh he explored running i3 natively well semi-natively i guess but
natively through windows uh he uses i'd seen people you know i've played a little bit with
the bash shell i know you've played a little bit but i've not played at all with getting
x11 stuff working uh so he uses moba x term and he he was able to set up the the settings
right uh to have the you know have the x server exported right he configures the ubuntu bash
setup he runs i3 and he gets it running i i don't know i'm i really want to try it out
i don't think it would be the solution for me but i can think of a few devs i know that
you know they they're more comfortable windows or windows what there's default are they're
playing games i don't know how i feel about it but it's interesting how far we can go
to really have like a mini non-virtualized linux world i think we're definitely making
progress and i think that we're going in a very good direction and the exciting thing
about some of this stuff is i don't think any of us would organically trust microsoft's
motives but i think where i get super encouraged and super giddy and super happy is microsoft
voluntarily or involuntarily is losing control over a large aspect of this for example they
can choose to implement bash they don't really have a ton of control after that the developers
are going to expect the same environment system inside of bash on windows as they would as
on bash on side of abuntu and as has been exemplified numerous times if that isn't the
case they'll simply log into a vps and do all the work in the vps and it makes it less
valuable go ahead dar but there could be a reversal because what matters is who sets
the expectation and who has the most users that's the trend right microsoft had i'm
not trying to doom the vision i just said that they will transition i'm just trying
to be transparent here microsoft originally was a company that provided software for other
operating systems they became platform because their apps were the most adopted in those
systems and they developed an ecosystem that supported development and how do you arrive
at that microsoft started basically from the get-go as an operating system company i mean
that they're they they competed at the fundamental level by they provided an operating system
to ibm who didn't have a way to function their computers and so when you so when they had
software software that ran and had to run on their operating system and that was like
that from day one yes and no because one of the the biggest department of microsoft that
made money was on the one that was selling to apple they were developing software to
apple but but what developers look at is how they can where are the people that are creating
things that users want and they can make money that's why people moved gradually to microsoft
it's not it's not because apple stopped being a good platform because they saw that this
company not only was able to develop software had an entire developer friendly ecosystem
something i've criticized uh our our ecosystem a lot for not having which is you go to developers
to uh to mdn on microsoft you go to developers.apple.com we barely have something similar provides
a tool chain that you can know this is how you develop for ubuntu this is only now we're
looking at it yeah the quickest we have that the better and easier to fix but they become
a company that provides these awesome tools and demonstrates by building tools themselves
acquiring tools themselves now they become attractive the days that standard again the
day that snap uh we were going to do snap i mentioned to a couple different developers
you might have even been in the room when i had this discussion there was instant throwback
to or instant pushback and i'm hearing well i don't i don't think this is a good way to
go about a prescribed tool chain because the great thing about linux is that every distro
has its own way of getting packages in and that that enables us to have much more flexible
and much more distro aware developers and they're going to dumb all of the software
down to not take advantage of the environment of all of the environment variables because
they have to go with the lowest common denominator and i i guess what i'm i guess what i'm getting
at is that yes this is yes universal apps are a great thing yes we don't have some of
the stuff that that is at its core functionality microsoft windows and mac os x but at the
same time there are a lot of people and the primary users of that operating system that
i think really like those differences and it to some degree this whole universal app
thing is a problem is a is a is a answer to a problem that that only really new people
to linux really have an issue with i have not had an issue of having to get software
for my computer in a very long time chris has not had an issue having being able to
get software in his computer for a very long time now him and i struggle with different
aspects of that he that is true why so he is going to have so it is a there's a two
it's a two-sided coin though on my side of the coin yes i have to go to a ppa and
yes sometimes the software packages are are slightly less up-to-date but there are hoops
but on his side of the coin he can download the latest version of teamviewer but it might
not run and he can download the latest version of lightworks and it may not run and so the
he's got the he has the software availability but because of the the dynamic nature he can't
necessarily guarantee that every piece of software works unless of course we're talking
about you know gnu open source you know all that so if we're the standard yeah right well
okay the standard for somebody who is only using open source apps yes yes true but you
back away from that and you say well the the standard in the it industry for remote controlling
somebody's desktop what piece of software can i be almost guaranteed that they're going
to have on their computer that i could log into well teamviewer is a pretty good chance
that that's going to happen and we don't use that for work i have a i have a different
program and that if we weren't doing it if we weren't going to use it talk about it on
sunday i would talk about it here but totally yeah but but we use it all the time i use
it all the time for personal things where somebody calls in and says hey you know grandma's
computer doesn't work my mother's computer doesn't work you know those things are excellent
examples of where teamviewer works but you know all the coming full circle i think that
i think that you know that that uh i don't know i we'll just leave it there we'll leave
it there that i i think that there there are are different advantages of how you can get
that software and how you get that stuff to work on so uh anyway uh wes it doesn't work
on linux at all and then you're screwed right yeah well that's for example someone who wants
to get for like as someone who needs something for their jobs and it doesn't work on linux
at all and they have to go to this workaround of like using a virtual machine or something
like that so this the solution is more importantly to bringing in things that companies and developers
don't want to mess with this ecosystem that is incredibly convoluted but if someone who's
already in the ecosystem yeah it doesn't feel that convoluted except for when you look find
an application you're like cool they release it as a deb but i use fedora so i use rpms
i can't use this deb but they don't make anything other than a deb but what about someone who
uses debian and they provide provided a deb for specifically ubuntu like there is so many
reasons why this is our current ecosystem is not a good idea like as far as the core
the core operating system it's fantastic but the application layer no yeah so right you're
saying we should all standardize on snaps running on gnu slash k windows i don't yeah
maybe i don't care really i i want the standard application layer i don't care what the distro
decides as the core fundamental format they want to use but i do care that i can have
an application that will actually run on my system and that or as a developer that i can
release an app that i don't have to release four apps for the same distribution based
on the different versions of that distribution or that the fact that i have to release uh
technically 20 packages just to support linux as a whole like that's absurd and if i could
just if i could release a flat pack a snap and an app image and that's it i would be
happy to do that that is at least 10 times better than what it is right now or the more
important thing is when they get the developer they get the packages from a repo that the
maintainer decides i'll update it in a year i'll put out that uh let's just have the crazy
idea what about you treat each distribution as their own operating system and give them
the goddamn freedom to innovate and be different as they wish yeah honestly honestly if people
didn't do different things we wouldn't have the diversity or the benefits we got some
things got adopted cross-wide they took their time fair enough we'll leave it there guys
i really appreciate you guys being here thanks so much it's been a lot of fun hanging out
with you and chatting about linux that'll put this episode of linux unplugged in the
books a special thanks to our mumble room who takes their time every week to be here
michael tonnell our producer rekay our video editor and of course the entire team at jupiter
broadcasting for making this show possible hey if you have any questions comments or
concerns head over to jupiter broadcasting dot com click on the contact link and choose
linux unplugged from the drop down menu while you're there don't forget to check out jupiter
broadcasting dot com slash calendar to stay up to date on current time show times we'll
see you right back here next week
so now if you try tiling uh there's no going back episode yeah here's the thing i gotta
talk kristen to it and i have i have like i've like sort of brought it up kind of in
like a passing sort of way and there's just like i can read people super super well it's
either a gift or curse i haven't decided what uh which yet but it's a gers i think so but
the but the thing is like he i i can just tell it just it does not it does not tweak
him the same way it tweaks me right yeah i actually do tiling but not through a tiling
window miniature i just use i use tiling functionality oh yeah something that's pretty i will say
i do sometimes get away with like if i'm in cinnamon or something like it can at least
do the quadrants which will often be enough if not not all the time but sometimes it's
enough