There's one story I've seen going around more than any other this week, and it's the announcement
of a new project that promises to create a Linux-compatible kernel completely written
in Rust.
The aim is not to replace Linux, but to create something written from scratch that aims to
be ABI-compatible.
In other words, it would support running unmodified Linux binaries.
Wes, I think you're a little skeptical pants about this one.
Oh, no.
I don't know about that.
I think what I like about this project is it's intentionally limited in scope.
The project author is really just trying to make something that's Linux-compatible but
that can run in a function-as-a-service runtime environment, actually using Firecracker VMs,
also written in Rust.
And so, you know, you don't have to worry about things like kernel crashes because it's
not doing long-running workloads.
That doesn't sound impossible, does it?
I actually was thinking of this as more like a tiny VM environment host, our guest kind
of a thing, or container runtime environment that's just this itty-bitty environment that's
binary-compatible.
But I liked that the motivation was the conversation around how could we use Rust in the Linux
kernel?
That kind of evolved into inspiration for this project to say, okay, well, let's take
this all the way.
And it seems like the exact kind of thing that Free Software lends itself to, where
you can have just these, it's not, this isn't necessarily a fork, but you can have these
side projects that may never really ship, may never go into production anywhere, may
never even be a container runtime or a VM guest OS.
But it can be an R&D factory for things that do actually make it in the mainline Linux
kernel.
Yeah, it teaches the person working on this, any contributors, and anyone along for the
ride, you know, like, what does or doesn't work about doing it this way?
And maybe it informs both future operating systems and the Rust language itself.
Now, it is very, very early days.
This isn't gonna, you know, this isn't gonna be like something you're gonna have some weird
distro Frankenstein thing with, with this kernel, which I think is BSD licensed, like
this isn't happening anytime soon.
But I'll tell you what, if it does start to happen, we're gonna give it a go.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent.
Hello, you two.
This episode is brought to you by the all new a cloud guru.
You know, they are the leader in learning for the cloud Linux and other modern tech
skills.
They got hundreds of courses and 1000s of hands on labs get certified get hired get
learning at a cloud guru.com Well, coming up on the show today, it's fedora 35 release
day and we're making a whole theme out of it.
We're gonna have a project check in with Matthew Miller.
He's gonna tell us what's going on over there.
We're then going to do our exit interview with fedora 34.
We had an opportunity to give it a spin later in its lifecycle.
And it's a totally different fedora.
So I want to have that chat and then it's our review of fedora 35 will tell you what's
new, what's different, what works, what doesn't work.
And then we'll round out the show with some great emails, some pics, some follow up, you
know, all that kind of stuff that we do.
So before I go any further, I have to say time appropriate greetings, mumble room Hello
virtual lug.
Hello.
Man, hello, everybody.
It's nice to be back in the studio this week.
Everything's back to normal.
I'm no longer in the woods.
I don't even think it's raining right now.
You're right.
It finally stopped.
Oh, man, that's been nice, although it was raining on the drive in.
So it's really only stopped while I'm in here.
But that aside, I mean, the weather does suck, but I kind of have I kind of have an idea.
Maybe this is stupid with with it getting close to the holidays and all of that.
But there is an opportunity at the Museum of Flight here in the Seattle area to go see
the new Mars rover and the Linux copter, you know, like their clones.
They have a whole Mars set up right now at the Museum of Flight.
And I thought, you know, maybe, maybe some in the audience might be interested in like
a little micro meetup at the Museum of Flight where we go check this thing out.
I don't know.
What do you think?
I'm in.
All right.
Sign me up.
Yeah, you go.
You go.
I mean, we can't go to Mars yet.
I don't I don't think Starship is ready.
This seems like the next best thing.
Yeah.
That would be nice one day to be able to go visit Mars and see the Linux copter.
What a thought.
I haven't really thought it all through yet, but here's what I do know.
The copter and the rover will be there October 30th, so they're there now through April
3rd, 2022.
And I think maybe we should pick something in there sooner than later with the holidays.
But let me know if you'd like to go and do a little micro meetup at the Museum of Flight
Linux Unplugged dot com slash contact or the Jupiter broadcasting telegram group, Jupiter
broadcasting dot com slash telegram or on Twitter at Chris Elias.
Let me know if you'd be interested in a little hyper local meetup.
I know this doesn't apply to ninety nine percent of you out there, but what an opportunity.
I thought if some of us got together and went down there, Wes and I could bring our microphones,
we could capture a little bit of it and we'd share it with you guys.
So it kind of be like you went.
But I don't really have any other details than that.
I guess I've been back for what, two months and I'm jonesing for a meetup again already.
I guess that's how long it takes to get back from the woods and I'm ready to see people.
I guess that's a good thing.
Well, I think it speaks well of our audience.
Yeah.
So let me know.
Contact page is probably the best place.
And once I hear from a few people, if I even hear from I'd say four or five people, really,
it doesn't need to be a lot.
It's just enough for like, you know, like a lunch crew so we can we can share all our
fun learnings.
Although I have to say, I'm a little upset because just about every week I get an email
from somebody in the, quote unquote, Seattle area and I'm like, how come I've never met
you?
Why have you never been to anything we've done?
Why don't you go to Linux Fest?
Like there's a lot of people who listen in the West Coast area, secret Seattle JB fans
out there.
What are you doing?
I think they're all hanging out with you downtown.
That's what I think.
And you guys just aren't sharing.
But that's fine.
That's fine.
Well, I mean, we already had a crew.
There's a lot to invite you.
I'm so far away.
You know, you got to wait like a half hour.
Think of Levi.
That's true.
That is a good point.
Well, this is our Fedora episode and we wanted to have a little project check in with Matthew
Miller.
He's the project leader, perhaps maybe better known as the real beefy miracle.
Matthew, welcome back to Linux Unplugged.
Hey, glad to be here.
And thank you very much for taking the time to join us on release day.
Yeah, absolutely.
It's a little chaotic, but you know, I got some time.
Well, we appreciate it.
And we've been checking out the new release and I want to get there.
But you know, trying out the last several releases of Fedora, I really felt like this
trend picked up momentum in 33, then 34 brought us GNOME 40, now 35 is bringing us Wire Plumber
and GNOME 41.
Where I sit and having watched this stuff for a long time, I think there was a period
of time where Ubuntu was really setting the tone for the desktop.
And I feel like the transition of that baton has been completed with the last several releases
of Fedora, and now it really feels to me like Fedora is leading the direction of future
desktop Linux.
And people are looking to the Fedora project to see what direction things are going in.
And as a result of that, I think we're seeing some better traction with things like Wayland
and PipeWire and the entire ecosystem is improving as a result of that.
And I think it contributes to that momentum.
And I'm curious if you see this from where you're sitting at in the project and what
your, or maybe you think I'm wrong, but just what your observations are about this trend.
I'll take it.
I think people in Fedora have been working on these things for quite a long time, longer
than that.
I won't speak bad about the other Linux distributions at all.
I'm going to try to just completely avoid the comparison.
But I think it's often the case that we've had a hard time getting those out to users
in a timely fashion.
We struggled with meeting our own schedule for a while.
And despite a one week delay this time, it's fine.
We've really been meeting our six month schedules really reliably, which helps.
And we've been doing a better job about kind of talking about the things we've done.
There's been a lot of cases where people working in Fedora, people in the Red Hat desktop team
like actually made stuff that ended up being headline features in other distros first.
So we're actually getting it out and talking about it sooner.
So I think that's part of it.
I think that we generally have a lot of new positive growing enthusiasm and energy around
Fedora as a project overall.
And I think that reflects in what both the actual technical output of all the people
working on it and just kind of all the polish around it that goes into making a release
and then in delivering a good experience to everybody.
So I'll get to my experience in a bit.
But while we're on this kind of trend line here, I'm curious if you can fill in the details
on how something like the following will work for Fedora.
So I've been noticing that Red Hat's been making a lot of significant hires that are
going to have a big impact on future desktop features at some point.
You know, I mean, it's very early because they're just opening the positions.
But I've recently seen positions open for HDR support on Linux.
I've seen more positions open for improving 3D and Vulkan and video.
I've seen hiring in all kinds of areas that are really like the low plumbing of desktop
Linux.
And the Red Hat hires, but that work that's going to be developed, that must be happening
in Fedora.
Is that correct?
Actually, generally, that work, we try to make it happen as far upstream as possible
because it's the right thing to do and it's less work for Red Hat really in the long run,
even if it sometimes feels like harder work up front.
So a lot of that work actually will go into the upstream projects and then kind of by
its nature, but also because the same people are working on it, we then try and bring those
things into Fedora as features pretty quickly and soon.
And it obviously helps when it's the same person working on the thing in an upstream
and in the project itself.
So like the pipewire stuff, I think is a good example of that.
I wonder if you felt like I did over the summer as I saw these positions.
I counted it up for Linux Action News a few weeks ago and I think it was like seven new
positions that have been opened and since then, there's like another position.
So I think in total, it's like eight positions.
It just keeps going.
Yeah.
I saw that as, you know, there's been a lot of talk of post IBM acquisition.
What's it mean for Fedora?
What's it mean for some of their free software contributions that contribute upstream and
some of us worried it could mean like the bean counters are going to get involved and
dial that stuff down and we're now several years into this now.
And it seems like there's actually increasing investment in this stuff that doesn't directly
translate to a rail product.
I mean, I acknowledge there is rail workstation and all that, but you know, I'm getting that
like it feels like this is this is the actual walk that is matching the talk.
Yeah.
Some of that I got a very carefully bracket with, like I can't speak to IBM business or
anything.
I have no idea, let alone like even even if I knew I couldn't.
But actually, the case is, I don't even know.
And my question really is about is, does this feel to you like the real kind of validation
that there is going to be continued investment here from just a personal feeling?
Yeah.
So, right.
So, yeah, I can speak as a person and an employee.
I think, you know, a lot of us at Red Hat were worried about this acquisition, what
would happen.
But we were assured at the time that, you know, well, like that was really important
to them and they wanted to continue to invest in it.
It wasn't it was not an extract money thing.
I think we kind of see some validation in the spin off of Kindle.
I don't know how much big boring business news you follow, but that's happening like
this week, which is like the IBM managed service stuff is basically going away.
So Red Hat is going to be a bigger chunk of the new IBM than it ever was before.
So it's really significant.
So yeah, Red Hat real success is very important to the future of IBM.
And I think we're seeing that borne out.
Another thing that's going on here, there's actually a lot of these things you're seeing
are desktop related technologies, but they're actually hires related to an automotive initiative,
which you'll see automotive keywords and a lot of these hires as well.
And I don't have a lot of the details on that, but it is connected into things that
are, you know, useful on the desktop, but also useful in other contexts as well.
And, you know, the more we can find things that tie all these things together, the more
we all benefit.
It's funny, Wes and I were just kind of remarking about that off air yesterday that even some
of the work in the pipeline is about to enable AV in automotive Linux.
Yeah, exactly.
And then that benefits us all.
So yeah, that's awesome.
I'm down for that, right?
Like I think that's actually been one of the low key brilliant things about desktop Linux
that we underappreciate is how we have been able to leverage where the business is willing
to invest to also enrich the desktop and benefit from that.
It's just like the next level of shared infrastructure, right?
The kernel is doing that and the desktop is trying to do that, too.
Yeah.
Maybe Fedora is the king at that, really.
Yeah, I hope so.
Yeah, I think so, maybe.
So this is, okay, so this is release day of Fedora 35 and GNOME 41 is in here.
Fedora is going to be out ahead with GNOME 41 for a while.
But when you look at the release overall, Matthew, I'm kind of curious, just personally
as a longtime Fedora user, what's jumping out to you?
So yeah, on the desktop, I switched to it when the beta hit.
So I have to remember back to what's new.
But I really do feel like this is a really like a polished release and not in a bad way
where GNOME 40 had a lot of changes and then there's a lot of things that are responding
to people's feedback about that.
Like one of the things that's a big change that I appreciate is there's a setting for
the multi-monitor workspaces now that wasn't there originally.
And also a lot of little things like that were looked at and addressed, I think like
the new power settings, things like those are some nice things that kind of build on
features in GNOME 40 before, so I'm glad to see those things.
I think there's also a lot of exciting things going on in the project, like the Fedora Cloud
work in group is really energized and I was looking at the Fedora Linux 34 statistics
and we have something like 15% of Fedora systems are Fedora Cloud when you look at systems
that are installed over a period of time.
So we don't track individual systems, but we have a thing where systems by default will
report in once a week just with a count me.
And so we can tell if a system, and there's no UID or anything attached to it, so we can't
actually tell which systems they are, but we can kind of get a difference between the
number of systems that just show up once, like test systems and so on, or systems that
show up beyond that.
So of those test systems, 30% of them are Fedora Cloud and like another big chunk of
them are Fedora Container, not surprising.
So it's interesting to see like how much non-desktop use is going on in Fedora as well,
which I think is important because, okay, I was talking about that Synergy and Synergy
is a terrible business word, but just that like thing we get when we've got lots of
different things working together in the same project.
If we were to become just a desktop OS, it's kind of harder to get all of the investment
from Red Hat, but from everybody who has all these different interests working together
in one thing that lists everything.
So I think it's exciting to see, even though the cloud stuff isn't desktop focused, I think
it will help lift up desktop Fedora and just like the enthusiasm around desktop Fedora
and GNOME and so on kind of helps, I think, support that enthusiasm around our cloud offering
as well.
That wouldn't even be there if the desktop weren't there and people were not paying attention
to that.
So I think it all works together really nicely.
Well, you can see that maybe with cloud shipping, ButterFS as the default file system now, right?
After kind of having proven itself over on the workstation.
Yeah, yeah, great.
Exactly that.
That's exactly what I was thinking, Wes.
I wonder if some of that adoption is because of that ButterFS switch.
I've never really thought about it in the use case of like on a VPS, but I actually
now that I'm working through that, I could actually see the logic.
Just like the data integrity stuff, I appreciate that from my photo collection, right?
Like I want to know if some bit rot flipped, like that's important.
And you like the send receive stuff is pretty nice as well for server uses.
Yep.
So I just overall I just wanted to this isn't really a question so much as I just wanted
to pass along how impressed I was at how complete the arm ISO felt.
This is the first opportunity I've ever had to download an ISO image of a Fedora arm release.
Usually it's like I get an image file and I flash that to an SD card and I've never
really gone through like the complete process like I would for a real x86 computer is how
I put it where I get an ISO image and I run through the actual installer and I installed
it on a computer, but I had a chance to run it in an arm VM and I don't think people would
in fact.
In fact, now that I think about it, my son didn't even realize he was on arm Linux at
people.
You just wouldn't know.
It feels like a very complete implementation and you maniacs have all kinds of architectures
you support.
When I go and look in the in those download folders, I'm just amazed at the amount of
ISOs you must be spinning out.
Yeah.
If you have an S390 mainframe, IBM Z, we've got you covered.
I know some people who have power system workstations, is it a laptop, the Talos system?
I've never actually seen one, but yeah, what you were saying, this has actually been somewhat
hard for Fedora because this has always been our aspiration.
When we have another architecture, we want to make it an equal thing and make it, like
you said, you don't need to know you're in a different architecture.
You get the full, powerful, complete operating system.
Some of this stuff where other distributions have been content to have specialized kernels
and stripped down versions, which there's nothing wrong with that.
It's just a different approach.
Sometimes we've been behind because we're not able to get everything out so quickly
because we want it to be so complete.
But then the final result, when it gets there, is you have an amazing, fully functional operating
system that you can know and understand and treat like something else.
ARM is now, I think there's the RISC-V stuff, which is pretty interesting.
I'm talking to a lot of people about that as an emerging architecture.
I'm not going to pick any winners, but I find it really fascinating.
It's basically an open hardware implementation, open source hardware, and there's a lot of
enthusiasm around that.
That's not an official Fedora architecture right now, but there are some unofficial builds
of it, and we're looking at bringing that on maybe at least as a shadow architecture
and then maybe official sometime in the next few years.
I think that's pretty cool.
That is really exciting.
I love to hear that.
I love that you just got your eye on it.
Well, Matthew, will you please relay our congratulations and our gratitude to the entire Fedora community?
They've created another fantastic release, and thank you for taking some time to come
join us.
Yeah, absolutely.
And I'll be very interested in hearing what your experiences are.
So I'm going to run off and do some other things, but I'm going to listen to that later
when I get a chance.
Thank you very much.
Leno.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you support the show, right?
Just like saying, hey, thanks for supporting my favorite Linux podcast.
It's really what makes this work is you guys go there and Linode is willing to offer you
something pretty substantial in exchange.
I mean, $100 that says go try it and go form a real opinion, right?
Like they could give you $15 of credit.
You could start to get a first impression, but they're giving you $100 to really go try
this thing.
They've been around for 18 years making this the best way to run applications on Linux.
If it runs on Linux, you can run it on Linode.
They are our infrastructure, and I suppose I could go get locked into one of the big
huge hyperscalers who has a totally custom weird system.
And I could just just spend money like crazy as people download podcasts, or I could go
like buy some rack space somewhere and some colo, but I mean, that almost feels like caveman
stuff.
Like that's what we did back in the 90s, right?
I mean, and when you look at Linode's pricing, it's 30 to 50% cheaper than any of those hyperscalers
and you're going to get $100 from our offer to actually really try it out.
It's a great way to try out new projects too as things come along.
It's like my R&D place for sure.
It's when you look at the invoice that comes in, like some months there's like all these
weird R&D servers that come on the next month, they're all gone.
And I'm just kind of messing around with stuff all the time.
But I also noticed in the news today that Zoom announced the free versions of Zoom are
going to get ads now, yay, ads in your Zoom meetings.
And this is maybe just one of those windows of opportunity where you can say, hey, y'all,
would you rather switch to something free that we can host ourselves and have control
over?
Because Linode's got a one click deployment for Jitsi.
This could be your window of opportunity.
You get the $100 credit, you deploy that thing, $100 means y'all could try that out for a
while and not have to pay a dime.
They also have lots of other one click deployments or you can go the whole DIY route.
I mean, like nuke and pave and build up your own thing, like I have a crazy esoteric VPN
distro for my PEP wave on Linode.
My peplink router and it has this crazy combo LTE VPN.
And of course, they have their own Linux distribution.
Well, wouldn't you know it, Linode has so many great guides and tutorials, they've even
got a guide on how to do that kind of thing.
And they have super fast networking, incredibly fast rigs, they've just upgraded their MVME
storage.
They're just blazing fast and they support a lot of community projects.
And they've made things like our Jupiter colony reunion road trip possible.
I doubt that made them a ton of money, right?
It's expensive to drive lady jips, but they wanted to make that community connection.
They brought out their own people too.
They were hanging out with us.
It was pretty cool and it's pretty neat to see them do that kind of stuff.
They don't have to do that kind of thing.
So go sign up today and try it out.
Linode.com slash unplugged get $100 in 60 day credit on your new account and your support
in this here show Linode.com slash unplugged.
All right, before we get to Fedora 35, all the hype, all the new things, let's conduct
a Fedora 34 exit interview.
This is something we'd like to do more of something like a chance to follow up on a
distro a little later in its release cycle.
And we should be clear about this too, just because 35 is out doesn't mean Fedora 34 is
going anywhere.
It's going to be with us for a bit longer.
Actually the end of life is scheduled for May 17th, 2022.
So let's see if you're a regular Fedora day to day user and you're not quite ready to
try out 35, which just lands today.
What's life like for you right now?
Yeah, I recently had a chance to give Fedora 34 a go.
And kind of like Matthew was saying, I never do this.
I'm always trying out Fedora as it hits the beta cycle, that I really kind of get serious
as it firms up and what you could kind of consider the RC phase.
And then I'm always doing like fresh installs of the actual released version and I'm doing
upgrades to the newly released version and I'm always kind of in that mode of Fedora's
life cycle and I kind of live there.
I almost never ever go back to a late stage distro, if you will, somehow you've moved
on already.
Yeah, I just don't normally have a reason to.
But I've been thinking recently about how it'd be nice to move my son and then if that
works for him, my daughters over to Fedora because then they'd be on what I'm using.
I want to be able to recommend Fedora to friends and family, but I didn't feel like I could.
And so I wanted to try giving a slightly older version a go and see if that changed my experience
and what it might be for somebody who might have, like my son, a more gaming focused desktop
setup.
Yeah, that's a good question.
Like what does the support life cycle of a Fedora family member actually look like?
But beyond that, I think Fedora 34 in particular, it just had a lot of changes going on and
something of an elephant in the room because when it landed, we were kind of still reassuring
people that Fedora was OK after all the big CentOS news, plus GNOME 40 had just shipped
and was brand new and had a ton of changes that were quite controversial.
And we were switching to pipeline by default.
And all of this was going to be the base for RHEL 9.
I mean, it was just it was a lot of neat stuff and a lot to be excited about, but also a
lot of stuff that had to be tested and maybe had some questions around it.
Yeah.
And so many like GNOME extensions were broken.
PipeWire was causing issues for people that were joining like Zoom meetings.
And so the question was, is what is this going to be like after things shake out?
So we're six months into its life cycle now, pretty much right on the nose.
And I did an update of a Fedora 34 install I did today, just a regular update.
And yeah, sure enough, you know, there's still every few days fresh packages.
In fact, I have to say, because they keep the kernel current and they keep pretty much
everything else current, except for really they just iterate on the desktop environment.
And up to date, Fedora 34 install right now, even as 35 releases, still feels quite modern
in just about every way.
But the thing that's kind of nice now is just about all the critical, if you will, for lack
of a better term, GNOME extensions have caught up to GNOME 40 now.
So the situation there is a lot better.
And I noticed a significant improvement for third party software for Fedora 34.
Like you can go find prepackaged RPMs for Fedora 34 for like a commercial application
or a popular open source app, or they'll have their repository already updated.
Yeah, exactly.
All those things that you're kind of understanding when you're trying out the beta because of
course they don't have support yet.
And then, oh, yeah, eventually they do update.
And the other thing too, Wes, is like a lot of the guides are just not all of them.
Some of them are still horribly outdated, but a lot of guides have been refreshed for
the new version of Fedora.
And so by that point, six months into it, like if somebody is going to update their
guide for Fedora, they've done it at that point.
And that those all those things, they're like they remove paper cuts to switching.
And I actually think a Fedora release six months into its release cycle is sort of sitting
in a special sweet spot in the Linux ecosystem where it's got a lot of kinks worked out,
especially if you grab fresh packages.
It's got pretty good third party support and community support at that point.
It's still because it's Fedora, a very modern install, and you've still got months of support.
So you could just ride that for at least another six months and then upgrade to the next version
that's now becoming the old version of Fedora.
I think it makes a life a little easier and I think this is the one that's the version
of Fedora, the one that's about six months into its life cycle that you can recommend.
And I've teased people before that say, oh, wait a few months when you're looking at it
for like a family machine.
Just wait a release.
That's what you're saying, huh?
Yeah, right.
Wait a release because each each release gets 13 months of support.
So you got some buffer time for everything to kind of get worked out and they don't care
if they're on the latest and greatest.
That's just it.
You're right.
Most people don't care.
I mean, we care, but it's not necessarily rational.
Yeah.
Part of it's enthusiasm driven for sure.
But you know, but it also means I could wait a little bit on my main machine, maybe three
months after release, update a little bit before everybody, do a little checking around,
see how things are going.
You know, like there's I kind of I like this idea that maybe my main rig that I'm on, maybe
three months into that final six months, I upgrade and I figure out what needs still
to be fixed or what works fine.
And then when the next release drops, I upgrade the kids machines.
And then, of course, you've got you know, you've got stream in the mix, too.
If you have something that might need to be even more stable than that down the road.
Yeah, true.
There that could be interesting.
A sent us nine stream for a family, for family and friends, perhaps.
But when we were trying this out, we wanted to give this an honest go like, can I give
this to friends and family?
And what I envisioned is bringing everybody to Fedora, put everybody on Fedora and put
everyone on a tail scale network, which is a wire guard mesh VPN solution.
All right.
So you've got everyone there.
You can access everyone machine just right over tail scale.
That makes sense.
Right.
Super simple.
And if they need support, I can SSH to their machine.
But I wanted to go a little bit further than that.
And I wanted to do remote desktop support.
And I love Rust Desk, but Rust Desk is X11 only.
No.
And, you know, in Fedora 34 and in Fedora 35, on GNOME, the Wayland supports.
It's really nice.
It's you get a better experience now and I don't want to I don't want to go backwards
for them.
I know, right.
Maybe in some ways.
But when Wayland works, it works really well.
Yeah, it's smooth as butter, but not butter, but butter.
But so we were digging around.
You and I were doing this, I think, after we did LAN one day.
And we found that the recommended way to kind of do this now on Wayland with GNOME Shell
is to use the RDP server that's built into GNOME Shell that I think uses pipewire and
all this kind of stuff on the back end.
But we discovered that it's not actually shipping yet.
Some of the documentation talks about it like it exists, but it doesn't actually fully exist
yet.
Yeah.
So, like, you might see this.
You can enable the remote desktop stuff.
But by default, it just exposes it over VNC.
And we gave that a try.
But it's a VNC.
It's not going to be great over a remote network.
But at some point they added via free RDP RDP support baked in as well.
But yeah, there's just no.
Because this is Linux, there's just nothing exposed graphically right now.
And setting it up and enabling it and providing default credentials, well, there's a guide,
but it's not exactly simple.
It wasn't horribly bad.
Like, I think we ended up pulling down a few things from GitHub and building them and then
moving them around, right?
Then maybe we had to start something with systemd.
So there was some futzing.
Yeah, you're right.
We did have to.
There's like a little script that's posted.
We'll have it linked in the show notes that you got to compile and then that lets you
configure like the credentials set up so that you can put a password on it and then you
go in and modify with decomp some settings.
And then I think, yeah, we just logged out, logged back in.
It did work, though, at the end of the day, that that was the part that was pretty nice.
It seemed decent.
Oh, man, it worked really good.
If you had the right RDP client, like we tried a couple of them and I wish I would have written
down the one that didn't work very good.
I want to say it was Romania, but I'm not sure.
But if you got the right RDP client, like Microsoft's RDP client or there's there's
like XRDP, there's a couple with the right settings.
It's impressively high performance.
It's much better than VNC.
I think it was near real time because we had the laptop and we had the remote machine right
next to each other.
It was there's just a very, very slight lag, which makes me think that if I was supporting
them over a remote link, it'd probably be fairly usable.
Yeah, that's that's the test.
But I just need this to work a little.
And it would work for family support machine, I think.
I think it would actually do the job.
So the only problem is, and I haven't tested this yet, dang it.
Now that I think about this, I wish I would have.
I'm not sure if this is going to break when I go from GNOME 40 to GNOME 41.
And I just did that on my machine that we we did this test set up on.
So after the show, I'll see if RDP is still working on it.
We've got some follow up to do.
Yeah, I should have thought of that.
I was just you know, I was so focused on getting the upgrade and so worried that it was going
to break my Fedora 34 install, because as I was going through this little journey.
To see if this was a usable setup.
What I ended up with at the end of my Fedora 34 walk, if you will, is one of my all time
favorite Linux installs.
I really liked it.
It doesn't happen very often anymore, but it became precious to me and I was worried
that the upgrade would break it.
I know that's how much I liked the 34 experience six months into its life cycle.
I'd say I was impressed, but it felt early days when it released.
But six months in, it became my favorite setup I've ever had on that ThinkPad.
It really it really rocked.
So yeah, I think this is a really capable family distro if you just give it a little
bit for the community to catch up to it.
As well, Fedora isn't as just crazy moving forward as Arch.
It is fairly out there on the edge of things.
So I don't know if this is just me being crazy, but Brian, I kind of actually feel like maybe
we'll get into this in our review, but I kind of feel like this might be the perfect Fedora
set up for you.
Oh, tell me more.
Why do you think that?
Well, if somebody came to me like I have this, I have I always remember this conversation
I had.
There was this buddy of mine who was this big time PHP developer and he said, Chris,
I am so frustrated with Linux.
I just want to get my work done.
And he said, I installed Ubuntu and I can't remember what it was.
It was probably like eight, ten or something.
It was a long time ago.
And he said, you know, this isn't working.
That isn't working.
My PHP environment is broken and went on and on.
And so I introduced him to the Ubuntu LTS model and I said, here's what you need to
kind of whenever the LTS was kind of new.
So I don't know how long ago this was.
And I said, this is kind of what this is what you probably want to be running for your kind
of workload.
And Fedora doesn't offer anything like that.
They don't have an LTS version.
They have 13 months of support.
And then, of course, there's sent off stream, but it's not really quite the same comparable
desktop environment yet.
But I think this this model that we're talking about here where you kind of you ride six
months behind release is essentially as close to an LTS model as you're going to get with
mainline Fedora, because the upgrade experience is pretty smooth and the reliability and community
support is pretty high.
So when you want to troubleshoot in the middle of the night, you can find a guide online
and you can get it fixed instead of having to wait for somebody to, you know, like figure
it out, who's still like maybe waiting for the bug report to come in.
Right.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Like, it's those are all things I love for sure.
Yeah.
It's a more reliable target for the for if you wanted to be in the Fedora user land,
but you wanted that kind of reliability, I think that's the target right there.
Well, and to be fair, I do the same thing with the Ubuntu LTS right now.
I wait a few I wait several months, actually, because the reality of how much engineering
goes behind these things is that there's just inevitably some stuff that once you get it
out to users, there's like thousands and thousands of users who find all these bugs and things.
And then it's so three months later, six months later, of course, going to be more polished.
So I think that's a good strategy for anybody who's risk averse.
Maybe it's a good way to put it.
Or the first job is that it's a work tool.
The second job is that it's a tinker tool, right?
Like my see my think a lot of times my ordering slightly different, like sometimes tinker
tool is above work tool on some of my systems.
But you don't have seven systems like I do, right?
So you've got to you've got to narrow that focus a little bit more.
So honest, what I'm saying is if you came to me, like we just met at an event and you
and I didn't, you know, know each other and you said, Chris, what Linux should I use?
I'm a photographer and I want to be very reliable and I have a lot of things going on right
now and I need to be able to just open up my computer and have it work and perform well.
I would today if you asked me that I'd say fedora 34.
I don't think I'd say anything else.
I'd say go get fedora 34 and bring it fully up to date.
unpluggedcore.com want to support the show directly go to unpluggedcore.com and become
a member you get the full live feed the very long version of the show if you'd like or
you can get a nice cut down version with limited spots that Joe makes his full production you
know it's got all the Joe quality it just a little bit shorter runtime which can be
nice if you have a shorter commute but you also are supporting the show and on top of
that you're going to get access to special promo codes when we have new merch if and
when I'm not saying anything not announcing anything but I'm just saying if new things
were in the works and they were going to be announced as a thank you to our members we
offer discount codes so you can support the show get discount codes on new jb merch and
of course you get access to the two feeds the live uncut feed or the fully produced
shorter limited ad feed that's just a thank you for everyone out there who supports us
at unpluggedcore.com okay I think we've stretched out long enough we got to talk about fedora
35 it lands today and the way the fedora release cycle works is they kind of have some target
weeks and they release when the blocking bugs have been fixed or a solution is in place
it's not so much a date driven release as it is things aren't broken so we can ship
release and I have to say I'm I'm actually completely fine with that model and we just
kind of watch the bug tracker because it's all out in the open and you all can kind of
just follow along and find out when they're gonna release and yeah you know we get it
when it's ready why not yeah no rush and this version features gnome 41 which has been
out for a little bit in fact it looks like gnome 41.1 is just about just about out and
it includes in gnome 41 some improved power management options which we can touch on in
a little bit also like Matthew was saying those new controls for how the virtual desktop
layout I guess is how I'll say it works with virtual monitors and some more work on that
RDP back end that we were talking about and I have to say the thing that I'm most excited
about is the continued evolution of pipe wire in fedora and wire plumber as the session
manager so in fedora 34 we got pipe wire and under the hood it was kind of just using some
some default hard coded logic but pipe wire can do a lot more than that and so what wire
plumber is is it's a session manager that's going to enable future customizing that we
might use here in the studio of routing audio and setting things up in a very particular
way eventually there'll be things that sit on top of wire plumber there's some graphical
applications in the works right now one called hell VM I think that is a GTK patch bay it
really actually kind of replicates the patch bay of the early days of the music industry
where you're taking a wire from one device and you're running it to another device and
that's in the works right now and underneath that will be wire plumber and you'll be able
to save different sessions so you could maybe have like this is my jitzy meeting session
where my audio comes from my microphone and I also am taking audio from my other browser
so maybe like you have Firefox as your second browser like I do you could have a wire plumber
session that brings audio from your USB microphone and from Firefox and sends it in as an input
device that you have selected in your video meeting so you could play audio from your
web browser into the meeting or from VLC it's it's going to give you this kind of flexibility
so when you hear us talk about pipe wire and you hear us mention wire plumber the session
manager what you're going to get as an end user for you never going to do audio production
is you're going to get that kind of flexibility you can do a you know a VoIP call with somebody
and route audio in there and have your own soundboard if you want and have your own wacky
zoo thing or maybe you want to screen share your web browser and you want to play a presentation
and you want to capture the audio from that as well now you're going to be able to do
all that kind of stuff and what wire plumber does is it lays down the session manager piece
of this that's going to manage how this stuff works Wes am I explaining this appropriately
yeah I mean I think so because I feel like I'm kind of not doing a very good job explaining
it wire plumber replaces the you know some of the stuff that was built into pipe wire
by default that was kind of a just a simple bare bones version and but you can think about
you know pipe wire has all these facilities but you kind of have to make actual configurations
of those actual sessions actual arrangements of everything and you need something that
can help manage that and provide tools for other things to interact with it and that's
basically the layer where wire plumber fits so yeah as an end user unless you get into
the details of pipe wire you probably won't care about this but this is one of those pieces
I mean like I play around with pipe wire all the time building it from source I hadn't
set up wire plumber I was still using the other stuff this is like the area where fedora
is taking these disparate pieces and really thinking about it and building something more
coherent together yeah I'm looking forward to it Neil give me an idea of what we're going
to get down the road in the future like wire plumber is going to enable a lot more than
we have today but I don't think I'm giving it justice here the biggest thing you want
to think about when it comes to wire plumber and pipe wire is that what pipe wire actually
does is quite a lot more than what people see right now so pipe wire can manage audio
sources and audio syncs we're all familiar with that part we introduced that in 34 and
the other part that it has that we've had for quite a light longer but we've just really
not talked about it is the fact that can manage video sources and video syncs so this means
for example if you do a screen share through the pipe wire portal api to redirect an application
or whatever like you know how that apex rdp window fx i for remote fx thing that windows
has you can do something similar with this and the cool bit is because wire plumber is
a session manager for pipe wire that can manage sync sources and sites you can do programmatic
redirection of those things too so you can do things like orchestrate the connecting
of various different syncs and sources for video as well as audio from various sources
like a camera if they're going through lib camera into pipe wire out or a screen share
or an application share or any of these other things like for example you were talking earlier
about remote desktop through rdp and yes it does use pipe wire underneath pipe wire and
wire plumber contribute to supporting the ability to do these sorts of things in the
future if there's interest and development around this you could also see things like
an implementation of something like windows's remote effects which does you can do per application
shares and screen sharing or replication on like remote connections to applications you
know like you have a more powerful server computer running gnome on it with the application
running there and then you could screen share the application itself back to a weaker thin
client those kinds of things become possible there's all kinds of interesting things that
you can do for vdi use cases for instructor cases for screen shares for video conferencing
for music production for concerts for whatever you want when it comes to av there's a pipe
wire pipeline in there i love the sound of that and we're going just a little bit at
a time but overall when you look at other initiatives in the past i think i'm pretty
happy with the with the rate of progression there is a known bug right now some people
have no sound after they upgrade we'll have a link about that in the notes essentially
maybe for some reason wire plumber didn't start appropriately so if you have that problem
after you upgrade there is a note about it it's a known problem and a note on how to
just quickly start it up it's not that bad i guess i lied you should know about wire
plumber yeah maybe so so i did the upgrade on that fedora 34 install on my thinkpad
and overall things went really smooth you know it really didn't work as expected were
a few gnome extensions a lot of them actually have updated for 41 that's nice to see but
not all of them so you know you're gonna get that if you upgrade on day one but and i'm
really happy to see this if you have that new gnome extensions app when you log in for
the first time to gnome 41 on your recently upgraded fedora session or whatever it might
be in the future maybe it's a bunt or debian or whatever arch um that extensions app will
give you a notification that says hey man some of your extensions have updates and aren't
loaded and if you click it it launches the extensions app and that extensions app gives
you an overview of which extensions have been disabled which ones have updates again and
then it puts a banner along the bottom of the application that says the next time you
log in i'm gonna update some of your extensions for you would you like to log out now and
you hit that and it logs you out you log back in they're up to date and if they're compatible
they're up and going my doc extension for example hasn't been updated my tray icons
i had tray icons reloaded that hasn't been updated yet but anything that's pretty essential
to the use of gnome shell for me that's been updated which is a pretty minimal set now
and then i have like a nice to have set so that's good i mean outside of that really
no issue i haven't tried rdp yet but all of my apps work i think flat pack's doing a fair
amount of the heavy lifting there a dream of containerized applications alive in fedora
35 yeah and i think it's i think it's a good use case for things like slack and discord
and element and all the other there's a few other ones that are electron base that i have
to have open and you know shipping them as flat packs kind of makes sense i kind of like
having them sandboxed as well and so that just all goes really smooth works pretty well
for me but i didn't have quite the same experience brent did because i think brent you tried
out the plasma spin right yeah we were talking about you know last week talking about which
one i should try and we kind of went back and forth you said oh you got to try the gnome
implementation because it's fabulous obviously you're a big fan of it i actually decided
to try the kde spin because i'm super familiar with kde and i have to say that i hardly spent
any time in modern gnome so i thought i don't want it to be so different of an experience
that i'm not really focusing on the usability of it or the distribution itself so i decided
to try the kde spin and as some context i will admit neil that i haven't used fedora
for more than like a few minutes ever so this was my chance to really dive in and and chris
has been basically talking really positively about it for a few years now so i thought
okay now's my chance so if you want to find uh what i ran which was fedora 34 five's pre-release
the kde spin it's actually a little confusing to find uh if you go to fedora project.org
it just kind of redirects you to the main releases so you have to go to spins.fedora
project.org i found that as a someone who wasn't that familiar with fedora to be kind
of confusing to find and i tried it on some bare metal i had a have a thinkpad x240 that
i guess i found in my basement that i wasn't using and so i decided to uh throw that on
a usb and give it a go directly on an SSD i didn't know anything about fedora so i did
dive into the docs first which i think is probably a good idea um one the most uh worrisome
thing was about how to update packages i know it used rpms but i didn't quite know how to
go about doing that and i loved the documentation it was good enough like it went into enough
detail to get you where you wanted to go or i should say get me where i wanted to go with
my level of um knowledge about linux and stuff but it wasn't so exhaustive that it was hard
to find what i needed so kudos there for whoever's writing the documentation i really really
appreciated it i also uh here's a skill testing question for you chris and us um do you know
what dnf actually stands for oh man yes i do but now i've forgotten now that you asked
i feel like i could like stall and be like well you know it was uh inspired by yum which
was the yellow dog update manager isn't it like the dandafied package manager or something
like that right yeah i chuckled there and so i thought okay the door is gonna be fun
i really appreciate this and i know yum has a lot of history and i don't really know it
that well but i've heard a lot of good things about dnf so use the kd live disk and uh usually
my typical method to do this is i have my main laptop in front of me and then i have
some friend's laptop or family member or some laptop i'm playing with and i like to use
my main system and just do a vnc session over to that other system so i have the keyboard
that i'm used to and all of the programs and i can look up you know notes in my regular
applications and from the live disk uh that didn't really work for me and i was sort of
i was like okay well it presented a black screen i was like okay this is likely a wayland
thing because i knew that was an issue in the past so i can do without that so i continued
with the anaconda installer and i know a lot of people say it's kind of clumsy and stuff
and i thought it was fine it was actually kind of nice and it was pretty visual which
i appreciated uh i did notice there's encryption as an option disk encryption which i love
and i always put that on laptops because i do a lot of traveling and stuff so that was
a really important thing for me another thing i appreciated was that it told me my password
was awful by doing a dictionary word check which is such a small little thing but i think
for new users chris like you're suggesting for family and stuff that's actually really
nice um i was using a terrible password because i didn't care to you know it's just a testing
machine but um that was actually a really nice thing that i think everyone should have
so uh there was one question or a warning that i didn't understand and i'm gonna read
it to you guys and even on mumble i want you to try to figure out what it means so this
was in the encryption section so i was encrypting doing some disencryption and it said warning
you won't be able to switch between keyboard layouts from the default ones when you decrypt
your disk after install so what are they actually trying to communicate there okay okay you
won't be able to switch between keyboard layouts when you decrypt your disks after install
i think i know what this is okay what are they saying wimpy if you've used special
characters in your encryption passphrase using say a french canadian keyboard and then try
to decrypt that using a u.s english keyboard those special characters are not going to
align it's got to be it he's got it and i have run into this previously and i think
anyone who's spent enough time with decrypting disks at boot you will eventually run into
this but anyways i thought that was worded a little confusingly maybe visually it's a
bit different than than that but anyways it all worked fine and it only took about eight
minutes to install which was really uh lovely actually but that's where things started going
poorly for me on the first boot you get the background of fedora and i am a visual person
and i thought the background they chose which is not a technical thing but i thought it's
like this teal almost like seafoam green pool reflections photograph i believe and it just
made me feel a little queasy i think guys what was your take on that with all due respect
to the to the art team yeah because i often like what they do um literally on every single
install of fedora 35 i've done the very very first thing i did was change the background
i find it kind of jarring i know west did you have that i bet if anybody's gonna be
chill about it no i had to say i had the same reaction i've really liked some past ones
i was trying to give it an open mind but now that this default background is i mean i generally
don't bring it up but yeah i i agree i first impressions are important right yeah doesn't
speak to the rest of the release yeah yeah so then i thought okay well i'm gonna try
you know i've installed it i'm gonna i'm gonna try this vnc thing again because i really
want to use that um so i'm used to using the krfb which is a kde um i guess vnc server
uh has worked amazingly for me in the last several years um and i went to use the menu
launcher and it just didn't do anything and i thought oh that's odd i'll just ignore that
for now and actually now that i'm thinking about vnc maybe it's a wayland issue and i
i knew that uh so maybe i'll try x11 so i logged out and uh logged into x11 and the
krfb menu launcher worked fine um and then i tried to connect to vnc from my other laptop
and uh that just crashed krfb oh so i certainly wasn't going to use my preferred vnc methods
yeah i'm sorry brad i'm so sorry yeah so i decided to unplug my main laptop you know
from all of my stuff and switch the two and just focus on the fedora stuff which is fine
so i thought okay well the next thing i like to do typically on a system is play with some
of the uh you know install some minor things like htop and i don't know sometimes you have
to install ssh server and stuff like that so i'm going to do these um basic applications
that i like having so dnf is the first time i use it fair enough uh but it's super simple
so i just did dnf install htop that simple because i wanted to see okay what's it going
to do how's it going to work and it started downloading a package but it wasn't very descriptive
and then it just kept going and going and i thought okay htop i know is very tiny what's
going on over here um and so the description it gave was fedora 35 x86 64 and that's it
and it was just downloading it downloaded 61 megs of stuff and i was quite confused
because i knew that was unlikely wow where are you seeing the 61 megabytes if you've
used apt or most other you know it lists a package on the left and then gives you a progress
bar of how much is downloaded on the right hand side it gives you the total download
or how much time is going to you know be left in your download fair enough i don't have
a great internet connection here so 61 megs actually was kind of depressing here's what
i'm wondering you know because when you are on fedora brent for the and you install something
using dnf for the first time if you haven't first updated the repositories it will do
that for you automatically because that's actually one of the things that drives me
crazy about apt is it will actually let you go ahead and install something even though
it's looking at all old versions of the packages because you haven't updated the repositories
yet so what dnf will do is it will say okay now actually i have to first refresh the repositories
but on a new install it might be pulling that stuff down for a long time and because you
know i notice it takes forever to update the repos when i'm on a bad connection too and
that and because dnf does do that so frequently it makes the overall experience feel kind
of slow you know i think that's a great insight and i can't remember and my notes aren't good
enough to tell me if i did update um sort of the indexes beforehand i typically do because
that's my process with apt and this seemed like a very easy translation from one to the
other um but i kind of wish it just described that a little bit better it was a bit cryptic
to me yeah yeah after it continued sort of doing a bunch of stuff it did eventually change
that to suggest fedora 34 x86 64 updates but even that was kind of cryptic and so i didn't
love it but anyways it did ask me about downloading htop so after you wait for all of the refresh
of the repos and all the dependencies to be met you get your 170 kilobyte application
yeah that's that is sometimes the dnf experience so after all of that i decided okay well i
know i want to try wayland because i haven't tried it that much so i'm gonna i'm gonna
log out and go back and um when i logged in back to the wayland session krfb decided to
crash again just on login so i knew that wasn't gonna be any hope i did decide to change the
desktop as you guys did but i ran it immediately into some weird issues uh i was changing the
wallpaper and the apply button never appeared so i couldn't actually make that change commit
and like that's such a small weird basic thing and it made me really worried actually about
all of the other things i was gonna want to try because it's like one of the simplest
things and so i had to quit the settings application come back and then it worked but it was like
okay well what else am i gonna run into um so i decided to do a system update because
i knew okay well i'm on i'm on a pre-release and i downloaded a few days ago maybe some
people have you know i knew the release was going to be today but immediately i typed
dnf upgrade and it gave me a little bit of information it said there's a problem with
some of your packages so i hadn't done any updates yet and already there was some conflicts
that specifically being a kwin common requires kd decorations conflict it said it was trying
it cannot install 523 and 522 at the same time and literally this was a brand new system
i hadn't done a single thing so that too worried me because what was gonna happen next i bet
you got caught right in the switch over to the newer version of plasma perhaps that's
definitely a beta thing that couldn't what can happen sometimes although it's not common
is some of the packages land but not all of the packages land for the next version of
plasma that could potentially be what happened there right and and now that we explore this
here i'm seeing how this likely led to all of the other issues i ran into so i updated
the whole system that way and rebooted and then things just things just did not work
like abysmally did not function properly oh no i hate to say that because i was so excited
about this but upon reboot i tried to log into wayland and i just got this login loop
and it never ever would log into the desktop so i was like okay i know i can try the x11
session so i did manage to get logged into the x11 session and i thought okay i'm gonna
get some work done so i plugged in my external monitor and this was the beginning of the
end the super key on my keyboard didn't even open the menu which is really frustrating
and then the taskbar was on one monitor but then the menu when i clicked on it appeared
on the other monitor and none of the window controls were available on any of the windows
which is probably that conflict that i ran into uh because it had to do with kd decorations
so that's likely the issue but then i thought okay well it's been 12 hours and it's release
day etc etc maybe i'll just bring up a terminal and try to like update again and maybe some
of these things will be resolved and so i you know control alt t to bring up a terminal
and i literally got only the toolbar functions i did not get a terminal i did not get window
decorations to move things around so i it was just that was the point where i said i
can't go on that i can't there's nothing i can do i can't even troubleshoot this thing
is like uh so i had to give up and that made me really really sad oh no there's a lot to
this and there's several i think really important lessons here and one of them is this is why
betas are not like for production use fair enough there was a warning sticker on it but
still oh yeah and we know that right when we're going into this we have we always have
that in the back of our mind we know that in fact you know like if if you were to install
today and had these problems i'd say okay well it's time to start you know making out
some bug reports but i think what you got caught in is a beta transition that does happen
but i think that's a good thing for people to know listening to this that if if if say
someone is basing their impressions on that they got to give it a little bit uh and this
goes back to what i was saying about if you caught this say six months in you you installed
fedora 35 in six months i bet you this entire experience would be smooth as butter for you
all that stuff's completely worked out and that's where i think it makes that that's
where it's really in a sweet spot it's in a special kind of place it's in a special
sweet spot for desktop linux six months into its release cycle and right now it's still
early i think too one of the other things you probably got bit by is there was some
and i have a vague recollection one of the blocker bugs was related to something in plasma
and it was one of the things they had to fix right before release and it may have may have
been this conflict i looked at some of the common bugs and didn't see any of those but
maybe that is just for the main release not the spins and i think you're right like i
liked the experience errors aside enough to give it another try after you know maybe in
a few months wouldn't that be an interesting thing to do is do a follow-up review with
it in a bit and try it again and see what it's like well how about we do that okay all
right we do that but one thing that i worried about and maybe that will change my perspective
in a few months is how distributions treat their you know this is this is an official
spin and it seemed pretty officially busted like maybe i'm one of the only people who
ran into that but i i really hope that the next test in you know a few months is very
different because i worry that the spins don't get the attention that the main release does
the plasma spin has been on a on a trajectory of becoming more and more serious for the
fedora project like now for example a a serious bug in the plasma spin is a blocker for the
entire fedora project right that means that they're not going to release the gnome version
if something's wrong in the plasma version so they are they are taking it very serious
now but and they might they might push back on this but i'd kind of argue that wasn't
always the mindset uh but i think what you have here is sometimes very late in the in
the phase they have to fix something and that was something they were working on but we'll
do the follow-up and we'll see how it is in a little bit and you know when at some time
one of these days i'll get you to try out my gnome setup the way i have it and see if
you like it yeah i could use it to her i'd appreciate that oh yeah maybe you you bake
him an image you just ship it over there brent flashes it on tries it chris's way could do
so mr pain you got your hands on fedora 35 would you try would you think yeah well i
played around with the uh you know the main gnome version a little bit but then i thought
i'd i'd go even more out there than brent i played with kina white oh yeah right there's
silver blue version that's plasma based yeah come on immutable desktops for everyone including
plasma and flat packs for days it's been a while you know i have played with silver blue
but it's been a while i was at 33 i don't think i tried it for 34 so it has been a little
bit but i i was pleasantly surprised now you know i love don't love anaconda but it does
work it works just fine did seem like the kina white install took a little bit longer
but other than that it felt just like a normal fedora install of course things get a little
bit more interesting when you have to do some updates or start messing with the file system
or packages or anything like that because it's immutable rpm os tree based system it's
it's really neat i i think this could be a great development workstation for me personally
as um you know someone who tinkers maybe a little too much with some of my systems there
probably be one too many roadblocks but but for like a software development workstation
admin workstation just getting work done where you don't have to do a ton of packages or
customizations or you're fine with doing most of your things in flat pack and toolbox it's
really nice i was impressed how well this just worked in the katie environment i mean
it's not perfect discovers lacking some support for really working with rpm os tree for instance
but the flat hub support and discover was really nice because i you know i can just
turn flip that on and i got everything i need it is uh encouraging to see that kino night
development because i don't know if it's necessary that silver blue and kino night be two separate
projects but i think you're you're never going to have silver blue that can support both
plasma and gnome unless kino night exists it has to kind of be the project that keeps
the plasma torch burning so that way that silver blue doesn't become just a gnome thing
yeah you need somewhere to organize the the effort of all the little details that need
to get changed or fixed or packaged to make it a good katie experience and the idea west
of that i got a really rock solid workstation that has this os tree approach to very careful
updates and that combined with something like plasma and you know butter fs potentially
like i mean i'm really seeing some seriously awesome workstation potentials just around
the corner in the future plus it comes with you know a bunch of the latest stuff like
python 310 which just recently came out that's here like if you're using fedora you're up
to date which which is you often want for development yeah all right well i'm glad you
had a chance to kick the tires one question i have for you west and maybe chris you have
some insights or someone in mumble is um why make this if they have silver blue why put
some effort into something like this as well what's the what's the reasoning behind it
i think it is mostly just right now silver blue has always kind of been built with a
gnome first kind of perspective and so you do your software management through gnome
software and it's kind of using that entire pipeline and there hasn't been a bit much
focus on making sure that a system like silver blue will work with something like plasma although
it should right but and that would be the time now to start validating that out and
not years down the road when perhaps silver blue starts to become pushed as the predominant
workstation spin maybe of fedora could happen yeah i mean these these big desktop environments
really do have their hooks into a fair bit of how the system works and so yeah it ends
up being that there are things you need to think about when you've so radically changed
the system with these immutable variants so while we're talking about this a big thing
that makes all of this work is a lot of your application all your applications right are
flat packs and flat hub integration with gnome software landed for all the different versions
of gnome that use it so including the just a standard workstation version but it's not
like the full flat hub but it's pretty close but it's not full flat hub explain this yeah
so i mean you can still of course enable flat hub as you always have you know by manually
doing that but but now fedora's providing a filtered list of stuff from their own repository
that they've sort of gone through and approved and made sure that doesn't cause them problems
to include it's an interesting start and it means that that some of these applications
that you might want are already there without having to do anything that's that's really
nice for a new user yeah and of course they do have that filter public which we'll link
to in the show notes if you're curious i was like well what are they filtering out uh it's
in there there's nothing really all that surprising in fact it mostly just seems like obvious
organizational stuff but it's nice to see them including the flat hub because flat hub
has really grown uh it has if you haven't been over there in a while go pop it up in
your browser flat hub.org and take a look at just like the new app section or something
like that so having that built in to gnome software is a pretty solid experience and
i'm glad they did it even if they have to take out some stuff for platform reasons or
legal reasons or or whatever it might be and once you noted we've got butter fs on fedora
cloud now that's good to see yeah right marches on go go a little butter fs go and nice to
have if you are using um fedora cloud does seem like a good sort of polished release
all around there's other stuff in this this release that we talked about like um making
sure that user services are restarted after upgrades which is especially important when
you're doing all kinds of audio stuff like pulse audio or pipeline running in the system
d user level instead of at the system level they've also started shipping the power profiles
daemon in fedora workstation enabling it by default and it's just those little things
you know those little things that the distro is thinking about for you that make fedora
you know a little more like a mainstream desktop and a little less like an arch setup yeah
real quick this power profiles thing's interesting and a lot of us are going to have a different
experience because the way it's integrated with gnome settings in your power area you're
going to see different stuff depending on what your hardware supports and it's even
integrated in with your thermal sensors and whatnot so for example if your laptop's running
super hot it doesn't make high performance mode available it'll even have a little grayed
out text that says we gotta wait here your laptop needs to cool down something to that
effect but if your hardware doesn't support this stuff you see limited reduced options
so they're only revealing stuff that your hardware has support for but it also means
that a lot of us see different things and i know this is true because i've tried it
out now on vms and several different physical boxes they're all different the thinkpad has
the sweetest integration like i i think wes i sent you a screenshot where it's like high
performance mode has been disabled while the laptop is in your lap what yeah it's impressive
honestly i mean this also kind of speaks to the added challenge that these you know desktop
environments linux distros have to to work on all kinds of hardware and make an interface
that can work in all the situations so we have the link in the show notes to go download
plus a link to some of the common problems people are hitting right now but we'd also
love to hear your experience what you did to make things go smoother i'd also like to
know what didn't work so we can put the word out head over to linux unplug dot com slash
contact and fill us in on your experience and your tips and your tricks now we are kind
of running out of time so we're gonna just do the pics really quick because we got something
super cool i think wes found it it's a nintendo switch emulator and i gave it a go oh you
did yeah you jinx i don't know how to say it but it's an experimental switch emulator
written in c sharp it's in the a u r as you would expect uh and so i gave it a go on the
arch box and um i immediately started getting error messages that i knew not what to do
with it's something about some some file missing that you have to go get but they're being
cagey about you anyways it is legitimate though and the gooey works and it promises
pretty good compatibility and what's cool about this project and we have it linked in
the show notes as i said um it is emulating the hardware really like accurately of the
switch so game compatibility is good it's like pretending to be the right arm cpu and
the right gpu and it's getting a lot of that right so even things like the newest metroid
game that just came out appear to be working in it i kind of got to give it a go it recommends
you have a system with at least like 8 or 16 gigs of ram which probably most of us do
and you know some cpu yeah this is really neat and it looks like they've got a pretty
nice website set up as well as a blog and i always find that the work that goes on behind
the scenes to make this kind of stuff possible just fascinating it's worth worth worth a
read i have to be honest when you linked it i was like oh another one of these huh you
know how's that guy but then i wouldn't check it out and i'm like this looks legit and so
i went the next step and gave it an install and i mean sure enough it installed and i
got the gooey launch but then it just sort of uh it just sort of broke on us um all right
we gotta wrap it up there because we're going kind of long uh i i'd love to have you join
the love plug we do that on sunday every sunday at noon pacific in our mumble room you can
get the time at jupyterbroadcasting.com calendar and remember it is time zone wonkiness because
europe does the daylight savings now ahead of the u.s so keep that in mind that's why
i just say go to the calendar page and you can get our mumble server details at linuxunplug.com
mumble we'd love to have you join the love plug and then who knows maybe you got a tuesday
sometime you can join us live because we do the show live on a tuesday see you next week
same bat time same bat station yeah that's right noon pacific 3 pm eastern jblive.tv
you got it you know it wes knows it linuxunplug.com slash matrix if you'd like to join our matrix
community and we'll have links to everything we talked about today at linuxunplug.com slash
four three zero including all kinds of extra goodies in there you never know you never know
it's like we back it up with the links we got the documents to prove it it's all over
there plus our contact page or subscribe the whole shebang and it's going to render in
your web browser it's incredible thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode
of the unplug program and we'll see you right back here next tuesday!
all right way too long i declare there is no posho today posho's been cancelled we've got to
cancel it what you're hearing right now this is not a posho don't think of it a posho we're not
doing a posho it's not that we don't love you it's just that you know we don't want to kill joe
so this isn't a posho there's no posho can i still have my dessert yeah of course i
ice cream for everybody