Anybody in the mumble room having Wi-Fi issues?
And do you have a Chromecast?
Because it turns out that's all it takes.
Have you heard about this?
Really?
Wait, what?
Yeah, so router vendors are going to be pushing out
firmware updates.
Google's actually known about this for a little while.
There's an issue recently with Google's Chromecast,
if you have it on your network, and you launch the YouTube app
on the phone or device.
When the YouTube app wakes up, quote unquote,
this is the documentation language, when it wakes up,
it does a broadcast packet to see, actually,
anything that supports Chromecast does this.
It's not just YouTube, but this is the most common one.
It does a broadcast to say, hey, is there any Chromecast
devices here?
I'm awake, and I would like to be able to broadcast to you.
And these packets are normally sent
in 20-second intervals, which in network timing
is a pretty long time.
But it turns out there's a bit of a bug,
and sometimes the devices will broadcast
a large amount of packets at very high speeds
in a very short amount of time.
And it's around 100,000 packets instead of a 20-second interval
where it sends a packet.
It's hundreds of thousands of packets
as fast as your little device can cram it
over your Wi-Fi network, overwhelming routers.
And it's pretty much all of the major ones.
NETGEARS acknowledges this.
Linksys has acknowledged this.
ASUS has acknowledged this.
TP-Link has acknowledged this.
And Google themselves has acknowledged this.
Although Google says it impacts a small number of users,
and they're committed to providing a fix in short order.
Does it affect OpenWRT and LEED?
I would think it'd be possible, but because it's
like an overwhelming DDoS.
It's not necessarily like a flaw in the software, I think.
Right.
Does it impact Google hardware, specifically like Google Wi-Fi?
If you have, no, I don't know about Google Wi-Fi.
But if you have a Chromecast, and a lot of us do,
and then you have an app on your mobile device that
supports Chromecast, this is what you get.
What about half-supported devices?
Thankfully, both of my Chromecasts
are powered off the TV.
So if the TV's off, the Chromecast's off.
Same, yeah.
Wonder if Roku's can affect this.
They accept some Chromecast.
Well, it's on the Chromecast side.
It's sending out the packets from their Chromecast.
And it uses UDP.
There's no congestion control on UDP.
Exactly.
OK, so my Chromecast is getting unplugged today.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 232 for January 16, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's fending off the plague, talking brand new Linux
hardware, and answering your questions.
My name is Chris.
And I'm the beard.
Hey, beard.
Beard's joining me this week, but not Wes, because Wes got
poisoned by Beard, so that way he could step up and actually
be in the intro.
So we got that taken care of.
Good job, sir.
Now, also coming up on this week's episode,
we will go through a whole bunch of community news.
This episode is really going to be all about the community,
about stuff they're working on, about upcoming events,
and then answering a lot of your questions.
And Barton George from Dell will be joining us
to talk about the new XPS 13 developer, the Sputnik
line of their sweet Infinity edge-to-edge display laptops.
Well, they just shipped out a brand new one
with the latest eighth generation Intel processors,
a bunch of new features, Ubuntu 16.04 installed by default.
So Barton will come on.
I'll pick his brain about the new machines.
And then I'm going to ask him a couple of questions about,
because he's in a large corporation,
so he's maybe the perfect person to ask sitting
at Dell in a large corporation shipping Linux desktops.
Barton, what's it going to take to get Linux
on every machine at Dell?
What would it take for corporate systems
to be able to switch over and get out of that Windows trench?
And we talk about that.
We talk about big trends that Dell's getting ready for that
are coming down the pipe.
And we talk about the transition to 1710, Gnome,
a little Meltdown Inspector.
It's all coming up later on in the show.
So I think it's going to be, what are they,
like not a doorstopper.
It's going to be, I need a good name.
Mumble Room, what's a good name for what this week's about?
And hello, Virtual Log.
This is like a blowout episode, right?
It's Barnburner.
It's a Barnburner!
That's exactly what I was looking for.
OK, hello, hello, hello, Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greeting.
Hello.
What's up?
Guys, boy, it's good to hear all your voices.
I missed you guys.
It's been a long week.
But the only thing that really got me through this long week
has been the good news coming out of the Plasma project.
So we've got a couple of different things
to cover for the Plasma desktop.
I figured you Plasma desktop users have
been yearning for some coverage.
So there's a new LTS in the works.
It's the second long-term support release
from the Plasma 5 team.
And they're working on fixing speed and stability.
It's a speed and stability release.
Boot time for the desktop has been improved by reviewing code
and getting rid of anything they found that blocked execution.
They've been triaging and fixing bugs
in every aspect of the code base,
tidying up artwork, removing corner cases,
and ensuring cross-desktop integration.
Interesting.
Specifically in regard to the performance,
because that's what got my attention,
they say we have been concentrating on speed and memory
improvements with the 5.12 LTS release.
When Plasma is running, it now uses less CPU and less memory
than previous versions.
The time it takes to start Plasma desktop
has been reduced dramatically.
And Plasma support for running on Wayland
is now more complete and more suitable
for a wide range of testing.
So they're ready to bake it into the LTS release.
And they have got output resolution scaling working,
screen rotation, enabling and disabling outputs
through Kscreen, automatic screen rotation
based on orientation sensors, automatic touch calibration.
Ex-Wayland is no longer required to even run the Plasma desktop.
Big one right there.
Yeah, and Wayland Windows can now run full screen.
That's a big one for the beard.
Kaywin's been integrated with their night color system,
which is awesome.
That's so cool and kind of removes the need for people
to even run Redshift anymore on the Plasma desktop.
And the compositor is now automatically kind of smart,
depending on the desktop and the input and responsiveness.
And if you're using Wayland, there's
been a lot of work there.
So this really is being positioned as the Plasma
desktop to use.
It's version 5.12.
It's in development right now.
And they seem pretty excited about it.
I'll defer to the Mumble Room for a moment
if anybody wants to talk about Plasma.
I do have a second part to the story, though.
So going once, going twice.
Hey, you know, it sounds great.
But I hope, for their sake, that they lose the reputation
of being bloated just with this release.
You know what I'm saying?
Yeah, yeah, maybe.
I mean, I think that's sort of been, well,
boy, it's really what's your definition of bloated.
Because resources-wise, I feel like it
hasn't been that bloated for several releases now.
In fact, I was shocked when I started
running Plasma for a while how little resources are used,
based on just what everybody said.
So that's one version of bloat.
But another version of bloat is the package mess.
And I know this is a soft spot, and they
don't like people talking about it.
But just two days ago, I was going through and updating
my last remaining Arch system.
And of course, there's a conflict
between some standard accessibility feature
and a Plasma desktop accessibility feature.
And I have to choose between one of them.
And either one of them breaks a series of dependencies.
And just as a thought experiment,
I went down the path of what would happen
if I tried to uninstall the Plasma desktop accessibility
version.
And it unwinds 35 packages, which eventually ends up
at uninstalling the entire Plasma desktop itself,
because I want to remove a singular component.
I just wanted to uninstall the accessibility metapackage
and just remove the accessibility stuff altogether
because it was hanging up my update.
And then I would reinstall it later if I wanted it.
But to get there, I eventually got
to the point where I'd be uninstalling the entire.
It's so intertangled with everything
that that is another kind of bloat.
And that's a reputation I don't know if they're
going to get away from for a while.
They might be able to conquer the reputation one.
But people will still be throwing that bloat term
around, I think, because of that package mess,
unless somebody could snap all that up.
Yeah, that's something they were trying
to get rid of when they went on to Plasma 5 and KDE
Frameworks 5.
They were trying to get rid of all that dependency issue.
And now I'm hearing and actually using it, too.
It's just when the needle's at 11 and now it's
been dialed back to 7.
But my opinion, there's more dialing back to go, I think.
JJ, you had a question about the undestructible desktop.
Are you talking about the Bulletproof project
we had a while ago?
Yes, sir.
I was sort of trying to point that also in terms
of your recent crashes with Gnome and comparing that
to switching over to a new desktop possible.
Yeah, the unbreakable Bulletproof desktop project
sort of is what got me going down the path of solace
for a while.
But then I ended up having some issues with Budgie,
and so I moved off.
And that's sort of when the project died.
However, recently, as a thought experiment,
I've thought about how it might be fun to just poke
at Fedora Atomic Workstation.
So I'm going to try to have someone from that group
on in a few weeks to talk more about that as a possibility.
That kind of transactional update, whatever it might be,
if it maybe comes via snaps and flat packs,
or if it's something that's for the entire way you deploy
all software on the system, more like Atomic,
there may be a solution somewhere in there.
I just don't feel like we're there yet.
I do genuinely feel like we're on the right track to that,
in part because of snaps and flat packs and Docker
and all these other things that we love to hate too.
Yeah, and personally, I'm sort of on this similar boat
with me switching back and forth
between Ubuntu distributions,
but I've been stable on Ubuntu Mate for a little while.
Yeah, it is a nice landing spot, isn't it, Mr. Wimpy?
Wimpy, I was just thinking of you
because you and I have gone back and forth
about the transition to Wayland
and some of our different thoughts
about what kind of transition
that may actually end up being.
And so, Wimpy, I wanted to know what you thought
about this post on the Kaywin development blog
about Kaywin is now considering X11
as indefinitely feature frozen,
that their support for X11 is feature frozen.
They'll still do maintenance, so security fixes and whatnot,
but specifically, they won't be making
specific improvements to X11.
Kaywin won't be adjusted to any new requirements
in the X server, Mesa or the input stack
or proprietary drivers.
If something breaks, it's the fault
of those components which broke it,
and they're going to be focusing their effort,
their development efforts on Wayland
after Plasma Desktop 512 ships.
What do you think about this, Wimpy,
about going just all in on Wayland
and saying that X11's done, it's done?
Well, KDE are in the fortunate position
where they've invested a huge amount of effort
over the years to keep pace with Wayland as it's evolved,
and the only two desktops right now,
or rather, the only two desktops
that we've had for a long time, Gnome and KDE,
have arrived with Wayland support,
so it makes sense for them to invest in the future.
And that's their project decision.
I mean, if they feel it's ready for prime time, then.
That's pretty political, I'll admit.
I gotta say, because to me, I feel like a lot of users
are gonna have a super rocky transition to Wayland.
I wonder if it's not gonna be 10 times harder
than the community expects it to be.
I don't know about this, because what I haven't done
is I haven't run a Wayland-composited desktop
or window manager other than Gnome 3.
So some of the rough edges that I've seen on Gnome 3,
That's a good point.
I don't know how that translates to things
like Sway or Lyri or KDE.
Yeah, point well made.
You could be absolutely correct there.
And Martin points out in the blog post
that they've sort of architected their,
essentially their Wayland system, their KWIN,
they've architected it in such a way that
they don't really need to implement a lot of stuff
at that level.
If you read through the blog post,
he says that there will be new features that'll come along,
but most functionality in KWIN is independent
of the windowing system.
Any improvements to the areas that benefit Wayland Annex 11,
so if they make some new feature,
and he gives examples like tool tips on decoration buttons,
improved blur effects, or rework of side desktop effects,
they're making those improvements to KWIN.
They're not necessarily X11 or Wayland specific.
Both X11 and Wayland users will get that stuff
because of the way they've architected KWIN.
And so with that in mind,
I think it does make a lot of sense.
I think that's actually a pretty good move.
And it does kind of make me want to try out Plasma 512,
probably eventually 513,
because that's really when all this stuff lands
is Plasma 513.
Does kind of really kind of make me want to try it
because you make a fair point, Wimpy.
I think the bulk of my experience
with a few exceptions has been Gnome 3 on Wayland,
and I may have made some assumptions
based on that experience that aren't fair.
So I think when time gets right,
I got to spend some time on KWIN and Wayland
and just see how that compares.
That's a good point.
All right.
It's some really, really good news this week.
We talked about it pretty in depth on Linux action news,
but I'd be derelict in my duties
if I didn't tell you guys about this here
on the unplugged program.
The city of Barcelona is switching to Linux
and open source software in a pretty smart way,
and they're doing it in a pretty smooth timeline.
So first of all, the first thing they're really doing
before they've even switched out a single desktop
is they're going to invest 70% of their software budget
into open source software development.
Then they're creating a transition period
that lasts until the spring of 2019,
and they're going to replace Microsoft Office
with LibreOffice.
They're going to replace Internet Explorer with Firefox.
They're going to do that type of transition,
and then once everybody's up and running
on these applications,
and they've developed the new backend applications they need
and probably like web versions of them,
that's an assumption on my part,
they're going to move people over to Ubuntu.
They're going to just ship with the Ubuntu desktop
instead of trying to build their own desktop,
which is really where Munich went off in the weeds,
and they're already running 1,000 Ubuntu-based desktops
right now as a pilot project.
This is how you do this.
They're doing essentially all the things right here.
Like, I was joking with Joe on Linux Action News,
but I kind of want to know what you think, Beard,
is this the silver lining of Munich blowing up
in the Linux community's face,
and the fact that it was a public thing
that Microsoft fans like Paul Thrott today
is making a Munich joke on Twitter today?
But maybe the silver lining is cities like Barcelona
can watch that and go, oh shit, don't do that.
Yeah, learn from their mistakes.
I think that's exactly right.
I mean, you just do a staged migration.
That way, if you have problems,
you can roll back that one specific step
instead of the whole thing.
Yeah, I hope this works.
JJ, you have thought about government
and funding of open-source software?
Well, sort of the usage of a software in government,
like a lot of these systems are Windows-based,
and a lot of them are using older versions of Windows,
and hopefully this Barcelona example,
it seems to be doing all the right stuff,
and like you mentioned before,
and maybe it'll bring a spur to some certain universities
that are reluctant to support Linux,
or certain companies, certain support companies.
Currently, I'm in a university where their IT department
sort of looks down upon Linux at this moment.
Yeah, I've been there.
Boy, that seems like an attitude of 10 years ago, though.
That's sort of unfortunate to hear that in 2018.
Well, I mean, thankfully, some of the professors
are somewhat like one of the professors
that just transferred over to my university.
He's sort of been a pro-Linux advocate,
sort of been, even though he doesn't say,
like, he uses Linux for his code examples and all that,
but he's not like, he's like an advocate,
but he's not like outright wears it on his sleeve,
if that makes any sense.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I can understand that.
Well, so Popey's drawn my attention to it,
so hashtag blowing Popey.
Thank you so much, Popey.
Breaking news right here on the Unplugged program.
This is CNN breaking news.
Crypto is ruined.
Everything is ruined.
This is why we can't have nice things.
Bitcoin has gone bust.
Popey, you're our Bitcoin reporter on the scene.
What are your thoughts, sir?
What's your analysis of the current Bitcoin crypto market?
All crypto coins are down.
Your analysis, sir?
Those red colors, they're not good, are they?
I don't think so, yeah.
It seems like those are bad, right?
And they're way over on the far side.
You see how far over they are?
That seems bad too, right?
Yeah, they got minus signs and everything.
That doesn't look good to me.
Oh, you got a prediction
if this thing's gonna go down to 5,000?
What do you think?
I know you're a big follower.
Yeah, I think everyone should switch to Monero.
There you go.
Yeah, okay, okay.
I had a prediction on the Ubuntu podcast
for the end of year predictions
that said that in December 2018,
the price of Bitcoin would be,
give or take a couple of thousand dollars,
the same as it was in December 2017,
and cited a massive crash,
but a recovery that we've not seen in Bitcoin before.
Yep, as soon as I heard that prediction,
I said to myself,
shit, that's way better than my prediction.
He's absolutely right.
And I knew it.
In fact, after I thought to myself,
I wouldn't be surprised if in the next month
we see this thing get down to 10,000,
and now here we are at 11,000.
I hate making predictions about Bitcoin.
I totally blame Joe for that.
I'm just kidding, Joe, I don't.
It was the meme-y thing to make predictions about
at the end of the year.
Yeah, it was huge.
Yep, yep, and now it's going down like crazy.
You know, I still maintain that open source currency
for fun internet money
or for clandestine worldwide transactions
still has a value.
It's still, I think, I don't think,
I don't know if it's Bitcoin.
See, the problem, I think what happened was
is people started realizing that,
at least in my opinion,
that these transaction costs were getting to the point
where essentially you had unusable Bitcoin.
If you had like some Bitcoin Satoshis hanging around,
they were unusable.
You couldn't, you would have to spend more
than they were worth to get them
to even move across the network at any reliable speed
for any kind of like online transaction.
And I think once that really sunk in with people,
this is what happened.
Maybe if they would have solved the blockchain,
the block size issue months and months
and months and months ago
when it was a hot topic at the beginning of 2017,
we might not be here right now.
But they punted on a solution.
Several forks emerged as a result.
And this is, I think, that playing out right now
because the network became unsustainable.
Just too slow, too expensive.
It is probably gonna come back up eventually though.
So I'm sure people will call it a fire sale.
There was an article, I don't know if you saw it, Wimpy,
going around that, it was pretty popular,
so you may have, going around that just several,
just a couple of key Bitcoin players
were moving the market as much as 40% some days
back in the Mt. Gox days.
Just a couple of people.
I can imagine in the Mt. Gox days that was fairly easy.
That was, those were dark days.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it seems to be getting,
it's interesting though,
that story is getting a lot of attention today.
So it's back from the Mt. Gox day,
but today's the day that it's getting passed around
a lot online.
And who knows, by the time this episode
actually is available for download,
it could be down another $5,000.
I don't mean to laugh, I'm sorry,
I know some people are dying.
Jeez, I've always kind of figured this could happen.
All right, well, I want to give an overview
of a bunch of really cool community events
that are coming up in just the next couple of months,
including, oh, you know what I don't have a link for,
is that there are flaw stocks.
You guys, so you guys in the Mumble Room,
if you have any upcoming events in the community
that you want to spread the word about,
I'll give you a few moments to think about it.
So prepare your links, get them ready for Discord,
and then we can mention them here on the show
if you have any.
And I'll take a moment and I'll thank Ting
for sponsoring the show while you guys prepare yourselves.
Linux.ting.com is where you go to get $25 off a device
or $25 in service credits.
This is pretty sweet because they have a CDMA
and GSM network, so you can probably bring a phone
and get $25 in service credits.
And the way Ting works is you only pay for what you use.
Your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes.
No contracts, you just pay for what you use.
It's $6 for the line and your usage.
Average Ting bill is gonna be around $23
per month per phone.
That's amazing.
Think about that.
I went from, before even all the taxes were done,
and the final bill was higher than this,
but like right around a base bill of $120 a month
for my three phones, and I think that some,
I don't know how it goes from 120 to like 165
after all the crazy taxes and weird fees.
It just, it seems unsustainable,
but yet they make billions in revenue.
And if somebody could get in like a Starship Enterprise
and go around the sun and turn back time
and then relaunch wireless networks,
they'd all have to do it this way.
It's pay for what you use.
You just pay for however much you talk, text, and data you use.
They give you really good tools to control all of it.
I've been a Ting customer now for three years
and called them twice.
One was because I was doing something crazy with a MiFi,
and the other was because I didn't know
you could actually activate a phone
on their website at first.
It's like, what company lets you do that?
But they do, and it's great, which means now,
like I turn MiFis on and off like crazy.
It's just, it's perfect for me
because I take advantage of both network CDMA and GSM.
They always have a very active blog.
They're talking about right now a referral giveaway.
You can check that out at their blog.
Just start by going to linux.ting.com.
That'll take some money off a device
or give you service credit,
and then you can get started
with pay for what you use mobile wireless.
Linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com,
and thanks to Ting for sponsoring the unplugged program.
Okay, guys, so does anybody have a community event
that they want to pass along?
I'll give a plug for one that's coming up
in just a couple of days to warm us up.
Devconf.cz is a 10th annual free Red Hat-sponsored
community conference for developers, admins,
and dev-op engineers, and many more,
and it's in the Czech Republic.
So I'll have a link to that in the show notes
if you're gonna be there.
It's the city of Brno, B-R-N-O,
so I'm probably butchering that,
and it's at the Faculty of Information Technology.
I have all that information in the show notes.
January 26th, I believe, is yes.
The 26th through the 28th online registration
is already open if you go to devconf.cz.
Give them a little mention
because that is coming up right around the corner.
The other one that's just not too far,
at least in my world, is Linux Fest Northwest 2018,
April 28th through the 29th.
You know Jupyter Broadcasting's gonna be there.
We're gonna probably do something different
than we've ever done before.
I don't quite have it all worked out,
but we're thinking about potentially attempting
to record one of each show that we can there.
So instead of just sitting there on the livestream
and just sort of DJing and just sort of shooting the S,
we'll actually be doing shows live there,
maybe all of the shows if we can, as many as we can,
live at Linux Fest, maybe pulling different appropriate
guests for different types of shows.
Alan will be there with us and it's always a great time.
So April 28th through the 29th, Linux Fest or lfnw.org.
They have a call for, if you want to talk,
they still have an open presentation.
You can submit it now for like a couple of more days.
So get that in if you want to do that, lfnw.org.
And then Floss Talk Live, which I was gonna get more
from Joe on and I forgot, cause I'm a bad person.
But, or no, was it-
Good job, I'm here now then.
Oh, well then there, look at, geez.
Geez, you just say his name and he shows up.
That's, so was it Floss Talk we were gonna,
now I'm actually thinking it wasn't Floss Talk.
I'm thinking it was Fozdom, actually, now that you're here.
So Joe, what the hell's going on?
Tell people about it.
So Floss Talk Live, not Floss Talk Live.
Ah, that's what I, I knew I was mixing something up.
Yeah, yeah.
So it's a live event that's happening in June.
Okay.
And it's, well, we've done it for the last couple of years
in the summer.
It's in a small pub in King's Cross in London.
And it's traditionally been Linux Voice, Ubuntu Podcast,
Linux Luddites, or Late Night Linux.
And then a mashup show featuring Stuart Langridge
and Dave from Geek News Radio.
And it's just been an excuse to get together, drink,
and watch some live podcasts.
Nice.
When is it?
Do you guys have a, do you have like the,
I know the site's, is the site updated yet?
I don't think so, right?
No, I haven't updated the site.
I've updated the Twitter, but not the website.
All right, so it will be at fostalk.com
eventually for details,
and then go check it out on Twitter right now.
I'll put a link to the Twitter in the show nizzles.
There you go.
So maybe we'll-
We've got our hotel room already.
Yeah?
Oh, GC now?
Now I'm getting FOMO.
God dang it, guys.
Come on my own show and give me FOMO.
It's the 9th of June, by the way.
So everyone put that in your calendar
if you're around London, the 9th of June this year.
Very good.
The 9th of June, 2018 for a drunken mashup
of a bunch of different Linux podcasters.
And go say hi to Mr. Popey, he smells great.
And so it's always a pleasure to bump into him.
Joe, thanks for popping on real quick
and setting me straight,
because I was going to blow that.
Yeah, no worries.
I am out and about.
That's why I sound a bit different.
Yeah, no, I still appreciate it.
All right.
Well, so then, of course, there's the next event,
the granddaddy event that always gets a lot of attention.
And this is the last one I'm going to mention this week
before we get to Barton.
And that is Scale16x, March 8th through the 11th
at the Pasadena Convention Center in California,
which has a new vibe this year.
They're kind of really trying to push a new vibe.
They wanted to make sure I knew about it.
They wanted to make sure that late night Linux knew about it.
So they sent us information about a Libre photo workshop
that's coming up and even a photography walk
around Pasadena, which actually would be kind of legit.
If you're going to Pasadena,
why not go out for a photography walk?
That actually sounds kind of worth it,
because you could always use a walk
and it's kind of a beautiful area.
And so they're focusing in for at least one of the tracks
on Libre-free tools to work with graphics.
And they're going to bring a collection of artists,
projects, developers, and just, you know, users
that just want to make the best possible-looking art
on a free desktop.
So Libre Graphics at Scale is going to present talks
designed for general audience of users and developers.
They're going to vary in subject matter from tutorials
and workflows to project announcements and packaging.
Specifically, that'll be Friday the 9th of March
from 10 a.m. to 1700.
The 16th Annual Southern California Linux Expo.
Anybody in the Mamba Room planning to go?
Really?
Just me?
That's so sad.
I don't know what's thinking about going.
Well, you know, I don't know exactly.
I haven't fully figured it out, but I think I'm going.
I have trouble getting vacation time, so yeah.
Yeah, my boss makes me go.
So.
Ha ha.
We'll be at a company thing in Budapest,
so it'll be difficult for us to go.
Oh yeah, okay.
All right.
Okay, I'll be lonely there.
But you know, I'll just hang out
with all my other Linux friends.
That's fine.
You guys just make it a good party.
That's cool.
We ought to just sync up our schedules ahead of time.
We just get a Google Calendar,
so that way I can make sure I'm always
wherever you are, Poppy.
That's really what I want to go for.
So you can find out more at sociallinuxexpo.org.
That is for scale 16.
And I'm going to be there in some capacity,
there with Noah doing our thing,
trying to pull him constantly away from all the ham guys.
That's what Noah does.
Noah goes there, he gets a feel for the layout,
and then he just goes and hangs out
with the ham guys all the time.
Because they've got the cool toys, they really do.
And they're proud of it.
So it's actually kind of a blast.
Let's get Barton on.
The XPS 13 is, it's kind of this strange beast.
Because if you just go out on the web
and Google search XPS 13,
you get something that runs Windows 10.
It's probably not what you're looking for
if you're listening to this show.
But you've heard that there is,
there is specifically a version of it that runs Ubuntu.
We've talked about it many times.
I've done reviews in the past.
Went down there to Dell last year,
got kind of my eyes on all of the different products,
including things outside the XPS line.
And so there's this sort of Skunk Works project
called the Sputnik project that we've covered on and off
that's been brewing in the background.
And it's been getting more and more prominence
at dell.com too.
Like now, today, if you go to dell.com slash developers,
or dell.com slash Sputnik, you find it right away.
There was a period in time
where it was kind of like buried on the Dell website.
It was like, wasn't clear.
Is this something they're really into?
But we are now seven releases,
the seventh generation,
we're seven releases into this product line.
Over five years now into this product line.
And they've been iterating on it over and over
and over again.
And so last week, middle of last week, I think,
they announced the new XPS 13 with eighth generation
Intel processors and all of those goodies.
So I wanted to bring Barton on to talk about it
because I honestly, I expected Dell to blow it by now.
I just thought, nothing good lasts forever.
And they've been doing it for like five years.
I just kind of thought, it's gonna slip, it's gonna slip.
But they've proven me wrong.
So when I saw the new release,
I immediately fired off an email to Barton,
said, come on the show.
So before we go to Barton,
let's stop right here and thank DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program, DigitalOcean.com.
You go over there, you create your account
and then use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, it's one word,
and you get a $10 credit.
And they've just recently adjusted their pricing
to make it even more competitive.
And they got a new website too that is gorgeous.
DigitalOcean.com, create the account,
use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, and then go dig around.
They got the best dashboard.
Every other vendor in this area
is attempting to rip them off
and they can't even compete
because DigitalOcean doesn't stand still.
When they're not making their features better,
when they're not adding things like monitoring or spaces,
or when they're not doing those things,
they're revving their website and they're revving their API
or they're publishing amazing documentation.
They just do not stand still.
It's such a great service that anytime I wanna try out
a new open source project these days,
anything that's server-based at all,
I don't even bother with a VM.
I just go spin up a droplet in seconds.
I've been talking about it this last couple of weeks,
it just blows me away for Linux action news.
Just over the weekend,
I'm gonna try out NextCloud 13 for the weekend.
Let's see how that goes.
I'm just gonna try out NextCloud 13
with the new NextCloud talk.
I had that up and running in five minutes,
but you're in a combination of 50,
I think I would deploy in, I say usually 40 seconds,
they say 55 seconds.
I mean, it just spins up so damn fast,
it almost doesn't matter.
You get a system up and running, you pick the data center,
they have data centers all over the world.
I chose Ubuntu 16.04, I SSH into that sucker.
I then immediately did a pseudo snap install
NextCloud dash dash edge, I think it was,
to get the NextCloud 13.
So that was within, I don't know,
two minutes of creating the create machine button.
I was installing NextCloud 13,
and then by minute three,
I was pulling up my NextCloud,
you know, the final configuration wizard
in my web browser on my desktop
off of a DigitalOcean droplet.
And then I could do calls,
and with DigitalOcean's incredible network speed,
40 gigabits coming to those hypervisors,
so I'm sitting there doing the,
it just, it blew me away that I just,
back in the day, I used to take,
it took me two to three, sometimes a month,
to get a new server.
And now I can do it in five minutes,
I have the whole damn thing set up.
It's really incredible.
They have cluster deployments,
they have different kind of optimizations
for different compute types, pre-build applications,
or you build the whole thing from the ground up.
It's really awesome, it's a really good service.
DigitalOcean.com, try it out,
and use our promo code DOUNPLUG.
So we've got this new fancy XPS 13,
there's only one thing to do.
So joining me to talk about the new XPS 13
is the horse's mouth, essentially.
It's Mr. Barton George.
Barton, welcome back to the show.
Well, thank you, yes, horse's mouth.
You don't mind if I call you a horse's mouth, do you?
I love that one, I'm gonna put that on my business card.
You know, it's not a comment on your physical appearance,
it's just a comment on your authority on the topic.
Oh, authoritarianism, yes, I like that.
Well, there is one source I go to
when there's a new developer edition,
and it's your blog, and I don't know how you guys did it.
I mean, you're supposed to be screwing this up by now,
but it looks like the new, what is this, the seventh gen?
XPS 13 is- Yeah, exactly, yeah, seventh gen.
Knocking it out of the park, I'm impressed.
Which is a bit confusing,
because we're one behind the Intel generations.
I wasn't gonna say it, but-
Featuring the eighth generation.
Yeah, and so people, I got that on Twitter,
some people say, wait, shouldn't that be eighth generation?
So. Now, you know what?
I have a feeling with all of the Meltdown Inspector news,
you may actually catch up eventually,
or they'll catch you or something.
And pass them, man, I think that's, you know.
I think that's very likely.
This will just set our sights low.
Well, so the XPS 13, it's like the,
it's the laptop in the Linux world
that really needs no introduction anymore,
which is a pretty remarkable achievement,
if you think about it, and it's been around
for how many years now?
Is this the fifth or seventh year?
Well, you know, the fifth anniversary
was end of November last year,
so that, and by fifth, I mean, anniversary,
I mean, the first one came out then.
We had about six or seven months before that,
that we really flew to market with that,
as far as going from PowerPoint to product.
So, but yeah, we do the counting
from the first product ship.
Well, so- So five years.
Still what seems like the best screen
on any laptop in the market.
I'm surprised that it's still just like,
I mean, nobody really seems to be touching it.
And it's not me that's even saying that anymore.
You probably saw this,
but Linus Torvalds posted on Google Plus
that when he tried out all the different laptops
in this category, the XPS 13,
not only was it the one he went with,
the developer edition, but he liked it so much
that he also bought a second one for his daughter.
So that's pretty high praise.
I think he actually, I think it went,
yeah, yeah, no, exactly, you're right.
I do remember that.
Yeah.
Well, that kind of thing didn't go unnoticed by us,
believe what you mean.
I would imagine.
So it really is the laptop that needs no introduction,
but I'll be honest, you're supposed to screw it up eventually,
but it just seems to be getting better.
It's got an i7, what is it, 7,500U i7,
all the way up to that, 16 gigs of RAM, 512 gig SSD,
4K screen, under $2,000.
Oh wait, it's got one terabyte option as well.
Oh, okay.
Okay, well that probably puts it over the $2,000 mark.
But it starts around what, 900?
So that's the entry price?
Exactly, yeah.
And I should also say we're keeping the previous one.
So if you give them numbers, so one's the 9370,
the other one is the 9360,
and we don't use those numbers usually for marketing,
but I use that.
You can search on Google on those terms
and the right ones will come up.
Yes, also, if you go to dell.com and check on,
I think you can look on Developer Edition or XPS 13,
it'll show both of those.
Ah, okay, and why are you guys keeping, why?
As opposed to in the past where one has replaced the other.
And that's, and you're asking why is that?
And that's because they're at two different price points.
They're not that far apart,
but there are folks who are gonna say,
hey, Quad Core, I don't really need that.
I'd rather save the money and get something
that is more appropriate for what I'm doing.
Yeah, and the, I mean, I have a fifth generation
XPS 13 Developer Edition.
Oh, well, there you go.
And it's still a great machine.
So I could imagine the sixth generations
would make a lot of people pretty happy.
You also have a non-4K version with a 1080 screen.
How well do those do?
Do the 4K sell a lot better
or are you selling more of the 1080s?
Do you know, can you say?
Well, you know, I don't have the actual split,
but we get people who want, you know,
I don't wanna drive a monitor that,
that, you know, that kind of resolution.
You know, the other thing is just tangentially,
whatever we offer config wise,
there's all these folks who say, dang, that's, you know,
if I would have bought it, if it just had this config.
And so that's one thing we're compiling is
what are the configs that people are saying
that they would want?
You know, what combination?
And then we'll go with, see if we can add it.
Cause we get a time or two during the life cycle
where we look at, well, does it make sense to drop
or add a, what you call it, the config.
And that's the point where we go and we look at the,
how well is this selling versus that one?
And so if you get one that's only selling 5%,
you drop that and you think, okay,
what else might be something that people would enjoy?
So along those lines, I've noticed something
that's actually the absence of something
that you guys are doing and it has to be intentional.
So I want to pick your brain about it because it's,
no, it's something that I think other OEMs
need to take a lesson from.
And it's, when I get a Dell XPS 13 and I boot it up,
it's not Dell, Buntu, it's not like a custom version
of the Mate desktop that's been themed for Dell
and has Chrome pre-installed and Eclipse IDE ready
to develop and push applications to the cloud.
It's just Ubuntu.
It's about as vanilla with a few changes here and there
that are probably just for like driver support or whatnot.
I mean, it's obvious at this point
that this is a very intentional decision.
Can you talk about that a little bit?
Yeah, I think in the beginning, although people did say
when we're collecting initial feedback,
we did get a lot of people, it was before we launched it,
a lot of people saying, hey, I just want vanilla Ubuntu.
But we thought, hey, we can really add some value here
by doing a couple of things.
We're going to pick the utilities and tools
that people want most and we'll load those.
And we'll also go and we're going to create this thing
called the Cloud Launcher, which allows you to take LXE
and take what you create on the laptop as a micro cloud
and then push that out to the cloud.
And we're going to do this thing called the Platform Launcher,
which is going to allow you to take software stacks
that are pre-created and load them up with dependencies,
everything, get them good to go.
I'm seeing other manufacturers do that currently.
This is something they're embarking on.
Yeah, and so we went down that path.
What we found though was the utilities and tools,
people really wanted to pick their own.
That wasn't much value adds, we stopped that.
The profile tool turned out to be a heck of a lot harder
than we thought, and so that on top of the fact
that we didn't have people clamoring for it,
we put that aside.
And then the case of the Cloud Launcher,
serendipitously, this company called Docker came along
and did what we were trying to do,
is get a way to write the application
that you have on your laptop and then get it to the cloud.
So we started out with these grand ideas of value add
that the customers would love,
and in the end, we're at that vanilla point
that you just mentioned.
Interesting that the developer community
seems to be of the mindset of if we want it,
we'll just load it ourselves, which is less work for you.
That's like the best, that's the best of, right?
Oh yeah, no, exactly.
That's interesting.
I think just in general, just sort of zooming back,
targeting this at the developer community has been great
in that they offer lots of feedback.
They also can, certain issues they can, or tweaks,
they can work amongst themselves to do.
And so as long as you speak honestly and are transparent,
there's a lot of feedback and help
that they're willing to give as well.
Well, you know, one issue that comes to mind
that it's the number one question I get
when I review an XPS product, it's about the coil whine,
which is not unique to the developer edition of the XPS 13.
It's something that can happen
because of just the, I would assume the compact electronics,
but maybe you can talk about that.
But it wasn't until I started reviewing it for Linux users
that I started hearing about it all the time.
Yep.
So how is that in the new release?
And were the Linux customer base
or the developer customer base, as you put it,
were they particularly demanding in that kind of issue
in a way that the Windows users weren't?
Like where does that all stand today?
Well, I think, so, you know,
well, I can't go into too much detail
because it involves third parties, et cetera.
And, you know, anything we say, oh, it's perfect now,
and then somebody has an issue with it,
that's not gonna look good.
And somebody, no matter how perfect anything is,
something's gonna come up.
All right, so we got a big couch here, but I follow you.
Yeah, yeah, no, I think it was a small subset of folks.
That being said, if you were one of those lucky subsets,
that wasn't a good thing.
And I think too, there's also a tolerance level for people.
So there's certain people that would,
whose parameters were more acute than what we set.
Sure.
Say maybe you or I or somebody else
would hear that same thing and say,
oh, well, that just sort of sounds like
what things normally sound like.
And then there's other ones
that were outside the normal boundary.
And you'd say, oh, yeah, that makes sense.
So, yes, we have taken steps to ameliorate that.
And, you know, that's basically what I'll say at this point.
Yeah, I understand, you know, I have a fifth gen
and I reviewed the sixth gen
and never had the problem myself.
But I have worked extensively
with small compact machines in audio production.
And I know that it is an issue that can crop up.
I've, for example, had three or four,
three Intel NUCs actually hooked up to my mixer at one point
and two of them exhibited coil winds
and one of them didn't, same exact model.
But it does sound like it's gotten worked on.
I've been following some of the threads
and I've been seeing people talking about it.
It does seem like things have gotten better
from what I can observe.
I wonder though, down the road,
is it, am I being over cautious
when I worry that maybe Linux users are persnickety
but they're too demanding?
Like, it seems like maybe we're high maintenance
or is it a good thing?
You know, I think in general,
and getting back to what I said a little while ago,
as long as you treat developers fairly,
they're okay with a certain amount of slack here and there.
And I also find that oftentimes people have,
you know, Linux users will joke themselves
as, hey, we're willing to,
I'm not saying courses in regards to anything we do, no,
but they feel that, you know,
things have been so tough for so long
when things do get better,
even if they're not 100% perfect,
they're very happy about it.
If things tend to be trending in the right direction
and there seems to be steady progress,
then yeah, I think you're absolutely correct.
And I would say it's the opposite.
Not that you're not gonna get somebody who is persnickety,
but I think in general,
the developer crowd seems to be much more understanding
and willing to work with you
as long as you're working in good faith,
you're being honest about what's going on, et cetera.
Well, let's see then, let's shift gears.
And I think, I was just gonna say one thing too.
Sometimes it's tricky, you know,
with regards to honesty in that,
or I shouldn't say honesty, but you always are honest,
but as far as how much you reveal
in that it involves other partners as well and players.
And so you can't,
and even if you wanted to come out and say,
this is what's going on,
it would involve other folks as well.
Yeah, I think everybody gets that.
Yeah, I think it's pretty understandable.
Now, so let's shift gears
and see if we can make things uncomfortable
with a different partner, Canonical.
Oh, please do. Obviously, yeah.
Let's see if, yeah.
Now, you and I were sitting in a room together
the moment it was announced.
In fact, I was the person that delivered the news to you
that Canonical was dropping Unity 7
and switching to the GNOME desktop.
How has that-
Switching back, back, back.
Right, right.
How has that been brewing inside internally?
Because 1710's been out.
I know that you're shipping 1604 currently still.
Probably won't be shipping 1710 ever,
because why would you when,
especially with 1804 right around.
Is 1804 looking like it's gonna ship on Dell products?
Is GNOME desktop gonna ship on Dell products?
What's your answer for that?
I'll say that what we usually do
is when we launch a new system,
it comes with the LTS that is current at the time.
Right, so we don't, like you said,
we won't do a 1710.
We won't do an 1810 or a, what's after 18?
19, 1904 or something like that.
We only do, no, we do best efforts
and we try to support people
with issues they have in the interim releases,
but the one that we're gonna guarantee
is the LTS that ships with it.
I mean, just, you don't even have to,
not even talking about Dell,
but just like your personal opinion,
shipping a Linux desktop now for a while,
working on this.
How is Bart and George feeling
about the transition to GNOME?
Well, so without knowing all the intricacies,
because I'm sure there's all sorts of things,
oh, you didn't think about this
and realize how it affects that.
But it does seem like a big switch for some,
it really does affect a product you're shipping.
It does, and I think one thing is,
as a company, you need to know
when to hold them and when to fold them.
Because one thing happens,
and I've been in other companies
that just keep pouring money into things,
long after it became obvious
that it wasn't great benefit to the customer at that time,
and it really wouldn't be going forward.
And yet, there is this desire sometimes
to keep working at something
long after it's been obvious that it's not the right move.
So I think it's, and it's always tough.
I mean, I say it as if that's an easy thing to do,
but I do have a lot of respect for companies
that early on say, you know what, this isn't gonna happen,
we're gonna stop it.
And so that's sort of the bigger picture.
And so within that, put that lens on it,
I think it made sense to realize they had an awesome vision,
they'd done quite a bit of work,
and it just, they weren't gonna get there to the end.
They weren't gonna get there to the end.
There seems to me, Barton, to be a similarity
between what Canonical has done with their desktop.
They went to Hacker News and other places,
they said, what do you want out of Ubuntu?
And people said, just ship stock GNOME,
just give me my basic applications.
Sort of reminds me of what people said to Dell
when they said, just ship stock Ubuntu,
just give me vanilla Ubuntu,
I just wanna load my own applications.
You see a similarity there?
Yeah, and I think it's, you know, once again,
it's does it add value or not?
Are you just putting bells and whistles
that nobody cares about,
and it comes across as bloatware.
So, yeah, I would see that,
that there are certain things that are gonna be value add,
but oftentimes in the Linux world,
it's stuff that you're gonna pull down yourself,
as opposed to if you're buying a Windows PC,
having certain applications bundled with it
really increases the value of the system.
Now, before I let you go,
I have to ask you something that you're not gonna have
an answer to because you're not the processor guy,
but I kinda have a tangential question.
42.
Right, okay, answered.
No, thank you.
If I, do you know, is this assumption correct?
If I am a Dell XPS 13 user,
running the Ubuntu that was installed on there
when I got the machine,
am I likely eventually gonna be able
to just open up GNOME software
and get microcode updates for meltdown?
I know you might not know the intricacies
of how it's gonna get patched,
but the firmware delivery mechanism through GNOME software
is something that Dell has gotten uniquely good at,
and I wonder if, what I'm trying to get at is,
how much awareness does it have
at the Barton George level, this functionality?
Like, how much of a topic of a conversation
is this particular feature?
Because it seems hyper important right now.
The firmware updating through GNOME software,
that working with fwupd, sorry to be vague,
but that's a specific question.
How much is that at your level?
So, hardly any at all, right?
So we have folks that are knee-deep
in everything Ubuntu and working on all this,
and yes, they would be,
we have folks like that on the team,
but my role as chief plate spinner doesn't go that far, so.
Does it come up though, the feature,
as a topic of conversation, or is it essentially,
is it just an assumed, baked-in thing now?
So I can't answer that specifically,
not meaning that I'm not allowed to, but I just don't know,
and I know, because there's a separate team.
As you can imagine, technical meetings,
internally about how we, what are we doing with Ubuntu
as far as, from a technical point of view.
Because it also involves your server products
and not just the XPS 13, so I totally get it.
The reason I wanted to ask is because the one thing
the audience are gonna say after this interview
is how come you didn't ask about Meltdown or Spectre?
And so I had to try to get as close to something
I thought you'd be able to answer in that regard,
unless you wanna talk about-
Yeah, I understand, we put it in bite-sized chunks,
but the answer is, yeah, I don't know.
I mean, if you wanna get into x86 architecture new ones,
is with me, I mean, we could do it, but it doesn't seem
like that'd probably be either one of our power areas.
I was hoping we'd get into the Spark chip, really,
I think, or the old RISC MIP chips.
Right, right, absolutely.
That's here is coming into my eye right now as I think back.
So what trends is Barton George watching
in the Linux world that he thinks will be something
that Dell needs to respond to in the nearish term future?
Oh, gosh, putting me on the spot.
Yeah, it's sort of like, put your strategy hat on.
Well, I think for us, it's much more,
you go back to that, what is the customer looking for?
And we just take what's out there and make sure it runs
without a hitch on our system.
So where Dell is looking at is, okay,
how do we make, from a hardware point of view,
how do we make systems that are continuously better
for our customers?
And then given that, how do we work,
take what's out there in Linux
and make it work on the laptops?
So I think we're much closer focused in,
also because, as I said, that's a lot of the stuff
that the customers in particular will do
and will decide on their own.
Do you have any sense of what Linux could do better
to be more successful in large corporations
as an actual viable desktop OS?
Is it just, is it an application issue?
Take Dell, for example.
If even if you're, Dell, you have to,
even if you have a Linux machine,
you still at some point, you functionally need
a Windows machine to fully participate on the network.
Is that an entrenched, irretractable position
that Windows has etched out?
Or sitting at your desk at Dell,
could you foresee a day when even corporations
as large as Dell could be shipping Linux
on all of their desktops?
Well, I think I'll answer that some of the key things
that are missing is you got internal apps, right?
Whether they're name tools or your expense reports,
et cetera, that need to be done.
They need to be rewritten if they're gonna be a Linux.
Right, exactly.
And so there's all that, as well as,
as you say, we as many large companies run on Windows
and we need to have all those applications.
And so, for right now, they're great developer boxes
within ourselves, as you say, within a large corporation,
but they aren't general purpose machines.
So that, I think that's gonna be tough
that you're gonna need to sort of,
at least to begin with,
figure out what use cases you can pick
and you don't wanna overestimate the power of Linux
to supplant everything else.
So don't overshoot, maybe?
Because here's what I was kind of angling to is,
is perhaps the strategy, or whatever you wanna call it,
or perhaps should the goal be, maybe the goal post
should now be a niche of the market
that is large and growing and sophisticated?
And should the discussion be more about
retooling our desktops like GNOME
to super serve a more sophisticated developer type audience?
And maybe it's worth, stop chasing that
total new computer user, that fantasy Linux user.
Because it does seem like if we double down,
if the Linux community could pull a Sputnik project
and sort of just say,
what would we build just for developers?
We might have a lot of success there.
What do you think?
Yeah, no, I think that's what it's all about
is sticking to your knitting, as they say.
So it's not the, it's iterative, right?
You start small, you're agile,
you see what works and what doesn't work.
As opposed to, by the year 20, what are we in now?
2022, we're gonna be all 100% Linux
on the desktop in our enterprise.
And it's looking to expand beyond that.
But as you say, the obvious targets to begin with
are how can we do a developer machine
that keeps meeting more of the developer needs,
developers needs, or scientists, engineering scientists.
Might we make a machine learning AI developer box
that would have all those goodies,
whatever those might be.
Right.
Or do you find out, once again, that it's,
hey, whatever I want, I'll pull down myself
so I don't need anything tailored to learning it.
What we're kind of getting is,
these users are generally capable enough
of customizing their own system
for their particular edge case
if you give them the right base.
So take machine learning and AI.
That's a different machine than an XPS 13,
but it's a type of machine that Dell certainly does sell.
And if you could tune that right,
give them the platform or the tool,
and then they take care of the software side of it.
And so maybe you get really good at doing that
for a couple of markets.
And then once you've really nailed that,
you move on to another market.
And then you nail that one.
Yeah, exactly.
And you look at what is value add in that area?
Just like we said, when we originally went out with this
and asked people what they wanted, they did say vanilla.
And like I said, then we said,
well, no, no, but we'll even give you more than vanilla.
We'll give you all sorts of swirls
and chocolate chunks in there.
But yeah, to find out, say, once again, machine learning
or people in the music industry or whatever it might be,
what would you see as something that would be,
that would make your life easier or better
if we could provide it?
Now, my last question is crystalline silica material?
Wow.
Now you're very gracious.
This isn't, no, this is the quote.
You would know because all retweets are,
you fully support them.
You retweeted a quote right here, not painted white.
The new Dell XPS, don't get this wrong, everybody.
It is not white.
It is made of crystalline silica material
that literally weaves the white color in like fabric
in nine composite layers.
Yeah, no, I tell you.
You must be watching my tweets very carefully.
You retweeted that, I don't know.
Well, I'm on there right now.
I'm on there right now, yeah.
Okay, there you go.
At Barton808, I go there every day, at Barton808,
and all of our audience should too.
Because if I were a betting man, dear audience,
I would bet that there may be an update
along the precision line soon,
and that's one of my favorite lines.
So keep an eye out at Barton808.
I can never, I can neither confirm nor deny wink wink.
Of course not, of course not, yes.
And of course you saw when I retweeted that,
I also put in the shameless plug for the developer edition.
Yes, of course, good man, good man.
Yeah, we'll have links to-
It wasn't so much about what they said, it was just, hey.
A chance to plug your stuff.
As you should, as you should.
The XPS 13 is, so like Barton said,
available now in the 6th gen and 7th gen model.
The 7th gen is hot.
It's the 93070, not hot literally,
but hot like in the, you know, yeah, yeah, yeah.
With lots of different configs,
I will link to bartongeorge.io in the show notes
where you guys can read about it
as well as the other product pages.
Barton, is there anything else we want to mention
before we roll out of here?
No, I think that the one thing that I would say is,
I was completely blown away by the amount of interest
generated by this release.
Oh yeah.
Because as you know, it's number seven,
and I thought it would be incrementally, you know,
or same sort of level of interest.
And I got more hits on my blog that first day
than I have in 10 years that I've been doing that blog.
So it was just, it was not what I expected.
As I said, I expected people to be interested
because we have folks who are interested in it.
But, you know, I'm glad to hear that.
It doesn't surprise me a single bit, Barton,
because, you know, the reason I drove my RV
down to your office was because I could tell
there was momentum building around this product line,
which snapped my attention around.
And so I am not surprised to see it's continuing to build
because I could, I could smell it coming, Barton.
I could, like an Austin barbecue.
What was it, your bunions were tweeting
or something like that?
You knew it was going to rain?
I don't know.
I'm not sure, I'm not sure.
Right now, I'm just thinking about Austin barbecue
now that I said that.
But Barton, thank you very much for coming on.
And a pleasure as always.
I really appreciate the opportunity, Chris.
Maybe one of these, maybe one of these short weeks here,
I can get my hands on one of these
and tell the folks what I think.
But in the meantime, they can go read up about it.
And I'll retweet new reviews for the developer edition
I see coming along too,
so people can keep an eye out for that.
All right, Barton.
And then as we were talking about before,
easiest way to get there is either,
well, easiest to remember is dell.com slash developers
or dell.com slash Sputnik.
They'll take you to the same place
and that's where it has the line
and you can click through for the new one or the other ones.
You know, I never even got to ask Barton about his dogs.
I was going to ask him about his dogs
because somehow I go down to Dell,
I hang out with Barton for a week
and I didn't even know he was a dog owner.
And now these days, that's all I care about
is a new dog owner.
But I digress, let's move on.
We still have some great emails to get to.
I want to recap something that we've covered
back in 2016 on this show and things have changed.
I've been doing a head to head comparison recently.
So I want to cover that.
We've also got some quote unquote breaking news
from the Ubuntu Mate project all to come.
So let's take a moment and thank Linux Academy
for sponsoring the unplugged program.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there to sign up for a free seven day trial
and support the show.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
What, what, what?
You don't know what Linux Academy is?
Friends, let me tell you this.
Well, actually, how about a highly paid voice actor
will tell you.
Whether you're an experienced sys admin
or new to the world of Linux, Azure and AWS,
OpenStack and DevOps, a sharp skillset
is an absolute necessity to succeed.
Meet Linux Academy, an online Linux
and cloud training platform that uses self-paced
video courses and hands-on labs
to give you real world experience
for a wide range of skills.
Train for your certification,
learn the latest DevOps tools
and grow your skillset to do better work.
Linux Academy is not just a video library.
Our scenario-based server labs and quiz system
allow you to learn hands-on.
We also have full-time human instructors
who answer questions and help you earn that certification
or promotion at work.
We add new training every week
so you'll always be up to date on the latest tech.
Sys admins of every experience level
use Linux Academy to stay on the bleeding edge
of the Linux ecosystem.
You should too.
One thing the voiceover guy doesn't mention
that's my favorite feature of Linux Academy
is they have full-time human beings
that are available to help you if you get stuck,
like instructors that really know the content material.
And they have a course scheduler system
specifically for us busy folk.
Just the more you know, guys, the more you know.
So go check it out, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Learn how to build a secure system
so that way when the hackers are dropping malware
on your system, you're on top of it.
Why are you laughing?
The hackers are dropping malware into your system.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
And a big thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
So Wimpy, I heard a little birdie tell me
that there could be something interesting
over at the Monte Project this week.
Ubuntu Mate, I should say, not the Mate Project,
but Ubuntu Mate.
Actually, the opposite.
Oh, really?
Oh, I got it right the first time.
Oh, good for me.
Yeah, you did.
Hey, look at that, accident.
And then I messed it up by correcting myself.
That's a life lesson.
I can also throw some news in about Ubuntu Mate
if you like as well.
Well, then that would be just right all along,
so that would be great.
So let's start.
Let's start with Mate.
Okay, so Mate 1.18 was released about one year ago,
and that's been a long-lived version.
We've been supporting that,
and we've had three point releases,
so it's very robust and stable now.
But we have just closed the feature branches
on the Mate desktop,
and we'll be releasing Mate 1.20 in the next week or so,
so expect that to hit your distributions soon.
That is really exciting.
So, okay, so it's 1.20, right?
1.20, yeah, I wanted this one to be a 2.0,
but I've gone with consensus of the team.
We're going with 1.20.
I thought the next one would have been 1.19, though,
so you did skip one rev.
1.19 was the development snapshots.
I see, okay.
I see.
Wow, so what's the headlining features?
Are there headlining features?
Well, there's some boring things that are important
in that there's thousands of bug fixes,
and a lot of those we've been cherry picking back
into the 1.18 stuff for the important things,
which is why people have seen that Ubuntu,
Mate 17.10, and 18.04 daily
are really very robust at the moment.
But there's been a lot of work
in the Window Manager, for example,
so that's now got hardware acceleration.
Oh, I love that.
Yeah, and is, what's the word, screen tear-free,
and now supports quadrant and upper and lower panel tiling
within the standard Window Manager,
and a whole heap of key bindings as well.
That sounds huge.
That actually sounds pretty big.
Yeah, that's quite a bit of work,
and this really came about because we were looking
at where we needed to go with things,
as a team, we don't see that right now is the time
for us to invest in any serious Wayland development,
and there were things that we could do
to improve our desktop on top of X11,
so we've taken steps to do that.
And this is work that won't arrive in time,
but we've also started the work
to really finesse the high DPI support.
So high DPI support is much improved,
it's still got the experimental tag in that
it is not a seamless, it just automagically enables,
but if you twiddle the right knobs,
you actually get a fairly decent high DPI experience
with Marte now, and a blog is forthcoming.
I've actually got it drafted, had it drafted for weeks,
I need to get on and post that, how to turn that stuff on.
Oh boy, oh boy, I mean, just, that's a,
I could see why you wanted to do a 2.0,
especially with the Harburg seller.
Is it Marco, is that the?
Yeah, Marco is the window manager, yeah.
All right, that's pretty great.
Is there anything else in that arena,
or do you wanna slip in a little secret about Ubuntu Marte?
Well, in order, exploiting the features
that we've used there, and some of the changes
we've made in Marte itself,
there's one sad thing about Marte 1.20.
As a rule, we don't like to remove features,
but we've actually had to remove some of the features
we had to remove a feature.
So if you've used the desktop,
one of the panel applets is a stock ticker,
and we've had to drop that,
because Yahoo have ended their API
that we were hooked up to in order to get that data.
Like many other services around the internet,
we're all using this Yahoo API.
That's gone away, it's not coming back,
and there is no drop-in replacement.
So unfortunately, we've had to drop that applet,
because it's defunct.
I'm sure many-
You should replace it
with a crypto coin monitor instead.
Absolutely.
But they already exist,
we don't need to carry that in the core project.
I'm sure many serious stock traders were using that.
Yeah, yeah.
So building on top of the features that exist in Marte,
in fact, as we've been talking,
I've been working on the global menu.
So the global menu implementation in Ubuntu Marte 18.04
will be such that that is permanently available,
not necessarily enabled,
but permanently available in all of the various layouts.
And what that means specifically
is that the HUD will now work in any of the layouts
in Ubuntu Marte rather than just the few
that had the global menu enabled.
So that's an improvement I'm hopefully gonna land
this evening after we've finished chatting.
And then the other thing we're looking at doing
in Ubuntu Marte is we're working on our next generation
of the Ubuntu Marte welcome and the software boutique.
And at the Debian conference last year,
the Debian Marte team were asked to more closely align
with Ubuntu Marte in terms of default settings and setup
and things like welcome and the software boutique.
So we're going to be delivering Ubuntu Marte welcome
and the software boutique as snaps
so that Debian can take advantage of that.
And a little bit longer term,
we'll be adding some support so it can be white labeled.
So when it's running on Debian,
it can present a different look and feel and content.
That is fantastic.
And it's fascinating to me that snap applications
can be contained in a snap,
but still have the ability to manipulate
the package management on the host system.
So it's like-
Well, these snaps would very specifically be classic.
So these would be snaps that are effectively
like a deb installed on your host system
that effectively uncontained because they need to do
exactly as you've just described,
they need to add and remove software
and welcome does other things,
to configure peripherals and what have you.
So yeah, very much unconfined applications,
but by delivering them as snaps.
Welcome and boutique are our USP.
It's what broadly defines Ubuntu Marte's identity.
We haven't been moving very quickly recently,
but that's the development's ramping up now.
And what I want to be able to do
is continually deliver improvements
to the Ubuntu Marte users through welcome and the boutique
without having to use PPAs that people don't know about
and all sorts of other complicated systems,
but having a snap,
we can just keep delivering new
and improved versions rapidly.
That sounds great.
That sounds really great.
I am obviously a big fan of sort of eliminating
some of those PPAs as much as possible
and probably more and more as time goes on.
When does, so I'm clear,
when does that kind of,
is that the 1804 release of Ubuntu Marte?
That's where some of that will land?
Yeah.
Ah, okay.
Wow.
How big of a risk is it to switch over to,
that's a pretty big fundamental switch for the LTS.
I guess you have time to iterate on it if needed,
but that seems like a pretty big switch for the LTS.
Ubuntu Marte shipped a snap in 1710.
Oh, that's right.
We have some experience in what's involved in doing that.
And our friends in the Ubuntu desktop team
and the foundations team have been improving
the hooks that exist in the build infrastructure
so that it's easier to ship snaps on the image.
So at the moment they are simply installed on the image
and you only get them if you install an ISO
that had that snap on it.
Whereas the changes they're making are,
if you installed say a beta and in the final release,
an additional snap was added,
it seeded like other packages.
So you get that package added to your system
as part of the upgrade.
As I recall, it was a pulse audio mixer, right?
A command line pulse audio mixer?
Yeah.
Yeah, it's pulse mixer.
Has that gotten much testing or,
and I know one of the other things I was gonna be curious is,
has it been updated?
It has been updated, yes.
In fact, we did it a couple of few weeks ago, yeah.
So yes, it's been tested by thousands
and thousands of people.
Great.
So that, and so, and now it's been tested
to have a snap desktop application shipped on the distro
that gets updated after the distros release
with active users.
Yeah.
That's a pretty good milestone.
Yeah, so JJ, you had a question about the beta, go ahead.
Yeah, so is there any way for me
to test out any of the new features
of the new version of Mate possibly?
I'm sort of interested since I am a user of a bunch of Mate.
So you can test any of the daily images
for any of the flavors.
The URL is cdimage.abuntu.com
and in there you'll find directories
for each of the flavors.
And inside there, you'll find the release name.
So it's bionic at the moment.
And in there you'll find a directory daily live
and whatever architectures the flavors support
you'll find ISO images for in there.
And you can download those and install them
on spare laptops or VMs or what have you to test them.
And then there are also scheduled alpha and beta releases.
So when those come around,
there's a more organized test schedule for a week
around those where each of the flavor teams
are looking for feedback and looking for the bugs
that get reported in order to fix and improve.
So it's like all or nothing.
What do you mean?
Sorry?
So it's like all or nothing, the image,
like you can't really upgrade
the actual individual Mate environment possibly or?
Oh, you're asking like a current install
and go to a new version of Mate?
Yes, you can.
You could run through the same process
to do a distribution upgrade.
And you could upgrade from 1710 to 1804.
To be honest with you,
none of the flavors did an alpha one
that was scheduled to happen January the 4th
for obvious reasons that didn't happen.
The next alpha will be alpha two,
which will be the beginning of February.
I think you'd be best to wait
until the alphas are out of the way
cause there's a lot of things moving at the moment.
If you need your machine to be reliable,
just avoid 1804 for the moment.
Now you're telling me I started the upgrade
before we started.
Oh, yeah.
You're fine.
You've got.
I've got a hotline to you.
Yeah, exactly.
Understood.
Yeah, that's a lot of great stuff Wimpy.
Thank you for the update.
That's pretty, can I want to pick your brain actually?
I've got an email come into the show from Robert
and he says, in regards to our Linspire discussion
last week, he says he loaded up Linspire
and then loaded up Zubuntu
and looked at gnome software in both of the latest Zubuntu
and he saw a different highlighted selection
of applications in Linspire than he did
in the machine he was looking at the same time in Zubuntu.
And so he wondered, does that mean is Linspire injecting
like their own suggestions into that list
or is it more of like a random rotation
with the way gnome software displays
like those featured ones that you guys are curating?
Yeah, there's a list of say 16
and like six are picked from that to be displayed.
Ah, so does gnome software just do like a random selection?
Yeah, and it rotates I think every 24 hours
so it's not particularly rapid
in the way that it represents them.
Ah, it's confusing.
That is actually, I kind of, yeah, okay.
And so any Ubuntu flavor or derivative
that is shipping gnome software
is likely just using that same list
because it's coming from the upstream
to gnome software that they're repackaging.
So which Linspire would be doing.
And so if they were injecting their own list,
would they have to be modifying gnome software?
Would it be a fork or is there just some sources file
that they could go?
If they were modifying that,
they would have to have forked it
and made their own version.
So that's hard coded in, interesting.
Well, the source of the data is in one of the plugins, yeah.
Interesting.
Learning.
They could certainly choose to ship their own plugin
which points to their own data sources
and they could promote their own applications
that they prefer for their target users, that's for sure.
Or remove the plugins they ship by default on Ubuntu,
that's another option.
So they can certainly affect the list, that's for sure.
But it's not likely because it takes then a list
you have to maintain, right?
And is that an XML file up somewhere or RSS feed?
What is that?
It's a REST API.
Aha.
I'm learning over the last week that gnome software
is deceptively complicated.
It looks very simple on the front end
but some of this stuff is more complicated
than I thought it was.
I envision this stuff as sources lists
and a simple text file that somebody could just
throw an RSS feed in.
I mean, no, no, of course not.
Of course, in this day and age,
you gotta support flat packs and snaps
and firmware updates and all kinds of things
and software channels and plugins.
It's all above my pay grade apparently.
I'm just glad it works when it does.
So I wanted to take a moment on the show
and talk about Ambient Plex again.
Oh God, I know, I've talked about it too much.
But I gotta be honest, we actually haven't covered it
since 2016 on the show and things have really changed.
In fact, not always for the better either,
I'll get to that.
Maybe I should start with that
so I'm not ending on a super pissed off note.
But Chris is a little upset about something.
So let's see, when was the last time
we covered this here topic here?
Yeah, let's see, it was Linux Unplugged,
I think it was like 156.
So if you dig around in that range,
you will get a more comprehensive coverage
of what we're about to talk about,
including things like Tiny Media Manager
and integrating more with Kodi and whatnot.
But just really briefly off the top,
I've been head to head comparing MB and Plex,
which are two different streaming options
that allow you to collect a massive media
on a file server or on a desktop.
I actually have been running these for testing,
one just on a workstation and one on a server,
a couple different servers actually.
Anyways, it is a server side software
that has a client side piece
and the client side can run on a Roku,
an Android TV, an Apple TV, a web browser, a mobile device,
and it allows you to throw a bunch of media up on a server,
it scans all of it, figures out the metadata,
downloads the information from the internet
and artwork and descriptions
and organizes all the seasons
for your TV shows and your movies.
It's quite handy and it makes you feel
like you're living in the future, it's great.
And there's two main competitors in this field these days,
there's MB and Plex.
And Kodi does fit in here, like I said,
check our past episode for more.
But just really briefly, if you're running Kodi today
and you're wondering why the hell would you want MB or Plex,
just a quick versus like Kodi,
Plex and MB are not nearly as fast as Kodi.
If you're pointing Kodi at some local files on a disk,
Kodi is going to whoop its butt in load times
and fast forward every single time.
And these both require fairly reliable networking,
a reliable LAN or Wi-Fi
and a pretty solid internet connection
if you're doing streaming.
So those are their main detractions from Kodi.
But they're also better than Kodi at certain things,
like on my testing, they are better at media detection,
getting the right metadata information
about esoteric shows that are named something kind of off,
identifying a series that maybe isn't quite right,
it's much better at that.
And obviously, as I started with,
it's very easy to use for streaming
for your friends and family.
In fact, Plex has a feature called Plex sharing,
which allows you to share with friends and family,
you just add them as a buddy.
And so let's take my buddy Chase from Unfilter,
he and I are friends on Plex
and we share each other's libraries.
He happens to have episodes of Voyager that I don't have.
So if I'm in a mood to go watch Catherine Janeway
make out with some Irish guy in Fairhaven on the holodeck,
I will just switch over to his Plex server
and I will stream Voyager from his server for a bit.
And MB has something similar to this.
And so what I wanted to know for purposes of this show,
which one might be better for the audience
and which one's more open source,
as if this is some sort of measuring stick,
but which one's more open source.
And so I looked at both the Plex project
and I looked at the MB project.
And this full credit goes to a discussion
that really got kicked off in our Telegram group
where people were asking questions about this
and getting clarifications,
trying to figure out what parts of Plex are open source,
which parts are closed source.
I'll say this, for Plex, I was pretty surprised.
I was pretty surprised.
It's amazing actually.
They have a whole page that goes over all their licensing,
but they have everything
except for the backend server part up on their GitHub page.
And it's all kinds of crazy.
You realize what a project this must be
when you just go through their GitHub page
and look at all of the fricking projects
that they're contributing to or have forked for Plex.
And one of the ones that's on here
that I was really happy to see,
and I didn't know this before I really did the digging,
even though I use this,
guess I'm not that observant.
The Plex for Kodi add-on is developed by the Plex project.
Plex folks are actually creating that add-on for Kodi.
So if you prefer to use Kodi for playback,
but want it to connect to your Plex database,
Kodi's actually writing that plugin,
or I mean the Plex people are actually writing that plugin.
So it's about as official as it gets.
But how did it compare to MB?
Which essentially has a similar feature set to Plex.
Couple of differences in how they're implemented for sure.
Plex is simpler, maybe slightly more user-friendly,
but MB is more flexible.
It's completely open source.
And it feels more like a self-contained application.
That's not often the weeds connected
to like online news streaming.
And it just feels like something that just is simple.
I actually prefer it for my LAN streaming.
And I use Plex for my internet streaming.
Everything, everything regarding MB is open source.
The front end, the back end.
I believe, I believe perhaps the Android apps might not be,
but the server, the web client,
some of the secret sauce it uses to stream all of that
is open source.
And both of these projects have a revenue model.
Plex sells the Plex Pass and MB sells MB Premium.
In MB's case, it's a little more of a,
hey, thanks for being awesome.
Here's five bucks.
You get a couple other things,
like some nice file syncing features with MB
if you become a premium member.
Plex Pass, Plex Pass has been getting more
and more appealing.
You can buy a monthly or a one-time.
And you get nicer features.
You can be in the beta channel.
You can use their Plex Cloud streaming service.
It's nice, it's kind of worth it.
I bought a, they had a sale two years ago or something,
and I bought a lifetime subscription, just done, done.
And these are obviously vital avenues
for these two different projects,
whichever one you might like or not like to stay afloat.
But one of them is being attacked
by the very open source community it serves.
MB is being eaten from within
its own open source community.
And I feel like this is a warning sign
that is going to stop other projects
from ever doing a fully open source project.
It's gonna lock in this model, potentially,
of a closed source proprietary server component
and only open sourcing bits and pieces here.
And if nothing else, least of which,
the least of which is gonna happen,
is the Plex group will be able to look at this incident
and point at this incident and say,
this is why we will never 100% open source everything.
We will never do it.
We never have to.
This is why.
This is now the ultimate justification.
You gotta look at this and you gotta wonder
if maybe this isn't a fundamental flaw of open source.
So one user of MB got really pissed off,
kind of for legitimate reasons,
but where he goes with it,
fundamentally is going to undermine MB's revenue source.
And I don't recommend anybody install this
because these projects need to be funded
or else they're gonna go away.
And somebody created an MB unlocked project,
which just gives you all of the premium features for free.
Because why not?
It's just open source, right?
So at some point, the MB developers added a nag screen
before playback that reminded you
that you could get MB premium.
I've never seen that because pretty quickly,
like my first couple of days into MB testing
a long time ago, I bought MB premium
because I thought this is a good project.
It offers good competition to Plex.
I like seeing that.
I wanna keep them going.
So I paid for it.
I've never seen this nag screen.
And I admit if I saw a nag screen, I wouldn't like that.
And the community did ask them to stop
and they basically said no.
And this guy, this is a quote, says this is bullshit.
For the GPL2, it's a GPL2 licensed product.
This is bullshit that they're doing this.
And his justification is because it's a GPL2 project,
how dare they?
And so I decided that I would just go remove the nag screen.
But in the process of removing the nag screen,
I discovered that unlocking all of the premium features
was just the simplest way.
So here you go.
And there's a AUR.
Of course, you can just get a Docker image
of an entire MB server that's been pre-activated
for premium, ready to go, just a Docker install away,
which is actually a pretty common way
for people to try out these projects.
So that actually really sucks
because that gets same billing
as the actual MB project in Docker Hub.
And if more people start downloading this,
it'll actually show up higher in the ranks.
And what would prevent any other,
what prevents anybody doing this to any other project
that's completely open source
that has some sort of revenue system
where you can unlock additional features?
It feels like this fundamentally validates the fear
of a lot of developers who've been looking at coming over
to Linux and can't quite figure out
how they get the licensing right.
Well, we just validated their fears with this.
I don't know, maybe I'm, just to me,
this is just so, so upsetting to see this
because if we make it impossible for people
to make money at open source,
all we're gonna have left is commercial stuff
and Electron apps and proprietary backends,
and this problem is never gonna get any better.
It's pretty disappointing.
So don't install it, don't use it.
Or if you do, you know, also send them a few bucks.
I mean, I just, I really, it's one patch.
You know, this guy just applies one patch
and it unlocks all of the features.
And maybe the MB project could like obfuscate their code.
I don't know.
Mumble, remove, what do you think?
Is this something that is addressable?
This is not the first time this has happened.
Other projects have suffered with this in the past.
I mean, I remember this happening in the subsonic community
for much the same reasons.
And there was another one as well recently.
It may have been MB.
I think Mark talked about this on the Ubuntu podcast,
the whole nag screen thing.
Yeah, your subsonic's a great example of that.
That's a great example.
Yeah, it feels bad.
It feels really bad.
It feels like it just takes one pissed off open source user
that knows how to fix this thing
and then you've just undermined an entire business
that has multiple employees.
Many employees.
Go ahead, sorry.
Yeah, so it sort of reminds me a little bit
about the email clients as well
having this sort of similar sort of conflict, I guess,
with regards to supporting certain email protocols
such as Exchange and all that.
That makes any sense?
Yeah, I do follow what you mean there,
where the sort of like premium features and whatnot
and additional add-ons that they sometimes
have to pay licenses for and whatnot.
You know, just to wrap up, so head to head here,
my takeaway is if streaming to smart devices
and streaming between friends
or streaming to family members
that maybe kind of just have like a typical network setup,
they're not really doing port forwarding,
Plex is the way, if you need those things,
Plex is the way to go.
If you don't need those things,
I would really give a hearty endorsement these days for MB.
It's got a couple of things I'm not a huge fan of
over remote connections.
I've even had problems where I've punched a hole
through my firewall, we got port forwarding
going to the right box, and yet for some reason
my remote MB system still can't connect.
Whereas with Plex, it'll do a relay if it has to
to make that work.
But if I'm using the two different products on my LAN,
I find MB to be faster on the same exact hardware
doing head to head, same hardware, same server,
I find MB to be faster.
I prefer the way it displays some information.
Plex has been abstracting away your individual episodes
more and more and trying to boost things
into new arrivals and trending
and all these different things that make it feel
like YouTube that I just hate.
Whereas MB feels more like here's your stuff,
here's your season, just go.
And then the creme de la creme mode for me,
the perfect setup here has been now,
and this is since 2016, so it's really kind of bared out,
is if I can, Android TV running Kodi
with the MB or Plex plugin,
depending on which particular media pool I'm pulling from,
connected to wired storage.
So in my case, it's a QNAP
that has hardware accelerated decoding.
I've reviewed the QNAP in the past.
You can install codecs from its app store,
you get hardware accelerated decoding.
I can be streaming to multiple boxes, no problem,
my NAS is still fully responsive.
There's no big, huge, loud server anywhere.
It's an Android TV and a QNAP and it's glorious.
And both MB and Plex can run on it just fine.
And so it's really great to do head-to-head comparison on.
And what I walk away with, at the end of the day,
I'm gonna go with the GPL2 product,
if everything else is coming up equal
and I'm watching on the LAN, I'm going with MB.
And so I have this setup now
where when I'm just watching something off my hard drive,
I'm watching something here at the studio,
we do the same thing here at the studio LAN,
it's watched over MB.
And then when we watch something remotely,
we watch over Plex, and I know that sounds crazy,
but they just point at the same files anyways.
It's not like I have two sets of all my movies or TV shows.
So it works out pretty well.
I really have, I've come to love this setup in a way
that I've never quite achieved
with my media setups in the past.
And I spent money on all kinds of things.
I even took a weird dark turn
down the Windows Media Center lane
where they had these Media Center front end boxes
from like Linksys and whatnot
that were trying to get to that hardware appliance style
and it wasn't there, just wasn't there.
It was horrible and also Windows.
And this, this has finally been it.
Anyways, I have links to all of the MB stuff,
including the open source projects,
the Kodi plugins, and that goodness in the show notes.
Before we get off the topic of MB or Plex,
Pierre, are you setting up a new Plex server?
What's your plans there?
What are you doing?
Because-
I need hardware first.
Why not just run it on, see, that's the thing is,
why not just run it on your workstation
if you have it on all the time?
It's not like you're watching TV while you're gaming.
First of all, I don't have a TV.
Well, okay, but you know what I mean.
It's not like your machine's gonna be decoding video files
while you're playing a video game and streaming
because you're gonna be playing video games and streaming.
So I just, I recently tried it out on workstation
for different testing of versions
and I realized it's great having it right there
on my desktop is great because I can hook up a USB disk
and I can add that and I can download something immediately
and have it scan my downloads folder.
So for like a full week, I'm like,
I'm just running it off my workstation.
Well, you say that, but while I'm streaming,
the girlfriend could be watching videos.
All right, Popey, Popey says he's caught me
in a hypocrisy loop.
What have I done wrong, Popey?
Set me straight here.
So the argument is we should not patch out
and make it easy for people to use content
as in MB or whatever piece of software
that somebody else has developed
and is trying to make some money out of.
And that's a bad thing,
but the chances are what people are using MB for
is downloaded TV programs
that they probably didn't have the rights to watch.
So how is that rationalized in your mind?
Well, in my view, because the product itself,
MB was still fully functional, right?
It was just that NAG screen,
which does sound super annoying,
but it wasn't as if it couldn't say like playback MKVs
without the premiere feature.
It just would say, hey, did you know we have
a premiere feature and then you click play.
It's so it, when it's-
No, it wasn't that part.
It was more the part that, hey, you guys out there,
you should pay for this thing
that someone has worked hard for
in order to watch this thing that you've stolen
in inverted commas that somebody else has worked hard for,
TV programs and films, right?
Yeah, no, I follow what your question was.
I just, I was just trying to say like,
if MB had disabled the product and made it like,
so in my case, take Star Trek Discovery.
I download Star Trek Discovery every single Sunday
as fast as I possibly can.
And I watch it via MB or Plex, depending on the setup.
But I also am a CBS All Access subscriber.
Same with the House of Cards.
I'm a Netflix subscriber.
I don't ever watch it on Netflix because it's ass.
I just prefer to watch it on my TV.
And I have a MiFi.
So you're right, it is up to the individual
what the morality is.
And it's, you're right, it's also not surprising
that people that are comfortable stealing a lot of content
would be comfortable stealing the product
to watch the content.
That does make sense.
I feel like the, it's self-harm though.
When you, if you download Game of Thrones,
you're not putting Game of Thrones out of business.
But if you fundamentally undermine the way for MB
to monetize MB, they will go out of business.
And they will, they'll be gone.
And then you'll have no way to watch your stolen TV shows.
So it's sort of like pissing in your own well.
Right.
But yeah, you do bring up a good point.
And I wonder what the audience would say about that too.
Let us know.
Tweet me at chrisles or leave a comment on the YouTubes
so we can all read it or linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
Now we gotta go because the Ask Noah program
is just around the corner.
Mr. Noah, what's coming up on the Ask Noah over there?
Dude, we got so many cool things
we're gonna be talking about.
We're talking about high resolution audio.
Ooh.
There's somebody out there
and they're gonna be like, that's snake oil.
And then there's the other half of your audience
that's like, no, no, no, that he finally caught on.
And so you're gonna find out which one it is.
High resolution audio under Linux.
Is it possible or is it snake oil?
Hmm, interesting.
Now rumor has it that there may be a topic expert
coming on the show to discuss it with you as well.
There is, anytime we dive into the topic,
we go find the person in the industry
that knows more than anyone else.
And in that case, when it comes to hi-fi audio,
I was telling you last night,
there is nobody else other than Bob Carver.
I mean, he's just the guy when it comes to hi-fi audio.
That's sort of a pretty good get.
Nobody networks like Noah.
Nobody does.
I gotta say it.
It really comes to your advantage sometimes.
Well done, sir.
I have friends in high places.
Yeah, I'm looking forward to that.
And so now we're doing the Ask Noah program
and the Unplugged program back to back.
So you come over to jblab.tv on a Tuesday.
You can hang out with our virtual hug
and all these wonderful gentlemen.
And we'd love to have some wonderful ladies in there.
Then you stick around and watch some content
and hear the extra live stuff
that doesn't make it in the published version.
And then you keep watching and get Ask Noah.
It's like a whole week,
or I mean like a whole afternoon, evening,
depending on morning in your time zone,
block of Linux live with your participation.
Cause we've got the Mumble Room on the Unplugged program.
And then we've got your live calls on Ask Noah.
And from time to time rumor has it,
there'll even be some Mumble participation in Ask Noah,
which is probably difficult every time you have a guest.
So every time I say that you got a guest, but.
Yeah, well actually, so Bob doesn't,
Bob is not a computer technically savvy.
So he'll be joining us over phone.
So we can have Mumble today, yeah.
But yeah, we call it the Linux sandwich.
Is that what we call it?
Oh, good to know.
Good, good.
Go get yourself a Patreon account
and go over to a patreon.com slash Ubuntu underscore mate
to support some of the fine work
that Mr. Wimperis is doing with the Ubuntu mate project.
And a lot of times that stuff funds stuff
that just goes upstream to mate as well.
So Ubuntu underscore mate at patreon.com.
Of course, we're Jupiter Signal.
And they're off, they're off right now.
They may never return, they say.
But if you'd like to catch the backlog,
go check out the Ubuntu podcast.
There's some great episodes posted over there.
They're on season break right now.
Is curry and beer been scheduled, gentlemen?
Is that?
Not yet.
We've had a pre-curry, but we haven't had curry.
I understand.
Okay.
There's a pre-curry.
You got a, do you have a post-curry too?
Is there gonna be a post-curry?
You need to, you know, flex your stomach muscles.
Yes.
Before you go for the proper curry.
So that way, when you're ready
to have a real serious discussion, you're warmed up.
You've trained up.
It's like a marathon.
I understand.
All right, guys.
Well, thanks for being here.
And thank you, audience, for being here.
And hopefully Mr. West will be back to health next week.
In the meantime, go get him at Wes Payne on the Twitter
and get more of him at the TechSnap program,
TechSnap.Systems.
Like I mentioned earlier, I'm at Chris Ellis.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
Our subreddit is linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
And you can email the show, Jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash contact.
Thank you, Robert, for emailing us this week.
And everybody else, I had more emails queued up,
but they were for Wes.
So maybe we'll get those when he comes back next week.
And again, those live times,
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
Thanks so much for being here.
We'll see you right back here next week
on the Unplugged program.
See you next Tuesday.
I've never installed, you know, slash Linux.
Get it out of here.
Get the hell out of here.
All right, let's see if we can title this thing
before Noah takes over the airwaves.
Eabtitles.com, you can still submit.
You can also submit in the Discord,
Discord.me slash Jupiter Colony.
I'll be searching that.
Let's go pick a title and then we'll get out of here
and Noah will take us away to AskNoahland.
Bangsuggest.
Thank you, gentlemen.
I am so hooked, JJ, on Indian food.
I'm actually taking a break right now
so that way when Noah comes in here,
I'm not burned out because otherwise...
Attaboy.
Yeah, I'm doing that for you, Brown Bear.
Oh, that's good, that's good.
That makes me happy.
Yep, and I've already warned Angela
that there will be a business expense
of butter chicken and stuff.
Noah refuses to come unless you buy him Indian food.
That's the reason why I'm sort of trying
to explain a little bit.
Yeah, I would imagine it's delicious,
but man, I don't know.
There's something about that butter chicken.
You're gonna have to tell me, Noah,
what you think, but there's something about it
that's just, mm, it's healing.
I had it on Friday.
Me and Wimpy met up with one of our guys
from the community and spent the day co-working
in a library in near where Wimpy lives
and then we went out for curry in the evening
and it was so good, so good.
I wish.
I have a funny story relating to Indian food,
but you can finish first.
I was just gonna say, Poppy,
sometime when you're out here,
it would take a long time because it's like an hour,
well, it's like 50 minutes, well, an hour,
depending on traffic.
Dude, I'm gonna be in Seattle in like a week.
I know, I know, but do you think you could break away
for like three hours or so?
Because we'd have to come all the way up north
to go to this place, then there's the time to eat
and then the time to get back.
That's the problem.
But it is, I've traveled around some places
and I've never had Indian food better than,
at least here in the States that I've traveled to,
than this place.
It's just so good.
I just bought six of them.
I went in and bought six butter chickens at once last week
and ate it for four days or something like that.
It's so good.
The best curry I've ever had is in Japan.
Oh yeah, really?
Okay, okay.
Yeah, they make some awesome Indian curry in Japan.
I imagine there's something that surpasses it.
I mean, there must be.
What about Indian curry in Japan?
Yeah, the best, he said, the best curry in Japan.
The best curry ever is in Japan.
I don't know if I agree with the best curry ever,
but they do have some really, really motivated
Indian people in Japan.
They make some good food.
I'm not kidding.
I mean, they make some.
What does that mean?
Motivated Indian people.
Here's the thing, here's the thing.
Here's the thing, you have to understand
something about cuisine, right?
So think about this.
In the US, it's easy to make,
even the worst Indian food passes as amazing here
because Americans are more or less.
Boy, does it seem to.
Bland, yeah, they're just bland.
I mean, because every American food is just bland.
But when you go to Japan and you have,
they're competing on a different culinary level,
now you have to have a really motivated Indian person
if you're gonna make it there.