and then everybody hey hey there Joe hey anybody want to say hi to Joe this is
your chance hi Joe hi Joe hey Joe huh I noticed poppy couldn't be bothered that's
interesting that's that's interesting sorry I was busy talking to Neil on
the telegram it's showtime guys
well hello friends and welcome in episode 382 of your weaker Linux talk
show my name is Chris my name is Wes Wes prepare yourself because this episode is
brought to you by the all-new cloud guru the leader in learning for cloud Linux
and other modern tech skills hundreds of courses thousands of hands-on labs get
certified get hired get learning a cloud guru calm yeah so this episode is it's
my coming out I have a big secret that I have to reveal that will be will be laid
bare in front of all of you for your own judgments later in this show and then we
thought it'd be a decent time to check in on the plucky little distro endeavor
OS which you'll probably remember came up out of the ashes of enter gross which
was a arch based distro that really kind of aimed at getting pretty close to
upstream arch and endeavor OS when it launched we took a first look at it and
we said this is interesting but it needs some work we're gonna come back at it
and now here we are towards the end of 2020 they've had a couple of releases
and it's kind of an opportunity to do a state of the distro so we'll give you a
new update and a couple of things that I found really surprising and then sort
of led to a whole series of revelations but we've also got a bunch of community
news to get into something we're launching that we want to tell you about
so before we do any of that I got to say hello to the virtual lug time
appropriate greetings bumble room
what a crew today how about that was how about that huh you know they are mighty
and powerful in there in the virtual lug if you want to join our mumble room and
get your voice on the show we have all the info on our website at linux
unplug calm what you do is when you're in there you just tag me in the IRC mum
Chris last with a little description of what you want to say and then I'll
generally work you into the show and I'll call on you live and you can have
your thoughts on whatever we're talking about I don't always call sometimes we're
like moving on and I won't call on you but that's basically how it works so you
can get information about how to set up mumble which is an open source VoIP app
at our website Linux unplug calm let's start with our announcement first
because we have kind of some disappointing community news but I want
to start with the good you know there's been a lot this year Wes there's been a
lot worse I've seen it all and we thought we could do something kind of
fun we were inspired by some friends of ours and other podcasts out there and
we're gonna we're gonna announce right here on the show get ready for this
ladies and gentlemen I am proud I am excited I am stoked to announce the
Linux unplugged is launching the 2020 tuxes that's right a special segment
right here on the show and you can help nominate your favorite projects we use
that term loosely and other tech for 2020 tuxes and we will at the end of the
year we will announce the winners of the tuxes and they will be sent a 3d printed
tuxi award with what they won on there and it'll also serve as a fantastic
resource for you to get an idea of what projects and distros are really
resonating with the community this year it might give you an idea of something
you could check out and I think it's just gonna be a great way for us to get
an idea of what you all love and what we love and then to send them a little
thank you at the end of the year saying thanks for making that thing that we
love so much and our audience voted you the best a nice way to reflect on the
year and I mean we've covered so many great things on the show plus a bunch of
stuff that didn't make it in I've already forgotten about half of it I'm
sure you've forgotten even more so we really need some help making a good list
yeah and I wanted to be something kind of special so the distros they they can
receive or whatever it is a project there's you'll see all the categories
and I want to expand those two this is just the first year but I think we could
do this every year and I'd like to expand it and get your input on what
other categories we could include so it's just a form you go fill it out with
some questions about favorite this best that worst evens in there I think on
something and then we'll collect all the results we'll submit it to the committee
and then we'll announce the winners on the show we do get some vote power in
that mix but we're also gonna include we're gonna submit it ourselves so we
need to get as much input as we can because I'd like this to be reflective
of the audience so we're gonna run this for a little while the link will be in
the show notes for the 2020 unplugged tuxes and of course it also gave me an
excuse to include a super a super duper mega retro Jupiter broadcasting beat if
you get this deep cut then you've been listening for a really long time and
this is the official tuxes theme music
I'll see how long it takes until somebody can figure out where that's
from now let's talk about the community news we'll do the tuxes soon but please
do go get your submissions in but we need to start with what appears to be
some super bad news for a reason the Linux PC manufacturer that sold
desktops and laptops it appears they've shut down entirely they say as many of
you've noticed our product line is getting smaller and our tech support has
been slowing down to a crawl unfortunately the pandemic has been the
final ko blow or knockout blow that's what they write and it's hit our little
town hard and we have not been able to recover from it as of Tuesday November
24th 2020 za reason is no longer in business if you have a computer from us
we hope that it gives you a long and solid lifespan if it does not and you
would like warranty work done we regret there are no employees who can answer
those questions or do service repair employees usually want to be paid and
without sales there's no income to pay them yeah that is really unfortunate and
they they have an in tiny text at the bottom let me zoom in and hands here
they say note that when a business dies its warranty dies with it we know this
part is hard to accept it is sad disappointing and unsurprising that our
reason is shutting down this is them saying this there are many many reasons
but sickness and part shortages are the top two at this point there is no other
option we wish you the best and we hope you and your computers are healthy and
we help you and your computers are healthy and thriving a colonel you have
some experience with our reason yeah so I haven't actually owned any of their
machines but there's a convention that I have met them at personally and they
were really good just down-to-earth people even invited me to come by hang
out with them at their shop if I was ever in the area they're just they were
fantastic wonderful people and I'm sad to see that are having to shut down I
have to say I hadn't considered that the PC parts makers could be having supply
shortages it has slammed the RV industry surprisingly hard because when you have
different areas that are responsible for manufacturing certain parts and there's
been various different lockdowns implemented you've had various kind of
ebbs and flows to the production and so the people downstream from that are kind
of left in the lurch and I hadn't really considered that that could very easily be
affecting PC manufacturers and it honestly makes me wonder about if it's
affected our friends at system 76 because they're just hitting their 15th
birthday and they've you know they've they've really grown but at the same
time they could be vulnerable to some of these same supply chain issues and
perhaps our reason is just not nearly as well positioned as system 76 but I
don't know I just I worry yeah it's a wake-up call I think yeah it is it's
something you had I hadn't really it would be really kind of it'd be really
sad to see this spread you know there's other there's other manufacturers out
there we wouldn't want to see go I think from a competitive positioning
perhaps our reason wasn't necessarily the most competitive of the bunch though
but we haven't seen this happen for a while we haven't seen a Linux hardware
vendor shut down recently we've seen a lot launch but I suppose it was
inevitable and also just a little bit sad since they've been going since I
think 2007 yeah Jill you had some thoughts on czar reason yeah I was so
sad to hear this there are actually personal friends of ours at the Linux
chicks of Los Angeles there they were stalwarts at the Southern California
Linux Expo they had a booth every year for a lot of years and I got to know
their family very well and they even donated equipment to the Linux chicks of
Los Angeles and I have have one of my favorite they make a wonderful stuffed
pen penguin text penguin it's so cute well it's that's a great story yeah but
I just I'm just very very sad because a lot of lot of the Linux chicks have have
have their computers and this is just very disappointing and they their
computers are still running great I have a very old dual core laptop of theirs
and it runs beautifully still hopefully will for a while yeah Neil you have some
thoughts on it too yeah I mean when I found out I was I was incredibly sad and
disappointed like and the reason I found out actually was the saddest of all I
was trying to buy a Linux laptop oh yeah and I went on to their site and found
out that they shut down and it was just it was a blow to me I haven't directly
purchased as our reason laptop from them in years like I mostly got it through
friends who bought one for me or some other circumstances but they were nice
computers and the team was friendly and really they really cared about making a
good Linux experience and making it useful like regardless of Linux
distribution I think that was the that was the thing I valued the most yeah but
the the other part of this you know just about Linux laptop vendors in general
moving a little bit away from our reason the Linux laptop vendors in general do
not have a whole lot of marketing power unless you knew someone who knew someone
who who had one from one of these vendors I don't think you would know if
they existed I think system 76 is an aberration in this regard and and
tuxedo computers in Germany is a similar aberration but like most Linux laptop
vendors or Linux desktop vendors many of them exist but many of them aren't known
and I think they basically operated on like what you call family business
margins and budgets and and something like this pandemic which induced all
kinds of interesting supply shortages people shortages all that sort of thing
they don't have the powder on hand the cash to weather that and this is what
happens and so if we wanted to have more Linux laptop or desktop vendors you know
survive really the way to do that is to help promote them and bring them out you
know from the shadows of being just you know these little shops that help people
to being known to the greater community so that they can be supported in the
same way we did with system 76 when they came out when they came out with a
splash with their with their brand and their first laptops you know all those
years ago yeah I myself wasn't a customer but it it does it does remind me
that it is it is important that we buy locally essentially that we buy it when
we can buy from a place that is selling it as a Linux product if that's system
76 or maybe it's Dell or Lenovo now it's you buy it in that ecosystem to keep it
strong because of when you buy a machine preloaded with Windows and we all have
to do it from time to time I suppose I'm not shaming anyone but it is
essentially it's a vote for the Windows marketplace it's a it furthers and
that's that's the tricky thing here is it makes me think we got to remember
that and there's a lot of hype right now about Apple's m1 and how exciting it
would be to get Linux on there but I think ultimately when you look at what
serves us as a community long term it's it's buying locally from these from
these vendors well and it's a little more tricky these days too with you know
great Linux support coming from companies like Lenovo and Dell and I
think you just got to make sure it's on your list of you know when you're
assessing a new laptop Chris you've been you've been going through this
there's a lot of different trade-offs and I think that item of is this a
business that needs my business and would that help the community well it
should at least be somewhere on your list even if it's not the only factor
yeah there's a lot of things to consider I don't think it can be the sole factor
I don't think you should buy just for that reason solely alone but it
definitely has influenced my shopping I am NOT gonna buy anything that comes
preloaded with Windows for this very reason but let's talk about these m1 max
because there is a lot of interest like it or not I think you could make a
really solid argument that the effort that we're about to talk about would be
better spent on pursuing open platforms and I think a lot of us feel that way
but I don't think that takes away from concurrent tasks of making it possible
there's some value in making it possible to run Linux on the m1 Apple machines
and it seems that Hector Martin has launched a patreon I invited him on the
show but it was such short timing I don't think it's it was gonna work out
but he's launched a patreon that he's pausing billing on until it reaches
$4,000 a month that will in theory be a commitment that he can use to
essentially pay for his time to convert or I guess port or whatever you want to
call it make it possible to boot and run Linux on these m1 max which I guess he
has some experience in this area what's your read on this Wes long shot well I
think it'll just it'll just be tough what will be tricky I think is deciding
what's the right level I think there's a lot of interest seemingly already
they've crossed that threshold in in donations where it looks like it you
know it it will get funded at least of the 4,000 although the goal itself
they're not all complete but getting it to like a really solid experience that
you don't have to be so heavily motivated by Linux to make it worthwhile
especially with so many changes in the m1 things like the the new Apple silicon
GPU involved it's just gonna be a long March you're right you know there's some
history here he was hacking on Linux on the ps4 for instance clearly a talented
individual it's just gonna be a long time I think even if it goes as well as
possible you know even if it gets workable I guess we check back in in two
three years and by that time well how will Linux be doing on the m5 it seems
to me the only shot this thing really has is if Apple supplies some kind of at
least if not code documentation of how the disk controller works or how to
interface with the necessary components of of those disk controllers and whatnot
because getting Linux to boot on the m1 while valuable is not nearly as valuable
as actually being able to install and run it on the physical disk and and use
all of those components but unlike getting like around just a bootloader
which apparently Apple does have provisions to allow users to unlock the
bootloader and install whatever OS they want they they've apparently built that
into these m1 Macs but it's not just that right it's it's the drivers for
everything in this thing because it's all custom to Apple it may be from some
vendors upstream then we can once we figure out who that is we can take large
swaths of another driver and make it work but it's not like getting Linux
running on an Intel Mac where the t2 or the bootloader is your biggest challenge
but then it's Intel motherboard components and it's Intel wireless and
it's Bluetooth that you know how to work with and it's an audio interface that
you know how to work with like these are all going to be different on an m1 Mac
and so the scale of the problem is massive and then of course Apple won't
be sitting still especially at this stage in the m1s lifespan so they very
quickly are going to be iterating on this platform and will leave these m1s in
the dust surely by within two years yeah I think the question there will be you
know how much does the platform change and how much does the basic low-level
sort of communications channels that are needed stay the same and how much you
know is it an iteration or do we see a continued revolution on there on their
new totally custom platform which they have a lot more leeway to change and
like Lin mob says in the IRC room just imagine how difficult it's gonna be to
get the GPU working well so there's some good discussion in the in the Twitter
thread someone asked you know do you think it's gonna be feasible to put an
open stack on Apple's GPU and Hector's responses time will tell but I don't
think it's impossible Nvidia GPUs aren't exactly simple and yet new though exists
and yeah that's definitely true but I think that that is the right context to
look at this you might get something that's usable you might eventually get a
Linux desktop that displays you a desktop and you can use to browse the
web but it won't be all the things you're excited about from the Apple side
of the platform at least anytime soon and that's where I get to imagine this
amount of effort and this skill level being poured into open power PC or risk
five it just seems like so much more benefit from that right it just
ultimately while yes it would be great I feel like what needs to happen is a
shift in perception and maybe Apple will prove me wrong and I actually would love
it if they did but I think we need to shift our perception of these they're
not necessarily computers they're inclusive products they're a holistic
device like your Nintendo switch yeah you can get Linux on there but that's
definitely not what it's meant for it's not a general computing device that's
meant for you to load Windows or your own Linux or freeBSD or or whatever the
hell you want and we have to stop thinking of it that way because that's
just not what the intention is it's it's designed to be the best Mac possible
which is what those customers want and I don't think it's ever gonna be anything
else if Apple comes out with open source drivers or I mean starts working upstream
to make it possible I will be the first to cover it probably quite literally and
I will be the first to congratulate them and retract the statement but I just
don't think it's ever gonna happen I guess time will tell I mean you know you
can't stop hardware hackers from from hacking on things trying to make it work
and it is exciting to see you know what possible gains might be out there but as
ever it is a question of resources and this one won't I won't be planning to
buy M1 hardware for Linux at least anytime soon it has happened it's gotten
it's got up and running on the switch it's it's works on they've got it
working on the PlayStation before it absolutely happens and and somebody will
find a use for it so there's there's that as well so maybe maybe in a year
so I'll be sitting here talking about how I'm thinking about buying an arm
based Mac so that way I can run arch on it maybe it turns into a little you know
little headless box you use for your iOS builds there Chris actually you know
what thinking about it quite literally how I would use it is I would use it as
a way to bring life into older MacBooks so even if the support leg behind if you
know you could take a Mac book that maybe Apple had abandoned and was no
longer shipping Mac OS for but you could get Linux confidently running on it I
think that would be a victory that would be a success if that's the goalpost
ultimately then I'm a hundred percent for it I might even consider backing it
I want it you know what the more the more we talk about this the more I think
I want to talk to Hector and and kind of get his take on it where he thinks it's
going because that could be something I get behind I could talk myself into that
Linode.com slash unplugged get a $100 60-day credit on your new Linode
account we'll have a link in the show notes or you just go to Linode.com
slash unplugged they're the largest independent cloud provider full stop and
they make it easy for anyone at any skill level to get started no matter
what technology stack you use Linode can help your ideas come to life if you just
need a personal web server for a blog or a portfolio or maybe your business needs
to scale to serve millions Linode can help you with that and unlike entry
level hosting services that lock you into their platform Linode gives you
full back-end access to customize and control your server to fit your needs
they have a great DNS manager simple to take backups one-click app deployments
and if Kubernetes is your speed to manage your infrastructure Linode has
you covered there you can easily manage your Kubernetes cluster with Linode's
fully managed container orchestration engine also a great way to learn if you
want to learn cybersecurity or practice something before you have to do it in
production Linode has some great options there at great price points but one of
the things that I encourage you to look into is their s3 compatible object
storage if you're not familiar object storage is essentially an easy way for
you to store and access data in the cloud without having to run a front-end
file server it's perfect for data that doesn't change regularly this is where
we use it all the time for show assets that are essentially static and what
something is up in their s3 compatible object storage it's really easy to get a
URL and share that file if you want or maybe even use something like that to
power a static website we use Linode's powerful virtual servers to run our
infrastructure our matrix server our encoding server our new next cloud
server all of its on Linode my personal servers are on Linode Linode started in
2003 as one of the first companies to even get into what is now known as cloud
computing three years before AWS go check it out see what I've been raving
about and support one of our sponsors who's made our transition to
independence possible linode.com slash unplugged thanks to Linode for
sponsoring this show and thanks to everyone who supports our sponsors out
there linode.com slash unplugged okay prepare yourself because we're gonna get
geeky about ZFS because some major milestones have just been reached and I
want to try to understand it all obviously we're ZFS users here but also
as things change and you just it's nice to stay up to date and keep keep current
so it's now called open ZFS 2.0 and I wanted to play a little bit of Matt
Aaron's at giving us a brief state of the union on ZFS and then what I'm gonna
basically do is try to talk Weston explaining all the good new stuff to us
now I'd like to talk a little bit about the overview of the state of the project
so last year I talked quite a bit about what's gonna be coming in open ZFS 2.0
and the big thing is that we we've now combined the source code for open ZFS on
both Linux and FreeBSD and last year I talked about how this is going along
really well it's going to come out in 2020 it is still going to come out in
2020 so this project is very far along we've released three release candidates
so far it's on 2.0 RC 3 right now just came out last week and the final
release will still is still on track to come out before the end of the year
possibly even before the end of the month please don't quote me on that but
that's that's that's what we're aiming for and here's some of the features new
features that you'll see in the next release of open ZFS so this basically is
superseding the zol releases so this is stuff that's new since zol 0.8 and this
is a continuation of that code base but now with support for FreeBSD as well and
most of these a lot of these we've given talks at previous conferences about so
things like you know all this performance work redacted send and
receive in fact we will link you to some of those talks but in addition to the
unified code base for now Linux and FreeBSD it's no longer ZFS on Linux it's
just open ZFS now right Wes yeah isn't that neat I mean from something that
felt like a weird stepchild of the whole ZFS family to now be in the place that
you know a lot of the development effort is actually happening and it's also just
a great example of a wonderful open source project that manages to work with
like pretty much full parity across two very different operating system kernels
but both of them being open source software that's amazing yeah it is and
now they say they're targeting macOS as well so they may have macOS support in
open ZFS 3.0 they've they kind of talked up some of the features the one that
kind of stands out to me and I don't fully grasp why you would need it but
it's L2 arc support so the level 2 arc in ZFS is like this cache right that is
sort of the most frequently used stuff that ZFS keeps in there well it's the
second layer and you've got the arc the adaptive replacement cache and that's
that's for the first you know the nice smart cache to handle stuff that you
don't really need to go fetch off disk again just keep that hot and fresh in
RAM and ZFS does a great job of managing that but if you just you know grams too
expensive you'd only have a certain amount you want more cache for stuff
that's not quite as as well used but in the next layer of used you can have a
faster disk say right you've got like a big pool of old-fashioned spinning rust
then you've got like a nice shiny NVMe that you can use as a cache for after
RAM that's the L2 arc well this new feature is known as the persistent L2
arc and this just basically saves you time let's say you know you had to
reboot your system you did some updates or you just something happened there's
a fault there's kernel panic whatever most of the time with the existing
implementation of the L2 arc well you have to go rebuild that cache so you
won't get the advantages of having a good cache until you've actually done
gone through you've had your service up and running stuff's actually looking at
stuff from the disk trying to pull it but if your workload doesn't change
that's just wasted time rebuilding basically the same or a similar version
of the cache with persistent L2 arc that's just gonna get loaded back up and
you don't have you can skip that time ah that's handy there's a couple of things
in here that make it seem like just using ZFS overall is gonna be quicker
amongst just general performance fixes there's also a new compression standard
Z standard Z standard it's a modern high performance general compression
algorithm which should give better compression levels really similar to the
GZIP but with much better performance and it's also got a big selection of
different compression levels so depending on what your data is what your
trade-offs that you want to make you can choose and configure that I think it's
also neat because it's just a cool open source project that was invented at
Facebook back in like 2016 then the Linux kernel got it and it's been an
available compression option over in butter fs for a while now and then free
BSD got it originally to compress core dumps thanks to our friend Alan Jude
who also made a proof of concept over there for using it for ZFS that's
finally now been integrated how neat is that welcome to BSD unplugged your
weekly BSD talk show that's too busy getting actual work done to care about
what your silly display server my name is Alan love you Alan yeah that's great
that is really cool to see that get in there tons of stuff like we could do a
show that'd be way too long about all of the stuff that's in 2.0 so we will link
to some of the details and of course as always Michael Arbol over there crushing
it with the deets he's got an article that summarizes some of it as well and
it's cool to see this stuff landing I do wonder if we're really gonna see any
movement on what distros adopted or not I doubt it but if you have means of
accessing it it's gonna be a nice little upgrade get yourself prepared for
another round of DKMS rebuild exactly let's something we should probably do
kind of soon too well maybe next episode we should do an art server update but we
need to look into the future with with GNOME and there's a major feature
announcement for GNOME 40 remember that's what they're going to next is
version 40 and mutter is moving that's the back end display compositor is
moving input work to its own dedicated thread a separate get ready for this
Wes a separate CPU thread for the input this long in development effort led
by red hat aimed at restructuring mutter that's I mean it's just good right you
don't want the input work handled on the same thread if you don't have to and now
the import work will be able to be moved over to a separate CPU thread and it's
finally at a state where it was merged into git I think it's been developed
it's been played with but I mean this is a fairly big architectural change right
the merge request had been open for the past three months but was merged on
Friday this is massive this input should the input thread should allow for
avoiding possible cursor jumpiness and situations where your pointer kind of
lurches across the screen it should deal with high-frequency input devices a lot
better it should make sure that no lib input events are missed not to mention
it's just a superior way to architect a workstation desktop and recently on the
show I've talked about how much I've really been enjoying desktop you really
have a little gnome Renaissance over there it was like I came back home for
the holidays and my room was still there and it was like oh I love this I love
this and it was great and I got I got the green bean casserole just the way I
like it when I came down for breakfast it was just like being home again the
the thing is like being at home it eventually all comes crashing back down
and you remember why you moved out as early as possible and why you only go
back for the holidays Wes you saw a little bit of it because was it Sunday I
was you showed up and I was stuck upstairs in my office for like an extra
15 minutes before I could come down and say hi to you at the studio because I
was just dealing with my computer being slow and input lagging because I was
editing god forbid a two and a half hour video file and I was cutting audio from
it for the shows and I was getting I was extracting audio segments and having a
large file and working with an application that is trying to display a
very large waveform and move about and then have to have some other
applications in the background that are transcoding maybe wave files to flack I
mean this is you know it's it this is a system that I've built that has 12
overall addressable threads and I have a dedicated rate 0 14 terabyte scratch
array that I use for any files that I'm working on editing my OS is on a
dedicated MVME disk that's where my root is and then my home partition is on a
dedicated fancy fast Intel two and a half SATA disk and I have every I have
it all split out like that plus I have 32 gigs of RAM so I mean it's not like
I'm doing and I'm just cutting audio from a video file it's opened up in an
audio editor but the whole interface just when I'm doing a task that for me
is a really standard occurrence the UI becomes unresponsive like right-clicking
on say like an icon it has a delay and when you're moving windows around they
get kind of leggy and they kind of stutter around a little bit and when
you're trying to move really quick and it's something that maybe you do every
day and so you're really fast at this task and when you're really fast at
something and you're waiting for your computer like even if you have like this
experience at work if you have something you do for work kind of repeatedly and
you really can just blast through it faster than anybody you know and then
you're you're waiting for your computer at each stage for every time you alt tab
and every time you click on a menu and every time you try to bring up files and
when you drag and drop and it just becomes so aggravating and you think to
yourself what more can I do I've got a modern high-end AMD GPU I've split up my
disk workloads as much as possible I've got tons of RAM I'm only using six gigs
of it I've got 12 addressable CPU cores it's a desktop plugged into Ethernet
like what more can I do to let my computer work it so I can work as to
the my computer lets me work as fast as effective as possible why are you so
slow and so you know I came downstairs like I just don't know I'm gonna do yes
it's just like it's really aggravating because this is I do this kind of all
the time and I was I was having to talk about it because I've really been
annoying enjoying gnomeshell but I find this very annoying so I was asking you
what would you do what should I do what distro should I do and that's that's
kind of how we got to Endeavor OS but we'll save that for the analysis but I
ultimately I decided to go back to the plasma desktop because I just don't
experience this particular kind of frustration there are other paper cuts
but not that paper cut right you you know you win some you lose some but
especially for you who are on a high-end machine with real workflow needs it's
sort of like that the existing state of genome and not all of it was necessarily
built for the way that you're trying to operate and I kind of enjoy with my
monitor setup I enjoy the window rules where things always open up in the same
spot when I launched them I like that consistency for my kind of setup yes so
that's that was nice it was like it honestly to complete the metaphor it was
like when after you're done visiting family and you get back to your own
place and you're like oh yeah I way more prefer this it doesn't look as good I
didn't decorate as nicely but all my things are here and I know what food is
in the fridge yeah exactly that's so much what that's so much what the
experience was like and I didn't I thought the I thought it'd feel like a
big compromise but I was like oh no this is actually home and so I have so much
respect for what both desktop teams are doing because there's things I just love
about all of them but to see this kind of move for gnome 40 where they're gonna
start to break this stuff off that's that's huge because that may end up
ultimately being the best of both worlds for me and no one had to get assimilated
so big things look like they're in the works for gnome 40 they've also
officially announced gnome circle which is kind of a way to include I guess more
people in the gnome clubhouse you don't necessarily in the past if you wanted to
be part of the gnome project your projects needed to be hosted on gnome
infrastructure and you had to follow their rules but gnome circle aims to
sort of change that yeah now to become members projects must simply be
open-source software and use the gnome platform both applications and
development libraries can apply and projects don't need to be hosted on
gnome infrastructure nor do they need to follow gnomes release schedule now what
do you get when you'll be eligible for a range of benefits including promotion
gnome foundation membership and that gives access to things like travel and
marketing funding services including an at gnome org email address blog hosting
video conferencing and hey I'm gonna next cloud account so you actually get
to be part of the family but you don't have to play by all of the rules yeah I
might mean we get to see a bunch of cool desktop applications and whatnot start
showing up that are maybe a little more independent but sort of follow that
desktop ethos so they look really good as a part of your desktop I think that
could be a really lovely development just a little bit of cleaning just a
little bit here and there every now and then it's always worth mentioning you
should join the luck plug our virtual lug has a whole other event outside the
show on Sundays and they do that at noon Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern in the lobby we
have our mumble info on our website and it's kind of it's perfect because if we
ever have a backup time where we need to record the show that's when we do it
because we know there's people in there and so there's other reasons it's kind
of fun you know it's a great place to hang out and chat with people but can
also maybe every now and then catch a live show and I'll also give a mention
to the all shows feed if you're subscribed to that you'll know that
Linux action news has recently been revamped with mr. West pain joining the
team and I'm really loving where we're going with it and if you're if you're
only listening to this show you're only getting half the story there is a whole
other set of stories that we cover in Linux action news and that's the stuff
that kind of dense the open source universe every week particularly great
if you want to be or are in the industry and you want to stay current on stuff
that has wider ramifications to Linux action news has got you covered so check
that out if you're not already linuxactionnews.com and that my friends
is all the tidying we need to do today so it's time for an endeavor OS check
and something I promised when they first announced and we took a look at it and I
sort of judged it as need some time to cook but we should come back to it and
that was a little bit ago and here we are they have a new release in the works
right now they just put one out in September and then of course because
it's based on arch you can get up-to-date in between pretty quickly so
endeavor OS has found itself a comfortable niche in the distro world
because God knows there's a plenty of Linux distros out there and you really
kind of have to wonder what makes different distro stand out from each
other especially when you have mangero which is clearly filling a big need for
people who want a productized arch right there's already arch with an installer
in several different forms so like what do we get in here yeah and a big
community too right so I think and it's it was evident when they launched but I
think as time has gone on they have refined their position in the market
with a maybe more clever pitch they very much are not focusing or even pushing a
desktop or even branding they say on their website endeavor OS is mainly a
terminal centric distro with some gooey tools out of the box like our welcome
app reflector auto and a kernel tool to make jump-starting easier and with these
tools and the power of the terminal we offer you the opportunity to give you
full control from the start in creating a system that suits your idea in
computing they even kind of list no branding as a feature so wrap your head
around that because that's got to be as a distro that's that's got to be a hard
choice you're gonna you're gonna remove your wallpaper you're gonna remove your
branding if the user chooses well then how are they gonna remember are they
gonna know but they offer that if you use their online installer you get a
choice of desktop environment but they really seem to be refining their pitch
as as close to arch as possible they say on their website and I love this with
the exception of our in-house developed reflector auto the welcome screen and a
kernel manager and the update notifier all of the packages are installed
directly from the arch repos or from the AUR they are not customized or modified
they're not coming from our own repo we want to stay as close to arch as
possible and so that's I think where they're trying to position themselves is
a Kickstarter to get into just a long term arch setup for the desktop does
that appeal to you you know it kind of does at least you know I don't know if
it's necessarily what I would choose to use to set up my next arch system which
by the way I do think my next system will be an arch system again but I'm
glad this exists because if I'm going to be working on a system if I'm gonna
advise other folks to do this I just don't know that many folks who've been
down the road of setting up an arch system have gone through all the
installs have done that and who really just like doing it all the time I kind
of do for me that's it's like a rite of passage it's a way you sort of get
familiar it's almost like you're paying the upfront cost to really understand
and feel connected to your system that I really like about running arch but I
also get that for many you just want the you know the easy maintenance the
simplicity and the great access to packages and for that use case this
seems perfect and they never have to install it again if you don't screw it
up you know that's that's super appealing to me some of my longest
installs have turned out to be arch boxes and I know this people listening
there oh arts are talking about ours you can roll your eyes I kind of I think you
should try to put that aside if I could be so direct and and consider that
there's obviously something that's appealing to a certain market because on
top of whatever everything that West just touched on I have to be honest with
you I think just because I've been around for a long time I don't think
this would impact new users to the desktop but I find it a big relief to
not think about if I'm installing a flat pack a snap a deb or an rpm it's such a
relief just to say yay that's the that's the helper I use yay dash s slack or
telegram and I'm not doing the overhead of what do I want a flat pack of this if
it's a snap and it's confined am I gonna have some issues because I do
attachments with this app it's just a binary it's gonna be as fast as possible
because there is there's no there's no like structure around it it's just a
binary on my computer and it's gonna get updated really quickly sometimes as soon
as the git repo has been updated and I'll only have to run one command ever
do that ever like what I was doing on pop which I got down pretty well I was I
would have to do apt updates and then I would have to do flat pack updates and
then I would you know and I have to do both of them I just got down and snap
just takes care of itself but I just as a longtime user I guess I guess I
haven't really liked that overhead that the that I take when I even on fedora
it's like I'm always kind of wondering what's the downside of having my video
player as a flat pack is there a downside to that does that mean it's
gonna does that does that mean there's gonna be any difference in where it can
get to on the file system or access to what video decoding you can do like I
just have to do that math and it's exhausting and I don't have that with an
arch based distro and so what endeavor OS is done here is they've said hey we
get that you want arch but you also don't have a lot of time you don't want
to be worried about who's maintaining these packages what the delay is you
just want if it's an arch you want it but you don't want to bother with the
whole setup process it's an interesting kind of middle of the road too because
it's not it's clearly not aimed necessarily at you know like brand new
users folks you don't who aren't prepared for arch it's terminal centric
distro right but at the same time they have a lot of nice little utilities like
in there in their welcome utility that sort of get you going explain some stuff
helps you out with helpful tools helps you know some guides to like well here's
how you start installing stuff from the AUR so it's it's an interesting sweet
spot of yeah you want to use this computer but we're still gonna cut you
some slack we've got some docs we've got a wiki we've got a forum got all the
usual structure it's like you do need some help well there's folks around and
there's some docs for that too they have applied their customization at just the
right points so a live session starts with their welcome app it's an XFCE based
desktop which in general the any GTK desktop is just a mess about where it
puts the windows across my three screens but this one was particular hilarious
like it would just be random what screens different dialog boxes would
pop on and what orientation they would be in but once I got everything
centralized on one screen I noticed that they have a tool right there they're
the reflector auto tool reflector is a tool in arch that goes out and helps you
find the fastest mirrors and update your mirror list well they just have like a
one-button click to do that they ask you a couple of questions and then it gives
you a super fresh fast set of mirrors and that's really nice because that's
something I do when I'm setting up an arch box already then they have an
update this app button so that way you know you have the latest version of the
welcome app and presumably the installer and then I like that they have an
offline mode and an online mode to install offline mode just gives you like
a their XFCE desktop environment with the packages that are released on that
ISO and it's a good-looking it is you know actually that's what that's what I
went I figured that's what I'd try and I stuck with it because it's a it's a
sharp XFCE enough that took me a few minutes of having to go poke around to
figure out oh yeah this is XFCE the first time I booted it up that is
legitimately the benchmark when you know they've got XFCE right is when you
can't tell it first because it just looks like a modern desktop and that's
slick and you could really see the appeal to that or so that's the offline
mode or if you use and that's nice to have I should say I'm all over the place
I'm very excited about this but offline mode super nice to have really
appreciate that that's an option and they kind of have a little bit more
experimental online method which lets you select a desktop environment at the
time of install and pulls down the latest versions of everything from the
arch repo and again that's where having that reflector tool comes in handy
because that means as you install it's gonna be the fastest package
installation transfers as possible and I think these features and even the
process are just clearly more appealing to experienced Linux users who've
probably been through this rigamarole before they understand that like using a
fastest mirror for example means your system will install faster like that
could be as an example of the type of user that understands that difference
it's kind of the type of user this is targeted at and I think endeavor OS is
nailing that it's for people who like to mess with computers it's for people who
like to mess with computers and you know who you are and it it's not better it's
not like the superior distro it's just another option it's it's a set of
features that are appealing to my uses of Linux like I mentioned with
everything Wes and I talked about plus these options right at install the ones
you're done are just kind of out of your way but having these these choices of a
custom partitioner that is actually surprisingly customizable it recognized
my LVM raid and even even recognized like the the disk that is the is the
output of that and all of it and let me manage all of it in a way that is
possible in most distros but some distros don't even make it don't even
make that approachable and it's not like because endeavor OS has all these things
Ubuntu or Fedora are bad it's they're just different it's a matter of personal
preference but I think I'm the kind of user that prefers to have access to
these kind of more power user style features at the beginning of install and
I you know I went through there on my main workstation which I originally
wasn't gonna install this on but then I really started to enjoy it and it was
fantastic to just choose this disk layout that I mentioned earlier and and
be able to visually see it and lock it in and reboot my box and it just it was
all there it's a very basic plain install but it's all there I mean I think
if you were gonna set this up by hand in the regular archway I'm not sure you
would have been done by the showtime no no I did it this morning not planned I
was just gonna just keep on keeping but I thought you know I was really enjoying
it so I was like let's see if I can get this done this morning and I chose
plasma as my desktop environment again and it's going pretty smooth so far I
really like it it's it's there's something else I find kind of appealing
about and I don't know if this is gonna be a factor but I'm trying I'm trying to
be open-minded when I get my new laptop whenever that happens I want to put an
OS on there that I'm really gonna stick with for a while I want to put a distro
on there and I know myself I know that sometimes when I get like kind of
stressed out I can I can kind of start to distro hop as a way to quote-unquote
problem-solve with immediate results where maybe I'm struggling with
something that takes a long time to resolve and it's frustrating so I want
something I can make a change to immediately and see some immediate
benefit and sometimes that's why I think I distro hop so I have to be aware of
all of these aspects it's it's a complicated psychological thing for me
with you know it's hard to pick a distro these days well it is and you know
you're gonna leave it running for a while forever at least with you but it's
gonna stick around you want it you want to make the right choice and you don't
want to regret that later when everything's broken and on fire I got in
my head too I started thinking if I say it was on air and I ran Ubuntu all the
time and I talked about how I always run Ubuntu or what I noticed when I talk
about how I use pop OS people think like oh he's so in the bag for Ubuntu or
he's running pop OS because system 76 paid him to do it or if I run Fedora
it's like oh he must he must be a big fan of Red Hat and I worry that like the
distro I choose to run like sends a signal in a way just because of being on
the show and while arch sort of sends a like oh by the way use arch it doesn't
signal any kind of corporate allegiance it's sort of like neutral territory much
like Debian is and so in a way it kind of feels like that in the back of my
mind is playing a role in the distro I may choose to going forward is just
simply I know arch I can make it work for me I'm very happy with it and it
essentially means I'm I'm neutral yeah you know I I don't I don't have some
sort of perceived bias because I use pop OS or because I mean right because I'm
running on Fedora we all know you're in the pocket of the Linux foundation
anyway yeah I'm getting that big foundation money for sure I don't know
maybe that's just maybe I'm just up in my head about it but it's been on my
mind too as I go through this and I kind of like that I don't really I know that
over the years there's been drama with arch here and there but I can't really
articulate anything at the moment but mostly not right I mean you don't you
just don't expect the next big thing the back next big tumult that we'll end up
talking about here on the show if you're running arch it probably won't be about
your distro might be about some software you're running but then you'll
just be running the upstream stuff anyway I do like them fresh packages
that's the it's like if I was gonna go if I was gonna go gnome desktop Ubuntu
and Fedora I'm much more appealing because you get that fresh gnome shell
sauce right when it's pretty much as soon as possible like arches it takes
even longer to get an arch than it does in Fedora Ubuntu you know but yeah I
looked at it and I thought you know it's very it's a you tilt it's a
utilitarian move for me much like plasma is a very utilitarian desktop for me and
I think the two things might work well together and I think endeavor OS could
be the way I got there and I kind of love it because anti gross was my
solution in the past for some machines but it felt like too much where I do not
get that sense with endeavor OS it really feels like it's pretty much there
to help me get it rolling and then they're out and it's peace out have a
good time enjoy your arch box yeah that's not too much and it felt like
like with the with the little reflector helper it was kind of just of an enough
of a gooey for me like I can do it I know how to edit this in the command
file but scrolling through to find just the countries I want or you know
whatever else it's just really nice to have a quick gooey I could click it had
already figured out that I just wanted you know servers in the United States
had HTTPS already selected boom I also when I was in the forum and Frank was
just reminded me Frank it sounds like one of the founders of endeavor OS has
been having some medical problems recently yeah Brian is really a very
nice guy and he's been having a few medical issues but I really think you
should get him on he is a wonderful person to talk to and is really focused
on his community and that forum that you were talking about they are really
helpful that's a really nice thing to hear I don't think I've had enough
exposure yet to really make a call but it's good to get that feedback yeah I
we will try to track him down or Brian if you're listening reach out to me on
telegram or Twitter I'm Chris lass or Chris at Jupiter broadcasting comm I
would love to chat and I hope he gets better I saw that news and it's really
sad because it's such a great solid distro so my best goes out to him so I
really like it West would it be stupid nuts ridiculous to put this on the new
studio hardware would it be crazy I mean Ubuntu has served us so well that the
only reason I would want to replace it would just simply be for consistency
whoo now you're getting exciting I thought you're gonna say reinstall it on
our server in the garage but okay okay we'll start with the studio hardware
well no the server is already arch it sure is you know if if we get jack maybe
pipeline you're going I think we I think it could work I think it could work well
test box yeah but we need a text box we should probably run the test box for a
little while go through a couple update cycles and figure out this is gonna work
for what we need yeah I think we're gonna stick with it it's just we are
getting to a point where we really have to we you know we we were we were very
generously sent some hardware so we have to run that through some validation
testing and we have some machines we have to replace its maintenance season
in the studio very much so funny how that always seems to happen around the
holidays and I don't think we're gonna put 1804 on there which is what some of
them have now so where do we go next this is a serious perpetual problem I
have but I enjoy I think at the same time we'll figure it out we'll figure it
out maybe folks should write in and let us know you know if we should if we
should go down this dark road yeah I'd actually be curious to know what their
studio production experiences are what are you doing audio on out there
listeners in the world Linux unplug calm contact oh it's Black Friday season and
a cloud guru has a Black Friday deal for you we have a link in the show note you
know that the cloud is growing like crazy and so is the demand for skilled
cloud professionals 82% of hiring managers they say that cloud
certifications make a candidate more attractive well a cloud gurus annual
Black Friday sale is your last chance for low prices this year get access to
the most effective hands-on cloud learning you can keep up with change and
develop the skills you need with ACG developing cloud fluency can be hard but
you can use ACG's platform to keep up to date they make it easy by providing an
engaging way to learn retain and stay competitive the Black Friday sale only
comes around once a year it's the last chance to get the best prices we'll have
a link in the show notes for a cloud gurus Black Friday sale now you went out
and did some email spelunking and we have a couple in the mail bag and I'll
take the first one West why don't you take the second one Zach writes in says
while visiting the Linode site I typed in Linode comm slash Linux and I found a
pleasant little Easter egg oh that's why I couldn't get Linux I see I wanted to
get Linode comm slash Linux I was wondering we have slash unplugged he
said if you visit the site of this address you'll get a smile for sure
warmly Zach oh that's great well thanks for letting me know Zach I when they
said it was taken I was like oh okay I just assumed some other like podcast
had gotten it but I guess that's that's what it was all right West fire well we
were just talking about Black Friday and Mark wrote in with a little bit of
confusion no Black Friday deal for cork and
contributor I'm altruistic but cheap as well so I thought maybe you could have
you could just clarify that for us Chris I thought I did do one I thought it yeah
well there is a coupon code it's Black Friday and it takes two dollars off
crazy Chris is blowing the prices out and if you want to be a core
contributor and you haven't done it yet it helps the show stay independent it
helps us be picky about advertisers you get a limited ad feed there is some ads
in the feed but limited and you also get access to the totally live version that
starts well before we hit record in the some of our best stuff actually is well
before we hit record and well after we stop recording you get the whole live
stream as a possible RSS feed just packaged up and delivered as a podcast
if you would like to do that use the coupon code Black Friday when just as
one word when you become a core contributor and you can find that at
unplugged core calm thank you for thinking of us all right well moving on
I've got another question for you Chris and this one from Harry what are those
RF earbuds that you're using I've heard you made reference to the fact that you
use RF earbuds instead of Bluetooth what are you using and what are you using in
conjunction for your microphone oh man well I so I have some bad news is
they're not earbuds so that's the bad news maybe those are out there if
anybody has any recommendations do send those in but what I have been using is
more like over-the-ear headphones and I was just searching my orders to try to
get the exact model number of them but and I know I have them somewhere in the
show notes you may be able to find them on the website but when I search my
order on Amazon they don't show up they're like Corsair RF headphones that
have a microphone built in that auto mutes when you put the when you put the
mic up and then it unmutes when you put it down which is what I prefer but the
brilliant thing about it and I've had some good success with Bluetooth but the
brilliant thing about the RF headphones is not only is it super reliable and
rock-solid wireless obviously but there's a USB dongle that is an always
on existing sound card even if you have the headphones turned off so you're not
having this problem where the headphones come and go and so your sound device
comes and goes because that that's sometimes like for example maybe chrome
doesn't switch over when you first turn on your Bluetooth headphones because you
have to close and reopen chrome before it'll start sending audio to the new
audio device those kind of annoying little problems hate that so much they
don't come up because the USB dongle is always there it's always acting as your
sound card so it's always your default output device and then you just turn the
headphones on or off when you want system audio which just how I prefer to
work oh you found it thank you yeah they are premium gaming headphones I don't
know about that but they do work just fine with Linux and they are great for
gaming I don't know about premium gaming headphones I guess they do have an RGB
logo on the side that I don't think you can control from Linux so a disclaimer
of course yeah well that's good I'm glad I knew you have been using those and I'm
glad to hear that they're still working well yeah I I pretty much use them every
weekend at least I don't like to use them as much for video conferencing
because they are so big but yeah all right so Bennett writes in about the pro
one X smartphone hi Chris and Wes I was wondering what your thoughts are for the
pro one X smartphone from FX technology and the XDA developers I hadn't heard of
the original pro one and my jaw hit the floor when I saw a physical keyboard and
it ships with Ubuntu touch and lineage OS and the specs well they're pretty good
I'm fairly active on XDA I was fairly active and the phone would be perfect
mix between an old Android and my current love for Linux they demolished
their IndieGoGo campaign and it looks like it's gonna ship in March I hope to
hear your thoughts Bennett how did I not hear about this Wes this one was new to
me too I know thank you for hiding in Bennett yeah I I'm really happy to check
it out I actually be kind of down for a I have a I have a very small phone now
which I'm really happy with and I could see room in my heart for a bigger phone
with a keyboard it's that style where you slide it back and up so the screen
kind of pivots up so it kind of is tilted right at you and they say it's a
purposely designed function for Android lineage or Ubuntu touch so that looks
really good and of course it has USB C out and they talk about connecting it to
a larger screen and they have some shots of it with the Ubuntu desktop a
Bluetooth mouse and keyboard and then it's connected over USB C kind of kind
of one yeah you know this would be pretty nice even if it was just like a
handy little remote terminal machine even if I didn't use it as a full-on
replacement for my regular smartphone just having this in my bag and my back
pocket and the car I'm interested get this West that has a removable battery I
didn't think they still made those they have three left at their Black Friday
sale price which is down from 829 to 599 too rich for my blood but I think it's a
fair price for what this thing is so they'll probably be sold out out of that
particular one by the time you're hearing this unless you're listening
live I'm gonna drop it in the IRC right now so if you want it oh you already did
look at you as we're hooking them up but I'll put it in this I'll put the direct
link to the Indiegogo in the show notes if you do want to check it out because
even I mean if you have the money to burn even at full price it looks like
really nice and the fact that they're aiming for multi OS compatibility out of
the box and they have what looks like an actually pretty decent QWERTY keyboard
I'm down with that I think that's a pretty solid recommend recommendations
so thanks for sending that in those are those are solid all right West have
yourself a taco because it is time for the picks and I mentioned earlier I
wasn't sure about having a video player as a flat pack well I'm gonna recommend
a flat pack that's a video player it's a really great MPV front end for the
plasma desktop yeah yeah of course right I'm always looking West for the best
video player this is gonna replace dragon player for me and it's gotta look
native so that when you full screen that you can easily forget about all those
mismatched window orders of course he's savage yeah it is a cute QML video
player built on top of lib MPV and it's available as a package of course but I
have a link to the flat pack and I think it's great it reminds me a lot of dragon
player but it's it's current it's maintained and I think MPV is the best
video player for desktop Linux I love me MPV soloid or whatever it was was great
on GTK so this is great for plasma now we do have a second pick you want to
cover that one yeah this one's interesting we've talked a lot about
YouTube DL lately but maybe you're not interested in moving pictures you just
want regular pictures well enter gallery DL a command-line program to download
image galleries and collections from several well they say several but turns
out many image hosting sites I like this so it's like YouTube DL but for
galleries the chat room says I didn't mention the video player names because I
don't really know how it's pronounced Haruna Haruna yeah so Haruna is the video
player and then gallery DL is the command-line app that downloads image
galleries and collections it doesn't say exactly what right here in the in the
release notes but they do have a page on their github and it's just about every
damn picture site I've ever seen I could see this being really handy for like
backgrounds getting wallpapers yes or you know maybe some some you don't want
to be on a platform anymore you just want to back up a bunch of your old work
something like that because you know they've got got things for Instagram
they've cut they've got things for all these popular sites like flickr or
various places you might post art on here a lot of other sites as well but
hey that's the sign of a good tool that's right that's right if you'd like
to give us a suggestion for an app that we should try out maybe talk about in
the show contact page is a great place for that too you can just let us know
over there Linux unplug calm slash contact or hit me up on Twitter I'm at
Chris oh yes he's at West Payne over there West Payne the host of Linux
action news yes that West Payne yes yes how did you know oh you've heard of him
yes he's on Linux action news hey I think that's me we'll be doing the next
episode live on Tuesday at noon Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern see you next week same bad
time same bad station and we'd love to have you hang out with us hang out in
the chat room or just watch it live or maybe go all the way and join us in the
mumble room we'd love to have you also thank you to everyone who just shares
the show or supports our sponsors we appreciate you and of course a big thank
you to our core contributors for really helping keep the wheels on this thing we
we really have a great audience and as the holidays get closer and closer and
as we have now across the threshold of three solid months of being independent
I just really couldn't be more thankful so thank you so much for joining us on
this week's episode of the unplugged program and while it's a long haul until
next Tuesday we will indeed see you right back here next Tuesday
all right let's name this thing JB titles calm gonna come up with a real
good name right that's the secret to podcast success it's got to be it I
think with the new laptop I'm gonna kind of refresh the home setup I'm gonna try
getting monitor mounts and a laptop mount that goes on the monitor mount so
I can have screens and my laptop mounted and yeah I'm really gonna I'm gonna put
some effort into kind of like a 2021 setup so I want to try to get it all
kind of going and then I think I'm gonna talk about it here on the show talk
about what I did and what didn't work for me I think it's gonna be I think
it's gonna be a solid kind of at least start for the year I don't know if I'll
stick with the whole setup but I'm kind of I'm kind of aiming for that sounds
like we'll need to play some bets for how long it lasts oh I don't know if I
don't take any of that action with