So, how's mr. Hartley doing not bad not bad yourself
Yeah, I feel like we I feel like we circle each other all the time, but we never actually I mean
We directly interact on Facebook every once in a while
Yeah, it does seem like that doesn't like that. I'll be popping in for a bit tomorrow
So I heard I see you then I heard for this for for for secret project 109
Alpha dog
That'd be kind of cool if everyone had call signs
Right that would just make life a lot simpler. I think
I don't know then you could really would yeah, I guess we kind of do though. That's what screen names are for right
I guess so I mean it kind of starts with whole you know
You know you got your CV handles, and they're kind of a ball. I'll see you from there, and we call Colonel Linux
Yeah, there you go. What am I getting am I getting made fun of I feel like I'm getting made fun of
I'm basically I am just a little bit
Like military this is a this is a poor week for you guys to make fun of me because right now
I'm sitting in front of mumble, and I have a feeling this account is rather empowered
I feel like you walk around in a constant state of
Evaluating other operating systems as they compare to a bun to and all of their phone mobile operating systems as they compare to a bun
to touch
Not all the time in your spare time
Well when I'm awake yeah
No one's on the nook no one's on the nook no on the nook actually and a yoga as well. Yeah, okay?
So hold on a second. I'm on a think center. I'm in a Lenovo think center. I'm on a nook. I'm on a yoga
It's just wow man. Yeah, it's crazy. Well. I got so many computers up in here
You you're in studio at the moment. I am
Both of you, so you've not headed off to the big jamboree yet not yet
No, that is on Friday. Yeah, oh, oh wow now you you're putting in some hours there then no it came in early
Last or late last week, so that way he could be here for the for the big switch Angela to Linux effort
which was
Is ongoing Chris you know it's ongoing
You know I will say for the she's reinstalled the rest in order. Yeah, I'll say no no no
Don't don't give it away. Don't go away. I didn't
Is this a show topic? Yeah, this is gonna be a show topic. We got it all right. I'll say we gotta save it for the show
But I'll just say so Noah flew in if he got here Friday
and
He so he basically he eventually did get to sleep Sunday after last
Yeah, oh there you go hours for like basically yeah, we're not no neither
Nor I slept much from Friday until Sunday after the Linux action show yeah
I think towards the end of last you could start to tell both of us. We're getting a little cranky. Yeah, hey a little
Night owls you well
If we didn't stay up all night there wasn't gonna be a show in the morning
So we stood about we just and it wasn't just us either. No yeah, Rekai like he every guy
Yeah, every guy pulling double time like no, and I went off
I got like a solid two three hours of sleep Noah got a solid two three hours of sleep mm-hmm
Rekai got zero yeah
We didn't get sleep you just slept during last week I slept during last while we were doing last
And then he woke up after last to continue working
We're gonna give him a burger eyes because you know Rekai if you're not aware can be bought in five guys burgers
Yeah, people have no people like I become a podcaster. How easy must that be? Yeah?
For a day yeah, I'm up for a day. I'm seriously this job's making me old and that's and then here
We're wearing ourselves out right now
Yeah, yeah, she can't here's the thing though Chris. You have to understand something use you feel the stress right from the outside
This is amazing
Nobody wants to see us roll in there and everything work on the first
Yeah
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that has an anchor around its net. Oh wait a minute. No, that's a Macbook
My name is Chris and my name is Matt. Hey there Matt guess what in studio?
We've got a special guest and that is Noah
Thanks for having me. Hey Noah. I didn't have your mic muted. I had your mic muted cuz it's like who's never he's never in studio
Yeah, why would he talk?
Hey, buddy. Well, I'm glad you're in studio. Yeah, Noah's hanging out because Linux fest Northwest is coming up in just a few days
And we have been slaving away for hours
Before the show and after the show converting my wife Angela to Linux. We have learned a lot
and in the process
We've also bought some new hardware
We will be giving you a review of the ThinkPad yoga 2 in this week's episode of Linux Unplugged
Oh yoga 3. Sorry yoga 3. We went all out. Oh shoot shoot and we'll also tell you about that
But um after that there's a very interesting thing going on with John Deere tractors. Yeah, I said John Deere tractors
But it really show. Yeah, it actually very much relates to Linux free software and free hardware
And it's pretty cool. It's pretty cool
Yeah, it actually very much relates to Linux free software and free hardware and it's picked up a lot of traction in our subreddit this
Week, so we're gonna talk about that as well as some
Great great follow-up since Linux action show and today like I cannot believe how much good news has come out
It's a huge show this week
So before we go any further we cannot we cannot take another moment without bringing in our mumble room time appropriate greetings mumble room
Oh
Handsome handsome group hello there everybody man a house
It is it's lovely having you here, and I'll have to tell you what I'm glad you are because we have got a great show
And we're gonna break it down
Let's start though with a little follow-up a little just stories
We have talked about before on your unplugged program that need a little a little attention
Oh, hey there
How you doing and that is your friends are good buddies everybody loves system D
What no not everybody and a group is doing something about it one of the most tantalizing components of system
D is login D
and it's something that you got to have if you're gonna use like say gnome 3 on Wayland and
It's caused some consternation in the BSD's out there and all them folks well
I would like to introduce to you e login D
What essentially this is is login D ripped out from system D?
And it's gonna become its own project to be a standalone version of login D
So those distributions that don't want to use system D can put this in have it be API compatible
It'll lay out on the file system
It'll integrate in with PAM so that way it'll use PAM and policy kit or a login kit or whatever
It is a Paul kit Paul kit
It'll use Paul kit so that way it works with the underlying authentication infrastructure
So you can get all the advantages of having login D without system D
So is this have we reached a point now where we can stop saying things like red hat has taken over
System D, and that's a that's a totally red hat thing and nobody will else be able to play at the party because
Red Hat controls the party. I mean is this not a first step of
Allowing other people to do things different different ways well
Breaking compartmentalize things out Matt do you in your opinion is this is this sort of proving all of the system D?
Proponents point they was saying look if system D gets big there's an API you can clone the functionality well
Guess what system D got big and they clone the functionality isn't that exactly what we're seeing play out here isn't
Isn't all the naysay and all the doom and gloom maybe turning out to be
Not quite accurate because look look what we're doing right here. Mm-hmm is this proof of in the pudding Matt
I think that the whole thing was just blown out of proportion
It's obviously people with entirely too much time on their hands that sit in their parents basements whining and complaining about whatever the point of it
Is is that the whole thing stupid?
It's this takes care of itself, and it's beginning to I mean that you know solutions are already making themselves evident
So yes an answer to the whole thing being blown out of proportion absolutely hmm
And I wonder if anybody anybody in the mumble room that wants to take the counter-argument you're more than welcome to
All right, I would like to do that. Yeah, so when it comes to to the complaining well
That's pretty much what we do
The complaint is what improves the quality that's my argument on that one and in service we do
I
Guess it does
prove the case because it shows that apparently there is enough people interested enough to
To the point that they will do the effort of you know cloning and just having an API compatible
It's good that it has the API
But it's still work being done because it's getting to be right and that API is unstable it changes
So exactly so it means that now there is quote-unquote duplication of efforts, right?
Something that we're always bitching about
Yeah, that's what I feel. That's what I feel well, but it does prove that
Okay, so and I thought nothing that and it is early days not not a lot other than this to it, but I
We the system D drama does continue on its own way all right
I thought this next story was particularly interesting we talked about the whole Debian
elections and all the stuff going around there and the different sort of platforms that the different candidates ran on and I don't know if
Anybody else caught this, but I thought it was particularly interesting that Neil McGovern. I think is his name
he's the one that ended up being elected as the new project lead for Debian and
part of his election platform and
You know maybe it won't be exactly this but part of his election platform was introducing PPAs from Ubuntu
Into Debian to give users of Debian an easier way to install PPAs
Now that there could be a lot of ways to skin that cat it might not be an exact implementation although that seems like that
Would be the best
user adoption
Seems like it on the surface. Yeah, yeah
What do you think wimpy? I?
Think this is a great idea and and probably a bit overdue
Because with Debian sort of two-year cadence more or less. You know when it's ready
And really you've only got the back ports repositories, and then you know if you're on a server platform
It's a little easier because some of the big projects maintain their own repositories for things like
nginx and varnish and
Postgres and things of that nature
but if you're a desktop user you're kind of resorting to either sticking with what you were given or
Compiling stuff from source or making your own packages, so I think having
PPAs
Brings us closer to that stable base and then rolling applications on top which is terrific
And you you don't have any concerns you think the current PPA system is good enough that Debian you think they just take it as is
I've no idea if they're just going to take what Ubuntu have already created
Doesn't it seem like that would be the most advantageous, but maybe they couldn't because there'd be too many differences between
Debian and poppy
Isn't all the launchpad stuff open now, so they could they could potentially take all that
They could but it comes along with I think a significant amount of baggage
And it's all very well integrated into launchpad. I think they want to do something
akin to PPAs, but not yeah like you
You know going and getting launchpad and putting it on a server somewhere and saying there you go
There's PPAs for Debian
I think they just want I mean there be an archive admins know how to maintain an archive and a
PPA is effectively a very small archive
That's all it is right and it has behind it has builders
And so they they would probably need to put restrictions on the PPA building infrastructure in the same way that we do so that
PPAs only build like x86 and i386 or i686
And optionally arm HF and optionally power PC and so on and so on
Otherwise their builders are just gonna be flooded with people in the same way that ours are sometimes
People uploading their own random like Firefox or cute or open-office whatever packages
Which take a very long time to build
You know they need to put restrictions in place and I think they're quite capable of doing that without using launchpad
So I dare Devon are we putting the carpet for the horse? You say that's not the first step. What is the first step?
Okay
So apparently what they've just set out to be doing more often and more quickly is to okay
So like the core few set of packages to be core handle those and things that are out of that spectrum
Let's not keep them around and trying to fix them as they have been doing
Let's drop them and let them come in again
And I think that is because they're getting they're realizing the limited resources and they have more and more traction and I'd say vol
And others as well coming more and more to Debian are opening
That Avenue, right? So PPS will be a next step type scenario where okay if there's too many things being dropped
So constantly then we need to figure out a way of you know
Allowing those to exist and that's where PPS fill in
But I think they're first streamlining the process that they already have try to have that to be a quicker process
For people to enter into the Debian project. Yeah, then something with you
Yeah, you got to build that community to create the software and package all that stuff. You got to cultivate all that
Okay. Can I say something here? Yeah, I
I personally like the idea because I think it would make a Debian a lot easier to use for us regular
Users who are not so really that much first in the Linux world
Yeah, I think it would I feel it feels like it would make whatever it is a PPA ripoff or not
I think it would encourage people to switch over to Debian from Ubuntu
I think if that kind of availability was I think it'd be one of the one of the things that keeps people on Ubuntu
Is that that math software available available? They might as well call PPAs Ubuntu crack really?
Like it seems to me like right now Devin is aiming for a completely different kind of user that I agree to it
I agree. Well, I I do I can see that however, Debian stable is appealing to a certain class of machine
I mean, there's a you know
there's a workstation class or a server class where Debian stable has a real place to it and
There's also political reasons as well
I suppose if you insult Debian stable and then put a whole lot of packages from PPAs
By some random people. It's not really
Debian stable and the reality is I think they they target drastically different. Is this going to change?
Well what we think of Debian is this going to change Debian a little bit? I don't know
Do you think you're still you know right now? No, I can tell you right now. No, yes, there's already a way to install
packages or build sure packages for Debian
Well, there's third-party files from well, you can use the build
Files from launchpad from PPAs to build the packages on Debian, right?
Yeah, so there's kind of a this workaround way to use PPAs on Debian. I like
I like the process q5sys producer q5sys says Debian's user repository would be called the der not a great
The reality is that I would put my mother on Ubuntu
But even if I had access to all the software and PPA I still wouldn't be I still don't think I'd feel comfortable sticking around
A Debian box. I mean unless I'm going to be there constantly to do stuff for yeah
Yeah, man
I've been using Ubuntu for going on three years and I just recently tried a deep
Debian based distro AV Linux and let me tell you it was a quite a bit difficult for me to use
So yeah, I like Ubuntu and Ubuntu based derivatives a lot better
but I suppose I
Yeah, I'm reaching to really come for a good answer to that question. So I'll grant you that Derek Devlin
All right, your closing thought on the zero install
So zero install is this type of package manager really that this allows you to quickly install something that is listed on a website
And it pretty much is able to pick up from tarballs or search your package manager
See what's already installed use that but installs like a different environment for that package
It follows you pretty much to have these foreign packages
I think that might be a way of having okay. This is an exception to my stable system and
It is kind of better than PPA necessarily
That's my impression and it's already working with Debbie and they are actually making efforts and it works on Windows even though
I don't know. How is that going but it is interesting project. Hmm interesting a zero install
I I find all of this stuff so much potential and yet still so far away
But I'll tell you what's here today what you can capture today in your very hands listeners
And that is our first sponsor digital ocean go over to digital ocean comm right now and check them out and use our promo code
Of absolute knowledge and power do unplugged lowercase one word Noah's got like a jillion droplets
I'm sure he used the promo code do you unplugged on his account?
Absolutely that way you got a ten dollar credits. You could try out digital ocean two months for absolute what wait what you don't know
It what you don't know what digital ocean is well digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider
Dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to spin up your own cloud server that you're gonna have root
Dizzle access to up in the cloud sizzle and that's right
They're gonna use the HTML 5 nizzles so you don't even have to have Java when you want that console
You can watch it from a post all the way up to your login screen and you get started in less than 55 seconds and pricing
Plan started only five dollars for one outrageous month five dollars for a month
I mean, I'm just trying to think you and I went out today to the walk. Yeah, and we spent $30 on lunch
Yeah, that's right. Yeah, you can barely get ice cream anymore. You go to Cold Stone. You'll spend $7 on ice cream
That's insane that lasts like 15 seconds nuts and so so for five dollars a month
You can get 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a frickin terabyte of transfer
Yeah, a frickin terabyte of transfer. Yeah a frickin terabyte of transfer for five dollars a month
It's just it's nuts and they got data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam
London and a brand brand new one in Germany. I'm gonna tell you about that because it's hot
It's hot and their interface speaking of hot their interface is amazing. You think gnome 3 looks good. I
Think so. Yeah, no three ain't got nothing on digital oceans interface digital oceans interface is out
I would if I could legally get married to digital oceans interface in the state of Washington
Yeah, I think I would consider that I mean give it five years. I first of all, I would like to have multiple marriages
I don't feel like I should leave my existing wife over that but I also feel like I have room for another wife
Yeah, if that wife is digital oceans dashboard
Yeah
Especially looking that good and at that pricing structure and and digital ocean really just like come on the perfect spouse the perfect spouse has an API
Let's admit it. We all wish our significant others had an API digital ocean. You're my significant other you've got an API
It's very straightforward
They just released the brand new version so you can replicate the functionality of their dashboard on a very very straightforward basis
Plus there's tons of great community apps
We take advantage of the API and the apps around that and if you didn't ever need to use that their dashboards gonna take care
Of all your problems. You got full DNS management. You can take snapshots of your servers
You can build servers from previous snapshots to save ton of time
Of course, they go tons of one-click installation
So you can deploy the latest and greatest software on top of your latest and greatest Linux installation
Riding on top of KVM that sits on top of Linux top of those great SSDs connected to tier one bandwidth with data centers all
Over the world remember how I mentioned they had a brand new data center. That's right
They got a brand new one in Germany. And what I love about this data center is it is hooked up
They got 40 gigabit e networking to each hypervisor
They got their fastest yet SSDs on those hypervisors and the data center sits on top of the German German commercial Internet exchange
The largest Internet exchange point worldwide by peak traffic serves Germans neighboring countries with unparalleled connectivity and speeds
$5 a month do one plug do one plug one word do one plug lowercase $10 credit
Try out your own Linux rig. They got free BSD to I don't know why you'd want that
They got that though. They also have core OS now
I know why you'd want that containerization with a rolling base and they have direct channel upstream to from core was that's super badass
That's a long-term infrastructure. That's totally worth investing some skill set and time and learning and you can get started two months
Absolutely free up on a production droplet where you can point people at that
You can point services at that core OS is something you should check out do it for free do one plug two months
Absolutely free digital ocean calm. No, have you played with core OS yet? I have not really played with
I have I have however played with digital ocean using
X2 go. Oh, yeah, man. Oh, yeah, you got next to go up there, huh? That is nice
All right, so digital ocean calm do you unplug? Thank you digital ocean for sponsoring some plug program. All right
So wimpy is it customary now?
I know this is just in your opinion
but is it customary for canonical to make up crazy random numbers in their press releases or if if
If canonical writes today we count over 25 million users and that number keeps going rapidly
Is that is that trustable? Is that 25 million number legit? Because that seems you know
Cray, I I have no idea
No idea where those numbers come from Popey, Popey
I'd say what do you think Bobby?
It's not it's not infeasible. If you look at just the digital ocean being the most popular one you think about
Okay, if it's most popular at least 30% of that
Okay, you can contact a good numbers of that. All right, and it's on the tone easy to a lot, right?
It's on a lot of cloud installation
Yeah, it's very I mean it doesn't sound too off honestly
Why do you say that that number that number 20 million was quoted from mark years ago, like
five years ago something like that and
Within the first week or so of me starting at canonical someone mentioned numbers
And so I asked on an internal mailing list
Look this 20 million number has been banded about a lot
Is is there an up-to-date number and now bear in mind I started at canonical three and a half years ago
And I asked that question and I had a conversation
Unfortunately internal private conversation with someone
Who explained where that number came from and that it?
Yeah, it it was as accurate as we could make it given that you know
It's possible for someone to install them into and be behind a firewall
And so we have no idea and pass the CD around and we have no idea of that install, right?
So we you know, we can't be a hundred percent accurate but based on you know, various things
You know people upgrading hits on launchpad archive hits NTP update hits or you know all kinds of stuff
We can make an educated guess right and that was some years ago
the not the trajectory the graph was going in a particular direction and
We could extrapolate forward and continue to monitor those numbers. And yeah, they're not inaccurate
But that number 20 million was some years ago and people keep asking us for an updated number and I I personally think
That the company regrets ever giving that number out because people keep on asking for an updated number
I think that might be so you think 25 million is a is a trended estimate is what you're saying
No, I personally 25 million is massively under. Ah, really? I personally think it's way higher than that
So I have no evidence. I can't I can't possibly corroborate that or I have enough
No data to to provide to back that assertion up. So you could say that with a grain of salt because I work for canonical
Yeah
but when you factor in like it's
One of the major use cases for for Ubuntu is the cloud deployments and in number one
Thing about a cloud deployment is probably behind a firewall
I mean like a lot of those like the number one use case for
Ubuntu server is generally behind a firewall is gonna be harder to count if they're all coming from one IP to check in updates
And whatnot, right and if a company spins up 20 30
100 300 we just wouldn't and then and then to make that even harder than you have like when you have when you have companies
That have a lot of Ubuntu machines a lot of times they do internal repos, right?
And that's what I that's kind of where I was thinking of at first
I was like wow that seems high and then I thought about it
I'm like man in Grand Forks alone and we're only a town of 50,000 people we have Amazon
They have 4,000 workstations and I know for a fact every one of them is running a bunch of desktop
Hmm, so you look at that and now you extrapolate that and say well if they're doing that
They're probably doing that at every Amazon call center
How many computers is that in addition to all the computers that we have at home in addition to all the computers that we have?
In the cloud in addition to all the computers that places like Google and you think about how cheap a VM is these days
Yeah, we'll just have thousands of them
Yeah
But I mean like even Google has their their workstations that they do work out some modified version of Ubuntu
But there's a bunch of when I say people have thousands of people like data centers. I don't mean people like us
There's data centers where there's could be a thousand VMs in some in one data center and maybe they're only doing a few things
So then that number starts to see you highly realistic if not low. What are you gonna say poppy? I
Think people get really hung up on the numbers and and really
what I
Part of the problem is, you know, a lot of the time developers want to see numbers to be able to yeah
Know that there there is a target audience. Is it worth my investment of time exactly and and I I
Can see why people want more accurate more accurate details, but really in the large scale of things
I'm not I'm not sure that you know having super accurate numbers about exactly how many deployments there are
I mean
It's good for the Apple to go on to it's great for app for Tim Cook to go on stage and say we've sold
X-million, you know iPhones or iPads or MacBook pros because there's a share price there that that you know the the market
They're interested in keeping the market happy. Mm-hmm. Yeah, it was a privately held. Yeah company. Yeah, we don't have any shares
Right, you're publicly traded shares. So that's not important to us to make those announcements. So it's a different kettle of fish
Really? Can I I wanted to ask you something that I think I'm reading the wrong way
and I know you're not an expert in these areas and so I'm not asking for an official canonical opinion, but I
always think of you know friends of the shows like system 76 when I when I'm seeing kind of hardware related announcements from canonical and
I want to talk about certified hardware images. And so it reads as this the Ubuntu image preload
This isn't this is on the same announcement. So the Ubuntu image preload will come with all the drivers
Integrated and maintained throughout the life cycle of the Ubuntu version
This is a certified image from canonical the end clients were to use a standard image from Ubuntu comm
It's likely that not all components will work. So here's what I'm here's what I'm taking away from this
This is how will Ubuntu
Certified images differ from the Ubuntu comm images and Ubuntu certified image offers end-users radically different experiences
Because all components within the hardware will simply work out of the box and continue to offer great performance throughout the life of the Ubuntu
Version canonical will ensure that any modifications that may be necessary due to security
Updates and patches are fully tested and integrated into the master image before the updates are pushed out to market
So this would be like an OEM image provided to Dell or somebody like that, but
the way I also sort of could secondarily read this is if
If you're buying hardware from vendors like system 76, that's that's sort of like a doc
That's the image they downloaded off of the website
We can't guarantee that but if you want to buy a certified laptop with a canonical certified image
That is going to be maintained by canonical
So essentially canonical is kind of going to kind of do the job system 76 has been doing where system 76 has you know?
Made any drivers or changes or patches needed to make Linux work
Well now canonical is kind of taking that role on but offering it to almost any hardware OEM
Am I following this?
we've had
An engineering services group for years that have done this right is not new. So this we've is this
Why is this in this and not really?
Well, I think it's more that people just didn't know we did it. Okay, that's what I was trying to understand
It's what's been changed. I think part of this came from a
Conversation that was had internally about the new Dell Sputnik, right?
so there was a there was a conversation on Intel my list where
An engineer says yeah, what laptop should I buy and and someone says well you should buy the Dell one because you know
It works really well and there were I know you and others have reported problems with the Windows version of the Dell laptop
That's all pretty much done Windows version
Right, but the the Linux version is now available. Yeah, and the we helped Dell make that work, right?
So it wasn't Dell that did that. It was a collaboration right canonical and right
So someone's gonna do that and someone's gonna pay for that work
it kind of though, but it kind of sounds like it does kind of sound like it creates a
A difference between the vendors that have certified images and the vendors that don't that maybe right?
Well, someone's got to do that work. Somebody should be so there's got to be commercial relationship going on between
Dell and canonical in order to make an excellent experience for people who yeah, I don't want people to go to Dell com
Type of them to get a laptop and it arrived and so this doesn't work what I'm trying to ask though is like if I were
to buy a certified canonical certified Ubuntu
machine
The updates for that machine would actually be be developed by canonical not the OEM. I bought them from
Am I falling? It's it's our average. Okay, this is the canonical and they'll work together. So it depends on what the arrangement is
Right, but it's it's at the whole point of this is getting a machine out the door that that is satisfactory for
Dell's customers or whoever that OEM is and what we're saying is we'll work with you to make sure it works
You know, it's it's a positive thing
It's not you know, there's an ISO image chuck that on your machine and off you go and good luck
Yeah, we want we want you to have a good experience. We want your customers to have a good experience
We want the touchpad to work. We want the touchscreen to it
We want the the Wi-Fi to work and we'll help you to do that. That's that's part of the value add that we're trying to offer
is
That that's what that that press release is really all about is like, you know
Look at the services that we offer that actually can make the experience for your customers better. I love you poppy
So while we're talking about hardware, I wanted to mention the yoga 3 that we ended up picking up
Which we'll tell you more about here in a little bit why we just picked this up and I'm gonna hold it up
To the camera
So Noah right now is installing on the yoga 3 and
What's been your first impression Noah out-of-the-box compatibility with ThinkPad?
Yeah, I mean so why but why are we doing a USB thing?
Well, so okay that so that's just the wireless needs to get the updated drivers before it will work
Which I need the internet that that wireless card is really finicky
It it it the laptop is incredibly well built as you would expect from Lenovo and in true Lenovo fashion
To get it to boot
Instead of having to do some stupid goofy shutting UEFI off and all that other crap. There's a little button. You push a little button and
Now you're booting USB
And it disables security
Disables the UEFI you can do regular BIOS boot the whole nine yards
Yeah, but yeah, the only thing is the before I
Understand from from the from the Google that once the operating system is installed
All the updates are done. We'll have
Drivers support for Wi-Fi and Bluetooth right now that doesn't seem to be the case
So what we have is we have a wired Ethernet adapter
The problem is the wired Ethernet adapter keeps coming unplugged and then my down my down
No, you know, so thanks, but it's it's really finicky and or the cables finicky. I don't know but so
1080p screen version. Yeah, and
Having seen this compared to your 4k XPS. It's still really good way
Yeah, yeah, and then you don't have to worry about all the weird high DPI stuff. Frankly. I'd prefer this
Yeah, I mean I'm being honest. I well I after I saw this like gosh. I kind of want to give Angie the XPS
But so we're gonna tell you why we're doing the yoga over the MacBook later on in the show
But so right now if somebody was just coming to you and say no
I'm at Best Buy and I want to pick up a machine that can run Linux and I know they sell the yoga 3 at
Best Buy would you say go ahead and pick this? Yeah. Yeah, you know the Wi-Fi is not working. Yeah
Yeah, I would like to
I was gonna say I'd like you to ask me that question again in 20 minutes, but okay, but you work on it during the
Show I will and then it will
We'll see if you get the Wi-Fi going now if that is so that's assuming we don't knock off the the adapter now
Also now if all goes well, you'll see Angela rocking her new yoga 3 at Linux fest Northwest April 25th and 26th
That's this weekend. If you can't be there in person
We'll be streaming it live Saturday on Sunday JB live TV and we'd love to have you tune in to hang out in the chat room
We'll be taking questions when we have guests from the chat room and it should be a pretty good pretty fun experience
It's been fun the last couple of years at least. Are you excited? I am I'm super excited. Yeah, Matt. Are you excited?
Oh, definitely. I've been looking forward to it all year now Matt
I if there were say going to be cake at the booth
Would you I mean would you have like even a bite? I?
Can't I'm literally alright. I actually have cake here. Yeah, I'm not saying there's gonna be cake. Don't assume there's gonna be
No guys, but Matt what we'll do is we'll arrange it so if there was gonna be cake
You're as far away from as possible
So you're not tempted because all as I'm saying that there was gonna be cake
It's gonna be delicious cake if there was gonna be cake
We'll make sure that we'll put you as far away from this delicious cake as possible
And if you know what we'll do is maybe people just show up at the booth
They can eat all the cake for you if there was gonna be cake work, but the cakes probably a lot Linux fest
Northwest is gonna be awesome
We'll be doing a party on Saturday evening you can go to meetup.com slash Jupiter
Broadcasting and we'll have final details in the Linux fest Northwest event as that approaches, and I'm really excited
I'm it's all in now. Who are you picking up tonight? You're where are you going after this?
I don't know I have to I'll have to look up. It's I think Ellen is is tonight
There's people coming in all all hours of the day all different days of the week
So it's gonna be an ongoing process, but that's just another service. We provide you're a trooper Noah. You're a real trooper
I think you're a you're a what do they call it? What is it? What's like the guy that does like the?
I think they call you a
Gopher no
Come on come on come on
Alright, so let me tell you about our buddies over at Linux Academy cuz they just had a freaking great great week since we got
Together last year on the Linux unplugged show our Linux Academy had their big live special on the 16th
And man you guys it's like a serious serious thing and so I've got a little summary for you
But I encourage you to go over to Linux Academy comm right now in fact go to Linux Academy comm slash unplug that we get
our 33% unplugged discount and
You're gonna be impressed by this so if you don't know about Linux Academy
They've been a sponsor for a little while
They are a resource for you to go learn really some of the best technology in Linux and open source
It's built by people that are truly enthusiastic about this stuff, so they really close that 10% gap
It's not a site that does like Photoshop tutorials camera tutorials after effects tutorials broken sync tutorials
And an Apache server tutorial they only focus on the Linux in the open source stuff because that's what they eat and breathe
They got together with their buddies that are educators and developers, and they created the Linux Academy platform
There's seven plus Linux distributions
They get to choose from that automatically adjust the courseware to match that distribution and also make sure that the virtual machines match the courseware
So if you choose an Ubuntu box for the courseware then the virtual machine is a buntu box once you spin up that virtual
Box you get a public IP address to you get to SSH up to that bad boys you get to work from your desk
Maybe load up mosh or something like that so that way it's real responsive. That's how I prefer to work
My lesson in my guake terminal. It's outrageous. They have scenario based labs that way you really get hands-on with the technology
So you really know what you're doing they have everything from Linux essentials up to open stack Docker virtualization
But after the 16th it just they just blew it off the door
It's just like the door came in and smacked me in the face is like oh my gosh
I had to print it out look at this right here
I got yeah two pages and how small is that type yeah? Yeah, that's wow that's ridiculous. Yeah, I know right. That's crazy
That's how much stuff
They did so I'm just gonna read through a couple these things cuz like I'm just gonna be reading off this for a little while
It's it's it's amazing so a couple of things. It's what are you guys gonna? Love the most they have new types of in-depth courses
They're totally nuts
You'll really seriously get in depth with that technology, so you're really gonna understand it
But they are also like hey, you know what sometimes. There's just like small nuggets of stuff. You need to learn
It's not really attached to any specific courseware, so they have nuggets now
So when you have downtime you just want to jump in and learn something new. It's a really cool
It's a single how-to that allows you to walk through specific tasks. They're not really course related
I like about two to sixty minutes long depending on which one it is. It's brand new something. They just introduced also
I love love love this
I'll tell you about all the other things they've done
But I think you guys are gonna think this is pretty enough pretty neat they're announcing the Linux Academy Foundation open source grant program
They're gonna give a $5,000 grant to an open source program, which is pretty amazing pretty awesome
So they are they are truly their community members. They haven't back any open source license project can apply for this grant
They have an external page up shortly, so we'll tell you more about it when I learn more about it
They Linux Academy
This is this is the guy who this is an email I sent me so they believe in supporting open source and ensuring great projects have
A lasting future in the community in order to celebrate and support open source. This is the email
He sent to me. This is not even an ad bitch
This is what I wrote me in order to support open source the Linux Academy Foundation will be opening the applications for open source projects
To receive either part or all of the $5,000 grant we believe in bettering the community
And we are excited to have the help of the founders Club members
I'll tell you more about the founders Club members soon and vote on which projects will receive the grant
So you can become a member of the founders Club at Linux Academy and you can get a say in which projects will receive the grant
I think that's awesome Linux Academy comm slash unplugged to get our 33% discount and
Go up try it out. You get it applied it to all of the courseware there, and there's a ton of good stuff now Chris
That's only the stuff that they told you about right because here's the thing I was at dinner the other night
And we sat down and what did producer q5 sis ask he goes hey, I heard you talking about xyz Ruby
Yeah, Ruby. I I don't see that on their side. They got really they got Ruby courseware Python courseware
I know after Linux fest. I'm gonna have to dig into one of them
I just don't know which one of those things where you have they they offer so many different services and so many different courses
They can't even you won't be able to include all those in a sales pitch
You'd almost have to sign up for an account and try it for a month
Yeah, you know it's funny
That's funny
You say that because a lot of times like I kind of get like in a I get like in a zone of what I've been
Interested in and then I and I get out of my course when I realize oh wow yeah, that's right
They have like a ton of other stuff
I should mention from time to time because it's just it's one of those things where you until you go see it yourself
You don't really have an idea of the depth of courseware, and that's why I really like their model a lot
alright, so
Let's talk about Angela's switch to Linux and
Wow what a monstrous event this has been so we ended up deciding that Angela has a Macbook and
She really likes the Macbook, but she's willing to try Linux, so let's get Linux on her Macbook
But because her pictures and her data are so precious plus. We don't want to interrupt her workflow
We just set it up on a secondary Macbook which is actually a pretty good rig
It was a 2011 model pretty high-end 16 gigabytes of RAM 512 gigabyte Apple SSD
Dedicated ATI graphics with the extra memory added a high-resolution
Non-reflective screen core i7 processor, so this is a high-end Macbook Pro that had died. Yeah, it was dead
Yeah, it was dead and then Apple just recently said hey so those of you who have this GPU issue a couple of years
ago will replace it for free and so we took the Macbook into Apple store and we gave him the Macbook and Apple said
Your battery's dead. We can't test it. Well the guy did some magic
He hooked up to a supercharger, and he got the battery working, and he did a test
He said yeah your GPU failed so we went down there
We picked up the Macbook after they fixed it for free and he's like hey
I threw in a free battery for you, too
So they replaced the battery the logic board the GPU so now we essentially have a brand new Macbook that just has
2011 parts, but it's a new motherboard new GPU new battery, so we're like we'll use this as
Angela's laptop that way we don't even hurt her existing laptop
But we will prove the point that to her that she'll be able to use Linux on her Macbook and that was
The original sort of idea that we set off with about Friday night. Yeah, yeah well really we started out with that
Yeah, we started talking about it
You know early Friday
And then started putting these pieces into these pieces of the puzzle into action late Friday
And what we kept finding was there was tiny little robux
And you know how you write those off because as somebody who troubleshoots
I mean it wouldn't be any fun if it worked the first time yeah, so having a good time
It doesn't work, so we try something else. Yeah, I can try something else and we start we're pinging developers
And we're trying different we are literally talking to the developers of the distributions
We're trying and so and so it fast-forward 24 hours later. We have now reloaded the machine no less than three times
We now have three different and we've tried it like with OS 10 with no OS 10 with refine with no refine
But we wound up with three bootloaders
Refined refit and grub all three of which could get you could you could click on the right option you would get into this endless
Boot cycle where one would boot into the other would boot into the other boot into the other and eventually at some point
We decided this just this just isn't gonna work, so we decide we're going to bed. That's it. We quit
Yeah, we go to bed. I go to take a shower. I get back up and Rekai's like no man. We're gonna get this to work
Yeah, I'm like halfway through planning an alternative episode. Yeah, I'm like we're never gonna make it what time in the morning
Is this what this is about 7 a.m.. 7 a.m.. And the Linux action should goes live at 10. Yeah
Yeah, so so we have like three hours mind you it took us two hours the first time to copy all of our data
Yeah, we got pretty good at that because like we're figuring out exactly you know that's way to get that done
Man, I can change permissions from HFS back to to ext4 like you wouldn't believe yeah, right
Yeah, so so so we're getting this that we're in the stuff that and the frustrating thing apart part about it is the computer
That we're working on is actually really decent hardware
Yeah, I I don't think there's anyone
Involved in JB that hates Apple as much as I do and I have to admit
That's a nice machine every time we look at it. Yeah, we look at it. We're like
Yeah, and when we could get things to work they work they actually work pretty well
But it's when you have a new Linux user and I have dealt with this numerous times. It has to work the first time
Yeah, you don't have right
We have all these little nuances from the production standpoint that like other people like maybe we just write off like we have to have
HDMI mirroring because we have to show the audience Angela's computer exactly so if we don't get aged up
So then that sends us down the path of okay
That means we now have to get the ATI dedicated graphics working and then this sends us down to all these different modes
We have to pass the grub menu or we have to put in grub in grub configs that way or type it in at the grub
Menu at boot so that way the ATI car gets activated over the Intel card all these little you can only boot in UEFI
We can't use the BIOS part and it's like if you know what I was thinking to myself this time
It's like man, you know if this was my rig, I would totally be willing to tinker with this stuff
Mm-hmm, but this is like I don't want to blow this. I really really really don't want to opportunity
It seriously is I've said it before but like there a crack has opened in the Apple ecosystem for us to take advantage for her
And her workflow and in my entire relationship with her. I've been with her for 17 years
I have never had an advantage like this and I'm like
This is our moment two advantages because the other thing was when she sat down and saw
Antrigos for the first time that blew her away. She liked it. And then it was a double punch
She got hit with triple punch. She got hit with an awesome hardware awesome software
And then the chat room did a bang-up job of saying hey, hey, that's cool that she's using hardcore Linux
Yeah, and she got into that. Yeah, she's like, hey, they think I'm there. Yeah, they're really proud of me
I'm using real Linux and yeah now now anything else like a bunch of elementary OS is is kind of out of the
Picture we have to do and Tegra so we have to do it, right?
So we were starting to think you know, the problem is is a there are a few things that are finicky
Like we're still having a problems with dual display
Which is a critical part of her workflow for like spreadsheet stuff that she's working on
We're still having issues with the dedicated graphics. We can get Intel graphics working, but we're right now
I'm not sure we're at with the ATI graphics and so no one I've been going back and forth like we really really really don't
Want to mess this up and we don't want her to have any troubles with this and if she ever does have troubles
We want to be able to bounce back immediately
So that way we don't want her to think boy something ever goes wrong
I'm out for a couple of days then she's gonna be petrified the entire time
I know how she works that'll scare the crap out of scare the crap out of me
So we decided to sort of preemptively grab this yoga 3 laptop
Hoping that it might work out as a little bit more of a stable machine
But still meet those sort of build requirements that she has the expectation she has from her MacBook
And and have the keyboard and all that that she expects from her MacBook and though and the weight and portability in fact this thing
Is thinner than the new Mac just a MacBook that they keep touting and it was funny because Lenovo actually sent out a tweet
That said oh, yeah, and then they gave the actual dimensions are like real cool Apple
That was so last year
This is also one of the number one recommended laptops from our audience now
The thing is is right now. We are not in a position to do this especially with Linux fest coming here
We're totally not in a position to do this
Well, we are out of funds before Linux fest started so what we're thinking of doing and it's up
Do you guys are welcome to have a first crack at it?
We're gonna put Angela's Ted the MacBook we've been talking about up on eBay and see if people want it now
Because we have it here in studio
You can have it however you like if you'd like to have it with just OS 10
We can load it that way if you'd like to have it with OS 10 and arch or anti gross
We can do it that way if you'd like arch only we can also do that and
Ship it to you that way right straight from the jb1 studio now
It's gonna get better Chris because we're not we're actually offering it at a lower price
So we had a price point in our head and we started a little bit lower for the mumble
So if you're in the mumble room, then you get kind of first crack at a slightly reduced cost
Yeah before we're gonna crank it back
Yeah, the price of that of the 512 drive when that was new alone was $1,000 in that laptop Wow. Yeah, man
We've come a long way. Yeah
Yeah, I really have and so the in the picture here. You're seeing if you're watching the video version. That's the Macbook. They're running
anti-gross with gnome 3 and
the gnome to shell dock extension there at the bottom and
That's there in the other room and it it it's a good machine
Like if we had the money I would just keep this as another production machine when you keep looking over it and you go man
Mm-hmm. Yeah, it's a nice-looking machine
It really was like it was a really all-out like our main like workhorse editing machine when the GPU died
And then like once the GPU died
It just sat on the shelf and never got used and then Apple just refurbished it basically for us
I would I could put it to work if I had the funds. Yeah, but I you know
We need to recoup the cost of this. Yeah, we just right now especially there's no money
There's no slush there and if we're gonna really be serious and want her to stick with something for a long time
Angela is a savvy enough user that she wants to feel that it's a quality product
She really needs to feel like this is you know, like she likes the build of the MacBook
I think this is gonna do that. Absolutely. It's in fact, there are a lot of things
I like it actually better about the MacBook one
It's not a MacBook and two doesn't have an Apple logo on it and three
It's a little bit thinner a little bit more portable. I think
Than the MacBook and I've had experience now that said though
Yeah, I mean what we're gonna put this in the show notes and it's in the chat room right now
I I am not an advocate of Linux on a MacBook as your primary unless you're okay with some tinkering
Yeah, what we were what we were kind of coming to is set it up and then DD the machine
Yeah, and that could that could certainly work too. Yep, but if you're a geek
I don't think this is necessarily gonna be a problem for you
If you are if you are if you are somebody that wants to set this up for somebody else and you want them to kind of
Run with it independently. That's where we have some real concerns
It's it's a 2011
and so it sort of sits in that spot where
Like enter gross you get it going pretty easily and then it takes about 15 20 minutes of tweaks and then if you really want
to dial it in it's about a little bit more than that once you get the graphics and all that so it's it's an interesting device and
It's available there and we'll let you know at Linux fest how it all turns out
We did decide to go with anti gross again on the yoga wimpy was asking. What do you think wimpy? Are we crazy?
Yes, I've made a catastrophic error of judgment
Well, I've I've made this mistake with my wife I installed Arch Linux on my wife
computer with gnome 3 and
The only way I could keep her on a Linux based operating system was to make my own damn
Distribution so you've no idea the heartache and effort you're gonna be
Here's what I'm working off of wimpy and tell me tell me where I felt tell me where this logic falls apart
So I would be right there with you if it was up to me and I was picking a Linux distribution for a new user
It would be stock Ubuntu and I would keep it as stock as I possibly could
However, there are three big factors to consider one
Angela really likes gnome and she was not only blown away by gnome, but she was impressed
She's used to using gnome on Chris's laptop add to that
She has tried Ubuntu in the past and it and and that that was turned down
So we're working with that second of all and this is a big thing if it's in my house
I want to be familiar with it because I know who has to ultimately answer for those for those problems
And so if we leave here with Angela running Ubuntu or elementary or any of those other
Distributions when she has problems and then Chris has to come home and she goes hey, honey
In addition to the lot in this and this can you fix this and then he sits down and goes man
I just followed this problem on arch. I have no idea how to do it on XYZ. So there's that aspect to consider
so
Here's the thing. So I I went through I went through a period where I had all of my immediate family
That were running Linux running arch Linux and you know, I am an arch Linux to you
I'm heavily invested in the arch Linux community, right, but it did not go well
This is not an operating system you install on your immediate family's computer
Yeah are not Linux savvy because what do you do about updates? You're responsible for doing those updates now, but is that about you it?
Is that he maintains control over when those updates?
Chris are you busy? I am I am but I see my logic is I have I have like three or four other machines
I would do updates on before I do hers. So she should be the last machine. I have I had I had the exact same logic
This just doesn't work you're just not gonna get around to that machine and what happens is months go by and then you think damn it
I really need to do the updates and then you've got all of those configuration conflicts to deal with and suddenly
what should be a simple task is a mess that you need to un-pickle and you don't have time to deal with it and
There's a slight thing that you haven't paid attention to there is Rekai
Well, okay, that's he has nothing to do
But what I think who is it in the chat room is is is saying the same thing that I'm thinking kz6
Fiddy sent
Um
Ubuntu gnome
Angela is not Chris. Angela doesn't know what the what she's missing by running
314 versus Ubuntu gnome
360 Chris you might appreciate those differences
But Angela won't and if you went with that with all of the automatic
You know update utilities that that's got built into it. You can just let her
accept the update prompts and hit you know apply now we start my computer I mean
That makes the most sense to me for up to ten machines by far use landscape and you could remotely
My wife I would say
I don't know. I mean, I don't want to I don't want to totally discredit Angela's ability your wife runs arch
She does and she installed it herself and she knows probably less about is that can I say that on air?
Am I gonna get in trouble? Hold on think yeah
She I think she knows less about Linux and technology than Angela does and she was able to follow the wiki and figure it out
I don't a I mean, I don't know. I I'm always for
What man what RIP? No, everyone's saying RIP. No, no, it's it's one of those things where I
I organically I agree that that stock a bunch who is usually gonna be better for users
but in this particular case having seen Angela's immediate reaction and
having seen
How how she how she reacts to when she's using Chris's computer
I think in this particular case since everyone is kind of in that arch mode and you know
You know who does this Linus Torvalds himself does this he uses Fedora
And so he makes sure that all of his other computers in his house are using Fedora and he specifically said that's because he doesn't
Like to run multiple distributions in his house. Yeah
That's even why I put it on my server
I can totally get behind that
See, but I feel like all you guys are saying don't run don't run this for your wife's computer
We're also the same guys that tell me don't run it on my server
Yeah, no, no, that's not me at all. I'm just the guy that says yeah, I mean you are but you're scaring me the most
Nine months in it's easier to maintain a whole distribution than look after one
Of its information on your wife's computer. Yeah
I'd have to agree with you this time wimpy because you know
There is a lot of kernel tweaks that go into the Ubuntu kernel which kind of help a little bit of the hardware
So but here's where I get to if I'm gonna go with an Ubuntu base
Then I start getting pulled towards elementary and I love Matei, but I start thinking well
Then I should give her something that'll really give her a you know
Sort of a sex appeal that sort of she's used to you was you were saying that Angela likes the gnome desktop
So why don't you go with that been to canine? Yeah, we were talking about all the advantages of PPAs earlier on in the show
What could it kind of come down to either elementary OS or Ubuntu Matei 1504 well, let's be clear
It wasn't so much gnome specifically that drew her to it
It was the fact that she was using the same hardcore Linux that you were using when you install a bunch
You know that then that changes. Well, yeah, it's not the same thing
Mm-hmm. So I wonder if the appeal for her is gonna change and that brings us back to elementary. I
Guess if you I'm sorry good
Oh, I was gonna say I guess if you mirror and like if you have if you keep frequent mirrors of everything to where she's done
It's like everything's it goes to crap. You just push a button it all reverts back to what it was five minutes ago
It's fine. Whatever. I mean if you if you have a push button solution for it, it makes sense
But I don't I just don't
Advantage of I just don't get I think you're right. I think what we do is we let Angela pick
Do you want arch or you want to bat a 1504 and here when here's the other thing?
the nice thing about this over over the old silver sliver is
With this when she changes her mind, it's a matter of plugging in a different USB drive and restart
Yeah, you know, it's no longer a weekend project. Yeah. All right
So we'll we'll we'll make her a pitch and we'll let her make the choice
And see what she thinks is best
I wouldn't be surprised if she goes with arch and then we'll load the yoga either way she chooses
Well, and make sure you're using a laser pointer and PowerPoint slides because that really will help get your point across
Yeah
A lot of users don't ever realize or notice the underlying operating system very much. It's always the desktop experience. Mm-hmm. Yep
Always I agree. I agree
I just want to make sure it's one that she'll like
And I think we'll find it and we'll let you guys know and so that the bay auction is up now and don't worry
It's going so fast because I'm not I don't think we've had it. We had zero bids. It's your bids
Yeah, no, that's that's kind of won't stay that way for long
No, you think and as someone at eBay is frequently it watch for the snipers. So you'll see I said the same thing
Well, I'll tell you about another great deal
How about our friends over at ting go to linux.ting.com that'll get $25 off your first device or
$25 of credit if you have a ting compatible device and you probably do plus it supports this show
Things got a GSM and CD main network coverage
So when I say you probably have a device that works you probably do there's a lot of them ting is mobile that makes sense
Ting's my mobile service provider ting's Matt's mobile service provider ting is Noah's mobile service provider
We all use ting and we all love it ting
Not do you have you both phones with you right now just the way I have one it's in the car
Yeah, the other ones in the car. Yeah, you know why cuz it's so small. I forget it everywhere
Well, and it's why not?
I mean, it's yeah, you said Noah got one of those nine dollar GSM car a SIM cards from ting
And then he just pays for what he used
He just takes your minutes and messages megabytes and they add them all up whatever bucket he falls into that's what he pays
It's a flat six dollars for the line so we can have an emergency phone with a nine dollar SIM
Sitting in this car that has two weeks of battery life and he's just paying for what he uses which is not very much
That's why Jupiter broadcasting is able to have three lines because I don't have a lot of money
But I ting well
We just pay for what we use and we make a ton of Wi-Fi calls and they have some great devices on ting
I'd like to recommend the Moto G if you're looking for a value device
Ninety one dollars unlocked modern version of Android you own it six dollars for the line. No contract
That's pretty sweet. Yeah. Now. It does get a little more crazy after that
Ting has just started directly selling the one plus one. I think that's pretty awesome
Yeah, you can now buy the ting want you from ting you can get the one plus
Unlocked get it on ting. It's yours. You own it. What a great device. What a great device for a ting network
What a perfect device for the ting network and then also if you're like me and you've been looking at that Moto X to
Second-gen ting is now selling that directly as well unlocked you own it
That's your rig
Go take it on the ting network or if you have a GSM or CDMA device that works with them
You get $25 a service card that might pay for more than your first month. It did for mine
Yeah a smartphone for under $25 a month. It is actually possible
Linux dot ting comm they got no hold customer service a fantastic dashboard and I really really love the way they do business
Check them out Linux that ting comm and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring the Linux unplugged
I said did you see this story about the John Deere tractors or stuff and the software and I got it
I'll just recap this for all of you who may be not following the story
It's it sort of lit up in our subreddit today
But the headline from wired reads we can't let John Deere destroy the very idea of ownership
That's pretty bold. Yeah
In a particular spectacular display of corporate delusion John Deere the world's largest architectural machinery maker told the copyright office
That farmers don't own their tractors because the computer code
Snakes through the DNA of modern tractors farmers receive what they are farmers receive an implied
License for the life of the vehicle to operate the vehicle. In other words, it's John Deere's tractor
You're just driving it several manufacturers recently submitted similar comments to the Copyright Office under an inquiry into the digital Millennium
Copyright Act
Carrie Adams a farmer hasn't been able to fix an expensive
Transplanter because he doesn't have access to the diagnostic software. He needs he isn't alone
Many farmers are opting for older computer free equipment because of this very problem
Some companies have even leveraged the DMCA to stop owners from modifying programming on those products
So you might be wondering what does copyright have to do with modifying a tractor
Well owners can tinker, you know, and you have homebrew hackers
They have to copy programming in order to modify it in the first place product makers don't like people messing with their stuff
So some manufacturers place DRM when you break the DRM and make a copy
You are essentially violating copyright law and that's how manufacturers can turn tinkerers into pirates
And even if said pirates aren't circulating illegal copies of anything
John Deere the company argues that allowing people to alter the software even for purposes of repair
Would make it possible for pirates and third-party developers and less innovative competitors to free ride off the creativity
and unique expression and ingenuity of the vehicle software and
the piece of resistance as they say piece of the resistance or sauce sauce
in John Deere's argument
Permitting owners to root around in the tractors programming might lead to pirating music through the vehicle's entertainment system
Oh, they're really reaching here. Okay, so there's a few things wrong with this entire
First of all, if someone's gonna actually decide to you know, break the DRM
They're gonna find a way to do it second of all if they're doing it for themselves because they've purchased the equipment
Congratulations, they're already a customer. Let's not piss them off and third of all pirating music. I mean the whole thing
Pirating music. I mean the whole thing. Mm-hmm. They're just completely reaching for it
I mean I watched a thing or a documentary yesterday showing how you can take most cars made out and trucks made after
1996 flash the software and wait for it run alternative fuels right now. No additional hardware
So, you know, but and but because you can't it's illegal to change that software same same basic thing. This is not a new problem
It's just now coming to light
Yeah value of this is negative. So you're saying Matt that people are not buying $25,000 tractors to pirate music and I
Know I just I look at this at a situation
It's obvious what they're trying to do is just lock things down and use copyright to do it
But it's a pretty scary thing when everything has software in it and it's not just so we're picking on John Deere
General Motors told the Copyright Office the proponents of copyright reform
Mistakenly conflate ownership of a vehicle with ownership of the underlying computer software in the vehicle ie the car you own
General in General Motors opinion you do not own the computer or the computer software in that car
But of course you need to drive the car, right? Yeah
Convenient, right? I got to be honest as a Linux user
This really kind of pisses me off. Mm-hmm
That should scare you it should scare you that it's culturally acceptable that we can sell a device that you that
the
Concept even 10 15 years ago of buying a computer that you didn't have administrative access to would be ridiculous
And yet we allow this now consistently with smartphones with smartphones apparently with tractors apparently with cars. We just don't think about it
It's not good. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, you do to make them if this is the true what how where what's their liability with errors in that software that lead
To loss of life. I do wonder about that other automate automakers have pointed out the owners who make unsanctioned modifications
Who I like that one could alter their vehicles in bad ways
They could tweak them to go faster or change no parameters to run a foul
You know like APR tuning I could tune my engine to run faster, too
Mm-hmm
Give me a break or I could just apply more pressure to that pedal on the right and I could also go faster without
Altering the software again the arguments idiotic. It's pretty weak, isn't it?
It's just terrible GM says that locking people out helps innovation this week though. There is some good news
Senator Ron widened and a janitor Jared polis
I think is the last name will introduce the breaking down barriers innovation act of 2015 which might help improve the DMCA process
We'll see although the fair repair legislation also has some
Work to do. Well, we'll see where that goes. What are we gonna say right now?
I'm sorry didn't there was a Toyota had a problem with their their gas pedal got stuck
Yeah, and it was a software issue that they had that you had to go to their dealership to get it to fix it
If it wasn't, you know proprietary you could actually fix it yourself
Toyota moving you forward whether you want to or not this this kind of stuff is
Particular spooky for those of us who are really hyper aware of how important software is to pretty much everything we get involved with now
everything we use and
It does kind of like you think RMS was right in a way. Mm-hmm
I guess it's kind of what he's been saying all along right and just saying yeah
I think and unfortunately for honor the unfortunate thing for RMS is I think it's wasted effort
Perhaps has been wasted effort because here we are anyways
so what worries me about this is not just the big devices like
Tractors that are used by farmers, but also the little devices like light bulbs, you know
The fact you have to firmware update your light bulbs or firmware update your fridge or something
And they can choose if you've if you've hacked it in some way they can choose not to let that work
And so you're left in darkness or you're left with rotting food in your fridge because they've chosen not to allow you to
Fiddle with the stuff and yeah, I agree with you. I think RMS was right in some ways with these things
Wow, or even expanding on that imagine if they thought that you adjusted it or they thought that you made an adjustment when in reality
You didn't actually do anything
But because you've been labeled as such we get the same result that was just pointed out to us. Mm-hmm
That's scary dare Devlin you wanted to make comment on the sad consequences of the logic
Yeah
I think it's even worse because if you lock down and if they successfully keep locking down to in this path
What eventually will come down to only certify developers on blah blah blah, which already happens in certain fields
Yes, but it's going to expand to all of the fields like I know you have these like you have for doctors for software
Because it will be everywhere and you will have blah blah blah
Specification or certification and a lot of the innovation will be just stagnating
I mean ultimately that's what the locking down leads to hmm
If you to have access to the car you have to pass blah blah blah specification, right?
Then I mean just gonna study for that particular. You're right. That is sort of the inevitable conclusion of this logic
That's a great point. I hadn't thought of
WWI wanted to give you a chance to jump in on how you see this kind of happening with digital media today
It's already happening. I mean the WikiLeaks stuff that just came out from the Sony hack that right everybody
That's in this IRC and in mumble who watches text that
Knows that you know Sony had that big half and now we're seeing the
Consequences of that and what these companies are really doing behind your back
You have the evidence that anybody can go to WikiLeaks and just look it up and you can see the interaction
Between these different companies on digital media and they want to control the content
They want to control what you see on any US website now
So where's it gonna end if people should be literally up in arms about this and they're not and that's what I think it's now
You know what they're doing and I it's of course only benefits me, but I think they're just going somewhere else
I think they're going to alternative media
I think they're going to podcasts are going to internet media and those of us that become more aware of it
we seek out independent entertainment and
I think they are going to be the catalyst of their own downfall because people will realize
Brian Williams is just the tip of the iceberg my friends
Yeah, and you can jump on you know, it's funny too when I get when I pick up a new passion your new hobby
One of the first things I'll do is I'll jump on YouTube and I'll take a look and see what other people have channels and that
They're talking about it. It's kind of fun, right? Yeah, you don't go on TV anymore for that kind of stuff. No, no
Yeah, so maybe it's actually all for the good in the long run
we'll see but it is pretty it is pretty it's pretty frustrating to watch this kind of stuff happen and I would love to see
Ron Wyden's successful with the breaking down barriers to innovation act and you of course
I will have information in the show notes and the link to wired the link
I have to wired has links where you can contact the Copyright Office and
The the URL to do that is specific for the DMC. It's dmca.digitalrights
digitalrightrepair.org dmca.digitalrightrepair.org and they have a way for you to contact people and
Representatives I'll put a link to that in the chat room, too
If you guys want to get involved with that, so maybe that can help maybe we can make a difference. Maybe good old Ron Wyden. Hmm
Yeah, you know, I'm probably one of those guys
It's gonna stand there on the top of my hood with both my middle fingers out going I'm doing it bite me
Because that's more how I'll be there with you. I'll bring the hot dogs. Okay, you know
The legal defense on them. Yeah, you bring the hot dogs now Matt'll bring something gluten-free you bring the beer and that'll be our protest
Actually, that sounds a little bit like Friday night, Matt
I don't know if I don't know if you have any plans Friday, but after we get set up at Ballyham and Linux for Linux Fest
We're gonna take the crew out to dinner. I'd love to have you join us all I'll contact you later in the week
I'll talk to you tomorrow about that. I'll see you
Tell you all about about our cool plans on the weekend
And so for those of you out in the audience, we want you to join us JB live TV Saturday and Sunday
Or come say hi at Linux Fest Northwest. It's gonna be really good to be good to see how you guys there
Anything else need to cover before we get out of here?
Somebody buy that MacBook. Yeah, I do that
That'll help us out a lot also Linux actually show that reddit to come to make this show even better Jupiter broadcasting comm slash
Contact and Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar for updates. See you next week everybody
I
Think wouldn't be talking me to 1504. I will get this. Oh, really. I've maybe I don't know. I'm gonna be so much easier
I'm gonna call it that
Think it'd be easier really. Oh, yeah
Live installer thing and then all the guys at ease
But here's a sign of a broadcasting professional when you hear the outro coming up and you're like I will get everything
I'm about to say up before the music
So it sounds like it
Your voice elevates right
Right there I could do it's like I'm doing an auction. Yeah. All right
I'm using 1504. No free at the moment and it's awesome
It's wonderful
Really really really really fast really reliable. I haven't had one single problem on it
I've got a 4 gig laptop with Intel onboard graphics card
Nothing special and it just runs it perfectly. What's the support? Is it nine months for 1504?
Yes
Everything
What do you dislike
Stable nonsense no nonsense LTS Chris really
Yeah
So so
Chris so boring you guys the Ubuntu gnome team maintain their own
PPAs with the updated version of the desktop in there so you can install the LTS
you can add the PPAs for the desktop and the other applications that are important to you and you can just maintain a
semi rolling applications on top of a standard base
Try when I said to you are you busy Chris the the the extension of that question is
When are you?
When do you have free time? I know they Angela's computer when she is not using it. All right
You don't you use landscape
You on your machine you log into landscape and you press a button that says update all my computers and it just does it and
You don't worry. Yeah
Definitely what we're talking about here is potentially Chris having one Ubuntu machine on home network
Yeah, not not ten Ubuntu machines on the home. All right. Well, so now I'm wondering
To my add it to my account and I'll update
So is it really better to go Ubuntu 1404 with gnome 3 PPAs or Matei
1404 what do you think she'd like better?
probably
Okay, yeah, it's what she was why don't you ask her and would you try them both and see if I
That's where everyone with that Mac like interface so you can share with that
That's where everyone kind of falls off because we this has to get done like by the end of today so that she can try it
So they're gonna get back on. Yeah. Yeah, we're swapping her out like this
We want to get her back because you realize every day that we every day that we she doesn't have her new computer is one
More day that we have to go collect all the data off of her her existing computer. I'll move it all over
There is no doing this twice. We need to get it right the first time
Three times ago, right? Well, we're we're stopping to redo it, right?
We just don't want to go this arch kind of screwed up your plans doesn't mean you
That is arch have anything to do with the plans
In fact, if anything arch has been the easiest distribution out of all of them to get running on there
We couldn't get a bunch of we couldn't get a bunch of the boot
We couldn't get what else do we try and then no, it's not like it's some arch maniac
No, in fact, I really dislike arch in this particular case. He's right. It's the only one that even booted on the system much less
Let's look at this. Okay, so we've established that arch is working a boon to at some level wasn't really working out
Previous at all at all. So
Even though I'm not an arch guy anymore necessarily that kind of gravitates us just just sticking what's what's working
I think well, but now run but now it doesn't matter cuz now we're on the yoga, you know, so now well, okay
So now we could oh, you know, I see what you're saying. I see you say, okay
So the based on that stick with gnome a boon to gnome done, you know
She's already grown to like the desktop environment make keep it simple
You know, you're rarely I rarely ever recommend you bugged you but here I am doing it
I feel like I feel like we recommend a boon to because we're all scared
I feel like we do it because we're scared of we are scared of rolling
Software it's a practical. It is a practical scared thing because it's bitten me enough times
No, I just hate giving in so let's say you have you have arch like it's just a flood of perfectly flawless updates
I'm saying that without laughing and or you have a book because I've broken shit so many times or you have a boon to
Which you know can still have issues obviously, you know, I'm both both options can roll back their packages just fine easy enough
No big deal. Yeah, but I have less
Wonderful updates of one than I do the other I guess for her
I get
Yeah, all right. All right, JB titles.com. Let's get this thing banged out
Yeah, so I mean it's so from owner. What's that? I
Said five minutes. I got a puppy on there. That's all you guys
Oh
Dear RMS was right. It's not bad. That's excellent. Actually Chris. Does she not like unity at all?
No, she does not know
But once you depart from Ubuntu, I almost say it at the risk you get my head bit of I almost say elementary
You know guys, he doesn't like unity because he has choice
Elementary has a lot of USB stick. Yeah
Issues I've had a lot of issues
A lot of issues with their
I agree, but it's not an issue in elementary. I think the US is a little bit too far removed from the parent project
Well to be honest, I mean I would be I would probably be more willing to go with it, but it's in beta fray is
Yeah, that's true. So
I thought fray I thought was a bit like the release. No final version
Well, if you ignore the three thousand seven hundred bucks in launchpad, it's it's final release, okay
Care about making a desktop really
All the applications that Angela probably need isn't part of elementary's vision
So they don't care about anything else other than their Pantheon and no blessed application
Well, no, she needs the web browser. She needs photo and she needs mail and they do all that
But yeah, yeah. Well, all right
I think right now
Someone rely on that I think either way I think either way we go it's gonna be okay. So I'm not
About it go safe go safe with a bun with a bun too long lean initially
And then if you want to go to watch or something that once she she's been on it a little bit longer and got used
To it then then go for it then
Here's the end of the thing is like let me paint you a picture. You've got two three week circumstances three weeks from now
You're like, oh crap. I haven't updated that for a while. Which distro do you want to be faced with what doing that?
So I'll let you guys know which way we go
I will we'll get the installation going here in a few minutes now once we get off air and we'll update you guys soon
Have a great week, and I'll see you tomorrow minute. All right. I'll see you then. All right, buddy