Okay Wes, I'm almost there. This will be the last machine, and then they're all
gonna be Ubuntu. Are you ready? Oh yeah! What? Uh-oh. Oh no.
We better ask Noah. This is Linux Unplugged episode 223 for November 14, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux sole injection. Now featuring a
hundred percent more of Chris, Rekai, Wes, myself, and of course the Mumble Room. This
hour we're going to take your phone calls, 1-855-450-6624, and welcome
everyone. Welcome Chris, welcome Wes. I'm welcoming you guys to your own show. I'm
kind of the guest, right? No, you're here Noah, and you're saving the day for us.
It's a Fedora 27 Extravagant. Blowout! And you know what? It's funny, as a
Fedora guy, I'm the only person as one of the hosts that's not actually running
Fedora 27. So how pathetic is that? Noah, to make it up for you, all three of us are
running 27 right now in the studio. How many people in the Mumble Room, hello
Mumble Room, how many of you are running Fedora 27? Yep. Oh my gosh. Long day.
Every day, all day, of course. Well I think this is going to be a super fun
show. I don't, I think we've only done one other episode of Linux Unplugged where
we've had a bunch of us all in the studio because sometimes it's not even,
it's not even technically possible because there are only so many
microphones that we have when we're all together, right? And so this is, and if
I'm filling in, oftentimes you're out of town or you're traveling. So this is the
first time we've actually gotten together for this, you know, big Linux
party, so to speak. Yeah, it's pretty cool and we have a great turnout in the
Mumble Room this week, including, I'm very excited to say, we have a special guest
from the Fedora Project who will be chatting with us a little bit. Dan from
Elementary OS just had himself quite the interview and we'll talk to Dan a little
bit about that, but we also just have like a great showing, like Popey and
Wimpy pulled themselves away from Rust to be here with us guys. I'm very excited
about that. That's, that's great. And Kits and Kitty, I'm actually playing Rust whilst we're in the
Mumble Room, by the way. Yeah, we didn't pull ourselves away. Yeah, okay. I should have known. And Kits and Kitty's here.
I don't, I kept, Kits and Kitty, I can't remember how long it's been since you've
been here, but I'm, it may even been last week, but I'm excited. Either way, Noah,
it's gonna be a good show. I agree. So starting off, the first thing that
we're talking about today is Firefox Quantum. So tell me, you know, as a
Firefox user, you get to enlighten me because I don't know what Firefox
Quantum is. Oh geez. Oh, oh, it's, it's Quantum Day, Noah. It's not, it's not
just Firefox 57. Today is and shall ever be remembered as Quantum Day. And it's,
this is it. This is where Mozilla realized that they could bunch up a bunch
of features all at once and actually get everybody excited about their browser
for a chance, for a change, and really make a big splash. No, no, no, no. I'm not
being critical. What I'm saying is Mozilla really figured this shit out. Like,
okay, they have, they have staged a bunch of fundamental changes to the browser. A
new UI. They've switched back to Google for the default search. And the Quantum
part, the Quantum part refers to a brand new way of getting shit done in Firefox.
It's twice as fast as the previous version of Firefox. It has a new CSS
engine, supports multi-process architecture so you can prioritize for
different CPUs, different jobs. You can have properly sandboxed and isolated
tabs. And it is significantly faster for the same, essentially, yes, for
essentially the same memory footprint. It's, that's fantastic. It's the version
of Firefox we've all been waiting for since Chrome was released.
Well, so I, I don't know if I've been waiting. I don't know if I've been
necessarily waiting for that, but it is nice to see Firefox starting to step up
and compete on in some of the same ways that Chrome has been competitive because
you know, as a person and I've bound, you have to, but we've both bounced back and
forth between Chrome and Firefox. And for me, we kind of, we're opposite, right?
I primarily stick to Firefox and every once in a while I try that Chrome thing
out. In fact, I'm using Chrome today, but there are legitimately performance
things that I notice anytime I'm using Chrome that just don't exist in Firefox.
To me, it feels sturdier. It feels faster. It feels like the pages pop faster than
Chrome. Um, I don't have all of my extensions yet, which has always, has
always been my, sort of my, my problem, but I'm trying to just come up with
other ways to do that stuff. It's pretty, it's pretty nice, Noah.
Huh. Well, that is exciting. I, you know, I knew that today was national pickle
day. I did not know that today was national quantum day for Firefox. But
today I learned.
In the show notes, I put a link to a blog post at hacks.mozilla.org and they
talk about, um, everything. But the things that I like the most is they talk
about laying the foundation for what they call coarse grained parallelism. And,
um, it's, it feels like, uh, it feels like they, they looked at what Chrome's
doing and they went, shit, we really have a problem here. We've got to really
fundamentally fix this. And instead of pulling like a Microsoft approach where
they just sort of like back port fixes to windows and windows just keeps getting
a bigger and bigger beast that can do more stuff. They really did like a house
cleaning here. They went through and they broke some stuff and they reinvented
some stuff and they replaced some stuff and they redesigned the UI and they, and
then they, and then very clever, very clever for the Mozilla project. They,
they saved it all up for this big release, this big quantum release and they
gave it a name and of course that's from the quantum engine. They gave it, they
gave it this whole spin. It's been, we've been talking about it for months now and
it all landed and by doing so it gave them time to test and refine the
features. So they were ready for launch and it gave everyone a common target to
look at for Firefox. Yeah. And it gives you a night and day experience. If, as
long as you don't have any extensions that block the quantum engine, it really
gives you a night and day experience. And it uses, at least on my machines, it
uses less memory than Chrome. Okay. So here's, here's really the, here's really
the bottom line question. Who out there, and I'm kind of looking at you guys
mumble room, who out there is currently a Chrome user and is now as a result of,
of this news considering switching back to Firefox? That would be me. Okay, tell
me about it. Yeah. Tell me about it. Well, well, you know, if they claim to be faster,
I really want to look at it and see if they claim to be, if they claim to be
faster and they actually are, if they've got a new, they've got me switching back
after probably several years. Yeah. So what does, what does Firefox offer you
that you're, that you're willing to jump ship on, on a working platform? What does
Firefox offer you that's above and beyond? Why is it that if both are doing
the same thing, basically we're saying is Firefox has caught up. Why then are you
going to jump off Chrome to come back to Firefox? Well, one thing I've noticed is
that Chrome can get very laggy as it goes, because like if you have a ton of
open tabs, it will actually bog down your processor because it is actually
literally running each tab in a process. Chrome seems to be streamlining out into
like shared processes per tab. See, you know what I'm saying? So if it is, if it
truly is faster and more efficient on the memory, more efficient on the CPU,
then that gives me more power to do other things like video editing or audio
production, that kind of thing. Okay, that makes sense. Anyone else? I'm looking at
partly. Okay. Who was it that spoke up? One of our friends across the pond? I
think it's been me. Okay. Sort of a switching over from, I think when they
went Firefox 56, which was the recent speed up, I've sort of been about, from
Chrome going to about 5050 between Chrome and Firefox. Some of it is just
partly to half de-Googlify stuff and give support back to Firefox as a
competition against Google. Right, and that's my, that's my position on it too,
is a large reason that a large portion of the reason that I put up with some of
the things I put up with in Firefox is largely because I like the organization,
I like what they do, I like what they stand for, I like their principles, and I
want to support that. And I am willing to sacrifice a certain amount of features
and a certain amount of usability, I guess, is what it really amounts to. I
mean, that's the truth. I'm willing to sacrifice some of those things. You know
that means that's bad. They cannot, that cannot factor in at all in their
strategy. Not a single tiny itsy bit. If that's what they're relying on, then they're not
going to get adoption. I agree from a business standpoint, however, I think that
they have earned enough good, because there was a time before Chrome was ever
even a thing, where the Mozilla, where Firefox was my retreat away from
Internet Explorer, and they bought themselves so much, so much buy-in
capital with that from me personally, and as I continue, you know, there's so many
things that the Mozilla Corporation does, that all of their meetings are open
meetings. Anyone can attend a Mozilla meeting. I think they have a phone
number you can dial up, or they have an online web stream, and you can just
listen to what they're talking about, their line of thinking, how
they're thinking. I mean, they're a very transparent organization, as opposed to
Google, which is very much not a transparent organization. And so today, if
we're saying that, you know, as the as the as Firefox becomes a technically
competitive product against Chrome, then I think they really start to hold their
own to be able to say, look, now we have the technical features, plus we have all
this really good community offering. Yeah. Well, not only that, Noah, but also it
seems like if I'm in the enterprise, this is the horse I want to bet on if I'm
building internal applications that are dependent on a browser. Chrome is very,
is very, is, is, everything's built around Chrome now. Like, you look at all these
electron apps, it's, they're really all built around Chrome and Chromium. But if I'm
in the enterprise, and I'm looking at building applications around a browser, I
would, at this point, I would be much more inclined to go with Mozilla's
products simply because what the foundation's purpose is, don't you think?
Like, you can try, you have a lot more trust, and just that they won't suddenly
change what they're doing. You have access to this act or secret sauce if
you need it. Yeah, exactly. So I'm not hearing much from from Rika. I know
Rika, you're a really strong Chrome user, real strong proponent of Chrome. What do
you think about this? I'm not gonna change. Okay, that's fair. There's no
real reason for me to do so. I like Chrome and a lot of the extensions that
I use on Chrome aren't available on Firefox. Yeah, I think there's a couple
people in that boat. I definitely heard some people just around the office chatting
about it who I wouldn't say are that interested in browsers. I mean, they are
technical people, but I was, I was kind of surprised. I will say for my own usage
as well that I already use Firefox and Chrome, you know, I have a, I use Google
apps, etc. But I think Firefox is gonna be even more of a part of my life, and
there'll be some systems where I probably will just drop Chrome altogether.
Yeah. Popeye, I don't know if you're willing to talk about this on the air,
but you have a very interesting workflow that Firefox is not currently capable of
mimicking. Is that something you'd be willing to talk about? Well, yeah. So I
use Chrome all day every day, and I use lots and lots of separate profiles,
separate users in Chrome. And I like the way that Chrome lets me click a button,
switch to another user, and I'll have a completely separate browser window with
multiple tabs. Everything's saved for that user, which has a separate Gmail
account. Everything is completely separate cookies. And whilst Firefox, I am
told, can do this. And every time I try this, there are various extensions and
ways and command-line options that let you do this. It's never as smooth as it
is in Chrome. And, and I, what I want is a browser which is my work window to the
world, and a browser which is my personal window to the world, and then another 10
for my other online personalities that I have. And Firefox just can't do that,
and Chrome does. And what's funny is, you know, so aside from the puppet account
thing, what's interesting about that is I think you are willing to push the
envelope a lot further than the average user, even the average technical user is
going to do. Because I can tell you, I'm a fairly technical person. There is no way
in this earth I'm going to sit there and open up terminals to start launching my
web browser just to get, you know, it's just not practical for me. And I think
there's a lot of people, so I think if you aren't able to fit that into your
your workflow, I think anyone else that has that similar, you know, concept of
they want to have online personas, and I think a lot of people do, I think those
people are hosed. At least, I think I'm just as lazy as the next guy. I want an
easy way to separate one bunch of work from another set of work. On a
Friday night when it's five o'clock, I want to be able to close an entire
window and all of my work disappears. So I can say I don't have to
worry about email notifications or tabs that have documents in that are related
to my work. I can just forget those as soon as I close that tab. Now I realize
I'm a bit of a special snowflake because my my work machine is my personal
machine. Yeah, and I know that's not the same as use cases. Most people have a
work machine and a personal machine. I would say that that landscape is
changing. I would say that the vast, there's a lot of people that are working
from home, and I think a lot of those people are going to wind up with some of
the with some of the same challenges and desires that you have. And I'll tell you
what's interesting about working from home, because I do it too. It
becomes so important to be able to distinguish this is home and this I'm
spending personal time and I am doing working time. And when you're
working from home the best way to do that, if you can, is to have separate
machines. But the problem with having separate machines is oftentimes they are
expensive. And so one of the advents that has come along in the past couple years
that has really opened us up to be able to play with things, especially those of
us that that are doing things from home and are trying to do simultaneous
different projects, is obviously the ARM architecture. And up until recently I
have had this issue where I I'm deploying Red Hat all day long and I'm
deploying CentOS all day long and all these servers and then I get home and I'm
like, and this just happened just a couple months ago, we were testing an EMR
for a clinic and they said can you set it up and just show us kind of how it
worked. So sure, so I'm kind of setting everything up and kind of got
everything set up on a Raspberry Pi because they're cheap and they work. The
problem was when we went to actually put it into production, we had to end up
exporting out all of these, you know, SQL templates stuff because I couldn't just
move everything over because it was it was the ARM port of it. It wasn't the it
wasn't it wasn't binarily compatible with the x86 processor that that they
were going to use in production. And and so what Red Hat has announced today blew
me away because it's going to in a large way change a lot of that. And this is
from Red Hat themselves. Red Hat has announced Enterprise Linux for ARM. So
the article goes on to say today marks a milestone for Red Hat Enterprise Linux
with the addition of a new architecture on our list that fully supports
platforms. Red Hat Enterprise Linux for ARM is a part of our multi-architect
strategy, the culmination of a multi-year collaboration with upstream
community and our silicon and hardware parties. And so the article goes on to
talk about how Red Hat basically took this pragmatic approach to ARM servers.
And I remember, and Chris and I were talking about this earlier today, Linus
said that a couple years ago that one of the things that excited him about ARM
was he believed it was a true competitor to Intel in a way that he hadn't seen
since back in the old back in the old Mac days when they were on a different
architecture all together. And and and now we have a true competitor to Intel.
And at the time I was kind of skeptical of that. I was like are you kidding?
Because the ARM like basically at the time was like the thing that was running
inside of cell phones. This couldn't do anything serious. And then year after
year I've watched these things literally double in power until just last year I
think we were doing our for last we were doing our review of the latest Ubuntu
Mate and lo and behold I was installing the same operating system on my
Raspberry Pi for $35 Amazon Prime available that I was installing inside
of my studio. And it's just it's just this mind warp that I just couldn't get
over. And I know Chris you you as a person in the studio I mean how many
different computers are you sitting in front of? You can put your hand on
probably eight of them right now. You know the thing that I think you touched
on there that really is just un it's just it's an impossible force for Intel
to deal with is because ARM processors are in all of these routers and all of
these little tiny devices and all of these lady tubes and obviously in all of
these phones. Yeah they're lady tubes. No I know I just I think of something else
until I figure out what we're talking about. This is my safe way of not
triggering them because people they're listening to the podcast they get
really frustrated when you trigger their lady tubes. So I just refer to it plus
it's it can be the Google it could be the it could be the. There's all kinds of
annoying people in tubes these days. And there's a lot of annoying lady tubes so
in fact they're all kind of annoying in their own unique way. Oh yeah. And the
thing is all of them have ARM processors every damn cell phone though that's
really the thing right every cell phone has the ARM processor in it and this has
caused a momentum of investment and year-over-year improvement in a
platform that Intel and AMD just can't simply sustain on the x86 side they just
can't compete with that. Now they're so far ahead that it hasn't really mattered
but the thing about these ARM CPUs is damn if they don't work great together
because you can write and use modern operating systems to sort of carve out a
few of these cores and so you have companies like Cray and Qualicom that
are launching 48 core systems oh boy 48 core ARM systems and they don't carve
they don't they don't even I mean Noah you and I were chatting about this
earlier they don't they don't really cost that much. No they start out at
lowest price I found and this isn't for the 48 core I think this is 30
something cores 20 something cores 30 something cores but they start at 900
bucks and then for the 48 core version you're looking at like just under 2k but
you know the core is 2k but if you compared that to what you would what you
would pay for just just just a quad core Xeon you know that's that's half the
price of what I pay for some of the servers that that we we have that have
four cores in it so the the amount of computing power that you're getting per
dollar and then you know we haven't even talked about the energy because the the
power consumption of these ARM devices is just a fraction of what they are on
Intel or you know or AMD and so and and then by then by proxy then or by
translation the heat that is output by a lot of these ARM devices is a fraction
that's a big thing and then the fans are quite easy right yeah it means well it
means less cost for the data center to run cooling and while these per core I
think beard is probably about to say this while these per core don't compete
with an Intel or an AMD chip yet the thing is is you can you can build core
specific jobs so you can slice off 20 or 24 or whatever the cores for this
particular application that you've custom written for this job well I can
also think of like any number of servers I run and or have that it's not like
they're at their peak performance all the time a lot of times they're just
sitting there and if you could just have a especially if maybe you're running
some sort of maybe you're running a chat server something else that has a high
degree of parallelism but doesn't actually do that much it's mostly just
sending keepalives between the million clients connected to it these seem like
great fits for anything like that yeah now can I just say all of this aside and
and much congratulations to the Red Hat folks for getting full Red Hat
enterprise support behind this platform which is I think a huge milestone for
the industry in general I also part of me has to say welcome to the party by
the way a lot of us have been here for quite a while now especially those that
are Debian based or Ubuntu based and then you look at some projects like the
canonical has that like specifically some of the like long-term investments
that some projects have made into working on ARM platforms into into
really solid upgrades on those platforms and delivering software it I mean it's
good that they're here but I kind of wonder what took them so long at the
same time if actually I wouldn't mind commenting on that actually yeah sure go
ahead go ahead Christian yeah so so as you know Red Hat the business model of
Reddit right is that you sell a as called the standards operating system
that you traditionally have installed on x86 systems and I think for anyone who
worked with ARM in the past right it's historically been you know highly
custom platforms where you basically like you get some sort of Linux version
from usually the hardware vendor and it's a lot of manual tweaking to get it
to running and maintain it and then ship your device right with with this
Linux version and and of course when you need to do an update it is usually a
bit painful so so when Red Hat decided to enter this market one thing that we've
spent a lot of time doing was actually working to ensure that there is a
standardized platform we deploy towards so oh so so I mean like the fact that
this ARM service will be using UEFI that's partially because we said you
know we need a standard way to boot the systems you don't want to you don't deal
with ten different bootloaders on ten different platforms Christian if it
would it be an accurate to state would it be an accurate statement then to say
that some of the delay was Red Hat dragging the industry towards some
standards yeah I mean it was working with you know Linaro and the industry
partners to say that okay you know we are happy to put Red Hat's name as an
enterprise hardware software vendor behind this but we also need you to then step
to the plate and say that hey we're going to have a standards platform that
you can install a standard operating system on you don't need to have a
bespoke operating system to install it because I mean Red Hat is not I mean
I don't even say this but Red Hat doesn't really have an interest in going
into you know the bespoke OS market you know that it's interesting because that
seems to align with what my perception of Red Hat and a lot of times if I'm
being honest is a lot of times what is what pushes Red Hat to the top of the
list anytime I'm sitting in front of a university board you know or what have
you is that if something is put out by Red Hat I know that it's mature
technology and I know there's there's an argument to be had here about system D
but but for the most part when when Red Hat put something forward here they're
usually one of the later adopters they're not one of the you know the the
cutting-edge pioneers at least not on Red Hat Enterprise so what you're
describing seems to fit with what my perception has been and again that's
just I'm just some guy talking about you know my experience but that's what I
have seen mumble room who else in here is is interested in who would deploy Red
Hat Enterprise an enterprise operating system on an ARM architecture what does
this change anything for you or is this something that you say well like Chris
said you know Debian's had it for a while canonical has had it for a while
so this is it's really nothing new this really doesn't give us a tool we didn't
have in the toolbox anyone the problem the problem is probably that people are
not using ARM architecture on business level right now but that might change
soon I think so I think I think it is going to change soon I don't think it's
I mean everybody's been predicting this over and over again but you now have
Cray you have Qualcomm I mean you have a lot of big players they're saying we're
not replacing x86 but if you have an application specific task for us we're
ready to go it also seems like it might lower that entry right because like well
we weren't even considering it before but suddenly if we can run the same OS
we can use very similar image versions from the people who maintain that no
like we have a bunch of Raspberry Pi's that run TVs at my office right we
already had that option if if we were a rel shop now that would that would be
great right and so that that's actually what I was about to say was I
respectfully disagree that that arm doesn't have a strong foothold and in a
wide foothold inside of an enterprise audience I think where that where it
best fits though is in a lot of you know appliance type applications but but but
in that same way and kind of what you were touching on Wes is in that same way
a lot of these a lot of these platform systems if you have software stacks and
you have you know management systems for us that was really big our remote
management system to log into systems and pull statistics and all of that when
they came out with an arm port that was huge for us because we could then enroll
all of those arm systems that we had even if they're just appliances into
that central management system and so I would imagine that there are tons of
businesses out there like you said they're either rel shops or they have
custom software that runs on rel and they can say now we had these kind of
one-off appliances that were out here that were on arm if we switched
operating systems we could then have all of those standardized and I think that's
hugely beneficial to businesses yeah I just want to know when I can build my
arm PC you know as a longtime x86 user all I really care about is that I can
build my own PC system because that's just cool and when I can start building
my own arm systems then I'll care that's really for me that's it yeah and I think
to us I mean if you're you know if you're happy with a raspberry pi you can
do that today there also are there are more robust arm architectures out there
in fact some of the I think some of the some of the best representation we have
for that is from the arch arm group and those guys and I see them all the time
at different Linux events and stuff and they have a whole table full of you know
because we when I think of arm and when you think of our most people we think of
these $35 raspberry pies but they have like four and five hundred dollar
computers that are arm computers that you can install that are designed you
know with with tighter tolerances because at the end of the day the
raspberry pi was never designed to be a general purpose computer it was designed
to be a teaching tool turns out it's such a great teaching tool and was built
so well and designed so you know above what they targeted to do that you can
use it as a general purpose computer and for 80% of people it works just fine but
it does you know and I've tried to put it in some critical applications and
I've gotten bit and so there are other devices out there and I wish I could
tell you what they are I don't know I tell you what I do know Colonel 4.14 was
released olinjiabuntu came out with an article today said Colonel 4.14 features
a large number of new feature changes and is set to become the next long-term
LTS release backed for several years by ongoing maintenance and support things
that they have a whole list of things that they have added and those are in
the show notes but things that stood out to me that I think are particularly
interesting the Asus T100 touchpad support now if you don't know what the
Asus T100 is it is a small laptop UMPC not quite UMPC more like like a netbook
size PC they sell for about $150 to $200 you can pick them up at you know any
Best Buy Target has them that kind of thing and it had the computer and the
display is all in one so it's kind of a tablet style but the keyboard can be
attached or maybe it flips around I'm not exactly sure but it is one of the
most cost-effective well-built little netbook computers out there and Linux
was originally very problematic on it when they when they first came out we
tried to put Linux on one and we couldn't get Wi-Fi to work couldn't get
Bluetooth to work the touchpad didn't work sound didn't work so basically you
had a display and a keyboard and that was it and that was still such a good
deal that I would run into people in fact I ran into somebody at Linuxcon I
think last year and he had like this can just concoction of USB dongles to get
all of the connectivity and devices working and with kernel 4.14 the last of
those devices is now supported that's the touchpad so I thought that was
pretty cool but yeah a better support for Ryzen processors if I can make a
quick plug next week on the ask Noah show Monday 6 p.m. central we're going to
have Wendell Wilson from level one Tex and Wendell is just he's a really great
guy and he's been doing some really cool things with Ryzen and and threadripper
doing PCI pass-through and and so that he can run Linux on his bare metal and
but yet he can still take advantage of all of the software that Windows has to
offer and he has some really interesting theories about how none of us are we're
all going to be using Linux in just a couple of years I think I think he backs
it up pretty well so make sure to tune in for that but but better Ryzen support
for Linux means that that is all the more realistic yeah yeah I mean I as
somebody who has almost exclusively either Intel or Nvidia hardware I got to
admit it's looking really good for AMD GPU users these days but you know no I
gotta say that I think the big thing about 4.4 don't say butter fs don't say
butter fs nope no it's just the fact that is this is the new LTS kernel
that's gonna be like six years and if if we start getting this in these here
Android devices we might actually have ourselves like a sustainable patchable
manageable Linux kernel that's used by millions of devices like this could be a
really really good thing for Android let alone all the other distributions but
just Android alone this could be a huge thing if if OEMs and and Google start
shipping this kernel at some point absolutely
mumble room what do you guys think who's super excited about the new kernel
release oh well I mean there's butter fs
produce back who comes in with the butter well yeah what are you super
excited there you lie new compression support for butter fs everyone that's
what that's what the feature set is just so that you can continue to they did
also improve their SSD allocation algorithms and other which which I will
say like we're all pretty down about butter fs especially for large storage
but I think maybe OS volumes on SSDs is one of the places it does see some use
yeah yeah I wouldn't put our fs on anything the no one that actually stood
out to me is HDMI CC support for the Raspberry Pi no kid yeah yeah let's talk
about which I believe is the thing that lets the Raspberry Pi yeah like here in
the studio the Nvidia shield TV supports HDMI C so when you wake up the shield it
automatically turns on the TV without you having to grab the TV remote so it
kind of solves like the universal remote problem by just not needing it and my
added support for more Raspberry Pis as well my understanding too and somebody
correct me if I'm wrong on this but CEC allows you to not only just turn the
device on but also acknowledge which is the active input so you can set CEC so
if I have four different devices that are plugged into a TV when a device
starts seeing activity it will switch the input to that particular device and
power the TV on am I am I right about that yes yeah yeah it's great I mean it
works here in the studio with the Android TV devices so it makes sense
that you'd want this on a Raspberry Pi because you could put this on cody
appliance work with previous kernels because I have auto arm here on a
Raspberry Pi 3 and if I launch it my TV launches too yeah okay so there are two
things there's HDMI CEC which is what Rick Rick I is talking about and that's
where the Raspberry Pi is actually talking it's it's talking via data over
the HDMI cable there is the box well so but just so we're clear a lot of TVs
just support if there was an active HDMI signal just turn on the TV that's that's
my bed my Western Digital TV which rest their soul they're great devices even
though I'm not using them anymore those devices didn't support HDMI CEC but
still when I powered the device on my TV would come on and that was just because
the TV had a feature of if I see an HDMI signal just power myself up so there
there is a different just because the TV came on doesn't necessarily mean it was
doing CEC but it could have existed I have a Sony I have a Sony Bravia here
so all I had to do I have to I had to install lip CEC now it's introduced in
the kernel but I just had to add lip CEC install it and then it worked out of
the box well okay all right if you had to add the live then it's not out of the
box no no I don't don't feel bad we got to kill the term out of the box cuz
when's the last time anybody installed Linux from a box give me a break we got
to kill that yeah it's this giant nice big monolithic kernel I would buy one
just for the novel have it on the shelf funny story guys Red Hat 7 shipped with
a boxed version of Red Hat 7 yeah as a promotional item you could buy a boxed
version of Red Hat 7 and they would deliver it in a box to your house you
could open it up and they were like I don't know what they put inside I hope
it was an optical disk because I wouldn't know what to do with it in a
server these days we don't have optical drives anymore in storage somewhere I
have a nice CD case with Red Hat Linux 5 yeah do you really yeah I collect
versions of Red Hat I bought every single version of Soos and Mandrake that
came out I got the free CDs from Ubuntu as long as I could I was all about it as
long as I could because there's there was there was a celebratory fact or just
like I have this I have this physical thing and one of the things I one of the
things that made me use Soosa early on was this beautiful gorgeous detailed
updated manual for every single release it was a book it wasn't a pamphlet Soosa
had a book and I would read through that and I could feel the texture of the
paper and it would have screenshots and it just it was so awesome that this
Linux thing had this really physical book and I would still do I'd buy it for
Ubuntu 1604 I'd do Solus I any you know I really would because not only is it a
nice way to contribute but it's there's just but what I would want now is I'd
want a branded USB Drive like like Martin there knows about a he seems to
he seems to have found somebody who can make a very nice looking Ubuntu mate
thumb drive maybe people should talk to to wimpy about that because damn that
thing's hot looking it's a nice metal thumb drive and you could put that in
like a packet with like a book or a pamphlet about it like oh I I'd spend
$65 for something like that as long as like a good percentage of it went to the
project you know that's yeah that's an that's interesting that might be a
funding source or a funding revenue source for them you know I and I like I
said I think redhead did it kind of as a promo thing so hopefully we don't find
out if that actually worked out you know it's interesting so when you got that
book did you go through and like read it like was there it was a reason in there
I would say I skimmed it I skimmed it it was more about converting something that
was this hobbyist crazy-ass nearly hippie ideal to a physical good that
came in a box yeah like six discs and a book it was more about like that like
reality of this thing that I had so I never had the soos but I had the
redhat thing and the redhat I don't know if anyone out there remembers this but
redhat used to come with a little pamphlet and it gave you like this
quick start like this is Linux and it's a different operating system that you
might not be familiar with and here's kind of the the basic how to kind of
getting started thing and one of the things that you know the thing I guess
that really kind of drew me to it was at when I sat down at Linux for the first
time pulling these things out of the box I had no idea what I was doing and so
every little tiny hint that I could get including those little pamphlets you
know that was that was a big help to me of course today if I was doing that I
would head over to Linux Academy slash unplugged because Linux Academy is going
to do that same thing where you're going to have the ability to just visit a
website and get a tutor that and these people these people care about Linux
these people understand Linux they know Linux and you can tell if you've ever
taken a bad online computer course a video course you can hear the
instructor kind of like reading through his notes or they'll have bad takes or
something and you can tell when you're sitting down and I did the the Red Hat
7 one I think most recently rather than actually paying for the Red Hat course
and I didn't find myself lost at all and I could tell as the instructor kind of
went off on on little real hand stories well when I was working for this client
or when I was doing this we found this to be most useful and this is why I'm
super excited about this being in Red Hat 7 you can hear that personal
commentary that's stuff that you just don't get with somebody who's just a
paid voice to to read or or to to explain something right so Linux Academy
slash unplugged they've worked out a really great discount for you so you can
get started cheaper than ever and get started on your you know on your next
Linux career we get emails all the time at both at the ass know a show and I'm
sure you get them here on unplugged Chris but people are saying hey you
started my career you jumpstart my career in fact is Eric still in the
chat room with us Eric Eric H maybe not Eric I think I think it was smoking the
crack pipe yeah maybe Eric H was he was telling me just the other day he was
like you know what you and you and Jupiter broadcasting and thanks to
companies like Linux Academy you got my new career started I started because of
what you guys were we're doing on the network and for what things like your
sponsors like like Linux Academy have done for me and it launched his in
launches entire career and now he's on a completely different path and and I
think that's just really great because we spend the majority of our lives are
working here so you want to be doing something you love so head over to
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and make sure to take advantage of that
discount sorry going I was just gonna say you know the thing about Linux
Academy to that I really love about it as a Linux geek is they they passed the
sniff test because when you start using it you go oh yeah these guys are
definitely they're geeks they love Linux and that's when you that's when it
clicks that's when it clicks so apparently I'm talking about Linux
Academy like it's something that everyone knows they have a website it's
linuxlinuxacademy.com slash unplugged apparently there's there's a URL that
you have to go to to actually get there oh then you get the free seven-day
trial so that's that's useful yeah that's academy.com slash unplugged there
you go all right so is it is it is it Chris or Rekai who oh no no no no I'm
sorry I'm sorry I jumped ahead so one of a new software new software release yeah
I know I know I know but I didn't I didn't see that until I scroll down a
little bit new software version of OpenShot 2.4 is released and I tell you
what I I played with it for just I didn't have a lot of time to play with
it when I when I saw it I was I saw it just for researching the show and I
downloaded it and I was just playing with it a little bit man are they making
some progress OpenShot even if and I'll be the first one to admit even if
OpenShot is not the video editor that I could use today to do the things that I
need to get done even if that's not for me today OpenShot is definitely the
nonlinear video editor on Linux that I want to succeed long term yeah I don't
know if that makes sense you know no it does that's the nicest possible way to
say it and I would like Jonathan to get a hold of me and I would like to have a
conversation with him because I can honestly tell just by looking at the
screenshots that this is never gonna work for Jupiter broadcasting this is
never gonna work for me and you know if you look at the Linux gamecast I think
there's a very specific reason that they're on a much older version of this
program in this current one and I completely support somebody working
their ass off on an open source project and I completely want somebody to build
something for Linux that does this but Jesus if if it's not gonna be
completely irrelevant by the time he gets anywhere where this thing is usable
pipewire is now just a couple of years away to be completely feature complete
and this thing's gonna have to be completely rewritten to use any of that
and the UI is fundamentally impossible for anything that's more than just a
couple of tracks of editing so which means if it's anybody that's trying to
edit anything more than their Thanksgiving dinner it's never gonna
work for anybody that was a really nice dinner yeah right that's all it's good
for and I totally respect Jonathan I totally respect the OpenShot project I
have used past versions of OpenShot which are really great this unfortunately
is like skating to where the puck was about six years ago and I really I
really am a disappointed to say that as somebody who actually backed this
project when he did it on Kickstarter I was a backer of this I mean yeah I mean
you have to be realistic you know I will say they have they have done some they
have done some cool things improved playback one of the things that Linux
has struggled with is both 4k and video that is above 30 frames per second so
this has a smooth playback for 50 50 frames per second 60 frames per second
and 120 frames per second so they are making progress and I'll tell you where
OpenShot really fits in is if you just need to clip some video files up if you
just need to drop a video file in and clip off the beginning clip off the end
or you know make a clip mashup or something like that if you want a really
easy simple video editor to do that I think OpenShot fits the bill there but I
echo a hundred percent your sentiment I think when you start getting into any
even remotely complicated workflow you're just you're gonna be struggling
I mean Kdenlive is is is is a great fantastic open source editor that I
think is light years ahead of open OpenShot I agree Kdenlive is a is a is a
much better candidate for this particular type of work and then when
you need to go beyond that Lightworks it's a bit of a learning curve but it
is absolutely a capable editor and that's available for Linux as well and
so it's getting you have you have go ahead yeah yeah yeah talk about that
is it rotten are you using DaVinci resolve I have used it I don't use it
typically because I don't like the way they distribute it but overall it's uh
it's it's still it's definitely a good editor and I wish they would make a more
reasonable distribution method well what are you using for tux digital Kdenlive
basically okay always Kdenlive I use Lightworks occasionally too but it's
almost always Kdenlive but I just wanted to say like I think OpenShot's more in
the iMovie realm yeah I would agree I would agree it's it's one of those
things that you can you can pick up and just throw something together real quick
I'm curious what do you find egregious about the distribution for DaVinci
resolve they have a it's a binary that you have to run a rooted sh file to
install it so like it's not any kind of format of it's it's a it uses this thing
called make sh and it's just like it's a weird binary compiled bash
script essentially you can't see what the script is doing and you have to root
give it root access as a script oh and then you and it's and it's so weird
because you can't like unpackage it or anything so it's like if anything at
least do an app image like do something that's reasonable yeah even OpenShot
doesn't have image yeah yeah yeah well anyway I think part of that I think is
there's a discussion to be had on you know how software manufacturers are
supposed to target distributions because when they go to make an installable file
it's like well which distribution are we installing for something I think
there's a discussion to be had there and I think that snaps and flat pack and
stuff are gonna go a long way to fix that so Chris tell me about this gnome
show for proposal this is really interesting because it's it's gotten a
lot of immediate reaction today on on the internet and some of the reaction
has been are you kidding me you've just gotten gnome basically stable and now
you want to reinvent the wheel with gnome 4 and then the other other end of
the spectrum has been finally what the hell is taking you guys so long to
address some of these fundamental issues so we have two links of the show notes
ones to a pharaonic article that summarizes it really well and then one
is to the actual wiki post by the gnome project that gives a lot of detail but
essentially you have gnome 3 shell today which is doing great right everybody's
loving it it's getting deployed in all the places but it's built around x11
it's built around the era of x11 and with gnome shell for they want to build
it around Wayland a Wayland first design as the project puts it and the whole
idea is to do away with x11 slash X org support entirely their words not mine
the new gnome shell would be better fitted for low latency input 40 and low
latency visual input event feedback who doesn't love that and low latency zero
copy client 40 those all sound good because they have the word low latency
in front of them you hate latency I kind of like zero copy I don't know what that
means but I like it it's good because it's like you can copy without having to
copy on the back end of them for back to the client it's good Rekha it's good
based on synergy yeah it is and that's so so that's the the Wayland first is
what's getting the headlines but what I think is more interesting about this
story and you you learn more when you read the actual wiki post is the gnome
project is facing a couple of really really hard choices three I think to be
exact and they identify they identify a few core problem areas the number one
problem that need new solutions and man if I don't agree with every single one
of these number one low latency input 14 is a problem that they need new
solutions for number two low latency visual input event feedback like
specifically to put that back in user terms they mean cursor movement feedback
you move the cursor it should be glued exactly to your mouse movement exactly
you you move that mouse a millimeter it should represent that exactly it should
be glued together low latency and zero client copy forwarding also input methods
in the shell and this is the number one thing that they put as number five on
their list but for me this is number one stalls on the main thread and stalls on
the compositor for frame redraws now that one line item is a really really
big deal because it means breaking gnome up into a bunch of different processes
where you don't just rely on one primary renderer which is what always ends up
being the fundamental criticism of gnome now they have a few different potential
solutions for this that they've outlined on their wiki and some of these are
radical option a is pretty big and it's the closest to the I would say the
plasma desktop setup it's a UI process and a compositor process which is
exactly how the plasma desktop does it today there's also a few other like less
dramatic options that they have available to them that they're
considering another option potentially being less drastic but would only solve
three out of the five problems I just listed is to introduce a proxy display
server yeah proxy display server would be somewhat similar to an X server and
then they would essentially have gnome talk to that and then that proxy would
talk to Wayland you know kind of like Mir but let's not bring that up and then
they have pros and cons outlined for all of that and what it left me with is this
is what I was talking about earlier in the year on this show is the transition
to Wayland and we've all been like let's get Wayland going let's get Wayland by
default let's get Wayland working on Nvidia let's get Wayland working on
Intel the thing is is once you get to Wayland there is so much more work for
these desktop projects and they in some cases are gonna have to reinvent some of
the core aspects of the desktop and in the case of gnome shell 4 it would
break most likely and and the projects the one saying this not me gnome shell
3 extensions so all the extensions that you are currently using to make your
gnome 3 shell usable would likely break with gnome shell 4 now I'm not saying
that's gonna be the end of the world I'm not saying there's not gonna be an easy
transition or maybe a new standardized stable API out of this it could all it
could end up in something much better
yeah but but he could end up in something that's better than what we
have now but in the immediate short term your doc your crazy hack to do XYZ could
break you know for me be my Bitcoin widget I'm sure because they like to
break that a lot and so gnome shell 4 is now on the horizon and it's it is just
one of the millions of dominoes that are gonna fall in this transition to
Wayland yeah I it so it's gonna be interesting to watch but I kind of
resonate with what you were talking about earlier when you said why not why
not start working with you know canonical and mere to do a lot of these
things that they're trying to reinvent the wheel on well you know you know here's
got a lot of a lot of you know we call this thing called drama I don't know if
would you guys call it over in Grand Forks but here on the west coast we call
it drama well here's and here's well here's the other drama if we're talking
about drama then what kind of message does that send from the gnome community
up to canonical would have basically just banked their business on this on
this desktop I wouldn't say bank the business I'll say that at least the
desktop part of it yeah yeah I don't know that's a good question
they're desktops I don't they don't seem to actually have like they care about it
but business-wise they don't care about it well I wouldn't say that I don't know
about that I wouldn't the desktop art because you can say like this server
implementation doesn't really matter if gnomes there or not the IOT stuff doesn't
matter if gnomes there or not yeah but so here's the thing here's the thing
rotten is if I'm Dell or I'm HP or I'm anybody that's gonna pre configure and
ship a canonical derived desktop I feel better right now that they're using
gnome because I look at business risk and I evaluate other companies and
compared to me canonical is a small shop that is struggling to make it by and I'm
super rich I'm worldwide I want to ship my products to millions of customers and
I'm a little skeptical that they can pull all that shit off and so the fact
that they're now deferring that work to the community that the wider community
and a huge part of that development is backed by redhat and that's no secret to
anybody anybody in the industry you know you look at these facts and you say well
now we've just deferred our risk because now canonical is not solely responsible
for the development of the Ubuntu desktop all of these companies are all
in and they just have to do a great job of packaging up and make it work right
and that's all I need to ship it on my hardware you know and that's that's the
harder that's the hardware vendors perspective but then you have to look at
the and this is not an insignificant amount of dollars not an insignificant
amount of revenue and not an insignificant amount of the Ubuntu
infrastructure look at companies like Amazon and Google and I'm not talking
about Amazon servers I'm not talking about Google servers I'm talking about
the workstations that sit in front of the human beings that use them those
machines are running Ubuntu on the desktop Amazon has and I've talked to a
number of different Amazon employees one of them is a good friend of mine he's
been on you've been on this show and on ask Noah Sean and and he's one of the
guys that works in the the IT department for Amazon and Ubuntu is by far the
dominant operating system desktop dominant operating system on their
computers and very much the same thing if you talk to a Google employee they
have a lot of Chromebooks they have some people what using MacBooks and really
the common denominator for Google obviously is going to be Chrome and
they've tooled Chrome to do all the things they need it to do but the actual
workstation that does the calculations the actual thing that they're remoted
into the actual thing that's doing the thinking that's a Linux Ubuntu desktop
I'll give a brief you know because I've talked about it a lot recently on the
show here but for us I was looking at different options for the studio because
we were having a different array of technical problems that essentially came
down to running multiple Linux distributions I mean not to not to make
but that's what it kind of came down yeah yeah and so we if we just
standardized on one thing and I emphasize that by hitting my mic if we
just standardized on one thing then we would kind of like have one common thing
to work towards and so after after a bunch of testing which I've talked about
a ton on the show we landed on Ubuntu 1604 for the production OS yep now the
reason one of the things that did factor into that is there isn't multiple
versions for me to figure out there's one Ubuntu LTS that gets five years I
don't I don't have to go get like a CentOS version of Ubuntu right or like
some sort of rolling version that's supported by a open source subset of a
corporate backed it's just it's Ubuntu LTS and then later on after I get it all
set up and I go oh guess what this shits actually working for me and it hasn't
cost me anything I can I can then go choose to subscribe to landscape or some
other some one of their other subscription services which then all of
a sudden turns them into legitimate systems yep that I'm centralized managed
and I don't have to like play this mental game that feels like it's from
the 90s deciding which version of Linux I need do I need the Red Hat corporate
version where I subscribe to their service do I need CentOS which is kind
of like the same thing but I support it myself do I want tumbleweed do I want
leap none of this crazy stupid abstracted different versions I get
Ubuntu 1604 full stop it's Ubuntu 1604 it's the same one you can download for
free it's the same one I can download for free it's the same one I can put on
my personal laptop is the same one I can put up on a server on a VPS it is the
same Ubuntu and the systems that are important to me I subscribe to landscape
and I get a bun to advantage and now all of a sudden they're enterprise systems
and to me that simplicity that felt like it was more kind of like like a basic
straight approach was what was the eventual like okay well you combine the
commercial support you buy it you combine the software support and you
combine the selective commercial software like back support by canonical
where I need it and it's great because I can have we can standardize 16 systems
in the studio on 1604 and I can subscribe for support on six of them
yeah absolutely and I you know the other thing is you are you are very involved
in the community so probably not much comes as a surprise to you but there's
there are a lot of companies that they just kind of they kind of just you know
ad hoc trust that they want a company to to do the thinking for them and do all
the planning and they deal with all the community minutia and just deliver them
a product and that is a valuable service and that is also a valuable selling
point when I'm going to talk to people about you know switching to Linux
basically sure sure I bet it is and and when I was when I was working with a
company where we were deploying lots of really critical Linux servers it was it
was it was no question to buy the $5,000 red hat enterprise support I can't
remember what we called it back then but they had multiple grades I don't know if
they still do this and one was like you got like ten years and you got like a
hotline to call support and that was what we bought we bought that really
yeah yeah you know I'm talking about yeah and that wasn't even a big deal
like whatever that's fine that's just it was just included as part of the
purchase cost of a server and so you spend $15,000 and about 3500 of that was
the server license and support and it was there wasn't even a conversation it
wasn't a debate it wasn't looking at the merits of it it was you buy Red Hat and
it's fine but now when I'm running my own business my own small business it's
a completely different perspective I have on it and so I think that's why Red
Hat can make billions of dollars still with this particular setup they have and
it doesn't and and canonical can make a profitable revenue source with their
setup because they're they're essentially appealing to a bit of the
same market while at the same time super fulfilling different ends of the spectrum
absolutely anyone if for the mumble room have any perspective to add before we
move on actually I did so in regards to the whole gnome for thing you know with
them the question should be is are they deprecating or are they reinventing
because this sounds like a process that they've been working on for years it
sounds like and have been building up to it just sounds to me like that the media
is just freaking out in the same way that with pop OS and calling it a fork
when they're just changing the theme around no they're okay one pop OS is a
fork system 76 said it is to the the gnome thing it has been in process for a
while yes but it they also said that it would know gtk4 and gnome 4 would break
all compatibility gta3 that's why gta3 is going to have a very very long LTS yep
and you know you also have to figure that there's more and more LTS distros
these days shipping it yeah so they're gonna have like they're not deprecate
yes they are deprecating it but they're going to wait a very long time before
they deprecated it yeah yeah you should double down on your point to they have
been they have been forecasting this for a very long time it's not like this is a
surprise this is something that they've been talking about for a long time
version 4 is called version 4 because it's meant to warn developers there's
gonna be some breakage here yeah they said that about I think three years ago
they started saying that this will have breaks and to chime in a bit here I've
been at the wikipost was written by Jonas Odal who's on my team and who's
been on the main guys behind a lot of our port work to to Wayland so I mean at
the moment no code is written here this is basically him saying okay you know I
spend a lot of time helping off with the port of gnome 3 to Wayland and we still
have things we plan to do there but here's some of the problems I see and I
think here's maybe how we want to look at resolving them in the long run so I
mean my recommendation to anyone be that not don't hold your breath for gnome
shell 4 it's sort of multi-year thing so Chris tell me about James Nugent yeah
so this is a friend of the show a podcast they've put out over at advanced
tech media org and they just did an interview with James Nugent and James is
an interesting interesting fellow he's across the pond over and I I'm gonna I'm
gonna try to I'm gonna give an attempt I feel like I can get this one bath
England yeah he works at joinette which we talk about about on this network
especially the text net program and in BSD now they were recently acquired by
Samsung Electronics and they still are super active in the open source
community and he's a core contributor at hashicorp and event store and he also
produces the open source stream database with a built projections system I don't
know what that means but I would almost listen just to find out you almost got
it Chris it's actually joint oh I know I know I always get it wrong I've always
gotten on joint you're right you're someday so joinette joint this looks
like a great podcast oh man yeah yeah that's the interview fans tech media org
and it's put on by Alexandra and Adam and they both came to our barbecue meetup
that we had a little bit ago so I thought we should give them a plug so I
know what I'll be doing after the show plug skis we'll have a link for that or
you can just go to advanced media org it's episode 9 with James and he's all
in with joint or joinette however you want to say it I don't judge I don't
judge where those things the guys that in the sous vide yeah well I yeah yeah
yeah they were and I don't know I don't know I don't know if we got actually a
chance to eat it during the barbecue because it would took so long that's the
problem with the soup yeah they did give the go and they brought the whole unit
with the cooler and all that so it was me and Adam yeah yeah yeah that's right
bachelor fruit was here too of course Dustin was yeah yeah yeah Adam and I
just came down together I love it I love it so their podcast is at advanced media
org check it out advanced tech media org check it out for episode 9 you know what
I would totally recommend to them if they if they're if they're not doing
this already is they should check out tune in because tune in is it's a it's a
really cool service and what they do is they allow you to basically you can you
can use their infrastructure to have a mobile app that people can listen to
your show or they can listen to a web browser they can listen to it on the
Alexa all of that kind of stuff there's a really cool tool that I really like
it's called easy stream it's a command line based streaming utility that you
can use to send an ice cast either a file or an ice cast stream out to a
service you can just take you know a given mp3 and you could put it on a
loop people could go to that tune in site and they could and they could
listen to it to your show and crazy well here's the thing the problem is when
you're first setting this stuff up there's like this config file you have
to write and I'll throw the config in the show notes for anyone that wants to
play with it but let me tell you the first time here's what it is it's you
install the operating system you set up the software and then you try and see if
it works and then you're not quite sure well maybe this thing is wrong or maybe
that file is wrong or maybe I put this in the wrong location I'll just better
start over and then you blow it away and then you start all over again you know
what the easiest way to do that is with something like digital ocean digital
ocean is Linux on demand it's like Linux on tap actually that's what you could
call it and basically I can get a Linux server anytime I want it just by going
to digital ocean comm I have I'd say probably I'd say I think at this point
all but two of my servers on digital ocean are on the $5 droplets all of them
are on the $5 you know the $5 droplets just get you everything you need of
course they can go up to $10 droplets $15 droplets $20 droplets but it gets
even better because if you use the code do unplugged then you get free droplets
at least the $5 ones you get those for free for two months so if they so these
guys they want to do a streaming service so they want to set this up and have a
mobile app they could use easy stream they could go over to digital ocean use
that code do unplugged and they'd have a mobile infrastructure for free for the
first two months and after that's only five bucks so how you getting better
than that digital ocean comm make sure to use the code d o unplugged dashboard
for dashboard you and your dashboard I don't you know we've never said the word
dashboard on the ask no show I don't think oh no you are doing your viewers a
disservice my friend is a good dash an amazing dashboard you know why you know
I know what you better be talking about the API oh that's right yeah you say
that all the time yeah oh no okay that yeah no you don't but finish you should
finish your thought though why is it that you always talk about the dashboard
I lived in servitude to really really really really really really really
really really hold on really really bad virtualization you eyes and I and I and
sometimes like the whole infrastructure all of it would run on on Linux and then
I would have to have a Windows machine to manage it and it would drive me so
crazy works in Internet Explorer yeah oh oh it's active active active X yes
Internet Explorer 5 or 6 maybe oh and I suffered through a lot of that in my day
and so now to go to to go to digital ocean and have all of it work in
whichever browser you want to use on Linux but it more importantly to have it
be better than anything I used and some of those things you know they cost 200
300 thousand dollars three hundred four hundred thousand dollars maybe actually
be expended there why wasn't me it was the businesses that were buying it and
it was and you ended up with these total crap you eyes well not only that but it
shows that they have total trust in their API because the dashboard is
sitting on top of the API yeah yeah it's pretty great it's pretty great that's
all that's why you know what I thought you know what I thought you were gonna
say I thought you were gonna say well I say dashboard because a bunch of people
who got all upset that I said the word dashboard like twice and so then they
went on this like they went on this like rampage to like Twitter and read it
right all this other stuff I'll just say that's why I say it now yeah I mean
that's why I say it for now that now that's why I say yes okay so so
interestingly enough in the show in this show that I'm I'm guesting with you guys
I'm not the one that puts the new fedora 27 workstation features in the doc I
feel very ashamed about they're ahead of the curve over here you see Noah that's
because you're not running fedora because you you hate the the dis turn
out you're such an Ubuntu apologizer it's embarrassing for us it took us
hardcore redhat users here at jb1 to get this straight and oh sorry yes right
right hardcore redhat users yes you know we're back to the good old days we're
back to the good old days of Linux where fedora and Ubuntu kind of have the same
features but Ubuntu ships a month early and
you remember how it used to be like that because it's known again and a lot of
the progress comes from known because that's where the fedora project invests
a lot of its time and so I joke but at the same time a huge part of fedora 27
is it's everything you love about fedora with gnome 3.26 but one of the things
for me as somebody who likes to just follow all of this is this was really
the release that marked the end of the alphas and there's something else that I
just anecdotally noticed that I got to give them credit for not only did they
kill the alphas with this release cycle but I more than I have ever seen in in
well I I have actually I have followed the fedora project since it was the
fedora project I you know so I mean literally since I've ever seen this
distribution I have never seen more people anecdotally say across different
places that I monitor that this has been the most stable most reliable beta that
they have ever used of the fedora project and so not only did they end the
alpha sort of release cycle but they definitely upped their game on the
stability of the beta because just anecdotally I mean this is just my
observation monitoring a lot of different sources having followed this
project since it was just a glimmer in somebody's eye this seems to be the most
stable release they've ever had now I will say selfishly what I really like
about fedora 27 is this is the release that really lays the groundwork for
pipewire which is the new media oh boy yeah oh boy yeah we're excited about
that here at Jupiter broadcasting because this is something that we think
Linux really needs to be competitive with macOS on the video editing side
and it was something just a year or two ago I thought would never happen and so
the fact that the fedora project is taking this on they will they will for
the rest of my life have my respect taking it seriously I mean they
recognize that this is something Linux community me mm-hmm yeah and and it has
been it has been something that I thought would never come to bear because
it seemed like it took it would take like this huge multi project multi
distro cooperation but I think pipewire the way they're doing it is it's humble
it's a it's a good steady slow approach so in fedora 27 it's it's nothing major
it's just gonna handle screen sharing and screen capture under gnome shell
it's like laying the fundamental groundwork and of course it's it's the
groundwork to support these functions under Wayland which couldn't couldn't be
done before so I really like the way they're their way the way they're
approaching pipewire the KDE version of fedora hasn't seen a lot they've switched
to five dot nine one for cute five and there's a few other things but Christian
is joining us he's there we he is very dutifully filling in at the very last
moment to join us from the fedora project to talk about some of the new
features so Christian welcome to Linux unplugged and I know I've mentioned a
couple of features but I bet I missed some feature fedora 27 that is deserved
of mention yeah thanks for having me yeah I think you mentioned some of the
important things and I mean I think what I mean you were talking about that you
know we are a month late but on the other hand we spent that last month
fixing a lot of last minute bugs in home so hopefully it's a bit more stable to
rinse us under a lot of multi-month ratios that we were hammering to the last
minute yeah sorted yeah I mean the one of the things that really stood out me
when we installed fedora 27 is it is a straight-up showcase for gnome for like
upstream known and it's the the background is gorgeous and the
transparent the transparent bar up top that it's just it's it's a beautiful
default theme for fedora it's a great showcase for stock no thank you I mean I
think one of the features I would love to highlight a bit which is almost sort
on the side is is that this is also first release really where we where we
have fleet commander available which is our new tool for administrating a large
number of desktops okay so fleet commander so is fleet
command you haven't played with fleet commander no I play is it like is it
related to cockpit or is it a separate thing it's it's an extension of cockpit
so when when you have cockpit stolen and fleet commander you will actually see a
link where you can click into fleet commander from cockpit so it's but of
course my cockpit of course was written and it's mainly targeted doing server
administration a fleet commander is all about you know administrating desktops
oh nice and I'm in the background for fleet commander actually was we had a
discussion a couple years ago in how service saying that you know if you ever
want to see for instance Linux making a headway in corporate settings against
Windows we need to come up with something that's a bit more accessible
to people than you know telling them to you know rewrite scripts figure out how
different command and tools work on Linux to configure stuff and instead
have something that's all graphical and and you know won't click deploy and it
integrates with the people's director services you know Christian I have to be
honest if this this is this is the dichotomy I have with the damn fedora
project right here you guys have cockpit you have fleet commander you have atomic
you have fedora cloud you have all of these things that would make fedora so
frickin perfect for deploying in production except for that fact that the
fedora releases are only supported for a few months like this is the dichotomy I
just can't get over yeah but maybe what they've done there I mean I mean you're
not the first person of course who complain about that but I mean for me
fedora is it's definitely like you know the distro we're targeting towards an
old enthusiast users developers and people who want to you know get the
news right away straight off the press yeah and at the same point of course I
know people were not so happy by use with CentOS or well because I felt it
was like okay it's fine real new rel out but then as the years go by you know a
becomes a bit long in the tooth for a desktop user so what we did switch for
in rel 7 is this model where we actually updating the desktop in rel and CentOS
of course as a result of that every second release okay so so that way you
get a refresh desktop experience continuously and so so that's also what
I'm telling people and I said hey I want a more long-term thing I said like well
you know I know that historically things like CentOS might not have appeal to you
or getting a rel subscription just because you didn't want to be there at
you know the dot six release and feel that you were using you know the desktop
yeah from ten years ago but that that's no longer true with well now you're
getting a brand new desktop every second release and every old release we're
updating a lot of the major applications there okay and I think as we go forward
and this so it's called a strategy we'll we'll call it coming to folks a bit more
because I mean one of the big goals I I hope that we will achieve it with things
like flat packs is that you suddenly can create like you know an application
stream that's independent of both fedora and rel so that you no longer have this
sort of tight link between like you know which application version you have and
which desktop version you had sure you just have you know hey I want to let
this gimp and I can deploy it either in fedora or on rel or of course or else
good point that's a that's a that's a really good point is the this may be a
non-issue once that's once that's in the pipeline so I have so many things to
ask you about and I don't know which which you'd rather answer so I'll give
you I'm gonna throw two at you actually how about three Christian I'm gonna give
you three questions and whichever one you feel more comfortable answering you
go for number one is what are your thoughts on on gnomes position about the
system tray icons to quote the fedora project workstation release notes the
quote-unquote antiquated system tray has been removed to reduce visual clutter
so that's question one is what are your thoughts on that question two if you'd
rather answer this is some big changes in fedora atomic including the support
for kubernetes have been introduced which seems like a huge huge was one of
the things I was most excited about like a huge change there and then also some
badass support for trim support on encrypted disks I know that's three
totally different topics Christian but since you haven't you know you know I
just thought I'd toss you those three and you pick which one's the best for
you to answer I think the last one is sort of old summer scope I mean just to
give you a little background on who I am and I'm actually the senior manager for
desktop graphics I 18n and fedora inside reddit all right great to meet you then
so of course so even though of course the fedora team that I manage are in
charge of all the fedora editions of course due to all the other groups being
distributed that's sort of usually where my focus and it's being so so I don't
necessarily have a lot of insight into call it these other parts of of fedora
and so I'm also interested in just your opinions too so you don't you don't feel
like when you come on the show you have to have like I'm speaking on behalf of
the fedora project I'm just interested in your opinion as a Linux user too yeah
yeah I mean it's a talk to take the system tray I mean I think it was
something that was single for a long time that they wanted to stop having
people use these data cycles because a they were using an old an old extender
that was problematic in terms of focus and many other things yeah and so they
tried to do this thing where I you know we sent up an awesome saying hey you
know eventually this will be deprecated and of course nobody ever moved on those
yeah but do you think but what makes you think anybody will move now well the
hope is of course that once it's not a default feature that you have to know
install extension if you want the system tray it will motivate and at the same
time we do have an active outreach effort at the moment working with
various vendors who are still using the system trade to try to basically say hey
this is a better way of doing it well that's good yeah that's nice I mean so
I'm glad to hear about the outreach so the thing that crosses my mind is that
see here's where it gets sticky and I again I know you're not speaking
officially just in your opinion it seems to me like if the position is we need to
stop doing this in the meantime use an extension but oh by the way that
extensions totally gonna break and inversion I mean that that is a
particular sticky situation don't you think yeah no I agree and what I guess
what not very well communicated was that at least you know speaking for for the
team I managed at Red Hat I mean we took ownership of making sure that that
extension works in Fedora okay okay and thus I mean it's it's a community
extension but of course if if you see that it breaks we will fix it to make
sure it works so if I install that on Fedora is that coming from the Fedora
repository no it does come from the extreme extension repository but we
would go there and fix it oh guys officially announced that he was not
going to continue maintaining it hmm yeah so I mean as I said we will as a
project you're gonna keep ah okay and I mean what you have any background on
that decision that's that's awesome to hear that thank you for telling me that
but what's the do you have any background on did that did the project
sort of did Fedora debate you know this is something we need to do or how did
that come about because I had no idea about this no I mean well this we had a
decision that that in universe some people who had you know an old
application where they still acquired a system tray I mean I have to say though
I have a couple applications that still use a system tray icon but I have
forgotten about them right because even with old UI they were sort of hidden in
a little weird corner and done at the bottom yeah yeah and so the multiple
applications that you know builder UI in a way that require it are quite few and
far between these days and yeah the few know about this ones we're trying to
work the hardest with to get moving to a different setup but but in terms of you
know discussion we had inside Fedora and reddit was like hey okay we know that
this needs to be there and of course we need to step up and make sure it keeps
working because you know well at the end of the day right we a lot of these
things you know end up also in rel and us we have to make sure over sharing
customers have things at work you know having thought about it for a couple of
weeks I agree they are kind of user hostile in a sense and you know the
thing is is if you're if we're all honest with ourselves it's a paradigm
that was that was forced upon us from Windows and it's one that we just
adopted on Linux to fit in and it kind of sucks it really actually sucks and so
I'm not I'm not opposed to figuring out a better way of doing it and I think
it's it's it's pretty decent of the Fedora project to say we're gonna try to
work upstream to keep this thing working and and that sounds like it worked for
all gnome users to not just necessarily Fedora yeah that's pretty cool and also
going back to the gnome 3 thing since that's I mean that's not gonna be
deprecated for a while anyway so that the support for this extension will
still have a long life even though the guys not maintaining it it's still he
also said it's gonna still be around for a very long time yeah yeah yeah so I
also just a just I'll just touch on this point just to make just a follow back
people that heard it might be wanted no more so trim support has been around in
Fedora for a little while now but the thing that's really great now is that
the Fedora 27 has introduced trim support for encrypted disks which I know
Noah's gonna care a lot about because it's gonna greatly enhance the
performance of Fedora workstation on SSDs that use encryption and I know
that's got to be you brown bear absolutely I I don't own a computer that
doesn't have an SSD anymore everything has either an SSD or is envy any which
you know SSDs but yeah yeah first so everything is and you know everything is
going that way too right I strongly suspect that for the rest of the time
that I ever buy laptops I'm not gonna buy a computer with spinning rust in it
I mean that's just that's just the reality of 2017 hey guys I want to get
one last plug 8 5 5 4 5 0 6 6 2 4 that's the phone number you can join us live on
the air for a special edition of Linux unplugged Jay is calling hey Jay you're
on Linux unplugged what's on your mind hey I'm calling about well I'm doing
tech support for club well I I was one client that I do freelance and I work at
the software developer actually but I still have one client I do freelance
that I'm good friends with the CEO and I was wondering how I could resolve
issues where I make mistakes and I don't feel like I should go for them how do
you how do you handle that if you if you make a mistake and you spend a lot of
extra time doing something and then you feel like you shouldn't build them but
you still spent the time to get it done yeah so part of that Jay though it's an
ethics question right and the way I answer ethics questions is I simply do
the moccasin test if put the other person's moccasins on and walk them out
in their shoes and see how you feel so for example if you if they asked you
they said we want you to come install a router for us so that we can get our
four front desk machines on the internet so what you should do is take
the router out of the box and plug it into the modem and turn it on and plug
all the computers in and they should just come online that that's what you
need to do and you'd build a client for like an hour of time and in instead you
pull it out of the box and you know unbeknownst to you maybe you maybe you
inadvertently shut the web interface off and you can't figure out how to turn it
back on and you're trying to get in you're trying to SSH in so you're
calling the manufacturer what's the default password for the SSH oh yeah
well I don't know what version I have and you're doing that dance right and so
come lo and behold you spent four hours doing it is that if you were the client
would you want to get billed for four hours of work for that while you're
while your IT guy learned how to do his job right no of course not but at the
same time if you get called in and the client says yeah we need our internet
went down we don't know what to do and you say well I've never been here before
tell me the layout where's your network documentation who is the last guy that
worked for you and they say yeah we don't know anything about that listen
this that closet at the end now that's where your breaker room is whatever then
it's the other one over there that closet yeah okay that's the right one so
where's the documentation we don't have any documentation there's the owners
manuals I think if that's what you're looking for those are in there now if
you're spending time resetting username and passwords and you're spending time
tracing wire connections that's not I mean yeah absolutely you should bill for
that and and and that comes down to again how would you want to be treated
and so and sometimes you take a hybrid approach to sometimes you get somewhere
is some you know so far into something like maybe you're tracing a cable and
you get to a point you say I should oh I'm an idiot I should have known that
this cable would run to that switch room or I should have looked for if there was
another switch closet that may be your fault that may be something you feel
guilty about but at the same time unless you were told about that it's but you're
perfectly lit you're perfectly within your right I would say to build the
client and a lot of times what I'll do in those six in their circumstances is I
will I'll kind of do my no affair billing so if I look at something and I
said well I was technically here for six hours but I think I got about four hours
I think I delivered four hours of work I'm only gonna build that client for
four hours and I'm if I especially there's a particular client we work for
and they pay me or they would pay me if I build them for it they they would pay
me hundreds of dollars to stand in front of locked doors because they have this
idiotic policy that the security guy is the only guy that can come unlock a door
for me and so I walk up to the door and I stand there and I call in the front
desk and I say yeah I need somebody come it just it's ridiculous and so if I was
billing them you know and I would I would say I'm within my right if I'm
standing there for 15 minutes every time I need to get through a door I would be
within my right to build them are $75 an hour and I don't partly because mostly
because I value their business and I like the owner and I understand why
those security principles are in place given the nature of their business does
that answer your question yeah yeah because I really like to you know I try
and give give give my customers the the the kind of service I would like to have
and it and and and I knew that if if someone made a mistake and they were
just you know spin the wheels for a couple for a couple hours I wouldn't I
wouldn't want to get those for that and at the same time I just I spent time on
it and they did get done yeah but that's just yeah I hear you it's kind of a
different it's kind of a it's kind of an interesting thing to thread one more
room do you have any thoughts as well as the answer I gave is that is that how
most you feel or somebody have a different opinion I agree it just it
depends on how much of your mistake like how much of a setback is your mistake if
it's if it's a something that's not that big of a deal that you know maybe cost
you an extra 30 minutes of time and work you could you could say that that's
that's something you can just kind of throw in but if it's something that you
you I think if you cause the problem that gives you yourself an extra four
hours I think you shouldn't really but you shouldn't really charge for that if
the mistake was solely on your fault but it was not you know well lack of
information or something like maybe you configured something and you come back
an hour later and you realize oh you have to start all over again this is why
you build research into your contract you build a right hours for of research
in yeah yeah and you Pat and you know that's the thing too is I and I explain
this to people a lot I'll say if we're gonna quote something we're gonna quote
high and some people you know they're put I mean I'm serious if we're if
you're gonna yeah over I mean 100% 100% every time you know we don't under bill
if I if I go into a place and I'm being honest if I go into a place and I think
somebody's going to if something's gonna take 10 hours to do we're gonna build
that client for 12 or we're gonna estimate them for 12 or 15 and the
reason for that is because I've done this long enough to know that things
come up and on the off chance that something doesn't come up well that just
offsets the number of times that something did come up and we went 10
hours over and like you said after a while you start to budget that in and
you start to get a good feel of it but if you and we'll do real-time real-time
billing we do that if you say just come and do this job fine we'll do it and
we'll let you know at the end how long it actually took and we'll believe for
that but if you want us to stay because it goes both ways if I'm gonna go in and
I'm gonna sign my name to something saying we will only bill you for this
many hours well I'm gonna make sure that we don't lose money on it that's just
the way we do things but you know more often that more often than that more
often than I'm worried about not losing money I'm worried about saving my
clients money oh yeah one of the ways I've done that recently and this was
actually with a law firm we recommended them with Ting and Ting if you're not
familiar with it is a mobile service provider where you own the service and
you own the device I remember the first time I switched to Ting I instantly I
knew well there's two things I knew first of all I knew that any service
that had a URL of linux.ting.com and when I went to that linux.ting.com it
saved me money if I get somebody's gonna give $25 to go to a Linux URL that right
off the bat I knew that was a good thing but then after I started to get
involved with Ting and I was previously on a big-name carrier and they sent me
the phone and it felt like my phone because they're not they're not locked
phones they're not locked to Ting you can take it to any service you want and
vice versa you can go to Best Buy and buy any phone you want about my son and
Asus do you remember what that was Chris he showed it to you when we were in
Minneapolis ZenFone I bought him an Asus ZenFone at Best Buy and you know
we and I had anticipated this so I'd activated the Ting SIM card which I
have on hand I have like 10 or 15 of them that I keep around just you know
and we get out to the car and my son goes as soon as he opens a box I knew
this was coming just dad this thing doesn't have internet how do we get an
internet I'm like I got you buddy I got you here's your SIM card and I just
handed him a SIM card and with Ting's dashboard yeah I said it dashboard the
dashboard allows me to control how much data he uses how many minutes he uses
and how many messages he sends and so I've gone in there and said he doesn't
need to be texting anyone there's nobody he knows that he would know how to text
he doesn't need to do that we want everything over Telegram where I can
monitor his communications I don't care if he calls people but I don't want it
to last I don't he never needs more than a hundred minutes if he accidentally
inadvertently dial something and just leaves the phone sitting for three days
you know I don't want a big bill because I'm gonna be calling you Sarah or my son
and until we run yeah exactly exactly and so and so they're they're only pay
for what you use and the ability to for that granular type control absolutely
fantastic linux.ting.com and huge thanks to Ting for sponsoring the Linux
unplugged program so I have a article I don't know if you saw this Chris I
threw it in your kind of last minute but there is a gentleman by the name of
Tommy Jordan really liked the guy and basically he has a website that he runs
called eight minutes of fame it's a long story about that relates to a YouTube
video that that kind of cast him into the limelight unexpectedly but he wrote
a very interesting article about encryption and basically the article
starts out it says we've seen it plastered all over national news these
last two years the encryption debate between tech companies and civilians
wanting to keep their data private while being weighed against the government's
desire to gain access to anything and everything that can be hunt to stop the
terrorists now he goes on to say and he outlines us very very well he says the
government argues that these kinds of data being hidden behind encryption
provides important clues that they need to stop terrorists the data that they're
able to retrieve out of a cell phone tablet or encrypted message can be
viewed in simple terms and I think that I can give you an inclusive list and
then he lists them so what things can we get out of encryption well he says we
can get where where they have been so the GPS location when they were there so
you know when they were there the timestamp what they what they read
online so the browsing history stuff like that who they've talked to messenger
it telegram email contact lists etc how they've communicated analyzing which
apps they've used and all that stuff and then the contextual conversations of the
email and then they show what files they that they've downloaded onto the device
but you know the one key thing that is missing out of all that stuff that we
could get if we just done away with encryption if we just turned encryption
off and it is an on-off thing and he goes so far to explain to make a real
big point about that that the government keeps saying they want reasonable
encryption there is no such thing as reasonable encryption it's a light
switch the light is either on or the light is off there is no in-between and
if you say if your argument is but but no what they're talking about is they're
saying that they want encryption that's weak enough that the government only can
crack well then it's not encryption that's not actually encrypted if the
government you get into it try and hold the light switch in the middle of the
thing and it's either on or off but what the important thing is even if we do away
with encryption we turn that light switch off you know the one thing we
don't ever get why why did somebody do this why did somebody send this message
why does somebody feel this way and the why is the most important aspect of it
because the why tells you what they're going to do and you know of that so
good I'll say this so this is this is a big problem for open source projects and
I haven't really figured out how to talk about it yet because I don't know how to
talk about it without seeming like I'm I'm like I didn't like I need to get
like a tinfoil hat and need to run around about the sky falling right
because to me I don't I don't I don't understand how the US government is
going to Institute laws about how encryption is implemented that affect
open source projects that are developed all over the world they can't
tributaries yeah I just don't understand how how can open source comply with
anything and and anything anything that the u.s. district just decrees
encryption must follow these these projects are built by people all over
the world yeah and people that largely couldn't care people that largely not
only don't care what the US government thinks yeah but largely want to combat
what the US government thinks and the reason that that encryption exists in
the first place or yeah or have no reason to give a shit
no right yeah yeah but there are other governments that they also might have to
comply with that yeah the opposite well and and if the US government decides it
wants it well then how soon after that does China and Russia you know what all
the other governments want it honestly it doesn't matter if every government in
the world wants it because what you're fundamentally trying to do is put a
genie back in a bottle I mean it is it is it's just this to me seems like the
same argument is when a celebrity has pictures that are leaked and then they
say we want to start taking them down yeah right don't look at them I think
what they're gonna ask for and when I say they I mean the US government is
they're gonna ask for some sort of escrow system where they're not gonna
say give us the keys give us the backdoor put it in an escrow and then
when we have a lawful when we when the FISA court gives us the lawful right to
peak we will go to this escrow and we will activate the backdoor so they'll
go where's my rubber stamp it's around here so oh there it is okay they'll go
to Apple they'll go to Google and they say with your messaging platforms and
they'll eventually go to Telegram and WhatsApp and all of them that they can
and the only the only the systems like wire and signal that are better designed
will be immune from this everything else skype's already a victim will be in
slack I'm sure will be subject to this you know the thing is though the people
that care are going to know I mean it's not gonna be a secret I mean it's a
secret the first time and then after the first person is convicted or or their
messages are decrypted then then the cat's out of the bag and then everyone
that cares about keeping their stuff private it's gonna move to something
else so I don't seem like a one-burn match I would like to hear from somebody
from the mobile room who it may be is even outside the u.s. a bit or inside
the u.s. is fine but you know this is something that's gonna affect the whole
world yeah to make extra one point there though I mean I have no direct
knowledge about this but I mean what the US government or any government can do
right they can enforce what local companies do and so I mean it's not just
about stopping you know well some of in London kind of guys here I mean it's
also about like you know catching white-collar criminals for instance in
in big banks or whatever and of course if you have policies in place that
enforces this bank to for instance provide any encryption key that used to
escrow that means that I can get to you know the email exchanges whatever that's
happened inside that company yeah but I I mean I don't mean to be the cynical
person of the room but to me it seems like anybody who wants to break the law
in any significant way is going to be hip enough to realize they shouldn't use
any system that's been proactively tapped by the US government they'll use
the system outside of that and there will always be system outside of that
and the only people subject to monitoring will be the standards regular
old Joe Schmoes let me pose it let me let me pose it let me pose another
question to you guys the problem one of the problems with giving up encryption
is that if you had a guy and there's the article I'm not coming up with this this
is in the article if a guy goes through an airport and he has caught trying to
bomb that airport and they take him down and they search his person and they
find a camera I don't think anyone in this room would argue that that camera
is not pertinent to the investigation of why this guy was trying to blow up the
airport might contain evidence right we agree on that but the camera might only
contain 30 or 40 pictures when we start talking about they want access to you
know your Google photos we're not talking about the last 30 or 40 pictures
you took you're talking about everything you've ever done the entire scope of
your life when you're talking about the phone right you're talking about every
Wi-Fi exact point exactly and so and so who thinks that who out there legitimately
thinks that any government has the right that once you commit one crime because
of that one and actually really you're accused of committing a single crime why
who out there actually believes that the government should get unfettered access
to every your entire digital life which is more and more of our actual lives
these days who actually thinks that's fair I would say it's it's a bigger
problem than that though because we can all decide as as a democracy and the
Republic of the United States we can all decide that's fine the land of the brave
and the free that we want to be screened we want our devices scanned we want
everything downloaded that is totally fine and 100% as a democracy we've
decided it's great I'm talking like in the future we've decided we are going to
trade all of our freedoms for security the thing is that doesn't necessarily
mean that the citizens of Canada want to live that way right and the problem that
open source has to address here is how do we serve a market as huge as the
United States that has all of these fuck crazy laws that are essentially 1984
draconian laws that the rest of the world except for Iran and Russia and
Syria those countries have these laws in place but outside of that nobody no
others no other modern democracy has these kinds of laws in place so how do
we serve the United States and everywhere else and I don't understand
how you're gonna have people that can contribute to one common code base that
have significantly different laws that they have to adhere to can work
together I don't understand how you can ship one distribution for the US and one
distribution for Canada when we have significantly different encryption laws
that fundamentally mean back doors into encryption versus no back doors I mean
Chris it's really easy you just have a setting in the settings you flip a
switch yeah totally crappy encryption we can have a dashboard American week
encryption and world encryption the solution is obviously turning all the
US laws into internet laws and everybody has to associate to the right and we'll
all go by UTC right well that's the one logical thing I've heard in this
conversation but no you know it's it's going to be something interesting
because this to me seems like it's largely one of those things that is is a
driving force in one direction I I very seldom see anyone the government
reversing its opinion and suddenly deciding well actually you know we're
not going to push to to try and break encryption and the one thing that we
have working in our favor is this is the one time when market reality and social
reality doesn't really mean anything we're really it's about the technical
advantages that's really what matters so I actually a funny thing about the one
of the recent releases from from the current government is that they they are
saying that they're kind of pulling back on not wanting the encryption broken but
you know just just make copies of everything so we can look at them later
yeah yeah well it's like I said it's one of those things that I think as long as
we have the technical superior order superiority in our corner I think we're
gonna be sitting good hey guys thanks so much for joining us for this episode
really appreciated letting me guest host with you that'll put this episode of
Linux unplugged in the books you can follow us on Twitter at Westpane at
Chris LAS follow the network at JB live I'm at the Colonel Linux and of course
at Rekai LP oh there's a message coming out there we go there's telegram okay
thanks so much make sure hey check out Jupiter broadcasting comm you'll find
the schedule for the show as well as all of the show times check me out ask Noah
show calm and we'll see you next week
negative in the freedom dimension
something tells me you like having the ability to scream like a madman without
it actually winding up in a recording that matters long into the outro before
I've never heard it I felt like I was just jiving with it it was what did you
say was yeah that was did I play the wrong one no I'm just that we just never
we cut it off before that sometimes I just hard cut it you know we all really
oh you don't want that nice grad that's such a good fade it's good though it's
good right I mean I did originally and I didn't originally build that fade to
just let it play out but yeah you know in the last 30 weeks or so I we've
started we just can't shut up because everything's too much fun that's what
the thing is yeah not only did I not only did I let it play out then I gave
it a good like one or two seconds before I started talking so we're Kai has a
nice tape cut point all right so we got to pick a title we got to pick oh yeah
I haven't participated in this process in a long time I'm gonna do this okay
the process is kind of a convoluted now no you just always it really you well
you go to the discord you search for your bang suggest so you can't do it's
not JB titles anymore I'm sorry you can go to both oh you can do both okay so
you got to search the search them you guys search the discord okay bang
suggest because you can just it turns out a discord has a great search so you
just search for bang suggest and you just see all of them in one result and
then JB titles for you know like the bot action I'm not liking these titles yeah
well what do you think we should go with what anybody like Dora quantum leap hmm
that's not bad but that was a very small part of the total thank you Christian
for joining us that's the combo thing I don't know if there was a was there a
big part of the show hey before we get out of the post show I because I wanted
to mention in the main show that Dan here from elementary OS was just
recently over on late night Linux had a great interview they gave him a few hard
questions and he was he had some great answers so if you want to hear Dan have
to answer some tough questions go check out late night Linux do you remember
what episode number was Dan that's a great yeah you know I'm gonna do Dan is
what I'm gonna do is why you and I look it up is I'm just gonna fill a little
bit of air time and by doing so I'm just gonna sit here and talk for a few
moments because what you want to do right is you want to Google it real
quick episode 24 everyone yeah episode 24 of late night Linux has this here Dan
the rabbit in there and he answers the hard questions about elementary OS that
have been on your mind by the way we forgot something for the Mozilla review
there's a new chapter in the book of Mozilla right now with the quantum
release it's now chapter 11 colon 14 you know the story about that well chapter
11 here in the United States I think means you open the Mozilla browser and
you're typing about colon Mozilla and you will get a chapter which normally
tells you about to release and the time of the release so if you have version 16
it's starts with the twins of Memon quarreled and now with version with the
new version the book of Mozilla is 11 colon 14 which started the Beast adopted
new Raymond and studied the ways of time and space and I didn't it goes on like
that whoa it's some kind of Easter egg it's some kind of Easter egg hey guys
hey guys Jordan Jordanism from the chat room suggested member when JB cared about
IRC that really seems like that'd be appropriate for the title don't you
think that seems like that'd be a really fucking good title for this episode I
think I think it really exemplifies what happened in the episode I think we
talked about it a lot throughout the episode there was a lot of good
discussion really respectful for all of the work that one two three four five
six seven eight nine ten eleven twelve thirty forty fifteen sixteen people put
into this week's episode and all the topics we covered yeah that's really
that's great that's thank you Jordan thank you I wanted to kick Chris's
nostalgia a little bit you'd mentioned open CC in the box it actually didn't
come with one book it came with two so it came with the user manual I don't
remember when they started doing this but they put a second book in there with
all the printed man pages that's what it was I couldn't remember I thought so
good good memory good recollection do you have like a box around it have you
looked at a box recently how did you remember that oh I I don't have my box
anymore and that's depressing I threw it away oh that's sad yeah so she said
well yeah man printed man pages that sounds really nice though just keep it
right on your desk thumb through it totally searchable I love it well okay
so we got a title this thing we got it we got to get a name for this thing
because this is this is going off the rails I got a real I got a real crash
course and installing applications fedora oh yeah we should talk about that
the beard had to install a few apps on the door for the show today we didn't
even get to that a lot less fedora than I expected I I installed apps we have
five different methods or attempted to anyway you first you have the the normal
DNA software oh okay and you didn't go gooey first who was gooey for installing
software people that like to install software these it's for people who like
to mess with the computer pretty easy and plus the other thing is three of the
methods don't have ways to do it via the software okay I was pleased that slack
had an rpm I could easily install that was nice yeah okay the second thing I
tried and this was actually pretty easy to get chrome installed you just add the
third-party chrome repo from Google are you telling me they have a repo for
fedora yeah that's they did the same thing for Debbie and as well I gotta be
honest with you I'm sorry you guys but Firefox yeah the third method which I
managed to get nothing installed via is copper okay that was no good no the
fourth method was enabling rpm fusion that was to get telegram installed mm-hmm
oh nice method because I could not get discord via rpm fusion or copper was
that I also had to use flatbacks oh my god I enabled a flat hub and I install
that via the software stuff okay so okay so let's back up for a second so what
did you say before discord what did you install before tell good how did so how
did the telegram thing go down how does that work so did you what did you do to
get telegram working rpm fusion so you added a repo yes so you did like a DNF
command use there's a DNF commands yeah and then did you install it via the
command line or did you install via the software center command line okay and
then the last thing you installed was discord and you installed that via
flatpak but you added a repo for flatpak yeah I enabled a flat hub and
did you install it then after that via the command line or if we had known
software known software interesting so it now it just shows I actually couldn't
figure out how to install via the command so you added the flatpak repo
and then you you open gnome software and you searched for discord and then
discord showed up it told me that the source was flab oh interesting in when
you want to install flat pack flat pack from the the command line you also have
to include the repo in the flat pack command yeah yeah yeah I'm not a big fan
of that it's a little convoluted but yeah that seems counterintuitive like I
already added the repo why is it not just searching the enabled repos yeah
welcome to PPAs yeah mm-hmm yeah I know this is this is so this is PPAs don't
require you to tell the prepo after you haven't installed though so no but you
do have to do an update right so you add the PPA you add the key when you add
it and then you have to do an apt update and then you have to do that then you do
the install it feels a lot like PPA yeah but with flatpaks you have to every
time you install the app you have to specify the repo URL that's true yeah
that's true yeah everyone should use a UI anyway that's how we designed it say
again everyone should use gnome software I mean that's a whole point here to move
away from needing command line tools it definitely it definitely does feel like
that like the whole thing is pretty straightforward install the repo there
right well that's true yeah adding the repo you still drop to the command line
yeah I the reason I tried to do every the command line was because I was
already on the command line to add the repo I don't think there is a way in
gnome software to add it through and add it add a flat hub anyway yeah that does
seem like something that needs to get I guess that does feel like a feature that
needs to be added because it'd be nice yeah yeah I actually want one thing
we're looking to do there actually subject is we are going to start
pre-populating this database with various repos so that so the setup will
be that when you start fedora since it's meant to be all free software you'll
better get a question as part of the initial setup saying hey do you want to
enable third-party repositories and if you say yes a lot of these things like
chrome and and steam and nvidia driver and and and so on will just be
pre-populated for you to download that's wonderful hmm yeah I I when I they it
seems like it seems like a decent solution like I the more I the more I
see distributions implementing flat pack the more I see how it really does make
sense for a lot of different yeah different uses for open source software
yeah I think if I do use fedora in the future I'm gonna start with flat hub
yes yes exactly that's what I would do too now because it seems like it has
most of what I wanted like I actually just searched telegram and gnome
software and now there's two different versions I have one from flat hub and
one from yeah our people and then you could and then the fact is you can still
get snaps working on there too so that kind of covers some of the other space
and then it's like well what do you have left that isn't covered by those two
things and the list well but thankfully they package it for the distro you want
yeah I mean they're doing that work now right yeah I can see if one of these
things takes off either way that I could see Google changing that if if fedora
supported both snap and flat back then that would solve most of the issues of
packaging entirely mm-hmm and I'll use app image for everything else