This is Linux Unplugged Episode 72 for December 23rd, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's already tracking Santa's
sleigh.
My name is Chris and we have something kind of special for you this week.
It's a little different.
It's a first for a lot of our shows on the network.
This week we're playing some of the audience's favorite moments as submitted by you.
So if it's a train wreck, I'm officially transferring all blame to those of you, no I'm kidding.
No, actually it's gone through some of our favorite moments and to be honest, on the
Linux Unplugged show, it's just the way it goes you guys.
Some of those, they're rants.
A lot of great rants though, at least I happen to think so.
And they inspired a lot of, I think, really good reflection and discussion.
That's what I think Linux Unplugged oftentimes is all about.
And so this week we're going to go in and look at some of those moments and other moments
that you submitted into the show.
In fact, it's, there's a lot, it's dense, there's a lot to get into.
So in fact, so that way I don't have to interrupt, I will be joining you from time to time, moments
throughout the show.
Chris will come in and spend a holiday moment with you.
But to kind of clear the air, get us ready for it, I think I'm going to thank our first
sponsor this week.
You guys know them, you guys love them.
That's the amazing folks over at Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com.
That's going to get you not only a $25 discount off your first Ting device, but a little feather
in your cap for supporting the Linux Unplugged show, linux.ting.com.
Ting is mobile that makes sense.
Ting is my mobile service provider.
And as I sit here and take a holiday sip from a holiday beverage and reflect on the things
that I do feel very thankful for, Ting is one of them.
I'm coming in now on two years of Ting service.
You can get started by going to linux.ting.com.
No more contract.
No more termination fee.
No more scams.
No more getting you to pay for data that you may or may not use, or a certain amount of
text messages you may or may not use.
Just pay for what you actually end up using.
That's how Ting works.
Ting takes your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes.
They add them all up at the end of the month, whatever buckets you fall into, that's all
you got to pay.
You want to turn on hotspot, you want to tether that, then just pay for the data.
You don't have to be in some sort of special plan.
And Ting has no hold customer service.
I don't need it.
To be honest, I've never had to call them.
I take advantage of their incredible dashboard.
But if I have friends and family, I absolutely let them know, you know what, you can call
Ting and they'll answer your tough questions.
They hire the Android geeks, give them the ability to solve your problem, give them the
authority to resolve any kind of account issue, and then they have them answer the phone when
it rings.
I know.
It's a crazy concept.
Linux.Ting.com.
They have that powerful online control panel where you can take control of your account,
turn things on and off as you need them.
It's really impressive.
And one of the things you may have heard about is Ting is expanding into GSM next year.
They're going to have CDMA and GSM coverage.
And they posted up a video where they talked to one of their executives about that.
So I'm going to play it for you.
Dean asks, I've been happy since my switch to Ting a year ago.
Any chance that Ting will offer GSM service besides CDMA?
I'm sure you've seen by now that we are actually offering GSM service in addition to Sprint.
There are two great things that that gives us.
First, it gives people access to a wider variety of phones that they may already own or get
in the secondary market.
Second, probably a little more specifically, it does now mean that you can go down to the
Apple store, buy an unlocked iPhone, new iPhone 6, 6 Plus, grab a SIM from us, pop it in and
use Ting.
And for a lot of people, that's been a real limitation.
You know, I do think it's worth noting that this is and not or.
And we're thrilled to be able to offer multiple networks.
Linux.ting.com, mobile didn't make sense.
Thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show.
They're also getting into fiber internet to change up landlines.
Love Ting.
And I think you should go check them out.
Start saving right now.
And they have a special $100 and 50 bones credit if you have to cancel a line that has an early
termination on it.
No more ETS with Ting, linux.ting.com.
And a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show.
Well, SystemD sure came up a lot this year, didn't it?
And there was a lot of different discussions on the Linux Unplugged show, but we figured
we've got to touch on it once officially to market for 2014.
So this is one of the highest submitted discussions around SystemD.
Enjoy.
Did you guys see the roll up your sleeves, we may need to fork Debian site.
Did you guys catch this?
Oh boy.
And I'll just read the first paragraph here.
We are veteran, which is bolded by the way, veteran Unix admins, and we are concerned
about what's happening to GNU slash Linux Debian edition, and they're considering forking
the project.
I want to stop right here.
I think that's a great idea.
I think fork it.
Like instead of delaying the progress of the distribution or the direction, fork it and
go your own way.
That actually seems like the right approach to take, especially if you're never going
to be satisfied with the SystemD version of Debian.
That seems like a pretty reasonable response, and I hope they do.
I think the competition would be good.
The thing that I can't get past, and it seems like a lot of other people have picked up
on it, is the language used there.
Veteran Unix admins and bolded.
What that does is sort of projects old farts, and I'm not trying to be derogatory, I'm just
saying like from a messaging standpoint, people are saying that makes you sound like a bunch
of old farts, and then people sort of write it off.
What do they care?
A bunch of stick in the muds.
And it immediately makes people not take it very seriously.
Well looking at it from my perspective, I think it's a combination of quote-unquote
old farts as well as people that are of the mind that if it isn't broke, why fix it, at
least from their perspective.
And so you might have an inner mixture of individuals in that space.
Wimpy, do you think they're just crazy?
Well they're exercising their right to free speech and all power to their elbow and everything,
and if they want to have a go at forking Debbie in, then I think everyone should just stand
back and let them get on with it and let themselves burn themselves out trying.
Let's just take those two words together.
Fork Debbie in, okay?
Forking is hard.
I have first-hand experience of forking really small projects in the comparison with Debbie
in.
So they want to fork Debbie in.
Just think about all of the infrastructure that's involved there and all of the platforms
and everything.
It's just crazy nonsense.
And Ian Jackson's obviously got an opinion about this, and he posted his thing to the
mailing list to suggest that this was evaluated one last time, very expressly stating he didn't
want to turn this into a system D versus whatever in its system debate.
And then the internet explodes with system D inferno again.
This is so disappointing.
It's just laughable.
And if they want to fork Debbie in, yeah, go on, do that thing.
I'm all for it.
I'm going to watch that gleefully from afar.
Yeah, I would be pretty skeptical myself.
And Valt, you think, no, no, don't fork.
Don't do that.
We need more resources as it is, not less people working on the same stuff.
Well, that's obviously my actual practical point is, no, don't fork it.
Find a way to accommodate multiple-init systems in Debbie in.
I'm starting to change now.
But if you want to fork Debbie in, yeah, go on, do it.
But they're never going to be interested in being involved with the project in that state,
then they should just fork it.
You're not really losing resources because if they weren't going to cooperate anyways,
you're not losing them.
They're already lost.
So let them go off and do their own thing.
Well, no, the thing is, is that, no, well, yeah, okay, if they want to fork Debbie in,
fork Debbie in.
But there's system BSD, there's useless D, there are shims around system D. If they were
really serious about coming up with an alternative, they would be looking at those projects in
terms of developing them and supporting them within the Debbie in community rather than
saying we're going to fork Debbie in, which is frankly insane.
Well, yeah, you're talking the biggest distribution there is, the mother of most of our distributions.
Yeah.
That's a huge undertaking if you're even thinking about that.
Would you do a complete fork or would it be more like sort of a clone of straight up Debbie
in where you're just constantly swapping out the system D parts for something else?
Well, one thing that comes to mind that I want to point out here is that now, last time
I checked, most computers with blogging platforms attached don't have breathalyzers ready.
So it's entirely possible they were fit-shaped and they got on and yeah, Debbie, baby, baby.
No, I'll tell you, I'll tell you who's a little S-faced.
How about this one?
Fork fedora.org.
Shall we fork fedora?
Oh, that's brilliant.
And then here's the next one.
Not really.
It's doing great.
Maybe we're not veteran enough.
That's great.
That's really good.
That is fantastic.
That's the best response.
They sound like they're really housed.
You know what?
Yeah.
They're really housed, right?
I would like to buy a beer for those guys.
I've already verified this is a factual thing.
Yeah.
No, Matt did prove that.
He did actually later up on G+.
All of my 10 people on the whole internet, but still we exist.
Yeah.
That actually is getting housed as a term.
It's like got a ridiculous origin though or something.
I don't remember.
Yeah.
It's abbreviated from, you know, the other word.
So, okay.
But this fork business, like shall we fork fedora, time to fork Debian.
I've never.
Well, actually we have.
The only time I think we've ever seen the Linux community this riled up and just unable
to just move forward for a long time was like the Microsoft Novell deal where you had boycott
Novell prop up and you had all this stuff and there was such decisive lines and it went
on for like two years, but really not, I mean, you know, it was, it was not as bad for two
years, but it really went on for a while.
And this is like, we haven't had a good old classic drama like this since then.
It's like the good old days again.
Oh, I remember the old Novell thing and I'm sitting there going thinking, that's great.
I'm going to go watch TV now cause I'm just like, this is going to be a week long thing
and people are going to blow it over.
Yeah.
That still cracks me up.
Just all right.
Wimpy.
Go ahead.
Ask the questions on everybody's mind.
Well, I'm putting myself out there again as the, as the bloke that says, you know, system
D is really quite good.
But I, I often wonder reading what some of the people say about system D and also listening
to other podcasts and what they have to say about system D and I'm left with the impression
of you've never actually used it.
Not only have you never actually used it, you've never actually sat down and written
a unit file.
You're not a package maintainer.
You haven't had to deal with init scripts and you haven't seen the benefits of migrating
a package from an init script to system D and, and the many other benefits of system
D. Now I can appreciate that people are very, very firm in their opinion that they like
the way things are and there's a place for that, but I think a lot of the speculation
and commentary about system D is being had by people who simply do not know what they're
talking about.
So I'm not suggesting necessarily that fork Debian falls into this camp.
They would claim to be seasoned Linux administrators and Debian veterans quite.
So maybe they do know what they're talking about and they have legitimate reasons as
to why they feel system D is not going to suit them.
But there are some podcasts where I've heard them debating the various init systems and
talking about the pros and cons and then admitting partway through their, you know, slagging
off of system D, they've never used it and you just think, well, how are you qualified
to have an opinion?
So my stance on the system D discussion, I think if you look over the history of this
show has an arc where I'm pretty neutral, don't give a crap, and then I become pretty
pro system D.
And then I get to a point where I was a little belligerent to people who didn't, who didn't
seem to think going forward with system D was a good idea because the reason I've, I
don't know if belligerence is the right word, but I'll just label it that.
The reason why I felt that way is because as a sys admin of like 14, 15 years, there
are literally things that I see in system D that I think if I had that when I was managing
servers, I would have hated my job so much less.
Like it's not just small stuff that I see in system D. Some of the things that system
D brings as a whole, I see as fundamentally necessary for Linux to remain competitive
at scale.
Like without those things and with and without those things, FreeBSD could easily eat our
lunch really because essentially we're, we're, we're just as capable and, but system D offers
so many things and the problem is you really don't know how important they are until you've
deployed Linux at scale or you have a, a, you know, a very network demanding thing or
you have something that has to be as absolutely minimal as possible and support socket activation
or you need something that's integrated with namespaces.
All these things that are edge cases, but together matter so much and may, and are so
important to keeping Linux competitive, not just on the server, but also in mobile.
That when you, when you come, when you argue against system D, what you have to realize
is you have to really come with something that's extremely compelling because what you
are arguing for is essentially removing what I, in, in my personal opinion, and I'm not
saying it's right, but in my personal opinion are fundamentally critical features to keep
Linux competitive.
So if you're going to say no system D, you've got to have an answer for those problems.
And yeah, I don't think you and I can have a debate about this because I think we're
clearly on the same side of the fence and we've got, we've got our personal opinions.
It sounds like the largely similar reasons.
So really what we need is somebody to step up and tell us why we're wrong.
And I, I, I think part of is some of the more vocal people debating this are not the same
people who are as impacted by it.
Like I think there's a group of people that care a lot, but they're just not as vocal
about debating it.
I think I'm trying to, cause I get emails that seem really well reasoned, but I, even
then I've still not been convinced.
The biggest things that convinced me that it might be a problem are always the what
if scenarios.
And I think, yeah, if that happens, we could have a problem, but that's not a today problem.
That's a what if problem.
Quite.
Anyways, so how do we get talking about, oh yeah, the forks.
Yeah.
The system D conversation once again has been stirred back up by these project forks.
And you know what's interesting is you check the Linux forums like r slash Linux and just
general discussion forums and people are constantly still asking about it.
It is genuinely a topic that even though it seems like we've talked about it ad nauseum,
people still seem to care about.
I guess that's sort of the fun of being a Linux user is you get to care about such nitty
gritty things like your display compositor and system D and all that stuff.
So I guess that's why we do it.
And that concludes the system D portion of this show.
However, something does tell me we'll probably still be talking about system D in 2015.
I can't help myself and it's obviously a huge area of interest for the Linux community.
2015 is going to be a big year for system D. 2015 is also going to be a big year for
our sponsor, DigitalOcean, and I mean that.
They have some very impressive stuff in the works that you guys are going to find out
about very soon.
Head over to digitalocean.com right now.
Check them out.
Give them a ding for that.
DigitalOcean and use our special promo code, UNPLUGGEDDECEMBER, while you're over there.
UNPLUGGEDDECEMBER.
Remember, that's our promo code of domination.
UNPLUGGEDDECEMBER when you check out.
That'll give you a $10 credit and you'll see why you want that, but first, let me back
up a bit.
I feel perhaps I have gone too fast for you.
I want to slow down and treat it right and tell you about DigitalOcean, a simple cloud
hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to spin
up a cloud server up in the cloud, my friends, with root access and unbelievable speeds.
And speaking of speeds, you can actually get the cloud server created in less than a minute
and pricing plans start at only $5 per month.
Remember that promo code?
The promo code of domination.
UNPLUGGEDDECEMBER.
Remember that?
Well, that's going to get you a $10 credit.
Well, I just said it's $5 for one of their rigs, 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte
SSD, one CPU, and a freaking terabyte of transfer, my friends.
A terabyte.
That's a lot of Christmas movies.
Or something else.
I don't know.
I don't judge.
Honey badger over here.
What's great is DigitalOcean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore,
Amsterdam, and London.
So you're going to get a data center somewhere that makes you look like a boss, or you could
diversify your regionalness with that.
I think it's pretty great.
But really, what's great is that interface.
DigitalOcean has the most intuitive control panel for managing something like this.
I wouldn't have thought it could be done.
It really is great.
And power users can replicate the control panel, the functionality, on a much, much
larger scale with DigitalOcean's straightforward API that I'm told is gorgeous.
And I've recently been checking out some of the applications that take advantage of that
API.
Like Swimmer.
Yeah, it's called Swimmer.
A full featured open source Android client for DigitalOcean.
Look at this thing.
It's open source.
It's up on GitHub right now.
You can check it out.
And this allows you to manage your DigitalOcean droplets.
You can SSH into the droplet, reboot, power cycle, shut down, resize the droplet, snapshot
it, rebuild it, turn backups on, create a droplet from your phone.
Amazing.
Look at all the options you have with this thing.
This is what's so cool about DigitalOcean's API, and because it's so great, developers
are excited to use it.
And now you can go take advantage of something like this, like an open source Android app
so you can even trust it.
That's so awesome.
DigitalOcean.com, and use our promo code UNPLUG DECEMBER, the promo code of domination, to
get a $10 credit when you check out.
Try out that $5 rig.
Go deploy GitLab.
Go deploy Ruby on Rails, WordPress, Ghost with one click.
Man, that is so slick.
I really think that's it.
It's such an impressive setup.
And the one click installation, you combine that with the spin of time, and you can really
get hauling fast.
DigitalOcean.com, Unplug December when you check out.
And a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
You guys, I'm looking forward to 2015.
I know you guys have something.
I can't even say.
I can't even say, but let's just say I know some things, and I'm really impressed with
what I know.
Up next, though, is an interview with a talks developer.
This was sent in by quite a bit of you.
Encrypted messaging space is something I'm following really closely myself.
I find it to be a fascinating field with a lot of cool things happening right now, but
not one that I've really zoned in on as my go-to messaging platform.
So when we had this chance to interview a talks developer, I was really interested in
what they had to say.
I hope you will be, too.
Enjoy.
So I want to welcome two developers from the talks project onto the show.
Joining us on Mumble right now, we have STQ and I run Gentoo.
So I know talks started up as sort of a discussion thread, and I'm told I think it started on
4chan.
And now here we are.
We're what, seven, eight months down the road?
It's become a very active project.
So where is it at from where it started versus where it's at today?
Well, talks started as, well, I actually, I had this idea, this very basic idea, and
then, well, I was on a thread, on a G, that was speaking about how Skype is, well, privacy
issues with Skype.
So, well, I had just, well, I just decided, okay, hey, let's, I was actually a bit maybe
drunk at the moment or something, and I said, okay, let's make a Skype replacement.
So that's how it started.
And then, well, I was very impressed by the positive response from everyone.
So I said, okay, let's start writing code, let's start planning stuff, and that's how
talks started.
So it started kind of as a crazy idea that maybe after you thought about it for a little
bit realized, this could be a good idea.
Have you worked on this kind of stuff before or something like this before?
Well, I played around with some BitTorrent DHT.
I did a couple of scripts to, like, I once made a script to find out which, to try to
track everything on the BitTorrent DHT, but, well, there were some little bandwidth issues.
I would have needed a big server and something, so the idea kind of died, but that gave me
a bit of experience on, like, how peer-to-peer software works and everything, so that's how
...
Yeah.
Well, can you tell me a little bit about, and I guess it's actually pronounced salt,
but the networking and cryptography library that talks is sitting on primarily.
Is this the big piece of functionality here?
What does this component play?
What role does that play?
Well, that's the... Seriously, I like that crypto.
I love that crypto library.
It's very simple to use and everything, and it's very secure.
I don't think talks would have worked without it since, well, when talks started, we didn't
know what crypto library would use.
Right.
That seems like a huge choice to make, right?
Yeah, but then someone suggested it in a thread, and then I looked at it, and I just saw this
is perfect.
It's simple to use.
It's fast.
It's very secure.
It protects against all types of timing attacks, et cetera, so we picked that, and I started
reading a lot, okay, so how do I implement this correctly in talks without screwing up
things?
Right.
That was my question, because I've heard that I think also the Telegram Messenger program
uses the salt library, but I guess they maybe... I don't know the details, but I guess
they've implemented it incorrectly.
Have you looked at that situation and tried to kind of balance what they did wrong and
adjust accordingly for talks?
Telegram, they don't use the salt library.
They use their custom crypto implementation.
If they would have used the salt library, their crypto would have been fine.
Nobody would be complaining about it.
Right.
Gotcha.
So something that seemed kind of like a big deal, you guys got accepted, the talks project
got accepted into the Google Summer of Code, but you know a lot of people have asked is
that going to influence the project in any way?
What about their independence?
What are your thoughts on the Summer of Code and what it means for that aspect of the project?
I'll go ahead and answer this.
Sure.
Well, I think with Google Summer of Code, we're really going to be able to finish a
lot of things that we wouldn't have the time to do that due to our prior commitments we
would never be able to do.
We would be able to have people who have different skill sets in areas we might not have.
It would be able to help out that way.
Okay.
So what about this criticism that people have said, oh, well, this is a bad sign.
This is about influence.
What do you think of that?
Has there been communications from Google about suggestions or anything like that?
No, they don't do anything like that.
They exist purely to foster the development of open source projects.
No secret influences, no link to this secret library, nothing like that.
No insert go to fail line here.
That's good considering that there's a lot of hopes riding on a secure messenger and
I got to tell you guys, this is a pretty contested space right now.
So I think people are looking for a lot of things to pull out to kind of criticize on.
And to that end, I don't really know if there is something to be worried about here, but
a lot of people have criticized that they started as a threat on 4chan.
Have you guys dealt with growing pains as a result of that?
Well, we didn't start like that, but as we developed, we got people with skill sets from
Reddit and all these areas and sort of nurtured.
That's exactly, I mean, so when I, I mean, not to interrupt, I'm sorry, but when I, when
I, so I've seen this question, it was sent into our show a few times and to me it just
seems like these are locations that technical people hang out.
True, so 4chan specifically, that little area is a lot of trolling.
I think it was pure luck that the people who we have now, that all the skills matched up
just perfectly.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, I, and I, and I know, I know it's something that's on people's radar and it maybe seems
like one of those things down the road.
It probably, it, it probably won't be as big of a factor, but what are any other growing
pains you guys are seeing as the project is becoming more aware?
People are becoming more aware of it?
Not really.
Well, there's always a bit of issues, but we can, we, we've dealt with them and it's
good.
Well, okay.
So now that's the big picture stuff.
I want to talk a little bit about maybe features and stuff that talks is hoping to support
down the road.
What are your plans for, three, there's three major things I've seen requests from the audience.
Uh, conference call setups.
You guys have any plans to do things like group calls and things like that down the
road?
Yes.
Okay, good.
What about multiple presence?
As in I can be logged in on a, on, on multiple computers and the message goes to all locations
or maybe I'm on my, I'm on my Android phone and I'm also on my laptop and I want my messages
and calls to go to both locations.
Is that possible with the security model you're using now?
You know, we haven't worked out something like that just yet.
We're still working on a lot of our group chats, how we can do audio and video, how
we can do things like that, but when the time comes, I know we'll be able to reach that
area.
Yeah, it's a, it's possible, but, uh, it's a later after, after we've done the TCP stuff,
after we've done the, the group chats and the work and yeah.
Is that how you're focusing right now?
It seems like the talks clients that I've tried are all text chat based to get that
working and then as the plan to then to get the next set of functionality working and
then the next.
Yeah, it's a, it's how, uh, well, I think it's the best way to develop software to do,
make a feature, test it correctly, add another, add another and, uh, that's a.
So what's on your immediate list and then what's on your sort of, after I get this next
immediate problem solved, after I get this thing that's bugging me fixed, I really want
to start working on.
So what are those two things?
Well, we have first the, the thing that I want to finish first, well, that I'm working
on right now is, uh, the TCP, uh, TCP stuff so that, uh, I want to add a TCP relay functionality
to talks, uh, nodes so that, uh, people that are behind bad knots and, uh, can, uh, can
also use talks currently talks on the works people with that can a whole bunch through
their knots.
Okay.
But that's not everyone.
Yeah.
Some people are behind enterprise knots, some symmetric knots that are weird and on and
block certain, uh, like, yeah, they only have a maximum number of UDP connections that can,
well, that can be a problem because well, tax needs to connect to a bunch of people
for discovery.
Yeah.
So, okay.
I look at this and I think if talks was really successful, I, if, if you could truly create
a Skype replacement that was secure, you would have a system that would be used by, by journalists,
by dissidents, by the paranoid and by cheaters.
And, uh, it would be this, these groups of people would fundamentally rely on this technology
to be absolutely iron clad solid.
Have you considered code audits and, and maybe you add a certain like quote unquote official
release point saying we're going to audit the code, have a third party look at the code?
Well, yes, of course, but we want to wait till a lot of our major features are done.
And talking about what you mentioned earlier, we're designing talks to be something that
everyone can use someone talking, someone somewhere.
I have no idea what I'm saying right now, but long story short, we want to design something
that's so fast, so easy, so smooth that people would use it instead of Skype.
I mean, we're not going to truly accomplish our goal unless everyone's using this, unless
there's nothing that can be spied on, nothing that can be new.
Maybe it's not a selling point for end users, but we want to give it to everyone.
That's an interesting way to put it.
I mean, it's definitely is.
It's definitely for some, but yeah, you're right for the general user, it's not really,
it's not really a big deal.
Uh, you know, the only really other question I had sent in from the audience that was kind
of kicking around is, uh, how do you guys plan to make money and are you going to take
donations?
No, we might take donations and so Gentoo's been talking about it a bit, but right now
all of our expenses, our build systems, everything comes out of my own pocket and I haven't really
been taking anything in.
Well, you're a good man, SDQ.
So have you considered like a donation system or like a Kickstarter system or something
like that?
Um, can you repeat the question?
I couldn't hear you.
Are you thinking about, are you guys?
Cause the reason I'm asking is we had a few people send in like long play wrote in and
asked if, uh, you guys would, he wants to send you money, but he couldn't find a way
to donate.
Are you considering doing a donation model?
We might put a donation button on the website because the reason I didn't want donations
to, well, us accepting donations at the beginning is, well, what if, uh, we just started and
then everything fails and well, people are going to be angry and everything.
But well, we've, uh, we've gone a long way from there.
So we might, uh, yeah, that's good.
It's good.
Yeah.
You want to make sure you got something that, uh, you can, you can show for before you ask
people to start taking money.
Well, also I'll open it up to the mumble room and see if there's any questions that the
group has.
Um, and you guys, if you do just ping me in the chat room with any questions you have
for the folks and we'll, we'll get through those.
In the chat room, I'm also checking your questions as, as we go, but, uh, guys, I want to thank
you for coming on Linux Unplugged.
As this project I'm going to be watching, you know, I'm, I'm still really interested
in picking the mobile messenger of the future.
And right now the Jupiter Broadcasting Network really kind of uses Skype a lot for our shows
because at the end of the day, it seems to be the, the sort of the best combination of
deployment and ease of use and actual video and audio quality simultaneously.
I'm really excited about the talks project.
We talked about it a little bit this last Sunday on the Linux Action Show and I demoed
a couple of different apps you can use for it.
It's early days right now, uh, but, uh, I, I, I want to encourage you guys to keep going
at it, keep working at it because this is a space that people are going to be more and
more interested over the, uh, the next couple of years.
Crossroads asks, uh, how does this compare to other chat programs, e.g. BT Chat or Tor
Chat?
And actually that's a great question.
Have you guys seen the announcement of Tor Chat and what are your thoughts on that versus
talks?
Well, Tor Chat is, uh, they're going more on the anonymous, uh, well, they want to make
an anonymous chat, but, uh, talks is, uh, isn't anonymous.
You connect directly to the people you're speaking to because, uh, we want performance
because, well, streaming, uh, high resolution video through Tor is, well, doesn't really
work well.
That's true, right?
Yeah.
That's a great point.
I hadn't thought about the video aspect of it.
And to reiterate further.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
I mean, we're trying to design something that everyone can use, not just the paranoid.
Well, and, and to that end, is that why, I mean, I'm seeing a lot of, a lot of different
talks clients.
There's not like one official talks client.
I guess it would be conceivable that you could have chat programs like Pidgin out there and
others that support talks and Tor Chat at the same time.
Right?
Yeah.
Pidgin for a, there's a talks plugin in development already.
So it, uh, it already supports talks, but very good.
That's very interesting you guys.
And, uh, I'm glad you're working on this to tell you the truth because, uh, one of my
predictions for, uh, the, the, uh, the Linux action show for 2014 was that there'd be an
explosion in secure messaging.
So you guys are right now confirming my prediction.
So that's awesome for me.
Most definitely.
Yeah.
I know, right?
Uh, so you guys, I know, I know you guys probably are not big fans of giving out timelines,
but do you have a general big picture timeline or roadmap of when features will roll out
or be available?
I can tell you the, well, the order at which we're going to roll them out, but timelines
are a bit, uh, I'll take that.
I'll take order of you that you want to roll things out for sure.
Well, first of all, we're gonna roll out the TCP relays.
Then after that, we're going to work, uh, on, uh, fixing our group chats and making
audio video work in group chats.
And well, that's the two main, that should take a while because they're, they're two
very big, uh, features that they're going to need lots of testing and everything.
And after that, we're going to concentrate on, well, whatever, uh, well, maybe optimizing
code or, uh, trying to implement other features like offline messaging and like how someone
who wants to be logged in at two computers that we might, uh, might work on that.
It depends on what we feel people want the most.
What they're asking for.
Yeah.
Well, let me ask you this.
What if somebody, Daredevilin is making a great question, making a great point in our
chat room.
What if, what if you, uh, were, uh, you wake up one day, you go to slash dot or tech meme
or Reddit or whatever, and you see a top headline, new secure messenger launched available
on Android, iOS, and the desktop, um, it's, it's awesome.
It's rock solid.
And you dig through it.
And when you see they're charging, they're charging for the app and then you'd read through
the details and you realize, holy crap, they're using talks.
How do you feel about people creating clients or potentially business models on top of a
system that you're building today?
Well, the core is licensed under the GPL v3, so they can't take the code and not give the
source back.
So well, if someone does take it and improves their source and if they make money, I don't
care if they, because they're improving the software.
So Daredevilin, I didn't realize you were in here.
Go ahead.
And did you have more you wanted to add to that?
Daredevilin?
No.
Sorry.
I'm here.
Can you hear me?
Yeah.
So what happened is, uh, the reason I got this question is because, uh, I was wondering
more, uh, I know it's GPL and people are contributing back, but there's kind of business models
that could involve, for example, a company making their own nodes in a way that, um,
will allow them to mimic users.
And I mean, it depends of course on the intrinsic of the project, but then goes to something
that is something a little bit deviated from original thoughts plans.
And it goes like uses talk source code.
It uses all like a Bitcoin's Litecoin, that kind of thing.
Yeah.
Kind of, sorta.
So it will be with some differences that will make more a company driven perspective and
not actually providing the users direct access.
So what are the measures in place for you to incentivize people to just come to your
project instead of just working, doing something crazy that goes completely out of town?
Well, if, if a company does something like that, well, end users actually use the software
from that company.
That means you're doing something good.
So that's a win for you.
Wow.
You can always take the code out and put it in our, in our project.
So Josh, go ahead.
That's a good point.
It's like, okay.
Oh, okay.
I mean, that's an interesting way to think about it.
Yeah.
Like OpenBSD makes FSH and they give it away for people to do whatever they want.
Right.
Great point.
I mean, that's, that's an interesting way to kind of frame that Josh, you had a kind
of a question more about funding, right?
Yes, I did.
So you guys talked about maybe monetizing or accepting donations in the future.
So what is your opinion on allowing, you know, people to back certain features with something
like Bounty Source and allow you guys to get paid to like implement certain features like
group chats and maybe help speed the process along or provide some sort of monetary incentive?
You know, I think something like that really hurts people's trust that something doesn't
need a timeline.
If something looks good, looks like it's easy to do, but it doesn't come up and it ends
up taking a lot longer than it should or something.
People get disappointed.
Hmm.
Well, the main issue is that implementing something is relatively easy.
Implementing something that's bug free and works perfectly, that's, that's hard.
So well, that's, that's, that's an interesting point.
Yeah, you know, yeah, I, it is, so it's something to consider I think because it's really fascinating
to really, it truly tells you what, what people's priorities are when they assign a dollar value
to it in a way that is so much more tangible than, than emails and bug requests and all
these things.
When people are actually willing to put money down for something, then you really know it's,
it's literally of a value to them.
So I, but I do understand you don't want to overset expectations and you guys seem to
be, you know, walking that line pretty closely.
I'm going to take a quick break right here and when we get back, I want to talk a little
bit about maybe your thoughts on the future of mobile for talks, but first I hope you'll
have some time this holiday to visit linuxacademy.com slash unplug so you can take advantage of
our special 33% unplug discount, which is an incredible deal.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
Go check them out right now.
There's never been a better time.
Step-by-step video courses, downloadable comprehensive study guides, bring them offline with you.
This is reading material, but also audio and video material.
You can plug it into your podcast player.
You can learn from the presenters.
They've got great audio setups.
They're genuinely passionate about the topics.
That's what makes them such great educators and you can sit there and absorb it as you
travel as you're in the shower, like spooky sprite comes with your own server too.
So when the courseware requires it, they automatically spin up a server for you on the backend and
all of this, you get to choose from seven plus Linux distributions and have that courseware
and the VMs automatically adjust to match the distribution you've chosen.
You can keep track of your progress as you go and quiz yourself and Linux Academy has
rolled out courses recently on Docker.
Great opportunity to go learn Docker, Vagrant and Puppet and I'm talking about stuff that
takes you from beginner, absolute beginner to professional, ready to be certified.
One of their students recently took the AWS course and I got an email about this.
After the AWS course, he got a certification and he actually went and got a job at Amazon.
It's amazing.
They have a community there that helps kind of bump you.
When you're having sort of a down moment and you're having a hard time motivating, that's
just enough to just give you a little bump to keep you going and the management system
you have when you log into your Linux Academy dashboard is really, really great.
They have something called learning plans too where you can say, okay Linux Academy,
I got this much time this week and then Linux Academy will generate courseware for you based
on your availability, custom tailored to you and it can send you email reminders about
quizzes and stuff.
I mean it's a really good way to adapt the program to you to match your ebb and flows
of availability.
It's life.
We all have it and you can get started by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Also a lot of great new DevOps content has been flooding into Linux Academy as well as
live streams so check it out, linuxacademy.com.
We've also got some development stuff for Android, Python, PHP.
If OpenStack is something you've heard a lot about but you don't really have your head
wrapped around it, great OpenStack courses, great, great OpenStack courses.
Some of the best in the industry really right there and in fact some of the biggest companies
in the industry are working with Linux Academy because their courseware is so great.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the unplugged program.
Okay, well before Ubuntu 14.10's release there was a lot of talk about how boring of a release
it might be.
I made an offhand comment in the news one episode and man oh man did I get a lot of
response.
Popeye was one of the blokes who felt perhaps my comment needed to be responded to so he
and I had a nice chat about that.
Alright, so I want to move into the topic that was sparked after Sunday's coverage of
Ubuntu 14.10 and before we get into that, so in the Linux Action Show subreddit and
in the email there are a lot of people that apparently decided that I am very biased against
Ubuntu and one of the reasons decided was that I skipped over talking Unity's touch
support when we were talking about GNOME 3.14.
I just want to clear the ground right now, just quickly mention that was not me sliding
Unity at all, that was just me focusing on GNOME 3.14 because we were covering GNOME
3.14.
We were not covering what Unity can do, we were covering what GNOME can do so I just
didn't mention it.
It doesn't mean I was intentionally because I don't like it leaving it out, it was because
I was talking about GNOME and what GNOME was adding and what Wayland was adding.
But there is more contention over our coverage of Ubuntu 14.10 itself.
It's probably, you know what Matt, people hate crickets I think is what it is, people
just hate crickets.
I think it is, yeah.
I think the crickets may have been something that kind of set folks off, I don't know it's
funny.
Yeah, it's just too much I think.
Should have been a bomb going off.
People love that, people love explosions.
A lot of it boils down to a misunderstanding of, I think a lot of people attributed it
to arch fanboyism on my part and that I was such an arch fanboy that I was putting Ubuntu
down because of it.
And I think a lot of it was probably coming from people who haven't watched the shows
for a long time because I think people, sometimes what happens is people see that I am pro something.
I was very pro Ubuntu, very pro Unity, the desktop for a long time, I still think it's
a good desktop.
And so because I was pro something for a long time, it is to them illogical that I would
now say something that is not pro.
Because once you like something, you're supposed to like it forever.
But I think people who watch me know that my opinions change over time based on results
and the way things go.
I'll give you a great example.
I think you could go back in time and you could clearly see episodes where I was slamming
on Fedora, pretty handily slamming on Fedora for maybe the entire review.
Now my position on Fedora has changed quite a bit as they sort of are addressing some
of these problems.
I would say I still approach Fedora with some depredation and some level of skepticism,
but I am impressed with the changes they're making.
I'm impressed with their project leader.
Obviously we've had him on the show twice in a few weeks, and in the times of course
the second time wasn't really about Fedora.
So it was funny because in that very episode of people saying, well Chris is such an Arch
fanboy, they were completely negating the fact that we had like a 25 minute interview
with the lead of the project, of the Fedora project.
My point is, it's not a bias towards Arch that influences my reporting on Ubuntu.
I don't have any distribution bias at all.
That would be ridiculous.
The reason I go with Arch is because it does everything I need it to do, and it doesn't
feel like a distribution.
It doesn't have politics, it doesn't have councils, it doesn't have advisory boards.
It just is, and you don't have to worry about the politics and the people.
It feels just like a meta layer on top of Linux.
That's why I like Arch.
I could just as easily switch to Fedora next when they've got that rolling.
I could see that happening in the next year or so.
I don't have allegiance to any one particular distribution.
I do have a bias though, and that bias is a bias towards winning.
People who are doing it right.
People who are producing results.
People who are coming through on what they say they will do.
And as a company, any project, doesn't have to be Ubuntu, as any project slides in one
direction or the other, my coverage of that project will reflect that slide.
So if they say, now I'm sorry Poby, but let's just say there were supposed to be two phones
already in the marketplace.
Let's just say Mir was already supposed to ship.
Let's say that Ubuntu 14.10 is the most boring Linux desktop release we've ever seen from
the most important distro maker out there.
Let's accept all of these things as genuine facts, unfortunate facts, but let's just accept
those things.
Me reporting on that does not mean I have an Ubuntu agenda where I want to tear Ubuntu
down.
It's me reporting on the state of Ubuntu, one of the more important distributions in
the market.
It's not coming from an arch influence, it's coming from following these things and maybe
a little disappointment.
Does that make sense?
Matt can you fill in, am I missing any gaps here?
I think you pretty much hit it.
I mean, it's basically different, it really boils down to different strokes for different
folks.
I think it's just where it is at the end of the day.
And for you, you have a specific set of expectations that one distro or another may or may not
be meeting.
And that could of course change over time.
I think what I'm trying to get to is it feels like the conversation, I don't know if poisoned
is the right word or derailed, but this latching on to, oh well, he's just saying that because
he's a fan boy.
Or Chris is too biased by Arch to cover it.
Just me saying that out loud sounds ridiculous and childish.
The concept that I would have some sort of allegiance to some Linux distribution that
would influence my coverage of it is ridiculous.
What I will do is identify a Linux distribution that does something interesting, and if they're
doing that something better than everybody else is, I might suggest those other distributions
try to adopt some of those things, but that doesn't make them invalid.
I've used every distribution out there.
I also don't report much on Mandriva, do I?
That doesn't mean I have an anti-Mandriva bias, it just means they're not really moving
the needle much these days, so they don't really work their way up into the coverage
very often.
Well, and I think it's also worth mentioning, and someone will undoubtedly point out, okay,
then why does it appear that we quote-unquote rip on Ubuntu but not on Mandriva?
And my response to that would be simply because we have a set of expectations for this particular
distro, one that we've had a lot of great experiences with, and we just simply want
to see certain things addressed, and that's not happening.
I'm speaking for myself.
Ubuntu's relevance in the marketplace makes it more likely to receive criticism, and it
also makes it more likely to receive praise and hype, and I mean, there's two sides to
that coin.
Absolutely.
Higher expectations.
And so, like in the chat room's pointing out, why do we dog on Mir and not Weyland?
Well, actually, I don't really think we dog on Mir.
In fact, if you trace the-
We didn't mention Mir in the last-
Well, no, but if you trace the history of our show back, when Mir was announced, we
were some of the biggest offenders of, hey, let him try it, give him space and let him
do something, and we took so much shit for that.
Like Matt and I-
I dressed up in a monkey suit.
I mean, come on, you know?
Exactly.
I brought the monkey suit to-
Like, we were there saying, let him give him a shot, and the thing is, it's not that we
don't want them to still have a shot, it's just the fundamental fact is, we're still
waiting.
That was a long time ago.
That's fine.
These things take time, but results, at the end of the day, are what we have to report
on.
That's what we have here to talk about.
That's what the discussion is about.
That's the reality.
And so, when OMG Ubuntu is in bold and italic, saying there's no new features, not even a
new wallpaper, what is the Linux action show supposed to say?
What dick am I supposed to suck to make all of you happy?
Because there's no dick I can find.
Holy shit.
Pretty much.
Right?
I mean, seriously.
Yeah.
I mean, I-
So, we are working right now on a different approach to our Ubuntu reviews.
That I think, it was producer Eric's idea, and I think it's a really solid idea that
will make our Ubuntu 14.10 reviews extremely interesting.
But it is requiring a completely reformulation of the way we approach a Linux distribution,
because we have to find something to talk about, to talk about.
Otherwise, we just wouldn't review it.
And that doesn't seem like a good option either.
I have covered this distribution for a long time, and I've never been at a point where
I've literally had no idea what to say.
Other than bad things.
So, I'm working, so we're working on a new formula to come up, give the respins some
attention and really kind of have a nice comprehensive look at it.
But I'm pretty happy with where we're going with it, but it's required a total adjustment
of our approach, because of the situation we now find ourselves in.
And I feel like, you know, there's a lot of energy being put in by our community.
There's about five threads in the Linux Action Show subreddit right now, if you count threads
that have also devolved into this topic.
So there's two or three primary threads, and one or two that have devolved into this topic.
Currently live in the Linux Action Show subreddit, claiming that we are so far off base with
Ubuntu 14.10, because of our biases and et cetera, et cetera.
There's no way for me to tell you this.
There's no anti-ubuntu agenda here.
There's no arch bias here.
There is a bias towards winning.
There is some Linux elitism, because we've been Linux users for a very long time, and
we start to know when something smells like shit, and we start to know when something's
winning, and we call it like it is.
I will grant you those things.
Bias towards winning and an elitism that isn't arch elitism, it's just a Linux user elitism.
It's just there, because honestly, after you see enough of this crap, you start to tell
people to get off your lawn.
It's not a function of being against Ubuntu.
It's just calling a spade a spade, or whatever the saying is.
I don't even know.
It's just that's where we're at right now.
I want to address this, because I'm seeing there's a lot of energy being put into this.
So here's a great, and there's some great posts.
I mean, a lot of thought is being put into this stuff, but it's kind of misguided in
the sense that the trouble is we will continue to say if something's bad, I believe it is
our responsibility if something isn't going right.
We cannot sit here on this show that is the number one watched Linux media.
I cannot sit on that show and say something is great when it's not great.
It is our responsibility in any way we can to help these things move along in the right
direction.
If that's just our voice that's just echoing the thought of some users, that's fine.
If other projects watch this stuff and go, hmm, maybe we should rethink this.
That's great.
It doesn't really matter, but we have to be genuine to what we believe, and you have to
understand that it's not about us going after Shuttleworth, or making Popey cry, or anything
like that, because at the end of the day, if you watch the show long enough, you will
know that if they start producing results, if in 2015 we start seeing several great phone
models come out, and it's kind of great, and down the road, Unity 8's got its bugs worked
out, and it's great.
We will be beyond elated to cover that on the show.
I love covering stuff that rocks under Linux.
That's why the word action is in the Linux action show.
We like covering the stuff that kicks the most ass every single week in Linux and open
source.
I will be the happiest person.
Trust me.
Nobody will be happier than Chris, because it'll be great content for the Linux action
show when they have something that we all love.
Go ahead, Popey.
You might as well go.
So, there's a few things I didn't know about your review, because I was away at a conference
over the weekend, and then someone pointed it out to me, and so I watched it a bit earlier
on.
And there's a few things that struck me.
One was that you kind of missed the fact that we've been saying all through this release
that the focus is on phone.
We've said it over and over again.
Oh, yeah.
It's not lost on me.
Not lost on me.
It's pretty apparent.
Right.
But you've waited until beta release before you decide to review it and then say it sucks
because of what we've been saying all along, which is that we're not focused on the desktop.
This is specifically why I aired those concerns when we were talking about the beta release,
because I want to put all that out on the table, and I don't want it to influence the
review.
It's out there now.
Now it's not going to be part of the review.
What I was essentially doing was taking that and extracting that bit of what would have
been in the review and putting it in that news bit.
And now when the review comes, that's not a review.
Us covering something, and I'm picking on you about this because we get this all the
time.
Us covering a news item is not us reviewing something in the show, and it's a common misconception.
You specifically said that we make a big song and dance about it, which we didn't.
We've mailed a mailing list saying the beta is out, OMG posted an article about it.
That doesn't mean we've made a song and dance about 1410.
We haven't made a song and dance about 1410 because we're not focused on it.
No, I think Matt's point there was that there used to be a song and dance.
No, you specifically said about there being a song and dance.
Anyway, that was one thing was why bring it up when we keep saying this is not a big release.
It's not the first big release that's not had major stuff in it.
Because it's more unusual for the in-between LTSs to be so boring.
It's more often the LTS is about the refinement and the polish, and then the big experimentation
happens in the.10 release.
And that's always the one that's-
Well, not really.
610 didn't change much.
1210 didn't change a lot, but 1210 had the shopping lens, so everybody had something
to talk about.
Right.
Well, I think a lot of interesting things happened in the 10 releases, and shopping
lens is obviously the big one.
But those were both post-LTS releases, and they didn't have tremendously huge game-changing
things in them.
Are you going back to 610?
I mean, that's-
Well, that was the first one that came to mind, because the ones in the middle and the
ones after that had Unity, and obviously that's a massive thing for people to talk about.
Yeah, exactly.
Go ahead.
So the other thing is, it's not just Ubuntu.
Not a lot has changed in Ubuntu, but then there's Kubuntu, Lubuntu, Ubuntu, Ubuntu Studio,
Myth20, Ubuntu Studio.
I agree.
That's where the interesting stuff is happening.
It's just one distro.
It's one flavor of the distro.
Right.
Well, oh, now they're just one flavors.
Now, when that's the only place where the innovation is happening, now Ubuntu is just
one of the many flavors.
But of course, when all the innovation is happening-
It's always been one of the many flavors.
Now, of course.
Of course, it's always, yeah.
They're just, yeah, it's just one of, it's the main dog.
And the point is, is all the innovation, all the excitement is happening in all of the
other flavors, which, you know, worked great for a lot of-
I wouldn't say there was a lot of excitement going on in any of the others either.
Oh, ouch.
To be honest.
I haven't landed here, dude.
Look at the Mate.
Kubuntu's got Plasma 5 preview, dude.
That's great.
That's huge.
That's not in the archive for the release.
That's a preview ISO, isn't it?
In the same way that Unity 8 Next is a preview ISO.
Also the Mate project isn't officially an Ubuntu flavor.
It seems like there's a common thread here.
Which is one that I didn't list.
My point is-
Specifically because it's not an official release.
So you don't think it's a problem that all of the interesting things are happening in
all of the distros based off you?
I didn't say that.
I said there are other distros, there are other flavors of Ubuntu, and there are interesting
things going on there.
You only focused on Ubuntu.
You didn't mention any of the others.
Because what I was talking-
That's the point I was making.
Those others were going to- again, this wasn't a full review.
This is an announcement of the Ubuntu 14.10 beta.
Right.
Well, in fact, Ubuntu doesn't participate in the alphas and betas as much as all the
others do.
So it would be more interesting to talk about all the others on this particular release.
Oh, I like how you're telling- okay, oh, okay, right.
So Popeye, you don't-
No, is that not fair to say that these guys are all participating and building up to a
beta release, so it would be good to talk about them?
You don't see the justification you're doing here?
You don't see the deferment that's happening by saying, well, yeah, of course, nothing's
happening in Ubuntu.
But don't pay attention to main Ubuntu.
Don't pay attention to the most important distribution.
Don't pay attention to the one that has all the people officially working for Canonical
on.
Pay attention to all the ones based off of us.
Pay attention to these guys over here.
This is a total change.
No, I'm just saying that these others are just as important as Ubuntu, and, you know,
we-
That's not true at all.
We provide support.
And you know that's not true at all.
No, that is not true.
They are very important, but they are not as important as Ubuntu.
I don't believe that they're not as important as Ubuntu at all.
Oh, come on.
Come on.
No, I don't.
We have an archive that has a variety of desktops, and more than there are flavors, you know,
there's lots of other desktops in the archive that are important.
In fact, Marte is now in the archive as well, and they're all important, but none of them
are-
I love all my children.
Exactly.
I know years ago, KDE felt themselves as the blue-headed stepchild, and that was frustrating
because we put a lot of work into all of them.
I'm just going to put that out there.
I'm not a fan.
So I think-
You're entitled to your opinion.
Of course.
I just think-
But it's not an opinion.
I mean, yes, my opinion that it is- where the opinion comes in is in my disappointment,
but the fact of the matter is there really is nothing to talk about.
Right.
Okay.
But you could argue that that's the same thing with every LTS.
This isn't an LTS release.
No, they're the same package with every time there's something that they release right
after an LTS, it always happens.
It's just more refinement to the LTS.
Not always.
No, that's kind of my point.
The 10.10, 12.10, 14.10, it's the same.
You just listed all the ones where they rolled out major changes to the Unity Dash, including
search and privacy features.
The ones you just named where there was massive changes.
No, the 10.10 was known too.
12.10 was slight changes with the adding search, adding Amazon search to it.
That's not a slight change.
That's a huge change.
As far as functionality, it's the same.
I mean, it's basically...
All right.
I don't want to argue version numbers.
You add Amazon search to the dashboard, that's a big change.
There's a lot to talk about.
When you're an LTS, just being an LTS, that's something to talk about.
Okay?
You guys...
We're getting down into the weeds of what versions of Ubuntu have what features.
The important part is, what I want to walk you from is, A, that wasn't a review, okay?
We're going to do something different for the actual review where we'll take a look
at the spin.
So don't consider that like our final opinion on Ubuntu 14.10.
However, we are at an interesting point in Ubuntu's history right now.
We're kind of in the thick of it, and we are documenting what happens while they are making
this huge, huge, huge transition.
This is what happens right now.
We don't know, and we're not casting what's going to happen.
We're not projecting what's going to happen, but what we do know is right now, what we
get, so what we will get in the long run is potentially a competitive mobile operating
system that has some great features that could tie in really nicely with desktops and offer
power Linux users a great experience.
But what we have today is not a great experience for Linux power users today, and that's what
we're documenting.
The fact that we...
Just because we released 12.10 doesn't make 12.04 instantly, sorry, doesn't make 14.04
instantly obsolete.
Right.
Actually, I think that's the interesting thing about 14.10 is, in a lot of ways, it doesn't
change 14.04's relevance at all.
You add a few PPAs to 14.04, you don't even have to change anything, right?
Right.
And we do hardware enablement kernels and XOR back ports to the LTS release, so yeah.
You could consider 14.10 to be not exciting, not that much going on, so fine.
That's happened in the past.
We're focused on other stuff, and we'll come back to desktop next release.
I kind of feel like, I mean, so why am I getting beat up on for saying that?
I don't know.
I was quite surprised myself that people reacted so badly.
My only point was that you only focused on Ubuntu and didn't focus on the others.
Well, and that was a little slight of hand because I plan to focus more on the respins
later and I figured I'd get that criticism out of the way so that way it wasn't in the
review.
It's me pre-setting up the review.
It's me kind of, so some of this was formatting for the show, for the arc of the story here.
I didn't talk about Unity's multi-touch support because we had just talked about that and
I was talking about Gnome, so people took that as me sliding Unity.
And then when we got to the Ubuntu 14.10 discussion, I didn't really talk about the remixes and
the reflavors because that's what we're going to focus on in the review because what the
hell else can we focus on?
And I don't want to just spend the whole review criticizing all of the mistakes and retrashing
the software center like we often do.
So we got it out right there in the news segment.
Now it's done.
Now it's sort of like, it's setting up the narrative for the review, setting up the expectations,
setting up the state of things, and then-
I tell you what, I'm really looking forward to this review.
This sounds awesome.
And then we deliver.
Well, we'll see.
I mean, maybe not.
We'll see.
But you know, so I guess people kind of jump down like our throats a lot lately whenever
we kind of bring up the topic of Ubuntu.
And it sort of feels like there's an expectation that we really should only talk about the
good stuff.
And I could agree there could be more good stuff we talk about.
Yeah, but we get grief for that too though.
Yeah, exactly.
Well, that was the thing is like we used to get a ton of grief about that.
But this week it was particularly strong.
So I don't know if we've helped.
I don't know if we've made any sense in any of this, but I definitely want to tamp down.
I find it personally insulting to be called an arch fanboy because it implies that I am
so simple-minded that my preference for one distribution over another would somehow like
infect how I think about everything in my life when really-
There was one other thing.
Oh, yeah.
Go on.
I forgot to mention the gnome release schedule, meaning that we don't have the latest and
greatest gnome in our races anymore.
Yeah, okay.
That's a good one.
Yeah, that's kind of sad and it's a bit frustrating that we can't sync those things up.
It would be nice if we could, but our six months releases have been like that for 10
years.
And when we had gnome as a desktop, I think we made exceptions and would pull it in at
the last minute.
But now gnome isn't our default desktop.
So should we bust a gut to get gnome in there for the final release when it isn't even our
default desktop?
I agree.
And the fact that there is a pretty good PPA system in place where you can grab it.
The reason why, and I don't think I said this in the show, but the reason why I would love
to see it just as a personal preference is, A, it would definitely make Ubuntu feel much
more like a contender for me to use as my daily driver.
But there's Ubuntu gnome edition.
But also it just kind of seems like maybe while Unity isn't seeing a lot of stuff, why
we're just going just small bug fixes here and there, wouldn't it be really cool if there
was a very fresh, being worked on desktop, available to me to choose from, and that would
be gnome 3.14.
And to be honest with you, I honestly think a lot of Linux users are going to install
Fedora 21 because it'll be one of the first distros that does gnome 3.14 out of the box
and they will install it just for that reason alone.
And so it would just be a nice feather in the Ubuntu 14.10's cap if it could be like
a great way to get gnome 3.14 right out of the box.
That's why I kind of brought it up because I think that would be a great combo while Unity's
kind of on the shelf.
But I understand release schedules and whatnot.
That's just how it goes.
And the PPAs solve that.
That's fine.
Jaron mentions maybe it's not what we're talking, but maybe it's how it's brought up.
I think maybe that's potentially true, but at the end of the day, you have to understand
that we have to provide some level of entertainment too.
So there has to be something to engage people.
There has to be something that makes people really feel passionate and want to engage
with us because sometimes if you just keep it really dry and boring, people get bored
and they tune out.
So sometimes if it's presented in a certain way that you find offensive, consider that
maybe it's being presented in a certain way to grab attention.
Well, for the love of God, people, stop being so friggin' sensitive.
I mean, that's my big thing.
First and foremost, I recommend Ubuntu to everybody.
I do.
And I rip on them hard because I have high expectations.
Everyone I know that recently switched to Linux is using Ubuntu and I will continue
to do so because it's a good distro.
I will also continue to rip on it because I care.
I'll throw this in for you, Chris.
Today I installed Fedora 21, Fedora 20, and Antegros.
What possessed you to do such a thing?
You'll find out later.
Oh, okay.
Oh, Mr. Relic.
So I just, I don't know, I don't know if we're going to ever resolve this because it's such
a fundamental.
I understand, you know, you guys are really passionate about some of these projects.
Some of you don't just contribute, you know, your voice, but you also contribute your time
and your code.
And I don't want to discourage anybody from volunteering on any open source project they're
into.
And I hope you will maybe consider, just stick with us for a little bit and consider that
our opinions are not, I think it's a benefit to be somebody who constantly reevaluates
the way they think about things and their opinions of things.
And you can see over time those will transition.
There's a lot of things over the history of the Linux action show where we came down pretty
hard on something.
And as they were, as those things were addressed, our, I mean, Gnome is another one.
Gnome 3.
Oh yeah.
Right?
I mean, and the reason was is at first Gnome 3 was no good.
It just was no good.
And it has gotten a lot better.
And now our tone, our coverage of Gnome has changed to reflect that.
It's just kind of natural if you think about it.
It's not that weird.
It just, it doesn't, it's just kind of, it's not a fanboy thing.
It's just action speak louder than words.
I'm teasing it off a lot, Wimpy.
What process are we about to go through right now?
Right.
Okay.
So everyone probably knows that's listening to this, that Ubuntu MATE 14.10 was released
a couple of weeks ago and we've been preparing an Ubuntu MATE 14.04 release and I'm actually
ready to go through the keystrokes to release it live now.
So we're going to release the latest version, which is based on 14.04 right here on air.
That's right.
Let's do it.
Right here on air.
Okay.
So I've got my terminator sessions open and I've logged into my two digital ocean build
servers.
This is where I prepare the ISO images.
I've already prepared the images and I'm going to run the release scripts and the release
scripts build the WebC torrents, actually make the ISOs from the squash FS, add the
assets from the official Ubuntu CD releases, and then I'll sync them to my distribution
servers.
So let's do that now.
So off we go.
Right.
So that's the power of digital ocean.
That's just shunted six gigabytes of data.
Really?
Wow.
We'll now just edit the release flag on the article.
Now we'll run the deploy script.
This is so exciting.
I know, right?
I know.
This is actually the geekiest thing I think we've ever done on the show and I love it.
So the deploy script basically takes all the markdown that the site is generated from and
turns it into HTML.
So that's done.
So now I go to my CDN and I prefetch all of those images into the CDN and that's done.
And now I purge the blog index from my cloud flaring and that just makes sure that the
updates go through and I think we're done.
So you just witnessed an operating system being released live.
So you pushed the whole website and everything in that.
Yeah.
There you go.
So if you go to Ubuntu mate.org slash blog, the article that you'll see now is the release
notes on the article.
So if you go to Ubuntu mate.org slash download, yes, that should redirect I think because
there's two bits in there.
You know what, Wimpy?
You just earned yourself...
Very nice, sir.
Very nice.
Thank you very much.
Let's stop talking about the future for a second and let's talk about something I think
most desktop Linux users who bounce around desktop environments have experienced.
You ever seen this problem where you got an application and it has a little system tray
icon and maybe that particular developer decided, I don't want to implement the app indicator
support for Ubuntu.
So when you're in Ubuntu's Unity desktop, you don't get an icon up in the right hand
corner.
But when you're in KDE, you do get the icon and know maybe it's hit and miss.
You've seen this kind of thing, right?
Oh, absolutely.
Absolutely.
And it's something I've definitely experienced, but it also colors based on the level of difficulty
which direction I'm going to go through.
Sure.
Because I've certainly had that experience both in Unity and KDE, less in Gnome.
But yeah, it's certainly happened.
Sure.
And see, I feel like I've had more success in like almost all of the little tray icons
show up in KDE.
It's totally hit and miss in Unity and Gnome's gotten a lot better about it, but it's still
hit and miss in Gnome.
And this itty bitty tiny bit of fragmentation was introduced when a couple of different
desktops decided to implement or really one desktop decided to implement app indicators
differently than the other desktops.
And even today, years later, we still get that wrong.
And let's be clear for what it is.
It looks like amateur hour.
It looks pathetic.
It's something that the Mac OS or Chrome OS or Windows would never get wrong and does
not ever get wrong.
It looks ridiculous.
And I think we have to be clear when we're having this conversation that this type of
little itty bitty fragmentation has much wider ramifications than how people appreciate and
experience a desktop.
And this as I'm going to use this example because it's something we can all relate to
and then we're going to look at the larger ramifications of the fragmentation at the
display server level.
But what I want us all to think about as we are moving forward in this conversation is
look at the future directory of Linux of desktop Linux, quote unquote, desktop Linux competition,
because it's not Windows.
It might be Windows today.
It might be Windows for the next few years.
But five, 10 years down the road on the high end, it's Mac OS 10.
On the low end, it's Chrome OS and Android.
And those desktops would never be caught dead with that kind of amateur hour implementation.
That was not going to happen.
And that is our competition.
If you look at the forward directory of the trajectory of the desktop market, that's who
we're competing against.
And those platforms, specifically Android, Chrome OS and Mac OS 10 already have a worldwide
distribution system with massive amounts of momentum behind them.
They have stores in almost every country around the world.
You can order online.
They have a brand image around them.
And that's what future Linux is going to be competing with.
That's what we're competing with.
And we are not even bringing our A game.
We're not even we're not even doing a very good job with our current setup.
And now we're about to introduce fragmentation at the core level of the desktop that we have
A, never had fragmentation before, and B, are fundamentally under resourced to properly
develop it as it is.
The X team already split to have one team work on X11 and one team work on Wayland.
Well think about this.
What if Ubuntu in some parallel universe had decided to go with Wayland?
That would mean millions of more users banging on Wayland.
That would mean more bug fixes, more refinement at a higher pace to Wayland, making that core
part of the Linux desktop experience more refined, more tested, more performant.
All of these things that matter, especially as game developers are moving over to Linux.
But instead, we are splitting our resource.
We are splitting our attention.
We are splitting our testing.
We're splitting our development time.
And at the same time, we're introducing all kinds of fragmentation that developers are
going to have to account for.
Because here's how humans work, right?
You're going to have your distribution.
You're going to develop on that.
It's either going to be a Wayland based distribution or a Mir based distribution.
And whatever it is, that's the one you're going to properly test on because that's the
one you use, and that's the one that the features are going to work correctly on.
When I go to the next track in Clementine, whichever distro display server the Clementine
developer is using for, that's the one I need to use if I want the next track onscreen notification.
And that's even more amateur hour.
We are introducing a level of fragmentation at the core of Linux that will mean that applications
are even more hit and miss now in what they feature.
Does this application have a screenshot button?
Maybe it does.
Maybe it doesn't.
It depends on what desktop you're on.
Do you get an onscreen display?
Maybe you do.
Maybe you don't.
Maybe you don't care.
Because if you only want to use Unity for the rest of your life, then Mir is going to
work great for you.
But if you ever want to use Ubuntu with another distribution, well you better learn how to
install Wayland.
You better figure out, this is going to be an explosion in blog posts on how to load
Wayland on Ubuntu desktops.
Because everybody out there that wants to use anything but Unity ever is going to need
to learn how to install Wayland on their Ubuntu machine.
And that's another reason why you should care.
The reasons stack up.
And this, these very issues, these fundamental issues are exactly the kind of thing that
affect users.
So why I might not care if it's Mir or Wayland, I sure as hell care if my application doesn't
work correctly.
I sure as hell care if I have to spend an hour figuring out how to install Wayland on
my Ubuntu install so that way I can try out Gnome 3 whatever.
It does absolutely affect users.
It fundamentally affects users.
I think it also slows down adoption in a very serious way.
Big time.
Yeah, and that's the piece that I see the biggest.
Because at the end of the day, granted, I fall back to my old, the market will sort
it out and it will.
But we shouldn't have to sort it out in the first place.
I mean, that's the big piece of it right there is that we're spending unneeded time sorting
this out when it shouldn't have been an issue in the first place at all.
Right.
And it's going to get sorted, but it's going to be like a 10 year process.
Developers are always like, oh, Linux is too fragmented.
I don't know what I should target.
This just changes the equation even more.
You look at how 3D games capture the mouse pointer.
That's going to be different between desktops or display environments.
Game developers are going to have to think about this kind of stuff.
And the other thing is, you know, from my old contracting background, and Aaron touches
on this in his post and I thought it was really well done.
He says, think about it from an IT support perspective, right?
You already get people like, I had several clients that had Linux on the desktop.
And you know, the problems would always arise if one person was on one distro and another
person was another distro.
One person would have something work.
Another person wouldn't.
And then it would be, oh, well, you need the build utils.
Well, what's that called on Fedora?
What's that called on Ubuntu?
I mean, it's already the diversity that we have there, while in some ways it strengthens
and empowers Linux, it also from a support standpoint is already too complicated.
Well, that's what's just going to happen when the display server changes.
Currently, as Aaron writes, guides and manuals covering Linux can assume that Xorg is running
and other troubleshooting tips with that assumption can be in place.
This is also one reason why the Linux world is standardizing on system D is such a good
thing.
Support will become easier when we don't have to ask, are you using system with system
5 in it, system 7 in it, system D, Upstart?
You just have to start troubleshooting at that level.
Multiple display systems will produce a similar result.
In commercial settings, this also translates to more cost, particularly to companies who
provide professional IT support for companies running desktop systems.
Does this matter to users?
Well, it means less clear documentation, more difficult support for Linux and higher commercial
support costs.
So yes, I would argue that matters to users.
And man, did that resonate with me because I have been, I have watched Linux go from
the ha ha ha joke when I recommend it to, yeah, let's implement Linux, right?
And I have been advocating the deployment of Linux in businesses for years and I was
already feeling the pushback from like my doctor clients all wanted Macs and all my
doctors wanted to get Macs.
And I really, it is, you know, as soon as that support argument is brought up, my arguments
are clearly deflated because how do you compete with Apple stores everywhere?
How do you compete with a, you know, a warranty in writing and a system that's honestly less
of a moving target?
It's really hard for me to fight against that.
Yep.
It's a unified experience that I don't, even if we go system D, we go Wayland, we go the
whole thing.
We still don't have a unified experience.
We don't at any level.
And it's happening at a time where we could be coalescing around Wayland.
We could be coalescing around system D, right?
And these are major coalitions that could be happening.
And he says, go ahead.
I was going to say, if they get those two and they get the packaging figured out, you
know, Bob's your uncle.
You're good.
Those three things together would do wonders.
Aaron points out, you know, this matters to display systems.
One thing free software does not have is enough of its graphic developers.
With Xorg, there were exactly one place you could contribute to if you wanted to push
forward the display stack on a free software operating system, such as Linux.
Then Mir came along and introduced a split in the developer community, which means fewer
human resources applied to a topic that really needs every single pair of hands we have.
Instead of one system that as good as we can make it, we'll end up with a slower development
of two systems with the risk of more of them being less than great.
And I think this part could be argued because you could say good competition spurs good
innovation.
But at the same time, if you're familiar with the core X development, you know how bad that
situation is and how much we do need all hands on deck for that kind of thing.
And you know, Aaron points out this is obviously no minor task.
Mir was originally promised to be the display system of choice and desktop Ubuntu in 2013-10.
Then it was pushed back to 2014-04, and now it's pushed out to 2016-04.
This is not a trivial sort of project, and making it harder by limiting human resources
available is unwise.
And I think what we fall back on too often, and I think something we can chant, there's
a couple of things we chant a lot in the Linux community.
Well, yeah, maybe KDE isn't making you happy, but you know what, it's great because you
got choice.
Well, that choice is not all that great if none of the choices are awesome.
So but you know, Saigo says he's hopeful.
He says, I do hold out hope.
The free software community is speaking with a singular voice, and that voice is saying
after X, it's Wayland.
Wayland itself is still being worked on and has reached a level of maturity that allows
real world use.
Several of the major desktop products are well on their way of supporting it as a first
class option, including Plasma by KDE, Gnome Shell, and Enlightenment.
All the major toolkits upstream have support for Wayland today, and Wayland has the broadest
driver support next only to X itself.
So that's a good point to be made.
So he's a little hopeful.
And he goes on to say, the Mir team keeps bringing up these topics, although so does
the KDE team.
What's up?
But he says maybe they need to defend their position, so does the KDE team.
I can emphasize with how, how they, how, how, I don't want to repeat what he's saying here,
but what he says is, I can emphasize that they are working on something they truly believe
in, and they're being told it's the wrong thing to do.
He says, I feel it is their right to develop Mir at their heart's content, and I cheer
their moxie.
Similarly, it is our right as developers and users to choose what to support and what not
to.
Such decision making is aided by having an accurate and complete information, and it's
with that goal in mind that I wrote the post above.
I thought this was a great post, because I think what we are entering into is an era
of unprecedented fragmentation in the graphical space for Linux.
And I want to, and I, and I, I want to reel it back in here, because I'm pretty upset
about this, the more I think about this, because what I see this potentially as, is I see this
as, I don't want to use the words I'm thinking of, but the,
Is this a politically correct version, maybe?
Well, it is, it is hobbling desktop applications in order to push forward the Ubuntu agenda.
I don't believe we can, we have already seen Unity itself introduce a level of fragmentation
that is below commercial desktops, that would be intolerable for commercial desktops.
We have already seen that frag, we've already seen the play out of that.
So when you introduce some fundamental stuff at the, at the display server level, you either
have two options as a developer.
You try to target both main display servers, and one of those targets is probably not going
to be as optimal as the other, or you simply ignore one altogether.
In either scenario, users lose.
So if you don't care about what display server you're using, then you probably ought to stop
using Linux, because at the, at the end of the day, this is going to fundamentally change
how the application landscape looks on Linux.
And even if it is just one application has an on-screen display on one display server
and doesn't on the other, that is enough to have me upset, because that is unacceptable.
It is not good enough.
And I want the most kick-ass display server possible.
We have the most kick-ass kernel possible.
How about we get the rest of the stack as kick-ass as we can?
And to sabotage a display server like this for one company's personal gain in a mobile
market that is not likely to be tremendously successful anyways, feels awfully selfish
to me right now.
Well, you know, I honestly, and I think even Valve will be included in this, I don't think
anyone's going to give a ripping rat's butt about Mir one way or the other going forward.
I really don't.
I think just from the backyard developer guy who's doing this in his boxer shorts down
to the multi-billion dollar corporation, I don't, I think they're going to look at
this fundamentally and be like, you know, honestly, uh, I'm going to go whichever
way the community is going, whichever way the draw, uh, you know, the video card vendors
are going, whichever way direction they're headed, basically it's a numbers game.
And so I think this potentially, I'm hoping I'm right on this, that this could work itself
out fairly early on.
I'm hoping the more I think about it, the more I think that it's a, you know, look,
I mean, it's definitely early days.
And I think something I wanted to kind of kick around to the mumble room is maybe abstraction
can solve it.
Cause we're all looking at this with today's set of problems and today's set of tools to
solve this problem.
Sure.
And I think also, you know, uh, something that Martin and Aaron were trying to make
the pushes is developers are users too.
And in fact, I think developers make up a good user base of Linux, right?
I think that's probably who a lot of the develop users are, are developers.
So by impacting developers, you are impacting the users of Linux.
And I think you're going to, that's it.
That's a segment that's going to continue to outgrow any other segment of Linux usage.
But I don't, anybody in the mumble room want to take a first shot at this?
Is this a, is this a problem that future Chris and Matt aren't even going to have to worry
about?
Can I ask you a question, Chris?
Go for it, puppy.
What's the single most used display server on Linux right now, as in, in most, in most
deployments?
Xorg?
No.
Surface Flinger on Android in way more deployments than anything else.
Wayland, Mir, or Xorg?
Hmm.
Good trick question, Popey.
That was a good one.
Surface Flinger is the display server on Android.
Nobody seems to have told them that they can't have their own internal project for a display
server, which is used on millions of devices.
But the difference there...
Why do we get, why do we get that flag?
But isn't the difference there, those are, but that's a, that's sort of, in a sense,
a whole cloth creation, right?
Where it's a whole new ecosystem with a whole new set of apps that are designed for that
system.
But on the Linux side...
Just like Ubuntu 5.
Yeah, exactly.
Well, if anything, the most biggest problem is it's a whole different paradigm compared
to our legacy or at least what everything else has ever been.
I mean, I think Popey makes a good point, but I think that, I think the, the subtle
difference is that you only have to target Surface Flinger on Android.
All right.
So when you're making your Android apps, it's not really something that even has to be a
consideration, but on...
No, you don't.
You don't.
Because the stack, that's abstracted away from you in exactly the same way that Robert
and Robert Carr have both blogged about that stuff is abstracted away from you by the toolkit.
You would disagree then with the assertion that Cygo and Martin are making that it's
not quite as abstract as everyone would like.
No, I'm suggesting that there are certain edge cases where you need to know about the
underlying fundamental bits and pieces.
And yeah, a screenshot tool is a real easy shooting fish in a barrel, you know, one to
pick because it obviously needs interaction with the display server.
But there are way more applications out there than there are screenshot tools.
And there are way more developers out there developing tools with toolkits, which will
just work on these display servers and won't have this problem.
So you say the canonical has the amount of influence and power that Google has when it
comes to the mobile marketplace is just a little bit of a excessive state.
Did I say that?
When it comes to comparing surface slinger to mirror a little bit.
No, you didn't.
All I'm suggesting is that it's not actually important.
All I'm suggesting is that it's entirely possible for someone to come up with a display server
on Linux which isn't Wayland and isn't X and for them to deploy that to a large number
of handsets around the world and it work and for application developers to do their work
on top of that and not really care that it's surface fling underneath and not Xorg or Wayland
or whatever.
So I think the fundamental disagreement I see here is one side thinks that it's really
not going to be that big of a ramifications for developers or application functionality
and another side seems to disagree with that position.
The surface area of mobile is also far smaller in a way that it's very specific.
Its kernel is predefined other than the Cyanogen mods or whatever personally built mods that
Android has.
Otherwise the desktop is very, very different.
There's a lot more ambiguity.
And it's a lot harder to do which is one of the reasons why Mir hasn't landed in the desktop.
It's kind of the point you mentioned that if it comes down to here's a toolkit you can
use to build your app and it would guarantee it'll work, that works but that's not a model
that Linux is typically gone with before.
I think their argument is no toolkit is actually that comprehensive.
There's bugs or there's just gaps in what it's capable of providing that eventually
in a special case of Unity pretty much only.
I think their argument is eventually you have to close a few gaps and when you do that you
got to write directly to the display server, you can't write to the toolkit.
And I think the concept of a perfect toolkit is sort of like a dream but I don't think
we've ever in the history of computing achieved the perfect toolkit.
No, and I agree there are going to be holes in every toolkit and there are bits that we're
going to have to do at the plumbing layer and components that we're going to have to
provide that won't be provided by Qt.
We know that and we're building those as we go and yes it's a bit of a learning exercise
for us as well but I don't think the criticism is necessary.
I don't think it's as warranted as some might think.
In some ways it feels like okay, right, we've got them to switch to system D, right, what's
next?
Oh yes, me.
Let's have a go at them about that.
Let's see if we can get them to change that one now.
I guess what I'm worried about is I'm worried that wishful thinking is influencing that
thinking because in an ideal world I think that's too ideal and I think the history of
specifically desktop Linux shows us that things are very fluid and things are never quite
as great as we want them to be and the idealism usually gives away a little bit of pragmatism
and I think at the end of the day there's a lot of bets on things kind of coming together
at the right time to make all of this work.
I think Ubuntu's time is coming to an end soon because I mean they've been alienating
and alienating the user base so much over the years with Unity, with Mirror, with...
Yeah I don't know about that, I hear that a lot Riley, but the thing is you can't discount
the massive cloud deployment that Ubuntu has which will naturally push a lot of developers
and sysadmins to want to run Ubuntu.
I mean they're doing really great there and I think also, I think let's look at it from
an alternate perspective.
What if we fast forward three years down the road or 2016 or whatever it is where we have
like this great Qt based desktop which I think a lot of us think Qt has a strong future ahead
of it.
You know maybe this is a little bit further down the road but it's sitting on top of SystemD.
The only piece that has a lot of questions is how is...
I think what people are really worried about is the fragmentation being introduced at such
a critical layer.
I mean we can all argue about package names and how they're different between all distributions
or the locations of certain libraries and how they can be different or where the config
goes can be different.
But we as a user base and as developers have never had to worry about that display layer.
I mean yes it's gotten old and its time has come to be replaced but at the same time it
has been at least a consistent thing not just across Linux but also across Linux and the
BSDs.
It is a consistent aspect for software development when you're targeting these systems that is
now no longer going to be consistent.
And I think you cannot undersell that except for that other platform that you keep forgetting
about that has more deployments than all of those.
Well I mean there is a reality to that but I'm very focused on the actual desktop aspect
of Linux and maybe you know down the road I mean we're already seeing more and more
laptops that are shipping with Android.
I just recently saw a post for a full-fledged desktop with a keyboard, mouse and monitor
running Android.
So I mean you know it could be a fair point that again we don't know what the future has
ahead of us but right now I'm really focused on you know making my desktop version of Linux
better than ever and I'm really worried that if we cock this up and if we get this wrong
at this critical time with new types of companies getting on board and making great products
but also all of the desktop environments are getting to the point now where they're so
good that it's these little things that bug us like the indicators and all this kind of
stuff we're really getting to a good point and if we kind of screw this up I just Android
and Chrome OS and and the Mac are gonna eat us alive.
It's been a lot of fun having the spirited conversations.
I think one of the things I love about Popeyes is always willing to have a great spirited
conversation and then we have a laugh at the end of it.
Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Linux Unplugged for me over 2014 has changed a bit and I really like where it's gone.
It's become a place to openly talk about issues that we as Linux users experience.
It's a place for Linux users to talk about this stuff.
It's one part talk show maybe one part counseling a little bit and also we get those surprisingly
great insights from our Mumble Room and that's always been and having great guests just randomly
show up.
Join us for a live show sometime won't you our Mumble Room is always open we just got
to check your mic and you can submit topics to our subreddit linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
We'll see you back here on the 30th for some of our virtual Lugs 2015 predictions.
You can be part of that should be a great episode.
Thanks so much everybody.
We'll see you right here next Tuesday.