Since we're in pre-show mode, we should crack open our beers and talk a little open source
retro gaming hardware.
It's called the Game Shell.
And I think Poby was saying on the Ubuntu podcast that he's a backer of this thing.
It looks just like a Game Boy with a few more buttons on it.
And of course, it's a modular open source hardware that is meant to run classic games.
And the price is pretty reasonable.
You can get the early bird price at 108 bucks.
And they have real like already built hardware playing Doom, of course.
That's the handheld one.
Yeah.
It looks just like an old retro Game Boy.
The old black and white Game Boy.
Well, see, the problem with that is how likely is it going to be that Nintendo shuts this
down because it looks too similar?
Maybe you think.
Boy, that would be pretty awful.
Nintendo is pretty heavy handed with their confidence.
They are pretty litigious.
The thing is, is you have seen other products kind of like this.
This is the most Game Boy looking.
It is colored screen that one of the pictures they show it being black and white, but it
does have a colored screen.
And of course, it runs different emulators.
It's got support for Lua and Python.
Of course, it's an open source operating system.
The hardware is open, of course, of course, of course.
Yeah, I think it's pretty neat.
They got a pretty reasonable like set of goals and stretch goals and they're doing well on
funding.
They wanted $50,000.
And as we record this episode, they've raised $252,509.
Hey-oh.
Yeah.
They've got 2,280 backers.
Not too shabby.
No, they're doing great.
So this is a game show.
It's a Kickstarter.
So, you know, the usual Kickstarter disclaimers apply.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 226 for December 5th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's counting down the days to
the new year.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
And hello, Beard.
Hello.
Guys, today's a big episode on the show.
Yeah.
You know, we do that from time to time.
Just sneak them in.
It happens.
I don't know how this happens for an unplugged show, but coming up on today's humble podcast.
That's right.
We're going to kick things off with a new Runs Linux this week, just for old time's
sake.
We'll get into that, then some local community news, and then something that Google's doing
to get people into open source.
Those of you looking for the perfect remote desktop solution, we may have you covered.
Say it's not so.
It could be so.
It could be.
Ugh.
And then we have some great news for you VLC lovers.
I think really, really great news.
And then, before we get to the Gentoo challenge this week, I want to take a moment, if I could,
carve out a little bit of your time, and tell you a little bit why Linux users, more than
just about any other segment of the internet, should probably care a little bit about Bitcoin.
So Bitcoin for Linux users, why you should care about it, and specifically, I'm going
to answer a couple of common questions that I think Bitcoin doubters have.
Not that I'm trying to convince anybody, but I just want to give you a different perspective
and maybe help put some context into why the hell, as we record this episode, one single
Bitcoin is over 11,000 green US BACs.
What is going on?
Well, there is an expert in the Bitcoin community who I have pulled a few quotes from that'll
explain how Bitcoin compares to services like PayPal, how to think about all these other
cryptocurrencies, these altcoins that are coming out and what they mean, and is this
going to be an open source mess?
And then the potentials that Bitcoin has for charity, as well as why, without question,
even if it's not Bitcoin, cryptocurrencies are 100% here.
They're never going back in the bottle.
They are here forever.
And I'll kind of give you the ironclad reasoning behind all of that, too.
So this is really the pitch on why you should care as a Linux user, because it's an open
source money protocol.
And it's going to take over the world in one degree, not like the way Linux has.
Right.
It's easy to overstate, but it's also potentially serious.
If you were back in the early 90s right now looking at Linux, that's what Bitcoin is.
And so it's going to be an implementation detail that is incredibly valuable, just like
Linux is for Android and a bunch of set top boxes.
And I'm going to explain why.
And so that's why you should care about Bitcoin, because it's at the early stage that Linux
was.
And it's also an open source project that's going to change people's lives, it's going
to create new work.
And the thing you're going to see a lot of is tons and tons and tons of hype.
In fact, you're already starting to see blockchain apps coming out.
Did you see this CryptoKitties app that everybody's talking about?
CryptoKitties.
And there's a bunch of other ones that are coming out now that help you invest in Bitcoin.
And Joe and I recently talked about one that's partying up with Yala for Sailfish.
Is that right?
And they're creating a Zip currency that developers will use inside the development community
and bug testers.
And they're going to create their own cryptocurrency for development on Sailfish.
All kinds of interesting things are happening.
And we'll give you some of the background, but we won't take too much of your time, because
nominally today, we are going to get into the Bitcoin challenge.
We're going to kick it off officially here in a few minutes.
So get your systems ready.
Then we're going to check in with folks in the virtual lug and see how they're doing.
And then we'll reveal the desktop environment that the audience voted on for West to build
in our Gen 2 challenge.
So without going any further, let's stop right now and bring in that virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Howdy.
I love it, every.
Every.
Single.
Time.
Hello, guys.
It is good to hear from you.
So let's kick it off with a little community news.
And this one just sort of, I don't know if you could really classify this as community,
but for nostalgia purposes, for old time's sake, I wanted to start off with Arun's Linux
this week.
And this one's a little odd.
It is a little odd.
Amazon has released an Ubuntu driven AWS deep lens cam.
And it's got a four megapixel machine learning camera with AWS hooks that runs Ubuntu on
an Intel Cherry Trail system on a chip.
So it's an Atom processor.
It's got a HD ready AWS deep lens development camera, is for machine learning, available
for $250 and a pre-order.
And to describe the look of it is like a big boxy webcam bolted on top of like a gigabyte
nook, like a tiny nook.
Yeah, it does look like that.
And this thing's running Ubuntu 16.04.
Or maybe like a cute robot with no hands and legs.
Yeah, like the beginnings of it.
One that is aware of its environment but can't interact in any way.
Right, it's just watching and brooding.
With a nice howl circle.
Yeah, it does have a circle, oh man.
So it's billed as the world's first video camera optimized to run machine learning models
and perform inference on the device, inference from the images.
It's Wi-Fi enabled and it's working with the Amazon SageMaker development framework for
managing machine learning models.
Now that's something that I'm just sort of tossing in there, but that's kind of a big
deal.
Like the models around machine learning are sort of like the recipes, right?
And so if you have a marketplace to share these recipes, then you can take your hardware
and you can go grab a recipe and all of a sudden you can take your box and you can start
doing machine learning, just any average Joe.
And so we got the SageMaker development framework for managing machine learning model processing
on this thing.
And some of the things that it can detect, there's like I think a category of 30 different
activities that this thing is aware of.
It obviously has face detection and object detection, it can detect the difference between
a cat and a dog, which is similar to Google's TensorFlow AI vision kit, which is available
for the Raspberry Pi Zero.
But this thing can also detect different activities that you're doing, ranging from brushing your
teeth to playing guitar, probably baiting and other things I would imagine this thing
is going to be able to recognize.
And you'll be able to train it to learn new behaviors as well.
And then it all can talk back up to AWS.
1604 LTS on an Intel Atom, the thing has 106 gigaflops of performance.
The Cherry Trail Atom processor with 8 gigs of RAM, a micro SD slot, 16 gigabytes of flash,
which can be expanded as dual band Wi-Fi, USB ports, HDMI out, an audio jack, reset
buttons and a power jack, it's pretty well spec'd, does 14 images a second by default.
So it's not like it's, it also does have a video mode, but by default has taken 14 images
a second.
Yeah.
I mean, but it does bring machine learning down to a price point for an individual because
it's only 250 bucks.
So that's what this is for.
This is, this isn't a consumer product.
This is for people at home, enthusiasts or developers to learn machine learning.
Is that because I'm trying, I am, I'm struggling to understand why the hell anybody would ever
want a product like this.
Well, yeah.
In traditional AWS fashion, they've made it as confusing as possible for someone who isn't
already invested in their ecosystem to understand what the heck is going on.
So if I'm leveraging the rest of their machine learning infrastructure, this thing could
be extremely handy.
Yeah.
Well, if you like to read their, yeah, if you read their like PR announcement, you'll
see they reference their own products like 17 times.
So that'll give you a sense of how interconnected it can be.
Yeah.
You're right.
It's a cheap way of leveraging AWS to do machine learning interfacing with the real world.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Was somebody in the mumble room going to chime in?
Yeah.
Actually he covered it all.
I guess.
Okay.
I can see in that context, it doesn't creep me out as bad in that context.
Yeah.
Just where's this going eventually?
Is this going in echoes eventually?
In some regards, I wouldn't mind my echo telling me when Dylan's come home from school versus
when Abby's come home.
You got the video echo, so it's already like 60% of the way there.
I also see it as their cloud play.
They're launching more and more products to help like, the more machine learning you do,
that's a lot of math, a lot of numbers that end up being crunched somewhere.
AWS obviously wants you to crunch those numbers on its cloud.
So if they can make like development kits, that's why they have all these other things
like cloud nine, they're like cloud desktop, anything they can get you to like, if it's
easier to integrate with them, and then when you go to production and spend real money,
that's where you go.
Right.
You're already there.
And I think they are having a better strategy vision on this than Google at this moment
because of that point, precisely, that actually you will get to see the data yourself.
It doesn't just get crunched on their servers, but you actually get to be able to get the
data back because of how their services are modeled.
And in comparison, the Google is not doing that, it's doing the Google Assistant that
you can just put it in any place and you can just use their service as a whole package.
It is easier to bury entry, but you don't have the control there.
The other thing it underscores just though is that Amazon sure uses the heck out of Linux.
It's here, it's in their data centers, it's all over the place.
Yeah, and they're putting 1604 Ubuntu on there, it's the next 86 box.
I do think this is also kind of a thing where they are giving a cheap product to get developers
to expand the capabilities of their framework for them.
Yeah.
I mean, they can probably take advantage of those models too, right?
So that makes sense.
And if it's a price point that's around the cost of a high-end Echo or Kindle that you
can use to get into machine learning and then it plugs into the AWS infrastructure, it makes
sense.
Plus, they also get feedback on what developers doing this kind of stuff actually want for
basically free.
Yeah.
Oh, clever, Amazon.
So let's talk about something else that's clever.
Linux Fest Northwest, April 28th and 29th, 2018, coming up pretty soon, surprisingly.
Yeah, the April 28th and 29th.
They move it around from time to time.
They sure do.
This is the 19th year of Linux Fest.
Wow.
Yeah, and I feel like they're at a transition point because different conferences have come
up over those years, obviously.
A lot of commercial conferences in the last 19 years have come up.
So they're trying something a little new.
They're doing a message in a bottle theme, which I think is interesting.
They say they're encouraging but not requiring that presenters touch on a theme, message
in a bottle, security, containerization, and personal data.
They don't have to follow that, but they do have a call out for papers right now if you're
going to be at Linux Fest Northwest or call out for presenters.
Why not help them make it a good 19 years because it is a transition point for them
where they can become a slightly different style conference and it'll be interesting
to see which direction they go.
I would also say it's just such a friendly event.
Like if you haven't spoke before, you want to speak, you're not sure like, well, what
is this?
You will have a great audience.
You'll have lots of people at your talk, most likely, if it's Linux or anything close to
that.
And everyone's just in a happy, sharing, open source mood.
Yeah.
And it's a good town in the Pacific Northwest to visit.
And even if your talk goes terribly, just go get some delicious food in Bellingham.
Yeah, Bellingham's got some great restaurants, got a great vibe going, and it's got tons
of beer.
Now, it's a little busy during Linux Fest Northwest weekend, so you got to plan for
that a little bit.
But there's also just a lot of social events going on at the hotels, there's game nights
going on, people sitting around talking about Linux and all that stuff.
LinuxFestNorthwest.org, if you want to know more, if you want to maybe submit a paper,
we're going to be there.
We're going to be doing something different than we've ever done, too.
I think we may have a live stream going, but I think we'll be doing something different.
Instead of us sitting there like emceeing the booth, it'll be different productions
happening live at Linux Fest that people can tune in for.
Maybe some shows that aren't traditionally live.
Yeah.
But while those shows are being recorded, if it's one that not you or I or Noah is on,
we'll be out on the floor going to the sessions talking to people.
We'll be out and about.
The whole experience.
Yeah, it's going to be really good, I think.
But Chris, how are we going to get JB into a bottle?
Well, I could talk about security and personal data.
Containerization, I feel like that just sort of turns me off a little bit when I hear that,
because it's almost like it's like it's slabbed in there like now.
You got to talk about containerization, and you got to talk about Docker.
We got to talk about containers, because that's mandatory.
You got a conference, you got to talk about containers.
Absolutely.
In fact, we should even create ContainerCon.
That's the only reason to have a conference is to talk about containers.
It's OK, Chris.
You can just go to DockerCon.
Well, I've been to ContainerCon, and I've been to DockerCon, and I've been to LinuxCon,
and I've been to all of these where they just go all in on containerization.
It sort of defocuses it instead of just putting it all in one place.
It sort of diffuses it, and it's not as useful.
It could be different with a convention like Linux Fest Northwest, though, because it's
more community focused.
Right.
Yeah, you got people in the industry coming to do talks.
It's a different thing.
So I'm curious to see how it goes.
I like that they're trying a theme, and if anybody was going to do it right, and you're
going to get the right voices in the conversation, it's going to be at Linux Fest, at least around
here.
LinuxFestNorthwest.org.
And now we have just a little bit of hardware news to get to.
This is sort of the last breaking news, really, in the last couple of days.
And this story is getting more and more traction, and it seems to be a good way to get attention
these days.
And it's disabling the Intel management engine.
So we first start out with Purism.
They announced that they'd be disabling the management engine on future computers going
forward.
And then a few weeks after that, System76 announced that they'll be rolling out firmware
updates to disable the Intel management engine on some of the laptops sold in the last year.
And then some eagle-eyed Redditors noticed that Dell has begun selling computers that
can be configured with an Intel vPro ME inoperable custom order config.
Is that right?
Yeah, no Intel ME on the Dells, too.
So it seems-
Sort of subtly.
Yeah.
Not without much fanfare.
Now, the interesting difference between Purism, System76, and Dell is the Dell one is the
only one that's actually shipping.
What System76 and Purism have done is have announced, which is funny because that's not
how the news articles read.
They read like if you were to buy a laptop today from either one of them, it would be
shipped without Intel ME.
And so you see that sort of propagate in the different blogs, and Ferronics did this, and
all the different outlets just ran with the headlines as it just spreads out.
And now, I've actually seen in common threads that, well, PopOS has custom code to disable
Intel ME.
Now, it goes from they haven't even shipped it yet to PopOS has been custom engineered
to disable ME.
That's what the pop is for.
I'm really curious to see how the System76 solution plays out because they're going to
be delivering it through their PPA, which means you'll have to be running Ubuntu.
So if you're putting a different distribution than a modern Ubuntu on your hardware right
now, you're going to have to switch back.
And I think they're still yet to announce exactly which models and which versions of
the models will be getting the firmware updates.
So that's also to be developed.
And I think Purism has also said that they'll be working potentially on updating some of
their previous models.
But I really don't think anybody gives a shit.
I mean, I know some people do.
I mean, I kind of care.
I care on a obviously on a technical level, I think it's shit.
And I care that it could be vulnerable.
But just even seeing the sloppy, inaccurate coverage of these announcements and how people
just propagate it around as if it's now done, it's just happened and it's fact.
It all reeks of armchair technologists who are taking a moral high ground position.
But at the end of the day, when it comes time to buy a new rig, they're going to get a ThinkPad,
they're going to get something, they're going to get a MacBook, they're going to get a machine
that Intel and management engine would be a factor.
And I don't think it's really more than a small percentage of people really care.
And those people are probably already buying ThinkPads with core boots that are two or
three years old that have been retrofitted.
Yeah, the people that are covering it, they were they just found a story that would get
them clicks and then they found a nice bow to tie it.
I'm not saying that if I could buy a computer and the computer that I wanted had an option
to disable management engine, I would choose that option every single time.
But it's not going to move the needle on which computer I buy.
I'm going to I'm going to pick a computer that best suits my needs.
And the management engine thing is it's happened.
It's just like the baseband.
If this was a problem, then everybody who is on Twitter and on Reddit making a big deal
about this wouldn't be using cell phones because of the baseband.
We will just it'll become the new normal, just like the Equifax breach becomes the new
normal.
All these things just become the new normal and we make a big stink about it.
But it actually reflects in our accuracy because all these armchair technologists and all
these armchair Linux enthusiasts on the R-Linux subreddit, they're kicking around like it's
already come and gone.
You can buy a computer today.
Operating systems have been custom fitted to disable the management firmware as if that's
even possible.
Nobody really cares.
It's just like this something, hurrah, we're better at kind of thing.
Yeah.
The way it felt to me was that before all of this, before that recent vulnerability,
you had people that were concerned about it and this is a small niche market that has
valid concerns.
Maybe they're journalists or other people that are really concerned about this and are
probably the people running Coreboot or as you say.
Exactly.
There's definitely a market for it.
Right.
And then there's this.
But then you had these people that were previously like, yeah, whatever, it's not a big deal.
Suddenly for like a split second, they're concerned about it.
But you know that in six months from now, everyone in that camp is just going to be
back.
It feels like the Linux user equivalent of changing your avatar.
I think there's actually slightly more to that.
I mean, when you think about that, we're moving to and touching a topic that was mentioned
in the beginning of the show, that Bitcoin and you're going to carry your money now yourself.
So far you trust on an institution to do it, your bank.
And the more you start doing that, the more you care about that security, the control
you do have on your device.
And it always starts with a nurse like us.
Yep.
Yeah, I do.
The research thing, do it, it kind of evolves and then all of a sudden it's needed.
But there are other products on the market.
So there are other products to support this use case of having like completely open firmware.
Like if you look at the Talos 2 workstation, they're taking IBM's new power CPUs and they're
going to build a workstation and that has entirely open firmware for the entire chain.
And so if you are interested in going that route, it is expensive, but you can do it.
Unfortunately, it's not a mobile solution, but it's like a step in the right direction
I suppose.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I mean, see the thing about all this stuff about disabling the management engine,
I do think it's a good thing and I'm really glad that researchers are pushing that and
making the discoveries that they're making.
But it isn't a guaranteed solution.
See they're flying blind and what they've managed to do is they've managed to take out
chunks of the management engine, but still get the CPU to boot.
And that's where we're at right now.
That doesn't necessarily, it's a black box, am I wrong?
You do need parts of the management engine or in AMD's case, the PSP in order to boot
because they are actually critical.
They do bootstrap the processor to some extent.
That's what I'm saying.
It's like they've taken out a chunk of it, but it's not completely gone.
It's still there.
No, but it is modularized enough that you're basically eliminating anything that's not
needed to boot or is not needed to keep the system running.
Okay.
I mean, it feels like you're not necessarily objecting to any of the ongoing, like two
months ago as Purism in particular, they've done some good work, you know, continually
to explore this space.
There was like a reasonable amount of coverage.
I did not object to any of that.
It's just more, I think more like this, the inaccurate and recent explosion of coverage
without really understanding or by people who aren't really invested in that effort.
Yeah, I think that's probably a good summary of it.
Not to mention, Dell is getting credit for already having this stuff shipping, but my
guess would be that they already had that option many, many, many months ago for the
small sector of the market that is very security focused.
Or the Chinese sector.
Yeah.
And it's a huge sector potentially.
It could be the other way around.
It could be because if I'm a non-US, if I'm like a company in Iran that's buying a bunch
of Dell laptops or Syria or China, anywhere where the US government might want to peek
in on what I'm doing.
Yeah.
You don't want an American company being able to look into your CPU.
That's why they don't like Microsoft either.
So Mr. Payne, what do you think?
Are you ready to officially kick off the Gentoo challenge?
Let's do it.
Fascinating.
Oh boy.
All right, Wes.
We're officially going into the Gentoo den.
The virtual machine is spun up.
It smells weird in here.
What's going on over there?
Well, we're getting ready to build ourselves a kernel.
You've heard about it.
The one, the only Linux.
All right.
So now Wes is off to the races.
He'll be building his system.
So it's not yet bootable.
No.
Not yet bootable.
You think we might get bootable?
Because the kernel is going to take a while to build unless you build a really lean one.
It might take the rest of the episode just to get to the kernel.
We're about to find out.
All right.
We'll check back in on you.
Okay.
All right.
So there you go.
The Gentoo challenge has officially kicked off.
Fascinating.
Is he going to do any like special things with the kernel compiling options?
Are you there yet?
No.
I'm in the menu config right now.
So if there's people who have some opinions about how this kernel should go, we can also
fix it up later.
I mean, we just got to get to booting first.
Well, all right.
Yeah.
We got to get a booting.
That's true.
That is true.
But if we have any quick tips from the...
Chris.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
I have an idea for Wes, for his kernel.
Okay.
I have my kernel backup on my Google Drive and I'm willing to share...
Let me just finish.
I have it saved and I can help him with it if he wants me to.
That would be an interesting cheat.
But would it take more time to rig up a way to transfer that thing and then get it in
your VM than it would to just config and build it?
Well, here's the thing.
It's almost fully set up.
You would just have to edit it for virtual option.
It still kind of feels like cheating though.
It feels like cheating a bit.
Dude.
It might be.
It's not cheating.
It's like he downloads the.config file and puts it in his user SRC Linux folder and he
can just change it to his hardware.
It's not that hard.
Yeah.
I say we wing it and the mistakes are show content.
We build it live.
I mean, we got to build it live.
We got to build it.
Yeah.
That's probably true.
If you build it, they will come.
Because part of the problem, right?
Yeah.
That's part of the fun of this thing.
You know, having a good time building a beautiful system.
It's sort of like we're doing the show.
We're doing the experience here.
Trying to build some Gentoo on the side.
Yeah.
All right.
I kind of like it.
It's exciting.
So Wes is off to the races right now.
Yeah.
It won't be the prettiest kernel I've ever built.
That's for sure.
But it will be a kernel.
All right.
We will check in, say, towards the end of the show.
See how it's going over here in the Gentoo corner, okay?
We're leaving the Gentoo corner now.
And with that, let's take a moment and thank Linux Academy this week, linuxacademy.com
slash unplug.
That's where you go to sign up for a free seven-day trial.
I am super jealous.
I think it's DeBill.
Wasn't it Ja-bill?
DeBill?
Yes, I believe so.
Check this out, Wes.
DeBill, now the place he works, when you sign up and you start working there, they hand
out Linux Academy subscriptions to get the team up to speed.
How brilliant is that?
What?
I think a lot of businesses should look into this because there was always training budgets.
And this is something that is going to snap in perfectly with that kind of system.
It's a great platform to learn more about every Linux, cloud, and DevOps topic with
hands-on scenario-based labs with instructors that can help you whenever you get stuck.
And Learning Pass, if you want to go down for specific types of content, like a very
specific track that you just need to get up to speed on.
Or if you're going for certifications, they got training that's dedicated to really immerse
yourself.
And they also have the whizbang sort of practice exam and quizzes approach, so whatever works
better for you.
And they have cloud servers they'll spin up on demand when you need them, a course schedule
if you're busy, especially with the fricking holidays coming up.
Trust me, this is the best thing ever.
They'll help you pick a course instead of time frame to fit to your schedule and your
learning goals.
And then they have a public profile where you or your employer or a potential employer
can see the courses that you've completed, iOS and Android apps so you can study on the
fricking go and study tools that you can take with you, like the guides or the lesson audio
and your personal notebook and different tools that are offline that you can just use as
reference or study as you need.
And they're always adding new stuff.
That's what makes the subscription valuable, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
That's where you go to sign up for a free seven day trial.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the unplugged program.
So we noticed that the elementary project has been keeping the public up to date on
their endeavors with the app center and other things that are happening over there.
And we just happened to have Mr. Daniel Fore from the elementary OS project in the mumble
room again this week.
Daniel, good to see you again.
And what the heck is going on over there?
You guys are just on top of it with this stuff.
Yeah, well, you know, people have been asking about stats.
And so I kind of poked everybody and we pulled together some some fun numbers if you want
to take a look at them.
Yeah, I was OK.
I noticed right out of it that the new version of calendar close was 28 reported issues.
Sounds pretty good.
So it's like it's like these are the core apps and these are the things we've been doing
to them.
What's your what's your highlights here?
OK, so this.
This represents our this last blog post was our updates for November.
So we've got a calendar update app.
We got a few little bugs fixing here, but the big the big ticket items actually are
still app center is where we're putting huge amounts of focus.
Yeah, it looks like it looks like new automated tests were added.
Is that like automated for what?
What are you testing with these new automated tests in the app center?
This sounds really fancy.
Yeah, so when a developer submits their application to app center, the first thing it does is
it goes through an automated test suite.
So before it ever gets to a human reviewer, we run all these tests on it.
And since you're connected with GitHub, then we can kick back issues to you automatically
from the test suite.
So it might take a while of robot testing for a while before you even really get to
human reviewer so we can do reviews really quickly with this way.
That is really great.
Wow, I love it.
And I notice then you do have the OK, alright, OK, OK, here we go.
We got some real numbers here we got.
So 70,000 downloads from the app center.
Wow.
Is that the whole run of the app center?
70,000?
Is that the whole thing?
That's that's just this month, what?
That is crazy.
Oh, that is.
That's fantastic.
That is amazing.
elementary OS was downloaded 61,000 times, with about 77% of those coming from closed
platforms, which I think is always the goal of the project there is to convert a bunch
of those users over and $132 were paid out to developers this month, 70 app releases
this month.
Holy crap.
Wow.
That's really taken off, Dan.
I mean, I think this gets it's, it's kind of a hit.
Yeah, it's been pretty crazy to see, you know, that's the 7070 releases a release is either
a new app or an update.
We've got 65 total apps in the store right now.
So that means some apps updated more than more than once this month.
So we're getting regular app dates up to users.
And I think I think it's pretty neat.
Geez.
Well, I'm every time we talk about this after afterwards, I walk away from the show and
go, I kind of want to try this out.
I want to just give it a go again.
It's been, it's been a little while since I didn't, I haven't checked it out since it
first launched.
Um, I like it.
How do you guys handle firmware updates and stuff like that?
How does, how does that get like these Intel ME stuff through, say some firmware update
that came around to fix stuff like we've seen in the past?
What happens in elementary?
I was for that.
Um, we don't have a GUI yet hooked up for that.
I think the plan is to use a whooped, right?
Is the kind of standard.
So.
Yeah.
Well, I will link to the post lots of nice screenshots too.
I really like the design of these apps.
Just all good stuff.
I got, I got nothing but good stuff to say.
This has got to be one of the best distributions that I'm not currently running.
I kind of, I got to put it, I got to, I had a laptop, my, my, it goes so well on my XPS
13 laptop.
Oh yeah.
I bet it's just beautiful.
Edge to edge.
High EPI.
Oh man.
It's nice.
So I think that's the laptop I'm going to put this back on and try this stuff out.
Wow.
I can't believe that.
70,000 downloads in the month.
That's great.
That is really, that's a really solid number and shows you that your users are going in
there and really trying it out.
I think that's pretty good.
It really makes me think too that if you introduce some new users into the elementary ecosystem,
they would get a really nice idea about what this Linux world can be.
So Dan, what about the possibility of something like one day I could go in there and install
telegram or Chrome?
Is that, is that possible?
Like with flat packs or snaps, is that somewhere this could go or is it always going to be
a just stuff that's been built specifically for the platform?
We want to keep it to just stuff that's been specifically built for the platform and we've
actually seen in our Reddit and other places that our users want this too and without even
us suggesting it, we constantly get suggestions of, I want to be able to hide apps that come
from Ubuntu and Debian.
I don't want to see them.
I just want App Center apps.
Yeah.
Cause they wanted them to match the aesthetic and fit in with the overall design theme.
So that makes sense.
Yeah.
And they know that these apps have been tested and work on the platform.
Right.
So what would be the solution?
Say I'm running, say I want to switch over to elementary OS for a bit and I want to get
a telegram and Chrome and some of those things set up.
What would be my, what would be my best solution on elementary OS?
Our stance on, on sideloading outside apps, you know, not from the store is that you should
use flat pack or snap.
And because it's, you know, we were built on the same Ubuntu 16.04 base.
So snap works great.
Flat packs works great.
It's the same stuff you're used to on other Linux systems.
So how do you install Chrome?
Me personally, I still grab the, the, the Deb.
Yeah.
And it's not a PPA.
It's a repository.
Yeah.
And they set all that up for you for future updates for your convenience.
Okay.
I'm going to give it a go.
I think pretty soon.
I really liked the aesthetic of it and I think that App Center has got to, I got to check
that out.
There's some cool stuff.
There's some weird distribution to get that right.
Since before the software center was everything on Ubuntu and since maybe click and run.
Right.
Oh gosh.
Yeah.
I think it's since click and run.
I've been waiting for this to get done right.
So I'm really pleased to see this.
Good work, Dan.
Thanks, man.
All right.
Was there anything else from the lug there before we move on to something kind of cool?
Something getting young people involved?
I have a quick question.
Go for it, Ben.
Can you use App to get on this distro or can you not?
Sure you can.
It's Ubuntu LTS on the, under the, underneath the.
Okay.
I was just curious.
That's all I had to ask.
Yeah.
You can go to town.
If you want to go that direction.
I don't know.
Yeah.
Well, that's what I'm used to.
So if I did install it, that's what I would probably end up using personally.
That's just me.
So Wes, are you familiar with Google Coden?
I am not.
I wasn't really super familiar with it either, but it's been going on since 2010 and they've
had over 4,500 students from 99 countries involved in a contest.
Now it's for kids.
So maybe that's why you, you know, I didn't get it.
It's like the kid version of the summer of code.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So it's running, it's running right now until January 17th, 2008.
And I think they're still accepting submissions.
So I'm kind of putting this out there just in case anybody, anybody that's younger in
our audience might be interested in something like that.
Students choose the tasks that they wish to work on from the following categories, which
are coding, documentation, training, outreach, research, quality assurance, and user interface.
And students will earn prizes for a successful completion of tasks.
And one of the organizations that's participating in Google Coden this year is Ubuntu.
So this could be a great opportunity if you want to work with Python or JavaScript or
snap craft or work on the gnome desktop environment or UC or C++.
There are tasks that are available for people that want to do this.
And so you just subscribe, you get in there and then you can go look at the tasks that
Ubuntu has put up there.
And some of them are not even really to necessarily go directly into Ubuntu.
Like this one's just package and publish your first Node.js step.
Install the Ubuntu 1710 desktop.
I think that's pretty doable.
Translate Ubuntu components.
And there's some ones that would generally get a student involved in creating open source.
And this work goes upstream and Google's flipping the bill here for this.
That's great.
Yeah.
So this is a Google Coden and it's going right now, November 28th through January 17th.
And I will link to the Ubuntu entry if you want to get involved there.
There's a few other organizations that are in there.
But this is pretty cool.
And it's a great chance to get some work on some legitimate open source software and have
Google behind the whole thing and orchestrating it all.
You know what I'd like to see?
They have this for the kids.
They have Summer of Code for the university students.
What about something just to connect people that have free time to projects?
Like a bug?
Well, there's bug bounties.
But yeah, there's nothing that's really taken off.
Yeah.
Different projects have different solutions.
But like us, we need somebody to help us with our bots.
I think one of the benefits of things like Coden and Summer of Code is that there's a
central place to look at all these different projects that want all these different things
done.
Yes, exactly.
That's the value.
There's like 500 organizations that are involved in Summer of Code now.
Yes.
You can just go to one place and go through whatever projects might interest you.
Organizations and projects.
And now, the Coden is kind of getting, it's not the same scale, but it's getting more
and more popular.
I mean, they've been going for a few years.
Yeah.
Plus something like Summer of Code offers sometimes monetary incentives as well.
I didn't look to see what the monetary incentives were for Coden, but they did say prices and
whatnot.
I imagine it gets a little different when you're...
So here's a, upon successful completion of tasks, eligible students can earn prizes.
Digital certificates, t-shirts, and hoodies, and grand prize winners will receive a trip
to Google's headquarters in Mountain View, California for themselves and a parent or
legal guardian for four nights in June of 2018.
Plus, that's pretty great.
You know, it probably could maybe be a stand in for some homework if it's involved with
school.
Well, imagine if you're like a high school student.
What a great addition to your resume.
Talk about getting some real, putting, you know, Ubuntu on there and working with Google.
Those are things that go on a resume.
That was, I think, the real value there.
Just one last quick Ubuntu little community news item.
Just an update here.
If you're a fan of all-in-one boot CD that that project, you know, the Linux AIO, is
the ISO image that you download and it's like all of the versions of Debian or it's all
of the versions of Ubuntu.
So they just updated for Ubuntu 17.10 Linux AIO so you can grab one single ISO and get
Ubuntu Gnome, Ubuntu Budgie, Ubuntu LXDE, Ubuntu Mate, and proper Ubuntu, Kubuntu, all
in one ISO image.
And then you just choose.
I'm really glad those guys are still doing that.
Yeah, 10.0 gone and dead.
I was involved with the project earlier on.
Yeah, I could, you know, you never know.
They could have gone the other way.
You could have, it could have faded away.
But now they've expanded.
They have Linux Mint now.
They have LMDE.
They have, so you can get different, you know, like, anyway, it's Debian Live, Fedora, and
then they have what they call secondary releases, which I didn't look at.
They also have Ubuntu, which you didn't mention.
Yeah, well, yeah, it's just all of the different Ubuntu's.
You can get LTS when they just did 17.10.
So it's like you can have, you can write, the reason why I mention it, if it's not obvious,
is you download this one ISO, you DD it to a thumb drive, and then you've got all of
the different versions of Debian or you've got all the different versions of Ubuntu
for that release.
Something I also noticed that is becoming somewhat of a rarity is that they still do
a 32-bit version.
Oh yeah, right.
Huh.
Hmm.
I wonder if that's true for all of the distros.
So yeah.
So there's a little update and then, go ahead.
Manjaro and our other Arch-based systems including Arch themselves have dropped 32-bit.
Hell, I wouldn't be surprised if Gentoo eventually drops it too.
Yeah.
Just, you know.
Good news.
For those of you looking for a remote desktop solution and have been avoiding TeamViewer
forever like I have, maybe we can look at it again.
This could be really great news.
And they drop a little Wayland tidbit in here too.
TeamViewer 13 preview is out for Linux and it's no longer based on Wine.
Yay!
Is that right?
Yeah.
That's big news, kind of.
Wow.
It is.
Native 64 bit.
Yep.
It's cute.
Be still my heart.
Yep.
They started by building a new back end for the host and then from there they built out
the front end, it's the front ends in Qt, and they say that we just decided at one point
when we started building the new host that we needed to start over due to technical limitations
of our Wine port and increasing user, they note here in their blog that more and more
users that are doing technical support are doing it from Linux hosts and that their Wine
version just wasn't up to the task anymore, which I think is, this is just terrific news
because it's another company saying customer demand is making us release this for Linux
and write a native version.
Hallelujah for that, right?
And they're writing one sort of TeamViewer and TeamViewer host common code base to make
it...
Oh, see, that's awesome.
It is.
That means we can probably rely on Linux support to continue.
Exactly.
And they say that they're going to continue iterating on it and that they're going to
continue to make it seamless to work with modern Linux desktop environments too.
Now, there is a big disclaimer, or as they say, a note on Wayland.
On Wayland currently, only outgoing remote control and incoming file transfer are supported.
If you need incoming remote control, you have to sign into classic Xorg.
This is a funny part of the blog too.
This is like really frank.
From a developer perspective, we'd be more than happy to leave the archaic X11 technology
stack behind and jump on the new and shiny Wayland train, however, it is not as simple
as it may seem.
Now, if you've been listening to this show for a while, you are very aware of this conundrum
that they're facing.
This is, who else but TeamViewer is going to get, I mean, like this company is going
to get screwed by this.
By design, Wayland does not provide an interface to do remote control.
We're talking screen capture, mouse and keyboard emulation.
It's not in there.
It's to keep Wayland core lean.
The idea is that the compositor provides these interfaces, which could mean that TeamViewer
would have to implement different interfaces for every desktop environment we want to support.
This is what I've been talking about and why having like a common API like Mir or something
in between there that can implement these feature sets could be extremely useful.
So they write, this is unfortunate, but even more unsatisfying that these interfaces are
not even available yet.
The closest to having something useful is Gnome, they're talking about PipeWire.
So it's likely that it will be the first desktop we can support in Wayland.
We want Wayland support as much as you, and we're working on it, but it's a bit complicated
than just make it work.
But they have a native cute version of TeamViewer.
It's in preview right now for Linux, 64-bit versions.
They have devs and RPMs available and no more wine.
I am so happy to hear all this.
Thank you, Lord.
Okay.
As much as I want to be excited for them and that I understand their pain, I'm not feeling
bad for them having all this work.
With Wayland, you mean?
With Wayland support?
With Wayland, yes.
And I'm going to give you a reason.
TeamViewer as a company has actually to a member of the community requested payment
where he was not using for more than a month just because he didn't went to the panel and
cancel, but he actually canceled the actual payment.
So the member had to pay for an extra full year because the terms say that if you don't
cancel, it gets automatically renewed and you're due to pay even if you're not using
the service at all.
And there's proof of that because he didn't log in at all.
Yeah.
I have my qualms there too.
But at that point, you're kind of giving crap to the development part of TeamViewer for
the billing department's issues.
Well, it's just that, you know, over the years-
It's the company's overall approach to a customer base.
Like if you were paying a customer and you treat it like this, I don't expect better
treatment because I'm an open source project.
And I am concerned about the Wayland developments for the open source alternatives, not for
TeamViewer in particular.
Yeah.
It's interesting that they're suffering and they're having to pay the bug.
Stooge, you had a take on this.
Go ahead.
Oh, I'm kind of reminded of your rant at Chrome last week.
Yay, we have more proprietary programs now we're a feature party with Windows.
Yeah.
This is one of those applications where I completely agree.
I'd like guacamole or some other remote desktop solution that just becomes the industry norm.
But having worked in IT for many a years, watching TeamViewer in production, I can say
it is, when you have it set up right, generally fairly bulletproof and easy for a basic user
to get set up and they can read a number to you and you can connect to that.
And it's very compelling from just a pragmatic remote support, get the job done.
I know I installed this TeamViewer host once and I know I'm going to be able to remote
support that user and IT shops have full dashboards with all their TeamViewers categorized by
different companies.
And I mean, I've really seen this thing produced at scale and it seemed like a pretty valuable
tool for them.
So having support on Linux is definitely a good thing.
But I do feel like for most of us that aren't working in corporate IT or doing IT support
for large groups of people, it'd be nice to have something that's just 100% free and open
but offers similar functionality.
Yeah.
I've never used TeamViewer.
I probably won't.
Yeah.
Google Chrome just works.
I mean, Google remote desktop, you really want something that just gets inserted and
works.
I've used a little bit.
On the flip side, there is something to be said for not having to punch something in
your firewall even as an individual user and then on top of that, somehow still getting
like insanely awesome performance.
Yeah.
I mean, you and I have used it, both of us, when we're remote and we need to get something
out production wise, you and I, TeamViewer was the one that ended up just working for
us when like we're moving desktop environments or we're switching different distros.
TeamViewer was the one we could just kind of hit the button and it did work.
When I was in Long Beach, I edited and released user error over TeamViewer.
Nice.
Okay.
Go ahead.
I have been using TeamViewer forever to help my family out and it always seems to work.
Yeah.
It is a good one for that too.
And there was a time that it worked for the people who just could break the pin codes
too.
Remember that time?
Yes.
So this is just a preview.
It's still early days, but the rewriting with the user interface in Qt, I think it's a good
move.
We'll keep an eye on it.
We'll probably end up trying it out here.
I'd like to pick Noah's brain about it too because I know he's been a big TeamViewer
fan in the past.
He's moved to other things.
Yeah.
Symbol help.
But I'd still like to talk to him about it as well.
And then one last note, just community news-wise for folks that are big fans of VLC, some
great news.
The European Parliament has approved a budget to essentially allocate funds for bug bounties
around VLC and they're doing it through the HackerOne project, which I am a huge fan of.
I've been covering that since TechSnap days and I just think it's a great way for companies
to get one central arbiter to act as sort of escrow and arbiter between the company
and the people that have made disclosures about vulnerabilities that they've discovered.
That's sort of the role that HackerOne can play.
Make it easy on both sides.
And it's a directory of this is what we are looking for, this is what our bounties are.
It's sort of one centralized location like we were talking about earlier for other things.
And the European Parliament is, I don't know exactly how much money in total, but we do
have an idea in terms of bounties.
And so looking at this, they're looking for all kinds of different issues.
I'm assuming they must use VLC.
And the nice thing is the core developer of VLC is one of these guys who has been approached
several times with very lucrative offers to install advertising into VLC and he's declined
it every single time.
So I love to see...
This is a great use of public funds in my personal opinion.
So they don't have really huge, huge, huge bounties.
But again, you're doing open source development here, so you're getting some money.
In fact, the top bounty isn't even worth a single Bitcoin.
It's only $2,000 for critical, 750 for high, 300 for medium, and 100 for low is what you
get.
And these are all based on like the CVSS score.
So if you find something that's like a 7.0, you get 750 bucks, which would be like code
execution without user intervention.
And then if you get remote code execution, you get $2,000.
These are all in US.
It's interesting.
I've never really thought of VLC as being like an attack vector for a system.
What if we could like...
What if we knew about a vulnerability when somebody connected to our RTMP stream?
We could do like some sort of buffer overflow with our stream and get access to their box
through VLC.
Yeah.
That would be a pretty amazing hack.
We should do this.
This would be a good revenue source for Jupiter broadcasting.
We can use it to mine Bitcoins.
Yeah.
We'll start remote Bitcoin miners on people's machines.
So yeah.
That's that HackerOne.
You can go to hackerone.com.vlc if you want to read the details on that.
I think that's great.
I'd like to see the US government get in that.
Because the truth is this situation sucks as bad as it does because these governments
are buying up zero-day exploits on the black market to stockpile.
And they're giving them an extremely high value, which is driving people to break software
at a rate we've never seen before.
So it's about damn time they use some of that money to also pay for public bounties too.
Yeah.
Right?
And it helps.
You may not use VLC personally.
There may be media players that you prefer.
But it's part of this open ecosystem of there is a free and open source video player you
can use that will probably meet your needs.
And it's nice to see that reflected in the comments.
I agree, Wes.
So hey, while we're over in the Gen 2 corner, let's check in and let's go over to the corner.
How is the build going?
How's the kernel?
What are you doing right now?
Oh, it's compiling.
Oh, is it?
Oh, yeah.
So you've selected your options.
I've selected my options.
Anything interesting and noteworthy?
Well, I made sure to choose ButterFS support.
Did you?
Just for you.
Did you really?
You're going to spend time building ButterFS support?
No, of course not.
Oh, that's funny.
I did throw XFS.
Oh, good man.
That's worth building.
Yeah.
I wanted to make you smile.
So you're off to the races over there.
Yeah.
You'll probably be building for almost the rest of the show.
Well, that's good, because coming up here in a second, I'm going to play some clips
of Andreas Andonopoulos, who is, I think, one of the best thinkers and speakers on Bitcoin.
If you're a Bitcoin skeptic, and I've been hearing from some of you, stay tuned, because
we're going to get the Bitcoin out of our systems.
We're going to talk about it, and then we're just going to move on for a while.
But it is an open source issue.
It's not even like a Beanie Babies kind of tulips.
It is an open source issue.
And I want to talk about that.
So first, let's talk about DigitalOcean.
Oh, DigitalOcean.com, you go over there, you create an account.
Once your account's set up, you use the promo code DOUNPLUGED.
It's magic.
Then you get a $10 credit.
And the next thing you know, you're spinning about infrastructure in less than 55 seconds.
Everything is SSD powered.
They're all SSDs.
They have a gorgeous, simple, elegant interface to manage all of it.
And it's not simple like in like the per her dumb way.
It's simple in, of course, it should work like this, which is the sweet spot.
They have all kinds of storage options from built in storage to your droplets, object
storage, which is simple object storage, block storage, which is one of the easiest ways
to go because it just shows up as a dev SD device.
And they have monitoring and alerting that collects metrics.
And you can receive alerts when things go down.
Load balancing is a service that are fully managed out of the box and distribute incoming
traffic and 40 gigabit connections into the hypervisors with data centers all over the
world.
And they have a lot of information.com, go spin up a Linux rig of your choosing.
They got a bunch of distros to choose from.
Use the promo code do unplugged and apply some of that to a future project.
And amazingly, you can use that on BSD.
You could, you could, you really could.
You could go all in or you could do, I've been doing a lot of LTS for like even just
like a half hour.
I'll spin something up, try it out and be like, and just destroy it.
Why would you do that, Chris?
You got Portsons EFS.
You don't need none of that stuff.
You know, the other thing too is like when I'm doing this, like I start working, I'm
like, Oh, this is something I'm keeping around.
It takes like two seconds to set up the DNS.
It's really easy.
And then you can also attach your SSH key.
So you don't have to like even like mess around with like changing passwords after the machine
spun up.
It's just, it's aces.
I like the portability of storage between different droplets.
DigitalOcean.com use our promo code do unplugged and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
the unplugged program.
Now let's talk a little about Bitcoin here and Andreas Antonopoulos was on the Kevin
Rose show, which apparently is a thing.
Didn't even really know this.
Is that right?
Yeah.
Okay.
From the Ashes of Dig.
I am.
Yeah.
I'm a big fan of Andreas and I've read some of his books.
I'm going to recommend them to you right now.
Mastering Bitcoin, The Internet of Money and his one that hasn't been released yet, but
I think it's going to be the one I read, Mastering Ethereum, which we'll talk more about at some
point in the future.
And there's several issues that I want to talk about today on the show that I think
probably apply the most to Linux users.
And it's the idea of closed services, centralized services versus distributed services, open
protocols and community efforts.
And it's in this context, I think it's where we could start talking about Bitcoin versus
things like PayPal or other payment services.
There's lots of payment services now.
Everybody's got a payment service it seems like.
So what's the difference between being able to send money with Bitcoin and be able to
use these payment services that actually use like your local currency?
And it's sort of the same difference between Linux and a commercial operating system.
PayPal, Venmo, they're services.
Bitcoin is a protocol and there's a very big difference between those two.
Bitcoin is a protocol that allows you to do trusted transactions with people you don't
trust and to independently verify the authority of those transactions without trusting anybody
else.
And that's really the magic behind it.
By turning money and other trusted transactions into an internet protocol, it opens the door
for all of the internet related goodies to happen.
When you're talking about Bitcoin, you can't really talk about Bitcoin without talking
about the technology of the blockchain, which is sort of that trust guarantee system.
And I think that's one of the unique aspects of Bitcoin that you can't really rely on PayPal,
you can't really rely on your bank and these two organizations have to be competing with
each other.
They don't even necessarily trust themselves and the entire relationship is awkward for
the customer.
All of that goes away with a public ledger.
So that is one of the true core values of Bitcoin outside of the currency that you can
spend itself.
But I know one of the other things people are getting confused about these days and
it is really confusing is all of these other currencies.
There's tons of other crypto currencies.
Back during Plan B, there was a couple, you know, you had Dogecoin, you had Litecoin.
Now there's...
It was simple, clean, easy world.
Now from that has emerged great complexity and there's many crypto currencies.
And this is something that people often point to and say, well, obviously Bitcoin is going
to fall apart and disappear one day because there's all these other crypto currencies
out there and it's just a mess.
Well, what does that sound like?
Money.
Yeah, it does.
And it sounds like there's a lot of Linux distributions out there.
There's all these different Linux distributions out there.
There are thousands of Linux distributions out there.
How will you ever be able to pick?
But just because there's thousands of Linux distributions doesn't mean that people don't
install CentOS or Ubuntu.
So you have to think about these as niche products.
I think there are a lot of promising things happening across the entire ecosystem and
I think part of the adaptation that we're having to go through is this idea that we've
grown up having monopoly currencies that are national flag currencies that exist in a zero
sum geopolitical chess game where one only wins if it beats the other and all of that
attitude.
Very much like in the past we used to have five national newspapers, they existed in
direct competition, the space was limited, the market share was fixed.
And then bloggers happened.
And then you have to ask, well, how many bloggers can possibly exist?
And the answer is all of us and it doesn't diminish or change the value of mainstream
news if they had value in the first place, if they retained value in the first place.
And it doesn't mean that all of them are good.
Most of them are not, but some of them are great.
And so the same thing has now happened with currencies.
We have to get used to a world in which there are now thousands of currencies, there will
be tens of thousands, then hundreds of thousands, then millions, and then billions of digital
currencies that can be created and destroyed in moments that can be created by anyone for
reasons as silly as a loyalty currency that's created by Joey the five-year-old in order
to socially engage with their primary school friends versus a global reserve currency that
China is using to buy oil.
Both of those are digital currencies.
Both exist on the same spectrum of continuum, have nothing to do with each other.
Once you get comfortable with that idea, you start realizing that all of these currencies
effectively are now playing an evolutionary game where as programmable currencies they
fit into specific niches and they compete for those niches.
And some are successful and some are not.
And they emerge to occupy new niches.
And they may be designed to do one thing and then somehow the market twists them into doing
something else, et cetera, et cetera.
Now one of the things I think that is hard for people in the States in particular, I
think people outside the States maybe don't suffer this problem as much, but in the US
a lot of people, a lot of the people that don't get Bitcoin at all, they don't get the
value of it because they have the benefit of using the US dollar, which happens to be
the world reserve currency.
It happens to be very well established, very good value.
So Bitcoin doesn't really have as much of a, there's not as much of a need, there's
not as much of a market demand here.
But we've all heard of countries like Zimbabwe and other places where currencies are going
like crazy or countries where they're using it to control the citizens in a very oppressive
way that are outside the US, you start seeing where a worldwide accepted internet based
currency could be extremely useful.
But there are uses even in the West, even though our governments are fairly stable and
our currencies are accepted for paying taxes and we're all pretty happy with this arrangement.
Think about how open source software development brought an entirely new level of transparency
to the software development process and there's aspects of it we still suffer from today.
Like when Linus yells at somebody, we go, oh my gosh, somebody said something hostile
in the workplace, as if that doesn't happen at every major company like HP and Dell and
Apple and Amazon, as if there aren't tyrants in all of those companies that are the iron
hand that actually get the project done, but we don't see it.
Open source development brought a level of transparency to software development that
we'd never seen before.
In fact, it would make companies like Microsoft back in the 80s extremely uncomfortable and
Bill Gates famously penned a letter to a computer society just talking about all of the downsides
of free and shareware and open source software.
It was a big warning piece because this would expose the way software was developed and
it did and it has.
The development history is in the public.
We can review it.
The mailing lists are in the public.
That kind of transparency fundamentally changed software development, just like open source
money and a public blockchain with a public ledger can fundamentally change money and
fundamentally change trust and think about it in the context of charities.
Part of the difficulty we have in the area of charity is that a lot of the need is in
places far away across borders.
A lot of the resources is on the other side of these borders and getting the money across
the borders and distributed to people without 99% of it disappearing in the cracks is a
big problem with charities.
So there's a favorite charity of mine called BitGive that's doing, it's a Bitcoin foundation,
it's a Bitcoin charity that is a charitable foundation and it uses this technology to
re-envision how charity can be done and they have a project called Giftrack and what this
allows you to do is watch on the blockchain and track the money you sent in all the way
down to the money that got spent to buy the bricks to build the well for the water project
in Kenya and so you can actually see all of the flows of money.
It's not an accounting report that's sent to you.
Every single contributor to the charity can in real time and without asking anyone audit
the charity online and just looking at the blockchain track all of the information.
That seems really like a very compelling use and you could, charity is one example I think
we could all sort of wrap our heads around but there's so many others.
I mean what about public broadcasting?
Think about that for a second.
It's just real or open source development where you could see exactly how the Gnome
foundation spent every single mil a bit down to like you know the the forks if you wanted
to which would just totally change transparency and you know the trust level that end users
would have by giving and you could stand out as a brand if you participated in that level
of transparency and cryptocurrency isn't just Bitcoin.
It's all and you can have all these other crazy currencies but this concept, cryptographically
verified transactions with a public ledger, it's already a huge source of application
development.
There's a lot of different stuff come out companies like Bank of America, IBM, the Linux
Foundation.
I was about to say we've talked about the Linux Foundation's hyper ledger several times.
Yep they're all working on like their hyper ledger there which is a blockchain based technology.
Cryptocurrencies are here to stay forever.
There is no putting this genie back in the box.
This idea of a network based open and decentralized currency and all of the other applications
that happen, that has happened.
The recipe was created, it's repeatable, it can be recreated as many times as needed until
it succeeds.
If it has flaws those flaws can be fixed in various evolutionary iterations, some continuous
some discontinuous and disruptive.
The bottom line is the world needs that.
The world needs an open public neutral economy that's not you know being kicked around because
of geopolitics or used as a tool for surveillance and control.
That is needed and it's needed so much that I have no doubt in my mind that it will be
wildly successful and it will completely transform the way we do commerce in the next 20 years
absolutely.
And it's going to transform in ways we can't even expect and that thing will underpin trillions
of dollars of economic activity whether it's Bitcoin and we still call it that I don't
know.
I know that such a thing will exist there's no going away from that.
You know I think I agree I don't know if it's Bitcoin either.
You know in a year Bitcoin could be could totally crash or it could be worth a hundred
thousand dollars.
And I think what you were talking you know like it really is the 1990s in the Linux world
in the in the public ledger world there's a lot more that we haven't yet seen.
Ethereum is still pretty niche like there's just there's a lot of potential application.
If you're going to be stuck in a cash controlled society then if that's going to be the real
master that we all are obeying then why not have it be something that's open source that's
publicly trackable that's cryptographically verified that's detached from the state.
So we've you know you always hear about the divorce of church and state the separation
of church and state.
Well how about the separation of state and money.
That's what that's what cryptocurrency represents is money and state becoming separated.
And even I mean all the actors that are involved right because like right now it's really just
a good old boys network of places that are deemed on the trustworthy list that get with
algorithms that we never see that get to handle how these digits and accounts work.
And if you if you follow the unfiltered show there's been lots of manipulating of things
of like light all and or whatever it's called the yeah.
So anyways I haven't I have a bunch of additional resources in the show notes including the
link to the Kevin Rose show that has the entire interview with Andreas it's it's it's it's
good.
Kevin Rose is a really good speaker and he's really good.
He's thought a lot about this and it's episode 16 of the Kevin Rose show.
I got a link in the show notes if you want to catch that it's a it's pretty good because
Kevin's a Bitcoin investor himself so he's got a lot of questions like what about quantum
computing is that going to screw up Bitcoin.
And Andreas answers that also have links to a couple of the wallets that go on your phone
that he likes the best that bit give foundation that he mentioned and a link that was provided
in our discord.
That is so cool.
There is a command line utility that you throw on your good news slash Linux box and it's
called Coinmon and it spits out after you install it's like if you have MPM it's MPM
install dash G coinmon and then you run coinmon and you could tell what currencies you want
what not and you get look at that screen there with you get this you get this like like there's
a dump of BTC value and the theory of all the different coins and it's a you know me
I love a nice sort of anchors style it's not actually it's all ASCII.
But I just love that in a terminal especially when you can put it in like a quake drop down
exactly just your nerd fix right there.
That's coinmon we'll have a link in the show notes just a great way to track different
crypto currencies.
You know we just we just kind of had to get out of our system I feel like because people
been asking when it gets when it gets to these new price milestones more and more people
either come out as skeptics or more and more people come out as interested all of a sudden.
But I really do think it's a Linux you I think more than say your average tech enthusiast.
I think Linux users should be more keen to recognize the values of something this important
being open source.
It's an old open culture sort of from the aspect of even aside from the technology aspect.
Yeah yeah yeah yeah.
Daredevil wants to jump in I think on it.
So before we wrap up on the Bitcoin topic Daredevil and you want to do a shoot.
Go ahead.
Yeah I actually see a couple of issues with these existing everybody that is optimistic
and especially people that are invested want to see it succeed.
I understand that perfectly sure I understand the value of having the transparency which
is great.
But there is the other point of now certain governments like Venezuela's government that
is actually issuing their own currency Russia that is issuing their own currency cryptocurrency.
The idea is that then they are able to avoid sanctions so you lose a little bit of the
equilibrium that exists politically and you might think that that's not important but
I personally actually believe that there is actually great importance right there as if
it wasn't for the new strategies of war really putting in words as they are the political
spectrum sanctions being a form of not actually investing in physical aggression you start
actually having again a lose of an ability that you currently have.
What is the difference between honestly I'm asking what would be the difference between
that or them choosing you know another currency that's not Bitcoin that's like it's gold.
So it's not so much that is Bitcoin they're using they're actually created right.
The purpose here for me and that I feel is this will lead to another imminent problem
but don't you feel like that would be the same if they use any other currency like even
if it wasn't crypto.
No I don't think actually no because so when it's not crypto because there is an actual
institution behind it you actually when people talk about the PayPal being a service and
Bitcoin is a protocol not quite.
There's actually an international service how trade needs to work.
You actually have to set up other countries have to believe that they can actually buy
and have some balance on your currency so they can actually trade with you.
It's actually a protocol.
Now they put a name to it and then there's an institution in the government they can
look and say it's your fault you did it wrong.
So the argument though the core of the argument is that if they go to an uncontrollable currency
that doesn't have an organization behind it then other governments lose levers of negotiation.
Yes and not so much not only that actually there's actually another piece a little bit
which makes it worse is we're moving towards a spectrum and a state that governments will
want to actually be regulating Bitcoin.
They have the actual capacity to be having the majority of the servers just so you guys
know and I'm not sure if you've been looking actually the current Bitcoin economy economy
only Bitcoin already spends more than 21 European countries in electricity bill.
Yeah I've heard that.
I don't I don't buy it either and not combined.
It's not combined but if you look at individual European nations are small so it is very likely
impossible that that can happen but in order to get that that's a rabbit hole I don't we
address that on Linux action news a few weeks ago so I'll just I'll refer people to that
but so just to just so you see I guess where I'm coming from here is I totally follow your
point that if Russia goes off and creates you know the Moscow coin and now the Russian
economy is doing sales with other large economies using the Moscow coin I do I do grok that
then the US and the West in general lose a hammer that they can hit Putin over the head
with but at the same time that feels almost similar to the argument of well if you open
source the software and give it away then these huge corporations are going to go out
of business and there's lots of jobs they're going to be not at all I'm not going on that
route what I'm going is there is a lot of things that are tied to the fact that there's
actual power structure and money is what governs this power structure yeah what we're moving
away is the power structure for us as people that have been enjoying democracy it is fantastic
that we can get these extra further control of our lives it's awesome and it feels great
as a principle the problem I see is the other power plays that we actually don't have to
deal on a daily basis that we are totally dependent on but we don't realize in an every
that's a hard sell that's a pretty hard sell to get people to care about that I mean because
you're essentially you're also at the same time advocating for the for the ability for
some nations to abuse that lever which likely happens more than it gets used correctly try
really hard to not be hypocritical when in the way I live my life and that requires that
I acknowledge what the advantage you're right there is an advantage there it's a fair point
it seems like a lot like oh sorry I mean advantage in in the terms of you know as Trump would
see it that's an advantage for Donald Trump or Rex Tillerson at the State Department is
not necessarily advantage for Chris the podcaster well you also get other than the benefits
I guess I receive remotely at us as a citizen of a nation that is using those levers to
make life better I would say to I would wrap I would wrap this segment with this thought
is we are at the really early stages and it's weird because the value is trying to get to
the point where it feels like it's bigger than it's it's like it's bigger than it fits
in its own boots right now exactly and I think we're gonna see probably I don't know 20 years
of iteration and that's where all these different cryptocurrencies will sort of battle it out
and again to make a comparison just like we see a bunch of different open source forks
and projects sort of battle it out over years and sometimes it looks like a waste of resources
or a deferral of resources but over time usually projects emerge as the dominant player in
that particular vertical if you will right and it's I think we're gonna see that same
thing happen with cryptocurrency I think I mean to summarize both you and daredevil
its points it's this is early days there's a lot of effects both positive and negative
so it's just we should be paying attention proceed responsibly yeah and there we go yeah
and also consider that any of this stuff could be replaced by something superior because
it's a technical thing right so you can actually have something even more innovative come along
one day in theory yeah so it's a it's a totally different beast that people are now actually
putting real money into and overall it is going to make like international monetary
stuff more transparent because like if foreign governments implement something on a blockchain
well you can now track the the movement of money through foreign governments on a public
way boy it'd be really inconvenient to have like isis on the blockchain that would that
would be really inconvenient track that let's go let's move on now and get ready for the
gentoo challenge so everybody get ready that wants to check in uh we're gonna we're gonna
follow up on the gentoo challenge here in just a moment yeah you feeling good over there
yeah yeah oh very good all right well before we go to the gentoo corner i'll mention ting
real quick here go to linux.ting.com go check it out this is the perfect time to pick up
a ting sim for about nine dollars seven dollars depends on the sale they have going you can
even get it off of amazon prime you can get a ting sim you pop that in a device and when
you're ready it's pay for what you use wireless service your minutes your messages and your
megabytes whatever you use that's what you pay my friends it's that simple it's just
six dollars for your line and then you got the uncle sam cut in there for your particular
region and then it's just your minutes and your messages and your megabytes with no contract
nationwide coverage you pay for what you use and they have a cdma and a gsm network to
choose from which gives you the option to pick up whatever might be better in your area
like i did a little speed test here and i think on average i get about i get about 21
megabits on gsm here at the studio which is a little bit better than i got on the cdma
so for the most part i i use gsm now and it's wonderful when i travel to have those different
options they have a dashboard that makes it easy to use you can see your usage at a glance
have complete control set up usage alerts if you want to buy a device directly from
ting you can do that too you don't have to buy the sim card if you want you can just
buy a device directly it's a really easy process to bring a phone over though and i recommend
that because if you bring a phone you get 25 in service credit and that'll probably
pay for more than your first month average ting bills 23 a month per line the compatibility
is pretty crazy especially with both networks like of all the people i've switched to i
don't think any of them wasn't able to bring your phone it was just like they have a real
easy pyod page too that makes it super easy to look it up is this going to work or not
um so yes go to linux.ting.com because if you want to get a device if you just want
to hit the easy button and buy one directly from them they'll take 25 off the device too
you deserve it a new shiny christmas present i mean come on yeah really yeah give it out
to somebody in their stocking they can put in a device they have sitting around all of
a sudden they have great use at a device they just pay for what they use with it and it's
a stepping stone from there you go geez ting's great then you get another device and it's
only six dollars for each line so it's easy to go from there and they'll love it you can
get it for yourself too i suppose linux.ting.com linux.ting.com all right so let's go over
into the gen 2 corner here how is your build going over there mr wes oh we've got a kernel
do you oh yeah i'm impressed so i think that's a pretty good way to end it uh now we just
need to do a little more configuration yeah bootloader fs tab a few couple other niceties
to have hostname you know those things yeah i think next episode will be booted and ready
to go i am impressed i am glad to see that's going well so are you ready for the reveal
then on the desktop environment that people want you to build yeah i'm excited should
we take guesses yeah all right i mean do you remember do you remember which ones we asked
about we asked about three enlightenment uh sway and lumina you are correct those are
the ones do you have a guess as to how it's gone knowing our audience they probably chose
the most boring one sway why is that the most boring one i think that's the most exciting
one it's boring yeah 48 of the audience voted for sway lumina desktop came in at deuce and
then enlightenment uh with 25 of the votes actually really close to lumina oh wow see
but the thing about sway is that it's a wayland compositor and dropping a replacement for
i3 so you got the i3 lovers and you got the wayland lovers they're all going to come together
behind sway and it just seems to make sense to me yeah but you don't get like the esoteric
ness of lumina yeah or the eye candy of enlightenment but it will be our first sway review on the
show too true yeah we do need to get back to enlightenment and lumina though that is
something that does need to be all right we got to get to that all right so let's check
in with the virtual log uh how are we doing in here guys how's your how's your gen 2 day
going anybody anybody no i thought ben was i'm a bit sad that you went with sway even
though i understand it's the most popular yeah yeah but you would have covered sway
inevitably at some point that's true i like that you did with it like that you actually
went with it because i've been actually uh the lame i switched this way so well we put
it up for a vote so it was really you know on the flip side it does mean that we're going
to be compiling wayland on gentoo yeah well it's either that or x so right we're building
one way uh now bashful were you doing an install uh along with us i noticed you said you grabbed
the minimal iso during the show there what kind of shenanigans were you doing no that
was actually back regarding the multi-abundance installer oh that'll work too that's an easier
path that would be yeah that would be so are you feeling good about sway i'm meeting to
try you could as a challengee i suppose you could override you could submit an override
but i i have been wanting to see it you could secretly install all of them that's true was
built taking a long time yeah i might have to do some pre-building in that case i know
we have some people building along with us and so if they would like to do sway as well
i think though ben did um it's like gnome 2 recently so that's an option we should we
haven't considered at all dude it's hell you do not want to go down there i've got i've
got i can imagine let's do gnome one it was just such a huge like going from sway to gnome
2 that's a bit of a leave that's what it is wow so might be tricky gnome 2 on wayland
yeah that would be a thing and it will it all be in an x wayland session yeah the power
of x wayland there so any other notes ben on your journey so far as we've uh as we've
done the gen 2 challenge i think i'm good thank you okay i like that you tried gnome
2 though good on you and uh i think the report works so next week then we'll get the system
bootable it sounds like and if anybody back for that okay all right and if anybody else
wants to play along at home if you want to catch up to us at this point you have to get
your vm essentially uh booting off of the install yep stage three get your kernel built
with your particular parameters and then i suppose next episode it's bootloader set it
all up and reboots have you already partitioned uh yes okay so you've got your file system
set up uh yeah that's right yeah yeah okay and it went just real simple this time so
it's basically like an efi partition we are doing gpt efi here so uh okay that's an extra
layer of fun all right well that closes out the the gen 2 corner this week very nice wes
good job over there you pulled it out it's making me want to build some gen 2 on digital
ocean too now that we're just doing this already well i need to have a lot faster cpu yeah right
exactly yeah but you got the kernel built so challenge day one is completed episode
one 226 we're gonna see how long this takes i think you're gonna go faster than we were
initially expected i think you're gonna have this done pretty soon all right well let us
know what you think on your thoughts about bitcoin and open source currencies on the
gen 2 challenge and any other news items you think we should cover go over to linux unplug
dot reddit dot com linux unplug dot reddit dot com is where you go if you want to give
us your email thoughts if you don't like the social medias you can go to the jupyter broadcasting
dot com slash contact otherwise you can also always hit me up on twitter at chris las with
your show thoughts and ideas also check out wes and i on the new brand new rebooted texas
coming out later this week i guess we probably should have teased this a little more that's
probably true it's going to be a soft lid it's going to be a re-envisioning of the show
and i think one for the better and i hope you guys will give it a go and share your
thoughts with us and in the meantime go over to jupyter broadcasting dot com slash calendar
and uh observe the live time observe the live time because there's only a few left this
year wow yeah boy and there's some more bitcoin coverage on upcoming user as well yeah we'll
do a little more yeah stay tuned for that friend of the show often a frequent contributor
and all-around great guy martin wimpers joins us a very special user air in the future that'll
be coming out down the road though there's just so much good stuff a holiday yeah like
a holiday special if you will which we may do a holiday special of this year show too
as well so i'm open to ideas for that too if you want to leave a comment on what we
should do for a holiday special let me know at chris las thank you for joining us on this
week's of unplugged and you know what we'll see you back here next week
i feel like for the holiday show all options are on the table so i think we should be
drinking some sort of uh oh like a holiday beverage alcoholic holiday i'm in oh i don't
do big on eggnog no oh just because the dairy yeah right but like what about like a spiced
apple cider or something yeah i'm sticking with the eggnog what would we do i'm open
i'm open to ideas from the chats and the and the discords and the uh and the mumbles on
what we should do for a holiday special open source yule log maybe i don't know what that
means yeah yeah like or suveen with wes and chris oh boy is our food judge yeah we um
we could uh make things from the open your mouth repo yes that's right i forgot about
that we could that's an interesting those open source recipes are up there uh so a bit
of emerging value emerged unplug gen2 madness those are our irc kind of like gen2 madness
it's not bad although it doesn't talk about anything else in this show plus we got to
save some bitcoin yeah and we got it oh that's right and plus i think we want to save it
for the finale too the gen2 thing um so we have uh the open economy welcome to the real
world open source doing it in public that's not bad kind of like doing it in public so
i had a real basic one but i thought it would maybe be the most descriptive and it was bitcoin
for linux users yeah kind of felt like that is like the heart of your message in this
episode yeah i think that's reasonable um all right so yeah anybody in the mumble room
have any ideas on what we should do for our holiday special bashful you could come down
and celebrate with us come down here and do a holiday special what day are you doing it
i don't know i just thought of this we just we literally just we have something we know
we need to do we're probably gonna do it in the next couple of weeks you know so that
way what with the holiday time yeah yeah the sooner probably the better but we need to
come up with a fun idea first i like it sounds like we're trending towards food at the moment
but i don't know if that's what we're gonna do we're trending towards food you could you
could uh play a bridge game on gb did you see how many people did you see that was like
one of the number one feedbacks from the last user errors people want people wanted to learn
about like you use a video stream bridge game or something okay yeah that would be good
that is doable i'll bring my 2v machine i'll show west like one thing and then he could
destroy me at bridge what a great how do we do that how do we do bridge in an audio podcast
though that's the question probably a video stream for that one yeah because a lot of
people listen to unplug that's the you know um but there's something there there's something
there too hungry though right yeah that's the problem something to think about we should
have talked about this at the end of a podcast when we're tired and hungry yeah something
to think about that if you guys have any ideas give it some thought all right well i think
we're gonna go with the boring basic bitcoin for linux users just because that's sort of
the best of what we do it open economy yeah i saw that one i don't mind it but it sounds
too um like uh corporatey to me a little bit like like an american express ad or something
but i do appreciate you guys being here thank you very much love your faces and uh probably
see you next time right i hope see you guys oh god oh god don't leave us please come back
all right okay okay sorry sorry okay okay