Speaking of breaking, how about a little breaking news?
This is CNN Breaking News.
Coming in from the beard himself, GetGamesGo.com, never even heard of it, but I guess they're
known.
GetGamesGo.com is having a 75% off Linux game sale, and some of them are just Steam codes,
some of them are direct downloads, some of them are DRM free, some of them aren't.
Anyways, I'll have a link in the pre-show, I don't know how long it's going on, they
take Visa, MasterCard, and PayPal, and it's GetGamesGo.com, and 75% off Linux game sale.
Thought I'd mention it.
Check it out.
See?
See what I do for you?
Now you can go get some gaming going for your 75% off.
No?
That didn't work for you?
All right, okay.
I'm just scrolling through the list.
All right, how about this one?
All right.
Nothing's jumping out.
All right, here we go, here we go.
Here's the answer, and you're in the situation room.
Hello guys, I'm here reporting on scene at GetGamesGo.com where I can report there is
indeed some sort of catastrophe going on.
I believe it is a cyber attack, a glitch in the computer.
All Linux games are 75% off.
Situation, situation.
That's right, Wolf.
This is quite the situation.
We recommend you go over to GetGamesGo.com.
I've never heard of them before, but holy crap, 75% off.
Hackers be crazy.
Do you like that one better?
Actually, it's gotten me kind of interested to go to that website now.
So I saw Wimpy posted, or someone posted some screenshots of Marte on BBC.
Yeah, that's pretty popular, isn't it?
Wimpy, what's going on there?
What the hell?
What did I do?
Oh, PowerPC.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
This is not something that I've had a huge amount of involvement in.
This is community developments.
So a couple of people in the Ubuntu Marte community have ported Ubuntu Marte to PowerPC,
and this whole underculture of people that are sitting on PowerPC equipment have suddenly
turned up, and we've reinvigorated these computers that previously were struggling for a decent
operating system.
So there's these guys turning up with PowerPC G4s, PowerPC G5s, and Amiga X1000s, and all
sorts of funky stuff.
People are just hanging on to these old Macs, and then they're just putting Linux on it.
Not just old Macs, but other equipment that's based on PowerPC.
Like anything, we all gravitate to something that at some point we really love.
I still have a real soft spot for the IBM ThinkPad 760, which came out in about 1998,
and it's an old piece of cruft now, but it was the first really decent computer I had.
So I think of it fondly.
And I imagine these guys that have got these PowerPC equipment, they know it, and they're
able to make it work for them.
And some of those G5 rigs that they've got are really quite pokey.
And were very expensive, though.
Some of those G5 rigs they bought, they may have spent eight grand on some of those high-end
production rigs.
Yeah, and these guys that have got eight core systems with eight gigs of RAM, so back then
this would have been a significant investment.
And yeah, they've got Ubuntu Mate running on it, with QEMU running, and they're doing
multiple Ubuntu Mate sessions running within there.
They've got all the 3D gaming going, the whole nine yards.
So I'm working on it at the moment.
So I've actually bought an iBook G4 off eBay, secondhand, to help with the PowerPC testing.
And last week, or the week before, did the PowerPC enablement in the official canonical
build infrastructure for Ubuntu Mate.
So I don't know if we're going to get over the finish line, but we've started to put
all the bits in places to introduce it as an official architecture.
That though, wow.
I mean, when you go down that route, that is big.
That's a new arm of the distro.
Wow.
Although, you know, I think about it, there is an old G4 tower that is kicking around
here somewhere that just, it does nothing because it's worthless.
If I could throw a Linux on it.
ISO's available.
ISO's are available.
You could say that it's Wimpressive, I'll say.
Oh, don't.
This is what all my school teachers used to put on my school reports, thinking that they
were being clever and original.
What was it?
Wimpressive?
Hey Rob, did you hear that?
Wimpy basically called you a dick then.
Yeah, yeah, he totally did.
I'll see myself out.
It's okay.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's getting ready to flip some
old power PC equipment on the side to fund its RV ambitions.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
One of these days, Matt, I will be broadcasting this very show from the road.
I can't even say it's going to happen before episode 100, Matt.
One day.
One day, Chris will be in the Jupiter Broadcasting Mobile Studio, broadcasting the Unplugged
show.
And we'll have a real lug meetup with real in-person microphones.
This week, we're going to have a great show.
A project that you may or may not be familiar with, and maybe not familiar with as well,
as I should be, is the Arch Linux ARM project.
Now I don't really know what you would use Arch on an ARM device for, but I have a few
ideas.
So one of the members is going to join us to give us a little bit of background, tell
us what some people out there use Arch and ARM devices for, and we're going to pick his
brain and we're also going to have the mobile room ask any questions they might have.
And then in the second half of the show, something we've talked a lot about is delivering applications
on Linux.
Something where you could make an application and move it across distributions, maybe have
it secured from the rest of the system sandbox, so that way if the application has an exploit,
it can't really go very far.
Well, this week, we saw the first demo of a fully sandboxed application on the Linux
desktop, thanks to advancements in Wayland, and a lot of other things that we'll get into.
And it was actually a video game, a OpenGL video game that was fully sandboxed, fully
portable, and demoed this week on Linux, and we're going to talk about that and how far
out it might be.
It might be closer than you think.
So to get started, Matt, why don't we bring in that Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Greetings.
Hi.
Hello from Trinidad.
Well, hello from Trinidad.
Let's put Poppy right up there on the spot.
I just wanted to pick your brain, Poppy, on any updates.
Since we talked, the launch happened, the flash sale was very flashy, and I'm just curious
if you got any updates for us on how it's gone, and maybe we're going to see any future
sales.
Yeah.
We had a flash sale for the Ubuntu phone, the first Ubuntu phone, the BQ, last week
on Wednesday, just after the show where we discussed it.
Hence all the sales.
Yeah.
They sold out pretty quick in the morning, and so they ran another sale in the afternoon
and they sold out then as well, and I think they sold out in minutes, you know, really
stupidly quickly.
I don't think they quite anticipated how many people were going to buy them, but there'll
be more flash sales.
There'll be one this week at some point, BQ have said, so keep an eye on the Ubuntu Twitter
account and the BQ Reader's Twitter account for more info.
Any early feedback or responses or anything like that?
You guys just sort of like listening and collecting data right now?
What's going on right now at Canonical HQ after the phone finally ships?
Yeah.
Or I guess it hasn't shipped yet, but sales have gone out.
So I guess they're not...
Right.
We don't really have them in consumers' hands until, what, a month or so?
Well some are.
There's 30 of them for the people who came to London, and they've been giving us loads
of feedback.
You know, some of it we didn't go and ask for, they just started posting photos and
screenshots and, you know, problems that they've had or, you know, things they've liked, and
we've been gathering all this information, like, you know, stalking them all on their
social media accounts to see what they're posting and, you know, gather that feedback
and give it back to the developers.
But also some of them have been filing bugs and giving us log files and stuff when there
are problems.
So it's been a really useful exercise because they're using it in the real world.
Now Wimpy, you had a question that those of us maybe with a Nexus 4 or Nexus 5 device
want to know about.
Yeah.
So I've got the Nexus 4, which I've just had for a few days because I wasn't successful
in the flash sales last week, and I wanted to learn more.
So I've noticed there are some differences with what the Nexus 4 ships with versus what
the BQ ships with.
For example, the Scopes implementation on the BQ phone seems to be a little bit more
tightly integrated and it's got this today scope, and I was wondering if Canonical are
going to bring that same software enablement to the other devices.
So yeah, they should be.
I mean, the idea is that each manufacturer or carrier or OEM can tailor the experience
and add their little layer on the top and some of what you might see in screenshots
and videos of the BQ phone might be BQ specific stuff for Spain or for BQ's customers or based
on deals that BQ have with partners and that kind of stuff we probably wouldn't put on
other devices.
But the generic stuff like the today scope and nearby and other stuff, then that should
go into the store and it should be available to anyone.
It just hasn't yet been done.
I did ask you, you asked me earlier on Telegram and I pinged everyone and they said it's currently
in process.
Yeah, I'm being a bit of a stooge here, but you know, it was topical for me.
I have to say, having played with it, I get the scopes concept and I'm just disappointed
there are not more scopes built in for the core apps, because they're really...
So here's a bit of feedback for you, Popey.
Scopes to me are like a cross between widgets on Android and Google Now, and I don't know
if it's because I live outside North America, but Google Now for me is completely pointless.
It doesn't actually do anything useful, doesn't tell me anything that I want to know, so consequently
I go to great lengths to disable it on my Android devices.
I have to say, in just a couple of days of using Ubuntu phone, scopes actually deliver
the promise of what I thought Google Now was supposed to do, which was to keep me informed
about the things that I wanted to know about, because I've chosen to follow it, or because
it's geo-located around me and it makes me aware of my surroundings.
I'd like to see more scopes, particularly things like the...
There's a decent text messaging app, but there's no scope for it, and the killer app on Ubuntu
phone as far as I'm concerned is Telegram, because I've moved all of my immediate friends
and family over to it, and there's a scope for that and an app for that, and it's brilliant,
but the text messaging app lacks a scope, and I feel it needs one.
There's a scope for Telegram?
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
So it shows you your most recent messages and the people you contact the most, that
kind of stuff.
But we made a change in the way that apps are packaged so that you can bundle an app
and a scope together at the same time, so when a user or a customer installs it, they
get both and they share the same data set.
And that Telegram is an example of one of those.
And I agree with you.
We need more of those.
Yeah, that's fascinating.
I can't wait to play with it on an actual device.
And we won't know anything about that until more like June, right?
That's kind of the word?
What, for the US market?
Yeah, I think Christian Perrino teased to OMG Ubuntu a couple of weeks ago that we hope
to announce something in June for the US market.
So far away, Bobby.
Sorry.
That's all right.
It turns out making phones is hard.
Yeah.
Who knew?
Who would have thought, right?
Okay, so I wanted to kind of spend a moment to reflect positively upon Linux as a general
bit of real time feedback, as an exercise from the chat room and the mumble room.
And I'll start and then I'll have maybe Matt chime in with something that he would miss.
So every now and then, you have to spend a little time away from Linux, less and less
these days.
But every now and then it happens.
Maybe let's just say for the sake of argument, you're on the Windows platform.
So that way we can all just kind of focus on one thing.
What is it you miss the most from Linux?
I was inspired by a thread I saw a day ago on our Linux and it's a lot of great responses.
And I would like to be curious about your response.
So I'll tell you mine.
Just as like one of the first things I noticed when I sit down at a Windows box that I miss
when I'm sitting down at a Linux desktop is that you have to click to focus and then scroll
in order to get scroll to work.
Like you can't just bring your mouse over any random window and scroll it under Windows.
It has to be a focused window in order for the scroll to work.
It turns out I use that all the time with multiple Windows and stuff.
I always am scrolling Windows without wanting to actually click them.
Like maybe I have my web browser up and I'm also looking through a directory, but I want
my web browser to be the active window, but I still want to be able to scroll the list
of the file directory.
You can't do that in Windows.
You've got to click the Explorer window and then scroll it.
That is just like one of the first things.
Like there's a million things, but like in terms of like things that bug me when I move
away from Linux, that's one of the first.
Matt, do you have one that comes to mind?
I think the most annoying thing to me personally would definitely have to be the fact that
I can't just do a couple of button clicks and get the launcher that I want or even just
the menu layout in general is just obnoxious.
I mean that's been the big stuff that I've noticed.
Yeah, were you thinking, Popey, what, like KitKat, because there's like a program.
No, I mean years ago I used to do Focus Follows Mouse or Sloppy Focus or whatever you call
it.
On Windows 2000 there was a tweak for it from...
Focus Follows Mouse though is, I don't know, yeah, I don't know.
I thought that's basically what you, yeah, you can either have it raise the window or
not and if you have it not raise the window, put your mouse over it and scroll.
I mean, yeah, it's not built in.
It's not easy and it didn't work all the time.
What about you, Popey?
I love that.
When you're not on the Linux desktop, what are you missing the most?
Opening a terminal with Control-Alt-T.
Yeah.
Because I just find myself doing that all the time.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Yeah, Wimpy, you too?
Terminal?
Yeah, yeah, the terminal is the best hotkey utility ever created, so fire up a terminal
and then you can just ping off and manipulate everything on the system from a few keystrokes
and it's deeply frustrating to not have that on Windows.
Yeah, one of the nice things about it, basically every Linux desktop now is there's a built-in
launcher of some kind and some of them are better than others and then it's nothing like
that.
You have the start menu but it's not quite the same thing.
Eric, do you have any that jump out at you for things you miss when you step away from
Linux?
Yeah, well, you mentioned the terminal thing.
I also was thinking about, in terms of the terminal, I was just thinking it's nice to
have that F12 for like Yackquake or Guake for the terminals to just pop down.
So like if I need to get to the command line, I have to type Windows R to open that up.
So it's just, it gets really aggravating but also being able to tile my Windows where
I want them.
Windows Aerosnap only does the left or the right halves.
It won't do it in quadrants at all and I like that.
You know the big one, I'm surprised nobody's mentioned, the obvious one, package management.
Oh, duh, right?
How did I not mention?
Oh my God, I feel ashamed now.
Yeah.
And then of course, another big one is the virtual desktops.
The Windows is getting those things as well.
I mean, 10 is addressing a lot of these things, isn't it?
I believe also the scroll wheel thing is fixed in 10.
It does but it doesn't really properly address package management.
Please feel me as a proper launcher though.
Yeah.
Surprisingly, the thing I miss in Windows is pulse audio.
Really?
Yeah, right?
Yeah.
It's a fact that I can send it over the network instead of it just being on one machine easily
as well.
So, and how easily and how often do you actually take advantage of that feature?
Not often but it's a neat feature.
Yeah.
Yeah, I agree.
Even along those lines, being able to quickly change your input route, output device when
it comes to audio.
You can't do that very easily in Windows.
You can't.
You have to go into the control panel and mess with a few things and you can't do like
simultaneous outputs or simultaneous inputs or anything like that.
You have to choose one and stick with it.
Very interesting, gentlemen.
All right.
So, moving on.
I'll link to the main thread in our Linux.
They had a whole bunch of good ones in there.
Package management was the one that jumped out at me and then, of course, millions of
other things.
Nobody said wobbly Windows, unfortunately.
I'm sure...
Oh, oh.
Yeah.
Desktop cube.
Okay.
Very good.
Yeah.
Burning your Windows when you close them.
That kind of stuff.
Yeah.
Not was.
Is cool in my world, Matt.
Is cool.
Hey, you know what else is cool?
Our first sponsor this week.
That's Linux Academy.
Head over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and get our special 33% discount.
Linux Academy is a great resource to go train yourself up on something.
They have step-by-step video courses with everything you're going to learn, downloadable
comprehensive study guides.
A lot of the materials you can just download and pop in your MP3 player and listen in the
shower or listen on the road.
As a podcast, it's great supplemental learning material.
They have learning plans so you can set your availability.
They have seven plus distros you get to choose from and all of the courseware will adjust
to those distributions.
And they have some really good stuff because the thing is is the guys behind Linux Academy
are really passionate about the source material.
They don't run courses on Photoshop.
They don't run courses on AutoCAD.
They focus in on this material because this is their world.
Linux enthusiasts, educators, and developers came together to create Linux Academy.
And it's successful because of that because once you get in there, once you start using
their dashboard and see how easily it is to wrap your head around what you're going to
have to do, how each section is broken out, how they have all of the courseware, how everything
kept up to date.
If there's changes in Docker, they make those changes in their courseware.
They have live streams where you can ask the educator questions and those educators are
currently up to date.
They're deploying this stuff and you get to deploy this stuff too because they have scenario
based labs.
So if you're going to go do an NGINX implementation with like an Amazon S3 backend storage, they're
going to have a scenario that actually has you use those utilities including provisioning
that storage and setting that up and getting all of that to work with every application
you're going to be using to do that storage and talk to S3.
You actually get to work with this stuff so you have a real idea of how to use it when
you're out in the real world.
And you're ready to go get trained and they have a good community too that constantly
helps lift you up if you slow down a little bit.
And really I think one of the other things that I've liked a lot about it is I can go
in there and kind of jump around and see what's new and interesting to me.
Because I honestly really haven't had a chance to play with some of the stuff as I've got
out of consulting a little while ago.
And it's great.
Like when I'm ready to jump into a new language like Ruby or Python, they have courseware
on that.
Including a whole set of courseware on AWS and they've really got some great stuff.
And they're adding stuff like new Live Labs two to three times a week right now.
And they also have accounts for groups.
So if you have a business and you want to have a group of you on there, that's a great
way to work together.
They've got Python, OpenStack, Android, Linux courseware, Red Hat specific stuff which is
always extremely valuable, PHP, Android, it's really good, DevOps, Ruby and the list goes
on and on.
I just go over there from time to time and just check out some of the new stuff because
they're always adding stuff and they're really good about updating the community in the news
section when you log in.
Just go try out the dashboard.
So go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and go poke around.
It's a great opportunity to take it up to the next notch and they've got lots of great
resources for you to try it out.
And I want to do a little PSA.
So this weekend is scale.
And I don't know how many folks, let's see, anybody in the Mumba room going to be at scale
this weekend?
It's going to be February 19th to the 22nd.
Nobody.
But one of my coworkers is.
Okay, very good.
Well Noah will be there.
He'll be there this weekend and he'll be there Sunday live during the Linux action show.
So you can hunt him down.
So scale is the 13th, this is going to be the 13th annual Southern California Linux
Expo.
It's going to be the Hilton Los Angeles Airport.
And you can bump into Noah and say hi to him and he'll be tweeting from his Twitter account
at Colonel Linux for where he's currently ranting about how much he hates PayPal right
there.
Oh yeah.
You know what I'm going to do?
I'm going to give that a favorite.
I think I might as well.
I've been on that side of it.
Oh, you've done something odd that we're just going to go and hold onto your stuff forever.
So he'll be tweeting if you want to meet up with him and then during the Linux action
show he's going to try to do it live from the floor and if he can get a hardwired connection,
hey if anybody from scale is listening and you want to hook Noah up with a hardwired
connection we here would really appreciate that because he wants to give you free coverage
live from the floor and he's also going to be there conducting interviews so if you are
there and want to hook up with Noah you can email him, noah at jupitabroadcasting.com and
talk with him and he'll probably get you on camera and then so here's, this is a good
time for me to mention this.
So this, because we're doing this, scale is landing during the Beardpocalypse.
I don't know if you guys know about this but we are currently going, starting Friday, Jupiter
Broadcasting goes nearly dark.
There's a Beardpocalypse.
We are running on a reduced staff.
Reduced staff next week and so.
We need like an evil bumper set for this.
I do have a few things.
I could try out a few things and Matt won't be able to hear them but Erica, here you tell
me if you think, is that appropriate?
No?
Okay how about this one?
Next week is Jupiter Broadcasting's Beardpocalypse.
There we go.
Perfect.
It's the Beardpocalypse next week and so there's going to be a reduced show load next week.
You'll hear more about that soon and one of the things we're doing is Linux action show
on Sunday's release.
It's going to be a retro blasted action of the Linux action show where we've gone back
through your best of submissions, dusted off the ones that didn't suck and then we kind
of gave them a massage and then put them in a righteous position of hindsight and then
allowed you to re-watch them.
You're welcome.
And I show up from time to time with random anecdotes and tell you about people I love.
So that'll be on Sunday's Linux action show that'll get released into the feeds.
We will be live though on Sunday doing scale coverage.
We just will not be releasing it that Sunday.
It'll be the following Sunday where we do a scale extravaganza and we put all of Noah's
on location live coverage and pre-recorded interviews in one episode and we make it the
master scale episode and that'll be it.
So if you followed all of that, good job.
If you didn't follow all of that, screw you.
I'm sorry.
There's nothing I can do about it.
It's complicated.
Welcome to the world of production.
And then let's talk about something that's really going to rock and I don't even need
to ask the Mumble Room because I know every single one of those Mo's in the Mumble Room
is going to be at Linux Fest Northwest in Bellingham, Washington, April 25th to the
26th.
We're going to try to get as much of the Jupiter Broadcasting crew out there and have as big
of a party as possible.
If you want to party with us, you better show up early because I think we're going to be
partying Friday night and then Saturday and Sunday we'll do a live Linux action show on
Sunday.
Saturday I plan to kind of get up and go around and maybe not sit at the booth the whole day
this time.
I don't know.
Yeah.
But, yeah.
And we're going to have, we're going to try to get extra space mats so we can have a good
spot for How To Linux and Women's Tech Radio and we'll be doing some interviews for some
shows at Linux Fest Northwest.
So that's going to be a big show to go to and most of the Jupiter Broadcasting crew's
going to be at that one.
So if you want to say hi to people and we'll have swag there of course and all that kind
of stuff.
We'll have stuff to give away and it's going to be a good show so you can book it now if
you want.
It's April 25th and the 26th, Bellingham, Washington.
It's going to be a pretty good party.
And no food illness.
This will be the second year in a row.
Oh yeah.
I'm going to make sure it's going to happen.
I'm going to wear, I'll be the guy in the really weird mask.
I still remember that one year like it was yesterday.
Oh my God.
Yeah.
All right.
I just, I had a quick question while we have everybody assemble.
Yeah.
I know.
It came in from the subreddit from RDP5008.
Hey guys, I finally decided to try Guake and I'm loving it.
Now if you're watching the video version, boom, that's Guake right there.
Bam.
It just drops right down.
It's a terminal that I just hit with my tilde key.
Bam.
There it's great.
Boom.
All right.
And when I go to drop down terminal and I go to drop down terminals online, is Guake
the original or are there other worthy alternatives?
Please educate me.
I'm running Linux Mint 17 cinnamon on my laptop, Arch with normal on my desktop and a bunch
to 14 report a bunch on my HTPC and I want me some drop down terminals.
So he was curious about dropdown terminal alternatives and I realized I'm kind of a
Guake bigot, I guess I've never looked outside of Guake.
Gosh.
I listen on KDE.
Yeah, right.
I think I'm going to fall into the same category.
All right Wimpy, you know of one, right?
I know of two others.
Lay it on me brother.
okay okay there's one called yeah yeah quake yes another quake right I've not
used that there's another and there's yet another one simply called tilde which
has all of the features of quake but it uses more modern underpinnings for
managing configuration and such and it is significantly lighter on memory
resources and I've integrated that into Ubuntu mate 1504 so when you install
Ubuntu mate 1504 you zap f12 or tilde and you get a drop-down terminal all
themed and matching the Ubuntu mate desktop well now I recommend Tilda oh
okay so Tilda yeah I saw that also recommend in the subreddit so I will
look into that yeah Tilda a go T I L D a and the site on
the source for it does not seem to be working but I'm sure it's in everybody's repo and
it's also on guess what surprise surprise there's also an arch wiki post
about it everybody shot I know it's oh yeah shotgun stand yeah all right I'll
put a link to the github page oh yeah this is this looks nice this looks
really nice I'm gonna put a link to that in the show notes for people that the
people that want to grab it only runs in five mix of RAM so I like it for that
reason whoa do you do have a music in the chat room mentions xfce drop down
terminal and cue terminal has dropped out as well so there's a couple more okay
I know it I mean wimpy do you happen to remember what quakes memory usage was
compared comparatively ah it was several times that it was about 30 Megs because
it's um Python application and it uses the old g-comp for settings and what
have you I'm gonna look right now yeah I'm 28 6 right now are you really eight
megabytes of RAM yeah it bounces in the beat up between that and 30 yeah all
right I'm yeah that's I'm switching that's that tears it that is crazy I
never even thought to look like look at that I pride myself on stripping the
stuff now and I'd love to switch I'm sorry what was that you pride yourself
on I pride myself on stripping it I pride myself on you know running down
hard to the metals again so I think I'm gonna switch this looks really cool are
you still on mate man oh yeah yeah oh man I I've not worked back I've taught
and I I did elementary kind of lulled me over on one of my one of my old laptops
that I had and it barely runs but you know I got it going you know it's like
oh that was cool for about ten minutes and then I kind of you know but all my
other computers run mate it just just what I do sure so before we get on to
arch Linux arm right arm arm arch Linux did anybody want to touch on the
elementary OS topic I know rotten corpse you mentioned you wanted to bring it up
so I was gonna open the flight up I don't want this to turn into like a dog
pile thing on the project though but if there's any follow-up I'm happy to hear
well I don't want to you know attack him or anything but there was a part in the
interview where Noah asked him do you know how much has been how much of the
money has been updated has been sent to Debbie and in a bun to because they were
talking about the entire operating system yeah and the answer is nothing I
thought it was like a couple hundred dollars or something no they're bounty
source actually bounty source is not really that good of an idea because the
concept is it's good but it's also broken because they you're fit you're
not paying the project you're paying the developer who fixes a particular bug so
if someone just comes in and fixes it that just fixes that one bug and you're
paying for that bug but that that doesn't even mean that that bug is a
really good fix and that the project will even take the fix so not they don't
get the money and they don't maybe don't even get the fix in the first place but
there has only been like roughly there's like okay GTK get like 35 bucks don't
you feel like like saying that the poor people aren't donating to people more
like I mean they're they're currently clearly saying they're not making enough
money as it is well no they made well they allow themselves to call other
people cheers for not contribute well also and it's not that they don't have
the money is because they spent $1,300 fixing bugs in my Pantheon files I mean
if they just gave anything at all to Ubuntu or Debian that'd be fine it's not
it's not about the money anyway it's it's the fact that they say that they
don't know when they do know and it's nothing and also that they are still
claiming that for their for one they're claiming that they're asking for money
for the entire operating system which they're not actually putting money into
the entire operating system they're also saying that you're not cheating us
you're cheating open source so implying that not paying for elementary is
somehow cheating the entire open source ecosystem and that's just absurd
www as a user of the OS you want to chime in yeah you can consider me an
ex-user I'm gonna move to kaboom 2 I've talked to the mumble room throughout the
week in depth about this since even before this happened and I've talked to
some devs that have tried to contribute to the project and been spurned away
and I'm just I'm just kind of done with what I what I've seen the how the
community has been managed like Eric has said in the past and things like that
I'm just gonna move on to something else and maybe even think about getting more
technical knowledge on Linux to do my own distro eventually or do contribute
more to other distros so that's actually good so daredevil and I mean
he would love to cap this entire thing off but now some rumor-mongering go ahead
there devil good guys it has been a while the problem is mostly the people
apparently the looks are good the technicalities could be improved and the
problem is on the social aspect I see a forthcoming mmm we'll see we'll see I
will see I think this distribution what it is is that what we're watching is can
can can a distribution be led by truly just led by ultimate ultimate design and
if you if that is the distribution's purpose and you fork it and you don't
have those people okay what's the point but we'll see I'd be really I would be
skeptical if I was well one possibility and this is horrible and I hate myself
for even mentioning this but I think one possibility that could happen if someone
forks it and essentially waits for elementary to do a UI update and then
they say oh that's great we take the they take the code they update it to
their fork and they sit there nothing happens and that happens I that's how I
see them overcoming the design thing it's a horrible thing but you know karma's
a beyond becomes the upstream and they start sending it's not sending us the
package of patches and stuff up to them it could happen but the other thing is
it's just one more thing is that people typically are saying that why are you
getting mad at people wanting for money and no one's doing that it's not about
the money if they ask for money great feel free if they sell it for money and
they don't actually give out buying Azure free that's fine there's a lot of
dishes that already do that I don't care it's not about that it's about them
telling people that they are doing something wrong when they're actually
just doing what they said they could do that's a messaging thing that they'll
work on and this is what I point to you when they say we don't need community
managers oh yes you do well yes you do provoke a you had an interesting piece
over at data nation people should go check out yeah take distributions it
kind of fits in with this whole thing check out Matt's article over data
nation calm all right well so we gotta let's let's talk about arch and arm here
for a sec I mean this is come on come on this is why we're gathered here today so
real quick I'll mention our next sponsor and we'll do that digital ocean head
over to digital ocean right now and and but guess what you can go over there and
I'm gonna give you something that makes you a little special so you're not like
all those other people that are visiting digital ocean it's a popular website it
gets some traffic but you my friend you have the unique promo code of power do
unplugged one word lowercase $10 credit over there you're gonna be one of the
few the elite that has that and supports our show and they go over to digital
ocean comm and what is digital ocean digital ocean is simple cloud hosting
provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive easy way for you to spin up
your own cloud server users can get started in less than 55 seconds and
pricing plan started only $5 per month they get your 512 megabytes of RAM a 20
gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte terabyte of transfer and digital ocean
is data center locations in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam and
London but boy let me tell you oh just go over there check this out this is a
masterpiece in design right there speaking a good design it's dat interface
it's intuitive control panel and you can replicate that functionality on a much
larger scale because digital ocean has an API and it's a good API son I'm
saying it's a good one and people are already taking advantage of it because
it's so good you know when something's good people use it like digital ocean
and they're great API so there's a lot of great apps you can just take
advantage of right now that make it even more powerful like command-line stuff
for your Linux box applets for your Ubuntu menu shoot they probably got
scopes who knows go check it out you can write your own you you could write the
first Ubuntu phone scope oh my gosh you should do this actually you should go
over to digital ocean and write a scope for the Ubuntu touch phone thingy to
manage your droplet that would be so awesome because they got a straightforward
API you can do that you can manage your systems you got your DNS management your
snapshots your one-click installations all through this crazy great interface
all sitting on top of Linux powered by KVM all riding on top of SSD drives so
that way you get that IO performance then connected to tier one bandwidth it
is an amazing package and you can try it out two months for free when you use the
promo code do unplugged I love it we're gonna tell you more about our super cool
video conferencing system that we built for last that's all fancy HD great audio
quality high-fidelity all powered by digital ocean droplets we'll tell you
more about it in an upcoming episode and it's like when I go to deploy some
infrastructure on Linux now this is just where I go it's so fast it's so great
the values there and it's all under one account digital ocean comm do unplug when
you check out in a big thank you digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplugged
program alright so let's bring in warhead here hey warhead welcome to the
Linux unplugged show and first of all start with your first name because I
don't want to just you have you on the internet known as warhead and tell us a
little bit about yourself don't worry I've already been known around the
internet for about ten years as warheads anyways okay my actual name is Jason
plum okay and I'm one of the core developers well Jason I'm really glad
you could make it because this is getting to be a pretty interesting
category and it's one that we want to spend a little more time talking about
from time to time on the unplugged show and maybe we could start could you give
us a little background on the arch Linux arm project like when it's been around
and anything like that the UK to share with us yeah sure so in 2009 before I
was actually involved with the project a little thing that some of you may have
heard of called the Shiva plug came out of the market oh yeah and at the time
the only thing you could get was Debian and a particularly aging version of
Debian at the time as well and then after that a commercial piece called the
pogo plug came out of the market after that and you had a very specific set of
change and everything went out of date rather horribly fast but at the same
time people went this box literally is the same thing as the Shiva box and I
can get it for a reasonable price hmm what if I can run the full-blown Linux
instead of just what they gave me hmm and that's where the original project of
open pogo came along that was where you would have our binaries that would you
would use on that through an originally a mix through IP case so it was sort of
in the Debian behavior and then we became plug block plug box in early 2010
and that's when we actually became officially a port of arch to the arm
architecture and at the time we only had arm v5 support now this isn't
necessarily so could you help me understand the relationship between I
arch Linux arm and arch Linux it's because it's not officially part of arch
is that correct or am I wrong no you're very much correct we are not the same
distribution if you go to their forums and ask about our stuff they will point
you at us and if you ask us about Nvidia we will point you at them either which
way neither one of us knows how to fix those proprietary bits if we aren't
familiar with it hmm just kind of how it is but we actually got our name as it is
today in early 2011 and before we did that we got permission from the arch
Linux team and everybody involved there to use the name arch Linux appropriately
and contacted arm and got their rights to actually use the arm name and the
logo obviously unaltered so we can actually call ourselves and label
ourselves arch Linux arm so we are a complete port that is separate from arch
Linux but we derive 90% of our package builds directly from the ABS trees a you
are etc and then anything that we do differently we put into our github okay
so that sounds pretty actually pretty clean and pretty manageable really from
like from a standpoint of somebody on my side and wimpy you wanted to kind of
mention something up from the arch developer side yeah when when I was was
first working on the Marte packages for arch Linux I was aware that alarm take
the packages from the ABS tree and cross compile them and build them into their
repository so and I it's still running here I've got four alarm boxes running
in a cluster here that we're doing that initial building work and I built all of
my packages on arm to make sure when I release them into the official repository
they'd build cleanly and just flow into arch Linux arm and I know other
developers are mindful of that and do some testing before they release things
and there's this good bug reporting coming back the other way from the alarm
team into the arch bug tracker if we release something that doesn't build on
on arm very good so warhead what would be so this is when I told a few folks
that we're gonna be chatting with you on the show today they said this so the
response I got is oh why would you run arch on an arm device like what's the
advantage there and so warhead what are some typical use cases for arch on there
okay so what's the biggest problem that you see with an Ubuntu install from
somebody who has used arch and you know that when you install Ubuntu out of the
box what's the biggest difference between an Ubuntu or a fedora 20 etc
so arch install it's not even necessarily the age no it's your amount
of decisions that have been made for you yeah yeah of course sure but couldn't
you say I mean there's other there's a ways of paring that down there's things
coming along yes is it is it not is it not the rolling nature that is appealing
to some people is that not part of it no the rolling nature and the being able to
keep up with upstream packages at the speed at which arch itself can keep up
with those is definitely the advantage of being able to run arch on an arm
device especially where you have kernels that are evolving at a weekly pace right
we have some of our devices that are actually running RC kernels they get
rebuilt every time Linus tags hmm yeah and this area is under you have element
it isn't ridiculously rapid development and now we're finally getting
manufacturers to listen to us and begin doing the mainline work Marvel was
traditionally a problem in that area and they've been kind enough to listen to us
after several years of going please please please can you try and they've
enlisted to help with the guys over at free electrons and it's where you see a
lot of the Marvel tree the and the EBU architecture stuff coming in from their
work that's fascinating and so has it been just the size of the community over
time has gotten larger has it been the persistence that you think has made them
start listening to what has changed that attitude on their part as more
consumers get the devices and say somebody gets an older Android tablet
that they've they can now run Linux on now tablets being a really special case
because of the nature of the drivers but the pogo plugs the NAS devices that you
may have floating around the office or have given to one of your clients in the
past the various other things that are available I mean the entire generations
of the Beagle boards the Beagle bones of course the Raspberry Pi one and two the
entire o droid line everything that olem X makes like cannot leave them out they
have created a demand in a market space that didn't exist before and previously
you were as a manufacturer working almost exclusively with corporate and
you're dealing with things that are going to be put in place and then
maintained at their state and then replaced in the near future hmm whereas
now you're getting consumer device who generally speaking these are people that
are technical and they want to go and see hey how well can I make this work in
a low power environment be that from a power usage standpoint or a low CPU
power you know which way do they want to look at that aspect and they're
realizing that to really keep up with the Linux world they can't sit in the
dark ages and just plug their ears and I remember if anybody has any questions
for I guess take me mum in the chat room I I guess what I wanted to kind of get
out of you is I'm trying to I'm still trying to place all of this in in in my
world in context in my world and so I'm curious from you warhead what is sort of
one of your favorite implementations of an arch arm powered maybe it's a server
maybe it's a it's powering a combat robot I don't know but could you give me
an example of an implementation where you've been like that is a great use of
that technology I may set the mumble room off but I do know of at least three
drones that are running us personally I have a Zeiss L NAS 325 under my desk
that runs the lighting control inside my house runs MPD that streams out to my
chromecasts and is one of my primary sources to feed my chromecasts through
my plex that's pretty neat and rotten curves you had a you had it wasn't me
on ring for noobs yeah is the arch Linux package in early structure in the noobs
for Raspberry Pi is that an alarm build the original images were made by us the
foundation was not able to keep up we issued a new image on a monthly basis
and they generally updated the image every three months and at that point it
was a month behind every time so now we are only available through the net
installer type which uses a download to get the tar to actually do the install
so that's why we don't make SD card image files anymore because their CDN
apparently couldn't update fast enough but the there's the news has an install
doesn't it then there is now a net install noobs SD card image yes but the
here's my noobs image that has all the distro bits on it no we are no longer a
part of that image okay okay very good so warhead if I'm listening at home and
I'm thinking okay maybe I want to start playing with this I know I can get a
device that's not too much money I could load Linux on there what's your favorite
what are you recommending people grab the Raspberry Pi what do you tell people
to try with they're gonna jump into this I think it really depends on what
exactly they want to learn what are they already familiar with when it comes to
Linux personally if you want something low power that has all the options you
want to be able to get to the Odroid c1 is an awesome choice if you want to
learn about how all the components interact and maybe can take some of your
knowledge from Arduino and immediately apply it over into running with Linux
and having all the GPIO and SPI access that's very direct and has a lot of
existing documentation through sites like Adafruit etc then the pie and the
pie two are possible options but if you're looking for sheer capability the
Odroid line currently outclasses everyone on the market except for the
Chromebooks ah yeah I'm noticing in your forums it seems like a lot of people
like the Odroid a lot of people using that in there so yeah well you get a
very performant device and they come with the capability of using eMMC 5.0
which is a ridiculously fast storage medium the Raspberry Pi 1 & 2 have the
same SD controller that runs at the same speed and also the Ethernet is much
faster on the c1 as well yeah because it's actually attached to a bus
design for Ethernet big difference then yeah a lot of people talking about the
c1 c1 on the arch Linux arm dot org form so it looks like that yeah the Odroid c1
hits the price point of the Raspberry Pi and even if you take the direct
comparison between the Raspberry Pi 2 and the c1 yeah that had been done all
over the place on the net at this point yeah it definitely comes down to exactly
what you want to do with it there are some things in which the Raspberry Pi
does win unfortunately most of our users would prefer the performance and
behavior that you get out of the c1 yeah that makes sense and it seems like
that'd be a good way a good way to go if you want support from the community too
yeah right well again it's all which way you want to go but yeah warhead thank
you for the fascinating insights I mean I then I'll just I'm just kind of
getting you know my head wrapped around all of this and I appreciate any kind of
info is there anything you want to touch on before we run yeah just remember that
it's not arch arm it's not arm arch it is arch Linux arm if you want to
abbreviate it's alarm alarm arch Linux arm or alarm I like it and I'll put a
link to the to the board you were talking about up on your on your site
there well check in with us from time to time and keep us up to date on cool
developments and stuff well the appropriate people know how to reach me
yeah very good well and I I one of these days one of these days I'm actually gonna
get around to setting up a Raspberry Pi in here because I have one from the same
person who got in touch with you a little birdie yeah I think you have a
u3 floating around somewhere too yeah maybe so maybe so oh I guess and
mandatory I should ask you where do you want folks to go to find out more about
the project oh that's very simple arch Linux arm org there you go arts Linux
arm org and we will have a link in the show notes I might also put a link to
Jason's blog in there and the team link on the wiki as well all right well
warhead you sir are more than welcome to stick around we're going to shoot the
the breeze on the first actual sandbox Linux application that seems to be
portable but first I'm going to tell you about my cell phone provider and that's
ting go to linux.ting.com right now once you and support this show you also got a
$25 discount off your first ting device or a $25 credit ting is mobile that
really does make sense no more contracts no more early to my name no more
illiterate nation fees $6 a month and then you just pay for your usage they
have an amazing dashboard that kicks every single other dashboard or those
other guys don't even have dashboards so I guess I don't even call them that
they're crappy little slow websites that are horrible and seem like they're
designed for an explorer don't even hold a candle to what ting can do so not only
does ting have the best dashboard out there kicks all their butts they've also
got no whole customer service they got a whole great range of devices they're
unlocked they're adding GSM supports they're gonna have CDMA and GSM support
by the end of the month they're rolling out a beta program right now you can go
pre-order an iPhone 6 or get yourself a fancy one of them I think I think myself
the new moto x2 looks really sweet anyways they got a whole range of
devices seriously I want you to go over to ting and check them out they are an
amazing company and where your money should go because think about this if
they're doing this and they're putting pressure on the big guys and if we can
get them to keep putting pressure on the big guys that's good for the entire damn
mobile industry and one of the things I'd like to recommend you check out from
time to time is the ting blog they have stuff posted up there all the time and
this is really a great way to get sort of insights into the company and they
just recently read refined a few feet of a few details on their bring your own
device program and they have those changes up on their block again no
contract nor the termination fee you only pay for what you use and they also
have an early termination relief program if you're stuck in a contract right now
it's flat six dollars for the month then it's just your usage on top of that no
hold customer service go check them out at linux.ting.com I've been using them
for over two years and I'm even more excited than ever as a customer out of
the rolling out GSM because when I go to events and stuff like that I'm just
gonna use whichever network works best and I know things gonna have that super
dialed in linux.ting.com supports the show and gets you a discount off your
first device thanks to ting for sponsoring the Linux unplugged show and
thanks to you guys for supporting our sponsor so the first fully sandbox Linux
desktop app was showed off this week it's pretty exciting has a few
requirements no x11 right there totally impossible if you have x11 cannot do it
it cannot be secured enough got to have Wayland and they also have to have KD
bus which means you got to have a super modern kernel and totally up-to-date
system D to allow desktop integration to port fully be filtered down to the
kernel level so wait recently using the big strides made in Wayland loaded on
fedora 21 we can start to see some true genuine sandboxing and this is over on
Alexander Larson's blog he's a developer and right here he's gonna start on a
fedora workstation a build of never ball running inside an absolute minimal
sandbox it is absolutely independent of the host distribution has no access to
any system or user files other than the ones from the runtime and the
application itself has no access to hardware devices other than DRI for GL
render because that's what's been allowed no network access I can only get
input via Wayland can only show graphics via Wayland can only do audio out via
pulse audio and of course all the other benefits of sandboxing like can't touch
other stuff on the file system and as you would expect as he starts it up he
builds the container right here so he's just done he's just done all of that and
now he's about to fire it up and he runs it from the gnome launcher and from the
gnome launcher it starts up in a sandboxed environment and now he's
playing never ball in a sandbox that is so wild and in theory he could pick this
up and move another distribution if they had all of the same things like Wayland
KD bus system D and all of that it is so crazy trying to think back to when we
had the whole monkey suit bet and all that and where all things are evolving
to now yeah with Wayland and everything and what Wayland's making possible well
that's what I found really striking about the entire thing is that this is
possible like almost before all of this technology is laid down mm-hmm it's like
it's like here that we're gonna do where we're gonna do KD bus that we I mean
obviously you couldn't ship this today but it's not close up poppy go ahead
you were something it's what do we get wrong something on the details what
what's the matter no no I'm confused as to how this is the first given the unity
next desktop ISO that's been around for months has had siloed applications like
this already so I'm confused how this is the first this is the first one of the
this is the first one of the kind of version that we've been talking about
for several episodes like this this whole gnome start with the gnome
application go all the way down to the kernel sandboxing right which we have on
Ubuntu I which is why I'm confused why this is the first fully sandboxed Linux
desktop app when it's the only one I mean this is the one this is the this is
what we've been talking about for a few weeks it's gonna be coming and now it's
right I don't I don't know I'm using this implementation yes yes yeah you're
using Wayland and under context using all that but I'm sure I'm sure I'm sure
Ubuntu's is very nice poppy I'm sure I'm sure lots of people use how does it is
it now is the sandboxing under is it Ubuntu is it legitimate sandboxing or is
it app armor and enforced profiles it's a palmer so it's not really sandboxing
why not well if you let go through the end go through the steps that he's got
there no access to system files check no access to hardware devices check no
network access check how it's actually done though like the way so so the app
armor is things happen it's checked against a set of rules and then denied
whereas in sandboxing those things just don't even exist for the application I
mean it's not really I mean at the end of the day it's kind of the same thing
but fundamentally like the application under app armor can be aware that there
is a device out there it just is denied access to that device whereas a
sandboxed application would be completely unaware that there's even a
hardware device to begin with I think you're splitting hairs I mean if you
want to if but if you wanted to if you wanted to say that you could say Sousa
had sandboxing ten years ago when they first shipped that open open Sousa or
when they first shipped Sousa Enterprise with with app arm I mean that's not it's
interpretation of a definition I at the end of the day I kind of leaning with
where Chris is at and that one one's missing these things and another one's
comparing them based on rules that seems like a fairly good thing how we label
them we could label one you know a Pepsi challenge one and then Pepsi
challenge to just kind of put that I'll tell you the difference the reason why
I'm talking about this one because this is the first one where you could see
this this is something you could pick it up and move it between distros right
you don't have to have app armor profiles it's not it's not a boon to
specific this would move you could pick this up and have the same stack on an
arch box and run never ball in on the arch desktop and that's kind of the big
piece interesting right yeah so I don't know if now the other question is how do
you deliver that but yeah yeah and it's all up in the air who knows I mean a
lot of technologies as well though yeah which need to be there yeah not as
widespread yet very nascent technologies right now yeah so I think I think it's
interesting to watch but I think like like you're saying it's not gonna be
probably not even this year maybe because you figure there's no way you're
gonna get out in the next couple of distro release cycles no way so you know
if you think of it in terms of distro release cycles it's a ways out it's not
coming well and this particular implementation is as you put you know
it's a ways out where a boon to his implementation and their vision of doing
essentially you know their vision of it is available to everyone now so that I
mean there's some benefits there too you could go up armor up by your ability
right now yeah you betcha and I you know I I also just from somebody who had to
implement app armor and se Linux I always found app armor to be a little
easier to use but yeah I have I actually prefer so and better branding hey one
actually one last story that just because every now that I like to prove
that Richard Stallman was absolutely right and we probably should have been
listening to RMS all along okay yeah that's cool no I did you hear about the
equation group where the Kaspersky Kaspersky labs Kaspersky the Kaspersky
labs guys over in Moscow have pinned hard hard drive firmware based malware
square on the nose of the NSA and it kind of makes that Richard Stallman's
point that all the firmware in your machine should be free I'm just saying
oh no I agree with his vision that's just the implementation that I have
concerns about but now in defense of his vision he's been spot-on for a while I
mean like really spot-on I just wish there was a way to give him another
spokesman maybe in front of him that is more presentable to the company I mean
I mean even Richard Stallman has to use a hard drive how can I exactly can you
how can you like how can we as just regular like just humans how can we
possibly think about the firmware in every single device like can't be done
and that's the problem that's the rub is is you're basically forced into you know
living living in a cabin in the woods and just saying screw everything or you
know basically accepting a certain level of it and I say accepting with a shutter
I hate the idea myself but you know there's a certain level of we're here
and unfortunately our ability all we can do is make everyone known know about it
and hopefully folks will gripe enough that something will happen maybe enough
open source projects will get together and create a multi-billion dollar
company that can start reproducing these pieces of hardware without that stuff I
don't know I wish it would happen I really do but I just have concerns that
it may be too late I hate to say that but you know I mean there doesn't you
want to chime in with something yes one is once it becomes a company and the
off the suggestion might just give it becomes usually tight or to
responsibilities to a government so it may just result into the same thing
again that said there is another thing that I sometimes really wonder is we
campaign so much because what there was a potential was that campaign an open
eyes an opening of eyes off the actual potential right leveraging that did it
did they make them aware of it yes because it's like in like 13 years it's
more than 30 years with this mission and this for example this project is 14
years so it's off it's a baby that's funny that's a good catch I don't think
so I think they're probably pretty clever to figure out on their own but
that is sort of funny like a self-fulfilling prophecy if you had a
time machine the way to prevent massive NSA surveillance would be to make RMS
not out there warning of it that's a big great that'd be a great Linux nerd novel
right there I think that would be right travel and dinosaurs and you got
yourself a seller dude RMS fan fiction why is this not a thing I think it has
to become one okay so one last little public service announcement before we
run so as we talked about and I got to tell you I maybe gonna have to go find
myself some anxiety medications it's gonna be it's dramatic but as we said
next week is
so your Linux unplugged show episode 81 will be a retro extravaganza of your best
of moments but don't worry see these new these are like it's new in a way it's
stuff you've seen your favorite moments but now available with the self
gratifying feature that we've just implemented known as hindsight so now
you can listen to the things we said with that smug hindsight and nail
everything we say nails for it so they were just gonna do that next week
because of the beard apocalypse and then we'll be back in full force with the
show in episode 82 but it's gonna be good episode because they're all the
ones that you guys submitted a while ago when we did the best of for the holiday
season there were so many and we threw out a bunch of they're like wait a minute
these these are really good we should use these again we're like what would we
ever use these for we're not gonna do a best of we're never gonna take a week
off and then we guys like actually yeah I gotta leave and nobody's gonna be here
to edit and that's the weekend of scale so and I'm like oh you know what maybe a
best of would be a good idea and so it's not a best of it's a retro look back I
don't know what the difference is other than it's slightly different wording
branding yeah yeah exactly Matt so you get to take next Tuesday off but tune in
and listen to all the crazy things you said as like you know homework or
something okay sounds good sounds good and I'll go check out Matt's article of
data nation is a great article about the danger or risk I guess of boutique
Linux distributions as I got totally nailed it totally nailed it and you could
also comment come over join us live on Tuesdays over JB live TV hang out in the
mumble room Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar for the local time alright everybody
thanks so much to this week's episode join us next week for episode 81 when we
have the retro flavored edition of unplugged
we should do we gotta get like a special group of people sending like a runs
Linux in the field we need more runs Linux in the yes so if that would be
cool when you're traveling or something and take a picture I'll even accept a
selfie if it's in front of a Linux machine send it into the Linux action
show Jupiter broadcasting.com with runs Linux in the subject I'll have to get
you an aerial picture yeah I need to get up to Ferndale and see I've been meaning
to do this for a while I need to get up to Ferndale and see Jed cuz he's got
he's got lots of runs Linux up there yeah that'd be great that'd be some
really cool stuff a lot of heavy networking armed with ARCH sound the
alarm those are good JBtitles.com do you see that American prison where
they're learning development on Linux yeah I did that's you know well it's
shaking more time you don't have to pay for to educate people on the system to
be able to do something when they get out oh we're paying there you go trust
me you're paying for it yeah oh no we're paying for them to be there but we're
not paying to teach them to run an OS they don't have to pay for in the first
place yeah I'm the open source Regis that's what Regis is about.
yeah that beard pocalypse music is perfect because I did have a small heart
attack when you played it yeah your heart just drops in your your feet it's
like oh I'm gonna be playing a special edition of women's tech radio today on
the stream a little bit and you know there's some people they've been
interviewing some ladies on there that are big-time Linux users like one of
the one of the one of the gals they interviewed was a big system D fan
I was like what really oh they start how much system dealing okay that's
interesting that's cool yeah I was just at a play lug meeting last night where a
Gentoo developer was talking about system D oh if it got to the Ubuntu
project you know it's gonna eventually get to Gentoo those guys that are
going on if gentoo start talking about system D we're gonna have another system
the flame war they do have it separated out so you can actually replace open RC
at the time yeah to be able to do that now so you can actually replace open RC
or just install system DS binary so that you can manage remote items through
system D journal control machine control etc so I mean they're using bits and
pieces of it from the user land you can use it as the init you don't have to
etc ZFS for the wins just posted in the chat room about these bloody HP right
that so here's the the final report HP amazing HP are they are I don't have the
words actually I don't have the the derogatory superlative that sums up
their incompetence sufficiently so after they've done after trying to place the
order four times and and then and then cancelling it twice okay so on two
occasions they cancelled the order we placed so we were like right enough of
that nonsense we'll we'll just cancel the accessories order and we'll we'll
find something else my boss has been off in Singapore for three weeks doing some
business down there and of course you've got every vendor imaginable has got
storefront you know shops down there so he's been able to go around the
bazaars and have a look at everything and actually touch it feel it play with
it and and he's come to the right conclusion he's he's bought himself a
brand new think pad x1 carbon yeah that's what he's that's what he's got
and that's what he's traveling back with and I think this is a very wise
decision and then today we we get an email from Hewlett-Packard saying our
order has been dispatched and then and then moments later fuck mothering HP 14
Z turns up at the office two weeks after you cancelled the order and the things
just turned up and they've billed us for it this is two and a half weeks after
they dated the last order that they cancelled no as in you said they said an
email sent an email saying it was dispatched that oh moments yeah so it's
really been the gift that keeps on giving