There's a lot of news today in the show.
But this one, I'm just still reading the room.
Microsoft is said to be in discussions
to buy Discord for over $10 billion.
And you can see the advantage for Microsoft.
They could immediately get a very relevant chat platform.
There's potential integrations with their Xbox chat platform
there.
And they'd probably be willing to architect
in a way that makes surveillance entirely possible,
like they did for Skype.
So it's just a win for regulators.
It's a win for corporations.
It's a win for the Discord founders.
It doesn't feel like a win for the users, though.
And I wonder if this is going to be like a Matrix sale,
essentially.
Everybody check out Matrix.
It's over here, and it's great.
What?
You don't think they'll open source it?
No, I don't.
I don't.
Hello, friends, and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes, and yes, I am smelling what you're cooking,
but I'm just not sure about a crock pie in the studio.
Oh, you'll see later, buddy.
We'll see about that.
And I want to thank A Cloud Guru for sponsoring this episode.
It is brought to you by A Cloud Guru.
They are the leader in learning for the cloud,
Linux, and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses, thousands of hands-on labs.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at acloudguru.com.
Well, on today's episode, we're just kind of having fun,
because we're getting close to 400,
and we wanted to share one of our favorite WireGuard-powered
tricks to get around your ISP and get any system you
have behind a net, a public IP, and accessible
from the internet.
We do this often, so that way the chat room can abuse a box
that we have on our LAN.
So we've set up a hot box on Linode,
and we'll walk you through our favorite way
of accomplishing this trick.
It's pretty straightforward.
And we'll also chat with a new business that's
built on top of WireGuard and Linux that's
trying to make this even easier for you.
Plus, we have a bunch of community news.
We've got feedback.
We've got probably some pics if we've got time.
But more importantly, we have our esteemed room
of internet experts.
Time-appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, Virtual Lug.
Hello.
Hello, Chris.
Namaste.
A special hello to Dan the Rabbit in there
from Elementary OS.
Hello, Dan.
Nice to see you.
Hey, how's it going?
Also, Dalton Durst from Ubuntu Touch Project
is in there as well.
Hello, Dalton.
Cha-cha.
Hello.
Good to have you.
Of course, lots of friends.
We have lots of friends that we always have,
returning friends, too, in here.
So Brent, it's good to see you've been a little bit,
too.
Hope you're well.
I'm good.
Thanks for having me.
And of course, thank you to everyone
who makes it all the time.
We've got 17 people in there in total.
We have some in the quiet listening and most everybody
in the on-air room.
That's one of the things you can use our Mumble Room for
is just a live, low latency, very, very low latency,
high quality audio stream if you just want a live stream using
free software.
And then the whole stack's free because we're
doing it on Linux using free software
and you'd be listening on free software.
So that's a cool way to listen to a podcast
about free software.
But we really actually have a lot to get to,
so I should stop fooling around.
And there is some breaking news this week.
This is CNN breaking news.
By the time we come on the air, it
is becoming more and more known that Richard Stallman is back
at the Free Software Foundation on the board.
He's not running it like the president,
but he is on the board.
And Stallman, as we have talked about on the show before,
he is a hard man to like, as Lawrence Lessig put it.
He's driven.
He's often impatient.
His anger can flare at friends as easily it does foes.
And he is uncompromising.
And he is persistent.
And he is patient.
That is something else about Richard Stallman
is he is willing to wait for a long time.
And so this week at a live event,
he announced that he was back.
First, I have an announcement to make.
I'm now on the Free Software Foundation board of directors
once again.
We were working on a video to announce this with,
but that turned out to be difficult.
We didn't have experience doing that sort of thing,
so it didn't get finished.
But here's the announcement.
Some of you will be happy at this,
and some might be disappointed.
But who knows?
In any case, that's how it is.
And I'm not planning to resign a second time.
It was a while ago.
It was before the pandemic.
It was September 2019, just a few months after the world had
learned about the horrific sex trafficking operation run
by the influential billionaire Jeffrey Epstein.
Revelation after revelation had come out
about powerful people and influence,
and MIT got wrapped up in all of that.
Epstein had donated $850,000 to MIT's Media Lab.
He had visited the campus many times,
and of course, he had associated with several professors
and administrators there.
Now, RMS wasn't one of them, but an associate of Stallman's,
Marvin Minsky, who was an AI pioneer at MIT
and passed away in 2016, was involved with Epstein,
and allegedly in some very serious ways.
When that information became public in 2019,
it created quite an upset.
In response to that upset, protests were planned at MIT.
The organization of those protests was done over email,
and it was sent out to several email lists.
Richard Stallman was on one of those lists,
as you would imagine, since he had affiliations with MIT,
and he replied all.
And in a very typical Stallman fashion,
he took issue with how words were being used, specifically
the term sexual assault. And in a very insensitive
to the moment kind of way, went on a whole diatribe
and rant about the use of the term sexual assault.
That email thread made it into the hands of an MIT alumni,
who then forwarded that email to reporters.
But really, the reporters didn't do much with it.
So she then turned to Medium, and she
penned a post entitled, Remove Richard Stallman and Everyone
Else Horrible in Tech.
That post did get traction, specifically on social media,
and groups began digging into Stallman's past who were not
familiar with Richard Stallman.
They began unearthing lots of objectionable content
that you can find on his personal blog.
From there, with the connection to Epstein and the content
on his blog, things escalated very quickly,
and regular media outlets started
reporting on the incident.
The pressure grew on Richard Stallman and the FSF very fast.
So Stallman resigned from MIT and the Free Software
Foundation, which he founded in 1985,
a week after he sent that reply all.
And it's been since September 2019
that he sort of laid low.
Did I make a prediction that he'd be back, Wes?
Was it this year that I predicted, or was it last year?
Yeah, I think you did.
We'll have to check the archives after the show.
But I don't know that any of us expected him really
to be gone forever, at least in all capacities.
Did you expect to be back on the board?
That I'm not sure about.
Yeah, it seems like this was supposed to be a splash,
but they kind of bamboozled the announcement video.
And so they just kind of casually
set it in a low-attended live stream.
Is it possible there's hidden in here
is sort of a diss on free software video editors,
and that's why it was so hard to put that together?
Yeah.
This, for the FSF, is a key moment.
And there will be some that decide that they no longer feel
represented by the FSF.
And you may see some other organizations stand up.
I mean, it's been around since 85, so it has quite a history.
But that has to be, I think, in a sense,
it's going to be a social forking that's going to happen.
Yeah, I mean, it seems like we're sort of evaluating here.
It's not really clear how this happened.
Yes, he's now listed on their website,
but there wasn't a lot of clear, at least at first,
sort of announcements around these changes.
And the way he says it in that video is sort of like,
you get the idea that there's some force of will being here.
He seemed to want to be back.
That wasn't said in a way that sounded like, well,
after discussing it with all the parties,
we've determined this is what's best for the Free Software
Foundation and the advocacy for free software.
And that's where it's tricky.
It's like, OK, we want to support free software.
We want to support these ideas.
But what does the Free Software Foundation do,
and who do they associate with?
What are their parties, and how do they advocate,
and does that match our goals?
And you kind of have to suspect and wonder
if this wasn't the plan all along.
You know, lay low, wait for the temperature to drop on this,
and then when we feel like it's safe to do so,
we'll bring you back to the board.
Perhaps.
I mean, how else do you get somebody as radical
as Richard Stallman to step aside
without some kind of, perhaps, compromise like that?
Regardless, he's back, and he has a renewed focus
on the problem of web apps.
And it seems the pandemic has made
him think more about this than he has in the past.
There used to be a few of these, but there are lots of them
now.
Government websites are inaccessible.
For instance, the House of Representatives website,
without running non-free JavaScript code,
you can't see a page, any page.
The WhiteHouse.gov interface doesn't
allow you to send a message.
Various Massachusetts websites don't work.
The websites to get vaccinated for COVID-19,
something that you should definitely do,
don't work without running non-free JavaScript code.
Fortunately, you can make appointments in some places
by phone, and that's what I did.
And I listen to this, and I think, boy,
this is a tough position.
If the bar is even all JavaScript has to be open
source, which understandably would be for him,
and I look at the direction and trend line things are going,
I don't think he has any influence in this.
I think his influence has waned.
He says we have to move away from web apps entirely.
I've been talking about web services and their web apps.
Well, one bad thing about them is how they depend
on running non-free software on your computer
and send it to you, and you have to know to stop it.
But they do other bad things, too.
For instance, web apps frequently spy on users,
mislead users, can sabotage users.
And so we need to move away from web apps.
If you depend on a web app, you're
depending on something that some organization can
change on you at any time.
It can sabotage it totally.
It can impose new conditions on you, anything at all.
So I call them online disservices,
because what they do to you is not, in my opinion, a service.
He's got a joke in there.
Pithy as always.
Yeah.
Doesn't it feel like, Wes, especially
after the work from home, school from home
year that we just had, that we are further away
from this than ever?
Web apps are more dominant and in use than ever right now.
Yeah.
And as ever, he's not wrong in spirit,
but it's just so far away from what the norm is.
And I think from pushing any of the compromises
that we're actually likely to see successful,
we need to think more about privacy and data
sovereignty and ownership.
And OK, maybe I do need to pay some proprietary service
over the network to do a job for me,
but how can I make sure that that's reasonably in my favor?
I'm not going to get to the point probably ever of being
able to dictate what someone I exchange data with over
the network runs on their side.
That's just part of the internet and the web, right?
We can't enforce that.
But if we can set up some better frameworks,
and it just doesn't feel like that's where his head is,
I mean, maybe we'll see if there's some interesting things.
He's certainly contributed a lot,
and I'm not proposing we erase Richard Stallman in any way.
It just doesn't seem like he's connected enough
to what's going on in actual popular culture
to be an effective advocate right now.
Right.
Manimek, there's a message here that is worth listening to,
but it's like we need a spokesperson or maybe
a group of spokespeople that are not as polarizing as RMS.
Yeah, I totally agree with what Wes just said.
And still, I think we need, even though his positions might
be a little bit extreme, we need some people like him
in the Linux new community.
We need this little talk in the background
that tells us, yeah, have a point on open source
and try to use software that is open source.
So I think he has his place in our community.
And we've all thought about this, about web apps.
Here I am on my full free software system,
and I'm connecting to a proprietary web app.
And I guess my comfort level with this
has always been as free as possible.
PyCrash points out you could GPL the JavaScript.
I mean, you could.
So that's an option.
But I live in a kind of a more reality-based situation
where I kind of feel like where I want to really focus
on free software is the core of my OS, what makes my computer
boot and function, how I access the hardware on my system.
I like that to be free.
Then I really like my user land to be as free as possible,
my desktop environment, my mail client, my web browser.
I all have preferences to use free software there.
Then there's like another layer, which
is like the nice-to-havities that I don't think
would destroy the computing experience if I couldn't
launch Slack or Steam.
And it'd be nice if they were open source,
but I want them to run on that free software stack, number
one.
And so the lower you go in the stack,
the more important in my mind it is to be free software.
And for some reason, that means websites
are kind of like at the top of that stack.
They're kind of like the furthest removed from me.
And I somehow have just gotten used to the fact
that these damn websites will just change on me.
And that's something he goes into more in his talk,
that these websites will just change.
The UI will read change, and you can't go back
to a previous version like you can with physical software.
But that's also just sort of the trend line of development.
And in some ways, it's a positive.
And it's just not a black and white issue.
And I think where RMS loses touch with the rest of us
these days is that he cannot connect
with that position at all.
And while you do need somebody who tugs at these ideals,
you have to do it in a way that doesn't seem so extreme
that it's unable to be processed.
And so I don't necessarily, I can't really
see this being a net benefit for the Free Software Foundation.
But time will tell, really.
We will see.
It's one of those stories where we can only just say,
we'll see what happens, sort of like the first time
back in September.
Well, let's move on, Wes.
Let's talk about something that's
coming a little bit down the road, something a little more
entertaining and exciting, perhaps something
you'll want to catch yourselves.
It's the Elementary Developer Weekend.
And Dan's here to tell us a little bit about it.
Dan, welcome back to the show.
Hey, how's it going?
You know, pretty good, Dan.
You know, there's a lot going on these days.
But I'm feeling like it's time to talk about something else.
And you apparently wanted to have more work to do, Dan.
You know, I wake up every day, and I'm
like, I don't have enough things to do.
What more can I pile onto my plate?
Because if I'm not completely exhausted,
there's something else I could do.
Right, of course.
So you have the Developer Elementary Weekend
that you are announcing.
It's the very first of its kind.
And it feels like perhaps something
that in the past would have been considered as an in-person
event.
But with the current COVID situation,
it's a great opportunity to try something virtual
and see how it works, I imagine.
Yeah, absolutely.
And this is something we've been thinking about for a long time.
And we've always envisioned it as an in-person event.
But in-person events are really expensive.
And so there was kind of, like you said,
this opportunity to go, huh, well,
maybe we can try it online first and see what happens.
Yeah.
So what's the idea here?
It looks like there's a call for papers.
It's going now until April 20, and looking for ideas and talks.
What kind of stuff are you guys looking for?
Yeah, so kind of like the whole thing
is that we've been to a lot of different open source software
conferences.
And there's kind of like two big things.
There's either events that are really inclusive
and for everybody, but aren't necessarily technical,
or they're more like expo focused.
And then there's events that are very technical,
but they're usually like you see a lot of the same people there.
And they're people that are kind of already insiders
in the free software community.
And they're usually the people that
are making the platforms themselves,
like GNOME developers, and KDE developers, and stuff
like that.
So we want to really create an event that's
about app developers that are people that
aren't necessarily on the inside in these communities,
but that it's also a really technical event.
So we're asking for people to either submit ideas of things
they would like to see, or to submit talks
that they would like to give that
are focused around development and building applications.
And we want to create this really educational space where
we can help people be the best app developers they can be.
And that could lead to some great Linux desktop apps
one day.
So the website to check it out is edw.elementary.io.
And of course, we'll have a link in the show notes
where you can suggest an idea or submit a talk.
And rumor has it, perhaps, your humble host here
may be involved to some regard.
I don't know if we've really sorted out how much we'll
be on air or not.
But if nothing else, we're going to be here pushing buttons
to make it all happen.
I like that it looks like submitting a talk
is done through GitHub.
This feels very open source.
Yeah, good idea, Dan.
Yeah, we've really been trying to stretch out
the new discussions feature in GitHub
and thought this was a really cool way
to do it because you can vote on subjects too.
And since it's a developer-focused thing,
people don't have to create an account
in some special presentation software.
They probably already have a GitHub account.
So we're trying to go where the developers are at.
Clever.
And I like that you've thought a lot about the format as well.
I know that's something that you and I talked a bit about off
air, but how to do it where the presentations are, well,
quite frankly, presentable and enjoyable to watch
and easy to understand and still have
the optional component of interacting
live with people and all of that.
So I think you guys have got a clever idea of how
to formulate it there that has taken a lot of the lessons
learned from the virtual events we've seen over 2020
and brought a lot of the best ideas together.
Yeah, I really hope so.
I mean, this is our first event, so not going down in flames
would be awesome, but also being able to do something really
useful and fun for the community would be cool.
I just want one day to just have the,
I want this to be successful so that one day we're
doing this in person.
We're drinking beers.
We're hanging out again.
It's like a full nerd event.
And so this is the first step, I think.
Yeah, and I think that's the best part about creating
these kind of conferences is like hallway conversations
and going out afterwards and really
that community and camaraderie and friendship.
So hopefully we can springboard from this
into a much larger in-person event.
Absolutely.
Well, Dan, thanks for joining us and telling us about it.
Yeah, thank you very much for giving me a space to.
And also here today on the show is Dalton from Ubuntu Touch,
and they just had a new release, OTA 16.
And Dalton joined us on Linux Action News
to go into some of the details and nitty gritties
about the release.
And it's looking like it's running pretty sharp
on the 3.8 Dalton.
Oh, you got it installed?
No, no, but I wouldn't YouTube spelunking.
So it turns out it's not Wes that has the 3.8,
so I wasn't able to take his phone and flash it.
Man, you got me so excited there.
And dang it, you still took my phone.
Yeah, well, I just wanted to wipe it.
There's reasons.
Let's just put it that way.
Also really cool that we are almost at the four-year mark
since this became an independent project.
Yeah, it's kind of crazy to think that.
April 5, 2021 is our four-year anniversary.
Man, does it feel like it's been four years,
or does it feel like it's been 10?
Both.
It's like having a kid, yeah.
It's interesting, because I know you guys have
been really super committed.
It feels like it's just been a four-year push, really.
But it kind of feels like it's coming together.
I mean, of course, there's a transition to 2004
on the horizon, but right now, it
looks like it's getting pretty solid.
The Pixel's out there.
The Vala phone's out there.
The 3a is a great phone.
A new Samsung phone just got support.
I mean, it's kind of all coming together right now.
It really does feel like that.
It just feels like we're in a really good, decent place
to work on the project and do things
that we think are fun in addition to things
that move the needle forward.
Well, you know, Dalton, something
we didn't touch on in the Linux action news chat
that maybe we should touch on here
is I didn't realize that in their effort at Vala phone
to support Ubuntu Touch, they have set up at least some people
in their offices that are supporting Ubuntu Touch
directly.
They're developing and working on Ubuntu Touch
now and getting paid by Vala, right?
That's correct.
Yes.
That seems like a big development.
Can you give me an idea of how long you expect that to be
and how big of an impact you expect that to make?
Ooh, how much can I say about?
Yeah, I understand it could be kind of tricky.
So what you are comfortable sharing is fine.
I feel like it's a long-term investment for them.
They feel like this is important to their platform as Vala
and to mobile use cases in general.
There is some other cool stuff coming up
that I don't know when it's going to come to fruition
and especially not in full light.
But I can just say it's really cool,
and I can't wait to talk about it.
And it'll probably be more reason
why they would need staff to support the OS,
I would imagine.
Yeah.
Yeah, OK, interesting.
That's really exciting, man.
I'm getting kind of like to the point
where I'm feeling kind of ashamed that I'm not running it
on a device currently.
Like that's the state it's gotten to.
It's like, oh, this is something I
need to start checking in on now.
Should I wait until the transition to 2004,
or should I just go for it?
I'd say just go for it.
Good answer.
Very good answer.
Well, Dalton, thanks for coming by and updating us.
Thanks for bringing me in.
It was good to chat with you.
Go check it out.
OTA 16 just came out last week.
And we will have a link to that in the show notes.
And more details about the release in this week's Linux
Action News.
Now, something that we don't have details about yet,
but I just want to let you know that if you are running
the security updates for any of the boxes,
if you're responsible for that, the OpenSSL project
is bracing us for a big update.
They are announcing an announcement.
And they're telling us that there
will be a new release of OpenSSL on Thursday the 25th of March
2021.
And they're even giving us a time range
between 1,300 and 1,700 UTC.
It's a security fix for a high severity issue.
You just don't see this very often, Wes.
No.
I guess we know exactly where our sysadmin friends are
going to be.
Yep.
Maybe it's a good time to rob them.
Wow.
Yeah, because you know this is going to be really public,
right?
So this is one that people are really getting to jump on.
Yeah, we're going to try to get full coverage, a full breakdown
in Sunday's land, because we should have all
of the information by the time we're recording Linux Action
News.
We just don't know much right now.
We could speculate, but that just
wouldn't do anyone any good.
So we won't.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get a $100 60-day credit towards your new account
and go there to support the show.
$100 means you can really try it out.
You can do a lot.
Linode is our cloud server provider.
And what we're about to tell you about just in a few moments
was done on Linode.
We always use Linode for these experiments,
because it's super quick to spin up a system.
It's really easy.
It's also really easy to clone them and back them up
and take snapshots.
And so within minutes, we'll get something up and running,
and we can take a risk.
We can take a risk of breaking something
that might destroy the networking,
and then we can't connect to it, because it's really easy
just to revert back.
So that kind of flexibility makes
it super easy for Wes and I to prototype ideas
for infrastructure, but also for show segments.
And I know that that would translate for your projects
as well.
And so I think that's something worth just using the $100
credit for right there.
But personally, one of the things
that I really like about Linode as a longtime Linux fan,
don't know if you knew that, but I've
liked Linux for a little while.
They really support just about all the Linuxes,
and even some of the ones you might not
want to run in the cloud.
But you got your reasons.
Even the Sooses, even the Sooses.
Actually, of course, the Sooses are up there.
They have a bunch of distributions they support.
I like that a lot.
But there's other features we play more with now
than I expected.
I'm always constantly finding new ways
to use object storage for back end storage for things that,
especially things that are shared between systems,
or when we need to send a segment to a sponsor
or an interviewee, we're using object storage for that now
too, because a lot of times, they're
bigger than what a lot of email server attachments support.
And so we just use the Linode command line tool
to pop it up on the object storage
and generate a public link.
It's fantastic.
It really is nice to just find ways to integrate it
into your workflow, because these tools are really good.
Some of the stuff we're about to talk about,
you could achieve with Linode's Cloud Firewall.
They started in 2003, and so they've
had time to really focus on how to do this right.
They haven't gone off and tried to create
every single different service under the sun
and do all this different stuff.
They've really focused in on what they're good at.
And over the years, they've built something really awesome.
In 2016, they took over control of their networking
and became their own ISP.
On some of their dedicated CPU rigs,
they have some really high-end AMD Epic CPUs
that are just crazy fast.
They have great disk I.O. They have fantastic network
connections, 40 gigabit connections
coming into the hypervisor.
They're dedicated to offering the best virtualized cloud
computing.
If it runs on Linux, it runs on Linode.
But go try it yourself.
I mean, $100 really means you can actually try it.
So go over there and give it a go and support the show.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
We have some potential news for the Linux kernel.
And it's pretty exciting, Wes, because it involves
one of our favorite technologies.
Uh-oh.
I think I know what's coming next.
Initial support for the Rust language
has landed in Linux Next, which I assume you all are probably
just running it already.
But for a long time now, Linux kernel developers
have pondered the prospects of allowing the Rust language
to be used in kernel device drivers, kernel device
drivers, which could be a particular area of interest
for Rust and could potentially bring some of Rust's
best features like safety and performance to device drivers.
So announced just recently on the Rust for Linux mailing list
was word of initial Rust support hitting Linux Next.
Although, the announcement was quick to note
that this does not mean we'll make it into mainline,
of course.
But it's a nice step to make things as smooth as possible.
Of course, another issue with all this
is support is obviously conditional on having
a Rust compiler on the system that you're
building the kernel on.
That's a good point.
But really, if you think about it,
that's kind of a good place to start for this kind of thing.
Because you're going to have less platforms you're building
40 ways with device drivers.
They target fewer platforms to begin with.
So it kind of seems like there would be a lot of benefits
to drivers in Rust as well.
And it's not an area that's going to really break anything
major.
Right.
You're not like rewriting the whole kernel.
You're just saying, hey, I've got a new device.
This was going to be new code anyway.
Or maybe it's some old code that was never very good.
Let's see what it looks like in Rust.
While Rust is now in Linux Next, we should be clear.
It's not yet known if it's actually
going to get into mainline.
That depends on some stuff.
How does Linux Next bake?
Could stay in there for a while.
Could end up never getting merged.
But it's a step in the right direction.
And it seems like some of the kernel leaders, including
Linus, have some thoughts.
Yeah, that's true.
Greg KH has chimed in on the matter.
They all kind of have an air of skepticism,
as they probably should, regarding this issue,
I would imagine.
They've talked about this.
But they've kind of looked at it as, OK, we can give it a go.
Linus Torvalds says, personally, I'm in no way pushing for Rust.
But I'm open to considering it.
The promised advantages of avoiding some safety pitfalls
seem good.
But I also know that a lot of times, some of these promises
don't pan out.
Isn't that true?
The part that I like in this is just sort of getting support
for this, people not saying no, and letting people
hack on what that initial implementation looks like.
How does this play with the existing methods and data
structures that exist in the kernel?
Can people figure out some of that low-level integration
work, so that down the road, maybe we
can benefit from the pool of people that already know Rust
and want to contribute a device driver,
but really didn't want to do it in C?
There you go, Wes.
We knew eventually it would make its way.
Will it ever actually ship?
We will see.
But Rust is invading the kernel.
All right, let's tidy it up a little bit around here.
I want to let you know to keep an ear out
for episode 401 of your Linux talk show.
401, I chat with someone who ended up
building a Linux-powered bus to automate, to build, all of it.
He didn't know any of it.
He didn't know Linux.
He had to learn it all from scratch
at each step of the way.
And I sit down for a chat with him, and we discuss that.
And that is coming in episode 401,
which means we're taking 401 off.
Well, we're not taking it off.
But we won't be live, because it'll be prerecorded.
You know how that makes sense?
So if you're subscribed, you're going to get it.
Probably don't even need to mention it.
But I wanted to let you know that if you do
like to join us live on the 13th,
we will not be live as a result. But then
we'll be back to our regular bat time after that.
All of this is just easy to keep track of in our Telegram
group at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Telegram.
So you can join that.
Maybe if you were going to join live,
use that time to figure out your mumble setup
if you haven't done that already.
Yep.
We have that link at linuxunplug.com.
This Sunday as we record, so coming up really soon,
I want to encourage you to join the LepLug.
Minimek, you have some details about a great Lug session
coming up this Sunday.
Yeah.
What I can say, LepLug is going strong.
And we will have another recording next Sunday.
And there will be the presentation of a tool
called Meerschaum.
So if you have seen the movie National Treasure,
you know what a Meerschaum pipe is.
So now I could try to tell you about that project.
But we have the developer of the tool right here in Mumble.
So Bennett, tell us what you will be talking about.
Thanks, Minimek.
And hey to all you sysadmins and Linux lovers out there.
So in the next LepLug this Sunday on March 28th,
check jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get
the time in your time zone.
I will be presenting a passion project of mine
called Meerschaum.
Meerschaum is an open source data management system
which makes getting your time series
data onto a dashboard as quick and easy as possible.
I'm always looking for feedback and user testing.
So if you'd like to help out, please
join us in the next LepLug.
You can read more about Meerschaum
at meerschaum.io or mrsm.io.
I hope to see you all next Sunday.
That's going to be great.
Like you said, the dates and time are on the calendar.
There's also a LepLug channel on our matrix
if you want to jump in there and start chatting.
All of the info, the mumble info, the matrix info,
it's all linuxunplug.com.
Just make it easy.
You just go over there, and you'll find it all.
And with that, that's all the tidying we have for this week.
So we wanted to share our favorite network trick with you
this week.
It's something that we've done in various iterations
over the last year to let the chat room come in live
and abuse a machine we have on our land.
I mean, obviously, I don't want to expose the studio's
public IP, but I want to give people an IP to connect to
so they can interact with what we're doing.
Some of you may also have a desire
to self-host something at home.
But perhaps your ISP blocks ports, or maybe like me,
you're behind some kind of crazy carrier-grade net.
There are ways to get around it.
And one way to get around it is a new service
that's launched called Hoppy.
And this is a way to do what we're about to tell you about,
but just do it real easy through their service.
And it's also one of the reasons that Wes and I have been
so keen to follow WireGuard, because we knew since we saw
the announcement that when it landed in Linux distributions
and made it into the kernel, it was
going to enable all kinds of network connectivity
fun, trickery, and solutions that we hadn't really
seen before, and make some older solutions that are still
viable, but make them seem a little obsolete.
And Hoppy is a good example of this.
Hoppy.network has created a business built
around WireGuard and Linux.
It's a service that lets you get a public IP on a machine
behind an ad, which is a big win for us self-hosters.
And I chatted with both the co-founders this morning
to get an idea of how it all works.
I chatted with Yoon.
My name is Yoon, or Yoon Sik Park.
And I am the co-founder of Hoppy Network.
And his other co-founder, Logan.
My name is Logan Collins, and I am a co-founder at Hoppy
Network.
And I asked them to give us the elevator pitch on what Hoppy is
so you guys could understand the value.
Hoppy is how you can lease a public IP address
and attach it to any device that you want.
It's a way of making a device public to the world
and bypassing any kind of inconvenient networking
situations that you might have.
It's a way of enabling you to self-host your own services
and take back a little bit of control
in the digital landscape that's been changing
over the last couple of years.
I like this idea.
I knew why Wes and I wanted to accomplish something like this.
So I asked them what was their motivation.
It kind of arose out of my self-hosting journey.
I was trying to decrease my reliance on iCloud specifically,
trying to self-host everything.
And the biggest roadblock was self-hosting a mail server.
And the reason is most ports are unblocked at home
except for SMTP or port 25.
And that's because this port specifically
is used to spam others.
And a lot of ISPs want to block that.
There wasn't a way I could really get around that
without putting my server into the cloud again.
And I thought, is there a way to get a IP address and unblock
ports within my own home?
And I was looking into different VPN services
that could accomplish that.
And there wasn't really anything like that.
And I spent a few months learning about networking.
And what I came up with was a prototype
of Hoppy Network that would actually accomplish that.
And like you probably are right now,
I was wondering, how does it work?
Each one of our servers, they use BGP
to get access to an IPv4 block as well as an IPv6 block.
But I'll just simplify it for now.
And that's slash 24 cents split up
across the different WireGuard clients.
So in our routing tables, we have each IP address routed
to the WireGuard interface.
So as long as you have that WireGuard interface connected
to us, we'll try to forward that IPv4
address over that interface.
And once your client receives that packet,
as long as your client is configured properly
to assign that IPv4 address to its own interface,
then it'll just accept IPv4 addresses
as if it was like a native system interface.
To use an analogy that is horrible,
but I still love using it, you can imagine these WireGuard
tunnels between our server and yours
as a giant ethernet cable that is just,
it's like you plugged in a new cable into your F0 port
or whatever, and you got assigned this public IP
to that network interface.
As far as your machine is concerned,
you have this public IP address, and we don't exist.
All the ports are open because the traffic for that IP
is coming directly to you.
So obviously, my next question was, well,
what about security, monitoring, those kinds of issues?
First of all, nobody can man in the middle of you
because the connected WireGuard is fully encrypted.
Between us and you, the traffic is encrypted,
nobody can view it, it's really great.
Between us and whatever client is connecting to you,
your IP is public, you should be using SSL or something.
We're not looking, we don't care what you're doing.
And we have a really good privacy policy,
it's less than a page long, anybody can read it,
it's something we adhere to.
I think Logan's saying there's not much we can do
other than promise that we won't spy.
And after we had wrapped up and I was saying goodbye to them,
they gave me another insight that wasn't prompted,
but it was just something that came up
while we were saying our goodbyes.
And I thought it showed that their hearts really were
in the right place with this project.
It's new, but I think their goals
align with what we'd like to see.
We hope that this service encourages people
to self-host more, it also encourages IPv6 adoption
because you get like a slash 56 as well.
Pretty much we want to make the internet a better place.
Yeah, and that's about it.
So cheers to them, thanks for coming on guys this morning
and chatting with me about it.
You can find it at hoppy.network.
And they've created a business around
making it really simple for you to get around NAT
using WireGuard.
You just connect to their WireGuard instance
they have hosted.
Now, of course, you could do this yourself too.
And so that's what Wes and I want to talk about today
is while we found Hoppy during kind of investigating
different ways to improve our solution for the studio,
we thought, you know, there's probably reasons
we could do this ourselves and would want to do this
for ourself and pondered how we could get around
my extreme double carrier grade mutant NAT
that I have at home and take advantage of that as well.
That thing, I mean, we've had to try a lot of solutions
and I think it's safe to say that your home networking
is not exactly simple at this point.
No, no, it's even crazier now that I aggregate two carriers.
Okay, yeah, let's put that aside just for a second here
because regardless, there are a lot of ways
to solve this problem.
Probably a lot that the audience is definitely
already familiar with, right?
You've got things like SSH forwarding,
that's super resilient.
You can do all kinds of fun tunneling,
take local ports and forward them,
take remote parts and forward them, all kinds of stuff.
Maybe you use a service like ngrok,
which I suppose focused perhaps more on developers
exposing HTTP services on the web
but does the same kind of NAT busting and NAT traversal
and forwarding you and putting you
on the public interface and proxying to you.
That's also another approach, right?
Like you could just use a VPN like WireGuard
and then a reverse proxy setup on your cloud host
like nginx or traffic if you've already got multiple sites
or you're just familiar with how those work
or you want it to do TLS termination for you anyway.
But of course, this is Linux Unplugged.
We started things off using WireGuard.
We do love it.
And part of why we love it is because it's like,
it's just so integrated into Linux at this point, right?
Especially now that it's merged into the kernel,
it just makes it easy to play
in whatever complicated networking setup
you might already have like Chris
or if you just wanna play with whatever tools are integrated
that come installed on your Linux OS.
Once you've got WireGuard,
all the normal sort of IP and Linux networking tricks
that you might have, those work just fine
including what was maybe our first approach to this
which is just forwarding ports with IP tables
over that WireGuard connection.
Yeah, and you know, it's not bad.
We use that setup for a bit
and this might be the one I would recommend for most people
because it essentially becomes a cloud firewall.
You allow certain ports like in our case, 80 and 443
and only those ports.
And so you're not sending every bot
that wants to come knock on your SSH port
over your connection to your home machine.
You're blocking it there at the VPS level using IP tables.
And so this is neat because you set up IP tables
to forward those things down the WireGuard connection.
It's a pretty simple straightforward connection.
It can be done with literally
just a couple of lines of IP tables rules.
I mean, very simple.
Yeah, I mean, I think our sort of proof of concept
was two commands and that was it once WireGuard was set up.
Yeah, and then you're just sending those two approved ports
back to the machine,
which I think is probably the ideal solution.
But what if you wanted the entire machine,
like maybe you wanted to expose a firewall
that had a WireGuard connection on it
and you wanted to then manage it at that firewall level.
Right, or, you know, in this case, it's sort of,
it's much like the just running a proxy on the box.
You kind of have to manage both boxes, right?
Like when you add a new service on your backend,
you got to go tell the front end about it too
and make sure that that's all working,
it gets properly forwarded and allowed,
which as you say, that can definitely be a good thing.
And you should take security seriously.
But sometimes you just want to say, you know,
maybe you're not on a network where you could forward ports
so you don't have full control.
And you really just, as you're testing something out,
you want to expose this machine, put it in the DMZ,
get it right out there on the internet.
And yeah, with WireGuard, you can do that too.
Yeah, in fact, we have done just that.
In your browsers right now, you can do it after the fact
or while you're listening live, go to WireGuard.club.
I should make sure this is still up.
WireGuard.club in your web browser.
And what you will get is a beautiful,
extremely intricate website
that I spent hours building just for you
that is actually running on a VM on the machine
I have right in front of me in the studio right now.
I didn't know you knew web design.
Look at that, right?
It's pro work right there.
Your connection will hop through a Linode,
running WireGuard back to a VM on my machine.
So the VM has the WireGuard client active,
connected to the Linode,
which is then routing all of the traffic down here.
So how the heck did we do this, Wes?
Oh boy, well, yeah, definitely WireGuard is involved.
And so we were just talking about sort of the,
maybe traditional port forwarding approach.
And in that style,
you basically just set up your WireGuard tunnel
and you've assigned sort of private IPS behind there, right?
So you can talk between them.
And if you're just on local host there
on your box in the cloud, your Linode, your VPS,
you can go hit that private service.
But you need iptables to both forward the ports on
so that things from the internet can get there.
But also because the whole WireGuard system,
that's using private IPv4 addresses,
you also have to introduce NAT.
And sometimes you just don't want that.
I mean, it works fine.
Linux kernel is great at doing that.
And iptables has no problems.
It's easy to do and many people have done it.
It's just not quite as flexible.
Maybe you're trying to do
a complicated WebRTC audio setup
and you just don't want more levels of NAT involved.
It turns out WireGuard makes this super easy.
What we did on Linode in this case
was get a second IP address and assign that to our Linode.
They make that easy and tons of hosting providers do too.
You just gotta get yourself a second IP address.
You need one still to keep the host accessible.
But that second one,
much like you just assigned whatever arbitrary,
say 10.200.200.1 address to your WireGuard network,
to whatever machine you're connecting to on the backend,
you can just put the public IP address there.
And if you're using something like wg-quick,
we'll have a link in the show notes
that has sort of an example setup.
That example is using IPv6,
but works just the same for IPv4 pretty much in this case.
And WireGuard figures that out.
So on the backend side,
the system running right at Chris's fingertips,
right there in the studio, we just told it,
hey, this is your IP address for WireGuard.
This is gonna be the public IP address.
And then on the server in the front end running in the cloud,
you say the same thing like, hey,
here's this WireGuard peer that's gonna connect to you.
Here's the IP address that it's allowed to send from.
And oh yeah, hey, in the reverse direction,
we're just gonna send everything.
So not only can you access all the ports
on that hosting machine, but the hosting machine,
all of its traffic is going at that IP address too.
So on that machine, it really just feels like
this is your new public IPv4 address
right out there on the internet.
That's exactly what it seems like.
It's so slick and it's wherever you connect as a client from.
You just established the WireGuard VPN
and you could be mobile.
You could be at a coffee shop, you could be at home,
you could be wherever you connect from,
it'll just send the traffic there.
So it's really slick because I realized very quickly
that this is kind of handy on my laptop
because I could just turn it on briefly,
send you the IP from wherever I was at
and you could connect to my laptop
that I was sitting at at that moment.
And then when we were done,
I could just disconnect WireGuard and it goes away.
And that was super useful, but I also thought,
boy, this could be handy for just home systems
that I wanna turn on from time to time
and get them exposed to the internet.
I might prefer the style where you use IP tables
to just forward certain ports,
but routing all of the traffic has the advantage
of just, it's like it's a node on the internet
and then you manage it with whatever firewall you want.
Exactly.
I mean, how many times do you end up spinning up a VPS
just because you know, like, okay,
this isn't behind any of my stuff.
I don't have to futz with this weird router UI
or play with any of that.
Like it's just gonna be on the internet.
What I run there will be public.
I don't have to think about it beyond that,
which can be good or can be bad.
And I should say, this is sort of how people view NAT
is a sort of kind of firewall
just because you have to do
that network address translation step
to actually get traffic to go both ways.
All you really need to do
if you want to have that same sort of stuff
is just not forward everything by default,
set up a deny by default firewall.
We're using a Fedora 33 box in this case on the Linode.
So you've got firewall D there or UFW,
or in this case, actually, I disabled firewall D,
gotta tell you that, and installed Firehole,
which I just kind of like to use anyway,
wrote up a quick config.
I sent it to you, Chris.
I mean, it's really, I don't know,
20 lines long at most, right?
Yeah.
And you just say like, these are the services I want.
You can allow all ports.
You could block specific ports.
Or in this case, we took the secure route,
pretty much blocked everything except the services
we knew we were running.
Now, it does mean you still have to do that,
but I think what's nice about this approach
is you get the flexibility.
You can forward everything if you want,
or you can lock it down a bit more.
Or if you didn't want to mess with IP tables at all,
you could use like the cloud firewall
that's probably built into whatever VPS provider
you're doing, like we could do on Linode.
Yeah, there's so many options.
And then ultimately, the even simpler route
would be something like hoppy.network,
where you just sign up,
I think they're using Stripe for the billing or something,
and then you provision a box after you pick.
They have like an $8 a month and an $11 a month.
And it's like the difference between one terabyte
or two terabyte of transfer.
I signed up a little bit just to try it out.
And what you have to do as an end user
is download a WireGuard comp,
and then just do a WG quick up the name of that comp,
if you put it in Etsy WireGuard, and you're connected.
So it's really just a matter of starting
the WireGuard client and connecting
if you want to use Hoppy.
But the VPS side of stuff,
like what we built up on Linode
with IP tables and WireGuard,
it's good entry level stuff.
If you've been looking for a reason
to learn a little bit about networking
and a little bit about different firewall options on Linux,
and you want to do something that could also mean
maybe you could access a home system from time to time,
this is a really nice setup.
And of course, we got you hooked up
with links in the show notes,
where you can go through some of the steps
and figure out how to do this.
And you can always go check out Hoppy
and see how they're doing it,
and get an idea and a feel for it,
and then go build this yourself,
because even if you really have never done
any of this before,
with a few hours of work and reading,
you could have this set up
and get it running yourself.
I think it's a fun way for us to expose the system,
and I'm looking at the resources right now.
It's actually, I got to say,
I'm running in KVM, Vert Manager,
and it does a good job of distributing the load.
My memory usage is going up quite a bit right now
on the system at WireGuard.club,
but the CPU load's getting spread out pretty good.
Yeah, maybe we should talk,
I mean, all right, we were harping on
about the cool aspects of the Linux networking stack,
which we should, because it's awesome.
But you're also running the Linux-powered virtual machine,
and you're even running a kind of interesting
Linux distribution inside that virtual machine
to power the website.
Yeah, this was an opportunity for us
to play again with Turnkey Linux,
which I wanted just a quick VM that ran WordPress.
I didn't want to spend many hours building a website.
I was joking earlier, obviously.
And so we grabbed the Turnkey WordPress installation,
and it really is a pretty good experience.
It didn't take any fuss to get it up and running,
and it had a decent WordPress site ready to go.
It has integration with Let's Encrypt,
if you want to go that route, makes that really simple.
I was impressed.
It'd been a while since I'd visited Turnkey Linux land.
And what's also great, Wes,
is none of this is really new hardware.
These are like 2017 machines,
and we've got a couple hundred people
knocking on the door right now,
and it's doing a pretty good job.
Man, I'm still using the machine
to read the show notes and whatnot.
Yeah, that was gonna be my main concern.
Gonna break the show.
Yeah, I know, because this one, it really matters.
This one, it really does.
But man, this is a lot of fun.
It's one of our favorite things
to do with WireGuard right now,
and we'll have links to that in the show notes.
And we'd love to hear how you do these kinds of things,
because there's lots of ways to solve this problem,
and probably some of them are pretty interesting.
Linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
Unpluggedcore.com, if you'd like to become
a member of this show, support the show.
Not only does it keep the show independent
and keep us going,
and helps us cover the cost of production,
but as a thank you, you get a couple of perks.
You get two different feeds.
Well, you could really listen to both,
but then you'd probably have time for nothing else.
So I don't recommend it.
So you must choose between door one and door two.
Door one is a limited ad version of the show.
Same full production, just no ads.
Door two is the full live stream feed,
which I have no idea what condition it's gonna be in today,
because OBS crashed on us, it was a mess.
So I have no idea, but it's everything, it's raw.
It's like every time my mouth didn't work today,
or when Wes dropped an F-bomb, it's in there.
It sure is.
The topics we talk about before and after the show
that don't make it into the recording at all,
because we hit stop, and then everybody opens up
and talks about everything, that's in there too.
We got you, suckers, ha!
Well, for the most part.
I suppose, you know, there's really no real replacement
for really being here live, let's be honest.
But that's what's in feed two,
is like as much as we can pack in there.
It's a whole show, pre and post show.
It's basically a whole extra show that never gets released,
because a lot of it's tech and Linux and open source topics
that we're talking about.
And sometimes that stuff actually does become a topic too
in the show.
So it's a way to feel like you've been here,
like you experienced the whole thing.
So that's feed number two.
And all of that, door one, door two,
is at unpluggedcore.com,
and you can become an Unplugged Core contributor.
And thank you to our members who support the show.
What do you say we do a pick, Wes?
Ooh, it's been a while.
Yeah, it's been a week, maybe two?
Don't know.
But it's been a while since we've had on theme picks
that match what we talked about in the show,
that's for sure.
And DSNET is one of them.
And Wes, I have a feeling it's WireGuard related.
Oh, yes it is.
DSNET is a simple configuration tool
to manage a centralized WireGuard VPN.
Think WG Quick, but quicker.
And really the context here is,
all right, so the box we were testing,
that was running on KVM on one of the studio machines.
While I was setting things up
and playing around last night,
going in and setting up Let's Encrypt,
even though I didn't realize that turnkey
already had to integrate it.
So I hacked it on additionally, dang it.
But I did that over a VPN connection,
a WireGuard VPN connection from my house, right?
And how do we manage that?
We've got multiple people with access to the studio,
remote setups, Chris, you just lose your keys all the time
and constantly have to add new ones
when you buy a new laptop to play with.
We're currently using Subspace for that,
which is a neat, gooey, web gooey project
that we talked about, I think, last summer or so.
Unfortunately, it doesn't really seem
to have been updated since then.
And it was a little more than we needed.
It had its own custom database and going in
and working around some of the lack of features
meant I had to go into the container,
restart things, disable it, really customize it
more than I was looking for.
And we're not managing a whole organization,
but we do have a centralized WireGuard VPN.
And we do want a way to record a name and description
about every peer we're allowing
and a way to add peers as fast as possible.
For one of us sets up a new machine,
we just want to be able to go in there,
add it real quick, give the key out
to whoever's being added and be done with it.
And that's where DSNet comes in.
Yeah, it's slick.
I think we're gonna switch to this.
I think it's what we're gonna use, don't you think?
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, I've only just tried it out a little bit.
We'll have to try it in practice for real
and see if it holds up after adding a couple folks
or redoing, modifying keys.
That's my main concern.
But it's kind of just enough.
It's simple.
It doesn't have a gooey.
It doesn't try to reinvent things.
It's just a nice little shell interface
that you can run on the command line
and get your stuff done.
And we have a spot of feedback this week.
This one's a special one because the author
is in the mumble room.
But Wes, why don't you read the highlights of it
and then we'll engage with Bennett.
Sure.
Bennett wrote in to us,
hi, Chris, Wes, and the LUP crew.
I just ran across this on the Linux subreddit.
This engineer has been building a modular ecosystem
for the Raspberry Pi Compute Module
over the last several months.
And it's nothing short of magic.
Think phone blocks, Project Aura for the Raspberry Pi.
I'm talking hot swappable blocks for cameras,
ethernet speakers, and even things like GPS and LoRa.
And here's a demo video
which we'll have linked in the show note.
The project's homepage is pocket.ai.
Now, I know how much Chris loves his pies.
So I thought it'd be a good pick for the show.
Regards, Bennett.
And boy, Bennett, were you right.
Yeah, Bennett, thanks for writing
and thanks for joining us in the LUP blog this week.
Now, what do you think?
Is it real?
I feel like we've had this promise so many times.
So I just came across it yesterday
and to me it seemed like the holy grail of mobile computing.
Google couldn't accomplish this with Project Aura.
Phone blocks seemed like a pipe dream.
And yet this single developer
casually put up this video on the subreddit.
And as I was watching it,
the amount of disbelief kept rising
as he kept showing more and more crazy modules.
Yeah, it seems like there's a real big community
of builders and makers
that are using the Raspberry Pi 4 compute module
to build out even more fancier systems.
On this week's episode of Self-Hosted,
which by the way,
if anything we talked about today interested you at all,
check out selfhosted.show.
But on this week's episode of Self-Hosted,
we interview a YouTuber who set up 16 SATA disks
to a Raspberry Pi compute module.
16 SATA disks.
It's all kinds of stuff they're building around that.
And I wonder if maybe it takes something
like a popular platform like the Raspberry Pi
to make the modules a actual sustainable business
because there has to be enough users
that could actually buy them
to make manufacturing them viable.
And it looks like on the post that I sent in the email,
so many people were interested
and it seems like the developer might be selling test kits
in the coming months.
Now, hardware, hmm, that changes things.
Yeah, that would be interesting to see.
So that is at pocket.ai, right?
P-O-C-K-I-T.ai.
We will put a link to that in the show notes.
It does look really cool.
I can't help but have my really big skeptical pants on
for this kind of stuff these days.
But boy, would I love to see it.
Boy, would I love to.
That would be great.
Well, Bennett, thanks for sending that in.
If you'd like to give us an email here on the show,
something for us to read,
something to make, that I can make Wes read, at least.
At least one email so I can make Wes read it
at linuxonplug.com slash contact.
I don't know, Wes.
I don't know, I guess I just felt like trolling, I guess.
I mean, I need a challenge, I acknowledge that.
All right, well, if anything we talked about today
interested you, like I said, check out the self-hosted show.
We talk about this stuff every other week.
If you do the Twitter thing,
you can follow this show at Linux Unplugged.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
And there is an entire network of fantastic podcasts,
which can be found at jupiterbroadcasting.com.
And if you're interested in the updates
for the Ubuntu Touch Project,
be sure to check out Linux Action News.
And of course, we'll have the open SSL news in there as well.
As of for this year's show,
we'll be back at the same bat time.
See you next week.
Same bat time, same bat station.
Oh yes, because the Linux does roll on.
Make it a whole Linux Tuesday.
Join us live, 12 p.m. Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
Links to everything we talked about today,
how to contact us, the mumble room, the matrix info,
how to even subscribe, all of it, all of it.
It's at linuxunplugged.com.
What a great idea.
A website, Linux Unplugged, it doesn't have to be an app.
It could be a website.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode
of the Unplugged program.
And we will see you right back here.
Not on Sunday, not on Monday.
Nope, not Thursday.
You guessed it.
We'll see you back here next Tuesday.
Hey.
All right, there was some bot shenanigans, so go to JBtitles.com and let's figure this
out.
Let's title this thing.
Someone didn't start the show.
I don't know who that could have been.
Some sort of shenanigans.
JBot!
Happy Gnome 40 week, everybody.
By the time most people are listening to this, I think if all things go as planned, Gnome
Shell 40 will have landed.
Of course, most people won't get in their distro yet for a bit.
But there is a Fedora 34 beta out too, right?
Yep.
I already approved it to land for this evening's update sync for Fedora 34.
So if you've installed the Fedora 34 beta ISO and then do an update from Gnome software
or using DNF, you will get it.
You hear that, Chris?
Switch the studio tonight.