Now that Wimpy's here, and he's got an audio setup working, and Popey's here, right?
Popey, you still here?
Or did you leave?
What an asshole.
Maybe.
Oh, okay.
So, I saw some shenanigans on Google+.
I don't know if you guys are familiar with this.
It's a super-secret social network that apparently nobody knows about.
Yeah, that's the first town I had.
Yeah, that's what I've told.
Yeah, there's no one on it.
But just some guy on there, Alan something or other, Pope something or other, posted
a link about a super-retro installer that reminded me of the good old days.
And then I dug a little deeper, and I discovered there is a brand new edition of Ubuntu Mate
in the works, but it's not based on like 1504 or some shenanigans like that.
No, friends, it's based on 1404.
What the heck's going on here, guys?
People want it.
It's as simple as that.
Just giving them what they need.
Since we started this, the number one thing that everyone's been asking for is when is
there going to be an LTS version.
People want to install it and forget about it.
Set it and forget it.
And then after that, it'll be 1004, then 804, then 606 Mate edition.
Wait, isn't 804 already basically Mate?
Yeah.
That's interesting.
So I guess, boy, huh?
Look at that.
What's wrong with this picture?
It sounds like you're listening to your users.
I know.
I actually pay attention to what they say.
Well, actually, yeah.
I was listening to the user, the guy who comes in and says, I would like 1404.
That guy?
We're making a distro just for him.
No, that's awesome.
Thousands of people would have asked for this.
I'm kidding.
No, that's good, though.
I think it also shows that people are all in on the LTS model, which is-
Yeah, it really does.
Exactly.
Especially on Ubuntu, that's what wins.
But actually, 1404 is quite an evolution on 1410.
So I think this 1404 release is going to be what 1410 should have been, a lot of new features
and a lot of fixes.
Really?
So in some ways, it's more of a newer version?
It is a newer version.
So for example, in the 1404 version, there's indicator support.
So you can add indicators in there now.
And we've pulled in all the latest Mate packages from Debbie and Jesse.
So there's a number of updates there.
And then I've been working with all the guys from the Accessible Computing Foundation.
And we have fixed everything that they've reported that didn't work with regards to
accessibility.
So for them, this is a big deal.
This is freaking brilliant.
Yeah, yeah.
I like it.
It seems backwards.
And I think it's better.
Yeah, it is backwards in a sense.
I'm good with it.
And you know what else?
Like the Mate desktop environment is perfect for something you can set and forget for a
long time.
Because it's very much like of a time that is sort of already established, right?
So it's like perfect for that.
I think it's the coolest thing.
And I've just come back from a weekend in Germany where I've been at the X2GO gathering,
where the Mate desktop is very popular amongst them for deployment of remote terminal services.
Oh, really?
Boy, I've been wanting to do a segment on X2GO for a little while now.
Well, okay.
If you look at X2GO, there's a couple of new features.
They've got this new layer called telekinesis.
And then they've developed this mTelePlayer.
And that is stonking.
So this is a tool that's been developed for doing real time streaming of audio and video
through the remote terminal services.
And the demo I saw this weekend was a dual screen with full 4K video streaming over a
remote terminal desktop.
And it was stunning.
Wow.
That is slick.
Going to check it out.
Yeah.
And this has been developed because there's a company that's trying to develop some sort
of set top box type devices for use in China for delivering streaming video services.
And they're doing it by bringing the whole desktop application to the client rather than
just the streaming video.
That's going to be exciting.
I've played with some of that stuff.
And it works surprisingly well even a few years ago.
Yeah.
Well, it's hot rocking now.
I'm really impressed.
I didn't know much about it until this weekend.
And I came away thinking, yeah, this is something I really need to get more involved in.
So I've already started adding some integration pieces for X2Go into Marte.
All right.
Wimpy, just before you wrap up, Chris, there's a question in the IRC.
One of the JB Live listeners is asking, can you turn a standard Ubuntu 14.04 install with
a PPA into a Marte 14.04, do you think?
You can.
And there's a blog article I posted on the Ubuntu Marte website that explains how to
do it.
Boom.
Nice.
Yeah.
That's exciting.
I think it's almost new.
It's not as good as the real thing, though.
Wait for the ISO.
It's coming out at the weekend.
That's what you want to use.
Boy, isn't it interesting how the Mateo edition, in a way, is sort of eschewing so much of
the trendy, like, it's different.
It's pushing it forward and introducing a lot of new stuff and making users happy.
But it's not chasing the shiny, right?
It's a different kind of pushing it forward.
And it's really cool to see it.
So the LTS makes so much sense in that context.
I think that's really exciting.
It really appeals to me.
I like it.
Yeah.
That's exactly it.
I'm thinking Skype machines.
You want to install the 14.04 version because you know how you like to wait a couple of
months for all the bugs to get wrangled out.
I do.
Well, curiously, it's that backstep to 14.04 that's got all the stability and fixes in
it that you'll be waiting for.
So that's the one you want to install.
Nice.
Yeah, I'll check that out.
14.04 install, just because it's going to get, like, hardware enablements for a while
and I mean, so that's awesome.
It's brilliant for running Steam as well.
Nice.
Yeah.
Or I was actually thinking it's probably the perfect Skype and Mumble rig always.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's what I'm using exactly that now, 14.04 Ubuntu MATE with Mumble.
It all works fine.
I have a random question.
Do you guys know of any, we've been playing with a couple of different packages, VSXU,
I think is one of them, something like that.
I'm looking for something that will monitor your default line in and do a full screen
real time, like, waveform visualizer.
Almost like, you know, like the old classic Winamp or iTunes plug-ins.
Maybe not something as gaudy.
Maybe something that's just a straightforward waveform.
So like right now in this show, we have the chat room up on the screen, but from time
to time, we might want to have a show that's not live.
So we wouldn't have a chat room to put up there, so we were thinking, but it's an audio
only show, it would be neat to have the waveform as we talk and I'd love to have a Linux box
that just has whatever is coming in on the default in, visualized, that I can then capture
and put that into our video recording.
I believe there is, and I will look at that while the show is going on.
Cool.
Yeah.
Maybe you mentioned the post-show or something, because I've looked at a few of them and like
we really need something that would be kind of full screen, something that's attractive
and something that doesn't require, like a lot of them I looked at will play your music
collection or things like that.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's powered by deep philosophical
discussions.
I don't even know what that means, but I'm going to go with it.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
I guess it'd be philosophical discussions.
I was trying to come up with a new term and I had nothing, Matt.
Nothing.
You were kind of morphing with the words.
I felt it though.
That's what I get for doing a cold open.
Well, 65, episode 65, and we've got a big show.
We got some follow up on the OpenSUSE review, plus some new news and developments there.
Producer Eric, he's become like our local OpenSUSE advocate.
He's been running it.
He's switched to Tumbleweed.
He's even rolling the good stuff now.
And he's got some follow up notes from our review, so we'll cover that.
There's a new device, an open source hardware device that promises to replace all password
managers.
I think we can talk about that a little bit.
And then one of our brothers has fallen, one of our fellow podcasts is coming to an end.
And we'll spend a little time talking about that.
And maybe what the root, the cause of that, and if it's a problem that's going to spread.
We'll discuss that in the show today too.
Plus lots of feedback, Matt.
So man, we got a whole big show.
I got like 15 tabs open right now.
You know what I need, Matt?
I need something like tab groups.
Just imagine if I could group all of my tabs together.
Too bad Chrome doesn't support that, huh?
That's really a shame.
I was waiting for that to dig in.
I guess there's just no way to do that.
Anyways.
Oh, boy.
Hey, mumble room.
How are you guys doing?
You know, I was actually waiting for that discussion to happen at some point, ever since
I became a producer.
I don't know.
Is that something Firefox does?
Oh, that's good to know.
Yeah.
Well, that was a heated discussion we had on the pre-show where the entire mumble room
ganged up on me and tried to get me to switch to Firefox.
But I believe I emerged unswitched, although still considering.
I have tried it before.
I may try it again.
You never know.
Like sometimes I walk away and I'm like, I'm never switching.
And then a couple of days go by and you know, I'm going to switch.
I'll take a challenge.
So if you're inspired to take a Firefox challenge, you know what, all right, all right.
I'll do it.
I'll take it.
You just convinced yourself.
Yeah, I just did.
I just, I literally.
If you guys are wondering what the pool's going to be for how long, how many days he
does this, I'll start one later.
Yes, I just flip flopped right here on air.
All right, Popeye, I'm going to, I'm going to, I'm going in with you, Popeye.
I'm going to take, starting tonight, I'm going to start taking the Firefox challenge.
So if anybody out there at home is listening and is ready to switch back to Firefox or
switch to Firefox from something, maybe it's Chrome, maybe it's Internet Explorer.
I'm going to start tonight.
So start with me and we'll see if we make it to the next Linux unplug.
That's my benchmark.
And I'll tell you upfront, I'm concerned about UI leginess, inadequate syncing, and a lack
of appropriate markdown extensions, primarily template, which is the name of the extension,
which is extremely hard to Google when the template extension is called template.
Anyways, you know what the most important thing is, Chris, is that as long as you can
go ahead and watch Netflix in it without any problems, you're golden.
Oh wait, that's right.
You can't.
And by the way, if I have problems with Firefox, the answer coming back is, well, you should
submit a bug is not going to be acceptable when there's an alternative that does the
things.
Anyways, moving on from that, we'll do a, we'll do follow up in next week's episode.
And so if anybody out there wants to take the Firefox challenge with me, let's start
tonight.
In the meantime, and Popeye, how long are you going to do it for?
Are you going to go try to make it till next week or are you just going to keep going as
long as possible?
I'll, I'll try and last longer than you.
Let's have a little competition, shall we?
You know, so wait a minute.
Okay.
Are you, are you going to try to make, okay.
All right.
Fine.
Popey.
No, wait, no, I can't do it.
I can't do it.
Cause I have show prep stuff that you don't have to do.
You don't have to worry about the markdown stuff like I worry about.
All right.
I'll tell you what, I'm going to try to get it to next week.
Show prep is going to take longer and I have a lot of shows.
All right.
I'll get to it till next week and then if I can keep going, I'll be like Kramer driving
on empty.
I'll keep on going as long as I possibly can until I run out of fuel in the, in the Firefox
tank.
I'll check it on you.
Okay.
And rotten corpse.
You're going to take a challenge too.
Yeah.
I'll take the operium challenge.
Okay.
You know what?
I'm younger than all of you.
I better stamina.
So I will try to last the longest on the Firefox.
What are you on right now?
I'm on Chrome of course.
Okay.
Good.
All right.
Okay.
Good.
All right.
So we've got, we've got, we've got a, we've got a genuine masters of our own domain competition
here.
I like.
Oh hell I'll join.
Ooh, can you install Firefox on openSUSE so they got a repo for that, Eric?
Don't need a repo.
It's in the main.
Oh, is that how that works?
All right.
Uh, so David from Alabama writes in and uh, he says, save me from unity.
Sorry guys.
For those of you who love unity, don't take offense, but he'll, he, he breaks it down
here.
He says, what's up guys?
I love all the JB shows, especially last foe and unplugged.
I'm a football coach.
And he says, yes, insert your dumb jock joke here.
Hey, jocks are allowed in Linux.
Just us.
It's fine.
I mean, we might just resent you a little bit, but your totes allowed.
Uh, no, I kid.
Uh, but really, he says, I like Linux and I listen to you guys on my way to work on
my Nexus 5.
Even though a lot of what you guys talk about tends to be over my head.
I learn a lot.
I noticed that you said Borderlands 2 and Borderlands the pre-sequel have come to Linux.
So I downloaded both on my Ubuntu 14.04 box.
I have the Nvidia proprietary drivers installed and my hardware specs are pretty good.
I got a GTX 750 TI.
It's got an AMD FX 8320 CPU.
Everything seems groovy under Ubuntu, but he's just, he's not liking Unity.
It's not working for him.
He says, I just don't find it aesthetically pleasing for myself.
So I loaded Gnome.
I like it a lot, but when he plays games in full screen in Gnome, he notices there's like
a screen tearing effect.
He said under Unity, he used compass settings manager to disable full screen rendering or
what's it called, the unidirectional, unredirected full screen applications is what the checkbox
is called in compass manager.
So he did that for Unity, but now there's no such setting under Gnome.
So I'm not totally sure that the screen tearing he's seen under Gnome is due to any compositing,
but I thought maybe we could punt it to the mumble room.
Maybe there's been some folks in here that have trouble shot this kind of stuff.
Any ideas for what could be causing screen tearing on his 3D games?
Well, by chance, did he say what kind of game it was?
Borderlands.
I'm assuming it's Borderlands.
And it's an Nvidia graphics card with the proprietary driver.
And I was wondering if it could be a V-Sync issue.
Me too.
It sounds like it.
Yeah.
Sorry, this cropped up on the Ubuntu Marte community a couple of days ago and somebody
actually found a fix for it.
So if you give me a minute, I'll go and find the solution.
There's a similar problem in XFCE with its compositor turned on, causes a lot of screen
tearing.
You can get rid of that by using Compton, I believe it is.
Yeah.
And I'm not positive because I've been essentially the same setup, Gnome 3, Nvidia graphics card.
I think mine's, I've tried it on a 600 series and a 700 series graphics card.
Full screen, Borderlands.
I don't have any tearing on my local screen.
I actually sometimes get tearing on capture because it's sending an interlaced signal
out.
But on my local LCD panel, no tearing.
And I cannot remember if V-Sync plays a role in this.
I seem to remember it does.
So if anybody has any suggestions too, you could also put it in the comment sections
for the feedback.
I'm reading the chat room right now.
Floppy Bacon says GLX blank is the option.
Check for that.
GLX V blank.
Look for that.
So yeah.
And if you do find it, you can drop it in the chat room or if you're listening after
the fact in the subreddit.
I believe the Arch subreddit has something about that with graphics in particular.
Okay.
Yeah.
And I know like Cinnamon 2.4, which was just released last week, one of the things that
they enabled by default is when an application goes full screen, the compositor disabled
is disabled.
Kaywin does this as well.
My understanding is though Mudder does as well.
But I'm not sure.
And I have not noticed the problem myself.
Okay.
Next email comes in from Les.
So we just heard about a hardware woe.
Les wants to take the other track.
In fact, he thinks maybe we don't do this often enough.
He says, hey Chris, Matt in the mumble room, in a recent episode of Linux Unplugged, there
was discussion about a laptop that had a graphics issue when booting Linux.
Chris made a comment that he was disappointed these kinds of things are happening still.
I think as a Linux community, we beat ourselves up about this far too much.
Yes, there is occasional problems, but as a community, we focus on these problems, often
cite them as reasons why Linux is unsuccessful on the desktop even.
But to counter this, I wanted to mention my recent experience.
I bought a Samsung laptop.
I use it for testing and have had no problems installing Ubuntu, elementary, or even OpenBSD.
With the exception of a binary driver for Wi-Fi and OpenBSD, everything works out of
the box, including graphics and power management sleep mode.
Last week though, I had the need for a Windows 7 system.
So as the laptop originally came with it, I installed a fresh copy of Windows 7.
After the install, the graphics were terrible and on inspection, Windows had failed to identify
nine items of hardware.
This included both the wired and wireless NICs.
I then had to spend a whole evening first trying to get my NIC working and then trying
to track down the drivers.
I had many hours of searching using Samsung's tool, only to find six of the nine drivers.
After many hours, I finally got it all working using another detection tool from Intel that
identified some of my chipset.
Then when the system finally restarted after installing everything, it all ended with the
blue screen of death loop.
At that point, I gave up and just installed Ubuntu Mate edition, which of course worked
perfectly.
Sorry for the long story.
But I think it's important that we recognize it's far worse than other platforms and maybe
we should focus on the positives a bit more.
Linux hardware detection is pretty good.
I remember the days of Red Hat 4.x.
Keep up the great work and stay positive, Les.
Isn't he right?
He's really right.
Yeah, I would agree.
I would definitely agree.
It's gotten so much better.
And then out of the box, the only system that is better than hardware detection out of the
box is OS X because you can only install it on Macs.
But as soon as you try to put it on anything else, it is a full-fledged train wreck.
And Windows is just as bad.
You get lucky with the Windows box if your NIC's detected and it's semi-older hardware,
like it's in that Windows sweet spot, it'll pull down a lot of it, but nothing matches
Linux with the diversity.
Right?
I mean, nothing.
That's true.
I mean, I remember back in the repair days, you always had that spare NIC that you kept
on hand so that when you repaired someone's computer and you knew you were going to have
to chase down those drivers, you had a means of connecting to the internet to do so.
That was a definite interesting time.
And yeah, Linux really solves those problems.
I mean, legacy peripherals are even a better example.
Derek Devlin, do you suppose that we sometimes focus on the negative stuff because we're
problem solvers?
We want to analyze the problem and try to fix it?
Totally.
And I think this non-acceptance of something still missing or something not working is
what puts us in the position we are really.
And I think we actually should keep that mentality, is that we'll keep improving Linux.
But Windows folks, which stabilize, look, they're dying.
Eric, have you ever had that experience where you pull a drive from one Linux rig and move
it over to another machine and plug it in and it actually boots up?
Yes, I have.
It's brilliant.
It just automatically, the kernel knows what it's doing.
It detects the hardware, configures the machine for that hardware, and boom, you're done.
I actually, not exactly moving a drive from one machine to another, but using Clonezilla
to clone an entire disk from one disk to another.
And it just works.
It works better than Windows and a lot better than Mac.
Yeah, Windows will just blue screen if the controller changes too much.
And Wimpy, you've got some experience with moving the hard drives around to do an install,
right?
Yeah, I mean, I've got some really ancient hardware.
And back in the day, I used to install the operating system, I used to take the hard
disk out of a laptop that had no NICs and had no Wi-Fi and had no USB and put the disk
in a different machine, install Debian, then take the disk out, plug it into the laptop
and then boot and configure everything and install the desktop I wanted.
And I was doing that back in the late 1990s.
So it's been possible for a long, long time.
Yeah, it's just so cool.
It is, I think, one of the best aspects that Linux doesn't get credit for anymore.
And I think there was a time where the Roses were not as red, but it's pretty awesome and
something that really sells people when you show them, like, yeah, this USB thumbstick,
I can just boot your computer with this and everything just works.
And it just blows people's minds still.
All right, Aaron writes in, I like Aaron, I like the way he thinks, he says, I'd like
to hear more about your latest experience with ButterFS and why you switched to XFS.
Where's the love for good old Extended 4?
I'm running OpenSUSE a factory, soon to be Tumbleweed, and I was affected by the ButterFS
read-only snapshot bug after upgrading from kernel 3.16 to 3.17.
So for now, I've disabled snapshots by uninstalling Snapper and the Snapper Zipper plugin.
Thankfully, the damage seems to be limited to some corrupted snapshots.
Hopefully, when the bug is fixed, the snapshots can be re-enabled and my two dozen corrupted
snapshots can be deleted.
I don't want to go Nuke and Pave style, but if it's necessary, I may go back to Extended
4.
From there, I can at least upgrade to ButterFS when it becomes a little more stable.
So I want to talk about, over the weekend, I finally reloaded my Bonobo Extreme that
was the original install since our Arch Challenge, that I was pretty proud that I held that install
that long.
And it was really, really a great install.
The only problem was, I was totally out of storage space.
Like I couldn't install any more games, it even got to the point where I was having a
hard time, like I couldn't do any more VirtualBox images for demos for LAS, I couldn't install
some of the apps I wanted to install to demo on LAS, so it was actually starting to impact
show production.
So when I really realized I was hitting that phase of the install, I decided to Nuke it.
And I used Angros, Antaragos, Antardos to install it.
And it's been rocking.
And I decided to go this time around, XFS instead of ButterFS.
Even though I was so tempted, you guys, I was so tempted.
But it was really the discussion that we had had here in the Mumble Room at some point,
where so many people were really advocating XFS, that I decided to pull the trigger on
that.
And my main problem with ButterFS came down to just the fact that DF doesn't actually
report the file sizes isn't a huge deal, but it was like, it just really gnawed at me that
I never really felt like I had a super clear snapshot of what my storage situation was.
And it was slowly getting worse and worse over time.
And so, because I have, in my Bonobo, I have a 128GB SSD for my home drive, and I have
a 256GB SSD that I slice up amongst my main Arch installation, another distro that I'm
trying, and like all of the applications and anything like that.
So it's kind of a tight operating margin, and with ButterFS just sort of fudging the
extra metadata and things like that, it just became too expensive.
And I don't even remember, I can't remember if it was Blaster or if it was Wimpy who was
really advocating XFS so strongly, but somebody sold me on it.
And I was an old XFS user from years back as a sysadmin, so I'd had some experiences,
it seemed to be a good file system when I used it.
Anybody in here a big XFS user?
Who was that?
It was me.
Okay, Wimpy, so do you remember the bullet points of sort of what your main points were
for me to switch, because you convinced me.
Yeah, well I went through something similar when I had a disk fail recently, and what
I've done is slightly different.
I've kept ButterFS for the root file system, but I'm using XFS for the home partition,
for the reasons that you've just outlined.
Toolbox machines and large files, ButterFS was, I couldn't seem to rebalance it to get
the space back, I don't know where it had gone, but it wasn't letting me have it.
And I knew full well that there wasn't as much data on the device as it was claiming
was there.
That was my situation as well.
So that's why I made the switch.
But for me as an Arch developer, I want ButterFS on my root file system because I get all the
benefit of ButterFS on the development tools, so that's where it pays off then.
You know, I actually like the, it sounds crazy, I never thought I would become a fan of it,
but the real time LZO compression on ButterFS worked excellent for me, performance was good,
so I missed that, especially on an SSD.
Yeah that is great.
And then I've still got that on the root partition, so I've got those benefits at boot time.
Yeah, maybe I should have done that.
I was just, I felt so burned at the time that I thought, no I'm going to go XFS everywhere.
Keep it simple.
I typically use XFS everywhere, but on my Arch machines I'm sticking with ButterFS on
the root partition.
So the million dollar question was, why XFS over XT4?
It's just brilliant.
It's rock solid.
It's been, it's a bit like Marte, you know, it's got a long heritage, it's super mature,
it performs as well as or as close to everything else or exceeds some of the others, so you
don't need to tweak it.
All the defaults are tuned for performance and it's just bulletproof and if you want
some ButterFS like facilities, then stick LVM underneath it and then you can snapshot
it.
Yeah, that's true.
Yeah, for me it was sort of the antithesis to ButterFS, like it was going to something
that was, I mean I literally deployed systems with XFS in the 90s, so I mean I've used it
for a really long time and so I just trust it and after getting burned by something new,
I think I went to the other extreme.
Wizard, I know you had to mention about parallel writing, is that for ButterFS or is that another
file system?
No, that's XFS.
Oh.
XFS does do, it does a very good job at parallel writing at the same time.
So you go and you have multiple files, you're writing them all at the same time, it'll go
on and it'll actually split up and it'll write them in a very even way and still maintain
a fairly decent speed.
XFS is great if you don't want copy-on-write or if copy-on-write isn't a super big deal.
Right.
That was sort of, I think I remember from our discussion, it was sort of like you get
a lot of benefits of ButterFS, a lot of optimizations I wanted from ButterFS, but if I don't want
copy-on-write and I don't want compression, then might as well just go XFS.
Yeah, it's absolutely wonderful.
The only real thing that you'll hear from people and they're usually people that have
been using XFS or used XFS in the very distant past was they'll go and they'll say, well,
I had a brownout and this did weird things and I couldn't recover the file system.
And you know, it's not a big deal, at least I don't see it as a big deal, and I wouldn't
worry about it yourself just because you have a laptop battery, you know, and it's going
to go and shut down.
That truncating to zero bytes on files, that was fixed about 10 or 11 years ago.
Exactly.
It's old news.
People still bring it up.
But one other thing that kind of burned me about ButterFS was I realized maybe six, seven
months into the game that there was a thing called defragmenting that I should be doing.
Right?
And Wimpy, that's not such a problem with XFS, is it?
Yeah, XFS has got really brilliant defrag tools.
So you can do online defragmentation and it works really well and you know exactly where
your data is being used.
And for someone like you who will have large video files, you can defragment individual
files rather than having to do the whole file system.
So if you leave your laptop on overnight, just stick a cron job in there to do the XFS
defrag on your partitions and it will just stay all nice and hunky-dory.
And Wizard, do you have a comment on the XFS toolset?
Yeah, the actual commands for going and doing stuff like repairing your file system, all
this other stuff, you can use all the stuff that you're regularly used to, like fcsck.xfs.
That was big for me too.
Yeah.
There's also, and if you're used to the ButterFest, you're like, oh, I want to use X program to
deal with this.
You can do that as well because almost every single one of them has a program of their
own, like XFS repair, or they all have their own.
And it's super simple, they're not crazy, you really can read a man page for once and
know how it works.
Right.
That is very true.
And Wimpy, we probably should make a mention because the chatroom is asking, XFS, as far
as you know, supports Trim, right?
It does, yeah.
So there you go.
And I remember one of the reasons I went ButterFest was, well, it's SSD optimized.
When you look into the SSD optimizations, I think it's like they don't massage the access
times, and it supports Trim and a few other things.
And I realized when XFS can do that too, that was one of the deciding factors for me to
choose ButterFest.
It's like, this is the SSD ready file system.
Actually the old dog XFS can do it too.
So yeah, I thought, what the heck?
So anyways, that was my thought process.
Long and convoluted, and probably a lot of it was in pre and post shows.
But it was a long series of discussions that brought us there.
And I still have, let's see, one, two, three, four current production systems that are still
running ButterFest.
So it's not like I've switched.
I just switched my main, my Bonobo.
I haven't switched all my systems.
And I still have a server running ButterFest.
Here's a question then.
So you were obviously loathe to lose ButterFest and the compression from the performance point
of view.
Did you notice any performance degradation?
You know, not really.
But it's hard to tell when it's such a new install.
Because my...
So you really need to fill it up in a few months time and then call back.
Yeah, I think as the drive gets fuller, I'll see if I start to notice it slowing down.
You know, the interesting thing is this Bonobo is a couple of years old.
And when I was setting up, I was like, wow, this, I really could not ask for this to be
a faster computer.
Like, this is still exceptionally fast.
And so it seems like the current higher-end hardware for the last couple of years to throw
at desktop Linux is more than sufficient.
If you have an SSD and a decent processor, you get really good performance.
So I don't know if I'll be able to tell the difference, to be honest.
But I do feel like when ButterFest really filled up, like when I'd have a virtual machine
that was sort of eating away at storage and I didn't realize how fast my drive space was
ticking down because it was all happening inside a VM, I really felt like I could tell.
It almost seemed like to me, I went down to like spinning hard drive speeds and it was
painfully slow.
Like having to watch like my directories like actually like load out and you know, all that
just felt really slow.
And the only thing that happened is I'd fill up the drive.
And when I deleted the drive and rebalanced, the performance came back.
So I don't know if that'll happen.
I doubt that'll even happen in XFS.
We'll see.
Only find out after a little bit of usage.
Hey, we're going to follow up on some of our OpenSUSE coverage, including producer Eric's
notes.
But before we do that, I want to thank our first sponsor, Linux Academy.
Go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged to get our 33% discount.
And that's on your subscription.
You're going to stay subscribed to Linux Academy once you go over there.
I heard from a lot of folks at Ohio Linux Fest who've really been enjoying Linux Academy.
And I just got a message from somebody last night that said their power was out.
But they had downloaded Linux Academy's comprehensive study guides and the tutorials offline before
the power went out.
And they're still doing their study without the power.
It's kind of incredible.
So go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Check them out.
They've got all the different distributions you could possibly want to try.
You choose from those.
They'll automatically adjust your courseware.
They just added four more courses over the last week.
It's a ton of new stuff coming out.
They have stuff in the pipeline all through the remainder of the year.
Go over there.
You can learn anything you really could possibly imagine in the Linux system itself.
And they're expanding beyond that into AWS, OpenStack, DevOps.
You can go over there and get an introduction to Android development, introduction to VMware,
VFXI.
If you ended up having to support a VMware environment, go there and pull that down.
And what's really nice is as you go through these courses, you can keep track of your
progress.
They'll give you estimations as you log back in and say, here's where you left off.
Here's the index of where you're going to go.
This is how long it's going to take.
Here's the guide that goes with it.
And they also have learning plans where you can set exactly how much availability you
have.
And they'll automatically adjust the courseware to match that availability.
And they'll nudge you and say, hey, remember, you've got a test at the end of the week to
keep you involved, to keep you going back.
They've got an active support structure in their community as well, live streams where
you can ask questions directly to the instructors.
It's one of these things that you really don't understand until you go there and you engage
in those resources that are available to you.
You begin to move something forward.
And it's very rewarding.
I've been doing it now since they became a sponsor.
Every week I go in there and I try something out.
And it's very rewarding.
It's intellectually stimulating.
I'm able to see what new things interest me.
And I'm able to stay current at a much deeper level.
And so even though I'm not in the IT field anymore, I still find it to be an incredibly
valuable resource.
I could only imagine if I was still in IT how handy this would be.
You can get a full end-to-end course on the LAMP stack, Apache self-signed SSLs, remote
GUI administration set up on Linux, setting up an NFS server, NGINX, Nagios, backing up
with rsync, taking care of the Heartbleed bug, all of that.
They have scenario-based training too.
So you can do some of these things in lab environments where you'll actually go end-to-end.
You'll deploy the software, you'll deploy the application on top of that.
You'll integrate in third-party services.
You'll have a working product that's accessible from the public because as the courseware
requires it, they automatically spin up Linux servers for you on the backend, give them
public IP addresses, give you a login, you're going to sign them roles.
It's a really cool system.
People just go on and on about it when I meet them in person.
It's awesome to hear that.
So go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and keep sending in your success stories too.
I really love hearing that.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a really big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the Linux Unplugged Show.
Okay, so OpenSUSE as the version 13.2 is officially here.
We got ourselves a new green baby.
You can go over and get it at the OpenSUSE website.
Lots of nice stuff in there.
They've also given us the new deets on their new rolling setup.
And so I thought we'd talk to producer Eric and anybody in the Mumble Room that's up and
running OpenSUSE.
Do some follow up from our review, touch on a couple of items.
Eric, let's start with, really quickly, I know we mentioned it in the review, but you
kind of, you had a defense for GNOME software that I thought was fair, we should give it
some time.
Because in the review I was like, man, there's so many ways to install software in OpenSUSE.
You've got three or four different ways, and now they've just thrown in GNOME software.
And you kind of raised the point.
It does serve some purpose.
Yes, it does, absolutely.
If you understand OpenSUSE, and this is something that you've actually had a gripe about in
the past, is that they don't have any good way for software discovery.
Well, that's where GNOME software comes in and fills in that gap.
So it's not the best for software discovery, but it's definitely better than nothing.
Yeah, I would love, love to see an app that could expose the coolest and best stuff in
software.OpenSUSE.org.
Because I feel like there's projects that are plugged into that and generating RPMs
for SUSE that I don't even know about.
Yeah, but software.OpenSUSE.org is something that you want to search because it's directly
tied to the build service.
Think of it almost like the AUR in ARCH.
Basically there's no way to discover software in the AUR.
You've already got to know about it and then search the AUR to find out.
Well, software.OpenSUSE.org is the exact same way.
In fact, there's the Firefox extension for being able to search the AUR.
I've installed that a lot when I've run ARCH, but also in OpenSUSE, I've actually made it
so that that search box in there, I can directly search that from my bar using a keyword.
Oh, that's handy.
That's neat.
Yeah, that makes it super handy.
It makes it super fast to search it as well.
Okay.
And I also noticed too that you had a Chrome extension in the show notes for a one-click
installer for OpenSUSE.
Yes.
Basically this kind of comes by default with Firefox.
Oh, it is.
Oh, that's in Firefox.
So you mean an add-in to Firefox?
Oh, okay.
It's not really an add-in.
It's basically they kind of have it in their code.
There's like an OpenSUSE enhancements extension that does a few things, right?
Does a few small things to make Firefox work a little better under SUSE.
Yeah, just a few small things.
This basically fills in the gap for Chrome.
If you want to use Chrome, you can just click on that.
It'll bring up the YMP file in your browser and say, do you want to install this?
You can click on yes, and as long as you follow the instructions from the plugin page on the
Chrome store, it will just basically start that one-click installer.
Yeah, it'll fire off the install and you're off the races.
Exactly.
Calls your uncle, as you say.
You had a make good in the review.
We forgot to touch on how horrible the fonts are by default in OpenSUSE, but it's actually
pretty easy to fix.
Correct.
In the show notes, all you have to do is you could check out that there's a repo that Chris
has on the screen if you're watching the video version and select one of those repos on there,
depending on which version you have, whether it's 13.1, 13.2 or factory slash tumbleweed.
You click on that, go ahead and copy that into that whole URL into your software repositories
in Yast, and then you add that into a pseudo-zipper DUP, which is Distribution Upgrade, basically,
and it will move your font config files over to that from the default and basically change
them to the Infinity version.
That's pretty straightforward.
If you're having trouble following, Eric has links in the show notes to do that.
I would definitely recommend that because I meant to mention that in the review.
You're absolutely right about the font rendering.
It's atrocious by default.
Why is that?
I don't know.
It's like they haven't taken anything that Infinity or the Ubuntu people have done forever
and integrated.
I don't know.
Honestly, in their defense, it's also pretty crap in Fedora by default, too.
I'll give them that.
Fonts just need to get better.
This is the thing I'm the most excited to talk about because the rolling release thing
could be extremely compelling if it's done right.
You took the dive, right?
You've been doing it for what?
Two, three weeks or more?
How long have you been running?
About two or three weeks.
After we got done with the Ubuntu back at last 3.35.
That was three weeks ago, I think.
That was about three weeks ago.
I went ahead and went all in with OpenSUSE and knowing it's coming out next, I had been
running Factory off and on since Factory was announced to be a full rolling distro.
I've been very impressed with the results, to be honest.
There's the initial article right there.
That's about Factory merging with Tumbleweed.
Have you had to do any open source versus proprietary driver installs on their role?
How does that work?
I don't have to do that on my machine because it's running full Intel.
I really don't have much experience with that.
However, there are one-click installs for the NVIDIA drivers using an actual Factory
repo or whatnot.
One thing that's important to note is that as of today, Tumbleweed and Factory are pretty
much synonymous.
Basically, the Factory repos are just linked over that is alias to the Tumbleweed repos,
and Tumbleweed is now the name for the rolling distribution as of today, November 4th.
We have linked in the show notes frequently asked questions that the OpenSUSE project
has posted up.
Do you get updates every day?
Pretty much.
It reminds me a lot of Arch in that way, except without the headache of having to manually
config files and whatnot.
You mentioned, too, something about the way the update manager is constantly running the
background, right?
Correct.
Now, that update manager you were talking about for GNOME, the package updater, that
is constantly running in the background, just kind of checking to see, pinging the repos,
see if there's anything.
It's always using zipper as the backend.
It's just basically using zipper.
If you were on a rolling release, does this just kind of constantly check for updates
and just sort of notify you when there's a new update?
That's the funny thing about rolling is that I'm not sure if it does because I haven't
had it pop up at all, but in rolling, you're supposed to use zipper dup every time you
want to update.
Oh, okay.
So, you don't use any of the built-in software tools?
Correct.
Not for factory or Tumbleweed.
It's basically that.
But those tools are still there if you convert to rolling?
Correct.
Yes.
Yeah.
The other thing that's kind of nice is there is a way to sort of jump in more current.
If you want to go straight to rolling, you can get snapshot ISOs, right?
Or am I wrong?
Yes.
There are snapshot ISOs you can do if you want to go straight to rolling, like do a
fresh install with rolling.
You can also convert your repos over to the factory or Tumbleweed, and there are instructions
on that.
But it seems cleaner.
Wouldn't it just be cleaner to go right into a rolling release?
Yeah.
That's exactly what I did.
I didn't even bother with installing 13.1 and switching the repos over.
I just installed from the ISO.
Right.
I've converted one install to rolling, and it was pretty painless.
But I remember there's like a couple of repos I had that there specifically was like a 13.1
version for, but there wasn't a Tumbleweed version for, so I couldn't switch that one
or something like that.
That was a problem where people haven't published more updated quote-unquote Tumbleweed packages.
There's only like the release versions of packages, and it sort of depends on the project
or something.
I don't know what I ran into, but there's a couple of repos that had to get disabled
when I switched over to rolling.
Right.
I've run into that myself, and it's kind of annoying when that happens.
At the same time, you can still stick with those packages and just install the packages,
not subscribe to the repo.
And so there's a six-month transition window as we switch from factory to Tumbleweed?
Am I getting my terminology right?
That's kind of correct.
Basically factory is just kind of linking over to Tumbleweed, but what's happening is
that that factory alias is going to go bye-bye in six months, so basically it'll stop working.
The new repo that you have to subscribe to is that Tumbleweed repo.
Okay, RottenCorps, go ahead.
I think you're reading my mind.
One thing that annoys me about OpenSUSE is their phrasing for the one-click install from
their software website.
It irritates me because it's like 15 clicks.
Yeah, it is a lot of clicks.
It is a lot of clicks.
It is, and it's really just a branding thing.
Basically the reason it's one-click install is you click on it once in the browser, and
then you're starting the install process as opposed to having to copy a repo, paste it
into the software repository.
In one click you get the repo added and the software installed.
I can activate a dev file, open one click, and that's the same thing.
Well, let's not take it literally.
Well, they could just not use that term, and it would just be so much better.
It's all marketing, man.
Yeah, it is.
It crossed my mind during the review.
During the review, when you first set it up, it's like when you run that the most.
When you combine that with the media manager trying to check my thumb drive, which also
brings up two prompts, and then you combine that with the fact that I enter my password,
and then to kind of make it a little worse, and it's not really their fault.
This is kind of the way GTK theming works a lot of times, is you start the first process
as yourself, as in my case, my ChrisF user.
Then once I entered my password, those following dialog boxes are now running as root, so they
drop all of my GTK theme.
They look completely different, so not only is there three or four windows that come up,
several prompts that come up, but half of the windows don't look like the other half
of the windows.
It's not a very...
Yeah, it's not their fault.
KDE does the same thing.
It's not a very elegant transition or process, but after I went through it a few times, it's
like, yeah, this could definitely be tightened up, but I also just appreciate the ease at
which I am getting a subscribe to the repo, which is really, for me, the most valuable
thing, because at the end of the day, I could go to any website and download an RPM and
install it, and just do that, and that's fine.
But for me, the true value of the one-click install is not only am I installing it, but
I'm also getting that repo, so I'm getting those future updates.
That's more than just installing software.
That's also sort of, quote-unquote, subscribing to that software, and to me, that's worth
a little extra hassle.
I think it could be rebranded, too, though, but you know.
What's also cool about that is once you subscribe to that repo, say you find another package
that you want to use with the one-click install on, you don't remember if you're subscribed
to that repo or not, it's not going to double up the repo.
It's going to use the same one.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that is nice, too.
All right, Eric, is there anything else we want to cover in our open SUSE follow-up?
Oh, Plasma 5, didn't you want to mention Plasma 5?
Yeah, Plasma 5 is a separate repo you have to subscribe to if you want it.
There are instructions from the KDE portal on how to do that, but yeah, as far as Plasma
5 goes, it is the best Plasma 5 experience I've ever had on any KDE distro at all.
That includes Kubuntu.
I mean, all of the breeze theme, instead of having the, what is it, the cute curve theme,
actually there is a dedicated breeze theme now, and I was only able to find it in open
SUSE.
That's nice.
So that's something to look forward to.
Yeah, and it looks really nice.
Something definitely to look forward to.
I have reason to believe that if Kubuntu is doing this in the next version with Plasma
5, I have reason to believe that 13.3 will also be Plasma 5.
That makes sense.
Yeah, so there you go, and the beat goes on, I agree, Rotten, that it does sound like a
better way to do PPAs.
That's kind of what my impression was.
It's a centralized way, sort of like the AUR is a centralized way to find stuff.
You get to subscribe to the repo.
It is more clicks than it needs to be, and yes, I realize you can also do app colon slash
slash and a lot of browsers on Ubuntu will recognize that.
It's not a totally unique system, but it works well.
But that doesn't subscribe you to the PPA.
Well I suppose, I suppose, it depends, like if you, there are some debians, like the Chrome
deb file, when you install that, it also installs a repo.
So some of them do, kind of depends, but it doesn't matter.
Like it doesn't matter if they're the only ones that can do it.
What matters is that it works, and that there's a nice interface in terms of the website to
find stuff.
And that part I give them all high marks on.
Yeah, consolidating the efforts is much better.
Yeah, it's better than in Fedora where you essentially have three repos.
You have Fedora's repos, you have Copper, and then you have the community RPM fusion,
so it makes it a bit of a pain to determine where you're getting that from.
I agree, I agree.
And Derrick Devlin, you had a comment on, you ran into a problem with network settings?
Yes, there's only one major problem, which is, if you don't read the page when you're
going to install, and you, for some reason, you're still not on IPv6, you need to go manually
on the settings and enable that.
Right, yeah, what was interesting is the installer uses YAS to configure the network interface,
but the desktop uses Network Manager.
So once you get through the installation, those two things don't communicate.
So if you had to join Wi-Fi in the installation and it has a password, when you reboot the
box after installation, you have no connection.
And it took me a second to think, wait a minute, I was just on Wi-Fi, oh, right, one was YAS'd,
one was Network Manager.
Now, how would a regular non-Linux person know that?
Like someone just thinking about IPv6 and IPv4 difference, someone that's not a computer
geek.
And what kind of tipped me off is once my desktop was booted up and installed, I was
just looking at YAS, and I brought up the network management utilities to see what options
were available in there.
And I got an error message saying, no, you're now using Network Manager, you can't use this
tool.
And I was like, oh, yeah, of course.
You can disable Network Manager and use that tool.
Right, but I don't want to, I don't want to.
You don't have to.
I want to use Network Manager.
I know I want to, so that's fine.
Network Manager's fine.
It was just kind of a thud when I logged in, and I went to go, I didn't even realize at
first that I wasn't connected because so many times, when I build an arch box, during that
installation process, the network is established before pretty much anything else.
And when I install Ubuntu, if I join the network during installation, that holds over.
All distributions really, for the most part, do that, because a lot of distributions now,
you boot up into a live environment, and in that live environment, you use Network Manager
to configure, and they must just move those settings over.
It's fine.
Right, and that's what they do in terms of Ubuntu.
If you want to use that network's settings in Yast, you can.
It's just that one tab is disabled for you if you're using Network Manager.
In fact, that's the only way you can change your host name.
It's just funny, it bit both Matt and I, so it must be common enough.
Exactly.
Yeah.
All right, so, but Eric, great follow-up and great links in the show notes, which we'll
have, especially if you want to work on your fonts and stuff like that.
He's got all that in there, so check that out.
And if you've been rolling OpenSUSE, let us know how it's going in the feedback thread
in the Linux Action Show subreddit.
Hello, Jack.
How you doing, Jack?
All right.
Well, why don't we take a... I want to talk about something kind of neat, and, oh, you
know what?
Actually, let's reverse the order.
I was going to talk about a new piece of hardware, but that's a little bit more of a positive
note.
I want to end on a positive note.
So, next, I want to talk about our brothers in arms over at Linux Outlaws calling it a
day.
Before we do that, I want to thank our friends at DigitalOcean.
Head over to DigitalOcean.com right now, DigitalOcean.com.
And save this promo code in the back of your mind.
Like channel it to yourself.
Say future self.
It's a critical piece of information that I have collected from the past, and I want
to put this forward.
So just think about it hard right now.
Unplug November.
That's your promo code.
Unplug November when you check out.
At least it should be.
I actually haven't checked my inbox this morning.
I apologize.
Unplugged October will probably work for a while, too.
Now to get you a $10 credit over at DigitalOcean.
We love DigitalOcean, and so many of you have tried it out, but yet so many of you have
yet to try it out.
So you're really in a perfect position to go over there and play with something.
And then later, I think you'll be surprised at how easy it is to put that in production
and how well it'll work for you.
So what is DigitalOcean?
You're not familiar?
Well, DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way to spin up a cloud server.
I was playing around with some of my droplets just the other night, and I turned one off.
Just to move, you know, I was experimenting actually with taking snapshots and resetting
passwords and all this.
Just trying different things out, because I love the interface over at DigitalOcean.
And I've been adding more machines, and I thought, okay, let's try a few things.
So I turned off a box.
I didn't know Reekai was using it for development at the time.
Oh, no.
You know, the thing is, is like we spin these droplets up, and they're just so useful.
We keep finding more and more uses for them, and they make it so easier over at DigitalOcean.
You can get started in less than 55 seconds, and pricing plans start only $5 per month.
They get you 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte of transfer.
And DigitalOcean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam,
and London.
So you could build a global distributed network if you want.
And their interface, their interface is simple and intuitive, but yet very powerful.
And the best part is, is you can replicate it on a larger scale with their straightforward
API.
And you're already seeing a lot of great apps out there that integrate in with Puppet, Unity.
There's some great command line tools, Python scripts.
There's so many things you can use that API for that the community has already created
for you too.
That's just the great thing about that API is it doesn't mean you got to do the work.
Other people are doing it as well.
But you could too.
You can snap it right in.
And then if you need to scale on demand, if you've got a busy day, you need to make sure
your web front end is still responsive, you could integrate that API and deploy right
up there.
You can scale right up to DigitalOcean, use their droplets, spin them up when you need
them, spin them down when you don't.
They have hourly pricing if you want them.
And if you use our promo code, unplugged October, or probably unplugged November, depending
on the timing, you can try it out for two months for absolutely free.
And DigitalOcean's taking the tutorials up to the next level.
They're offering up to $200 if you'll write a tutorial for them.
And if you go to their Instagram feed today, they posted one of their tutorial editors.
I think he might have broken his leg.
I'm not sure what was going on, but he was sitting there editing one of the tutorials.
It was a pretty funny shot.
It was on DigitalOcean's Instagram feed.
They also got some DigitalOcean data center porn up there, which is, I'm a big fan of
that.
So I think it's just Instagram.com slash DigitalOcean, but you'll probably be able to find them.
Go over to DigitalOcean.com.
Run up your own free droplet, try out Core OS for a couple of months.
It's pretty innovative.
It's pretty exciting.
I think it's going to be a big deal in the server space, and you can go play with it
right now on a server that's got tier one bandwidth and a data center anywhere you want
it.
It's an awesome opportunity to do it for absolutely free.
You just add the promo code, unplugged October, to your account.
It credits your account to $10, and you just run it as long as it lasts.
DigitalOcean.com.
And a huge thank you to DigitalOcean for being so damn awesome and sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Okay, so let's talk about the Linux Outlaw guys.
They announced, I think it was yesterday or the day before, let's see, where is the date?
November 3rd, so yesterday.
They announced that in five episodes, they'll be calling it an end after seven years of
producing Linux Outlaws.
It sounds like kind of for both the guys, for both Dan and Fab, that maybe their interests
have diverged over the time.
They're not done necessarily podcasting, but they're probably going to take a break and
come back and do something.
They're super passionate about.
It definitely sounds like maybe the production just came a bit of a chore and definitely
understandable after seven years.
I mean, that can become a lot of work.
And so I wanted to take a minute to kind of talk about how sometimes there's certain pillars
in the community that go away because maybe they're not as involved anymore or they're
not as interested anymore.
And is this something that is concerning?
Is this a general trend?
I mean, I think, Eric, when you and I were talking about it on the pre-show, you're like,
I'm worried that this suggests maybe something that just happens to enthusiasts over time.
And I started thinking about that when you mentioned that and I thought, well, we've
all been in this a while.
Like Matt and I specifically have been following this particular scene for a long time.
Burnout is a big problem and people move on.
I mean, Matt, when you hear about things like this, when you hear about somebody or a group
of people who've been working at something for so long, what crosses your mind when they
call it an end?
Well, usually sometimes it ends up just being an extended hiatus.
I mean, for myself with podcasting, I mean, before I joined Jupiter Broadcasting, that
was actually what had happened from another popular podcast.
So they may come back with something even cooler.
So yes, burnout is a thing and sometimes people just have to kind of keep trucking and find
out what works for them.
But I don't think it's necessarily a problem.
I think it's evolution.
I think people just evolve.
Yeah.
It's sad to see something go.
Yeah, right.
Things change.
What would be, you say, missing friends?
What do you mean?
Yeah, this reminds me.
I mean, I know Dan and Fab quite well, on the Ubuntu UK podcast with Linux Outlaws,
we organized a bunch of live events in the UK called Ogg Camp.
So we worked quite closely with them on those and I'll be interested to know what happens
in the future.
But it's reminded me of, I was doing a presentation recently and I used some photos from previous
Ubuntu developer summits and the kind of collective photo of everyone who was there and I was
looking through picking out faces of people who used to contribute to various projects,
Ubuntu and other stuff, who no longer do or whose careers have moved on or they've just
stopped contributing.
They still use the software, but they stopped contributing.
And I got a little bit sad because these are friendships that we've built over the years
and they've people who've moved on to something else.
See, when Eric said this, what I started thinking is maybe what we're really worried about is
in open source, we're so dependent on so many people volunteering their time based on their
passion, but sometimes passion has its limits.
It runs out after a while.
And is it maybe what we're actually afraid of is so much of what we depend on, it's created
by amazing people, those people eventually go away.
And so-
Right.
And you've got to have coping mechanisms and time off.
That's one reason why on the Ubuntu podcast, we finish at Christmas every year and take
a break for two months.
So we don't-
It's a good idea.
We don't solidly go-
You lose all your listeners, but it's a good idea.
No, we don't.
I can't.
We don't.
No, it's good.
It's like...
And Linux Outlaws has taken a lot of breaks over the years, but at a certain point, it
still becomes a chore.
And that's totally understandable.
I guess, Eric, I didn't want to speak for you too much, but did I kind of summarize
your thoughts or when you heard this news, what crossed your mind?
That's exactly what crossed my mind, actually.
You did summarize my thoughts very well.
The thing is, if you get at something for a long amount of time, you don't take a break
every now and then, you don't pace yourself.
I've seen this time and time again.
You will burn out.
It's just the way the human body is designed.
Yeah, I wonder-
It is designed to take rest.
I wonder if I didn't do this full time.
I couldn't imagine.
Definitely obviously not this many shows.
Well, there's a difference though, because you create content and you have a whole team
of people around you.
With Dan and Fab, it's just the two of them.
As I understand it, Fab does all of the editing.
To be fair, he's a bit precious about it and doesn't like anyone else.
Other people have offered to take on the job and he's quite a perfectionist and wouldn't
let anyone touch it.
Yeah.
In fact, I think if you don't build a team, that's exactly what happens, right?
Right.
People like you who have a team of people, whether you pay them or not, or whether they're
community people who are volunteering their time, is largely irrelevant.
They're people who are helping you get the thing out.
If you don't have that crutch to lean on, you're screwed.
I think too, I look at it and what I don't like is I don't want it to represent a decline
in the interest, because I don't sense that.
I think a lot of people have associated with, oh, there's less of an interest in the market.
I don't think that's actually true.
I think it's just sometimes the people, like in their case, Dan and Fab, sometimes their
interests change.
It becomes harder and harder.
You could see in the evolution of the show, they start covering more generalized technology
and topics and security in the NSA, diverging more and more from Linux as a topic itself.
Arguably, Linux is more popular now than it has ever been in the past.
It can't possibly be that it's not popular, it's just popular to different people for
different reasons.
Exactly.
Yeah, and I think it's natural that as that changes, it might not be as appealing to some
people.
But yeah, Wizard, go ahead, jump in, that's kind of all the thoughts I had.
I just wanted to make a mention to it and tip of the hat to him too for all the hard
work for so long.
But Wizard, go ahead.
Yeah, so it is sad when you see good people leave and all, but I tend to find that a lot
of times, it's not so much that they're leaving.
It's just whatever they're making, it kind of comes to summation or it stabilizes or
whatever they're doing, it just seems to slow down.
And as whatever they're doing slows down, they just quit putting as much effort in,
not because it doesn't need it or anything, not because it's totally imperfect.
It's just they've got what they needed done and now they want to go and use the product
because whatever they're doing, it's because they're passionate about it.
They want to see it work.
And when it works, it's like, okay, I'm done.
I'm going to sit back, be happy for a little while and then maybe move on to something
different.
Very true.
And so we wish them the best of luck and we'll stay tuned to see what they come up with
next because I have a feeling we haven't heard the last of them because I think Six Guns
itself is sticking around and Ogg Camp itself as far as they have plans, they aren't changing
anywhere.
Hey, I have something fun to talk about.
Something that will sort of lift our spirits before we run, maybe get a good debate going
first though.
I want to tell you about something that lifts my spirits every single month.
Oh, who was it?
I got an email.
I think it was Tony.
I'm sorry.
It was Tony or Terry.
It was a T name.
I'm sorry if I'm getting your name wrong.
Matt.
So you know how we always talk about the savings calculator over at Ting?
Oh yes.
Tony went over there and plugged his actual usage in and he's going to save like 177 something
a month.
In two years, it's almost going to be four grand or it's over four grand is what he's
going to save by switching to Ting.
Holy cow.
That's like a liquid powered computer.
Yeah, I know, right?
That's a serious gaming rig every couple of years and it's really simple.
It's because Ting is on a mission to make mobile make sense.
You only pay for what you use.
It's a flat six dollars for the line and then it's just your minutes, your messages and
your megabytes.
There's no special plan you have to be in to turn on tethering.
If you want to use it, you just check the box and it's just your data usage and Ting
has an awesome dashboard that lets you manage your account, see exactly where each line
is at, nickname them so I've got funny names for each line.
I can set individual limits, alerts, disable lines when I don't need them and then I don't
have to pay for them.
And to top it all off, Ting has tier one tech support.
Like you immediately go to the top level person when you call them at 1-855-TING-FTW anytime
between 8 a.m. and 8 p.m. and a real human answers the phone and they are set up to solve
the problem.
Like they have the power to do it.
They don't have to talk to their manager.
They are the boss.
It's great.
They also have an incredible website that you can help yourself over at help.ting.com
I believe or ting.com.
Here's what you do though.
Go to linux.ting.com.
That's where you get started.
That's your home base, linux.ting.com.
That will take $25 off your first device.
If you have a Ting compatible device, they will give you a $25 credit but even more important,
you're going to tell them you appreciate them supporting Linux Unplugged by going to linux.ting.com
and you get to put Linux in the URL which is always fun.
Go over to their blog too because they just announced that they've rolled out tri-band
LTE to 17 new markets.
They've been working on this a lot over the last year, tons of new markets.
They now have tri-band LTE in over 400 markets across the, I'm sorry, 500 markets across
the United States.
Wow.
Yeah.
Tri-band, if you're not familiar, is a superior method of LTE where there's three different
frequencies that you can get on and so if one of them is working, you get a good connection.
If you get all three, it's amazing.
I've got tri-band LTE here at the studio, 1820 megabits on my speedtest.net.
Not uncommon at all.
It's really awesome and now that they just rolled it out to 17 new markets, Ting is constantly
getting better.
If you haven't checked them out in a little while, it's worth revisiting.
They've invested millions of dollars into rolling out this tri-band LTE infrastructure.
Now 500 markets across the United States have it.
Go to linux.ting.com, take $25 off your first device, try out that savings calculator, start
saving money right now, own your phone, don't get screwed over by the mobile carriers, get
decent support, use tethering when you need it and only pay for your usage, linux.ting.com,
linux.ting.com and a huge thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged and thanks
to everybody who checks them out.
I think you'll be pretty impressed and you'll save lots of money.
Okay, so here it is, you guys.
Finally, someone has invented the multi-pass or multi-pass from, if you remember, 5th Element.
It's called multi-pass, an open source offline password keeper.
It's a hardware based password device.
I'm gonna play a little bit of the video so you get a little introduction.
It's on IndieGoGo.
They're trying to raise funds.
They're trying to get to $110,000 roughly and they're at $18,000 right now.
So I don't know if they're gonna make it but I'll play a little bit of the video for you
guys and then you tell me if you'd back it and what the problems could be and what security
problems you might see.
So here we go.
I'll let this go.
Open and passwords are an integral part of our daily lives.
I know it.
They're what prevent malicious users from doing harmful things with our personal data.
People tend to use the same credentials for the different websites they visit.
However, recent news has taught us that credentials stored by websites are compromised on a daily
basis, which means that once an attacker gets your credential set, he can use it on other
websites.
This is why using different passwords for different websites is important.
Remembering many different passwords is difficult and one option is software-based password
keepers.
Essentially, they store an encrypted credentials database on your computer.
To unlock this database, you would enter a passphrase, which means that at some point,
both your passphrase and database must be stored in your computer or smartphone's memory.
Therefore, a malicious program could gain access to both and compromise all your passwords
at once without you knowing it.
To solve this problem, we introduce the multi-pass, an offline password keeper aimed at saving
and encrypting your passwords in a more secure manner.
The main device contains your encrypted passwords, while a secure smart card and a PIN code allows
their decryption.
Even if an attacker gets hold of your encrypted database or smart card, it is completely useless
without your personal code.
And don't worry, we implemented the possibility to make backup copies of your credential database
and smart card without compromising your system's security.
As opposed to software-based solutions, the multi-pass only runs our tested code independently
of your computer.
This means viruses or malicious programs cannot compromise your credential database or PIN,
neither of which are directly accessible from the computer.
Furthermore, our product is open source, allowing you to make sure that your credentials are
only kept inside the device and not leaked to the outside.
And with multi-pass, you can be sure that your credentials are only in the computer's
memory when needed, and when you explicitly permit the multi-pass to send them.
Okay, so let's talk about this.
Part of me likes the idea of a hardware-based security device, I'm not going to lie.
I like the smart card with the key codes, that's nice.
But there's a lot of good software-based solutions like LastPass and KeyPass already existing.
Anybody seen this already in the Mumba room?
Anybody sort of like ready to go jump on this?
I've actually, I was looking at this earlier today, actually.
What do you think?
It's interesting in and of itself, but what I'm going to just say that it comes down to
is that it's going to require you to carry things around.
And not that that makes it bad, but it's something that's going to stop me because I'm so forgetful
and I can't keep that thing on me all the time whenever I need to go and just shove
a password at something.
So there's another option, like LastPass has a thing called Open Sesame.
And basically you could put this on, it's kind of the same thing but software-wise,
put it on a flash drive, put the flash drive on your keychain, and then you always have
it.
Yeah, and you could also with LastPass use things like YubiKey as well.
And with KeyPass you can store the database on a flash drive and that way you keep it
with you.
It's always with you.
Yeah, to me there's too many drawbacks.
Losing of the physical item because I'm mobile, so that means I'd have to bring this with
me.
I'd have to bring it to my office, to the studio, and to home.
Which is just not a good idea.
So that's why I'm kind of down on it.
But if I was super worried about security, for some reason this does feel better.
Okay, here's what it is, I think, is you've got to understand the guys behind it.
They come from an InfoSec background and I think a lot of them are operating under the
assumption that the computer is compromised by default.
So you go into the situation assuming the computer is untrustworthy, therefore it's
a bad place to store your passwords, it's a bad place to copy them to memory, it's a
bad place to input your passcode, all of that, because you're supposed to assume the computer
is already compromised.
This removes it from that, they say it only runs their quote-unquote trusted code, even
though it's open source, I don't know exactly what that means.
It's not for me, but I thought it was interesting enough that maybe the audience might be into
it.
I kind of like it for some reason, something about it I like.
What I thought was really interesting about it was it kind of combined the smart card
reader with something as simple as something you can plug in and just have it automatically
fill in passwords.
That certainly is something in and of itself that is really interesting for what it does.
It combines what we already have had with smart cards for so long and combines it with
something that we've typically only ever seen in software and it kind of makes it very interesting.
However though, it still has a few fundamental limitations.
First of all, with bad USB, we now can't fully trust USB if we're super paranoid, which this
device seems like a device for the super paranoid.
And number two, if it's inputting the password, it's probably using a human interface driver
and sending keystrokes with the password because what you do is you go to your Gmail page,
you click on the login box, then you enter your PIN code and it sends in the password.
That's exactly what it does.
It emulates a keyboard.
But that could still be captured.
If you have something that's reading the memory on a Windows box, for example, that could
still capture that stuff.
Oh yeah.
And Linux has got very good software capture options.
Yeah, and that target breach, that huge ass target breach, that malware was just scraping
the RAM.
It wasn't doing key captures, it wasn't doing screen dumps, it was just scraping the RAM
and sending the details straight out of RAM.
And so this device doesn't really get around that if you still have to enter it in.
I don't know exactly, but I guess maybe it's harder to monitor something at the human interface
driver level, but I doubt it.
Derek Devlin, I know you wanted to get a chance to chime in and then I think we'll jump on.
Yeah, I think this is a good initial step.
And in the next generation of these kind of devices, the way I see is better browser integration
or better website integration as well, to the point that you can generate a cookie that
has your key and you never actually send any data, so your password is not sent to the
computer.
Right, right.
That kind of thing.
Like a token or something.
Yeah, something like that.
I think that's kind of the future for that kind of product, and they have a place.
And as Ken Seko points out in the IRC, something else I like a lot about it is they've put
all their code up on GitHub.
The code that runs this thing is open.
It's available now.
And the other thing about this project is they've got real units.
They've already had it in testing.
People are already using, quote unquote, production units today, and have been for months.
They've got a field of beta testers.
So this isn't necessarily like a pie in the sky project either.
This is something that's already a physical device that they've made.
There's already existing open-sourced code, so you're kind of backing a sure bet.
But their funding is a little short right now.
So I don't know.
I'll put a link in the show notes.
It's neat.
I love open-source hardware, or at least software that runs on it.
So yeah, they've got 30 days left, 18,000 of 110,000.
For this release?
Go ahead.
No?
Okay.
All right.
Well, something that strikes me as I'm looking into this is that they did a nice job of showing
what it's capable of doing.
What they're not really...
And again, this is only from the fundraising point of view.
What they failed to do is to show what happens when your current methods, methodology, local
access, local software tools fail.
Show that, then the money might start kicking in a little faster for them.
I don't feel like they did a very good job showing that.
Right, because people already know that using the same password in too many places is bad.
That's not making them stop.
Yeah.
They stopped using one, two, three, four, five, six a long time ago.
It's been a week.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, it's not a week.
Yeah, now use four, five, six, seven.
Let's get real.
Obviously, right?
Yeah.
Or just numbers backwards.
That's all good.
Well, it's an Indiegogo.
It's called MultiPass.
Great name.
Got to love the name, if nothing else.
It actually kind of saddens me that they don't have a cow as their logo.
Oh, yeah.
That would be good too.
MultiPass.
Or what's your face from Fifth Element?
Yeah.
What's?
Me and Joe.
Yeah.
MultiPass.
All right.
I think we're all done.
I think we've done our damage.
I think we'll wrap it up right there.
I just wanted to give you guys that.
Hardware is always fun and something you can get on early, and it's a neat idea too.
So that'd be neat.
We'll have links to everything we've talked about today in the show notes.
If you'd like to give us some feedback, some comments on anything we've talked about, go
to linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
That's also a great place to submit stories, topic ideas, or discussions, or just comment
on the existing stories to give us your take, your insights.
We integrate all of that into our shows.
You can also check us out every single week live over jblive.tv.
We do it at 2 p.m.
Pacific.
Go to jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone.
I got some cool projects I'm working on for this week's episode of Linux Action Show,
Matt.
So buckle up, and I'll see you on Sunday, okay?
All right.
Sounds good.
All right, everyone.
Thanks so much for tuning in to this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
I'm just going to mention it again, because it's a great place for you to get involved.
And if you want more show, there's another spot.
You can get just a lot more content, stuff that doesn't even make it in there, pics.
Oh, and we want you to run to Linux.
You can also submit them there.
Videos would be great.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
And also send us your emails.
Go to jupitabroadcasting.com, click the contact link, choose Linux Unplugged from the dropdown.
Feedback is a huge part of this show, and we love getting your emails.
Okay, everybody.
Thanks so much for tuning in to this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Don't mind me, I'm just going to go ahead and install Ubuntu Mate Edition 14.04 here.
When is that going to be out, guys?
Hopefully Saturday at the latest Sunday.
Very cool.
All right.
JBtitles.com.
Everybody vote.
Got to get a title.
Got to have a title.
Thanks for all the show notes, Eric.
I just put all that in the official doc.
So that's great.
Awesome.
You're welcome.
Isn't it weird that I do like air piano every time we get the outro going?
No, I love it.
You guys, it's great.
It's great.
Blast just slow danced with himself.
I think that's sweet.
There you go.
That's real dope.
Actually, I think I slow danced with Josh because he was slow dancing with me.
Hell yeah.
Yeah.
I did the Stevie Wonder dance.
Wow.
Oh, boy.
And it just got weird.
Angie and I have decided we're going to go see a concert in a few weeks for her birthday.
We're going to go see Fleetwood Mac.
Good choice.
It's going to be crazy, I think.
It's going to be crazy.
Don't know.
Yeah, I was following the two options.
I was rooting for that.
Right.
Yeah.
One's on Thursday.
One was on a Saturday.
And the Saturday one would have been easier.
But the Fleetwood Mac's on Thursday.
Yeah.
Yes.
JBtitles.
JBtitles.com.
Everybody, let's vote.
Can I ask for some help?
Yeah.
Do it.
So, I've had an audio failure, and I've heard some of you and the other guys talking about
USB sound cards and what have you, and I'd like some advice on what should I get that's
relatively inexpensive and reliable for plugging in headphones and mic.
I got this.
Good.
Anything with a cMedia chipset is going to do perfectly.
Honestly, the cheapest one.
The cheapest one that does that is actually it's called the Daffodil.
I know it's absolutely ridiculous, but if you go on Amazon, it's called the Daffodil
USB sound card.
It's like $8.
It's the most wonderful little thing that you'll ever buy.
I was going to mention that one actually.
It uses a cMedia chipset.
Yeah.
And then it's super simple.
They almost all do.
That then has mic and headphone jacks, does it?
Or do you...
It does.
Yes.
It is.
Right.
It's a USB headset and mic integrated thingy.
Is that a good idea?
Yes or no?
Yeah.
Those are good too.
That could do the trick, especially if your main sound chip is blown.
Yeah.
That's what I use right now.
My microphone that I'm using right now is a cMedia chipset and it's a USB microphone.
Yeah.
A lot of the headset ones are cMedia too.
The nice thing about the headset is then you've got headphones and mic in one, so that's nice
for mumble.
I literally have three or four, five of those really, so let's see, one, two, three in my
view right now of those cMedia sound cards.
We just use them around the studio because they work so well under every OS and when
I need audio out of a box, I just go there and plug one in.
I don't have...
This is it.
I've got two workstations here, both of which have let me down this evening.
My laptop, I couldn't get on last week when I was traveling because my laptop mic input
has died.
So I'm trying to find something that I can plug into whichever machine I'm on and rely
on.
Plug and go, really, the headset's super easy.
Right?
The headset's going to be the most dependable in my experience.
Platronics, I buy them by the gross.
I get them at thrift stores and just stick them in a box and I'm overflowing with them.
The biggest variance is going to be mic quality on the headsets and you just look at the different
reviews and stuff and you'll probably find it.
Yeah.
There's not too much difference between the actual USB sound device at all.
So a RAM, one, two, three.
Is there any hardware compatibility issues there?
Well, like Ram's pointing out, and I have run into this too, in fact, it bit me during
the pre-show.
Sometimes, I don't know if it's the cMedia driver or what, but sometimes I go to shave
off like just a little bit of volume towards the low end and it just totally silences it.
Like there's a really, like it just drops off at the end really fast.
Yes.
And that's more than cMedia because I have an Audio Technica USB cardioid microphone
and it has a built-in sound card so that the whole thing can just be plugged in via USB
and it's the same thing and it's not a cMedia chipset at all.
I have no idea what it is.
I don't know if it's a USB thing or...
I can speak for the Gamecom 780.
I actually submitted a patch into the Linux kernel for it.
And is it causing you problems?
Nope.
Oh, okay.
They took it?
Good.
Okay.
Any Platronics headset will work.
I've had minimal problems with them over the years and I've used like 15 of them.
I've never had compatibility issues ever.
I agree exactly with that because I had one when I first started doing this and it worked
brilliantly.
Did we ever figure anything out about the tearing issue that our emailer was having?
Yeah, sorry.
I pasted it in the chat room earlier.
Okay.
Oh, okay.
Would you mind pasting it again?
Let me find it.
Yeah, let me find it.
Thank you.
And I'll add that to the post-show notes.
Cool.
Thank you.
I'm sure somebody listening at home will probably put in a comment too.
And whatever headset you choose, really the big test is that if it can take being run
over, dropped, stepped on, lost, basically abused, that's my... Exactly.
And never be afraid.
If you find one that works, buy a couple.
Trust me.
You'll thank me later.
Yeah, because they go out.
They just... Plantronics had a really, really good one for a long time and they just... They
still have good ones, but they quit making the one I really like.
They just quit making it.
It's like, oh no.
I got the old school one.
I got the one I have on the other computer and it's got the actual adapter attached to
the cord midway.
I mean, it's like the best one I own.
So the other headset after they stopped making the one I really liked is I got the Logitech
Gaming Series, the G-something.
One thing I like about that one is it has a light on the mic itself so you know when
your mic is live because it actually lights up the end of the microphone and then you
just flip it up and it auto-mutes the mic, which is kind of nice.
You know your mic's muted if the headpiece is up.
Oh, I like that.
You can turn it down and it un-mutes, which is kind of cool.
And then if you have it on a Windows box, it supports... I don't think it... I've
never tried it on Linux, but it supports 7-point surround sound, quote, unquote.
I don't... It's kind of a thing.
And with any USB anything with audio, again, don't ever depend on the default sound chooser.
You're just going to frustrate yourself.
Get yourself the Pulse Audio, a PavDev chooser or whatever the hell they call it.