You guys have you guys noticed that if you watch
The show in VLC or MP at do with a watching MPV actually don't watch it in VLC
Have you noticed that if you watch the show in MPV like the RTSP stream like?
It's like a two second delay versus the flash player
Which is like a seven second delay
So if you want to interact with me in the chat room and you want me to be able to read you like you want to
Be able to respond a lot really fast and stuff
Maybe this is how JB Hawk a truth gets all the best titles if you watch the RTSP stream like an MPV
You just have to have a good connection
Yeah, I'm a con. I think it's true. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah
Yeah
Yeah, yeah, I've been so burned by my s6 this last couple of weeks oh
Man don't give me you're good trying to get you are trying to get me into a rant
I am a con that's what you were trying to do you are trying to get me into a rant look at him oh
Oh
Man go ahead go ahead API. I want to hear that or aka Andy
Okay, thanks, so does we'll see support the RTSP protocol. I am using RTMP for the moment
VLC is great. Yeah, VLC is good, too
MPV is just a little better and
And you are right about the delay, I think it does have a little
But I haven't measured it I
MPV one of the things I liked about MPV is I was watching the stream once and I had it in guake
I had I just did MPV on the command line MPV, and I pasted in the URL of the stream
And I watched MPV as is like this is the codec
This is and you know you just see all the cool nerdy output on the on the command line
and I
noticed it started saying something and
Then I when it when I read what it said I from that moment forward
I knew I would never use another desktop application to do live streaming and
it said
lip-sync mismatch detected
Automatically correcting and it automatically delayed either. I can't remember who's the audio or the video just enough. How did it detect that I?
Don't know I don't know
But it fixed it for me automatically right there on the fly, and I thought to myself
Brilliant people wrote this this software was written by brilliant people and your MPV is it's got a lot of legacy to it
And it so it's got a good hit, and I thought this is the application
I have noticed now as somebody who watches a lot of live streams
I'm a cord cut. I don't have cable television, so I consume a ton of content
Over live streams, and I have I have squirreled out some of the bet like I have found the RTSP streams at some of the
Internal networks used to send content around to each other like I probably I can't really say this
But I had a recent live coverage of a big tech event that I put out for our patrons
And I got the master feed that they were sending out to all of their endpoint stores
And I've got this whole stash of RTSP feeds that I use to watch shows and and and get content and get news and I
Tell you what VLC is very very good VLC is amazing for like capturing and recording and doing streaming converting and VLC is like one
Of my favorite applications on the Linux desktop, but if I'm just watching a live stream
Nothing beats MPV
This is Linux Unplugged episode 96 for June 16th 2015
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's mocking the Concrud
From afar my name is Chris and 96 is gonna be a packed episode for you guys
I am super excited I
Love this about the Linux Unplugged program our connection to the community and and really how crucial is that to open source?
That's what we're talking about today in episode 96. We're gonna get an update from the open tech conference
that was across the pond this weekend and then I
Scoured through all of the live footage from self this weekend, and I found an amazing chat
That our Noah had with a contributor to open source comm mr. Semiotic robotic
You may have heard of him before they had a great chat on the live stream
It was like a 45-minute chat. I paired it down to the best of it. We're gonna play that then
We're gonna meet one of the authors of the
Really the man who wrote the book on slackware mr. Alan Hicks will be on the show today to talk about his impressions of
Southeast Linux fest and the kind of fest it is and why that's so critical to how open source software is made and how he'd
Take the lessons learned from these fest and applies them to his job as a system administrator, but first before all of that
before
All of that we're gonna get to some feedback and some updates that have occurred somehow
Between Sunday's show the Linux action show and Tuesday's episode of Linux unplug if you can believe it or not somehow news is actually
transpired between now and then and
Unfortunately, it's actually huge news that probably impacts a large large majority of the Jupiter broadcasting audience
So before we dig into this first story, let's bring them over so that way we can all commiserate together time appropriate greetings
my virtual hug
Okay, so I'm just I
Apologize if you happen to be one of those listeners who happens to catch a lot of the Jupiter Jupiter broadcasting shows
I hope you don't get burned out on this topic
But I feel like it's a public service announcement that we cover this on all of the shows and I know it impacts a lot
Of us right here on this show
This week last pass announced that their services were compromised your individual passwords were not compromised
But potentially the salted database has been you know
Encrypted like a hundred thousand times over has been stolen of your master password
Email reminders about when your passwords expire
Which kind of is sort of an important bit of information for an attacker to use and other bits of information
Have been revealed and last pass is advising that everyone change their master password
And if you do not have two-factor authentication, if you do not have two-factor authentication turn that s on
And now I
Have been a pretty big proponent of last pass and I I fully acknowledge that our open-source alternatives to last pass. I maintain
That the convenience of last pass if you I should back up
Security is always a compromise between convenience and practicality and and unfortunately
Having a password for every different service
Having a password for every different service I use is a very hard thing to actually pull off in practicality when I have a studio
And a house and I move around a lot and I have multiple offices and I have different computers
And I don't keep everything synced having a cloud-based service
While inherently risky
has an inherent value to it and
To me last pass sort of walks that sweet spot where I have local encryption. It's available on my Android device
It's available on an iOS device. It's available in my browser. It's available on the web
So I have advocated for last pass a lot and I've even done specials on last pass
And I wonder now and I want to bring this so I want to I want to turn this over to the mumble room
When you hear about something like this, do you think all right? This is it. This is another proprietary service
I can never use I can only use an open-source solution
I'll start I'll start with Popey because I I know Popey's here. I just talked to him Popey
Does this to you? Is this is last pass dead to you?
Are you gonna switch to key paths forever or does this reinforce your belief? Oh
So the frustration for me is the reason I switched to last pass was when Gorka was hacked four years ago
And I and I realized that I reuse the same password in a bunch of places. You know, that's my story too, right?
You know, that's my story
Exactly it. Yeah, so I switched the last pass and I thought yeah
this is the least worst option for me that enables me to have the convenience of having my password filled in when I need to and
my
feeling of security that the
Security file the password file is in unencrypted on my local machine and it re-encrypted on my local machine with my master password
Which is really long and I never use anywhere else. It's like I learned my lesson. I'm using that one password. So
Part of me thinks, you know
This is a problem and I should jump ship and go and use something open-source and only store on my own computer
But then who am I kidding?
I'm already using like Gmail and Facebook and Twitter and I'm already using other people's computers. This is just yet another thing and
I checked with our
internal is people and because we
We canonical use it as well. So, you know, I actually have two accounts. I have my personal account
I work out there and I check with them and their opinion was not that you know, everyone should you know
Nuke the world and go some good do something else. So I trust them. So I stick with it
I set up two-factor authentication there. Yes, right and and and can I add something to that and and this is of course
hindsight, right etc, etc
but I would say
This is here's the lesson. I have learned going forward from this last pass breach. I
Will no longer wait for a notification on a blog from the company telling me I should change my password
I'm going to set a reminder in my calendar to just change my master password from time to time
And I recommend to you do not wait
Do not wait for them to get hacked
Turn on two-factor authentication now change your master password every three months. Why not? I mean really is it that actually?
When I when I went to the dialogue to change my master password, it said your master password was last changed
1502 days ago
I'm not gonna lie
Bopey I won't lie. I actually have a little sentimental attachment to my master password because it is a paragraph
I came up with a long time ago like before I really truly understood computer security
I thought to myself well geez a paragraph seems like a much better idea than a six center six six
character six character password
And I can remember a paragraph and so I wrote a little paragraph in my mind that I have been able to recite for
the last 15 years and
I I have zero zero zero worries that anybody will ever guess what it is because there's a completely nonsensical paragraph
It doesn't make any sense and I came up with it, and I love it, and I'm I'm going to go change it
Um I know that sounds weird, but I'm attached to it. Yeah
Full stop on the end. You really only have to change it by one character
So you can add buffers to the beginning and end and there you go one two three
So of course
You know keeping our audience in mind
This sort of provokes thoughts of switching the key pass, and I found a thread on hacker news
Oh, did I oh did I grab it let me see oh?
I might not have actually grabbed it for the show notes
As you would expect though the focus has changed now to key pass well now that last pass is no good
And then let's be clear. Let's be totally 100% legit honest
Last pass is a big old target it has
It is really at the target of all targets. It's everybody's password
That's I mean even if you could never crack it like
just the idea of that makes it a target and and by by by
Participating in the last pass service you are participating in what is got to be one of the largest targets on the internet
So you have to have some faith in encryption and the general technology there and and so I don't think it's unreasonable to say
I'm not doing that
That the concept of just how big of a target they are is too much risk for me to assume
I'm not doing that and if and I'm gonna go with key pass, and I don't think that's unreasonable
But I think it is unreasonable to say
Key pass is flawless now. We all respect key pass. We all are thankful
They're making an offline solution. They're making something that actually has a very awesome Firefox
Plugin they're making something that has awesome Android apps they really are making one of the best open source apps in the world
But like all open source applications that can't be flawless because they're created by humans
And there could be a flaw in key pass as well
And so the there is a lesson to be learned globally here for all of us
And I I do not think it is Linux specific
But I think it is super important when so many of our credentials so many things online
I
I can get so easily on a soapbox about this
But whatever the case may be just I would recommend everybody change these master passwords often
Try to keep this try to try to make this the thing that you are actually diligent about
Because going forward these things have a way of getting away from you
So try to make this the thing if you maybe you're lax on backups
Maybe you're lax up on commenting your config file
I don't know what it is, but but of all of the things I plead with you make this the thing that you are diligent about
Because it good password hygiene can is just it's just a little bit of work up front to prevent so much chaos later on
And I'm gonna end with this hashtag watch text now boom. That's all I have to say
I'm an end of topic mumble room anybody have anything. I want to throw them before I finish
Yeah, I would like to defend
Last pass in this incident because they actually did act
Responsible and they did act in a timely manner to let their their users know that their data could be compromised
And they give them the tools to lock it down and secure it
Yeah, I mean and the value of this is negative. Here's the thing how many lessons do we need to learn?
How many times do we need to be taught?
That we should be that we should have used the open source
Publicly audits audited solution. I do not want to stand here and say put trust trust last pass trust everything with a proprietary solution
Because I mean time after time after time. It feels like
We sit here and we can mock what RMS says but then like three or four or five or six or seven or twenty years
Later turns out dude was right dude was right
The problem is only the really tech savvy people are the ones who are
going to be the ones that are diligent enough to do this right where everybody else is
You know not and yeah, like I'm gonna come was pointing out something earlier this morning
Open-source is great and all and it could be audited
We don't know the last type
Stuff has been audited or bugs have been found and you know, there are people that don't report bugs
So, you know
It's still something that boils down to the most responsible tech savvy people are gonna be the ones that are gonna be ahead of this
There is currently a bug floating around the hacker news a kind of a flaw in the dotnet version of key pass and
It could potentially expose users
now
This audience that doesn't affect you you're using the Linux version
But don't put key pass on some sort of pedestal like the chat room is doing right now
There is today a flaw in key pass and like WW NSX just said in the chat room
There are people that are motivated to exploit these things and I I completely agree
Like I see here and I think just remember it really comes down to your personal responsibility
It is it falls on you. Don't put don't put your faith in an open source project
Don't put your faith in a proprietary project. That's kind of what you're saying, right WW
Yeah, you know you're you're ultimately going to be responsible for your own security. Yes exactly
Yes, Sunsell do you want to expand on that?
Oh
I mean just basically what the video was saying that it really is the user responsible of one's ability about their passwords
You know keeping care of what they do with their passwords and how they manage them because no matter what solution you use
Open-source or proprietary now no matter what or less that you use to manage this stuff. It's still on you
It could be the greatest solution ever and you're not managing your stuff very well. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, I agree and Sean PC says that it's made by humans
Right and thus it likely will have flaws wizard. Do you want to add in something here?
Yeah, I just the the one thing that I can you know, I don't want to sound like that
You know part of the mob saying oh, yes, which keep ass but no go ahead there is
Yeah, but there is there is kind of the it is a lot easier to protect key pass than last pass itself
Because at the end of the day, it's like we follow the things we've been falling for
You know as long as we have, you know, you know sandbox applications and you know, make sure you have your firewall
Then you know on because it does use localhost to go and communicate
If you had cover the basics, you should be okay with key pass
It's when you start going outside that it's when you start and you start just kind of giving up on security everywhere
That's when you screw up. Well and wizard I will say to this
Couldn't you make the same argument for Dropbox versus think thing
Think thing is peer-to-peer. It's machine to machine. You don't have to worry about them indexing your files
Submitting the list of your files to the RIAA for DMCA takedown, right? It is machine to machine
There is an inherent advantage to just using key pass in that you are one person
And you have realistically you are not very interesting to the global hacker community
Whereas last pass is a global target
Now all that said, I am not responsible enough. I am not judicious enough
I should rephrase this
I care more about my children than I care about good password hygiene
I care more about my children than I care about updating the patches on my home server
I would rather have sex with my wife than manage my passwords
I would rather have a really good rib dinner
I would rather barbecue something that is delicious than manage my passwords
That's my personal choice. I recognize that is not necessarily your choice, the listener
But because that is my list of priorities, because those things become before password hygiene
If I am being completely honest with my audience, those things are more important to me than password hygiene
So for me, last pass is a really great solution because it manages to straddle that sweet spot
Between automation and holding my hand, but yet local encryption, transparency
And empowering me to make the decisions I need to choose if I continue to use the service
And because they check those boxes, I continue to use the service
Because I have to fundamentally believe that it is more important and it is better that I use last pass
With two factor authentication and a great master password
Than it is to potentially botch some local password management solution
So that's where I live. And Rekai comes in, not to mention he says
Why is it safer for me as an unexperienced person, good point
To maintain my own security and hope I do well and trust the people to do this for a full time job
So he is saying, this isn't my job, this is not what I do for a living
But this is what last pass does for a living
Even if they are a target, they know what they are doing while I don't
And Rekai is a very smart person
Like if Rekai wanted to put his mind to it, he could create the most ultimate password storage solution
But that is not what he would want, that is not what he chooses to dedicate his time to
And I cannot judge him for that, so he continues to use last pass, as I will
Just as I will not judge you for using key pass or a text file on some Lux encrypted volume
Have at it. I say it works for you? Good for it
I wanted to cover something really quick before we move into a couple of more things
This is the week that we cannot move forward without mentioning
Guard your wallets, it's the Steam sales
I have spent some money this week but not actually that much
And Linux underscore gaming on Reddit has had a daily update on some of the best sales
There is a lot of different dynamics to this, so if you are following Tech Talk today you are already hip to all this stuff
But if you have been kind of on the fence about trying out gaming under Linux
Maybe you don't have a great video set up, maybe you are not using the proprietary driver
And you are not sure how well games would work with the free driver
This is a great time to create a Steam account and show Valve that they are not wasting their money
Go in there, go get some of these games for ridiculous discounts
Go show these developers that there are Linux users out there
If you have kind of been motivated to show support for the Linux desktop that are not a big gamer
This is a great time to do that
I'm just putting that out there, I'm going to have a link in the show notes, it's the roundup of the best sales
When the sales are happening, it's a thread on Linux gaming
Right now this one is created by Spinner Will
I'm sure Linux Gamecast will have better coverage on this than I can
But they have when the deals end, how much the discount is
They have it in USD, Euros, Canadian funny money, Australian monies and all the other monies too
And I'm mentioning this because if I don't mention it I'll get a hard time
And also, I know some of you are like me
Where sometimes you might buy a product just to show the vendor you appreciate them supporting Linux
And maybe later on you'll enjoy it
This is what the Steam sale is all about
I also, like Waltiff in the chat room, he says I've been waiting for some of these games
I bought the ones that are 50% off
I've had a whole bunch in my wishlist for a long time and now I'm going through and collecting them
So I might give away some games on the live stream for this Sunday's Linux Action Show
Tune in live on Sunday and I might give away a few games
Because I've been buying a few on sale that I've wanted for a while
And I might not even play them
But one was like a four pack of a game that was normally $40
And I got a four pack for $6.99
What's up? What you got?
So check it out, we have a link to that in the show notes
But that's all I have to say on that
That concludes
That concludes the Valve update
Right there
Now I wanted to mention something real nice for Mr. Dominic
Coda Radio is...
Man, what did we just talk about this week?
Oh, snaps
In fact, I'll save what we talked about
But it relates to something we're going to cover a little bit in this show
Coda Radio has been going on for a while now
And Michael Dominic, he's an independent software developer
And he originally launched with a focus on Mac OS and iOS
Pretty understandable, really
For somebody who wants to make money
And he has sort of gone through a transition
To pivot and focus on open source and Linux
And he's launched a new company around that
And I just wanted to kind of support that initiative
Because he's one of our friends
He's the co-host of Coda Radio
And so if you're out there and you need somebody who focuses on things like
Docker, or AngularJS, or Ruby on Rails, or PHP, or Android development
And he can still do iOS development, obviously, as well
Or HTML5 stuff
Native mobile development
Buccaneer Tech is his new company
And for JB listeners
I think if you go over there, he's going to give you a free consultation on your project or your business needs
So if you've got like a small business that maybe needs an app
Or a website
And you'd like to give it to somebody who's trying to support Linux and open source
And one of the Jupyter broadcasting communities
You can email him and mention in there
Like say, offer code Sparrow or put that in the subject line
Put Sparrow in the subject line, something like that
And he's going to give you like a free consultation
And I just wanted to mention this
This Buccaneer Tech is his new company
And I really wanted to support one of our co-hosts going out and saying
You know what?
I know the big industry trend is iOS and Android
And it's all Apple development right now
And Windows 10 apps or whatever the hell they're going to do
I mean, yeah
I can totally understand why that would be the trend
But instead he's saying
You know what I'm going to do is I'm going to try to carve out a niche
Right here in Linux and open source
I'm going to try to do this
And so BuccaneerTech.com
Go check that out
And use the promo code Sparrow if you want to email him
Just, I don't know
Go over there and do sales at BuccaneerTech.com
And send him an email and say
Hey, we want to talk to you guys
I just want to give him a mention because
You know, he's a friend of our show
And we just got back from Self
And there's so many independent developers out there right now
That are doing the small businesses marketing
And just one of the things I talked about in Coda Radio
That I was hinting at is
I recently attended some small business meetings
One in our local town where the studio is
It's Arlington
And another town that's about 15-20 minutes north of me
Burlington
And I went to both these towns
And I attended some local business referral meetings
Business groups
Where you can go to see if you want to become a member
If you're a small business owner
And you want to become a member of the small business community
That's not why I went
I specifically went with the intention of trying to get show content out of it
And I wanted to get a feel for like
What kind of proprietary solutions are they using?
Who's developing their websites and their applications?
And I just wanted to get a feel for like super local businesses
How are they getting technology solutions?
And for the most part
You know, a lot of it was Linux based
Wordpress based
And things like that
And I was pretty stoked by that
However
The second meeting I went to
They had a guy from Microsoft show up
And he did a presentation on why Windows 10 is going to be great for their business
I couldn't even
I had to laugh
Like the guy shows up and we're at a restaurant
So they're having this business meeting at a restaurant
And because this is something they do on a weekly basis
There's like six things you can order
So I get like this
Pecan crusted chicken salad
And I've ordered this pecan crusted chicken salad
And I see on the agenda
Windows 10 for your business
Okay, I'm already like
I'm thinking to myself
Chris, you have a couple of options here
You can just sit here and listen to what this guy has to say
Or you can stand up
And go into show mode
And give a Linux pitch
And I didn't know which way I was going to go
Like literally I sat there and I thought
I kind of got a little nervous
Like I didn't have much of an appetite
I kind of ate like the pecan crusted off my chicken
But I'm like I cannot sit here
And listen to this guy tell these people
How Windows 10 is going to help their business when it's not even released yet
Like at a moral
At my moral core
I cannot sit here and listen to this man
Tell these people how this proprietary product
Which is not even on the market yet
Is going to help them
And I sat there and I ate my pecan crusted chicken
I just ate the edging of it
And the guy didn't show up
He no-showed
He totally no-showed
And I thought to myself wow, well I was right
So I sat up and I did a little 30 second commercial
When he didn't show up
And I gave the pitch
For podcasts in general
And I advised them to go find a podcast
About your passion
And I said if you're a small business
And there's about 15 people here
That are all like the owners or CEOs
Or whatever and I said if you have a problem
Today, if you have a need today
There's probably already
A solution out there that somebody else has created
For you and I just, I ask you, just do
This one, I only had 30 seconds, I only had
30 seconds you guys, I said do this
Google it
Google the solution
Before you pay for something there may be a free
And open source package that can do it for you
And that's all I could say
And that's all I could get in
And that was one of the two meetings I went to
And the second meeting
I was like I was all fired up and now I don't know if I'm going to go to another one
I'm not sure yet, but Kits and Kitty you wanted to jump in here
Go ahead
Microsoft has always
Promised the next
Product will be good
Anybody remember Object FS?
Right, yes this is the thing
I started to feel like a bit of an anxiety
Attack because I'm like this guy cannot
Come up here and promise these people the world
Again and again and again like somebody has
To say something
That was like
That was a serious intense
Situation and I wanted to enjoy my salad
But you know
It worked out, it worked out and I got
A good plug in for open source and Linux and for
Podcasts in general, so hopefully
I think I might well I might
I'm finding good insights when I attend these business
So this is the second one I have attended now
And at first I was like I'm not going to do
This crap, I'm not going to waste my time doing this crap
This is stupid, I have better things to do
But then listening to
Them talk about some of their problems and listening to some of the
Things they wanted, how technology can fit in
Like a lot of these
Meetings have been based about the technology solutions
They're going to use to solve their problems
So I may attend another one just to kind of get
Some more insights there
Alright well I want to talk to Popey about
The conference that he attended this week, well
Actually before I
Before I get too far into that, this is really
This is the part where we're going to transition to some great stuff
For the show, and I want to thank
First of all, I want to start, let's start with the community
Let's start with Linux Academy
They're from the community, they've created something for the community
They're truly Linux enthusiasts
And this is, you know, if you go back
You look at what, Linux Action Show, it's been around
Now for nine years, which is ridiculous
But it's been around now for nine years
But if you go back seven, eight
Years ago
It's rough
It's not so good
But the passion and the enthusiasm
What we wanted to accomplish
What we cared about, the enthusiasm
About that, right, like how
How much we wanted to share with you
That was the spark
And now looking back at Linux Academy I think
Boy, maybe I should have gone this route
See they had that same spark, they had that same passion
But they went a different route
They took the people
That were truly passionate about
Open source, Linux
All of the technology around that
They met up
With developers
And educators
And they were able to create something
Really unique, just for the Linux
Audience
There's other educational sites out there
That'll teach you everything, I mean really
They promise everything
From how to build a rocket
To how to
How to edit something in Adobe After Effects
I mean they really, they promise everything
Not Linux Academy
They don't promise
They promise everything
They promise
To focus on Linux and the best technologies
Around Linux
They promise to focus on the things
That'll make you more employable
To make you better at your job
To scratch your educational itch
To challenge your mind
That's what they focus on, that's Linux Academy
They have self paced courses
You can go in there and see how much time is available
How long it's going to take, and you can tell
Linux Academy, I've got this much time available
On a Monday, I've got this much time available
On a Wednesday, you want to base your
Educational courses around when we're not live
You can do that
Linux Academy has self
Setting educational plans, they'll fill
In the gaps with reminders and all of that
They have scenario based labs so that way you
Work with this technology in the real
World, you get a sense of how to configure
These things, so when you go out there and do it in production
It's not the first time you've done that
And that little bit of confidence
Makes
All of the difference
As somebody who's been in the industry for a long
Time
When you walk into a place with confidence
When you sit down at a job with confidence
Everybody around you
Is reassured, everybody around
You feels a little bit more comfortable
Because you're confident
That's what scenario based labs do
I want you to go to Linux Academy
Right now, I want you to check them out right now
I want you to go to linuxacademy.com
Slash unplug to get a 33%
Discount, a 33% discount
That's not a number that was just picked arbitrarily
Linuxacademy.com
Slash unplug, they have instructor help
Available and I know you're busy
I appreciate you just
Listening to this podcast
So I want
You to use your time wisely
And Linux Academy does too
That's why they've rolled out nuggets
It's a cute name for an awesome
Feature, a nugget is
A single how to that walks you through a specific
Task
That make you better at that specific task
It doesn't necessarily belong in a big course
Or some big hourly multi
Hour courseware, it's a lesson
Between 2 and 60 minutes
That teaches one specific thing
And you can actually, look at this
Go to linuxacademy.com
Slash nuggets right now
Create an AWS EBS snapshot
Bash script backup, right there, you need to backup
An AWS machine, I don't have any
Freaking idea how I would do that
I tell you what, if I was
Put in the position of being responsible for an
AWS instance, and I
Didn't know how to back it up
That might give me some anxiety
That might make me
A little stressed out
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
That's the first nugget
Right there, and they got a bunch of other great ones
Cloning a virtual box VM
Building an IP tables firewall
Creating a pixi boot server, what
The hell is active directory
How do I have single sign on with linux boxes
And windows boxes, these are individual
Nugget courses, linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged, go check out linuxacademy
Linuxacademy is freaking awesome
You guys
Seriously, I wish I had a
Resource like this when I was in the business, linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged, and a big thank you
To linuxacademy for sponsoring
The unplugged program, you guys
Keep it up, and keep building that platform out even
More and more, alright so
Kitson are you hearing me okay, or is the
Mumble room dropping us out, what's going on over there guys
We've had Comcast issues all day
Seems good to me
Alright, good
For a second there during your pitch
It just dropped you
And the lips
Weren't red, they were just gray
Well good, well then just go to linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged and you got it all, alright
So Mr. Popey is here today
And he, hello
Hello Popey, hello, boy
And Corky, I know Corky
Couldn't join us today, but he was here earlier this morning
On linux, or I'm sorry, tech talk today
And he talked a little bit about OpenTech
2015, but Popey
I couldn't attend it, I wish I could've
Attended it, and it sounds like it was a pretty
Fun event, it's been going on for a while
Could you recap with the folks that are listening
What OpenTech 2015 was, and
Anything you want to add in there? Sure
So it's an event that happens
Regularly, irregularly
It's happened six, seven times over the last
Ten years, and
It's a low cost
Tech event, which
Focuses on what you might
Call OpenTech
Which covers quite a lot of ground
Actually, there was quite a lot of
Different talks that covered
Vaguely related
Topics, but there were also some a little bit
Out there ones as well, I tried
To push myself to go to
Talks that were outside
My comfort zone, so rather than go to a talk
About Edward Snowden or
Something that I kind of know about, I might
Go to something else a little bit more weird
And there were three tracks
So three separate rooms
And they were full all day with
Various talks, and
Yeah, it was good fun, and it was
Nice to see some familiar faces there from the
Tech crowd
In the UK, I've
Made some notes about a few of the more interesting
Talks, if you want me to go for a few of them
Yeah, I do, I guess I'll start with
Kind of a basic question, so it doesn't necessarily sound
Like it's a Linux
Event per se, but more of a
Technology event
Anything that's open in technology
Is that right? Right
So people were talking about
Getting access to
Your medical data
For example, or preventing
Someone else having access to your medical data
Or they were talking about security topics
Or privacy topics
Those kind of things that are
Open data, getting access to data
From the government, and using data that's been
Provided by the government, so those kind of
Topics, it wasn't so much open source
In fact, it was encouraged
For you not to have your laptop out at all
And I didn't see many
Laptops there at all, because
You know, at some of the conferences, if you
Go into a room where a talk is being given, you can see
A bunch of people sat around with their heads
Down on their laptops tweeting about what's going
On, or you know, chatting with friends
Not actually paying attention to what's going on
And here it was very different, people were very
Engaged and discussing topics
With the presenter, and
Not focused on whatever's going on
On their laptop. Interesting, very interesting
Now, I
Hope I gotta
Ask you, just sort of, if you could just
Remove all filters
Pretend like you're recording a podcast
For the UK audience
Is there a
Is there a sort of
Sense of
I'm trying to frame this correctly
What is the feeling of
Is there a feeling that the American government is overreaching
Is there a feeling that let's talk about how to protect
Ourselves from the NSA at a conference
Like this?
Well, that kind of topic
Kind of did come up in specific talks
But it wasn't the main focus
Of conversation, there were
Talks about
Privacy on the internet, and
You know, Snowden
But actually there was more about the European government
And the UK government doing
Religious things than the US
Because we're doing just stupid things over here
As the US
You know, three letter
Organizations are as well
It's just as daft here, unfortunately
Yeah, interesting
But how many people would you say attend this thing?
It's a good few hundred
I don't know, it's not like massive
Event, it's just
It's not like massive event
It's held in a university
In London, and it's got a low
Barrier to entry as well, it's only five
Pound to get in, which is what, seven
Eight dollars, something like that
And it's
In the middle of London, so it's really easy to get to
It's at a university
So there's plenty of facilities nearby to get
Food and drink at lunchtime and that kind of stuff
So yeah, it was
Really enjoyable
Now, I would love to hear some of your notes about the event itself
So, a couple
That stood out for me, one was
To give you an idea of the diversity
Of the topics
That were covered, there was one talk
That was called
Objects of Intrigue
And it was by a woman called
Rachel Mote, she's on
She's on Twitter as atrachelmote, and she
Volunteers at a school
For children, specializes in help
For children with special needs, and some of these
Children have difficulty doing things
Like even feeding themselves
Or they have
Reluctance to
Touch certain surfaces
Or
Textures
There are certain things
That they just have difficulty with
And what she wanted to do was
Help children with their eating
And
She had out on the stage, she had
Three bowls, one of them contained custard
One contained water, and one
Contained spaghetti, and
She's constructed with an
Arduino, and a little
Speaker, and some
Various other components, she's constructed a little
Setup that encourages
The children to touch these bowls
Of food and
Liquid, and they
The way she does it is there's a
Touch sensor underneath the
Bowl, and when the kids put their hand in the bowl
And like touch the custard, or touch
The water, it plays music, or plays a
Drum sound or something, so they can actually make
Music just by putting their hands in
These bowls of water, and that might not sound
Like a major achievement or a particularly
Technically advanced thing, but getting these
Kids to touch stuff like custard
Or spaghetti
Or something that they wouldn't normally touch
And then when they take their hands out
Putting their hands in their mouth and actually eating the
Food afterwards is quite an
Achievement for a child with special
Needs, so that
Gives you an example of how someone's using
Technology like an Arduino
And simple circuitry
In order to
Help someone else, and
I think she's made the designs and the
Details available online, so
It was a really nice
Different talk that wasn't just
Privacy and tech
And nerding out
Completely, but there were some
Nerdy ones, one of them
That I found particularly fun
Was there's a hack space in London
LHS, London Hack Space
And they've got a caravan
Which they've converted
Into a spaceship
And it's
Completely awesome
If you imagine being inside a really
Really tiny
Star Trek Enterprise
Bridge, I love it
It's excellent
They've got loads of controls, switches
And buttons and dials and wires
Dangling and stuff, and
Everyone's got their own screen and
Their own readout, and then there's a main screen
As well, and there's a comms link
And an engineers station and a weapons station
All of that, it's
Just brilliant, and they wrote their
Own game in
Unity 3D, which runs on a
PC out the back, and people are
Invited to come in and play the
Game, and it's a multiplayer game, and you're all
Sat inside the
Caravan, each taking on the role
Of a different member of the crew
And the people
Who own the caravan throw certain
Scenarios at you, and you have to do things like
Press certain buttons at a certain time, or a certain sequence
Of buttons, like you would on a real
Spaceship, but also you have to do things like
There are cables that become
Disconnected, and you have to figure out which cables go
Where, and you have to get up from your seat and actually
Do manual stuff like you would see on
Star Trek, it's pretty impressive
And they've got a website for it, if you go to
I think it's LHS
LHS
LHSbikeshed.com
You'll find pictures of this caravan that they take
To events, and invite people
To come in and fly the missions
This is so cool!
It is, it is really cool
That's one of the nerdier things
It's really good fun
So, one of the other ones
That I found particularly interesting
A woman called
Kat Matfield, I think it was
She works as a consultant
Developing applications
And they do privacy related
Applications, and
She gave us some tidbits of information that
Feedback they've got from user testing
Of privacy based products
And some of the notes I took
That kind of surprised me a little bit
The
Perception of privacy among normal
People, like, not you and me, but like
Normals out there, right?
Is a little bit strange
People focus on passwords
And people, they think that
The password is the most important thing
That I have to have a safe password
And that they think that
Bad people target
Specific individuals, they don't realize
That fraudsters can just go out and buy
A list of credit card details
And they're arbitrary, they don't care
Who those credit card details come from
People seem to think that
I am a target, that I am
The individual that they're going to come after
When in fact they just like
Reap thousands of credit cards
And take money from all of them
Wherever possible
One of the interesting things
That came out of their user testing
Was that adding
A Facebook button, like for
Facebook login to a product or a
Service, actually makes people
More uncomfortable, having
That button there, when you're logging into
Any kind of service, if there's a Facebook button on
The screen, people in their user testing didn't
Like it, because they felt that it associated
That product and service with their personal
Data, and that their
Brother or sister or friend or parent
Might see what
They're doing on that website, because
Of the Facebook button, and that made them
Feel very uneasy, and that kind of surprised me, I thought
People loved the Facebook button, I thought they thought
Well that's an easy way for me to log in and I don't have
To worry about it, but it turns out
Exactly, and I don't have to
Remember yet another password, so it surprised
Me that people, normal people, not just
You and me, but normals, don't like that
Facebook button, and
The funny thing that came out of this was
People focus on
The little padlock, they see that as
A way of ensuring
That the page is safe
And so, in their user testing
They started adding padlocks to
The page, and they kept
Adding more and more padlocks all over the place
To the page, and
As they added
Padlocks, people felt the page was
More and more safe, and
They never managed to get to
What they called peak page
Padlock, and peak page
Padlock, peak page padlock would be
The maximum number of padlocks you
Could possibly have on a page, and they never got to that
Point, they could throw as many padlocks as they wanted
On the page, and people would just
Accept that that was more secure, because
There were more padlocks on there, it was brilliant
And it's all security theatre
But it was great to
Hear those kind of user experience testing
Results, it was great
It was a good conference, I would certainly go again
Wow, and so, do you know at this point
Will there be another one next year?
I don't know actually
That was my first one, I've not been to it before
You know, based on
My experience, and the people
That I was chatting to afterwards in the bar
They all enjoyed it, and would certainly
Go again, so
Did you get a chance to say hi to any Jupiter
And the meetup page was so new when you guys
Launched this, did anybody actually make it there?
Yeah, there was a couple of people
Who made it along, I was just standing
There, and we didn't actually have
A specific place to meet up
Or anything, it was just
That's the thing we gotta do next time, right? You gotta have specific
Details, but if you don't know the venue
It's hard to do that
Right, well the good thing is, people just walked up to me and went
Hello baby, and they recognised me
And so
You know, we
Had a chat, and then later on afterwards in the bar
There were a couple of guys there from the
Linux Luddites podcast
We sat and had a chat with them in the bar
And then we made our way to a pub
Which is the traditional
British way to end a conference, is to go to a pub
Afterwards, had a few beers
And chatted about all kinds of stuff, including
Jupiter broadcasting
And all kinds of other podcasts and stuff
All good things I'm sure, all good things I'm sure
Yeah, it was good fun, it was really really good fun
You know what's funny is, when we go to some of these
Events, people walk
Up to the booth, or they'll walk up to us and they
Just kind of stand around for a bit, and maybe you've
Noticed this, they stand around
For a bit, and they wait for us to talk
And then they're like, oh
You're Noah, you're Chris
And they recognise the voices
After we've talked for a bit, and then they introduce themselves
Did that happen to you at all?
No, they just walked straight up to me
And said hello, so they clearly recognised me
You know what that means is, your mug
Your mug chasing that chicken is all over the internet
That's what that means
Yeah, that's true, but it was really lovely
Because everyone's, you know, a typical British event
Like, everyone's really understated and
Really pleasant and friendly, and it was good
It was really really good
Good, boy, I tell you what, if I was
Somehow able to make it next year, that would
Boy, that would be amazing, that would be the highlight
If I was in a position to be able to make it next year
We are
I mean, these events are so awesome
I would love to have audio from these kinds of things
I mean, Poppy, don't you think this is one of the best things
About our community?
Yeah, and I kind of
I did take a handheld voice recorder
With me, and I was tempted to do
Some interviews and record some
Stuff, but actually
I was on my own dime
And I thought, you know what, I'm just going to
Focus on the talks, and
Absorb this stuff, and especially
As I wanted to go to the ones that were
Out of my comfort zone, there was one
I'll give you one last talk that I went to
Towards the end of the day, and
It was called Science as Art
And it was a
Woman called Leah
And a guy called James, who are
Very artistic
And they've been
Trying to use open data
That's been made available by
Governments and NGOs and other organizations
And try and
Represent that in different ways, rather than just have
Graphs, and they actually made
Some music out of
Open data, it's quite hard
To explain, but they've got
Information about the rise
In CO2 gases
In the atmosphere, and they map that to music
Yes, they map that to one
Instrument, and then they took something else
Like the number of earthquakes
Or floods in Pakistan
For example, and then mapped that
To the drums, and so they play a
Little snippet of each of these, and then they
Mashed it all together into
A piece of music
And actually it was really
Thought provoking, because
You knew that that big drum sound
Was an earthquake 15
Years ago, and then another one, and then two
In quick succession when there were two more earthquakes
Or something, it was really, really nicely done, and they're
Looking for more sources of data
And how they can
Map that into music or
Theater
Or anything, it's a nice way to represent data
That might be a bit dry
Otherwise, so that
Also I found particularly interesting
Boy, no kidding, I bet that was actually
Kind of powerful, to see, to
Represent data through music
This sounds corny
Because you're going to laugh at me
There were some skeptical people in the room
There were, in a vertical, real scientists
But it's pretty powerful, isn't it? It is in a way
It's kind of, it's a different way to
Visualize it, but
Yeah, it sounds funny to say visualize, but you know
What I mean, yeah, and
Yeah, that's great, well thank you Popey
Thank you so much, and thank you honestly
Thank you very much for helping
Being willing to take on the Meetup page
So we had an event, meetup.com
Broadcasting if you were going to make it
And Popey was
More than willing to be an event organizer
And if you want to go to the next one
Popey, you know, let's do it again
Let's just, any events like that in the
Area, because it's an area that
You know, we just don't have a lot of oversight
On, and so I really
Appreciate you kind of filling me in on that
Because we have 30% of our
Audiences over there, and so
Like, I feel like I
I know, we're really packed in on this tiny bit
You guys are
You probably all know each other
I assume
Oh yeah, yeah, totally
So meetup.com plus Jupiter broadcasting you for future
Events, I don't know, one of the next
Live events we might do
I would really
Really, really love to do
Linux Unplugged on location sometime
Why?
Not because it makes the show better
Necessarily
Why? Because I
Wanted to do it before I ever launched the show
So, a couple of weeks ago
Two weeks ago on the Linux Action Show
We said if we got to 530 patrons
I would go out to Noah's house
And I would go
And I would tour Noah's automated house
I would put on his freaking
Google Glass, even if it stings
A little bit, and I would walk around his house and get a tour
And
If I find Windows
I will tell you about it
Like, I will tell you about it
And I will search out Windows
In Noah's house, and we got to 530
In fact, we're at 538 right now
Which is awesome
I'm really excited about that
So we might do Linux, I don't know how the timing will work out
We might, oh god, wouldn't it be cool if we could do Unplugged 100
From Noah's house
I'm really looking forward to this
Because one of the things I want to do, I mean, we're going out to Noah's house
As a way to sort of just celebrate a milestone
But long term
I really
Want to do more of these event coverages
I really, really, really think this is an area
That if Linux Unplugged and
Linux Action Show focused on, and by the way
Just wait
Because we're about to get into
One of the discussions that Noah
Had at Self
And I think you guys are going to meet
Somebody you're probably just going to start following now
Somebody who's a thought maker in Linux and
Open Source that you've probably never even heard of
And after today's episode you're probably going to follow them on a daily
Basis
Going out and meeting these people and talking to these people
And if you haven't heard Poby's description, it's awesome
And it's what's the best thing about our community
And so, yeah
We got to 530 people
And now 538, which is cool
Yeah, I'm going
To Noah's house as a way to celebrate
And yeah, I'm going to do Linux Action Show from Noah's house
And it's, in a way, it's a way for me to say
Thank you to Noah because he comes out here all the time
But what it's really about
Is it's investing
In the content that I think
I'm almost so positive
That if we could expose more of this
In a better way than we do it now
Like the event coverage we do now
Is like 10% of what I want to bring you
Because what I want to bring you
Is, I want to
Make it like you're there
And I want you to experience why when we go to these events
We come back so supercharged
About Open Source, about the community
About Linux
I want you to experience that
And that's why I'm excited about 530 people
Not because I'm going to Noah's house
Or I'm going to do a segment or the entire show from a boat
That's awesome
That's not why I'm excited
I'm excited because after we do that
We're starting to
Kind of move into the next phase
We're moving to the next step
We're going to the next area for Jupyter Broadcasting
Where pretty soon
Let's be real
What's it going to take to make it possible for me to go to Self
And for me to go to things like Open Tech
And for me to go to things like BSD Can
What's it going to take? It's going to take somebody right here in the studio
It's going to take somebody sitting here at the spot
That I'm sitting at switching
It's going to take somebody vamping
It's going to take somebody that can mix in remote locations
It's going to take a producer in studio
That's where I'm going with this
I know it's crazy ambitious
But I want to be able to raise the funds
To afford a full time person in studio
And I'm willing to start part time
A couple times a week, whatever I can do
But where I eventually want to go is I want to have a full time person in studio
And I don't want to pay for it with sponsors
I'm willing to, because in some ways
It feels like the shortcut
Because I could get a sponsor
I could get a sponsor to sponsor just that
I've got two emails literally in my inbox right now
From two different companies that want to sponsor our shows
And I'm sitting here telling them
I'm sorry, I only want to have as few sponsors of the show as possible
Because I only want to pick the people I use
And I only want to talk about the people I think you guys would use
Right?
But holy shit is that limiting
Turns out that's a super limiting model to go with
But it's the only one I can go with
Where I can show up at this microphone and genuinely talk to you
So what I like about this
Is this is giving me some runway to start budgeting
God, you know what?
If we got to 600 I could start thinking about actually budgeting
To have a part time person
And then I could actually start traveling
And when I start thinking about it like that
I get really excited
Because then I'm responsible to the audience
I'm responsible to you
I'm not thinking
How am I going to formulate this new show
And make sure I got good spots for sponsors
How am I going to make sure this content
Is going to make enough people click
That the sponsor gets enough return on their investment
What I'm thinking about instead
When it's a Patreon inspired show
Is I'm thinking
God, what does the audience really want?
Does this show even need intro music?
It's a 10 minute, 15 minute show
Does it need intro music?
The audience doesn't need that?
What do they need?
What do they want to know about?
And when you expand that out to covering things like community events
I can't think of a better way to have
Coverage of community events
The fundamental foundation of what inspires
Our open source community
I can't think of a better way to cover that
Than something that is also funded by the community
And I'm not totally opposed to sponsorships
I tell you what, one way or another
I will make this happen
And if I go to commercial sponsors to make it happen
Because I think this is
The most important aspect of open source
Coverage that is neglected
Because nobody can do it
Because it's expensive
And it's a risk
And I will make it happen
I will make it happen one way or another
If I go to sponsors and make sure that
Every live event we go to is sponsored
I will do that
And I will find a way to walk that line for you
To make sure that it doesn't influence our coverage
I will do that for you
But it will take
It will take going that route, it will take sponsorships
It will take making sure we only go to events
That have enough coverage to make sure
That our sponsor gets a return on their
Substantial investment
And what I want to do instead is I want to cover it for you
Patreon.com slash today, yes it's a
Tech Talk Today page, yeah I get that, I know that's confusing
I understand, that was a dumb idea
But Tech Talk Today is a thank you
To 538 people
Who make
Expanding our coverage
Genuine coverage possible
That's what Tech Talk Today is
For 538 people, I do a show for 538
People, that's dumb
Nobody would do a podcast for 538
People, and if you do you should stop
You can't make any money
Doing that, unless it's this model
That's why Patreon makes a difference, Patreon.com
Slash today, it funds this show
It funds the Linux action show, it funds future
Shows you don't even know we have in development that are
Focused on open source, well you might actually
Know because it got out for a little bit
And I'm not trying to
Shame you, I'm not trying to guilt you, but what I am trying
To say is, I'm going to make
This happen one way or another, I'm going to make Jupiter
Broadcasting the company that covers these
Events properly, and if
You watch BSD now this week
You're going to see the same exact thing happening
For the BSD community
And they've got a lot more together
Right now
And I want to make sure that Jupiter Broadcasting
Is the company and the community and the Linux action
Show, Linux Unplugged is the podcast that represents
The Linux community and the open source community
And the life that they deserve, because right now
What we get is a bunch of bloggers that want
Clicks, and we get a bunch of people that want
To get people to retweet and they make crazy
Ass headlines, and if it's not that
If it's not people trying to get clicks for advertisers
It's websites that are set up by
Proprietary companies or huge companies or even
Open source companies that are huge in our industry
That are paying journalists to write pro things
About them, that's the state of open source
Journalism right now, and all of them
Are neglecting this fundamental
Aspect, the core community
Aspect, and I know I'm making a huge case
Right now, but I, throughout the rest of this
Episode, will speak for
Itself of how important covering
These events are
I am willing to go out on a ledge right now and tell you how
Important this is based on the rest of the content
Of this episode, patreon.com slash today
Please go there, help expand
Our coverage, I want to be able to go to things like
Open tag, I'm sick of standing here
In the studio, I want to go there, I want to cover these
Things, I want to bring them to you, I want to bring video
I want to bring audio, I want to bring all
Of it, I want to bring exposure to all of it
Not for me
Alright, I'm done
Alright, I'm done, I'm done, I'm done
In fact, we should probably get into some of it
I know, go ahead kids and kitty, go ahead, am I
Am I up in my soapbox too much?
No you're good
I wasn't asking you, I was asking
Kids and kitty
But alright, alright
Kids, you say you want to say something
Jump in, but what did you just leave?
No, go ahead
I'm used to push to talk, working
On the keyboard, not in the window
Sorry about that
No, no problem
What you said though, it's
That's just like most of the other internet
In terms of journalism, it is
All dominated by
Clickbait basically, and I think
That is a huge problem, and I think it's
Great that you're looking to
Alleviate that
Through an independent means
Yeah, and I mean
I know that anybody can say it
Anybody can
Make that claim, the only
Proof I have is in the content
That we produce, and
The only thing I can make
The only plea I can make is if you believe in the content we've produced
So far, and you like the direction
We're going, that's the bet I'm asking
You to take
Not necessarily for me, I don't even really
I don't really need a lot, I just need to be able to do this
On an ongoing basis, and be able to go do these
Things on an ongoing basis
I don't need a lot, I
I know, I know it sounds like a crazy plea
This, I can't write code
Right, like
I'm just too ADD, like I'm never
Gonna do, I don't even submit bugs that often
I do about, like what, a dozen bugs a year
Tops
It's not who I am
I know, I know, I know, but this is
What I do, this is what I can do
And I just
When we go to these events man, it's like
We're so close to covering them in the way
We want to cover them, but yet
I can see the huge gap, like
Like, sitting at a desk and
Talking to people, and getting great people
To stop by the desk, and talking to them
Is great, that is
Super good content, and
If I objectively observe it, it's
Exclusive content that nobody else has
And I'm very, very happy, and man
Did the team work super hard to accomplish that
It is awesome
It's not enough for me
It's not enough, I really want to show
You how awesome, I feel like you guys never get an idea
Of how awesome these things are
And that's all, and I feel like
I feel like if we knew that, I feel like
All of the bickering, and like
The religious wars
Around system D, and all of it
Would sort of melt away, I know it's crazy
It's crazy, but I just
Feel like that's my way to contribute to the community
Is to try to
Bring
Some sort of balance
To what the commercial interests
Are bringing to the dialogue
I want to bring balance to that dialogue
That is focused
And funded by the community
And that's my goal, and I know that sounds crazy
But I feel like
The reason why that's important is open source
Software is created by people for people
And I know that sounds so stupid, but
When people get all crazy
And people start making death threats and stuff
People bail on open source, they don't develop open source
Software, it creates this barrier to entry
It creates this mystique
About how hostile the Linux community is
And none of it is actually true
It is a small
Percentage of our community
It is a minority, but they get all
Of the attention because all of those jerks
Out there want to write headlines to get
Clicks, and they want karma
On Reddit, and they want retweets
And whatever the hell the
Pretend internet points is that they want
That's what motivates them
And I
I will never be motivated by those things
Go look at my Twitter feed right now
Go look at my Google Plus feed
Right now, go look at my Reddit
Submissions, I could not give a shit
About those things, I never will
I never will be motivated by those things
I am generally motivated
By these, by
I truly believe that if people could see
More about what happens at these conferences
About what Popey just shared with us
About what we're about to play for himself
If you could see more of this, you would understand
That these are real people creating amazing things
That when they go to these conferences
It is not a hostile environment
It is real people that connect and collaborate
And create and move forward
It is not like the comment threads
That you read online, and it is not
What you have been led to perceive
By the tech journalists that want you
To read their articles and click their
Headlines, and I know
That seems like it's not a big deal, but I think
If you set the tone correctly
It sets the tone for the entire community
And it creates a collaborative
Environment that trickles down, and I know I'm sounding like
Ronald Reagan right now, but I think it's the truth
It's trickle down community
Okay, I gotta shut up
Cause I could literally
Spend an entire episode talking about this
It's one of the number one things I think about
All the time, and it's a huge soapbox
That I've been on, and I apologize that I've just wasted
This much of the show, why don't we talk about something else
Let's take a minute, I'm gonna talk about Ting
I want you to go to linux.ting.com
Right now, go check them out
Listen, we wouldn't be able
We would not be able to do this without Ting
They have seriously a great product
Here, and you know how I've often
Advocated you need to vote with your wallet?
That's Ting, Ting is changing the mobile
Industry, you only pay for what you use
They take your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes and they add them up
Whatever bucket you fall into
That's what you pay, it's a flat six dollars for the line
Now
In practicality, what that means is we are
Able to give every one of our members
At self this weekend, a phone
I don't have a lot of
Money you guys, and I gave every one of our
Members at self this weekend a phone
That made production
Possible, and that's how we were able to coordinate
All of this, that's how I was able to send
Noah messages saying, hey this clip has
Five minutes left and then we need to transition to you
With an interview, you need to have that person on mic
In five minutes, I could not have done that
Without Ting, Ting is awesome
And either if you just have one phone
Or if you have more than ten devices, you're going to save
Money, because think about this
Current mobile industry practices are getting you
To pay for plans that you don't necessarily
Need, you might need four gigabytes
You might need a thousand
Minutes, you might need five hundred
Messages, you might not
Me, I don't
Okay, all of my text
Messaging happens over either Hangouts
Or Telegram, majority is Telegram
Voice calling
Happens over Hangouts or
Viber
So I'm able to have three lines
And I only pay about
Well, I think last month it was like 37
Dollars for three lines, that's an
HTC One
A Nexus
Five
And an iPhone 5
All
On one account
See Ting isn't based on your device
Ting is based on you, so if you want
To have a MiFi hotspot, if you want to have a couple
Of devices, if you're a developer
And you want to be able to test across multiple
Devices, maybe you need iOS, maybe you need
Android, maybe you need multiple Android devices
And you don't want to pay a whole bunch of
Fees every single month
Ting is perfect, linux.ting.com
You're going to get a fifty dollar credit
Off your first device, linux.ting.com
You're going to get a fifty dollar
Credit, and if you have a Ting compatible
Device, and you might, because let's
Be honest, cell phones have been around for a while, and
Ting has got coverage on GSM and CDMA
If you
Have a device, you're going to get a fifty
Dollar credit on your entire Ting
Service
Which, for me,
When I signed up, I got like a twenty five dollar credit
That fifty dollar credit is only good
Till the end of June too, so jump on that, and by the way
Ting also has an early termination relief program
To help you get out of a current contract
Get out of that duopoly!
With the Ting ETF program, you can find out more about
That, and also
If you've listened to these ads, and you've thought
Yeah, okay, that sounds too good to be true
I've been burned by mobile service providers before
Okay, that's fair
That's fair. I invite you
To check out Ting's hangout
Ting is going to have a hangout on Thursday at noon
Eastern time
Just around the TechSnap time, so
Watch this, and then join us for TechSnap
And you can ask the Ting crew
Anything you want to know
How the hell do they make money?
Are they going to be around for a long time?
Why do I only pay for what I use?
How can they have unlocked devices?
How can they afford an early termination relief program?
How do they have no hold customer service?
Are you skeptical?
Ask them! They have amazing
Answers
And I think after you watch that, you'll be impressed
In fact, they have all kinds of great tips, you can go check it on their blog
Go to linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com
Right now, get a fifty dollar credit
No contract, only pay
For what you use, no hold customer service
Boom! That is Ting
Right there in a brief
linux.ting.com, and a huge thank you to Ting for sponsoring
The Linux Unplugged Program
And check out this week's Linux Action Show for
Noah's new Bat Phone, which is
Ridiculous. Noah's got this new kind of crazy
Mobile phone that
I'm a little jelly of, to be honest with you
Now, Mumble Room, I was talking about
Open Source Journalism
And we're going to hear from somebody
Who has
Been directly involved with Open Source Journalism
Now, for quite a while
And I actually kind of rather
Enjoy this man's commentary
So, Noah sat down during self
And he had a chance to talk with Brian
And Brian is an author at
OpenSource.com
So, he's also a Red Hat employee
And so, OpenSource.com and Red Hat kind of have the
Connection there, and he had a lot of
Good commentary on the things that Noah wanted to
Chat with. And so, we
I want to play a few clips for you from Brian
So, here he sits down, he talks about how to
Tell whether Open Source is one or not
Like, there's a metric that I think we could probably all
Agree on. Is Open Source
One in this category? How do you tell?
How do you know once you can declare victory?
Well, he's got some thoughts on that
And also, knowing
Him chat about how you can add value to
Open Source software when you are
In the IT department and you want to say, hey
I want to switch off Microsoft
Office, let's switch to Libre Office
And the first answer is, how could something
Free be better? It turns
Out, there's a way to make that
Case pretty crystal clear.
I want to see you. I want to see your face.
Do you hear my mouth in your ear hole?
Hi there.
So, I'm Noah. Good to meet you.
I'm Brian. Nice to meet you.
So, tell me, Brian, what it is
That you love about Linux.
Well, I love everything about Linux, but
I love the concept of openness because I like
Collaboration.
I am a contributor
To a website called opensource.com
And I've worked for that
Open source.com team
For about five years and there
We tell stories about the ways
That open source values make
A difference in people's lives
Outside the realm of software.
So, that's what I find most intriguing about
Open source. I love the way that it can be
Adapted to different domains like
The government or your health or
Education.
Now, do you attend a lot
Of different conferences? I don't.
This is my second time itself. Oh, no kidding.
Yeah, second time itself. I was here two years ago and loved it.
I don't attend too many conferences, but
I do love this one. And I live up
In the Raleigh area, so I wanted to make sure I shot down and got here.
Now I know why you value
Openness. Because
Here's why. For those of you that don't know
Red Hat is based in Raleigh.
And Red Hat has, from my perception
From talking to other people that are from the area
And around and work for Red Hat,
Basically, everyone
That is involved
Has
Red Hat has had this influence
On the community around them to encourage
Everyone to be open. That's right.
So I had a chance to sit down with the folks from Red Hat and
Interview them. And we were talking to them
And I would give them
Opportunities to pump their own business.
I'd say, tell me what advantages
You can offer over your competitors.
And they would say, well, we're
Open source, so anything that we can
Offer, our competitors can offer.
Because we're all just teammates.
And I think that goes a long way.
Now, do you use Linux on your desktop? I do, yeah.
Okay, which distro are you using? I'm using Linux Mint.
Alright. Linux Mint XFCE.
So what would you say to people that say
When you walk around
And you see people that aren't using Linux and they say
Well, you know
I need a bash shell to get my stuff done
So I wouldn't be, I don't think I'd be able
To use Linux. I'd have to use the Mac
Because I also have to have an office suite.
Stuff like that. Yeah, well I'd say
That those two are not mutually
Exclusive. So I would say that
Out of the box, you get the software you need
To do all the things that you just described
By using the software that I would suggest
That you use. So instead of
Creating a false dichotomy between software
That has and software that has not
I would try to suggest that these people look at
Software solutions
That do everything.
And the thing is
I find that the people that
Keep telling me Linux isn't capable of doing
Things are usually getting in my way of
Making Linux do things, right?
We were told, so our company
Jupiter Broadcasting, we were told I don't know how many times
That you can't do live
Broadcast on Linux.
And everyone else in that
I don't know
It kind of looks like the answer to that question
Yeah, no, this is actually a version of
Windows. It's Windows with
Mate. Yeah, yeah, Windows
But no
For a long time, everyone
In that sphere told us, well you can't do that
You have to have a Mac, or you have to have Windows
To do it. And
We're fortunate
At least I feel fortunate
That the owner of the company has
A deep-rooted belief in using
Linux where he can. So when I came to him, I'm like
Hey, Chris, guess what? This works
It works on Linux. I mean, he wanted to see it
Work first, but as soon as I showed him
It took him, I bet, less than seven seconds
Of me flipping through the cameras and saying, look, it does it
And he goes, great, let's start the production
I mean, it was that fast.
Yep, yep, yep, I can agree
He's done the same thing with people
Fixing up old computers, plopping them in front
Of them, and with little or no
Guidance, they're able to work their
Way through the system easily
I think one of my
Favorite success stories was
My parents just bought
A new computer. They got a Mac
And I said, okay, I'll help you set it up
So I helped them set it up. And my mom
Does a lot of word processing
So she wanted iWork on her computer
And she called me a week later and was like, look
This iWork thing, I just don't get it
I just don't understand it. I was like, look, I'm going to try something
I'm going to come over and put a new
Program on your computer. It's called Libre Office
And we're going to see
What it's like. A week later
I get a text, oh my god, this is so much better
And it was
No learning curve at all. I mean, I just put
The software on her machine, and
That was it. That was the end of the story
And she figured everything from there, and I think what you're saying
Is true.
I'll share
A success story that's kind of similar. I was at a
I do a lot of IT contracting work
And we're big into the hospitality
Industry. Right. So
A lot of hotels are moving to web-based solutions
And of course, web-based solutions really lend themselves
To Linux because I don't have to worry about virus protection
Malware protection, you know, all that
Not to mention the ability to remotely
Update Linux. It's a heck of a lot easier than trying to
Remotely update Windows, right? Right, sure.
So we had installed this computer
And I had put
Libre Office on it, and the girl looks
At it, and she goes, aww. And as soon as
She did that, I knew, I thought, oh, she's
Heard of Libre Office, and usually it's a
Oh, I don't want the Microsoft Word replacement
I want actual Microsoft Word. She looks
At me, dude, and she goes
Why do you have Macsoft? What, do I have
To use the Mac version? I'm like, what do you mean the Mac version?
Yeah, I'm like, what are you talking about? She goes
Oh, the school system, they all have Macs
And they have this Libre Office, and they've switched the whole school
And I'm like, what?
What'd you just say? And I'm like
The entire school district is using Libre Office, and she's like
Yeah, and I'm like, so
Open-source software has gotten to a point now where
It gets confused for the overpriced, overinflated
Mac stuff. Yeah, that's awesome
I think that's a huge compliment to the Libre Office folks
Some people wouldn't consider it
But I think that's perfect
That is
That's what you need
You need the
How do I put this? When it becomes a non-issue
When it becomes so commonplace
You know, Clay Shirky
Has this bit in his book
Here Comes Everybody, where he talks about the common
Placeness of technologies, and he says that
He recalls
He recounts the story of his
Parents meeting for the first time
And it's a story they told him many times
How they met, and he said
It involved a car, and the one thing that was
Didn't resonate
Wasn't part of the story at all, was the car
The car was just a mundane thing that was there
And it was part of the story
But it didn't bear any remark at all
And that's sort of how
Open source software needs to function
When it becomes the default
And it becomes taken for granted, we've won
Yeah, that's right, and the nice thing about that is
Now we're vastly
Approaching a point where companies are
Starting to, they don't necessarily value
The ideals like maybe you and I would
But they value the way
That it can be cost effective to them, so the fact that
They're not locked into a proprietary
There's no vendor lock-in
And the fact that typically the cost
To implement the software or roll it out is
Low, and a lot of things is
I worked for a large organization
A very large organization, and I
Pitched LibreOffice to them, and because
I knew what they were capable of
Monetarily wise
I had recommended, I said rather than
Pay $400 for Microsoft Office
Technically we can install it for free
Make a donation to LibreOffice
And we'll install
For every copy you install, instead of paying $400, make a donation
For $200, and I knew
We're going to roll it out over X amount of computers
That's going to add up quickly
But the company, even though
It was going to cost them money, they were happy to do it
Because they didn't have vendor
Software lock-in, they had an upgrade
Path, so in their mind
They were going to pay once and upgrade forever
And so yeah, I think that brings a lot of value
Absolutely
Now I love that Chad, and
It's an interesting idea, like bringing value
To open source software by saying
Okay, we're going to use this free software
But let's donate a little
Money first, and you'll donate once
And then you can use it guilt-free going forward
I don't know if that worked for everybody
But I suggest that
As an interesting idea, if you run into
A barrier, and I've
Been there, and I don't know if this is still as common as it used to be
But if you run into
A barrier where they say, how can this be any good
It's free
Before the conversation
Ever gets to that point
If you know that's your company's inclination
Maybe suggest to them
That they start by making a contribution
Let's use this software, and we're
Going to make a contribution first
You're going to spend $200 per
User, for the rest
Of that user's
Existence, you know? Like you're not
Every three years going to spend $200
You're going to spend $200 once per user
Maybe you even do it, every new user that rolls out
You spend $200, right? It's still half
The amount
Wouldn't that fundamentally change
Open source software? Isn't that a great idea?
I was really inspired
By that
So that was Brian's take on that
Now, Brian and Noah talked about
Maybe the best way to get
Started is, you know, a lot of times
You run into this tool bias
And this is going to be a theme of their conversation
As we go forward, tool bias
Well, I know I can
Make it work under Excel
Well, I learned how to do it in
Well, I know that
I've done it before
Under, you've heard those
Excuses before, why you can't switch to Linux
And maybe
The strategy actually is
Maybe Microsoft and definitely
Apple got it right all along
Get them while they're young, maybe that's what it is
I think that's why
A lot of these, I'm reading a lot more
Initiatives about open source
And education and the way that people are not
Only taking open source principles and importing them
Into classroom settings, but what they're doing is they're trying
To change
Computer education to talk
About digital rights
And to talk about privacy rights
And to talk about openness and to talk about
The way that the tools we use define
Our capabilities in some way
That is extraordinarily important
Those initiatives are extraordinarily important because
Like you say
People who don't
People like us are reflexive about the tools we use
We care about them, other people don't, and that doesn't
It's not a criticism, it's just
It is what it is
To have a tool
Synonymous with the job, I use X to do Y
If I don't have to think about
Using X to do Y, that's better for me
So when I learn that X does Y
Whether it's LibreOffice or Word or whatever
It might be, that's what I'm going to go to
That's what I'm going to use
Getting started early
As has been the Microsoft strategy
As has been the Apple strategy
Getting people started early is
Teaching them to associate their computing
Experience and their computing habits
With open source solutions, I feel like
Sounds like a great strategy
If I were to be invited
To a school board and they said, Noah, tell me
Tell me why we should use this software
That or the other, I would
Submit to them that by
Implementing things like LibreOffice
You empower your students
With more, so it's more
Fair to your students, so for example
A financially underprivileged
Student is going to have a hard time kicking out
What's the education version, $100, $200
Or whatever, so even that is a lot
Of money for a high school student or even some
College students to pay for
So this idea that if a professor is
Going to release a presentation, why not
Release that in LibreOffice
Where everyone can download it and use it
I have two things to say about that
The first is that
It's an uphill battle because people
Associate openness with price
With open source software with price
And so what they will do is they will say, oh, well
You get a student discount on Microsoft Word
There's no reason for you to
If you really have a problem, you can get a free
Copy, you can present a financial hardship
Application or whatever
And get the software for free, and it's like
People don't understand that it's not about that
But for so many people
It is, so we need to fight that fight
I like this
Idea
I want to change the conversation
When somebody says, well look, I can get Microsoft Office
For free or I can get it with a discount
You say, it's not about that
It's about, yeah, yeah, yeah
Sure, you can buy today's version
But just look
At how much it changes over the last few years
You can learn
See, when you learn Microsoft Office
You are learning Microsoft Office
When you learn
LibreOffice, you are learning
Skills that apply to a free platform
That can be applicable anywhere
In the world
There's such a huge difference
When you
Learn skills that work with LibreOffice
Versus Microsoft
I feel like what we need to do is we need to change the
Yeah, you can get a discount on Microsoft Office
Sure, yeah, you can do that, of course you can
And you can
Become super well skilled
In a very limited time product
But technology is always changing
It's always moving forward
And LibreOffice allows you to stay current
You keep
It's free, you can keep staying up to date
You can keep that skill set
Now, let's talk about specifically
How to get past that bias
Of, well, I've seen this font
And I like the way this font looks
Or I know this application
Like Publisher, that was a huge one
When I was trying to convert somebody
Somebody special in my life
I tried to convert to Linux, and they couldn't do it because of
Publisher
How do you get past that tool bias? Well, Brian and Noah
Have some thoughts, and Noah shares his
Super secret trick
Welcome
On opensource.com last week, we had a new author
Her name's Lee Brian, she told
We have a regularly
Occurring column series on opensource.com
Called My Linux Story
And it's where people who, it's where people come on
And just tell their story about how they got started with Linux
Why it appeals to them, and sort of
Where it's taken them in their life
And we had a really great column last week by
A newbie writer, Lee Brian
Who wrote about, wrote her Linux story
And talked about how tough it was
For her to adopt opensource tools as a student
Because teachers
Would see that the default font
Was different in the documents, or the margins were wrong
Oh, they rail against it, yeah
Yeah, they rail against it, and it's like
You know, a lot of great comments, over 100
Comments on that story, people just saying they didn't
Understand why
You know, the criticism was about
The way the paper was laid out, and that was written
And why
The tool became so important
And I didn't know how to answer those comments
You know, I really didn't understand
I haven't yet figured out the strategy
For how you dislodge
You know, the bias towards
Certain ways that things appear, and the way that
You know, certain tools function
And make their final product, it just doesn't make any sense
So, I had a client
She had a
She had a computer, and it had failed
And I went to take a look at it, and she goes
Can we put Windows 7 back on there? And I said, well
You know, let me tell you about Ubuntu
You know, it's a software we use, it has
It is basically immune to virus
Spamware comes with the, we're going to put
An office suite on there, we're going to provide that for you
Your mail client is going to be there, you're going to be able to do all the same
Things, and she worked in an
Environment where all she was doing was office documents
And I said, you know, it's really, it's going to work just as
In fact, she was even using LibreOffice
I said, it's going to work just the same as Windows, except it'll be
A little bit more reliable for you and such
And I get done explaining that, and she goes, no, I'd really rather have
Windows 7, and I said, alright, well, no problem
We'll go ahead and get the restore disk sorted for you
Because we don't have those, so I'll get those from HP
So, call HP
Order the restore disk, they said it's going to be 7 to 10 business days
So I called her back and said, so, it's going to be a little bit
Before we can get that out to you, and she goes
Do you have a loaner computer? I said, I do
We have plenty of them, but I don't have anything with Windows on it
I'm sorry, it's just we can't pay for the license
It's just going to be a pain
And she goes, well, I guess if it's only for
10 days, I'll use it, and I said, okay, sure
Great, Trojan horse
So we get it put into her place
Into her desk, now I paid $53
For the recovery disks, which, if we had restored
Her computer, that would have gotten passed off to her
Plus, I would have charged her for my time to come out and install it
So, I come back out
And I said, hey, I just want to let you know that
The restore disk came in, so we'll be there on Friday to restore your computer
And she goes, is it too late
To change my mind? Because, I'm not
Going to lie, I actually
This is working really well, and she's like, I've never
Had my computer perform this fast
Now, I do have a secret weapon
When I switch people to Linux, or when I get them to try Linux
The first time, traditionally
Computers, this might change in the near future
But right now, desktop computers are
Typically shipping with spinning rust
And so, what I'll do is, I'll rip that out
And I'll swap it for an SSD
And there are a couple people in the chat room, they always give me
Crap about it, and they say, wow, you're being dishonest
You're misrepresenting, and I'm like, you know
I'm giving Linux a little bit of an edge
You know, when you get it on that SSD, all of a sudden
You click on something and everything flies, it's like
Oh, this is way faster. Well, she told me, she goes
This is just so much more faster and responsive to
What I'm used to, and
But I keep it, and at that point, it's like, wow
This is where the whole commitment to open source comes in
Because I'm just going to eat the cost and tell her, alright
So, you know, it was all set up
And so, you know, we didn't end up billing her for anything
Yeah, exactly, but
The point was, what you were talking about
Once you can get past your preconceived
Ideas of how something should function
Or how something should be, once you can
Get past that, and she didn't have a choice, because
We just sat the computer in front of her, once she
Got past that, then all of a sudden
Linux became a viable option for her
I like
Inagura's comment in the chat room
Cost of the SSD is basically
The cost of a Windows license, and it's a one-time
Investment. What a great point
What a great point. So,
We got a couple of mumble
Commentary. Kits and Kitty, I wanted to start with you
First. You made a great comment during
That clip, and I wanted to let you jump in right now
Yeah, one of the things that I do
Because I work in sales
Is when I want to sell somebody on a
Product, I ask them, well
What do you like about
What you're currently using?
Tell me about that. And then I
Use that as ammunition
To push the sell
Because I know everything
About the product that I sell
So you say, what feels
Good? What do you like about
Solution A?
Exactly
And a lot of times what you
Will find is people
Don't have much to say
About the product that they have
So then that lets you
Come in and present
Option B. Actually
I don't want to
Skip over this. This is
Pure brilliance. Make them
Focus on what they like. What do you
Like about X, right?
And then say, okay, well you know what
I get that. And by the way
Y provides this and even
More. And I think if you could make that
Case, that's a very, very, very strong
Way to do that. Great point
Kitson. Sunsol, you wanted to make a comment about
Awareness overall. Go ahead.
So I'm in the same
Boat as I guess most people
So I'm trying to make people
Aware, especially in my
Small community. People who are
Blind or visually impaired about Linux
How it can help you
Especially for how it's advantageous for them
So I always present the case of
Look, what is your current
Workflow and how does it work for you
And I try to show them this is how this
Can work for you because
In my line of people
They have to be shown
It's kind of like
What Noah and Brian had started
Talking about, about change. A lot of people
Are really hard on change
So when you try to show them
Something new and try to show them the benefits
They're almost not willing to accept it unless you can show them
A good way of how this is really going to
Enforce a good change.
Wow. Great point.
And thank you for bringing up the accessibility aspect of that too.
Great point.
And
You know, I wanted to talk about
As we move, as we zoom
Out a little bit because that's
Such a good point and yet
It's really in the weeds, right? And so
How do you address that at a
Global level? And
As somebody who has followed
Linux forever
Basically
I've never really known where to put
Red Hat, right?
I grok a lot of what they
Do. At the same time, I kind of
I'm inclined because
They're worth a lot of money and they're
A company. I'm inclined to put them
Sort of at a far and
Watch them at a distance.
That could all change though.
I don't know where I'm going to stand.
I'll tell you more about this, but we had something
Really unique happen this last week for
The Linux Action Show and
Red Hat. And
This clip with Brian
And Noah touches a little bit on this. I'm going to
Expand on this more after we play this, but
Let's talk about Red Hat a little bit.
Welcome.
I guess what surprises me so much about Red Hat
Is they're so big.
And I guess I'm surprised
I shouldn't be, I guess, but
I guess I was pleasantly
Surprised at how such a big company
Can get to a point and still
Maintain their integrity. They still
Maintain that really strong
Sense of community and they really get it.
I mean, they really, really get it.
Well, you know, it's really great to hear you say that
Because I feel that way.
And if I can just make one more
Shameless plug, our CEO
Jim Whitehurst just wrote a book about this
Very topic. It's called
The Open Organization.
And it's about Whitehurst's
Time at Red Hat.
He's very open about the fact that he came
From Delta seven or eight years ago.
Very traditional hierarchical
Organization, you know, real button
Down, straight laced place. And he came
To Red Hat and he thought his mission was going to be
As he says in the book, I thought my mission was going to be
To clean this place up. This is chaotic.
You know, this company
Is just, you know, it's doing things
In a way that I've never seen things done before.
And he said instead of changing the company
The company changed him. So he wrote
This book that I just finished reading
And we write about on open source dot com
A little bit. It's called The Open Organization
And it's about the ways that open source principles
Function in organizations.
The way that they actually present a model
For organizing that is more in line
With 21st century business practices, right?
And the way that, you know, our
Economy today demands in some ways
Demands that companies
Adopt open source principles. So what he says
Is that, you know, Red Hat's been a great project
And it's taught him a lot. But what he's saying in the book
Is that other companies can begin
To adopt, you know, these principles
And make their companies
Open. And in fact they will have to survive.
Yeah.
Now, this is something I'm pretty fascinated by.
How connected
Is Red Hat with the community?
And really how tuned in are they?
So we're going to do something kind of unique.
Something we've never done
For really the history of the Linux
Action show.
We're going to totally drop the format
Of the show. And we're going to do a special Linux
Action show visits Red Hat on Friday
At 3 p.m. Pacific. Go to
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get that in your local
Time.
Self was
Kind of within range of Red Hat's
Corporate offices. And so
Producer Q5 Sis and
Noah went out there
And talked to Red Hat. And we
Have three hours plus
More than three hours
Of footage. And we're going to try
To whittle all of it down to the best of in about an hour
Format. And for
The next week's Linux Action show
For just that episode we're going to
Kind of
Throw the format out the airlock
If I could use a Star Trek reference
If I could. And for episode
370 it's going to be the Linux Action
Show visits Red Hat's offices.
And we're going to go down there and talk to them about this.
And so when I heard that interview with
Brian I got pretty excited about that.
And I'm really looking
For that. So this Friday join us won't you.
We're going to do a special 3pm Pacific
Jupiter Broadcasting dot com slash calendar
For a Linux Action
Show visits Red Hat. Now
That was Brian from
Opensource dot com. We'll have links to his material
In the show notes. Thank you to Brian too for tuning
In. And apparently he's a big fan of
The network too. Which I am
You know I can't lie. I'm a fan
Of him too. So Semi-Robotic
He's known as online. And we'll have
A link to his blog and more
In the show notes if you want to follow up with Brian.
Now we have one more thing
To get to.
Something really special. I'm really looking forward to playing this.
And part of it is because
When I play this next clip I think
Of all of you outside the good old
United States of America. Who
Don't get really exposed to that good old
Southern twine. Well this next
Clip is going to be Alan Hicks. A long time
Contributor to the Slackware project. In fact
The man
Who wrote the book on Slackware.
He's going to join Noah. He's going to talk
About self. He's going to talk about Slackware.
I really want to play this clip for you. But first
I'm going to tell you about Digital Ocean.
Last sponsor
Of the Linux Unplugged program. Go to Digital Ocean
Won't you? And use our promo code
DOUNPLUGED. That'll give you a $10 credit.
Get a $5 rig. Try it out for a couple
Of months absolutely for free.
Now what I love about Digital Ocean
Is they're a company that recognized
That look there's a few key points we got to hit.
We got to have great connectivity.
Like for example they just built out the new data
Center over in Germany.
40 gigabit e-connections
To each hypervisor.
Their fastest SSDs yet.
And like Digital Ocean
Is like a tactical strike when they do this
Kind of thing. They made sure that when
They picked their data
This new data center in Germany it's
Perfect if like not only
Germany is a great country but you got to distribute
To anybody around Germany
This is a great data center. So 40 gigabit
E-connections to each hypervisor.
Their fastest SSDs yet.
That's awesome.
But really what I love about Digital Ocean is they
Early on decided we're going to go SSD only.
They made that bet way
Before anybody else.
And yeah you know
Linux is the obvious bet. And yeah
KVMs are the obvious
Bet. But for a commercial
Company to go out there
And base their entire company around
Linux. Around
KVM.
That's a bold bet.
That's a bold bet. I got to respect
That. And that's what Digital Ocean
Did. But they realized it's not just
Linux. It's not just KVM.
We got to have super great hardware.
We got to have SSDs. We got to have the
Best best best data centers anywhere.
And that's why Digital Ocean has data center locations
In New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam,
London and that new one in Germany. Right?
And you can get started in less than a minute.
You can get started in less than a minute.
And remember use the promo code
DOUNPLUGGED. You'll get a $10 credit.
You can try out Digital Ocean a couple of months for free
Because for $5 a month
You can get a $5. $5 a month.
Just $5. That's less than a burger.
512 megabytes of RAM.
A 20 gigabyte SSD.
One CPU.
And a terabyte of transfer.
That's crazy.
For $5 a month. That's crazy.
And if you use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED
Not only are you supporting the show and keeping us on the air
But you're going to get a $10 credit. You can try it out for 2 months for free.
Guys. Go try out
Core OS. Go try it.
Core OS is like. I don't know.
I love it. Because you know me. I'm all in
On rolling. But there are some
Serious disadvantages to our rolling distribution.
Well Core OS sort of solves that. Right?
Between containerization. Between Docker. Between the rolling
Base OS. That's a great solution.
And Digital Ocean worked with the upstream project
To make sure that way you get the
Updates directly from the Core OS
Project. I love that.
Digital Ocean has the big picture
In mind. And when you use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED
DOUNPLUGGED
DOUNPLUGGED. One word.
Lower case.
You get a $10 credit.
I want you to just experience it.
Go create a machine. They have an HTML5
Based console. You can get from post all the way
Up to the boot screen.
All HTML5. From your mobile
Device to your desktop. No
Flash required. You know you love that.
You can transfer devices
Between clients. So if you want to make something for somebody
And sell it to them. You can.
They have the best tutorials on the web.
I'm sorry Arch Wiki.
Fact of the matter is. Digital
Ocean has you beat. Ah you're a good
Number 2 Arch Wiki. And
Gentoo. Yeah you're number 3.
But the Digital Ocean
The Digital Ocean documentation is so good
Because they're actually willing to pay people to write that
Stuff. And they actually have open
Positions right now for technical
Writers. That way.
It's all about. You can get started. You can do one
Application deployment. Sure yeah you can deploy Ruby on
Rails. Wordpress. Ghost with one
Click. That's pretty cool.
But you might run into a wall.
And you might decide. Well okay I've done this
But now I'm not getting anything out of
This.
That's where this really
Really good tutorials kick in.
And you can get a little more out of Digital Ocean. Go to DigitalOcean.com
Right now. DigitalOcean.com
And use the promo code DO
Unplugged. It's all one word. Lowercase.
You'll get a $10 credit. You can try out a
$5 droplet. Two months for free.
If you've been a long time Linux
User. Maybe this is
The opportunity. To
Experiment with FreeBSD. Cause they've got those
Droplets as well. Or maybe if you've been a long
Time Debian user. If you've been a long time
Red Hat user. Try out
Core OS. It's a different approach
To doing Linux.
And I think it's gonna go big.
DigitalOcean.com
Use the promo code DO Unplugged.
And a big thank you to DigitalOcean for
Sponsoring.
Linux Unplugged Program. Alright. Now before I completely
Die of heat suffocation in this freaking
Studio. Cause it is freaking hot.
It is ridiculous. I want to play Alan
Hicks. Now you may have heard of Alan
Hicks if you were a Slackware user before.
He wrote the book on Slackware. Or he was part of it.
He's been a long, long, long
Time contributor to open source.
And he's one of the main contributors to the Southeast
Linux Fest Conference itself.
So he sat down with Noah.
And he talked about South. And can I give
If you've been wondering, is this something I
Should attend? Is this something, is this worth
Me spending the money to fly out there and visit?
Well, this talk might give you a little
Perspective.
Welcome. So Alan, tell me
Tell me who you are. And
And what distro you're using.
Well, the distro I'm
Using is obviously gonna be Slackware.
That's what I've been using since about 2001
When I got started. Actually 2000
When I got started. But
My name's Alan Hicks. I've been
Working with Slackware and
Working professionally
With Linux for
14, 15 years now.
I'm currently a
System administrator for
Well, I forget what
Our new name is. Cronky Sports
Group or something. We recently got purchased
And we're going through name changes.
So I'm not sure about all that.
But I've
Been involved in a lot of different projects.
I've been
One of the most frequent speakers here
Itself. This is actually the
First year ever that I'm not gonna be speaking
Presenting, doing networking
Stuff. This is the first year that
I'm just taking it easy and enjoying the conference.
Yeah, yeah. You are in
Relax mode this year. But even on relax mode
Alan, I watched you set up tables down
That way and people pull you right and left.
Well, it's just
The way it goes. You know, 80 percent
Of the people do 80 percent of the work.
I was one of those unfortunate
20 percent when I was born.
So this is what I think
Is particularly
Kind of cool about self, right? Is that
We have, you and I
We both like Linux. And we could talk about
Linux all day long. But the reality is the
Majority of the conversation that occurred last night
Was about guns.
Was about guns and about politics and how the world's
Going to hell in a handbasket.
And that is something that I
Don't get at other conferences.
And I think part of that is
Because of the nature of the open
Source community. We all want to build relationships
With each other. It's not just about how can
I make money off of this? Or how can your
Project benefit mine? When I go, when I used
To travel for work, I would
Go to conferences and it would be a very typical conversation
We talk about what we do. And then at the end of it
It would be, well, I think our company
Would really like to work with yours. I think that you could
Really be an asset to us. And I think that we could
Really be an asset to you. And if you put me in touch with
Your PR people, I could put you in touch with my
Secretary. You know, that kind of nonsense.
And that's not the kind of environment
I see here.
Yeah, and I've never really liked those kinds
Of environments. This is really the
Only conference I ever attend each year.
And I've only been to one or
Two others and they were in
South Paulo, Brazil for a
Slackware conference many years ago.
And I don't
Really go for the whole
Corporate networking thing.
That's just not me.
I'm not big
On that. I don't enjoy that aspect.
I like a one
On one relationship with a person.
Rather than a business
To business relationship. And
While there's plenty of businesses here
Who have their wares,
Their offerings and stuff
On display and will, you know,
Happily work with you. Self is
Really geared towards that
One on one relationship person to person.
Yeah, and my experience has been the same.
And it's not that I particularly enjoy
Corporate networking.
I just sometimes feel like I don't have much of a choice.
Because if I want to provide
A competitive advantage to my clients,
Then what that forces me to do sometimes
Is to become,
I have to become knowledgeable and I have to
Work with those people. And a lot of
Those companies, the way that they want to do business
Is they have it all
Situated. They have everything
Kind of set out the way that they want you to follow a
Process. And then
Deviate from it. And you're exactly right.
When you want to talk to, you have a problem with a
SQL database, you can go find the guy that did SQLite.
You have a problem with Red Hat. I can go talk to Red Hat
Right there. There's a guy right there from Red Hat.
If I wanted to talk about Slackware,
I'll ask the guy that wrote the book.
And you'll tell me about Slackware.
Yeah.
That's what I love about these conferences, you guys.
Is, you know,
I sat down at lunch and had a barbecued
Salmon with the guy that wrote my SQL.
And that's
Different. It's different. It's an experience.
And so, Southeast
I gotta go next year.
I gotta go to that. It's a really
Cool experience. And thank you to Alan Hicks
And thank you to Brian for stopping by and chatting
With Noah. And
I can't go forward without saying a huge
Thank you to Noah
For all of his crazy
Hard work.
Only I know how hard he worked
And I really
Really, really, really, really, really
Appreciate it. He is awesome.
Now, one of the other guys
That's awesome is producer Q5 Sis
And he had a talk itself
That I think might be right up your alley.
He talked about creating
Your own Linux laptop.
Building your own Linux laptop.
This is an hour and
Five minute talk. I can't play for it.
I cannot. I'm sorry.
I cannot do it. But I wanted to
I went in about six minutes
Into his talk. I have the whole thing linked
In the show notes. Really, if you've ever
Wanted about building your own laptop, now
Is a better time than ever.
I jumped in about six minutes
Where he talks about batteries. So you want to get a
Board that's going to be power efficient and
Still be able to accomplish the tasks
That you're going to want to accomplish.
As for
The screen, who's heard of Adafruit?
I love this.
If anyone that has their hands
Up, is anyone next to
Them that is a friend of them that doesn't have their hand up?
This is
This question right here is Mr. Q5
Sis. Producer Q5 Sis.
Perfect. This is what it's like
To work with Mr. Q5 Sis.
He's so great because he
Once he researches something
Once he understands something
He evangelizes it.
Don't we all do that? And he's so great
About that. Not your friends.
I want to back up a little bit. I want to play a little bit of this
For you. I want to back up.
Hold on. I want to play a little bit of him talking about this for you.
So you can find the whole talk.
And there is a couple of minutes where you might
Have some audio issues. Do not worry about that.
There was a little bit of YouTube issues.
I think top 2 needed enhancement.
Oh there we go.
So he
Notes to me here that there's a couple of minutes where
YouTube didn't quite capture the Hangouts audio.
So if you listen to the
I have a link to the show notes. Mr. Q5 Sis
Talks about battery issues.
3D printing your own laptop.
Building it around a Raspberry Pi.
All of those topics are in his talk.
And I have it linked in the show notes.
It's over an hour so I can't play the whole thing.
But I really recommend you check it out.
And it is also like Micro 89 points out
Available in the Linux Action Show subreddit.
Oh yes. The Linux Action Show subreddit.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Make. This. Show. Better.
You weren't happy?
What? What?
We didn't do it? What?
You weren't happy?
Okay. I'll take that.
Submit a bug. Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Make it better. Seriously.
I listen to the community over there.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com. Go check it out.
I will also, by the way, we'll have a feedback thread
For this episode.
I am trying to figure out what all of you
Are doing in response to the last pass.
What are you doing? What is your response
To last pass? Let me know. Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Go find the feedback thread
For episode 96
Of the Linux Unplugged program.
And let me know. Are you going to switch
To key paths?
I want to know. The anime says he's doing nothing.
Hmm. Okay.
Alright. I'll take that as well.
Go over there and let me know what your plans are
For this and other things.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
And also, if you want to
Hook up with us at a
Future event, meetup.com
Slash Jupiter Broadcasting. Go there
And sign up and
Future events will be there.
I was planning to do episode 100
In Seattle, but now...
Now I think I might
Do episode 100 of the Linux
Unplugged program on location
With Noah. Patreon.com
Slash today if you want to get in on some of that.
You guys are awesome. Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode
Of Linux Unplugged. And by the way,
You can make this show better right now
By going to Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
I will leave you with this.
Episode 96 marks
What I think...
Is one of the coolest, coolest
Episodes we've ever had. I love
I love talking to Brian. I love self.
Thank you so much to Noah. Thank you so much to Rekai
For editing all of this together.
Thank you so much to producer q5sist. Thank you so much
For Blaster, for communicating remotely.
Thank you everybody. Go to meetup.com
Slash Jupiter Broadcasting and the community members.
Thank you to Popey for giving us an update on Open
Tech 2015. I hope I can be there next year.
It's a great episode, you guys.
Thank you so much for making this possible. Patreon.com
Slash today if you want to see us do future episodes.
Episode 96 in the can. I cannot
I know it's 96. I'm looking forward to 100.
Join us back here next week
Tuesdays. Jupiter Broadcasting.com
Slash calendar if you want to join us in the
Virtual Lug. See you right back here.
Next week.
Thanks for watching.
Alright.
In the IRC right now,
Kids and Kitty, you've submitted
a straw poll.
I won't steal your thunder. What is it about?
Go ahead.
Kids and Kitty.
I don't hear you.
Are you muted? Still having trouble with that mic, kid?
So, Kids and Kitty
asked the live stream, will you be migrating
away from LastPass? And it's just a simple
yes or no question.
And I'm going to vote no right now.
But I'm curious.
Ooh, it's split. It's literally split right now.
50-50. 50-50 in the live stream.
Ooh, wow.
Wow, you guys. Really?
Should've had third options
because I'm using KeyPass
and there's no option for that.
No, no, no. Because that's a no.
If you're going to KeyPass, that's a clear no.
No, I like this. Two options is good.
It's good.
I specifically did that
intentionally because the
question is, would
you move away? Right.
So, it's irrelevant whether or not
you have LastPass now
per se, as
if you were using it, would
you move away?
Are we going to be talking about Fedora again?
No, I think we're all done. Why? Do you have something to say?
I just tried it out this week.
It's awesome.
Should've tried it out last week.
I'm sold.
I'm sold. I wiped the
SUSE partition
after I used it
for a few days.
Whoa.
So, you're like switching?
You're that sold?
I am that sold and I'm a hard
sell from SUSE.
Okay, all right. What is the big
diff? Because at the end of the day, they're both
RPM distros.
One's got the build service. One's got
copper. What?
What's the big difference?
You know what sold me was the fact that
everything was just so consistent.
I didn't have to, pardon the language,
dick around with four
different software managers
to do what I wanted to do.
I could go into software or I go into
DNF. Oh, yeah. It is a bit of a
it's a little
I sometimes feel like OpenSUSE is a little
bipolar. It's a little
chaotic in that sense. There's a lot of
different tools available to you. And that honestly
maybe is my bias of all the transitions they've
done with their package manager. But when I sit down
to use it, I feel like
there's a lot of places I go to manage sources
and I just
but I felt like with Fedora,
okay, I've got DNF repos and
I've got GNOME software. Boom, boom. I can use
it on the command line or I use it in the GUI. Is that how you
felt?
Largely. And the other thing
is that I noticed is every
time I wanted to do something with
this installing software
at one point, it wanted to
drag a bunch
of packages in
because they were part of the
meta package that I had installed.
So I had to taboo those
in Yast. And they would
still want to install.
And heaven forbid, you have to do any kind of
conflict resolution
through Yast. That's
where it kind of gets hairy because
I feel like when I have to do
conflict resolution for RPMs and dependencies
and because the meta package
wants to be able to replace a package that another
meta package wants, all of a
sudden I feel like I'm back in like 2006,
Linux. And
I kind of just start shutting
down and I think my time could be
spent better than this.
But, okay, come on chatroom.
Come on. Strawpoll.me.
Strawpoll.me.
Oh, I'm, alright, well
see
the problem is like 40
to 50% of the people are not even in the
chatroom. So I've got to give it to them over air.
The strawpoll URL sucks, but it's
strawpoll.me slash 46
strawpoll.me
slash 46
782.
And there's a link in the chatroom.
We have 19 votes
right now. 20 votes.
I just can't see moving away from
last pass. It seems too practical to me.
But I, at the same time,
like part of me recognizes they are a
huge, huge, huge
target.
On another
note, I kind of wish that Colonel
Linux would have been here to join us
because I wanted to
ask him if he ever saw anybody
show up the self
in full leather bondage gear.
Confused. Okay, alright, okay,
alright, okay. So
going on at the same time of
Southeast Linux Fest is the southern
I don't even know the whole acronym, but it's like
Southeast Leather Fest
and it's a leather
fest. And
last year, if you searched Twitter for
self, you got pictures of
65 year old ladies in leather.
Now, this year
they coordinated and self had
there was self and then
there was the Southeast Leather Fest and they had their own
hashtag separate from self.
But no, Noah
very, very much so. I believe
I'm not positive. I think
he's in Amsterdam right now.
So what Noah does is
Noah works at like
300-400 percent
and I'm not exaggerating. I've never known
anybody who's ever worked
harder in his life. I don't
know how his wife and
his kids accommodated,
but nobody works harder than Noah.
And so he goes out to these conferences
and then he's hooking up with a
buddy of his and I think he's in Amsterdam
right now. So he goes out
and he just totally goes all in
on these conferences.
And then I think right now he's like
on his way home, on his way
home from self, he's stopping by
Amsterdam and he's having a party with his buddy
and then he's going to go home.
And then he'll be back by Friday so that way we can
do the Linux action show.
That's pretty crazy. But I think that's
how he rolls so that's why he couldn't join us today.
Swift,
I'm okay. I'm a little stressed out.
Yeah, it has been very difficult
to make all of this happen centrally
and it has been very hard
to watch all of it happen remotely, if
that makes sense. So it has been very
hard technically to pull it all off
because Jupyter Broadcasting has grown
and so we have
Roku devices and
Tivo's and audio
streams and web browsers
and VLC that when you
think you can tune in live and watch,
you think you can go to your Roku app or you
think you can go to the Kodi app
or whatever, XBMC app, whatever,
and just watch live. It takes
a crazy amount of coordination
behind the scenes to actually deliver content
at all of those endpoints.
And thankfully Rekai and I
really, Rekai managed
to pull it all off, but it was very stressful.
And it was also stressful because
I wasn't there. I really wanted to be
there. But otherwise, I'm okay.
I'm good. I'm very happy.
I think Noah is an incredible
asset. So I'm very good
about that. And Rekai has been amazing.
So everybody say thank you to Rekai
for how hard he worked this weekend.
We don't pay him to work over the weekend and
yet he did. And
he made it possible for us
to stream the content from self-live
to all of the endpoint destinations.
The beard made it all
happen. So thank you to Rekai.
And as
all things, our poll is
completely split down the middle. If you're a long time listener
or a viewer, you know,
everything, every freaking
poll, every
time, goes 50-50. You know
what this happens if you've been
listening. You know this if you've been
following for awhile.
16 votes say...
This is so ridiculous.
I can't even...
Okay. We've had
31 votes from the live stream.
This is incredible.
I didn't
expect anything less.
16 people will move away from
LastPass and 16 people will not.
It's
literally split right
down the middle. You guys
are such sons of bitches. You are
so hard to please because you are
literally split on every single
topic. And you know if you've been watching
for awhile, you know this is true.
You know I always run into this.
You are so hard. I
love you though. I love you.
Chris, um,
blue bricks or red curtains?
I'm sorry.
Well, last week it was blue bricks and the week before that it was red curtains, obviously.