Well, I think we're having ourselves an emergency podcast right now.
This is like thrown together.
We gotta like just really slam this one out because I got called into jury duty tomorrow.
You know, you've got to help out the state here, Chris.
You know, Wes, somebody's got to go in and pet the bald eagles.
It does make me feel comfortable that you're the one making the decisions.
Oh, yeah?
Are you sure about that?
I got a whole line I think I'm going to go in there and give a speech about what I think
should be a user voted type of justice.
Think that'll get me on the old board?
Hello friends and welcome into the old unplugged program where we're celebrating user created
software.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello Wes.
Here we are on a Monday, no live stream, no mumble room by ourselves.
Well we've brought in a little backup.
You might say some of our favorite friends, Mr. Cheese Bacon and the Drew of Doom.
Hello gentlemen.
Hello guys.
Drew, it's been a while since you've been on the show.
Glad to have you on there.
Been loving the Choose Linux.
Of course.
So and Fridays with Drew on Linux Headlines.
Yeah, but you guys know I missed you over here.
I just couldn't stay away.
Oh Drew, I know you're lying.
I know you're lying.
You're just helping us out because we really did get ourselves in a bit of a situation
this week.
So I apologize if you were planning to make it live and we weren't there.
We'll try to do something.
We'll try to do something for the live stream, but I don't know what.
Since it's kind of a special edition, we thought we should do something we haven't done for
a couple of weeks.
Something we wanted to stay accountable for.
And so Wes, are you ready sir?
I am standing by.
All right, ladies and gentlemen, it's time to check in on the Arch server.
So if you will recall, we replaced a FreeNAS box with a Fedora box, which seemed like a
ridiculous decision.
Level one insanity.
So then we thought, well, what could we do that would be even more unreasonable?
So we replaced that Fedora box with an Arch box.
Now this system is responsible for a bunch of media storage that's critical to our operation,
as well as several applications, more than several, that run in containers that are vital
to our day-to-day operation.
So we thought, what better way to take care of a box like this than to update it live
right here on the show.
Mr. Wes Payne, are you SSHed in right now?
Oh yes, we're ready to go.
All right, kick it off Wes.
Oh, some new kernels, upgraded WireGuard, new system D version.
This is a good one.
Oh God.
All right.
And I kind of love Arch, downloading like 1.6 gigs of software for a net upgrade size
of two megs.
That is really great.
I always love it when a package manager does that.
Well, coming up on the show today, we're going to have a bit of a theme on the episode.
After we get done upgrading our rolling server, we're going to read a blog by Richard Brown,
the former OpenSUSE Chairman, who has a really deep take on the fundamental way we maintain
and distribute software in the Linux community, and he's advocating for micro rolling servers.
We'll tell you about that and what we think about that idea.
Plus, we've got some software towards the end of the show that is fundamentally designed
to help you recover from major system issues like a bad update.
It's called Timeshift.
It's a beloved piece of software on Linux Mint.
We discovered it during our Linux Mint review.
Now we've extracted it from Linux Mint, because you can put it on any distro, and we're going
to focus just on that recovery method.
Plus, we've got feedback and pics, but right now we're going to check in on that Archbox.
Okay, how are we doing, Wes?
Downloads going?
Downloads going.
It's always a little nerve-wracking when you see the step, you're getting rid of all your
old DKMS modules, and you just have to hope they come back.
All right, Wes, well, we'll check back in on that in just a little bit.
In the meantime, let's talk about something from the no-crap department in the news.
Google is publicly shaming Samsung for making unnecessary changes to Linux kernel code.
Now, how about this one?
This is coming from Google's Project Zero department.
They write that Samsung is creating a more vulnerable Android ecosystem by adding its
own downstream custom drivers for direct hardware access to Android's Linux kernel.
Yeah, this is really no good.
Notice that the Linux kernel has, as they put it, a few sharp edges, and these changes
that are being implemented by Samsung and other vendors, they're not being reviewed
at all by upstream kernel developers, so that means no one outside of that organization
is checking them.
The researchers actually found a similar mistake in the Android kernel of the Galaxy A50, and
that unreviewed custom driver added security bugs related to memory corruption, which that's
no good.
No.
Can we just sit here and just acknowledge the obvious?
It is absolutely no surprise that when a vendor is adding their own patches that is not being
peer reviewed by the rest of the community, that there is vulnerabilities in there that
they did not catch.
It seems obvious on its face, and that somebody in Samsung's position clearly, someone in
that organization must have at least acknowledged the risk that they were assuming by taking
this action.
And as an organization, they must have chosen to either ignore that individual or actively
ignore the risk.
It does get a little more complicated, I guess some of these are really mitigations or intended
mitigations for other security issues.
In this case, the bug affected the company's process authenticator security subsystem.
Oh.
Yeah, they describe it as a moderate security issue, but from the Google engineers at Project
Zero perspective, a lot of these things, they're just not necessary, and so rather than being
a mitigation, they just introduce more attack surface.
Not only are they not necessary, because there are some facilities in Android that enable
some of this same exact functionality, but at the end of the day, some of these are enabling
arbitrary code execution.
Fundamentally, they're enabling arbitrary code execution.
And that's even on Android 10 devices, which is just such a shame.
You think you're getting yourself a secure device by getting the latest and greatest
version of Android, and they've bolted on these custom fixes so that way they can add
value.
Yeah, it is a shame.
I'm not having it.
And Google's been doing a lot of good engineering effort to make Android more secure.
Why throw that away?
It seems so obvious.
That's why I find it frustrating that it still continues to happen.
I understand that there are other options out there.
This doesn't condemn all Android devices, but Samsung is such an important player in
this space.
You'd really rather see it that way.
I know it's a big organization.
They have many departments, but you'd think that at least to have some experience knowing
you kind of work upstream with the kernel community.
That's just what you should do.
It's also kind of awkward that their partner, Google, is calling them out publicly.
It's sort of weird, Wes.
You know what I mean?
All right, Wes, your break is now over.
Let's check in on that Archbox.
Upgrade complete.
I mean, I don't see any errors.
You ready for the reboot?
Let's do it.
There's only one way to find out what these things are.
All right.
It reboots so fast.
It almost makes me feel nervous.
It's gone.
And then it takes so long to get through the bios.
Do you think that maybe you should have installed time shift first?
We do have a series of snapshots on there.
Yes, and I did see it taking those snapshots, so that's good.
And I'll remind everybody that our philosophy with this rolling Archbox has truly been keep
that base install of Arch absolutely as thin and lightweight and minimal as possible.
That thing's really designed to do one thing, mount ZFS storage and run containers.
That's our philosophy with this.
So we're hoping that this ultra minimal approach to an Arch deployment is a safer bet than
something that's really built up.
We'll see.
We're going to find out because at the end of the day, you're still updating fundamental
packages.
Right.
There's a lot of change and we do have to upgrade more often.
But the flip side of that is I feel like I understand the system a little bit better.
That's true.
I think you and I both stay more current on what that thing's doing.
Well, let's let's shift gears into Richard Brown's post, which was titled regular release
distributions are wrong.
We're going to pull a few bits from this because it's pretty thought provoking and we'll link
you to read the rest.
As we record right now, I think the site might be having some troubles.
So we'll try to include both a link to the source site and maybe an archive.org version.
That's what we had to use.
When you want to start with this one, Wes, you think maybe there's so much to including
his setup here.
What do you say we start with his bit in here about regular and LTS releases and how they
mean well?
And this is, I think, a point that we could discuss as a group here.
He writes, the open source world is made up of thousands, if not millions of discrete
free software and open source projects.
And Linux distributions exist to take all of that often chaotic, ever evolving software
and condense it into a single consumable format that is then put into very real world work
by its users.
The traditional mindset for distribution builders is that the regular release gives a nice,
predictable, planable schedule in which a team can carefully select appropriate software
from various upstream projects.
The maintenance often comes in the form of making minimal changes, seeking only to address
specific security issues or customer requests, taking great care not to break the systems
that are currently in use.
Right.
So this is really an example of a classic LTS system.
And often, I mean, that can be appreciated.
You don't always want the rug pulled out from underneath you and having to adapt to constant
changes, especially if it's software that you're not super familiar with, or you didn't
really need the new features.
That wasn't your concern.
You just wanted the software to keep working.
Yeah, sometimes it's required by a commercial vendor.
Yeah.
And you want a reliable service, especially for something like a server.
But it is a little more complicated than that.
Because I mean, especially here on Unplugged, we want the new stuff, you know, we're always
talking about the shiny new features.
And so the downside of an LTS often is that you don't have that or you have to do some
really, really terrible workaround or build stuff from source to get it extra.
And that doesn't always work.
When we've talked about rolling releases versus traditional, we've often identified that there
is a type of user that wants access to current software, either to stay current with their
peers or to stay current with somebody they're working with in industry or because they like
to follow software.
Maybe a tool you need for your work, and it's important that you get the new features as
quickly as possible.
Yeah.
And that's really the nature of what we consider change in a Linux distribution that Richard
Brown is calling into question here.
He continues, is this change too risky?
It's a common question.
And quite often, highly desired features take years to deliver in regular releases.
Because the answer is yes.
This often means avoiding updating software to entirely new versions, but instead, opting
to backport the smallest necessary amounts of code and merging them with much often older
versions already in the regular release.
We usually call these things patches, updates, maintenance, updates, security, updates.
Richard suggests, though, that we're really avoiding referring to them what they what
they really are.
Freaking software.
Okay, so weird, unholy hybrid of things that were never meant to be.
Yeah, hybrid software, you could would be a little more charitable.
But what it is, he says, no matter how skilled the engineers are, that are that are doing
the work, no matter how great the processes or testing are around their backporting, fundamentally,
the result is a hybrid mixed together combination of old and new software, which was never originally
intended to work together.
In the process of trying to avoid risk, backports instead introduce entirely new vectors for
bugs to appear.
Okay, let's sit with this for a second, guys.
He's saying essentially that when you have a regular stable release, and you start backporting
fixes, you may be solving one security issue, but you could be opening up a whole series
of bugs.
And I'm no software developer, but it does make sense that if you're taking two bits
of code that are very close together, but not intended to work together, it could create
other possible issues.
It certainly depends on the specifics, right?
But you can imagine simple changes that are just change the default config option or something.
But depending on how how far the software has progressed, you're basically having a
totally separate fork.
And to make certain security fixes, it might mean significant re architecture or touching
a large swath of the code base, because it's changed, and you can't just apply the fix
that gets applied to the head of the branch, right?
Right.
And I think a lot of times we'll charitably call these a regression, always a regression.
And we continue to do it as a as a model of delivering software.
It's not just Linux distributions.
For example, you have Firefox 73, that came out last week, and version 68 DSR, or whatever
it was also came out.
Well, clearly, they're taking some bug fixes and security issues, and they're backporting
it from the current version of Firefox to that old branch.
And it's so common that we don't even talk about this process anymore, because it's just
how you do it.
It's just normal.
Yeah.
But he's kind of calling that entire thing into question.
And I think if you narrow the scope, which he is here to just servers, and how server
software and open source software is distributed, his argument starts to make sense.
When you consider and he writes, the more people involved in working on something, the
more eyeballs looking at the code, the better.
That's a fundamental truth.
And yet, when you think about it, it also means you have handfuls of people contributing
software at different paces, at different schedules, updating all different aspects
of a system at all different interests, commitments, timelines, motivations, etc.
And it's it's a massive spectrum.
And perhaps in this reality, when software is developed in this way, we're kind of fooling
ourselves a little bit here.
And that if we could build a system where we could continue to just stay current with
the latest stuff, like all like the way Linus considers bug, security issues, bug fixes,
just everything's a bug fix.
Everything's a fix.
And we have seen this this attitude more prevalent on all kinds of systems, right?
I mean, with some, some would say some a lot of the DevOps philosophy.
And if you think about the flip side, have you ever gone, you know, you waited a couple
LTS is maybe I mean, I was personally involved with 1204 to 1604.
That was part of the system D change.
It was a nightmare.
I mean, there were just so many changes to the system.
And you've got to imagine in some sense, if developers have been given a little more time
to get used to those, adapt during the process, in the end, it might be smoother.
My wife's clinics workstation is on 1604.
And a lot of the repos don't work anymore.
So the updates are failing.
And I guess it doesn't that version doesn't auto clean the boot partition.
I thought it did.
But her boot partition filled up again.
So then it stopped updating for a minute.
It's really getting decrepit.
And the software on that thing is it's just still running unity seven, right?
I mean, it's really feeling old.
But it works for her.
But it's clear that the rest of the software world has moved on.
Drew, since you're our special guest, I wanted to kind of get your take on this from your
sys admin days.
Obviously the rolling argument falls down when you start talking about server deployments.
But Richard goes on to make the argument here that, well, you solve that by creating micro
server OSs that just do one thing, much like our Archbox.
He's got a point.
But I do think the argument does fall down quite a bit here in 2020.
Three years ago, I think this would have been a much stronger argument.
But nowadays, with the prevalence of containers and snaps and flat packs and app images, I
am less inclined to go the way he's going.
I was a rolling user for a long, long time.
But with the advent of, you could almost say containerized applications and containers
themselves, I don't see this as something that's strictly necessary anymore, especially
in server software.
How many people are deploying things on bare metal anymore?
Just about everybody is using Kubernetes and Docker, and increasingly, even enterprise
level stuff is moving that direction.
So to me, the ability to have a very stable base that's been quality assured by the team
who put it together, and then stack software on top of that, that is rolling, that's based
in a container.
Why do I need the base system to be rolling at this point?
You flip the argument around is what you've done here.
Yeah, exactly.
It's just not something that I buy anymore.
I would rather have in production, a system that I know is dependable and has a solid
team doing the security patches like Ubuntu or like Red Hat, and is putting together a
product that I know I can rely on, and gets really good, tested, quality assured updates.
And I don't feel like I get that level of quality assurance testing, whatever you want
to call it, in a rolling distro.
It just doesn't feel rock solid and bulletproof like some of these others do.
I think to buy his argument, you have to accept that the distributions are not providing a
ton of value, that they're mostly providing organizational and smoothing of rough edges.
And then when they backport, they're kind of slamming the software together.
That's sort of what he's implying.
And he may be in a better position than I, having been the OpenSUSE chairman and being
involved with OpenSUSE forever, he may know better than me.
But I feel like it's a little uncharitable to distributions, I feel like that's sort
of underselling what they do.
But I think I might agree with his fundamental argument.
I might see it the opposite way Drew does.
What about you, Wes?
It is complicated.
A little more data, I think, would be useful because there's a lot of philosophy in this,
and rightfully so, and well-made questions and arguments.
But do we see that many problems of regressions in patches, security patches?
Is this burden of maintaining these really that big of an issue?
It seems like, at least from Drew and many other admins that I've talked to, LTS is appreciated
and they have security compliance in play.
If that was a major problem, then they would probably consider moving to a rolling distribution,
right?
Okay, so there's a bit of philosophy in here, like you just said.
And I think we should touch on that for a second.
And she's put on your philosophy hat for this question.
Imagine if all of the open source developer time that is used to backport to old releases
was spent working on new stuff, like we took X amount of time and dedicated it to new stuff.
That is part of his argument.
He writes, a small handful of committed volunteers and those that are employees of companies
selling commercial regular releases.
These are limited resources that are often siloed with only time and resources to work
on very specific distributions with their specific backports and patches that are often
hard to even be reused by other communities.
I think he's got a fair point for better for worse.
That is true.
What if all of a sudden we had all that time back and it was all just new stuff?
I feel like we probably would be further along in some areas.
Yeah, I mean, I think that we would be further along in some areas if we were progressive
about it and we continued to take that time from doing all these backports and ensuring
that these LTSs were secure and moving forward with software would probably fast track us
to create, just evolve the software in itself and create new and interesting software.
But in that same vein, I think that you could say that that also introduces bugs and potential
security vulnerabilities.
So it's damned if you do, damned if you don't, right?
So I kind of align with Drew and what he says and with an LTS, I mean, it is long term support
and you expect that.
But if you had this additional time and you could use that time to further the software
along and create new and interesting software, I mean, you have that opportunity as well.
So it's really, this whole article is really more of a philosophical article in and of
itself, I believe, and is really an opinionated piece.
I do agree with a lot of what he says, but there's part of me that thinks that there
are LTSs for a reason and between these LTS releases, that gives your sysadmin and your
developers time to come up to speed with the latest technology.
So when do you have a lull so that your devs can get up to speed with this new technology
if you're creating the technology so fast?
Okay, so that's a great point.
They got to have an opportunity to learn, which, okay, all right.
But in some ways, Wes, couldn't you argue that perhaps rolling at least at some level
could be easier to understand?
Right.
It's all about cadence, right?
I mean, a rolling is just a lot of little tiny releases.
And so you can learn these changes.
There's less to learn when you have constant changes instead of one big heap of changes.
Right.
You're maybe updating a dozen packages versus a thousand packages.
And there's maybe three changes for each package versus 200 changes.
Right.
And I think a bit from maybe a development angle as well.
And that's just, you know, minimizes your pain as long as you're doing it sometime.
And you might not update every day.
It might be that you update every week or every two weeks so that you're aware of those
changes.
But having a smaller change set to go diff and look back through when you're trying to
debug something or figure out why something won't compile anymore.
That's really nice.
Hmm.
So where does this leave us really?
I think there's one way to find out.
We could check on how our server is doing and that could be the ultimate answer.
I was hoping you weren't going to say that.
Has it back up yet?
All right.
Well, it rebooted.
No problem.
It didn't load the ZFS module.
You're kidding me.
I know.
No.
So no containers were running, no ZFS file systems mounted.
I'm currently rebuilding the DKMS modules.
We'll see if that just, you know.
Oh, that is sometimes a thing.
But usually not.
We have not had that problem.
It's working.
Hmm.
Well, I think that proves it right there.
I think Cheese and Drew are right.
You guys got that one because, I mean, we'll see.
It's probably not a big deal.
I guess that's a fair part of the conversation is every now and then these things happen.
I suppose if this was a real honest to legit revenue generating piece of equipment, we'd
probably have the storage on like an iSCSI device.
And it wouldn't be directly attached to this one host where we're using a ZFS kernel module
to mount it.
Right.
You'd be on another host that's running the disk that has it mounted or we'd be iSCSIing
it and mounting it that way over iSCSI.
And there's also other things.
I'm sure we could have detected this problem before we rebooted or adjusted some parameters
to ensure that.
However, good on us.
We're going ButterFS on the root so that way at least the host system gets up and you can
troubleshoot.
Right.
That's really been working very well.
You were able to SSH in.
Yeah, no problem.
Came up rebooted normally.
I think one of our belt and suspenders approach to arch, it really was, is get snapshots,
which we're not going to bother with in this case because it's probably a pretty easy fix,
but also give yourself a way to get in when the system doesn't work right.
And the snapshots here do mitigate a lot.
I mean, we're not going to use them.
I'd rather just sort of roll forward in this case.
But right, if we we wouldn't do this unless we had an allocated at least some kind of
maintenance window.
And with snapshots, it means, OK, it didn't work.
Try it again later.
Roll it back.
And then it's you don't have to miss that window.
We've done some offline, I mean, off air, I should say upgrades to it, too.
So this we haven't only been upgrading it on the show.
And so it's been probably a dozen times, maybe half a I mean, I know I've probably done a
half a dozen times and you've probably done another handful of times and it hasn't had
an issue.
But I'm pretty glad that when we did, we got it on the show because this is how this is
this is the real world.
And these are the things you need when you hear why you don't why you shouldn't run arch
on the server.
It's like, well, if you don't want to deal with this, if you don't know how to reinstall
a DKMS module, which is just a Pac-Man command.
But, you know, if that if that goes over your head, then it's not the right OS for you.
I didn't even read the arch blog before doing this, which I probably should have.
Well, there was that whole I had a game show music countdown play.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, I think that this is the the perfect type of system to test this this idea
on the right, because it's not like Equifax is database server or something, right?
It's right.
You know, this personal server that they were using some podcasts, right?
And it might it might, you know, disrupt a little bit of a file storage thing.
But you always have your ZFS pool that you can reattach to.
So it's not like theoretically anything is really lost, right?
Like you've got some containers you might have to rebuild and and you've got, you know,
let's say if you change the host from arch to something else, you might have to rebuild
those containers and reattach to your ZFS pool.
But other than that, you still have a security net there that you don't have to worry about
the system actually breaking and falling into pieces.
So there is one aspect of this conversation that I think he nails before we completely
move on.
And that is treating the server a little bit different than we traditionally have with
old school Linux.
In old school Linux, you got these DVDs or CD-ROMs or whatever, and there was like six
disks and you would do this whole install, it would be you install kinds of packages
just in case you ever needed to install another kind of package.
And it was assumed that you'd have all these different things in a distribution that was
much larger than it actually needed to be if that was only doing one job and one job
only.
You made a big standalone multipurpose machine.
Yes.
And even if you installed just a mail server on it still had all this other stuff.
That has shifted.
And the idea of one server one function in the world of VMs and containers is very, very
affordable and very attainable.
And I do think that is the way to just really solid server systems in the future is one
micro install instance that only has the bare minimum of what it needs to run a container
or a VM.
And in that VM, it's again, it's an absolute bare minimum install only needs what it has
to have.
And you're only maintaining that small set of packages.
And that's why there's so much room for all these different flavors of Linux.
From openSUSE, a micro OS to Alpine to the rel core stuff now.
Yeah, there's even unikernels where the programming language, they don't even have a regular kernel.
It's all just that.
Yeah.
And in the meantime, the rest of the world will just keep on using Ubuntu.
Well, and he's also spot on about atomic style updating.
He mentions micro OS, which is the openSUSE version.
But the whole idea of transactional updates is fantastic.
It's something that I've really taken a liking to not just in servers, but also on the desktop
with things like silver blue, which I think could be the future of how we do a lot of
things having an immutable base, which is read only.
And then you can layer stuff on top, including containers.
That's really what it's built for.
And it really feels like the next generation of server computing, especially, maybe desktop,
I don't know, I'm back and forth on that.
But for servers, yeah, it's the ability to roll back without having to deal with things
like snapshots because they're baked in.
It's fantastic.
I agree.
That's why we're going to talk about time shift today.
So that way, folks that are listening can implement this on their desktop or laptop
or even your server in a way that's really straightforward, just using rsync.
Or if you have butterfs, it uses native butterfs snapshots, because these snapshots are really
great functionality.
We decided to install it on our recording system here that has an awesome jack setup.
It's a lot.
But amazingly, we are able to expose all 32 inputs and outputs from our mixer to jack.
And so we can wire the mixer in jack and then send it to Reaper for recording and pipe it
out to our remote guests in the mumble room with virtual syncs and whatever you call it.
It's just flexible.
And it's awesome, however, you could see how an audio package could come along and break
the whole thing and we would not be able to record.
We're really dependent on it now.
Yeah, there's like there's PPAs involved in a lot of specific configuration.
It's delicate.
So we thought, Jesus, this is a perfect candidate, perfect.
So Wes, he laid his hands on the machine and he blessed it with time shift.
And we're going to tell you how that went in just a moment.
But first, just some quick housekeeping, just a few items of note.
If you haven't had a chance, go check out Linux Headlines, linuxheadlines.show every
weekday in three minutes or less.
What's going on in the world of Linux?
I do Mondays, Drew does Tuesdays, I do Wednesdays, Wes does Thursdays and then Drew's back to
wrap us up on Fridays.
So we just sort of shifted around so that way not one of us completely burns out.
But what's really cool, behind the scenes, we have a dedicated staffer to doing research,
to collecting stories, to verifying them.
But we also bounce it around the team before it publishes.
And then we do a peer review before we actually release the MP3 file.
So in that three minutes, you are getting super tight, accurate, condensed information
with the hype removed, with all of our different perspectives on it, regardless of who's hosting
it.
Really proud of that work.
LinuxHeadlines.show, and of course, one went out today.
It's a great way to just, when you're going down the road, why not just start out with
a three minute show and then get into whatever you're going to listen to.
That's really great.
Also Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Telegram, just going great.
Yeah, come join the party.
I think I owe the whole Telegram group a beer now.
I'm not sure how we're all going to get in one place.
I think I need to give them tacos.
It's PBRs.
It's going to be a good night though.
Not going to be on PBRs.
Don't work tacos in there.
Everybody wants tacos now.
We're not doing tacos again.
At least that's on you.
You want to bring the tacos, you're the taco guy.
I'll be the PBR guy.
You'll be the taco guy.
Dude, this is sounding great actually.
Now we just need a place.
Also, if you haven't checked out my side thing, Chris Lastcast, me and Brent, we're launching
an empire over there.
No, actually, I just decided when we were talking about the burnout stuff to do a little
creative outlet, and I've kind of been keeping it going.
Brent talked me into it.
I sat down and I did a thing about how I created myself a little note challenge.
I got my notes right here.
I'm sticking to it so far.
You have a lovely notebook there.
So Brent and I checked that out, chrislast.com.
That just went up this morning as we record because we're doing this one a little early.
Hopefully, things will be back to our regularly scheduled program next week, Tuesday at noon
Pacific, but since I'm at jury duty, we don't really know.
We don't really know until I just go.
So I go tomorrow.
If we're not live, we'll try to figure out another time.
We'll do like a late night lup party.
Oh, that could be fun.
We'll do that.
We'll come.
We'll do some pizza.
We'll watch a movie.
We'll watch Revolution OS.
We could really do this.
Yeah, I'm down.
We could grab some clips, watch Revolution OS, have some pizza, and then go record a
lup.
I mean, if you've got to do jury duty, you might as well chill out and make it fun.
We'll figure out something.
It might be kind of a weird one, but we'll figure it out.
We won't leave you hanging, at least hopefully.
Anyways, that is our housekeeping for today.
Let's talk about time shift.
Before we do, I've got an Arch update.
Yeah, it turns out the latest kernel that we just downloaded, not yet supported by ZFS
on Linux.
There's another GPL only symbol change that has not yet been fixed.
So revert, go back.
Back in time.
Very good.
Well, that shouldn't be too hard of a fix.
You think you'll have it done before the end of the show?
Oh, yeah.
You think so?
I'm going to do it right now.
Okay.
I mean, that thing does take a while to reboot.
So time shift is a Linux application that provides functionality similar to Windows
Restore or maybe Time Machine on Mac OS.
It protects your system by taking incremental snapshots of the file system at regular intervals.
Now, these snapshots can be restored later to undo the changes, and we'll use rsync with
hard links on a system that doesn't have butterfess.
And the nice thing about those hard links is common files that are shared between the
snapshots will just be hard linked, and then you don't have duplicates, and it saves space.
Each snapshot is a full system backup that you can actually go browse with a file manager.
But here's what's also really cool.
In butterfess mode, snapshots are taken using built-in butterfess file system features,
which is really cool.
Now, I think the one thing that might surprise people is if I recall when we were setting
this up, Wes, by default, it doesn't back up user data.
Yeah, and that's actually intentional.
It's designed to just try to keep the system safe.
And so if you break something in your system, you don't also want to lose all the latest
Excel files you were working on, right?
You want those to stay, and so the idea is with time shift, you can just roll that right
back.
All those Excel files.
That's your example?
I don't know.
I like your picture of the typical Mint user right now in your head.
That's what that was.
Yeah.
Hey, spreadsheets.
All right.
Okay.
Well, that actually makes a lot of sense because a lot of times you'll have maybe your most
personal or important stuff in some public cloud storage with the permission set to public,
or you'll have them in Dropbox with a single encryption, or you'll throw them on sync thing
that isn't actually syncing because it's always breaking on you, and they won't actually be
only in your home directory.
Come on.
That's how it goes, right?
That's how it works.
But you could add it.
It's just a matter of going in the configuration and adding it to backup.
Yeah, absolutely.
So you could do it.
We did not, though.
We just had it focused on the system, and we wanted to...
I did add a few.
Oh, yeah.
Well, I did add some of the files in that we don't ever really change, but just some
like handy binaries that aren't stored in the usual system.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
And then, of course, we actually excluded the recordings themselves.
Absolutely.
We don't need to back those up into a snapshot.
We just really want to restore the configuration state so we can record again.
That's really the main thing.
And because we have committed ourselves to keeping these systems fairly up to date, we
don't do it like every day, but, you know, about once a month we upgrade all these boxes.
And so we do want to have an escape hatch just in case something goes wrong.
Snapshots can be restored by just either using the GUI, which is nice.
It comes with a GTK GUI.
Or you could boot into another live environment, and you can restore using a live environment
too, as long as you can access it.
Yeah, really mess things up.
So I'm going to pull it up.
Let's take a look at it right here.
Yeah, it was very easy to get started with.
I'm going to...
And, of course, what really put us onto this was the people that were writing in when they
were explaining why they use Mint talked about how Timeshift had saved their bacon a couple
of times.
And it's nice because when you go in here, you can look at individual snapshots.
It has a big green badge saying that it's active.
It gives you a big number on how much available storage you have and how many snapshots have
occurred.
All just clearly listed right here.
And you didn't have to set anything up.
That's just how it shows up.
And it will automatically set up cron jobs for you to make sure it takes those snapshots
on time.
Yeah.
So that was the thing is when people wrote in there, like, you really got to go use this
because it really makes this simple.
And now I can see it.
I can really appreciate it because it's so simple.
You can right click right there and you have mark for deletion.
You can do file management.
You can browse the files or it's one click to just restore that entire snapshot.
And you can have a field in here.
So if you want to go back in later and say, okay, I'm taking a snapshot.
You can add comments.
So you could say this is our pre-upgrade snapshot, you know, and I can leave a little note here.
So if you showed up to record tech snap and something wasn't working, you could go in
there and say, oh, Chris did that upgrade.
Yeah.
That's really nice for multi user systems.
Mm hmm.
So I had something happen the other day and I thought, oh, Jack, it broke.
It finally, it finally broke on us.
And I got ahold of you and we troubleshot it for a little bit and ended up like just
having to like restart pulse or something.
But it was at that moment, I was thinking to myself, hmm, I really need to get going
on this recording.
So I wonder if we, if we had a snapshot system is so a time shift kind of came on our radar.
I thought this is going to be a perfect solution.
So we loaded it here and um, I don't, I don't see any reason why we're going to stop using
it.
I think we'll just keep using it on our production Kubuntu system.
Oh no, now it's XFCE.
It's a Kubuntu install with XFCE.
I'm curious though, um, you, you can schedule this in like a cron job so that you can dump,
uh, maybe have like three backups, dump the oldest, create a new one sort of scenario.
Yeah.
It has, um, some retention configuration set up already.
So you sort of choose like how often you want and how many you want to keep and it'll do
all the, all the updating and rolling for you.
Yeah.
And it gives you a nice GUI for going and setting the location for adjusting the cron
schedule so you don't have to be a cron expert.
Yeah.
I'm looking at the GUI now and the GUI looks actually fantastic.
Uh, it really does look like a quality piece of software.
There is, um, one issue you may run into, which we did, uh, as I was trying to add a
couple extra things in the home directory.
There is a nice little filters part, so you can sort of add, excludes or include files
specifically, uh, on sort of regex style patterns.
That doesn't really work in the GUI, uh, turns out any rule and what you add stuff, but that
never doesn't make it to the config file.
There is an issue open.
It seems to just be a recent regression in the latest release and thankfully the config
file is just like a simple JSON file.
So you can, there's already some filters in there.
You can see how it is.
Just got to copy and modify a couple of lines.
I'm close to calling this a, I must load for any system where you are really serious about
needing to get back up and running or a family member, if you deploy a Linux box for a friend
or family member.
The nice thing about it was that, especially because of the R sync support, you know, we
didn't have to do, when we set up the server with snapper and stuff, we spent a while considering
like how are we going to do this file system layout?
What's the right thing with time shift, just installed the PPA, got it going.
And that was it.
We spent 20 minutes of just playing with it and now we haven't thought about it.
We have all these snapshots.
Yeah.
And I love our sync.
You know, that's good.
If you use the butter FS support, there is a couple of requirements on how you have things
laid out, but they're totally reasonable, but just worth checking before you use the
butter FS support.
Well, Brent just joined us, Brent, have you had a chance to look at time shift?
You got any thoughts on it?
Yeah.
You know, I've seen time shift.
The first time I saw it was in Linux mint, I don't know, a few years ago and that got
me kind of excited about it because of the our sync backend and I'm a huge, huge fan
of our sync because of its, you know, robustness.
But also because I know like a tool like this, I love seeing our sync in the backend because
I know that if for any reason time shift stops working the way I want it to, I understand
what's happening on the sort of on the bottom end, you know, so I can use tools I'm familiar
with to diagnose something that's going wrong with the backups if that ever happens.
So that is some pretty good peace of mind.
Yeah, that's a great point.
It's not some magical special backup format.
It's just directories or butter fs snapshots.
Mm hmm.
Now it looks like reading around on their website that you'll get unpredictable results
if you're pointing at containers and stuff like that.
So beware, this is more for like a workstation snapshot.
That's the ideal use case.
I think.
Yeah, this looks really cool.
I haven't had any experience with this project yet, but one thing I'm wondering is if they'll
integrate ZFS snapshots at some point, I think that would be super, super cool.
I saw someone on their GitHub offering to start working on ZFS support and then contribute
it back.
So that could be in the works.
I agree, especially with 2004 shipping ZFS.
I would love to see that.
Now, Mr. Payne, we do have some feedback to get to, including one from Troy about new
users and Linux Mint.
He writes, Chris, I've been listening to your show since the Linux action show days
when Brian was around and I love the shows.
Love the work.
Keep it up.
I was just listening to episode 339 of the Mint Mindset and I just wanted to give some
feedback.
I know with your background that the show is probably focused more towards the geek
community than the average operating system consumer.
Most people in your sphere of influence are programmers or inspired by the bells and whistles
that people seem to love.
Now, come on now.
He's that Troy.
OK.
He's probably right.
He's probably right, actually.
Most.
Yeah, OK.
Well, OK.
Go on.
Continuing on.
I don't think he was accusing me, but he's probably right.
I mean, we do like the shiny.
He goes on.
Well, I work for a computer service shop in our area.
We make most of our money supporting the various bugs that occur in Windows computers and doing
virus cleanups and so forth.
However, we've gotten more and more requests from customers, both businesses and home users
about purchasing computers or upgrading their computers to Linux.
And after trying a large variety of distributions myself and trying with different customers,
I have to say that the feedback they give us about Linux Mint is how similar it is to
Windows 7.
And they love it.
They love it.
Linux Mint is not only easy to use, but it looks sexy as hell.
It also allows for geek and power users to get things done as well.
I met several people, including myself, who run Linux Mint web servers.
So there you go.
All right.
Last bit aside, which frankly scares me a little, I think the point of like this is
working for users.
They like it.
It's an easy transition.
It's important.
I agree.
Um, I guess what matters the most right there, I know there's nothing really else to say
about it.
He says, I guess he writes up, I guess I'm saying don't always look at everything from
such a high level since most computer users are just average consumers.
They want to use it and get their daily tasks done.
I think we agree with that, actually.
And I think that's a lot of times where we've even wondered if Linux is the right answer.
And I think elementary OS and Mint are telling us, yes, I would also wonder, Troy, if you
had a chance, I'd be curious to know what the feedback would be for something like Ubuntu
Mate 20.04 when it comes out.
Maybe try slapping that on a few machines because I recently gave the daily ISO a go
for Mate 1.24 and it is looking real good.
And it's not Cinnamon, I'll grant, Cinnamon does have that Windows 7 vibe going, but it
still has that traditional paradigm and 20.04 will be supported for a long time and it seemed
really good.
Daniel writes in with a question we've gotten a couple of times.
It's about these ThinkPad T480s.
He says, in episode 323, you mentioned a shim is being developed for the T480 fingerprint
reader.
This was back in October and it seems that the official drivers were released for almost
everything bad except the T480 and a few other models.
As far as I know, there's no official development going on for the fingerprint reader, but maybe
you could get an update on this because if there is, I'd like to know or if it's been
abandoned.
Thanks in advance, Daniel.
Unfortunately, I don't have any updates on official support.
There was a project over on GitHub to reverse engineer the protocol and add support that
way.
They made some progress, I guess, on the specific model that's on this ThinkPad.
It will initialize and the LEDs work, but scan doesn't work and unfortunately, at least
on the master branch, the last commit was like a year ago.
Oof.
Oh, see, I kind of heard a rumor it was in development, but I bet it was that.
Here's hoping though.
Oh, well, just a couple of more.
One more from Jason and this one is so cool.
I had no idea, so I'm so glad he wrote it and he says, not sure if y'all heard of this,
but there is a community plugin for Cockpit called Cockpit ZFS Manager.
He says it's a great plugin to help those that are used to a GUI style of managing ZFS
from FreeNAS, but are moving over to ZFS on Linux.
It's still in the alpha beta stage for the developer and requires Cockpit 201 or greater
and Samba because it can also do some Sambasheer stuff.
I think we're going to have to give it a try.
This does sound pretty cool.
He says, maybe the JV community could show the developer some love.
I agree.
I think that would be really cool and he says, love all the shows.
Hopefully one day I'll find time to join in live.
Well, hopefully that, hopefully it wasn't going to be this Tuesday because we're not
here.
I'm in the courthouse.
That is really neat.
I didn't actually need it, but now I want it.
Right?
I mean, just thinking back on our fake names there, Cockpit was one of our favorite parts
about using Fedora on that system and having ZFS support would have been perfect.
And you know what was great about that is we totally had no intention of even really
trying out Cockpit much, but we kept getting little notes from the audience saying, hey,
you should try out Cockpit.
Hey, let's check it out.
And they were so right.
Will writes in with our last one and it's a shorty.
It's a prediction for the show.
He says, follow up prediction for Wes's Bcash prediction.
If BcashFS does make it upstream in 2020, Jupiter Broadcasting will be using it in production
before the end of the year.
I think that's pretty solid.
Seems right to me.
I mean, I'm absolutely putting it on my laptop for sure.
And I use that for production.
So I mean, come on, how great would that be?
I've just said it too many times.
I have to install it once it's there.
Bcash for the root file system, ZFS for the data, ButterFS for my home.
I'm a happy guy.
That's like a perfect setup for me.
I'm all about that.
It's all about seeing how many different file systems you can use at once.
I mean, that's the great thing about Linux, right?
It's all about choice, Wes.
Okay, we have a really cool app pick for you that I'm going to let Wes pick or tell you
about because he found this pick and he wants to geek out hard on it.
It is pretty neat.
Yeah, okay.
You've probably heard of JQ, the handy little command line tool for manipulating JSON, making
JSON queries, that sort of thing, right?
It works really well.
But a lot of the time, at least on the Linux command line, you don't always have JSON.
I mean, we do have the Unix philosophy, so you have this text output, but I'm sure we've
all been in the experience of, okay, I just want to grab the IP address field and now
I have to like grep and awk and cut and it just gets to be kind of a mess.
It's almost a little embarrassing too when you think about things like PowerShell where
they do have a lot more structured output.
I was going to mention that, yeah.
So I mean, we're not there yet.
Some tools, I learned this today, IP route 2, the new IP command, that has a dash J flag
and it'll output JSON for you right there, so boom.
Some of this is handled, some newer tooling does have integrated JSON support.
But for everything else that doesn't, there's JC.
It has a whole bunch of built-in support.
So if you have a handy, classic Unix tool, you just bypass that as a command line option.
It'll ingest the output, it already knows how to parse it, and then give you JSON right
out.
Whoa.
Okay.
That is legitimately geeky cool.
I mean, it's definitely a hack, but I think it's better than everyone rolling their own
little parsers all the time.
We can at least here have a sort of semi-standardized community to make sure they work well.
Check out the link in the show notes if you want to visualize what Wes is talking about
because they have some example outputs on there.
This is one of those where people hear about this and they're like, huh, okay.
And then one day they'll need it and they'll be like, what episode was it you guys talked
about that had that JSON thing that now I need for some weird arbitrary reason that
I never expected I would need?
It's episode 341.
So you can get those links at linuxunplug.com slash 341.
If you'd like to send us a pic or send us some feedback like we just read, linuxunplug.com
slash contact.
Please do.
I really liked that one.
That was pretty good.
And we'll have links to Timeshift and Richard's article and all the other things we talked
about in those show notes too.
And of course, those are found in your podcast catcher of choice.
And if you haven't enjoyed our chapter markers yet, why not take a look?
Yeah, give it a try.
It's pretty nice.
And it's also very easy to jump back to a topic if you ever need to.
So those chapter markers are great.
And we thank our great editors like Joe and Drew for making those possible.
Thank you, Drew.
You're very welcome.
And of course, Joe, but he's not here.
I don't think Joe.
Come on.
Gotta give him a hard time.
All right.
Well, hopefully everything will be back to our regularly scheduled Linux Unplugged program
on our regular Tuesday day at noon Pacific.
You can get that converted over at JupiterBroadcasting.com slash calendar.
I'm at Chris Ellis.
He's at Westpane.
The show is at Linux Unplugged.
See you next Tuesday.
OK, I think I could use some advice kind of on topic, too, with what we've been talking
about.
Lay it on us.
So I've got access for a limited time to Hedia's clinic machine.
Like I said, this run, I think it's 1604, it's got to be.
What do I do with this thing?
Do I attempt to, say, replace like all of the repos that it's like the Telegram, PPA,
the Chrome repo, there's several that aren't working.
Do I spend the time to get all that working again, if it's even possible on 1604, and
then just update it and she just stays on 1604 for a little bit longer?
Or do I try to bring her up to 1804?
Or do I just wait and just skip this window of opportunity and just take her straight
to 2004 in maybe a month or two?
Well, but the thing is, I don't...
Can you wait that long?
I don't know if I'll get access to it again.
How risky is it?
But what's it do?
What's the use case for it?
So what's it do and how risky is it are both really good questions.
So what's it do right now is essentially just information input to web applications or some
light printing and scanning.
It doesn't do a lot.
So it's been perfectly fine on 1604 with Unity 7 and all of that for ages.
I think 1604 was a new release when I put it on there, which is crazy.
Right.
Wow.
I haven't really been super motivated to throw it on the latest and greatest because they
like Unity and it works.
But things like Chrome and Telegram are yelling at her that they're going to stop working
because they haven't been upgraded in so long.
And those are kind of essential to the workflow.
I know you guys have been playing with 2004.
How crazy would it be to put her on like a development release considering we're kind
of close?
Is that out there and too wild?
I don't know if I have like a really authoritative opinion on it yet, but my initial impressions
have been the 2004 is close to daily drivable, if not there already.
It seems like it's been pretty solid.
But I've been mostly using the Maute version.
So I don't know about the Gnome shell side of it, but I've heard from others that it's
solid.
My inclination would be to go ahead and document what all they have installed on there and
actually use and then take them to like 1804 Maute.
And when 2004 Maute comes around, it should be, if you find another upgrade window, it
should be pretty easy to roll them up to 2004.
But if I don't, no big deal.
They're on 1804 and it's going to be supported for a while.
Yeah, exactly.
And I'd go ahead and enable live patch too.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, that's pretty solid, I think.
And maybe make a backup before you get started.
Put time shift on there.
Seriously.
I'm going to write a note.
That's actually a really good use of it for her.
That's a perfect use case example is this is a front office computer that they want
to book appointments on and scan information into.
And I've got to keep it up to date because it needs to be secure.
But we can't have a break either.
And that GUI, assuming they can at least get to the desktop, that GUI is totally usable
by them.
Yeah, it's very intuitive.
I think that would be a much easier transition from Unity than, say, GNOME or even XFCE
or Cinnamon.
It's going to feel a little different, but not so much that they can't find what they
need.
Yeah, I could use that mutiny layout too.
Yeah, could do.
That pre-configured layout.
Oh, that might be really nice.
Thanks, guys.