You guys see this TechCrunch is running the story about Avast did this report this morning
that reveals a new form of malware on the Google Play Store, which begins to display
advertisements disguised as warning messages to end users when they unlock their Android
smartphone.
So like, I guess it waits?
Wouldn't that be just a different version of like any other website than just on mobile?
Because I remember like some websites try to freak you out and just...
Well, I think the particular one here is that you're not opening an app.
It's just happening as soon as you unlock the device.
That's what it says.
They show a card game that it's embedded in, an IQ test game, a history app were also found
to be infected.
Well, yes, it's like as if people haven't learned by now, don't install random IQ test
apps.
Well, I think they haven't.
Yeah.
So here's a video of it.
Let's see what happens.
Let's find out.
So they got an Android device here and they say, okay, now I'll unlock it.
Oh, when they say unlock it, they don't mean unlock the phone.
They mean unlock the screen.
So when you unlock the screen, it brings up you an urgent prompt to do something at the
Google play store and then it gets your stuff.
Okay.
So I misread unlock is actually like unlocking the device, but they just mean disabling the
screen protection.
Okay.
That is much more, that is much, that, okay.
That's a bigger problem.
That's going to hit a lot more people.
I'm slightly confused with the difference between unlocking the phone and unlocking
the phone is.
Well, unlocking the screen just to wake it up versus like unlocking the phone to move
it to a different carrier or like rooting it.
Right?
Yeah.
Right.
So it's just when you enter your pin code.
Yeah.
Or slide a little thing, it comes up and yeah.
Hmm.
I didn't know that Google ever had urgent warnings or something.
No, I don't.
I guess it's all.
I need to update software.
It normally just shows up as a notification.
I guess users probably wouldn't know that though.
I just can't fathom.
I mean, I, I don't know what it is, but I just can't fathom why people switch distro.
I mean, I get it if you're a distro reviewer, I get it if you are, well, I get it if you've
got ADHD or some other medical condition that forces you to like must have change, must
have change.
I get that, but I can't for the other 90%, I can't understand why people do it.
I know a lot of people change distros because of the experience they had inside of a distro.
I don't know, I can't change so much that I, yeah.
Distro hopping makes no sense to me.
It's got to be.
I always try to settle on a distro, but if something happens, then I might switch.
It's got to be the grass is greener thing.
You know, you get frustrated or something just isn't quite right.
It's not quite how you want it.
You know, in this case, Unity is great, but now Eric's having problems with compiz and
maybe he keeps having problems with compiz and something wears him down.
He starts thinking, gosh, you know, I'd really like to try this.
And so I think it's like a grass is greener kind of thing.
It's partially that, but for me, it's also a matter of, okay, there's something not working
right in this case, but it works right over here, so let me try that for a while, see
how I like it.
Right, but in your house, if you didn't like the wallpaper in the bathroom, you don't knock
the entire house down and build a new one and then wallpaper the bathroom.
You don't?
You fix the wallpaper in the bathroom.
Well, no, I just switch out the furnace.
I find that it's because the current distro I'm on doesn't actually reach my expectations
and I just want to move to another one.
The other thing with me is I just like to try it out, see what it's like, basically
because, and that's one of the things that is cool about being a distro hopper and being
a producer for this network, I can offer a lot of valid input based on a plethora of
knowledge.
Here's the undisputable facts, all distributions have little wiggle points that people don't
like that drive them crazy and make them want to use a different distribution.
Ergo, everyone should just use Arch, fix the problems that don't work for them, and enjoy
the master race distro.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's jonesing for that new Raspberry
Pi.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
Hey there Matt, I'm not normally the guy that gets into these really small gadgets, but
when they're talking three to six times the performance, maybe I could throw Mate on that,
you know, maybe even go, I'm just thinking, you never know, so now I kind of want one
for 35 bucks.
We're going to talk more about it in the second half of the show.
It looks like a pretty cool gadget, and of course we've got folks in the mumble room
that are all about them Raspberry Pis, so we'll get their take on it.
But before we get to that in the show this week, we're going to get a little recap of
Fossdom.
Unfortunately, and maybe this will be the last time, I don't know, I'll see after I
get the report.
We weren't able to make it out to Fossdom, but that is across the pond, and it is a great
open source conference, and Poppy and others in the mumble room made it, and they're going
to give us their update.
I think I'm going to be totally jelly too, so that's cool.
I think that's going to make me go next year, but we'll find out.
So I think it's going to be a good show, Matt.
Nice.
We've got a lot of stuff to cover, and we also got some surprisingly great feedback this
week.
I was like, I don't know, I don't know if I really want to do feedback, and then I saw
this stuff, and I was like, okay, we've got to talk about this.
So before, just to make our first email a little more poignant, I want to talk about
a development that's recently occurred, and it's been talked about in our Linux action
share subreddit a bit.
It's not technically Linux news, but you'll see why I want to bring this up, but it's
come out that Google, Amazon, and Microsoft are reportedly paying the ad block extension
that you might have in your browser to allow their ads to pass through ad blocks filter
software.
The confidential details were conferred by the Financial Times in a paper that came out
on Tuesday that we were recording this.
So I mention that because that brings us to our first email.
So to cover our first email, let's bring in our Mumble Room.
Hey, Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, guys.
Hello.
There's lots of people.
I'm hungry for pie.
It is a lot.
So yeah, we will get the pie.
So guest one wrote in specifically addressing the Mumble Room.
It says, hello, everyone reading this email.
During Linux Unplugged 77, the Mumble Room commented that ad block is heavy, and I'm
here to present you with a solution.
It's called uBlock, pronounced uBlock, and it's a you-decide-what enters your browser.
uBlock supports Chrome, Firefox, Opera, and Safari, and it's licensed under the GPL3.
And he links us to it on GitHub.
So I just wanted to pass that along to the audience.
I'm not a big fan of ad blocks because A, people have got to get paid, and B, if that's
how people want to represent their work and their website, then I think I should be able
to take that into my judgment about their property.
And when I block the ad, sometimes I don't see some of that, and I don't see some of
the decisions they're making from a content standpoint.
And so I make maybe the incorrect judgment, not to point out and single out our buddy,
Mr. Michael, over at Ferronix.
But I had been a user, I've been a reader of Ferronix for a while with, sorry Michael,
but with ad block turned on, and I kind of had a rethinking of this, and I thought, boy,
I really shouldn't do that.
You know, the man deserves to eat, and I'm reading his stuff.
So I disabled my ad blocker on Ferronix, and I was so taken aback by pop-up ads and cover-up
ads.
I really haven't gone back much anymore, just because it was so off-putting.
And I felt like that gave me a different impression of the website when I had ad block on versus
when I had it off, enough that it changed my opinion about visiting the site.
Well, I can kind of give you my perspective on it, both as a publisher and as someone
that visits websites.
So I've worked with, so I guess the long and short of it comes down to this.
I will take ad block and whitelist any site that I plan on visiting on a regular basis.
I want to support them, I dig them, they're great.
Now if it's a website that I want to visit on a regular basis that is going to pollute
me with crap, then that gets a little sticky.
I may, in fact, just ad block them and figure, hey, I'll support them in other ways that
we'll find something else to have happen.
Maybe I'll promote them or talk about their stuff or some other way of supporting them.
But ad blocking software is a tool that allows us to choose how we want to interpret our
content.
The problem is that, especially in the tech community, ads like banner ads and AdSense
ads and things like that aren't terribly effective.
They're historically not.
They're very effective in non-tech circles, but in tech circles they're pretty, it's pretty
hit and miss.
Right.
I kind of just tune them out.
Yeah.
People want engagement advertisement.
I mean, well, they don't necessarily want advertisement, but they tend to respond better
to that.
So anytime you've got something on a webpage blinking at you, especially with pop-ups,
I mean, come on.
Right?
Yeah.
Nobody needs that nonsense.
No.
It's a bad experience.
So anything you can do to block that.
Yeah, let's get rid of it.
Get it out of here.
Heaven's Revenge, you had some comment on the uBlock project itself.
Yes.
I've been using uBlock ever since it was coded up.
I love it.
It uses half the RAM of Adblock Plus, and it gives a lot of preset block lists in their
configuration.
And it actually helps pages load a couple of milliseconds, maybe 150 milliseconds faster
than when you're using Adblock Plus.
No kidding.
Yeah.
I'm going to check that out.
They say, here's their philosophy, uBlock is not an ad blocker, it's a general purpose
blocker.
uBlock blocks ad search support of the Adblock Plus filter syntax, but it can work with custom
rules and filters.
That's really interesting.
Yeah, it's completely compatible with all the Adblock syntax, and I recommend it here
quite often.
Wow.
It actually says that the overall memory footprint is less than with no blocker running.
How can they claim that?
It's because when you actually go and you block things, and it isn't triggered by it.
Oh, sure.
Doesn't have to load it.
Makes sense.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And way less CPU usage, too.
Yeah, well, Adblock has gotten big.
I'll give you that.
So uBlock it is.
Well, not only that, but it sounds like they've completely sold out for what they were trying
to do to begin with.
Yeah.
And these guys got lots of graphs, lots of statistics.
Yeah, they do.
I'm generally a bad person.
I just block everything.
Well, I just installed it, and I'm really impressed.
This is, wow.
It's also really easy to block things.
You don't have to right click on loads of menus.
You just have to click on that giant power button, and it blocks that site.
It stops blocking that site for you instead of you having to go through all these settings.
So uBlock sounds like it's a hit.
It's a little bit unusual.
Oh, this is awesome, dude.
Yeah, you got to check this out.
If you want to create your own custom filter, you'll get used to it.
It's really different when you make your custom filter.
But other than that, it's good.
Tyler, I wanted to give you a chance to chime in.
Oh, I recommend it anyway.
Oh, yeah.
I just wanted to add, you know, sometimes I feel you don't even need an Adblocker to
get rid of the annoying stuff.
Just block Flash from the get-go and block certain scripts.
That's not a bad catch-all for sure.
Yeah.
All right.
Christian wrote in.
Check this out, Matt.
How cool is this?
And then he says, I'm from Vivaldi, and I want to talk.
We were talking about the Vivaldi browser last week, because I'm a long-time Jupyter
broadcasting fan, which is super cool.
And I listen to all your tech shows as soon as they come out the door.
I also happen to work for Vivaldi here in the US, although I'm a Norwegian.
We're a company with developers and business people all over the world, but I'm located
outside of Boston with a couple other employees of Vivaldi.
Before Vivaldi, I worked in Opera since the end of the last century, which is also when
I installed Linux for the first time, and I've never looked back at any other OS.
We are, of course, very excited about launching Vivaldi, which is the browser we hope Opera
would become.
And Linux is important to us as both as other OSs some people use and our own.
Keep up the good work, and make sure to be always supporting Linux.
How cool is that?
That is so awesome.
I love that.
And I love the fact that he reached out like that.
Yeah.
Christian, we'll see if we can't sync up and maybe have you on a future show to talk about
what you guys are doing.
And maybe if you can, talk about some of the interesting things about developing the browser
for Linux.
I'd be pretty curious about that.
So I'm really glad to email this.
I'm glad I caught it, too.
It's awesome.
Because you never know.
And, of course, we want your emails, too.
Go over to jupyterbroadcasting.com, click the contact link, and choose Linux Unplug from
the dropdown.
We have one more quick email and then two shout-outs to get to, but first, I want to
tell you about something amazing, and that's Linux Academy.
Go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplug to get our special Linux Unplugged discount.
They want to give the Linux users a special discount because they're super passionate
Linux users.
That's where they were Linux Unplugged got started.
It's a resource for you to use to further your own education, and the reason why I think
Linux Academy is something specifically for our audience to consider is because if you
are going out in the field of anything around Linux or any major open source technologies
like OpenStack or even AWS, there's training in a lot of places, but none of them are like
Linux Academy because Linux Academy was created by Linux users themselves who are crazy passionate.
They considered launching a podcast network and then decided, well, Jupyter Broadcasting
has got that down.
So let's do something else.
Let's do education, and they have developers that they brought in and educators they brought
in.
In fact, they have live streams with the educators, which is a great experience.
You can ask those questions in real time.
They have so many amazing courses for you to take.
I like to talk about some of the newer ones because I think they're really on the cutting
edge of the latest, coolest technology in Linux, the stuff that you probably want to
keep your skill set fresh on anyways, which is another really great benefit of Linux Academy,
but what I'll talk about, what I've started doing is I just started taking the Ruby on
Linux courseware.
And that's another thing I love about Linux Academy is a lot of the online educational
resources out there, you could go learn Ruby from other places, right, and what's it going
to tell you to do?
It's going to tell you how to set up your Mac to do Ruby development, but that doesn't
apply to me, right?
But Linux Academy is designed by Linux users for Linux users.
So everything's for Linux users.
So it's getting set up and developing in Ruby on the Linux desktop, right?
That closes that gap.
That makes it so much more useful for me and I look at that and I say, okay, well I'm going
to take five and a half hours to learn Ruby.
I can wrap my brain around that.
I get that.
That is an achievable goal, something that I can attack.
It's not this big nebulous thing, how the hell am I going to learn Ruby?
Oh, I'm going to learn Ruby because Linux Academy has coursewares on it and it's going
to take me five and a half hours.
That's how I'm going to learn Ruby.
That is kind of the confidence and direction that I need to actually get off my butt and
do it.
And they have learning plans where you can set your availability so depending on how much
time you have free, the courseware will automatically adjust to that and send you reminders for
that.
Think about that.
That's crazy.
Cool.
And you can download the study guides on the go so you can read when you have a little
bit of extra time including like the walkthrough stuff so you can listen to it as a podcast
which is really handy if you're in the car.
Why not spend some of that time when you're done listening to your JB content, go into
education mode.
Switch from one type of Linux content to another type of Linux content.
Your brain's already going to be in that gear.
It's a really cool service.
I want you to go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
We got that special discount for you.
You'll see why you want the discount once you check them out.
Go try out some of their courses.
You can pick from seven plus Linux distributions.
The courseware will match that distribution.
The labs when they spin up virtual machines for you which is a really cool system.
I got a little bit of the inside scoop on how it works too so I'm pretty impressed from
like a system administration design standpoint too like how they have some of this stuff.
It's damn impressive because they're really passionate about it.
So I can respect that.
I know like what I love is like okay the courseware, guess what?
You need a virtual server, they just spin it right up on whatever Linux distribution
you chose.
It's good to go.
You get an address on there.
You can SSH from your desk.
You know so you get really great performance while you're working in the lab environment.
It's crazy cool because they get you and they get Linux.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the
Linux unplugged program.
Love hearing the success stories too so keep sending those in as well.
Those are great.
All right.
So I wanted to just cover one more email.
It comes in from Chuck and this is kind of exciting.
We've been kind of kicking back and forth.
Different production software for Linux and of course Ardour gets mentioned all the time
as Audacity, Okan Audio got mentioned.
But something really high-end, multi-track, do mixing, do audio like a music kind of stuff.
So Chuck writes and he says you mentioned Ardour being a little cumbersome.
He says I agree.
I've used it for years but when you need to do high-level production, you can't beat the
latest offering from Bitwig and he links me to it and I'm going to bring this up here
in a second.
He says it's amazing.
It's like cleaning up podcast, making production music, live DJ sessions by piping mix into
it and piping that out to IDJC.
Just something worth checking into.
It does have a hefty price tag.
I thought okay, this might be interesting.
What kind of, is this like some sort of like weird old like XUI kind of app for audio editing
and because I hear a lot of this.
I hear a lot of this.
Oh, you got to check this one out.
It's really, it's a good one.
And then it's never.
It looks like 1995.
Yeah.
It's never a good one.
No, man.
This is a good one.
I'm checking out.
They have a blog post up about their next version.
The UI looks amazing and there's a little bit of a video here I'm going to play and
I'll just play just a little bit for the audio listeners.
Don't worry.
It won't go too long.
But it's pretty cool and it gives you an action.
If you're watching the video, it gives you a chance to see the UI in action which is pretty
sweet.
So it's available for Windows, Mac, and Linux, it's called Bitwig Studio.
Now here comes the UI.
So there's the recording UI.
Now you got, I don't know for those of you watching the video version, this is a super
pro level UI that easily, easily matches Pro Tools or Apple's Logic easily.
Wow.
That's actually, wow.
I actually want to look into this.
Yeah, me too.
I'm geeking out right now.
Yeah, this is, I'm looking at some of the audio stuff.
It's just so sweet.
So Bitwig Studio.
This looks like one of the coolest audio editors I've ever seen on any platform.
So I'm going to give it a look probably later this week.
Do they have a demo?
I hope so.
I'm sure they do.
Yeah.
There's a demo on the page.
Anytime, any big ticket item like this in software always has a demo.
They just have to to survive.
But that's just, wow.
Take my money.
Yeah, take my money.
I know, right?
Should we see how much it is?
Let's see if we can find out.
Let's see.
Oh, it's on sale.
So let's take a look.
Let's see.
It's on sale, guys.
Jeez.
Oh, actually it's doable.
You know, for a high end piece of production software, $300.
I guess.
No, that's actually less than I figured.
I guess it's on sale.
So I don't, I don't know.
That's about what I figured.
So the demo worked out and everything.
I mean, honestly, $300 for really high end audio production, a software that has a good
solid UI on Linux.
Exactly.
And cross platform too.
Yeah.
I mean, I'm all for it.
Yeah, of course.
I will keep watching.
I would keep watching the open source software too, but this seems like a really nice piece
of software.
But this illustrates a real defining point of, I love using open source apps, but honestly
I'm going to use the tool on Linux that works.
I'm sorry.
I just am.
You know?
Yeah.
That's just me.
So here's what we have going in the Linux action show subreddit and we could use your
input.
Number one, first up, producer Q5Sys created a thread.
Your help needed coming up with a list of the best GNOME tweaks and extensions.
And this will have linked in the feedback section of the Linux unplugged show notes.
It's also currently sticky to the top of the subreddit.
Now here's the thing.
We've gotten a lot of extensions, which is cool.
Like I'm totally trolling it and like adding a few more extensions to my GNOME, which you
know is a great idea.
But we haven't gotten a lot of straight up tweaks and hacks.
Now don't freak out.
We're not going to try to say, hey, this is great ways to break your GNOME.
But if we were going to have a little fun, like if we're just hanging out and having
some fun, what are kind of things that you do to GNOME to make it more better beyond
just an extension?
Now extensions are welcome too, especially if they're not well known.
We'll have it linked in the show notes.
There is some future content coming down the road that may use your answer.
I'll just put that out there.
Q5, anything you want to...
Did he leave?
No.
Not really.
He's kind of still here.
Yeah.
Well, he can chime in later if there's anything he wanted to add to that.
No, I just dropped into another channel because of mic issues.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Is there anything you wanted to add to my coverage of your thread there?
Is that good?
Just basically, yeah.
We're looking for more than just extensions.
Yeah.
Okay.
If that's other applications or other things that work well with GNOME that make you enhance
the desktop experience, we want to know about it.
I've got a hack.
It's called Cinnamon.
I was going to say, made in material.
Okay.
The next thread I want to give a little attention to, which AUR helper do you guys use?
I wanted to give a link out to this because we might do a roundup of this very soon.
And I wanted to kind of get everybody's input.
Right now, pack AUR is leading the pack.
I'm surprised how many people are saying your word, you masochist.
So go over to there and put your comments in there.
Any other kind of like Pac-Man tricks and techniques you have?
Yes.
I know it's arch-specific.
Don't worry.
Don't get...
We're going to do it for other distros too, but we're just experimenting with it because
XOO started up and I thought, Hey, you know what?
Let's do this.
So we're going to do a roundup of some of the tips and advice people give in there.
And then we'll do it again for future distributions as well.
So don't worry.
I'm sure next up on the list will be one of them Debian based distributions.
I hear those are popular.
I hear people like to use those.
No, it's a myth.
Aren't you on 14.04 Ubuntu Mate edition right now?
I am and I'm proud of it.
Yeah.
I'm actually quite happy with it.
It's definitely different.
Do you count to how many PPAs you have set up right now?
On this machine.
This is my...
I think maybe two.
I just don't use that much stuff.
That's not bad.
Yeah.
You know?
Maybe three.
I'll be generous.
So I guess...
Seriously, here was my most recent run with an Ubuntu based machine is I did 1504 alpha
two or whatever it is to get the latest KDE Plasma and I had about three or four PPAs
and within about two weeks of using it I was getting a 404 on one of my PPAs.
Uh-oh.
I don't know.
That just drives me crazy.
It's a small complaint.
It's not a big deal.
But it's a great OS.
Yeah.
And it's something I would like to see evolve because I'd love to see the PPA system evolve
into something better.
I'm definitely open to that.
That'd be awesome.
What I find to be pretty interesting is I don't know if you saw that Dell's going to
be shipping a couple of Linux laptops.
And one we knew about and another one that's a larger laptop and on both laptops they're
going to use Ubuntu 14.04.
Not surprised.
I mean, because a lot of times people when they're buying a system, if they're buying
it pre-installed, they probably don't give a rip about bleeding edge.
They probably just want it to work theoretically.
Yeah.
And so that makes sense from and from a support perspective.
But here's what's interesting about the decision.
The kernel in 14.04 doesn't have Thunderbolt support.
So the laptop will be shipping with an unusable Thunderbolt port that may get updated later
in 14.04.
Again, thinking of the fact that it's who's buying the laptop and what their general audience
is.
I just think it's interesting.
I think it's still, yeah, I think it's something that hopefully they disclose clearly because
that could definitely be a real problem if they're boasting the port and then it doesn't
work.
That's a big no.
I think it means 14.04 is a clear winner.
I think, I mean, I guess they couldn't really ship with 14.10 really, but yeah, I just...
Well, and how does Dell do that?
So it's like, okay, so they're presenting this new laptop.
They've got this port they're probably talking about.
Do they disclose that in their materials?
They must, right?
They must.
I would hope so.
Just hope so.
Wizard Jed, you wanted to toss in, if you found yourself in this position, there is
an option, right?
Yeah.
I actually had this problem itself.
I needed 3.16 and I could not go and use the kernel that was in 14.04 itself.
And anyway, so to go and get it, there's actually backported kernels themselves inside of every
single LTS for every version above it.
I didn't know about that, but that's something you got to go and read the Ubuntu Wiki about.
Ah, well, here's good news.
And I was wondering if this is true.
I knew they were going to do hardware enablements for 14.04.
Well, JBLive, who just joined the chat room, said that there's going to be a hardware enablement
stack in 14.04.2, which will be released in a couple of days.
So that works, right?
So pretty much by the time anybody gets their hands on these, the update will be out.
So once you get your machine and you install an update, you'll be okay.
It's not so bad.
There you go.
Yeah, you reboot and you have Thunderbolt.
Hey, isn't that kind of magic?
See, 14.04, I tell you, it's a pretty solid release.
All right, Matt, well, hey, guess what?
We're going to do a recap of FOSDEM, a conference that I think this is almost, I'm almost going
to run out of excuses why I can't go, especially since I'm going to be going to Canada soon.
But first, I want to tell you about the great folks over at DigitalOcean who are now rocking
FreeBSD, CoreOS, and a bunch of other great distributions.
Head over to DigitalOcean.com right now to spin yourself up your own server up in the
cloud that you get root access to in less than a minute.
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
simple way to spin up your own server.
It feels like I am the master orchestrator of my own data center.
And here's what you get in less than a minute for $5 a month.
Let's go over there.
It means crazy, right?
Think about that.
Less than a minute and for $5 a month, 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU,
and a terabyte of transfer.
DigitalOcean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam,
and London, like I always mention, if you're like me, I'm not even kidding.
I like data center porn so much that I really do, and that's why I always mention the DigitalOcean
as the pictures of their data centers up on their Instagram and their G Plus feeds.
So here's how I am.
I went over to, there's a brand new hotel that just opened up here in Smokey Point,
and I kind of wanted to check it out because I think we're going to be sending the host
there when they arrive.
I'm not sure.
We might move hotels, right?
Because this is brand new and it's fun for when people come in out of town to stay in
a new hotel.
That's a nice thing, right?
And so I've got to go check it out.
I've got to check out the Wi-Fi, right?
I've got to go make sure the crew is going to be taken care of when they come in for
Linux Fest Northwest.
These are the things you do as a podcaster apparently.
So I go over to this Best Western, and I'm walking around and I'm kind of getting the
lay of the land.
I'm looking at what the conference centers were, and the guy, the manager who's running
the place, he happens to walk out, and I started asking him questions about the infrastructure.
I say, hey, can I see your server closet, and he actually lets me in.
I mentioned I used to work in IT, so I'd warmed him up a little bit, but I'm so interested
in how people have their setups.
It's just the coolest thing to see how different people do their configs.
So I got him to show me the server room, and I'm like, okay, this is pretty great.
It's not exactly what I expected.
I'm like, you're not managing all your telco and Wi-Fi equipment here, right?
That must be in a different room.
He's like, yeah, it's upstairs.
And so we go up, we ride the elevator up a couple of floors, and I go look at their telco
closet, and I was like, this is awesome.
That's why I'm always over the DigitalOcean page checking out some of their pictures,
because not only do I appreciate the fact that all their technology is running on Linux,
which I love, sitting on top of KVM, which is the boss, all on top of those SSD drives
that DigitalOcean invested, and then they connected to tier one bandwidth in those data
centers all over the world with this interface, right, this super simple, intuitive interface,
which is really simple.
I mean, it's so amazing how you can move a machine between data centers, back it up and
restore that snapshot, create a machine based off another snapshot, do DNS management, set
up SSH keys, HTML5 console, like, but it's like crazy in your face easy, and on top of
all of that, all that power, like if you want to get nitty-gritty, can be replicated with
their straightforward API.
And people will just be building apps like crazy for that, so you can take advantage
of that, too.
So go check out DigitalOcean, but here's the thing, this is what you got to do, you got
to support your favorite unplugged, right, this is your favorite talk show, Linux Unplugged,
you got to support that.
So use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, and I'll give you a $10 credit over at DigitalOcean,
which is really nice, too, and I like this a lot, is you can kind of get started without
even having a credit card, because you can just apply in a balance, so if you got a couple
of bucks in your PayPal account, you just pop that into your DigitalOcean account, but
you can get started for free with our $10 promo code, try out the $5 rig, two months,
$5 rig.
That's awesome, right?
DOUNPLUGGED, go build our own cloud, go play with CoreOS, go try out BitTorrent Sync, why
not do SyncThing, I mean, GitHub, or GitLab, Ghost, I mean, the list, I mean, the crazy
list goes on, and there's a bunch of one-click deployments, too, I could just go on about
how great it is, and how it's, for me, like, whenever I just know I need, okay, I need
a Linux rig to do something, I just spin it up right there.
I'll tell you, and when you're running something for clients, and you're like, okay, well,
I don't necessarily want to run anything on their stuff initially, I want to run it on
mine, transfer it over, makes transfers easy.
DigitalOcean.com, DOUNPLUGGED, all lowercase one word, when your face is over at DigitalOcean,
and a big thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring our faces.
So FOSDEM15 wrapped up a free software event for developers to meet, share ideas, and collaborate.
They say every year, thousands of developers of free and open-source software from all
over the world gather an event in Brussels.
I wish I was there.
But Popey was there, and I've been, Popey's been trying to tell me about it all morning,
and I said, Popey, save it for the show, don't tell me anything, Popey.
So Popey, I've got to start, I'll ask Alan's question, did you see the BSD people at FOSDEM?
Nope, not a single one.
Sorry, Alan.
I probably did, I probably did, I probably bumped into them in the corridors, it's absolutely
rammed, the places that you say.
Thousands?
Is it really thousands of people?
So the biggest room they have is a lecture hall, it happens at university in Brussels,
and the biggest room they have holds officially 1,400 people, and it was pretty rammed on
more than one occasion, and all the other rooms get full as well.
So yeah, there's a lot of people there, it's a very, very busy conference.
So it was-
Yeah, like I was just looking at it, and you know, the conferences I'm used to, they're
at most four talks going on at once, and I think there are 24 happening at FOSDEM at
a time.
Wow.
Right, yeah, so they have it split up into a number of tracks, so you've got like a
desktop track, distributions track, internet of things track, Go track, you know, you've
got developer, separate developer rooms for Mozilla, for Java, MySQL, you know, it's all
grouped nicely, so you can, you know, you know where to go, because a room is dedicated
to a particular topic, so if you're MySQL heavy, you would go to that room, and if you're
interested in most of the Mozilla talks, you'd go to that room.
But they have an app that you can put on your Android or iOS phone, and a website where
you can see the entire schedule, and you can bookmark the talks you want to go to, and
then your phone will, you know, ping you when that talk's coming up.
This is really impressive.
This is like the best-
It's unbelievably well-organized.
Yeah, this is like the best system we've ever seen.
Look at this.
This is incredible.
I'd schedule, I'd put in my bookmarks on the way there, what I wanted to go and see, and
the app updates over the air and lets you know, you know, when talks are going to be.
I haven't been for like five, six years, and this is my first time for a while, and it's
just as I remember it, it's, you know, information dense, there are a lot of very detailed talks,
there are some high-level ones, like a little introduction to what, you know, some project
here or there is doing, but there are some detailed ones, and they cover a really wide
gambit.
You don't have to be focused on just one topic, there's so much there.
So I went to, I'll give you a few highlights of what I went to.
One was one from fWatch, which is a GPS watch made from free software, free hardware, 3D
printed case, components you can buy off the shelf to make your own GPS watch, make your
own apps, to have a thing on your wrist that you have total freedom over.
That was cool.
I went to a talk from the Tizen, not Tizen, Yola guys actually, both the Tizen talk and
a Yola talk about both had a talk about porting their platform to other devices, which was
good to see.
One about, there was a there's a legal room, which was surprisingly busy, a bunch of lawyers
standing talking about the intricacies of licensing was, you know, pretty rammed.
That room was pretty densely packed all the time.
And that was interesting to listen to their interpretation of upcoming laws in both EU
and the US and whether they will impact the validity of the GPL, which obviously is going
to have an impact on lots of people at a free software conference.
So that was that was pretty interesting.
And there was also one on in the legal room, there was one from Bradley Coon, who gave
a retrospective of a GPL violation that he had to deal with.
And it's a very interesting talk.
And it's called fighting a GPL violation by coding instead.
So instead of suing someone, they fork and, and continue developing under a different
name.
And the good news is that the FOSDEM organizers videotape all of these, I say videotape, and
I sound like I'm from the 80s, but they actually record it onto SD cards or some brand new
technology I haven't ascertained yet.
And they put them online.
So you go to the FOSDEM website, you can see a lot of these.
But there's so many awesome talks.
The one I think one of the most oversubscribed that I couldn't actually get into the room,
the room was full was Lennox talk on system D 2015.
What's new in system D, it's been reported on in the press by people who were there.
People were like live tweeting, Lennox talk.
What does that make you think when you hear that, right?
Like here's a here's somebody who live blogged it.
And he notes that there was no slides, none whatsoever, no presentation, he just talked.
Right, he had notes on his phone in front of him, I think.
But yeah, no, no slides, he can just, you know, he's a bit of a superstar, isn't he?
You know, when we go to somewhere like FOSDEM, where there's, you know, 1000 or more people
who want to get into a room and listen to this guy talk about something that's very
fundamental to the platform that they're developing on or developing for.
Of course, they want to listen to it.
It's it's like our equivalent of queuing up around the corner to an Apple Store to get
a you know, a new iPhone, you queue up to listen to Lennox talk about what's coming
in a piece of software that he's developing.
I think it's much the same thing.
I had a couple of just not to derail you because I'm loving the cover.
Sure.
I had a couple of quick things that he did talk about because I know you didn't make
it in the talk, so I just wanted to call out a couple of things.
Console D, support for higher DPI screens on the console, systemctl cat, systemctl edit.
You can cat the config file of any unit so you don't have to know where the actual config
file is, but you can do systemctl cat Apache 2 and it will just cat Apache 2's config
file wherever it is on the file system.
That's something that's coming.
Ping gateway, automatically resolve the gateway of all interfaces and ping them.
Very useful for network troubleshooting and questions like, am I online?
The ping gateway gets resolved automatically, so you actually just type ping gateway at
the command line and it will ping your gateway for you to see if your network is up.
Here's a big one.
Network D, because networking is such a basic function of the US, Lenart believes it should
be part of system D, so they want to roll that in.
Auditing, improved application auditing, he says it was for the NSA, can log all system
calls made to etc password, etc to the audit log.
Network D adds support for multiple resolvings, DNS cache per interface.
Journal D remote, so a whole new remote system for the journal D. The binary logger now gets
remote support via HTTP.
Journal D has a pull and push model, pull HTTP get and request for JSON streams from
the journal.
Push model pushes via an HTTP post request to the remote journal D instance, allows for
simple implementations of programs like via PHP and Ruby to send data to remote journal
D endpoints, since it's just an HTTP post.
They're talking about the log here, people, that could replace this log.
Time sync D, the idea it's not to run NTPD on every device.
It's very simple, trivial, not a server, as simple as possible, NTP client built into
system D. Automatic GPT partition table discovery, even if you don't have an Etsy FS tab, which
is sometimes absent on stateless systems, a lot of things going into system D for stateless
systems.
I'm giving you the highlights here.
You can read more on the page.
But it'll do auto discovery of GPT, discover swap devices, and root partitions even without
any flags in the Etsy FS tab.
Also I'll tell you that the thing that's most exciting in that list for me is high DPI port
in the console.
Yeah.
You know, being able to run Linux, Lynx web browser and high DPI mode on a TTY, it's just,
you know, I've been wanting that for years.
Finally, right?
The last one that's getting some controversy in our mumble room.
They are discontinuing read ahead.
They say in the age of SSDs during boot, they don't really have it.
None of the system D developers even have spinning hard drives.
All system D developers have SSDs, so nobody really wanted to support it anymore anyways.
And they say the read ahead bits needed during the boot process aren't really needed with
SSD drives anymore.
So I'd agree with that.
What about those of us who have spinning hard drives still?
It's still so minimal.
Well, technically they kind of pointed out that, yeah, it didn't make enough of a difference
to bother maintaining it even, you know, despite the fact that it was, there are people that
are still going to not have SSDs.
Yeah.
The main problem was is that it was read ahead only really gives you a bonus when the, whatever
application that is benefiting from read ahead is programmed poorly.
So as people went and actually fixed the applications, it became less and less important.
Yeah.
So Popi, how was the, what was the culture like?
Did you guys eat a lot?
Was there a lot of beer or a lot of eating?
It happens in Brussels and Brussels has a reputation for having lots of beer.
And in fact, the conference starts on the Friday evening, really everyone meets up at
a bar called Delirium and you need to get there early if you want to get a table, otherwise
it's standing room only and they have loads of different beers, many, many different types
of beer and it's all delicious.
And it's great because there's a great atmosphere in there and you get to see all the famous,
you know, free software luminaries who all go there for a beer.
And in fact, it's so busy that I had to queue to get out of the bar.
It was that busy.
Oh boy.
It's, it's, it's completely rammed inside and rammed outside.
And there's bars at Fozdem as well.
So once you get to the actual venue at the university.
There's bars at the university?
Oh yeah.
Loads.
Oh hello, hello.
Yeah.
So there's street vendors selling Belgian waffles and you know, other kinds of food
and then yeah, there's, there's bars all around the place so you can have a couple of beers
while you're, while you're watching a talk or at the end of the day, you know, relax
and digest, you know, I just wanted to mention a couple of, yeah, it's a very different culture.
It's one of the reasons it's part of the culture of Fozdem is, you know, it's, it's very information
dense in places.
That's great.
Equally.
Yeah.
So it's a very, very social.
Yeah, I love that.
Social meetup.
So I just wanted to mention a couple of other things that are worth looking up if you can,
if you find the videos.
One of them was a talk that I, I was surprised I, I didn't think would be spun out for 25
minutes.
I thought, wow, it's gonna be five minutes and we're going to be out of here.
And it's by a guy called Daniel Stenberg and he's the author of Curl.
You may be aware of Curl, the command line tool that allows you to communicate with servers.
And it was really interesting because I didn't realize how widely Curl was used.
Oh, sure.
And what it could do.
Yeah.
And you know, there's millions and millions of installations.
Every company uses it.
Probably every person in the room in his, in the guy's talk had a device that had Curl
or libcurl on it.
That was, it was quite interesting to learn, you know, the ubiquity of something like Curl.
Right.
And the final one that I wanted to mention was a guy called Ryan McDonald who gave a
talk called Living on Mars, a beginner's guide.
And it was the closing keynote and the room was rammed with over a thousand people, I
would say.
And it was all about how he's applied for a position on the Mars One mission to go on
one way trip to Mars.
And he talked all about the plan and the preparation and some of the pitfalls, but also how they're
using open source in the whole project.
Cool.
It was brilliant.
It was, if any video you should look up, look up that one.
It's very, it's very positive, very forward looking, actually made me think that mankind
isn't completely living on Mars.
I will have it linked in the show notes.
I just found it.
Good one, Poby.
So that was that, was that your favorite keynote?
Yeah, that was one of them.
I mean, they were all brilliant and I've got so much to think about and I took loads of
notes and I learned lots as well.
So and I, I took on board lots of information from other communities as well.
So it wasn't just sat in the Ubuntu room all the time.
I learned a lot from Tizen, from Yola, from Mozilla and from lots of other projects as
well.
So it was, it was totally worthwhile and I'd highly recommend anyone goes.
If that was on the West Coast, would you travel the distance to go to it on the West Coast
here in the United States?
If someone else paid?
Yes.
Okay.
Somebody else paid.
That's always the trick, isn't it?
Yep.
Well, that's, I really want to go.
And so they do a course every year.
Yeah.
But it's in the beginning of February, it gets announced kind of mid, midway through
the year, like August time or something like that.
And everyone starts booking their hotels or their train or their, their plane journey
pretty early on.
All the public transport in, it's funny, you're going to stand at a bus stop in, in Brussels
and it's just nerds everywhere.
And it's quite amusing when they get on the bus, they're all trying to figure out how
to use the ticket machine and you can spot the newbies who are getting on the bus at
the wrong end.
That kind of stuff.
That would be me.
Hilarious.
Yeah.
It was me as well.
Well, good.
I, geez, I, uh, I hope that more of the videos come out.
I, I, when I looked around on YouTube this morning, I saw a, uh, a lot of, uh, from 2014.
I haven't seen a lot from 2015, but I did see a couple.
Right.
Well, I mean, as Alan said, there's so many tracks, so much video content they've got
to get online.
I would think they're, you know, just about now, a couple of days later, having a hangover
recovery and, uh, they'll start getting them online soon.
Uh, so before we, uh, totally move off, uh, just one quick SystemD thing, uh, there's
also a blog up, uh, on how, uh, Plasma Desktop will use SystemD and in short, they're going
to rely on Lognd for a lot of things, uh, and including, uh, device management, uh,
and the inhibitor locks that Lognd offers where, uh, devices can get root, uh, something
like the login manager can get root access to the keyboard and mouse without making it
available to other applications.
Uh, they'll probably take advantage of time, date, D, uh, and other things, so user units,
so quite a bit of things coming, uh, in down the road for KDE relying on SystemD, too,
so 2015.
Yeah, and they, the KDE stand was, um, was quite busy.
There's a bunch of stands, obviously, exhibition area, and, uh, they had a few, uh, PCs out
with, um, the latest version of Kubuntu with Plasma on it, and I had a little play with
that.
Nice.
Um, it was nice to say hello to them and all the other projects that were there.
It was really good.
Did they recognize you?
Uh, a couple of them did, but, you know, I keep a low profile, try and wear a funny hat
or something.
Did people recognize your voice?
Like, once you open up your mouth, they're like, oh, are you Popey?
No, I'm not, I'm not as well known as you think I am.
Oh, I don't know.
I don't know.
I bet.
I was waiting for Alan to flip a table on that SystemD with KDE stuff.
Well, they're working on, they're working on their, uh, shim.
You know, they got a shim.
Yeah, that's true.
That's true.
Uh, all right.
Well, Popey, that was, uh, that was a great update.
Thank you very much.
I'm a totes jelly.
Totes jelly.
Uh, all right.
Well, uh, so I know something that's on the, been on the back of my mind all week.
I don't know.
It's got me especially kind of excited.
I'm also curious to see what producer Q5 says, thanks, uh, cause he's a big Raspberry
Pi fan.
The new Raspberry Pi 2 is out and we're going to talk about it here in a second, but first
I got to mention my buddy's over at Ting.
You know, I got a Ting device now for like two freaking years and it's unbelievable how
much money I've saved.
It's like $2,000.
Uh, I should take that savings and buy Bitcoin right now while it's on.
Isn't Bitcoin on sale right now still?
I think there's still a Bitcoin sale going on.
I think it is.
Yeah.
So I could take some of my Ting savings.
Buy up some of them Bitcoins.
Uh, Ting is mobile that makes sense and the reason why I say that is because they're finally
doing it right.
There's no contract and you just pay for what you use.
It's, so you pay for a $6 just to have the line.
That's it.
Just $6.
$6.
Okay.
And then it's just your usage on top of that.
You turn on hotspot, you just pay for the data.
It's not a big deal.
Uh, and they have a great dashboard so you can manage all of it.
I like that a lot too because that's always been sufficient for me, but they even have
no whole customer service if the dashboard won't do it.
Here's what I want you to do.
Go to linux.ting.com.
Not only do you get to put Linux in your URL bar, which is always good for your internet
history and you know it, you know you need to sanitize that by putting some tech stuff
in there.
linux.ting.com.
Okay.
That'll give you $25 off your first Ting device.
Oh, you got a Ting compatible device because you checked their BYOD page.
Good news, my friend.
They'll give you a $25 credit that will probably pay for your first month.
It did for mine.
Uh, I've got three devices right now.
I think my bills are on $35, $37 usually.
It's great.
Go to linux.ting.com and go check out their blog too.
They've always got some great stuff over there.
I'm, you know, as somebody who's a Ting fan for a long time now, I'm always like, is Ting
feeling the heat?
Well, guess what?
People have been wondering that and Ting answered.
So I thought we'd play a little bit of that.
Kyle asks, is it easy being Ting and do you feel heat from the other carriers for being
different?
Well, I think there's two things there.
One, it is incredibly easy being Ting.
You know, I think what would, what we can't imagine is how hard it would be to be one
of the big traditional telecoms.
For us, all we're trying to do is save people money and make them happy.
That is really, really easy to do.
Sort of trying to trick them, fool them, not provide great value.
That would be hard.
And the good news is we're still well small enough that they don't notice us at all.
I think that we certainly do get noticed for some of our innovation, but we're not threatening
anybody yet.
We have to get many times bigger before that's true.
Go to linux.ting.com, it's linux.ting.com.
That's actually the lyrics to that song, Matt.
Did you know that?
I thought it was.
I mean, the jingle just gets stuck in your head and I'm humming it all day long.
Linux.ting.com.
Exactly.
Thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show.
Guys, go check them out.
I'm really happy for a long time and they're adding GSM support soon, which is going to
be making them like the mega carrier.
That is so exciting.
It's going to be interesting to see who basically says, oh, hey, wait a minute.
I got one of those phones.
Yeah.
I ran it through the compatibility thing.
That's right.
Hey, this could work.
Hey, yeah.
In fact, they're also giving out some, which, oh God, this is the phone I want so bad.
The Moto X2.
It's the new Motorola X with the five inch screen.
They're giving out some of those for people who sign up for the Ting GSM beta.
You can find out more on their blog.
Ooh.
They're feeling so bad.
No kidding, right?
Hey, Matt, did you see that there's a new Raspberry Pi?
Oh man, I see it.
I've been living it.
I've been like trying to come up with use case scenarios on why I should just buy it.
Well, here's what we know.
Okay.
So it's still going to be the same $35.
It's still the same about shape and size as the Raspberry Pi.
It's got a quad core 900 megahertz ARM A7 CPU.
They say about six times the performance.
I've heard speculation otherwise.
One gigabyte of memory.
It's a 2X improvement over the previous model.
And it is totes compatible with the Raspberry Pi 1 as far as the GPIO pin layout goes.
And because you got yourself an ARM 7 process in there, you're going to get yourself a lot
more serious things like Ubuntu snappy core, more different versions of Android.
And ladies and gentlemen, wait for it.
You guessed it.
That's right.
Windows 10.
And proprietary software is not ethical.
Yeah.
It's going to be able to run Windows 10.
Ooh.
That's going to sting a little bit.
Yeah.
A little bit.
But you know.
And then I think people will be like, oh, this is horrible.
Look at this UI.
I get my, I get my Raspberry.
It's too much.
They got too much going on and they released the B plus not that long ago and now they
have this one.
I don't, I mean, whatever.
But.
Well, it'll be Windows 10 chump edition, obviously.
I mean, that's probably what it's going to be on there.
So.
Bentley, I'll open the floor to you, sir.
Yeah.
I, like I said on Coder Radio, I don't like it.
I think the having Windows on it was awfully not good for open source and it seems like
the first step in Microsoft's whole, um, the three years I'm not remembering off the top
of my head.
Embrace.
Extend.
Extinguish.
Yeah, exactly.
Uh, yeah.
I guess so.
I don't think so.
I think it's actually going to make Microsoft look like a chump.
I think it's going to be a clown show.
They're going to show up late to the party.
They don't even have shipping code right now.
Right?
Linux has already had shipping code for years.
They have a totally mature ecosystem around it.
Uh, Windows is going to come to the party.
Is it even going to have a GUI?
Do we even know if it'll have a GUI or is it just going to be a command line version
of Windows?
What's it going to run?
What apps is it going to run?
Who's going to make apps for Windows on an, on one arm device?
Now it's not going to be one arm device for long, but let's be serious.
It's like Raspberry Pi is running Linux or production ready to be like the glue that
holds the internet of things together or like this weird web server that runs your coffee
machine or like this thing that's your XBMC media entertainment system.
We've been there for a while now, right?
Windows 10 showing up way late.
It's like everything Microsoft does.
They're just way late these days and it's, it's going to, you know, a few people will
use it.
It'll probably show up at few high schools for, you know, a few high school teachers
will use it and you know, students will, it's fine.
It's fine.
But it's not, it's not serious.
I'm not worried about it at all.
I think it's going to be a joke.
I do like the irony of the fact that you're pointing out, Hey, Hey, has it even got a
GUI?
Isn't it just a command line version?
Which is exactly what they used to say to us.
Well, here's why I bring that up because there is an expectation with windows, right?
With Linux.
That's maybe the advantage on a raspberry PI is no GUI, but with windows, like you tell
me I can run windows 10 on it while I'm starting to get a picture of the modern UI and my start
menu.
Like I'm starting to visualize or windows.
Yeah.
But people are using the raspberry PI for the wrong thing.
They're using it as a cheap computer, cheap desktop computer, and that's just not what
the raspberry PI was about.
It was about teaching people how to program, teaching people how to code.
It's not about running a desktop operating system and browsing Facebook on a cheap computer.
Yeah.
No, I guess that's what a stream PCs and Chromebooks are for.
Mr. Q5 Sys, you're a resident raspberry PI fan.
What are your thoughts on the new fancy raspberry PI?
For me, it's too little too late.
As I mentioned in Coder Radio, I don't see why anyone would go out and buy this if they're
actually looking for a decent system other than if you're just already a raspberry PI
fan.
The raspberry PI 2 specs are actually less than what you can get if you get the Odroid
C1 and they're the exact same price.
They're actually even the same form factor.
You can use the same cases and accessories between them.
The raspberry PI 2 does come with the quad core 900 megahertz chip, which people have
claimed will reach 1.1 with a mild overclock.
Whereas the Odroid C1, it comes at 1.5 gigahertz, still a quad core, but it's been overclocked
to 1.7.
For me, the biggest drawback on the RPI 2, the raspberry PI 2, is that it's still a hundred
megabit networking.
The Odroid C1 has gigabit.
Now it's not a full absolute hundred percent gigabit.
I actually reached out to Jason, the lead developer with the Arch Linux ARM port and
talked to him and he's talked with the hard kernel devs.
He was trying to get me the actual throughput from them before today's show, but kind of
had a communication disconnect.
He said that in his recollection that with iperf that the Odroid C1 will do 400 megabit
up and 900 down.
The NIC is a big thing.
It seems like the NIC is the full gigabit, it's just the processor can't handle the
event stuff.
There might be some optimizations you can do there, some tuning that can happen later
on that might improve that.
The biggest question that's been going around in raspberry PI circles itself is, why did
they drop this raspberry PI 2 just a few months after they dropped the B+, because we all
went out and just bought the B+, because it was the newest one and now, oh look, there's
another one and this is what we wanted to buy, but they didn't give it to us.
Here's where some good old conspiracy bacon comes in, because there's two prevailing theories.
One is that they took a page from Apple's handbook and put out the B+, so everybody
went out and bought it.
Then when everyone realized that it had shortcomings, they then released the actual item which everybody
wanted, so everybody would go out and buy it the second time.
The second theory is that the raspberry PI 2 was actually slated for a later release,
either later this year or early 2016, and the reason that the raspberry PI foundation
pushed it forward was to try to actually take back any market segment that Odroid would
claim with their C1 device.
Hmm, I mean, I don't know-
I imagine the B+, was probably later than intended, and then because of other things
like, you know, we saw the BeagleBone and there's like a hundred of these little devices
now that they decided to try to rush the-
Yeah, and I mean-
I don't buy it at all.
The PI 2 has been under development for a while now.
They've been working on that with Microsoft and with other partners as well for some time.
I don't buy that there's a significant competition from the Odroid at all.
I think Odroid is big in geek circles, but Raspberry Pi have a massive mindshare in the
educational sector, which is where they target.
Well and I just want to-
Yeah, and I think-
I want to just mention, we're not talking about $400 iPads, we're talking about $35
Raspberry Pis.
Yeah, and I think that is why Windows is kind of getting involved, is because they're looking
at this as something that they can bundle and package for education.
They can get a bunch of them, have a Windows version for it, and sell thousands and thousands
of them direct to school boards, school systems as, here's something you can deploy, instead
of going buy these units by yourself and then you go ahead and set them up and do all that.
That's where I worry about Microsoft coming in, because they've got the money and resources
to kind of do a complete package like that to sell them and market them in mass quantities
and they can work with a reseller and that's a little bit harder for the Linux side.
But I think when you look at the momentum where Linux is the platform that runs across
all these different devices, not just Raspberry Pi, it's got the years of development ahead
of Windows.
Just the momentum there will keep the Raspberry Pi running Linux in the majority forever,
I think.
But I agree.
I think there are going to be some areas that are susceptible to Windows running on the
Pi because of Microsoft's ability to organize those kinds of things.
Well it does seem like it's something that's old platform.
The integration with their platform, there will be developers out there who are already
.NET developers using Visual Studio on Windows and they want something which is a portable
embedded system and the first place they turn is Windows.
So for them it's perfect.
For people like us where the first place we turn is, right, what can I find that runs
Linux?
They'll go, you'll go Odroid, Raspberry Pi, BeagleBone Black and a whole bunch of others
and we've got a lot of options.
Raspberry Pi seems to be the only option if Windows is what you want.
For now at least.
I can't imagine that'll last.
Well then there's the Intel Minnow board and a couple of others but there's not a huge
selection, nowhere near as huge a selection as we have.
We have a lot more choice there, which is ironic really.
I think that this is just the first step since Nadea has come on board with Microsoft.
They seem to be back in their habit of looking to the long term goals and not just the short
term things.
And I think that on the Raspberry Pi 2 that this is Microsoft's perhaps their first step
into the ARM market.
I fully expect them to create more trimmed down versions for some of the older Raspberry
Pis and I wouldn't be surprised if they don't actually put out a version for some of the
stronger ARM boards out there like the new NVIDIA TK1 that has the Tegra CPU and a hundred
and ninety two CUDA cores and it's, you know, system on a chip, small board, small form
factor.
Could be, yeah, could well.
All right Colonel Linux, you have something you wanted to add.
I just wanted to get in there that every other time in history when Microsoft has tried to
scale Windows down, they've always seemed to fail.
Like when they try and put it into like Windows CE or Windows Mobile, those kind of things
don't seem to work.
Whereas Linux has always been, because it by nature it exists very, very small and we
scale it up to meet needs and that has always seemed to work very well but when we need
it to remain small, when we need it to be able to fit on a small embedded device, it's
always done very, very well.
Very true.
It seems to be, you know, the fundamental way Windows is built.
They have to tear it down to make it work whereas Linux, you build it up, you build
up.
Right.
And that approach is even apparent like I definitely noticed that as a difference in
philosophy when I switched from Windows administration to Linux administration full time and the
security model back then on Windows was sort of open by default, secure one by one by going
through a checklist of group policy settings and all these kinds of things and on Linux
it was ports are closed by default and you open them up when you need them and those
kinds of things.
It's the same kind of philosophy only in how the whole system is built.
We'll see.
So I'm not too worried about it but guys, any other thoughts on the new Raspberry Pi
or Windows running on Windows 10?
Not even out here.
I've ordered one so I'll let you know when it arrives in a couple of days.
I want one too.
I was tempted by it too.
I'm just not sure what I would use it for.
The really nice thing about the whole thing is that the VC4 driver that so much work has
been pushed into is going to work on the Pi 2 because that is the one thing that when
I heard the Pi 2 I thought, oh my goodness, I hope that they don't just throw all that
work that someone did reverse engineering the Pi's graphics for nothing and it's going
to be there.
So it's improved graphics though but it's just the same driver?
It's a free graphics driver.
The VC4 is the reverse engineered open source graphics driver that was made for the Pi.
Well, if anybody out there tries it with Windows 10 let us know how it goes, I guess.
Go to jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Hey, that would be a good spot to send in any kind of feedback for the Linux Unplugged
show.
Just go over there.
Send it in to us.
That's a good idea.
I kind of want one, Matt, but maybe if I could come up with a good segment idea.
I think that $55 isn't bad.
It's not bad and I think honestly you want to set it in front of people that aren't geeky,
that perhaps are thinking, yeah, you know, I could use a new computer but I don't have,
you know, $500 to spend, if you can park it in front of someone that really gets value
from it, that would be really cool to see.
If it really is six times the performance, too?
Well, how many cores did it?
It was like...
Four, yeah.
At 900 megahertz.
Yeah, I mean, it just depends on what kind of a desktop environment you're running and
how you're rocking.
Yeah, yeah.
And how it launches the browser.
Yeah, that's how Facebook pages load, right?
That's what's going to be...
That's right.
But I look at this and I think, you know, the Pi itself was already a pretty competent
media machine.
You give it something more performance, I think that could be something really interesting
here.
Well, and you bundle that with YouTube switch to HTML5 from Flash, thank God.
Yeah.
You know, it's like a little bit easier on the arm side, doesn't it?
It does.
Yes, it does.
Interesting.
Well, there you go.
All right.
So if you'd like to help contribute to any of our shows, there's a couple of ways you
can do it and we'd love to have you help.
Something I don't mention too often on this show, but as we are spinning up the How To
Linux show, we'll be funding the launch of that via our Patreon.
We decided initially that we're not going to do sponsorships on the new show.
We've had offers too, which is super rewarding to have sponsors just sort of preemptively
say, hey, we'd love to sponsor that.
But what we've decided to do is be genuine to just as tight of a focus on the content
as we can initially.
And we have some runway because of our Patreon model.
This is...
The Jupiter Broadcasting Network is sort of multi-funded.
We have sponsors and then we have the audience funding.
And that gives a sort of leverage to opt not to have sponsors or be picky with the sponsors
and sometimes launch shows without sponsors.
And we could do that even more if we have more support.
We're kind of getting to a point where we need a little more help from the community
to take on some of the future expenses like How To Linux.
And we may eventually, depending on how that show goes, if it really sees a lot of traction,
spin that off into its own Patreon just so that way that's sort of easily distinguished
all on its own.
But initially, as we sort of get things going and we take that cost on, we could use your
help over at patreon.com slash today.
You have the Tech Talk Today video on there, but this funds all of the shows on the network
and Tech Talk Today is a daily tech show that I do to sort of say thank you to the patrons.
There's also behind the scenes videos over there, including the death of the last Hackintosh
in the Jupiter Broadcasting Studio is available to people who support us over at patreon.com
slash today.
So that's one way, direct value right there.
That's obviously another way you can...
That's like the most direct way you can support us.
You can also help content-wise, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Submit links, app suggestions, comments, and votes.
That feeds both the Linux Action Show and that feeds Linux Unplugged and in some ways
it also is going to be feeding How To Linux.
So that's a really important nexus point you can go that helps contribute to all of the
shows, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
You can also join us live.
We do the show live Tuesdays, Pacific over at jblive.tv and you can go to jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone.
I'd love to have you join us.
We have an open mumble room.
We call it our virtual lug and it's available to you to come take advantage and tell us
about the things that are on your mind in the Linux ecosystem.
We also do pre and post shows where it's just kind of an open mic and we chat.
So jblive.tv, you can go in there, get the mumble room information and join us.
Also hang out in the chatroom, help name the show.
It's a good experience and it happens every single freaking Tuesday.
We'll do episode 79 next week, Matt.
Are you feeling like 80 around the horizon?
I'm feeling it a little bit.
It does feel like it.
I have days to where I feel 80, but it'll be nice to celebrate 80 in a more positive
light.
Oh wait.
Nope.
You know what?
That was a little gas.
I'm sorry.
I thought that was 80.
That was just a little bit of gas.
All right, everybody.
Well, thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Go over to the contact page, send us in your feedback.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Okay, chatroom, it's your last chance.
Go bang suggest.
Get your title suggestions in there while you still can.
We'll go boat here in a minute.
Go boat.
Go boat, everybody.
Hey, I saw a really cool video.
It doesn't work so well in audio, but Popey, I don't know if you're, are you still here?
Yep.
So I saw this great video that makes me want an Ubuntu tablet real bad.
Hang on.
I'm just, I'm not actually watching the livestream, so that's okay.
It's all right.
It's a, so, uh, pop pop you sore in or whatever, pop you sore in whatever his name is.
Oh yes.
Yeah.
Uh, he made a video.
Uh, let's see.
When did he post this on the video?
Yeah.
Yesterday.
This is really great.
So watch those of you watching the video version.
It's it will be linked in the, if you're on the audio, but he sort of fades in.
He realizes running on the desktop and then he expands the app out and I'll just kind
of re expands.
I like it.
It's nice.
It's still a little touchy, but it's a nicely edited video.
Actually.
It gets me fired up states of the app.
Yeah.
That's good.
That's exactly the kind of advocacy you need because people, you know, they can wrap their
brains around it.
It looks really good.
There's basically two guys who wrote that app, but that music app, Andrew and Victor
wrote that with some designs from the design team.
It's I just love what they're doing.
Yeah.
That is really good.
So I will, uh, I'll have a link to that in the post-show show notes.
If people want to watch that and I'll drop in the chat right now.
All right.
Okay.
JBtitles.com.
We got a vote on this thing.
Chris, that bitwig demo is a 145 megabyte depth file for Ubuntu, just so you know.
I'm sorry.
Did I laugh out loud?
My bad.
No, I'm sure it's an upstream.
Probably arch it up.
Pretty easy.
Oh yeah.
Uh, okay.
So pie to win.
That's not too bad.
FOSDM nerd herds.
That's not bad.
Straight out of FOSDM.
Oh, I kind of like that.
Yeah.
I got to get a beat going.
I kind of like that.
That's kind of straight out of FOSDM.
A little bit of NWA going on there.
Yeah.
I could see that.
All right.
Go over the titles.
Go vote, everybody.
We got to get you a grill.
Got to get you a grill.
There we go.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
It's going up to the top of the charts right there.
There it is.
Very nice.
All right, guys.
Well, I think we're going to go with that.
Boy, that was one of our easier titles.
That was really easy, actually.
Something I didn't mention there.
Have you ever seen a key signing party?
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
They do those there?
Yeah, that was a massive key signing party.
It was going for like two hours.
I went into a talk and came out and the people were still there.
They're standing in a line.
Yeah.
Right.
So imagine like two lines of people facing each other, like some kind of weird country
dancing thing, right, where they're facing each other and they've all got these little
notepads and they've all got their government issued ID and they've all got their like printouts
of their keys and stuff.
And when they've done, when they've done someone, they just moved down the line to the next
one.
And they were just there for ages and ages, all these people signing each other's keys.
It was amazing.
Yeah, that's a good way to do it.
I wonder if Keybase.io would help with that.
Yeah, maybe.
All right.
Well, I guess it's time to put my pants back on.
Yeah, that'd be a good time.
Yeah.
All right, guys.
Thanks very much.
Good show.
Cheers, Chris.
See you next week.