Headline the anatomy of a linux user by ken stark, and i'm just going through here
Her computer was a decent machine a mid 2005 asus desktop with a dell 19-inch monitor
Unfortunately it had all the toolbars and pop-ups that a windows user can collect when not properly tendered
After getting all the files off the computer we began to product the process of installing linux
We sat together through the installation process, and I made sure she understood partitioning process inside of an hour
She had a bright and new shiny pc linux os
desktop and I think
that right there
pretty much
Exemplifies most of the people that I end up switching to linux right it's that easy it is it's that easy
And it you take hardware that already existed and is no longer useful, and we make it useful again
There's a lot of power to that that is so happy hacking
This is linux unplugged episode 147 for may 31st 2016
Welcome to linux unplugged your weekly linux talk show where we've kicked your host out of his seat and made him the soundboard operator
Where he let the batteries die in the mouse?
My name is Noah. My name is Wes welcome Wes pleasure to have you here, Noah all right, so this week
We have a ton of stuff coming up in
Linux unplugged we're gonna be talking to Ryan from mycroft. We're gonna be talking about openSUSE
I know that you've installed remix OS
Which is you've somehow decided to take your useful laptop and relegate it to an Android device
And we're gonna talk about Yubi keys which I have gone on the record numerous time extolling their
virtues and as it turns out they have turned from a
Open-source company into a closed-source company, and I just bought some but does that really matter. I don't know we'll find out
We'll talk about it and of course every week. We have to welcome
The mumble room which sometimes I forget about so hello
mumble room
Oh my gosh, we have we have a full mumble room and we have beer
Those are my two favorite things in the whole world beer this week is
Almeda Brewing Company Alameda
All right, so gentlemen with the beer tell me how the beer is
Hmm well, so hold on yeah, hold on still here. We got we I got him
I got a beer and West got a different beer. I got the pale ale from Alameda
I have their IPA the click a cat or clicky tat clicky tat. I think yellow wolf. It's pretty good. It's actually pretty good
It's from Portland, Oregon
It's from so the I'll be just be standing by in the background drinking well Brown by your drive, okay?
Yeah, that's I I had to have a Desi there you go no back to you
Yeah, polar bear is polar bear is on it. Just make sure to charge those mouse batteries
So we have beer and so that makes for a good show
I
Don't know how many of you remember arch assault and arch assault
for those of you who are not familiar is basically a
A distro kind of like Cali except based on arch. It's a distro specifically designed for penetration testing and
network security testing right
obviously when you're doing network security testing and penetration testing one of the really important things is
Is to stay up-to-date and to have up-to-date software and of course you want to be aware of up-to-date exploits
And so you want to go to pull down the latest packages, and so there's a fundamental
disconnect
You know to to some degree anyway when we are trying to do that on a distro
That is not rolling that is that is stuck in time right and so that's kind of where arch assault originally
Kind of took off and I had the pleasure of talking with these guys back at Southeast Linux fest
2014 I believe yeah, and we had a really good discussion
And they were showing you know the the the gentleman that I talked to he really took the the project to heart and he really
Spent a lot of time and effort and passion they had shirts they had you know little banners made up
And this is when the project is at its infancy right and so him and his wife are sitting see people that excited about it
Already yeah, yeah, you can you could feel the passion and him and his wife actually took the time
To settle this stuff was a very well-branded project, and I understand that they have gone through some changes well turns out
This week we learned that
They have announced a new name
So headline this is from softpedia
Dot-com the team over at arch assault a new Linux operating system based on the famous arch Linux distro
Designed for ethical hackers announced a few minutes ago on their Twitter account that they were changing the name to arch strike
Designed from the ground up as a security layer to arch Linux the arch assault project provides security researchers and
Hackers with one of the most powerful open source and totally free Linux kernel based operating systems for penetration testing and security
auditing operations under the new umbrella band
Called arch strike the project promises a bleeding-edge pen test distro to anyone who wants to join the fight for freedom of expression privacy
On the internet and it can be considered a direct competitor to Kali Linux previously known as
Backtrack has anyone in the mumble room
Let's start with this has anyone in the mumble room participated in a penetration penetration testing
Or have you have experience with Kali Linux? I?
Have personally used Kali Linux for certain purposes. I can't legally say what?
That I've had limited experience with it. They worked fairly smooth when I tried it a few years ago
So I haven't had experience since then okay, so you have have you had a chance to try?
Have you have you heard of archers alters as the first year you're hearing about it
No, I've heard of arches Hulk. I'm sure other people have in the chat room. Yeah
The have you have you played with it at all
No, I haven't gone back to arch yet, so I'm debating going to arch
Yeah, I'm not sure if I would have used for a pen testing to show outside of a work environment
Well, I think so I I think I don't think this is geared
Outside of that spectrum right because so nobody installs a penetration
I mean well most most people most practical people that are not the star of a reality show
Don't install a penetration testing distro as their daily driver, right?
It's not it's not a terribly practical thing not to mention you have a bunch of software in there that you don't really need
So I'm you know my thought on it is that I think that arch assault is basically
designed to do what
What Cali is doing except do it on based on arch no
Yeah, that would be a fair assessment
It's really weird because I have seen reader posts on reddit or other
For websites where people all I'm gonna sell arch assault or Cali Linux
And I'm like why you don't need to unless you're doing this work. You don't need to
Use this operating system for that it doesn't make sense. Mm-hmm. I
Think more had had something to say as well. Yeah, I go ahead were it
Yeah, the I'm familiar with the guys from the arch assault and that arch strike team
And I just wanted to point out that it's not actually a distro in itself
It's more of a layer or a package set that goes on top of arch
so you have your normal working arch installation or
hand or gross or whichever variation you choose to use and then you can pull these packages in to give you all that
Functionality and then if you want to later down run you just pull them all out and go away. Oh nice
So way more useful to me. So you so
So you're telling me that they they do intend you to run this as a daily driver and then just pull down
This set of packages that you need to do your work
Exactly. So it's actually an addition to whatever your daily driver is. They're not gonna make this OS version
That's just for penetration testing and security tools
It's I'm gonna give you all the packages you want that arch itself doesn't have and we're to keep them up-to-date and rolling as best
We can gotcha my mind that works very like if I personally at least have a lot of arch based workflows as it's you know
The main distro I use right would fit very well in that right a repo your package is there now
You've built yourself a new pen testing laptop from your same install script
So you touch on something that I think is is really pertinent. So Chris for example does not
he lives inside of arch right and so
Taking him outside of that takes him not only outside his comfort zone
but it also decreases his efficiency right because he is the ability to find the tools and make them work in a given distro and
so if you take somebody that lives on arch all day and all night and now you put them into a work environment and they
Can bring in that that tool set that they need to do their job do their job and then relinquish it and go back to
You know, whatever. I think that as a global idea
I think opens up a lot of real possibilities for Linux
Anyone else in the mobile room have any thoughts or experience with arch assault or if warhead if you have more dad
I know that you're you're a pretty well heavily in communication with the guys that do this
Anyone and yeah, I can't really add too much to it. The change actually happened quite a while ago
It's just that somehow we realized that people had missed it
So we added it to the recent Twitter's and now soft media has it it's been resubmitted across blogs across the net for like two
days straight
Yeah, that's about how it goes, right?
All right. Well moving on headline from seuss.com
Seuss Linux Enterprise 12 SP service back to beta and open QA status of QA automation and
And the article goes on here to say in mid-may we have reached the beta phase of sluss 12 SP 2
So I would like to look back a little bit and see what we've achieved and it's not it's also it's not just less
in fact, there's some really cool stuff this one of the reasons I think we should talk about this is
Sless and the other projects are now sort of interweaved and Richard could could tell you about that
It's it's sort of fascinating because when you see a new beta of less coming that also means
There's a new version of something for us average users coming too. I think is that right Richard?
Yeah, I mean this is actually like the first time we've been doing this
Full hog this this interweaved. It's a bit of an experiment still so the yeah the sluss 12 SP 2 beta
Yeah, the beta phase has started beta ones just come out which
that's basically like the
The real go point for open suzer to now start working on a leap because that's the point where?
You know sleepy two customers now have their hands on the sleigh code
Well, if they have the hands on it open suzer has the hands on it, too
So we've got that now in OBS and we've started building leap. So within like a day of well actually a day before that announcement
We've already got
Leap 42.2 out for one. So, you know sleaze in beta we're in alpha and
And we're basically kind of following that that mirrored route all the way up to November
So every time we have alpha 2 coming out
Any day now because sleaze doing beta 2 any day now
and you know following following this all the way along and
Yeah, it's it's really it's really interesting seeing this whole thing working because we're doing
really exciting things on both sides
Like on the enterprise side this service pack is definitely going to be something special
You don't normally see a an enterprise service pack that goes. Yeah. Okay
We'll have a new gnome and a new kernel and a new system D and I've probably missed something big in there
I do
Have a question about leap. Does it have support for?
It have support for does it have support for
Backfires no, no, no not ZFS. It's a oh
I can't believe it just slipped my mind. I thought about it and then a boom lost it
When it comes back, it's fun. Yeah. Yeah, so
You know Richard, I guess wait, can you give me some examples of?
Some of the common common things that you've seen some of the big things that you've seen less being used for lately. Oh
Slez is
Slez is doing really well as usual in all of those kind of big heavy mission critical enterprise environments. I mean sues is doing
Very well with that at the moment
I'm not allowed to speak too much about it because we're a public company
But you know figures are coming out soon and it'll be fun to talk about
Because it's it's looking it's being used really heavily in those sort of big hefty mission critical environments. Let's 12 is really kind of
Sues it in that place. So I joke with you guys from time to time
But the reality is I do encounter a sues, you know in the wild and I actually I was working for a client
Just a couple weeks ago that was using that was using sues enterprise and they were using it
Actually in a lotus notes domino hosted environment. Are you familiar with that? Yeah
It's actually it's so the the domino version was was version 8 5 3 and the lotus notes version was was 9 what they call
social edition, but the cool thing was is that they came to me and they had a
whole host of infrastructure that was hosted in this and they said our server died and we don't know what we're gonna do and
So and they were hosting this on on on Susan so I was kind of learning the ins and outs and while I'm doing this
I actually made a recommendation. I'm like, well, you know, it would take a couple days for us to get a server here for you
We could take a couple days to get a server here for you
but what we could do for the time being or for a permanent thing is we can rent you a server over a digital ocean comm
And they were actually able to use the code do unplugged to get a $10 credit off there
We guys cooking chicken, yeah
They were able to get $10 off which got him the first two months cuz they were actually able to run that on a $5 rig
And actually sometimes I think that people don't understand all the things you can do on just the $5 rig
The thing that they fall down on in that $5 rig is of course storage, but guess what digital ocean is working on that
I'm so excited. Are you signed up for the beta? Yes, I am. I'm signed up for the beta. That is neat
Yes
So they
Basically the the one one thing that I have I have desired
Well, there's actually two things I've desired from digital ocean
One is I want to be able to custom upload my ISOs
But because they have basically ever destroyed use anyway, not such a big deal. The second thing I want is more storage
So this block storage thing
I'm in the beta program and I think we're getting closer to actually getting it because I got an email from them
Three days ago or four days ago and they wanted a survey about all the things I was going to do
Oh, yeah, did you get that? I did. Yeah, so I answered that and and hopefully that means that we are getting
hopefully that means that we're getting much closer to the
It's actually having block storage is something I'm super looking forward to
Now I want to talk about
So I have numerous times gone on record and talked about how much I
Like the Yuba keys, right?
they have fundamentally changed the way that I do my job and at this point, I
Don't know that I'd say I can't live without a Yuba key
But I certainly can't live without the functionality and convenience that the Yuba key gives me. I mean, they're like it's um
It's a little bit like a root of trust in your in the way you operate, right? So quick recap
Yuba key what it's allowing me to do is
Without giving up the private key store my SSH certificates on a hardware based token that literally never leaves my side
And I say that as I'm looking around for it. I have two
I have one that I wear around my neck that I've taken off because it jingles when I'm in the studio and the second one
Is actually you can't see it, but it's it's just trust me. It's in there
They have recently come out with the four and said that
It is no longer going to be an open source device that they're gonna close source it now
the critical question is
It doesn't change anything because you couldn't really do anything with the source code anyway, right?
It's a hardware based device and you still have to trust and you couldn't change the firmware on the device, right?
And you still you're essentially you still have to trust the manufacturer
Needless to say I am a little concerned how many people in the mumble room are using Yuba key
Lots I see I I did just buy a Yuba key for before this news came out like oh, did you weeks before?
Yeah, okay. Well, I'm not I'm not ready to hand up my Yuba key. There is a competitor up that I am in seriously considering
And it is called the nitro key
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's what it is
Yeah
Uh-huh
So and what the nitro key is is it's kind of the same thing where you have a hardware based device that allows you to store
A certificate now a couple things jump out at me
The first is that it is an open source device
So that I'm happy with it has an open source public post by Cardware public software software
The thing that I'm not so big on is
Look at the thing, right?
If I go up here and look this is a very large device
Also, it's a very plastic looking device
The Yuba key is sleek and the Yuba keys I got to tell you I have had one on my lanyard
I when I first bought it actually bought two
Actually, I bought a lot more to it, but I bought him for everyone in the company, right? Everyone in my company gets
Yeah, yeah, we issued about and because if I fire somebody I
Asked them for the Yuba key back. They give it back to me
I know that those servers are still secure because that Yuba key has never given up that private duplicate. You're right
But I bought two for myself
Originally and the idea was I was gonna have one around my neck and I was gonna leave one at home and my fireproof safe
It's kind of like a backup because I have contracts
with certain places that you know, um, I
Don't know really what I want to share in the air
But I have contracts with certain places that have very very high you need guarantees
security protocols
And so I am NOT allowed to access the the SSH files if I want to add a key
I have to write out a justification form and I have to explain everything and I have to give the key and I have to
Send it in then they have to make a change. It takes like three weeks and it's a real pain and so
Absolutely to avoid all that, you know, this has really changed everything, but I wanted to have two of them one
I kept it with me and then one I kept secure
and
What I noticed was that it was originally I was concerned that it was going to get broken or damaged
That's why I needed a backup turns out like those things are indestructible. I put my through by washing machine
It has fallen out of my Wow. I'm driving down the interstate
And you got it back. Yeah
My laptop has fallen over on top of it. Like they are practically indestructible. I
Can't say the same about this thing. It it does not look like it has the same build quality as
The Yuba key and that's a little concerning to me
Mumbo room, even if you guys don't have experience with the the Yuba key. Do you guys have any opinions or thoughts?
Yeah, I do the nitro key. I looked at their website and they're really lacking in detail
Like does that does it even retract? Does it have two slots like the Yuba key does with the long press and the short press?
And it just seemed like there was no real comparison between the different models, right?
It's quite early. I think for the for the company. So I have to wait and see I think if I'm not mistaken
It's based on the FST zero token that's already working with G knock
And so yeah, it does have a couple key slots and everything. It's similar to the way the Yuba key works
Okay now in terms of the open PGP stuff. Now, what is your thought William about what about the
About the lack of of Yuba key being open source. Does that matter?
It doesn't really matter to me because I still had to trust them as a manufacturing partner, right?
Like they are ultimately manufacturing it. They are, you know planting the firmware on it at build time. You can't change it
It's impossible thing. I don't necessarily like about the nitro key. Is that you can change the firmware and
Typically with Gina since they are using Gina it will wipe all the keys on there
But I feel like you could probably flash it in such a way that it won't necessarily wipe the keys
And so the security of that whole environment is kind of questionable, especially with that cheap plastic case
That's easy to take off right see and that's that's see and you're hitting on kind of where where I come at it
too is it it feels like the Yuba key was built for commercial enterprise grade use and it feels like the nitro key is like
somebody's really great garage idea
Basically, I would like to weigh in that, you know there we we used Yuba keys here for quite a lot of stuff
Especially for folks who are jumping into servers all the time, but Red Hat released an open source app on
On at least it's on Android. I don't know if it's on iOS called free OTP
It's essentially one-time password generator, but software, you know
So you can you can load that up on your phone and use it to generate your one-time pass
And it works with everything that we've got deployed
You can also use it in place of the g-auth indicator a Google indicator app. It's quite wonderful
Yeah, you know the thing is I I
I just there's something about me and I'm sure I'm gonna catch flack for saying this especially after Sunday's episode
But I have a problem with the idea of Google two-factor authentication
When I'm logging into my Google account on a Google server with a Google password
And then the two-factor authentication I have is a software app written by Google put on a Google device. I
mean
That's a lot of Google
iPhone man. Yeah. Yeah. Well the software still written by Google, right? I just the thing that I like about my YubiKey
What when it comes to two-factor authentication is like I feel like
The parties involved like last pass and YubiKey totally separate entities and really have nothing to gain, you know from working with each
I just I guess because Google have anything to gain from
Sidestepping their authentication parameters. They can already do that internally. Anyway, I would imagine that's kind of my point
What do they really have to gain from somehow subverting what they're trying to do with these different applications?
That's exactly my point when it comes to last pass might my last pass vaults encrypted client side with it with the with the key
You know, there's two-factor authentication that is totally separate from last pass with whereas Google is you know
You're making my point is they you're essentially you're essentially saying like it's basically to keep the honest people honest outside of Google because if Google
Really wanted to get to your stuff your host anyway
If I'm not misunderstanding you
Yes, but you're still using that two-factor for your Google services, so yeah
well, anyway, so I
Just there's something about me that likes having having those two separate. Maybe I admit maybe that's just maybe that's fun
Maybe I'm just maybe I'm an old fuddy-duddy. I don't know
but I
Haven't quite decided if I'm if I'm ready to jump ship on
On YubiKey or not. I feel like it could go both ways
anyone else in the mumbo-room have thoughts or
Opinion on the on the whole YubiKey situation, even if you haven't used it. I'm interested what you think. I
Think they should have kept it open source. Keep it free software
Okay, why do you say that? Why do you think it matters?
Because Williams right at the end of the day you're trusting it rather the manufacturer publishes the spec or not
You're you're essentially you're trusting them
I mean unless you have an electrical engineering degree and can go verify these things you're trusting the manufacturer anyway, right?
The hardware if it's got the code in the hard way, and you can't change it. That's fine
but if
You but it does have access to it and you can change the hard software on the hardware
You should have access to the source code
GPU G and a that
Yeah, the GPL
Please offer foundation. I'm a member here. Yeah, I'm gonna throw back to you William. What was your response to that?
My response was the YubiKey does not allow you to change the software. It's physically fused onto the board
Like you can't change it once it's printed
And so I'm where is there and correct me if I'm wrong and correct me if I'm wrong
Somebody correct me if I'm wrong doesn't Richard Stoneman himself advocate as it'd be okay to have binary blobs as long as they can't be changed
Yes, he does
He'd use the microwave example, I think for this where if your microwave has software running on it that you can't change. That's fine
And the YubiKey is kind of the same thing. It's a black box
So if you can validate that it works correctly then and the software can't be changed. That's fine, right Ryan
You're thinking there's a security
implication here
Well, it's just the ability to audit, you know, that's what that's what for me
Brint makes open source more secure. And so I I can't say that I really understand the reasoning here
I understand that it's a simple tool that generates, you know based on a counter, you know
The one-time password, but I don't like the ability to audit. I mean, I can
So, let's back up for a second first of all, that is one
Very well, that is one component of the YubiKey, right? There's a lot of different ways to do it
Very well, that is one component of the YubiKey, right? There is the there are three components the YubiKey
There is the smart card identification, which I'm using for SSH authentication
There's the one-time password authentication. Then there's the U2F standard. So
So it is a little bit more complex than just it is it is it is spinning out a random number generator
Coupled with a you know an algorithm to spin out a one-time password there
There is there so there is something to be said about like I eventually am
You know in trusting that the SSH certificate that I wrote onto this device
You know is is secure. So there's some argument to be made there. I just I question how valid it is in the world and I think
Was it wizard Jed you were going to say something?
Yeah
I was going to say you can test every single one of these things in a really basic scenario
And the only thing you can't do and I believe it's for the YubiKey Neo
It has a an NFC that would be more difficult to test but it should also be just as easily tested
Yeah, yeah, it shouldn't be that hard to test
All right. Anyone else have closing thoughts on YubiKey?
Yeah, I think with the trust issue. I personally trust an open source company more than a closed source one
Um, but I mean if all you're doing is using it as a two-factor authenticated to get into your google account
I don't think it really matters
If you're using it for sort of encrypting your email that is super sensitive. I'd I'd be a bit more wary
well, I mean
So it to some some degree I am trusting that every server that I own or run has my YubiKey
ssh certificate in it. So I I mean there is a certain level of trust there, but
I'm hoping that they um that by them doing this that doesn't um that they're not doing this to their older products
So you still have those available that are open source that you can use nothing
I've read suggests that they are doing this with any of their older stuff
It seems like all of this is is their new production, right? I don't think they're changing any of the old stuff
I want to talk about Krita 3.0 Krita 3.0 was released today the team at Krita releases 3.0 the animation release
Wrapping up a year of work. This is a really big release animation support integrated into Krita's core
Instant preview for better performance painting and drawing with brushes on big canvases ported to the latest version of qt platform and many bigger
And smaller new features and improvements to mention now. I know we have a number of different graphic artists in the community
I know. Mr. Rotten corpses. I know Odyssey Westra is
Has anyone had experience using Krita?
No one huh? Well not in any professional sense, how about in an unprofessional sense
And I guess like, you know, you're using this in place of GIMP or something like that. Well, here's why I ask wizard is because
There is a lot to be said for
An application that is easy and approachable and Wes
I know that you you and I kind of fall into this at the same time like you and I have very busy
Professional lives and so when it comes to our to enjoy software
We have to find software that's easily approachable and we can just sit down and do something right?
I mean if it's going to take more than a half hour to really get going or have some sort of progress
There's there's not I can't do that every day, right? Like maybe maybe a weekend if it's important software
But if it's really gonna be useful to me, I need to be able to figure it out pretty quick. Yeah
And and I feel the same way like I you know, I want to sit some sit down and bang something out
And one of the things I have used, you know, I found I found the GIMP to be
totally
Unintuitive I I can't I can crop pictures in the GIMP and I can make some minor changes, but really
The way I see it is like I can do all the things I've always been able to do in GIMP
But I haven't really learned how to do anything new and different quite some time. Whereas it feels like
Other software, it's a lot more easy to explore or I'm actually excited about the new features and
Krita is always talking about stuff
So wizard, I want to go back and ask what how how is it from somebody who who is not an artist?
Because I'm certainly not she's man stick figures
Yeah, so I mean I struggle with stick figures sometimes how is Krita when I sit down and you know
I'm looking at the I'm looking at the user interface. It actually looks you know
I guess fairly approachable. I mean there's an awful lot of tools and buttons
It is it's uh for for people that might have used, you know, proprietary software in the past
It's it's kind of a nice mix of you know, the Corel Draw of the past and uh, kind of photoshop of today
And it's and it's a good mix. It's not like uh, oh lord. Where why is this all messed up?
Why is everything everywhere else? Like you kind of get with GIMP and the best they don't mean that in a bad way, but
It's a very different from what you would expect it tends to take a little while to figure out
But it's it's kind of what you would expect where you expect things to be. It's like, oh, okay
Everything's fragile here along the left side. Oh, okay. Oh, there's the layering tool. There's this tool
Everything's where you would expect it to be
And it doesn't it doesn't take that learning curve like you need with GIMP where it's like, oh, okay
I see layers here. But you know, where is the patterns menu? Oh the patterns is behind it. It's a weird tab
You know and I I can speak, you know, they're apparently they're not here today
You know and I I can speak, you know, they're apparently they're not here to talk for themselves
but I I can tell you having talked to people like rotten corpse and people like odyssey westward that
You know, honestly restress told me on numerous occasions if it wasn't for projects like krita in my paint
He is a graphic designer would be on windows or mac
And so the important thing is even if you don't use tools like krita and I certainly don't I mean i'm i'm i'm
You guys probably have more art in your pinky finger than I have my whole body
I'm just not an artsy guy but uh
It's important to remember that these projects are fundamentally
Are are fundamental cornerstones to the people that are in that field and so uh, and I think it's a society like we
If someone wants to just get started
Maybe they're like in high school and they don't have money for professional software or they're just starting out in whatever
You know whatever age it's important for you to have free tools that are really
That can actually do what you want to do and let people be creative
Exactly exactly you you you you you lower that barrier to entry
And you take somebody that has that creative spirit and you give them professional grade tools and say here you go kid
Have some fun that you know, that can be a really empowering thing
Gentoo how many people use gentoo?
Uh, this again comes from soft pd headline the gentoo linux operating system has received an updated live dvd iso image dubbed choice edition
Which brings the latest gnu linux technologies according to the announcement gentoo linux choice edition live dvd has been released in celebration
Of the continued collaboration between gentoo developers and the community. It looks like it brings some of the latest software
releases such as the kde plasma 5.6 desktop environment
what
There's some sort of troll in the background folks
Um, so but how many people how many people are using yeah and zfs, right?
I was getting there uefi support and zfs on linux. How many people are using gentoo?
Is anyone using gentoo in the mumble room?
Have you used gentoo?
Yeah, I know a lot of x gentoo guys. Yeah, what are they on now?
tumbleweed
I've used it in the past. I don't have anything current. I've run it on a wee back in the day
That was a lot of fun. Mm-hmm
So chris and I were talking about doing a gentoo review have you heard about this?
Yeah, I I think you should I would also run if you guys are installing it on things
I would do it, too
That sounds like a blast
So the the fact that zfs on linux is becoming such a big thing and you can tell these early adopters things like arch
linux and things like gentoo, you know now
That tells you where the drive is for a given file system, right zfs is is a big deal
And what's funny is I still can't get it to work on abuntu
Yeah, I know that's funny
And I can kind of see gentoo as an interesting thing for like our container world
Like maybe you want to make yourself a really tiny minimal gentoo user land and since everything runs on x64
Virtualized things anyway, like the architecture doesn't matter as much and just run it like that
You know gentoo folks they are they're much like chris and his arch love, right?
They use it once they get hooked on that train. They use it for everything
And so i've got a really close friend of mine. He has it in his living room
It runs his projector his tv projector thing. It runs his media center and then for a living
He actually he hosts a website and he runs all of his
Uh all of his servers on gentoo as well because he becomes so familiar with it
Yeah
And the thing that he always says that he likes about it is that he can build that installation
To serve that given purpose in the living room. It's a media center in his in a server. It becomes his you know, his web server
um, and so I I think that it's important to get these
You know these features things like zfs that is going to fundamentally change how he can run it in on his server
Anyone in the mumble room have thoughts about zfs on on gentoo?
And not zfs on gentoo. How about zfs on linux in general or anything related to the current topic?
Does anybody know if they've actually got the zfs module compiled on that live cd or are they compiling it on the user's workstation?
You know, I don't know. Maybe if we do a gentoo review i'll be able to answer that for you
Yeah, because that that would actually be my question because you know
Ubuntu is going the way of having it pre-compiled and you're pulling it down and
Well other distros debbie and then I believe there's a couple others that are coming out and trying to do this dkms module
Which is built on the system. That'd be
That'd be an interesting way to see it. Like how are we doing this?
Are we doing it the nvidia way of compiling on the system that you're on or are you pulling down as a binary?
So in it for those of us like myself who are ignorant explain to me
Why that's important. Why does it matter if it's if I understand that that the the perception is that a dkms
Dks ms module is not going to be as
stable reliable
To start with the simple like I am not a lawyer thing but based on the free software
Uh the sff sff and software freedom conservancy
The the simple part is is basically with all this open source stuff
If you you know you as an individual user can do whatever the heck you want
But the gpl brings with it certain responsibilities for distributions
and so if a distribution is
Breaching the gpl the conditions of the gpl are very clear in this they can lose their right to distribute gpl
licensed software so
You know if you want to you know from a very narrow reading but you know, obviously ubuntu think otherwise
But you know ubuntu effectively are currently risking their right to ship gpl software. So
the
The you know, if you're just if you're doing like a debian or or you know, other others are ship the source
Users compile whatever the heck you want
That's generally seen as a loophole around all of that
But of course, yeah, if you know, how do you know it's going to compile properly?
How do you know it's going to work properly? There's more things to go wrong there because
Like your kernel is going to move
Then you need to make sure that's going to recompile properly blah blah. There are definitely more moving parts. That's for sure
Well, there are more moving parts. You know what? I like I like operating systems like centos and redhat that are predictable
And they just they have a nice even flow
You know what else I like I like when I can learn about those things
In a structured manner without having to guess and and and stab and search around the internet at places like linux academy
where I just got done doing my uh, my my redhat my redhat 7 training and now I realize that they are still releasing
Different versions of redhat 6 i'm thinking now I should go back because I still got a couple clients on 6
Maybe I need to go back and
Brush up on six skills
They still have the ability to I can still go take a course and brush up on that because now everything's changed
And I don't know about you west, but I have I have I fundamentally changed my behavior to
Everything is system d now, right? I go to stop a service system d
I go to start a service system d I go and enable like the whole check config to to enable something and service to start something
That my brain no longer works that way everything is I honestly it's it is until you go back to a six box
Then you're then it's not so great lost but you have linux academy to fall back on
So, uh linux academy is a great place to to go and learn about
Uh linux linux academy dot com slash unplugged and if you go to linux academy dot com slash unplugged
You can get a great uh, a great deal on signing up for linux and here chris has so kindly pulled up the redhat certified
engineer exam now if you're not familiar with the the the structure of certification in redhat
The first the entry level is the the csa the certified system administrator and then from there is the ce
which is the certified, uh engineer and then after that is the
Ca which is the certified architect and I don't remember exactly what the numbers are off the top of my head
But the last time I was talking with the redhat employee
He was there like they're like show shockingly low like the amount of certified architects in the world
like there's just there's a handful of them and like
I gotta tell you guys if you have one of these certifications
Maybe not so much the csa because that's kind of the entry level one
But definitely when you start approaching the ce and definitely if you get the ca
Man, you write your own ticket. That is a marketable skill to have because there are so few people
It's a lot of trust you can get yeah
And the other thing students, you know, it's gonna come with the you know
It's gonna come with a decent salary too because you know and and so and you can learn all of this stuff on linux academy
uh the uh
the uh
the the the the site is structured for people that are busy professionals that don't have a lot of time and
That has fundamentally enabled me to learn the things I need to learn it and again i'm comparing this
You know from from being going to a week-long class and now taking this class online at night. Yeah for sure. I think do
Uh for me, it's not even just about how busy I am. It's about how the how they break down the individual courseware
Yes, and so that I just look at that and I go okay. That's something I can accomplish. That's something I can do and
I no longer have this big nebulous question of this task. I want to complete
I have a very specific range of time. I need to commit and instructions and comprehensive study guides I can use and it's like, okay
I'm i'm ready for you to just pick that nugget and say i'm gonna i'm gonna tackle that nugget
I love that too. The nugget system is really cool
Like you just want to do a deep dive and they got availability planners, too
Just go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged to support the show
So, uh while i'm on the mic
Why don't I take over and start talking about something i've wanted to chat about for a little bit. It's the mycroft project now
Mr. Ryan was going to join us last week, but we got our wires crossed on timing
And that's actually sort of works out because there's something now
I want to talk about it's not directly related to the mycroft project, but it's sort of the power of open source
So let's get started by saying hey ryan. Welcome to linux unplugged
Hey, i'm glad to be back as always
Now I i'm assuming you saw this morning
This uh, super super cool gnome extension that brings mycroft for the desktop right into the gnome shell
Look at that. Yeah
It looks like it's professionally done. I mean, it's really really slick and this is just a great example of
What's one of the great benefits of having something like this be open source. So ryan what the heck what's new with the microsoft project?
There's a lot new. Um, so last week we released the code
Uh mycroft core, which is kind of the piece that ties it all together out to the
Open source community. Um, we know that it's an alpha. It's got a lot of bugs. We're going through and fixing them and
Honestly, you know once we put it out there
Immediately, you know, we got so much great feedback
But we also got like so many people trying it in so many new environments that now we're kind of just in crazy
Patching mode. So we'll be probably doing that for another week or two, you know, just trying to fix it all the bugs people found but uh,
So be ready for an alpha experience
But I encourage everybody to come play with it and even install this extension and provide feedback
this we it was so ironic because
I was actually talking to a group and we have a we have a slack channel that you may can join you uh,
The documentation tells you how to do that
Um, but we were talking about start starting to make a gnome extension and then somebody linked me to this gnome extension
Oh, okay, and it was right before you pinged me on twitter
And so I learned about it just as we started talking about possibly talking about today, but it's awesome
It's freaking awesome, and i'm so happy to see it
So, uh, you seem like you've been pretty busy these days. How are how are things now in an open source project?
That's getting some attention like some interest from other parties. I have things
Do they feel like they've leveled up in difficulty for you?
Absolutely, absolutely leveled up in difficulty, but you know, the thing is
We're making jarvis an open source jarvis, you know, so it's we knew from the beginning. It wasn't going to be easy
and so, uh
As the project has grown I I actually we've hired four interns to help just manage all the little tasks good. Nice
And so, uh, we're we're also leveling up our account
We're also leveling up our capability to try and keep up with the the difficulty as things, you know
Increase but the cool thing is is we're in the right space, you know
Well, I would say it seems like there's a lot of attention here
I mean everyone's aware of google home just was announced
Of course, we don't know when it's going to ship yet
Everybody's familiar now with the amazon echo and the big rumor coming ahead of wwdc is third party api integration
With siri which apple seems to have directly linked to the information to put the word out there that
Third party integration is coming to siri. So it would seem every major player and then of course, let's not forget
Microsoft has that adorable cortana as well
You ever wonder if they see like this type of movement in the open source community?
And adjust accordingly, you know, you see like parsi mac parser
you know get released and you ever wonder if they they see like
uh
A project like adapt our intent parser get dropped out there and they're like, oh, well
We don't want a whole bunch of people adopting that, you know, so let's let's put something else out there
That ties kind of people into to our, you know ecosystem
So, I mean it's all great
We're making use of everything that these guys drop, you know and and evaluating them and seeing how they can improve microsoft
But it's just and it's great. It's great
That's what this whole point of this project was was to introduce an open source alternative
You know into the into the environment and to give people like us a chance to integrate this stuff into
you know, for instance gnome, yeah, we're
We're not going to be able to necessarily grab, you know
Cortana or would we really even want to like and integrate that into our linux desktops and into
You know these various random devices around our home
and so that's the whole point since the beginning was to provide a platform to enable people to do that and
You know just last week we we finished tech stars, which is an accelerator. It's like y combinator
it's one of the big accelerators in the nation and that was powered by tech stars and sprint and
We got a lot of value out of that
But uh, you were asking about a video and I totally forgot that uh, josh's keynote was recorded there
And he talks about how open source has you know?
Rose to the occasion to rule like mobile and the desktop and how you know
This is just another space where it makes sense when you have this ubiquitous technology. That's going to be everywhere
What about to have it be open?
So okay
I follow you there ryan and I agree this is
And fundamentally an area that we have to have a great solid open source solution to
What about that ecosystem though? Like what makes google home attractive is that it ties in with the entire google ecosystem?
And all of the third parties that will integrate with it simply because google is a name that gets their respect
And so they're just so they'll work with google
Um, how do you compete when it seems like that is going to be one of the larger feature sets of these devices?
good question, so
the answer is that
uh, we don't you know the the answer is that
That sure you can have a google home device
That's this black box, you know that that you talk to but what about voice enabling? You know your oven?
What about voice enabling? You know the random?
Internet of things that are around your house or the new device that you create
Yeah, you we don't have we're looking at this all you're looking at this all wrong
It's it's what we're what what microsoft gives us an opportunity to do is to make voice command ubiquitous
Throughout the house, you know to to it doesn't have to be we we keep pushing down
What this stack can run on and the idea is to get it on the smallest micro processor possible?
So that your garage door opener can be voice enabled, you know, that's the goal and and to make voice
Be everywhere, you know and and uh, do you need to talk to your microwave?
Not necessarily, but it'd be freaking awesome if you could you know, uh same with the oven preheat to 375 degrees
And set a timer for 10 minutes, you know, this is something that I don't necessarily see
um people
I don't see people adopting google and echo and amazon solution simply because if i'm ge and i'm
Installing, you know one of those stacks if if they come available to where you can do this
If i'm installing it on an oven, I now my relationship with my customer is shared with amazon
You know and everything they say is going to be hoovered up by amazon
And it's the same with like a sonos speaker or a bose speaker if you were to put amazon's
You know technology on that speaker if you ask the speaker. What's the best speaker in the world? What is it going to say chris?
Is going to say the amazon echo. That's right
That's right. And so amazon like, you know, I know that that you can load amazon, uh the echo
software onto raspberry pi, but the the question is
Do you want that relationship with amazon to permeate everywhere? It's like when you ask siri
What's the best smartphone siri says the iphone of course, uh, you know boy it's so it's it's bigger than any one device
That's for sure. And it's it's
It's almost the raspberry pi of ai and voice
Where you can you can build it into anything and then give that all of a sudden
There's lots of devices out there
But the raspberry pi is when everybody knows you take a device like this and all of a sudden
You can put a computing you can put a computer in something that was never possible to have a computer at a price point never
Possible before yeah, and the thing is this is the big thing for years and years and years. We thought the most
Innovative way to talk to your computer was to point and grunt
And now we're at a point where that computers can understand what you're saying
And they can understand natural language and respond to that and that's powerful
You know that's going to change what we perceive to be computers
And what can be a computer because we they you need a speaker and a microphone in this case
And then you can have a conversation with this device and make it do what you want it to do
Wizard jet actually has a good use case for talking to your oven go ahead wizard
Yeah, you know, uh when everyone goes out and they realize oh I left my oven on you
You can actually go down and ask your phone. Oh, did I leave the oven on? Hey my craft?
Yeah, I try it
so the so some things that I i've been waiting to tell your audience, you know is is uh, we would we we've seen a
Successful funding around
So we'll have more details on that soon, which means that we're we're in this for the long haul
and uh
And we're going to be working with every community that will work with us to try to get the microsoft core
To permeate, you know throughout open source projects that you know, be it applications or or desktops
Or or anything, you know, I I used home assistant the other day home assistant.io
Which is a really cool project
And I noticed that they used you know, some really simple google speech to text
to do
Pretty simple commands and this is another place where you know microsoft might be able to help extend that capability
And so if you're if you're involved in a project that you think could benefit from voice, you know enablement
um, please come over and hang out with us and talk with us because
This is this is something that where we don't have to be behind this time
I mean
We're we might be a little behind as far as like if we're talking about the desktop
because windows 10 has had cortana for a little while but but there's now an option and the only thing holding it back
Is getting you know people contributing and porting it over to the different desktops and
And making sure that it's easy to use and enable and we saw that with the gnome extension
But unfortunately, there's just not enough people on the team to be an expert
In how to integrate into each of the desktop environments
So i'd love to see you know this permeate as an option for people who want to voice enable their their
Uh desktop and and maybe even their linux powered phone and i'm looking at poppy
Even though i'm sure he's not listening right now, but i'm but i'm looking at him
So uh stereo blow you made a you made a comment in the chat room about the importance of some sort of
Open dictation system something like that. Could you expand on that a little bit?
Yeah, i'm not sure if people have tried to use a dictation on linux, but it's not that easy to get a
uh working uh dictation
uh going I mean you have the option of using something like
um dragon naturally speaking or something
but uh having a open
Dictation technology would be just great on linux. Mm-hmm
I like the idea too of all of these really interesting chat applications that are coming out now like you have
A silent circle and of course telegram and all these could use
Is they're working on early versions of bots, but wouldn't it be interesting to see them integrate some sort of micro functionality
Yes, that would be very cool
So it's kind of like the perfect time to be the plumbing of this kind of stuff because there's a lot of stuff in development
Want it and if we have like a really good friendly
Open source upstream. That's awesome
And it sounds like you guys will be a good horse to bet on it with the funding going successfully
It'll be around for a while. So that's good news, too
Yeah, and the other thing is you know one thing that holds us back in the in the keep that the jupiter broadcasting community can
Help with is we just need people to test on all different mics, you know, unfortunately, uh, we found some people whose laptop
Mics give them a really really difficult time
But that's great information to have and that's great information to take and and try to adjust the experience work
Everywhere, you know and we can only get that like we're not an enormous company. We don't have uh, you know
20 million dollars and 100 engineers to throw at throughout a problem
So the best thing that people can do for us is to come over and provide us with feedback
And we're not perfect and we're not going to be perfect
You know, we're not it's going to be it's it's rough to do what we're doing
But the the best way to accelerate that process is to get feedback and and contributions
And so, um, I probably say the same thing every time but you know
We could really use the help of the open source community to help us kind of drive development and drive testing
So if people are if people have time and they want to contribute to a project we could really use the uh, the eyeballs
In the in the hands. Yeah, excellent. Thanks ryan. I think that would be really that's probably uh, you're helping out with the mics
That's something anybody can do without any development skills, uh swift
You had a you had something you want to mention regarding simon real quick as we wrap up
Yeah, I was going to talk about that. You can use that as dictation software. Yeah, it's not the prettiest in the world
But it is nice. Yeah something for people to look into so ryan. Well, thank you for stopping by and uh, giving us an update
It's a project. We've been following for a while here on the show and we can
I continue to find every single time we talk fascinating
So yeah, i'm I hope to uh, I still hope to head over your way and hook up. Uh, lady jupiter that would be amazing
We'll make it worth your time. Yeah
Okay. All right. I'll help you do that. Lady jupiter knows how to party. That is a great
As linux fest can attest, uh, so before we go any further speaking a party, you know
It's a party for your pocketbook ting go right there to go
So get yourself just a great cellular plan go to linux.ting.com to get our discount and support the show
It's your own terms wireless. So they got cdma and gsm you get to pick from which is dead simple
Which means if you have a better gsm signal in your area
Switch over to that if you have better cdma signal you can switch over to that
You're gonna get that. I love that flexibility. I love also
Well, I suppose what I really love about it is it's six dollars for the line
And then it's just your usage on top of that. That's the brilliance. That's where it's just simple and straightforward
It's how wireless should have been from the beginning
No contract
No other termination fee. No, you go to linux.ting.com you get 25 off your first device
If you got a compatible device and you might you get 25 in service credit
Now the average ting bill for per line is like 23 bucks
They're doing a giveaway of the anzatel one touch idol 3, which is a pretty decent
Freaking gsm 4.7 inch and 5.5 inch. Oh nice. Yeah android phone. I know so we got details on their blog
Right now you beat free. You can't be free wess. You can't beat free phone and then that ting service
You're paying nothing nine dollars for a sim
If you just need a sim card, uh, then they have great devices including the volt 2 for 66 bucks
If you're just looking for a nice android phone to just make calls and stuff. That's or do like telegram, right?
It perfect the netgear zings back in stock. That's great. That's great
They also have the uh, the old nexus 5 if you want something for under 200 bucks
That is a google experience phone
And of course, I got the 5x and the 6p and the internet phones and the samsung phones and all of them
Yeah, they got them all you go to linux.ting.com go there. Try them out. Like I said, there's no contract
There's no other termination fee. There's really no risk. They have a savings calculator right here
You go there you plug it in you see how much you would save and you know what wess
Girl, you're gonna save
So much wess. I can't okay. I can't wess. I can't you just have to go there for me
Yes, I can't linux.ting.com. You got to go there and try it out
See what i've been talking about that supports the show looking at what they got
Reading their blog learning more about the company maybe doing their savings calculator all of that's a way to support the show
And maybe save yourself some money. It's a great service. I've been I mean i'm like two and a half years now or something
Because it's almost freaking june which is crazy linux.ting.com
Linux.ting.com
So wess, uh, I don't know if the does the mumble room know that we asked you to sacrifice your laptop once again
I'm, not sure we did talk about it pre-show
Yeah
So, uh, i'll bring i'll bring the brown bear back in for this segment because I know he might have more interest in this
Than I do, but I I will confess I was the one that asked you
To do this. That's true. And you've actually gotten sacrifice. You've gotten remarkably further than I expected
Uh, I am I am damn impressed when I looked over at your machine and saw what you've been up to
So ladies and gentlemen, uh, we asked wess for the good of the virtual lug and our audience
Take a look at what might be a desktop linux competitor someday
Remix os for the pc. What is it wess? Well, it's a combination of remix os and android x86
Uh, and it's android on your laptop. Oh, that's what i'm running it on here anyway, and it's a it's kind of like a
It's like a regular desktop experience
Uh, maybe like a little windows 10 ish, but they've got like a pseudo desktop with like your android icons. It doesn't
It comes with like a guest mode
So you can start out and you can just run it like a you can burn it to a cd or a usb
And then run it in guest mode and it'll just be like a regular live cd without persistence or they have the uh, a resident mode
They call it where it will make itself like a little loopback image file and and write on there
So that's what i've been doing i put it on a usb drive and edited grub
And had to do a little futzing with grub that maybe that's my fault. Maybe that's their fault
You know, it's hard to say but i've got it running and it doesn't come with play services
But play services they have like a easy install for play services that took I don't know a minute
You just reboot and then the play store was there. So i've been able to install telegram. I've got slack
I've got google drive you did you got all those up?
There have been some couple caveats like google drive
I I can download the show notes as a pdf
I have not been able to get it to actually show me the show notes and be able to edit them
Uh, but telegram works slacks working great do this for me if you don't mind
Can you look and see if any what go pay is on there and here's and here's here's why I say that
We have a payment solution for for for the you know
So we do we we offer services in some weird places and i'm i'm an entrepreneur, right?
So I never tell somebody no so somebody calls me and says yeah, see if that installs and runs
Somebody calls me and says will you come service me at my rv or?
Or in the middle of a park in the middle of a parking lot or where some other weird places we've done
Somewhere you'll be able to get this right? Yeah, I have no problem going out there and doing service
The problem is billing somebody that I met in a parking lot or billing somebody at their rv
That poses a challenge. I'll send you an invoice. Yeah, right
And so and you know my my front desk staff they get you know
They get all hot and bothered anytime something isn't like laid out for them. And so one of the only in a foreign language
No, no, no, it's it's normally in it's normally in it's normally in english
uh
Yikes, okay. All right. Well, but it might work. Maybe we have to change the user agent or is that a thing?
The thing is though
I hate using tablets for that kind of stuff
It would be much more convenient if they could just boot into a vm
Type in the credit card number run it that way
and um
And so this kind of thing is not it's really not my wheelhouse, right?
like so for one I have a hard time really getting behind wanting to run android on a
Taking a perfectly good usable laptop and then running
android on it
No, I feel yeah, I mean I I don't think i'll keep it and it is like android is it's okay on my phone
It works on the phone, but it's not perfect
Well where I do see a lot of value coming in is there is in any way go pay is one example
But I think there are others
There are a lot of applications that are not written for linux, but they are available on the play store, right?
Absolutely, and so the ability to have to be able to run those applications
Especially if I can virtualize if I can get it to run in a virtual box man
Now we're cooking with gas in the front right burner. I I you know, the you know
What go pay isn't even available. It's not a windows app. It's not available on macOS
Yeah, it is only available in ios or android and and you're seeing that more and more
There's a lot of applications that are only available
Inside of a mobile atmosphere and so and as a person who wants to use a desktop for everything
There is I I think that there is a lot of value to be had in
Being able to virtualize that stuff and being able to run that on my laptop. Totally
Now how have you have you run any intensive applications something like plex?
Or any sort of game? I do have plex installed. I've not tried actually watching it yet
I maybe I can get youtube going though
I will say it has been nicely integrated like my function keys for brightness and sound those are working right out of the box
No kidding. I mean it hasn't been slow. It seems to be compositing and accelerated wi-fi seems to work
Okay, wi-fi was there like in the installer process like no since then it's been just perfect
you know a lot of this leads me to wonder the direction that google is traveling and I I
I would not be at all surprised if in if in 10 years when you buy a macbook pro it's running ios and when you
buy a
A chromebook it's running android
I think that you know as these companies continue to invest more and more money and time and effort and
Into their mobile operating system and as companies start to develop apps
And put their infrastructure in you know a mobile atmosphere. In fact, I was doing contracting for a company just last week
And they had an app that I had to send all of the information into them
Right was not available from web browser could not do it from a desktop had to be done on a smartphone
In fact, they actually told me when you know when we were negotiating the contract out
They said, you know, we want a subcontract we want you to do xyz and we need you to
Use our app because that's how we it's actually it's honestly was kind of creepy because they they actually they could take control of the webcam
so they and the microphone so that they could see what was going on and
Again, this brings me back to
I think it would be really useful to be able to virtualize something like that
And have something like that available to me so that I can you know, I can complete the the assignment
But at the end of the day, then I can shut it down
I know and heck i'm installing that on my phone, right?
It just so happens that I happen to have an android tablet that I don't really like and didn't really want
Right, right. And so I you know, I just I load it on there
In fact, I have a google account specifically for things. They don't want to use but well youtube
Wow
And that's surprising playbook
I I don't know if you can hold that up to the the camera and they they can see the playback is remarkably smooth
If you can't see that
Yeah, i'd have to hear it with sound to know if you know, it's syncing up and stuff like that
So we'd have to maybe look at that a little bit closer
But based on what i'm seeing here, I think that's I think that's great performance and you know, the thing is really
What is that a core i5? Yeah, so I mean it's got like way more hardware
A little less ram than I should be proud of
So, you know, I I think that there's a lot of use cases mumble room do you guys
Uh, what do you guys think about running android on a laptop?
I would run it in a vm. Okay depressing
Depressing why why is it depressing? I'll do it in a vm as well
so
Now i'm gonna run, you know, all of these other os's in my laptop or in my computer. It's like well
It's like well, i'm gonna have all these off-baked experiences because nobody actually targets
The thing that i'm using
right, i'll just keep letting layers so that I have
um crappy experience on my laptop supporting these
Half-baked infrastructures. Mm-hmm. No, thank you
Now you say that you say that as a developer or as an end user?
both
Okay, right as a developer. I don't want to target a thousand platforms. I want people to adopt one thing
But at the same time, um as a user I look at it's like
I'm if I support these type of things these will become of uh incentive for developers, right?
and no
Okay
I you know, I I how about outside of just uh, how about outside of of development or sandboxing security concerns?
Does anyone see this as being like?
Man, you know, I would use linux more if there were just more apps available
So now this really enables me to do that and i'm going to blow away my linux installers anyone thinking that route
I'm not i'm thinking the users might be like that
I'm actually thinking I already explained to my I know
Grandmother my father how to use android phone now
Now I don't have to explain the same thing to them again how to you know use uh google docs
on their computer because the experience
Is the same if I use remix os or a similar android pc thing, right? So they they have one
Sort of device in their pocket and the same experience on their desktop
It could be used for for users like that who are not power users
um
They just want to streamline the experience everywhere, right?
You know what non-power users should just relegate themselves to alexa google now and things like that
Not actually touch the machine and uh one thing or not
These will actually save us
And then we can actually focus on getting linux as a platform
Which if you think about it works on windows on linux in solaris in bsd
And android is based on it. So why don't we just rip android and keep the linux layer?
Which actually is what we need so that binaries work target that platform instead
Actually runs everywhere already. I find this. Uh, well, okay a couple of things about this that strike me is kind of nice
First of all nice or not. It definitely looks a lot like windows 10
But what I really think they've done right is the window controls the window border so you can use the android apps in a windowed environment
The window borders match the header color of the application. So it really looks nice. Yeah, it looks it looks like those
Applications are meant to be borderless windows and now that even desktop environments are dropping scroll bars
It doesn't look that weird to have an application with no scroll bars. It just looks like
A desktop app. I mean when you look at that, I wouldn't even know those are necessarily android apps, right? Yeah
Yeah, no for sure. It you know
And I think as that line gets blurred
I I see that as kind of a problem to be honest with you
I mean it it's great from the from the familiarity standpoint the press was saying, you know
how you know, you can show your parents to use this and the other but the thing I do get a little bit concerned about is
I like my desktop. I like I like my desktop operating system
And and it seems like every day we take steps to make
The desktop a little bit less relevant and mobile a little bit more relevant
And it seems like this is one more step in that direction
No, no
No in that case would gb more comfortable with running something like chrome os where you can run android apps
But you're keeping a more stock linux experience under the hood
You know, I feel like chrome os is the closest i've I have gotten
to uh to mainstream linux
That I could live with but it misses the beat
I mean we discussed this on linux action show a couple weeks ago
it misses the beat because one is we start to fall into this fallacy of
our team's winning rather than
We actually have a good solution chrome os. Let's face it is really not a whole lot better than mac os or windows
It technically has a linux kernel
And it technically has a linux shell
And that's pretty much where it ends and then
We're stuck. I mean I can't install gimp. I can't install inkscape. I can't install libreoffice
I can't install I mean all of the things that I want to do with a linux installation feel like a traditional linux desktop
Linux desktop, right and all the freedoms that come with a linux desktop and all the you know
And the other thing is too is and i've said this before on the air and it is worth repeating because it applies to both
Chrome os and it applies to android on a laptop
I don't fundamentally trust those operating systems. And so I will not put highly sensitive information pictures videos documents, whatever
on a chrome os laptop or on a
Or on an android laptop and you know actually and to second that
All of those important files are encrypted with lux and I don't know about you
But I haven't really found a way to get lux to work
On chrome os or on android. I have not tried but uh, you're right
it's just
As far as the um
thing you mentioned earlier that um, you
still want your uh
Classic desktop experience and you don't want that mobile thing to take over that battle is already lost. Uh,
I think two or three years ago. I talked to uh,
Uh, I think he was a backend developer at tablo
Okay, and he said their user base is growing and it's growing steadily
But the desktop user base
Is stagnant all the new users that come in are phone and tablet users
So this is the next generation
well
It's a growth trend that just continues in that direction, right? So the next generation of consumers are all
People who want that mobile experience. Well, I have to be honest with you
I'm, really hoping what that means
is that it opens up a void in the desktop space and allows linux to take more of a foothold because I think that
I think that windows has been dying a slow death for a long time and I I I
I continue to hold that hope that that mac os really isn't making any serious headway into the desktop space
Uh, and so, you know, they're you know, really their their eggs are, you know a lot in mobile as well
Um, so hopefully they just it kind of leaves that void and you know a lot of people do that a lot of people are
You know, they see laptop and desktops as the old generation the old way of doing things
Um, and if that's the case great leave that kind of stuff to me and that's what my generation
Maybe there are different types of people where like you just don't need it and okay
That's fine and you can zoom and create to the level that you can on those devices
Well chris said it best when we were at system 76
He goes yeah tablet living works great and mobile living works great until you need to get real work done. Then you need a laptop
Um, so it is what it is. Hey guys, then you buy an ipad pro
Yeah, which doesn't have a key which doesn't have a keyboard and is really more of a tablet and runs ios and so that's you know
You have these new microsoft tablets the surface book, you know
Yeah, i've tried getting linux to run on those those I haven't you know
Had much of a chance to get that to work well either. Hey guys, you know
One of the things that I uh, I come here every time I come here
I i'm excited to work with chris and i'm excited to meet up with rikai and have a chance to chat with wess and whatnot
but
The other thing I always try to look at is what is the network doing?
What changes is the network making what direction is the network growing?
And as a you know as a person on the outside
I always thought I kind of had a decent idea because I think chris does a really good job of keeping people up to date
but he he has been working night and day for the you know months to make some of these fundamental changes possible like the
Streaming services there are streaming servers that are going out to the different services and providing you guys with an uncut feed
of
All of the shows here and that's huge. Yeah, it's huge
but the the thing that I think often gets overlooked is a lot of people are great at doing addition on the internet and
Not so great at doing subtraction and the reality is that there's a cost associated with that, right?
When he is when he is paying rikai
To you know to to work on all of this stuff or when he's having me do all this stuff when he's having other
People come in and you know and try to get all this infrastructure not to mention actually pay for the physical infrastructure itself
And let me tell you
I mean I was here I watched firsthand how carefully he was counting
Costs trying to make every single penny count because we had to stretch it as far as humanly possible to make this possible
And then you get to the end of it and it's like well
We still aren't going to be able to make this work quite the way we really want it to well
We'll find a way we're gonna we're gonna shoehorn this we're gonna shoehorn that or we're gonna we'll we'll outsource this and thank god
we have you know resources like digital ocean that allow us to expand that but
I see so many people that they will pay for a ten dollar netflix subscription
My in-laws and I was showing chris the text this earlier
My in-laws have a netflix subscription that they don't use they pay every month for a netflix subscription
But because they bought one of these smart tvs that turned out to be outdated like in six months
By the way, I I think I did mention this to them like six months ago when they bought it
I imagine like I was like, you know smart tv not a great choice
And so the smart tv goes out of date and so this netflix app isn't working and I don't know
Working and I find out about this and i'm like, well, you know, you could buy
You know one of the little streaming sticks or whatever and stick in there and i'm explaining this to my in-laws and then it dawns
On me they are paying ten dollars a month
For content that they don't even watch right and don't touch and the reason for that is well
I think it's a couple fold one is I think they they buy into the netflix experience
They buy into the netflix desire that they have access to this on-demand content in the back of your mind
You know, you can watch it whenever you want exactly you never do exactly and and then second of all
It's they put it on you know, you put it on automatic, you know draft or whatever and you just forget about it
So I guess what i'm asking you guys to do is why not do that for jb the people here
I promise you the people in this building
Are working twice as hard than most of the people at netflix to bring you content and the thing is we don't restrict the content
We give it to you in labor respecting formats. We give it to you in the the the most common formats
You just you you download it and we don't even charge you for I mean you go to the website
You just download it and all we're asking in return is that if you appreciate the content if you like what we do here
You know, I used to have a friend he used to say
Gratuitous, uh, it was uh rabbi lapin. He used to say, um
gratuity is
Is what you give people with president's faces on them and their tokens of appreciation, right?
And and you know, there are so many different levels that you can contribute now
um, you know i'm looking here you can get started at three bucks three bucks a month and
That's a great way to say. Thank you
And the thing is like I think a lot of people fall into this they say well
I don't know if I you know, I don't know if that really does anything
You know, the reality is if everyone that said that just signed up for three bucks a month
Which by the way is a third of the cost of netflix
So if you think about it, you're you're getting it at like 66 percent discount nothing
Yeah, exactly and it it does a lot
Of course if you can afford to help more than you know, and people do we get emails in all the time
And you know, we don't always read them because it's quite frankly
There's no good content weight to read flattering emails sometimes
But there's a lot of people that have said the network has helped them get a new linux job
The network has helped them, you know double their income because absolutely, you know, they're now working in a different field
So I would just encourage you guys if you like the content we're producing here go over to patreon.com
And sign up to be a patron
If this became a wider spread thing
If more people were involved in the patreon and putting their voting with their their money
Chris and the entire network becomes beholden to them and them alone
And so really you are you are you're not only saying thank you. You're not only saying
Uh, we hear we see the content that you're doing. We appreciate the content that you're doing and we thank you, but you're also
You're also buying a piece of power, right?
You're also buying that that little bit of this is what I want to see done
And you know, we try and listen to that. So we're at
3981 now every time that i've been here
I kind of have i'm starting to get a record like if I come here
And I and I make some ridiculous promise then something ridiculous happens, right?
Right. I I don't know what I mean. I wore a window shirt. I mean, what else do you want from me? You know
Uh, but I think it would be super cool if we could get to 4 000 patrons now that is
That is what 19 patrons. It just had 19 people 19 people sign up
We'd have like four that's a really nice that is doesn't that have a nice ring to it really does
It has a nice ring to it
I think that that would go over I I think then chris would be like
No one west do not totally screw up the show when we let them do it and then and then our beatings are way less
Severe they are they are he doesn't get nearly as he doesn't get nearly as as as upset with us
And we might even get to eat tonight. Yeah, if only we could get 19 patrons. So let's try to make that a goal
Let's see 19 patrons. We get 19 people to sign up for patreon.com
slash today
I'll have to think of something. I don't know what I again I just you know a window shirt. I don't know
What else am I gonna do?
um windows tattoo
To that ain't gonna happen too far 10 000 patrons. It's not no it's not gonna happen
Like even if they were my patrons, I know patreon.com
Today anyone else in the mumble room have any closing thoughts?
Not necessarily about patreon but just about linux in general you guys come on now
We are
You what? Yeah, I guess so I guess everything has
Either we have gone through and said everything humanly possible or everyone is totally tuned out because we totally screwed it up
But that's all right
All right. Well, thank you very much
Thank you very much mumble room for being a part of the linux unplugged this week
I really appreciate the opportunity to step in here for hair master chris
Well, he's out getting some much-needed rest and then he can just kind of pop in here when he has great things to say
The hair doesn't maintain itself folks. No, no, it sure doesn't. Thanks a lot west for being here. I really appreciate it
It's wonderful to see you know it great. Well, we'll see you right back here next week
So
I've never installed gnu slash linux zombies don't run linux
Is and the value of this is negative
So
So get it out of here
You know one thing I uh one thing i'd really like I wish that soundboard thing had like a waveform so I could see
When it's about to hit the thingy. Yeah, I have one that does that wouldn't you? Yeah good show. No a good show
Thank you. Good show. Oh boy to get warm in here or what? Yeah
I changed
I literally changed mid show I changed so that all that stuff about patreon air conditioning would be amazing. Oh my god
Thank you mumble room. You guys are great. Think about how much longer they can work
But you can't run it during the show, right?
Dot com well if we got a unit that's across the yard and then we ducted it over here what we would do is
Then we would run it into the furnace and then the essentially the furnace would be the distributor of the cold air
That's the plan. You tell the real central air. Yeah, i've been looking into this
It also means our furnace here in the studio is 18 years old now, so we'd have to replace the furnace, too
Just get the whole job done. Jimmy titles
Now we all gotta go boat. Oh, did you have fun noah? Yeah. Thank you. Good good
Uh, the talking gnome noah's arch the gnome talks back
Arch will strike kelly down titles on android. Oh, that is a pretty that's a more solid implementation than I expected
Me too. That's what honestly. Yeah
There was some reason I was like wanting someone to run android or I was wanting to run android
I would use it like it's totally if there was an android app
I had to have yeah, or if I had a device like this that I wanted to have a sling tv on or something
Like that, okay. This will fix your android
You got angros on that usb
I like how every time you get on mic these days you paint me as like this
Unmovable arch user who is so in entrenched into arch. All right. All right. All right, mr
Hot shot like like I couldn't point the machine running a running a distribution under the arch. Are you really?
I mean, this is kind of unfortunate because that's running mint right there
You see that mint menu right there, yeah, yeah
I I just I just I just if it's here's where my
Point to the machine that's that's not running arch that you didn't install for a review
Well, okay, that's true. But also it just comes down to this if it's a computer. I want to install software on
Then I don't use ubuntu
That's just that's the calculus if it's a machine if it's a computer
I'm gonna install one piece of software on like mumble and skype
So two pieces of software then it's no big deal to run a ubuntu can handle that just fine
You know, it's really easy to install telegram from the play store on android
Yeah, you know, maybe you should oh, whoa
What if skype was better on that on remix os and it is on desktop linux?
Then we could start using that for our calls
Actually just something quickly on telegram
I didn't I didn't realize this I just got an ubuntu phone the first time ever and the telegram client on ubuntu
Like ubuntu touched is beats the crap out of the android. I've heard it's really good
Stickers yet
It's uh, I don't know
I'm going to send you a message. Let's see
Okay, because last time I checked
um even support stickers, which is like
You know what, you know what, oh my god, I don't know i'm not normally this guy
But this guy on reddit was giving me so much crap for how I covered
The own cloud story in the linux action show this sunday
and then I just realized that both frank
and
Joss tweeted out our coverage specifically. I was referring people to it, which gives me the sense that we were probably close to the mic
Yeah, I saw that nailed today. What's that?
They've got more news today
the uh foundation
Yeah from own cloud inc
Like if you if you have a look at it like
If you look at that in the context of everything that yos and frank and everybody said about why they left
like
The pieces are starting to come together. It's like it's pretty clear to me
This is why they left
This foundation
Yeah, because like they like think about frank's initial bit of like who owns the community blah blah blah
then look at the foundation thing and
There's only two community elected seats on that board
There's four corporate seats where any company can effectively buy their eligibility for that board
There's one own cloud appointee. So that's out of a seven person board. The community's only two people
And that's the kind of thing that I could see getting
When you put that in the context of frank stuff that that's all looking really interesting
Dude, you're totally right. Like I was reading that all backwards. I thought the foundation was a reaction to
You know some of this bad
It's press that they were getting because of people leaving but I bet you're right. I bet it's the opposite. I
Mean the weird the weird thing with me I read that announcement and I read their their current spec and it's like okay
I mean, I know i'm biased i'm, you know chairman of open sues of heaven's sake but
looked at their rules and foundation charter and it's like
They took everything out of the open suzer board spec
And like ripped out the community part
Yeah, people say i'm creating fud in this in the subreddit. I don't
I find that I find that subreddit. Sometimes I just can't I can't track their same thinking. I don't think it's spreading fud
I think it's I think it's like I guess
What is exactly the fud of it? What's fun about saying these these people?
And not only did I not cover it when it first started happening because it just seemed like drama
But I waited till like multiple people left and another organization reported in this case. It was pharaonic
I think even like I I don't think necessarily you did anything wrong
But even if you covered it in a poor way
I think it was clear that your intentions were there like you you've you've discussed that quite clearly
I don't even yeah, I I guess when I look at it
I I guess it feels like it feels like we're walking the line of
If you talk about this stuff that equates to spreading fud and that's the line that makes me uncomfortable
Don't say the bad things just don't ever talk about the bad things
I think the bit the subreddit is trying to get onto and and I I agree with this part if this is a subreddit's point
of there's a distinction between own cloud inc and the own cloud community and I think
Yeah, what frank is trying to allude to actually part of the problem is that people don't see that distinction. So
Your coverage is kind of evidence of that because you didn't really make a distinction between the two so you kind of equated
Well, no, I did specifically say
Well, no, okay. So when we started the coverage, I did specifically say that there are two different entities
But I think I I think it's because I am of the opinion that if frank and joss and others leave
It's it is a bad sign. It's not necessarily they're doomed, but I am
Honestly of the opinion that it is a bad development for them
I don't think that's necessarily
Bad analysis either. I think that is a concerning development
I have no idea what they're planning besides. I have a pretty good suspicion. They're going to announce something tomorrow and
obviously frank is a keynote speaker at open suzer conference later this month, but um
the you know
This could be like the libra office of the open office for own cloud. Hmm. Interesting
Yeah, I I don't know if that's true this is purely speculation
My end but you know, you know everybody said the same with libra office
What are these crazy guys doing getting all idealistic and you know skipping away from that and it kind of worked out all right for them
Well, you know i've had a lot of conversations with frank
um, and he seems like a pretty intelligent individual and he seems like he's a pretty he's
He very much is a big picture kind of person and uh, I I I think
For that kind of project. He's a good person to be involved
And so I just think it's a little unfortunate and hopefully if it does kind of go like the way of libra office open office
Um, hopefully it'll sort of work out the same way. It has long-term, too
For them, I don't know. This is linux unplugged episode 147
For may 31st 2016
Like what month is it what month is it?
This is bsd unplugged, okay, here we go. All right, let's try again
This is linux unplugged episode 147 for may 31st 2016
So
Welcome to linux unplugged your weekly linux talk show where we have kicked your host out of his seat and made him
The soundboard operator. My name is noah
My name is west
This is what happens when we this is why we don't have nice things this is why we don't have nice things technology
All right, the one the one thing this thing's supposed to do the one thing the one job this computer literally has
Okay, no, it was micro usb. Probably wouldn't have that problem. There we go. One more time. No