I've got a big problem and I need your guys's help
I I've discovered there is a major hole in my life that I did not know was there until I got a couple of
Days of downtime. I'm sitting there on the Thanksgiving holiday week in the rover
I'm like, you know what? I want to do. I want to watch some TV. Maybe even I want to watch some home alone
Cozy up watch some home alone
Then I remembered that my whole rover runs off of a my fight connection and all of a sudden I went from not caring about
TV at all to I got to have a way that I can like come down to the studio
Sink media to some kind of device go back to the rover and play offline still with some streaming options if I want them
Right, I keep and so here's the solution
I don't want to use because this is what seems like the easy solution
Take an iPad with the Plex app
Yep
Come down here to the studio
sync to the Plex server to the iPad bring the iPad back to the rover and
Watch like Plex on the iPad offline
Mmm, but that's not very Linux II. No, there's got to be a way to do it
Like and I'm so I'm I'm curious what could what could be like a decent?
What are people's offline media solution where you have maybe like a collection of media somewhere?
I have a quick question for you Chris. Yeah
How do you have a defined way you'd like to be watching it in the rover?
I mean, do you have a TV? Do you know?
No, I don't I would for not to be on definitely not on the desktop
Are you do you have a mobile a laptop with a decent-sized screen would be okay or a tablet would be okay
Basically something that's decent enough to watch a TV on but it doesn't have to be that big
So I thought maybe I could do like an MB
server with maybe like a tablet app right or on a laptop or maybe like well
Like I said Plex on a tablet could be an Android tablet, too
But I just I hate Android tablets sure or our sink, you know
I could just our sink some files over from time to time and use VLC, right?
but I would really like something that has like played status and resume support for where I left off and maybe
transcoding support for different devices
So I don't really know what the solution is here because the ideal the ideal thing would be like, okay
It's a Friday and I'm here at the studio. I'll sync up a couple of shows and then I'll go home for the weekend
And I watch all my stuff and then I come back
On Monday for Kota radio and I think but I watched we take some stuff off put some stuff on
It would be really nice
Wimpy do you have an idea because I see my you you said I know you know what it is. Tell me when we yeah
okay, so
What we have here what we have in the house here is
a server running open media vault with
Plex installed on that so all of the media is on there
So consequently anyone in the house using any device
can watch the film when our shortwave radio is down to
You know stream it to your device with transcoding working and all the rest of it. So if you had a small Plex
Server or you could do it then be as well. I suppose does anybody do transcoding for devices? Yeah
Yeah, yeah, then you could use that as well and you you host it in
The RV and then so and then and then just sort of over time
Trickle content down to it and content add content to the server as and when you get the opportunity, you know
So the way that we add content to this is we buy
Blu-ray discs and I have a machine that I ripped the films off the Blu-ray into the media
I mean, yeah, that's actually pretty good. I have seen just in that same vein if you're an MB supporter
They have a folder sync. Yeah, and so you can transcode out you can target a specific
Yes, and so you might be able to do that to an external hard drive and bring it in if you hadn't it at one
There maybe too much work. I'm not sure it wouldn't have probably that probably wouldn't have the watch status
I wonder about that
That would go basically I would use MB to organize all the files and then use its folder sync plug-in right to manage
I have not tried that but Popey you said you had an idea
Yeah, I just posted a link in IRC it's a device which is a mobile wireless access point
That has a USB port and an SD card slot and it's got a battery
So it's designed to be a portable media server
so you just stick all your media on a USB Drive plug it into that thing and then you can go anywhere carry this thing with
You and it creates a wireless access point you connect to connect multiple devices to it and just stream media straight off it to any
Device. Oh, wow. Nice. So basically probably uses what DLNA to to connect to it
So anything that supports DLNA playback and stream off of it
I'm not sure what protocol it uses but the good news is it is flashable. So you can actually stick anything
You can put like Linux or open WRT or some other random stuff on it as well
You can hack it
but the fact that it's got a battery and it means you can go out and about and still carry on listening to content off of
It or like watching media off of it when the power goes out Wow
I mean this is so they even have a newer version. I
How can this be? I've got the old one. It's like 30. It's like 30 bucks us. That seems entirely too reasonable
Yeah, I mean, there's no there's no storage in it. So you've got to provide an SD card in there, right?
But you can have an SD card of TV shows and SD card of movies and who doesn't have one laying around
Interesting interesting that is actually pretty neat. I'm gonna put a link to that in the show notes. That's a pretty neat idea
I wonder though if
You know what to me what what I really would like is something that is kind of what wimpy was saying where I just have
A rig in the rover that's that is receiving files through maybe like sync thing or something. Yeah, that's my idea
You sink thing. Yeah, okay, but then here's the problem though at first of all
It requires connectivity in the rover all the time. And the second thing is I'm still not sinking my watch data
So do I do I just give up on that? I guess well, you could like deleted or something
You don't necessarily have to I don't know you could find some other way put it in a separate folder
Just use the file system
Yeah, deal with more status connection all the time. No, does it only needs connection periodically, you know in order to sync synchronize?
Yeah, it's like, you know, whenever you like pull up outside McDonald's get it to synchronize over there Wi-Fi or whatever
I mean you can set it up in such a way that you had to be at home
So it had to only sync when you were local at the studio
Or you could do it like when you set up a VPN connection so it could be explicit
So it's only sinking when you're on a connection that you think has enough bandwidth
Well, it feels nice though. I mean what I was kind of fantasizing the reason why the
The iPad or Android tablet running Plex is so fancy to me is because I just bring it with me one day
And I just hit a button it just sucks down all the new stuff
And then I walk away and it's got all the new stuff and no connection required at the rover at all
I have a wild idea what what if you use something like
ZFS or butter fs snapshots. Yeah, take snapshots of your MB installation
Oh, hold on West send that right to an external or something and connect it up and run MB from that drive and then have it
Rescan your library and then it would only show you things that you you had kept that is interesting
I don't know. It's overly complicated. You'd have to set it a lot of stuff. I love it though. I love it
I love it
I know it uses a sequel like database to store a lot of configuration and probably the watch status too
I don't know
I think I have there's a lot that appeals me to a popes old device and also to wimpy solution
Yes, the thing the one thing I like about
Something simple is I guess I'm trying to I'm trying to punt for as long as possible on setting up a server in the rover
At least I'd like to get through the end of winter
I don't know, but we'll see maybe maybe maybe a NUC and a little hard external hard drive
It's just I don't know. I don't know. It's a lot to set up
Yeah, it is it is and I've already I've already set up two in two other places and I have a third on digital ocean
Right now so it's like do I really want a for how much infrastructure? Do you want to be responsible?
Yeah, I just uh, it's getting I'm getting tired of it
I want something to move to a smaller house, but with more devices because it basically I don't watch media that often anymore
But right. Yeah, it was and then of course I'm thinking to myself. Where is my dang?
my dang purism laptop because I could just
Do that right now. I could just as a 1080p display. I could watch some 1080p on there. I
Got nothing
Yeah, yeah, I agree I might just do VLC I might just do VLC and an NFS mount over the net
I don't know. I could do that too. And to be honest, you know, both ambient plex have pretty good solutions here
So I might just watch to see what they do too, right?
I'm that MB that MB sync folder sync thing might be a nice go-between in the meantime, right?
Interesting to try anyway, you'll have to let us know
This is Linux unplugged episode 121 for December 1st
You
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly the next talk show that it wants its portability and its horsepower
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello Wes
That might be a little hint to something we're gonna talk about later in the show today. Oh look at you Chris
I know look at me teasing in fact coming up on today's episode of 121. We got a lot
We're gonna start with a little look back over some recent things that developed including from the GIMP project a topic
We touched on last week Fedora 24
Has got something brand new that no other distro is doing and I'm gonna put it to the virtual lug
Is this maybe something we should all consider setting up on our own Linux installations?
We'll talk about that and then later on in the show. It's the tiny mini itsy bitsy PC revolution
Whoa, in fact there have one right here in studio. We got it right here. It's called the Omega onion
Yeah, and it is a modular stackable PC, but there's a lot
You know we've also got that new Raspberry Pi micro mini thing tiny little computer that's done stuff floating could probably put Cody on
Um oh, and then in the end of the show I
Can't believe it Wes here. We are December 1st 2015 and Adobe has announced. They're killing flash really well
Not more. Yeah, it's yes
Yeah, don't believe the headlines, but I thought you know what we will tell you what's happening, and I thought why don't why?
Don't we just chat about what we do as Linux users to avoid using flash whenever possible
And I am on a flash anti crusade this week because it basically locked up my accession this week
So Chris has got an agenda to well
I'm gonna grind some gears to be honest with you and then towards the end
Maybe even in the post show if we have some time
I'm gonna ask the virtual lug what they're thankful for kind of as an homage to what we did on Sunday's
Linux action show that's on a stuff West yeah, that's great
I'm pretty sure what's a big show, so why don't we get started by bringing in our virtual lug time appropriate greetings mama room?
So guys guys
I don't know how many of you are gamers
But I talk about steam games way too much so I want to just mention something really awesome
When a total kickbutt open-source game has an update and it's a big update
Warsaw 2.0 released with better graphics creative commons license game assets all that goodness with a 30 to 50 percent faster performance
New heads-up display all kinds of weapon parameter tweaks, and it's that game that has that cool cell shaded effect
Oh, yeah, yeah, this is a cool cool open-source game
And I kind of left it off my list accidentally on Sunday
And so today they have a brand new update West a brand new update
And I already installed it this morning and played it a little bit. It's a lot of fun
It looks like a lot of fun. We should set something up people to play it and it's a real fun window to land game
It's really easy to get going and because it's open-source everybody can be on the same version
No awesome CD key generators required or anything like that so Warsaw 2.0 release congrats to those guys
I just want to give them a shout a shout out
Because yeah
Because we should have probably mentioned it on Sunday now something to follow up on from last week's episode 120 of Linux unplugged
We talked about GIMP hitting 20 years old quite the milestone on a years old and now can't quite drink yet
And it doesn't get a discount on rentals, but they do have some brand new features that they released
Just after Linux unplugged came out like they heard our show and they're like boy those dicks
Let's show let's show what let's let's show those guys those Linux unplugged bastards over Jupiter broadcasting
So they came out with a new update and they've got some good stuff in there now
Of course as I'm done to find the chat room points out GIMP can now drink in most
most countries yeah Rod and are you still around and did you catch anything in this GIMP update that
Caught your interest because I know you were kind of hard on GIMP last week
Yeah, they've actually made some announcements that they're they're gonna be using
GEGL
Do non-destructive editing in the future they don't have that right now, but thanks to the GEGL
They're also doing 16-bit and 32-bit projects, right so that's
some
Fundamental things that that was missing so they're I'm optimistic
But very cautiously optimistic we call it GEGL. I think that's more fun
Yeah, but
No
Yeah, I mean so the 32-bit thing's a big deal also huge improvements to open up PNG TIFF and PSD files
Which if you think about people that are making the migrations, that's a big deal and and one of them, huh?
The PSD thing is the PSA thing is overrated because you think they're saying that you can open up things
That's true, but there are things that you can't open regardless of the they're better supporting the format
But the majority of PSDs are gonna have features that are not going to be available
So for example, if you try to open up a CMYK PSD just breaks. Yeah. Well, yeah
Yeah, that makes sense and also some new canvas rotation tools that some people are said well, okay
We've kind of needed that for a long time. I mean at the same so there's a it's it's it's sort of what we talked about
Last week. It's really hard not to talk about the GIMP and talk about how it's not stacking up to the commercial alternatives
And I kind of tried to make the case last week that really what we should be
Stacking it up against is anything else in this class that is free, right?
Because in this it's not that free is an excuse for not high-quality
It's that free is an enablement for a certain class of humanity that cost
Sometimes there's a huge barrier for
Hello. Hi there. Hi there. So I mean I'm I I I wish GIMP was more competitive at the same time
I'm really glad they've steadily improved the way they have in it. Yeah, I don't follow the development that closely but
Potential it seems like there's a little bit more renewed interest, you know, they've got the new website design out
I still think looks nice. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. They're pushing forward on some features. We'll see
I think you know, obviously I'm continuing to watch
I'm optimistic about it mainly because of a lot of the things that was really frustrating me that they didn't have
They're implementing now and they're bringing in
CMYK support they haven't officially given like a date when it's coming
But they have announced that it's coming and they're bringing them plugins for that are
Trying to get like layer styles and stuff like that, but just the fact that they are actually, you know
You know telling people that they're even doing this is an improvement
They're you know, printing out press releases and stuff
they've never done before and like they've they've changed a lot of their direction, which I appreciate as
someone who wants him to be a solution, but
Based on the you know, 20 years of it not being remotely
Relevant to me as a professional. I'm
Cautious, but I hope I'm wrong
All right, I'm gonna be it. It's actually going to be great. I'm gonna be that guy. I
Hate that I have to be that guy, but just consider this is Chris putting on his devil's advocate pants
It says devil's advocate right on the butt there. Thank you. Thank you. I
Is is it really just a matter of too little too late and I the reason I don't mean because you know
Photoshop's the thing because that's obvious
I mean, I've been reading a lot of reviews about people that are now drawing on tablets like
Odyssey Westra who joins us frequently right draws on a tablet and very very good drawings
The Apple's iPad Pro just came out with their hundred dollar pencil and their thousand dollar tablet for drawing
there are a lot of apps out there now that take the touchscreen and maybe like a
Peripheral and you are now like reaching an entire different audience
And and the reason why I wonder if this is kind of a little too little too little too late kind of thing for gimp
Is the audience those types of devices are reaching is?
The casual average everyday person the exact kind of person that gimp is perfect for only not all that appealing to and so I
Look at this and I go about 20 years now and now we're at a point
Where guys like poppy are trying to replace the desktop PC with an Ubuntu phone?
I'm like are they're gonna get to 25 years and then
That that usage that that that desktop paradigm is gonna be out of date and there's gonna be even less people using it than ever
before I
Don't know well, it's a as a professional I'm not looking at using a tablet except for a wacom tablet
So though those are just perfectly great using on a desktop and you would use that with gimp or something to say if gimp had good
enough feature set
Yeah, I mean right now I use
illustrator and Krita
Right and but see you're looking at it more from a professional angle and that seems pretty legit and I don't think you could really ever
replace
Like the wacom tablet and the desktop level applications for any kind of serious work
But if you want to sketch something out you want to just doodle a little bit
This is almost too much stuff and it's too much complication
But yet the very people it's appealing to you are people that maybe are not high-end professionals. Do you want am I making sense?
Yeah, I wonder if there's a distinct categories to like in in at least in in America, you know first world countries
I think I think you're right
I think that people you know have enough means that if they want a nice drawing environment
That's easy to use and doesn't have all the crazy features. They can get a nice tablet or something like that. I wonder about maybe
The developing world, you know places where they have less access or they can't kind of expense this spend that money on a whim to get
Just something for drawing, you know as a hobby
Maybe maybe that's what you can have more of a place if you're drawing
Not just like if you're creating design, right? It's more of Karita in Inkscape
Yeah, yeah, if you're if you're doing web design game, maybe it's a better tool
But yeah drawing I would push Kimpa side because I doesn't have the features that create a house, right?
I think really I still free and open source line and speaking of Albert Odyssey Westra
create I believe is what he uses to do his drawing so that and that that makes sense I was just kind of what I
Was postulating was is if the average use case is perhaps becoming more and more niche for GIMP, right?
It does kind of see it does seem that way but at the same time
One more thing. Yeah, go ahead. Yeah, right the the the the introductory like the beginner
Introduction to drawing is actually easier for a desktop because you can get a Wacom tablet for 50 bucks. Mm-hmm
So you could actually get you know, use create
I use a Wacom tablet and or even use something else and you'd be able to do a lot more for a lot less
To just to get it started
You know what else is kind of interesting for me from a technology standpoint
And I'm probably nobody else really cares about this
but GIMP is
Obviously a showcase of what the GTK toolkit can do right and Corita in its own way if I believe is QT
Right, so you have two completely different toolkits here that the two big toolkits being used to create two very high-end
Art applications. Where does Inkscape fall in this?
Is Inkscape GT GTK? I don't know. Yeah
It is. Yeah, okay. It's just fascinating from a couple of different angles to watch these two applications
Even though as somebody that has zero art skill that doesn't totally really ever apply to me
Funniest thing about GIMP and the GTK toolkit is
The fact that the newest version of GIMP has a 2.9 point X has like a much improved theming system
Why can't they use it?
Like they built a cool toolkit. They built a cool theming system yet GIMP is still hideous
It's kind of weird that they build the fundamentals, but they don't have the ability to use what they build
Yeah, that's unfortunate. Yeah, I mean
Yeah, I guess I do agree. That is pretty it is it is there's a lot going on
You can make that customization argument with almost anything
Look at Gnome lots of theming potential there
But really there's only about four strong themes out there that really look good
Yeah, I had to fall of Gnome looks pretty good just by it by itself. All right, it's okay
Well, it's when you compare it to things like XFCE that oh, yeah. Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah, absolutely
I mean, it's it's a good design
Even if it's not perfect, but it's a little okay
Ed way to is a weird design but yeah, the shell itself is nice. Yeah, you put arc theme on there
You're good to go. Yeah, you're good. Have you installed the arc theme? I have that's from the yeah
That's that's pretty slick. That is a seriously great theme
yeah, and then you just mix and match the icons as you feel at it and I'm telling you I
My personal opinion is I don't think there's a better looking desktop
If you match the icons you go all dark and you put the arc theme on there
I think it's the best looking desktop on the planet
So yeah, yeah gnomes are and why whatever is your yeah Unix point, right? I should you're right. Well, it's right here
It's on all my rigs
They've slowly over time what I what I what I found is kind of interesting is I just sort of landed on this in each
Of my gnome installations too. It's not like it's not something I don't sit down and go. Oh god. It's all the arc theme, right?
No, it just kind of happens
Anyways, I mumble room any other thoughts before we move on from the GIMP topic or create or anything else wimpy
I know there was you'd ping me at one point was there anything you wanted to add to the chat?
I know I think you've covered it just that some creatures and better tool for freehand drawing. Yeah, then gimp gimp is a photo editor
Yeah, I'm glad we made that point because I didn't want to yeah, I didn't want to walk away from that. I had something. Yeah
I don't think it really
replaces the tablet and everything because there are different use cases totally the
Tablet is a console is not a console. It's a consumption advice device not a
Production, I think that's starting to change though
You know
You look at Microsoft with their surface and you look at convergence device that are coming and you got iPad pros now with keyboards and pencils
I guess
Laptops that have touchscreens and stuff. Yeah, even like I've tried hooking up a keyboard with a tablet never
It's just not the same as it really is. No, I do agree
It's not there yet totally different feel but I wonder if it's there enough enough if it's there and for some people who do want
To create, you know, they don't need a futz with anything
They just want a canvas and enough to work or you know
Like so my mom is a professional graphic artist, right?
And so one of the things that I know she would do is you start with a sketch and you could do that on the tablet
And then you move it into Photoshop where you get the actual work done would be how she would look at it
I start with the outline on this nice little touchy device here that lets me draw maybe at the coffee shop
You just got your tablet. Yeah, or actually I'm at the client meeting the clients talking to me
Just do it right there in the meeting
But then they can they can you know send that out in different formats and bring it into like Adobe Sketch is a thing
Even on the tablets and yeah
So yeah, it's interesting just to see that particular use case getting eaten up eaten up by that
But yeah in the long term if you want to sit down and do any serious work
I mean for her I maybe that's just because she's been doing it for so long now
But she will never ever ever consider replacing her desktop with a tablet ever
So yeah, but maybe for somebody heavens. Do you want to take us out on the last note here? Mm-hmm
Yes, the one thing that I think for you know open so much software might
Be a little bit
The underdog is that the producers are creators of the software
Do not need to force their consumers to buy their product
So they might not be or have incentive to actually make it really good or at least worth money
Or another way to say that is they don't have to they don't have to chase the shiny
Yeah, even though a lot of people can get paid for doing gimp work
They don't really need to you know, sell it do a lot of PR
Yeah, I think that's not why that makes them
I think it's the the the amount of money that they don't get money from it and they're not trying to sell it is
Not necessarily a bad thing, but it does make their production slower
So if they had more that they did like a Indiegogo or something where they could get money and pay more developers to do more
Faster GIMP would be a much more relevant program, but because they take so long to do
everything
That's one of the reasons why it's just you know fall behind so much
Even in the open source field because I mean if you if you're wanting to do basic editing, you don't really go to camp
There's stuff like pinta, which is much smaller simpler much easier to use and if you're gonna do like really
Extensive drawing you don't go to get by there you go to create it
So I mean GIMP is even falling back in the open source field
hmm
Boy, there's more to shame. There's more to this conversation than I first thought. Yeah, definitely
I'm curious to hear what the audience thinks listening because I feel like I feel like this is one of those conversations
Or maybe somebody's listening and screaming at their car stereos are driving down the road or something. I don't know anything
Yeah, which we don't that's fine Linux action show our reddit.com episode 121 if you would I'd like to hear your thoughts
Because this is fascinating because GIMP to me is just such a great case study
Such a good one for so many different highlights and you know, maybe some of the low points of open source. Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm, you know speaking of highlights our first sponsor this week digital ocean use our promo code get ready for this right in your face
Do unplugged one word lowercase $10 credit digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated offering most intuitive and easy way for you
To get your own rig up on their kick-ass servers Linux freeBSD. It don't matter
They got a great infrastructure all Linux rigs powering everything
SSDs for all the disk IO KVM for the virtualizer 40 gigabit e-connections for their data centers
It's rockin go check them out
You can get started less than 55 seconds and pricing plans are only five dollars a month for 512 megabytes of RAM
20 gigabyte SSD one CPU under terabyte of
Of transfer terabyte terabyte 40 40 gigabit. I mean, that's great West
Did you ever did you ever work on any kind of projects or stuff?
Like five six seven eight years ago that where you had to get like a co-located server and like put an actual server in the rack
It's a pain. It is huge pain
Yeah
And the cost is is nuts and and so when I say a terabyte of transfer in these reads
I can't help but look I mean I can't help but think back to when a terabyte of transfer
at the average transfer price was a thousand dollars just for a terabyte of transfer a
Thousand dollars just for the transfer, right just for you can get that for five dollars
It really blows me away and then the fact that the whole thing is like exactly the kind of infrastructure
I would build if I could like just have an unlimited budget and have at it
That's what exactly I would build and then like even if I could build like what I would I would do Linux
I would do KVM. I would do SSDs
I would do crazy great data centers and connections
But the thing that I could never do which is really awesome is that interface. Oh
Oh that interface is crazy great simple intuitive extremely powerful
Somehow they managed to do it and and what's not only great about that is not only did they manage to get those three impossible
Things actually accomplished, but they did it on an interface that manages virtual machines. Okay, that's crazy. That is crazy to my face
That's new to the world. I think it's new to the world
So use the promo code deal and plug to get in on that s and get it for two months absolutely free and also they have
A great API to extend that all the way up into the rest of the world that really means there's a bunch of great apps
So even if you don't know how to write nothing you can go take advantage some good stuff great tutorials
They got fedora 24 up there now
They got of course all your favorite Ubuntu's your Debian's your CentOS's and even that core OS and last but not least
Free BSD. Oh my goodness free BSD is even up on that digital ocean now
I don't know why you'd want to use that. I just tease. I love you guys, but go check it out
Use the promo code do unplug support this show. It's one word
It's lowercase, and it gives you a $10 credit isn't that something amazing you can support your favorite Linux talk show and try out
Digital ocean two months for absolutely free
Digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplug in a big. Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplugged Linux unplugged
Thanks you guys
Alright, so those crazy guys who you know we got folks in here that work on their own distributions
We got folks in here from canonical. We got folks in here from Sousa
We got folks in here from a gross time to time
We got folks in here from all these different districts. You know we don't know this yeah
Thank you know you you know where we don't have reoccurring folks from
fedora
So I'm just gonna speak for them, and if I get something wrong. It's their fault. Yep
I'm just that I'm correct us you are an open invitation here, but I think this is kind of neat
I think it's a neat idea
And it's something I wanted to bounce past you and the virtual lug to see if maybe it's not something we all want to consider
Doing on our own Linux rigs so fedora 24. It's that crazy distro
That's coming out in the future in the year
2000 and it's going to support Wayland and something else that I think is a really good idea especially somebody who's on a slower
high latency internet connection a
default local DNS server
they say plain DNS is just plain insecure and therefore vulnerable from various attacks like cash poisoning a
Client can never be sure that there is a no man-in-the-middle type scenario if they don't do DNSSEC validation locally
We want to have the unbound server install and running on local hosts by default on fedora systems
And also we're necessary have DNSSEC trigger installed so what?
The fedora project is planning to do is
include the unbound DNS server set up as a default local host res resolver and
Then it'll go out to the rest of the internet if it can't find the name for something you're looking up and
I wanted to start with us, and then I wanted to bounce it around the Mamba room
I can think of in an enterprise how this could nest maybe actually be a bad thing, but
Have you ever played with setting up local DNS on your LAN and have you ever noticed anything?
And what are your thoughts on fedora just including it by default well?
I think it's I think it's true because doesn't network manager already it uses DNS mask locally. I believe by default
You might think that I think they have those good points. Okay. I think where this is different one
They're using unbound yes who if they're specifically setting up DNSSEC support and yeah, all right
So let's break that down in two parts, so let's start with why the local DNS. Why do you think?
I mean, I think it's helpful
I know like network manager wants to use it for things like split horizon DNS. This is one thing
I hope fedora gets right like for me. It's important it works
that I can have a set of DNS entries that are resolved over the VPN connection and then routed over the VPN absolutely right so
If that doesn't work then that could be pain in our vice environments where you need to be referencing name servers that get updated
You know at a set pace or not not that uncommon. Yeah, no definitely not
But I think it does give you a lot of control it also lets you cache things locally which you know that's never bad
You know I was thinking about from that angle the you know back in the rover the Wi-Fi connection right high latency connection
And if I can make every time I go out to the web a little tiny bit faster
That sounds appealing to me now. Can you touch a little bit on the DNSSEC thing so DNSSEC?
So they're going to be they're going to unbound now, and they're going to be doing DNSSEC
What do you think about that?
Do you think it's maybe time for all distros to consider doing DNSSEC out of the box?
I don't know if I would say I think it's I think it's good that fedora is exploring this
You know it does seem like there are a lot of potential vulnerabilities with DNS setups without DNSSEC
Maybe it doesn't go far enough. I don't know further discussion there is needed
But I think fedora serves usually as a useful point where in Linux
They kind of try something at a scale fully integrated into their environment
And if it works other distros will adopt it if not you know we can kind of see it
I'm excited to try Fedora 24 and see if it works. Yeah, that is actually a good point like we don't have to do it everywhere
Let's let Fedora try it. I mean like in a year or six months
Well, I think we'll see like how well does it work, but it does I mean I've only ever heard good things about unbound
So I would imagine it works pretty well now look at BNX BNX NT in the chat room says an emphatic
No on DNSSEC
An emphatic no now. I don't anybody in the mumble room know why that might be because I I'm not a DNSSEC
Yeah, no neither mine about that, but he linked us here says DNSSEC is unnecessary
All secure crypto on the Internet assumes that the DNS lookup from names to IP addresses are insecure
Securing those DNS lookups therefore enables no meaningful security because all the other stuff is
Already thinks it's insecure. That's an interesting point right there actually. I like this from two standpoints
I like it obviously from the performance standpoint, and I've been experimenting with DNSSEC myself for about a month
Oh really yeah, and I I haven't really once I did it
I didn't I actually forgot until today when I was like oh yeah, we're gonna talk about this today
I've been using it for a month on my XPS, and I forgot I even had it. That's a good thing
Yeah, so I haven't from an end-user standpoint. I feel like it. Just gives me a little more peace of mind mm-hmm
Because I know that that stuff is not in here's I
Don't mean to sound like I'm repeating myself, but I do not trust any wireless carrier any of all now right
I mean how many of them have those super cookies right and so in the rover I have I have
Right now. I have a couple of different connections and and been depending on which one strongest is the one I'll use and so I've got
A unlimited my fight advice from Ting when you know it's you pay for what you use right that I'm feeling pretty comfortable
with I really have no issues, but the one that has stronger signal where the rover is parked at is an AT&T
Yeah, if I hotspot and that one. I'm pretty uncomfortable with
You know they view super cookies in the past where they think they are yeah
And and they yes they are and they inject it into HTTP traffic right now
And so those kinds of things make me super uncomfortable because all of my internet is going to be
All of my internet is going through that right now, and so I start looking at it's things like DNS sec or VPN tunnels
Or you know HTTPS everywhere, and I start thinking if I could add these different layers
What it really does is give me peace of mind
And it I almost wonder if we won't get to a place
Six five seven years from now where we go wow I can't believe we did so much stuff over the net unencrypted like it'll just
become a commonplace for encryption for HTTPS and DNS sec and all these kinds of things because
It's not even about the encryption. It's about the validation of the endpoint
It's about validating who you're talking to is really who you intend to be talking to and I think that's the aspect of it
That will take off over the next few years, and this is going to become obvious that what do you mean?
It's what do you mean? It's not encrypted. They're just spewing plaintext to whoever wants it. Yeah, that's crazy
Yeah, somebody could just be intercepting that how do you know you're actually talking to that person right? I think that might be
Really sort of a cultural thing and that's why I'm a big fan of let's encrypt as well is because it kind of plays into
That same thing and you know it allows some dude like me to have an own cloud server that you know has a let's encrypt
Certificate have at it that your friends with your friends use it
They won't yeah walk because there's a little red X in the corner exactly or if say I set up my own matter most yeah
Server it'd be another nice thing for that a mumble room anybody have any thoughts on setting up local DNS pros and cons and if
Anybody has done it anybody in the mumble room set up a local DNS server and using it right now
Yes, and what do you think a good bad?
I don't know
It's not a big deal anymore because it's part of my deployment configuration
So it just gets applied to all my machines, so you and you install a local DNS server on each machine
You're not just doing everything your lamb now. Why is that like roaming machines?
So it's nice to have the local DNS server when you're out on the go that kind of thing yeah, that's a good point
Yeah, that's not a big deal to run it even on the machines that are already behind another level of cache
Right and what are you using to do the local DNS DNS mask, okay?
Just because it was simple and why not unbound oh
Not unbound because I'm familiar with DNS mask yeah good reason yeah
I was thinking I was thinking DNS mask seems like the go-to, but then when fedora said well
We're gonna go unbound I went looked it up
And it looks like it's really easy to set up and get going yeah
I was thinking about maybe doing it looks pretty solid and I don't need the DHCP server from DNS mask
So I might consider it it seems like that depends on how flexible it is
Yeah, DNS mask has a lot of flexible settings to allow me to hit different DNS servers for different domains and that kind of stuff
I don't know if unbound is all the same functionality
We'll have to hear some report I kind of want to try it I do yeah
Because I've been deploying DNS mask as well
Yeah, that's just cuz that's what I write you how to use yeah, and that was always kind of the go-to
So vert which I want to say vendetta online, but it's a vert in the window a vert in the vert
It's a nudah very I knew that you there we go. I like it so you use it for VPN host resolving tell me about this
Yeah, basically okay, if you tie in your own name servers
You can resolve your individual VPN hosts for your token subnet
So what I actually do is I set up a DHCP server
Which links to my DHC my DNS servers by T SIG to set up okay?
Mapping for my VPN server for VPN clients and when they connect to the VPN they can either automatically resolve each other's
host naming on the VPN
Because they get the information from the DNS server care others been punched
It's it's a very easy way of doing it and and funny and funny enough
Okay, this is exactly what Tink ended up doing for me as well really
Into the VPN setup yeah
Basically once you resolve one host secure on that yeah, it will resolve hosts for all the other things so Tink is something that
my my oh
God, I just want to make sure you were saying Tink and not ting for the audience listening. Yeah
Yeah, so Tink is like a mesh vpn solution. Yeah, okay, and I was about to say the same thing
You know I like the local DNS
Yeah for that reason is that you can set up your own you can use your host file
But if you have a local DNS, it's a little cleaner. Yeah, you're figuring everything in the same spot. Yeah
Yeah, you can replicate that
Yeah, using local host file
Well, it just feels hacky. Yeah, all right and go ahead. Sorry vert. Did you want to finish?
Well, no, I was just saying okay, that's you with Tinker right it makes it a little bit easier because because you're doing over a
VPN anyway, you can now sync between each machine
Okay, right the host files we need to connect to each other
So you basically build up your own dark day if you like because only the host you're connecting to will know about all the other
hosts that you're connecting to right right and of course DNS is
There's several different DNS options for PFSense
JB live 87 54 is pointing out that PFSense has unbound as an option for PFSense servers. So there you go
Um, you know, I know that now that we've talked about this
I wonder if maybe I might not
Tonight go give this a little try at the rover and see how it goes. I'll report back
Maybe well, you know what? Maybe if it goes really well, I might make a segment on the Linux action. Yeah, that sounds fun
I'm watching that. Yeah, that'd be interesting
So all right a mumble room any closing thoughts before we move on any other DNS experts or DNS?
Experienced want to know go in once go in twice. All right. Very good. Very good. Good talk
Thank you guys for the information and also
You know what I should do is I will include a link
Same they go down here to the segment at the bottom of the segment in the show notes where we talked about fedora 24
I will include a link to the issues with DNS sex
So if you guys heard us mention that and you're curious what those issues are
I just added that link to the show notes so you can go and go read about that s
Maybe you can poke Alan and you guys can do a follow-up. I wonder if Alan has any thoughts
I bet he does you and I are on the same page my friend
Hey, I don't know if you notice this West but we relaunched the last jacket for a kind of I think I want one
I need one. You should definitely
So it is back it is it is awesome and you can find them at teespring.com slash
Last us or if you're across the pond and you don't want to have to pay exorbitant shipping amounts
slash last EU and here's the real shenanigans you get in on that order right now because we're only running them until December 13th
It's gonna ship in time for
The holidays. Oh, yeah for your loved ones. Yeah, you know just put a lot of the best network
Put a last jacket in every every single stocking
But really we have multiple colors and you can go grab yourself a jacket
These were maybe our most
Favorited item that we sold last year. We only run them for a limited time and then they're all done
So go to teespring.com is item last us or last
You it is a collector's item and it keeps your tummy warm and depending on how you zip it up
No, man boobs, which is really if you got man boobs. No, man, but cover your shame
Exactly no judgments. No judgments
We also we also have a link on the sidebar at Jupiter broadcasting.com teespring.com slash last us and last EU and the EU has better
Color options so you could actually be in the US in order from the EU if you want to get like some crazy colors
Yeah, they've got all the best stuff. Teespring got a good deal set up over there. Apparently they apparently over there
They know how to print and make sure it's real good. I see. Yeah, that's the thing
I want to tell you about something else. It's a thing. It's one of my favorite sponsors Linux Academy
I think this is a great fit for you guys because it's a great resource for you to go learn more about the systems
We all love what's great about Linux Academy is sort of what I think is great about Jupiter broadcasting
That might be one of the reasons why I think they're a great sponsor
They actually care about Linux and open source
Turns out when you actually care about Linux and open source and then you make content about Linux and open source you do it better
Than other people because you actually live and breathe this stuff
You actually care about this and you follow it from day to day go to Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged Linux Academy comm slash unplugged to get our special discount and support this show. It's a really good deal Linux Academy freaking rocks
They got seven plus distributions you get to choose from they got like almost
2,000 self-paced courses with videos and high-quality contents you can downloads on the offline
Everything's backed by a nice CDN with HTML 5 players. They have instructor help available for you whenever you need it
Which is a really nice feature. They got labs. They spin up on-demand. They got the AWS courses for the Amazon stuff
And the reason why I mentioned that is
I kind of found myself one time having a client that all of a sudden was my responsibility and had
AWS infrastructure primarily around s3 at the time, right?
I did not really in that's not like Linux as we know it or anything like that
It has its own unique works definitely does it definitely does now
I've told this story before but I can't remember the exact number now because it was several years ago
But when I was just sort of playing around on this three trying to figure out how to do things before I wouldn't charge them
How to do it or even just said yeah, I know how to do that
You know, I actually want to see if I could do it. I think I racked up like a $300 bill
I need it was something around there. Yeah, it was ridiculous
So what's really cool is regardless of what you know, you're learning Ruby. You're learning nginx or learning IP tables
You're learning how to do basic development or maybe you're learning AWS. They'll spin up the lab servers for you on-demand
They have a really great interface. You can SSH right in and rock that s they have scenario based labs
Which is really nice because that gives you really good hands-on experience
You'll work in their advanced live environments while completing these scenarios from beginning to end on live servers
Isn't that nice break somebody else's stuff? They have real-time feedback, too
They have great courses for the red hat certified courseware and they have instructor help available at any time
Nice content always getting updated refreshed
And keep track of your progress as you go along. They break things down into our lease. It is really cool
They have an availability planner
You can go into Linux Academy and say how much time you have availability and how much time you have available and they'll automatically
Generate the courseware to match your time availability. I think that's really really cool
Yeah, I mean that seems pretty unique
Dude, like so flexible even in the holidays when things get busy
You can find a way to like sort of schedule in like few hours a couple hours on Tuesday, you know
Dude, you know do while you're listening to JB content
I'm gonna listen to JB content for this hour while I have unplugged going on in the background. I'm gonna go do this
Yeah, you know what? Why not? Yeah, you can do all the time or in the shower, you know, it's a thing
It's a shower touch tablet in there open up your SSH session. You're good to go. Hey, oh, that's why you need a pencil
So the other thing I think is really great is they upgraded the server exercise
You can get your work evaluated while connected to a real server
Their courses include exercises where you log into a lab server and perform specific tasks in Linux Academy
Automatically grades your actions so you can see how well you did graded exercises are included in all Linux Academy memberships
They have a great step technology stack
Everything you'd want built around Linux including some of the simple things like our sink or IP tables or just basic Linux commands
Like tar like seriously fundamentals all the way up the entire stack all the way up to the Red Hat stuff Android development Python Ruby
PHP nginx Apache now I always go off on the list here
But you guys know all of the big technologies out there that are popular Linux Academy probably knows even more than you do
That's why they follow this stuff. They are following the heartbeat of open-source, you know
Like they just see what people want. They're seeing what's popular and because they use it themselves
You know what? They should take that and run with it. They are following the heartbeat of open-source Linux Academy
West is just an idea guy. You got to run with it. Yep, but he's gonna give that to you
We love you. So go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
We ask you to go there because that supports the show lets him know you heard about it here and you can check out their
services
But really it gets you a phenomenal discount Linux Academy calm
Slash unplug
Okay, Wes, so you had an idea which I once once we started kicking it around
I was like
This is a great idea because there is a lot of stuff happening in this space and you know when
When you first started kicking around this idea
If I had a little more time, I was gonna go over to the Computer Chronicles website
I was gonna get a clip because you know
We used to call the computer back in the 80s what we now call PCs and laptops and desktop
They called mini and micro PCs right because they weren't mainframes. Yes, you could fit them in, you know more than
Yes, so
Now here we are on the Linux unplugged show and we're once again about to talk about micro PCs or mini PCs only now
We mean something that isn't like an Intel based high-end powerful desktop
No way the history is repeating itself on the Linux unplugged show today
and to start off the conversation we want to talk about something that's kind of been big news over the last few weeks and that's
the Pi Zero and
This video will introduce us to it
These are two computers from our childhood so the BBC microcomputer I bought one of these in 1989 for 220 pounds
This is a Commodore Amiga. I bought this in
Christmas of 1992 for 199 pounds of leases and leads
When I bought each of these machines, I had to basically just drain all the money
I had I had to drain my bank account my piggy bank and you know
All of my savings went into each of these machines at the time that I bought them
When I was a kid the high cost of computers like these was a real barrier to me learning about
computers and really what we've been trying to do with Raspberry Pi is to
Make sure that cost is never going to be a barrier to anyone who's interested in getting involved in coding
When we launched Raspberry Pi we took about a factor of five out of the out of the cost of a typical low-cost computer
But we still meet people for whom you say tell us that cost is a barrier to entry for them
So lately this year since the Raspberry Pi 2 effort wound down in February
We've been we've been asking ourselves what we could do to maybe take a little bit more cost out
And today we're launching a new product. This is Raspberry Pi Zero
This is a full-fledged Raspberry Pi. We've got a 2835 here and half it says it's the same chip
We used in Raspberry Pi 1 except up clocked a little bit. So it's about 40% faster. Got half a gig of RAM
HDMI connector SD card USB to connect mouse and mouse and keyboard nice and the same pin out
Although it's not populated the same GPIO pin out that we have on on modern Raspberry Pi's on the B
Plus the A plus and the Pi 2
I'm just going on sale today. We've made a few tens of thousands of these this is going on sale today from our distributors of
five bucks, so
Five you just can't believe that
five
US greenbacks
Unbelievable
Unbelievable West and I I just I look at this and I think holy crap. This is the future. We're living in now and
I can't I just can't even wrap my head. They've already sold out. I believe I think they yeah
Yeah from a lot of retailers. Yeah, which is just whoo. Wow, but they'll be back. So the show show. Yeah
What's the magazine about what's the chair? I'm talking about the magazine. What's everybody talking about the man?
Oh, this was awesome that basically but when they first announced they were gonna do five dollar things. They also said well the
Pi mag magazine that was it's a community magazine and it's six dollars to purchase if you purchased one
On the day or a couple days after it was the reply zero was attached directly to the magazine cover
It's over like six bucks. I got a magazine and oh my gosh you you buy the make you so in the UK when it came
out
Like every news agent sold out of the the magazine straightaway because you know
It's a free computer on the cover who wouldn't who wouldn't want that?
But if you're a subscriber to the magazine you can you can still get it
And also in the US where they're coming a little bit later in the month
You can all wait you can get the mag pie magazine over there with the same rosebud pie on the cover
What the ghost name some people have some people have joked that you you buy a pie zero and you get a free magazine
Exactly. Yeah
Remind everyone I care of my generation that back in the day of early day computing
Okay, you used to get cassettes on the front of magazines free with them now you're getting computers
Yeah, and I remember when I was a big deal
Yeah
When you got a like Linux format came with a CD with a Linux distro on there or something
So yeah, the this $5 computer has a 1 gigahertz arm 11 processor
Which was 40% faster than the first Raspberry Pi 512 megabytes of RAM a micro SD card slot a mini HDMI socket for 1080p output
with 60 frames per second and
Of course, it has the 40 pin GPIO header
We love that and it has a unpopulated composite video header and it is 65 nanometers 65 meters
Millimeters, sorry by 30 millimeters by 5 millimeters and it's not even if the course there's the chip it now the chip is sort
Of been of course the chip wasn't exactly as cheap as they originally said it was going to be right
But you also have things like we have right here in the studio. We have this Omega onion
In the box Alan has one of these he's been talking about this too, you know
I hadn't heard too much about it, but that's a shame because these seem really cool. Yeah, it was a Kickstarter
I backed and how could I not back it after they had this crazy crazy crazy great Kickstarter video
So I want to talk about the Raspberry Pi zero and also this Omega onion check out their Kickstarter video
There are two worlds
The real world and the digital and then there's the cat world
Oh the lovely cat world
The problem with the two worlds is that in order to connect objects in the real world with the digital world?
You need to be a rocket scientist or some sort of physicist from the Manhattan Project
Or one of those brains in a jar
But not anymore
meet onion
For the past year we've been hard at work building something that's small
Affordable and really easy to use so that we can merge the two worlds together
We wanted to be like Tony Stark and be able to build whatever comes to our mind without
Learning how to build these things and that is exactly why we created this
the
onion Omega
Thanks Oliver
It's a tiny computer with built-in Wi-Fi and it runs the Linux operating system
Hey
Oh, you know that little bad boy lets you create connected devices in environments that you're already familiar with using tools such as
SSH get an NPM and it also allows you to write software in Python
No dot J at PHP or whatever language you feel comfortable with node.js now have the power to build anything you can imagine
such as smart home devices
Security drones drone security spiders spider
That's amazing I want it or even a cat feeder
A cat feeder that realizes your cat is too fat and then makes it exercise
Nice laser or if you don't want to build from scratch
You can browse the onion app store for ready-made apps
In fact, if you want to see what you can build on the Omega right now
Click on the live demo below and start to experience the Omega in real time
The Omega allows me to build things in languages that I'm that I already know and using things that I'm familiar with like callback functions
And I actually built this light bulb in just 10 minutes and it's remote-controlled
I really like working with the onion Omega. It was really easy to use
I'm not a programmer or an engineer of any kind, but I went to the onion app store and I was able to build a lightbulb
It was really easy to use. I'm not a programmer or an engineer of any kind
But I went to the onion app store and I downloaded and customized an app that allows me to draw images from my Facebook newsfeed
And put them into a digital photo. She's a high school teacher
The Omega is almost ready for production
We're so close to realizing our vision of making the Internet of Things accessible to everyone
And we want you to be a part of our revolution and start inventing your own
And we want you to be a part of our revolution and start inventing connected devices that will make our world a smarter place
Right, Oliver?
What happens when we connect the real world with the digital
Awesomeness
There you go, Wes. Are you ready to take part in the revolution? Do you want to unbox the onion?
Yes, I do. Have at it there. Okay, so it comes in a very small box. It's very smooth
It's a nice premium cardboard. The in the hand experience for the box is quite nice. I do agree
Yeah, and uh, it's got like a puzzle piece. It does it kind of comes apart
Yeah, because yeah, it has a actually very much a puzzle piece top. It's literally a puzzle piece, isn't it?
It's kind of hard to get open and then three individual boxes. So there's the expansion dock right here. Yeah, very nice
Oh, look at that. Yeah, so it comes and then here's the actual uh, here's the omega box. So that's the omega
Yep, yep
And so I got the mini dock and the expansion dock and that's where you can plug in different stuff
so I guess we can here I will uh, I will turn on the uh, the webcam a
A limited uh limited exclusive treat on the unplugged show here. I'm going to pull the omega out of the box right now
Look at how cheese. It's even smaller than it looks in their kickstarter video. It's unbelievable
It's smaller than the palm of my hand
Wow, look at that. Look at tiny that is
That is ridiculous
That is ridiculous. And there's the expansion. Oh my gosh
Gosh, this is a tiny tiny linux computer. Wow, wes. Oh, these docs are cool too. Look at this thing here
I'll take that doc. Here you go. So this is the bigger. So there's two docs
There's a mini dock and then there's the big boy expansion dock and that's this one here. This is the big boy mini expansion
And uh, yeah, so you plug in
the omega
To the top of the expansion dock right here
So it plugs into the top of the dock right here and now it has all of the functionality that the dock has
Dang, yeah
Which which in this case is a usb port and then another set of expansions which seem perfect
If you're prototyping and you want to you want to use those things, but you're not ready to solder on headers, you know
Isn't that something so you just snap it together? Wow alan was talking about this on the tech snap pre-show
Uh, wow, there's micro hdmi
Huh?
Yeah
So that's pretty much so there's your usb port for your input and there's your hdmi out right there
And it has wi-fi on it
Man, you could just duct tape that behind your tv and really go put mbi on this and my problems are solved
So that really seems to flirt with the uh
You know flirt with the border before we kind of had the arduino on one end of the spectrum and the raspberry pi on the other
And you have the full linux experience or you have you're writing it in c++ yourself
And this is like well, you can if you're familiar with linux, but you maybe you're not an expert in microcontrollers
You can just deploy it right here and you're here one way you go. No kidding
And ver you've had it you you've had a chance to play with it. What do you think?
Yeah, it's a really sweet
Tiny little pc it is and it is so easy to set up because basically when you power it on
Although be careful because the power switch is very fragile on the docks. Anyway, yeah when you power it on
Okay, it becomes its own self access point
It does so basically you just scan the wi-fi network find the you know
So omega whatever is uh access point as ssd
Join it
Go to the web
Configure it set your passwords your ssh set your network set your other wi-fi networks
And it will basically uh, just reboot if you're right into a proper pc on your network. It's fantastic. That is really awesome. It's running open
Wrt
Okay. Okay. Isn't that something isn't that something?
Uh, I I think it's sort of astonishing because it's I have the specs in the in the show notes
I just find it astonishing that it's it's getting to the point now where you know, I just backed some project on freaking kickstarter
I believe alan said he was making uh, he was setting up instructions for freebsd as well on this game, right?
Which is awesome. Yep. So yeah, it ships with open wrt
It has a 400 megahertz processor 64 megabytes of ddr2 ram
16 megabyte of flash got 802 11 pgn on it
Has 184 gpio. Yeah, it's
I love isn't interesting how they list node.js as a supported. Well, that's important. Yeah. Yeah
Uh wimpy, I kind of wanted to pick your brain because I know you've hinted before on some pre and post shows that
And I haven't gotten got I have quite not yet gotten the complete picture
But the raspberry pi is starting to play a more and more important role for the ubuntu mate distro, isn't it?
It's our most popular platform
Wow, you mean you mean other than x86 or including x86 it's more popular than
An x64 bit 32 bit x86 holy shit
That's crazy. Wow. Oh my world has just been rocked. Are you kidding me?
No, it's downloaded about
1200 times a day the image for the party. That's awesome
Wow
That's serious. That is that is so what are your thoughts on that?
Well, it means that in the last two releases of ubuntu mate. I've done the work for the pi version
In the last month of the release right but for this release it's got even
You know, it's being treated equally all the way through the development stage now
I I feel like I need to take a minute
Like I wasn't ready for that level of a bomb to be dropped
I don't know why I didn't know that because I kind of feel like I should have known that but I did to me is
Shocking to me actually, I've actually I've actually been paying attention to a lot of communities around raspberry pi and you know
reddit or google plus in various different places and
The majority of times people asked what to put on the pie
No, raspbian is no longer even mentioned and went to the bunta mate is always the first choice
I mean it makes it makes it does makes I mean it's way more
Pleasant to use and the defaults and it looks pretty with me. That's a that's a big deal though
I mean congratulations because that's a big deal and so when you look at these types of devices
Are you starting to say? All right, this these aren't just sort of toys. These are going to become
Possibly the next open PC now
Hold on before I I don't want to make sure I'm framing this right
but when I look at tablets and phones I get a little sad because they look locked down and glued together and I
I remember a time when I was in high school and I scraped together parts for
Months and months and months and built my first PC. I wouldn't picked out my own case and it was
It was it was a life moment for me and you learned a lot
Ton of stuff and I read I read I mean it was really my first geek project that I really researched and all that kind
Of stuff and now I look at this
Onion Omega here and I'm sitting here like Legos building a PC and I think geez I could give this to my kid and he
Could play Minecraft on this and maybe not this one, but the Raspberry Pi zero
I mean I I this is maybe getting to the point now where
It is actually going to be something that has some serious long-term legs as a serious desktop contender and one more thing wimpy before
I toss it back to you is I
in the late 90s
had a conversation with a guy named Scott really great guy and his job his day job was to run an IBM mainframe and
he
looked down at
desktop PCs as toys
That couldn't do real work that didn't weren't powerful enough and he called he called the desktops
Oh, you mean those Mattel inside PCs those Mattel inside because they were toys right and you know and I look at the Omega
And I go this is a cute Lego toy
But actually maybe I'm looking at it from Scott's perspective and when you when wimpy says he's getting over a thousand downloads a day
I'm wondering are you looking at this and are these mini PCs these Raspberry Pis and these
Omegas and and bagel bone and all whatever are you looking at this and going this might actually be something that
Gets wider adoption use than the traditional PC one day. I
Think so certainly if you look outside of the developed nations. I think this is going to be the print the arm based
Devices are going to be the principal computing platform. And if you're not doing stuff on arm, you'll be irrelevant
Wow bad time to own Intel stock
Yep. No, I think that will that will be relevant. It'll be a different market and different use case
but I think that we're we've not seen the extent to which arm is going to be relevant for
For Linux adoption and in particular Linux as a learning platform
Kids and kitty you kind of point out. I mean this these kind of machines get the basic work done
And well that kind of solves a lot of people's problems. Don't isn't it doesn't it? Yeah, I was just thinking, you know
What do 90% of what you do on a computer consist of web browsing email?
Editing a text file that kind of thing maybe watching a YouTube video
The pie can handle all that
Yeah, and so and it's not even see I think what I used to brussel at is I used to feel like we were talking down
and I kind of
hmm, I
wonder if I still do feel that way so
Something that that Carl said a few times during our visit at system 76 is one of the things that they're basic
Market research keeps and market research being you know being in a business for ten years selling PCs
One of the things that they have really learned maybe even the hard way is you can always err on the side of giving people
More powerful computers like there's there's never going to be a day where people don't need more powerful systems
And so I guess I kind of had that Scott like view where I looked at this and go well these these these
Little toy computers will never be powerful enough
But that is sort of looking at it in a in a perspective where there isn't
Lots of different things that you can do
It's a perspective where there isn't lots of different cloud options when you need to spin up like a droplet to do something really powerful
Or throw it on Google engine or whatever the hell as you're I don't care
There's a lot of different options there when you need really really really high-end compute
And there's a lot of options when you when you need really really a local something local really high-end
You can still have a desktop
But there are so many so many use cases where I've worked with people where their primary job is checking email
You know we're doing doing things on their corporate applications
Which are sometimes web applications sometimes not and they do all of these things that are really sort of
Low-end tasks, and it's not to be I'm not trying to be rude
I just like that's just all they use these particular quote-unquote tools for and so why what what what does it take then?
What does it take to make it from the hobbyist project to actually something that consumers could actually start start buying like why don't we have?
Why don't we have a Best Buy that has more ARM laptops and desktops on the shelves then they do x86 machines?
Why isn't Lenovo selling a an ARM an ARM laptop?
Why is an HP and Dell selling an ARM laptop that we're all buying and and and before we go there?
I also I want I'll have you answer that first quest, but before we go there you found this again
This is a perfect example of where the Raspberry Pi is really cool, but this is a straight-up hobbyist project
I like it, and so I'm gonna point out to the audience so they can read more about it
But it's it's a great you it's great example of where the Raspberry Pi is being used today
And it's it's this is not even an uncanny valley issue
This is way far removed from what consumers want anyways
This is you can make it you can take a Raspberry Pi and a Wi-Fi dongle and basically turn it into like a remote
Airplay receiver or audio receiver, so you can use a couple of projects that reversed Apple's airplay
right
Protocol and actually stream to this instead of having to go get like a really expensive device if you have iOS devices in the house
And you want to stream audio you can do with this Raspberry Pi. Yep. It's pretty cool
I I think that it's because a lot of people don't know that it's an option
But if you show them that hey
There's this 35 another $50 option that you can utilize instead of spending a thousand dollars on a workstation
I think people would go for it if they knew what it was actually capable of I
Don't agree. Do you agree? I don't it's a smart. It's a smart business
Here's why because this is what I'm this is what I'm saying is this what I'm asking you is
And Wes I'll let you have the first answer, and then we'll throw it to the moment room
Why why is nobody picking up on this? Why is Leno? So Lenovo today can take a
Intel spec motherboard an Intel CPU they can build a PC from parts that they assemble themselves in the housing
And then they ship why can't they take something like that Raspberry Pi or something just like it and build their own version?
Put it in a case with a great keyboard and ship it. Why is that not happening?
I'm not sure that they I mean I think you could do it
But I don't know if they see the opportunity in terms of operating systems
I mean, I think that Android isn't there as a desktop operating system
Maybe if they had partnerships with like I mean
I think what we see is Chrome OS Android isn't there or is it that Google creeps people out well
Maybe both and I think like you know for the main people who are using desktop. They're comfortable with Windows
You know a little newer one
Maybe they can now that like Raspberry Pi 2 will run Windows Windows 10 right so there may be an avenue there
But but I wonder if they don't see like something they can rebuild well hmm. What was that run?
It's an incredibly stripped-down Windows 10. It's not really Windows 10. That's a good point
Wimpy you think there's like that one piece really that's holding it up
well, not that's holding up, but I think that
For example that the things that I run into most with the question and answers
For up into Marte on the Pi 2 is can I run flash on it?
Which you can't right because there are no flash binaries for ARM Linux
Can I run wine on it?
No, or yeah, yes, you could kind of compile it in a certain way, and it runs really badly
And you get those sorts of questions and people aren't aware that it is just because it runs Linux doesn't mean it runs
Everything that you're used to running on you know
Intel so don't call it a Linux. I mean right we're so used to Wintel Google got away with that by calling them Chromebooks
Yeah, exactly well and and and to some extent also
You know rolling their own version of flash to bridge bridge one of those yeah that too
Yeah, but you know if you're Lenovo or Dell you've been selling to a traditional audience of x86 users
Who will be expecting to use the same or similar software and when some of it's not available there?
Maybe that's some that's a tough call, but you know so they're they're selling
Chromebooks and some of those in the Far East are ARM based now
Yes, that's pointing out that the things that are not available are the evil proprietary things. Yeah, I know so
Pretty so that's all as well. Yeah, well, and we were just discussing. You know this average
Just basic work type task type work where the computer is a tool
They might not care as much as much about some of these things in fact in a work environment
Not having flash is a security advantage and a work productivity advantage
Right like legitimately
So I I guess I still I don't I don't feel like we have fully answered that question
I
Don't know what it is exactly I think
The problem is that we look at it different
we present it actually the wrong way because we presented as the
replacement for a PC right
Whereas we shouldn't be telling people that because it's well
It's not capable of everything you can do on your desktop like it is not
GIMP is not a replacement for photoshop. It is a separate line of tool that is available
Yes, but what you should show people is like
this is a cool thing that you could use to browse Facebook with right or put up in your kitchen and
Look at recipes with and all you need is a you know some screen and something to you know
a keyboard and a mouse and you have a your tiny computer in your kitchen, right and then you can
Show them that look this what you've considered
To be just a recipe looking at device is also capable of those other things
Instead of showing them that this is a computer
That this is a computer that's not capable of all the other things that you are right using your computer
That's that's actually pretty good insight because that's why the smartphone has been so successful is because it was in as far as it
Was replacing the dumb phone which was a not a high bar
And so you could like Apple could launch their overpriced iPhone that didn't even have copy paste support for like two OS's
Because the bar wasn't that high and when you come in and you say I'm replacing the PC
Well, guess what pretty high frickin bar pretty high for that makes sense. Have you seen what PC can do PC do what?
Yeah, right exactly
Damn it Wes screw you
That is the worst advertising campaign ever, but it worked son of a gun
All right vert you want to talk about the future making everything a little bit smarter. Go ahead
Yeah, well basically with this kind of dropping computing and more specifically sophisticated computing
It means these little devices like the pie zero or the Omega
Can now be turned into a general purpose kind of smart sensor or smart device that can be plugged into anything
Basically, you know displays well like this article
This article that Wes found before the show is you know
You take a simple speaker and now all of a sudden this is a quote-unquote
I mean if I was in the industry a smart speaker because it can receive Bluetooth or
Airplay or DLNA audio pulse also multicast as well or MPD
Yeah, in fact, this is actually using pulse to send from your Linux box. I mean
A classic example is that it causes now I actually have a pie acting as a alarm clock
for my partially sighted father
Because he can't necessarily see the display all the time and so he wants to be able to hear it
So it's a talking clock and we can now it's a talking clock tech to the Internet it can now read things like emails and how
Do other things that it wouldn't be able to do that sounds great or horrible?
Yeah, good point wimpy I
also have noticed
Especially when it comes to a demographic that I am intimately familiar with my children
There is some essential use cases that the pie is totally capable of like things like YouTube or Minecraft
And that is pretty a poor by a huge core audience. Wouldn't you think?
Yes one it can do and one it can kind of do so when I've been going along to the pie jams
I've been
Taking an Ubuntu mate set up and getting makers and other you know
Visitors to come and have a look and have a play and give me their feedback
And it's interesting that when the kids go on it
They basically want two things they want to be able to play Minecraft and they want to watch YouTube and if it doesn't do that
It's irrelevant. That's that's the end of a discussion and it has to be able to play Minecraft without
Quote-unquote leg right and leg is frame drops. I guess I don't know exactly what leg is
But so there is there is a Minecraft version for the pie
It's the Minecraft pie edition, which is a bit like the pocket edition of Minecraft
Ah, but it comes with Python bindings so you can you know, you can program it and what have you?
and YouTube
At the moment, we don't have the fully accelerated graphics driver for the for the chip
That's on the Broadcom sock in the pie
so
That's all software at the moment and that's a bit poor
But I've embedded a utility in Ubuntu mate where you can suck down
You can visit YouTube within Firefox and pull the cut and paste the URL and then it will stream the URL into the IMX
Player which is the hardware
Assisted player so you get the full hardware assisted full screen playback streaming from YouTube ever
So actually you're kind of getting into my next segment
Our next segment is is really some clever tricks to avoid having to use flash all together partly because arm
But also because of Adobe's announcement this week
So pause right there wouldn't be and let's pick that back up because that's actually a perfect segue to our next segment
So I'll mention the perfect telco
Friends it actually exists because their business model is different ting is mobile that makes sense
Ting is an MV no of a couple of different networks
So instead of like getting all involved in like digging the trenches
Installing the towers running the fiber fighting the local city council to make sure they can actually run a tower right there
Which is an unbelievable fight?
Contracting with the designers to design the tower and all and it's interesting as a contractor
I've worked at each stage of the process for the and watch telco
It's interesting when a telco comes into an area
It's both an amazing investment for the local businesses
And it is it is just a nightmare for the telco
So it's an incredible investment for the local businesses when a telco wants to put a tower in
Because they're gonna have to trench and run fiber to that location and a lot of times
They'll resell that fiber to all of the other local businesses in that area
But can you imagine the administrative overhead just to manage that but at the same time like there's all of the local rules like you know
Like oh for here. It's the PUD
It's our it's our public utilities that they have to like get approval from where the poles can be at all this kind of stuff
Then they have to take it to an architecture firm to design the tower the tower then gets approved by the local city which then
Goes off to the state to get approved and then and it's all paying right in checks the whole way
Right sounds like a lot of work right in checks, right?
So what Ting has done is they right on top of all of that?
So that's why they're able to invest in the customer
So the other guys have done the work there and now they need somebody to come along and actually get some customers on it
That's where Ting comes in. So it's six dollars a month for the line flat rate right there
And then it's just your usage on top of that. No contract
Nor the termination fee and because Ting isn't out there digging ditches. They're able to have
Fanatical customer service they're able to have a great website and they're able to charge
Incredibly low rates and if you're just a like a little bit savvy with how you use things you can get by with
Unbelievable rates, so I've got three phones that I pay every single month for on Ting
The bill is like around 40 bucks a month 40 bucks a month for three phones smartphones. It's ridiculous
It's actually it makes sense and there's no contract. There's no early termination fee
They have a GSM and CDMA network you can take advantage of so if you know what that means
then you're probably clever enough to figure out which one's better in your area and
just go with that one and it also probably means you've got a device that's compatible with Ting and
Ting has a brand new app you can get on the Android marketplace the Android Play Store
To check to see if it's compatible with Ting to get all of the information. They made it easier than ever
They have the new brand new Ting compatibility checker. Whoo. Guess what? I didn't see this earlier
Kyra is here to tell us all about it too. Let's go check a phone to see if it's compatible with Ting
This is the app you'll need. All right. I'm Kyra and this is the Ting download
The
Ting compatibility checker app for Android. Well checks your phone's compatibility with Ting. It doesn't do anything else
Yeah, it's beautifully simple if we do say so ourselves
It's also a very small download. It's intended to be used once and uninstalled at less than 1.5 megabytes
You won't have to worry about deleting other apps to make space for this one. Smart. Here's how it works
Install the app and open it up. Cha-cha-cha. Tap to check your phone. The app pulls your phone's unique serial number
It's IMEI and runs it against the database of phones that'll work
It only takes a second. Once the process finishes, you'll find out right away
If your phone is compatible
You'll also get info on which network services it will support. As you'd expect the app is free and you can grab it from the Google
Play Store. The Ting compatibility checker is Android only. iPhone currently doesn't allow apps to pull specific phone info
Huh, but you can always use the web-based compatibility checker at ting.com slash check on your desktop or mobile browser. All right
It's almost as simple
Thanks for watching and we'll see you next time
Wow, did it just get easier than ever to switch to Ting? I think it did. Look at them. That's thinking
Well, and did I hear that they have their SIM cards on Amazon now?
They do Amazon Prime at that and you just pop them in a device check them out
So all you got to do is go to linux.ting.com to support this show and get yourself a discount. Go check them out
linux.ting.com and now it's easier than ever to bring an Android device
Interesting iPhone not
Letting you get access to that information
Hmm. I wonder which one protects your privacy
Anyways linux.ting.com go get yourself a great device and then would you tweet me and tell me about how much you're saving
Cuz you're gonna want to tell somebody and share it with your bro. Chris will always listen. Just contact him 24-7
He doesn't mind especially when he's doing shit. Just call me directly. All right, so let's talk about Adobe Killing Flash
Well the name
Not really killing flash, but you know if you got yourself Creative Cloud heads up. They're gonna rename your application
So watch out everybody big change is coming down the pipe a new name a new name
Really excited about that and they're gonna make an emphasis on HTML 5
9 binary output. How about that everybody?
You're really really excited now, aren't you? Are you are you amped up? If you're not amped up enough
Well, there's this French guy and this French guy. He's got a really really really shallow depth of field and he wants to tell you
All about it. Hello. My name is Michael shares
I'm a creative cloud evangelist based in Paris and a longtime interactive designer with the growth of HTML 5
Demand for animation formats that leverage web technologies has grown and the flash pro team has responded
Adding first-class support for exporting animations to HTML 5 in order to clearly define the role of this application as the premier
Animation tool for the web and beyond. I'm very excited to announce that flash professional is being renamed to adobe animate CC
Adobe animate CC and
Adobe animate CC will be you know, can I just stop here? Did you notice how he says the word Adobe?
I want to play that back just for a second and Adobe animate CC adobe adobe
The only reason I mentioned that is last week you and I were trying to come up with how you say hat in French
Yes, and we got so much shit for how we tried to say hat in French
Well, how about an Adobe employee in France? They can't even pronounce the company. He works for you guys
You give me crap all the time. Well, what's up? This guy works for Adobe doesn't work there anymore. Not after that
I'm just saying like they're giving me a hard time because I can't say hat in French
Meanwhile, this dude works for Adobe and he calls it adobe, right?
But it's fine because he's French now Chris who speaks English isn't allowed to mispronounce anything, but this guy that's fine
He's French. We don't care. He's French Chris
It's not a big deal because he's French and he's in Paris and there was a terrorist attack
So don't give him a hard time because he calls it adobe. There's not a big deal
What are you talking about nouns that flash professional is being renamed to adobe animate CC?
Okay, now you can't on here. Can you add a beam?
And adobe animate CC will be available in early 2016
We are not just changing the name. We are adding significant new features for professional animators. Let me show you what we are working on
You will be able to browse and license millions of illustrations photos and vector graphics
Adobe stock is directly integrated within the tool thanks to the power of creative sync
Same for creative cloud libraries. You can access colors vector shapes and brushes directly within animate CC and all right
So there you go
so this is they're gonna call it animate and they're gonna have animate CC for the application to use and the
Idea is adobe is gonna de-emphasize
de-emphasize
FLV and that kind of stuff and sort of re-emphasize
HTML 5 output but using Adobe tools to make that said HTML 5 output
I don't know what to think about this
So what I thought is let's just figure out how to stop using the flash plug-in all together and that's Chris's solution
So you really want to kill Adobe flash? I'm sorry adobe flash. This is how we do it
This is how we do it
And so I wanted to give my couple of tips and I want to see maybe what you do to avoid using flash and we'll
Toss it the bumble room. So I mentioned these on Sunday show but my two top tips to avoid using flash
First of all, don't install it second of all use live streamer to watch things that are in flash or if you want to watch
The JB live stream grab the RTMP or RTSP and throw that to MPV
That helps Alan get paid. Well and well you with live streamer. Well, I don't think we'll do the JB live stream
Okay, so live streamer will do like twitch and you stream you could watch the we do have a broadcast on you stream
Not you stream TV or whatever you stream calm
whatever the URL is slash channel slash Jupiter broadcasting and you could pipe that into live streamer and
Pipe that you could you could pull that into live streamer and it will it will work
But the the built-in embedded one on the jblive.tv page doesn't work with live streamer
But RTMP on RTSP work beautifully and MPV
So you just you know in the command line you type MPV and then you paste that link and it starts streaming
FFmpeg will record from those or HLS right as well right to a file HLS as well
and then then of course
Something that I use all the time is
Minitube and YouTube DL which is a great way to pull video files off of YouTube without having to use flash
And then my go-to solution is instead of having flash installed system-wide if I have to have to have to use flash
I use chrome and chrome comes with flash built-in and I just keep it there in their little sandbox
And that's where it stays and if a website requires flash like YouTube management tools, then I just use Chrome
What are you what? How do you avoid using flash when you need to you know?
I have to echo up pretty much everything you said I was just talking with my parents and they were kind of freaked out
Firefox is warning them about the vulnerabilities in flash and you know
They don't quite know what that means and I found myself just saying well if you haven't flash problems
You should probably just use Chrome and I haven't said that before but that's that's where we're at
I think is just you just use Chrome you use that for that page and you're done
Wendy you have a trick for getting HTML 5 playback on YouTube
Yeah, this is not so much about what you as a user can do but what you as a you know a content
Publisher can do so what if you embed YouTube clips in a website or social media and all the rest of it
If you add the HTML 5
Option to the embed URL it forces the clip to use the HTML 5 playback
Rather than flash by default. Oh
That is great to know I will also I went through all my sites and you know added that to everything after the last round
Of you know flash vulnerabilities when nobody can access flash for about a week smart. I added that
That's beautiful
Some older versions of flash or or players that haven't been updated will save temporary files that if you want to watch the video
But you don't want to use the flash interface it will download it to temp the temp folder, but it will delete them
Hmm, but it still has that file handle open. So the proc file system will show that to you
So you can then you can copy it right out of it
So you still have to have flash installed for that. Yeah, but if you want to kind of archive clips off some websites
That maybe live streamer doesn't work. That's a nice trick
You can do it doesn't some don't work for that. But damn I am so do that's a nice way to pretty much
I'll have to find a link for that. Okay. Okay
Yeah
There's actually a lot of stuff you can do with YouTube DL that are a lot more than people think they can
The name of it implies just YouTube sure there's about 200 different things that work. It's amazing
Yeah, so I don't even use live streamer because most of stuff I use YouTube DL works. So if you want to watch it
Twitch.tv stream you just use YouTube DL with mpv or technically just use mpv and it works
Now when you say technically use mpv are you talking? Are you doing like how simple is it mpv?
And then it's just a twitch URL in there. What are you doing? Yeah, it's mpv
Really all you need is YouTube DL installed and then mpv detects YouTube DL and then parses it through perfectly fine
You don't have to do it. Oh snaps. I am doing that
I want to say I don't think it's in a lot of repos yet
And I was just asking wimpy about this in IRC as well, but it I see a release note from mpv saying that they support
The hardware decoding on Raspberry Pi 2. I haven't ever tried I think it might be in the arch arm repos
Maybe mumble room was more but that would be pretty pretty neat combination right there
normally when there's
Pi compatibility for video playback you you can't just rebuild the source
Package from the Intel versions because you actually need to explicitly link it to
the OMX
Libraries for example. Yeah, so it usually requires a little bit of messing about with haven't looked at it yet
I was aware, but I haven't tried it. If you're talking about YouTube, there's a couple of utilities. There's also mini tube
which is a desktop client for Linux for browsing YouTube, which doesn't require flash and
There's another one called YouTube viewer and YouTube viewer is you know a desktop client for YouTube and behind the scenes
it pulls everything down and streams it either via
mpv or
Mplayer or something like that so it's got different back ends it can use to actually
View YouTube on the desktop, so that's another way to dodge flash right good a point good point
Okay, now
Kits and Kitty is pointing out the elephant in the room that I didn't realize until just now
but
There is a large use case for flash when it comes to porn Kitson, and you're mentioning that
There is certain workarounds for that too, right?
Yes
Apparently I have heard of that
DL works great on red tube. I mean I didn't actually think about it beforehand, but that's a little so
Google's new service you're talking about
I mean it certainly is it is the young there is an uncomfortable truth and the that uncomfortable truth is
Linux makes for a fantastic porn platform you can quote me on that
But the reason is is on Windows you are
legitimately constantly exposed to all kinds of different phishing attacks and scams and and malware that gets to drive by downloaded
That is really not a problem on Linux or any internet browsers will click on anything
so and if you know if somebody should probably maybe there already is should make a live CD around this premise to be honest with you because
It comes with a sexy background
It is a showcase it is a showcase desktop environment because you can get all the codecs on there
You can get flash, and you don't have any of the vulnerabilities. I'm just saying someone should make the porn too
Someone should make one of those ads this one cool trick makes your porn browsing experience better
Yeah, you know you can sell some Linux on BuzzFeed just me or am I the only person that has noticed that?
Sex online is just as dangerous as sex in real life. Yeah
More so I think actually yeah one one trip trick for that is if you use a browser
User agent changer because a lot of porn sites want to support mobile
Oh, and they have to then a lot of times use HTML 5 or oh interesting
So if you if you pretend you're like an Android device, or I usually get a link to some kind of MP4
That's great for all kinds of sites. Yeah, I just did some I'll be I'll put I'll get this to you
So you put it in the show notes, but I found the supported sites list from YouTube DL. Oh, yeah, it's massive
No, I linked it. I linked it in yeah, I linked it in Sunday's Linux action show
There's a quite a few
adult oriented
Mm-hmm
Solution I noticed that way only one I'm interested in is adult swim of course of course right
That's the only thought you care about and you know I just I guess I guess if we're being completely genuinely honest
That is a that is a legitimate use case for flash
Yeah, and it is something that keeps people using it
I guess which I hadn't considered until we started talking about this
But it's the elf in the room and there are solutions for that as well
Well, I think they are that industry is kind of you know
They kind of pioneered that they had a lot of video content to deliver and flash at that time was the only thing that could
Do it your tip about mobile is a good one though because I've read a couple of different articles on how high?
What a high percentage mobile traffic is for those types of sites. Yes, it's your board on the butt
I mean wow wow wow not me uh-huh yeah, no that's fine. That's no I guess zombies don't run Linux
So there you go there is plenty of ways flash can be dead today
If you just take action friends, and we all all of us can make a difference
You can't go vote and make a difference just ask Adam ruins everything good show by the way
But you can make a difference by not running flash
you could also make a difference by going to Linux action show dot reddit comm and submitting stories topic ideas or
Open source projects you think we should know about also feedback for episode 121 over at Linux action show dot reddit comm
We've also got a live stream. I don't know if you knew about that over at JB live TV
We do this show on Tuesdays probably only a couple of more this year like three Wow yeah
You better catch them be here live. Yeah, we've also got that mumble room
We love hanging out with our mumble room getting their live insights. We really mean it
It's our virtual lug and you can take part of that and share your thoughts
Just head over JB live TV go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar get a convert to your local time zone
That's Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar. Don't forget about that contact page while you're on our website and go check out previous episodes
We got a whole bunch avoid the family over the holidays. That's my personal recommendation hang out. You know talk about Linux
That's way more fun. There you go. Hi everybody. Thanks so much to this week's episode of Linux unplugged. See you right back here next week
Oh
There we go we went there, but it was I think I just felt like you know what all of a sudden
We should probably be honest. This is a genuine use case flash, so we did it. Yep. We happened
We had to go there, so I wanted to take a couple of minutes here in the post show and
Just sort of invite the mumble room to jump in on open source projects. They're thankful for but let's do it
Let's do it like we're still doing in the show so that we wouldn't all talk over each other
So take me first in the chat room and with mum and then we'll go for there
But I wanted to just I know this is probably gonna come up, but there was so many projects
I could have been thankful for
Wes I I realized tink might be on your list. Yes, it definitely is so I wanted to play with that more
I think I definitely want to play is there any others that are on top of your mind for your list
Mmm. That's a good question. You think about it. I'll think about it alright, so vert you can go ahead and oh actually nope
Sorry wimpy was first wimpy go ahead. You have your project. You're thankful for
Open SSH good one very good. I can't imagine life without it seriously versatile seriously
Yeah, it is maybe one of the most useful open source projects for all of us like use just broad spectrum great one
great vert
Do you want to mention own cloud?
Yeah, I mean that's really kind of changed my
Entire workflow now because I never really bought into the whole Google cloud services
and so when own cloud came along I started sinking calendars and appointments and everything else between me and my family and
Yeah, it's just been a really great store in that sense, and I'm just glad for now good point all right
Don't forget JB titles calm. Let's pick our title
us hey citizen you're a sort of our resident Jack
Showcase so I'm curious to hear what you're thankful for
Well yeah, definitely thankful for Jack the audio connection kit that helps you more
Necessary for doing any professional audio on Linux mm-hmm
Yeah, and it's something that is probably gonna be I'm gonna have to learn more about it in 2016 expect some
I've been putting it off, but you know you hear hey citizen there, and I have some co-workers who are playing with it
It just it seems like a ton of fun. Yeah, that's like yeah, and also Lily pond tell me about that
Yeah, Lily pond is
Another great app. I'm very thankful for it musical notation
It's kind of like the law tech of
music
Okay, Lily pond. I will google that um
Kitson oh my god the most obvious one that I use for every single show all our hosts use it
And I didn't think of it kits and go ahead
Markdown yeah
Yeah
Seriously markdown. You know what here's why markdown is great at the end of the day
I can just be fleet free flow like you know mr. Creative genius
Just writing like a madman
And I don't have to worry about like links like this is a big deal because I can just put I'll just put something in
A bracket, and then I'll just do you know open parentheses closed parentheses, and I'll just keep typing and then 20 minutes later
I'll go back and get the URL and then I can cite so I know the references in my head
But I just don't have the URL handy so I can keep writing and just quickly bang out stuff
You know format it a markdown and then put it out in consistent perfect HTML every single time
And there's tons of services that will just render that to what you want so many
I mean oh man markdown is a is really is really a good one, so yeah, so I like to go ahead
Sorry, yeah, I like the interoperability
between markdown and all the applications that are out there for it and
That's actually what switched me over from using org mode because with org mode. It was just emacs. Oh
Man rotten corpse you have virtual box. That's a good one to sit so cushy. I think I said
encryption
Encryption software, that's a good one
So yeah, I think we should all thank the people who writes
Encryption software that yeah makes it possible to for us to communicate
Yeah, safely and big picture. It's a big deal and
Yeah, and also the people who who come up with the ciphers and other
Like grip the graphic primitives and make them
Public to my domain and right and share with everybody and yeah, that's a great point
I I'll give will we should probably wrap up with these because this list could go on all day
But I got to get a last one to poppy because ffmpeg is close to my heart
Yeah, I chose ffmpeg, but really I want to thank for grease bella the guy who started ffmpeg
Yeah, and also cue emu because both of them. Yeah
Because both of them. Yeah
Amazing. Yes of software and from you know from okay
They've got loads of contributions, but from one guy to start those two projects guys genius. Yeah, I agree. That's a good one
Alright, so I'm gonna finish that. I'm trying to finish this beer. So if anybody else drinking with me today
Well West is anybody else have a beer
Got to finish this tea
I too am drinking tea. I'm drinking bulletproof coffee. Okay. All right. All right. All right
We got a bulletproof coffee drinker in there so now all of a sudden Chris isn't the only crazy guy
We'll take that now. I'm not crazy. Are you are you putting MCT oil in that thing? What do you got going on over there? I?
Just got the coconut oil. Yeah. Yeah sure yeah, okay, but see here's the thing you can get you can get MCT oil
Which is an extract down of coconut oil which doesn't have any coconut flavor you still get all the benefits of coconut
Oh nice without the coconut flavor, so if you don't want to coconut up your coffee
You putting butter in there
Um, yeah a little bit. Yeah a little bit of butter. Yeah. Yeah, that is any you doing
Are you doing like a like a like are you doing that for breakfast? You doing like a fasting thing? What's going on over there?
No, I just I use it to keep me going it does doesn't it for a long time before having to have lunch
Yeah, not only does it not only does it help you keep going in between meals?
But also, you know sometimes at least for me when the caffeine wears off especially coffee because it's like 120 milligrams of caffeine
I go into like
Starvation mode where I got to eat and I don't care what it takes or what it is or how long it's been in there
I got it. Isn't that weird? Yeah
Do you get like that sensation where your body just like really really really yeah, it's food
Yeah, and you when you do that how to describe it. It's really weird
When you do the bulletproof coffee you do not get that it is a more gradual ramp down
Yeah, why does this sound like a recipe for diarrhea?
Uh, well if caffeine makes you poo if coffee makes you poo then it will happen. Yeah
Gotta love the coffee poo, but I'm telling you what though this I don't I don't I don't do the official like bulletproof coffee
I just go get really good coffee and an immersion blender and I put MCT coconut oil in there and a little bit of butter and
You know
It I haven't done in a while, but it's when it's cold out
You know and you can also like if you don't care about if you're not doing it for health reasons
You can put a little chocolate syrup in there too now don't do that
But you could put a little chocolate syrup in there too, or a little go powder or a little liqueur
Yeah, a little look actually they say I've heard that chocolate is actually really good for you. Well there you go antioxidants shit
That's health food then that's basically health it done done. Let's serve up. Maybe not so much no
The high fructose corn ruin this for us high fructose corn syrup is the number one ingredient. I think in that
Sweet Lou says coffee does make you crap you know when I went to system 76 part of their cyborg
Versus robot versus human lie detector test asked if they asked you if coffee makes you poop
So I think that was one of the things that made me more cyborg less robot because I do poop
oh, did