Sounds like you managed to have yourself
an actual positive experience with Anaconda.
That makes at least one of us, I think.
Yeah, all right.
Well, I wanted to play with GNOME 42,
and I thought, why not try it on the upcoming Fedora 36?
So I grabbed a nightly, went to go install it,
and, well, it started with a less than positive experience.
I didn't have a mouse cursor.
Oh.
Yeah, so that was daunting at first.
My positive note is, turns out,
Anaconda works all right without a mouse.
Hey, there's that.
I got to say, though, the disk partitioner,
when you've got a lot of disks in your system,
and you're trying to put your home drive over here,
and your VAR over there, I mean, Wes,
let's just say I'm still restoring data.
It went real bad.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Bren.
Hello, guys.
Great to have you here.
Coming up on the show today,
we have a game changer release of GNOME just on the horizon,
around the corner, as they say.
We're going hands-on with GNOME 42.
We're going to report what's new,
and what we are so damn excited about.
Plus, the first official alpha
of Asahi Linux's M1 installer is out,
and we're going to try and get that installed
on a MacBook live during the show.
How you feeling, Wes Payne?
Ooh, I'm excited.
I've been looking forward to this for a long time.
Now, picture it, audience.
Wes is here.
He's got his ThinkPad in front of him.
And then off to the side, he's got a card table,
you know, like something you might maybe eat,
like a microwave meal in front of the TV.
I was hoping there was going to be some sort of food here,
but no, no, instead it's a very beefy MacBook.
Yeah, so this is the other thing right now,
is this is all really new.
So I just got this sucker updated
because it'd been neglected for a little bit.
So it just got all updated.
You got to have like the latest Mac OS on there.
And they got a shell script you can run.
Got all that sorted, but I've never really seen anyone
say they have this running on a MacBook Max.
I see a lot of M1 errors.
I believe the dev team has it running on their minis,
but I've seen nobody that's crazy enough
to put it on the MacBook Max.
So this may blow up in our faces.
I'd like to be clear.
I am not guaranteeing that I'm going to return
a working machine to you.
We'll find out coming up here in a little bit.
But before we get into any of that,
before we get into the booths and the pics and all of that,
I got to say time appropriate greetings
to our virtual lug.
Hello, Mumba Room.
Hello.
Hello, Brian.
Man, it's good to see you guys.
Powerful voice today.
I was all out of sorts last week.
Didn't even introduce the Mumba Room
because we only had like five, six people in there.
It was weird because of the daylight savings.
And I thought maybe the show was dead.
I wasn't sure.
But then now we've got 25 people in there.
So it's fantastic.
Thank you, everybody, for making it on a Sunday.
We love having you here.
Yeah, you guys.
Good looking bunch too.
All right.
Should we do it?
You want to like officially kick it off?
Because I got a few things I could get into.
I got to buy you some time.
You do got to.
I mean, yeah.
We've got like things to download.
Do you want to officially kick it off?
Now you do have 53 gigs of free space, right?
Um, I think I should.
I don't know.
You tell me, what does it say?
Does it tell you how much I have on there?
Can you do a DF on the Mac?
Is that a thing you can do?
What does it say?
Yeah, 1.3 terabytes.
Does that sound right?
All right, Westpain.
Let's do this.
You get it started.
I'm going to give you time.
I got a few things to talk about.
We got things to get into.
So you kick it off.
You give me the flag if you got any problems
or when you get to a major milestone
and we'll do a check-in.
You know, you'll be happy to know
the first step here recommends me
curling something and piping it to SH.
So thanks for handing me your very expensive laptop.
And don't worry.
I just did a pseudo dash S so you can go to town.
Because that's how we're going to get it.
All right, we'll check back in in a few minutes.
We are just a couple of weeks away
from our meetup on the East Coast
in Raleigh, North Carolina on April 9th.
There is a lot of people coming, Brent.
Have you, Brent, have you seen these numbers?
Have you?
Yeah.
I think we're like at 60 on the meetup now.
It's just going up and up.
I had a look and I browsed through all the names
and I just kept smiling,
but mostly because usually if there's like 60 there,
then there's even more that show up.
So I think it's going to be real exciting.
Yeah, I think we might have like a hundred people
or something.
I think it's going to be pretty big.
And I've heard from people that can't make it too.
We'll always try to do more meetups too,
but maybe you can.
We'd love to see you there on April 9th.
We're going to be at a park.
It's going to be outdoors.
It's a beautiful time of the year to be in North Carolina.
And this is just outside of Raleigh at a park
that has a barbecue on one end
and a brewery on another end.
And I don't think there's ever been
a more perfect meetup spot.
I encourage someone too to bring their drone
because last time we did a meetup in a park,
we got a great drone group photo.
So if anybody wants to do some drone photography,
this is my hint.
Bring it with you.
I think that'd be fun.
If you can make it, let us know.
We try to give the barbecue place
and the brewery a heads up.
We really at this point don't know what to tell them.
So we're going to have to go by that meetup number.
So you could join the meetup.
I know it's a panel, but it's another account.
But if you could join the meetup,
then we could give the barbecue place
an accurate number of the amount of cows
they got to bring in.
So let us know, meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting.
I guess, Brent, we'll be able to deduct your cow quantity.
Yeah, I'll donate mine.
That's fine.
That's really nice of you.
So really our only story this week
is that the Asahi Linux Alpha is here.
And keep in mind, this is an Alpha, okay?
Don't put this on your fancy expensive Mac yet.
One of the big missing things amongst a few others
is there's no GPU acceleration at this point.
However, Asahi Linux comes with a customized remix of Arch
that has the full plasma desktop
that is actually pretty decent
with CPU accelerated graphics.
So we're going to go with that.
We're going to use plasma.
I'm new sizing your APFS partitions right now.
Whoa, really?
Yeah, right here it just prompts you.
It's pretty nice too.
Like it lets you, I can specify,
you can just specify like how big you want to make it
or you can even put a percentage.
So I could just say like,
hey, we're going to leave 90% to the Mac
and then slice off 10% for Asahi.
And it seems like their strategy
is to make this a dual boot thing.
Like I think Hector, the main person behind the project,
I think Hector even kind of frames it as,
you can do a boot and you can still watch Netflix and 4K
and update your firmware via the Mac,
use your file vault encryption,
keep all of your secret stuff on the Mac that you need.
And then you can also put into Linux
and have a full environment over there.
And so they're really designing this as a dual boot thing.
Yeah.
And now if you're like,
I really just want to run Linux on here,
they do have a min options,
which just tries to like safely reduce the install of Mac OS
down to the smallest size.
Minimum viable Mac.
Yeah, exactly.
You know where that'd be perfect?
Is I actually see myself using this,
not so much on the laptop end,
but on a Mac mini running headless as a server.
Sure.
If they could get GPU acceleration working on a Mac mini,
and then I could run things like Jellyfin or Plex
and get GPU accelerated decoding of video,
maybe even using the built-in H264 decoders in the M1,
and you're looking at 20 Watts of power,
I could probably quintuple the load of work
that I have the machine doing
for my Raspberry Pis right now.
I could still run Linux.
And if I could get that hardware accelerated decoding,
that'd be pretty powerful.
It'd be really, and plus with Thunderbolt on there,
you could hook up a large external array
of solid state disks.
Not like with the Raspberry Pi right now,
I'm limited to USB.
I could really see this taking a home server setup,
running Linux to the next level,
especially if you're power conscious like I am,
because I'm trying to run everything off solar.
And so the difference between 60 Watts,
20 Watts or 130 Watts is huge for my family.
It's like the difference between being able
to run an appliance for dinner and not.
Especially since you've kind of already got over the hurdle.
Now obviously there's differences,
but you've already got over some of the hurdle
of adapting your workflow to supporting an ARM platform.
Exactly, I don't have to worry about that.
Yeah, so I want hardware acceleration,
but I actually don't necessarily want it for the GUI.
Although of course I would use that on occasion,
but my actual use case would be the home server setup.
You just want the GPU supported
so you can offload stuff to it.
Yeah, my bet though is the CPU might be fast enough
that I could probably get away with software decoding
and not really notice
because I'd be coming from a Raspberry Pi.
Right.
So it really kind of depends on how viable it is.
Oh no, process execution failed.
Uh-oh, what happened over there, what happened?
Red alert.
What does it tell you Wes, what does it say?
Failed to run process disk util apfs resize container,
process execution failed.
Oh, Python stack trace, turn non-zero exit status.
So it failed during the actual resize?
Let's try it again.
That sort of seems worst case scenario, doesn't it?
You know?
I mean, maybe.
You failed during the disk.
APFS can handle it, it's a robust file system.
Is it getting warm in here or is it just me?
Last time I didn't enable expert mode,
maybe I should this time.
Wes, if anybody should be enabling expert mode,
it is you, what are you doing?
Someone who's never used an M1 Mac before.
Yeah, but you learn quick.
You all right?
I mean, come on, have some confidence.
Brent, you gotta uptalk your boy here.
He doesn't have enough confidence in himself.
Yeah, I know, he's got this.
It seems like if anyone can pull it off,
it's definitely Wes, it's certainly not me.
So Wes, you got this, expert mode all the way.
Yeah, and if you don't get it working,
we're all just gonna be extremely disappointed in you.
Yeah, we'll have to redo the show, but that's fine.
Yeah, you don't wanna wreck the show, right, Wes?
No, no.
Note, your system may appear to freeze during the resize.
This is normal.
Just wait until the process completes.
That's a nice warning.
What is this, some single threaded bull crap?
What is that?
Okay, so you could do the minimal,
which is still gonna be based on Arch.
It's gonna shrink the Mac install down
to just the minimal viable Mac size,
and then use the rest for Linux.
That's pretty nice.
And you know, a lot of the secret sauce in here
is their mini bootloader stuff that they've been working on.
They've been also really good about updating documentation.
They actually had a big, something that Wes noticed,
so they had a big documentation push
right before this alpha release.
That's kinda how we knew this was coming, really.
And the Asahi Linux team has been doing
has been just absolutely stellar
about getting this code upstream.
The idea is, is that eventually,
support for this stuff just comes baked into Linux.
So once we're a few years down the road,
it'll be normalized and gobbled up by most distros,
and you won't even have to worry if that distro has support.
It'll just be built into the kernel.
Wouldn't that be something?
Yeah.
Now, how's it going over there?
Well, we're trying to resize again.
Mm-hmm.
But?
I feel like there's a button up.
I know, I don't know.
Oh, all right.
I mean, it's just doing its business.
We're at 15%, but that's where it was at before, so.
Is that where it failed before?
Man.
I could try giving it less space.
I mean, how much space did you give it?
150 gigs.
Oh, that seems plenty.
No, less space?
What are you, what are you, an animal?
Here's what I'm gonna do.
I'll buy you some time.
Lino.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account,
and you go there to support this here show.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You gotta try it for your next project.
It's what we use for anything
that we host up there in the cloud.
Our matrix instance has been growing like crazy,
and this has been a great test
of both Linode's alerting system,
infrastructure, and ability to upgrade.
I mean, I can attest it has really stayed nimble.
We threw it on a $5 system initially,
and it just seemed like that was gonna be fine.
There's only like, you know, a dozen people on there.
Now there's thousands,
and we have scaled that system up using Linode's tools,
and we've been able to use their dashboard
to see what the CPU is,
and what the memory's at, and the disk space,
because they really do a good job
of quantifying those essential metrics
in a really easy-to-read dashboard.
Just pop it right on there when you go to Linode,
and you get an overview of what the system's doing.
And of course, they have tools
to just enable monitoring and managing that thing.
So even though we don't have a big team here,
we can keep something that's kind of expanding
at a pretty rapid clip under control.
And now that Linode has been rolling out
MVME storage on their rigs,
things have just taken a whole new leap in speed.
So they are their own ISP,
so they just have the absolute best peering deal possible,
because they're dealing with themselves.
They got 40 gigabit connections
coming into their individual machines.
They got AMD EPYC CPUs on the high-end CPU systems,
and now they got MVME PCIe storage when you need that.
And you know, maybe you don't.
Maybe you just wanna run like a personal portfolio,
or a blog, or a Minecraft server.
They have systems that are just perfect for that,
and at really great prices.
Linode's 30 to 50% cheaper than the large hyperscalers
that wanna lock you into their crazy complicated platforms.
And they got performance that beats them.
It's just great.
And 11 data centers around the world
means you're gonna have the data centers
where you need them, right?
Like, what do you need more than 11 data centers for?
What are you, a maniac?
What are you?
You Bezos?
Come on, 11 data centers is great.
When they've been doing something like this for 19 years,
you know they're gonna do it, right?
So go see it for yourself.
See why we've been talking about it.
See why we've been using them for two and a half plus years.
And see why so many Linux Unplugged listeners
have been taking advantage of that $100 offer.
Now you can too.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Okay, I saw some exasperation over there, Wes Payne.
Failed again.
I wonder if it's like,
because we just recently did an update.
Could like another round of reboots, maybe?
That's not a bad idea.
We could, I mean, I'm down for that.
If you wanna do that, we could do a round of reboots.
That's fine.
You know, there is a lesson in all of this though.
When this announcement came out,
when Asahi Linux announced their availability,
I really had to have a think if I even wanted to bother.
Yeah.
I realized it sort of is akin
to putting Windows on the deck.
It just, like it can be done.
This is what the audience has been trying
to tell me for a while.
It took me a little bit to realize it,
but like, there's better ways to run Linux out there.
This is not, I don't think the advice of this show
is ever gonna be go buy a MacBook and put Linux on it.
I think that's just ridiculous.
I mean, I think this is the closest we've come
to maybe that changing, but you're right.
Before, that's kind of always been experimental,
or if you have one that's three or four years old,
then maybe it works decently.
The thing that I find pretty interesting
is there has been a couple of changes
that have happened in macOS 12.3
that have specifically enabled Asahi Linux
to work better on the MacBooks.
Two different changes happened recently.
And the only reason that Hector and the team
can even conceive that they happened
is to enable Asahi Linux.
There's like specific improvements for Asahi.
What do you make of that?
What are your thoughts on that?
You know what my theory is, and I'll explain it,
but what is your theory?
Well, I hadn't seen those comments by Hector,
so I can't comment on that part.
I mean, it does seem like there's some efforts internally
to make a consistent ecosystem
that does support other operating systems booting.
It does seem like there's been multiple avenues
where things could be locked down,
they didn't need to be locked down,
but knowing Apple, and if you compare it to, say,
their mobile platforms,
places where it would have seen some restrictions
that just haven't, and then above and beyond that,
some work on some of this tooling,
making things easier than it might necessarily have to be
to just tie up loose ends, make it play nicely
with the existing macOS that's gonna be there.
The other thing that they did, they being Apple,
that I just didn't see coming
when they announced their own hardware platform,
is a lot of the essential bring up
that you traditionally would need a binary blob for in Linux
to get that piece of hardware working.
That's being done at the firmware level,
and then it's presenting itself to the OS is ready to go.
And macOS isn't loading these weird proprietary blobs,
like they even did on the Intel systems,
even though they could more easily now than ever
offload that work to the OS because they write the OS
and the OS is only designed for their own hardware,
they could have had that firmware blob stuff
being done in the OS,
and they chose to do it at the hardware level,
and so that stuff is available and ready to go for Linux,
and Linux doesn't have to have those binary blobs.
Right, we have to figure out how to interact
with their proprietary hardware,
but it's interesting, like it's a different level
of communication and interfacing,
and so far it seems like it's kind of a new paradigm
for supporting Linux on an ecosystem
that is neutral at best to us being there.
Yeah, I actually think they want it there.
That's my theory, so my conspiracy bacon on this
is that they actually want Linux on the M1
and future hardware because once they start shipping
M2-based Macs and all that kind of stuff,
you know, once they work the M2 through the line,
they're not gonna stop building M1s.
They're gonna build their own custom M1-based servers
for their iCloud data center.
You know, racks and racks of M1s just on the shelf,
purpose-built for a data center,
and they're gonna need Linux on those things.
They're not gonna wanna run,
they're not gonna wanna run Mac OS on 5,000 M1 servers.
That's ridiculous, right?
And when you think about what iCloud is mostly composed of,
it's composed of database backends, object storage,
NGINX, right, standard stuff that runs on Linux.
They're not running iCloud on Mac OS,
and why wouldn't they want to use the M1 hardware
that has a built-in neural engine that uses less power
so they could save money at their data center,
it's less cooling.
You think about the economics of an M1
when you're dealing with 5,000 of them.
I mean, we know they love dogfooding when they can.
So I guess, I have to imagine internally,
the engineers have been making small, low-level tweaks
to make Linux more available,
or to make the M1 more available to Linux.
It's been my theory.
We'll see, because we're having trouble
even getting the disk resized at this point.
You could see it also just helping their own,
you know, yeah, they can get internal builds of things.
Maybe it makes it a little easier
to sort of try out experimental Mac builds
or, you know, other diagnostic setups
that you might be running to try out new hardware.
Yeah, yeah.
But let's say you want to avoid all that,
and maybe you just want to get a good old open x86 system
and throw GNU slash Linux on there,
and you want the top-tier Linux desktop experience.
You want the best of the best.
That, my friends-
XFCE.
All right, good night, everybody, that's it, and we're out.
No, I have to say, the GNOME 42 release is looking fantastic,
and since LAN kicked off,
we have been running it a couple of days before then,
and we're running it now,
and Wes has got it on his ThinkPad.
I've got it on my ThinkPad.
We'll talk about Brent's setup here in a moment.
We're both running it right here in front of us right now,
and we're excited to tell you all about it,
so keep in mind, it is not out yet.
The way we worded it in LAN was horrible.
I want to just eat that humble pie right here.
I apologize.
The release day is March 23rd, officially for GNOME 42,
but realistically, if you're listening to this at home,
you're going to get it in a distro.
That's how you're going to hear about it or use it.
That's how you're going to see it, right?
It's going to be like, that'll be one of the headline features
of Ubuntu 2204 and Fedora 36 is GNOME 42.
That's really where you're going to hear about it,
but you could actually get your hands on it early,
various means like GNOME OS and Fedora 36, et cetera, et cetera.
And it's here.
It's glorious, and it is the GNOME release
that we've been hoping would land since GNOME 40.
Big things are in this one.
A lot of apps have made the transition to GTK4,
which has a lot of underlying improvements.
But the other big thing here is this actually ships.
Is it Adwaitia?
Is that how we're saying it, LibAdwaitia?
Which there was a lot of controversy about, or maybe
misunderstanding is probably the way to put it.
A lot of misunderstandings about originally,
and we're seeing the fruits of that work now land in 42.
We're seeing a global dark theme that is actually
supported by upstream GNOME.
All of that lands here.
And it truly makes for a remarkable version of GNOME.
40 was a big one.
42 is arguably just as big, if not bigger, in my opinion.
And so of course, I'm very, very comfortable and familiar
with GNOME.
So Brent, I know this is one of your first experiences
You're a plasma guy.
So I'm curious what your GNOME 42 experience was,
because we sort of just threw you in the deep end.
I got to say, it looked beautiful.
I didn't expect how gorgeous it was,
and maybe that sounds a little silly.
But the thing that really hit me was the dark mode.
And I know there's been a lot of work going on behind the scenes
almost for years about this.
And it just worked flawlessly.
I would imagine, Chris, that was one of the first things
you changed as well.
Yeah, I had to try it.
You know what?
Much like Breeze recently, though,
the recent improvements to the theme are so great,
I decided to stick with the light mode.
What?
I don't even know you anymore.
I know.
I'm going to have to pull the dark theme off of the website.
It's a new era.
I'm going to have to implement that standard.
This is actually one of the great things
about using dark mode now in GNOME 42 is the websites that
support this standard will also detect if you have dark mode
or light mode.
And it's just so slick.
It's so slick.
So if you want, you change it in GNOME Appearance
to either light or dark.
And then a lot of websites now just automatically detect it.
Anyways.
I mean, I think that's one of the things
about the recent releases of GNOME,
and particularly this one, that it just
feels like a first class environment because it's
something that you might be used to or have seen
on other platforms.
And the more of those that land on the Linux side of the fence,
it just means people won't be complaining or missing
those features when they come on over.
Another thing, Chris, you suggested that I play with,
since you knew I was a deep KDE user, was the extensions.
And I had a deep hesitation there.
And you seemed really excited about it and suggested a few.
But my hesitation was that it felt as though extensions,
if they were needed to get a desktop running, that
was helpful, that maybe there was something missing
in kind of the vanilla offering.
I think Brent's been listening to Michael Dominic again.
Oh, no.
Yeah, this is definitely a soapbox of Michael Dominic
on Coder Radio.
Is it really?
This is definitely.
Yeah, well, this is actually kind of a sensitive issue.
This is kind of a touchy topic, I feel like.
And it's one that the GNOME community is still kind of
sorting out, in my opinion.
That's just my opinion.
Well, it's kind of a different way to do extensions, too.
There's not like a tight-knit extensions
API that provides this set of capabilities.
It's sort of like, well, you can do a lot
with these GNOME extensions.
And that means sometimes they do too much or are written poorly
and can therefore impact the stability of the system.
But they can also transform the desktop in a way
that you don't always see on other platforms.
It's pretty common to say you install four or five
extensions.
It's pretty common for one of them just to not even work.
That's not too unusual.
We all know of one that I tried that didn't work,
so I just had to disable it.
We were talking about it this morning.
And that happens, and that's not a great experience.
But Brent, I think your core argument or question
is one that a lot of people raise is,
should I even need to add this stuff,
or should I even add this stuff?
And I think that's a decision that ultimately each user has
to make.
And ultimately, I'm grateful that we still have the choice.
I think that's where I fall on it.
I think I kind of agree with you.
Now, since we're talking about it,
it reminds me of extensions, say, in Firefox.
And it's much the same.
There are a few that I can't live without
and that are amazing and that need to kind of earn your trust
from using it for a bit.
And the one you suggested that I install right away
was the app indicator support.
And that actually did make me feel right at home.
So thank you.
And I think I would need that to use GNOME 42.
And it seemed well supported and well used.
I kind of scrolled through the list of other extensions.
And some of them felt, hmm, suspect maybe.
There were some that were trying to, anyways.
There were some that just, my red flag bells ringing
sort of kept coming off, and there was no way
I was going to install those.
Yeah, yeah, for sure.
Yeah, I'd follow you on that.
I'd say for someone who's, I consider myself adventurous,
but also cautious.
So I'd say just kind of do some reading
and maybe play with them on a system that's not
your production machine at first.
Altair, you just made a great point in the IRC.
And that is, it's sort of a double-edged sword.
Having no API means that extensions
can kind of do anything, right?
There's no limit, which is not necessarily maybe
a great thing.
Yes, it's like a weird thing because part
of the reasons they're so powerful
is like they can touch anything.
But also, it's damn cool.
If we're like, it's kind of similar to how
the old Firefox extensions used to work,
where they could do amazing things
and all kinds of awesome stuff.
But once they started migrating things over
to web extensions, a lot of the functionality was removed.
And having to maintain an API is a really, really hard thing.
And coming up with the boundaries
and the capabilities of what you're allowing to do
is a very hard thing that requires lots of resources.
That makes sense.
Yeah.
Yeah, and I could see there being some pushback
if there was an effort around that
because this super popular extension would break.
But at the same time, you have to think maybe long term
that would be the best, right, Brent?
Because I think you're kind of coming at this as a plasma
user, where plasmoids are built into the desktop experience
and you can pull down more.
And it sort of feels maybe, is safer the right term?
You know, I was toying with that.
I think at first I felt it was safer.
But then I was like, well, maybe it's just more familiar.
And it felt like it was more integrated as well.
Like for instance, the GNOME extensions application
wasn't even installed by default.
So I had to kind of install that stuff
and go browse and find some on the web.
So maybe it was the process that felt a little different
or just that it wasn't familiar.
But Chris, I know you've basically
used extensions on your GNOME desktops for years.
And I wondered how you felt about it in this new version.
I always start with the absolute minimum possible
whenever I do a new GNOME install.
And I just kind of incrementally add the ones
that I'd like to have.
Although I admit I have a low threshold.
Like I like having all my virtual desktops displayed up
in the top bar.
So I have a visual indicator where I'm at.
So I'll turn that kind of stuff on.
So it's kind of a low bar.
But I also find that pretty much consistently
with every GNOME release, I have less and less extensions
that I find myself actually installing.
Either they've made some improvement
or I've just learned to kind of adjust my workflow
and we kind of met in the middle.
And that seems to be pretty common.
Like I'll give you, here's an example.
I used to install this really handy screenshot extension
that I thought was great.
And I take screenshots all the time
so I can send Wes stuff and bug him during the day.
Like I gotta have a good screenshot tool
so that way I can spam Wes.
And I would install an extension for that
right out of the box every time.
And now in GNOME 42, they have this new screenshot
experience, in my opinion, it's the best
on any modern desktop out there.
It's so clean, it's so quick.
And I think like Spectacle on plasma
is really great for screenshots
and it has a lot of cool power options.
But this is so simple and straightforward and smooth.
Yeah, right.
I mean, the UI is kind of just the right science
without being in the way and video built right in.
That was impressive.
Yeah, that's so great.
And that kind of stuff has just gotten better and better.
Over the years, the other thing that landed
that we used to have to do a little extra setup
that's just now built in is the remote desktop stuff.
We talked about this with GNOME 41
and the bits were there, all the server,
all the backend bits were there,
but the front end UI bits to turn it on weren't there.
And this remote desktop setup is a really great experience
because it's taking essentially a Wayland session
and piping it over RDP.
And so you use an RDP client
to connect to your GNOME desktop.
And the GNOME desktop is depending on your RDP client,
extremely responsive in that remote session.
And so I have used this combined with tail scale
as like my go-to remote solution for Dylan's laptop now.
And it's just great.
Oh, really?
That's your go-to, wow.
Yeah, cause he's always on the tail scale network
and you and I figured out how to turn on the RDP stuff
before the bits were exposed and it was too late.
We'd seen everything, so I just got it going.
And now that this is just built in
and you can just check the boxes available to anybody.
So you go in there now to the sharing section
where you maybe in the past would like turn on
a VNC sharing stuff,
but now you can take advantage of RDP,
which is Microsoft's remote desktop protocol.
Fine, I'll give you access.
It's so nice.
And it's just another example of a feature
that I'd never really thought was gonna get integrated.
That's just now built in and it solves that problem
of how am I gonna get remote access
to this desktop session that's on Wayland, right?
Because when we switched to Wayland,
we lost a lot of the remote desktop features of X
and this is bringing it back in kind of a modern way
that you can run on anything.
You can get an RDP client on an iPad, right?
And you can have your GNOME desktop on an iPad now.
It's so great.
Mini Mac, now you've got a question
that has plagued GNOME users for a long time.
Indeed, so what about the SysTray?
Is there still an extension for that?
Because I have some, I don't know, do you have a VPN?
If you have a VPN and you have that VPN icon
in the SysTray that you could just click on it
and then you have a VPN connection.
Or I have a Flameshot, which is a screenshot editor
with a beautiful SysTray and everything.
Is there an extension for that?
There's a couple of SysTray extensions.
If you have an app that still uses that older API,
there are a couple of options.
And the one that we've all been,
I don't know if you tried this one, Wes,
but Brent and I were using the one
that essentially just implements the Plasma Desktop API.
Oh, nice.
Yeah, it works, right?
And thankfully, that extension's already available
for GNOME 42.
There's actually a fair amount that are good to go
before it's even final.
Right, and I think that maybe is one thing you can,
you'll learn a little,
if you spend a little while in the ecosystem,
sort of figuring out what extensions,
A, are more sensitive to being broken,
release to release,
and then also which ones really stay on top of things.
All right, boy, I feel like this Libidwadia topic,
we could really, we could spend a whole episode on,
but GNOME 42 is the first version
that puts it at the heart of what defines the look.
And it's an updated toolkit that brings just,
I think the final level of polish that I was waiting for.
There was a lot of misunderstanding
about the direction of theming on GNOME.
And during the kind of heat of that moment,
I kind of had the realization that
if GNOME's default look,
the upstream look of GNOME,
was just good enough,
maybe we wouldn't wanna theme anymore.
And as someone who has literally themed
every version of GNOME since two,
and every version of GNOME three,
and I themed GNOME 40,
and I re-themed GNOME 41,
I am here to tell you,
starting with GNOME 42,
I'm going with the default theme from now on.
They've really nailed it.
The default theme is polished.
It's so well done.
And with the global dark mode
that is now just supported by the entire project,
there are aspects to the UI
that are more visible and usable
than they were with previous dark mode themes.
It really does make a difference
to have the entire desktop environment supported,
and to have the app start updating to support it.
And we're starting to see a lot of apps in the ecosystem
try to target GTK4 now.
And that combined with Libidwadia and the global dark theme,
it really comes together to a level of polish
that I've never seen before on the Linux desktop
in 20 plus years that I've been using it.
It's a remarkable release for that version alone,
so much so that even though you could get Ubuntu 22.04
with the triple buffering patch that we'll talk about
that would probably make it a slightly faster experience,
I still am really suggesting
that perhaps you try Fedora 36 instead
because they're shipping the default theme.
And the default theme is so good
that I don't think you should miss out
on the GNOME 42 experience.
That's my advice now,
is go with Vanilla Gnome because it looks the best.
That's a huge change.
Yeah, wow.
I mean, you-
They've nailed it.
That's kind of like one of the first things you would do
is sort of get things looking decent.
It's a huge change.
It's so great.
It really is great to be able to say that now.
We do have some applications that have changed
like G edit's gone.
There's a new text editor.
And Carl, you saw a note about the new terminal app.
I missed that.
What was that?
Yeah, it looks like there's a new GNOME console app
on the Fedora 36 nightly.
It's not installed by default, but it is in the repos.
And from what I'm reading about it online,
this looks to be a simple terminal emulator,
not really to replace GNOME terminal,
just for it's a console app
for people that don't use the terminal that often
is its own description.
It seems really limited.
It doesn't even have a settings that I can find.
But one cool feature that it has is that
when you elevate to root,
the header bar turns a shade of red,
which is pretty neat.
That is console.
Yeah, yeah.
Danger.
Danger, you're in the root zone.
Oh yeah, look at that.
Neat.
Yeah, it's very similar to the feature
that used to be present on SUSE Linux distributions
way back with their customized GNOME 2 and KDE 4,
where if you did privilege escalation,
the terminal app itself changed to indicate very strongly
that you were running as a super user
and you should be careful.
That's a good idea.
That is a good idea.
So I really liked Fedora 36.
And last night or this morning,
RC1 of GNOME 42 landed on my box.
So that's been really nice.
Brent, did you try it on Ubuntu
or did you try it on Fedora?
I tried Fedora, come on.
Try something new.
Oh, oh, oh, yeah.
Well, I'm not that familiar with Fedora,
but our last foray into that was a good experience.
So I thought, why not?
Plus you were championing it quite strongly.
So I figured I should go that way.
And yeah, it was flawless.
I didn't have any issues.
I loved it, the whole thing.
Wow.
I know.
Jeez, it's pretty- That's high priority.
This is actually the smoothest Fedora beta I've ever run.
Usually if I run the Fedora raw hide beta stuff
for like more than two weeks,
I usually, something crashes and burns.
So I mean, it may still happen.
Fedora 36 isn't final yet, so I may still get bit,
but there is an argument to be made
to try this on Ubuntu 2204 LTS when it ships
because it was canonical staff
that originally created this
GNOME triple buffering support.
And this triple buffering patch is nice
for those of us maybe around Intel GPUs
that are struggling a little bit to keep up
with certain aspects of the GNOME desktop.
And it causes the GPU to bump up
into a higher performance state
during this additional bursty work,
and then kind of scale back down transparently.
And I guess currently that's not happening.
And you put this triple buffering patch in there
and it's a noticeable improvement
in the smoothness of the interface
for those of us that are on integrated GPUs.
I think I saw this mentioned something
about Raspberry Pi is too,
if you happen to be trying it on there.
Hmm, hmm.
So Canonical's decided they're gonna just go ahead
and ship it in Ubuntu 2204
because the patch just didn't land in time
for 42, it seems.
That's at least my current understanding.
I'm very sad about this.
I really, really wanted that to land.
If it had landed, this truly would be the GNOME release
that has everything we've been waiting for, right?
Because even when 40 came along,
like that was a big update,
but we were like, okay, well, the transition to GTK4
and we knew that Libido was in the far off distant future.
And so it was like, okay, 40 is a big release,
but there's like more coming.
And basically everything is in 42
except for that triple buffering patch.
So it's like, okay, well,
now I'm gonna be waiting a little bit for an update,
but I actually really have no complaints
performance-wise, so it's not really a big deal.
Now I'm wondering how to put my own janky build together.
Jeez.
I'm a little concerned
that you're in the recovery environment right now
on the Mac over there, Wes.
I take it that the old Asahi Linux install
has hit yet another bump in the road.
Yeah, it's not quite going so well yet.
It is alpha.
Ugh.
So why are you in the recovery environment?
Well, we were having some issues
shrinking the partitioning
so that we can make some room for Linux.
And so I thought,
maybe if we try it from this environment,
it might go a little better.
Of course I can inspect the APFS volume and make sure.
Oh yeah.
Make sure there's no issues there to start with.
Do one of them verifies that they do there, right?
Right.
Do a verify of the old file system
and then you could resize it in the Disk Utility app
and that probably won't lose all my data.
So that's the way I think.
I'm not actually sure how to resize it.
I did copy the command.
So we'll, you know, one way or another.
All right, here, I'll buy you a few minutes.
Hey, I got a live stream coming up on March 31st.
So join me for a live Q&A
and I'm gonna give away some Satoshis
to help people set up their Boost wallets
because I really think we have a window of time here.
And so go grab yourself a new podcast app
at newpodcastapps.com.
We recommend the Fountain app.
Cast-O-Matic on iOS is really great as well
and BlueWallet's available.
But I think Fountain is the best experience
and I wanna help you get started
by giving away some stats
that have essentially been sent in by the audience.
We'll pull them all together
and I'll give out some of them hot Satoshis.
I hear you're even using Fountain
for some of your day-to-day podcasts listening.
I have, yeah, I've switched over now
because here's what my thinking is,
is I think we have an opportunity
to build out a peer-to-peer network
of Lightning connected Linux users.
We start by, you know, obviously,
I have some skin in this game.
This benefits me,
but we start by supporting independent media.
I'm saying the podcast audience, right?
We build out, okay, so let's just say like,
let's say the show has tens and tens of thousands,
five tens, maybe six tens of thousands of listeners, right?
And let's just say in theory,
I can talk a thousand of you
into supporting somebody who's been making content
for you for 15 years.
And let's say I can get a handful of you
who see the value in how hard we've been working nonstop
every single week for 15 years straight.
And I can convince maybe 2000 people to switch over
and start getting on the Lightning network
and supporting the shows through value for value and boosts.
So what happens when the next Linux podcaster realizes
that 2000 people who listened to the largest Linux podcast
are all now wired up to the Lightning network?
Well, that new Linux podcaster that comes online
is gonna immediately start also getting boosts.
They're gonna have a built-in audience already, right?
So there's an immediate network effect amongst me
and my friends once they figure it out.
But then what happens when we've got three,
5,000 people now on this network
and the first free software project that we care about
comes on the network.
That's 5,000 Linux loving users
that are already on the network
and ready to support that project.
And all they have to do is set up a Lightning node.
I think it all starts here.
We have the network effect to generate this.
Like this is actually something
the show can move the needle on
for the first time in what feels like forever now.
So let's get together,
join me on the live stream, jblive.tv, March 31st,
and I'll send out some stats.
I mean, I'm not like Elon Musk over here,
but I wanna help you get started on this.
And I recognize that actually getting something
in that wallet is like the barrier to entry right now.
It just is.
And I really believe in this.
So I'm willing to put my money where my mouth is on this.
And so just imagine a day
where this starts to take off, right?
So go grab a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com,
get in on the boosts, send the show some boosts.
Let's start playing with this.
Also, I think the other thing I wanna do
during that live stream is I'd love to help anybody
who's had trouble getting on our matrix server.
If you've been trying to like get on matrix
or you've been thinking about setting up matrix
and joining the Jupiter broadcasting matrix,
I wanna help you do that during this live stream as well.
So it's a Q and A, anything goes, ask me anything.
I'd love to get my friends to come hang out with me guys.
And also I'm gonna be giving out some stats
to people who are setting up a new podcast app wallet
and wanna help do some boosting.
And last but not least, we'll just hang out and chat
and maybe get some people on our matrix system as well.
So it's gonna be 4 p.m. Seattle time,
7 p.m. New York time, 11 p.m. London,
March 31st at jblive.tv.
I'd love to see you there.
We got a little bit of feedback
and a whole bunch of boosts.
So first for the feedback, we got a listener asking,
I'm interested in exploring the Fedora ecosystem
and I would consider moving my Arch jellyfin Docker
NAS Frankenstein machine to a more stable platform.
Sounds like they've been listening to us too much.
Amazing.
Is CentOS Streams something that one can let run
with automated updates and get away with monthly updates
like a big Pac-Man upgrade?
I think that's a great question.
It's one that I, of course,
everybody's gonna have an interpretation on,
but Neil, you wanna put your name on the line
and give an official recommendation,
quote unquote, official.
As official as unofficial gets?
Yeah. Sure, yeah.
Go ahead.
So I've actually been doing this now for a year.
I've been running CentOS Stream on a couple of boxes
with DNF automatic configured using Cockpit.
Like there's, you can activate Cockpit, install it,
and from within the web UI,
you can configure automatic updates.
I have it update every Sunday at 3 a.m.
and it reboots itself and brings everything back online
every Sunday, every week without fail,
no problem at all.
And it's been doing this since, okay,
when did I actually set this machine?
June, late June.
And nothing's blown up in your face yet?
No, it's been totally fine.
It's been phenomenal and the experience is pretty good.
Like I can't say the same thing about the desktop.
The desktop experience really only solidified in the fall,
but the server experience has been bang up awesome
pretty much since June.
And I mean, even the new Podman 4.0 is there.
The Cockpit management of containers through Podman
is present, Cockpit machines is there.
So if you wanna, if it's a bare metal server
and you wanna also manage a mixture of virtual machines
and containers, that's all present.
It's super solid, works great.
And I really have no complaints about it.
Of course, I'm working on CentOS Stream 9 Hyperscale.
And once I've got more of those pieces laid down,
I plan to migrate that machine to Hyperscale,
but that's because I like to eat my own dog food
and I think my stuff is awesome,
but I've been running vanilla CentOS Stream 9
for almost a year now and it's been fine.
All right, that's great.
I also think it would be more than fine,
especially he's coming from Arch, right?
So Fedora would even be like a scale back
in the terms of changes,
but I actually think CentOS strikes the right balance there.
If you think of CentOS Stream 9
as a continuation of the Fedora 34 code stream
for many more years, then you will be fine.
Like if you liked what Fedora Linux 34 offered
from Fedora Workstation 34 minus the Butterfest stuff,
and having some of the light touch enhancements
and backports of enhancements and neat things
that Red Hat and the community have worked on in 35 and in 36
and you just want a stabilized platform
with a good balance between feature enhancements
and stability, then you're gonna have a nice time
on CentOS Stream 9.
And if you want to, and CentOS Stream 9 is supported
for the quote unquote full support phase
of the RHEL lifecycle, which is five and a half years.
That's pretty good, yeah.
That is, especially for free.
Right, and once you're past that,
you could either use Red Hat Enterprise Linux 9
genuine article to get a full 10 year lifecycle,
and there'll probably be RHEL rebuilds
like Alma Linux or whatever that you could use
if you want to go that route instead.
Sure, yeah, yeah.
Now I want to make it clear,
because he is coming from Arch, Carl,
we should probably make a little disclaimer
that he shouldn't expect this to be a rolling distro.
Right, yeah, we're still seeing misconceptions
in the community.
Some of it caused by the own CentOS messaging,
but CentOS Stream is not a real rolling release.
Like most people think of it,
it's gonna stay on the same major version nine,
and the updates you see are going to be
the same updates you'd see within a RHEL major version.
So really the big change is that there's no minor versions,
but you're not gonna wake up one day
and have RHEL 10 content on there.
It's still gonna be what you see in RHEL 9,
and only the kind of updates you'd see
going from say 9.0 to 9.1
are the updates you'll see on that system.
Yeah, yeah, thanks for making that clear.
I think that's good for people understanding.
And you'll know when that's coming,
because we'll be talking about it here on the show,
so you'll have plenty of a heads up.
And now, as the French say, it is time for Le Boost.
Samuel Blair wrote in with a boost.
Been listening for years, already supporting the show,
but figured I would give this boost thing a try.
Keep up the good content.
Slow down a little if you need.
The community is not going anywhere.
Aw, well that's nice.
Pew!
Six days ago, 5,000 sats, thank you freak.
Sadly, the lightning system does not work
with the core contributorship.
It'd be very cool, for example,
to get access to an ad-free feed
at greater than X sats per minute.
What I'm going to do is play
with the sats per minute settings
and the occasional boost to get to around
10 to $20 per month over all my podcasts that support it.
Yeah, you know, there's a lot there that,
A, we're not happy with with our current setup,
because, well, this stuff's all new
and not all of the various pieces
that we've had to bolt together
to make the membership stuff work supported right now.
And then also just like, oh, this is kind of new stuff.
And yeah, you could see a whole SAT powered,
you know, lightning based membership system, maybe?
I don't know, what do you think, Brent?
Yeah, we've had a few people write in
about this very problem, and I think they're totally right.
Despite it being a little bit of an edge case,
I think just wait and see.
Like, this is progress that we're sort of
in maybe some transitional phases.
So, I mean, Wes, you've done a ton of work
on the back end to try to like,
literally, like you said, bolt things together.
So, I think it's been working great,
but there's always progress to be made.
All right, well, Mollusk sent us a boost saying,
great show, guys, been listening for over 10 years.
And I'm glad to see you guys in Bryce Podcasting 2.0.
Keep up the good work.
Our next one, DG Wolf writes in,
thanks for revisiting Jellyfin, guys.
I tried it years ago, but it was a little rough.
But he gave it another go after we talked about it,
and it's now replacing his Plex server.
How is that awesome?
Wow, dang.
Yeah, from North Carolina, too,
so hopefully we'll see him at the meetup.
We'll see him.
Always good to hear some Jellyfin love, too, you know?
I mean, it's maybe not for everyone,
but it's come a long way.
Scuba Steve, Scuba Steve, who's in the Mumble Room, too,
so like getting double points today,
four days ago sent us a boost that said,
can't wait to see you guys in Raleigh.
Oh, Scuba, you're gonna be in Raleigh, that's great.
That's great.
So, he asked what we think about Substack,
which is, I think I'm gonna punt this question
to Koda Radio.
So, tune into Koda Radio for that one,
because I think that's gonna be a good discussion
between Mike and I.
Hudson said five days ago,
you know, the thing about value for value
is that it gives you skin in the game.
It incentivizes people to create quality feedback.
Unlike a YouTube comment,
if I send you guys 1,000 sats to make a comment,
I'm gonna make sure it's thoughtful.
Otherwise, I'm just wasting my money.
Imagine this concept, but throughout all of the internet,
it may be a potential way to clean up a lot of the junk
and the noise on the internet.
I am of a really mixed opinion on this, Hudson.
I definitely have witnessed what you're saying firsthand.
And yet, at the same time,
I hate the idea of creating financial barriers
to participate on the web.
But I guess that's a little of an extreme view.
That's probably not what would happen, right?
You'd just get some places
that ask for a little bit of value to participate
to reduce the cost of harassment and spamming.
And I'm watching this play out in real time at stacker.news.
I mentioned this to you guys a couple of weeks ago.
stacker.news is like Reddit,
but you have sats, there's an incentive system
around quality posts and quality comments.
They're incentivized by a couple of sats,
kind of like the boosts are.
And I've been checking this site for about three weeks.
And what's interesting is,
you could cut out Reddit and Twitter altogether,
avoid both those dumpster fires.
And I'd say you'd still get 80% of the value
without all of this stuff that sets you in right there.
So it's like, if you're willing to miss out on some things,
but still get most of the value of Twitter and Reddit,
stacker.news has been really great.
And I have to think it's because there is an incentive
for quality content, but even more importantly,
there's an incentive for high quality comments.
So it's not just these crappy fights that happen.
It's like people are providing additional source material
and references.
And yeah, that's been really cool.
Yeah, it seems like it could still be vulnerable
to sort of group think or other problems,
higher level problems,
but maybe you could address some of those lower level,
just posting that, yeah, is it relevant?
Or yeah, as you say, is fighting or-
I think it's a nice social experiment.
I don't know if I'm ready to see something like that be,
like the concept be adopted everywhere.
But I think it is an interesting experiment
to watch a group do and see how it goes.
That's stacker.news, if you want to check that out.
I've been kind of following it.
And I mean, it's definitely Bitcoin heavy
and lightning heavy,
but that happens to be things I'm interested in,
but it's not just that stuff.
It's like the stuff that would normally kind of be
circulating that's popular and trending,
but without all of the garbage.
Anonymous sent us a boost six days ago,
says it feels very good to be listening to your podcast
and streaming in and streaming some stats back.
It's quite literally value for value.
I love it, and I could see doing it
for free software one day.
And I completely agree, Anonymous.
I think that's going to be, that's where I see the shift,
but we'll see.
We'll see if we get there.
It may happen.
It may not.
You know what?
I may just be wasting my breath.
We shall see.
All right.
Thank you for boosting everybody.
But with the boost all boosted,
Wes Payne, let's do a check-in on that MacBook Max.
I know you've been in disk utility for the last few minutes.
How's it going?
Bad news.
Uh-oh.
It seems like you've got some kind of disk corruption
going on here.
Oh, I like how it's my problem all of a sudden.
Well, I found it this way.
At least you think I've already corrupted it somehow.
I'm surprised you haven't fixed it already.
That's all.
Yeah, well, I've rebooted it into the recovery environment,
running first aid on it from disk utility,
and all I get is this pop-up here with the error sign saying.
So a file system, now I don't even understand
how that's possible considering
what if the resizing stuff that failed partway through
with that error caused the error?
It's possible.
Because this is like a fresh.
It failed because it found an error.
Oh.
So it probably wasn't that.
It's probably already existed.
The volume slash dev slash R disk 3 S5
was found to be corrupt and needs to be repaired.
Unable to perform declared repairs
without full space verification.
Well, it looks like we won't be getting
Asahi Linux on there today.
We may just have to nuke and pave the thing.
I mean, it's pretty fresh install.
It's like browsers installed.
There's telegram installed.
Yeah, I was gonna say how much junk do you have on here?
I mean, it must've been edge.
It must've been putting the Microsoft edge on there.
I can't trust it.
It's gotta be it.
That's gotta be what it was.
But we're gonna put it on Asahi as well.
We just can't get that far.
Yeah, I got a login on my Microsoft account and sync it up.
All right, well, let's do a couple of picks.
I don't know.
The whole show's ruined now.
We gotta redo the whole show now.
We have two picks for you.
First one is Fountain.
That's the podcast app that I like.
Version 0.3.10 just came out this last week.
And you can now opt to have your boosts public,
if you like, in the Fountain app.
And the second pick is Antennapod 2.5,
a really cool release because this one lets you be a cool guy
with your own Antennapod sync setup.
Really?
Yeah, using G Potter for Nextcloud, which is a thing.
You can load that up on your own Nextcloud instance.
Back up a little bit.
Uh-huh, G Potter for Nextcloud.
Okay.
It's an app now for Nextcloud.
Sweet.
Yeah.
If you think about it, it's genius
because then the G Potter folks aren't responsible
for like paying out for massive, massive infrastructure
all the time, right?
Yep.
And it gives you a backend sync
that you can self-host on Nextcloud.
So if you've already got an Nextcloud,
why not go install the old G Potter app?
And then you can take Antennapod
and point that at the G Potter app.
Are you following me, Wes?
Right, yeah.
And now you have like a sync backend
and then you take your mobile app
and you say, hey, sync over here.
It's just Antennapod doesn't get enough love on this show
because it's A, a popular app amongst our audience,
B, a great podcast app, and C, open source.
I just wish that they also supported Boost, you know?
Why don't you file a PR?
You're right.
I should file a PR.
That's a great idea.
I have a sense they're probably aware
of the whole Podcasting2 spec.
I'm sure.
I would hope so.
If they're not, they should probably do a little research.
But we'll have links to both the new Fountain release,
which is a great looking release too.
I mean, I mentioned Public Boost,
but there's a bunch of other nice stuff in there.
One of the other cool things about Fountain
I'm just gonna mention real quick
is that has the coolest clipping system that you can,
it'll combine the album art with a waveform
that it'll auto-generate
and then you can make a YouTube video out of it
or an MP4 or just an audio file.
And I really feel like a more popular clip sharing.
And then it has like a discover tab inside the app
where you can see other clips that people have made.
I really feel like that'd be a great way to grow podcasting
and help people discover good shows
cause you get a real taste of the flavor, as they say.
Also Fountain is working on transcription,
which is such a cool feature.
It can transcribe each episode.
So you can, it'll help do the edit.
You'll work with the edit too for that,
which is such a neat feature to take the transcription
and use it to help cut the clips down and stuff like that.
I mean, it's pretty cool stuff
they're building in this app.
At some point we're gonna be making our podcasts
in the Fountain, that's what it sounds like.
I know, right?
I know, geez.
Anyways, links to them in the show notes
at linuxunplugged.com slash four five zero.
Over there you'll also find our contact page.
We'd love to hear from you via the contact page as well.
And you'll also get, what Wes?
Subscribe links, matrix info, mumble info.
That's right.
That's all over there.
Easy ways to send us email.
Yeah.
If you wanna send us your pics or your thoughts.
That's fine, that's fine.
And of course you're welcome to join us live.
We do the show on Sundays,
get together at noon Pacific, three p.m. Eastern.
jblive.tv.
See you next week.
Same bat time, same bat station.
And of course, don't miss Linux Action News.
If you're in the industry,
you gotta catch Linux Action News.
It's almost a mandate.
Just not yet, not yet.
Yeah, you know, Congress can't get anything done.
No, we're working on it though.
We got a lobby group.
We're paying them with Dogecoin.
In the meantime, just go to linuxactionnews.com yourself
before you're compelled to do it.
And, you know, listen to it.
That's my worst pitch ever.
But I think you get the idea.
Anyways, we just appreciate you listening.
Nothing else, just thanks.
You're great.
We really do thank you and everybody out there.
And we'll see you right back here next Sunday.
I'm your host, I'm your host, I'm your host, I'm your host.
Last-minute update to the show here, Wes Payne.
It appears that Antennapod is working
on value-for-value support.
We have a PyCrash update with a link to a GitHub issue
that was opened up on November 8th, 2020.
And it even includes a diagram
of how the value-for-value flow model works.
Look at this.
If you were wondering what the hell we've been talking about
and you wanted a visual, this is it.
We'll put a link in the show notes to this.
And it's exciting to see that Antennapod
is indeed working on this.
How about that?
Yeah, I don't know if it's, right now,
there's some discussion on the forum.
Been a little while since there's an update.
I mean, it could happen though.
It could happen.
Like we have a thread to tug on now.
But it is, maybe it needs a little bit
of a demonstration of interest, perhaps.
That never hurts.
I mean, you know what?
You build out the network, the bigger the network gets,
the more everyone's incentive aligns, right?
Like, of course, JB stands to make some money,
but of course, so does every other podcaster
and so does open source projects
and pretty soon individuals.
Like, that's how a network effect works.
And the more people on the network,
the more valuable it becomes.
And why not go with something that's decentralized,
it's open source, and it's completely sovereign
so people can self-host their own nodes if they want to.
Just make it real easy for us to all shoot some payments
for us being cool to each other.
Pew, pew!
I like what you're doing over there.
Yeah, hey, good job.
Here, here, have some.