Welcome into Linux Unplugged, episode 385.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And no hiding it, there's a Drew over there too.
Heyo.
You guys, you look good.
You look real good today.
We all dressed up for the tuxes.
We're all wearing our going to town clothes because it's a very special episode where
we get to say thank you to a lot of open source projects and see who our audience voted as
some of the best in newcomers and distributions and text editors, just about everything you
think we'd nerd out on.
So it's a special episode today.
We're also going to do a special holiday unboxing here in a little bit.
And we have a special guest joining us to help us go over all of the new goodies that
have landed in Plasma and just the state of Plasma in 2020. Nate, welcome back to the
show, man.
Hi there.
Thanks.
It's great to be here.
Man, it's great to have you.
So hold on.
We're going to get to Plasma here in just a moment.
But before we do that, I have to say thank you to a Cloud Guru for sponsoring this episode.
They're the leader in hands-on learning.
The only way to learn a new skill is by doing.
And that's why ACG provides hands-on labs, Cloud Linux servers, and much more.
So get your hands cloudy at a CloudGuru.com.
I psyched your mind, Mumble Room.
You thought I was going to call on you.
Some appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Hello, everybody.
Good to have you in there.
Thank you so much for being here.
I'm looking forward to our discussions as we analyze who the winners are this year.
Also, I'm glad you're here for the surprise unboxing for Mr. West.
And this year on Coda Radio, I've started talking a lot about how I think Plasma is
a fantastic workstation for developers and administrators who want a really stable, rock-solid
Linux base, but want something that's like a power tool.
I've made the equivalence before that you know how you might have like a cordless drill
in your garage that's pretty capable, but then you go into like a vehicle shop that
has like one of these air-powered suckers and it just can take a thing apart in 10 seconds?
That's what Plasma is, in my view, when you look at the different desktops out there.
But they've managed over 2020 to really polish that thing and make a lot of these things
that were rough edges in the past a lot smoother now.
And Nate Graham has been tracking all of these developments week by week on his blog.
Since we've had you on forever ago, you're still doing it like a soldier of the Plasma
desktop.
I really appreciate it.
I love reading through these.
Sure am.
It's a lot of fun.
I mean, like, first of all, thanks, man.
You're welcome.
Like, geez, that's got to be a lot of work.
To do it every single week like that.
I got to admit, it takes quite a while.
I typically start writing each new post before I finish the old one.
Wow.
And I just kind of keep building them up throughout the whole week.
I used to do it on like Saturday night right before I hit post, but it would take hours
and hours and hours.
So now I just keep the draft open all week and add new stuff as I see it get merged,
which is a lot more a lot more reasonable to do.
But yeah, it takes a while.
I know those workflows very well myself.
You know, we have a similar kind of approach with the shows is they're kind of in development
from the moment we end them to the next one.
You must be doing what?
I mean, a bunch of VMs in some cases and whatnot.
That way you can get a screenshot or try something because you got to kind of understand it to
write about it.
Actually, I don't use any virtual machines at all.
I run my entire computer on built from source KDE Plasma stuff.
So the first thing I do every morning is build every piece of KDE software from Gitmaster.
And then use that stuff.
So when I need to take a screenshot, I'm literally taking a screenshot of my own desktop.
This is all stuff that's in in production in use.
And I feel like personally, it's pretty amazing how stable our Gitmaster stuff is because
so many people are actually running their their plasma sessions like this.
So we actually have a lot of internal QA.
But yeah, no VMs for me.
Careful now you're giving Chris ideas and maybe not good ones.
It's super stable, man.
You can do it.
And once once you use a rolling release distro, I've had people tell me that they read my
blog posts and they say, Oh, man, I switched to arch, I switched to Manjaro or tumbleweed,
because I wanted this stuff really fast.
But now I feel like it's not fast enough anymore, because I want the new stuff.
Now.
I don't want to wait three months.
Well, you make you make an art user look chill.
But I need to kind of it kind of feels like it's a new form of of journalism.
Like it's a it's a form of journalism that is unique, and only kind of possible with
free software.
And do you do you see it as a form of journalism?
Or do you see it as a form of project advocacy?
You know, I kind of see it as a bit of both.
This is something that I thought myself about, because I didn't really set out to do something
like this.
I originally wanted to just categorize and tell people about what had gone on for the
usability and productivity initiative that we had a few years ago.
And what I realized over time was that it had become a form of like marketing, as well
as just description, because people would be really interested in seeing what stuff
was going to happen in the future, like they would get excited.
And they would say, Oh, I want to use this stuff right now.
And that was definitely not my goal to start out with, it was supposed to be descriptive,
but it's, it's turned into something that's like a little bit between advocacy and journalism,
I would say.
And it also gives the users a sense of continued forward progress.
That was actually the entire point.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
When I when I originally started this a few years ago, I started using plasma and other
KDE software.
And I said to myself, Wow, this stuff is really great.
But you know, I read all of this negativity all over social media, people seem to have
this impression that it's like it's dead.
Its developers are mean and rude.
You know, there's all this stuff that doesn't work properly.
It's really buggy.
And like, that wasn't really my experience.
And I felt like if I could be a voice for the opposite, showing just what I saw of the
project, it would help to counter that narrative that to me seemed like it was very dated.
Like maybe this was true 10 or 15 years ago, but it didn't seem true in in that moment.
And I really feel like that was successful.
Because I don't think those old stereotypes are true anymore.
Like people used to say, Oh, it's so bloated, it takes up a gigabyte of RAM, I can't use
it.
But now, plasma is known as one of the most lightweight desktop environments out there.
And like, we still see people who believe that old stuff.
But you know, now there's there's always a cohort of people who understand the truth
that all this performance work that we've done over like the last couple of years, or
even like a decade or more, have paid off and everybody can benefit from it.
So I think it's really important to have a direct line to your users so that you can
be pushing a narrative that's true to counter misinformation out there.
And sometimes the misinformation, it isn't like it isn't malicious, right?
Like somebody who used KDE 15 years ago, their impression back then was was probably true,
even though it doesn't match the state of reality today.
So like, sometimes, countering that misinformation doesn't mean like putting somebody in their
place, but just giving out the correct information that's true today.
Yeah, and then letting another version be seen and read about and I think you I just
watching it and seeing how the community discusses plasma now, it's, it's, it's really in a much
more positive tone.
I think it's had a significant noticeable impact.
And so I thought, why don't we bring people up to date on kind of some of the stuff you've
you've really thought was the most interesting in plasma in 2020.
And maybe if there's other KDE apps to that you think we should include in there.
But it's a big question.
But you know, I took I kind of took most of 2020 off from plasma and then just came back
to it a month ago.
And I'm like, Oh, man, I can see even in that time, there's been noticeable improvements
with with like the brightness controls and just all the widgets down by the clock that
I use all the time.
Oh, awesome.
I was I was gonna talk about that quite a bit.
So I'm glad you noticed.
Well, do you want to start there?
Because I've noticed there's nice little improvements that have landed and maybe that's one of them
we should start with.
So this, this was a specific improvement that we really set out to do.
It's been in the planning stages for over a year, but the system tray, as I believe
what you're referring to, and this was one of the oldest parts of plasma five, it was
it was, you know, most of this code was years and years old.
And it was like good for the time, but it could really stand a lot of modernization.
And so Katie's VDG group, this is the visual design group.
We also do interaction design stuff, we set out to improve and modernize the system tray
applets.
And over the course of 2020, we've we've done a ton of that.
If you look at the current state in plasma 520, I think it's pretty good.
And in 521, it just gets even better.
And we made a bunch of improvements such as using a unified theming for all of the applets.
So they don't seem so unique anymore.
They all kind of have a common theme.
We have like a defined header area on top.
And in plasma 521, we're even going to have an almost like header bar style, where we
have the title bar and the controls merged into the same row.
We have common controls used for everything.
So the amount of code and the bugginess is hugely decreased.
We've worked on the visual presentation for system tray applets that have a visual component
like the media player.
Oh, the media player looks so nice now.
It's really, really, really pretty looking.
Yeah.
And so on and so forth.
We just we kind of went down the line with every individual system tray applet and reviewed
the usability reviewed the aesthetics and just said, how can we polish this and make
that individual applet the best version of itself.
And then we went back to the whole system tray itself, which is like the containment
for these applets.
And we tried to make them integrate well into the system tray so that it seems like a really
cohesive unit and just make it make it better, basically.
And I feel like we've succeeded.
So I'm really glad you noticed that and brought it up because that tells me that our work
was impactful.
Yeah.
No, noticeable.
It seems like and maybe this has been landing in bits over time to but system settings has
seen a bunch of rework.
It feels much more streamlined and easier to navigate.
Awesome.
It was a sensation that I just had to go hunt for everything and now it seems much more
discoverable.
That's great.
Yeah.
System settings is another example where we've done a lot of iterative design.
Most people don't realize that system settings is actually one of the most complicated pieces
of code we have because each individual page is actually a tiny app.
So system settings is basically a shell around like 120 apps, which is kind of mind boggling
to think about.
And that's why a lot of this work gets done in a very incremental fashion instead of,
you know, all at once and then it's done.
But I'm glad you noticed that, too, because we have definitely done that.
One thing that we're doing over time is rewriting the old system settings pages in QML, which
makes them a lot easier to improve in the future.
It gives us a chance to revisit the user interface for that particular page.
And it also makes those pages usable on plasma mobile, too, because plasma mobile does not
have the ability to use QWidgets based system settings pages, only QML ones.
So we have the convergence aspect there, too.
And over the course of 2020, we have rewritten eight pages in QML and there are a couple
more that are in review and hopefully will be merged within maybe a week or two or something
like that.
So yeah, that's a bunch of stuff.
But we also have a bunch of new features in system settings, too.
We also have one thing that's been really popular among our users is an automatic syncing
system for your KDE app settings to GTK apps.
So like when you change the font size in your KDE apps, it changes the font size in GTK
apps as well.
When you change the color scheme in your KDE apps, it changes the color scheme in GTK apps,
stuff like that.
This used to be a manual process and you'd have to do it yourself.
Now it's automatic.
It just happens on its own.
That's been very well received.
We also have a feature in system settings that lets you highlight settings that you've
changed from their default values.
We did this because people would often say, oh, man, system settings is really complicated.
I tweaked a bunch of stuff and now I don't know what I did.
So we did that so that people could visualize what changes they actually made so that they
could see whether they wanted to keep them or not once they found themselves in that
situation.
And there's tons of polish throughout the stack, too.
This is really neat.
I had not noticed this before, so essentially it marks them almost like with an unread indicator.
And you want to know what's really cool.
You're looking at the orange dot on the sidebar now, right?
Yeah.
So if you click on one of those items that has an orange dot, it will actually highlight
the individual settings on the page that have been changed.
This was a ton of work, by the way.
So it's I'm really happy with it.
Yeah, it looks slick, but you can tell there's some logic behind the scenes there.
Oh, tons.
Yeah.
There's tons of logic because, like I said earlier, every system's settings page is like
a tiny app.
So what this required us to do was rewrite a lot of these pages so that they used a common
base.
Previously, a lot of them were just like literally their own apps.
And now to make this highlight change settings feature work, we created a sort of framework
that they all inherit from so that when you write a new system settings page, you plug
it into this preexisting framework and that feature just works automatically.
And porting all, you know, 100 of those pages to use this thing was a Herculean task.
So I'm really happy that it works as well as it does.
Yeah.
And that is that's a feature now that I will mention that when people I had no idea.
I had noticed that button there, but I hadn't tried it yet.
And I can only imagine the amount of work that went into it.
And that's something I'll tell people to check out.
Yeah, it's pretty nice.
And a really cool thing is that because we've now ported all of these pages to use this
common base, all of the pages now know what their default settings are.
They know how they differ from their default settings.
So this opens up the door for us in the future to add a much requested feature that will
allow you to reset everything to its default settings because all the pages actually know
what those are now.
So we'll be able to do that without having to, like, brute force it by just blowing away
the config files.
You know, the chat room is, you know, the chat room is thinking they think, you know,
what we want now is we want to sync those settings between plasma desktops.
That's what they're thinking.
So this is this is another feature.
And again, it's something that's made possible by the plumbing work that we did for this.
Now that every page knows what settings have been changed from their default values, it
becomes really easy to, you know, reset them, export that.
A syncing feature between plasma desktops would be amazing.
But that, of course, requires a bunch more work on the on the server side.
You need all sorts of sync and deduplication stuff.
And that's a whole nother can of worms.
But that'd be great.
Sure.
So finally, maybe something over next cloud would work, you know, sync file like I could
see a DIY version of that working pretty well.
Is there maybe anything you want to touch on that maybe isn't so user noticeable but
still has been a good improvement, anything on your mind there?
There's another big thing that we did, which is the optional system deintegration throughout
plasma.
This is something that probably nobody will even notice because it's not even on by default
right now.
We're hoping, I believe, to turn it on by default for plasma 521.
But of course, because we're K to E, you can turn it off as well.
But the gist of what's going on here is that we have refactored the way plasma starts itself
and starts its components and starts apps to make use of systems, the slices and C groups
and units.
So now everything happens in a predictable order.
Things can be parallelized without them running into each other.
This means that startup times will be improved.
This means that we have things that are scoped properly.
So when you log out of your session, everything quits rather than having dangling processes.
It means that we're able to group an app's individual child processes into that app itself.
This is especially relevant for apps in Flatpaks and Electron apps.
Like if you run Discord or something and you look at the process tree, it has like 10 processes.
Yeah.
So it's sort of hard to tell what it's actually doing.
And when you now with this new feature activated, when you launch Discord using plasma, it will
be scoped in its own C group.
So all of its child processes will be able to be associated with the parent.
And we can now have an applications view that says, hey, here's Discord.
And it combines together all of the different resource usages of the child processes.
That is so cool.
I know.
Isn't it great?
It's super cool.
This leads me to another really cool thing, which is the new system monitoring app.
This is something that we have released as a standalone app and it's going to be, I believe,
included in Plasma 5.21 by default, but we basically rewrote KSysGuard, which is our
old system monitoring app.
And the new one is now fully C group and slice aware.
So it has that nice applications page.
It has beautiful, pretty graphs that use a new hardware accelerated graphing framework
that we wrote that now is used for other things.
And it's 100% customizable too.
So this actually reminds me of what you said before about Plasma being like a power tool
used by pros.
And I'm glad you mentioned that because this is like my personal idea of what Plasma should
be.
This is like a productivity tool for people who use their computers to make a living.
And we designed the system monitoring app so that it's super customizable.
If you monitor like a fleet of machines or if you monitor specific aspects of your system,
you can actually customize the pages on this new system monitoring app in a 100% granular
way to make it show exactly what you want.
And because it uses this fancy charting framework, not only is it customizable and powerful,
it's also really pretty too.
So that's a pretty nice improvement.
That's great.
Oh yeah.
Wow.
So that's probably one of my favorite things to see is that those kinds of tools are still
getting investment that they're not just sitting around and just, you know, ah, good enough.
I really could have seen that argument made for something like KSYSGuard.
Oh, it's good enough.
If somebody wants something more, they'll go use something on the command line.
One of those annoying top things we keep recommending.
Yeah.
I don't believe in good enough personally.
I think everything can always be improved.
So where does 2021 take us?
It doesn't sound like anything too radical as planned, but more just continued investments.
Yeah.
A lot of what I've told you is stuff that users don't have yet because it's just been
merged into Gitmaster and it's planned for Plasma 5.21.
And that's going to be released in a few months in the early part of 2021.
So to a large extent, getting this stuff to users is what's in 2021.
Personally there are two things that I am really looking forward to for 2021.
One is the remainder of our visual overhaul, which I believe it or not didn't even start
to talk about, but we have throughout 2020 been landing all kinds of visual overhauls
of other things too.
Not just the system tray, but we've been doing Plasma, our breeze theme for apps, technically
speaking lives in Plasma.
It's in like a Plasma aligned release cycle product.
So that's been happening there as well.
And I think we're going to continue to do this and really make people think that KDE
apps look amazing in 2021.
One of the remaining complaints that I feel like I kept hearing about people saying, oh,
it's lightweight now and it's really powerful, but KDE apps are really ugly.
So we hear that and we're working on it very quickly to improve the look of KDE apps.
You'll see that in 5.21 and Plasma 5.22 as well.
Another thing that I think we're going to see in a big way in the year 2021 is more
Wayland stuff.
2020 was a huge year for our Wayland session.
We got tons and tons of stuff.
We got screencasting, we got shared clipboard support, we got middle click paste support,
we got multi GPU output support, screen rotation, task manager window thumbnails, the global
menu now works on Wayland, we got high DPI screenshots with Spectacle, we have the virtual
keyboard working for GTK apps, and we have configurable mouse and touchpad scroll speed
on Wayland, which is also a thing that you don't have on X11.
So it was huge.
It was gigantic.
Actually for me, in 2019, Wayland was like a buggy mess.
Our Wayland session, I just couldn't use it.
It felt like a construction zone.
Whereas today, in the end of 2020, I can almost use the Plasma Wayland session for day-to-day
stuff.
They're just like little mini annoyances and problems.
So I feel like there's been a quantum leap in our Wayland compatibility.
And I feel like in 2021, we're probably going to see people start using it by default.
Fedora, for example, in Fedora 34, they're planning on using the Plasma Wayland session
by default.
They're shipping it to users and turning it on by default.
So you have to opt into X11.
That's how much they think it's come.
And you know, Fedora, they're very technology-first forward people.
They really like being on the bleeding edge, but they think it's ready.
So that is, I think, a good vote of confidence.
And I think we're really going to see Wayland become totally mainstream in Plasma in 2021.
Wow.
Well, you know, I have been testing it on Fedora Plasma, on my X1 Carbon.
And it works really well for me unless I start using an external display.
And then it gets a little wonky when I have both screens going.
But otherwise, I can pretty much use it all day long.
And I feel like it seems a little bit smoother to me.
Yeah, it should be.
So I like it.
I am really looking forward to 2021.
Like Jitty in the chat room said, that it's just kind of a no-brainer these days to use
Plasma.
Oh, I'm happy to hear that.
Personally, I feel the same way.
That's the way I want everybody to see it.
You know, I think you shouldn't have to compromise to use our stuff.
It should be lightweight.
It should have lots of features.
It should be stable without a lot of bugs.
And it should be beautiful.
That's my goal.
And powerful.
And, you know, I really feel like it's gotten there.
You really could set it up in just, you know, pretty much any distribution set by default
and use it that way.
Or you could spend, like I spent about a day slowly going through and just setting something,
using it a little bit like that and then adjusting it.
And after about that day, I never touch it again.
And it just stays that way forever.
Awesome.
It's great.
I'm curious.
What do you make to your plasma?
It kind of depends.
I, for some reason, didn't totally like the new taskbar and all of that.
And I ended up trying Latte Dock and putting it in the plasma mode.
So it's still more like a bar.
And I just kind of have liked that a little bit better.
Although on some of my plasma setups, the majority of them, I just have a standard taskbar
at the bottom, you know, Kubuntu style, and have just left it like that on the work machines.
And it's been fine.
Even on the laptop, I like to play around a little bit.
And so I went for kind of a smaller dock down there.
It doesn't go all the way edge to edge.
It's more in the middle of the screen, but it doesn't do all the fancy like magnification
stuff.
It looks like a plasma panel.
You wouldn't even know it's Latte Dock.
Yeah, it integrates really well.
I know a lot of people love Latte Dock.
I've liked it.
Yeah.
I may try going back sometime, you know, but it's worked pretty well for me.
And then of course, I try different dark themes these days.
I try out a couple of different ones.
I really like how things now work with the global theme to just change it there instead
of having to go to each individual colors and icons and application appearances, window
frame appearances, just the global theme now.
Yeah, that's great.
That's our intention.
As a fan of that, I actually have to mention in Plasma 5.21, we're shipping a new global
theme called Breeze Twilight, which has a dark color scheme for Plasma and a light color
scheme for apps.
Oh, interesting.
Hmm.
That's great.
Well, Nate, I could go on all day, but we have some tuxes to get to you.
I really appreciate you coming on.
And I also really, really appreciate and thank you for all the hard work you do documenting
all of these improvements.
We will have a link, of course, to your This Week in KDE posts.
What do you have?
Is that the title?
Is that the official title?
Yeah, it used to be Usability and Productivity back when that was a thing, but now it's This
Week in KDE.
Yeah.
And you know what?
It's not always just Plasma.
I mean, there's sometimes other things in the KDE ecosystem in there as well.
And I want to stress that this is my view of the project.
KDE is so vast.
We have like hundreds of apps, so I can only follow a small percentage of things.
So there's always much more stuff going on than what I can document, but it's like Plasma
plus what I consider to be sort of the core apps that most people are going to experience.
Also we should say happy birthday.
I think Kate just hit 20 years old.
It did.
So happy birthday to Kate.
I just reinstalled it.
I'm almost drinking the USA.
That's right.
The chat room is joking that the KDE Christmas party is spelled with a K. I like that.
That tickles me.
All right, Nate.
Thank you very much for joining us.
Thank you for having me.
It was great.
Yep.
Keep up the great work and happy holidays.
Thanks a lot.
You too.
All right, Wes.
Well, I'll let you update your Plasma desktop over there while I take a moment and take
a break here and say thank you to Linode at linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get a $100 60 day credit towards your new account.
Try spinning up a server on their cloud infrastructure.
They make it really simple to get a Linux server up in the cloud in seconds and they
have 11 data centers around the world.
They also have features like object storage and node balancers and a dashboard to manage
all of this and API that makes it possible to do it all from the command line, which
is actually how I do it.
It's not as nerdy as it sounds.
It's pretty easy and straightforward.
But they also have, well, brilliant support.
Mr. S writes into the show and he says, I was introduced to Linode based on your mentions
on the show.
I am not yet a paying customer of Linode, so having a somewhat particularly interesting
challenge with an NGO I am volunteering for, I contacted Linode support.
Now mind you, this was after I contacted several major cloud providers, some of which who I'm
a paying customer, some who completely ignored me, others just simply brushed me off.
But Linode was the complete opposite.
Even after understanding that I'm not a paying customer and you know, to be honest, my particular
problem won't generate any revenue for them.
They went above and beyond to try to assist me coming up with a resolution for the sole
purpose of doing good.
Their support team was just brilliant, Mr. S says.
He goes on to say they were responsive, kind, to the point and above all, with a genuine
will to assist and resolve problems.
I'm dealing with a major cloud service and their support teams on a daily basis and Linode's
support team, based on my experience, really stands above and beyond.
Kind regards, Mr. S.
And I remember when I had that feeling too, when I was like, wow, you stuck with this
problem when you didn't have to.
And it really feels good when somebody goes above and beyond.
And that's what Linode's support team does.
And Mr. S, he was, he felt so impacted by it, he bothered to write in.
I mean, think about that.
When have you, you know, he had to take a minute to actually write that email to us
to share that experience.
That's how much it hit him.
And that's Linode.
That's one of the reasons I love them is they're independent.
I get why they do this.
They do this for a love of Linux.
That's why they've sponsored projects like Kubuntu.
That's why they sponsor this here podcast and other Linux creators out there, because
they want to make it possible for independent content to give media about this away for
free.
That's part of what they're doing here.
And it's just, it's a great company all around.
Plus, you get that $100 credit when you go to linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there and get yourself a special something, linode.com slash unplugged.
And a big thanks to Linode for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
All right.
So I surprised Wes the other day.
Are you ready for this, Mr. Payne?
Oh, you sure did.
And this was a lot of fun.
So we were sitting in here just a day or two or three or eight ago, and we were doing one
of the things we do, podcast, and I had a moment to surprise Wes.
So I turned the mics on and I kind of didn't really tell Wes what was going on.
I was just like, come on, sit down.
Let's open up the Linux Unplugged profile.
He's kind of looking around.
He's thinking to himself, do I need to prepare?
Just kind of going along, which was great, because it worked out perfect for a special
secret Santa surprise we had for Mr. Wes Payne.
You know what I love about you, Wes, is that we have been going at this all day, and I've
told you all day long I wanted to record a Linux Unplugged segment, but you haven't actually
really even bothered asking me until just now what we're actually talking about.
I figured you'd tell me when you were ready.
I am.
But I forgot the box.
So hold on.
You stay right there.
You don't move.
I'll get the box.
It's my treat, Wes.
You're fine.
You stay comfortable.
I am comfortable.
Behind the red curtain.
I didn't realize you got this indoor jacuzzi, but I don't know why you put it on.
You hold it for me.
Oh, it's heavy.
Yeah.
There you go, because guess what, Wes?
It is a surprise secret Santa for Wes Payne.
What?
That's right.
It's a Christmas miracle.
What?
Ooh.
An unplugged miracle right here on the show.
So go ahead and unwrap your box and tell us what it is.
Well, first of all, it's some lovely wrapping paper.
Yeah.
I think that might be Hadia's finest, actually.
You got the wife's finest right there.
You don't have to save it.
You can rip into it.
It's fine.
I like that.
So Wes has been a huge, huge help in the transition to Jupiter broadcasting going independent.
I thought to myself, what can I get Wes for Christmas that would convey our appreciation
for how damn hard he's worked for us?
And you know, I thought about and I thought pretty much nothing because I can't afford
to do anything.
So I thought, okay, well, what I need here.
Here, I got you a knife.
Oh, thank you.
You planned ahead.
So I was like, because, you know, I'd like to get him something, you know, something
to reflect the appreciation.
I think the audience can tell you work really hard for us.
And I'm sure they'd like to see you get something.
So I started thinking, well, since I can't afford anything, what I need is a Secret Santa.
So I emailed our friends over at Synology and I said, would you like to play Secret
Santa for Wes Payne?
So what you got here?
And then I think I know which one it is, but I'm not actually sure because they just sent
this to us.
This is a Synology for you forever.
It's not a review unit.
It's keeps just for you for keeps and this is definitely one I would get myself.
I can tell you that.
Oh, it's got a handle and look at this.
All right.
What's the model on the box?
This is the DS 920 plus.
Yeah.
Okay.
This is the one with a little bit more memory so you can run some services on it.
Scalableness for demanding environments.
Hey, that sounds like me.
Yeah.
So the DS 920 plus has a SSD cache, but also one of the things that we were talking about
is, you know, with this guy, it's got four core processor.
You can put some serious applications on this thing.
Yeah.
ASNI support, expandable storage in RAM and hey, two NICs on board.
Awesome.
Also supports running virtual machines.
What?
Yeah.
So you can run some VMs on it.
Because I know, you know, you haven't really decided on what you're going to do for your
home setup since you got in your new place.
And I thought...
That's true.
This simplifies things significantly.
And you know, I'm a self-hosting kind of guy.
So this just seemed...
You were worried about my cloud usage.
Yeah.
Well, Angela's had a Synology for like seven years and it has run flawlessly.
So I thought, you know, it'd be just enough where you could mess with it.
But also if you get busy with the day job, you're not going to have to worry about it.
It'll just sit there and run forever, you know, so it's best of both worlds.
Well this is amazing.
Isn't it great?
Thank you Synology.
Yeah.
Wow.
Fantastic.
It was really cool.
You know, it was one of those things that just worked out perfectly.
So there you go, Wes.
Merry Christmas and enjoy your new disk station.
It's a Christmas project.
What more could I ask for?
Yeah.
You know what else is?
Now when you get it going and stuff, you come back, you have to tell us how it works.
Deal.
An unplugged Christmas miracle.
Ho, ho, ho, ho.
So it was the DS920 Plus, and I think they also put a couple of disks in there too, right?
Oh, they did.
Thank you Synology.
They put two six terabyte Seagate IronWolf drives in there.
That'll get you off to a good start.
Yeah, right?
You know what I love about this DS920 Plus?
You know what I love about it?
It uses ButterFS.
And they're not shy about it.
Actually they've got a whole page on their website talking about the benefits of ButterFS
and how it helps make a robust product for you, which that's pretty neat.
So this thing's got four gigs of RAM, expandable up to eight gigs.
It's got two gigabit NICs on it.
It's got an eSATA port.
It has two USB 3.0 ports.
I mean, this could probably last you a little while is what I was thinking, you know?
Yeah, that's what's nice.
It came with four gigs of RAM, but that's expandable up to eight.
It came with two drives, but there's four slots in there and I think you can go up to
like nine drives if you buy the Synology expansion unit, which I probably won't even need that
much because, you know, drives just keep getting bigger and bigger.
And it's got a pretty nifty little 10 watt Intel Celeron processor in there, which is
actually kind of similar to the processor I've got in my Linux powered router at home.
So it fits neatly into the family.
That's cool.
What's the setup process like?
Because you're not like hooking a screen up to this than a keyboard, right?
No, no.
You know, unboxed at night, nicely packaged in there.
The disks were actually already in the unit so I didn't have to do anything there.
Disks in there, locked up tight, ready to go.
So pretty much just found a spot for it, attach the power, plugged in.
It's got two NICs, which is awesome.
And then by default, before you've got it configured or anything, they've got a nice
little quick connect service online, as well as a few other things like find.synology.com.
And when you first boot it up, the firmware that it starts with goes and talks to their
servers and sort of advertises like, hey, you've got an unconfigured Synology here.
So all you have to do is go to find.synology.com.
It does a little magic behind the scenes to locate where on your local network, like what's
the new local IP.
So you don't have to go browse to your router or do ARP scans or just ping around the network
to try to find where this new box is.
And then it pulls it up right for you, prompts you to upgrade, install, and then gives you
a little screen to set up your first admin user and start configuring things.
And it was just super painless.
I mean, I have the know-how to find things on my network or go through whatever technical
setup that I need, but just none of that was necessary all in the web browser.
Could you do it over SSH if you wanted though?
I don't know if you can do the setup over SSH, but once you've got it up and running,
turning on Telnet or SSH is super simple.
It doesn't feel like they're trying to hide any of the Linux underpinnings.
It's not like a...
Yes, it is a black box in some sense, but it just doesn't feel that way with all the
applications that are available, with all the features that are available.
Really what stood out to me was that this is clearly a robust and well-developed platform.
Yeah, I would imagine because like I mentioned, Angela's had one now for, I mean, it's got
to be nearly eight years actually.
And I logged into it around Thanksgiving and did an update and everything just worked.
I told her, I said, you know, there's got to be almost a zero chance that this thing
isn't going to break because nobody's touched that thing in years.
It went way too long and it just did it like a champ.
How's the noise level on yours?
Not bad so far.
I mean, my apartment's not the quietest to be clear, but they've got actual configuration
for that.
So if you don't mind a little more heat on your device, maybe that affects the length
of life, hard to say.
But it's all configurable in the settings, so you can set like full fans on all the time.
You can set it to a slightly louder adaptive fan mode or maximize quiet mode.
You can also, which is nice, so after the first night I plugged it in, going to bed,
I realized like, oh, where I've got my router, I just put it in the area I've got like my
router and my wifi and all the networking stuff, all the infrastructure you might say.
And I can almost see that bright blue LED when I'm laying in bed.
I was like, okay, well, maybe I'm going to have to rethink this.
But that was before I discovered you can totally configure that in the UI, no problem, from
very dim to very bright or just all the way off, which is just another little sign I think
of like they've been through this before, they've iterated on these platforms and they've
figured out a lot of what you might need.
That's nice, you can just turn it off even.
That's pretty cool.
The other part that impressed me was that, so they've got a quick connect technology
where if you have like a Synology account, they'll run a proxy for you.
You can log in there and then, you know, discover your Synology, go talk to it without having
to actually forward ports on your network.
You know, kind of common these days, but a nice service to have if you just don't want
to expose your home network or don't have that technical know how.
But if you don't want that, they've also got automation in place to talk to all kinds of
different router brands and firmware.
So first it checks to see if you've got UPnP enabled and it'll try to forward ports that
way if you don't do a quick connect thing.
But if you don't do that, you can choose your router brand and then it's going to go like,
you give it your credentials.
It logs in and basically goes through the web UI or APIs if they have them and sets
up its port forwards.
And then if that doesn't work, they've got online documentation with a whole bunch of
router information for various brands about how to do it too.
So it's kind of neat that they've got robust security support and upgrades and monitoring
situations, SNMP support for instance, if you're running this in a business environment.
And they've got helpers for your mom or dad who needs help getting it exposed so they
can go see it when they're visiting you.
You know, I kind of was chuckling when you were talking about it because I'm like, oh,
I wonder how it handled your custom Linux router.
But then I was thinking, but also being able to do that means that my mom could buy one
of these and she could stop paying for cloud storage and she could have it right there
at her house because she works with large graphics files and it's a constant challenge
for her.
But I also, while I could go over and set it up, I really would like getting her something
that she could just do herself.
I think she'd feel more empowered by that too.
How did it handle, so with your setup, you just open up any ports you want or choose
not to.
I mean, you don't probably even need to bother with that, I would imagine.
Yeah.
I mean, it kind of depends on how you do, you know, your setup.
Some folks just have a VPN and then VPN back to their house or you can forward things.
So far I've not forwarded it because I don't know that I need to.
I've got a couple other gateways on my router box.
So for right now it just lives totally on my land.
I think I will try the quick connect stuff just to give it a go.
I could also see in the future where maybe some of those applications and services move
over to the Synology, like it becomes the VPN host and maybe that's when you'd change
some of the firewall rules.
Yes.
That's also pretty neat because it's got both support for virtualization and running Docker.
So I loaded up a Fedora 33 box on there to give that a shot and it just pops open a VNC
window right in your web browser too.
So it was really easy to get that configured.
And then on the Docker side of things, I got Jellyfin going, I loaded up a couple of media
files to test things out and it worked no problem.
I mean, the CPU in there is not like a beast or anything, but it has a nice balance of
power usage to performance and it was totally fine for like just me playing back on my local
network.
I don't think it was enabled.
It didn't have the configuration, but that model even has quick sync.
No way.
Yeah.
Right?
Oh, man.
So we're just talking about that on self-hosted and that's a big game changer, not just in
terms of CPU overhead, but a lot less power usage too by the CPU when you're using quick
sync.
I'm legit jealous.
That's awesome.
I'm really glad.
I'm glad.
It sounds like a really nice rig.
So what you should do is use it for a little while and then we should do long-term reviews
because I'm going to try to do a long-term review with the X1 and I'd love to hear a
long-term review for your Synology.
Yeah, definitely.
I've actually got a few more spare drives around.
So this was really just a test setup, sort of evaluate things, put it through its paces
before I committed to a particular setup because they've got a lot of different sort of like
integrated volume and storage pool options even before you choose if you're going to
use ButterFS or EXT4.
So I'm going to play with that a little bit more, maybe install two more drives just to
fill the thing out and then, yeah, I'm going to move over from my previous solution, which
definitely needed an upgrade.
So thank you, Chris, and thank you, Synology.
All right.
It is time for the Tuxes.
Ladies and gentlemen, the first annual Linux Unplugged Tuxes.
Our audience voted on the best open source newcomers, projects of the year, text editors
and more.
And it's our chance after a real ball buster of a year to say thank you.
The Unplugged Tuxes 2020.
We had a total of 221 submissions, which I love that number because having done some
submission challenges before, that's a decent turnout.
So you can get a kind of somewhat representative sampling.
But I hope that we will crush it next year.
I hope we get like 800 submissions next year.
And then I want to, I'd like, you know, every year I'd like us to double the number because
I really would love this to eventually be representative.
But we put out a form for a few weeks and we said, tell us who you think is the best
in these categories.
And the results have been tabulated and we're going to run through the categories and then
their winners.
And of course, your hosts do reserve the right to challenge a result.
But we will have to make our case in a court of a public opinion and to Drew, who is here
to play arbiter.
Hello, Drew.
Welcome back.
Hello.
And so we could, if we want to challenge one of the results, we have to make our case and
then the other hosts have to buy off on it.
But here are the categories for 2020, ladies and gentlemen.
Number one, the best open source project.
Number two, best newcomer project.
Number three, best Linux game of the year.
Number four, best text editor of 2020.
Number five, favorite desktop distro of 2020.
Number six, favorite server distro of 2020.
Number seven, best desktop environment of 2020, and these are all of 2020.
Then we'll just do a general best of tech.
And then we asked you all what your most life changing hardware or gadget was this year.
We've tabulated the results and we'll go through them and let you know what everyone voted.
So we'll start with, why don't we start with the best text editor?
Because I think that's a good place to start.
So get the divisive one right out of the way.
Yeah.
That's the elephant in the room.
And this is the one that I think maybe we even want to contest right off the beginning,
but with 53 entries out of 208 answers for this category, 25% thus the winner went to
Vim, Vim.
And there was a couple of runner ups in this category, VS Code came in at number two, Emacs
at number three, VS Code beat Emacs.
And if you include the VS Codium votes, VS Code handily beat Emacs.
26 submissions for Emacs, 29 for just VS Code alone, but then there were additional five
submissions for VS Codium.
Kate's in the list.
But Wes, what do you think here?
Do you think Vim actually maybe performed better than the numbers suggest?
Well, yeah.
I mean, there's also Neo Vim in there and some entries for VI.
So I think its lead would be even stronger if we had done a little more assertive tallying,
you know.
I did do a little cleanup here to try to make things fit into nice categories where there
were some, you know, a lot of fun comments that people wrote in, which was awesome.
Like one of my favorites for this entry is we got one vote for LibreOfficeWriter.
We got some votes for Sublime Text and Kate and Micro and GEdit and Mousepad and KWrite.
Didn't get much.
Only 0.95% of the vote for KWrite, which I've been using recently.
Vim, though, I feel like it handily wins.
I was going to try to make the case for VS Code, but even when you combine the VS Code
with the VS Codium, I think Vim still won pretty strong by the audience.
I mean, it's a pretty strong lead there.
I don't really think I'm going to challenge this one.
I feel like Vim is a little boring.
So there is a trick in place to solve this problem, and it'll be employed if Vim ever
wins again.
And then they just get, if they win two shows in a row, they'll get the Hall of Fame award
and they are disqualified from winning in a future show.
But we could give it to Vim this year, but that means if they win it next year, then
they win the Lifetime Award and they're out.
Well, I also think that VS Code, you know, edging out Emacs, that's something to watch,
right?
One, that's a good idea because we just, you know, we should mix things up, keep it interesting.
But then two, I think on its own, probably next year, VS Code is going to be doing better
against Vim, not worse.
Also, what's up to my Nano brothers and sisters out there, solid representation from the Nano
community.
I mean, could have used a few more of you.
All right, I'm not going to challenge this one.
We will award the first Tuxy of 2020 for Best Text Editor to Vim.
Congratulations to Vim, you've earned it.
Now our plan here is, of course, I still got to get my crap together and I could use some
help if anybody could help me figure out how to take a two dimensional graphic, a flat
graphic and convert that into a 3D printable object.
Somebody's actually done it before, but I want to take the last bearded penguin and
I want to take the ring around him that we have where he's holding the rocket and the
ring around it, I want it to say 2020 Tuxys and I want to print that and send that out
to the award winners.
So that's a bit of an effort.
So I need to figure out how to do that.
Alex has volunteered to do the printing, though, which is awesome.
And then we'll just have to start tracking down the projects and figure out where to
send this.
And Vim, you're going to be one of the first.
Now we get into the more interesting category.
This one I think is, I don't know, this one's going to be challenged, I think.
This is the best open source project in 2020.
And with 7% of the votes, wow, this is really spread out, but with 15 out of 217 submissions
for this category, the winner for the community is the Linux kernel.
I like to stretch it out a little bit.
The Linux kernel, and the reason why I'm a little hesitant with this one is it feels
kind of boring in a way.
But I actually think maybe it's appropriate at the same time that for our first Tuxys,
maybe it should go to the Linux kernel, you know?
You know, I mean, there was, Debian was a runner up here.
But then after that, things got a little more interesting.
Things like Nextcloud and Firefox were also high up on the list.
Yeah, I'm disappointed that it wasn't Home Assistant, I have to be honest with you.
I think Home Assistant is just not a, it's just people don't appreciate how awesome it
is, man.
But really, you know, we can talk about text editors and stuff, but Home Assistant has
changed my life.
It's made my quality of life better.
My particular living situation, heating, can be challenging.
And having an automation system that has managed that has made this winter and last winter
more comfortable than I've ever been in LadyJuice.
And then I combine that with a bunch of smart lighting that makes it much nicer and cozier
and tolerable when it gets dark out at 3.55 p.m. in the Pacific Northwest, I have a bunch
of lighting that comes on automatically that tracks the sunset and sunrise.
So it's always adjusting with the sunlight of the time of year and it monitors the weather
for me and it brings together so many aspects of automation, even security aspects that
when you start to use a project like Home Assistant, it actually changes your day to
day life.
And it changes how my family interacts with my home and how they interact with technology
and what their perceptions of what it's capable of.
And it has bridged all of these commercial cloud connected products all together in one
local LAN based system that has a nice, easy to use dashboard.
It's very family tolerable.
But I understand that it's it even spent a good portion as the number one project on
GitHub in 2020.
That's why I really thought maybe it had a shot at the best open source project.
So that's why I'm a little I'm tempted to challenge this one.
But when you stack that up to the impact of the Linux kernel, I don't think I can argue
that.
You know, they clearly are.
They've had a little more impact than a single open source project, regardless of the personal
impact it's had on me.
Yeah, you are in a particularly automatable setup, I think, right?
I mean, you have some different needs, you have a very changing environment, you have
a custom setup.
But having watched Home Assistant rise the past few years, I mean, I remember we did
a comparison with OpenHAB and a couple other stuff here on LUP in I don't know, 2017, maybe.
And back then it was kind of like, well, what's, you know, there's a couple of solutions out
here in the market.
They're all pretty decent, but don't you know, not everyone supports everything.
And that's just totally changed.
I mean, Home Assistant is king now.
Also the Home Assistant project has come across what may be a uniquely great, sustainable
profit model for an open source project.
So Home Assistant is all land based.
But if you would like for like less than $10 a month, I think it's like $8 a month, you
can subscribe to Nebuchadnezzar's Home Assistant cloud service.
And that gives you secure remote access through their proxy system to your Home Assistant
instance.
And it works even with some crazy double carrier grade NAT system like I have.
And it also allows for easy tie in with the smart cylinders if you want.
You can also custom build this stuff so you don't have to use the cloud service if you're
comfortable with setting up your own cloud service yourself and you want to manage all
of it and you want to manually connect to the different APIs, you can do all of this
yourself.
But they give you just a couple of checkboxes for like $8 a month that does all of this
stuff.
And on top of that, they give you a kind of like this peace of mind because you can now
check in on like your system itself, the health of your system remotely, which is great.
You know, so anyways, that then goes into funding the developers.
And now they've hired eight full time people at Nebuchadnezzar who are contributing back
to Home Assistant with the sole purpose of making Home Assistant better.
So that way they can pick up a few more subscribers and it just kind of is a really nice, sustainable
development model where you're not the product, but they also have found a way to give something
away that's extremely intricate and a lot of work.
It's an intense amount of work.
They've figured out a way to give that away for free, absolutely free, while also funding
the people who love to work on it and give them full time work that keeps the project
going.
I just think that's something really special and the way they've grown over 2020 is extremely,
it's just, it's an open source success story.
They've had a groundswell of support from people out in the whole world that are developing
these integrations.
The core team has come together under some pretty clear and I'd say concise leadership.
They've had a couple of missteps here and there with community communication, but then
they listened to the feedback in both instances and righted the ship in a significant way
that actually made a difference and addressed the complaints the community was making and
they pulled that off.
It's such an open source success story, but when people don't try it, even if you have
a simple home automation system, you maybe have one or two smart plugs or a light bulb,
so maybe you don't try it, you don't get to see it.
I understand that's why it isn't represented here in the votes, but as someone who has
watched open source projects and developments for a long time, it's so great to see something
like that happening in 2020.
It frees me from proprietary lockdown cloud services and it lets me have a higher quality
standard of living in my home.
It's that kind of project, but again, all that said, I can't argue that the Linux kernel
has been more impactful in this year.
It's just the math of it.
I don't think I can overrule it, but I wonder, Drew and Wes, you guys, feel free, but do
you think, what about an honorary best open source project of the year?
Well, I think it can absolutely get something like the crisp pick of the year, but considering
that it's tied for sixth, I have a hard time saying this particular project needs a special
award from the whole group when there are so many other projects that are above it that
really are hugely impactful too.
We're not just talking about the Linux kernel, which obviously is hugely impactful to all
of our day-to-day lives.
There's also Debian and Nextcloud, both of which are huge and touch a lot of people.
Then there's Firefox and KDE, and then Home Assistant is tied with Fedora.
All of these are huge projects that really have massive contributions to our world.
So I'd say make a new category for a crisp pick, but respect the will of the voters.
It's down there, isn't it?
It's down in the votes.
That's the math of it.
I'll just give it, I'll just say, unofficial appreciation to the project.
I think you guys can tell why I appreciate it.
You're right.
It is what it is.
But how does this not happen next year?
Linux kernel wins again next year could be a problem.
Well, didn't you make the rule for this already?
If they win again, then...
If they win again, lifetime achievement award.
It almost seems like they should just get one, but no, we'll see, we'll see.
You never know.
2021 could be crazy.
So I'll just say this, thank you to Home Assistant.
You are my arbitrary appreciation pick of the show.
And you get a little love explosion right there.
Okay, let's step into a territory that until just a couple of weeks ago was not very controversial
at all, but thanks to recent changes with CentOS and people are still adjusting as we
record this, the favorite server distro of 2020 results might be a little more interesting
than we were expecting.
And we had not as many people submit this category, but we got 208 submissions here
and we had a winner, a pretty clear signal on this one.
The community voted with 40% of the vote to give it to Ubuntu.
Yeah, Ubuntu got it with 84 votes out of 208, followed by Debian in second place and CentOS
in third place, Fedora in fourth, Red Hat Enterprise 9 in fifth, and there's OpenSUSE
just above arch at sixth place with six votes.
You know what's interesting about this, Wes?
Doesn't this kind of track close to what the actual web server market share stats are that
we looked up?
Yeah, it kind of seems like it, right?
I mean, Ubuntu is way up there at the top and probably rightfully so, it's just a trusted
server platform these days with a lot of niceties, all the software you could want and a good
track record.
Oh, the orange one says that an honorary mention should go to Alpine for being pretty much
all of the Docker containers out there that are getting used.
That's a good one.
Good point, orange one.
I actually am a little surprised Ubuntu is this far ahead in our crowd.
I actually don't doubt the numbers at all, but I think it shows you this is reflective
of what the audience is out there running.
Manjaro came in at two.
Now remember, this is a server.
Unraid with one vote, Void Linux is on there.
I don't think, oh yeah, Alpine did get two votes.
So Alpine did get some representation.
Although that was the same number as the folks who decided to still answer, but write in
I don't have any servers.
Yeah, right.
That's fair enough.
Fair enough.
So are you guys okay with officially giving that one to Ubuntu?
I don't see any reason not to.
I mean, the people have spoken.
I think it makes perfect sense, yeah.
They've worked hard on that LTS.
And at this point, you don't get fired for choosing Ubuntu.
All right, then Ubuntu gets our official 2020 Tuxy as the server distro of the year, which
means we move on now to the desktop.
So favorite desktop distribution, not desktop environment, but desktop distribution.
This one got a 19% winning vote.
There's 219 submissions for this category.
And the winner for the favorite desktop distro of 2020 is Fedora with 43 out of 219 votes.
How about that?
Ubuntu wins the server, but doesn't win the desktop this year.
Isn't that interesting?
Fedora gets 43 votes, and Ubuntu gets 29 votes.
Manjaro coming in at a solid third with 25, and Arch right after that, followed by PopOS
and then KDE Neon.
Yeah, after PopOS.
I mean, there's kind of a close little running for the second-third category this year.
It's interesting.
MX and OpenSUSE and Solus and Mint all kind of fighting for the same territory.
Zubuntu, Kubuntu, and Budgie and Monte, et cetera.
All of those, we put those down as not Ubuntu the primary, but one of the derivatives of
Ubuntu got nine votes.
So if you added the nine votes for all of the Ubuntu derivatives, Ubuntu looks a little
bit better, but Fedora actually still wins, even when you add in all of the derivatives
to the results for Ubuntu.
It's a stronger second place, but Fedora is still a winner there.
So that's a clear vote for Fedora.
I can't really think of any reason to challenge that.
Honestly not what I expected.
I expected Ubuntu and Fedora to be swapped, that Ubuntu would be in first place and Fedora
would be in second place.
I'm just a little bit happy because I feel like it validates some of the fawning we've
been doing over at Fedora lately.
Maybe or maybe we've just pissed off all the Ubuntu users.
That also could be it.
Well Fedora did have a great year.
They're shipping on laptops from Lenovo.
I mean they had Fedora 33 release, has been stellar.
There's a lot to really like in Fedora this year.
Yeah that's true and Fedora 33 got a lot of recognition for pushing the envelope and I
think you can attribute a lot of that to the switch of ButterFS as the default.
You've got to be pretty happy about these results here Neil.
Oh my goodness yeah I'm super happy about this.
I honestly didn't expect it given how much I tend to hear how Ubuntu is the way of the
beast or whatever but like holy crap I'm blown away and I know and I feel like maybe some
of what I've done over the past year might have helped tilt things in our favor but I
don't know what to say except for like thank you?
Well and I think the switch to ButterFS and the project also you know they took a couple
of other bold steps like switching to Nano as a default editor in some instances you
know bold steps Neil that made a big change.
It's fun too to still see all this cool stuff happening in 2020.
It's been kind of a weird year and so to see to see these shift around I'm really going
to be interested to see if Fedora wins again next year.
I wouldn't necessarily bet on it.
Well I'm going to try hard to you know you know within the Fedora community me and many
others will try our best to try to earn the vote for next year as well and also keep an
eye on Fedora server that's coming back in a hopefully in a big way next year.
So hey Wes do a little back of the napkin math for me before we fully lock this in because
we haven't locked it in yet.
If we took all of the Ubuntu derivatives and we took Pop OS does that put Ubuntu ahead?
Are we counting KDE Neon in here?
Well hmm see the reason why we separated these out is I actually wanted to get a signal to
people like the stock Ubuntu desktop or do they like the derivative desktops.
So I actually think this is the vote result that I wanted.
I wanted to know and it is clear by these numbers that the stock Ubuntu desktop is the
most popular but on its own it isn't the most popular in our audience.
Yeah so if you add up all the ones not including some controversial things like like KDE Neon
or other things that might be vaguely based on Ubuntu but actually like Ubuntu MATE,
Zubuntu, things like that it's a four vote margin so it's pretty darn close 43 to 39
but Fedora is still in the lead.
Okay yeah and then if you add in Pop OS it's kind of a it's kind of a smash and then if
you add in KDE Neon on top of that as yet another derivative it's Ubuntu is far and
away the most but.
And elementary if you put elementary in there which only got three votes in this in this
lineup but you know that's still three votes and yeah you really you could if you combine
all of the derivatives which I think you could argue is fair but it's not the signal we wanted
from the audience.
We wanted to know how many people were using the stock experience.
I don't know what do you think Drew what's your what's your judgment on it?
Oh I think it's still Fedora.
I think if we wanted to categorize you know the base OS that would be a different category
altogether.
All right so I think we're good then we're agreed we're gonna lock it in for Fedora as
the best desktop distro of 2020 as voted by the audience.
It is locked in so let's wander off into the best tech land the best tech of 2020 as voted
by the Linux Unplugged audience.
This one got a hundred and fifty five submissions and the winner with eight percent of the vote
which actually isn't a significant number but it's enough to make it the winner it is
ladies and gentlemen the PinePhone.
The PinePhone was voted as a best tech of 2020 in our audience and that out beat the
Raspberry Pi 4 and Home Assistant which got somebody included in this count so Home Assistant
got a few more votes over in this category.
It's well represented across the board I will say.
And Librem 5 is in here too but only two votes so the PinePhone got 13 votes in this category
followed by the Raspberry Pi and then WireGuard.
Yeah I could see that I could definitely see that.
PineBook Pro got five votes Apple's M1 got four votes interesting interesting.
That stood out to me you know in multiple categories including the next one there were
a lot of references to the M1 although an entertaining number also included sorry I
know it's not really Linux.
We want it we didn't we specifically did not limit the category it did not have to be Linux
I just wanted to know so that way we could get a sense of where things fit get a get
a sense.
So what do you think PinePhone that seems I mean 13 votes is a pretty clear signal.
I think people are excited about you know this this open hardware run whatever you want
embrace Linux on the phone potential maybe maybe it's not the thing that you're running
as your daily driver in 2020 but it's the thing that you have as your second phone that
you're playing with and excited about.
Now I do have to bring up one thing here and that is the Raspberry Pi 4 versus the Raspberry
Pi 400 combined those two equal up to 14 which just barely edges out the PinePhone.
Yeah but I feel like because they are separate products I think I think that is okay.
Yeah that's a good one I don't know though yeah okay I feel like probably that's a little
bit of cheating though because that you know the Pi 4 came out almost like a year before
the 400 and the 400 isn't exactly the same it's got a revved CPU and a different board
so not really they're not really the same product they're the same platform.
Yeah and I buy that although that said how many revisions of the PinePhone have there
been.
Fair.
Now remember we're also we're looking at 2020 here and I think the PinePhone has had
a they like they met their ship windows they got the devices out into people's hands and
we've seen a lot of open source projects just in 2020 alone spin up development on these
things and make it actually getting towards usable.
Yeah I think I'm with you there and it's also worth pointing out that it's not just the
PinePhone that's on here Pine64 in general is all over this list you've got the Pinebook
Pro Pine64 as a company you know there's PineSil.
Pine is all over this people are really excited about Pine this year.
True true good to see OBS is in here Plasma got in here I actually really like to see
that YouTube DL made it in here as well only one submission for Best Tech for Rust.
Podman that must have been you Carl.
That's awesome yeah Plasma got a KDE and Plasma were in here as two separate things.
Yeah one thing ZFS was stood out in this too I don't think it made to the top of any of
these but it was held had a healthy number of votes in several categories this year.
Yeah it was nice to see Matrix and Blender and Docker all kind of in the and Nextcloud
all kind of in the same region too all of them getting three votes.
So this is obviously a challenging category because it's so broad and the submissions
could be kind of variable and you know PinePhone, PineSpacePhone, Pine64Phone like a lot of variability
to it so that's one of the things we'll refine next year but this is after taking several
passes at trying to account for all of that and I think that you know the PinePhone still
kind of comes out strong when you look at what has been accomplished not just by Pine64
but the community around it too so I say we lock it in gentlemen.
Pull that trigger.
All right now we move on to the most life-changing hardware or device or gadget for you this
year out there in the audience.
This one had 142 submissions and with 11% of the vote we have a winner the Jupiter Broadcasting
audience Linux Unplugged Tuxi nominations go to the Raspberry Pi 4 and there you go
they just win the next category.
The Raspberry Pi 4 has been the most life-changing hardware for 2020 or gadget.
See if this is your vindication Chris you know you didn't get the Home Assistant thing
before but I think I think this one.
That's true this has been this is I'm really kind of I'm just as all in on the Raspberry
Pi's as I was when they first launched I mean it's really been great because on the desktop
side Manjaro has been the way I've gone on the desktop and then same with the Pi 400
Manjaro worked great on there and on the server side Ubuntu LTS 2004 has been exactly like
running it on an x86 box and with the USB disk support so I'm not using SD storage I
can unlock a lot more performance out of a Raspberry Pi 4 and I have gone off-grid many
times running off just lithium-powered batteries and the power draw matters so much in that
circumstance and I literally sleep well knowing that I just have these Pi's two of them now
that are just sucking just a tiny bit of power you know it's not like an x86 machine that's
pulling down 120 watts and it has made it possible for me to do things like go out and
camp in the woods for longer periods of time because they are using less power and that's
awesome and it's it allows us to go off-grid and still have essentially a full online experience
I talked about this and self-hosted but I have a lot of local media and reading and
audio and some wiki stuff cached locally on my Raspberry Pi's and we very much have like
a near online experience when we go offline but we're not getting notifications and messages
all of our smart controls still works home assistant running on the Raspberry Pi all
of our video streaming still works because the media stored there locally on a butter
FS volume of two USB disks it actually all works and this is also where I started to
really kind of reevaluate butter FS again when I was like looking at the use case of
laptop servers and Raspberry Pi servers and no longer these massive chassis with eight
disks in them but now something that's running over maybe a USB but USB bus or even on SD
card or or some other less than ideal scenario and I realized there's a real need for a flexible
powerful file system out there in a serious workload capacity and when I brought butter
FS together with the Raspberry Pi 4 using Ubuntu LTS 2004 when when that like trifecta
of Linux technology came together I was able to up my home hosting game to a whole other
level and the Raspberry Pi has dutifully been running for me 24 7 and I even took him down
into Texas where the ambient temperature outside was 117 degrees and they're inside a tiny
enclosed booth often never even getting below 100 degrees at night inside the booth and
they I brought them back they're still running they they ran and they they they one time
one time I ran into some thermal throttling issues one time when we were streaming multiple
videos from a Pi 4 but now that we're back in the Pacific Northwest it's a literal non-issue
it really is a solid machine and then you know you look at the price and you look at
what you get it it just it's it's so awesome that that tech of is available to us as consumers
when when the world is dominated by $1,000 Macbooks and $10,000 desktops and all these
crazy things it's really nice to be able to find a computer for $35 that can do so much
and this year they upgraded it to eight gigs of RAM to really the buying is better than
ever you can use it for more things and this wasn't even it didn't even need conflation
with the Raspberry Pi 400 to win this category because it's just regardless it's so darn
handy the pine phone also got submissions here so to the ThinkPad system 76 got three
votes in this category home assistant got another three votes here as well I noticed
you skipped right over to the Apple watch though yeah so that's the awkward thing about
this category the Apple watch got seven votes the Apple watch is actually our number two
life-changing tech of the year and I think I can understand why it was a year of work
from home and people needed help probably with their fitness more than ever remembering
to stand tracking what they're doing tracking their sleep the Apple watch is just simply
the best wearable computer watch if you want a computer watch that is modern and well-built
and has great battery life you know you can find die-hards out there that are they're
still rockin all the other kinds of watches but the Apple watch is just taking off this
year so I really last couple years I don't know is it had a particularly great 2020 I
mean must have it got a lot of votes and and this is on this is from a Linux audience right
so think about that so if you're walking around out there listening to this show and you're
controlling the playback from your Apple watch have no shame it got second place it got second
place out of a lot of nominations for the most life-changing hardware of 2020 all right
then we are officially giving it to the Raspberry Pi 4 for 2020 as the most life-changing tech
the best Linux game of the year this probably won't be surprised this won't be a surprise
to anyone that has kids my age or has gotten sucked into the latest game with 99 submissions
the audience has elected among us as the best Linux game of 2020 ironically not actually
a Linux game so that's where this category gets interesting right I don't know that we
gave clear instructions because yeah this is um you can only play among us via proton
although it is number four on their ratings for ten most popular over at the proton DB
so clearly there are a lot of Linux users who are playing among us and sounds like it
works pretty decently yeah it is rated gold so as far as non Linux native games being
played on Linux it seems like it's pretty well supported at least yeah my son extensively
tests it on Linux for me so that way I can be up to date on the latest among us developments
and a little junior show researcher over there and yeah and I did say proton was fine it's
really I think I want to celebrate the fact that we have more game options to us and I
think the great thing about proton it's not just Windows compatibility but it's about
preserving art as time goes on the platforms will move on but proton and the different
releases of proton will be around and you'll be able to play games that you know are are
you able to preserve games and still actually play them you won't just have to look at them
so I think among us deserves it you know it was it was an extremely popular game it's
on it's on all of the platforms my kids played on mobile and on on their Linux boxes and
as a parent I had that moment when they came to me and said dad can we play among us on
our computers and I always dread that conversation of hey I know all of your friends are talking
about this at school it's like the biggest thing on YouTube right now for the YouTube
algorithm that you get subscribed to and by the way you can't play it on your Linux box
because it Dylan already knows well there's Windows 10 and you could put that on the same
hardware because this come up before and I was just dreading that moment and I went on
Steam I saw it was available and I go on the proton DB and I look it up and I saw I had
gold support I installed it I had to make like I don't know I think I had to change
like one launch option or something it was it was documented and it fired right up and
it has worked flawlessly since then and I felt I don't know man I just had like I don't
know a sense of like I done right by him you know I got him a good computer it's running
Linux and he can play the latest games that his Windows and iOS using friends are playing
right now and I think it deserves recognition for that and same with same with cyberpunk
you know we were able to get that running on Linux day one super hyped game and it came
in at third place so Nautic which is an open source first person shooter came in at second
place super tux cart came in at fourth place and then the list kind of goes off from there
to all the great games you've probably ever heard of even Skyrim is on there but I really
think it's appropriate to give it to among us this year even though it's technically
a proton game I think the fact that we're getting these games on day one while the hype
cycle is at peak that means a lot for gamers yeah we're all proton gamers now right yeah
actually yeah I mean I have a little bit of both I definitely still prefer Linux native
it's a lot simpler ironically like the one of the few I've been playing a lot of proton
games and I've been playing one Linux native game and that one is buggier than some of
the proton ones it's funny how they can go both ways so the chat rooms making the argument
and I'm gonna pitch this to Drew to see what you think Drew they're good they're making
the argument that we should actually we should give this award to proton for best Linux game
of the year even though it's not technically a game it has made it possible to play so
many new games you know it's to get the core of this among us story it's at the core of
cyberpunk of being available on day one it's not technically a game though that's a tough
one I don't I don't know I mean I do think that we should definitely be giving proton
a lot of credit here because it is doing a lot of heavy lifting for us but it's not a
game I don't know like I really want to show my appreciation for it but it just it's it's
not a game yeah I mean it could have won the best new tech and it didn't right I guess
because it wasn't new this year I guess if you look at 2020 it's been more of it being
really awesome and it's great to see continued development but it's not like it's breakout
year either mm-hmm all right so you think we should give it to among us I think so yeah
I do all right the best new game for 2020 as awarded by our audience I'll have to figure
out who gets the tuxy for that one that's gonna be interesting so we have our best newcomer
open source project in 2020 and this one had a lot of possibilities there proton is on
this list again so as Vulcans on this list oh my gosh this is there's a lot of submissions
on this one the pine phone again showed up on this list things like rocky linux and then
project linux are on here pipe wires on here I think rocky linux could still qualify in
2021 to be honest with you but eight out of 154 different submissions five percent of
the audience voted for wire guard wire guard and you know that's even up against things
like proton OBS jellyfin bpy top it's a close one too because obviously we've been talking
about wire guard for way too long but it was just this last January that it really made
it into the kernel so I think we have to count it right yeah I checked I sound like you did
too it was indeed mainlined in 2020 it seems like it's because we followed it for so long
it seems like it's been around forever and I use it still nearly on the daily it's fantastic
I have no qualms about awarding this prize to wire guard and I think I even know how
to send them the tuxi what do you think drew should we give the best newcomer project any
any objections no objections here I do think we should recognize that bpy top getting a
close second place is impressive because we've only just discovered it ourselves true also
nice to see pop shell getting some recognition in here system d home do you got four votes
that's as many as rocky linux open zfs got a few pipe wire got a couple yeah there were
some good submissions in that category all right this is the one I was kind of getting
us to because this is the one I think we've all been waiting for let's see how this one
goes this is as voted by the unplugged audience the nominations for the best desktop environment
of 2020 with 218 submissions 34 percent of those went to gnome shell gnome shell wins
with 34 percent of the vote from the jupiter broadcasting audience as debt as best desktop
environment of 2020 you know you're supposed to hide some of your disappointment in your
voice chris when you're reading it well i'm no i i'm waiting to be convinced actually
um i i would have loved to have seen plasma as demonstrated earlier in the show i would
have loved to have seen plasma win this category and they did come in at a solid number two
interesting to see sway come in at number three with 12 votes i3 after that then mate
cinnamon xfce then budgie pantheon an awesome window manager and then from there it goes
to lxde lx cute and uh well there's actually even an emax on there as you would expect
only one x nomad gnome shell had a good year they really did they really really did uh
i i have ultimately ended back up on plasma but you know different strokes different folks
and you have to acknowledge the extremely hard work that that project has received from
um multiple parties and it's shown the work is shown so i i could i could go with this
i don't know wes or drew do you have a counter argument why we shouldn't give it to nomshell
no i i i do think you're right they've had a big year the work continues and probably
next year is going to be even more exciting for the gnome shell show i'm excited for it
and even if that's not what we are using day to day in the studio or on our personal machines
a lot of people are it's shipping in a ton of major desktops and it's a backbone of the
open source you know linux desktop community yep yeah i agree and hey look i live in georgia
currently so i know a little bit something about uh nail biting elections but the difference
between gnome shell and plasma here 74 to 68 that's not huge it absolutely is a nail
biter but gnome shell definitely won all right then we give the 2020 best desktop environment
tuxi to gnome shell congratulations everybody over there you've done you've done a really
kick butt job and i this has been a lot of fun now the work begins on getting these issued
thank you everybody who took the time to submit and go through this we'd love to get your
ideas on how to refine the process for the future also if you'd like to support this
show in future episodes please consider becoming a direct member a core contributor of this
here humble podcast you just get that at unplugged core.com and it helps us stay independent keeps
the ad load down and also means that you get access to two additional feeds a limited ad
version of the show same full production just no ads or the full live stream it's even longer
than this one with all of our screw-ups all the stuff that we talked about before we hit
record and everything we talk about after we hit record it's basically like a show that
never gets released and now it's available as a feed for our core contributors at unplugged
core.com but that does wrap up the tuxis for 2020 get ready and start watching projects
over the year because we will be asking you again to submit your votes for the winners
of 2021 at this time next year thank you very much and that's everything see you next Tuesday.