I know he's the internet in there. Yeah, dude. They're right there. They are right there
Yeah, yeah
Ham did you want to say ham come see the internet ham ham come see the internet look it's right there look ham
That's really right there. That's it. Wow that is amazing. That's where you came from really you came from in there
That is amazing. I know that is amazing
Yeah, lady Jupiter pulls you from the internet, and she transitions you to the real world. That is amazing whoo credible technology
Incredible yeah, yeah the internet the internet beard exists in both reality and the internet check check is this thing on yeah
Yeah, that's like the worst thing to possibly say professional professional
This is Lennox unplugged episode 141 for April 19th
two thousand and sixteen
Oh
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's podcasting with a full house. My name is Chris. My name is Wes
Hey there, Wes. Yeah, we have a bunch of the crew already here
Not even everybody yet some of them are just about to hit the air as we record this here episode
But the jb1 studios are packed and we have a packed show coming up in this week's episode of the unplugged program
It's here some of the first Ubuntu tablets real have arrived
We've got first impressions from our audience that we'll cover in the show later on
We've had a bit of a Linux build disaster. I will tell you about that
It's and of course it's leading up to our Linux fast Northwest coverage, so it has to be time sensitive
We'll tell you all about all about that and some of the shenanigans going down this weekend
And then later on in the show we'll do some follow-up on our 1604 review
some interesting things that have already changed since we've done that review additional features that we didn't talk about in the Linux action show and
Of course a chance for our virtual log to chime in with maybe some of the things
That they have a different opinion on you know just a couple of things
They might have a different opinion from our review. Did you get a chance to see the review us? Oh, yeah?
Yeah, and you actually have 1604 we once again right here. We've got an excuse for you to wipe your machine this week
Every week yeah
It is a warm warm warm. I do here for the Linux unplugged show so thankfully
Thankfully Wes has brought us a nice cool brusky
This is this is great because Noah's been saying out of ten all week long that he's been here
this is ten barrel brewing company from Portland, Oregon, I think or somewhere in that area from Oregon and
We are drinking their sinister black ale
You know what I love now Wes is people are stopping by the IRC chat room before I like the show like
After tech talk and stuff, and they're saying hey Chris. I got my beer
I got that today in the IRC chat room. I got my beer ready for our work everyone
I know aren't you impressed makes us happy and proud
It's pretty cool now just to give you an idea of what it's like here in the JB one studios
So here is the ten barrel brewing company's website. Here's what it actually looks like in real life
This is what the state of you get an idea here
You can see there's a McDonald's cup off to the right there a beer box
That's which is what was what the beer comes in some energy drinks and Chinese takeout
And of course a roll of paper towels
That's pretty much sums up with the JB studio is the condition of the JB studio right now in one photo
It is a crazy time, so you know we need to do we need more people we got to bring in more voices
More voices in my head time appropriate greetings virtual log
Whoa what I
Think I heard like a secret message in there like a Disney cartoon style secrets
Yeah
all right, so
This this is pretty exciting those of you who jumped right on those pre-orders for your Ubuntu M
Tablet may be receiving them in the states at least folks on the East Coast in the US seem to be receiving their BQ tablets
OMG Ubuntu seems extremely excited about the news Joey writes it
It's really here. This is the first device to offer PC convergence as BQ has noted
That's the Spanish hardware company behind the Ubuntu tablet device
Delivery is our plan to go underway the second week of April which means fingers crossed. You should have your tablet
Really by the time that 1604 is released
And it's just pretty cool. That's really cool. I really really want to get one
Poppy if you had a chance to try one by now nope yeah, I haven't I have not had a chance to buy one yet
I really want to try one soon. I'm hoping maybe someone at Linux fest will have one. Oh, that would be nice
Yeah, I think so, but we do have a post in our subreddit from adjunct vent event
And he writes he there's the pictures of it pretty neat. I like the artwork on the box there. That's cool. You know the whole like
Production quality of the packaging looks pretty nice, which I think is you know you don't want to see that documentation there
There's the charger
Nice charge indicator powered by Ubuntu there on the first boot. That's super nice man at that convergence though
Yeah, I see it. Yeah, so he didn't end up. He didn't really well
So 23 hours 23 hours ago. Here's what he wrote in our subreddit, so he says so far. I pretty much hate it
Can anyone find a guide for installing arch on this thing oh?
No, that's oh
No
You want to hear he says the interface is awkward
I can't seem to figure out how to manage apps there isn't a file browser the keyboard doesn't pop up when I need
Regular desktop programs in LibreOffice or Firefox there are settings everywhere for syncing proprietary sites with social media
But nothing for own cloud. I don't know. I'm sure I'll pay
I'll play with it more and get used to it, but the first impressions are pretty disappointing
He says he did manage to find the terminal
He did expect to be a bit more functional and customizable
He feels like maybe he's being tough on it though, and it's not all that bad
He says for one thing the screen is beautiful and the touch apps that are on there are really slick. He says
So and right now. He's browsing reddit and making these posts from the built-in browser you go
He also says battery life seems to be pretty decent
Put more than maybe he perhaps expected so maybe after some time with it
You know and the tablet category is pretty broad
You know from like very minimally functional for things like the surface
So I think it's not legitimate if this is not necessarily targeting at the moment right out of the bat
The full-on workflow that he has in mind, but obviously it's usable for like what 90% of tablet users
Do which yeah browse reddit plus? I think we all sort of have I mean
I'm not trying to be an apologist, so I hope it doesn't come across this way because I
Guess here's my qualifier. It sounds like this might be a tablet that I'd be willing to buy for myself
Probably not a tablet. I'm gonna buy for my kids
Even though eventually that's exactly what I'd like the Ubuntu touch experience to be is the tablet my kids could use because that seems the
safest option for them, but I need something you know I'm willing I
Mean I you can now you can ask Noah. He's walking around the studio here. I'm a crazy art user
I'm I'm willing to read an end will set it up
I will read that wiki if I need to and so for me
It's I sort of have a different level of expectations. I'm not trying to be an apologist
I'm just trying to say as a technical user
I don't mind a challenge a bit as long as I can get to a functional state where it offers some sort of functionality
I don't know does anybody in the mumble room have thoughts on the new bq a tablet device
Sure
I'd love to hear it
So I'm inclined to agree with you that I you know if I was if I was looking for a tablet for my kids
Today right now
I wouldn't buy the bq Ubuntu tablet and that I'm speaking as a canonical employee as an Ubuntu user Ubuntu enthusiast
I've been using Ubuntu for 10 10 plus years, and I wouldn't buy it for them because
truth be told the apps that they want are not on there and so right they
wouldn't be able to do the things they want and it would be a waste of my money because it'd be sat there the
The kind of people who are likely to buy this thing are developers
early adopters people who are going to write new apps or port existing apps or people who can
Cope with you know the janky edges here and there that there might be janky edges
That's a good title right there janky edges
Yeah
Yeah, and and isn't that sort of the isn't that sort of the phase it has to be and now now poppy does that?
Disenfranchise you a bit when you think you know the other guys are maybe
Five years into iterating their experience. They're not they're way past the janky edges
Is that too late the other guys that have billions of dollars and thousands?
No, I understand that they have a huge huge tactical advantage
But my point is it doesn't alter the reality of it though right sure and and yeah
I would love for us to be more advanced down the road than we are right now
I would love for us to have more apps
I would love to have the more popular apps that you and I both know or the games or you know the ability to
Export from you know unity 3d or for vplay or all these other platforms to support us
But we've got to start somewhere and right now
We've got the the sum total of one tablet on the market or arguably two if you can if you count two
resolutions of the same device
one on the market so you know
But nobody is going to target a market that has
One device with you know some thousands of users, so we've got to be realistic, and so you know we're fine with it being
developer mostly experience at the moment and people who are willing to accept
Over-the-air updates every six weeks that give them new stuff new crack all the time
And you know the fact that you can make the file system read-only and you know you could apt-get
Install cow say or whatever you know emacs or whatever you want to if you're willing to accept the compromise that that gives you so
There's you know this swings around amounts there. It's pretty neat like there's a lot of projects
I could imagine where a tablet would work before
But it would just be easier if I didn't have to deal with like an Android build chain or other like if I can just use
the bantu system
For a lot of that I could definitely say you know if some of these supporting software got there like in media production and
You could have a device that was both the capture device say has a camera, right?
And it has the editing software that you could maybe poke at
in in touch mode or
You could at least review clips in touch mode and then when you want to edit you sit down and you could you could you?
Know get a full desktop experience, and you think well a tablet. That's crazy
But you you actually look at like devices like the latest Nexus tablet the pixel or the iPad Pro
They have extremely powerful processors, and you can actually edit video on these frickin tablets
But they have a horrible desktop experience right so something they can have the real desktop. Yeah
Mm-hmm. I do want an Ubuntu tablet soundboard as well, mr.. Devlin you have a
developer appeal yeah, I
The promise that it will be much simpler device
deployment
To do the construction of applications when you're going to the other platforms right now is just full of
Frameworks and these and that and it's like vanilla experience that you used to have back in in Windows
See Windows embedded it was simpler to deploy an app
Back in the window see a day. This is a harsh criticism. I'm not sure how to take that
No, no, no, I'm saying that this is what Ubuntu is bringing on the table that Android iOS kind of got away from yeah
Yeah, and so it brings that appeal that you can make your application
It's an easy iteration and because it's an easy iteration
I I'm I'm betting that all of the applications that get built are iterating much faster
We're going to iterate much faster. Just because the platform has the ease to the play faster. Yeah, yeah
I don't know about get Google voice support. I
Guess I could argue poppy. Are you aware of any Google voice tricks for Ubuntu touch devices?
I
the support for Google Hangouts
Lands in the browser very soon, but Google voice. I don't know. I'm outside the UK. So Google voice is an irrelevance to me
Fair enough. Yeah, I guess that's kind of a you know, you're not really you're probably better off you're better off
It's I have never been super impressed with Google voice and I've been using it
I've been a user since Grand Central so but I bet there's the SIP client you can get for Ubuntu touch
Yeah, yeah, I bet there is and I you know, yeah
I I actually I think that's probably the better way to go. Yeah, it just takes a little more setup
You know, there's an there is an in-between step
There is a step you could take that makes sense right now and that's our friends over at ting you guessed it
Linux dot ting comm is where you go to support this show, you know, I noticed on the ting road trip
I have the GSM service turned on going down us 90 except for when I was I think at sort of the top of the
Pass, I think I had serviced the whole darn way. Oh dang. Yeah, we use the Nexus 5
To do maps until the Nexus 5 started to freak out on me. I don't know what was up. So
New egg had a had a fifty fifty dollar off sale on the Nexus 5x. I think it's such a steal
Yeah, dude, so I ordered the Nexus 5x while I was leaving to go on the road trip
don't know while I was on the road trip and
And so my Nexus 5 ended up just the batteries totally shot, you know, it's it's just old and stuff
So let this be the wake, right?
So I just popped the ting out the ting sim out of the Nexus 5 and I went to go pop it into the Nexus
5x pop that ting, right?
It's like it's a
Like they cannot get these SIM cards small enough anymore. Like the SIM card is tiny for the Nexus 5 that really is
Yeah, and so I'm like, yeah, and I'm like, ah, what am I gonna do? My SIM cards too big
I might I got I can't pop the thing. Oh, geez. Oh
But you know what ting has thought of this stuff ting is an experienced
Experienced mobile service provider. You can just you can just pop the SIM one more smaller. You just pop it
This is all true, I don't understand why it's so funny because it's all true and
So anyways
Now my 5x is activated
Okay, all right, so I hope I'll be the pro I'll pull it together
Anyways, now I have my GSM ting sim in my 5x and it's on the ting network now
I'll tell you one thing. I've noticed right away
It has two front-facing stereo speakers. I am very excited about that
Also, it feels a little bit better and the fingerprint reader is nice. So that's my like, oh, it's real nice
I've only very impressed
I've only had I've only had the 5x literally for an hour
Because I ordered it while I was on the road trip and just got unboxed it and it's been installing updates the entire time
I have had it but they'd like that
Well, so the fact that it's here's what I here's what I just love about it
I went on Newegg because there was a sale and I ordered it. I
Never called anyone at ting. I never logged into the website. I just pulled the SIM card out and I put it in a totally unlocked
Totally straight Google experience 5x put it in there and now I have phone service
It took I mean as long as it I thought carriers that would not work
It is so nice and and now I just pay for what I use. It's six dollars for the line
I just transferred it over to this device. I I love it
I end up paying like 40 bucks a month for like three lines
It's great minutes messages megabytes to add them up. You only pay for what you use ting is great. No contracts
No early termination fees and they have a great control panel if you do need it
Oh, I could tell you all about that
But you know what? I think I'm gonna do
I'm gonna say go to linux.com. That'll give you $25 off a device or
Or go get $50 off of 5x if the new if new egg still has that sale going and I think actually even the play
Store has the sale directly. Yep, you know about this. Yeah, definitely. Yeah, so I've been considering you should do it
You should do it because I think the 5x is a nice upgrade from the 5
I think it's a really so I mean you can play with it when it's done here
But I want to at least log into it once for goodness sake
But as it won't bond with you USB see it now when you plug it in it says rapid charging
Oh rapid charging. Yeah, that's sweet
So I think this is I think you know with that with that sale and pay for what you use service from ting
This is such a no-brainer, but they have all the great devices
You can check it out from feature phone SIM cards all the way up and they have a wonderful blog. I
Like this post about minimizing your mobile data usage in YouTube. I think they're like they're just like us
They're they use the phone the same way. Do you need 1080p when you're you know?
Like you probably don't need 1080p when you're on your mobile device and you're on you're on you're on LTE
So they just it's a bunch of great tips. They have some good videos posted over there, too
So just start by going to linux.ting.com that supports this show gets you the discount
You can do that anywhere in the world support this show big
Thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program linux.ting.com
alright, so the Linux fest Northwest mayhem is approaching and
I think maybe if you're watching Linux action show this week
You might have saw sort of the state of chaos this caused when we do a new Linux build
Which we want to get done before Linux fest Northwest and it is a massive undertaking and of course
Of course West things never quite go as you plan you can research the parts
You do your best
You can assign tasks to staff to do research for you and then buy what they recommend and then they blame you for buying it
You can do all of those things and get blamed regardless, but
You cannot accommodate for how they build things today now
I could explain our woes and I could explain our trials
But I thought maybe what we do is a little hot chicken dance swap first and maybe somebody else could tell you
Oh
Where they truly intro truly worthy
So I got here and there was a bunch of parts that were ordered and
we're working on building various things and trying to get various things working and so I
Just I am I am like kind of like a whirlwind and then I and I get things done and I worry about the consequences
Yeah, yeah
I do
I just you know like if I open a box and you know the thing is they could make this stuff a little easier to
Do if you know when a video card just came like if the video card just came in like a simple box
But no, they have to have all this plastic around and they've got a guy like, you know, it's fancy manuals
So they've got discs and that's all stuff. I don't need I don't care about and so the first bit of it went pretty well
I'm filming like every part and trying to give you guys a real good idea of exactly what's going on and then
We went to turn on the computer now. I built a fair amount of computers myself and
I have always built the computer and turn it on and it just works now Rekai tells me
I know what you should do is test each individual component like outside of the case and I'm like
That sounds like a waste of time. Like who's gonna sound like I just build the computer. I'll just pay attention to it
Right, it'll be fine. So I built the computer bring it into the studio disconnect all of Chris's nonsense that he needs to do
a little podcast
Plug in the computer and turn it on no boot. So then I'm like, wow
So I take all of his stuff that he needs to do his podcast out in living room where it's not so hot and I
Can see what I'm doing and plug it in out there and still not working
So then I start taking individual parts out as the video card was at the RAM
Is it the so finally I get down to just the motherboard and I read on the motherboards website that
Supposedly the motherboard is supposed to be able to update from the BIOS if you plug into a special secret super secret USB port
Yes, I heard of such things. I download actually I didn't download it. It asked the beard to do it beard downloads
Onto the US that's the same as I did
By the way, I was not the one that picked this stuff out so I
I we've done we download this stuff onto the USB port
Under the USB flash drive and I stick it in the computer turns on for like three seconds and powers off then turns on for
Three seconds and powers off then turns out three seconds and powers off. That is no good. Well, that's not updating well, so
Then I'm like, well, let's just open the second motherboard because we got two of these and let's see if the second one is any
Different right? Well, that's good troubleshooting. It's having the second one and by this time I'm like
stinking
I
Hold on if you have easier phone in your pocket, no
You could just play it but of course we'd have to beep it though a lot. Yeah
Hmm, maybe we'll save it for another time
There's a lot of swearing but it would be really great to play it. But okay
All right
So I was less than please because by now it's like so this is of course we always figured to do this stuff at like
You know five in the morning
That's the most productive time and Rekai's upset. I didn't I would I see upset about it
What I didn't three under the bus
Anyway, so anyway, so what I did home no, so what I did was I
What I did was I
Opened the second one up and realized that the second one is just as defective as the first one now
I'm not very happy about this entire process and I just you're telling me we had
We had two defective gigabyte motherboards
Like I mean like the first little thought that Chris you're not gonna date. Here's what I here's what I here's the message
I get Chris. You're not gonna be happy
I'm like what both motherboards are dead. I'm like, I'm like no not both motherboards something wrong. No, not both motherboards
He's like, yeah, trust us. We've tried it. So and you know, you got a feel for Noah here Noah
Here, let's all right. So a disclaimer. This was never ended to enter. It was it was never intended to air
It's all right. It's all right. I don't care Rekai can bleep, right?
Or maybe for maybe we should just say for the next
How long is this clip? That's about two minutes. So just if you have small children around
Turn this up. I usually try to keep it pretty family-friendly
No, you gotta understand this is like three in the morning five in the morning
Okay, and I have to get up and do last the next day because of course we don't plan this
This is Saturday night and so and this is all there's a lot there
You know
Basically if this Linux big build doesn't work out we might end up having to switch to a Mac for this work and that that
Is really I think what is driving Noah's passion about right and so then I will climb a clock tower
And I don't want to climb a clock tower. All right, so you've been warned. Okay for your ears earmuffs put on your
Okay, let me show you why you should never buy a fucking gigabyte motherboard
You're supposed to be able to update this son of a bitch
By plugging a fucking flash drive into the white thing what you should just
Yeah, I should but I'm too pissed to record it for the show
Oh, you notice the fan spins up
And then it stops
Then it spins up and then it stops
So I have been stripping components because they're but we we're two of these goddamn things
And I this one I got completely assembled because I'm used to using Asus that just fucking works
And then we bought these two fucking things. I didn't buy them Chris bought them. Ooh about this but
It just does this just they start up and stop and so we have researched the fuck out of them apparently
They just fucking blow and so they just restart constantly even with all the components removed. I mean I put the RAM back in but
Fucking blows. No, so don't buy gigabyte ever
particularly the
The hell's this goddamn piece of shit
x99 SLI
trash total trash
Merry Christmas
So that was my not never intended to be aired but like I was like, you know, you know people don't understand
You know when you spend from you know
9 10 p.m. Until 4 or 5 in the morning and then you know, and then constantly there's this there's this threat of
The antithesis of your being being the only alternative
that I that you get to a point you get really driven to get something done and then and then when you realize that you
Are being cock-blocked not by not by the inability of your operating system
which is supposed to be where the troubleshooting and problem is supposed to be no you are being cock-blocked by a
a totally useless manufacturer that manufactures something that is better suited to adjusting the height of your monitor then functioning as an entire
System board to connect all of your components not even very good at that
It's no because it doesn't turn out it would the best thing I could do with it was it was it was a decent
Nightlight, that's really what it was good for
So basically then and really I like Chris is laughing
But it honestly has caused him a lot of stress and trouble because now he has to the burdens on money to get new
A replacements of that and of course those come and UPS is so incompetent that they managed to break one of those kind of sort
of we're kind of in the process of dealing with that and so
You know, it's very very well
Maybe that I may end up ordering a third one because I think at this point it's Chris has tapped out
So but to until we have a chance to return all of these things and of course if you've ever ordered anything with new egg
You know that they're not as awesome as Amazon where I can just tell them that it didn't work and then they take it back
No, there's got to be a process and I probably have to send it to gigabyte
and they're gonna tell me that I did something wrong and try and update something and I'm gonna tell them that they can take their
motherboard and
Yeah, exactly or they can stick it in their ear and then
They and then they can take that and then get rid of it cuz I don't really want to look at it anymore
But I think when we get done we depend on a positive note when we get done
I think what we're gonna find is that Chris is going to have
Two amazing machines that are going to fundamentally change the way that we're able to do productions here in the studio
But I think it will all be worth the headache and troubles. Uh,
Yeah, I think that I think it's all content and at the end of the day it's all come on guys you're in my house
It's been crazy it's been crazy. It's the Linux fest Northwest. You guys know it's coming up. We are preparing like another website
I know it is just makes me happy. You know, we were I think it was hand that asked me on the way back from
Picking him up in Idaho. He said why is it in Bellingham and not Seattle?
And I think that might probably crosses a lot of people's mind because when you think of this area you think of you think of
Seattle and the Space Needle and all that crap
Well, first of all, it's I think the core reason is because it's put on by the Bellingham Linux users group
you know, we have a virtual lug here and
They have a real they have a have a real lug there and I think this is one of the things
It's pretty unique about the Linux community and other open source
communities now as well that have taken a page from this is
They are capable of putting on events like Linux fest Northwest self scale and you know
Of course a bunch of others that I I don't go to as well. Obviously, it's pretty impressive. Yeah
Yeah, it really is. And so that's one of the reasons why it's in Bellingham, but it is genuinely one of the prettiest areas
in the country
It is really
Yeah, it is great. You know, it is truly gorgeous there
And if you have an opportunity to make it out, it is really worth it meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting
We have a meetup page. We're gonna be organizing the switch competition, which you guys know is coming up
Even though Emma's been Emma hacked us last week during the Linux action show. It was rough. We got hacked art by team Emma
And they've been out in Denver, Colorado good. They've been practicing Denver, Colorado teams
You know, there's you know, as you know, there's betting taking place behind the scenes here in JB
Yeah, yeah
I am I I have a I I have a lot riding on this also we in today in tech talk today
We decided that if we got to a certain level of patrons on
Patreon.com slash today that no one I would wear he'd wear a window shirt and I'll wear an Apple shirt
Yeah. Yeah, so that's in tech talk today. If you guys curious about that. Yeah, we're really we're looking fun
And we have more crew showing up tomorrow, which is pretty exciting with so there is a project out there
that promises to bring Libre office C file the KDE group and
Maybe so I'm guessing some own cloud back-end code bring it all together to give you a Google Docs and Google apps like experience
Using all Libre software, so we're going to talk about that because you and I were poking at this
Noah's been poking at this and I want to talk about it for a little bit
So and it's probably something you could run on a digital ocean droplet
Oh, yeah
Hey, oh if you think about anything if you think about it
You probably could do unplugged as our promo code to use over digital ocean, you know as you're gearing up for Ubuntu 1604
You'll notice that they have new guides coming out on Ubuntu 1604. It is a great hosting provider built on top of Linux
They use KVM for the virtualizer SSDs for all the drives tier one bandwidth
They have locations all over the world if you want to deploy images or entire application stacks or just docker containers. Oh
Digital ocean has got that do unplugged is the promo code one word ten dollar credit now their basic rig
$5 a month
That's nothing
$5 a month you get 512 megabytes of RAM
I owe a terabyte a transfer 20 gigabyte SSD because they all SSDs and I love the fact that it is
Blazing fast even though even the $5 rig is blazing fast like log in there and do a package update and just
Just just update the package cache and witness the gorgeous speed that you get
I love awesome, you know, I've been playing around with track car
It was obvious to put that up on a digital ocean droplet when I wanted to convince know to use sync thing
You know what? He does he puts it up on a digital ocean droplet natural and like an animal
He just FTP's up to the digital ocean droplet and then let's it sync to me like some kind of animal
I hope that's SFTP
Me too Wes me too. Hey Wes, did you know that they have introduced now don't tell anybody
But did you know they have introduced a sign up for the block storage program? Oh, yeah, I think that's gonna be really cool
Yeah, and like I was sign up right now like I was mentioning earlier
They do have great tutorials now like how to upgrade to a boon to 16 before how to take it engine X and let's a crypt
I'm 1604 and go look at their new command-line client to manage your digital ocean. I'm so excited about that
I know I know me too drop down terminal has never been happier digital ocean comm just use the promo code D
Unplugged use it just like that
Do you unplugged over a digital ocean comm one word and you can sing it when you type it in that also it doesn't give
you a more like
credit on the account
But it makes you feel good. Oh, it really does make you feel deal
Unplugged
one word
digital ocean comm all right, so this week on the Linux action show
We had a candidate that we bumped
We were gonna talk about this online libre office
thing that exists it's called
Open 365 dot IO obviously a take on office 365 create
It says create the first open-source cloud with libre office online online libre office online plus C file plus KDE
Yeah, yeah, it promises to bring like libre to the online web space
Oh
You know what I got to do. I got to hook up the audio so you get well
You don't really need the audio you can hear the audio in the background
I so tell me West though when you look at that does that does that remind you of own cloud a little bit it really does
Yeah, I'm so I'm thinking they must be using some own cloud on the back end
They're using C file for the file distribution now. I know no you and I had it
We're looking at this too. What were your impressions of this sort of online libre office thing here?
You know my thing is that I've actually I've been excited about office 365 simply because it runs perfectly fine on Linux and so those
The dorks that insist on using office products that don't want to use a real office suite, then I have a solution for
but the more that I use things like like giggly docs and the more I use things like
Office 365 I find myself thinking you know for certain collaboration things and for certain you know I just need access to
You know to compose a document a little bit note more than what you know a traditional note-taking
Application offers that is the kind of time where I really want would like to have a cloud-based office suite
And it's not something that would be a primary driver, but it's definitely something that I would be using to you know
Maybe maybe even for showdocs
I'm probably not because there's probably not markdown support
But certainly if you know you could add that you and I were collaborating on a letter a couple days ago
And that would have been really useful to be able to have this you know all this thing opposed
And you can make edits, and I can make edits and stuff like that
We can keep you know the you know the rich text formats and stuff like that. Yeah
Yeah, and not having to have Google Drive would be nice. I think what what I find what I find sort of
interesting about this and also sort of off-putting at the same time is
It clearly seems like you're bringing a Qt application or something like this
Into the web browser. Yeah, that's weird
Like it's got the full regular menu
It's got a file menu and edit menu a view menu like it's LibreOffice embedded in the website
and I guess what what strikes me about that is
Hmm
Look at that though. Yeah, it does seem very functional
It does seem very functional, but what strikes me about it is it doesn't seem forward-facing. It seems like right
It's sort of what we have now. It's not
Trying new things that work. Yeah, and I mean not to be this guy
But if I have my bqabuntu touch tablet this doesn't really look like it's gonna work in that
I it
feels a little bit like
bringing a
Another desktop environments application over to say your desktop environment just something's quite not quite there about it
gigglydocs
Zoho and
Others they feel like they should be online
document editors that feels like you've taken a web desktop application and
Integrated it into own cloud and called it something that stuff looks like it's web, but you're right once you start editing. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, I'm curious. I'm curious if anyone in the Mamba room has had a chance to look at this at all
And if you guys have any opinions on it because it's it's been getting some press coverage recently
And we've been debating whether to cover it in the shows or not
Yeah, I don't think anybody's really played within our community
But Noah, and I were you know this one thing that really jumps out at me about it is if I could self-host it
Hmm. I probably would prepare the show most the time on my desktop device anyways mm-hmm. Yep
I mean, so if I can self-host it. Yeah, you know we switched over to pretty much using simple note no, and I have to prep
last and
It just gets a simpler cleaner faster environment
And we both prefer having a dedicated desktop application to do this so nice
That's one of the things is I I guess
I'm I'm ready for us to move beyond cloud integration meaning. It's something that's embedded in your web browser
I think okay. I think I'm getting to the core of what bothers me about this
I think this is a great idea, and I'm really glad they're doing it
but when I get to the core of what bothers me about it is I am I am I'm ready for all of the features of
cloud integration and syncing to be just
Part of a desktop experience. Yep
I want something like simple note and Chrome web browser that seems to be fully in sync with a back-end cloud service
But the front-end representation the way that that way that result is displayed to me is a native
Application that looks right in my desktop environment, and I don't want to have to run a runtime of my browser
I don't want my browser to become my runtime and
If that's if that even means that things like electron projects sort of hide all of that from me
Then they split they still accomplish that well, okay. I'm gonna try to build my next rig with more RAM
I mean, I'm ready for that. Let's bring it
But I want it
I want it in a desktop experience not crammed into a web page
And I think that's kind of what where this gets all the desktop integrations and full support for
Dragon drop and native speed native speed it launches as fast as my SSD can feed the bits to the CPU and as fast as
That can be blasted to my screen
I don't want anything in between that and I want it to come as fast as possible because honestly
That's why I buy a new computer. That's why I build new rigs
That's why I consider playing with the Linux scheduler
That's why I want to do a RAM disk for my Chrome browser, right?
I want it to be as fast as possible all the time. You've worked to get done
That's right
And so if you could make it if you could make a local native application that
Instantly launches but yet pulls in the latest data from the web. That's from like an API for a cloud service
I'm all about that and that's the perfect sweet spot for me mumble room any thoughts before I let Noah jump in with his thoughts
All right, Noah, they don't have any thoughts
Do you have any kind of closing thoughts on unlike the way that because I know one of the things you and I talked about
Is well, it kind of looks like they've just take LibreOffice and put in a web browser
But I have a sense that that isn't that probably doesn't bother you
It doesn't bother me because if you think about it, that's I mean really that's what we look for
And that's the that's the that is the very essence of open source
Somebody created a really good cloud based web browser system, which is own cloud. Somebody created a really great office suite
That's LibreOffice and somebody took a and B and combined them together to make office 365 and made basically a patent infringement calling it
Open 365 and they'll probably have to change
The great news about report on it then yeah, right
But the great news about that is that we have essentially
We have we've taken two great open source projects and combine them if that's in fact what they're doing and really I don't really care
How they're doing it
But even if nothing else the fact that we have the option at least I can tell
Clients when I tell them you should switch a LibreOffice and they go well, I'm really into the office
365 because I like doing everything on the web and in the cloud and that's great and it's backed up and accessible from home
I have an answer to that
That's about what they sound like
And and it's better than Google. I don't have to ask. I don't have to tell them, you know
You know how unprofessional it sounds to me to walk in and say I have a great solution for you
Let me show you how we're gonna do
This is how I tell people to do it what I'm going to recommend to you is I think you should
Go to gmail.com and sign up for a Google account and use the bill. That just doesn't sound like that is not
That's not providing a solution. And the other problem is is I have zero control
It's not like Google works with me to say these are the things that are upcoming
So by the way, make sure your clients are aware that this menu is going away or that menu is great
you know, that's a great point because
Even when you're giving them Google Drive and Google Docs and a Google Apps account if you're through business what you're really saying is
Even though it's easy. Here's another service. You need to manage. Here's another service. You need to pay
Here's another thing. You need to keep track of users on so that way you're not paying too much. Here's another thing xyz and
When you come at them with here's an implementation as a service provider that I can give you that is an entirely managed package
You write me one check a month. I take care of all user management all features all security updates all integrations
Where do I sign right? That's it. And you maybe if they hope if they allow you to host this you could do that on your
own
So that's that's a point well taken though
be interesting to see if it sees deploys to wear something where like, you know, maybe paying too much for like the
365 hosted in the secure data center where you have like really secure documents and you need you want the features of 365
Yeah, you need it to be internal to your land, you know, I wonder
North Ranger could this be something that local ISPs and different people in this space could come up and say hey
Yeah, you've heard of Google, but what about this and they could sell it. Is that kind of what you're thinking North Ranger?
Yeah from what you've just described. I think back in the day when you used to sign up for an ISP
It was your local ISP. They offered you email. They maybe offered you a shell account, you know, so
You know
Maybe it's not the actual ISP that you have because apparently today's ISPs are more
Interested in bundling a phone and a TV with you
But let's move ISPs more to like a VPS provider where you not only have email
but oh, by the way, we'll host your sync account or
your calendar or your photos and
You know use I'm not saying you have to use own cloud
But something like that where you know, you can be you can host it yourself
but when you go offline or
You know whatever like your ISP can you know have the canonical copy so to speak?
That's it. That's actually an interesting idea and also maybe a great way
What I what I would what I would love about that kind of business is
It's a way for open source to get deployments. It's a way for a company to make money using open source software
And then that means fixes or start going upstream bug reports start coming in
Yeah, and it doesn't answer all your security, you know problems
But at least in it like your ISP is someone you pay, you know
Like that's in their interest to help you out
So it should at least you know
They're not necessarily doing all the kind of my data mining that someone else might be now shots were fired in native versus web apps rotten
Do you want to close out the thought on just commenting on that a lot of the times?
The web apps actually look really nice and I don't really care if it's native or not as long as it doesn't look like garbage
So if it if it's if it's gonna run like an electron thing
I'd prefer it not because it's not gonna be as fast
But at least they look good and they run well, so I'm okay with it. What happens?
What do you do rotten when you have two?
Replications that are web apps and you need to move back and forth them and you're moving data back and forth now
I've got if I like these I think that works if you're using one or maybe even two
but when you start to get a plethora when I had
When I had own cloud and I had Evernote and I had you know Google Docs and I had you know
Whatever else you start to get like four or five different these web apps open wonder list for example
Moving between them is almost like they're I start to eliminate the ability of the operating system to manage my window
So I can't don't have you know along the side of unity. I can't switch between those applications now
I have to rely on the tab switching inside of the web browser
Well to be fair
There are window managers that can do that
But I would say that the art that that example is not very good because all of those essentially accomplish the same thing
So I think the issue is that you are using multiple like you Evernote and Google Docs and stuff
They're basically all the same
So if you were using a to-do list editor or a to-do list web app and then a web app for like telegram
Those would be completely different things. You wouldn't have to have that but I actually do kind of synthesize synthesize
I do actually kind of connect with what Noah is saying because
I have found myself like ripping tabs off all the time and all right
Oh, yeah
Me too this tab goes on this monitor now and I'm gonna I'm gonna I'll put this tab over here
I'll put that I'll shrink this tab and I'll float in them on top
Yeah, it's getting to be the point now where and the other thing I find myself doing in all the time now is right now
I have three tabs pinned. I always have at least three tabs up
Yeah, it's getting to be right there and and and I started to feel like they're forcing me to live a Chrome OS existence
a little bit
Well, they kind of are but there's also solutions in Linux
native applications that can provide a
you know direct connection with a window manager for example instead of having like the tabs being splayed out and then you have like
multiple different Chrome
There's a couple different options too that I've used to basically give a dedicated process to each web app, right?
We talked about that last year with the yeah, apricity and that's nice that works
For one apricity is actually using something that's still using Chrome, right?
Created by peppermint OS which is interesting. You should check that out. But the the reason I
Was talking about is that?
Chromium's web app solution is terrible
You have one session that is still like every single web app you make with chromium or with ice
It's still one session. So it's not organized at all. It's not separated. It's all just in math
I've run into that problem connected with that group if you look at epiphany and
Midori both of those have
Web app built in so they're all separate individual sessions for each web app you create. There's an
Web app manager for each one of those and there's also
Ubuntu has their own browser that you can use that was created for the Ubuntu touch
Yeah
But also works on the desktop and you can do the same thing and create different sessions
So they become like real processes as also it's also interesting to see like a lot of different open source
Wrapper applications, like what's that? What's that slack one called scud or something, right? Yeah, there's different and then Noah and I were playing with a
messenger
Application that is just a web app
And what it does is it uses one application and multiple tabs to integrate every messaging service from slack to telegram to what's-app
Everything that has any kind of web Skype anything has any web app all in one application
and that's kind of interesting because then it takes care of like
Now notification badges and stuff like that for you for all those different services, but and brykes it off into its own process
Which is kind of interesting
There was one that was created a couple years ago for Linux. That was awesome. And then it was discontinued. It was called fogger
Yeah, I know I did and you know, and and that's sort of why I've tried to recreate
Just using the the built-in Chrome thing
But yeah, you're right. It's not it's not the same. Yeah, and sometimes I'll use some stuff and yeah
If they made the sessions properly, it would be great
But like the fact that if you create a Netflix session if you open it in Chrome or you open it in the web app
It's still the same thing. So you're still in the same sessions
You can't have like for example
If you have two different Twitter accounts that you want to open up Twitter
You can't log into the separately with the chromium solution
But if you did it with like epiphany or you did it with Midori you can do that
And I think the Midori is probably one of the best options. Yeah, I
Try I tried Midori for a little while in it. I was starting to get it eventually would run out of memory. Listen
let's class it up in here for a second because I
Want to open the floodgates I want to talk about our Ubuntu 1604 review. I've gotten
Thanks, nice, I've already gotten like several like geez you and Noah really got into it kind of comments
And they don't even know the half of it. We got into it again today just out in the living room
So we got to talk about this so we got it we got to bring it up a notch
Got a clear space for our discussion. So first I want to thank Linux Academy
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you
I want to welcome them into this episode of Linux unplugged episode 141
why don't you welcome them to at linux academy.com slash unplugged go there and
Celebrate their support of your unplugged program by visiting linux academy.com slash unplugged
Not only will you get their new discount that they've just rolled out
brand new pricing structure
But you can learn more about their
2369 self-paced courses
Instructing married you're gonna learn something. I mean it rubs by accident accidentally learning at linuxacademy.com slash
Scenario based labs are totally badass because they put you in the middle of something that's real
God damn it. What is you just crew at least all of today?
If that doesn't work they have instructor mentor which I think you're gonna need you
For listening to this, but they'll set you right and you'll learn but remember it doesn't matter what we say because the music class
Just want you to know while this music is on but I don't hate you I
I think you're wrong about a bunch you but we can still be friends you can use arch
Yeah, except for I did back you into agreeing with me earlier. Anyways, Linux academy.com slash unplug go there learn about their great and server exercises
developing Linux
Applications learning about Linux firewalls and fundamentals routing all those things
Python development PHP opens that great chef tutorials up there. Thank you for mentioning that you're right
They are really good ones Amazon Web Services and the server is included. Oh, man. I know right? It's great
7-plus distros. It's
It's a wonderland Linux Academy comm slash unplug go invest in yourself
Learn more about Linux from the basics to the advanced topics and they are crushing the open stack courses right now. Check them out
at Linux Academy comm
Slash unplugged. All right, we're headed out of here. It is time for us to follow up on our Ubuntu 1604
review
Now there are many things to discuss in regards to this review and I want to cover all of them as much as we can
If you have not had a chance, it's not a prerequisite, but I would invite you to listen to episode 413 or watch
episode 413 of the Linux action show
Where we did our review and just as a background because I don't know if I really went into this in the show or not
but uh
Basically every machine in my life except for that one right there that bonobo got reloaded to Ubuntu 1604 Wow
Ubuntu edition was the one I ran with the longest and then I put the neon packages on there because I loves me the
fresh neon and
It I guessed actually going back for they really started the day. I got the Apollo. Yep. I
Got I got really excited by what a good implementation of Ubuntu Mate 1510 on the Apollo was and then as soon as it felt
Reasonable, I brought that up to 1604 and then I started bringing all my other machines to 1604 and yeah
And so I spent you know, I spent a real solid month in Ubuntu
which for me was a big transition again going back and
But part of the reason I wanted to do it is because I really wanted to spend
You know when you just do it for a couple of days
You get totally overwhelmed by all the little rough edges that are just different, you know
Just because it's not it's not comfortable and familiar. It just it feels abrasive
But if you actually spend time with it you you learn. Oh, yeah, I do it this way this now and the true character
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, and so, you know, I really wanted to give it its due
and so when we walked away I walked away with some some impressions that I had reflected on for that whole month and
That would those definitely took the stage of the review
I think that the bulk of the stage, but there's a lot of things covered in the
1604 review and I was curious Wes
If you why don't we do this if you be up for this?
Let's get your impressions sort of at the top
Then let's go to the mumble room
Get some of their updates and follow-up and their impressions and then towards the end of this shenanigans
Let's talk about some of the things that have changed
Already or fixed already since Sunday's episode of the show so it like a full spectrum coverage
So as follow-up to our 1604 review Wes, what are your sort of out of the first gate impressions of this brand new?
LTS release. Okay, so first for context both in work and kind of at home
I both skip to work the 1404 release and then that I use that at home, but I didn't use too much
So I guess this is kind of a this is kind of like for
For you a huge upgrade. Yeah, it really is a huge upgrade. That's an interesting perspective
So you've been stuck at 1204 for years and a majority, you know, I use some 1404
I do have like one system at 1510, but but yes, there's a lot of 1204 and so
There there's so much new and so much I'm excited about
I mean, I've used Ubuntu on system D before but I just I love doing you know
System control status and just seeing that breakdown. It's I'm really excited to see it at servers on work
Now did you play with the in-between ones? Yeah, I played with them a little bit. Okay, you just didn't use them wise
I just yeah, I didn't really deploy them. Yeah, and I'm kind of in the same boat
I mean, I didn't I traditionally just stick to the LTS, right, you know
And so and and it seems like a good point right now where when once it's out
It'll have it'll have fresh packages for quite some time
And then you have the snap packages and you have CFS right there. Have you played with CFS on 1604?
I haven't on 1604, but I've used it, you know building it myself or loading myself. Okay, it's on a third party
On earlier version. So like I'm really excited also about like LXD 2.0, which just came out
Uh-huh. I like LXD. I like I like that model and Ubuntu supports it very well
Yeah, so do you use a lot of this? So do you use a lot of other desktop environments other than just unity?
Yeah, I almost never use unity really. So I'm trying it out right now. It's not bad
The animations are pretty slick and it's definitely I've seen the touch-ups from what I'm used to, you know
Especially seen it work a lot of the deployments before so
So, you know you news nice but you know, normally I use a cinnamon a lot for Linux man, or I use a tiling window manager
But I'm really excited for just having like I feel like 1604 will be a release
I can deploy in almost every part of my life the places where I don't need
First-hand management or where arch doesn't make the most sense, you know
Maybe for less minimal stuff
But but anywhere where I just need a general Linux where I know that the packages will be what I need
They'll be away, especially with snap packages
There'll be a way to get the software that I want and I can figure it the way I need
It'll just be I'm really excited. Yeah, I that's sort of my takeaway too, and I kind of wanted to I
Tied I joked a lot during the live stream
I actually am kind of curious on Popey's take for it because not just be not just because he worked with
Ubuntu and works at canonical
but honestly because he's obviously been following this for a long time and has good insight on this and I
Wonder too if if maybe these are some of the elements that he's excited about and I know I've kind of asked him to dance
it like a monkey before on this topic, but I
I know that the snap packages are sort of the weakest area of coverage in our review and it's sort of I feel like the
Biggest long-term ramifications of 1604 and so I don't know puppy
Do you have any just sort of take on our review and thoughts on it and maybe thoughts on snap packages specifically?
Can't talk Chris. I'm busy playing games on 1604
Nice. Yeah. Okay. You know what? That's another thing is it is a great platform for steam game. Yeah, I kid I'm joking
I was actually believe
But
Yeah, the snap stuff, you know when I first heard about this company years ago
I
Was kind of skeptical because the guy who was telling me about this was outside a hotel
You know
We'd all had an intro to what snappy was and only a few people have been involved in what it what it was going to
Be and I I didn't quite get it and it's only now
that I realize how many people depend on things like a you are in arch or
Your self-updating applications like Chrome
And other things that just like sort themselves out and nobody nobody has to worry about it
Right, and you know, we used to think that PPAs were a marvelous way to get stuff to to users
But actually it's quite abrasive to get from you know
I want to have the latest version of whatever atom or you know sublime or whatever
Whether it's free software or proprietary. It's it's quite abrasive to get from I want that thing to
getting that thing and I think
snap can make that a whole lot easier and also make it so that you can
Have the latest version of stuff up to date all the time on your system and that that is compelling for a lot of people
Yeah, extremely and I know every year
I talked to Frank about this problem from own cloud and this I'm really curious this year to say
What do you think about this? What are your thoughts on this?
I know they're relying right now on the open source of build service
And so one of the things that we kept going around and around about is
This seems maybe like a little bit
Too late. Oh, it seems like maybe this should have come about but if you look at the origins of where snap packages
were originally created for
There is almost no no route to here without having gone through the Ubuntu phone
process, right
Yeah, we learn a lot from click packages on the phone and click back. That's click packages. Thank you. Yeah
Yeah, so, you know, it's like I'll give you a good example. There's a developer
who
created a game for Ubuntu phone called balls and
Hits, it's an SD. It's written in SDL to it works on the phone and
He cranks out a new version once maybe twice a day
Wow, he can just push a new version to the store and
It's on his
Customers handsets or his users or whatever you want to call them that the people who play his game
He can build a new level in 15 minutes that he has to work on his game
He can build a new level crank out a click package shove it in the store
Then thousands of people have it straight away, right and and so that works great on the phone
But you know you and I both know I'll give you a little secret, right?
We don't have millions and millions of phone users, right?
But we do have millions and millions of Ubuntu desktop users. So
Take that technology that we used on the phone to deliver
Applications super fast to the users on the phone and bring that to the desktop
Then all those millions of users can potentially have super up-to-date packages
With all the lessons we've learned from the phone. Hmm. I do like that
I feel like it's one of those things though. We won't see pay off for quite a while though
Potentially, I mean we're working on tools to make it easier. So like, you know, we're all working on
Snappifying we call it not formally. That's just like a stupid term not snapcrafting or
Yeah
There's not a verb for it really snapping
Yeah, you don't want to snap. Yeah, so we're all working on
Yeah, snapification sounds good. It sounds very George W. Bush
And we're all doing a bit of that to iron out all the kinks and figure out you know
Because every application is different and some things need have different requirements, right? And because of our security model to ensure that
One application can't stomp on the files of another or you don't get one file
You know
Able to access the data from another application and like send your key presses elsewhere
Yeah, there's the security side of things is
super critical and
We're just discovering the edge cases of you know, what each application needs in terms of security
We're snappy and so we're pushing the boundaries of that trying to make sure that we're getting all that done
So that when a developer comes along wants to snap if I they're crap
It's already full. This is this is something that I want to talk to you about
because I
was just
arguing with Noah that
one of the emails we get all the time on quarter radio and one of the things that Mike has run into is
He says right. Okay. I'm gonna develop for a boon to I'm gonna go
I'm gonna release an app for the Ubuntu desktop for Ubuntu users, and I'm going to use
Which SDK which tool kit which back-end language and I distribute it to my end users with reliable
Secure updates how?
Okay, so if I want to distribute for Ubuntu reliably via software update
How do I do that?
And if I'm just say just say I'm like salmon the developer of your favorite application that's available for another platform
That just has decided now's the time to target the Linux desktop. How do they how do they figure this out?
They either a somehow get it submitted to Debian
Downstream so it gets included in the Ubuntu repos and thus gets updated when they're set up
They figure out to how to create a launchpad account and create PPAs and publish their own repo
They figure out how to package a deb file or pay somebody
Which is a common thing that developers do is just hire some guy or gal to package a deb file for them and
Then they post it on their website, which then means you don't get to take advantage of any of the built-in package management
Nope
Check back. And so, you know what Mike and I have kicked around a ton on Coda radio is this is a shitty story to tell
Developers this is just this does doesn't work for them. They they can't they can't bank on that. They can't take that to the bank. And
And so I think that the snap packages is probably the best answer to this and I think it I think it answers a bigger
Question than we all realize is being asked. Do you agree with my sort of rough assessment poppy?
Right, and you know for for a slow-moving free software project
There's a good argument for you should put it in Debian or a you are or wherever sure that yeah
That hits the most number of free so that's not really practical for a lot of people
They're maybe bringing something over to the Linux desktop for the first time
Right and and and that's just one, you know method
I'm just trying to say that putting it in Debian is not a good idea
I'm just trying to say that putting it in Debian is not a not inherently a bad thing, right? There's nothing
There's nothing inherently if you could do it. It's great, right, but we've seen or if you can find a
Debian developer to sponsor your
Whatever the process is but we've seen recently friction in Debian where an upstream developer
wants
more recent versions of their application in the distro and
The Debian policy doesn't allow that to happen. Right? You're referring to the extreme saver thing, right and and so
with with a system where the developer is put in control of how they distribute their code and
With automated reviews and sandboxing these three things put together
means that
Developers are happy because they can distribute the version of their software that they're happy with when they want to
Users are happy because they get the latest version of crack that they want and users are also happy and sys admins are happy
Because the system is secure because the apps are siloed from each other
So it seems like a win-win-win all the way around our brown
I wanted to give you a chance to jump in because uh, uh, also
I mean, we've seen this play out in a lot of instances
But own clouds are probably one of the more prominent ones. Wouldn't you agree?
Yeah, um, they're a pretty good example of of one of those
Yeah, um, they're a pretty good example of of one of those projects where yeah, they're they're really well in the case of the
The debian one. It wasn't just a case of not able to get the version in there
But also the debian developer putting in what own cloud considered was an unsafe upgrade path, right?
Now, uh richard, I just want your frank opinion not even as a representation of susa, uh, just as a representative
As a representative of the linux community
Do you bang your head against your desk? Do you facepalm a little bit when you go guys guys guys?
We've got the open busus a build service. It's working great projects like own cloud are using the hell out of it
Don't reinvent the wheel of snap packages. Just put it in the open build service
Does it is there is there a facepalm moment for you or or do you see it in a different light?
I I there there is to a large extent when you mix in the wouldn't you mobile thing?
There's maybe a case to be made there, but i'm i'm not sold on it though
hmm, yeah, I
This is where our debate was going. I see uh in in the living room and and uh, no
No, I don't know when we talked about it. My my my take was
See, I guess it's i'm of two opinions because snap packages on their own right are are pretty slick technology
And a pretty great idea and something that I think
Pretty much anyone who's new to the scene? You can look at how to build these these things how to how to write the description file
And you're gonna get it. It's it's gonna be easy
I love that a lot and it might be familiar for how you're doing packaging things for other systems already. Yeah
Yeah, so that I I just I i'm pretty jazzed about it in in the big picture at the same time
um
I don't want to say this in a flamey way
but if if if ubuntu would have just if if we could have gone if it could have gone like this like what what if
It could have gone like this like canonical would have been like, all right, we're gonna go focus on mobile for a bit
So, uh, what we're gonna do is if you want to worry about getting desktop software on
uh on our desktop
We're just gonna hook in with the open open source to build service
And we're just gonna we're gonna hook in with that and that's what that's gonna be our sort of our official avenue for getting software
on our desktop and I feel like that would have
Been a game changer for desktop linux because instead of now getting packages bundled for debian and ubuntu out of the goodwill of
The developer it would have been a standardized method to deliver tech software to the linux desktop
What guarantee would canonical have had that the open source?
So it opens his bill service would have kept their values and their priorities in mind
Besides the fact we've been doing it for 10 years now. Well, i'm so I guess what i'm trying to say is
You know canonical has canonical invented the you know, the ppa system and the
Better for better for worse. They have these devs that are available on on the download
But that was at the time that that came out
That was far and away better than anything else we had had on linux
And so I think it's a little unfair to say that because other competition has rose up around them
And they are now taking those steps to advance it. I think it's a little unfair to say well all of a sudden
Canonical has just done it all wrong. And I guess no, I have that and I don't want to I don't want to come across to
Saying they've done it all wrong because I don't I don't agree. I think that ppas were a decent addition
And so here's where i'm coming from on this and and just just really quickly is uh,
Seuss martin in the uh, linux action show subreddit said sorry chris. No offense
Which is always it's like about to say something offensive. Yeah, I think it's a little unfair to say that
It's about to say something offensive. Yeah, I just I just pissed in your flower bed. No, not to upset you. Uh, anyways, uh,
but uh
That was not a review more like an hour-long monologue about how bad ppas are
And I want to stop right there. I I actually think as far as ppas go if they're not an awful system
I don't think it's that bad
I think it was a good addition when ppas were launched a long time ago
I'm trying to look at wikipedia to find out the date, but they don't have it 2009
Thank you
It certainly filled the need right? Yeah, this was solid in 2009 great idea
2009 is too long ago now and it needed to be iterated on continuously since then and what happened in my estimation
Is it just didn't become a priority?
And then the cloud took off and then rapid software development took off and people start creating entire applications that run on the web based on
node.js
And plugins that can be completely revoked. Yeah, you know what i'm talking about
And in days they have a new web application and then in months they have iterated three times and all of a sudden
we now find ourselves in a world where
unarguably openSUSE were the leaders
Where fedora has a very competent solution where arch has a crushing lead with the user repository?
We now find ourselves in a world where ubuntu is behind in this regard. I'm not saying ppas are bad
I'm saying that if we could have switched over to another solution by now
I like the build service just as my personal one. Yeah works well
We would have fundamentally changed how software is distributed for linux the answer for developers that I talked about earlier
Would have been target the build service
With clear documentation a large community and it would have made available to just about every damn distro on the planet
Now i'm very excited for snap packages
But at the same time I kind of feel like it's too little too well not too little but it's too late
Go ahead rotten
Well, I just want to say that the the
The problem with the dev files is not necessarily
The devs is we we can't have like devs kind of suck. Like if you think about it, there's
You you unpackage a deb. You have three archives and then you have another archive and set up another archive
They're they're kind of annoying to do
And I think anybody who's ever packaged a deb would would agree with that
It is but the problem is that the dev files are also a locked down structure for the just the linux
Entirely the ecosystem of linux is either stale stable releases or rolling super fast releases
You really can't have this. You can't have rolling applications sitting on top of the stable
stable core because
Those depend on new toolkits that are constantly being updated
So if your new application requires on a toolkit that this is not available
Well still having to but snap packages
I know that's the point. That's what i'm saying snap packages
Like they're not too little too late because we still even though even the open super boost build service is awesome
But it still has the exact same problem of the of the core. Yeah, uh packages not being updated. All right
Okay, okay. Okay for that. Okay, you the snap is it's i'm excited for the snap because it
Let me okay. Okay. That's a great point rod. Let me punt this to richard. So richard, uh, you mentioned in the chat room
You know a build service been around longer than ppas
What is your sober estimation of why it just simply hasn't been adopted then because it's clearly a competent platform with solid technology
Behind it yet. Here we are
Fedora has copper arch has aur
uh canonical is developing snap packages and and and
I guess I also you gotta you gotta admit the system they've developed is more modern. You know, it utilizes containers
It supports read-only file systems. It it pulls in directly from the project's upstream build services. It's very compelling
what is your sober estimation now of perhaps why this hasn't been adopted more widely and maybe if there is some sort of
perhaps modernization that now needs to take place with the build service or maybe
Not i'm curious now where you think this thing stand
Most of the features you stated have been in the build service for some time like for example refreshing the stuff direct from upstream
We've had that feature for so long. We've just rewritten it in 2.7, which we just released nice
So there's there's you know that that that's always ongoing that's always improving
Um, why wasn't it adopted? I I think that's typical not invented here syndrome. I mean if you look at most distributions
They're they're gonna trend towards their own tools and there there isn't many projects besides open suzer who kind of hits this approach of
We're going to build our tools for ourselves and everybody else as well. Why don't you come join us and
I I wish more distributions took us up on that offer. It's still open. It's still there
We're not going anywhere. The build service is still being developed. So
but but you know distributions have to get over this hump of
We know best how to how to build this stuff. It's it's not necessarily true
And even if it is true, I think we can do really exciting stuff when we do stuff together
And there's only yeah, there's not many projects that take that mindset
Popey how important is the ubuntu brand behind this idea?
So I know one of the things that so my fair estimation of the emails I've gotten is if I told them
This is the canonical recommended path or the ubuntu recommended software distribution path
And this is the open source community solution
They actually would be more inclined to go with the ubuntu solution simply because of brand name recognition trust in the in
in sort of a long-term investment there and
It's simply more familiar with how they expect things to operate on proprietary platforms
And so we are sitting we're saying oh you could have done the build service. There's a ur out there
But in reality, how important was it? Do you think that it was actually a solution from within?
How do you mean a solution from within well, why not how do you think there is serious technical and and obviously
Tactical advantages to developing snap packages versus using somebody else's solution
So snap packages service a need that we've identified that developers need
And that our customers want
And I i'm not sure
That other platforms do provide that I mean it's quite obvious that
other uh, non-linux platforms are trending towards that with the way android and uh chrome silo their things and the way
The windows, uh app store is going and the way the ios app store
Everyone else seems to have figured this out and is going in that direction
We're doing the same thing
But in the linux environment i'm i'm not sure do you think it's so when we're looking at this
Do you think it's a fair perspective?
To say this is a solution for the ubuntu platform. And this is something for ubuntu platform customers
Well, it's for it's for our customers and for free software and proprietary developers
It's sure i'm not saying it's closed source. I'm just saying like it's it's developed for people that are in the ubuntu ecosystem
Which is based on linux. It's not saying that there's not linux involved
But it's simply there are people that simply they deploy ubuntu workstations. They deploy ubuntu servers
They have an ubuntu cloud and so they're looking for things
That are yeah, I see where you're going, but I I don't see I don't see how
you know as
as
Someone who's been an advocate of ubuntu for you know, 10 plus years. I don't see why I would think anything
Other than this is for our users and customers and developers. Well, you know, what what else would it be for?
So I actually see a bigger point in here. Okay
It's it's like for the last part that you mentioned is like
By that principle canonical wouldn't use software developed by other open source projects and they completely do so the name is not necessarily the thing
The fact that canonical uses for those that care about the branding would be enough like canonical says we're using obs
Then it will be enough for those that want the canonical support
on it because if canonical picked it is because it's in line and those that are trusting a brand name will just trust it anyways
I guess the problem of the lack of adoption has to do with the strategy on the outreach the open source has had
Over time versus the other distributions arch has a core users that they target
Open source that wants to be so impartial. So
So generic so to allow everyone that suddenly fails to capture in each group that will be uh, evangelist about it
So because there's no evangelism about it people just think it's oh, that's a nice thing and it doesn't get out of the nice thing
And someone that has evangelists and has people pushing forward the technology in terms of vocality about it
We'll get to have the perception even if not the usage at the time
Vocality about it. We'll get to have the perception even if not the usage at least the perception so that it's wider
uh
You know what? I hadn't thought of that wes. How much do you what do you think?
Do you think maybe the reason why the aur and things like that have more buzz is because it's the arch user
Repository and the build service is targeted more to just those practical developers that want to pump out builds. And so
There's no hype machine
That is probably a good point. I mean
Yeah, especially like with the with the aur, you know, the users are directly involved
They're picking people to maintain the packages not always the developer. There's there's the comment system
And you know, it is a little bit harder to get involved with the build service
So that's a good that's a good point. All right, no at the end of the day
Here's the thing
The practical real world implementation is it's still if you wanted to play software on ubuntu
It's going to be your best bet. Don't you agree? I mean you still think
I I might I might say other services and other systems and other projects have better technology for developing and delivering and
updating software
But in terms of day-to-day practical use out in the real world deploying for clients
Where's ubuntu at? I think that and I think we hit on this
Maybe we should have clicked on it, you know on sunday
And I don't think we necessarily honed in on this
But one of the things that came up in a discussion today was that you know
I'm looking at this from a perspective of
I am a person that maybe was previously using windows or maybe i'm using macos and now i've come over to linux
And so I am going to cherry pick the applications that I was formerly comfortable with now if you had somebody
um
Like myself who will be available oddlinux, press northwest switching people to linux
Like I maybe have done
What would you say three or four times every place we've gone and had absolute 100 success rate if you have something buddy like that
Then that person is already switching you over to those linux applications while you're on windows
So your transition is easier. However, if you don't have that you boot into linux for the first time and you say
I need my friend to help me you download team viewer. You say I need to uh,
To you know to what was the other uh program I was talking about today is team viewer
And what was the other one that bit me? There's another one is proprietary and I hate mentioning it all the time
Virtual box for example, uh virtual box
Some of those applications
They work perfectly fine on ubuntu right out of the software center or right off of if you install from the command line
But it might take a little tweaking, you know, and another one comes to mind my ubiqui
Ubiqui works basically right out of the box
I just plug it into my computer and I can use a smart card reader right off of ubuntu
On arch I have to install a package and configure it now
That's not a hit on arch daemon and then configure it
Now that's not a hit on arch because arch is a configurable distro and you know that going into it
And so there's probably somebody out there that didn't want that smart card daemon running
and so they rightfully so don't have that installed and configured by default, but
I don't think it is fair to say that coming out of the gate ubuntu is the hardest distribution to install packages on
unless we take it to the level of
Here's the entire app ecosystem and the majority of these applications are you know
Aren't going to be available on ubuntu for a couple of years
And they are going to be available on arch if you look at it from that lens, then I think you're right
but but I think for the practical lens of these are the software programs that that i'm using and I am cherry-picking a couple that
Come to mind because i've had problems
In a day-to-day basis what I found is oftentimes I find myself having to tinker with arch to get it to work
You know for a daily use case
I think I think my opinion about it is uh is sort of I actually agree with you in some levels
Ubuntu is going to be out of the mind when they package virtual box
For example, or maybe let's go with your team viewer example because that's a little more esoteric
uh
When you install team viewer on ubuntu
That package maintainer made the decision. He said hey, you know what while I still have root permission on your service
or while I have room while I still have root permission on your linux box because you
When you executed my install script here, you gave me root privilege
While I still have that root privilege i'm going to go ahead and i'm going to start
This remote listening service as root and i'm going to go ahead and tell that to start every time your system boots
I actually think that's probably the right decision to make on a user-friendly distribution
And you want to install team viewer to get help
You probably want to receive remote connections. That's probably why you're installing team viewer, right? I could also
Very clearly understand why the arch package you're said, you know what maybe not i'm going to do the absolute minimum thing
I need to do while I have root privileges and i'm not going to touch your system any more than I have to and if
You want to start that daemon you can use system ctl enable team viewer dot service or whatever
Dot service or whatever it is and you can have added haas
And i'm going to be gentle while I have root i'm going to respect your security, right?
I can understand both perspectives
This is a wacky example. Actually, this is really a wacky example
You're implying your implication is that someone who's packaging a deb is somehow
potentially nefarious in in their
In no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no
Somehow that a arch arch packaging
One is developing for end users one is packaging I should say for end users and they probably just figure i'm going to make it
A little bit easier and one is packaging for a linux enthusiast and you know what?
I'm not going to make it easier for the enthusiast. I can understand both perspectives
I don't I don't think that makes one easier to install than the other I think what makes one easier to install than the other
Would be software availability and what is availability in your repository?
tie and if I can do packer dash s install team viewer or packer dash s virtual box or packer dash s heru pad and
I know with absolute certainty that I'm getting the absolute latest version of that package
And it's going to continue to get updated by my package manager in my estimation that is easier than other
Well than Ubuntu so that one packet you you're saying packaging for the Linux enthusiast
You're aiming for a target that has like half a percent of worldwide PC sales
If that right is that is that where you want to target or do you want to target where?
Real people spend real money on computers that I have us on them
Don't don't understand
I completely agree if I'm gonna target if I were gonna release a desktop Linux
Application that I thought would be great for web developers or people that are developing Android
Applications or anybody that wants to get worked on on Linux my primary user base would be Ubuntu
And I would do a PPA if I could absolutely
But my point is that doesn't the goodwill of developers and how they have assembled their packages does not
Excuse the fact that the platform itself does not provide a better means for sustainable software
But if it wasn't for the ease people wouldn't want a wart if it's exact a wart is just trusting
You know these can give people also packaging things that you are going to try to run exactly
You know what? You know what? I'm sorry my my my long time experience with the community is in whole
I I actually trust the community more than I trust any individual company and the AUR has a vote system
It has a comment system. It has a self vetting system
I I wish I could divorce the AUR from the distribution wars thing because I just want to talk about it in terms of a software
Delivery platform that's why I started this conversation with the build service
But the reality is I actually think the AUR provides a better example because it's user powered and then it's community vetted and it
Allows for me to go in with a certain level of confidence
I'd like I like me able to come on to the show for Linux action show into a desktop app pick and say
You can install this package and I had to drop three really really really really great desktop app picks last week
Because I couldn't come on the air and say this is how you install it on Ubuntu. I think that's a major bummer
But how many of those three were because the person hadn't provided a 1604 version yet?
All of it none of none of it was version specific none of the issues were version specific at all
None of it was it all was a matter of packaging and availability and repos and and all of it in every single
circumstance was available in the AUR and it just it just struck me as this glaring and the thing was is
You know one of them was like a two-year-old drop-down terminal that just never made it into downstream Debian or upstream
However, you look at it, and I just kind of felt bad because you know they're creating something really great here
And one of them was a chat program that I just mentioned earlier that
And what was that program no I had to build from source
And I actually started to write up the instructions
And I was just gonna give people and here's the other problem is it was an Ubuntu review episode
So I wanted to make sure that the Ubuntu the desktop app pick could actually run on Ubuntu right because that'd be a pretty jackass
thing to do
And so the good news is that's the thing we're fixing
Exactly yeah, right. I love that. I think and I agree, and I think that's why even though
It's not something that's already existed. It's still a very valid solution. What do you think Noah?
I
Think my tummy hurts
As soon as you said that he asked me like I told you so I told you that's I've told you all morning
That's what they're fixed. That's why I'm doing this house. I keep saying I think that I mean you know really
I think we're kind of going in circles
That's what I think but I think that I think we've gotten to a point where we have addressed that there is a problem
I think we all agree that there is a problem and that there needs to be a new solution
I think we've also all agreed that canonical has addressed that solution and
has or has addressed the problem in is formulating a solution and that really I think really what it comes down to is you and
I fundamentally disagree on if you think if if the software is available in the OR even if you have to tweak it
That's better than it
Just not being available and I would personally argue that it as far as easy
Installation even if I have to go to a website and download a deb that may not be as secure
And that's not a great overall system, and yes it may or may not screw other distros because it's occupying developers time on a specific
distribution, but I think that that provides a fundamentally easier way to get at you know linear in application running on a given distribution well
I definitely gives them more windows familiar feel I search for my installation thing I download it from the web, and I install it
I'll give you that I okay, so let's move on
Yes, that is true
But I want to move on because I don't want to bore people with this whole debate
I want to talk about some of the things that have actually already been sort of fixed up since our review, but
Honestly poppy. I'm really genuinely curious about your thoughts on 1604 it to me
It feels like one of the biggest releases for Ubuntu ever and I'm curious if you feel the same
Yes, I do
Honestly, that's it folks. You know no to you
I'm really what do you think that means in terms of long-term long-term impact of 1604?
And I'd also if you're willing to share with class why you think it is that it if it beyond snap packages
So we know that the vast majority of our users stick on LTS releases like significantly
like double-digit percentage higher
People stick on LTS is they don't
Generally our users don't want bleeding edge. They don't want the very latest
Colonel they don't necessarily want the very latest of like lib C or whatever wacky library
They just want something that's reliable and stable isn't going to change when they boot it up today from when they booted it up yesterday
So LTS is always important to us
But the flip side of that is app developers are changing things and chrome changes
Frequently chromium changes frequently and other applications that people depend on change frequently. And so I think
1604 could be one of those quite long-lived versions of Ubuntu a bit like the
Maybe the Windows XP of Linux. Yeah, I was gonna say 10 around I was gonna say 10 of 4
I still run into some 10 of what there's oh I do do you run into 10 of 4 still? Yeah, I do
Doesn't make me happen
with with with snappy packages that have the very latest version of an application which can override whatever
Core library is on the system without jeopardizing an existing
Package that's already installed right and not interfering with any other application that's already installed
That seems like that that could have the potential to live for quite a long time
Either that's very well put even though I said not about snap packages
You managed to put in such a great way that I completely agree and I'm willing to take the snap package answer
also, I think it's a pretty solid release because
Pretty soon a lot of S is gonna change in Ubuntu and if if people don't like the way things are going you can now
Say well just install 1604 and snap packages will keep you going while they
Right, isn't don't you think that's a guy so like, you know, you might say well
There's a unity 8 stuff is different and all these apps are different
Just install 1604 and shut your face
And it's gonna it's not gonna be in the past where you would say well, okay sure
But now I can't have X Y Z because I don't have GTK X or right that problem is gone
I think it's a big deal for that
Richard I wanted to ask you though. Honestly just kind of tingling in the back of my head here
Do you feel like when?
When a new when a new Ubuntu release comes out is the oxygen sort of sucked out of the room for some of the other
Distros because I see a lot of people talking about switching to Ubuntu open to this 1604 upgrade that and it feels like nobody's
talking about
anybody else
You know, in fact, in fact, we've seen a bit of a spike of tumbleweed downloads
I mean the servers were slow even because of it. Wow, we got it. We got a backer right there. We got a second. I
think I mean I just I'm saying that I experienced them slow and
It happened to be in the same time. He said about the spike. So all right
Well, we can't be in a bit busier than usual
I you know, it's funny because a lot of people we said hey Chris
Why don't you shut up and install tumbleweed?
That's a lot of people said in the in the comments a couple of things
No
I think you'll be glad to see fixed is the erase disk and install create and then create swap space bug that we ran into
That s has been fixed
Also a couple other little naglers have been fixed including a few other things we ran into actually
So I'm you know, and I'm glad I'm pleased to say that overall it was a pretty quick turnaround
You were you were pretty disappointed in this bug. Yeah, I was well
I prefaced it and I'll restate this I cannot really hold canonical or Ubuntu responsible for that bug
Unless it made it past release date, right?
Like absolutely tell you when you download it that you're downloading a pre-release software
It's not it is not fully baked yet. And so it would be wholly unfair. I mean
People start complaining about that pretty soon. They're just gonna stop letting you download it
Does it give you pause that it made it this far? No, not at all. As long as it's a liar
It doesn't it doesn't line hand to God. It gives me zero pause that it made it this far
As long as it doesn't make it past release I can hear you grouching just the other day about how you're really super
Disappointed that an LTS release like this has a bug that's gotten this far in the process and nobody noticed it
Hold on a second. Yeah, I was disappointed that it was an LTS release that had that that they that they would even consider shipping
With that book, but they didn't they fixed it and I don't think that that's I don't think that's at all fair like if
Especially it's coming from you like somebody who wants all these changes if you want companies to embrace
You want all the new stuff all the new crack
If you want all that you got to give them up until the very last day to fix
Just me that's that's not why rolling distributions are taking off like crazy. That's not why things like tumbleweed are blowing up
That's not why things like ours are continuing to see new users. That's not why things like it's just me
No, it's just you you're all your special snowflake
But but I just I don't know I can't hold them at all responsible if they fixed it before the release because here's the thing
If I would have downloaded out the day, then I would have just never even known. I'm not asking you that
Oh, what are you asking? I'm saying they did their job. They did a great job. They got the problem solved
Absolutely out of ten out of ten Noah, but what I am saying
And you just won't admit it on air is a little bit of you was disappointed that something like this existed and it and that it
Got this far and you won't admit that to you it felt like nobody was even trying to install this until we and other people
Started notice this problem, and you won't say it on air, but I know deep down you felt that way
I agree with part of that
I get I agree a part of me agrees with that when you when you phrase it like that
I guess I I'm a part of me agrees with it, but it's still it's just feels super
That didn't happen like it's I've installed it one two six nine four about six times. Yes
January and February all throughout the month. I didn't have that problem until I got here
Yeah, I got same here. Yeah, okay fair point. You know what fair pointer goes to rotten corpse. I didn't run it
I in fact we noticed
That I think about it
When we started to install I'm like I don't know I never ran into that problem man, and I've got it like on four rigs
Let's be you
He's told me he's like yeah, so you don't know how to install bunch. That's okay
Let the archers that come over here install a bunch you for you. I was that guy for a little bit
I will admit that I'm like always that
You can't help it because you're like I don't know wasn't me
I don't know what it's doing when I was in IT services. I was even the guy that said don't blame me
It's a hardware problem. I wore that shirt. I was I went all-in. That's why you're no longer in that
That is that's why I had to get out
So anyways yeah, it was funny to to sort of
One of the things that I enjoyed and I just want to wrap it up was I was all-in on Ubuntu Mate edition
During like my 1604 run that was my favorite spot to be so no one I basically swapped yeah
Yeah, yeah, I loved I loved me on desktop, but I mean in terms of
Well, I guess you know I had it here hooked up to the stream
I wanted a daily performer that was really sort of
Minimal that I didn't have to change a bunch of defaults
So that way stuff didn't pop up on the stream and Mate just nailed it
And it was a great experience
And I really like some of the changes that were made and so I was all about the Mate edition so and Noah
Traditionally because that's what he deploys for clients. I assume right is
Mostly a unity user plus. He and he'll sometimes he likes it because he can change the scaling etc etc right so we basically swapped
I said Noah you got to use Mate for the next day. I got to use unity for the next day and
No, I don't think you actually enjoyed it that much you you seemed like you were the feeling like it was sort of well
So in fairness to Ubuntu Mate I was running on on
Hardware that was giving me a lot of trouble and so that right off the bat created
I mean I spent the first 40 minutes, okay, actually hold on just a second this
This was your first hands-on with the Liebman 15
So I install a bungee Mate and I ran into the little swap here, and that was fine
I got through that but the real problem was
You know I spent the first 40 minutes trying to figure out how to turn off tap to click because I kept selecting text
I can't even scroll in the web page you also ran into problems with USB ports being powered. Oh, yeah, okay?
Backup, I couldn't even get the operating system installed because the USB ports half the time
They're powered and half the time. They're not I don't mean different USB ports
I mean a single USB port and I guess the answer is just to cycle the laptop numerous times until
Thank God I had a flash drive with the light on it because if I didn't I don't know how I would know if it's
Gonna boot or not
This is legit because I was trying I was trying different distros having a thumb drive that lights up when you add when it gets
Powered is very valuable information when you're troubleshooting this kind of stuff so half the time
There's no power the other half the time there is I'd say it's about 5050 so finally
I just keep restarting the computer until I see the light come on then I'm like well don't screw up because we got a good
One now and I get into and then I hit that installer error
Which was kind of a pain and so again not Mateus fault USB port problem not Mateus fault
So I restart another five seven times and 40 minutes later. I'm finally in the installer. Thank God
And so I'm clicking through and I get finally get the operating installed like fine good all right now
It's on to easier waters right well turns out. There's no touchpad driver
It shows up as a ps2 mouse, so I can't I have no
Are you saying this built for Linux laptop doesn't have out-of-the-box touchpad support $1,800 built for Linux
Laptop support and my my $500 system 76 was washing the walls with it
So it is I I can't scroll
I can't even
Research how to fix the scroll because I can't scroll and I can't type because I type three letters and it erases all my
Text I have to start all over again
so eventually I I drove to Best Buy and bought a trackball and then come back and
Seriously, and I'm working I'm working on this trackball trying trying to and I eventually research and find out not that they're this is
How I fix I I'm telegramming wimpy in the middle of his workday
Yeah to ask if they're why the touchpad support isn't in and of course he tells me what I knew he was gonna
Tell me which is it's perfectly in there if you have a touchpad well Ellis PCI showed me that the Libra um is
So I don't have touchpads, so I can't really size
So then the end of the night so I take it home with me back to the hotel
And I'm at the hotel and I start using it and that's when things kind of started to change
That's kind of when I started to see that like if I wanted a not changing desktop
Which I do like and I and I just wanted to get work done
And I didn't I and I didn't care for that doc which a lot of people don't
I can see Mate being a really really great alternative sure like that's that's just the desktop environment
What did you think about like the welcome stuff, and then they went to a tweak with me?
I am totally I didn't care about the mute that was not my thing. I mean if I was gonna have mutiny
I'd probably just have a
Traditional unity, but one thing I did care
I mean that software center that software boutique is so good. I will put it on every Ubuntu machine
I install from now on every single client that gets an Ubuntu installation from me will have that that that installation package that
Welcome package that is far and away
They should make that its own app store, and they should port it to like every well
Here's what it's that good Wimby isn't here right now, but here's a telegram. He sent me yesterday
He said he just pushed an update to Ubuntu Mate welcome
If you installed on another desktop flavor now the software boutique will appear in the menus
It was previously only in Mateia sessions. I got the idea while watching your review because we gave
We got the we gave the command to use to just launch the software
This is a perfect example of how Martin Wimperis does everything right?
No, I'm serious now. No now you think about what just happened. Okay? He listened to
You and I are not involved with the Matei project
And so and he he's not involved with you broadcasting and yet
I mean I would say he's involved quite a bit, okay fine fine, but as a member
He's not you know we don't get a paycheck
Yeah, so he is a community member and we because we are members of the same community and he saw on his own volition
Saw a problem that without we were having it really wasn't even a problem
He goes out of his way to make sure that it's going to be smoother from everyone if every
software distribution had somebody like Martin Wimperis on their team I
Agree because it's not what he actually did that's not what's the big deal
It's the fact that he kind of recognizes a pre problem and solves it before it's even a problem
Or you even have to ask yeah, and that's what I think makes the Matei edition of Ubuntu 1604 kind of special
Yeah, is and and I'm sure Wimpy if he was here would say that credit goes to a lot of other people, too
But I just it's all right Chris, I'm telegramming everything you're saying
Thank you
So that's why I wanted to I think that's what we sort of wrapped the review on it
But we kind of you know we got some grief for not mentioning Zubuntu and Ubuntu gnome edition
But you know
Talking about Matei talking about Zubuntu
your buddy
Mr.. Michael Arbel over at for Onyx
Did some benchmarking?
Let's see it. We've got some Ubuntu
1604 benchmarks, that's how you have to say it
Yeah like that yeah like that
For nice I compared unity is XFCE KDE LXD gnome Matei and
Open box in a head-to-head comparison of some classic open source games
Wes
Before I tell you Wes before I reveal Wes
Do you have a guess of which desktop environment, and we're not talking by huge margins here
Not big margins, but do you have a guess?
Which desktop environment perform the best?
for mr.. Lara bells
Benchmarks, I'm gonna guess open box. Oh, let's see here
No, I am sorry Wes that is not at the house
That was not a correct answer
Mr.. Noah, do you have a guess as to which desktop perform the best about you, but say
That's what I would have guessed
Anybody the mumble room have a guess as the disk as a desktop environment. Yes, go ahead Poby
Was it by any chance?
What you know?
No, it was not. It was not only because
It was actually plasma 5 fared very very well
Ubuntu gnome did not fare well because
For whatever reason the Ubuntu gnome desktop detected that the apps were no longer responding even though they were
Responding and kept coming up like the force quit prompt and just trashed performance
Otherwise Ubuntu gnome would have fared better. No ladies and gentlemen the number one performance desktop
Is unity
Are you serious yeah
Now this is only if you do not
Alter defaults if you go with a default install desktop and want to play games with the current 1604 flavors
Unity actually gets you that's a great job by a very thin margin
By a very thin extra three frames a second
Supposedly I guess
Unity will give you the best performance so there you go as much as much tersh talk as we gave
Tossed towards unity you know what I'm gonna keep it right here on my this
This is my this is my unity desktop here plugged into the production stream. I'm gonna keep it as long as possible
I made it with Kubuntu for almost a month on the live stream. I
Think I could make it for unity for two months at least
1604 I'm gonna lock it in now the only thing I could see changing this is I
Really want to demo a piece of software. I want to do a how-to or something like that
And it's just not available for Ubuntu which happens all the time
So yeah, yeah there you go if you want absolute performance be like me run unity I
You know what I haven't had the flicker problems anymore either
I started having the flickering problems when I hooked up my HDMI external and poppy
I wonder did that happen to you, too
Did you not have flickering until you try to a second monitor?
So I recently bought a new ThinkPad and yes
There's flickering and it's an upstream Intel video driver problem
Okay has been going for like four months see I had flickering once when I hooked up external HDMI
But I have not had a problem since then
So I consider myself lucky. I have a sky I did something that I promised myself
I would never do which is I rebuilt my own kernel, which I
Tried not to do that
Yeah
Patch one single line in the Intel video driver before and rebuild my own count before I was an Ubuntu user when I when
I was living the gen 2 life. I I was all about that. I was all about that
I just all the time
But since I since I started switching over to it basically every other distro since then I'm like, I just it's not
It actually is kind of my friends could can tell me hey
This is the line you need to patch and I patch it and then I rebuild my candle and now I'm no
I'm never ever moving off of this
This machine now becomes precious
Any any ideas of when that might actually get fixed ask Intel
Oh, okay. Doon. Oh, hold on. Who do I hold on? Hold on. Hold on. No, come on now. Come on
I wasn't ready for that. Who do I ask?
Intel I actually I'm still not ready. There we go
I'm so anyways, I'm just happy with my Ubuntu 6.04 install overall now that I have all my applications installed
I'm gonna keep it for a while. That's sort of my my ending thoughts on it. I'm gonna just yeah
I'm just gonna see how it feels. I'm gonna stretch it out
So Noah you you did a thing today you hosted tech talk today
What what? No? Yeah, it was it was great. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, it was good
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, you're gonna fly over every Tuesday, right? Yeah, absolutely
And so we stepped in the thing you and I you started it actually what you do this every time what I don't know
I legitimately have no idea what you're talking about
You're upset with me about a lot of things today
So it's kind of hard to pinpoint the exact thing that you're upset about in this specific. I actually think maybe I don't need to explain it
Maybe I should play it for the audience and then let them come to their own conclusion. You just tell me what you're talking about
Yeah, I could so I'm talking about the ending of this week's tech talk today, right?
You didn't you know, you started you started real strong
Well, um, you know what I like about you Noah is you're a hell of an improviser
Wow, there's that you you know, you like like if you're gonna be stuck at say like a Linux fest
Yeah, and you were gonna say have to vamp for like six hours on a live stream
Yeah, or like maybe the entire weekend of self. There's almost nobody better to be with then Noah like
Yeah, like oh, I'm a blabbermouth. Yeah. No. Yeah. I'm just an expert in my own opinion
If we were gonna storm a building and I like I really feel like you would have my back
It's like when we storm when we storm a stream. Yeah, you've always got my back. Yeah for sure
So in in traditional Noah style you just you had my back you rolled into this patreon, but I'm gonna play
There's poppy so there's poppy holy smokes. Why is why is that?
That was way too much poppy that was and why is he in why is he in the tubes of the youth?
He was in tech talk today. He was in tech talk today. I'm coming. I know what you're talking about now. Yeah, okay
I listen to tech talk today when I did I did but I don't know if I know what you're talking
I'm excited to see so basically hold on. I'm gonna play it. I want cuz I don't want I don't I don't know
Yeah, okay. I do. I figured it out. All right
like a day later a beer koozie shows up my front door and
You can get a beer koozie and random other gifts throughout the year. So Noah, you know, he's doing the tech talk today show
He's helping sort of direct attention to the patreon because it's critical to funding for the network
And so Noah mentions some of these things and I want you to just sort of understand how Noah is trying his best here
He's gonna come at this and he wants to build this up
but then he gets sort of towards the precipice of the cliff and realizes he doesn't have an answer and he's just got to make
Something up and he eventually winds up putting him and I in something that is going to be utterly
Embarrassing and perhaps completely damaging to our brand if you were to support not only tech talk today
But the entire network and you can do that at patreon.com slash today now, this is a way for you to show
That you care about the network and that you can hear he's thinking right there. You can hear him thinking
The network and if you're the kind of person that says I want less ad spots, I don't like ads
I don't want ads
I you guys are selling out to the ad
Advertisers because no all he talks about is is how many GSM ting cards he has and how many droplets he has on Digital Ocean
if that's you
Stop complaining and go put your money where your mouth is go to patreon.com slash today now
Here is a here is a special offer special special one-time offer and I know Ange, you know
I've known Ange for oh my god. He's gonna give something away
Totally totally sitting where West is sitting right now and she's just
Quietly panicking because what Angela and and she's completely right. She's thinking oh my god, whatever he's about to say
We have to stand by I actually I'm the one that's gonna have to do the work
And so she's thinking what what is he about to say this and I'm listening upstairs. I'm like, what is he about to say?
If I'm making this up on the fly, I don't have a special
If you if we if the current patron is at 562 so if people that people that's how many people are patrons right now
so if we can get to
Before we'll say you could tell he's totally making this legitimately trying to think how long could I realistically get it?
It's short enough time to make sure that it's evident that it came from this episode
Eight more people eight more people we get eight people to sign up before
Linux fest will say and that would show Chris that even though Noah has like staggered his way through this entire show
We got a couple patrons. So he actually did a reasonable job if we can do that. I will and this is where I'm
I'm sure yeah, what am I gonna do? I'm gonna do something. I'll do something crazy. You think about that?
I'm just gonna say you know, this is and right. She's trying to cover for you right now
So she did a great job pulling me through that episode. I appreciated having her here. I've been totally hosed
She's got good cover
Go go tech talk today
Forward slash today supports the whole network. But also if you do watch and filter and that's more your bag
You can support us there as well patreon.com Ford shots. That's a good idea. Yeah, so good content
Yeah, because we do I mean people do want to support in both places, but we understand you can't do that
But so as if you want to represent and support cheaper broadcasting you can do either one
All right
Here's what I'll do if you guys go over and we get up to five. What did I say 570?
Yeah, if we get to 570, I will wear a window shirt to Linux fest Northwest. Oh
Wow, I will wear a windows. You're gonna have to go find one, right? I
I will wear a Windows shirt to Linux fest Northwest if we can get the
570 well, so we could this is kind of where I start to crap kittens. I'm sitting upstairs and I'm like
I'm thinking Saturday and Sunday. We're on the live stream
I'm thinking we meet a thousand plus listeners and Noah's wearing a window shirt
I'm thinking all right, if we're gonna do this, we got to do this and salvage the I hope so
I hope that that chat room and the listeners come together and say we forgive you know for totally
botching this episode if you listen carefully in the background, you might hear me scrambling down the stairs and let me let me just clarify the
The can koozie that Noah received in the mail is for the swag level members. Oh, yeah, there's good patreon
Yeah, there's a there's a limited number of those. So just check out the different patreon levels on
patreon.com forward slash today and remember that you can submit your content for the shows at
And Angela hears me coming in the studio right here. She's doing good again. She's doing really good covering
She's gotten good at this show. So I'm at actually at this moment
I am bussing in the studio and I'm trying to figure out whose microphone I'm gonna take over
Talk today dot reddit.com. I was just thinking. Oh, no, if we I'm in trouble
We got to like 600 and then I'll wear a Microsoft shirt, too
Like both of us so eight for Noah and 40 for you
Well, if I'm going otherwise, I'm there otherwise I'm there to promote my brand not Microsoft
Yeah, so that brand being Linux action show at the Linux fest Northwest. I mean it makes sense, right?
We want to let Linux users know check with you before
Okay, I just think that'd be great what if we did it I or I'll wear an Apple shirt
So you'll wear a window shirt. I'll wear an Apple shirt
Okay
Hi, I'm a Mac. I'm a PC
You know the thing is we're gonna be on the live stream. Yeah in front of the cameras
What did I get myself into so I guess what was the number? All right, here's it's 560 right now 560 something
562 right now
562 so if we get to if we get to 600, which I feel like we should one up and just one more
Six oh what if you don't 601 601 we should do before doing this
Oh, I'm really serious about 601 otherwise. We're marking. We're I mean we're marking Linux fest Northwest 2016 coverage forever
I'm like we go out to after parties. We gotta wear that stuff
Calvin you know pissing on the
You can you can contribute at any level so
Even if it's just three dollars a month three dollars a month is why not even a coffee a month
Because I know I gotta go buy an Apple shirt of this
I might I might have one I might have one back at my house
Do you have like what do you have like one of the like the like the girl top cut ones that would be great
All right, so patreon.com slash today
We are trying to get to 601 patrons before a Linux fest Northwest
And we'll have some fun we can film Noah go into the Microsoft Store buying the Windows shirt. Oh, man
Oh, man, just to clarify just just to clarify before everyone freaks out because I see people freaking out in the chatroom
I see people freaking out about to freak out in the mumble room. I don't run Windows. I don't have Windows install
I'm not going to install Windows. I'm just gonna wear the shirt guys. I will be on I will testify to that
I'm more concerned about you in a girly top
Yeah, me too. I'm not concerned about that at all. It's better than him. I've seen him without pants on
Yeah, I know trust me well, I guess
Yeah, it's gonna be fun, I'm really oh I'm getting a call right now should we take it well yeah sure yeah
No, I don't know. It's a private number. I know we could do the thing but yeah
I'm gonna dismiss call because I don't know although I think I just turned on it
I think I also just turned on NFC and Wi-Fi calling so
Boy, that was that was a mess
So this is sort of our last moment of tranquility as we wrap up this episode of the unplugged program
I we currently don't have a live on filter planned because we're gonna start tearing apart the studio and
So we needed to get out the studio. Yeah. Yeah, don't worry. It's gonna involve more Linux. Yeah
Potentially a lot more Linux, and we will be making content out of that as we can
And and so check out the calendar Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar
But be sure to join us live on the weekend go over to jblive.tv Saturday and Sunday. No is gonna be there
I'm gonna be there Wes is gonna be there. No way the crowd is gonna be wild
I think it's gonna be the best Linux fest ever and the weather right now is ridiculous
Although if you're Noah, it's really hot. It's too hot and he's got allergies. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, that's nice. That's nice. That's that's good context. That's good context
We'd love to hear your thoughts on anything
We talked about today from Ubuntu 1604 all the way back up to the beginning of the show and did you know tomb raiders got?
The specs out. I'm really excited about that
Give us all your thoughts go over to Linux action show dot reddit.com and leave your feedback
for episode
141 I would love to have some clips and good stuff are unplugged from Linux fest
So if you're gonna be at Linux fest Northwest and it can maybe even get a little video of some of the sessions or something
Like that come see us at the booth and let us know maybe we can incorporate into a future unplugged
We'll get some coverage from our virtual lug
That'd be pretty cool
Anyways, we'd love to see you go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact to send us feedback Linux action show dot reddit.com to give us
Your stories your topic ideas and last but not least JB live TV you come over there and then you do a little bang
mumble in
That IRC room and you can get secret access to our virtual luck join us
There's basically no qualifications required other than have a solid opinion a great working microphone and figure out
How to join the mumble room by getting that info from our chat room. Hmm, and then you can start participate
in the discussion Wes
Tell people where they can find you on the Twitter's go ahead. Give it to him at West Bay. Oh, what about you?
Mr. Colonel it's working. They can find you at Colonel Linux. Hey, that's easy enough
I'm at Chris Elias follow the network at Jupiter signal. Those are useful resources as the fest is nigh
Thanks for joining us this week. See you right back here next Tuesday
You
Get it out of here
And
There we go. We're in Noah's the yeah
Windows has now bash on it. That's true. How did I know somebody who's gonna say no and make a great Windows user?
Hold on we've got our first submission for a Chris wears an Apple shirt now
Here's the problem in order to get this in time
I'd have to order it now and I don't know if we're actually get to 601 once you go back you never go back
Well, then it can just live on the studio wall
Mm-hmm
JB titles calm
You have totals JP titles. I thought I'd get more schooled by mr. Popey. That's what I was expecting
That's what I thought. All right. Look at that wimpy wasn't here, but he's got a title suggestion. I'll Pope. He's just a nice guy
Correct
So no, what was your impression right in lady jupes?
Why yeah your takeaway impressions
the
The oh jeez, huh? Wow. Wow fail
It's super nice. The thing I think that stood out to me most was
The concept like the total nomadic concept right like so when I am at my house
I have all of you know, I go we go grocery shopping once a month
We have all the groceries in the house and you know, the kids have all their toys
They'd have a bedspread that I really like on my bed. And when we go into our RV, it's
We've got a stock the RV for you know food that is gonna be
You know easy to take along easy to pack isn't gonna go bad real fast that kind of thing and
I we buy separate bedding that isn't terribly expensive because we know we're not gonna be in there a whole lot
and so
the ability to just you are living the entire week and I came and spent some time with you early last week and
Then all of a sudden. Oh, we're gonna leave and in you know, 30 minutes you push a couple buttons
You pull a couple hoses you unplug a couple things
and all of a sudden you take your house and bring it on to the interstate and now your house is rolling down the interstate and
That's awesome. Well, and he gets he gets like we get partway there, right?
and
Chris goes I'm hungry and just like we just stop his house stops in the middle of the interstate not in the middle of the
Interstate but you pulled off. There's actually it was like a historical pull-off area. It was actually kind of cool
No, no, no on the way down. Oh
Yeah, so we stopped actually was in front of a tire change start. I think yeah
You're kind of worried about it. But but so he pulls his house to the tires change store and pushes a couple buttons and his
House transforms. It's like transformers. He goes back from mobile
traveling down the road back into a house and then he walks into his kitchen and
His girlfriend starts making him a sandwich in the kitchen with the groceries that they I assume bought for the month
Is this some sort of paradise? Yeah
He eats us he gets out of his driver's seat and
And walks he wasn't in his boxers, but he could have been because he does shows that way so I was barefoot
Yeah in this version. He is in his boxers. Yeah. Okay. He's in his boxers
And so he gets out of his seat if you weren't there I would have been oh really?
Okay
so he has he had picture this no shirt just boxers and gets gets out of his seat of his driver's seat and walks over and
eats a sandwich and
chats her a little bit and relaxes and
Then he gets back up and goes well, I guess we better get on the road and goes back and sits down still with no
Clothes on I took a leak too. Oh, yeah. Yeah, you piddle a little and then sits back down in his chair
What's back and drive and then we continue on we never once left the RV on the way down there and we?
Like we didn't even it wasn't even really like a full like let's stop and transition into we're no longer driving anymore
We just basically stopped you push two buttons to like I don't know what you did
I suppose you put the jacks out and let the slides out
But like it was it was it was just interesting to be able to be to go from
Mobile to stationary to mobile
In under minutes, you know mere minutes
Yeah
And so and then we got to the our overnight spot
Which we just found happened to find on the internet on using all stays app and it was I mean like I would have paid
To stay here. Right? Yeah, so Chris was explaining that he has a trifecta. He likes it to be
Inexpensive he likes it to be close enough to the interstate so he doesn't have to spend a bunch of time effort gas
Etc getting out to the place and the third thing is
He likes it to be private and this place had all three plus it just happened to have like this little creek and it happened
To have a wildlife. Yeah, it was just a beautiful place
So we get there and then Chris of in his typical Chris fashion
Reaches under some storage bay and pulls out a grill and he's like this needs to be assembled
Where'd the brown man go brown man go to work and hands it to me and then I'm like but master I need to he's like
We don't have tools assemble with your hands boy. I'm like, alright
So I slave away outside putting the grill together and then we ignited it and you I had some of the best
Marinated grilled chicken this goes back to the fact that we just have our house with us
You know, we'd gone grocery shopping and had he had just thrown some chicken
She made up a marinade of like some spicy sweet chili and sesame sauce and stuff and just had it in the fridge
So we you know, we weren't sure if we're gonna get to cook anything
But since we had it we just threw it in the on the barbecue
So we we get after after after I slaved away instead assembly the barbecue
Then Chris walked over and clicked the chicken a couple times and made it into I guess. Okay. No, no, it's really good
It was it was actually it was actually some of the best barbecue chicken. I'd ever have well
I'm not really barbecued more of grilled, but you know, whatever
Excellent point no. Yeah. Yeah. Are you a believer?
I
Fall somewhere in the middle. Okay. All right, that's fair. So after eating some of the best grilled chicken
I think I never had then we curl up for a night of watching
Netflix and YouTube because just because you live in an RV apparently doesn't mean that you give up normal internet life
So we did that for a little bit and then just crawled up and went to sleep and the great thing is here's how I woke
Up, I'm you might say I'm a heavy sleeper, right, dude
Well, we have learned is which is great actually for RV living
No, you're a really good RV guest because when Hadid and I just needed to get up
We just got up started walking around made our breakfast just walking moving around Noah and Noah just sleeps through it all
You have to intentionally try and wake me up
But so I'm sleeping and I don't even notice that they're out
I'm just passed out and then the way I woke up was I felt us moving and I'm like, oh
We're driving down the road and then I realized like my arm is getting pushed like slowly above my head and I'm like
What is happening?
So I kind of like open my eyes and look around and there's Hadid with like an ear-to-ear grin and she's bringing the slide in
I'm sleeping on the couch that's on the slide
And so the slide is like moving in it like my arm is slowly getting pushed up and I'm like, oh good morning
And you know they've been up for a while and then so basically I just got to lay there for a little bit like
a lazy son of a gun and
we got on the road and started moving and when I was darn good and ready then I got up all the way and
And leisurely made my way up to the cab and said hello and hung out for a little bit and then went and had my breakfast
And whatnot, but to be able to live like that is
I don't know. There is something super appealing and I think the first thing is I'd really like to see a
Paradigm shift I would like to stop seeing people
You know demeaning those and looking down on people that live in smaller homes, you know
Like campers or trailers or tiny houses. There is a stigma
I think and I think that it's actually way more efficient and way more fun than people give a credit for yeah
Yeah, I thank you, sir. That's a good that was good. That was that was a good fun story
I loved I was so jazzed up about that boondocking spot that we found because it was
It was like three minutes from the highway, which is a big deal when you have a really large vehicle and you need to go
You got to go park
but you have to be really careful about where you end up because you don't want to end up down a road that you end
Up having to turn around or back up because you might end up having to back down a road for a mile or two and that's
Extremely challenging. So it's always kind of a stressful thing when you decide to go off in a town
You don't know and you just kind of go down a dark road because of course we decided to drive into the night
like we always do and
So when we found this place, it was so dark. I
Could tell there was a lot of space and there's a lot of gravel
There was some uneven ground and stuff like that, but it was so dark
I couldn't really get a didn't know what you'd found. Yeah, I couldn't get a perception of how big it was
And then when the Sun when the Sun came up it was like movie picturesque because we have a wind we have a couple of
Windows in our bedroom, but we have one window that that faces what's what side does the Sun rise on?
I guess we were parked that direction
So I guess we're our bedroom window is faced perfectly east and the Sun's the Sun literally came up and like rose in our window
In our bedroom, so we it was just this
Extremely yellow sunlight that came in and just blasted our bedroom with just gorgeous yellow sunlight
And that's what I woke up to and then when I came outside and realized that we had parked around lakes and ponds
And there were bridges and they were like there were trails and it was just really something and it was it was gravel
And so it was nice and clean gravel
It was you know you could walk around you weren't bringing a bunch of dirt into them into the rig and just just a perfect spot
And absolutely free they just have a three night max and the thing is is lady dupes has about 12 hours of battery
give or take and
then then a generator to cover any of the gaps there and the way the way the generator works in lady dupes is
It kicks on until the batteries are charged back up
Or if you're doing something that's extremely demanding electric electrical wise right have more look
Yeah, and then once you're done with either the batteries charged, or you're done with your demand the generator turns off
So you're not always running the generator. Yeah, so it's just basically a way to supplement the batteries, and so we're sitting there watching
Netflix and YouTube and it's all silent
It's it we're in the middle and like you got the windows open so you can hear like all the wildlife outside, and it was
Unbelievable it was it was kind of the perfect night to just start the road civilized adventure. Yeah, it was it was
Mm-hmm on the flagship of the Jupiter Broadcasting Network USS June