I was thinking about dropping the coming up
on this week's episode of Unplugged.
You know, I always like,
coming up on this week's episode of Unplugged.
The little pre-tease.
It just feels old.
You know, now that we got chapter markers and stuff,
like, I don't need to tell you what's coming up.
It's all right there.
Yeah.
You know, we now live in a post-chapter marker reality.
So I think I'm gonna drop it.
We'll see how it goes.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 297 for April 16th, 2019.
Welcome into Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's gearing up for the big Ubuntu 19.04 release.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
So I'm not doing the whole coming up this week thing.
I'm not doing it anymore.
We're skipping it.
We're not skipping it anymore.
We're gonna get right into the content.
So to achieve that mission,
let's bring in our virtual lug.
Time-appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
You want a lovely bunch.
Look at that.
Look at that over there.
We got Brent.
We got Elle.
We got Mimidus, Mini-Meg.
We got Neon Burner, which looks like Neon Burger
from where I'm at.
M. Mason's in there, Tech Mav, the project manager.
Turth and Wimpy in there, all repping our virtual lug.
And of course, joining us on a direct studio line
is the one, the only, Mr. Bacon.
Hello, cheese.
Hey, guys.
How's it going?
Everybody?
Pretty good.
I'm pretty excited today about Ubuntu 19.04.
Wes and I have been running it for quite a while
and have many thoughts to share.
And I have arrived somewhere
that I don't think any of you will expect.
I'm just gonna put it like that.
We'll just, we'll get there.
But what do you say we start with some community news?
We've got to.
We've got to, Wes,
because that's what we have lined up so far.
I thought maybe we'd do a couple like quick
like service announcements and then get in.
Normally we've been starting with birthdays,
but we're had a birthday, unless we missed one.
Did we miss one?
Raise your hand if so.
Is it, it's not anybody's birthday
in the mumble room, right?
Happy birthday again, Wes.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah, there we go.
No, let's start with just a couple of bits of like,
this is gonna matter,
but not a lot of conversation needs to be had.
First up is Red Hat is announcing changes
to their certified engineer program.
Currently the RHCE is a Red Hat certified
system administrator, R-H-C-S-A,
geez, I have these acronyms.
This, Elle could explain this better than I could,
who possess additional skills, knowledge,
and abilities required in data center services.
In the updated program,
we are shifting the focus to automation of Linux systems,
like administration tasks using Red Hat Ansible Automation,
and we'll be changing the requirements
for achieving an RHCE credential.
Yeah, all right.
So in the next set of this stuff,
there's gonna be a new course and then a new exam.
So Red Hat System Administration 3, Linux Automation,
which is basically designed for Linux system administrators
and developers who need to automate provisioning,
configuration, application deployment, and orchestration.
Basically, you learn how to use Ansible.
It makes a lot of sense, right?
In the age of the cloud, in the age of automation,
data center knowledge is important,
but this seems to have maybe a wider scope.
To me, it feels like what Red Hat is saying here
is having a comprehensive understanding
of the automation tools is just as important
as having a comprehensive understanding
of the operating system.
That's the implicit statement.
That's a big statement.
It's true.
I mean, I think the market feels that way,
but it's Red Hat kind of updating
their really well-known industry programs to reflect that.
Yeah, well, I mean, you just have a lot of systems
that you probably have to take care of, right?
It's not about one Linux server or two in an HA pair.
It's about all the ones that you have
in various data centers and cloud programs.
While we're talking about big corporations using Linux,
this is kind of an interesting one
that folks have noticed on the Google I.O. schedule.
There is a Linux for Chromebooks secure development track.
Learn how Chrome OS gives you a secure, safe sandbox
for the web, Android, and Linux
through Chrome OS design principles.
Yeah, that's right.
Ah, ha-ha, this session will also cover ways
to handle challenges to high performance
and trade-offs with safety.
Ha-ha-ha-ha-ha.
Well, that's something to watch.
So they're really going all in to position this thing
as a development platform.
I mean, they've slowly been piecing it together, right?
Every week, it seems like one little new piece
is added to Chromebook Linux app support.
Winby, I don't think I've heard your thoughts
on Google's moves here to clearly turn this thing
into kind of a Sputnik competitor.
Probably, I mean, yes, why not?
I mean, we saw from the OpenStack developer survey
that came out last week that there is 20-odd percent
of developers using Linux,
so wherever you can provide Linux to developers
is obviously going to be popular with developers, I think.
This is maybe my normal default reaction
for Google stuff like this,
but I am sitting a bit uneasy
after our conversation last week
about what makes desktop Linux, really.
Yep.
I'm less enthusiastic about this.
Yeah, I'm conflicted on this.
So we obviously had that conversation last week,
and there's a class of Linux devices
where you don't want to be able to do
all of those things that we described,
which is you express the ultimate flexibility
of the Linux desktop by being able to download,
compile, and boot off the kernel that you've just compiled.
That defines the true heritage
of Linux distributions in my mind.
However, if you're building IoT devices, for example,
you don't want to expose that kind of flexibility
to the device manufacturer, right?
You want to lock that stuff down and provide them
with a secure, updated environment.
And there's an argument to be made
for having a desktop environment
that kind of mimics that as well.
If you're only ever going
to be developing Android applications,
do you need all of the flexibility
that we see as an advantage?
Do you just need the ability
to install the development tools that you need
to create the development environment
that you need to get your job done
and then to go about the business
of creating Android apps or whatever it might be?
Does that type of developer actually need
all of the flexibility that we hold so dear?
Right, I mean, the same stuff when we talk
about the Windows subsystem for Linux, right?
And I think already too many developers,
Linux is a tool that you run on your servers, right?
You kind of view it as an environment
that I make for my application,
especially if it's going to be in some sort of container
or virtual machine.
So it's not necessarily the thing you play with
or are embedded in.
Yeah, so I'm being a little bit
of devil's advocate this week.
I'm playing the counter position.
The other thing is maybe it's just easy, right?
And then they're like, oh, this Linux stuff's
pretty handy and I like how it can do more stuff
than it can do in the outside application.
Maybe I should explore,
but that's going to be a tiny percentage realistically.
Once again, RMS was right.
I've never installed GNU slash Linux.
He just deploys it as a container and good to go.
So there is some buzz around video
that the Linux, the Linux, oh my God, I'm that guy.
Oh my God, I'm that guy.
The Linus Link.
Juniper Broadcasting, is that it again?
I never really said it out loud.
The Linus Link Tech Show, is that what it's called?
Linus Link Tech Tips, that's what it is.
Linus Tech Tips.
Okay, okay.
LTT.
Yeah, and I do actually watch from time to time.
I don't know why I just,
I guess I've never had to say it out loud before.
There's a lot of buzz though around a video
that they did recently around gaming on Linux.
The title of the video is Microsoft should be very afraid.
A noob's guide to installing Linux gaming.
It's actually a pretty well done video,
which is a nice change of pace in general
for this kind of stuff.
But they really made a pretty good sales pitch
for both Manjaro and Pop!OS in there.
But I would say they really kind of sealed the deal
right here towards the end of the video.
For Pop!OS and Manjaro,
and actually for a number of other distros
we didn't cover today,
the steps basically boil down to install the OS,
install Steam or Lutris, and start playing.
That's what makes these distros
especially enticing for gamers.
But while Manjaro is set up well
to cater to gamers out of the box,
it's not going to be as stable as a distro like Ubuntu.
And that's why Pop!OS and others like it
try to bridge that gap with updated drivers
while still retaining excellent community support
and stable packages,
which makes them a good choice for getting your feet wet.
So Emma, I'm curious what System76
has seen as response to this video.
So we've had thousands of gigabytes of data downloaded.
We had, since then we've had 18,000,
almost 18,000 downloads of Pop!OS.
It's very exciting.
Are you seeing higher than average,
like people sticking around now
that the video has been out for a little bit?
Like are the downloads still remaining high?
Yes, we're seeing about 2,000 per day.
The first day was about 5,000,
and each day after has been 2,000 or more.
So.
Wow, congratulations.
That is an achievement right there.
That is fantastic.
And I think, you know,
overall, the last few months,
I've seen more and more people talking about Pop!OS,
using Pop!OS.
It's becoming more and more
of a well-established distribution.
Well, thank you.
You are almost enticing me, I have to admit.
Yeah, I mean, I think, you know, there's a lot of effort
that's been put in there to tune some things,
and I think people are talking about that,
and other people are picking it up,
and be like, oh, I want that.
Why doesn't my computer do it already?
Yeah, and I've heard rumors
that there'll be a new installer,
that the new installer will support CFS soon,
and things like that.
So there's other advantages
that start to make it appealing,
besides just a few other things,
like maybe a new theme,
or a different way to encrypt the hard drive.
But there's other things that have been coming along
that really seem like a pretty good innovation.
Or at least a nice value add,
in a case like this, easy access to Steam,
and what not, that got the attention
of the folks over at Linus Tech Tips,
and I got it.
Good job.
Thank you.
And I just, I'm really happy to hear
that you guys have gotten some traffic from it,
and I'd be curious to know
what the Manjaro project has seen,
because the Manjaro got a fair amount of mentions.
They lean Pop OS, though, towards the end,
and I think for good reason,
especially for the type of user.
Yeah, for the video that this,
and the audience they're aiming for,
that's probably the best advice.
But the title, Microsoft should be very worried,
all uppercase, very, very worried.
That's pretty good.
Pretty, pretty good.
So that's cool to hear, Emma.
That's really cool to hear
that you got some downloads from it.
Hello, Mr. Popey, I see you sneaking in there
under the wire.
Oh, hello.
How are you doing, sir?
I'm good, thank you.
It's like when you sneak into class,
and then the teacher calls you out for sneaking in.
I saw you see me out the corner of your eye, but yeah.
I know you were just getting back
from the DevWan conference,
and so I just wanted to get your report
at the first ever DevWan conference, and how it went.
Wait, what?
Oh, I thought you'd just go with it.
Oh man, I actually feel a little bad
about giving these guys such a hard time.
At least I did until I read this blog post.
But before I read this blog post,
I was starting to feel like maybe I should go easy.
Like they've actually got some genuine.
I mean, it's not like it's a problem.
They're not hurting anyone by.
And they're finding a market.
And they're, you know.
If there are users and people who are happy to develop
and use the operating system,
then all the better for them to do so.
It starts out, the blog post starts out pretty good.
It starts, the conference took place in Amsterdam
in one of the rooms of a building
that is floating on the water,
and looks a lot like an anchored submarine.
This white submarine gives us home
to offices of dyne.org, D-Y-N-E.org,
a nonprofit foundation dedicated to free software,
art, and sustainability.
All right, okay, they got some pictures of food.
They say each day was filled
with lots of interesting speakers
and intermittent hack sessions
where participants got the chance to exchange ideas,
share knowledge, and plan future steps
regarding their role in the open source community.
But things kind of take a turn to the left
or to the right, however you, I don't know.
They just take a turn for the worse.
They go down a different route, Wes.
It starts around here.
There was an omnipresent feeling
that the people attending the conference
were superheroes finally being able to put on their suits.
That's one of many things that are in this post
that are very, very hyperbolic.
Now, I get what they're going for.
I get what they're going for,
but it starts to really kind of go off the rails
in the language here,
and I think this is why I originally gave them
such a hard time is the way they say things.
Yeah, I like this.
The submarine-looking building gave home
to an event gathering open source superheroes
and all sorts of magical creatures
because to quote the first Dev1 docs print,
software freedom your way.
We must apply thought and attention to software development.
We share responsibility as users and developers
of software systems to foster values of cooperation
in the spirit of science, human cultures,
and the diversity of life.
That's pretty bold.
They got a mission there.
They're a project with a mission.
I can't really argue with any of that though.
I mean, they really grandiose in the way they talk,
and if you're gonna do something like this,
if you're gonna fork Debian
and make a system-D free version of Debian,
you've really gotta have some fundamental beliefs
to be willing to put yourself
through that kind of hell and torture.
I will also say whatever salad that they're having there
looks delicious.
Yeah, I see a lot of cilantro.
I think it's like a nacho thing, Wes.
I don't know if it's a salad.
Cause look at that melted, that's melted cheese, right?
Oh, okay.
Yeah, I think it's a salad.
Look, then they got the plates with the cilantro on them.
They're really big on the cilantro over there apparently.
I'm down with that.
Yeah, I don't mind a little cilantro.
So speaking of ZFS, it appears that work is in way
for Ubuntu 20.04-ish.
And gentlemen, correct me if you know anything differently.
Michael over at Ferronix writes
that the ZFS undertaking is a huge effort.
And we really haven't heard much about it.
Although I was actually sniffing around
and I did see some status updates
about like testing and restoring stuff.
So there is actual work underway.
And it looks like it'll probably land
for the user installer in 20.04, the LTS for next year.
Feels far away, but really,
it's not that far and there's a lot to get right here
and you don't wanna mess it up.
Yeah.
Well, I've seen some stuff at company sprints,
but I'm not sure if we're gonna land this for 20.04.
Really?
I'll have to go away and confer with my colleagues
to be absolutely certain,
but I think this is due to land after 20.04.
Now the ZFS stuff or something else like a new installer?
Both of those things, I believe.
I see, okay.
But the work has already started
and I've definitely seen some prototypes working
and I don't wanna give too much away,
but there's some very interesting strategies
that are being used to deploy this and it's pretty nifty.
I will say that the time it takes to install
is radically reduced using this mechanism.
It's pretty impressive.
Ooh, okay, now I'm properly teased.
I also wanted to give a little plug skis
to TechSnap, TechSnap.Systems slash 401.
Wes and Jim did everyday ZFS,
just really, really good information about ZFS,
especially for everyday use cases.
Busted some myths,
covered some of the license and legality stuff.
You know, Jim just lives and breathes ZFS
and it's kind of a TechSnap tradition,
so I thought we should have our take on it.
I was gonna say that.
It is a TechSnap tradition, so yeah.
TechSnap.Systems slash 401.
If you want that, I enjoyed it.
I enjoyed it.
I did too.
Yep, you guys make a good team.
I miss doing the show, but you guys make a good team.
Well, that's the community news.
Pretty brief today.
Pretty brief today, so I think we should move on.
Move on with the rest of the show.
Let's get into a little housekeeping.
And for fun, I'm gonna do it
with a little music this week.
Yeah?
Yeah, just to kind of keep it going.
Just to kind of keep going.
Keep our house clean.
We do have a couple of things to talk about
in the housekeeping this week.
Yeah, get out, get it tidy.
First of all, big, big deal.
Linux Academy is doing a 299-year promo right now.
It's a 33% discount.
That's great.
Go take advantage of that
by going to linuxacademy.com and sign up.
It's in effect for about a week or two.
I don't know.
It started yesterday, and it's a limited time offer,
so go check it out.
Divide that by 12, and you'll be like,
okay, yeah, that's a good deal.
Very good deal.
Plus, they're launching a bunch of content right now too.
Now, Friday, Friday on the jblive.tv stream,
we're doing a little hangout.
We'll be doing it at 2 p.m.
Jupiter Broadcasting Time, that's specific.
You can get it converted to your local time
at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
Just hanging out.
We wanted to do some community interaction stuff.
We'll do a week in review.
We'll review some of the show clips,
expand on a little further, hang out, chat with the crew.
We're gonna try to have a lot
of the Jupiter Broadcasting crew participate as they can.
Just a little hangout session, jblive.tv,
2 p.m. Pacific this Friday, and hopefully next Friday,
when we'll have people in town.
Oh, yeah.
People in town can stop by while they're in studio
and hang out with us on the Friday stream.
Always a good time to join live, join the IRC room too.
Totes.
Speaking of Linux Fest.
Oh, it's coming up.
Yeah, and if you're coming and you're gonna hang out
at our Linux Fest parking lot barbecue,
if you're driving, consider bringing your own chair, please.
We'll have some chairs,
especially for those of you who are flying in,
because I can't expect you to bring a chair on the airplane.
But if you're flying up and you have the room,
you might bring a camping chair too with you.
Everybody likes to sit, right?
Everybody likes to sit.
And last but not least, very awesome,
our community is self-organizing
in the Linux Fest Telegram group right now
for carpools from the airport.
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Linux Fest.
Angela has made a spreadsheet
that people can put their names in
and time of arrival and all that date stuff.
And then people can organize and give each other rides.
That's happening right now in our Telegram group.
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Linux Fest.
And last but not least, Mr. Bacon's here with the job report.
We got a special community job posting, don't we?
Yes, we do.
We had one of our community members, Jacob,
reach out to me this last week on our Telegram,
which you can find a link to that
if you go to Jupiterbroadcasting.com.
Up at the top, you'll see a Telegram icon.
Click on that and you can join us.
But he works for a company called Simplot.
They're an agriculture company.
So they do a lot of work with farmers and such.
They're currently looking for
an infrastructure engineer three
to work in their Boise, Idaho office.
They go in to talking about what you'll need to do.
And we'll have this link posted in the show notes.
But you'll provide rock-solid platforms to run workloads
such as MySQL, Apache, WebLogic, Tomcat,
HANA, Docker, OpenShift, Hadoop.
All those things, obviously,
you can get training for on Linux Academy.
Maybe we have some Linux Academy students out there
that might be interested.
This would be a good place to apply.
I've talked to Jacob and he said that the team
is a really awesome team to work with.
So if you're looking for a job, this might be for you.
There you go.
Combining farming and Linux together.
Amazing.
That'd be pretty good.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
Go check that out.
Thank you, Mr. Bacon, for the job report there.
And that, ladies and gentlemen, is the housekeeping.
See, we got through it.
Good job, everybody.
Got through that pretty fast, actually.
I'm so proud of us.
I felt good.
That felt really good.
All right.
Well, I think this is why we're all
kind of in a rush today.
This is what we're really-
There's a lot to chew on.
This is what we're here for today.
Very, very much, very much so.
Looking forward to talking about Ubuntu 19.04, disco, dingo.
Everybody's doing disco, disco, disco, disco, disco, disco.
The new 19.04 release is a really big deal
for a non-LTS release.
In fact, I'd argue it's one of the bigger deals
for a non-LTS release in years.
In fact, even bigger than 17.10 was,
which was the first version that switched to GNOME.
And to give us some context,
while I feel this is sort of a big deal,
is I want to go back in time for a moment.
Let's go back almost two years right on the nose
when Noah and I were standing at Dell headquarters
covering the news that Canonical was dropping Unity.
So Mark Shuttleworth just sort of changed
the Linux landscape in a big way.
And I say that once we get into it,
I think you'll understand why I say that.
But what was announced was that Canonical,
starting with, was it 18.04?
Right, next LTS.
The next LTS, they're going to switch to GNOME by default.
And they will be de-investing efforts into Unity 8.
They will be sunsetting Unity 7.
They will be shipping GNOME by default
on the next LTS Ubuntu.
And the ramifications of that are ginormous.
There's a personnel ramification within Canonical.
And we actually ended up seeing shipping before 18.04.
It ended up shipping in one of the point releases
ahead of time.
And I think it is unquestionable that it has really,
it has really changed the Linux desktop
in the last couple of years.
It has been a couple of wild rides.
And while why I believe 19.04 is a bigger deal
than your average bear,
is because it is truly the release
that is the full net result of this new focus.
17.10 was the first go.
18.04 was a stable shot at it.
You know, let's make sure we're conservative here.
There's a lot to consider for an LTS release.
So this, you know, one more past that and...
And now with 19.04, you've got GNOME 3.32.
You've got Mesa 19.0, Linux kernel 5.0,
and the new default Yaru theme,
which gives it its own unique look again.
So Ubuntu looks modern, but unique again, and still.
And so I think it was these reasons perhaps
that you and I were,
I guess it wasn't just these reasons,
but it's these reasons amongst also all of the work
that's gone into GNOME Shell by Canonical,
by Red Hat employees, by Endless,
that have really made it much, much more performant.
And we had been watching the development of that,
you and I were like, we've got to try this.
There's just so much going on.
It kept feeling like it kept getting better and better.
Yeah, and we've been on Plasma at that point
for nearly a year.
A long time, yeah.
Almost, yeah.
And at least for me, yeah.
And nearly a year for you.
And it was just kind of time to like dip our toe
in the GNOME world again and see,
okay, how does 3.32 really shake up?
Like, is it better?
And you could just instantly,
instantly within moments of logging in,
notice a performance difference.
Animations were clearly smoother.
They just felt snappier.
Most of it is the things that you don't see.
It just is snappy.
Things happen quickly.
It's almost like there's the Joe style,
no transitions anywhere effect.
Yeah, and I thought, okay,
well, let's give it a go on Fedora Rawhide, right?
Because that's supposed to be a real GNOME showcase.
So let's give it a go over there
and see what 3.32 is like on Rawhide.
And it was pretty great.
It was quite great, actually.
Yeah, I remember you telling me that you were doing that.
Honestly, I know you, I know how much you like Fedora.
I expected you to be sitting out there
on Fedora for a while.
I did too.
But I will say this,
there are a few vendor modifications to the GNOME shell
that Canonical makes,
the combination of their doc and the Yaru theme
and the performance fixes that I think they've implemented
that aren't necessarily on Fedora yet,
kind of came together to make the GNOME 19.04 experience
superior, in my opinion.
And after running Rawhide for a couple of weeks,
I switched back to 19.04 and just went all in.
And I found the performance to be noticeably better.
Wow, and that is impressive.
It's funny to think about that we had two years ago
when we were first talking about this,
we were kind of wondering about what the future investments
of Canonical into the desktop might be, right?
Switching to GNOME, was this just gonna be,
we were like, is this gonna be a stock GNOME
or are we really gonna see something
that feels like Ubuntu?
And I think now we can say, we can answer that.
Yeah, in fact, going back in time again, two years,
you and Noah were sitting here on this very show
while I was driving up from Dell.
You lazy schmuck.
And we're pontificating on what this might mean
for future Linux users.
I think that it's gonna be a really great thing
for Linux as a whole to have the biggest manufacturers
of the desktop Linux operating system,
that being Red Hat and Canonical,
both of them working together
to form a single desktop environment.
And I think it's gonna be really good for the end users
because they're gonna have more freedom
to go from one to store the other
and it's all gonna look the same because,
hey, they're starting with GNOME.
And this idea that we'd see some real improvements
with everybody focusing on one desktop environment
was theoretical at the time.
But here we are two years later
and it's clearly had some great improvements for GNOME.
It's not 100% yet.
It has still crashed on me.
I'm gonna say, you've spent quite some time
on this here show talking about some of the problems
with GNOME.
And you had some shell crashes in 1904 as well.
Yeah, admittedly, I was kind of pushing things
to its limits.
I might keep Plasma as my audio workstation.
But the rest of the time, it was super pleasant.
And kind of, I might prefer that, honestly.
I might just like GNOME as everyday browsing.
It's kind of perfect for just, you know,
maybe a terminal, a couple of electron apps
and a web browser.
Where it doesn't need to be a mission critical workstation.
Mm-hmm.
It's not bad.
Not at all.
No, I really, it's snappy, it's easy, it's very intuitive.
And I like that I can just mostly, especially on 1904,
I can run the default.
I don't need to spend that sort of Plasma investment time
of tuning everything.
Right.
It just works.
I gotta give you a ding on that.
Because that is a big differentiator.
I just got right to work.
I really did.
I think I installed one or two extra extensions.
I like having the ping indicator up in my thing.
Yeah, that's right.
I like that.
And that might have been it.
That might have been it.
Yeah.
And I was good to go.
But 1904 isn't just the default release.
It is a ecosystem of flavors.
And I kind of wanted to turn it over to the mobile room
and talk with Mr. Popey and Mr. Wimpy about their thoughts
on the 1904 release.
Mr. Popey, I'll start with you.
Are you even trying out the betas anymore?
Or are you just sticking on 1804?
I was so excited about the performance improvements
in 1904 and other UX improvements.
I might get an opportunity to mention
that I upgraded two of my machines.
I've got a ThinkPad X220 and an Entroware Athena,
which is quite a beefy machine.
So I've got two ends of the scale,
one with an Nvidia GPU, one with an Intel GPU.
So I wanted to be able to see how this thing performs
on different chipsets at different ends of the scale.
And I love it.
It's really great.
It's so much better.
And I feel fine upgrading away from an LTS.
I'm usually the kind of person who sticks on LTSs.
On those two machines, I've moved.
That's the ultimate benchmark.
In fact, I want to come back to that very question
here in a second.
But you said two things I'd like to circle back to.
Number one, I'm curious to know what the performance
difference is like on Intel versus Nvidia.
And then I'm also curious what those other UI improvements
are that drew you in.
So I don't notice, really, a lot of difference
between the Intel laptop.
And it's a few years old.
It's like a 2012 Sandy Bridge i7.
So I mean, it's not a slouch.
But still, it's an Intel GPU.
And it's not a top-end brand new one.
And the Nvidia GPU is a 960 mobile device,
which is relatively common.
And it's, again, not the top of the range.
I'm not wimpy with 1070 Ti's coming out the wazoo.
1070?
I'm not a peasant.
Triggered.
Oh, man.
But the performance is comparable across them.
It's just the same.
It's the applications that are the problem now.
The shell isn't the problem anymore.
It's all these big fat applications
I'm running on top of them.
Sure.
And were there other?
You said there was some UI improvements, too.
Yeah, I've personally complained.
And I know many of our users did about some
of the UX of application switching
and the way the shell does application switching.
The alt tab and alt.
What's that key above tab?
In Unity land, we used to call it the key above tab.
Yeah, it's tilde, but it's not on a Mac.
It's grave.
Yeah, but it's not a grave.
It's a key above tab.
Oh, god.
It's, sorry.
But the improvements to the way switching windows
is massive for me because I often
have multiple windows for each application open.
And what I hate is alt tabbing between two applications
and being punched in the face by lots of windows
coming to the front.
I only want one of them.
And having to do a dance with multiple alt tab and alt grave
is just bizarre.
So we fixed that in 1904.
The desktop team fixed that in 1904.
I'll admit to being confused at first
because I got pretty used to the old admittedly
unintuitive method.
Yeah, yeah, totally.
And the sound panel is easy to use.
So it's a lot more intuitive.
Oh, I just love the new system preferences.
It's gotten so much better since I've used GNOME.
Yeah, GNOME upstream have done a really good job
with the redesign of the setting stuff.
And we're consuming that pretty much as it is.
It's great.
Now, what about you, Mr. Wimpy?
What are your thoughts on the 1904 release,
both from a Mat standpoint, but also just what
you hear around town?
Well, there's obviously, being a flavor,
there's obviously a number of advantages
that you get to inherit just by being based on top of Ubuntu.
So there's a couple of subtle things this time
around that are probably worth pointing out
that you might not notice unless you had it explained to you.
So everyone may have heard of or be familiar with WPA supplicant,
which is a tool to manage your Wi-Fi.
Yeah.
And the new hotness, maybe, is a tool called IWD.
So in Network Manager in this release,
you can optionally choose to use IWD
to manage your network authentication, which is good.
And that could well be a default in the future,
and that's one of the reasons why it's here for playing
and testing with.
And then a simple thing.
In the Boot Manager these days, you'll
find the Safe Graphics mode.
So for all of the different boot options,
you'll find a duplicate entry which says Safe Graphics Mode,
and that automatically sets no mode set.
And anyone not familiar with what that does,
that effectively sidesteps the DRM driver modules.
So if you have a GPU which is not well supported
by your kernel by default, you can
use that to get installed using a basic frame buffer
and then install your drivers after the fact
to get a working system.
And that's a small thing, but it's a nice little change.
So that's something that all of the flavors
get to benefit from.
In terms of Ubuntu MATE itself, it's
a bit of a dull release for us.
It's just bug fixes and finessing,
one of the reasons being I work alongside the Debian packaging
team.
They've got a release coming up.
Debian 10 is just around the corner,
and I've been doing all of the package
uplifts for MATE in Debian.
So we kind of put things on hiatus
because we've done this in the past
and made a right Horlicks of it where
we get this split of the versions of MATE in Debian
and the versions of MATE in Ubuntu,
and it all becomes a big pickle that we have to sort out.
So I've stuck alongside the Debian versions that are going
to be in Debian Buster.
I've committed all of my changes to Debian Git
last week for the new version of MATE,
including all of the fixes we needed
to do on some third party modules to get that stable.
So when we enter the 19.10 release,
we'll hit the ground running with MATE 1.22 from day one.
Now, I've been testing all of the flavors,
and I would just like to put a little hat tip out there
to the Ubuntu budget team.
That is a really, really nice implementation.
I was seriously impressed.
Yeah.
A great way to have a modern desktop
and run some GTK applications without using Home Shell.
Completely agree.
It's terrific.
It's really, really good.
I mean, it's been a while since I used it.
I think I last installed the 18.04 version, which was good,
but this version seems really bob on, really good.
So well done to the guys over there.
Congratulations on a fine release.
You should be very proud of yourselves.
You know, I'll also give a shout out to the Ubuntu release.
So I obviously spent the vast, vast majority
of my time on the Gnome Shell implementation of 19.04.
However, I have found it to be, it being Gnome Shell,
to be particularly challenging when I go beyond two monitors.
When I get into three and four monitors
that are like a DisplayPort over USB-C specifically, yeah.
That sounds complicated.
Right.
And so I grant you, it shouldn't be perfect, right?
I mean, it should be, but I understand why it's not.
But you like working.
Gnome Shell really kind of gets sporadic
about what monitor it's going to turn on when I boot up
and which ones don't get activated
and what orientate, because some of them are vertical.
And so what orientation is the screen?
And all of that basically changes every time I boot.
I never know what I'm going to get.
And maybe there's a method to the madness,
but I can't figure it out.
So after getting my feet fully wet on Gnome Shell
and really enjoying it, I think my inner Joe came out.
Everyone has one.
And I ended up installing the Zubuntu 1904 desktop.
And I have to say.
I'm kind of imagining you clicking over to the download
page and sneakily not admitting it to yourself
as you click the Download ISO button and install it.
I haven't even told you.
How could I?
He knew he was right this entire time.
That's amazing.
I have to say, it is extremely pleasant.
It is wicked fast.
It uses a tiny amount of resources.
All these things don't really matter.
I mean, that wicked fast matters.
But the resources, not as much, but it matters.
And yeah, there's things about it that are old school.
Like setting up my panel feels old school and stuff like that.
But once I have it set, man, like if it isn't just
set it and forget it and then just use your computer.
And just it's everything I got out of Gnome Shell,
but just straightforward and simpler.
And I really feel like it's a great recording workstation
desktop or a great workstation desktop.
I will very much be considering just switching my desktops
over to Xubuntu.
I mean, it makes sense.
It's been around.
Nothing needs to have changed except there's just
made steady improvements.
Now the question is, are there, and maybe Wimpy,
maybe you have an answer to this,
are there as many compelling reasons for me
to use 19.04 if I'm using Xubuntu?
Or should I just stay on 18.04 and use Xubuntu?
Because I don't think the XFCEs, I mean,
I didn't really check.
I mean, it feels like with XFCE it doesn't really matter.
It's, I just, I feel like it'd be the same XFCE regardless.
I think you're doing a little bit of a disservice to XFCE.
I know they are making the sort of steady march
to GTK3 only future.
And more of the component technologies
that make up their desktop offering
have been moved over to GTK3.
So that work is ongoing.
So and there's, if you follow Simon's blog,
this is a different Simon to Simon Quigley, obviously,
you will find that there's regular updates
on the improvements and new features
that they're adding to their suite of applications.
So, you know, they're going about their business
very methodically.
Yeah.
And not upsetting, you know, the Apple Car
in terms of, you know, how it looks and behaves.
You know, it's, I think Joe said, you know,
it was a comfortingly familiar when he installed 19.04.
It is truly a fantastic power user experience.
It is so simple, it is so straightforward.
In fact, not even for power users,
but just all the things I appreciate about a desktop,
it is that.
And no one complains that there are moving features.
I was very, very, very, very impressed.
So that brings me to the question
that Popey alluded to earlier.
Is it worth switching from an LTS 18.04 to 19.04
and getting back on that upgrade train
where you have to upgrade every so often?
And I'm wondering what your take is, Wes,
is it worth switching out, say, your laptop here,
which has Kubuntu on it right now, 18.04,
would you consider replacing that with 19.04?
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, for my personal workstations,
at least for ones that I touch every day,
let's say, or nearly every day, that's reasonable.
It's like a reasonable amount of work.
It serves as a good, you know,
good making sure that I have documentation
about everything that I know and need to install
on a workstation that I'm using.
And especially in the case, you know,
this time around with the GNOME improvements,
I like having up-to-date packages.
I used Arch for a long time.
I've been using Ubuntu more recently,
but I'm still that same Wes.
It is just getting to that age where it's like,
I could use a couple of packages.
Now, you do have to balance that, right?
Like, especially if you have like maybe a lot of PPAs
that you have to wait to tell,
they've got packages supported now with snaps
and other systems that's less relevant,
but it's still relevant to me.
Yeah, the PPAs are the only pain point.
Thank goodness there's so many workarounds around that now.
That's my line too, the line you just drew right there.
It's like, if it's my daily driver
and I'm on that machine as my main workstation,
I actually think it is worth the upgrade.
Normally I would say, no, hold off.
But in this particular case,
the machines I'm going hands-on all the time, I'm upgrading.
And the machines that are more appliances
that I just like the ones here in the studio,
I'm gonna leave on 1904.
Yeah, and then usually if you upgrade at least one machine,
at some point you'll figure out like,
is this really enough better
that I'm frustrated at the LTS release now?
And if not, just leave it.
I am a little annoyed
because when I came back to Ubuntu,
I just wanted to stay on one version for like five years
because there's this weird part of me
that really envies people that just like stick to an LTS
for like the full five years.
Because LTSs, in my opinion, go through like this life cycle.
1804 is just cresting the boring period of the life cycle.
And then it'll ride that for a while
and that sort of like curves down
and gets more and more boring.
And especially as like a 1910 comes out
and stuff like that,
1804 is gonna seem really boring.
And then when 2004 comes out,
like boy, 1804 is gonna seem like a cow.
But then it's sort of like it hits rock bottom around 2004.
And then when 2010 comes out,
it kind of starts to get interesting again.
And then it's like back up,
we're like 1404 and like we're 1604 is right now.
And it's like still people love it.
There's people that are still running 1604
and it works great for them.
And then you know what?
They've got all their stuff set up,
all their PPAs work, all their custom configs work.
Yeah, when you're still in the support cycle,
for the most part, it just works.
I wanted to be that guy.
Shall I offer you a hook to tempt you back to 1804?
Yeah, do it.
So those performance improvements
that you've been able to observe in 1904,
you're enjoying that, right?
I am, especially the non-shell stuff.
Right, so just to be clear
for the benefit of the listeners,
this is not work that Canonical are doing
and holding to our chest, they're not sharing.
This is all work that's going back upstream.
However, some of those patches
haven't completed peer review yet.
So aren't merged into the upstream known project.
And that's why we're carrying them
as vendor patches within Ubuntu.
So we can take advantage of those things now.
That said, all of that hotness is in 1904.
We have already backported it to 1810,
and those patches will be landing in 1804 soon.
How is that possible?
It's a totally different version of Gnome Shell.
Well, it is a different version,
but Daniel Van Vo is a magician and he's making it happen.
He is fixing multiple versions of Gnome Shell.
Yeah, and this is not uncommon
within the desktop team, right?
If you look at some of the applications that we carry,
we have multiple versions
across the current supported releases,
and they will be making patches
that are different patch sets
in order to deliver the same functionality
across versions of applications.
So they're not going to just upgrade 1804 to Gnome 3.3.2,
they're going to patch the version,
like what is it, 3.3.0 or whatever that shipped with?
Yeah, I forget what it is.
Was it 3.3.26 maybe, 3.3.28, something like that?
That kind of boggles my mind a little bit.
That is some work.
That is some serious work.
But it's important because people like sticking on LTSs
and depending upon the LTS
and depending upon which non-LTS you're looking at,
I've mentioned this before, it's between 10 and 20 times
the number of people stick on LTSs than non-LTSs.
And if we said to everyone,
hey, it sucks to be you on the LTS,
we're over here enjoying better performance in non-LTS land,
then our LTS customers would be very unhappy,
or 10 times more of them, very unhappy.
And so it makes total sense
for the patches that can be back ported.
And not all of them can, as Martin said,
some of them are too intrusive and too structural
and can't be back ported to an older release of Nome Shell
or the underpinnings of Nome Shell.
But those that can will be.
And so you don't have to look with envy
at the 1904 users who get all of the performance improvements.
You'll get some of them as well.
Somebody ought to send this episode to management
over at Apple and tell them they can back port
some of their fixes and old versions of Mac OS.
Okay, but MiniMac, you get what I'm saying though, right?
Like there are people that really benefit
from just sticking with the LTS for like a really long time.
I believe you're one of them.
Yeah, in fact, I have one computer
is my working horse desktop that I rarely upgrade.
So it's still running 1604
within an enlightenment E22 desktop.
And I run with enlightenment, some snaps and PPAs,
and that's working really, really great.
So no questions asked.
There's a sentence you don't hear very often
running enlightenment.
Yeah, that's great.
We should get the MiniMac review of enlightenment.
Totally should, yeah.
I haven't used that yet.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I will change my setup probably during this year
and then I can give you a review of enlightenment desktop.
For me, I think with the multi-monitor setup,
it's still one of the best desktop environments
you can have.
All right, I want that.
I want that, I want you to do that.
I totally want that.
Okay, promised, promised, excellent.
All right, so that's the big question.
And it sounds like, I mean, both Wimby and Popey
are kind of telling me I don't need to upgrade.
And I think we need to,
I would like to give an answer to the audience.
Is it worth upgrading from LTS
and getting back on this upgrade train?
And maybe it's not, if you're willing to wait around
and wait for those, I mean, it'll take time
for those things to get back ported.
But it sounds like maybe it's not worth it yet,
unless you really are a gnome shell enthusiast.
There's pros and cons to staying on the LTS
or jumping on the interims, right?
If you're a Linux enthusiast,
and I imagine most people listening to this are,
then running the latest stuff is always sort of compelling
on what you want to do,
because you want to play with the latest technology
and learn it and tinker with it.
But by the same token, you don't need to do that.
And there are benefits to staying on the LTS
because the LTS is well supported out in the wider world.
Outside of our bubble,
those people that are producing software for Linux
will absolutely produce packages and software for you
for the current LTS version,
not so much for the interim releases.
So it really depends what you need
to get out of your machine.
If you don't need to listen to us for advice,
then yeah, okay, upgrade.
I would say, I think the consensus is,
stick with the LTS
unless you have a compelling reason to upgrade.
If you're a performance hound,
and you really, really care about
the perceived performance of your desktop,
I will say out of the box,
the 1904 implementation is clearly faster.
And I have been doing for about 48 hours,
a little side-by-side GNOME boxes.
I just did a base 1804 install out of the box
and a base 1904.
That's a good little experiment.
Yeah, it was the most up-to-date daily 1904.
No updates though installed on either,
just installed them, rebooted once,
got back to the desktop and then let it ran for 48 hours.
And without a question,
I mean, it's clear just by looking at the charts,
the 1904 version out of the box uses less RAM
and continues to use less RAM the longer GNOME shell runs.
And I'm talking like,
it's a difference of about 500 megabytes of RAM right now,
difference, just sitting there running.
Yikes.
Yeah, so it really, you know,
there is clear advantages to the new release.
That sounds like some of that will be coming back
to the older versions, maybe not all of it.
And if you want it today,
then you basically have to go to 1904.
That's what it comes down to.
If you're willing to wait, then you're good.
Or if you're like me and maybe just gonna switch
to XFCE or Xubuntu, it doesn't matter.
I was, I just can't believe it.
I just, you know, I thought I wanted something sexy.
I thought I wanted a desktop that was like plasma,
that is very, very modern because-
I think you're making a transition here.
I think I am.
I think that's what it is.
You're approaching the desktop a little bit differently.
I think I am.
It's going from like the computer is my video game
and to the computer is my tool.
And I want my tool to be as effective and efficient
and at the best of doing just what I want it to do.
And XFCE is really good for that.
There's one other feature of 1904
that might be worth touching on.
Yeah, tell me about it.
It's a feature in the installer.
So when you run the install now,
one of the tick boxes,
it used to be where it used to say
install third-party codecs and that sort of thing.
That bit of text now says install third-party hardware
drivers for graphics and wifi.
If you have an Nvidia GPU and you tick that box,
it will install the proprietary Nvidia drivers for you
so that you've got Nvidia out of the box on your first boot.
That's great.
That's slick, wow.
Yeah, it's a good release.
It's a really good release.
And I mean, you know, it's not an LTS,
but it is a really good midterm release.
The Yaru theme is sharp.
I really like it.
I installed GNOME tweaks.
I used the dark mode of it, dark version of it,
and I think it looks really good.
I just left it.
I mean, this is probably the least tweaking
and modification I've ever done.
I spent a lot more time setting up XFCE than I did GNOME Shell.
So of course now my XFCE is like super dialed in.
It's really awesome.
I mean, yeah, once it's tuned, you can make it very lovely.
All right, I believe for one last time.
Everybody's doing the distro, distro, distro, distro.
Distro, distro, distro, distro, distro, distro.
Yeah, congratulations to the Canonical team.
They got a great release.
And now we look forward to other distros
that are shipping at GNOME 3.3.2
and see how their implementations stack up.
There'll be a lot of,
this is probably one of the more exciting release cycles
that we've entered in a while
because in a way we're entering a golden age
of GNOME development now.
And I'm really curious to see
what the other distros do with it.
What do you say, Wes?
What do you say?
A couple of picks before we get out of here.
No, let's do it.
We got two picks.
I brought one to the table today
and Wes brought one to the table.
And let's just say, please, ladies and gentlemen,
this next pick that we're about to cover here on the show,
please, please do use it responsibly
because you need to be a good internet citizen.
It's called Party Loud,
a simple tool to generate fake web browsing traffic
and mitigate tracking by essentially blasting web trackers
with a lot of noise.
Oh yeah, that's right.
You got a chance to give it a go.
In fact, we'll have a link to an ASCII video
in the show notes if people wanna see Wes's,
what do you call this?
A spoof session?
A Party Loud session?
Yeah, exactly.
There's a previously, there's a script out there
that's kind of popular, noisy.py,
which was the inspiration for this,
but that's Python, it's a little more complicated.
Party Loud has the advantage of being
pretty much just a simple bash script.
You can and should read it yourself.
And then otherwise it has a list predetermined.
You can add your own of websites, queries,
and then it basically just goes,
spins up a couple of threads with your resolvers,
goes out and pulls a bunch of websites
and walks around on the various URLs that they offer.
And it's like you're doing your own web browsing session.
Nicely too, it does display it for you
so you can see what it's doing,
it's not just off lurking in the background.
That's why I mentioned the ASCII video.
It's pretty cool actually watching it go on
and knock on the doors of all these trackers
and be like, I'm over here, I'm over here,
I'm over here, I'm over here.
It might be convenient too if you just need
some sort of simulated HTTP traffic for a while.
Yeah, yeah, I don't know, yeah, for testing I suppose.
Just be careful where you use it
because it could be kind of network intensive I suppose.
Its default configuration wasn't crazy,
it was like every two seconds and had four or five sites.
But yeah, I'm sure you could tune it to be pretty rough.
Okay, four or five sites, that's not gonna be too bad.
That's not gonna be too bad.
All right, well tell me about,
tell me about, did I, wait, or no, I found this one.
Oh, I thought you found, what?
Maybe we both found it.
Maybe.
Oh, maybe, oh, that's what it was is you linked it to me
and then I added it to my bookmarks
and then I took credit for it, that's what happened.
It's called NCSpot and it is an NCurses Spotify client
written in Rust.
I heard all those things and it just screamed Chris to me.
I know, that had to go in the show, right?
It's Spotify on the command line, what else do you need to know?
If you gotta use Spotify, this is the way to do it.
This is so great and NCurses is wonderful.
I don't know how you found this, Wes.
I have not tried this one yet
because I don't know that they have a release.
I think you have to actually have a Rust tool chain installed
and I don't own this laptop.
I just can't.
But I'm sure before long that will change
or maybe you can just get Michael Dominic
to compile it for you.
I do actually think this would be perfect for the studio.
I already want it, yeah, for playing music as well.
We just put my credentials in there
and just let it connect to my Spotify account.
Yeah, that's not bad.
That's pretty cool to have it on the command line
and I'm a sucker for any kind of NCurses you want.
They're just simple, functional and they look good.
Yeah, Spotify on the command line, I can't even.
You know, we ought to get some pics from the audience.
We haven't got, I don't think we've got any for ages.
Help us out.
LinuxUnplugged.com slash contact.
You can send us show feedback but also pick suggestions
or you can tweet Wes or myself at Chris Elias
or me at Wes Payne for him.
I've got a pic.
Yeah, oh, you do?
I'd love to hear it. Amazing.
I do.
Now, don't everyone groan when you hear the name.
Just hear what it does after I tell you the name.
Okay.
This is called Electron Player
and it's, among other things,
it's a Linux desktop Netflix client.
Oh, what?
Can you drop a link to that
and show us what's on the show notes?
Yeah, it's snapcraft.io forward slash electron player.
I spoke to the author a little while ago
and it also does YouTube and float plane
and a couple of other streaming services
but it's got all of the DRM modules baked in
so you can unclutter your browser
and dedicate some screen space
to a desktop client video player.
That's brilliant.
That's great.
That, oh, I love it.
I'm giving that one another ding.
Good pick.
Yeah, we'll throw a link to that
in the show notes right now.
You know what?
I'm gonna take that, Electron Player.
That's a great use for Electron right there, right?
Because you're using web streaming services anyways.
That's a great use case.
It kind of just makes sense.
It does kind of just make sense.
Go check out the Ubuntu podcast.
Go get more Popey, Wimpy, and Mark II
over at ubuntupodcast.org.
You guys want to tease anything for an upcoming episode?
Anything in the works?
Next episode's out in a couple of days.
We're apparently planning an extravaganza for Foss Talk Live
but I've not been completely looped in
on this extravaganza.
The other two have got planned.
So I'm looking forward to finding out
what that's all about.
And of course, both you gentlemen
will be at Linux Fest Northwest in just a few days.
Very exciting. We will.
This time next week we'll be on a plane or something,
I think, Popey and I.
Yeah.
I should be having stern words with him
about GPUs as well.
That's right.
Make sure he never gets that wrong again.
Yeah, when you get here, you got to stop by.
Maybe we'll do dinner or something.
Telegram me when you get in.
I'm going to, I'll be waiting, watching your flights,
tracking you now.
You cannot escape him.
We'll turn tracking on for you, Chris.
Very, very good.
All right, well, that brings us to the end
of this week's episode of the Unplugged program.
Links to everything we talked about
are in your podcast player of choice
over at linuxunplugged.com slash 297.
You can also get the RSS feeds for the show there,
linuxunplugged.com slash subscribe.
What else should we plug?
The Friday wrap up stream.
Mention that again.
Oh yeah, come join us live on Friday, 2 p.m. JB time.
That and this are like the two times
I get to see people live.
So come say hi.
You can also hang out here over at jblive.tv.
We do this on a Tuesday.
Go to Jupiterbroadcasting.com
to get that converted to your local time.
Thanks so much for joining us.
And we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Ah!
So Cheese, I'm curious, what do you think about Linus Tech Tips getting into Linux coverage?
This is like the third or fourth Linux video they've done in a year.
They're getting to, they're doing it more and more.
Yeah.
What do you think, Bacon?
You know, it's kind of interesting.
I have some friends that game on their desktops and use Windows primarily.
And this past week, I guess they caught the video, I didn't plug it to them or anything,
but they caught the video and they were asking me, dude, what's up with Linux?
What is this?
What's this all about?
So I had to kind of give them the quick two minute rundown.
Look at you, ambassador to Linux.
Yeah, right?
Well, and I've been telling them for years, man, that they need to look into it.
But you know, until it revolves around gaming, I guess it doesn't matter to them.
I am both very excited to get more Linux coverage and get more users over and both that and
a little nervous.
That's like, I don't necessarily know if gaming is the real hard sale we want to make.
Come over and emulate your Windows games.
I mean, I know I'm being harsh there, but I just feel like it's not the strongest foot
forward.
Like you want to come over and be a, you know, assistant administrator or developer or learn
to develop, you know, educational stuff.
Like that's great.
I think Google saying that with Stadia, right?
Yeah, it's just as Proton adds compatibility with more Windows games, it naturally opens
it up to a larger audience.
It's just it's sort of selling Linux on something that's getting much, much, much, much better
at and has gotten much better at, but it's not selling it on its absolute strongest,
strongest case.
That's all.
And I just.
Right.
It's hard to be like a really enthusiast evangelist when you're like, but also just to clarify,
this has been a weak spot that it's getting better at.
So it might not be perfect and a lot of stuff doesn't work great.
And when you play that network game that uses DRM, it's probably not going to work quite
right.
And those kinds of things like, at the same time, I'm like, you know, anything that gets
people interested and has them checking it out and downloading an ISO and giving it a
go, you know, maybe for every, for every thousand, for 50 of them to a hundred of them, it sticks.
Even that would be good.
Yeah, absolutely.
And, you know, MSS, they're seeing a bunch of big downloads, so that's great too.
And I mean, gaming has come a long way on Linux, so it's probably good to talk about
it a little more.
And it's also interesting to hear people outside the quote unquote community talk about the
distributions.
Like the way they talk about Ubuntu and the way they talk about Manjaro and the way they
talk about Pop OS.
I find that to be really interesting too.
It's sort of like getting to observe like a scientific experiment as they discover and
learn and explore.
Let's observe the humans as they try out Linux.
Yeah.
They're going to be so happy.