This is Linux Unplugged episode 45 for June 17th, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's raised from the ashes, stronger,
and more in-depth than ever before. My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
Hey Matt. Okay, so I'm gonna be clear with you. It's gonna be an express edition this
week because I've been here since about 6am and I was here until about 10.30 last night.
We had some hardware death, Matt. You know there's when hardware dies and there's when
hardware has deathed. And I have hardware death where it's like I came into the room,
I heard some clicking. It kinda actually did go down like that. It happened during Coda
Radio yesterday. I'm sitting here and see we have a mixer, it's all controlled by software
and it doesn't even have physical switches. It doesn't even have physical pots as they
call them where you can pull up or pull down a pot to make somebody louder or quieter.
None of that. No sliders, Matt. It's slider free. It's all controlled by software. Well
guess what happens when the hard drive in the machine that controls it by software starts
to die? You don't have access to the mixer anymore. So we won't have our mumble room
with us today because I actually just got it working like an hour and a half before
the show. I texted Matt, I'm like, uh, Matt, I think we're gonna have to reschedule the
show today. And then like last thing I try, like I was like while I was texting Matt,
then I'm like, well, I'm gonna try one more thing. This is not gonna fix it. And of course
it fixed it. So we made it just in time for the show. So that's good. Uh, which is nice
because I got, I got something kind of fun, uh, to talk about. I've, I've, um, recently
had the opportunity to take, uh, Android, Ubuntu touch and Firefox OS, slapped them
all on my Android phone. And I'm going to tell you how Rick, I did it. Wow. Yeah, it's
really cool. Sounds like a software sandwich. I'm triple booting. I, yeah, I am. I'm triple
booting and the latest Android Firefox OS and Ubuntu touch. I wish we were on the mumble
room cause I know fate and a couple others in the mumble room are doing this. So maybe
after the show we'll do some post-show troubleshooting and see what they're able to do. So today
it's, it's only a partial show because we wanted to be able to get up. We were here,
but uh, it's going to be abbreviated. So why don't we start, uh, with the feedback so that
way we can get that covered. Cause we've got some good ones. Uh, Nick wrote in, we talked
last week about, um, the whole Alienware going with a windows box. Remember that? I, I still
can't get over it. It's like a bad nightmare. I keep thinking I'm going to wake up and it's
all going to be gone. Yeah. So to recap, for those of you who didn't catch last week's
episode of Linux Unplugged, um, at E3 last week, Alienware announced they'd be shipping
not a steam OS box, but a steam machine. The steam machine is going to run, you guessed
it, Windows. So, uh, we won't, uh, we won't know exactly what it's, what their, what their
offerings are going to be, you know, what, until it hits the market. But, uh, we had
some heavy thoughts. We had some, we had some, we had some frustrations, I would say. And,
uh, we talked about them last week on the show and Nick, Nick, I thought came in with
a pretty good response. Uh, cause we, we definitely took a hard line response and Nick, you know,
he's a, he's, he's more rational than we are. It says in Linux Unplugged episode 44, there
was a debate over Alienware and it betraying Linux. In my opinion, Alienware made the right
move. Although Linux is gaining developer support for games, Windows is developer support
that currently far outreaches Linux. Even when running steam OS, a gamer would be limited
on the selection of content that was available to him or her. The move to Windows allows
Alienware to push out a console that allows gamers access to the array of content available
for Windows while having a better UI that circumnavigates the whore that is Windows
Metro. Don't get me wrong, I love Linux, but Windows is still the OS of choice for gaming.
Gaming on Linux has a long way to go, but if we're going, if we're going to be seen
squabbling about why gaming, uh, related companies are stupid instead of asking the question
of how to bring games to Linux, we will not be taken seriously by developers that may
be looking at Linux as a viable platform. He says, uh, by the way, many popular games
such as Battlefield run their own independent clients and services that have yet to be coded
for Linux. These games would still be accessible for those using that Alienware Windows box.
Hopefully these developers will begin developing content for Linux, but we'll have to wait
and see. It makes a good point about like things like a Battlefield who have their own
like networking clients and all that stuff. There's not even available. The backend for
that's not even available for Linux. Well, this is true. And it goes back to what I was
saying last week. And then at the end of the day, it comes down to titles, you know, which,
which platform has the most titles. And I, and I guess Alienware was looking at that
fairly practically and saying, okay, look, um, while I personally think it sucks and
it makes me mad and it doesn't shock me that the Dell slash Alienware guys would do this,
I, you know, having chance to kind of noodle it over, I do feel like that that's the decision
that was made. That being said, I still don't agree with it. Yeah. And, uh, I, like I'm
only, I'm kind of with Riley and the chairman's like, well then why not just wait, just wait
till steamOS was ready for that point. Because it seems like this is a failed product already.
Like we've seen this product bail and you're just shipping something that's already not
worked. And you're going to sort of, I hope they don't draw conclusions about what steamOS
itself would do in a marketplace. I guess that's my Alienware may and good for them
fail. Go away. Yeah. Maybe that's right. Let him get out of here. Get it out of here, right?
That's probably a good point. Cause after all, I think Alienware is wasted effort. Yeah.
Yeah. Um, all right. Well, uh, because, because we have a long email to get to, I want to
take a moment right here and I want to stop and thank team over to linux.ting.com. They're
one of our sponsors for the Linux unplugged show and it's mobile that makes sense. My
mobile service provider and Matt's mobile service provider too. In fact, I was just
talking with Matt at the beginning of the show about my nexus five and Matt's got the
note too. Now Matt, you know, you might want to consider, I mean, I'm just going to throw
this out there, but you might want to consider, uh, I think, Oh, I don't actually know. Oh,
you know what? I think this trick I did is limited to the nexus devices, but I am doing
it. I, so I made my first call today on Ubuntu touch on Ting. How about that? Now tell me
that's not mobile that makes sense. Right? Oh, that's awesome. Yeah. So this is what's
great about Ting is it's, it's a flat $6 a month and then it's just your usage on top
of that. And that's how they bill you. They'll just take your messages, your minutes and
your megabytes. They'll add them up at the end of the month. Whatever bucket you fall
into, that's what you pay. There's no contract, there's no early termination fee and you own
your device outright, which I think is really great. Plus every plan comes with caller ID,
tethering hotspot, three-way calling, call forwarding and all the other features you'd
expect. And it's just your usage. There's no ETF because there's no contract, which
is awesome. So you feel like you have the freedom to move if you need to. They have
a great dashboard. But the other thing I think is really unique about Ting is their customer
service. They have a no hold customer service and they just did a video about how they actually
scale that. And I'll play that for this, for the audience out there.
James M asks one question. How do you do it? I've had to call you once and got a live person
on the first ring who was cheerful and solved my problem. I emailed another time and got
an answer in about 15 minutes. Are you a real company? Could you teach Comcast?
Well, I don't know if we could teach Comcast, but we're definitely a real company. We decided
a long time ago that it was just important to treat our customers the same way that we
like to be treated when we call. Nobody likes being put on hold. Nobody likes waiting two,
three days to get a response to their email. And it certainly happens. We're not perfect.
But we really keep an eye on how many calls we're getting and how many emails we're getting
and how many new customers we're signing up and then do everything that it takes to make
sure we've got enough staff here that are happy and properly trained and motivated in
the right direction to make sure that they can perform up to those levels.
Go to linux.ting.com to take $25 off your first device. If you've got a device that's
compatible with Ting, good news. They'll give you a $25 credit. And if you're like me, that'll
last more than your first month of Ting service. It really is something when you switch over
to Ting and you can go find their savings calculator over at linux.ting.com and see
how much you would save, put in your actual usage, and see what it'd check out to be.
Also check out some of their devices. They've got MiFi-only devices. That's a $6 hotspot.
You get that hotspot and it's just your usage. And if you don't use it very much, then you
don't pay very much. If you use a lot, you pay appropriately. And it makes sense. Linux.ting.com.
And a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. I made so, I did make that first
phone call on Ubuntu Touch on Ting. And it's a little beta because two things happen. Of
course, now I'm ribbing Ubuntu Touch and we can't get in mobile for Popey to defend it.
So I made the call and it worked flawlessly to make the call. And it was nice because
I didn't really have to hardly set up anything. But then the problem was is when I hung up
the other end, the Ubuntu Touch end never recognized the hang up and then just blew
through half my battery in about two minutes. Wow. Well, as you pointed out, I'll play Popey's
part here. To defend it, I would say it's beta. It's early days. It's like a recent
build too. Yeah, it's a super recent build too. But hey, it works. I'm running Ubuntu
Touch and Firefox OS on the Nexus 5. It's living the dream, man. I'm living the dream.
All right. Russell writes in about high DPI support under Linux. And this is a topic that
we've been tracking because I fancy myself once the monitors come down to a reasonable
price level. I fancy myself running the GNOME desktop on a high DPI display. So he says,
hey, Linux support for high DPI screens has been brought up here and there lately. So
I thought I'd chime in with my experiences. I bought a 4K monitor a month ago and tried
several different desktop environments with it. And the winner by far is Unity. How about
that? He says, I was an Arch user on GNOME. I got my monitor around the same time 3.12
hit the repos. I heard 3.12 had high DPI support, but apparently that wasn't in the binaries
in the repo. And I would have to recompile Cairo and GTK. And I didn't want to get into
that for something that should have just worked. GNOME was bad. KDE was bad. XFCE was better.
But anything lower than that required too much configuration, often on a per application
basis. I tried Ubuntu 14.04 and it looked really good. It has GUIs for setting up the
window and font scaling and everything looks as it should. I'm sure high DPI support will
be more of a priority for desktop environments and distributions as time goes along. But
right now it looks like Ubuntu is the clear winner. Also with a GTX 770 graphics card
on Ubuntu, I'm playing Dota 2 on max settings at 3,840 by 2,160 at 80 frames per second.
That's pretty cool. Keep up the good work, Russell. Holy crap. That is an insane resolution.
3,840 by 2,160 at 80 frames per second. Okay. Yeah, that works. He got a 4K monitor. He
must have dropped a pretty penny on that because I think even the cheap ones are around two
grand right now still. I'm kind of asking, and I'm a little fuddy-dove. What's the,
you know. Hey guys. HD is nice. It's great. Can you visually with human eyeballs really
notice a difference? And the value of this is negative. Yeah, I think you can actually,
but just barely. I mean, I wear glasses and I don't know. I think you barely can, and
I don't think it's worth that kind of money. I think it's like, it's one of those things
where you look at it and you're like, oh man, that text looks particularly good. And that's
kind of it. It's not like when you went from VHS to DVD, it's not that kind of jump. It's
like when you went DVD to Blu-ray, I can sometimes you're like, okay, it does look better, but
it doesn't look that much better, especially if you have a great DVD player and a good
TV. Right. And I think it's kind of the same thing. Like I have a Monoprice Korean display
that's a, it's got a high res, it's like a 2K resolution and it looks all right. You
know, it looks pretty good, but I don't know, Matt, it's coming. It's coming. I just remember
when just LCD screens were $2,000. Oh yeah. No kidding. Well, I still got a plasma set.
That's my main TV. We have an LED TV in the bedroom, but our main sets of plasma and yeah,
I'm happy as a clam with it. Yeah. You know, I don't know. It's like one of those things
to where it's like, I would probably, if I got myself, if I sat in front of it and actually
had a side by side, then I might be sold, but I'm just not there yet. And then again,
I'll probably wait until the prices drop. So yeah, I feel like the prices need to come
down for 4K. I feel like the Linux desktop applications and environment sounds like they
still have some work to do. And I also want something that's like, you know, 22 inches
or 27 inches. I don't want like a 15 inch high DPI display. I want like a big, big screen
that, you know, is going to look awesome. And yeah, I don't know. Maybe, heck, if that's,
if that's a year away, I mean, I'll definitely jump when it's, you know, in the few hundred
dollar range. I think that's when I'm going to pull the trigger when it's like 380 bucks
for a really, you know, like a well-respected brand or something like that that people are
talking all about. And I'm like, okay, I'll jump onto that. Exactly. All right. Our next
email comes in from Dave, AKA Skullplate in the IRC and in the subreddits. He says, I've
been playing with the digital ocean server for a while and finally decided to put it
to work. A short while later, I got my own Debian cloud server, own cloud Debian server
up and running with fail to ban log watch. And I also disabled root login and many other
tips I've picked up listening to the great Jupiter broadcasting podcast. Oh, thanks.
And reading the JV subreddits. He says, most impressive is the performance. I'm getting
the sinking of folders to my digital ocean server easily 10 times faster than Dropbox.
So I just want to say a big thanks to Chris and Matt and the JV community and even Alan
too. It was really easy considering a year ago, I didn't even really know how or how
to use Linux at all. Thanks again, Dave, AKA Skullplate. Yeah. You know what? Go over to
digital ocean.com. Use our promo code snap or I'm sorry, unplugged June, not snap. I
was thinking a text snap because Alan unplugged June for digital ocean. I'll give you a $10
credit. You can try out their $5 rig for two months or you can go hourly and that $10 credit
will get you quite a ways. Are you not familiar with digital ocean? Let me tell you about
it. Digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way to spin up a cloud server. And I got to tell you, they've nailed it. Users
can create a cloud server in about 55 seconds and pricing plans started only $5 a month
for 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU and a terabyte of transfer. That's
all for $5. You know exactly what you're going to get for $5. And digital ocean has data
center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, and Amsterdam. Their interface
is amazing. Their control panel is intuitive and power users can replicate that control
panel with their straightforward API. Son, get in there and replicate that. Won't you?
They have a straightforward API and people call it beautiful, a beautiful API. Digital
ocean.com. Use the promo code unplugged June. Go over there and get yourself a droplet.
I've been hearing from folks that use it for an IRC server. An own cloud server seems
to be very popular and recently more and more folks are jumping on digital ocean to deploy
GitLab. Now digital ocean is sitting on top of KVM. They have a droplet system that lets
you manage your instances. You can back them up, replicate them, move them between data
centers, manage your DNS, access the console via their HTML5 console, written in Go, select
your data center anywhere in the world, then choose your distribution, the architecture
of that distribution, and then deploy. And you can do it all in about 55 seconds and
you can be up and running. And with our promo code unplugged June, you can try it out for
two months for absolutely free. Go get yourself an SSD powered server connected to tier one
bandwidth. Partner with the amazing hardware providers that digital ocean has chosen over
digital ocean.com. Use the promo code unplugged June and a big thanks to digital ocean for
sponsoring Linux Unplugged. Yeah. You know, here recently I've been doing this whole WordPress
thing with them, right? Because I've already got a Vidtor sync set up with them. So I set
up another instance because I wanted to try the WordPress thing. Oh my gosh, it's stupid
simple to do. Yeah, it's awesome. I couldn't get it. I couldn't get it. I was like, why
the hell is everybody else doing this with so much more difficulty? This is great. And
you know what I would always just keep in mind? Zombies don't run Linux. So you don't
have to worry about it. You don't have to worry about zombies. Yeah. Okay. So I want
to tell you just before we wrap up the express edition of Linux Unplugged, I want to tell
you about this wizardry that Rekai pulled on my Nexus 5. So I've been having some, I'm
trying not to hate on Android, Matt, but I'm, I just keep having these problems that are
just driving me crazy. And so Rekai just kind of jokingly said, well, why don't you try
it? Or actually I think it was Marissa and the chairman that Rekai do was like, yeah,
do that. Why don't you just try out Firefox OS for a couple of days, Chris, and see what
you think. I was like, oh yeah, well if you can put on my Nexus 5, I'll take the Firefox
OS challenge. Well then guess what? Guess what happened? He put Firefox OS on my Nexus
5. Oh my. Our buddy Jordan has a guide on the XDA forums on one way you can do it. I'll
have links in the show notes too. So if you guys want to follow along it, check this out,
Matt. Now it does require that you root the device, but on the Nexus 5, this isn't like,
that's not like a crazy process. And then once you've rooted the device, you can go
out and get a piece of software that's like a, it's not called ROM manager anymore. I
have a link to it in the show notes. Let me see if I can pull it up for you. Multi-ROM,
that's what it's called. It's called Multi-ROM. This is an app that you install from the Play
Store once you've rooted your device, and I'll have a link to the Play Store in the
show notes. Once you've rooted your device, you install this Multi-ROM and it essentially
is a multi-boot menu. So when I power on now my Nexus 5, if I tap the screen, otherwise
it just boots right into Android, but if I tap the screen when a little prompt comes
up, I get a very nice gooey bootloader where it says, okay, do you want to load Ubuntu
Touch? Do you want to load Firefox OS or do you want to load Android? And then whichever
I choose, that's the OS it boots right into and it rocks. It's full native. It's like
when you partition a PC and you install multiple operating systems and then load a bootloader.
It's not running under emulation. It's not running under Android. It's truly Ubuntu
Touch and truly Firefox OS on the machine on the Nexus 5. It's pretty awesome. It's
pretty cool. It's a good way to play with these things and I think the Nexus 5 is going
to make a killer rig to have because you have things like this Multi-ROM, which right now
only supports the Nexus 5, 4, and 7 series, 2012 and 2013 Nexus 7. The chat room is asking
about space. I have a 32GB Nexus 5, so I think maybe I've got a little more room to play
with than if you had a 16GB. Yeah. But it's pretty good now. I'll tell you, I don't know
if I could live in either one of them. That's why I really like that Android's still there.
You have to wipe the phone too because when you root it and set this up, it wipes all
of them and then you do a recovery and reload Android and you have to set it all up. It
means reconfiguring all my damn apps and all that stuff. But you do it once and then you
have the triple boot forever, which is kind of cool. Well, here's the $10,000 question.
We've got the whole, obviously there's probably some sort of a battery bug or maybe it's not
fully optimized in the Ubuntu OS for the phone and that's fine. But for Firefox OS, what
was your feelings on that? Because that has me curious, especially on the lower spec phones.
Yeah, man. Firefox OS, it's funny in some ways how much is like Android in the way you
pull down the notification tray and there's all your notifications and the way the icons
kind of look and stuff. And it's got some funky stuff too about it. Like the bottom
row has like a home button, but it's not a home icon. It's a worldwide web browser generic
icon. And you push that and it takes you back to the homepage. I was hoping it would perform
better on the Nexus 5 because I've played with it on lower end hardware. And I kind
of assumed perhaps the performance was because it was on low end hardware. And I think that
was part of it, but it also I think is maybe it's just not totally optimized for my device.
Like the camera doesn't work under Firefox OS and it doesn't detect my SIM card. Yeah.
So it could be a driver problem. So I wasn't quite as enamored with it as I was expecting,
but I think maybe if we keep updating it and keep tracking it. Honestly, between the two,
Ubuntu Touch seems like it's in a better state on the Nexus 5. And that's not great. Like
it crashed on me, right? It drained all my battery. So they're both a little ways off,
but it's fun to play with. Interesting. I don't know. Maybe I'll do a video on it in
the future if people are interested. Let me know guys. On the Linux Action Show subreddit,
linuxactionshow.reddit.com. We'll have a thread for this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Let me know if you guys are interested in getting more coverage. I don't really have
a good sense if you guys care about this kind of stuff, but I know we have talked a lot
about Firefox OS. We've talked obviously a lot about Ubuntu Touch. So it's kind of neat
to have one device I can carry with me and play with those right now. So I think that'll
help. I really appreciate like, oh, here's some screenshots of the multi-boot for those
of you watching the video version. So when you boot up the phone, this is the interface
you get. It says auto-boot, but you touch anywhere on the screen to interrupt the auto-boot.
And then when you do that, you can choose your distro or, I'm sorry, I guess, ROM that
you want to boot. And you can see in this case, you could load Tizen on there. You could
even load different like CyanogenMod and different Android ROMs on there too. So it could also
be a way to play with different Android ROMs. It doesn't have to be radically different
operating systems. It's pretty neat. And I think it's another reason to get the Nexus
5 too, because people are able to write that kind of stuff for it.
They're cool.
Yeah, man. Yeah, man. All right. So before we run, since we're doing an express edition,
that way I can wrap up here and tear apart the audio and try to get things like the mumble
room working and a couple other problems that we've currently band-aided over so that way
we can get on air. But you feel like, hey, Chris, not enough show. Not enough show, brah.
Well, then here's what I have for you, brah. Go over to JupiterBroadcasting.com and check
out Tech Talk today. Episode 10 came out. Matt, do you remember an old piece of software
called Pointcast from like the late 90s?
Very vaguely.
The push technology that was going to change the web because the web was too hard to use
and the web was too slow to download multimedia, so you had to do it in batch processing. Well,
because we were having so many problems this morning, I did a retro tech edition of Tech
Talk today and we looked back at Pointcast and the technology that almost shaped the
future of the internet but then petered out and those who bet big and lost. We covered
that on Tech Talk today. And of course, of course, go check out the first two episodes
of How To Linux. Getting that off the ground right now. We'll have more information on
that show very soon as well. So two shows you can go check out right now if there's
not enough show. And I'm sorry that we did have to cut it short, but we do have these
problems. I want to get fixed that way. By the time it's like getting towards TechSnap
and Linux Action Show, hopefully we'll have everything all ironed out. All right, Matt.
Well, heck, guess what? That's it right there. We're going to wrap it up. We're all done.
That was a quick and easy one, huh? Quick and easy.
Yeah, I thought maybe we'd have to bail and do it on Thursday, but I think this worked
out okay. This worked out quite nicely. Now, I do want to encourage all of you to join
us on Sunday over at jblive.tv at 10 a.m. Pacific for the Linux Action Show. You can
go to jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get all of our live show times. And don't
forget, when you join us live, you get to bang suggests. So chat room, last chance to
get your title suggestions in there. All right, Matt. Well, have a great week. I'll see you
on Sunday, okay?
You too. See you then.
Bye, everybody. Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged. See
you right back here next Tuesday.