Actually, no, I do remember Chris. Are you wearing your usual lumberjack shirt? No, I watched two live episodes
Got some great swag, but I can't wear it because it's green
The new jacket which I gotta say so wimpy sent me a
buntaise
Fancy with his auntie. Yeah, he's going custom design and
And the shirts are green like I would just be invisible in the studio
Which is kind of cool, but the jacket's black with a green logo like you know where the Star Trek comb badge would be obviously right
And so kind of looks like I have a Star Trek comb badge actually because it's kind of like
Well, I left it at home because the girlfriend loves the new jacket
She wanted me to personally thank wimpy because she thinks it's very well
I can't remember the word she used but she likes it. That's great
Yeah, likes it on you or likes it for herself. No, well no likes it on me. She likes she thought I was yeah
She thought was a good fit. Well, you're welcome Chris. Yeah. Thank you
That's what I'm saying now, of course the I do have that one of the shirts upstairs here, but otherwise it's all at home is
It took a little while because it came from where did it come from?
This is a good question a part of Europe that I can't even remember the name. Yeah, I remember looking at I'm going
What what is what did I get from? Oh, this must be
Yeah, yeah
Yeah, so the guy the guy the guy that runs this place Gabor. His name is it's brilliant
So it's a hello tux and they do
official
Linux
merchandise for a number of projects
and they originally started up as like a part-time endeavor and
it was they've got a
Computer system that you can fit, you know make designs effectively using Inkscape
Feed that into this stitching machine and then it embroidered as you know
These designs and originally that was all running on Windows and he reverse engineered the whole thing
To get it all to run under Linux
That is great. Yeah, and I think just recently like within the last nine months or so
He he is actually doing hello tux and these things as a full-time
Occupation now, but he gives back a rather hefty slice
To each of the projects. So, you know Debbie and are on there and open suzer and you know countless other things
And every time somebody buys one of the items from there, those projects get a kickback from the items
He sells so I like I like his you know
his
Business model and did you get a memory stick in amongst all those that was the slickest thing?
That is one of the smallest tiny neatest looking branded. I mean, it's I
It's like pinky size. It's upstairs. I should grab it. I will I'll grab it before we start the show. I really like those
Yeah, that is slick like I would buy that like if you were if this is back in the day where we had software on
Shelfs and stores right and I would go down to the computer store and I would buy it some new software
This would be like that like minimum price for that $40. It looks like a $40 like wow
It's a hike. It's a high-class like if I ever know why you're buying that
Much pain that much for these kind of things. No, I know I know that's crazy, but I get I take your meeting. Yeah, I got
Look at the guy. He's like I almost wish I had to reload
I just would love to see this in the side of the Apollo. It's because it's a metal nice-looking thumbstick. Yeah
Yeah, and those those you get free if you order like two of these things you get the the USB stick for free or you
Can order it, you know independently as well. So yeah, he's he's a good guy. It's amazing
What's the site for people to check out? Hello tux.com. Let me just
I'll go there right now
This is Linux unplugged episode 135 for March 8th
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's hunkered down in its secure enclave and celebrating International Women's Day
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Well, hello there, Wes. Good to have you here, sir
Oh, yes, it's a beautiful bunker. I think
It's a beautiful bunker
Oh, yes, it's a beautiful bunker. Thank you. It's a nice enclave, right? It sure is
Yeah
well
Broadcasting from today's enclave is a great show coming up in today's episode a brand new version of own cloud and it may
Dress some serious concerns I've had and also open up the door for those of us on a VPS that maybe doesn't have enough storage
At the moment super excited about some of the improvements in own cloud 9 including their code sign
And we're gonna be talking about that then later on in the show. It's a big topic. It's a huge topic
You've probably heard me talk about it already if you cause more recent shows
We've got to get the virtual lugs take on Microsoft announcing sequel server for Linux
That's melting my my whole head
what my whole head is melted by this as somebody who used to I
used to have to deploy sequel servers and the whole like
Lock-in that sequel server used to bring to an organization was unprecedented. So to have that ship for Linux melts my head
We're gonna talk about I'm curious to get your take on it too and then
Later on in the show towards the end of the show there is an application for the Linux desktop focused on the Linux desktop
That promises to seamlessly and transparently deliver Android applications today on your Linux desktop experience
And I'm talking like you go to your launcher you type in the name of the application hit enter boom that Android app is
Up and running on your Linux desktop
Wes and I have it loaded here in studio. We've thrown a few apps at it. We're gonna get your take and
And before we do all that we have like a whole bunch of project updates to get into whoa
I know it's so much show. I talked to the whole opening music. That's how much show it is. Holy smoke
So why don't we start by just talking about this beer super quick?
Wes you brought you brought us something special today
You brought us a lady for International Women's Day from Nineski Brewing Company. Ninkasi. Nineski Brewing Company
Ninkasi? Ninkasi. Ninkasi
Brewing Company. Yeah, I got that part right. Heyo! That's two-thirds Chris. Dawn of the red IPA
It is over on the beer advocate getting an 87 score, which is pretty darn good
It's pretty darn good. It says very good there. Yeah, pretty darn good rocking in at a seven point zero zero percent ABV
It's got it's got a whole lot going on with this beer. It really does, it's complex. Yeah, when you drink this thing
There is a freshness that is happening in your mouth. I feel like it's I feel like when I drink this thing
Would you say it's bursting with tropical notes Chris? Is that actually on the bottle?
That is exactly what I would say. I would say it burst the last year of
Layers of skin and sediment on my tongue right off my tongue when I put this in my mouth
Perfect kind of thing for doing a podcast. Exactly. Clears up the mouth. Alright before we get into our project updates
Let's bring in our virtual lug time appropriate greetings mumble room
Yes, of course, so I got I got a secret I'm very excited
I'm planning to pick myself up something in the near term new toy. Yeah, I I hate using the term toy
I hate calling it a toy new business item. Yeah, well because in my estimation it is legitimately
I'm comparing these different solutions. I mean I go legitimately I'm curious
I've been hankering for a really good Cody box and a really good plex box. Yeah, really good Netflix box
I wanted to do all of these things and then if you can throw in some YouTube and maybe a Hulu app
Now you're really getting my attention
But I you know
I don't I don't I don't really want a lot of the different options that are out there and I don't want to build a box
Really? I don't really want to use Raspberry Pi 3 because or 2 because you know, I want Netflix and whatnot. Mm-hmm
So I've been thinking about Cody but thinking about Cody I'm gonna tell you what up my solution is very curious first
I'm gonna just talk a little bit about the new Cody release that I'm getting pretty excited about
So version like 17 or some crap like that. I'll give you the exact number here in a second
Coming out real soon and they got a brand new look you guys a brand new look today with is a new milestone
They say a sanctuary. I think is how you say this one West. What do you think estuary estuary estuary?
I like in sanctuary estuary
And it's a brand new look it's pretty cool. You'll see that
It's got the main new eye catcher is a whole new home screen
Which will guide you through all of the main sections that are available
They've added some useful widgets for movies and TV shows like random and recently added in progress
Actually sounds a lot like it's been inspired from Plex unplayed. Most played are also available. Look at this UI
It's looking pretty good. They're calling this said they're calling this there
What's cool about this is this is also gonna be something that will make available for touch interfaces with a slight
Reface retouch of the UI
Enter the library you're gonna notice new views have received some facelifts developers tried to keep functionality information and balance
I think I think it does look pretty nice. It does look pretty nice and the one thing they also say
They've enabled themes in the default or colors in the default theme
So you can have a whole bunch of different colors now in the default theme which is which is new
Here's where I'm going with this West
Starting in version 17 encrypt on you're gonna be able to use this this nice-looking. I think it looks better than Plex
It's got you know all the plugins and features of Kodi plus if you don't like this look
There's a bunch of other games you can apply. Yes
So I've been thinking what would be the ultimate box and I mean I have a special requirement is I wanted to be able to
Run Kodi. I want to build a run Plex and I want to be able to do it
I want to build a run Plex offline if possible
Mmm, because when I'm going down the road and I got three monsters strapped to seatbelts behind me
I it is yeah, it is a road safety
Imperative that I can have inside out or frozen playing on the television
I mean it saves lives literally because otherwise it's dad. Can I have this dad? He did this dad?
I want this the whole drive Wes. Okay, do you understand what I'm saying? I understand so I
Think I'm looking at the Nvidia shield TV. Whoa. Yeah, I did not expect that. Yeah, I didn't think you would yeah
Tell me more about it. Well the Nvidia shield TV, you know, yeah, it's got good performance
You can run all of these applications. It's actually got the newer version of Google's
Television OS on there. That's not their first attempt at it
and
All of the apps we love available for it crazy great performance
Think I do 4k video nice. Yeah
I'm wondering right on the website says Cody. Yeah, I'm waiting likes. Mm-hmm
Yeah, they've tout all the different apps it runs you do you pair that up with something with Cody
So my thinking is wait till that thing drops in price a little bit
I'm gonna jump on that thing and that's gonna be my home entertainment setup. What's it? What's the cost now?
Well, it depends on which one you want
See, I need offline storage and I don't know what the you can get one with up to a 300 gigabyte hard drive
But the price starts to get to $300
So that's a little expensive, but I need the office so I'm gonna wait or maybe I can see if I can add my own
Storage, but I'm just thinking Nvidia shield TV with Cody is a super sweet
Low-power quiet combo. Yep. It could be a good way to go
I bet there's probably a lot of other boxes anybody the mumble room just waiting to shout out like Chris
There's this Cody box. It's so great. You can just get it right now
You'd know of one
I've heard a few
There's a there's some like some
Some Android sticks that are on Amazon. They could get for pretty cheap that accomplished the same fundamental thing
So you can still use Cody and you know Plex and Android apps so you can get the same experience
But it's not gonna be like for you. I don't know if I want to stick
You know, I don't know if I want to stick because the thing is is I want I want this is over sticks
I
Am over sticks because I just I want this thing to be as fast as possible. I I do not ever want time
I just I I want it to feel like it's right on the metal and I
for me, it's worth it like big-ass
MKV files and
HD streams and video games like it's all worth it for me to have
If the sticks they're just they're just as low-end as possible. I know I know I know speaking of sticks though
You know who is into the sticks?
Mozilla on March 1st, Mozilla senior vice president for connected devices announced that the open source organization
Seeks to develop test and evaluate for Internet of Things software projects. That's coming from Mozilla
project link project sensor web project smart home and project
What do you think West Vanny VAA and I Vanini?
mumble room anybody VAA and I anyways
They got it was funny, but yeah, okay
The announcement didn't really mention anything about Firefox OS at all
But it's probably a safe bet that these things have it there. It's probably a safe bet
It would use these things West my reaction and then this is just me being an out-of-touch Chrome user
my reaction when I hear this is
a
What
What Mozilla is doing what?
Why what I mean I what I don't understand is how does this make Firefox a better web browser?
Is this a super old way a limited way of thinking? Yes. I mean, I guess we'll see
I think Mozilla has been trying to pivot to something like this or at least explore for quite some time, but
There hasn't been a lot delivered. So I don't know. I'm curious to see what it would look like
I believe that Mozilla has the best intentions or at least very good intentions
But I don't know what this will really look like
It does seem separate though from them also having a pretty good browser
Their announcement about the Firefox OS not doing phones anymore. They yeah, they did say they're gonna do internet of things stuff
They're gonna do tablets and stuff like that. So it kind of goes in with that
But I mean if they as a Firefox fanboy, I also don't care if they can make pretty good standard supporting web
Focused internet of things maybe even secure devices then I would support that but I guess it really remains to be seen if that's what
they do
when they if they bring in the new
Engine their runtime engine. Oh, come on, dude. Yeah. No, you're just trying to get me upset
You're just trying to upset me right now. Stop it Rod and you are trolling me. That's good move, but I'm not falling for it
It's just around the corner, right? It's just gonna be yeah. Yeah. Yeah, could it be the next one? Of course
So let's start booby
I think you and I have talked about maybe it was on tech talk today before
Maybe was a Kickstarter of the week hadn't we talked about how we thought if there was gonna be a
IOT type device a chromecast type competitor or something like that. What do you think of that idea?
Um, well, they tried well someone tried before doing their matchstick
Matchstick that we think that was horribly. Mm-hmm. Yeah. Yeah, I
I'm I'm taking with a pinch of salt everything was that are doing at the moment. I haven't seen recently one of their
employees post a whole lot of
internal information about how
How the company works? I'm kind of just wait and see see what they come up with
Hmm kits and kitty. I want to hear your thoughts on this. I
Just think it's more in the line with all the news that has been coming out with Mozilla both good and bad
you know the bad being GTK 3 getting snubbed again and
45 but they do have all this really cool stuff working behind the scenes Mozilla servo
Which is breaking records right now in terms of JS performance
But the other interesting thing that I thought was
Rather interesting coming out of Mozilla was they're wanting to push gecko again. Did you hear about this in what context?
I mean the web browsers context or do you what do you mean when gecko is the rendering engine of Firefox, right as a framework?
To build other applications. It was
hmm
well
That seems like a good idea
well, um, that seems like it almost makes more sense, even though I don't I don't know why that is
Boy, yeah, that's an uphill fight
It is and I just like whenever I see this story
It just makes me think back to the icky situation around the early
2000s where they tried to do the same thing and they came out with like nightingale
Uh music player, etc. Oh great. Yeah, I forgot about that. Yeah, and it was just a bunch of uh,
disappointment really one thunderbird
Yeah
quiet
Uh, that's interesting. Hmm. I I was a good player though. Yeah, actually I would like I would love
I would love to see where they go with this
In other things, uh, I don't even know what the hell that means and it gives me a little bit of a stick in my
Stomach every time I think of it
I I know it's something that it's the only thing they talk about at trade shows right now and I know it's uh,
it's a huge industry I just
I
It feels like 3d to me a little bit
you know, it feels like uh
It's something we all talk about and it's something we all procrastinate about or you know
Procrastinate or whatever you want to say about what's gonna could or couldn't could go wrong
But who's actually buying these things outside of geeks that are just dorking around with them like you?
I'm not even buying things is is marketing to not geeks
It's like all kind like the amazon echo and stuff like that. I think the echo is the
I think the echo is the biggest example of a successful internet of things product
And I think what we do is we just arbitrarily go around and say well
This is now an internet of things product. What makes it an internet of things product?
It has an ip address. Is that where we're drawing the line?
It can query apis. Is that what makes it an internet of things?
I think it's just it's a device that has access to the internet
By itself without having to connect to any other devices, but it doesn't have access to the internet by itself
It requires a infrastructure in place a a wi-fi
LAN and a router, but I mean like it doesn't have to connect to like another like for example the freaking
Android watches like they require another device to even work
Like that's what okay
Okay, boy, that's that's a pretty broad broad definition
Yeah, but also, you know
It goes to the same thing about the cloud being incredibly broad. Well, doesn't that technically make the xbox and the playstation?
An internet of thing device that's an or smart TVs were kind of an early front of that
So I think it depends on how much they're made the default, you know
Yeah, it's starting to feel like a lot of marketing bs it's starting to feel like
You can call it a successful category because you can call anything an internet of things device and therefore if anything sells
That you put that label on you can say internet of things is successful, but in the broad context
Nobody's actually buying the shit or putting it in their homes
Uh except for us geeks and even then I think it's a subset of the geeks
Like I don't have a nest or the only internet of things like I have hues lights because i'm in a studio
And I want to match color to my green screen. That's a pretty niche reason to buy hues lights
Otherwise, I don't know if I would buy them like they're not in your kitchen. I bought them and gave them to my dad as a gift
And he's colorblind so that's not even a great gift like he uses them
You know like it feels like it is a gimmick
And I don't know so I wish mozilla all the luck as they cast off into a completely nebulous category
That seems to have no meaning to me. I mean
Anybody can feel free to disagree with me in the mumba room
But to me it feels like anything we want is internet of things when they say this is what they're doing
It sounds like a company that doesn't have really great focus is moving into a category that doesn't have any focus
Sounds like a recipe for disaster to me
But you know, they do have that super fast javascript thing down. So that's true soon as they ship that
Yeah
Soon as they ship that. All right
So we have a few more updates to go through uh before we get into some meat of the show
But I thought this one was interesting. I was getting tweeted this one a lot this week the fail overflow folks have released their ps4
K exec style code to load the current linux kernel
From the freebie freebsd based os. So that is really something they're not cool
They're not breaking the playstation. It's a kernel module. Wes. They must have had to break the kernel module must be signed
I mean they must have to have a sign module. So like what they say with this is that you need a way
To execute this. Ah, so if you get yourself an exploit like theirs was in webkit
For example, then you just take this you can compile it up run it and boom. There you go
Now you run it codes up on github. Yeah, I think that's pretty neat. That's pretty cool. You know what that means
That wolf cluster. Yep. Yeah, it does mean a cluster though. That is that is and they were talking about how they like
extract the radion driver and
Make it like work with linux this to me actually like if I was gonna buy a console would push it
I mean I was already in ps4, but this would push it right?
For for a linux geek like me. Oh, man. Yeah, probably it pushes it. It's just fun to make it right
I don't know. I had gen 2 on a wii at one point. Maybe maybe one day
Maybe one day they can really get some performance out of it and use a tin code video. Oh
I see your angle. All right, so I gotta give a little shout out to the elementary os folks
we talked last week with wimpy about funding of ubuntu mate and uh
Daniel from elementary os has posted an update about some of their funding initiatives
He said I want to put a quick update about our bounties as you might know elementary has a bug bounty program where we pay
Out people to fix certain issues anyone can create a bounty on any issue or contribute to an existing bounty. It's pretty great
So far elementary has paid out over 14 000 to developers fixing bugs
Uh, here's some of the big ticket ones were that are still open and you know what I you know
I was looking through this wes and something sort of really jumped out at me as I was browsing through elementary os's bounty source. Yeah
um
And I had an off off air conversation with daniel in the subreddit a little bit about this too
Because I asked, you know, is it slow things down because you can't just go contact the developers directly
And daniel said well, uh, no, we think it doesn't and he said he said I like the kind of transparency that it provides
Uh, of course bounty source isn't loading right now. That's the bounty source website
It's just all that's a whole lot of white in your face
But what you what you get by looking at elementary os's bounty source page is you get an idea of where the project is going
Like i'm pretty clear like you can see there's 300 worth of money to work on the file manager right now
And what those top you can really see where they're putting their money. Yeah
Where's the top concerns in the file manager?
They link all the bugs in the bounty source to launchpad, uh bugs too
Which is kind of a nice way to do for a boom to base distro
So it seems like a pretty good system wimpy
I wanted to just sort of get your sort of off the cuff take on a system like bounty source versus sort of the funding
that you've sort of come up with where you're working with developers directly and
Did you look at bounty source and decide it wasn't for you or you just think it's a a different strokes for different folks
What's your impressions on that?
Yeah, I mean bounty source is um
It's definitely a tool, uh platform that you can take advantage of I did look at it and I decided
Uh, it's a small project. We've been to math
There's a small project with a small group of people and I wanted to focus on
on building relationships with people rather than
so
With bounty source you can have a drive by committer who can choose to work on a thing
For 50 or whatever it might be
And work on that one thing and then never be engaged with the project again
And I wasn't so keen on that approach. I wanted to
um
Approach and reward people that had demonstrated a commitment to the project. So that's sort of the the
The route that i've taken I think that and I could also see different depending on the scale of the project how a different approach
Makes sense too. Yeah, I like I like browsing through there and uh seeing what they want fixed and I like the idea
that as a sort of somebody who doesn't have any capacity to um
Contribute code I could contribute money to their bounty source
But then also I found myself kind of confused like should I be contributing to the patreon or should I be contributing to the bounty?
source seems like
It would be better just to sort of focus everyone's efforts in one spot. Let them decide where it should go
Yeah
But well the patreon is like what they do the bounty sources is what they decide needs to get attention
So if you go to the patreon you're giving money to the project to then they could disperse it to bounty source
Wherever they deem that makes sense. Okay. Yeah, and that's that's so that's and of course
You could you could subscribe to bounty source directly too. It's yeah. Yeah, but there's also um
Like just to point out that 14 000 number is not true
They this is they've already posted this before not not this particular example, but about two months ago
They posted like we got 9 000 out for bounties and it's like well no
That's the total number that is potential to be given
Well, he's saying number given but he's saying here in this post he's saying paid out
He's saying that we have paid out not what's event what's hanging out there hanging
Yeah, but if you look at the claimed bounties, um, the math is not accurate. There's like four thousand dollars missing from their claim
Which i'm not saying that they aren't doing what there's you know
They're not doing a good thing and getting developers money and stuff like that
I'm just saying that they they they kind of inflated a little bit
So the uh, I always prefer them not to do that bounty source page is not loading properly for me right now
But it is worth it. There's a link in the show notes. It's actually I think
Elementary os when you when you follow them from the outside seems a little opaque
It's kind of hard to see what they're doing where they're going, you know, they got they're probably working on stuff
But when you go to this it's it's sort of
Sort of it's like pulling back the curtains insider's view. Yeah, you can you can get a you can get a pretty quick
Uh, yeah, this page just loaded for me. So you can see there's 625 dollars worth of bounties available for their new mail program
elementary os
565 bounties for gtk plus 520 for the shell 365 midori
315 pantheon files and they have different stuff in here
You can see like for their app center
One of the things they want work on worked on is the show the most popular apps feature and they're willing to pay money
for that nice
I remember this is making me excited for when their next version comes out. Yeah, it's been so long and I haven't wanted to
The current one's so old it is it is kind of fascinating to watch it
From that perspective, so I decided I'd toss him a few bucks to the bounty source
Just because I think it's an interesting idea
Totally, you know because when i'm i'm the reason why i'm what i'm
For those of you that are wondering why i'm looking at this stuff so much is
I eventually want to come up with a model like this for jb when we can afford to do so through our patreon
But I don't know
Support the community that keeps you here. And so I was kind of looking at the wimpy's model
I like that a lot because I like establishing those relationships with people, right?
Uh, but then this is another way to go
But this seems like for something that's not a if you're not a software project this this model doesn't really work very well
But it's interesting to kind of check in and see what different people are doing and I find both
Approaches to be very valid. So it's it's good to watch I think
All right, wes the way yes, go ahead. You could adapt the way you could adapt bounty source to jb
Is that if you are using?
uh open source software in the production of
your
podcasts and video casts
You could post bounties to add features or fix issues in the tools that you're using
Sure, because that that way then let's pick ffmpeg because I know you use it a lot
Let's suppose you need it to tell you the price of tea in china
You put a bounty up for that to happen in ffmpeg and ffmpeg benefit and you've clearly funded that
Body of work so you could make it work for you know
You know what you're doing and it might be a little easier to navigate because obviously elementary is a
A rather large project and there's lots and lots of bounties there and I imagine your the scope of your bounties would be a lot
Smaller. Yeah
There's a there's a big problem bounty source though in the sense that if you put money out for a particular thing
And then no one does it that money is still out
Like there's a difference between pay like that
This is actually one of the things that are mentioned about them paying money to developers
This is not true because of the way bounty source is structured
You're paying money to bounty source because as soon as it's put into that particular project to or that task
It bounty source takes that money
So maybe elementary has paid out that amount of money in general to bounty source, but no one's actually claimed it
So if you don't like if you scroll down their list
It says this is how much has been claimed by developers and it's it's a lot different than what has actually been put into the
The bounty source itself. So if you're going to
Donate to a particular project. It's better to just give them the money to the project
And say maybe maybe ask the ear market for this purpose or something
That sucks for elementary. So you're saying that elementary have
Put money into bounty source to say we want these things
Implemented or fixed or whatever they want and they've paid some 14 000 in to a thing
And that money has been invested by them, but the work hasn't been done
And it's the money's effectively sitting in escrow waiting for somebody to do the work
Yes, there's about four thousand waiting for someone to do it
I guess they figure that it's in the wash that eventually somebody will come along and claim that work
I hope so. Yeah, what happens if that does it?
Or you maybe the people don't even maybe there are people in those projects
They're not even aware that those are a thing that they're willing to pay for
And what if you cancel? Oh, that's a good point. Like if it's gtk work, for example
A gtk maintainer might not even know there's a a elementary bounty for it
yeah, he might even do the work and then that money is just
Already put into banning source, but no one claims because they didn't know to claim it and it's just there forever
I guess until they cancel the project right if they canceled that line item, I guess it would probably return the money
I'm, not sure about that
I I didn't know that's how bounty source worked. I'd certainly be really interested in hearing more about
particularly from elementary
um, i've just listened to a fascinating podcast today with stewart langridge on the uh, simply elementary podcast
It was a really insightful talk about his experiences with elementary and some of his
Thoughts on on their project and their direction. It's a great listen
If you if you've not heard that it's definitely one to go and listen to
But I I feel bad for elementary that they may have invested money that they're
Not getting full value out of
I would I would estimate it's a matter of counseling the bounty and then the money probably returns
So if so, but then it's but then of course, it's just the process of administratively following up on those things, right?
Yeah, there's a few of those gtk things those line items for gtk. They've been in for a while
For a while. I I know for at least at least two of those i've seen for a long time because I used I was
when they first the reason I know about this thing about a source of stuff is because when they announced this like
Uh a couple months ago
They said like 9 000 was paid out and I had a conversation with daniel and one of the developers that essentially
I was I realized that it's not
It's not exactly paid out to a developer. It's just paid out to bounty source
So, um, I didn't ask him about what happens if you cancel it, but um, hopefully
They could if they cancel that they get the money back. But at the moment it's just you know in limbo
Yeah, bounty source seems to have continued to grow but it hasn't grown at the rate i've expected either
So they have continued to expand it's it's uh, it's worth. I've also kind of created as
code based
Patreon type thing too. Hmm. I think that's interesting. I think for us i'm going to look at it
I'm going to look at it. I don't know if if if it works directly well for us or not, but I like it
So i'm going to play around more keep looking into it. I'd love to hear from the elementary os project. Yeah, absolutely
Okay, so I want to shift gears and start talking about this new own cloud release
This looks like version 9 is a pretty big deal. Uh, and you know, you could probably deploy
Own cloud on a digital ocean droplet. They'll probably have
They'll probably have a really easy deployment here in a few days for version 9
So use our promo code if you would do unplugged and get a ten dollar credit over digital ocean
Digital ocean is a simple cloud housing provider dedicated offering most intuitive and easy way for you
Discipline up your own server up in the cloud. They have uh, mostly linux. I mean, let's be honest west
It's the superior os
But they do have a little free bsd too. You can get that's your fancy
Yeah
You can get started in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans start only five dollars per month for 512 megabytes of ram
A 20 gigabyte ssd because they all ssd's a blazing fast cpu and a terabyte of transfer
Their pricing plan is crazy straightforward. In fact, you can go to their pricing page and do yourself a favor tab it over to hourly
Look at that wes
Three cents an hour two gigabytes of ram two core processor 40 gigabyte ssd and three terabytes of transfer, you know
It's kind of it's becoming you have just something you want to do. Oh you're compiling the kernel
Yeah, just do it on digital ocean droplet, you know
If you're using things like docker too, it's really ridiculously fast
You can get deployed on a droplet in no time and they've data centers in new york san francisco. Singapore, Amsterdam london
Toronto
Germany got a new one opened up in india, too. That stuff's crazy. I tell you what, but you know, it's cray cray
super cray cray
intense cray cray
That interface. Yeah. Oh my goodness wes that interface is so good. They have a straightforward interface
That's very easy to use but yet extremely powerful
I'm saying you can set like multiple machines dns host names at the same time set up ssh private keys backups
You can transfer between data centers. You can do private networking. You can destroy the machine
It html5 console all of that one click application deployment, but it's still cray cray simple
I'm saying cray cray simple and they have a straightforward api
To make it even better
To just step it up a notch
They have a really great api and there's a lot of great open source code written around and go check out some of those
Great community tutorials written too in their community section super good stuff super
Really well written well documented digital ocean.com. Just use the promo code do unplugged and a big
Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring linux unplugged linux unplugged
Okay, so, uh, I don't know if uh, you guys in the mumble room are own cloud users wes
Are you an own cloud user? Come on wes on and off again
But i've been thinking about using it again
I got I got an own cloud instance
I've been running out for about a year and I got a real heavy into it for a bit and I backed off for file
Syncing i've been using it for card dav and cal dab. See that's what I was thinking about. Yeah
Are you liking it? I do and I use sync thing for the file syncing and i'm using dropbox still as well
Hmm can't help it
So own cloud 9 is shipping
Uh, and this is kind of a major release the own cloud version 9 shipped with code signing
They say which promises to offer users with safer
Code, I don't know exactly how but by verifying the integrity of their own cloud installations during upgrades or installing apps
code signing
Yeah
Uh, they say with 8 million users own cloud is the world's leading file sync and share solution providing users with safe home for all
Of their data founded six years ago as a project with the goal of bringing privacy and control back to users own cloud is where it
Is today thanks to contributions from well over a thousand
Open source programmers designers translators and others
Uh the big hot features
You ready for this one? Oh, I want I want to hear administrators will happily
Happily learn that it is now possible to add as many own cloud servers as they want or need as trusted servers to their infrastructures
Multiple own cloud servers y'all sharing and exchanging of usernames along with automatic name completion
Yeah from all the shared servers is a breeze trusted own cloud servers can be manually added by admins who have control over the automatic
edition of servers
And starting version 9.0 organizations and institutions like cern. Yeah, that's right
We'll be able to integrate deeply with their massive own cloud installations with their various storage solutions
In their infrastructure thanks to the addition of a new storage api
That allows for unimaginable scaling levels. Don't even try to imagine it folks built into own cloud
Enterprise edition is also coming next month. We got some nice ui improvements that look great. Hello slack
Nice calendar. Hello
It's looking really good
I want to talk a little bit more about this
But I thought instead of me talking about it west I'd play a little bit from the own cloud site
Are you ready for this one? Let's hear it. This is direct from the own cloud site
I thought we'd hear it from the horse's mouth as always. We are working hard to give you tools to manage your files. Wait
Wait, that's no good. That was no good
I we got it. We got it. We got it. We got to give them a little tip
Let's fix that out. Hold on. Stop the show. Stop the show. We got to give them a little tip
This is this is us contributing back to the open source community wess
This is how we would do if you're gonna create you first you got to get yourself some hipster kickstarter music
For the that is essential, right? So you get that going that makes everything sound better
You wait for that to play a little bit then you start your video
Hello own clouders and welcome to your personal guided tour of own cloud 9
The newest own cloud release is full of improvements and new features
This is better, right much better. Let's start on the main files page. This is the default landing for the web interface
In fact, we should just have that for the whole show. That's not bad. I'm down to keep listening
So that's our advice to the own cloud project good release solid release
But you know, maybe uh put some hipster music in that video. Come on now, so it makes everything better
Uh, look at that though. It's looking really great. So own cloud 9 wess
What's been holding back sharing? What's been holding you back? Be honest with me
Take the gloves off wess
I think mostly just that there had been those concerns about you know large file syncing and I have
I've been using sync thing for a long time. So i've had that problem solved
So it's more been like am I ready?
Do I want to set up the card dev cal dev server?
But with like the documents app and like kind of the more features they're getting it's making it more like well
I already have more than enough servers lying around or I could spin up in an instant. So why not man?
This ui is looking is looking really good too
Anybody in the mumble room currently using own cloud and willing to maybe try upgrading to version 9 and reporting back in the near future
I'm I might do it
Oh, look at that. No, wait, hold on. Sorry. Let me see. That would be completely unknown
Nobody wants to do it. All right fine
I've never installed gnu slash. Oh, go ahead. Go ahead. Go ahead. You could take the you can take the fault
I don't want to have to do it
I'm not using it at the moment. I've tried
Uh, I think five six seven and eight
And yeah, the file syncing
Uh was a thing that I wanted to work and it didn't work for me
But i'm gonna try nine again
And I really want own cloud to work and and there are features of own cloud that I should be using because I do have
um
Sort of um notes that I sync around between all of my machines and it would make much more sense to actually
Use something like own cloud to synchronize that stuff. Yeah, I think I really want
I really want the file syncing to work and that just hasn't quite cut it in the past
So with that article about CERN and all of their petabytes of data that they're shunting around the place every day
I'm hope hoping that that's just not marketing spiel and and that's really being
I see i'm worried that until they replace c-sync
Because of the underlying sync library. I just I worry that the the actual client sync is never going to be enough
I just want to be good enough
So like my wife or I could like put up have a own cloud server with my friends
You know what you could do too is you could always point own cloud at a sync thing directory
That seems like the way to go
So I want to get a couple other people to jump here. So Rarian, you're you're a heavy own cloud user
Could you tell us are you looking forward to version 9? What are your thoughts?
I don't know. We'll see
Are you too worried or you're too dependent on it to upgrade?
I'm too dependent on it to upgrade. I I've had a problem with any
Syncing issues like you guys have described but I don't sync huge files like isos
So, okay. I'd be curious to see what muhahaha has to say in the mumble room
Does it sound like you might be planning to upgrade to version 9?
Yes, I just start to use it. So I don't think it will be that big of a problem. You're already using version 9
Oh, um 8.1. Oh, oh, oh, you mean it's a sort of a fresh install of 8.1. So it's probably gonna be an easy
Yeah, that does make sense. Yeah. Yeah jump on that. That's why you can all right
Maybe I should do it. It seems like yeah, maybe it'll be fun to just get it going
I could do a review of it too if I didn't upgrade
And would people be a chat room? Would you be interested in a rate and share files with each other?
Do people care anymore? Yeah, go ahead
Sorry, uh, so
I you I know you're a heavy gnome user chris and uh, so am I
And it integrates very well with the gnome desktop it integrates with the built-in notes app in gnome
Uh, so it's easy to sync notes across. It's really great in that regard
Hmm
See i've been i've actually been really enjoying mate
Okay, so I was actually considering
Switching but yeah. Yeah, that is nice. That is nice. You're just dropping the bomb like that. Yeah
Well, I don't know. It's just I've been I sat i've been using the apollo a lot and then when I sat down
Uh at the gnome 3 desktop
It was the file manager the file manager
I like I prefer the way kaja
works
That to me just works better. But yeah points well taken. I do like the integration with gnome 3
I'll consider if people are interested. Let me know about a review of own cloud
I'll take a look at it. Even if it even if it blows up in your face. That's still another episode. Jeez. Thanks
Thanks. Yeah. Uh, well, hey, no, I can't blow up my face because
code signing
You're secure code signing good to go. Don't have to worry about it
Hmm, I guess I do like the idea of updates
But you know, this is all goes back to own clouds when one of the big advocates that don't get updates from their repo
Right get them from us directly
All right, i'll dig around i'll see where i'll give it a i'll give it a consideration, you know, I was
I've been i've been recently thinking too about using own cloud to store. Uh,
Like a digital filing cabinet because uh, I just got so much paperwork, right?
Like, you know, like when you buy something or you get a divorce
Or you get a loan or whatever
Like there's just moments in your life where all of a sudden you have all this paperwork just dropped in your lap
And I feel like if at that point in time if I scanned it and saved it to a system that I used for years
I could I could actually manage this
But the problem is I set all the paperwork down aside and then it just goes a scatter
It goes all over the place and it never makes into a filing cabinet
So I was thinking geez if I could if I could get some scans of these things put them in an own cloud server
That's protected
But then I would be every time it came time to do an upgrade. I'd be like, oh my stuff you need backups
Yeah, that's true. You need backups. That's a good point
So I might I might I might give it a go because I have been needing like a digital vault for some things like that
And so you never know you never know kaja is pronounced kaha
Not like cougar or coger
Yeah, kaja the file manager kaha kaha. It's a good file manager. Yeah, it is a good reminds me of the good old days
All right, you know what else reminds me of the good old days ting because they're keeping mobile simple, man
They're keeping mobile simple and I love that they're just out to make mobile make sense
It's your minutes your messages your megabytes and that's what you pay
It's a flat six dollars for the line and it's your usage on top of that very straightforward. No contracts
No early termination fees
Really good customer support
It's kind of obvious average annual savings per device for a business
with 11 to 20 employees per device
440 dollars
Linux.ting.com linux.ting.com go there to support the show and get yourself a discount
They have really great customer service. If you want to call them 1855 ting ftw's
They got some great great supports all the nice devices from just the gsm or cdma sim card
Feature phone all the way up to the cadillac smartphones
The nice ones and they give you great control with their fantastic
Dashboard but wes let's not mince words. What's really important right now?
Freaking sales. Oh sales moto e second gen
10 74 unlocked off contract. Nobody's standing in the way of you and your updates
lg volt 2 yeah
66 bucks samsung s6
549 unlocked off contract you own that you're going to get the updates right when samsung finally gets around to releasing them
That's the way to go. It really is also they've got the nexus devices like they've got a refurbished nexus 5 on sale right now
They got the internet phones. They got them all
Linux.ting.com go check them out linux.ting.com support the show by visiting them try out the savings calculator
You'll be very happy you did. I think so linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring linux unplugged
Okay, we got to talk about this a little bit with the virtual lug because I just don't know what to make of it
Microsoft's gone totally cray-cray and they've announced sequel server on linux
On linux. Popey and I had a chance to talk about this a little bit today on tech talk today and Popey said he actually fell
Out of his his chair
So I think he was pretty surprised what was your reaction when Microsoft made this announcement. I was pretty surprised too
I'm curious to see it running
Yeah, so mumble room. Let me know in the chat room if you have well
I'd love to know your initial reactions, but Popey for those who didn't get a chance to listen to tech talk
Recap here your thoughts when you heard that sequel server coming out for Linux, and what do you think it means?
Popey that's your just talking to you Popey anyway, all right
Andy Karses you your takes you think this is a go to go up against Oracle you go
Yeah, I mean
There's been so much David losing so much ground to the Linux Oracle constellation hardware servers
I think you think that you so you really think it's more of a straight Oracle competition play and less of a
Trying to stay relevant by going to Linux play
Well, I mean they also want to sell this stuff like with virtualization being the primary platform being you know cloud first
Then you know the primary apparatus they need to get as much
Value at as they can so they need to like sell sequel server licenses
And if you're not gonna put Linux on the machine then at least you know be using a code for Visual Studio
Yeah, you know I think it's a pretty good move. I could I I wouldn't deploy it personally
But I could see it like at least from my perspective
you know if there's DBAs that manage the databases if that's what they want to do to provide like a
Redundant sequel interface that I connect to then if it works. That's great. I
I wonder if any of you recall a time and place where I
Was in a spot, and I wonder if any of you found yourselves there
You're sitting down you're trying to come up with the pros and cons of deploying different systems and when you look at an application
that required Microsoft sequel
from a Linux administrator standpoint I knew that meant a
Windows IIS server most likely a Windows server server
Windows sequel server, so maybe two three Windows servers locked into a sequel box
It meant that this was going to be yet another deployment a frickin Microsoft Windows and sequel sequel was the way
was such a was such a
Conversation stopper for me when I would go into oftentimes for clients one of the things I could do is we can move these things
Over to Linux you won't have to upgrade to Windows 2003 whatever etc etc won't have to go to 2008. We'll go to this
But when sequel came up that totally stopped the conversation and that in exchange right well, I'm just still
There's other things that's worse, but yeah, I wonder if if for people like me now who are coming into shops and
Trying to get people to move over
Maybe move off of Windows and move on to a different system like you could now spin up a frickin droplet running sequel server
Yeah, right right use that as your as your sequel server your your off-site premise of sequel server
I mean you can't right now Greece. It's not shipping at the moment, but it will be mid 2017. Yeah
they say I just find that to be a
Game changer, it's like and that combined with their announcement today as well
That they are joining the Eclipse Foundation
They say today
I'm happy to share that Microsoft is taking its relationship with the Eclipse community to the next level by joining the Eclipse Foundation as
a solutions member
Joining the Eclipse Foundation enables us to collaborate more closely with the Eclipse community to deliver a great set of tools and services for all
development teams
Continuously improve our cloud service services SDKs and tools what?
What did you know that at Microsoft their developer mission is to deliver experiences that empower any developer building any application on any OS
Get it out of here this I don't like that tone. I don't even I don't use though
Uh-huh. Yeah, it's pretty it's it's it's it's great except for the contradiction of the universal Windows platform
Yeah. Yeah, that is interesting in that light. You're right. You're right. I I actually wonder if this if this isn't really just about
Getting people to develop more services that use Azure in a long long run. I don't know though. I could be wrong on that
Java developers, don't you want to use Azure?
Yeah, wimpy you look at this and you say okay. We got Visual Studio code. We got Microsoft sequel
Dotnet going open source joining the Eclipse Foundation, but wimpy where the hell is Skype?
Where Skype?
well
And this is the important distinction
The previous four things you mentioned are all squarely
developer and enterprise focused and Skype is
desktop focused for Linux and
Microsoft don't love Linux Microsoft love enterprise Linux
And my only concern is if you adopt Microsoft SQL Server on Linux
What happens if it falls out of favor at some point in the future and you've got everything
Invested in it. Then where do you go? And this is why open source is the safe bet because you can't have
The rug pulled from beneath you, you know as best as people have tried when when Oracle
acquired
Open Office and MySQL and other projects and other organizations have they have always come out better and stronger because of open source. I
agree
What does Microsoft SQL have that Maria Mongo couch Postgres and the others don't?
Well now we're asking a question above my pay grade
But I do know that it's a well-respected SQL database server that has some nice features that I do know
Microsoft SQL Server. Yeah, I don't know
Microsoft on it. I well, I know the origins of the Microsoft SQL Server
Because I worked for the company that Microsoft
Bought their SQL Server from in order to create Microsoft SQL Server. This story is going full circle of us
Way way way way back. So Microsoft SQL Server was actually
Sybase SQL Server four point something. Oh, I remember that and they they bought the rights to the old
Code, so I think when Sybase released Sybase
SQL
10 or 11 they sold the source code to four point nine or something like that to Microsoft and then Microsoft, you know
reinvented it into Microsoft SQL Server
Yeah, wow good good callback. That is that does ring a bell. So what do you think wimpy?
What were your impressions when you heard this story?
That's that's a history with this
well, I was never involved in that side of the business at Sybase, but
It doesn't surprise me. I mean, yeah, Microsoft's loving of Linux is clearly enterprise focused and
It makes sense for them to have their database product in that lineup alongside
You know with the Xamarin acquisition and they develop a story
Which I think is going to continue to grow and we will probably see other Microsoft technologies
I think we'll know when they're really serious when exchange could run on Linux
Yeah, you know, I just look at this now though
And I two things strike me about this number one when it comes to Microsoft
You now live in a world where you can use Visual Studio code to write open source.net software to use Microsoft SQL services or
Linux servers running on Azure
That's pretty weird
And then the other thing that I find to be really interesting about this is at the other end of the spectrum is Apple
Open-sourcing Swift making Linux general libraries and the runtime available. I like all of the compiler like
This is a really crazy time for Linux on the server
It is it is so far and above the accepted platform now for on the server side. It's really remarkable
So eat that free BSD. I'm sorry. What what'd you say? What?
I didn't hear a word. This is BSD unplugged
Yeah, yeah, go ahead with yeah, I think you're right I think that
My Microsoft are reinventing themselves as a well as two things
It's clear. It's cloud and mobile
There are cloud and mobile first organization, which I would never quite understood how you can be first in two things
But hey, hey. Yeah, I thank you. Thank you
But I think this is a tacit admission that Linux has won the enterprise server space and that Microsoft have to
be a
Provider of software in that enterprise market in order to continue to be relevant, right?
it really has nothing to do with Microsoft being a good open source citizen or
No, and keep in mind sequels not open source, right? Just releasing it for Linux runs
It has to do with that
Linux is in such a market a dominant position that after years they finally bent to this position
But they seem like they're bending fast now
Yeah, now that they've come to this new reality. They seem like they're actually moving in the direction
Yeah, I mean this this sequel server must have been in the works for some time because that's not something you just cook up
You know in in short term that must have been
Going for you know, many many months. Yeah, and and even in terms of internal staff knowledge
Retooling your staff to work on Linux or bringing the staffing up. That's a big move
Yeah, like that all of that takes like when you think about behind the scenes a company who makes a competitive product
Having to retool to ship this on Linux
That's that's some interesting stuff right there and it's Microsoft we're talking about it's not Adobe which would be incredible
It's Microsoft and man, there's a lot of people that figure all into that
Just want to get things done crowd. It's like that's the tool they know
Mm-hmm, and so if that means that they can deploy it on Linux and they'll just works. That's that's that's nice
Well exactly right, you know, you've now got a migration strategy that doesn't involve changing your underlying
rdbms right you can just have a Microsoft SQL Server on Linux that scales out horizontally and
Your application can scale with that and you're not constrained by the limitations of the underlying operating system
You know, which is you know in order to do web scale applications. You need to be able to do that these days
I bet it was I bet it was ZFS coming to a point to the made him do that was
Huh, this is interesting though and what's next is there something next for Microsoft is there another thing coming I
Don't think it's exchange because I think exchange is too hooked in with Active Directory
Mm-hmm. So I think it's got to be see sequel sequel was its own beast on its own anyways. Yeah, so there's something else out there
Something else. They're gonna put office on Linux. No, I is
Oh, I hope not. Oh boy. I hope nice new you know, though
I do have a bit of a recommendation for all the gals and guys over at Microsoft that are having to train up on Linux
That's our friends over at Linux Academy
This is where you go to get brushed up on your skill set whether it's for your gerb whether it's maybe because you're a
Multinational multi-billion dollar corporations with tens of thousands of employees that has to retool on the new market reality
There's probably a use for Linux Academy. So go to Linux Academy comm slash unplug to get the unplug discount over
2325 video courses man
What would be crazy is a mash-up of over the like last year of that number because this has been going up and up and up
Self-paced courses are awesome and I love that for somebody who is self-motivated
But what I think is also really great about that is they have a great community to kind of help move you along a little
Bit when you need that and they have instructor help they have instructor help. They have instructor help did I mention?
Instructor mentoring is available. Yeah, that's nice scenario based labs. Those are really great
You can you go into an everyday environment you get something done you work in that advanced lab environment from beginning to end over SSH
So you're not an animal
Which is really nice. I tell you what Wes when I'm over at Linux Academy comm slash unplug
You know what I'm doing? I'm saving money on my future. Yeah, yeah
I'm making an investment in Chris and that feels good. The graded server exercises are brilliant. Why sit around and wait all day?
We got computers that can compute right now
Graded server exercise give you real-time feedback like a boost like they should you got a little exam anxiety. Ooh
Here's my tip drink a whole bunch before the test if you don't want to do that though
What you ought to do is go over to Linux Academy because they got stuff over that I'll help you prep for those exams
They have a fantastic
Availability planner you tell it how much time you got available
Automatically creates courseware for you you guys seven plus distros to choose from it's just the courseware and the server that it spins up
On demand. Oh, you need to learn AWS. They got courseware on that you get in the Red Hat stuff
They got courseware on that you're developing Python Ruby get into Android or PHP. Guess what courseware on that all of it and more
Linux academy.com slash unplugged go check them out and a big thank you to links Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Okay, so I'm pretty sure I actually did a little research before the show to make sure I'm getting the pronunciation of this right
It's it's something we've never talked about before. It's kind of new. I hadn't really heard about it
It's called I think you say shaw link and I got a little video to introduce. Oh, let's see
Hi guys, welcome to my channel today. I'm making something absolutely amazing
It's called shashlik and in translation is basically big pieces of meat on the skewer, which are grilled or barbecued
Oh wait, that was that was another video. Sorry. No, it's not it's not barbecue skewers
It is software that allows you to transparently run Android applications on a standard Linux desktop as easily and simply as possible
Not large chunks of meat. Don't sound good though. That's too bad because I thought that was a you see much better than the own
Cloud video it says the music and they got music on the on this one. I thought that was pretty good music and me
Yeah, they got music meat and you know what it really yeah
At this to the JB repertoire
At this to the JB repertoire man, I'll tell you what you're gonna talk about if you're gonna talk about meat on sticks
This is that is well, unfortunately, it's not what we're talking about what we're talking about is shashlik and
Wes and I you you've tried it on a couple of desktops. I tried it on an arch desktop
I've tried it on an Ubuntu Mate 1510 desktop. What are you trying it on right now? I'm trying it on Linux Mint right here
Okay, so this is a pretty new project and I'm excited that they're like
They're really giving a go at this and it's it's it's a big ambitious project. I gotta say Wes
I ran into a few bumps
Yes, it's definitely it's definitely bumpy
Hmm. Okay. I was hoping maybe we had more success cuz I've only got one application. I've got one as well
But it did work, I mean it like it it really did work and that was cool. Okay. Okay. All right
So when I tried it, I tried the snapchat own cloud
I tried Evernote. I tried telegram. Oh, I didn't think of that
And here's the first couple of there's a couple of limitations when you're gonna run these Android apps on your Linux desktop
They have to have
x86 builds
Not all of them
On your Linux desktop. They have to have x86 builds
Not a lot of Google Play apps are doing that at the moment because you know people are downloading on mobile
They want them to be as small as possible. So they're optimizing the builds. So that's one big downside is it does have to have
x86 build in it another downside, of course
You're not gonna have play services and then maybe on the minor category of downsides is it does pull down a bunch of KD dependencies
Oh interesting. So I installed the dev on their website and it didn't it didn't you know, there were no dependencies
I just installed it. I did have to comment out it did try to use KDialog
Yes, I just commented that out and it's been working. Oh, okay. Okay, cuz it still prints the message
It's trying to make a dialogue for
Okay. Okay. So I did have a it looks like some things on F-Droid have the x86. Oh, yeah. Sure. Okay
That's nice that I was able to download the Jupiter broadcasting app and open the live stream on your desktop on my desktop
That's cool. Emulated Android. That was pretty neat. I wanted to try the audible app because I have an audible subscription
And there's no way to listen to audible on Linux that I know of and so I was like, well
That's a perfect opportunity is I will run the audible app. It just crashes immediately
I couldn't get Evernote to install because Evernote didn't have an x86 build in their play store. So Evernote was a no-go
I will say it does seem to take quite some time to load. Yeah. Yeah that sounds a little
Little weird because the atom processes are x86
Yeah, I agree. I don't know
I thought that's why I thought there would be more there were x86 as well because there's there are x86 Android phones on the market
I was surprised by that Kodi would be an interesting one to try out the why would you bother since you could just use the Kodi Linux version
True. They show they show a whole bunch of apps
But the ones they don't actually show any of the ones I tried in there in their main screen
But here's what the experience is like is once you have it you download the APK you you tell shosh link to install it
And then it actually gets integrated in with your desktop launchers desktop menu
When you launch the app it shows up in your taskbar as a running application with the desktop app icon
So when I ran the audible app it showed up in my dock on gnome 3 and it had the audible icon
Which was pretty cool and I launched it by hitting the super key and typing audible in gnome 3 search and hitting enter
And so that but that part of it is really damn slick and they're iterating on this thing super super fast
I wonder if people out in the audience have messed with this anybody in the in the Bumble room mess with any of these
There's a couple other out there that let you run Android apps on your Linux desktop is anybody played with this in the mumble room
There's some validity to it I think
I've used not this one but I've used the one that Google was talking about
Right there's one that integrates in with the Chrome browser that I've used too
And there's also some I'm actually kind of yeah I was kind of bothered by when you said it uses K dialogue
It kind of makes me confused because KDE deprecated that like
Well there's that
You know that was just an install script too
Hmm okay well yeah I guess you were able to disable with that right so
I literally just commented that line out yes
Yeah yeah so it has so as you would imagine it's a couple it's a couple of pieces of technology
You have the shosh link D which runs Android space and responsible for a few things
Drawing a custom boot splash drawing the back and you know menu buttons and notification receiving and pass them to the host operating system
So that's pretty cool and then they have the runtime that's the desktop side of the integration layer provides small scripts to install APKs
Extracting the icon and creating the desktop menu icon and copying any relevant files around
It also provides the startup script which launched the emulator oh the emulator yeah that's the name suggests this is a fork of QMU
Of the QMU Android emulator from the SDK so that's where they're kind of getting the secret bolts
I see yeah it's modified to show the window icon and the title of the app are running not like the emulator
That's kind of an interesting approach though near future plans
Drop the manual APPD parsing fixed network stuff which I don't know what that means
Yeah I was I was you were able to stream video I was watching the live stream
Yeah simple window resizing to be more intuitive tighten the packaging getting access to the better access to the file system using fuse
It would be pretty neat like if you get this going and get good pass-through of you know devices
Honestly yeah because there are applications that come out for Android that I would kill to have on the Linux desktop
And I would use these for a decent Android or the Evernote client from Android that could actually use my microphone
Control clients on yes different things like that yes honestly you know what the huge light app would be nice to have on my desktop
A very simple app like that would be great so I could definitely see this there's a few things out there even maybe Microsoft Office
Hey possibly yep which is great great I remember many thoughts on Android apps on on the Linux desktop for you close the book on this topic
I haven't tried this but the idea is awesome because you guys should try it out and see which ones work see if we can find something that is it useful
Yeah I give them credit for shipping something right now yeah it's worth checking out and playing around with
It is a little hard to figure out like yeah when I installed the dev it didn't get added to the path or anything
Oh really I installed from the AUR on my machine and I did the bin so I did shoshlink-bin from the AUR
And then you saw I ran the you do the you do install and then there's run you don't have to mess with run but you do install install the APK right and that was it
But then you know you think about this maybe in context of Ubuntu phone right right and you think maybe this would be a decent way to run some APKs on Ubuntu phone
That would be pretty sweet be the right size hmm except for its arm yeah I gotta work on that so it's called shoshlink-shashlik
And we have a link in the showroom says no they do not want this for Ubuntu touch no Micah is upset about that sorry Micah sorry Micah you should join the mumble room and tell me why
Because it might be a way to get some nice like what about Waze right what if you want Waze or what if you want Google Maps on your Ubuntu touch device
I don't know if they would work because the play API and all that but I think I think they're actually some serious I think they're actually some serious uses for this
Doesn't mean stop developing Linux desktop applications certainly not that would be crazy we would never say that you know what else is crazy not attending a live Linux unplugged
Oh just don't make that mistake be here you really you really sold that way don't don't don't do that that would be don't don't no hey you know we should give a quick mention
You can come say hi to Wes at Linux Fest Northwest and me and the crew yeah that's Northwest is coming up the end of April all right jblive.tv for live shows
jupyterbroadcasting.com calendar linuxactionshow.reddit.com to get it converted to your local time zone we do it every single Tuesday we'd love to have you in our mumble room
Thanks for being here see you next week
Wow we haven't had a short Linux unplugged for a while that's kind of refreshing wow yeah crazy hey Chris yes sir I gotta go but I just want to tell you I just signed up for the Linux Academy
Hey very nice that's great enjoy that Mr. Radios all right have a great rest of your day sure right on you too we'll see you guys later right on
Actually I think we had two firsts today in terms of JB shows oh late on me we began 10 minutes early and we ended early no way we began early wow I began on the nail I started this show early no way no way it was
10 minutes early yeah 10 minutes early wow I never do that how did we not usually we have enough things happening yeah I just I'd managed to get through all the things wow there you go look at that
Rekai mentions I can use MPV to listen to audible books I don't know I don't know how to do that but that sounds good Rekai you gotta give me details on that
Oh I just installed Flappy Bird really using the using the thing I don't know if it'll work but that would be that would be decent that wouldn't be bad you know a games yeah that wouldn't be bad yeah
That's actually a game that I'm surprised hasn't been ported to Linux is Flappy Bird or like a clone of it yeah because there's web versions of it everywhere and there's like 5,000 different clones of it
Well Rodden I wouldn't mind a K Flappy Bird on my system that runs natively no that's Clappy Bird Clappy Bird oh there we go I like that come on let's not talk about that
Hey look at Rekai linking me to the Arch wiki here with how to play your frickin audible books use an MPV how about that I got Icon are you are you playing Flappy Bird not yet it's loading very slowly it's very slowly loading
Well you know that's a big game that's a real big game yeah that's a big game very complex too yeah this is not the fastest of computers no that's what it is it's the computer yeah blame the computer
Linux's fault slow as a dog you know what you gotta do is get yourself that new Sputnik that's got the Thunderbolt on there I have thought about that oh yeah I have
Is it on sale yet? No no although you could probably get the Windows version now can't you for some arbitrary reason
I want one of those new 76 systems that are out yeah which one it's the one that's one up from the gazelle I was looking at that one I was like man I need to find a need and justification for me
Oh I know right yeah hey look at this look at this yeah that doesn't surprise me using pie game there is a clone of Flappy Bird yeah are you I wonder if this is I wonder if I search the AUR if this is an AUR oh I'm not using Arch on this computer
I was gonna say if this is an AUR I'm gonna get it right now huh there's probably a PPA yeah there's probably a PPA