Are you listening?
Introducing sound beaming you hear the audio others don't without headphones
When you are inside of the bubble you get the sound the volume the immersiveness of it and where you outside of it
You can you cannot get it. Sometimes you can hear a little bit of noise
Sometimes you you hear there's something going on beside you
But you don't get the volume and don't get the immersiveness of the sound experience. You don't need
To tell the device where you are. It's not streaming to like one exact place. It it follows you wherever you go
So it's personally for you follows you place what you want
inside your head
It's sound beaming West and it's just as cool as it possibly could be
It's a futuristic audio technologies from Novito systems and on Friday
They'll debut a full-fledged desktop device. It sits right there on your desk and
Beam sound into your head noodle from wherever you are without headphones
Yeah
It uses a 3d sensing module and locates and tracks your ear position sending audio via
Ultrasonic waves to create sound pockets right by your ears
What's interesting is you can make me heard in stereo or a spatial 3d mode that creates 360 degree sound around the listener
So it's like headphones with surround sound. I think this is something you're gonna have to hear to believe but it it is so Star Trek
It's awesome. You should try listening to Linux some plugs
Hello friends and welcome in to episode
380 of your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Wes
This episode is brought to you by a cloud guru the leader in learning for cloud Linux and other modern tech skills hundreds of courses
Thousands of hands-on labs get certified get higher get learning at a cloud guru
Dot-com episode 380 is up
It's fresh and it's another Sunday edition of the show where West and I for the last time for at least
For the foreseeable future are recording ahead and we have kind of a special show for you today
This is one of those episodes where we attended some events and took notes
So you don't have to and we'll come back with a fresh report on some Linux events from over the weekend
We're gonna tell you what's going on with a Mac story and how it impacts Linux users and why it makes Linux the best
OS ever of course and then right here. I've been working on it. Oh gosh, it's big
It's really it's a huge machine, but beautiful
I had to wait until the honeymoon period was over so I could give you the full honest review of the Dell Precision
5750 mobile
workstation
People say this kind of stuff all the time, but this is legitimately a Macbook killer
this is Dell going right after the Macbook with chamfered edges and everything and I'll tell you how it stacks up and
What you need to know about it and how much it costs for a configuration like this and while you're distracted
I'm gonna sneak it into my bag. I don't blame you one bit
But before we get into the community news the pics that we have and all of that
I want to say time appropriate greetings to our mumble room. Hello virtual lug. Hello. Hello
We got 14 folks in there today because it's a Sunday and they had a huge
Love blog going earlier today with some jellyfin developers in there and we'll tell you more about that in a little bit
This is like the this is the post show to the love plug this week. Really it is
Yeah
So this weekend and late last week two pretty significant
Linux community events were going on the Linux application summit and
Seagull did you get a chance to go to Seagull much? Yeah, just a little bit
I'll probably check out more talks after the fact. There was just too much going on
Yeah, and Seagull had like a three track thing going on too. So I kind of had to pick and choose constantly
Yeah, a lot of good talks. Yeah, it was nice to see it
You know, they've this has been a which we'll talk more about in a little bit
but this has been a real thing this year is
how the heck to move all these
events virtual and
Various degrees of success for different ones and the Linux application summit has been building and building now for a few years
So this is when we were watching with interest took place November 12th through the 14th 2020 and there's lots of talks
We'll link you to as much as we can
For Onyx also has a rundown but to give you a kind of a taste a sense of the flavor
This is Alexi poll who we have had on the show before. It's the keys the KDEV president and he was he was talking about Wayland
but he's talking about it from not an end-users perspective, but he's talking about it from a
Developers perspective how developers can target their applications and write applications for Linux that use Wayland
Everyone please give a warm virtual round of applause for Alish who will be talking to us about Wayland for app developers
There's no applause. So insert applause here. Okay, thank thanks everyone for the virtual round of applause. It was virtually great
All right. So for the talk today, I thought that
Instead of talking about
Things that are happening, which is what I generally talked about because I am a developer. I thought
well
What will developers care about when they start developing their applications?
And he goes through a lot of the different history and things to consider there
But I think I'm gonna jump right to my favorite talk if you'll allow please do permit
My favorite talk like a lot of these talks did unfortunately, but it's how these virtual events go right now
My favorite talk does start with a bit of an awkward
Introduction. Good morning. Good afternoon. Good evening and namaste everyone
My name is Dakshit Vaishnavi Dogra and now I invite mr. Greg Hartman who goes by at GregKH on Twitter
I'm definitely sure that is that there is no need for an introduction
So ladies and gentlemen, put your hands together for mr. Greg Hartman. All the best
Okay, is that working now I
Hope so
I'm doing great. I have construction happening right below me
So we might hear some drilling in the background, but hey, this is the joy of working from home in the situation
These virtual conferences. They're always a bit, you know, like a zoom meeting and there's no way around that
In some sense you feel a little closer and in other senses, it's a little harder to watch
Yeah, it is. So Greg gives his own introduction, which is probably a little bit better than my introduction
I like to introduce him as the commander Riker of Linux. A little bit about me since they didn't introduce me
I've been a kernel developer for way too long. I used to be a embedded developer before that. I maintain stable kernels
I have done a lot of user space work
But at the low level I also maintain some user space packages
I will make fun of gnome later
But let me tell you I have been an advisory board for them for many years and I'm still a foundation member
And I've worked on lots and lots of different districts. We'll get to that gnome stuff in a little bit because I actually thought it
Was pretty poignant but he wanted to bring lessons that they've learned as a kernel team
To the app summit audience, which is all made up of a lot of developers what you do and how you act on
Creating code depends on who you are and I'll break everything down into about three different groups here. I'm kernel developers
um, this audience is not kernel developers, but since I am one I'll talk about what we've learned and how we've made mistakes and what
We've learned from that and how to apply it again to library developers and application developers
Which is the primary audience here now the full talk has some really good insights
But I think you probably agree with me West because I know you watch this one, too
There was one thing he really wanted to drive home with this talk and that is never ever
Ever break user space whenever possible. It's the kernels number one rule. You've probably heard it before he lays it out a little bit here
So first off kernel developers is easy thing
We only have really one rule and Linus gets mad at this whenever you see rants in the press or whatnot
this is when we do not we break this rule and the rule is we cannot break user space and
Cannot break user space on purpose
Um break it accidentally. We'll fix it. Whatever. We break user space if nobody notices
That's fine because we're we take advantage of things that when you don't notice different functionalities or stuff
But you just can't break user space. It's such a developer thing to say we break it when no one notices
So he he's mentioned this before you've heard probably Linus say this or read it if if you've been around for a little while
You know, this is a big rule of theirs
but I bet you may not know why they're why they believe it so strongly and I'll tell you what it wasn't exactly what I
Was expecting and Greg explains and we make this rule and other operating systems have this rules
Well, it's a very solid rule because we always want you to operate
And we want you to upgrade without worrying about it
We don't want you to feel scared if we got a new you see in the release and we say hey this fixes a bunch of
Problems, we don't want you to feel worried about taking that and that's really really important
Especially with security you want people to take all these fixes you want people to be able to upgrade you want them to also take
advantage of the new features and if you have them even hesitate about updating to your latest version
Because they you've broken functionality for them. They won't and that's not okay. So that's why
Because he want they the kernel developers want you to feel confident in upgrading
Yeah, I think he really hits on you know, there's a lot of trust here
You're only gonna keep using something and keep getting the latest versions if it has a history of working and you feel like there's respect
On the developer side for what you're trying to do and not just what's easy for the developers
It's a it's a hard learned lesson for the kernel team, too
I mean
There's only a few Linux users out there and when you have the rapid pace of development that Linux does you really do have to be
thinking about
What makes it safe for the users to upgrade what prevents them from upgrading and you see this in some commercial spaces, too
where
There is sort of this mean that goes around that iOS users always update and iOS's
Users are based or stay current place compared to Android, right?
But the reality is Wes because I seem to recall that actually took quite a hit when they released
I think it was iOS 7. I can't remember. It was a pretty dramatic UI change and
their upgrade rate dropped
Significantly dropped way off and then it's slowly slowly slowly rebuilt over time
Same for me with fedora, right?
I over time after after about 10 releases of having a successful upgrade
I'd pretty much just upgrade immediately now. I feel pretty safe about it. Right? You've built that trust with them over the time
Yeah, and so I connected with what he was saying there
But that just wasn't what I expected the reason for that number one rule of never breaking user space now
What can developers do when they need to make change because sometimes you're in a situation where your users don't want change
But for whatever reason change has to happen
Well, Greg has advice for that too
But what we can do is we can evolve things over time so that nobody actually notices
We can move to different ways things happen. We can do different things how stuff that
Works and we can provide new ways of doing things and we provide new ways of doing things
Hopefully people will migrate over time in reality. They don't they stick to the old stuff, which is fine
but we can provide new ways and this is how we constantly evolve and how we constantly move forward and
This is how you survive because you have to change with the world. So you have to provide new functionality a lot of people
I get this complaint a lot from a number of people have been in the IT and the computer industry for a long time saying
Well, how is Linux succeeding? It's an old model. The old Unix POSIX model is obsolete
We shouldn't be doing this anymore. And the problem is
In one way Linux supports that they support your binaries from 20 years ago from 25 years ago
You can still run really old
BSD
Applications you rebuild them and they work or you can run your application that was built 20 years ago and it still works
So people think Linux is stagnated
but in reality we've created new functionalities right next to the old functionalities and
That you can do different things. You can take advantage of stuff. We have eBPF which is taking over the world
It's a microkernel like architecture. You can run user space programs on the kernel
You can do all this fancy stuff proven that you can't lock up the kernel wonderful stuff
IOU ring is fast asynchronous IO in a different way that has ever been done before and it's again sitting right next to the old
POSIX model so that your old programs can work just fine
But new programs can take advantage of stuff and take advantage of speed increases
Of course Linux now is a real-time operating system
It's been real-time operating system for a while without a tree patch
Those changes are almost all merged. That's something people said could never possibly be done
But yet we did it right next to the existing operating system and nobody noticed
That's how you do it. You evolve and add new functionality
Without breaking anything. I think when I heard this it was sort of triggering a bias in my head
And that is you can't you can't have an old system an old subsystem and a new subsystem and have them coexist
that just adds bloat and
Bloat equals slowdown and security issues and that equals bad
But that's I think a bit of a novice understanding when I when I gave it a little more consideration. I
realized
Well Linux is kind of
Uniquely suited for this you have to get the balance, right?
but the reality is you can have somebody who maintains the current IO subsystem and you can have somebody else that comes along and
maintains the new IO ring subsystem and
There isn't some beam counter saying well, we can't afford to invest in two subsystems at the same time
This is open source development. So it can absolutely happen in parallel
But additionally having two subsystems that do similar things doesn't make one of the other
Slower that code path just doesn't get activated unless somebody writes for it
So there's really not as long as it's maintained. There's not really like a performance hit from it, right?
I mean if you ever call into that code, it's never gonna get loaded and run it just sits there
And so Greg's core point with all of this was is as much as you can
Keep support for existing features and slowly build in new features. If you have to make really really radical change
Maybe it's time to call it something new
And he brought us back
To the good old genome days to really kind of help sink this in for the developers that were listening
The biggest thing to do is don't take away things at work
If somebody's using this feature and using this functionality keep it there. It's that simple
It's being it was there you provided for somebody don't think by removing it. You're doing them a favor
You might be doing yourself a favor because you think it can be done a different way
But don't because it's not gonna work and the biggest example of this and the most public example this happened many many years ago
2011 the big day. A number of people here know what that date was
I have heard it talked to by as this date and this was the gnome 3 introduction
Everybody's system instantly when the distro switched it over it looked totally and completely different
That was a major major break. This was the day the gnome project realized that they had real users
Based on the feedback they got they always thought they had users. They always thought they were doing the right thing
They wanted to make a change. They wanted to do something different
But this was the day that they really broke all their users trust because all of a sudden they impose a totally different model
Onto them on to what they were currently using to do used to doing getting the workflow and it broke them
It just caused a number of major major pain. It was horrible. Um
Then ldn.net review of gnome 3 was actually really good. It was very comprehensive
It was very comprehensive. Um, but and the comments of course were horrible
But read this if you're an application developer and you are considering rewriting how you do everything in a totally different way
look at this you are seeing people mad because you took something that they were using and
Using to get their real work done. Their real work isn't to create a
Interface or application environment their real work is to do something else and you made it harder to get them to do their real work
You broke their trust and that was a long way and the known developers clawed back from that
It took them many many many years to do that. I think they're there now. I know myself
I switched away and came back many years. They've gotten better since 2011. They realize having a clean break doesn't work and
That was not the best idea. Please don't in your application do the same thing. I see this happen a lot
people
Evolve applications to do something totally different different UI. That's not a good idea
Please don't do that. And I I don't know if I completely agree that their reputation has recovered. I mean, I like
Like Greg stopped using it for a while same here
Yeah, and now I'm back on it and I'm pretty dang happy with it
But I think that's also at the same time plasma has gotten gotten really really sharp
He also he does cite plasma desktop as an example of getting it, right, right?
And you know, I'm immediately made to think of the systems we have in the studio and that I have at home running KDE neon
And it's just slow
Evolutionary change and I don't worry even if I'm getting updates every single week that my desktop suddenly gonna change out from underneath
yeah, I remember when I was an IT support and
A new version of Windows came along and it wasn't even a significant change
but it might have been like from XP to 7 or something like that and I was working with people getting them set up and I
I remember the comment that somebody made to me and it just really stuck out and he said to me he said to me
You know, I just don't understand why they keep moving the gas pedal on this thing and that's how he saw
It's like I learned how to drive this Windows XP and now you gave me Windows 7 and they moved the gas pedal on me
I think that's a common viewpoint, right?
You didn't have the problems that the developers seem to think needed to get fixed or changed or you know
Trying to make more revenue with and so why change it? Meanwhile, I'm often like hmm. Where can I stick the gas pedal?
You know, can I put it over in this corner? I want like three of them and I want them all shiny
But he underscores this point by saying, you know, look at the mate and cinnamon projects. They're still here
They're still going this really underscores the size of this change of this event that gnome was as a result
Everybody here knows made in cinnamon sprung up. They fill a real need
These are real desktops that are with lots and lots of users because they were used to before or they're used to that common paradigm
Um, that's fine. But this is an example that kind of shows that what the known developers did
Was major and was really big because there's two separate projects just to fill that void
That's fine. If the known developers want to do that they did
That was their decision to do again. We're writing software for free. You're giving it over throwing it over the wall
I would say that maybe that wasn't the best decision to do
But hey, maybe you should call it a different project gone off in different way, but like software development
Sometimes there is a reason to introduce real change you have to provide enough reason and enough
goodness
To force somebody to take the time to learn to do something else. That's very rare. It happens very rarely in an application space
Sometimes in library spaces as does
Um, I'll call that system D as a good example of how this they did it, right? They provide all the functionality
They solved a real problem that was there that unified all these existing
tools and problems in such a way that it was just so much better to use and
It provided enough impetus that everybody was willing to do the do the work to modify their own stuff and move to the new model
That it worked people still complain about it, but it worked everybody switched
Everybody updated the new stuff the kiddies doing with a system D on how it launches better is very nice
Gnome was integrated with a very from the beginning from very early. It works. Well, it solves a real problem again
That was a example of how you can provide a compelling reason to move on and make the change, you know
It reminds me that
We have some really intelligent people that are running the kernel
And that's one I think Linux is best strengths of the people closest to the core of it
They know what the hell they're talking about what they're doing
well, and you can see that this is really, you know, great got an understanding of being in the open-source space where you know
no one's required to use Linux necessarily like you have to
Work and have a value proposition to your audience to make sure that they use it and don't just fork you and do whatever else
They want to do or use one of your many competitors right in a corporate environment
If I'm writing some software
You might just be told that you have to use it or if I need to make a change I can force you into a zoom
Meeting tell you you got to fix your software by X date
But in the larger world of open-source software, you can't do that. And that is when he cited system D there
You know
You absolutely could have your qualms with system D and many people do and they still love to talk about it
but at the end of the day it was immensely successful in getting adoption and
In a way that we don't normally see with a disrupter in open source
And so it was kind of a rare case because usually it has to be slow progressive change
And maybe it is a good example too in that I think a lot of the folks who you know didn't like system D for
Them that change wasn't as well justified right there are reasons that they didn't have the same problems or that system D
Didn't feel like it was necessarily solving for them. So there was less incentive to move on. So the whole talk is worth
Listening to it's about 30 minutes long and you know, we got you, you know a few minutes worth of clips here
So it's worth checking it out
but at the end in the Q&A he was asked a question about what new technology coming to Linux at the kernel level and
Around it that he's the most excited about and so I'm gonna play that for you
And then we'll quiz West Payne to see if he knows what it is
Any current technology you just pay steps? Yes
I owe you ring you space developers who care about IO should pay attention to that
I know the Postgres developers are you looking at it now database other database developers that is asynchronous. I owe no system call overhead
Very very fast. I owe you can throw things into a ring and you get notified in user space when your data is there
Very very good. If you care about IO, I recommend looking at that
All right, West Payne
For the last chicken little in the kitchen
with cheese
What is IO ring? Well, it's IO underscore you ring Chris and it's a mechanism per for performing
Asynchronous IO. Oh, oh
Well, that's enough. That's it. That's all you got. Hmm judges. What more did you want? Well, what makes it so special?
It's new and faster and better you heard him talk about, you know less system call overhead
Yeah, it's no one's really been happy with the existing asynchronous IO subsystem options in Linux and classic Unix
IO is inherently synchronous. So this is a new faster method that's becoming very popular. All right, I'm gonna give it to you West Payne
You are correct. Yeah, there's actually one other technologies
He cited two technologies that he's very excited about IO ring was one of them. I owe you ring
Ha the second one though. I'm gonna say you have to go listen to Linux action news episode
163 to hear that one
Oh, you know, there's also some interesting talk about a breaking change coming to system D
Which I think is right on point for today's discussion. Yes, very much. So as a matter of fact
So go check out linuxactionnews.com slash one six three
Linode comm slash unplugged go there to get a one hundred dollar 60-day credit towards your new account
Linode is the largest independent cloud for developers. They are our server provider. Not only do they offer servers
They offer node balancers. They have object storage if you want some static storage up in the cloud and they've been around
Three years before AWS. That's when they got their start. They're like they're in this for like the long haul was that's for sure
And that gave them some very early opportunities in infrastructure and in private networking
They have 11 data centers around the world
They have a crazy fast network that they just recently made a blog post about that. I encourage you to go read
If they're my cloud hosting provider and they host all of our new infrastructure here
They have native SSD storage 40 gigabit connections at the hypervisors a really nice easy to use cloud manager to do all of this
Plus they also plug in with the orchestration management tools
So that's just like a slam dunk plus Linode costs 30 to 50 percent less than the major cloud providers like AWS
They're independently owned like you're like you're humble podcast network right here
And so that that that I really like
but additionally Linode was one of the first sponsors to step up and
Make us make Jupiter broadcasting going independent actually happen and possible there
They were one of the OG sponsors that came in when things were brand new and I was just a few days out from going
On air and I didn't have anything lined up and Linode stepped up
So they they have been they have been part of the community for a long time like they're they're also backers of
Linux fest Northwest they've sponsored projects like Kubuntu and they do lots of hackathons and meetups
Although I don't know how much these days, but I've been going to events for years and seeing Linode there
So I'd always wanted to try them out. So a couple of years ago. I had my opportunity and I've never gone back
See check them out. See what they can do for you. See what you can build Linode calm
Unplugged go there get that $100 60-day credit towards your new account and support the show
See why they're our hosting provider and why we love them so dang much a couple of weeks ago
I did a custom rig that I swear you could only do at Linode because they get it
Unlike entry-level service providers that lock you down and prevent you from being able to do some of the back-end stuff
Let know that you have at it. Check it out Linode calm slash unplugged big
Thank you Linode for sponsoring the unplug program and thanks to everybody who listens and goes to Linode calm slash unplugged
To check them out to support the show and let them know you heard about it here and get that
$100 60-day credit towards your new account
All right Wes this week there was a story that kind of reminds us why a lot of us choose to use Linux on our
Workstation set the scene. It's a rainy Pacific Northwest morning
I've lazily gotten out of bed wandered downstairs
Got the laptop rebooted set up ready to get to work or at least drink some coffee and start going that way
Think about getting ready for work
It's a multi-step process
And I notice you know, I'm using my my work Mac, okay
Apps are taking a while to load. All right, I thought at first that just this must be you know Mac OS doing something
Maybe it's rebuilding some caches in the background or had perhaps done some updates after I'd rebooted it, but it just kept persisting. Hmm
Really and and was it just during application load time just load time the apps would launch eventually and then run just fine
Yeah, I think a lot of people ran into this on November 12th when
Big Sur was released. Uh-huh. Big Sur came out and
hours after the initial release
Somewhere in Apple's infrastructure their online certificate status protocol servers just started crawling and
Part of the problem actually was that they didn't go completely offline
They just got really really slow and what could be happening in your case and some of these other individual cases
is that Mac OS in the background has this gatekeeper technology and it checks to see if the
Developer certificate is valid of the application before it runs
So say you have do you remember one of the apps like slack perhaps? Yep. So slack when they submit to the
Apple app stores all of them part of that process they they they actually like become an Apple developer
They pay for that they get an account for that
They they submit to these different app stores and their build has to be signed with their certificate
Apple signs the application and then they sign it with the developer certificate too and this all happens on the on the back end
the application when it runs
It generally just runs but every now and like if you haven't run it for a while or maybe it's like a fresh boot
it will check to see if that
Developer certificate is active if it's still valid and here's where the drama came in because yes, that means, you know
I'm launching an application. I'm doing stuff on my computer and suddenly we're sending a response to some servers over controlled in Apple's cloud
Checking to make sure that I can in fact launch this program. I've asked it to run
this is something Apple rolled out quite a while ago in Mac OS and they've evolved it over time and
ultimately the idea being that they could revoke slack certificate or anybody and
That application would then fail to launch on Macs or I devices, right? Let's say, you know, I've been publishing stuff
I just put out a new version of my application people are running it and I noticed that oh
I've been compromised and someone put some you know malicious crypto miner in my software and now it's out there
Well, I might not be able to do anything except in this case
I can I can ask I can tell Apple about it and
They can make sure that any new launches from there on won't work
So this is why it's built in there, but it also has the flip side
There's an evil side to this
If you wanted to implement your own app store in your app and Apple decided they didn't want you to do that
They could turn your account off
Additionally it means that these Macs have to check in semi frequently with Apple servers
Before they'll run an application think about that network activity has to occur
Before the application runs
So if you have a bad route if you've got some weird latency if you're on a my fi and it's just going a little
Slow that day you could have a ten thousand dollar Mac Pro tower and it will still
Wait to launch the application. Now. There is provisions in there for if it's offline, but when it's totally online
It won't you know, it'll just launch but when it's actually responding guess what it it slows the entire thing down and I
Really think Apple as this company that positions themselves as a privacy first company needs to be really super clear when they're doing something like this
Because you kind of get a sense of a person's
Basic meta metadata about the use of their machine application launch times IP address
I believe it's also sent in HTTP. Is that true? Yeah
That's a common thing in these scenarios and yeah looking at some wire shark logs that folks have been investigating this from it does seem
Like there's some information
transmitted over plain text now
That seems to be just information about the particular development
developers certificate and usually that certificate could sign multiple apps say in the case of Mozilla for both Firefox and Thunderbird, but
That's kind of a personal choice of how do you feel about that?
And as you say right there's you know, these are associated with time with your activity with perhaps your location. Yeah. Yeah, there's so there's
A couple of issues here the first issue
I'd say is this a system that people are comfortable with?
Because it gives Apple a lot of metadata and it gives them a lot of control
I I would argue if you buy a Mac you kind of already conceding to trusting Apple
And so this that probably doesn't bother you as much but then you have the implementation here
Even though this touches Akamai which is by the way a third party now getting in the mix part of this will touch Akamai's
CDN network part of it goes directly to Apple
I'd like some real clarity on what information is being collected and sent along because what has been
deduced by the community is
Kind of damning. It seems like a lot of information. I wouldn't want out there
Well, and I think a lot of you know, but for for being proprietary
I think there's still a lot of folks even in our community in the Linux users that
You know Apple isn't Google. They're not just trying to sell you ads and necessarily mine all your personal data
And they've tried to build a brand on that but not being clear here
I think is hurting that at least among say the developer crowd and there's that whole privacy aspect of it
But I I think this conversation so far as we've heard it because we're recording this on a Sunday
Hasn't really included the fact that iOS behaves exactly the same way, right?
I think that's this is this is the Apple ecosystem exactly how it works, right?
All right, the same fundamentals and and and in their ecosystem, they're king
Yes, and that may be part of the value proposition, right?
Like how often do you really worry about a bunch of iOS malware? Yeah, I suppose not really ever and
Most users aren't really capable of you know evaluating that do you maintain a list of trusted and untrusted software?
I mean, you know Apple does and they don't get security reports
They have whole teams of people that can monitor and keep these things up-to-date true
I give you that and if you're just downloading some random software and running it who knows what could happen
it also feels like it's potentially surveillance like it could be utilized for surveillance if you had somebody on your network who was
I don't know wanted to surveil you but I think I'm just gonna slow down requests to that specific domain all the time on all my
No, this is the third issue. No, really. I think this is so
You you literally have a system designed and such that it could slow down the operation of a Mac
And if I was using a Mac that day and I was trying to get work done and I was in a rush
Maybe I was trying to get down to the studio really quick or I had to take off. I
Would be very incensed. I I think I would be enraged that
That they designed a network system in such a way that it could slow down my local computer on my LAN, right?
And of course, you know
Like we talk a lot about the various trade-offs and security and I think it just underscores that
They've made the choice of where to fall in those trade-offs
You don't really have a lot of input so many Mac the way I put this in our show notes is it's really about who?
Owns your computer and Linux users. I think are the only ones who can who can really confidently say I own my system
Do you see this like it is is that overstating it? No, I don't think it is
I mean it comes down to these questions. Do I own my computer or does the company that?
Owns the computer. So does Apple own my computer?
Can I do whatever I want with my computer or does Apple decide what I do with my computer and in the end?
We Linux users say or ask themselves do I want that or not and we don't want that?
So we choose another system, right?
And I think the other problem is is it's going to encourage people who are concerned about this
Just to disable all code signing checks and that's not a good user behavior either, right?
Especially for folks who maybe don't know that much about security like most users and can't really weigh the pros and cons
So then there is a yet another wrinkle to this story. It is it's really something is in macOS Big Sur
They have designed it such that
certain set of the core system
bypasses VPNs and
Other types of things like maybe you have a popular Mac app as little snitch of an outbound firewall, right?
And that relies on some hooks that the kernel the Apple's kernel provides them to you know
I'd be able to make these choices and they've just said no our programs they do what they want
so that means that Macs are essentially
Leaky on VPNs now out of the box and now this is all provisional as you said
It's it's a Sunday right now, but at least from looking at Twitter
It seems like maybe some other third-party apps can start start taking advantage of that too at least right now
And it is still you know in beta. Yeah, but from what we do see on Twitter
It seems like someone else was able to essentially create a malicious app that took advantage of this new system
And it's it's ludicrous because again there I would expect as an end-user if I'm if I'm establishing a VPN
I would never think that Mike's my kernel and other parts of my OS are sneaky sending data to other servers
Outside my network level VPN. That's why I created a VPN something tells me there'll be some network
IT administrators who are none too happy about this. I hope that's a bug could be a bug. We will see
um the other thing that I I wanted to kind of just know in all of this is
It may not all be bad news there could actually be a little potentially good news here
It seems that there will be a way for users to bless
Their own kernels on these new arm max say what yes
So while yes, there is a secure boot like environment on these arm max
And you have to have a sign kernel before it will boot
We've now found out that there will be a process where you can
Manually sign a kernel and the developer of pongo OS one of the developers
Was getting pretty far on actually getting this to boot and it may actually be possible using the same approach to bless a Linux kernel and
And then potentially boot a second stage bootloader like this pongo OS and then load Linux from that right the pongo OS bits there
Because you're in kind of a weird environment that like say the Linux kernel wouldn't expect to be booted from so you need a little
Shim to get it going. This is interesting right this is kind of on the side of okay
Maybe you do still own it. Yes, we are going to enforce that you do it in a secure way
Yeah, but if you can you know add your own blessed signed systems and boot it
That's a step in the right direction
So maybe maybe it's not totally locked out there you know Apple give it an apple taketh away
But this story when I looked at this. I thought all of this combined together
I thought this is this is why I think
There will be a portion of of Apple users that are in the professional end that
Expect to be able to control their computer the people who noticed these things right they're good candidates for Linux
They seriously are for the Linux workstation like this laptop. We're going to review today
They are they are the exact target demo for this Dell Precision set them up on you know fedora 33
With a nice shiny GNOME setup all right all right you that may be too much
I don't know they may have to go Ubuntu. You know they they need a soft landing
But really like seriously it is it is how when you're talking about the differences between a Linux
Workstation and a Mac workstation how do you quantify something like this?
Because we'll often talk about telemetry or we'll talk about spying and privacy
but this is a this is a multiple layer cake here where you've got the privacy implications of metadata tracking of
When and what developers you're using you've got then the other aspect of this of course that Apple is able to turn
applications off which you may or may not be comfortable with that's a decision you have to make but then lastly you have the
Network effect where because Apple is not particularly good so far developing online services
They've designed this thing in a way where when they release the new OS that day
It can cause all of the Macs all of the Macs not just the Big Sur Macs all of the Macs to slow down
that to me is is a line that should not ever be crossed and
You know these things are never gonna impact your Linux distro, right?
It's just not gonna happen there was a time
Maybe where an Amazon referral search would be conducted when you'd searched in the launcher
But this kind of stuff is just not gonna happen on the Linux box the funny part that struck me too was all the very interesting
Good investigative work going on to figure out just what was sent and what was happening
That's all you know in the Linux world. That's open-source
Just go point me at the GitHub and you have to wonder with this move to arm Apple silicon really? Yeah, right
Thank you. It's true the m1 chip
The reality is is that we they really are closer and closer to a world where nothing runs unless it's signed
Today they allow you to bypass gatekeeper
but why why really go to the effort of having a
Ecosystem and a and a hardware and a software stack that you own top to bottom and you are the sole kingmaker
With if you're not gonna make that move and if you look where Apple is going where they're seeking revenue now is services and these app
Stores they they count them as services for the reports to Wall Street
And it just seems very likely that now that you've got Macs that can run
iOS apps and they're on their own custom silicon and
They have this all the pieces in place like gatekeeper the App Store
It's probably only a few years from now where they flip that switch and everything has to run through gatekeeper and there will be absolutely
Nothing you can do like you can't run
Anything but Big Sur or later on these m1 Macs just can't so there's just do you have no option and I?
Think that also is gonna make Linux more and more of a compelling platform for high-end professionals tech savvy professionals
I'm not saying you know for everybody, but it's just making it fall more and more I think into less and less
I should say in the general purpose computing category and more and more as a niche thing
Maybe you have it for your as your video editing utility
You know it's just a box in the corner that you need because it has the best applications for that purpose
But it's not a general purpose computer. Yeah, I could see that sure. I mean it's that's a pretty expensive
Non general purpose computer when you're spending that kind of money. You'd like it to be able to do everything
but
Yeah, I mean, maybe maybe what happens is if Apple goes crazy
Maybe you'll but maybe you can load Linux on those ARM Macs one day. Maybe it'll happen something tells me you're gonna try
Well let's talk about this Macbook killer that I've had in-house for a few weeks now
I really had to put it through its paces, but first I do have a little housekeeping
You should definitely join the le plug
We have a virtual Linux users group that gets together every Sunday in our mumble room in the lobby
It's really easy to get started go to Linux unplug calm. We have the mumble info in there now
Next Sunday is the jellyfin bug-a-thon the developers will be joining our our lug
they were actually there earlier today to doing a presentation and
we're gonna help them try to just
Stamp out any of the bugs we can find in the 10.7 release jellyfin is a open source Plex alternative
And we want to do anything we can here at the show to push that forward and so the virtual lug has extended an invitation
To the jellyfin developers to join them next Sunday at noon Pacific
And you can get that converted at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar and help them out
Hey, I'm excited and I'm a big jellyfin user myself. So the more bugs we find better for me. That's right, man
Also, I want to recommend you grab the Jupiter broadcasting all shows feed
You never know what could be coming up and these days all the shows are really great Coder radios back
West has joined me on Linux action news
It's a nice type production self-hosted be coming out later this week
And if you have the all shows feed you just get it all so you can search in your podcast app or or get it
From the website. I think it's a good way. It's like the pro. It's like the pro user move
Well or the lazy user move where you don't want to bother checking and making sure you got all the ones in the right spots
And in your feeds, that's a really good just one feed that it's the lazy and easy way
But also the pro way see sometimes sometimes the easy way is the pro way. That's right
You know you want to just you want sustainable podcasting West. All right, that's all the housekeeping for this week
So let's talk about this Linux MacBook killer a bold claim mr. Fisher it really is
This is the precision 57 50 and this is this is a really a pretty new beast from Dell
They've they really stepped it up. They manage to get this thing 10% thinner
So if you've seen the old edition, it's kind of got like some big fan gaps on the sides and whatnot
all that's gone with this one and now
With with this is really something I had to double-check this but now Dell can claim the world's smallest
17 inch mobile workstation it is quite a thing to look at. Yeah, really handsome shiny
Professional. Yeah, it's it's that same metal and sort of carbon fiber like mix that Dell uses on the XPS
but brought up to the professional precision line and
They've they've also done another pass at the edge to edge infinity display with just blow
This thing is it's really something
the the screen on this is
Well, it's I mean, it's always tops but it's a 16 by 10 aspect ratio. It has HDR 400 support
It's 3840 by 2400 resolution with touch support and it's edge to edge glass
I didn't even try the touch support and the webcams back up at the top now, which is which is pretty nice
So this precision as it's configured is really meant for a workstation replacement
It's meant to stomp a MacBook
It has the Xeon mobile processors in it that run at a base clock of 2.4 gigahertz
But can actually go all the way up to 5.3 gigahertz Wow eight cores 16 threads
Isn't that something I'm not used to type an n-proc and seeing 16 on my laptop 32 gigs of RAM in this particular one
Although I think you can go even further
This one has a quadro RTX 3000 with six gigs of video RAM
I'll tell you more about that in a little bit as an m.2 one terabyte PCIe MVM
It doesn't have a spinning rust
Sorry, I think you can actually put up to two terabytes of PCIe storage in it
But this is one terabyte 6l 97 watt hour lithium ion battery
So the maximum you could take this thing on a plane with and then they Dell does this and I really like it is
They've done a really beefy USB
C charger a hundred and thirty watts. Yeah
Yeah, so you can really dump power into this thing and it's or you just use any standard USB C charger
I like, you know in any of the ports any of the ports on the thing. It's really nice
So that that I really appreciate it because when you needed to throw power into it
They had such 130 watt, but when I wasn't doing much with it, I could just use like the 65 one
I can whatever you have. Yeah, like I was 65 watt that
Was pretty easy to use this one also features a much larger trackpad
I mean look at the trackpad compared to our ThinkPad trackpads. I mean, it's puny
Yeah, it's if this trackpad is it's MacBook style
It's massive and it's it's got a very nice. It's it's the best
It's the best touchpad I've ever used on a Linux laptop easily, which might not still be saying much but it's pretty good
I really have zero complaints
The other thing that's nice about this laptop is you can load it up with ECC memory if you like
If your workload calls for that, oh and I was wrong
You can get up to four terabytes of PCIe storage and you can get it in raid one or zero options, too
It's I did not see this
Also, they've worked on this to reduce the amount of blue light that the panel blasts in your face to reduce eye strain
This has an updated keyboard with a slightly longer travel distance. I'll be curious for your take on that particular detail
Yeah, I actually don't really find the keyboard much different. It's not offensive
Um, I am I find myself not to be a very good keyboard critic
I'm I definitely appreciate a nice keyboard and the better the keyboard the more I appreciate it
But I I can go on anything between the butterfly keyboard like that. I can't use that right?
That's the upper limit there right and then like a really nice custom mechanical keyboard like I I'm but I liked it
I found that when I did start to use it
It took my brain about a minute to really adjust to the layout and then I had it it was really no big deal
And then there's something that is really special about this laptop
this this laptop
has
What has got to be maybe the future of where where Dell is going on thermal management?
Get ready for this. So Dell wanted a solution where that you could really run this thing GPU and CPU go right and otherwise
But why are you filling it with so much beefy hardware totally doable in a desktop tower?
Yes, not very doable in a laptop in a thin laptop. Yeah, and a really thin laptop
So they've done some secret sauce work. It's patented
So it's not that secret, but they've done some secret sauce work on the fans
So they have these really kind of big special fatty fans in there
But then they also have something called dual opposite outlet where they have a pressurized air chamber and fans to really move the air
in this thing
So this thing manages with a combo of fan upgrades the dual air flow and the pressurization
They do in there to move a ton of air without a lot of noise
in fact, I'll say
Without really any audible noise even under some really significant loads. I know they also
Have done and in the little controller a machine
Learning dynamic tuning technology that actually comes from Intel
But Dell's the first to actually ship with this and it's a code based solution that automatically adjusts the performance based on
Application load what parts of the system the applications are hitting and it also can anticipate based on your previous performance
When like you start a CPU load and it might in the past
Maybe it's gonna attempt to avoid ramping up cooling because it's gonna see it's gonna try to wait as long as possible before it
Ramps cooling, but now with this adaptive workload system if it knows when you run this particular workload that the CPU runs for a long time
Oh, he's training another model. Yeah, it just ramps right up the cooling and it just gets right on it
But here's where they bring it all together and this is
ridiculous
Dell has built in a series of vapor chambers
Which are thinner than heat pipes and they can spread the heat out better and more efficiently and they allow for
Larger heat rejection paths, which is great for like your skin temperature stuff
And it really moves the heat and so they have the they have this thing
The vapor chamber stuff bolted on to both the CPU and the GPU and so you can
Crank this. I mean I'm throwing benchmark after benchmark at this thing for like a solid day
And it's just sitting there quietly chugging right along. Um, and then
I I hope this I hope this makes it into other models in the future
They have a graphite layer between the hot components and the outside of the laptop
So that way your hands and your wrist and stuff like burning my legs. No
Wow, yeah, and so they disperse the heat strategically throughout the system to prevent hot spots from affecting the user's comfort level
Yeah, i'm sold. Isn't that something? Um, so let's be real here
um
As configured. Yeah, what what is this gonna send me back? This is a 4800 review unit
4800 us greenbacks. Okay, but
um, I mean you got to think about really who is this laptop for right? That's the question here
Is this is for a professional. This is not my uh watching youtube on the couch laptop. This is our laptop
Watching youtube on the couch laptop. This is i've been using macs for years
I don't like where they're going and I want something that replaces my macbook
This is somebody who has a very gpu intensive workload
Perhaps they're messing with tensorflow like this is this is a particular type
These are several types, but these are particular types of users
I'd also say also people who like to treat themselves to the very best because
Uh, the reason why I waited so long to do this review is I really wanted to see if there was downsides to this
laptop because I just
Immediately fell in love with it and I knew I needed to like catch my catch my breath balance it out figure it out
You know use it for a while. And so I took an extended review with this one to the grace of dell. Thank you very much
um, and I walked away realizing that even if you're
Not in like this particular professional category
If you like a quiet laptop a fast laptop a beautiful laptop a laptop pre-loaded with linux
And you just kind of like the very best right? You've got you've got money to spare not an object and you just want the best
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, because you know, it's got it's got
Thunderbolts, you can hook it up to a dock. You can have a bunch of monitors
This graphics card had no problem powering external screens and internal screens
Um, there is something to be aware of though, and I think this is maybe the biggest caveat
I knew it couldn't all be perfect but in this sentence. Yeah, it currently requires and only fully works with ubuntu 1804
We haven't seen this for a while. So I called up dell and I said like what's going on?
Why why can I only use 1804? I tried fedora. I tried pop os. I tried 2010. I tried 2004, right?
That's kind of the standard thing right anytime
There's an xbs in here really any laptop running linux
Let's throw all the distros at it
See what it does because you know, I figure a lot of people in our audience
They're gonna run whatever they want to run. They're gonna reload it
So the thing is is the thing has some super fancy sound and um that sound max card required a lot of custom work
And they are targeting support for 2004 in january
But don't yet have it and the way this process works is dell is working with canonical
And then when there's an update for hardware support those updates shipped to the dell laptop
Through a canonical repository interesting. So it's part of just the system update process. There is an oem
Repo at canonical that contains the software
And this is how this partnership works is dell engages with canonical to do this custom work for them
So it's not like dell's doing this weird hacky work and then like just dropping a you know
A big blob file on the file system and saying have go at it
They are contracting with canonical who are experts on the operating system and building this out
So they presently are targeting january for rubuntu 2004 support
But you can you're not going to be able to put
Manjaro or fedora or whatever else you might want on here at least if you want to have sound and have sound
Yeah, you can use it. It'll work. Great
Performance is excellent. I have you know that um wireless rrf headset that I have that has a usb dongle
That's what I used for the majority of my usage time anyways, and that works just fine
So I ended up for the most part not running
1804 until towards the end of the review where I put it back on there when you first set up the machine dell asks
You if you want to recreate
Create recovery media nice and so I said yes flash that and so I knew at some point
I might want to go back back and I did and it was simple and it was straightforward
One of the things that is pretty well known about dell but worth reminding you is they have that service tag
system, right
And um the nice thing about that is you just go into the website you put the service tag in and you can redownload
The recovery media as well. It's got all this stuff for your specific model and documentation
But this thing's about the performance. So let's talk about benchmarks a little bit. I put some uh, i'll put some links in the show notes
But I decided to take this dell precision laptop and I decided to put it up against a ryzen
Workstation I decided to put it up against my own workstation and I decided to put it up against the macbook pro 16
I like this competition
Yeah, it was it was a really interesting fight because these are all nice computers in their own right?
I mean my workstations from like 2017 2018. So
You know a little old but the dell
Is a modern precision 57 50 so I expected it to stack up pretty well
But I wasn't sure about going up against desktops like a ryzen
The dell came out on top in most all the tests
As you would expect right because it can ramp up to 5 gigahertz 32 gigs of very fast ram brand new machine
Yeah, yeah, the ryzen workstation pulled ahead a few times, but I decided let's put it up against the macbook pro 16
Because I felt like that was uh, an interesting comparison and this is this is pretty telling
um
I ran a geek bench benchmark on the mac and then I ran geek bench benchmark on the dell because this is a very common
Mac benchmark and the macbook pro comes in with a multi-core score of seven thousand three hundred and ninety two
The dell laptop comes in with a multi-core score of seven thousand seven hundred and thirty-eight
So several so a few hundred at least a few hundred uh higher on the score from multi-core and also faster on single core
Counts and faster on gpu benchmarks not too surprising there
but
When I expect out the macbook pro that macbook pro was almost six thousand dollars. Ouch
Yeah, and of course it doesn't run linux. So there's that too
Um, so I I felt like when you look at it from in that range
It's the the dell stacks up pretty well price and and we've we've seen other laptops that are you know
Should be quite fast, but either don't have the the best thermal management or other issues where you know
A macbook just has those things solved. Yeah, there's that. Um, the dell thermals are they're they're in a class of their own
I decided to also throw the old thinkpad at it. Hey thinkpad comes in with a 3500 score. Ouch. Yeah
Yeah, it really so the other thing that uh going through all these benchmarks that this test really underscored for me is
There is still a pretty clear advantage that a desktop workstation has in some areas over a laptop
even a totally decked out laptop like this precision
but
You can't take the you know, the the desktop. What am I carrying the whole tower? That's awkward
So when you look at those compromises and you look at what dell tried to do here
They tried to come up with a mobile workstation where you can max out the gpu and cpu
And still get reasonable battery life and get and get reasonable cooling and you don't have the thermal throttling effect
Where you run the machine for a bit and then it just starts really eating on the throttling
that's what they set out to solve with this and they realized that
The audience for that were linux users. So while I dislike that it's limited to 1804
It's not really a deal breaker
I think for most people in this class, right especially if you're a professional and want to use a you know
A supported long-term release anyway. Yeah, and you got to remember that this also is because it's a dell
It's an option that's available to a lot of people from a corporate standpoint
And they're not going to be choosing their operating system anyway, right?
The other thing I didn't what they're really the only had really two dislikes with this and my second dislike was that
It seemed like sometimes the screen auto dimming logic was hunting for just the right light settings
and this seemed to persist across all the distributions I tried and it was really only when I was in a situation where there was
a bright light source behind me and my body was blocking
The photo sensor then the system would sit there and try to hunt for the right brightness to kind of a distracting degree
But if you don't sit
Like I was in front of a light don't do what chris does it wasn't so bad
But you know in conclusion, this is a work tool
And it is probably one of the nicest tools you could own if this is the type of system that you need for work
I mean, there's no doubt about it in my mind if I was rolling with it these days
Uh, i'd probably pick that up for myself. This would probably be my machine because it played the games
I wanted to play at high resolution. It did the workloads. I wanted to throw at it
It never complained from a temperature standpoint and i'm okay with the sound workaround for something
That's this high of quality. He's nice with your e gpu. Yeah. Yes, it does. Um, would I like the sound to work obviously?
But if I was really rolling in it and money was no object
For myself, I would get this personally
Clearly if I was in this work field, this seems like an obvious choice, too
and I think
That is a bigger and bigger market the people that need a laptop like this that run linux for tensorflow and other types of work
Um, we decided to also just do a little machine learning testing not just because you know
That's clearly one of the things it's one of the target areas. Yeah, and it's killer
It's just absolutely killer and it's you got to think about it from this standpoint
It's pre-loaded with linux and ready to go
I think this is a bigger and bigger market and it seems like dell thinks this is a bigger and bigger market
And so they've built this linux macbook killer and it's a moniker that has become cliche
It's one i've used myself in the past
But I really truly think this thing is a game changer for corporate linux or for professional developers or high-end game developers
Who want to move over to the linux platform and they want something they can buy from a name brand?
That they know or maybe their corporation already has an account with and this thing is just it's such a winner for those people
You can really see how the platform they started building with the xps has evolved and just it's shiny now
It's really impressive and it makes me happy that
Someone other than apple is playing in this space and making computers that can be this good
That's it is we now have something that is just top top tier
And I hope to see a lot of the awesome tech with the cooling system come down to the xps line
That would be right super nice because that's a little more approachable for me. I also I don't need a quadro, right?
So i'd like to have something that you do some gaming but nothing crazy, right?
So i'd like to have something maybe a little more in a different tier
but I could absolutely understand the people that do want it and um, my time with the
with the dell was
It was tricky because I didn't really know what the approach was for a review for a for a computer this powerful
Like I have out in the other room. I have 150 laptop
I know how to review 150 laptop, right? I can tell you if the value proposition is there really easily
I just don't know how it works with linux yet
But with this when you're talking something that's 47 48 hundred dollars
How do I come on the air and tell you it's worth your money?
I can't tell you that right because everybody has a different sense of value but what I can tell you
Is this is one of the nicer computers i've ever used and it runs linux out of the box
And when I walk away from it, I'd say they've hit it out of the park
And that's that's what I wanted to come and that's what I wanted to relate to you is what they've done
That's kind of unique and kind of interesting and just the success that we're now seeing with these laptops
Um, i'm really impressed and I wish I could keep it
You know, but I will now box it up and send it back to dell and then the review will begin on the 150 laptop
So long you beautiful beast
It was fun while it lasted, uh, and it was a great excuse to load up steam and try a few video games
Now i'm back to my old system
All right, mr. Payne moving on from the review. What do we uh, what do we have in the feedback section anything this week?
No, no feedback this week. Well, there is some we just haven't selected it. That's probably in the show
That's probably what it is. Well, then let's plug the feedback so we can get some so we'll do a little more feedback
The next episode go to linuxunplug.com slash contact and fill that form out and send us in your thoughts
Yeah, we love your feedback, you know, not all of it can make it to the air
There just isn't time and but we still love hearing from you and all the stories the adventures the projects in linux
That stuff's great. I might have a special request
Wouldn't it be great?
just to get like
Somebody's crazy setup. Like do you have a crazy setup? That's like as crazy as this laptop or crazier
Like what weird stuff are you doing? Like yeah, first of all, tell us. Yeah, we yeah
So first of all, tell us what you're running
Like give us an idea of your specs
And then tell us why you need that because i'd like to get an idea of what some of those workloads are
And then on the opposite end of the spectrum
If you're running on something
Ridiculously low end and you're making it work. I'd like to hear that too
That's always like I like both ends of the spectrum
So give us that at linuxunplug.com slash contact and we may just cover it in a future episode
Also, thank you to our unplugged core contributors. You can go to unpluggedcore.com to sign up
You keep the unplugged program independent and you help reduce the ad load needed to make the show profitable
Let us be a little more picky with who we work with but you also get some perks first perk is the limited ad feed
Which cuts down as many of the ads as possible and just gives you the same great show same production
And the second feed is the full show live stream all our screw-ups like one that just happened a moment ago
Uh all the stuff that we don't make it and we don't put in the show that that's in the live feed version
And you get either one when you become a core contributor at unpluggedcore.com
Yes, wes yes, it's time for the picks and finally I decided since we didn't have feedback this week
We should have two picks. Look at you first one comes in from a listener of the show and it's called yacht
Yacht yacht is a graphical interface for managing your containers with a focus on templates and one-click
Deployments and also a dark mode. I like that
Uh, it is early. It is a community member who is making this but it's pretty neat and you could try it out right now
I mean so far you got your basic container management. You got a template framework
You have an easy approach to updating those templates
and um
Centralized settings for volume management similar to qol functionality, which is neat
You know, I like it
I got it running right here on the laptop and it's already giving me a splendid little dashboard of all the containers
I'm running now. I don't have any templates or anything, but I can see why you'd want that. Yeah, that's pretty pretty nice
And I mean, can you be in a name like yacht just the nautical theme if it's all right in
So the other pick we have is the reason why another reason why we did too is because you've heard of this one
But they have a nice new update. We wanted to make you aware of a brand new version of lutris is out
Zero five dot eight now this the lutris gaming platform
Has been working on importing your steam library and your gog library and third-party libraries into one
Store one ui one place to manage them all one stop shop
And they've made some nice strides recently and now steam games are loaded directly from the steam api
You don't have to go manually sync do all that weird stuff you had to do on the website. It just brings it all in
And game banners and icons are downloaded from the services themselves. It's it's getting really slick
Even bonus content for gog games like manuals and soundtracks can now be downloaded and stored inside lutris
So if you haven't checked out lutris in a while go do it
It's a pretty great little app and if you've been doing some gamings gaming on linux just gets better and better
It sure does wes. It sure does. Let's give it on. Let's uh, give it a honorable mention. There we go
Get the valve bong in there
Now we'll be back at our regular live time next tuesday over jblive.tv, which is nice because
Just doing it on sunday thing is getting a little old
Right. Yeah, what happened to tuesdays? What a day that is linux tuesday
I know and doing it on sundays is uh, it's a lot because we're also working on linux action news and the same
It's just it's a lot so back to tuesdays for us. It is you can join us though
Yeah, we'd love to have you join us over at jblive.tv
We do the show at noon pacific
We actually tend to get kind of going about a half hour before that all that's converted
In your local time zone at jupitabroadcasting.com
Slash calendar links to everything we talked about today at linuxunplugged.com
Slash 380 the show is at linux unplugged on the twitter. He's at westpane. I'm at chris lass
I don't know anything else we should mention lots of good shows over jupitabroadcasting
Check them out. Go check them out
Okay, thanks for joining us on this week's episode of the unplugged program and we'll be right back here not on a sunday
But we'll be back here next tuesday
So
All right, well you were comparing that laptop
Against other laptops, but would you rather have that or for a very similar price a 2006 ponniac vibe?
Probably the vibe to be honest with you
Yeah, when you start getting those prices you really are getting to use car prices, yeah
Uh over the weekend carl and I were uh, kind of commiserating about a sense of a bit of virtual
Conference burnout. I kind of implied it there with all they all feel like zoom meetings. Where are you at on it? Carl?
Yeah, I definitely appreciate it. I mean it's better than nothing right?
Right if corona is showing us anything we got to take what we can get
but
at the same time
I mean
It just cannot emulate the feel of a real conference and you know getting to hang out with friends that live far away
You know go out for drinks go out for good food
It's just it's not the same, you know
So at times it just feels like you're sitting there just watching youtube and some of them are even live streaming on youtube
Yeah, that's just it. It's a lot of good information. I'm valuable, you know valuable time from the speakers and I really appreciate that
But you're right. It doesn't
Doesn't hit that human connection
I know a lot of cons are trying to mix things up and have you know separate rooms for hallway tracks or other methods and
Chatting in a live stream can be fun. But yeah, and some of these are very
very well attended some of them are very poorly attended and then it kind of looks like a big waste of everyone's time and then
Additionally on top of that and I just i'm not ungrateful
I am very grateful that all of these are happening even and that the information is being relayed
but
As a culture
We just haven't gotten really good yet about knowing how to have good audio quality and where to position our cameras
and there's still a lot culturally we're learning and so
So you really kind of get the worst of it when you're watching these virtual events
They tend to have a lot of audio issues. They tend to have a lot of camera problems. There's a lot of dead air
Right. There's not necessarily someone, you know being an mc keeping everything flowing, right?
That's um, yeah can make a big difference. There's sometimes people are accidentally muted all the stuff you get
In like your worst work conferences
Have been at these events too. And so it's almost like someone needs to develop a platform that allows somebody to
You mc it and mute and unmute people and kind of
Be the person keeping the stream going and and then making sure that when like it's west pain's time to talk
I can mute and unmute west like that's how we do it here, right?
I don't I don't rely on the individual host to unmute themselves. I mean they can but
You you know the host can do it and then you don't have this weird thing
Like I played that clip of of greg's introduction, which was slightly awkward
But his was actually like one of the best case scenarios
This went smooth compared to almost everybody else and his audio quality was better than almost everybody else
One of the big benefits is that it's really opened up the availability for a lot of people that either can't afford travel themselves
Or their work won't pay for it and allows going to conferences all over the world
You know, I missed I tried to attend some of the linux app some app summit, I think
Um, but a lot of it was on european time
So I missed all the morning ones. I got to go back and watch those on youtube
Yeah, but it's just really opened up the availability which is a plus so it's a mixed bag
Yeah, the timing was tricky on that one. That's why I wanted to grab some of the clips from it
um, but I also feel like there has been
a gain and so you gotta wonder if there isn't
some sort of
Maybe middle ground here carl
I don't know really what it would be because the the in-person track and the going out and eating in the scene people stuff matters
So you don't want to have something that's only virtual but it could there be
Some kind of virtual hybrid conference where part of it's online part of it's physical. Would that be worth doing?
I don't know. I mean that's an interesting idea. I think it'd be really hard to pull off
I mean where everyone that's having to do remote stuff more than they used to now
Uh is probably can probably appreciate that
There's a golden rule for virtual meetings is that if one person's remote everyone's remote because whenever you have
You know some people in person you have sidebar conversations going on and it's really just not as not a true a lot worse
Communication so I fear the same thing happening with a mixed conference
it'd be interesting to try and see see if there's ways we can mitigate that because
I mean, even if all it is is just that you have the live in-person conference eventually and then you know
It's just standard that you have to provide a live stream of it. Maybe that'll be the compromise
Maybe I can certainly recall going to conferences and staying in my hotel room and watching the live stream
That sometimes is the better way to go
And then still go out for drinks or whatever right you still get that you're still there. You know, you just