Meet SPUD, the spontaneous pop-up display.
Do you remember the first time you streamed a video on your smartphone?
At that moment, you were no longer tied to your living room for your entertainment
or to your office for work. You could access your content anywhere.
But there's one small problem, your small mobile device screen.
Almost all of us prefer large displays for entertainment and for work.
When those work deadlines are approaching, a large desktop monitor
or a dual screen setup will significantly boost your productivity.
So what if there was a way to have the mobility of a phone, tablet,
or laptop without losing the benefit of a large screen?
Sounds impossible, but that's exactly what we did.
Introducing SPUD, the spontaneous pop-up display.
SPUD is a high-resolution, 24-inch display that crosses
down to the size of a book and weighs less than two pounds.
Yeah, so it kind of rolls up like an arm pressure testing kit almost.
And then it pops up into a projector. It's kind of neat.
And it hooks up over a different USB-C or whatever kind of adapter you've got.
Now, it's called SPUD, which is a completely new type of product, they say.
It's the world's largest and most portable display
because it's essentially using projection inside that little housing.
You see right there, it just hooked up USB-C to send the signals. Overall, it's 24 inches.
You can use HDMI as well. That is a good question.
The resolution is... I'm not sure. Actually,
I don't see it on here. I'm sure it's on here, I just didn't look at it. But, yeah, isn't that
funny? Hmm, let's find the resolution, Wes. I like that.
Look at that. That's pretty cool. That is actually pretty cool. I wonder how bright it is, too.
That would be the other question I have. You know, I played with that once when I was
younger. Back when I saw the CRT TV, I had like a flat lens hooked up on the front to try to project it.
Oh, yeah. It did not work very well. So, I mean, this seems like something you'd have to kind of...
You know, I'd want to see the quality of the display to really know like how many uses you could
do, but it's a really cool idea. I love that. Okay, so USB,
HDMI, brightness dial, and the spud on button.
Everybody gets their spud on. All right, here we go. Here's the nitty-ditties.
Here we go. Here we go. You ready for the itty-bitties? 720p.
720p is your... So it's 720p. The battery runs for
4 hours at 785 nits, which is pretty good
really for... Or you can get 10 hours at 350 nits, and it's less than 2 pounds.
That's pretty cool. 16 by 9 aspect ratio
runs off of 12-volt DC power, or you can hook it up to a USB
plug and run it off of that. It's got built-in speakers, too.
That's kind of neat, and it's got this case.
I mean, you know, as far as something for, you know,
not in a crazy amount of price that you could throw in your backpack. If you travel a lot.
Picture it, Wes, with CONVERGENCE! Oh!
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 170
for November 8th, 2016.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your
weekly Linux talk show that's trying not to think about the election doomsday.
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Wes. Hello, Chris. We're going to have a nice, tight
show today, because it is actually election day, and everybody's like, actually in the chat room
today, they're like, just don't do Unplugged, and just do like an unfiltered Unplugged combo
show and talk about the election. I'm like, that's not Linux-related. You don't understand how this works.
We need our daily dose, weekly dose of Linux. Yeah, man. Yeah, man. We need our Unplugged dose.
So we do have a good show coming up. We've got a birthday to celebrate, but we've also got some great hardware
to talk about. And then later on in the show,
we're going to be helpful. Even if you're a pro user, we've got a couple of helpful updates for you this week, but
if you're getting into Linux, or you're going to help somebody get into Linux, we've got some great
newbie stuff coming up, some great tips, including embracing the command line.
I said it. I said it. Don't be scared. Don't run away.
We're going to embrace the command line. Also, if you're using FileZilla, knock it off.
Stop it. We've got something you should know about, and a replacement product.
A project? Not a product. Something like that. It's been forked. It's been forked.
Somebody got hacked, and it motivated them to fork FileZilla.
Yeah. We'll tell you about that. But, Wes,
before we get into any of the stuff, the updates, the segments we've got coming up, you know what we've
got to do? Oh, there's something very important. We've got to bring in that virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mombroon. Greetings, brother. Hello.
Hello. Hello.
Hey, hello. Hello. Man, I thought you guys should all...
Aren't you all supposed to be out voting right now? These must be people from outside the states, I guess.
I can't believe there's a particular thing there.
Listen to all these excuses. All these excuses.
I'm in. I am voting. Give me like five hours. I've got a plan.
Hello, everybody. I've already voted. Good for you. Good for you. All right. Well,
let's celebrate a very important birthday
that almost just passed us right by. I know, right? But we did manage to catch it, and
it's something that we all can relate to.
It's at a milestone, the 25th birthday, where
Vim's car insurance finally goes down in price. Happy, happy birthday
to Vim. This is a rowdy crowd.
Come on, guys. You're in my house.
That's right. Over 25 years ago,
over 25 years ago, it was started. You see, the problem was
that Bram, he wanted something like Vim for his Amiga. He was a big
user of VI. I'm sorry, I should say VI. He wanted something like VI, but they didn't
have anything like that on the Amiga. So in 1991, on November 2nd, he released
the first version of VI, Imitation Edition.
After three years of working on it, the VI Imitation Edition.
Two years later, with the version
2.0, so the first version took three years, second version took two years,
two years later, with version 2.0 of Vim, the feature set
had exceeded that of the original VI. Or VI.
And so they changed the acronym
from Vim Imitation to Vim Improved.
Isn't that great? That is really cool. That is really cool.
That is a big milestone. 25th birthday?
I mean, think about where it's gone and how widely it's deployed today.
Thank God we have Nano. I mean, what? No, come on.
They still don't know how semantic versioning works.
I used Nano once in a video recently, and I've been getting crap about it for two weeks.
Chris, you use Nano?
What are you doing?
I thought you would use VI or Emacs. Why are you using Nano?
I think it's nice. What are you doing, man?
Nano-W. Nano-TACW.
Forever. I don't even know what TACW does. Enlighten us.
Oh man, it just supports
wide characters without cutting it off.
But you know, I actually, if I'm editing the file,
I don't know what this is. If I'm editing the file,
I tend to use Vim, because I got my colors and all that kind of stuff.
But if I'm viewing a file, and I don't want to use CAT, or more,
or whatever, if I don't want to just look at the file, I just want to just
for some reason open it up, but not edit it.
When I'm going to look at a file, and I'm going to dig around, but I'm not going to use Pseudo,
I use Nano for some reason. And then when I'm going to edit the file with root privileges,
I Pseudo, VI, then the file.
Isn't that weird? That is weird. But I mean, I can see, if it's just something you've learned in your fingers now,
and you just type it, right? It's like, the one is my viewing editor, and one is my
editing editor. I know, it's so stupid.
It's so dumb, because I do every now and then when I'm already in there, and now I'm like, well, I'll just change that real quick.
And then it's like, I go to save, and it's like, you don't have the privilege
of using Pseudo-T to get out of it, right? Yep.
It's so stupid. But it's habit. It's habit from a decade ago,
when I was revolting, and I wanted to find a new text editor, and I had
this boss who was
the only other Unix slash Linux guy in the office with me, and we would prank each other
constantly. And so I remember, like, I had replaced Vim, like,
when he would use VI, it would echo, like, Bruce Stinks, or something like that
on there. Bruce is a monkey. And we did things, like we'd set up cron jobs to
send system-wide messages on the hour, so every user logged into the system would see
Bruce smells like a monkey, and things like that. Like, we'd mess around with each other, and I remembered
Nano was sort of the prank we would use, like, we'd set up an alias
so things would launch in Nano or whatever. Like, there was all these, so I think that's where it
started, and then it just sort of became, because I got pranked, I think I just
stuck with it. He's just like, well, I'm not going to let this, screw this, I'm not going to let this defeat me.
I will use this editor. Yeah, exactly. It is a fun editor. And then now here
I am, years later, and I'm getting crap from the internet, and it's like, okay, you guys don't understand.
That's how a lot of stories end. Then I put it up on Facebook
and got fired. Alright, well, let's talk a little hardware.
I'm always out there looking for, like, the next perfect set-top box.
And I truly believe something that's like the NVIDIA Shield, but fully
ran Linux, GNU slash Linux. Not Android, not NVIDIA's fork
of Android Linux. Yeah. You know, if NVIDIA's forking Android,
they're not forking it too hard, because they're managing to deliver the monthly
Android updates still. Yeah, I don't mean a hard fork. I mean, I don't know if they are or not, but it does
seem like it has its own launcher and stuff. So, I've been watching
this space, kind of with some curiosity, and the beard
found this article, because he knew it was right up my alley. Zotac is cramming an AMD Radeon
RX 480 into a PC that is the size
of, well, it's smaller than a NUC. Wow.
Hey, that looks pretty slick. Yeah, it's a Magnus ERX 480, and it comes
with the AMD Radeon RX 480 Polaris based GPU.
And this is pretty nice, because they're going to have three versions. Bare Bones, which is
Bare Bones, plus, which is the version you get if you're
buying it for Linux, and then they sell a Windows 10 edition, which is the version
that you buy if you accept defeat in your life and are a masochist,
and you like to label yourself as pushing the easy button, you buy that.
Or you really need Cortana just everywhere in your life?
That seems like it. Yeah, yeah. The Bare Bones version is what you'd expect.
Just a little kit with a 2.2 gigahertz Skylake CPU. Somehow
Kaby Lake didn't make it in there. They must have been working with Apple. But the one you probably care about,
the Plus version, you can get it pretty tricked out.
In fact, you can get up to 32 gigs of RAM in the sucker if you want to.
But it comes stock with 8 gigs of RAM, a 1 terabyte, 2.5 inch
hard drive, and 120 gigabyte
M.2 SSD. So that's not bad, really.
And it's smaller than a NUC, which
really is impressive, which could make this a really nice little Steam
OS slash Kodi box, possibly. You're not doing anything weird with a NUC with
trying to rig in an external GPU? It's there. Exactly.
Yeah, the external, come on. I mean, geez, come on.
It's kind of got a lot of ports on the back, too, like a lot of IO. Check this thing out.
I'll zoom in a little bit if you're watching the video version here. We got ourselves two display
ports, two HDMI, two Ethernet. Two?
Yeah. It's got a Wi-Fi.
Yeah, this port right here is for an external Wi-Fi antenna.
And then over here, this is an external power supply port. And it looks like we've got four
USB ports, and two of them are USB 3. This is some serious...
That's awesome. Yeah, and the front's got some IO on it, too. So, dual Ethernet,
dual HDMI. That's great on this form factor. Of course, dual display port.
I mean, if you've got a Polaris GPU in there, you can
afford to run monitors, and these ports are small enough.
That's pretty neat. So, if you're looking at tiny PCs, that Zotac one might be pretty cool.
And we'll have a link to the PC World article where they talk about it. And it was called...
Oh, yeah, the Magnus. The Magnus.
Speaking of cool hardware, Ben is joining us in the Mumble Room. He just got himself
a new System76. Did you get the Lemur, Ben? Or what did you get?
I got the Lemur. The Lemur. I'm not familiar with that one.
The Lemur. Yeah. So, tell me, what did you get? What was your spec? Did you get the base unit?
Did you modify it all? How long have you had it? I put some upgrades in it.
Come on, you've got to get the deets. Tell us the deets. Alright, alright. Here's the order page.
Let me tell you what I paid for. I paid
$1,334 for it. And I got second day air shipping.
Ooh. Yes.
I got 1604.1 on it with a
114 mod display IPS LED backlight. Yeah, the matte display.
So instead of the shiny display, right? Right. And HD graphics
620. Ooh. And I also got the 2.7
up to 3.5 processor i7 when all 9 yards.
Ooh. Yes. Are you worried all about heat when you go up to the i7?
What do you think? It's only two cores and four threads, so it's nothing major.
Yeah. I also got 16 gigs of RAM,
2400 megahertz DDR4, and a
250 gig M.2 SSD. Nice.
Good call. And I also got a secondary 500 gig drive,
as well as the upgraded Wi-Fi and Bluetooth and
yeah. It's nice to be able to get a laptop that small and still have an Ethernet
port on it. Yeah, definitely. No joke, because in honesty, I
sold my Macbook for this thing, because I just was getting so fed up with this stupid
thing. It was like, I can't run Linux on this darn thing.
That's how we started chatting about this, really. Right. And truthfully,
I just got so fed up with the thing I sold it on eBay and bought
this System76, because I just wanted to be able to run my Linux just fine, and
I finally just said, screw it. And you know, so... How's the keyboard
been, and the screen quality and all that? It's been fine.
It's, you know, been very wonderful. It's better to type on than any of my other laptops
I own, and I'm very pleased. And the screen? How's the screen?
The screen looks good? Great. Not having any problems.
These guys are all making me want to get a new rig so bad.
I've got the Apollo, which is really great, but it's only two core. And I want a four
core system for video editing. Your mobile editing rig. Yeah. So like
my Apollo has become my go-to at-home computer.
And that's wonderful. But when I want to edit video, I'm like, I'm kind of still going towards the MacBook
Pro, just because it's got four cores. And a dedicated...
And a dedicated GPU. And I'm loving this thing so much, Chris.
I might actually throw Arch on it as well. I think you should.
Just because I'm that daring. I think it would probably run fine,
really. Oh, sure. Yeah. Especially with those total of six
cores. I'm going to have so much fun doing that. And I might actually
stream the install. You know, one thing Mike was saying on Coder Radio is he's not a big
fan of the trackpad. What are your thoughts on the trackpad? Because you were using a MacBook Pro before, and
they tend to have pretty good trackpads. Well, I actually think
it's better than the MacBook trackpad. Really? How so?
Well, I'm going to be honest. I liked the Mac
trackpad, but it's just that tap to click was horrible.
And I'm actually finding that... Having physical buttons
is nice. And actually, the
HP I'm talking to you guys on right now has buttons on it, as does my System76.
So I'm finding that a heck of a lot easier. And I've actually,
when I'm playing like SWTOR or something, I'm having a
heck of a lot better time gaming. And made of Linux Steam
games, which I do do, I've had a lot better time like
playing Kotor 2 on Linux, which has natively ported
very much better. Hmm. Well, keep us updated,
Ben, on how it goes. Because I think a lot of people are looking right now.
No problem. I've been following this topic with a lot more interest
recently. Yeah, the more first person feedback we can get, the better. But also, I will
send you a picture of my soon-to-be setup as
well. Nice. I love setup pictures.
We've got to move to something a little disappointing, because it makes me
remember the time where I had such a badass PVR setup.
And I would have been crushed if I would have seen this news back then. But the official
Mythbuntu distro is going away.
The developers of Mythbuntu Linux Distribution have announced that the development of the official
Ubuntu flavor will come to an end in the coming future. They stated that it's just because of a lack of
manpower to work on updates and bug fixing. Of course, you can still just install
Ubuntu or Ubuntu and install Myth. But this is
sort of, I think, more indicative of a bigger trend happening,
where this is probably PVRs on Linux
probably just going to get rolled into something like Kodi. And I've got to imagine
there's a couple of projects... AmbientPlex are both also able to do this stuff now.
How do you think things like MythTV might be a little bit of
an older style and model? And especially it was great, like, early
2000s when you had all the cable channels, you wanted digital access to them.
Things like Netflix, etc., weren't necessarily big or streaming yet, so it made a lot
of sense. And maybe it still has a place, but it's not nearly as popular.
But man, I had such a cool setup for a little while.
Had to remove all the commercials and save them off to a special folder.
And I could access it on all my TVs.
Compared to something where you're using the proprietary thing, or you've got a VCR and
you're programming the time in, looking up the... No.
That's so not how I want to do it.
So if you're a MythBuntu user, don't fret. MythTV isn't going away.
Just that particular distribution. But I
back then was relying on these put together distros because I just didn't want to invest
the time in figuring out everything. I actually eventually even
built them on top of Gentoo boxes, so I did eventually just roll my own. But
getting started, it was really nice to have a distro. I can't remember which one it was called,
to be honest with you, but it was Fedora-based at the time.
You know, I think I'd like to hear Chris last, the Gentoo
years on UserAir or something. That would be good.
You know, people think
we're crazy for running Arch in the places we roll Arch.
I ran Gentoo Linux in the most mission-critical of
financial institutions where the ability to process and prove
transactions was running on these boxes, and I put them on Gentoo, so that would be a good story.
Because it was, looking back on it, as much of a fan of rolling
Linux as I am right now, never would have done that.
Never. But something, I guess, I don't know if I was stupid at the time.
Part of it was I was excited, and there was only so many
ways to get this version of CUPS with these drivers and this version of Samba.
That was sort of it.
Maybe if you'd like to hear that story, come see me in California. I'll be in the Oakland, San Francisco,
Berkeley area this weekend, Sunday, November 13th.
We're going to do a meetup where I'd normally be doing Linux action shows since we pre-recorded last weekend.
I'm going to do a meetup in California, so if you're in the area, go to
meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting, or just find the link in the show notes,
and let me know if you're going. Right now the plan is to go to the
Handong Restaurant, which is famous for their dumplings and all their
other delicious food, and we'll just hang out and chat.
Watch Chris eat dumplings, you know, buy him a beer. Or maybe I'll buy you a beer, depending.
You never know. You just never know. Meetup.com slash
Jupiter Broadcasting. That sounds like a ton of fun.
It might be. It might be. Yeah, and then we're going to stay down in the California area
through Monday, but that'll probably just mostly be doing the tourist thing
recording some video. Little vacay. Picking up what we call in the industry some b-roll
for the footage, you know, so that way when we come back and put it all together
I've got shots of California. The California experience. Location establishing
shots with air quotes. That proves that you didn't just make it all up. Yeah.
Didn't just go to video blocks and buy it off of b-roll. Yeah. Meetup.com slash Jupiter
Broadcasting. If you'd like to hang out while I'm on my way down to California,
and I'm sitting there working in Lady Joob's, I'll be connected to a ting
and my fi. That's right. That's right. Go to linux.ting.com to sign up
and support the show and get $25 off your first ting device or
$25 in service credit. If you have a GSM or CDMA device, check their
BYOD page because they support both types of networks.
And now newer phones, they just have like the universal GSM chips and they work everywhere.
It's amazing. So nice. It's the way it should have been all along. And that's ting.
Ting is the way wireless should have always been because you just pay for what you use. No contract, no
registration fee, no locked phones, no like ting experience layer
where they get in the way of you and updates and they hold back update. None of
that. None of it. Let's just stop. It's almost 2017.
Let's stop and you can do your part. Go to linux.ting.com and just
take the ting litmus test. Click that what would you save button. When you're
listening to this, we have a new president of the United States. And God knows, now that that person's
in office, you're going to need to save money. Works either way.
How timely, Chris. How timely.
Go there and check them out. They've got great customer service. They have a bunch of good devices
from the budget category and probably honestly ones you haven't even considered
because Ting's thinking outside the box with some of these things. Everything from feature phones like the
Moto G4 Play is also a great smartphone with a decent feature set
for a great price. Mifis, blue devices, Nexus devices,
internet phones, and they've got a great blog to top it all off. Did you see
this, Wes? They did a how-to on how to install a freaking USB power outlet
in your home. So you take like the power plug. Really? Yeah, no more adapters and dongles.
No, no. Just go right from the wall to your device. That's great. That's kind of a neat tip. They've got
a bunch of great tips over there. That's just an example. They're such nerds. I love it.
Linux.ting.com. Go there because Linux.
And you know, in case like you've got a significant other that sits down
at your computer and you're a little worried about what might come up in your URL history,
good to have Linux in there because it just looks like you're geeking out all the time. So it's also
just good for you. It's good for us. It's good for Ting. Let's just everybody do
each other a favor. Right now, you're watching live. You're sitting at home listening.
You're in your car doing 70 miles per hour down the freeway. I want you to grab your
iPhone. No, don't do it then. But I want you to grab your phone. Every other time.
Linux.ting.com. Go there. Check them out. Grab a device or bring a device.
Save some money and only pay for what you use. And a big thank you to Ting for
sponsoring the unplugged program. Linux.ting.com.
Well, we've got a little breaking news right now as we record the show, Wes.
Breaking news. Yeah, we got ourselves a brand new edition of Cinnamon
that just hit, well, stable. But it's not actually available to install. Version 3.2
has been released by Clem. And it's got some fanciness in it.
It comes with a workspace switcher that's been nice and updated and improved. Simplified background
manager, keyboard navigation for context menus, which is
dope. That's nice. Yeah. Updated app indicators and settings, support for display
and percentage next to the volume slider.
Also, I think there's a couple other nice ones in here like the placement of the system tray notifications was fixed
and is no longer dependent on GComp, which could be good depending on your view. And last
but not least, I think probably this is the most
expose Mac-like feature, but also kind of useful. They call it Peek
at the desktop. Oh, that's cute. Yeah. And it's, as you can kind of guess by the name,
it's a desktop applet that lets you quickly take a peek
at your active desktop and throws everything out of the way. Also support for the latest
GTK 3, I believe, is in there. Cinnamon 3.2
probably going to be hitting a point update in Mint soon,
Arch repos, and other places where you get your Cinnamon. That's not a bad
update from the Cinnamon team. No, no, no. I'm not using it a lot these days, but I still
have a great respect for Cinnamon just as a very usable, you know, it's not necessarily
the best or the prettiest or the newest looking, but I feel like it's still pretty cool.
You're right, though. It's traditional. Right? If you're not going to go full like
tiling window manager, I find it a good power user desktop.
Still think GNOME 3 edges out a bit for me, but I agree. It's in there.
So I asked Wes, I said, Wes, what's one of your favorite stories this week? And
you found this freeing my tablet, aka Android hacking, both the
software and the hardware. This guy writes, two years ago, I left my country.
It's a sad story, but this is just to say
I had some time, and I was working remotely for an Irish startup, and
he wanted to get Debian on his tablet.
That is an ambitious goal. There was no real open source process
for rooting the device, getting Debian on there, so he starts
up with an ASUS Memo Pad 10, specifically the ME 103k edition,
which came out in like August, I think, of 2015. It's got
a 10-inch screen, a gigabyte of RAM, quad core Qualicom Snapdragon, and
16 gigs of storage. Jeez, it sounds like it's about like a MacBook Pro.
But this is where it really kind of gets interesting, though, because he had to
do this whole deep dive into Android and figure out how the Android boot process works and
all of the secrets. What was it that grabbed your attention? Yeah, to me, it kind of just reads as
almost like a Rosetta Stone for, you know, like,
traditional GNU slash Linux desktop users, because we're used to our user land, and Android has the
kernel, but it's such a different system from everywhere up, and so he really kind of
talks a lot about how Android is structured so that you can replace it
with Linux. Yeah, that is a really cool
journey that he documents here. Just the time it must have taken
to stop at every stage and document this and capture it and then save
it for his blog later. That's a lot of work! And he's
looking at waveforms. It's really a deep dive, and it's a lot of fun.
Sometimes I picture, like, the guys at Canonical that were trying to figure out how to
get Ubuntu Android Edition working for the first time doing stuff like this.
Yeah, digging around in there. That's interesting.
It's probably the most important, or probably the most impressive part about it is the documentation aspect.
Yeah, because it's so well, like, the code aspect is clearly
indicated on here, like, he's using some nice formatting.
SE Linux. Oh, and he talks about having to work around SE Linux. So hopefully this will be more useful
as we see more Ubuntu on phones roll out,
as we see more stuff where, like, more Android stuff becomes in the mainline
kernel. Hopefully this will be more useful. I know, like, Nexus 5 is mostly supported in mainline
now, so maybe I can run Debian on here. Not that I would.
So remember I was talking about FileZilla, and I like it. I've used
FileZilla for years. It's not gorgeous or anything, but it sure gets the job done.
And according to this person,
FileZilla does not encrypt your saved FTP passwords,
and because of it, he was hacked, and so he ended up
forking FileZilla and calls it FileZilla Secure.
FileZilla Secure is a free FTP client that has all the features of the original
FileZilla, plus it encrypts your FTP passwords to protect from hackers
stealing them. But they're local passwords, so it doesn't really matter.
It's the same argument with Pigeon back in the day. Yeah, I guess
somebody either got on his machine, oh, malware got into my system through a browser
exploit, and within seconds, someone suddenly had access to all of my websites.
So do you know, does it then prompt you to enter an unlock key?
It looks like it from the screenshots, yeah. There's a master password to decrypt your
FTP logins. I haven't installed it, but looking at his screenshots,
that's what it looks like. He said it took him a week trying to clean up the mess after somebody
got his password file for FileZilla. I feel like at this point, would it be better spent
just making a plugin for key pass or other type database?
I don't think it's even a good idea because it's a local
issue. If you have a local infection, there's more than
that is the problem. And they do actually
do base 64 encoding, so it's not like you can just read a plain text password.
But it's not encrypted, but that's kind of the purpose. They want you to
know that it's not totally encrypted because that's
a security theater at that point.
I think it's still a good idea to do it. I feel like you should have security at all layers
like an onion. The only thing that bothers me about this
particular one is that the commits are associated to example.com
email. That's a little weird.
So also he says increase the maximum number of
transfer feeds from 10 to 1,000. He says
10,000 is not really recommended, but 20, 50, and even 100 threads
has shown to work and increase transfer speeds by 5x.
Well, it's interesting to see new development anyway. Yeah, and I guess it's something to be aware of.
Because I didn't actually think about it. I didn't really think about the fact that
I might have really important server logins just sitting on my hard drive unencrypted because otherwise
I don't put passwords and text files on my hard drive. Even if they're base 64
encoded, I'm not comfortable with that. The other thing that people should just stop using FTP. Use
keys, use SFTP. Is that what you were going to say?
I would say FTPT, but I also wanted to point out that
even though FileZilla is kind of ugly by default, there's a new theme
on Compact called FlatZilla that actually makes it look pretty good.
Okay, good to know. Nice tip. Telling people to stop using FTP is like
I don't know. You should know, but some people don't. You can use FTP, just do it over SSH.
There you go. You know what it is like all those hosts out there
that host cheap websites and stuff. That's why you've got to go with a great host like DigitalOcean.
Go to DigitalOcean.com and use our special promo code of
power, DO, one word lowercase, and don't host it on some fly by
night site that requires you to FTP up your files like an animal. Host it over
at DigitalOcean.com. In fact, DigitalOcean has outrageously great
pricing. $5 a month will give you a great rig with an SSD
hard drive that will easily run a personal website like nobody's business.
And with a $10 credit, you can run it two months for free. But look at this. Look at this pricing.
If you're watching the video version right now, I want you to lick your screen. I want you to stand up and lick your screen.
Three cents an hour for two gigabytes of memory, a two core processor, a 40
gigabyte SSD, and three terabytes of boss level transfer. Why is it boss
level? Well, that's a great question because you're reading from them SSDs over a 40 to a 40
gigabyte e-connection. And they've got data centers in New York, San Francisco, Singapore,
Amsterdam, London, Toronto, and Germany. You could spin up a droplet in each one of those.
Now you're boss level. You just went boss level.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED. I'll tell you what else is boss level.
Their interface. Holy shmoly
that interface. It is so well designed, so
well laid out, but yet doesn't feel watered down.
And then they have an API that's intuitive and command line utilities that allow you to run
large scale production workloads or just something in your quake terminal. Drop it down
and issue a command. You want to do a snapshot before you do a big transaction, a big upgrade,
a big change? And you do. And you do. You also have great apps you can
use on your phone. They have highly available storage. I said highly available
storage. It's highly available. And you can run up to 16 terabytes, attach
it to your droplet. Here's what I would do.
I'd start out with that three cents an hour rig. And then I'd put MB on there.
And then I'd get a whole bunch of block storage and
formatted all ButterFS. All ButterFS
all the time in RAID 5 mode. No, I'm just kidding.
I'm just poking fun. What are you telling me, people? I'm just poking fun. No, they got ZFS.
So I would use that. Why not? Go use a real file system. And they got FreeBSD if you want
to go that route. They got Ubuntu. They got score OS. You know, MB is right in FreeBSD's
package manager. Really? I wouldn't know that. I wouldn't.
And I would not. I would. BSD would not be my first choice for a
an MB server. But you could do it. You could do it for some reason.
You could do it. You could also run Fedora up there on DigitalOcean. You could
run good old classic Debian. Nice lean and mean Debian.
You could do it. You could do it. Why not?
And you should. Hey Wes, do it. Do it right now. Just do it. Just go to DigitalOcean.
DigitalOcean.com and use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
You apply to your account and you get a $10 credit and you support the show. Big thanks
to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged program. All right, we've got to help our friend
out. We had an audience member write into the Jupyter broadcasting subreddit. Yeah,
there is one. Who knew?
He says, please explain NFS to me before I destroy something.
And I think he probably had an effing in there, but he probably cut it out. And this is from
Bugabinga. And he says, are you planning or have you already made any guides or segments
to setting up NFS at home? I realize NFS spans a wide range of
use cases, but I'm interested from the perspective of a desktop Linux user. How to share
media and documents with my family on our LAN. Here's my environment, which I'm
curious if it's common amongst the Jupyter broadcasting audience. I have a small family household
with three to six persons, several desktops, laptops, and phones running
Android and Linux. All wireless LAN. All
5 gigahertz. He says, there are some problems I ran into when setting up NFS.
Old documentation with things confused, NFS 3 and 4.
He's not even sure if NFS is supposed to work well over Wi-Fi. Endless combination
of mount options. Confusing security model. Local UIDs and GUIDs
versus remote UIDs and GUIDs made by
old documentation. Hanging mounts on boot or logout. Cannot use
ethernet cables because we don't have, we can't use ethernet because we don't own
the flat we are living in, so they're doing Wi-Fi everywhere. He says, I'm so fed up with NFS
that I set up a somershare just for fun, and unfortunately
it works. Like, that's an unfortunate
thing. So I thought maybe we would discuss that, but
first of all, we should just say up front, if Samba works for you, there's no shame in using Samba. Not at all.
Samba, they've spent significant time making Samba work great from Linux to
Linux. It's first class. These days, there's graphical
utilities to set it up. It sounds like he's already got it working, so.
So Wes, do you have any immediate thoughts about using NFS on a wireless LAN?
I mean, I guess you will just have to make sure, like, it depends on
the distributions that you're using, but you need your storage daemons
basically, you need the dependency on the mounts with the storage daemons and on
the network. So that if the network goes down, you can have those
connections or that you won't take the network down before unmounting your NFS share.
How you do that probably depends, and wireless is obviously, because now you need
a wireless daemon, you need WPA supplicant, that kind of thing, it's less ideal
than like a simple DHCP.
If Samba's working, I really would probably just stick with Samba. I mean, unless you have like a
maybe NFS for some reason is better in your environment, or you prefer working with it, or you have
more experience, but if not, I mean, Samba gets you a lot of things.
If anybody in the mumble room has any suggestions, feel free to tag me with mum in the chat room.
I want to cover just a couple of things to help him out here a little bit. Quit worrying about NFS3
versus NFS4, really. Don't worry about that. You don't need to.
You don't need to worry about any of the maintenance issues or domain type things.
And I'm going to try to find NFS Arch.
I'm going to put a link to the Arch Wiki's NFS entry here.
I have it right here. Oh, good man. When you drop that in the doc, right by his question there,
because this is where he's getting hung up on a lot, is he says confusing
mount options, endless combinations of mount options.
Well, here's the reality. You can actually leverage
SystemD to make this better for you. SystemD can mount and unmount
automatically your NFS share or mount point when it detects
your network goes down and up. So, respectively, when the network goes down,
it will unmount it, and when the network goes up, it will remount it.
And this is really nice. So you're using SystemD to manage the mount point,
which is aware of your network state. So that's a really great feature.
So consider looking into that, and that will be in the Arch Wiki on how you set that up.
It's really simple. Some of those mount options can also help your NFS
share and mount tolerate
fluctuations in network connectivity. I like to think
of NFS as close to a physical connection
to storage as possible over a network connection before we had iSCSI and stuff.
It is designed in an era where the network is persistent, and it
expects it to be there, and the system that connects to it expects it to be part of the file
system. So this is the problem you're running into. Samba is more forgiving with connections
and disconnections because it was designed in an era where that's more frequent.
And then the other thing, when you said you're confused
about the security model, where there's local UIDs and group IDs,
and there's remote user IDs and group IDs.
This is something that is much simpler if you
have a little bit of forethought before you set up your local
box in your NFS server. I always try to make sure
that the user account I log into my Linux desktop has the same UID
as the user account I'm connecting to or with on my NFS
server. You same for you? Yeah, and I think this is where you see NFS pairs well with things where you already
have some sort of LDAP or you have some sort of directory management system set up so that you
do have the same users across multiple boxes. Yeah, otherwise what I try to do is I try to
make sure that my local user is user 1000 and my remote user
is user 1000. And that's generally, if I'm the first person to create an account
on my Linux desktop, that's generally I'll be user 1000. And so you
just have to take special note and make sure that the user account and credentials you're connecting
with are the same. Now you can specify the UID and
GID that you want to connect with in your mount options. So you can do some of that there.
But it is just simpler if everything lines up because then the security permissions
just work. And when you do it that way, I find it to be the security model to be
simpler than Samba, personally. So that is...
Alright, did we get anybody tagging me with suggestions from the... I thought this might be up the
Mumble Rooms alley file sharing. What do you guys use on your home networks to share files
around the LAN? Big files, maybe you're primarily on
WiFi, you're not hooked up. What are you using to share files between Linux boxes?
All about that Samba. Yeah, really? Mostly because I do
have some Windows boxes and other things that I want to share with. And like other little
big appliances for TVs and stuff that only talk Samba. So it makes sense just to do everything
over Samba. So are you setting up a Samba server on each machine or how are you doing that?
No, I just have a centralized NAS effectively with Samba on it.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Same here. So Pobie, you like
will from one laptop copy to a central share and then go to the other machine and copy it from that central share?
So I've got a HP microserver which I used to have
12 disks in a butterFS array but I switched to ZFS recently.
Or ZFS if you like to call it that. And I also have as another
backup Netgear NAS, Ready NAS thing
that I recently learned has butterFS in it.
And they're both Samba and I can just browse
the network on anything. Whether it's my Android phone or
Ubuntu phone or laptops or desktops or Windows or whatever.
I know Samba is going to work everywhere and I don't have to make any effort
whatsoever to connect to it. It just works.
Okay, so let's go Digitalize and then we'll go WW. So Digitalize, you're using
SSH? Yeah, I use SSHFS.
You know, it's just simple. It's installed and your operating system is ready and
it's ready to go. Yeah, that's not a bad way to go really. It's just using SCP or
SSHFS or something like that because I like having SSH on all my machines anyways.
The server and the client obviously. Alright, so WW, you have a cabling
idea laid on me. Yeah, so I live in an
older house and I can't really use a powerline
adapter. But I would suggest if he doesn't, maybe use that.
Or what we do is we actually run the cable
and then we use cable crimps which you can
lightly tap into the walls. So he could tape it
maybe on the bottom or run along the wall on the bottom with tape.
Or check with your landlord and see if you can lightly tap into
those cable crimpers and they're really easy to patch up
when you move out. You know, you can just spackle. The powerline networking
could be interesting. I would want to test it first because I've had mixed results with it.
Like here at the studio, I can't plug something in
upstairs and then plug the other end in by the TV and get networking from
that. It's because it's like cross circuit breakers or something. Alright, so I was
hoping Wimpy would represent someone using NFS because now I'm starting to feel like I'm a maniac
using NFS to share files. So Wimpy, what's your setup?
I use NFS exports effectively for me. So
most of the stuff that's accessed from the NAS's in the house
is over some protocol specific to what it does.
So there's DLNA used for the music and Plex used
for the photos and the videos. And that's what the
devices in the front room and all the rest of it
are hooked up to. For me to actually hurl photos
and videos and music into the servers, I use NFS.
And then I have a couple of Samba shares
which are just there so when family and friends visit
and they've got photos and things they want to share with us,
they can just connect them from whatever computer that they're
using and drop them in there and then I can deal with them after the fact.
Are you doing a guest Samba account too for that? Yeah, yeah.
It's just four guests. They've got their own wireless network as well.
Their own VLAN. Oh, really?
So like a dedicated router in its own VLAN? No, no.
It's the same router so it's just a VLAN on the same router. Nice.
And their own subnet and they can't peer at any of the management
interfaces or anything like that and the hosts on that VLAN can't contact
one another either. All they can do is get to the internet and get to that
Samba share. I just set up a guest Wi-Fi network in Lady Jupiter
because I figure we're going to hang out. I'm meeting a couple of people
on the way down and once we get there people are going to be welcomed into the Lady Jupiter.
And the thing you know about JB fans is they're technically savvy. First question is how do I get on
the Wi-Fi? And the thing is, well, now I've got a data server,
a file server on here and my password is honestly embarrassing
and so I don't really want to tell audience members that I just meet on the road.
And it changes your threat model, right? It's like, well, it's Hedea and you and
the kids and a couple other trusted people then you can kind of be a little more liberal.
Second, there's people you don't know or people you hardly know. That's different. And the router
supports it so it's just a matter of enabling that functionality and so I just took a little time
and I was like, I'm going to have some people visiting. Some people like they clean up
and do like dishes and stuff before they have people over. I set up the guest Wi-Fi network.
You should probably install something, you know, like ad blocking.
Yeah, yeah. So, alright, any other thoughts from the Mumba Room
on file sharing over your homeland before we move on? And hopefully
Bugabinga is, oh yeah, did you have some? Oh, I was just going to say, like when we said
DLNA is something that can get used if you're serving certain
types of things. I've also seen like WebDAV or even if you're
going one direction only, you can always just run an HTTP server. This is something
that Nextcloud does make kind of easy if you have a Nextcloud server on your LAN is you can do the WebDAV
thing or you could just be like, here's a URL to go to. This is something I do
for Angela with her Open Media Vault server. There's just a couple of things I installed
on there and I'm not setting up port forwarding on her router or anything like that.
It's just, here, go to this URL. It's all local URL, but she can give it
to anybody that comes over and so when they're taking pictures and stuff, they can put it on there.
That'll be a nice thing and it's like, why not just set that up and make it easy
enough. Give them a spot to go to and then lock down the stuff that you're really concerned about.
That's a good way to go. Go ahead.
Well, Chris, this is going to be interesting. I'm actually thinking about setting up
Ubuntu or some kind of server with file sharing after the show.
Oh yeah? What are you going to use?
Probably Z or NFS, something like that. But what are you going to use to share the files? Probably
Samba now.
Yeah, that's probably what I'm looking at.
I think a lot of Linux users, some of us when we move over to Linux,
we want to reject anything Microsoft and Samba
feels like a Microsoft thing. But I would look at Samba
as Samba actually represents a really kind of inspirational
decade long journey to not only
figure out what Microsoft is doing in a way that doesn't violate patents
and copyright and reverse engineer, but then
to build a superior product and then on top of that, they've built in
functionality to make it so when the Samba client, when you connect to a Samba server
and the Samba server realize they're talking to each other, they've built in hooks
to then communicate more efficiently and quicker and faster.
They are aware of the way the kernel works on each end of the system and it is
like a superior technology and that I think the Samba
project probably doesn't get enough credit for. Okay, Monkey Comm, you'll
wrap us up with a little Kaja slash SFTP
right in the file manager approach. Tell me about it.
Yeah, I've been using that for a while. It avoids having to set up something
separate, something like Samba or NFS. You just set up
SSH with user privileges and you use your file browser in MIT.
Yeah, and you can even just bookmark it on the sidebar there.
You click it and it prompts you for the password if it's not saved in the key ring.
That's how I get to a lot of the systems here on the JB network these days. The reason why I don't like it a lot,
and this is only if you're using it a lot, if you're using it heavily, is there is
the overhead of using GVFS and then there is also the overhead
of using SSH to encrypt everything.
I'm sitting here sending a 3.5 to 30
gigabyte H.264 file and I'm encrypting
all of it. That's all hitting my CPU and then it's all hitting the other
side of the CPU to decode it just so that way I can move it from machine to machine.
I don't give two craps if it's encrypted or not. So here's the question. Is there something
like SSH FS but Netcat FS?
Because I'll do that on the local network. You're just piping it through Netcat
and you go boom. Yes, there you go. What do you think of that?
You know what? You should save that for the five
top command line entries that
end users must know. New end users should learn and we're just going to accept that every
now and then it's okay to learn the command line. And you know what? Speaking of learning the command line, it's a great time
to mention Linux Academy, the third sponsor here on the Unplugged program, which
means we are winding down to the last segment. I am
really impressed with Linux Academy. They just closed another round of funding and they are
really kicking into high gear. I'll tell you about just some of the new things coming around the corner, but first let me give you
the basics. Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged. It's a platform to learn about
Linux and all of the really great things around the nitty gritty aspects of Linux and
the stuff built on top of it. linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged. Go there. Sign up for a seven day free trial and then
I have a course I want to recommend to you because it's such a no brainer and I'm not sure I've ever
mentioned it before. They have a course on how to use Linux Academy.
So you get the best out of Linux Academy by taking this introduction to Linux Academy course.
Wow, that's like man-man. Isn't this a great idea though?
It seems like it. No, that seems essential. Good way to get the most out of it.
But here's a couple of new things they've been working on. You ready for this?
I'm not even sure if they've released this fully publicly yet, but this is new stuff that's just come out.
That's why you listen here. We spill the beans. They've got the AWS Certified DevOps Engineer professional
level course now, the SysAdmins Guide to Bash Scripting,
the Cloud Essentials Certification Prep Course, Running Container and Clusters with Kubernetes,
which is very timeful right now, Apache Spark
Essentials, Red Hat Certified Engineer Prep Course, the AWS Certified
SysOps Administrator Course Refresh. They just refreshed the courseware on that
and they just refreshed the courseware on the Docker Deep Dive. Nice.
Yeah, that's also because there's been some updates there. Some big content updates coming
soon for the AWS Concepts and KVM Virtualization Essentials
as well. That'll be coming in the fall, which is just about now. Lots of good stuff
on Ansible coming down the pipe as well, which I know is interesting to a lot of our audience
member, as well as Big Data Essentials, Jenkins, Git Essentials,
and Azure Prep Courses. So there's
new releases just about every day right now at Linux Academy. So your
subscription has never been more valuable. LinuxAcademy.com slash
unplugged. Go there. Sign up for the seven-day free trial. Support the show by visiting that URL
and learn more about the first platform built exclusively to teach you
about Linux. LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring the unplugged program. So now,
speaking of command line tools that we need to learn,
PCWorld has an article up that I think we should vet. The five terminal commands
every Linux newbie should know. Dun dun dun. And I want to go
through the list. I'm going to read them off to you and then I say we put any of these up for replacement.
So we're testing you, making sure you know what they all are. So number one,
every Linux newbie should know sudo. Number two, and then we'll talk about
these, you should know your package manager, be it yum, apt, pacman, of course.
You should know your package manager. Number three, systemctl
to manage systemd services. Number four,
I'm surprised it took number, see I wonder if our list, if this wouldn't be maybe
a little bit up on the list, ls, you know, to list directory.
It seems like you might want that before number four. So this is...
And number five, man. Of course, we all know the man page,
man pages. So they have, again, to recap, five is
man, four is ls, three is systemctl,
two is pacman or
apt, and one is sudo.
I feel like, I feel like maybe nothing's missing
here necessarily, although ps would be nice or top
would be nice. I also, we'll get into
this, but I feel like if my list would be ls
first
and probably man second. Yeah, man's pretty good. And then
I think I would do things like sudo. I think that would be three.
And I think... Although should we not, maybe we shouldn't
tell them about sudo if they're reading this list? Okay, systemctl stays at
three. And sudo, I still feel like sudo should be in there. I mean, you will
need to learn it, right? Once you need to make any system change. I think sudo is four and your package manager
is five. I think like the last thing you need to know as a new Linux user is how to use your
package manager on the command line. You should learn how to list directories. I think you should
learn how to look at processes, maybe know how to
do basic things like read a manual, reboot.
Maybe free in there. If you don't know these tools, you're likely installing a distro that has a
graphical package manager. Right. So you don't...
I'm curious to know what... Let's see what some of the
Mumble Room thinks. So if you guys have a list or a command that
you think is missing, ping me in the Mumble Room. Oh, you do, Poppy? Go ahead.
So I just pasted you a command you can run, which
shows the most popular ten commands in
your bash history. Oh, that's a great one. And for me,
the top five, number one is ls by
a factor of two above the next thing I've ever run, which is cd.
Right, so ls and cd and then sudo, which is
not unreasonable on Ubuntu where you don't get root account by default. Yeah. And then the
next one is my editor of choice, which I'm not going to name because I'll just get hate.
And then there's other stuff after that. But yeah, ls and cd and
sudo, they seem like reasonable things to have at the top of your list. So...
I think you should say, and we can debunk a myth here.
I'll go first. My favorite editor is
Nano. Oh!
Were you here earlier in the show where I admitted to getting crap for the last two weeks
because I used Nano? I heard you mention it, and I wasn't here
to back you up, but I've been using Nano forever. And this is
mostly because the first Unix system I used,
Pine was the email client, and consequently
Pico was the editor. Oh my god, Pico, yes!
Nano is a Pico clone. So hard coded into my
DNA is all the key bindings for Nano.
I knew there was a reason I liked you, Martin. That must be it.
I forgot about Pico! All these people that say that Vim and Vi
are so powerful, and there's all these key bindings. Well, there's all these key bindings in
Nano as well. And if you know them, it's just as
fast and productive. I love you. That is amazing. I forgot about
Pico, and that absolutely, and Pine, yes. Yes, alright.
So is it Nano for you too, Popey, that I take it? Yep. Alright.
Now, JDA, I think I saw that go by, you also use Nano.
Yes, I also use Nano, and I'll say as a visually impaired
Linux user, yeah, I'm low, so it's
a lot more user friendly when you're zoomed in to a pretty high degree
on a monitor than the alternatives out there,
and just as someone who's tried all the different ones, in an accessibility
standpoint, Nano takes the cake, and I just wanted to
throw my two cents in there. I can't believe we started this show out with me admitting to all the crap I was getting.
And Ben, you use Nano as well? Yeah, man.
Nobody stood up, nobody said anything. Yes, Club Nano, there we go.
A wrong has been righted. Wait a minute, you see guys, I am
visually impaired too, I have to wear glasses because I have a stigmatism and light problem, and truthfully,
I just gotta use Nano because of my sight, and because
you know, I also have autism, so it's kind of hard for me to wrap my hand around
other editors. Dude, you don't have to justify it, just embrace it.
I love the Nano. It's fine. Sweetloo, you're a Nano user too, Sweetloo?
I am, and my hierarchy
is Pseudo, CD, TAR, LS, and WP.
Alright, you guys wanna know mine? Yeah.
My top RAND command, do you have a guess before I say what it is?
Don't look. OBS. JITC. Huh?
JITC or OBS? Nope, it is
Packer dash dash SYU. Dang.
Wow. Archbox, right? Someone has a problem. Typical Arch user.
I'm updating my packages, I'm updating my packages.
Yeah, spin got it, spin got it. Oh, ngrep for monkeycom.
What do you use an ngrep for so much, monkeycom? We're on telecom,
so I'm constantly looking at streams. That makes sense. Hence the name.
My top 10 has a YouTube DL on it. Really? I bet
mine upstairs does where I do the unfilter clips, because I pull a lot now these days off YouTube.
So my top command is CD, and then
sudo ls git nano rm ssh cat apt unyadim.
I think you can tell mine is a laptop, because like SSH,
ping, MTR, IP, clearly I'm on a lot of networks. And you're
testing your connectivity each time, like why is this not going as fast as it should, what's the problem with
this thing? Why is YouTube DL so slow? Oh man, YouTube DL is
one of the best applications ever. It's funny, I
see like lots of these scrolling by in IRC, people saying ls is their most popular
thing. And when you watch people doing screencasts where there's command line stuff,
when people are, if they don't plan their video well,
you'll often see them just type ls randomly. I've watched
people give presentations where they're about to type a command. It's like your
idle thing. Yeah, it's like, you know how like
valley people say so in front of a sentence? Like nerds say ls
in front of a sentence before they do stuff. It's like a nervous tick anymore sometimes.
That's my um and pause for thought last thing.
Yeah, I don't, you'd think I would use like PWD more to get my current
directory, but no, it's ls, and I always recognize where I'm at by what I see on the screen, and
I'm getting like, and I even do ls-la. I don't,
I like to have it. It's always dash la man, always. Yeah, I like to
have it with the attributes and the timestamp. Oh no. We are such nerds.
ls-lisa. Oh, lisa. Now, what is the
what is the s? I want to try it now. Now I'm going to go do that.
You could have told me something. Yeah, sl is probably 10% of my commands too. Oh my god, that's
too wide. Oh, that's too wide, yeah. It gives you everything. Yeah, it does.
See, I'll do a little. You need that stuff. See,
well actually ls still does quite a bit of stuff too. Look at all that though.
See, Rekai says ls-lot, and I like that because it's easy
to remember, but I always type it la, la, no,
l-t-r-a for some reason. I can't type it in the right order. We
are really geeking out now. This is
the best Linux podcast unit. This is the Linux podcast unit's finest right here.
Alright, so ls is obviously on the top of all
of our lists for these five commands for new users. Is there anything else missing?
I would say that if you have systemctl, you should really mention journalctl. Yes.
Because that's an under, I mean, people don't appreciate how easy it is to make it
review things. Michael Dominic's system kernel panicked on him, and he was not sure how
he was supposed to look at the logs anymore. It was totally foreign to him.
So yeah, that would be a good one. Yeah, monkeycomp saying tail-f
log, yeah, yeah, yeah. Or journalctl, yeah. Alright,
that's a good one. Any others? I think you want, maybe you'll want
like ip or ifconfig, but really ip just for... What do you think, Wes?
What do you think, Wes, of just admitting
that it's not horrible to know a couple of command line tools? Like, the computer is
a tool. Right. And do we have to pretend like there's no command line
all the time? And it seems like really the equilibrium we should reach
is you use GUIs for things that you enjoy using GUIs for, and it makes sense
to use them for, and use the command line when it makes sense to do that. And obviously it'll be different
per user, but it shouldn't be something that has to be hidden away. One of the things I've seen
happen a couple of times, either directly or indirectly, just
either by being involved with a migration or just watching a migration as a third party
is I have watched several times companies transition from DOS-based
like terminal input, like either through like an SSH login or a
VTR or whatever, like the old virtual terminals for mainframes or
just a DOS app, like they could fly through with the keyboard, you know, like they
and they go, okay, and then okay, Mr. Fisher. Okay, yep,
we're ready to go. And I just ducked all the way out of the concern chair room.
And now they're like, okay, let me, let's see,
I don't really know how to use the system. So you wanted to move your
reservation to, okay, well, yeah, okay. So if I go
into here and I click, like it's their efficiency
really dropped off. And I'm not trying to say that the command line was easier to use,
but there is something about
that particular interface that is sometimes the most efficient way to interact with the computer.
Right, it's that balance of like utility versus learning curve. And, you know, so something that
makes sense for a home user, a casual user might not make sense for someone whose job it is to use
software every day. William, were you going to say something?
Oh, I was just going to suggest even my parents are kind of like that. Like they kind of remember the good old DOS days
when I bring them back to a terminal. It's kind of hilarious. And it's kind of nostalgic and fun
the few times they have to use it. I was all like the first time
I was migrating a company from a DOS system. It was a DOS system that loaded up
and then it launched a DOS-based mainframe terminal.
I can't even remember what those terminals are called anymore.
And then they spent their entire day in this system. And that was the computer
to them. And I migrated them to a graphical version of that.
And it sucked so bad. It was, I had, I was so
gung-ho about moving this company into the modern day and getting them on graphical
interface. And it was going to be, you know, replacing all these old
custom built PCs with brand new thin clients. And
it just was a huge usability reduction. And it was never
part of the conversation. It might have been an 8270. It might
have been. That doesn't ring a bell though. I think people who don't actually use the system take for granted
how much muscle memory there is in typing that stuff out and how quick you can translate what you want in your head
to some pattern you type in on the console after you've done it so many times.
Yeah, and if it's a series of eight menu options and it's one through eight to trigger them
and your hand's already hovering to the keyboard, you just tap that thing out super quick.
Like especially the hotel receptionists and stuff who have got it down to a science and they're just like banging on the keyboard and just
get it all done immediately.
So I think when we talk about Linux, and
I think a lot of people are going to be moving over to Linux are geek power users. I don't know if,
I mean I'm sure it's not all of them, but we've been talking about this theoretical frustrated
web development user who's got a Macbook a few years
ago because it was BSD with a GUI and now they've realized, oh this is
actually a commercial product that has a lot of other interests and it's not their
primary focus, it's not their main platform, it's not their money maker, and there's a huge
strategy tack that's dragging this entire platform around by the ball sack. I want to move
to something where I can just get my work done, I can get a laptop with the hardware I want,
and I can still SSH into the same servers and build my same applications.
And there's a lot of little niche use cases like that, like
UserAir. UserAir two years ago, I never could have
produced the entire thing using Linux and open source software. And now we have an
entire system that's all open. I mean it's like a lot of
different use cases are switching over to Linux and each little
niche vertical is going to add up to a serious amount of users.
I hope, I think, that's the theory, right? That's the hope, that's the theory.
And so when they come here, why not say, yeah, you'll have to use the command line
sometimes, there's probably like six, five, six, seven, eight commands you should probably do. You should probably
learn, take a half hour and learn each one, and you will have
a good set of tools to learn more from there. If you know Man, you know LS,
you know how to look at processes, you know how to stop and start services, you know a
lot of stuff that you're never going to have to deal with the command line. And maybe that's a good way to approach it, right?
Like it's different than if you're going to the Windows world where, you know, like there's a whole
huge system of things to learn. On Linux there's a lot of, you can get by with a lot of like just a
few fundamental principles, you know, five or ten commands that you need to know, and then you can
administer a fair bit of your system.
Hurricane, you think Windows 10 users are ripe for the pick and two?
Yeah, well I started on Windows 10, or I was a Windows
user a couple years ago, and then two years ago when Windows 10s came out I just completely
dropped it. And that's when I started
packaging Namby for you guys and for the community and
now all my machines run Linux.
Well our one then, our benefit. That's awesome. That is really good.
Alright, so Ben I want to give you a chance to jump in because
you got the new System76 machine, you're switching over from the Macbook, you're not afraid of the command line.
You're okay with it.
Bingo. No? Going once? Going twice? Alright, Swift, I'll let you
have the last word on this particular one. Go ahead.
Yeah, in this case it's like with Vista, I remember when that came out.
I was Ben the guy who sold you the Macbook.
Okay, when Vista came out you would have thought that that would have been a big
deal to get people to Linux, and yet even though it was such a catastrophe
that's not what happened. No, they went to the Mac.
Yeah, so with Windows 10, I mean I wonder how that's going to
be the change now with Macbook Pros being what they are now,
and just with people getting aggravated with Apple.
I'm curious if that's ever going to happen and make people really switch to Linux.
That's what I want to see. I think that is what's happening.
I think it is. I think a lot of them, I think when Vista came out
people said to themselves, that's it, I'm going to get a Mac.
I was going to get a Ubuntu rig, but they ruined it. They ruined it for us.
They ruined everything. That was actually surprisingly common.
I feel like a lot of the blogs kind of talked about how they looked at, you know, right when the Unity transition happened
they had been looking at using Linux and then went to Mac OS, so it's interesting
that inflection point wasn't that long ago. I know, I know. I do think
that is partially true. So it makes me give the idea that part of this momentum is that like
some of these Mac users have had their eye on Linux for a while, right? Like they've considered it, maybe it hasn't met
the standards that they don't think it can. Or what they did before
isn't what they do now. Like Mike was all in on iOS development. Right. And then he's like, well
this isn't paying the bills. He's doing more back end stuff. Yeah, and now then he's like, well wait a minute
if I'm just doing back end work, what am I doing? And I think that's true for
a lot of them as well. And I think distros are better than they used to be.
Yeah. And a lot of progress has been made on that kind of thing. And, you know, we've, I think
Linux has learned some of like what Mac did by having such an integrated stack
and the kind of like seamlessness and the integration and the consistency
and we've gotten better there too. Meanwhile, Wes, we'll just sit
back and say we told you something to watch. We'll welcome them with open arms and tell them which five or
six command line apps they should probably bother learning. They probably already know half of them from the Mac anyways.
So they probably only have to learn like another three or four more. Yep. They probably are already set.
Alright, well we're going to get out of here. I don't know if this has ended up being a short show or not because
it kind of felt like, I guess it was just a regular size show. But we're going to get out
of here because the elections are coming up and then I am jumping on the road
and heading down to California. Getting out of town. Don't forget about that meetup at
meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting and do come back next week and
hang out with Noah, Wes, and the gang. Yeah, be here. Yeah, Noah will be in studio.
What a treat. So you guys can hang out and, you know, cut
rugs or whatever you got. Who knows? I don't know. You should tune in Chris. Be here live.
Yeah, maybe. I wonder what they'll be up to. Of course if I tune in and I don't
like it, then what do I do? Jump in the moment room and yell at you guys? No, I'm kidding.
We'll cut you off. Don't worry. Oh, that guy. Get him out of here. Kick him out.
Alright everybody, thanks for joining us. We'll see you back here next Tuesday.
Music.
Oh, there we go.
All right, JBtitles.com.
JBtitles.com everybody.
Get over that.
So what distro are you still running there on that laptop, Wes?
This would be Arch Linux.
It is.
Is it Apricity, though?
That's what I was wondering.
Nope, just Arch.
Oh, you reloaded to...
Really?
No more?
What are you doing there on the...
Really?
Pretty minimal right now, like very few plugins.
Have you had a chance to see the Linux action show from Sunday?
Noah had some really weird performance issues on his Arch box.
Yeah, that did seem weird.
I was excited that he switched, though.
Yeah, a lot of people think he's crazy for doing it.
What's the hardware he's running?
I don't know exactly.
Yeah, that performance stuff seemed...
I saw that.
It was a little weird.
Yeah, it seemed really weird.
Like the launch times were...
Like even for a fresh install, and he's doing all SSDs, I think.
Yeah, Chris, I actually saw that show, and I saw the lag he was getting.
I was like, what the heck is this?
Yeah, that was the weirdest thing.
And to me, it looked like network, because it affects both Chrome and Firefox.
I don't know what kind of Wi-Fi he's gotten in, but I got to tell you, it looked pretty
laggy.
I'll tell you, I'm on Time Warner with the 300 meg internet, and I was getting 350 today.
Should we have like a nano title?
We should probably have a nano title, right?
Maybe, yeah.
It was pretty...
I like that idea.
I like it until Popeye and Wimpy said anything, and it was really Wimpy that pushed it.
No, everybody else is like quiet about it.
I'm all up here admitting my nano sin, and everybody's like, I run nano, but I'm not
saying nothing.
Yeah, we should have stuck up a bit back there.
At my last job, not the job I have now, but my last job, when we were doing stuff, occasionally
you have to gather around someone's computer, when everyone used to gather around my computer
and I would edit something, I could actually hear them say, freak, as I typed in nano.
Yeah, nano shame's been around forever.
I mean, it started as a bit of a joke, actually.
And I think it was Pico we were using back in the day that started as the joke, not nano.
Well, I, so originally, I was, well, I was using Pico on Unix systems, and then on...
On Linux, I would load Pico too, though.
I wouldn't load nano.
Yeah, in the early days, Pico, and then a little bit later on, it was, nano was called
TIP, this isn't Pico, originally, and then it changed to nano, because nano is a thousand
times larger than Pico.
I feel like it was like Gentoo or something that made me switch from Pico to nano, but
I don't remember.
I feel like there was...
I was going through that transition of, you know, learning nano, not TIP, you know, not
Pico.
But yeah, yeah, it was all just because the only email I had available to was Pine, and
I just learned how to get around using Pico.
So as soon as I started exploring the system, I edited everything with Pico, and that's
just stuck with me for however many years it is.
Nano users unite, and nano aggressions are not bad.
Nano users come out of the closet funny, but it's too long, I think.
And nano the lesser Emacs is kind of slammy.
I was seeing a lot of lines of nano FTW, but that was, I don't know.
Not so nano now.
I kind of like that one.
I wonder how the drone thing worked out.
See now someone needs to implement nano, like there's the evil mode for Emacs, maybe there
should be a nano mode for Emacs.
Yeah, yeah.
Actually, I would like pirate mode.
Did you ever see, you have to be kind of old, but did you ever install Red Hat when you
could install it in, oh, I forget what they call it, but it was basically, it was Red
Neck mode.
It was when Red Hat was testing out multilingual support.
And so they were testing Red Neck mode, and they actually shipped a version, or it was
a beta, where you could, I think it was like in the 5 series or something, where you could
install Red Hat Linux in Red Neck mode.
Actually existed.
It was amazing.