Shop dot gnome dot org. I know should I say gnome or gnome?
I you know, I was wondering that when you're referring to a web URL. Do you say?
Do you which one do you say?
Gnome or gun? Oh, I would say gnu but it's just me who cares. They have a merch store and that's all that matters
Hello friends and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hi, Wes. Wow
Did you put those fancy boots on for me? Of course I did
I wanted to welcome you back from your grand adventure. Thank you
It is really great to be back and we have a great show so much to catch up on some more
Fun stuff coming up in the next episode. So stay tuned for more fun stuff coming up in the next episode
Adventure. Thank you. It is really great to be back and we have a great show so much to catch up on some
Solid feedback and some great picks this week. It's a real classic and before we get any further
I want to say hello to drew and cheese. Hello, gentlemen. Thanks for being here. Well, hello there. Hello
Hey, you both are also quite dressed up cheese. I don't think I've ever seen you in a suit before and the bowtie
I know dude, it's weird. Yeah, I actually think the bowtie is working. I think it's working drew in a tie though
That's gonna take some getting used to but you're supposed to put it around your neck
Not your forehead drew also before we go
I have to say a huge hello a hearty time appropriate greetings to our mumble room. Hello virtual lug. Hello
Tuesday happy Linux Tuesday to y'all and
It's true. I'm I'm back
Back in the Pacific Northwest. It's really nice to be back in the studio. It was about 5,000 miles
almost 50 days of traveling
Tricky keeping everyone healthy and safe during all of that while also visiting family and working and of course
Trying to also make it a memorable experience for the kids and do the shows
this is a lot, but it was maybe one of the
greatest road trips of our family's lifetime, so I really enjoyed it and
awesomely while I was out and about
Angela managed to get the roof replaced on the studio
So we got some really really important work done for the studio that we've been needing to do for a long time
Taken care of while I was out for so long
So that's pretty great big old thanks to and for pulling that off because I never would have got it done
No, or you would have scheduled it for the same day. We were doing a Linux unplugged
So there would have been roofing noises in the recording
Yeah, that was really the strategy of it
But now that I'm back, I don't know. I guess I was I was so stupid
I thought I would I don't know
I would spend 50 days on the road and I would be in such different conditions that when I got back I wouldn't have
RSI, but within a couple of hours of sitting back at my desk. I
was having
Significant bad RSI again. I mean seriously from my fingertips into my wrists into my elbows all the way up to my shoulders. There's
intense pain and I I have trouble now holding stuff
so I need some RSI tips from the audience because I was trying to pretend like this was gonna go away if I just
changed things up for a bit and
it's like even now I haven't really done I've tried not to be at my desk a ton this morning and
My hands are stiff and sore
Exercises anything people could give because you know
This is starting to freak me out because I'm worried
I'm not gonna be able to use the computer for more than an hour at a time without hurting myself
so I mean I've had issues and I know that
Previously, I was really bad about putting my elbow on my desk and then like resting my chin on my elbow
Yeah, I do that on my armchair. That's really bad
but you know one one suggestion I would say is get yourself a motorized desk where you can stand and then
Alternate between sitting and standing. I do that about every hour hour and a half
You know sit down for an hour and a half stand up for an hour and a half and that seems to help out a lot
you cannot buy any personal fitness stuff on Amazon really right now because of the pandemic, but
you can pick up a
It's like an elastic band set that you just throw over the door
And then that way you can do like a couple of you know, like different kind of strokes
Using these bands and it'll help out a lot, too
It'll strengthen all the muscles that are kind of in the front of your chest and down your arms and your biceps and help out
a little bit so that's helped me out a lot, but you know ultimately I did have to have a surgery
Related to my neck and I don't know if it's connected to that
We're not years of being at a computer desk
But it certainly could be Neil some of us Linux users are just aging a bit
Think it's gonna be something that happens to a lot of us. Is this something you've struggled with?
I've dealt with this quite a lot. It got much worse once I started working from home
because my setup at home is not optimized for
Continuously doing the same kinds of things I do at work
It's actually more optimized for me to just sit and play games, right? Yeah chill
My desk is actually a little too tall. So typing is like quite painful
so a couple of things that I wound up doing the first was I
I did some awful work to slightly lower my desk a little bit so that the height wasn't
exactly at eye level for me for the because my my I have no stands or
Auxiliary whatever's but like getting my keyboard to be lower so that I don't always have to like prop up
My arms to type helped
Also getting a very soft wrist rest across the whole keyboard
So that whenever I'm typing it can rest and not feel like I'm digging into my wrists
Having an ergonomic keyboard making sure you have a good wrist rest
Actually making that making it so that you don't have to prop up your arms to like type on your keyboard
It also makes it so that you have less
You're less likely to like dig into and put pressure across everything at least in my experience that has made it better again
Not medical professional, please go seek a doctor but so that's helped for me
It's kind of fascinating. It just makes me think about when I was a youngster taking piano lessons
And you know you got to learn the proper form and despite many of us being professionals or just hobbyists
Either way spending all of our time sitting at the computer
We don't think that we need to invest in that and you know get the forms, right?
If we're gonna be doing it all the time. I wish I had taken it seriously sooner
because it's gotten to the point where I
Was out doing some yard work in the junkyard just because while I was gone it turned into a jungle
And even 15 minutes of holding the whacker thingy
My elbow was was done for the night
It was really it just stinks like so I got to get ahead of it or or at least I I mean
Maybe I'm not ahead of anymore, but I got to do something about it
anyways, I
just wanted to put it out there because I think a lot of us who are into Linux are very intense about the amount of
time we spend at the keyboard and I
do want to try to get the word out there because I
I think one of these it's one of these things if you don't take care of it before it starts once it starts you're at a
Basically a stage of mitigating and managing it from that point forward instead of preventing or curing it. Maybe I'm wrong
That seems to be what I'm discovering moving on though because we have some really good news
And that's jellyfin has a brand new release that looks pretty great in general
But one thing that Wes and I both noticed is it introduces a new feature called sync play
sync play allows you to create a room that other users can join in order to share
Essentially a common viewing experience and there seems to be no limit on the number of users in a room
You're all free to join its jellyfin
so there wasn't there's a login but you can share that same user account or you could be the same user on multiple devices and
We had a chance to try it out this morning. Yeah, we did
I mean, this is something that both you and I have been looking for it. Now. There's various solutions for there's a there's a plugin system
For VLC there's stuff for Netflix. There's stuff for YouTube, but none of them really kind of hit the sweet spot
I think jellyfin sync play is getting close because you and I were able to watch
Co watch an episode of Picard this morning. I guess I should maybe step back if you're not familiar with jellyfin
It's a media management
System for your videos it indexes them it goes out and gets the metadata a lot like Plex one thing
I like is it's you know, it's it's just a little more lightweight Plex is amazing
Don't get me wrong, but you know, it's it's tied into the company. It's tied into the web servers
Jellyfin was forked off MB and you know, you just start up the doctor container get it going
You can make a guest account. You can make local user account
so it's really easy to share with people even if they're not totally bought into the whole
Ecosystem and now the supports getting way better. It works with the Chromecast
I don't think it has integration with many of the clients yet
But hopefully that will that will come down the road and really a huge
Thank you both from from me from Chris and I think from the jellyfin community to first-time contributor
Andre Hanka, who's a computer science student over at a university in Italy
He submitted pull requests for both the server changes and the web client changes that laid the foundations for all of this
And I think it's a really cool open source success story because they've actually been like a feature request for something like this feature
Since all the way back till like 2018 and it just took someone stepping up
Doing the work putting it in and then the project was you know
Happy to include it and actually shipped it out where we can all go test it and abuse it
Yeah
And the timing is pretty good right because this is a time when people maybe would get together and watch something that are now
Spending time apart, but there's still
options like this to do some kind of remote viewing party and
The great thing is is there wasn't something that was free software and readily available and didn't require cloud services
Until this came along so I'm really glad the jellyfin project proceeded
With implementing this because I know there was some people in the community thought oh, maybe this isn't something we should really do
We don't think we can get it right, but I'm here to tell you it works pretty well
Wes and I were pretty quick to get it set up and going we both had control over the player
We could skip ahead and skip back play pause and it worked really well
It seems like one of the little tricks they do is when you skip ahead
They pause the playback for everyone which probably gives the players time to sync up and then when you hit play by then
They've already kind of figured out their positioning and it picks right back up
When you consider how far apart folks might be the various latencies introduced between locations and how close you are to the actual server
It's pretty impressive
There were a few little details that you kind of have to get used to and I did find in my own testing that you know
If someone's watching something you join in the sink will be a little a little rougher
But once you've paused and then resumed playback, it was really tight
Yeah, and we immediately just started chatting in a separate text chat about the show. We were watching there's no chat aspect to it
So you provide that separately and I like that?
I don't want them to try to integrate some sort of web RTC voice chat into this thing
Just focus on the video playback and we'll use the existing communications channel
We already had to set the whole thing up in the first place
There's also just traditional improvements. They're working on a more modern web client
It's it's had a lot of technical debt. It's really kind of just coming from a fork of MB and then implementing it themselves
There's just old technologies in there at this point
so some of those until recently prevented them from being able to use modern JavaScript tooling which
They have taken a whacking to thanks to a contributor who worked on improving the way they build the web client
They can now get to some of this also Wes
It looks like some of this
greatly simplifies the support for some of their legacy clients and the reason why that's sort of notable is that means they could
Extend support back to web OS and Tizen versions of the client
And I just love that because if you've got devices like that laying around and they have the means to make it work
I think it's pretty great to see them put the effort into it
Yeah, you know once you've got some of this additional tooling available
That means you can target older versions of JavaScript, you know other ancient clients that they still have the hardware to do it
They just don't support the latest standards
But with a tooling cleanup now that can be a lot better and actually, you know
This is a pretty big change. Once it's complete. It should make the web client a lot simpler
I already think the web clients I mean pretty decent although you can tell there's some rough edges
Sounds like eventually jellyfin wants to migrate over to view one of the hot new JavaScript frameworks and really just you know
Do a good summer cleaning of all this code that they've inherited lots of good stuff
Lots of old stuff
But if you want it to be shiny and fast and new
You got to make sure you tackle that technical debt and it's really nice to see the project trying to take that on
It still feels like there's more to be done in that area
significant work to be done in that area, but
They're really making it attractive and if you've thought about Plex
But you're not comfortable with it for whatever reason take a look at jellyfin. We'll have a link in the show notes
Well, let's change gears and talk about Proxmox. Proxmox is an enterprise class
Virtualization system based on Linux. I used to use it in the studio
Now we run on arch and just put it all in containers
But I really like Proxmox and it's developed nicely over the years and this last week
They announced the Proxmox backup server. This will be an enterprise grade
Backup server for your virtual machines containers and the physical hosts
It is specifically optimized for the Proxmox virtual environment platform and allows you to back up and replicate
the data from that platform securely and it has easy management and command-line tools got a web user interface as well and
It's licensed under the GNU a GPL version 3. Hey, those are all good things
Other good things about the Proxmox backup setup and especially on the server side is that it supports incremental backups
deduplication compression and authenticated encryption
Plus Chris you'll love uses rust as the implementation language
So that there's good performance and low resource usage and maybe a high quality code base time will tell on that one
It also has strong encryption on the client side. Hey, that's where you want it
So you can back up to something you might not fully trust what I love about rust is
It's used to sell a tool as production grade just because you name drop rust. Have you noticed that? Yeah
I don't know that that's really fair because any new code base is likely to have bugs
Even if you have an amazing compiler like you do with rust
Yeah
But then again if you were to come to me and say hey Chris if you want us to build some really nice high-performance
Low-level enterprise grade tools. What language do we write it in? I'd probably say rust and here I thought you like to see plus-plus
All right, well that concludes the rust watch for this episode, you know, I'm not a huge Proxmox user
But I do know a lot of folks who found it useful
You know, maybe you don't like the license
Maybe you just don't like the tooling but it gives access to a lot of the you know
Ecosystem that we talked about here on Linux unplugged and I just like seeing in general
Making backups easier for folks, right?
If you're gonna have to go do it yourself or learn a whole bunch while that might be valuable
It might also mean delaying taking those backups. So if you can just integrate with you know with these new features, that's great
Yeah, I wish we had a reason to use it here
Like if that arch box would screw up a whole bunch
I'd say we should Proxmox it up if I wasn't all piled up in the RV and with x86
I'd probably use Proxmox underneath whatever I ran
But I just haven't had that use case for it yet
And the reason why it kind of bothers me is I want to talk about it more on the show
Because it's really good and we just don't talk about it enough, but I just haven't quite
Found that use yet before we kind of changed everything up and went on a free NAS tear for a while and all that
We used to use Proxmox to do a lot of what we now do in
containers
But that just made sense to use containers for the types applications we're doing if you have a good use case out there
Let us know linuxonplug.com
slash contact
Alright now for the Microsoft watch
Those crazy cats at Microsoft have released Procmon. No, no, no not that old sis internals one
Procmon for Linux. It's a process monitor tool and it's in preview now
They write process monitor is a Linux reimagining of a classic Procmon tool from sysinternals suite of tools
That were for Windows Procmon provides a convenient and efficient way for Linux developers to trace the syscall activity on the system
And I have to say I was shocked to find
It is not in the AUR at least when I checked yesterday. Wait, what how is that possible?
I I don't know. I don't know not enough ARCH users over at Microsoft. I guess I mean they do have a PPA
Yes, they do. They do. So what do we think about this story?
Is it still a big deal when Microsoft is releasing some of these classic tools as open source on Linux?
It feels to me like kind of routine at this point. I think that means things have really shifted
You know, this would have been huge massive news what two years ago, but just feels like it's been a long time
But just feels like a regular week with some new stuff from Microsoft. So that's kind of how I feel about it
Neil what about you?
What about seeing some of these classic Windows tools that were honestly some of the gems of Windows coming from Microsoft to Linux?
I started on as a Windows developer and I did do
Windows systems administration as well
So like these tools were things that I relied on when I did a lot more Windows stuff when I was younger
It's nice for me to see that these are coming to Linux. I personally relied a lot on Procmon when I did Windows stuff
so when I when I saw it was released, I tried to grab it and build it and
Package it up for Fedora, but alas it actually doesn't build. There's a couple of things wrong with it
They have bundled copies of libraries that don't compile and it tries to fetch stuff from the Internet
Which is a no-go for shipping it in any Linux distribution, right?
I know that a lot of people think this is kind of the good way to do things now
But like it feels real bad
especially from a company like Microsoft who should at this point know the value of reproducibility and stuff like that
And this also kind of showed a little bit of like they don't really get how to make open source software that people can
easily consume because they
They made it so that it's it's just like a bunch of silly putty thrown over the wall
Yeah, I think it's pretty early days. You know, if you look at the commit
It does seem like it's something developed maybe internally not introduced into any sort of build system and just yeah now
It's out there and Neil is that criticism fair?
Holy like if you balance expectations with how large corporations work
Maybe this is the best that's going to get for jumping code over the wall because think about it from this standpoint
this is probably after a long series of discussions about
This strategy this tool how this developer will spend their time and there's even like legal analysis, right?
Like a complete version of the project to an extent that has to probably be reviewed by several parties before they can release it
Sure. Sure. No that that's all good
Well and good, but but Microsoft is not new to this whole trying to release open source software thing
Microsoft today is not a company that I would consider
completely unaware of how you do free software or open source software or whatever term you'd like and
They continue to struggle with this in frustrating ways
with dotnet with MS build and
Monodevelop like they're not new to this it this is something that I expect from somebody who's really new to this and has no
Experts or no people from the community. Yeah
I think it's a fair criticism on how the code is released and that they've had time to adapt
So I follow you there. Let's talk about something that I think those of us on this show
We're pretty pleased to see although we'll wait to see how it ultimately plays out, but it's official
It's been approved for fedora 33 to switch the desktop variants default file system to butter
Fs the fedora engineering and steering committee formally signed off on this which means we're going from extended for to butter fs
Oh my god. Yes
But having it formally approved it all the T's are crossed and all the eyes were dotted
We're now, you know, we're just proceeding forward and getting everything working
Crossing my fingers. We'll actually have it in G in beta and GA. I'm pretty confident
It'll be at least in be a bit in beta. I
have no reason to believe that it won't make it to GA so I am I'm really happy about this and
Man years and years of effort are finally paying off. Well, it is very exciting and congratulations, and I
Thought it was sort of driven home recently because we just got an email from Steven or Stefan
I'm sorry Stefan if I'm getting it wrong
He was upgrading from open Sousa 42.1 to 15.2
And he said butter fs and snapshotting were a total lifesaver
He writes I've never had to start over on my main machine
Anytime I hosed the system by making a big error or an upgrade went awry
I just reboot into an older snapshot and use snapper to roll back once I'm in a working system
Of course the implementations would eventually be different in fedora once it got to that point
But just think about how critical a snapshot and rollback option is for a distribution that is
Updated as frequently as fedora and not just major releases which are frequent
but significant package updates including new versions of the kernel come down while you're running a current release of fedora and
While it generally works really well and dnf is pretty great at catching stuff
There's nothing like that belt and suspenders where you also have the reliability of those snapshots
And I think it makes the risk of upgrading to the next release of fedora even less now
So i'm excited to see where this goes. Yeah, um right now. We're not doing the automatic snapshotting stuff. That's down the road
That's down the road. I'm trying to be methodical about how we how we move forward and integrate these things
Well, it's kind of like I said recently you have to get the file system shipping before you can start building the tools based on
It exactly and like we can take advantage of the lessons learned from open susa
From other companies who have been rolling it out into production on nas devices
In in server fleets and stuff like that and we can hopefully make better decisions and and and optimize for our use case a lot better
With all of this, you know knowledge and experience and that's what i'm hoping to go towards like
Some of the choices that are a little bit weird from my perspective on open susa for their layout
We're probably not going to do those on fedora because we don't need to
Uh, and we're making already some enhancements are coming down the pipeline
There are some patches written for libvert to better handle the creation of virtual machines on butterfs making them no cow
For the disk images is disk image files. So that'll happen automatically
So that means that you won't be impaired by butterfs just out of the gate
Um in that sense and there's other things that we're working on across the board
Things for like improving performance when dealing with sqlite postgres mysql all the things
So like we're we're looking at it. We're actively doing these things
Um, i'm i'm confident. It's going to be a great experience
Um by the time fedora 33 rolls out it won't be like super fancy
The idea is that you won't notice anything, but it'll be there making things better
That's what i'm so excited about is that you know, suddenly without the user having to do anything
You've got all of these additional things like copy and write snapshots
File system compression optimizations for ssds built-in raid
You might not need any or all of these
But they're all at your fingertips now and you don't have to know about it before you go install your linux system
You can opt into it later. Yeah, I look forward to trying it in fedora 33 to tell you the truth
I think it's going to make it an exciting release
Just because of this even though nothing really fancy is going to happen and it's pretty much transparent to the user
I'm still looking forward to it and wes while we're shucking and jiving about fedora
One of the things we liked about the previous release was they shipped a user space out of memory killer
Which in our testing actually made a significant difference if you're on a linux box with some memory pressure
and now it seems
That this is going to be built into
System d yes, you guessed it because of course it will now I believe this is actually uh, some of the
Original code that was developed by facebook, right? Yes system d o m d is the out of memory demon developed by facebook
And now system d developers
They're aiming for this to be better linux handling of out of memory or just low memory situations
And while facebook originally wrote this code for their servers
And it's continued to be refined and adapted so that now it works pretty well on desktops, too
Now neil do we notice this likely mean that fedora will stop using their version and switch to this
I've been keeping a close eye on this as I told you when we were putting early oom into fedora
Last release cycle. We were actually also tracking this this this came up as part of it
Things are actually moving faster than I expected
Like I originally expected that uh system d oom d would not land for another eight months
And it looks like it might land in a few weeks
So this means that we're probably going to start looking at it in fedora 34. That makes sense
Wes one of the things that's kind of neat about having it down there at the system d level is it's also c group aware
Yeah system d o m d pulls system d for out of memory enabled c groups to monitor them and then kill based on memory pressure
Which is that that new measure that facebook helped add to the kernel or swap usage?
So I think it'll be interesting to see you know
If this solution that is already in place or this new system d based solution
I wonder if that might find different use cases that work a little bit better, especially, you know
It does say this works well for the desktop
But in the facebook world, you know
They could opt into all this stuff make sure that all their utilities on the server side were playing nicely with c groups
It may vary a little bit on desktop environments, uh, how well all this stuff works?
Why don't we stop now and do a little housekeeping just to change it up a bit
Because that was a lot of information to go through i'm out of memory
Yeah, and we're gonna kill it right now. Uh, I don't want to get the word out about guatic 2020
It starts july 22nd, which is tomorrow as we record this and goes to the 28th of 2020
The guatic is the gnome community's largest conference and it's online this year. So I would imagine
This could be the first guatic I ever attended if I had given it any thought and maybe I still can
Uh, i'll look into that and you can too with the link in the show notes
Also, if you want to join us live you'll find out when did you know that calendar jupitabroadcasting.com
Slash calendar link for that's in the notes as well and we do it over jblive.tv
Every sunday the lup lug the folks in the mumble room get together and hang out at noon pacific
That's the same bat time. We do this show. It's just on a bat sunday
We hung out last sunday. I talked about how I reflashed the computer in my rv for more performance and uh,
It made for some good stories
Uh lots of good stuff. We had some new folks show up. Of course as always we talk a little butter fs
so the lup lug is
It's often a multi-hour event, but you can show up for as little or as much as you like
Every sunday at noon pacific. It's also on the calendar if you just want to check that
so we'd love to see you there and
I've made it easier than ever
To get the mumble server info. You just go to linux unplug.com slash mumble
And it's all there the quick stuff
Or there's a link at the top of the page and the extended guide is still available at the jupiter colony page
If you want the full thing if you're brand new to mumble and you you want a guide on how to set up all the audio
Interface stuff the full guide is still available. But if you just need the quick server info linux unplug dot com
slash mumble
There we go see that doesn't that feel better west so much cleaner in here
And did you put an air freshener in the studio? Yeah, that's just levi. I gave him a shower. Yeah, he's much better now
So let's talk about element. This is something we've been watching really closely the riot chat
Program and the company actually has been renamed to element, which is a matrix chat
Client element, which I don't know if that's any easier to google than vector. I guess we'll see
It's the new flagship secure collaboration app for the decentralized matrix communication network
Element lets you own your end-to-end encrypted chat server. Well still connecting to everyone else in the wider matrix network
Yeah, that's right. That's the big federation play. We did know this name change was in the works
They explained it
Um, even a few weeks ago mostly in a in a blog post talking about some of the issues they had with
Gigantic game companies who blocked them from being able to trademark the name
Which then had a knock-on effect of them being unable to go after abusive forks in the google play store
And it just essentially came down to also being associated with
Violence rather than a more constructive form of chaos that they're into
As they write on their blog, and I think that's nice because the name doesn't really matter in the end
I got used to riot
I'll get used to element and I think it's great because they've also renamed the company now to just sort of keep it simple
Right. It's a little more consistent and you're right. We just got to we got to get used to these things
You had to put a label and naming is hard. Don't we all know it?
It's the worst part about coming up with a new podcast is coming up with the name. It's the worst
Uh, they said they wanted to future proof it as well. So this is their rationale for it
They said as matrix.org announced last month p2p matrix is in heavy development
And we see a world where element will literally be an element of matrix running your own home server within the app
So you can communicate if you don't have a server or even internet that actually is pretty cool
That is really cool. And that's one of the things, you know, the whole matrix ecosystem is filled with fascinating ideas
And a lot of potential the math names. I kind of love too. Hmm, and they're not just doing name changes west
They're rolling out pretty big improvements on their mobile apps and a massive refresh
To their web ui, which looks really good
I am seriously eyeballing matrix right now as the chat platform for jupiter broadcasting
The telegram group is still going jupiter broadcasting.com slash telegram. We haven't plugged it a lot recently because i've kind of just been
Watching how the chat ecosystem is unfolding because for self-hosted and the unfilter show
Discord has been very successful. So that gave me pause. I didn't want to just write discord off
But at the same time when I look at what would be a proper fit with this show
When I look at what would be a proper fit with this show, I think something like matrix which interconnects to all the different platforms
Which is the kind of thing our audience can geek out on but also it's free and open source
and
It's self-hostable
All these things sort of stack my general bias towards matrix as a chat platform that would potentially replace irc and telegram
And we would just use this for all of our primary text-based communication with the community
But at the same time
there's that network effect to consider so I have to look at things very seriously like irc telegram and discord and so i've been
Keeping an eye on matrix for a while and sort of mentally doing the math on how it would play into a wider ecosystem for us
And with element now making these improvements to the web ui and the mobile clients you have the general connected nature of matrix
And this new p2p stuff they're working on I find that to be a really compelling package all in we need it to be easy
Frankly, you know, it's got to be it's got to be worth the install
So the client can't be gross you got to be easy to connect with us
When you live in a world of so many solutions, that's how you differentiate. So elements of thing now no longer will be called riot
Now I don't really have much to say about this last one. It's just a little weird
There's a job posting over at microsoft's
jobs page
about a program manager
for a cloud pc project
That would be a desktop delivered
From azure and managed by microsoft at a flat per user price
They call it the microsoft cloud pc
A new offering that would be built on top of the windows virtual desktop to deliver desktop as a service
It would really be targeted to business customers that are looking for a modern quick workstation experience that have high connectivity
And I have to tell you
I could see this being appealing because I know of companies that sell versions of this based on aws right now
and you go into the businesses and
They don't have any on-premises services other than a switch a router and a wi-fi access point. There's no file server
There's no directory server
It's just a flat network that provides high-speed internet access
And I think you can hear that in the first sentence of that description that you read there that
This is the azure and microsoft managed solution that this already exists
And yeah, clearly it's interesting because as anyone who's administered windows pcs knows
It's kind of a pain and if you can just let microsoft handle it if you already have to be an internet connected company anyway
From all the other sas products that you buy that makes your company run in 2020
Yeah, all right. Why not use the desktop and maybe maybe
Microsoft can do this better than others since they control all the pieces
What's funny is I know that linux has all of the pieces to do this because I rocked linux terminal servers way back in the day
And we have all kinds of means to accomplish this now and there are companies out there working on it. But
Where microsoft is going to have this this sort of?
home turf advantage
Is they're going to sort of package it all up with microsoft's office 365 offering
which it's it's sort of like this obvious solution you have
All your data in the ecosystem of office 365 word excel teams
One drive is your storage or teams. It's weird and
You just need essentially a chrome pc, but instead of getting that google stuff
That's all connected to the google ecosystem. You get microsoft's version of it
You get microsoft's version of it and this one's a step further
And it's maybe even a more pure version of that chrome experience where it's a complete remote cloud pc
Managed by microsoft as part of your office 365 subscription. You know what? I want to know is wsl going to work on cloud pc
Brent i'm sure you'd get one of these wouldn't you? Well, it means maybe I'd I'd need less fancy hardware all the time
But uh, no, I'm sorry. I'm not in my hand is not raised
I would like to see a vendor come along and offer this up with mate as the desktop experience
Libre office as the office solution connected to some sort of central cloud storage
So that way you can have multiple users from a workspace use the same storage
maybe create some sort of user id system for them, I mean there's
Small versions of this have been implemented or there's amazon's implementation of these but there's not a complete
Package of you need office and a computer and you just need these storage services for your company
And here's another alternative for you. That's not google or microsoft the business ready
All wrapped up ready to go stuff
Yeah
And all of the pieces are there and it's something that linux could be particularly good at because I don't know which
System you'd want to use a remote desktop system or a linux terminal services setup
but the cool thing about a linux terminal services setup
is a lot of those programs run locally in memory and
They will use your local gpu if you have one which means you can make thin clients that have gpu acceleration
But additionally if libre office is loaded in your local ram
Your internet can blip or your latency can be bad and you're completely unaffected on a linux thin client setup
Now if you're doing something like xrdp or another type of remote desktop protocol that wouldn't be the case
So it just depends on the implementation, but there's so much opportunity here
it makes me wish I had the time to like start a business because
there is a whole area of small business in the states that is somewhere between five to 25 people and
These annual subscriptions just stack up and they're a little allergic to them
And they just need somebody to show them a solution that works for them and give them an implementation. That's not some sort of
Moral choice they're not choosing microsoft because of some moral reason it's just they don't have any other options presented to them
Right, they have the most hand holding that way and that's what they need
But kudos to microsoft. I think it's probably going to be a successful product if they launch it
They've tried stuff like this in the past, but I think you know now is the time
I wonder if it's you know, we've kind of talked about other microsoft assets like office 365
You know things you used to have to have a windows desktop to use or maybe a complicated wine setup that
Since they've migrated to the cloud into an online offering while we might not love having to use them from the free software world
It's good for people trying to use a linux desktop and still get work done
And I mean this almost seems like it's it's the ultimate in that it's making windows the same thing
I I somewhat recently had to go for an unfortunate reason go spin up a windows vm
And I did it on azure because I didn't want to clutter up any of my local systems
And it was kind of a painful process with all of the pains of using windows
If I could just have a cloud pc pop it up get my windows specific stuff done and then go back to my pure linux world
Yeah, all right. I'll I'll pay microsoft a couple bucks for that. So do you rdp into a azure windows vm?
How does that work? They've got like a web um a way to view it on the web, too
Of course, but yeah, I just rdp'd up uh up in there got my work done
And uh got the heck out of there
But it took forever and of course, you know
I was doing updates and had to spin all the way up and getting it actually installed and booted up took
Much longer than an equivalent linux vm. I was honestly surprised by how painful it was, huh?
That's a that's an interesting experience. Wes. Thanks for sharing that with the class
All right
So if anybody out there knows of a service like this for linux where you could go set up an account
It'll spin you up a virtual desktop and then you can remote desktop into it
Let me know linux unplug.com slash contact or chris lass on twitter because i'll give that a try and I want to give it a review
Because that's a product that should exist for linux desktop as well
We can do it better. Maybe rdp is actually kind of legit, but we can use xrdp. So we could probably do it better
What do you say we do some picks before we get out of here because we got some good ones and we got some
Feedback too and we start with poly bar a fast and easy to use status bar
And I think a couple of you had some experience with this one. Yeah
Well, actually I just stumbled across it the other day and I was thinking to myself man. This would be
A great addition to something like open box or i3 and then after mentioning it to you guys
I believe drew didn't you try it on i3? Yeah, i've used it a number of times on i3
i'm not using it right now, even though i'm on i3 but
It is a really great and good looking bar
That's easy to get going and easy to add like custom blocks and stuff too and change
the way it looks and give it a nice color scheme and
All around it's just a little slicker and more fully featured than you know, the stuff that like comes stock with i3
The orange one's been using it for about a year. So give us the the why i've been using it for a year review
Originally when I started with i3 naturally I found a rust implementation of those bars and it's really nice
But the nice thing about poly bar is there's just tons and tons of extensions
And the fact that you can have it show spotify cpu you see volume time current window. Everything is just great and
Massively like beats like the windows taskbar and what you'd normally expect from a taskbar like that. Hmm
That's a pretty hardy plug. So check out poly bar. We'll have a link in there and then
We have a fun one for those of you who like your stats. It's called y-top and it's essentially go-top
Only this time it's in rust
And you thought we were done with the rust watch heck no
Yes
Another system monitor only this one is written in rust. It's it's familiar to those of you who have been enjoying batchtop
I think we mentioned that in episode
351 so it's been a little bit, but this is another one now. There's go-top out there as well
But this is y-top and yes, it's it's rust based, you know
I think our unofficial goal here on the mix unplugged is to just find every single possible top
Implementation out there and talk about them on the show and i'm interested in what each one chooses to show because yeah
Okay, you're all just going to go scrape the kernel for a whole bunch of information display it for the user
But how you display it that kind of counts and you know y-top. It's a decent contender
It's got a really nice cpu graph going
I also like the network usage graph that it displays because hey right now i'm chatting with you. I can monitor my connection
Yeah, and the hit on the system seems to be very minimal, which is always my thing
I don't want the monitoring tool to put abusive load
On the box, which is really actually kind of an issue on the raspberry pi you you have to be careful
Like on the raspberry pi 3, uh, you could run net data
But it basically will can start consuming the device, especially if you're running off the sd card
But something like this is so much so much lighter. And if you just need quick information over a terminal session
It's hard to a bash top might look a little better, but it's uh, I don't know. It's it's hard to beat this one
I like it a lot. So get a link to those in the notes and
Feel free to send yours along. Why don't we get to a little feedback west? Do you want to take this first one about?
Some next cloud follow-up and questions. Oh boy, eric, aka
Pedestrian had some feedback for us about our recent discussion around next cloud
Hello chris and wess. I really enjoyed the next cloud discussion
But I have a few questions and comments to share
One are you using redis? If not, it might go a long way towards addressing any concurrency issues
You're still seeing. Yes, we are using redis. Although I don't know that we've tuned it a whole bunch
We're using a docker compose stack setup from the next cloud project itself
So we haven't spent a ton of time going outside those bounds, but we are running a redis container. That's a good tip though
Number two using the s3 compatible storage background has been great for me
The interesting part is that any s3 compatible storage provider will work. I've been using redis for a long time
S3 compatible storage provider will work. I've been using a do droplet with wasabi as the back end and it's both cheaper
And more performant than spaces
That's also probably a good tip. You know, we went with spaces because well, we were already a do customer
We had access to it. We had account set up for you know, access to the team all that stuff
So it made sense to plug right in
But the whole beauty of using something that is s3 compatible is you have options there including s3 itself
Of course now i've not used wasabi, but I will say we've received a couple other items of feedback that are also recommending it
Yeah, like rick here writes in and he said in your recent episode when you talked about your expensive next cloud implementation
I found it totally unacceptable. I cringed when I heard the price
This is homework for you and the jb crew to do he says 10 terabytes of hot aka active storage on wasabi's service
Is fifty nine dollars a month combine that with the 15 a month droplet and it should be just about 80 a month
with tax
Overages if any would be much more affordable and manageable can next cloud integrate with wasabi. Hell. Yeah
Here's what I found to get you and the crew started
And he says it also allows you can pick a cdn in front of wasabi
He says I have an idea use the storage on a droplet for temp storage and then move it to wasabi instances as needed
You just figure out a storage strategy and create docs for the crew
Save your hard-earned money. I agree with that. We are going to fix it for the record
I'm not affiliated with wasabi or any storage company
I think this is something we'll have to look at because we're either going to have to stop using it
Or switch to something cheaper and if this math is right, I mean around 80 a month
It's still more expensive than dropbox
But not by much, especially if you consider how many users we have because dropbox
charges by the user
Right if you consider how many users we need our cost is probably around a hundred dollars a month for dropbox if you were to
Take the annual cost and spread it out. So 85 would be cheaper. It's still it's still a lot of money
It's still a lot of money
And I wonder if what we really need is something that's just a small tiny storage of in progress files
I think that's big a big part of this is we got to go we should go do some pruning and see
Go do some pruning and figure out like what do we need to have hot and what can be left in archival storage?
And then invest in
Storage at the studio in the physical box here that we can add to
But then it just sort of changes the backup scenario here in the studio. So I got to think about that
It's a can of worms, but we do appreciate uh, the feedback guys. It's given us something to think about
Now, uh west there was somebody wrote in asking for time stamps. You want to take that one?
Yeah, oh, yes. Okay. I guess this is a request for me then
as it writes in
Wanting time stamps. Here's a humble request that time stamps be included in the podcast description
So I can go right to the segments. I most want to hear. Thank you. Love the show great work
Okay. Hey, that's pretty reasonable. We do have them, you know available as chapter markers and we've got them on youtube
But that might not be everywhere
I guess that's something we could consider because I guess we could just extract it from the chapter information
And there's just put it in the description. Yeah, we can add it to the long form description. That shouldn't be too big a problem
That's something we'll think about uh
But this also is just a good chance to remind you that we do have chapter markers for almost all our shows all our shows
Yes, and um, you can jump right past any segment you like or you can jump to a topic
um using those and they should be in just about every mobile podcast player and uh, we'll we'll start
Um looking into embedding it in the show notes. There's a possibility too there because we already have the information
All right. Now we have one last feedback that I will read and it's a plug for a audience member's own project
But it's so dang cool
I wanted to talk about it
He said i've created an app just for linux that I think fellow space nerds like you would be interested in it's called
Astro ninja and it's written in python using mostly pi q5 and scrappy spiders
I love it. It has the full worldwide launch schedules industry news hubble images
Launch tallies and spacex live streams built in the project just reached its alpha release and i'm trying to invite like-minded individuals
To check it out and seeing how I really oh, geez now he's bragging now
He's talking nice about it
He loves the show and he sees he's been listening for years
And he said he first thought of thought of us and wanted to pass it along
So in the show notes will have a link to his email where he has links to a youtube video that shows it off
And we'll put a link to his github repo
Um, which you can go check out the project if you're a space nerd want to geek out on that stuff
It's astro ninja and it just hit alpha and it's up on github kind of cool
This looks pretty handy as a little dashboard and it's not another electron app
So you just need python and uh cubed installed and away you go. Yeah, most linux desktops are gonna have that
So thanks for sending that along tom and congratulations
On the release it does look like it's a pretty cool project astro ninja is a good name, too, right?
I love that. I love watching those spacex launches too, right? And you know, they use a bunch of linux
So clearly linux and astronomy
They're just made to be together
All right. Well that brings us to the end of this week's official program. Thanks so much for listening
We'd love to have you tune in live over jblive.tv
or if you can't
Thanks for listening on the download. We like that too. That's just fine
In fact, why not share this podcast with a linux loving friend?
That'd be great, too. You can find links to everything we talked about at linux unplugged dot com slash
363 63. Yeah. Thanks wess. I was gonna get there 363 linux unplugged dot com slash 363
And the show is at linux unplugged on twitter
Thanks so much for tuning into this week's episode of the unplugged program and we'll see you right back here
next tuesday
So
So by bitten you were
Chatting in the irc that there is a linux desktop service out there called ubi desktop
Yeah, so I stumbled upon it and it is kind of neat for uh 10 years a month you get a uh, single core
3.4 gigahertz 2 gigabytes ram
Uh 32 gigs of ssd storage and one terabytes a month of trap traffic at one gigabits a second
How do you know how much your desktop traffic's gonna that's that's a tricky one, but a terabyte you'd think would be enough. Yeah, and uh,
It is depending on if the rdp or uh, what kind of uh,
Uh vnc kind of service if that data gets counted, uh against it or not
Uh, but it is very easy and they have a free to try option
And if you scroll a bit more down, they have a discount coupon code and they have an extreme version at 43
90 a month you get four virtual cpus eight gigs of ram 128 gigabytes of ssd and five terabytes of traffic
That ssd is a little tight though
That's interesting. If you were a new business that was starting up. You didn't have any machines
Right and someone was going to sell you this service. Would they just run on thin clients? Yeah, exactly
I mean think about another way
Isn't it silly to buy 800 pcs with 125 monitor and a mouse and keyboard?
That you then go license software for then you have to have an it person manage it
How silly is that for an office of five people or 15 people or even 100 people?
And if you scroll down far enough, do you need a vdi try desktop as a service?
They even support those kind of things. Yeah, it's pretty wild. Um, so it's coming and obviously it doesn't mean it's going to replace
Traditional computers because there's so many reasons why you still need a traditional computer at a desk
But you got to figure if chromebooks have been pretty successful
There's probably a market for this kind of thing too. And i've heard from listeners in the past that
Use this as a daily driver as part of their work. It's some other vendors virtual desktop solution right now
But it's already out there to some degree and being widely used one challenge. I can't get around is the
Necessity for always connected internet. I run into this all the time even at home, you know, okay
I've got this stable connection and it just you know drops and so if i'm in the middle of something that is one of the
Biggest productivity killers ever. That's why I think it's so office focused, you know, you picture someone in a downtown office suite
Their building has fiber connection
Probably, you know the best case scenario
It's basically the opposite of wherever Brent is. Yeah, or me