I don't usually go around from the rooftop shouting, have you heard of GIMP?
Have you heard of GIMP?
But this guy, four days ago, a story goes up about this guy who sucked so bad at Photoshop,
he spent 10 years mastering Microsoft Paint to illustrate his book.
And you know, I got to say he did a pretty good job, Wes.
It looks like basically the quality of The Simpsons.
So he got a lot out of Microsoft Paint.
I mean, I'll give him that.
When was the last time you did something like that in Paint?
I would tell you it would be never.
I didn't even know you could do something like this in Paint.
I mean, you'd have to use wine, but still.
He says, I honed my craft working long overnights at a hospital reception desk.
I'm not sure how I feel about that.
Then I decided to write and self-publish an e-book about summer camp in the 1980s.
So it's pretty cool.
It's all illustrated in Paint.
Look at that.
Yeah.
But you got to stop and go, in 10 years, you never heard of GIMP?
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's been running the benchmarks
all day long.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
We have a great show today.
You're already fired up and ready to go, too.
You've been rehearsing.
You've been practicing on that TechSnap program, so I know it's going to be good.
Oh, yeah.
As we go on the air, while I was at lunch, we have some really interesting news out of
Canonical about what they might be doing with Ubuntu.
We'll see.
Ubuntu has two posts.
We'll talk a little bit about the dues, and then we'll talk a little bit about the survey,
which may give us more hints, too.
I'm curious already.
Yeah.
I do have a little bit of a crisis of faith this week.
Been looking at some of the news coming out of Microsoft's build.
Yes, I said Microsoft's build conference.
What?
And they're bringing Bash to Windows Server.
Server set.
Yeah.
Just getting serious.
I know.
They're going to have SSH on Windows Server in legit ways.
So we're going to be talking about that, what that could mean for Linux.
We're going to help you with your shell stuff.
Got some shell problems?
Well, now that it's on Windows, I mean, now it's serious business.
That is literally why I was like, well, now people are going to have a bunch of noobs
trying it out.
It was literally my thoughts.
Some community stuff to get into, and then one of our favorite open source projects on
the show.
We're just going to give you a little recap on what's been going on.
And speaking of open source projects, our own community has been working on an amazing
soundboard project.
I can't wait to show you some of the things they've done.
They've built something that's truly, truly feature rich and competitive.
And then later on, towards the end of the show, but not quite, you know, it's not really
the end.
No, of course not.
In some sense, it's a whole new beginning.
We're going to talk about the Galago Pro.
What?
Yeah.
We're going to do a little review of System76's brand new Galago Pro, which is in Wes's hot
little hands right now.
Performing very nicely.
But that's just a tease.
That's me tapping it.
Yeah, that's real metal.
Have you fingered that logo?
Turn your hands over that logo right there.
You feel how good that is?
Yeah, man.
It's baked in.
So we'll be talking about that coming up in a little bit today.
A bunch of stuff.
Bunch of bunch of stuff.
It's good to be here.
I'm glad.
I feel like, Wes, I feel like I've just recently given delivery to a new baby.
Right.
That's a big moment for you.
I've been doing a lot of things.
So what have you been doing?
You been up to anything interesting?
All kinds of stuff.
Yeah.
But I don't know if it can compare with what you have just birthed to the world.
I don't want to take.
I don't want to take this.
I don't want to take away the spotlight, Wes, but pretty excited about Linux Action News
episode one.
Pretty excited.
You should be.
Linuxactionnews.com if you want to check it out.
Joe Ressington and me.
What's the elevator pitch here?
Think of it as this.
It's Joe and I who've been doing podcasting for a long time.
It's our take on the weekly happenings in Linux and open source.
And I started this show with Joe because I thought things are really changing in Linux.
There's a new reality that's in some ways extremely great for Linux and there's a few
other headwinds that are really concerning and so much stuff is developing.
It's really a great time to have a good discussion show.
And Joe has not only just a great take on the open source world and he's been following
it for a long time, but from his experience with Linux Luddites and now Late Night Linux,
all both of which are great shows, he's really developed a routine and a system down to collect
news and analyze news and really think about it really well.
So I knew like just from the podcasters I listened to, he'd be one of the best guys
to do the show.
I was like, well maybe Joe would want to do it.
And then it turned out, yeah, Joe did want to do it with me.
I was like, awesome.
That was like my first choice.
Totally.
And the thing was is when we announced the end of the Linux action show, the biggest
feedback we got is people really liked the news.
And they tuned in to find out what was going on each week with Linux and open source.
You were their evening news program.
And for some people it's like, well this is my living, this is kind of how I make my living
and it's helpful to just have another resource to stay up to date on stuff, to keep current.
And so it was kind of with sort of the lessons learned from Linux action show and that kind
of market in mind that we launched this show.
It's still early days.
The first few episodes are always kind of early days, kind of like rough.
It's not like it's rough because he and I have been doing it for so long that it's not
amateurs.
But at the same time it's like not what the final product is going to be.
You're still finding the right energy, how you want it to go.
And then of course there's all the cool stuff that we've been working on, like back end
technology to make it all possible and new hosting and all this kind of stuff.
It was a lot of work to get there and we're super excited because episode one is out.
I think it's been received pretty well.
I think so.
So I'd love to have you guys at least try it out and maybe consider it.
It's a little bit tighter of a show.
It's usually going to be about 30 minutes or so, so that means you've really got some
time to fit it into maybe an already busy podcast schedule or a commute.
It should be never like one of those shows that's going to monopolize your entire podcast
player for the week.
So what's the schedule going to be?
Mondays.
So hopefully it'll be out every Monday.
It's going to be a good day for the network.
News show out on Monday, four-year morning download.
You can listen to it whenever you want in the week, but if you want to start your Monday
with it or if you – so I figure we'll put it out there and whenever people want to listen
to it they'll listen.
I think that's great.
Yeah.
I'm excited.
If you want to just go to episode one it's linuxactionnews.com slash one.
Pretty simple.
Easy peasy.
I don't know if the WW is working or not.
We'll find out later.
I blame Dan Benjamin.
All right.
Well, so let's talk about actual news.
This was posted over at OMG Ubuntu just one hour ago, as literally one hour ago as we're
recording right now.
The Ubuntu desktop team has discussed some of their plans for Gnome on Ubuntu 17.10 and
things have sort of settled since Mark's initial announcement and people are processing
it going through the stages of grief with some of the Unity users.
It seems like they kind of picked up that people like needed a little bit more info
to really understand what this might look like.
XFCE users started walking around saying, I told you so over and over again.
You know, everybody's got their time.
And so we've been all curious to really kind of find out what would Canonical really do.
I mean, are they really just going to ship stock Ubuntu?
And so Kevin Van Dyne, I think, Van Dyne, I just Kevin V from Canonical, he's worked
there for eight years.
So I'm sorry, Kevin.
You're never going to learn it at this point.
Yeah, well, yeah, because he and I talk so often.
He spent the past three years working on various parts of the Unity 8 stack and he's now part
of the Ubuntu desktop team.
Now I think we should just start right there.
There was a Unity 8 team.
There's not a Unity 8 team.
But if you notice the way Joey wrote this, he's now moved to the Ubuntu desktop team,
which tells us there is, in fact, an Ubuntu desktop.
So that's an interesting little bit.
And he's tasked with the successful switch over to Gnome.
And they kind of I think we might be seeing a more customized Gnome from Ubuntu than we
were originally sort of led to believe because we had some worries that it was just going
to be like this.
They're just going to ship stock and that's not going to be great.
Mark said something to that effect.
It's like they're going to ship Gnome as Gnome intended to be.
But nobody's a huge fan of that, really.
And so Joey over at OMG Ubuntu asked Kevin if they plan to customize Ubuntu Gnome 17.10.
And it looks like they're kind of making some considerations.
Few tweaks here and there he says.
We want to give our users a good experience.
And so they're launching a poll with the help of OMG Ubuntu to try to figure out what some
of those tweaks should be.
And so OMG Ubuntu has launched a short survey that Canonical is apparently listening to
and they're going to take in some of the feedback too.
So it seems like a good opportunity to tell them what you'd like to see in the Gnome desktop.
Kind of a unique opportunity, I mean really kind of an incredible opportunity if you think
about it.
This is one of those ones where later you're going to complain and we're going to be like,
well, did you vote?
Did you go to that survey?
This was posted 40 minutes ago, by the way.
So yeah, so this is all still happening pretty fast right now.
So here's just a little idea.
Here's some of the extensions that people are being asked to rate, Dash to Dock, Impatience,
No Top, Left Hot Corner, Alternate Tab, Applications Menu, Better Volume Indicator, Top Icons Plus.
Is that your fan?
Is your fan kicking up?
I think so, yeah.
Yeah, it does that sometimes.
So there you go.
That's what they're looking at.
I kind of want to take the survey.
Yeah, you should.
Should I do it?
Do it.
Dash to Dock, what do you think?
Not useful or very useful?
Mumble room.
Oh wait, let's bring the mumble room in.
Yeah, what are we doing?
Let's make it official.
They can help us take it too.
We'll bring them in right now.
Time appropriate greetings there, mumble room.
Hello everybody.
So what do you say?
Should we take the survey together?
Sure.
Absolutely.
Ready for it?
Okay, Dash to Dock, useful or not useful?
What say you, mumble room?
Useful or not useful?
Five.
Useful.
Yeah.
Very useful.
Definitely useful.
I figure I could probably figure out the number rating based on how many people say useful
or not useful.
Like if a lot of people say useful, then it's more of a five, and if less people say, then
I'll say it's...
Okay.
So impatience.
Impatience speeds up the GNOME desktop animations for minimizing and maximizing windows and
triggering overlays and things like that.
Would you say this is a useful extension or not useful extension?
Never useful.
Useful.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
I'm going to give that one more of a three.
Yeah, middle of the road there.
Yeah.
No top left hot corner.
This disables the top left hot corner in GNOME, which triggers your desktop and makes
everything move around like I just did on my video screen here.
What do you say?
No top left hot corner.
Is that a very useful thing or not useful?
I don't care.
Useful.
I think it's pretty useful.
Sounds like it.
I'm going to influence it.
I think I like the...
I'm going to give it a four.
See, I've never thought about it before, but just during this last TechSnap program, I
was like, boy, it'd be nice if this didn't happen all the time.
Yeah, it does get you when you're broadcasting.
Yeah.
Alternate tab.
I'm just going to give that a middle of the road because I want to move on.
I don't want to take all day on the survey.
Turns out there's like Linux news or something.
Okay.
Here's the thing, though.
This is the one that I am very torn up about, and this is the one I've actually wanted to
get everybody's opinion on the strongest.
The applications menu, which introduces a category-based app menu for searching and
opening applications, which replaces the full screen applications menu in default GNOME.
Useful or not useful?
Useful for new users.
Fair.
Okay.
I feel like it's also a bit of an atrocity, though.
I mean, it's a huge diversion from the way the default environment-
I've actually never tried it.
I have.
It's okay.
It's no brisk.
It's fine.
I guess I hadn't really thought about the new user angle.
It can be nice to have sorted categories to find things.
Yep.
That's one of the reasons I deal with mate.
Do you think we should be catering to new users?
That's a very legitimate question.
Oh, boy.
See, here's the thing is I was going to make that an entire discussion in today's show
because I think that is the question of Linux going forward is I think we should really
refrain from even considering the new user because we are fooling ourselves at this point.
I don't mean to be a Debbie Downer about this.
I wasn't necessarily going to get into this because I'm still trying to put my thoughts
together on this.
But you look at this news from Canonical.
Okay, so here's the thing, Wes.
If Canonical couldn't do it, I mean there's been no greater success in desktop Linux history
than the Ubuntu desktop.
There has been no desktop that has been prepackaged, no Linux desktop that has been prepackaged
with hardware manufacturers more than the Ubuntu desktop.
There has never been a greater success story in desktop Linux than Ubuntu, Unity 7 even.
And if they can't pull it off, I would argue that it's not a measurement of the technological
prowess of the mere display server.
I would argue that it is not the buttons on the left-hand side of the Unity 7 windows
that prevented these things from happening.
I would argue that there is just simply no real market pressure in the West that is driving
consumers to seek out a solution that is not Windows, Mac, or Chrome OS or tablets.
In countries like China and India and other places, of course, there are different market
factors at play.
And those consumers have been driven to seek out different solutions.
And so there it is successful.
But in order to be successful in the West, it just seems it's an impossibility.
It is amongst the average consumer.
Now certain niches like engineering, software development, certain levels of high-end media
production, it seems likely that Linux will continue to just win there amongst people
who are seeking out a market alternative.
For whatever reason, the one they're using isn't fulfilling their need.
But that is just simply, simply, simply not the case for your most average consumer, the
quote, unquote, new user coming to Linux.
I don't believe they exist.
So maybe are there multiple tiers here of new user and what we should give up on or
not focus on anyway is this very casual user we have to cater to?
Because maybe we do still want it to be easy for the engineer coming from Windows to get
here who's willing to learn a little.
You still want to be able to, as a Linux enthusiast and geek, you still want to be able to solve
somebody's problem by taking some crappy Windows install off their laptop and putting Linux
on there for them.
You want them to be able to use it.
So there's obviously this quote, unquote, new user that we're always sort of theoretically
trying to make sure that software is easy to install so that they're happy and that
themes look right so that it's pleasant to them and that we have things like application
menus that completely overwrite the way that the desktop environment has been designed
to work.
It's not like GNOME accidentally doesn't have an applications menu.
That's some serious intentional design.
Well, and for me, it's like, also, I don't want us to think about this new user, super
new user, whatever, at the expense of power users.
Because for me, one thing I love about GNOME is I hit that key and I type the thing that
I want that I know that I want and I get it immediately.
And there are some systems where that's not the case, and especially if I have to go browse
through this menu to this thing that I already want.
It's not a workflow that I'm going to use and it drives me away from it.
Yeah.
Wimpy, what are your thoughts?
You raise a lot of good points there.
The first, so going all the way back to the applications menu in GNOME, I don't think
that that should be included because it's a real departure from how GNOME is designed
to work.
Totally.
And to follow on from that, you're kind of right about the new user thing.
I would say anecdotally, I do see a lot of new users coming to Linux for the first time
through Ubuntu MATE.
So through that community, I see new people joining all the time.
Is that, do you feel unique or do you think that, is it unique because Ubuntu MATE is
super appealing to Raspberry Pis and reclaiming old hardware or do you think maybe I just
am missing the boat on that particular point?
Okay.
So I'm excluding Raspberry Pis from that.
These are people that have had Windows on a computer and are now running Ubuntu MATE
on a computer.
And I don't know what the numbers are like.
I'm not saying it's millions or anything, but certainly they're out there.
They're out there enough that I've seen enough posts in the forums to register that there
are this group of people that are new to Linux.
And if you speak to the elementary guys, I think that they would tell you the same as
well.
So they are out there.
But what I would also say is that I think you're right, that Ubuntu has had good success
in appealing to a professional market.
And I think the default Ubuntu desktop should be geared towards professionals and specifically
developers and the flavors I think can attract the consumer market.
Wow, that's a powerful statement.
So I suppose I have some personal experience recently if we're going with anecdotal experience
of her Mother's Day, family member that I didn't even know was using Ubuntu, turned
out to be using Ubuntu, because some computer guy that helped her fix her computer told
her to install it.
Really?
And she didn't even know it was Ubuntu.
If I didn't see that Unity sidebar in that classic background, you should have seen the
double tag.
What?
So I think she had no agenda.
She doesn't really care.
She just wants to be all ease the internet.
Right.
So Wimpy you could be right, and to a certain degree, maybe I'm being a little more extra
pessimistic.
I think it's probably what you're saying, is I'm being a little pessimistic, but I definitely
feel like we're spinning our wheels and wasting our time constantly theorizing about a theoretical
user when it's not really an applicable…
Okay, so I guess I want to shift gears because there is a new user that is out there, that
it seems to be a real number and that would be say India and China, where people are walking
into stores and buying Ubuntu machines and there's totally different market dynamics
there.
What about them?
Don't they deserve a custom built desktop?
Or are they shipping something like Ubuntu Chillin and maybe it's just a totally different
experience.
Right.
Well in China that's exactly what they're getting but in general I mean is Ubuntu currently
geared towards one audience or the other?
Is it particularly new user friendly or is it developer friendly or is it pro user friendly
or is it just general purpose?
And I don't think that's going to change in Ubuntu right.
I think that whichever way these desktop extensions go and the way GNOME is implemented it's going
to be just as applicable to new users and pro users.
I think what's important is that these extensions just make things intuitive.
So here's how I kind of fell down on it.
I said applications menu I'm going to say not useful much I'm not going to say one but
hear me out, hear me out, hear me out because I also rated better volume indicator as not
very useful and then I put top icons as four which is pretty useful and window controls
on the right.
Now hear me out.
Here's why I started bailing a little bit on some of these extensions.
I get nervous about the idea of stock Ubuntu shipping all hacked up with extensions.
There's like a hard limit on the number that we should really be comfortable with is what
you're saying here.
So I'm starting to look at these and I'm starting to go not totally necessary to make
GNOME usable.
Especially if Ubuntu is not doing anything anymore right like they're not guaranteeing
the stability of these things or that they'll always be consistent necessarily.
So that depends too right.
Especially if we are still concerned about new users if we do have these extensions breaking
your whole experience that that's not great.
These extensions are going to have to be packaged in order to be part of the image so that means
that they're going to be maintained and therefore they will work release to release.
It's not like I suppose if you're on LTS it's not like you're going to go from a major version
of GNOME.
Yeah.
So but I still I still think probably some discretion would be would be advised on how
many extensions.
So anyways if you want to go vote yourself you can go to OMG Ubuntu Joey just put those
up and it sounds like this is a you know an interesting conversation that I would bet
is probably like likely happening at all different levels at Canonical too.
So we still haven't gotten a lot of details on Fedora or SUSE on the Windows Linux subsystem
thing which is kind of strange or whatever the hell everyone's already running arch on
that thing anyway.
Good one.
And maybe it doesn't matter because pretty soon you're going to be running bash on your
Windows servers Windows servers Windows servers running bash.
See there was a time when I would have I actually did climb very tall mountains to get SSH working
on Windows.
Well how else were you going to administer them back in the day.
I guess now there's like WinRM and more options.
Yeah.
And and I also had to bend over backwards to get event logs into Syslog and all of these
tools were either made possible by Cygwin or something that like bundled up Cygwin on
its own in its own little Cygwin environment.
It was always it was always the hacky at best.
Yeah.
And just felt so ancient.
So now I can only imagine if I if I was stuck around administering Windows servers and if
I could get a legitimate Ubuntu LTS bash shell or Fedora shell or Sousa that would be a game
changer for me because my bash grips now I could take so many of my I mean in theory
I would have access to cron which is way better than the Windows scheduler like all of these
things would shift for me I would have access to so many tools I could have I could have
good old traditional nmap right there on a Windows server which would be very useful.
For me I wonder how much I wonder how well like what's the interaction like between those
two because if I can start using like the Linux or the new tools that I know and love
to start maybe applying some automation to the Windows side not that I want to do that
but I could certainly see people wanting to do that there's also the scary thought of
like well now people can start doing like Windows server you know you have like Docker
containers for Windows that spin up different like more little Windows server containers
that each have different bash Linux distributions inside so your next VBS might be running on
Windows server Chris. Jeez wow. Yeah Docker is also by the way so I have linked in the
show notes the Microsoft server for developers blog also Windows server is joining the Windows
insider program so if you want to run beta versions of stuff on your Windows server that's
kind of cool actually I guess they but back to the containerization thing they said the
nano server that they came up with is picking up in popularity and they're gonna they're
gonna focus on providing the very best container foundation for developers with a nano server
that's okay it's so small yeah and they're gonna and they're also expanding their Docker
support which will use Hyper-V isolation technology and you can use your choice of Linux kernel
to host the workload while the management scripts and tool could use the Windows subsystem
for Linux. Oh wow. So you can run you can pick and match your your container it is isolated
using Hyper-V and you can pick and match the Linux kernel that that container runs on top
of and then you can manage it all with bash on a Windows server. Wow what kind of world
do we live in now I don't even know how I don't know how to feel about this. I think
we live in one where Microsoft figured out how to seriously successfully compete with
Linux yeah in a way that is going to fundamentally potentially shift the market maybe I mean
it's not like you've been able to run VM Linux VMs on Windows boxes for years yeah right
so I don't know it does see it in some ways I don't know what the server side is gonna
do I don't know how that will change things that I'm not I haven't really thought about
that seems more to me for some reason it seems like a bigger deal than the desktop that's
what I was gonna say for the desktop side it feels like well like half of everyone's
already stuck on Windows at work anyway it seems like to me it was this is more of a
threat to Mac OS desktops than it is to because like who's running the Linux desktop there
anyway either you are and you're not gonna change to go to Windows just because of this
or you're already stuck on Windows but if you have a Mac suddenly like Windows looks
kind of better than a Mac in some ways for running closer to a real Linux you know especially
if you want a variety of hardware choices or you need to work with a vendor that your
company already orders from. MonkeyGum do you want to walk me off the ledge a bit? Yeah
the nano thing isn't all that's replacing is everyone that's running VM workstation
with a Linux image running inside of it that's all it's doing because it's a piece of hardware
and yeah it's just replacing the VM workstation that's all it's doing. No it's not a bad
market for them to get into yeah I don't really follow it very closely I don't really have
much interest in. You're not in the insiders program? No I don't and I don't have any interest
in Windows Nano server but I do I just. They really are doing a lot of work to try to be
competitive. This is making me have a serious crisis of faith right now like excuse me today
there was a rumor that got posted that there's gonna be refreshed MacBooks at WWDC and even
if they're not at WWDC you know they're gonna be out in the fall there's also gonna be a
new iMac workstation I would I would expect it probably to be Xeon with ECC memory. Yeah
right there's been talk of a new pro at some point. Yep yep so it's not like the Mac OS
platform is gonna sit still forever within six months they're pretty much gonna have
their shit together. Now on Windows you've got Bash on you've got SUSE Fedora and Ubuntu
on Windows 10. In the store. So you can you can basically have your dev environment match
production on your Windows 10 machine that also lets you play your Steam games and has
all the other crap that I guess Windows users like and then and then we get left with on
in Linux we have really I mean Gnome is it's not like it's some huge project like there's
a lot riding on something that is not like it's that huge and it was just a couple of
years ago teetering on bankruptcy. Is this a good time to bring up plasma? Yes. I mean
yeah I know I'm just saying like more than ever our our independent desktop projects
are going to be more important than ever. And it does feel like just I just wouldn't
I wouldn't have attributed all of this momentum or whatever the feeling was I before this
I wouldn't have attributed to Ubuntu necessarily maybe unfairly but now it does kind of feel
like the wind has been sucked from the room or the air you know I mean like it's there's
like a pause here and it's like our big competitive advantage is starting to be taken away. Now
it doesn't and the thing is is it doesn't it doesn't erode our competitive advantage
in hardware or it doesn't erode the advantages that the GPL brings but it it does erode the
one thing that personally I've been invested in a long time which is the desktop. Yeah
I mean that's a lot of what we talk about here on this program even you know it's. And
I mean I and it's just there with Canonical making these changes it just puts this huge
elephant in the room that I feel like I'm ignoring if I don't talk about. Something
you said on a research maybe it was the one of the last I'm not sure but you talk about
how you're like wouldn't really call yourself an evangelist anymore and that's kind of what
strikes me too is it's like no one's saying that Linux isn't a useful tool and it's obviously
still very useful people still want to deploy it on servers look at Azure but yeah there's
less of this like gung-ho we can replace things on the desktop this is the whole stack you
can use now it feels a little bit more like well yeah I mean use it if you use it if you
want to we'll help maybe yeah I'll know a show basically I can I what my what my take
was is I don't consider my I'm not an evangelist anymore I don't go I don't go out and actively
evangelize the platform I do want to see it continue I do like so I I am in some sense
I'm an advocate because I try to I try to promote projects like on these shows and stuff
like that to help them and I contribute financially to projects and I try to be an advocate but
I don't really evangelize as much anymore because it's really getting to the point for
me it's like I don't have a super solid argument I can tell you that it's my preferred working
environment I can tell you that I work the best under it and I find it to be the less
for the least frustrating of the desktop operating systems and I like specifically with a with
a rolling distribution I really like the the fact that for a really long time I was reloading
my machines at least once a year every six months whatever and so since I switched to
Arch on some of my work machines it's it's the installation just lives as long as that
hardware lives yeah and that's really nice because it just means that everything set
up my SSH keys my GPG stuff you don't have to change it you don't have to worry about
it I just sit down and I can work and and and that's nice because it's been like that
now for like three years and it's like wow this is really valuable and I can't really
explain to a Windows user because you're always gonna get the Windows user says well I haven't
had any problems on my install for four years great good for you congratulations didn't
work like that for me and it's about me and so for me these these systems I find them
they stay the performance stays consistent if they generally get just better the desktop
are being stopped environments are just getting better with updates my applications are just
getting better and more competitive especially with you know a lot of the a lot of the latest
us all just on electron anyways I guess what it makes me think is like we're back to philosophy
instead of like before there was some camps right like you can't reproduce production
on your desktop if you don't run a Linux system you know and and there's like various ones
of those were like you just you need a Linux if you want to do this it seems like less
and less of that it's like you can still use Linux for that if you want to use Linux it'll
work great we encourage you to do so but it's now more of like should or you'll feel better
doing it or here's some like philosophical open source type reasons why you might want
to and for some people those just aren't as compelling monkey calm you think the tools
matter yeah I mean over the last five years the tools available to Linux users have just
quadrupled I mean we're running jet brain with Ruby mine and just the mysql tools that
are just they run and they work better and faster and more stable and Linux than Windows
and I have developers are run jet brain and mysql tools and Windows and I have developers
are running Linux and the Linux guys are converting the Windows users to Linux and none of them
run unity they all run either Gnome Mette or KDE yeah and I think canonical sees it
too I mean I think they understand that that that is it excuse me that is exactly the type
of user that is actively looking to switch to Linux right I'm not saying people aren't
switching to Linux I'm trying to build it I'm essentially what I'm building the case
for here is we really just need to forget about the general market and just really kind
of realize realize who's switching it's gonna be people we switch ourselves to Linux or
people like monkey calm that they just outlined or look at canonical right before canonical
made this huge shift what did they do they went on Hacker News start of the thread hey
guys what do you want to see what's Hacker News tell me we want to see Gnome we want
to see Wayland we just want to see basically printing a little better we want to see this
a little better and just ship it all stock so that way think about this and then we'll
move on if I was switching from Mac OS or Windows one of the things I would be exhausted
by at this point is all of the little whims that these companies have had over the years
to sell their operating systems you know Apple's experiment experimented with like Launch Center
and they have a handoff stuff where things popping up on your dock all the time when
you walk into the room and Microsoft has had just this last few years with Windows 8 and
the transition to touch and all of this stuff Cortana everywhere now the integration of
ads and Cortana into the windows and even just like to some of us it's just exhausting
these stupid bullshit names like the the fall creators update and all of these you know
corporate jerky little names that we all just get sick and all of that grades on your nerves
after a while or like today in the telegram group people were talking to somebody was
in there saying I just installed Windows 10 and now I'm spending two hours installing
updates and the way it just trickle feeds you the updates instead of just blasting them
on there like your package manager can these things drive you nuts after a while and you're
going to want to move to something that doesn't have this strategy tax and a pretty stock
gnome setup riding on top of a Debian or Ubuntu or an arch or Fedora is exactly that it's
not somebody's grand vision of the desktop it's not somebody trying to usher in a new
era of computing it's just here's a workstation OS if you don't like this one you can switch
to another one and you can still get your work done yep and that's what people that
are in the know want that's who our target audience is I think that goes right back to
what you were saying before you know just especially like even talking about in India
and China like we still need the desktop those things are still important but like clearly
Ubuntu has started you know decided that they want to focus as an organization on these
on these power users developers creators people who are using this you know in these worlds
and maybe there just isn't that kind of profit and momentum left in the desktop even if it
is still an important part of our mind share hmm all right anybody else in the mummer room
want to chime in before we move on I just thought we'd mention that totally wasn't going
to talk about today because didn't want to seem like a downer but I think it's I feel
like it is the elephant in the room right now it just feels like we gotta we gotta consider
that all of this if you're gonna be trying out bash by any chance or I would love to
hear more about people using that if you're new to that kind of stuff yeah really since
I'm not trying it maybe I should well if you want a positive spin on the whole bash on
Windows they do you always always look at it from the point of view that now people
who are stuck with Windows can run all of the fedora Ubuntu and openSUSE a user space
tools that they want and they could just be using Windows as a shell to get at that stuff
yeah to make them productive well there I'd say the other positive things it does mean
more open source in the hands of more users right which is always good to makes it really
the barrier entries low and when they start using that stuff through WSL eventually will
get to the point that it isn't quite as seamlessly integrated and maybe they'll start moving
over to a proper operating system as a result C sharp you wanted to chime in actually Wimpy
just touched exactly on what I was going to say and just to elaborate more on it I think
it's basically just Windows compromising because it's not Linux and we're seeing stage two
we'll see a stage five and a stage six and then you know we'll have a bunch of Linux
users I could also make the argument I suppose that it's sort of like the same argument why
it's great that we have LibreOffice and Firefox and tools like that on Windows and Gimp and
etc etc etc because then when you switch over to Linux your same exact application sets
available so more maybe that could be even more true I think it's just one of these things
where I'll have to just watch and see where it goes while people are trying it out just
want to mention explain shell.com a few people share that with me this week and it looks
pretty cool you can write down a command line to see how it breaks out so for example say
you're maybe trying out the tar command for the first time well you can put the command
syntax in the explain shell.com box and it breaks down the entire command into really
easy look at that isn't that nice and easy to understand so you can see what each flag
does what the command itself does and it really helps you understand so that is explain shell.com
and then if you're having some trouble with some shell that you've recently written how
about shell check at shellcheck.net which finds bugs in your shell scripts and you can
also install it on the command line if you just want to install it locally yeah it's
like a handy dandy little winter for your bash scripts yeah which I find handy especially
if you like you only write bash scripts occasionally you come back and you're like did I use the
right number of brackets what's happening or you know you just want to maybe sanity
check a one that gets dropped in like a stack exchange thread or something like that I don't
know before you run it on your system yeah yeah yeah so I'm there you go there was therapy
with Chris about I think it's I think you guys are probably right and here's the other
thing even if even if we just say okay maybe these average consumers that we're always
talking about don't really exist for Linux the markets that do seem to be materializing
like the very kind of people that be buying this galago pro that is not only a growing
market but that's a good market to go after there is nothing wrong with that segment that's
a good thing right it really is and there are also people that are more able to tolerate
slightly rough edges or understand what an extension is to a gnome desktop environment
and those might be some of the best users to have in our fold because they might be
able to help fix some of those rough edges too oh man West that's a very good point so
there you go that's the positive take on the whole thing so go ahead Microsoft keep at
it keep at it and while I keep keeping at it if you're at this is what I would do if
you're having problems with your bash scripts you got problems with your shell script you
don't know how to do something Linux Academy is where you go linuxacademy.com slash unplug
sponsor right here of the unplug program and they've been here for a while I think it's
a great service and more and more of you are trying it out all the time you get started
by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged then you sign up for a free seven day trial
try something out now the thing that's great about Linux Academy is they have courseware
for every type of user if you're an experienced Linux user and you're ready to kind of step
it up to the next level on stuff they got courseware for you if you're brand new getting
started with something and maybe it's something that's not even specific to Linux maybe you
want to get your Linux basics or maybe you want to learn how to program in Ruby or a
little Python maybe you could become the next Google linuxacademy.com slash unplugged seven
day free trial here's something else that sets Linux Academy apart they have real instructors
real people can actually help you that's nice because it's not like this is your average
online courseware there's so many online training places where they'll have like a Linux course
or they'll have the Linux plus certification or we'll teach you an AWS course nobody can
match Linux Academy they got great courseware in AWS too and that is its own beast isn't
it isn't isn't that thing a beast and it's so nice to have an authority to go to same
with OpenStack especially with OpenStack's modular nature it's really nice to have a
place you can go where you can wrap your head around complicated topics in just like an
amount of time oh oh okay six hours six hours and I know Ruby I can do that math linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged comprehensive downloadable study guides servers that spin up on demand
when you need them and courseware that matches the distribution you have chosen just try
it all for seven days for free at linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thank you to Linux
Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program if they can teach Chris Ruby then I mean anything's
possible that's very true hey how about a little admin and public service stuff for
the community Southeast Linux Fest is t-minus one month away and they're announcing that
the registration is up the schedules released and more so this I wanted to give a little
attention to now it's it's down in Charlotte North Carolina and they have it there at the
hotel it's always actually been a pretty pretty beloved one here by the crew I don't think
I've ever I don't think I've ever gone it's gonna be June 9th through the 11th this year
9th through the 11th of June so it's coming up pretty darn pretty darn soon like you know
a month at the Charlotte Sheraton Charlotte Sheraton say that three times yeah the Charlotte
the the Sheraton Charlotte Airport in Charlotte North Carolina there you go that's the whole
thing so I will say it does seem to like it's one of those things like they have a feels
like they have a similar energy to our dear Linux Fest Northwest you know yeah yeah there's
like they like their cousins yeah very much sister sister conferences yeah so check it
out and they also are on the tweeters if you like to tweet at se Linux Fest at se Linux
Fest if you want to follow them if you're gonna be in the area let me know it'd be
kind of cool that we want it I was thinking field report I'm Noah will probably go I should
ask him but I thought it'd be cool if people go to events like this and they're in our
JB telegram group that'd be a great way to meet up with fellow JB people live people
could post pictures of the of the fest while they're pictures of their beer and make us
all jealous yeah yeah yeah another piece of another piece of admin to cover here on the
show the new Linux unplug subreddit is officially launched look at that handsome devil talking
about it last week and it's happened we've already got people starting to go there and
submit stories thank you to everybody over there so it's a reddit.com slash r slash Linux
unplugged and look at that good stuff in there look at that right there about palazzo put
about the plasma 510 beta that survey we covered is already there wow dude that is nice look
at that story about Edward Snowden talking at the OpenStack summits in there as well
so all kinds of good stuff and the question about the studio I like it I like it thank
you everybody for helping us get the new subreddit set up for this show you can participate at
reddit.com slash r slash Linux unplugged which you know you think about it if you can't join
us live for the for the live virtual lug you could totally hang out with us on the subreddit
yeah that's like 24 7 you don't have to be here at any specific time for that so r slash
Linux unplugged it's kind of long that's what she said but hopefully it'll become a pretty
good community speaking of community holy cow the soundboard I was talking about recently
caster soundboard this thing is full-on nuts now this thing is I'll show it to you here
in a second just a reminder it's a it's a soundboard for podcasters written in c++ and
q5 and since last week I think or since the last time we've talked about it they've they've
they've added the ability to remotely control this thing over the network they've yeah they've
closed 16 features it's now feature complete and in beta that's awesome it supports the
open sound control protocol which I think I'm getting that right I don't even know what
that is but I'm excited there's a bunch of great open source and third-party apps like
available for your phone that you can install and control the soundboard from your phone
right isn't this wonderful you can they added the ability to duck all of the clips at once
they have app-wide ducking you can save an unsaved setups which is one of our original
big requests you can you can have hotkeys to fire off different things and it's been
added to the AUR which is totally totally awesome I think they've also added a jar jar
sub menu I don't know why we have a jar jar bink sub menu but we also I think they're
adding that so I wanted to show it to you so I have it installed if you guys are watching
the video version of the unplugged show I have it installed here if you're not listening
or if you're listening not watching what's up here is a tabbed interface I can have multiple
soundboard tabs and right now I have the Linux unplugged soundboard up and there's a couple
of sliders one is volume and one is position I can set different colors there are all large
touched objects so I don't have it fully maximized but so a picture it's even larger than what
would be on my screen the idea being that it's going to be on a Dell 21 inch touchscreen
so I can fire off all these either with a keyboard or with touchscreen because keyboards
when I'm sitting touch screens when I'm standing and we have of course names you can load files
in here it all it uses the local GTK open file even though it's a cute app look at that
that's super nice it like I was talking about just a just a moment ago it has the remote
control feature so with an open sound control server running on this you can do one way
or two way communication with this soundboard wow yeah which is great because you can have
somebody like yourself you could you know nothing we do in there but imagine like say
you went off to like to like some some conference in Seattle and you came back with some audio
you could be sitting there on your laptop and you could be firing off the clips of the
audio when you were ready for the press I don't it doesn't have to rely on me so in
the past that's awesome I you would have had to give me all the audio before the show I
would have to listen through it all to know when to cue it up and then I would have fired
off but now you could bring the audio in and you could fire it off that's amazing yeah
so that's something we could play with in the future they have the also added the ability
where I can grab the in and out part hi there you do that was good I was in and out yeah
all the same time I can grab the in and out parts of a clip I should do it I should so
I can pull down the volume right here so I do it again see it's quieter now and then
there is a isn't that great we also have app-wide ducking like I was talking about so it brings
everything down by 33 percent which is really cool I can tie I can drag it up a little bit
there so and then of course there is a global stop all clips button which is pretty cool
aka the shut up button yep and then I could just create more sound boards I could call
this one you know something that would be really relevant to the show and I can tab
through the different interfaces and have different boards loaded here save them out
import them out isn't this neat that is so awesome it's all all created by members of
their tool yeah it really is it is now it is beyond what the proprietary applications
on macOS could offer and a few short weeks all created by our community members for the
podcasting community so we have that linked up in the show notes it's sort of it's it's
a bit sorry about that loud noise the chat rooms give me a hard time but it's sort of
the it's sort of the coolest like little community project I've seen us work on in a while so
big thank you everybody on the github that is working you guys are awesome and we should
like I don't know we should like come up with a way to get you guys like beers or something
something yeah wish if I had if I had all of the monies in the world if I had all the
Bitcoin in the world I just fly people out and take them up from here for that I you
know if I could throw one more out there I would love to see if anybody has any interest
in working on another open source project it's an audio visualizer written in Python
it's a little gooey tool that renders visualizations on audio files now if you've ever watched
a video version of user air you've seen this this sucker in in action if you're watching
the video version too I have it I have an example up and essentially it takes an audio
input file and it takes a background image in and then it uses ffmpeg to render out a
video that matches the length of the audio file that has waveforms that match the audio
so that way you can put this up on you could put an audio show up on YouTube or put it
in an mp4 video feed or something like that and there's actually something there's a visualizer
there to look at that matches the vocals now the only problem with this is is it only does
this there's no variation we can do with it we can't put animation like we can't put a
movie file in the background even though ffmpeg of course supports all of this it's just the
rapper does not right and what we'd like to do is be able to have more variety so we could
use it for Linux action news we could use it for user air and then other podcasters
could use it for their podcast and we could all look a little different we could all have
our own unique look to it so that's also going to be in the github that might be asking for
a lot really it's python and ffmpeg so it's it's pretty straightforward pretty awesome
and it's already up on it's already up on github just go pull it down right now and
so we're working on this and one of the one of the pushes for us to do this is we're trying
to decide as a network if we want to be the podcasting network that delivers you get a
show and you get it in any file format any way you want it so if you if you want to get
Linux action dues in a video file and watch it on your Kodi box you can do it if you want
to download an mp3 of Linux action show you or text app you can do it if you want an HD
video version of text app you can get it I want an opus file Chris well that's something
we are actually working on too and so it's going into this thing like what do we want
to be as a podcast or because it's much more feasible for us to say well this is an audio
show so we're just going to officially release an mp3 because then we can get actual tracking
numbers on it we can manage the feed simpler we know where to focus all of the ratings
and the reviews and the different podcast networks which makes a huge difference for
discover ability and it's less hosting for us and it's less time you're kind of more
in line with what a lot of other you know more mainstream podcasts do right in and and
a lot of quote-unquote platforms that are built to host podcasts are dropping support
for og and webm and so they're just essentially supporting mp3 maybe m4a and so we've been
trying to decide well what do we want to do is do we want to just continue to like rebuild
replacement platforms to host these files when these things shut down and pay for the
storage and pay for the time to upload it and encode it for the editor and like what
it or do we just want to focus we and we're trying to decide like we're trying to find
a really good balance here and this this this this open source project is actually the linchpin
to this entire thing because this audio visualizer allows us to put in an audio file put in a
good background which we would like to have more flexibility with and have a little more
flexibility with the visualizer and then we can put out a file that we're actually like
I tried it with Linux action news and nobody liked the video file like ever I thought it
looked okay but everybody's complaining on YouTube that it's giving them seizures so
okay all right we've got to come up with something better but you'd like to have like a first
class audio only yeah supported pipeline it makes it makes it when you produce a show
for audio it makes it so much better I it just it's I don't need to go into it but and
if you make a show for video and you produce it for video it makes a video show that much
better and that's how we're gonna do it but I still think we should probably try to make
everything available when whatever way people want it and this tool is sort of the tool
that I think is gonna allow us to build a production pipeline around that so we would
love the help if you are if you have the interest on the audio visual Python thing yeah so there
you go yeah that's true thank you ww thank you that does make me feel better a little
bit but I love him you know what I love him I just I just love him one other thing I want
to talk about because I think it could be interesting maybe down the road and how things
like this affect Linux users too it's only affecting Android users right now but Netflix
is confirming that it's blocking rooted and unlocked devices which could be pretty significant
down the road for potentially other other types of and I feel like especially for some
of our audience you know we more than a lot of other people perhaps are interested in
having rooted devices or other modifications yeah so I thought that was using this is kind
of something that I've kind of taken for granted that it'll just work yeah yeah they're using
the wild vine or wild vine wide vine wide vine is that what it is Google's yeah they
bought that company yeah yes yeah and it's a DRM technology that basically has like you
can pick your layer layer of security how trusted you want a device to be and Netflix
has chosen the trusted level that disqualifies rooted devices which may be more I could say
that the content partners Netflix works with probably force them to choose probably we
don't know probably yeah so it's an interesting thing with Android and one of the things that
we're gonna be talking about probably more next week is magic device tool which kind
of goes in with all of this so magic device tool we've talked about we've talked about
it before it's pretty straightforward and it's pretty easy to get set up on your machine
you know it is amazingly powerful it allows you to load Ubuntu touch and Ubuntu phone
you know on it like a Nexus 5 I think I might be wrong on that so if anybody like wimpy
or somebody in the mobile room knows correct me but I think I'm like the Nexus 5 you can
load Ubuntu touch Android lineage OS maru OS sailfish OS and Phoenix OS with this one
tool with this one tool so I downloaded it and I have it on my machine upstairs and I
got my Nexus 5 charging up and I think I'm gonna try lineage first oh nice yeah didn't
know what mr. Joe does I think so yeah I think so I and it's the one I hear the most in our
community too in terms of you weren't gonna go for the Ubuntu touch well it just might
make me sad yeah I also have been very much considering maru or maru OS yeah right which
is it's like Android but also Debian XFCE I have I don't know if it'd be helpful but
I have that adapter the oh yeah HDMI out I will try it then yeah if you remember to bring
that I'll go find it so anyways I'm gonna be trying to play around this and if things
work out we may get a chance to chat with the developer of the tool next week if all
things line up Marius who works on this says you might be able to make it next week and
I would be great timing if you guys want to try it out too and join us next week in the
mobile room I have a link to the magic device tool which is also there's a snap for that
although I tried to install it had some problems on arch but if you're using snap on Ubuntu
you're probably that's awesome mm-hmm that makes it so easy yeah and you know what I'm
gonna do once I rock that Nexus 5 once I rock that Nexus 5 with lineage I'm gonna put it
on ting that's what I'm gonna do I'm gonna put it on ting you go to linux.ting.com to
save $25 off a ting device or if you bring one you just bring a ting device check their
BYOD page because they support CDMA and GSM if you just bring just bring it over and you'll
get a $25 service credit from ting now here's the killer thing and I was surprised I did
not realize this when I switched to ting average ting bell $23 so they're gonna give you a
$25 service credit it's mobile the way it should be you just pay for what you use and
that's it six dollars for the line and that's your usage on top of that no contracts nationwide
coverage pay for what you use with a really great dashboard check it out just go to linux.ting.com
and they got great devices too so if you want to be if you just want to grab one there you
can do that and if you get a like a Play Store device bring that over there if you get like
one of the Nexus devices or pixel you might take a look at what coverage is better in
your area because you could choose CDMA or ting I mean CDMA or GSM on ting they offer
both so many options you can just pick up a SIM card and then just put it in a device
that you picked up from the Play Store they also you can buy iPhones and motorolas and
all the you know like really nice devices like the high-end stuff and you know like
the stuff that's still pretty good phone but it's in the budget price range and then down
to like the flip phones holy crap holy crap yeah look at this the answer tell one touch
fling which is a flip phone but that could be kind of nice $20 see that's the thing like
$20 six dollars a month for the line yeah even if you break it or you just throw it
on the ground in spite like it doesn't matter wow it's so cheap it's amazing that is really
so game changer let's go over to linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring
the program that is wow wow wow how do they even do that how do they how do they that's
their secret how do they even do it how do they even do it I don't even understand so
mr. West right here in our hot little hands is system 76 is galago pro and this is a pretty
pretty exciting rig a lot of people were drooling all over this thing at Linux fest Northwest
people were constantly stepping by that was the highlight of the system 76 booth yeah
people are stopping by they're constantly to look at this thing and I'm playing with
this ethernet port right like that so I've been I've been messing around with it and
getting a sense for what kind of machine it is and who I think might be really into it
and where I think would fit in with my workflow and I kind of I got like I still have thoughts
in fact I I'm probably gonna still kick it around for a couple of more days I'm gonna
send it back pretty soon because these are in-demand product so I'll just give you the
basics if you're not familiar the galago pro is a 13.3 inch machine that weighs around
like 2.8 2.9 pounds hmm port wise it has them it's really nice in 2017 to get a machine
with these ports it's got one USB C with Thunderbolt and I've been told it has four PCI lanes in
that USB C port yeah which means as each GPU support gets better on Linux you're gonna
get full you would get full eGPU support with four PCI lanes which is really nice like I
said it has Ethernet it has HDMI out it has an SD card slot and DisplayPort now one thing
that might throw you off and this is just my understanding at this time there is also
a here it is there's like a little like a little GSM SIM card slot but I don't think
the corresponding hardware is on the motherboard that's too bad geez excuse me I'm getting
over a cold from Linux test yeah so I don't I might be wrong you might also be able to
pop the bottom off and put something in there so it might not be a huge issue but I think
right now it's just a dead slot it really is a ton of ports though and it's like I'm
just not used to seeing that number on a laptop it's not three it's not four especially especially
one that weighs under three pounds yes so it's this one the one I'm using has a core
i5 or I'm sorry core i7 is 7500 running at about 2.7 or ish they change depending on
what you're doing two physical cores four logical cores Intel HD graphics 620 8 gigabytes
of RAM 256 gigabyte MV and me drive and a 36.2 watt hour battery so that is my test
config of the system 76 Galago Pro I'll tell you too one of the things besides the really
enjoying the ports and the availability of a DisplayPort in HDMI is particularly nice
and the USB C port is nice it does also have a barrel charger it does not charge over USB
C right and I asked this from 76 if they think that might be something future models might
offer and they're looking at that so that may be that would be nice the the barrel connector
is pretty straightforward and the power brick is pretty small it's like that one of the
smallest I've ever seen from system so that's dainty yeah power button here on the side
too mm-hmm which I kind of like it's just an odd spot but it's it's got it one of the
things they discrete one of things they've done is they built a delay into it so that
way if you like bumped it with your mouse or something it doesn't trigger it you have
to hold it for a few seconds which I actually think is a pretty good idea the case is is
pretty nice it's it's particularly nice from system 76 too and one of the things that I
think they've done above and beyond with the Gallego Pro is the way they've done the logo
in and I believe this is probably how they're gonna do it on future products as well it's
a aluminum or metal type casing and the system 76 logo is is is like baked into the housing
yeah you don't feel it at all it's just it looks really good I'd say it's it's pretty
close to the XPS line and build quality I'd say it's on par with most Lenovo's for sure
what do you definitely yeah yeah I mean it feels sturdy there's no bend right in it right
the hinges with the screen which is always something I'm worried about yeah that's rock
solid yeah in my opinion the screen really pops too do you feel like that yeah yeah it's
got it's it's not touch though right correct correct which I think actually a lot of people
might perhaps they're not interested in that a lot of times it takes away from battery
life and other things but it is beautiful and it's high dpi it is it's like it's it's
thirty two hundred by eighteen hundred I think is that right is that the yeah I think so
so yeah that's the so the screen I I've been pretty impressed with that there's a bezel
around it so when compared to the XPS 13 right it jumps out at you but it's not as bad as
most of the other systems like I'd say it's a smaller bezel than you'd have like on the
Apollo and it it all is the housing itself is pretty nice it's well balanced too like
you can have a nice laptop that's weighted really weird and hard to hold and carry around
but this is like it's portable yeah yeah I've had a couple of I've had a couple of complaints
with the fan noise and I think I kind of got from a from a conversation I had with system
seventy six that they're still tweaking the firmware a bit on the cooling like maybe the
fans kick in a little sooner than they need to yeah right so that was that was a potential
issue you know looking at this machine this was probably one of the hardest laptops I've
ever you know I think it was the hardest laptop I've ever reviewed and I'll tell you I couldn't
really wrap my head around why does this feel like it's so so hard for me to review this
laptop and I realized that we are in like a three-year transitionary period that's extremely
awkward we are transitioning well let's start with the one we just been talking about we're
transitioning on the Ubuntu side which system 76 ships we're transitioning to Gnome and
Wayland that's a big transition that's gonna take a few years to work everything out we're
transitioning to high DPI there's still a lot of little nigglies there that need to
be worked out we are transitioning from lots of different types of connectors to USB C
and Thunderbolt 3 hardcore making that pivot right like there are all of these are huge
transitions and that machine is a product of that that is on the outer rim it's it's
a machine that is if you're the type of person that likes to buy a computer that is going
to where everyone's eventually going to end up this is that machine so if you want a two
three four year work machine this is going to be that computer where in some sense it
would if you could have everything in the entire world you would probably have more
like a 70 watt hour battery and you would probably have maybe a slightly larger trackpad
and charging over USB C yep but that's just not where this market is at right now we are
in a transitionary period and if you need a good workstation that runs Linux right now
that is lightweight that's easy to say take on a plane and travel with that still has
some pretty great performance I I knocked on this thing quite a bit specifically today
before the show to try to get a sense of like what the battery life is under some significant
work so I not only did I just do like a lot of my general show prep web browsing writing
up notes on the show but I also ran a few for on expense marks low-level stuff that
just sort of kept the hard drive busy for a little bit did little things here and there
just to keep the machine average busy but not stress it out too much so so I could kind
of get an idea of what the performance of the battery would be like if I have Wi-Fi
on if I have the screen about 50% brightness which is still plenty bright it's plenty bright
at 50% brightness if I put it down to 50% I'm on Wi-Fi and I and I'm just taxing maybe
the disk subsystem for a bit and then the CPU for a bit and then just general browsing
I got about about three hours I think I could have got three hours and 50 minutes out of
it if if I wasn't pushing it quite as much if you weren't you but I wanted to simulate
more of a real workload for me now I am the kind of person that is sufficient battery
for me yeah me too I think I mean like four hours issues like a good target no I'm not
he's like one of these guys he likes a 12-hour battery yes because he doesn't like to charge
his battery all day he likes to pretend like it's a tablet yeah even though he has docks
everywhere so I was but I was actually I was more impressed with that than I expected I
did have some issues initially with when I was first charging this thing up under stock
Ubuntu reading the full battery life but then after I installed system 76 is PPA that that
cleared up that pretty much became a non-issue the other thing I was considering too is I
might be able to push it beyond four hours if I installed TLP oh yeah and configured
that to like some just saying defaults so I contacted system 76 and I said are you considering
shipping this laptop with TLP pre-installed it's not on the radar yet they're considering
maybe some some tweaks like that but there's nothing like that yet they're gonna be shipping
it with unity still by the way people have been a lot of people been asking me is it
shipping with gnome and their new theme it is shipping with unity right now so I have
it with the latest Ubuntu stable release with the system 76 PPA on there it is really snappy
I gotta say yeah playing with it I played some race the Sun and other things and yeah
and the thing is you're playing I mean I know this isn't like the most demanding game but
you're playing race the Sun at 4k resolution on an Intel embedded graphics yes with a nice
frame rate yeah so I'm gonna do some more gaming on it to just get an idea of where
its limits are because I'm sure I'll hit them with an Intel graphics but it's nice to know
that the desktop itself performs well and some basic games seem to be performing well
even at high resolution yeah anyways so that's that's that's sort of my initial take on it
so far but I wanted to touch on one more sort of concluding kind of thing that I've liked
a lot about this laptop so for myself there's one thing that I always under sell myself
on and it's it bites me every damn time need that Windows Pro license that's what it is
right that CD key on the bottom that's what you want yeah man it solves so many problems
no it's the keyboard so many times I have under sold the value of a good keyboard to
myself and it it it the cost is daily frustration when I use my machine like not quite as fast
as I could be or my fingers still never learn the right position and it's it's it's so frustrating
I always always feel like I can never quite get that balance right on a laptop and I think
some people think system 76 is maybe missed the mark I think they've been better at it
in the last few years this one out of all of the machines I have in the studio right
now I can honestly tell you that this has the most comfortable keyboard now I don't
have like I don't have a mechanical keyboard with brown key switches or whatever there
I should come on clear clear okay all right okay see see apparently Wes knows I but I
don't so I'm not comparing it to somebody's ultimate keyboard setup I'm comparing it to
a bunch of Logitech keyboards in the studio a MacBook Pro keyboard a Logitech gaming keyboard
that's what I'm doing laptop keyboards are the class of their own right like it does
have to be portable do you what are you now I've had you that's one of the things I've
asked you to specifically sort of play around with since you've been in the studio today
what are your thoughts on the keyboard I like it it's comfortable to type with you know
it's not like the deepest ever but it's a key travel is nice and so like for me I have
like a 17 character password for a lot of things like my main go-to password for things
and on bad keyboards I can kind of tell it when I first got like the mechanical keyboard
I have at home one of the first things I noticed was like I don't make mistakes typing this
you know I type it like a thousand times every day same thing with this one like I can type
that very reliably I'm not making mistakes and that's really what counts because like
those backspaces are what really kill you yeah yeah that just shaving off those frustrations
is really nice so I was I'm pretty I'm pretty impressed with it I found it to be exactly
what you would want if you were somebody that wants to bust out a daily Ubuntu workhorse
and get some work done and gaming is it's in the back of your mind but you're willing
to sort of consider if I give it a few more months I could probably pick up an external
GPU and when I met my desk I could game like I can't tell you that's gonna work with this
I would love to be able to test that I just don't have an eGPU but I know that system
76 specifically worked to make sure that this was a 4 PCI lane USB-C support and that is
to me that is a very exciting future where you can have a ultra portable two two and
a half to almost three pound laptop that has Ethernet by the way which I think is a real
standout feature of this thing when compared to the XPS one of the things in my notes is
like if you if you need an Ethernet port and I consider myself one of those people this
is this is sort of one of your best bets at this size right so like for Noah that's a
huge deal right so he doesn't want those dongles yeah I have settled with the dongles but I
don't like it and so this would this would donk this would this would be a dongle is
machine for me which I think would be pretty great but anyways if you're somebody that
needs a machine like this this is a pretty good match for that the competition is stiff
right now but I think they have a pretty solid offering with this I would really like to
see system 76 stick with this machine over a few releases to keep iterating yeah eventually
you know add in things like USB-C charging maybe actually get that SIM slot oh man a
system 76 laptop with an active LTE SIM that I could pop in there oh that's amazing that
would be the other thing too is like it's a handsome looking machine and I know it sounds
silly but especially living in Seattle like I'd like to if I'm gonna be repping a Linux
laptop I'd like to not feel like I have look worse than the MacBooks in the cop shop yeah
you're gonna be competitive and that's why I think that logo on the lid is a kind of
an important thing to mention I would tell you I would I would definitely if you could
get your hands on one like at a convention tried it out try it out I'm hoping they work
out the the firmware on the fan stuff that would be one thing for me that would be a
little little bit of an issue but otherwise I really liked it I really liked it and I
was also consistently surprised at how fast it was and today when I was when I was particularly
trying to push it to kind of see what I could get out of it it's still the unity desktop
still remained responsive while I was slamming the disk or slamming the CPU like things still
felt like they wasn't like my whole desktop was laying out on me and I think that MVNE
is a big part of probably that performance story right yeah so check it out if you guys
are curious you can find it over at System76 lots of reviews are coming online right now
too I think people I think I saw somebody too is getting is receiving theirs or something
like it's it's beginning to happen it's happening Wes it's happening speaking of happening may
you can make it happen at DigitalOcean go over to DigitalOcean.com and sign up just
use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED and spin up a rig on their infrastructure in no time and
that's my favorite promo code it's just so fun to say DOUNPLUGGED DOUNPLUGGED digital
ocean.com go there you create your account first and then once you are signed up you
can apply our promo code DOUNPLUGGED and you get the $10 credit all SSD infrastructures
that makes everything super fast you can deploy in seconds they have highly available block
storage lightning fast networks team accounts if you want to work with a few people and
pre-built open source applications are ready to go go to DigitalOcean.com and use our promo
code DOUNPLUGGED and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program
so we have to go kind of soon because the text that program is recording another show
but I did want to give the mumble room a chance to ask any questions in the chat room if anybody
wanted to ask any questions about the Galago while I have it here in my little hands go
ahead anybody go on I'll go on twice are you a regular user of the touchpad on that thing
or do you use a mouse I've been using the touchpad the whole time I have not actually
hooked up to a mouse how do you feel about that compared to say the MacBook or the XPS
13 well I think it's comparable to the XPS 13 I feel like the new MacBook is it's sort
of that's a challenging thing to compare it to because it's so huge huge yeah trackpad
on the MacBook is crazy nice yeah I would like to see the trackpad be larger I tried
the Galago Ultra Pro at scale but it was before they had the final keyboard and it
might have been before they had the final trackpad I would say I would so I was not
impressed but I don't really have a lot of complaints the buttons aren't like super clicky
to me but they're fine it's got dedicated buttons the touchpad itself the feel and the
fact that the mouse didn't seem to move smoothly it's a little smooth for me you know like
the feel of it I will also say I do like that it's small I guess like I like that the Mac
one's big but Linux drivers have never been as good at the like you when you hit it with
your thumb or I kind of small hands so it's like a giant touchpad hard for me so I kind
of appreciate that this one's not huge yeah yeah chat room some people in chat room say
the battery life isn't for them and that's just a decision you have to make for me two
three hours when I'm working on it pretty hard is decent I blame some of that on Linux
too I mean if you put Windows 10 on here maybe you get six hours I don't know it's possible
maybe not either you're not gonna try that you're not gonna put Windows on the machine
born to run Linux I did run Arch on it for quite a bit I ran Arch and I actually am planning
to put elementary on here in a bit too yeah elementary and that would be a handsome combination
yes what I was thinking any other questions everybody else got any other questions before
we move on I don't know with William I really like the keyboard on this yeah what's the
RAM on that this one you can go up higher so this 32 I think yeah the the review unit
that I have has eight gigs of delicious tasty tasty RAM on it I also was considering although
I don't have a lot of time with this unit I have to send it back I was considering popping
off the bottom and seeing what the upgrade possibilities are you should post some of
those pics on Twitter actually add the LTE modem yourself yeah it sounds like it's not
in the skews they sell but I wonder if it's still on the board because it is you know
a clevo unit or something originally I wonder I wonder I don't know since it has VMs just
since it has 32 gigs do you see yourself running any VMs on it so this has a 256 gig hard drive
but you could obviously put a larger hard drive in it if you wanted to because yeah
you can get up you can get up to one terabyte MVM NVME if you wanted to actually they offer
up to two terabytes on the system 76 website two terabytes of MVM storage would be that's
another part about this this nice it's like a very configurable laptop yeah that yeah
you can put a dish you can put an additional disk in this compared to like like Dell's
website where you have to there's like six different ways you can try to configure an
XPS 13 and none of them have the same options you can put so you could put a if you wanted
to you could put a 250 gig NVME drive as your OS drive and then you could put a one terabyte
2.5 SSD in the second drive bay now you're editing video man well you are definitely
getting VMs definitely that's your steam partition right there yeah yeah I would say for like
that oh yeah it's got two DIMMs that's nice yeah you can get full 32 yeah you can get
full yep yep I would say for that so if I was gonna build this for myself if I was gonna
go nuts I would go with 1704 Ubuntu I would probably leave it at 3.1 gigahertz I don't
need to blow that money I would probably get 32 gigs of RAM I would get a 250 gig OS drive
I get a one terabyte SSD I would probably get the nicer Wi-Fi just throw that laptop
back in there you need a new bag Chris so my total wow this is pretty reasonable my
total for a pretty nicely specced 13-inch laptop with a 4k screen is 1800 bucks that's
under 2k that is actually really reasonable 1900 you know probably if you know after there's
some taxes or shipping or something I don't know but yeah that's really I mean compared
to the like I mean I'm comparing to a MacBook there but well even on some of the like higher
end XPS 15 or something like you're easily in that territory yeah yeah so you really
what you have to decide is are you ready to switch to 4k on Linux that's one of the things
you have to consider when you get the Galago Pro some of the things you don't think about
there is like grub screens other things are kind of a pain sometimes yeah Java apps even
steam on that like really yeah super small there is I've linked to it a few weeks back
there is like a steam theme that helps with high DPI it just makes fonts a little bigger
so you got to make that you got to make that call are you willing to be on a little bit
of a bleeding edge and then understand too that we're about to go through the Wayland
transition as well which probably should be fine for high DPI but just something to be
considered of and if you are and you want a workhorse that's Heidi this at a laptop
this is this could be a great one because it's fast enough to get work done and it's
small enough to travel with you and light enough that you'll actually put in your bag
that's pretty nice so they got a good mix there and I'd be curious to see if they stick
with it where it goes especially when they start building these there you go ww you had
a note go ahead oh no bashful was asking in chat and I don't think you got it he was wondering
what was the heat output on it is it running too hot when you're using you know I wanted
to ask that as well it's really not bad although I think part of that is the fan does seem
to kick in a little sooner than it should and it does have I mean it does have good
ventilation on the bottom it looks like yeah it really does it hold out this whole bottom
piece is then this whole piece where like the motherboarded motherboard is is vented
and they have do have a fan there so I think I mean I would say I would say it probably
has room to get warmer before the fan kicks and I think that's what they're playing with
right now yeah if I could keep it for a little bit longer I would try a few different production
things on it I would try editing doing some encoding on it just to give you that take
two but in the meantime kind of give you an idea of where it's at yeah well hopefully
if anyone out there buys one they'll let us know what they think of it too yeah we really
it does seem like there's some pretty good interest here oh yeah oh yeah oh yeah oh yeah
yeah yeah it looks like Mr. Martin Wimperst had to part but you can find him and poppy
over at the Ubuntu podcast do it so check them out they just had Joey on from OMG Ubuntu
which we were just covering a little bit earlier so check them out also be sure to check me
out on Linux action news it's my new show and check Wes out on the text net program
that's right look at us all our different ventures okay you ready for me to use our
new soundboard I'm so excited okay you're talking over it oh oh well all right well
then I'll just say this he's at Westpane I'm at Chris LAS the network itself at Jupiter
signal check out Linux action news too for that secret Jupiter broadcasting telegram
group get involved with the show when we're not on the air at reddit.com slash r slash
Linux unplugged hang on our virtual lug Tuesdays we do it at 2 p.m. Pacific you can get that
converted at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar and emails Jupiter broadcasting comm
slash contact all right everybody thanks so much for being here I'll see you right back
here next Tuesday say goodbye Wes goodbye bye everybody
soundboards doing so good right now Wes it's doing so good and soundboard officially played
it's in and out hashtag proud of our first production show good job community that's
pretty impressive that is that is so awesome in the background you might be able to hear
our lights screaming right now all the lights just came on in the studios we're getting
ready for the next text now let's go pick our title yeah be titles calm thank you ever
gonna fix bang suggest calm I just have to ask I don't think so because I miss you should
register it I'm sorry I forgot to bring you guys in so soon we got all excited about that
the boom to story and it kind of threw off the thing and then we got all right yeah I
know it's I'm new I'll get I'll get the hang of this podcasting thing eventually yeah this
this Chris guys yeah he's also apparently a Linux hater now that he quit the guy I didn't
want to talk about it but it just came up it just just happened so was there any push
back on the name Linux action news was Joe like this is like where's my part of this
no no I don't think so I think we're all I think we all liked it no it's a good name
I like it too yeah I think it would I think it would pretty well I now we now we just
need those Macs on eBay to sell so that way we can fund all the studio stuff that we changed
here oh my gosh Wes oh my gosh it's a world of changes it's I mean it's all good right
like it's actually really cool and awesome yeah I'm excited about you find it do you
find it easier to work with them yeah totally yeah good good that was part of the goal right
there ain't good I don't have to load any k kernel extensions on the Mac OS X anymore
and yeah you don't have to like I keep trying to use like the long options on the BSD user
list I like it because I'm up in my office and I'm listening to you and Dan on the live
stream and I launched the editor remote program and I tweaked Dan's EQ a little bit since
we changed this a little bit I never I don't have to come in and interrupt you guys like
you're none the wiser I just get it done and I'll get in the way you guys just go about
your business it's a really cool mixer yes it's that's a super nice feature of it just
top those Macs out Wes so everyone go go vote and then go buy some Macs yeah right go look
for kernel Linux on even I'm sure he's on there and I'm sure you don't