This is Linux Unplugged Episode 10 for October 15th, 2013.
Hi everyone and welcome to Linux Unplugged, the weekly Linux podcast observing the Linux
landscape from its unplugged observatory high above it all.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
I don't know about all that high above it stuff, but I thought it sounded good.
Sounds good to me.
Sometimes we kind of get down into it, actually.
This is true.
You know, this week, one of the things I want to talk to you about, Matt, is how to shake
off this Ubuntu hangover that I have right now.
Oh my goodness.
Yeah, so to really fully appreciate this week's episode of Linux Unplugged, there is a little
homework involved.
You don't have to.
I think it'll stand on its own, but if you have the time, you should go back.
On Sunday, we did Linux Action Show's Ubuntu 13.10 review, and that's sort of the jumping
off point for some of the stuff we're going to cover in this episode.
Then on Monday, we did an episode of Coder Radio called Betting on Linux, which I managed
to turn into a therapy session and really, really dug into sort of the issues I have
around the Ubuntu Dash and why it sort of viscerally bothers me, and some of the issues
I think it might cast about the Ubuntu project in whole, but again, not critical that you
listen to that, but I think it might give you some context, because this week, we're
going to follow up on some comments that you guys have made on our review, some comments
on learning Linux, and then we're going to kind of roll that into the big picture of
Linux, like maybe a world where Ubuntu isn't king, and a world where maybe not all distros
live forever, and they change, and sometimes people have to go somewhere else, and how
Linux users, especially the savvy ones, can kind of control that, and sort of instead
of be victim to it, sort of control what their destiny is.
I like that idea.
I definitely think it's important to remember that, you know, different strokes, different
folks, right?
Yeah, and what goes up must come down, Matt.
That's right.
Perhaps, perhaps.
But why don't we start with a little follow up for this here show, an ongoing topic.
We've gotten a lot of emails about it, and I've kind of had to be a little picky on what
we put in here, just because we've gotten so many, which is awesome.
But we talked a lot about recently with kids, and learning Linux, and learning computers
in general, and we got a lot of emails from teenagers, you know, young teens, and even
younger than teenage years, saying, hey, don't think it's all of us.
That's awesome, and good for you guys, definitely.
Mike wrote in, and he says, learning the nuts and bolts, Matt and Chris, not everybody either
wants or can understand how things work.
To some, their computer is an appliance and nothing else.
So here's his background.
He says, I happen to be one of the weird guys who does need to know.
As a kid in the late 50s, I built my own radios, learned how to read schematics and solder.
I was also the bicycle repair guy for the neighborhood.
At 16, my first paid job was an electric golf cart repair guy.
After two years in the Army as a draftee from 66 to 68, I got a job as a programmer trainee.
In spite of not having a degree, I just scored very high in the IBM aptitude test.
Next language I learned was the IBM 360 assembler.
He's also picked up five distinct assembly language.
Today, at 66, I still program and do web stuff and administer systems, including OpenSUSE,
Debian, and Ubuntu, and I'm still being paid to play with the toys.
I also have an advanced class in ham radio license, as well as a commercial pilot license
with instruments.
I can teach almost anybody to program, but if it's not fun and enjoyable, they'll suck
at it.
Mike.
So this is a great point that Mike makes here.
And you know what else I loved about Mike's email is, so we have, we've gotten emails
from 10-year-olds, 13-year-olds, 16-year-olds saying, hey, don't count us out.
And now you got Mike here at the other end of the spectrum saying, you know, at 66, we
still like to do this stuff too.
And you know, my grandpa, who's quite a few years beyond Mike, also, you know, he loves
playing with Linux.
He loves playing with netbooks.
And now he's getting into the open tablets.
I gave him-
That's cool.
I guess, I forget, I had a tablet that was going to be the Spark tablet for a while.
Oh yeah, I remember that.
Yeah, I gave it to my grandpa so that way he could load it wherever he wants on it,
because he's just, he loves doing that kind of stuff.
And I think he's, he just hit 80, actually.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
You know, it keeps you, it keeps you feeling young.
It keeps you involved and active and doing cool stuff.
You know?
Yeah, totally.
It's, it is good to see that.
And so while maybe, maybe the general populace, you know, and, and even in a decreasing number
of people will be specialists, there's still some out there.
Now Brian wrote in with response to last week's Linux Unplugged, where we call it, we titled
it the Ubuntu situation.
He says, I think everyone is overreacting.
I've been running Ubuntu 13.10 for a few weeks now and it keeps on getting better and better.
Other than the smart scopes, which I just choose not to use for the online results.
This is one of the best releases so far.
Ubuntu needs to be stable and boring for a release, maybe even for a few cycles.
Unity changed everything and they're now getting to the point of polish and they shouldn't
screw that up.
Everyone outside the hardcore Linux community wants a stable OS.
We are geeks.
We like the bleeding edge.
Do we complain when OS 10 doesn't ship the latest X?
No, we do not.
We don't even know about it.
That is the mindset that we need to keep in mind.
They want this to go big time.
The focus on mobile is important.
I can live with a stale OS for a few cycles and then good perspective to get on the show
since we've.
Yeah.
And then Zach wrote in with a, with another followup to the Ubuntu situation.
Zach wrote, Hey, Chris and Matt, I have a few comments regarding the most recent Linux
Unplugged.
Great show, by the way.
He says he likes the format.
He went to the big show first regarding Noah's email about young Padawan learning about Linux.
I would recommend probably not right now, but sometime in the future when he gets a
little more Linux under his belt, taking a look at Linux from scratch.
Yes, it's hardcore and pretty damn hard, especially for a newbie.
But between Linux from scratch and Gentoo, I learned so Goran much about Linux and how
it works.
When I first started out, see now he's mixing Star Wars and Firefly references.
I was going to say there's some Firefly.
Yeah.
I obviously wouldn't use it as a daily driver, but for learning and experiment, it's a great
tool.
If you could pass that along as a just name or mention the show, that would be awesome.
Second, Christopher, regarding your recent cock up with your KDE configs, why aren't
you using get to keep revisions of your dot files?
It's such a great tool and it's a great way to keep track of any text based configs, which
they all should be.
Make a get folder at the base of home and then make a get dot ignore that filters out
everything that you don't explicitly allow.
That's a good tip.
That's an excellent idea, actually.
Yeah.
I think that get dot ignore is an example and he includes it and he says you can also
use the syncing tool to keep the same config files between your machines.
Just some thoughts.
Thanks for making the awesome shows and keep up the good work.
May the force be with you.
I did kind of admit that I probably should have been doing a better job of backing up
my KDE config.
I admit to that, but I'm happy with my gnome now.
Exactly.
It's almost a mood issue.
I would also go so far as to say it's not a matter of not, I mean obviously know how,
but it's also a matter of you have X number of hours in the day.
You have X number of tasks to be done in that day and where are you spending that time and
honestly I don't know if setting that up really would have crossed your mind with as much
as you got going on.
Yeah.
I suppose it didn't because I did know it was technically possible.
Sure.
It also seems like one of those things that you could probably, if you just had some time
on a weekend to set it up once, you'd probably be good for a while.
It's a cool tip though.
I mean I got to give props for it.
It's really, really a creative idea.
I like it.
Yeah.
It's an interesting use of get too.
It's an interesting use of get and that's just another one.
Okay.
So now we're going to kind of shift gears and get into some of the stuff that I think
is probably our jumping off point for our talk about the big picture around Linux this
week.
Danny wrote in and Danny said, please continue to beat the canonical drum beat.
You in this case are not wrong.
The issue here is greater than a simple feature that can be easily turned off.
The issue is a canonical trend.
I think Shuttleworth's vision is extraordinary.
I think he's right on with convergence, but canonical at present is incapable of delivering
on its promise.
Hubris then showed itself when instead of going and selling his vision to a hardware
partner capable of fulfilling it, instead he goes to the carriers and to interweb financing
to complete his vision.
This is when we meet the underwhelming and self-congratulatory execution.
The sad ballot has played itself out over and over again.
The Dash, Ubuntu TV, Unity Desktop, Upstart and Mir, the same sad song.
I ask you, where is the shame in perfecting the desktop experience?
Where is the pride in being the creator of the most popular Linux base?
Where is the love for the open source community which Ubuntu is built on top of and made it
what it is today?
So Chris, as long as the sad song plays, please continue to beat the drum.
Get it out of here.
Well, this is an issue.
What do you think about it?
Are we now seeing a history of sort of over promise, under delivering?
I think it's important to report on it.
I think it's important to maintain the discussion about it.
Where I draw the line though, because I think this needs to be talked about and shared and
whatnot, but I think where people need to draw the line is that if it's affecting you
on your personal desktop to the point where you draw the line in the sand and say no more,
move on to something that's not creating problems for you and then continue the discussion in
a rational adult way like what we're doing on the show.
I think that's an important way to handle it.
I think it's a healthy way to handle it.
I think that we should all make those businesses fail.
That's basically the summary of it, yeah.
Yeah, I completely agree with you.
Now, I think Danny could have a point here.
We are starting to see a bit of a trend.
Unity was sold to us as the ultimate touch interface for all and then we realized, okay,
we got to rewrite it a whole bunch of time.
Ubuntu TV was sold to us like three CESs ago and here we are, it's still not there.
I don't know if I necessarily agree with upstart and mirror.
I think the jury is still out on upstart.
It was out before system D. It solved a problem and a need and it's continued to function
well.
Some people would say swapping out something like that's a big change.
Mirror obviously not looking great at the moment, but it's already playing out okay
on mobile and I think it makes some sense there.
So we'll see.
On the desktop, I'm not convinced, but I'm willing to give it a little more time, a little
more time on mirror.
See, for me, I think that I would need to see it accomplish a specific task or some
sort of a purpose.
Perhaps it's providing an experience with steam that maybe I'm not getting with another
distro, which at this time it's not.
Let's say that does in fact happen over time.
It solves a problem for you.
Yeah, it solves some sort of problem that I've got to identify.
Then okay, fine.
I might stick with Ubuntu.
Right now, I'm using it on this other desktop simply because it's installed, it works, it's
fine, it's doing what it needs to.
It's okay.
I don't care.
I just don't get too excited about that because the fact Linux has so many choices, I choose
not to get all excited and butthurt over Ubuntu's decisions and the team that develops that.
If they want to do something stupid, hey, more power to you.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
What we are witnessing is not necessarily an Ubuntu problem.
I think this is going to happen over and over again.
I think if you look back at the history of Linux, this already has happened just in different
iterations.
This is where we get into the big picture aspect of Linux and why Linux is stronger
than any one distribution and why that actually really matters and why I actually think that
Linux users today are not taking advantage of that fact.
But before we get to that, before we kind of shift gears into our main topic today,
I want to thank our sponsor, Ting.com.
Ting is mobile that makes sense, my friends, and my mobile service provider and Matt's
mobile service provider.
That's right.
They got the new Note 3 out now, Matt.
I'm just putting that out there, just letting you know.
Oh, yeah.
Now, one of the things that I think is absolutely fantastic about Ting is how they do their
rates.
You don't have to pay into a big plan that you only use.
Say your cell phone bill is like 60 bucks a month.
Well, how do you know if you're only getting $30 of value of that?
Ting separates out your voice, your megabytes, and your messages into individual buckets
and you just pay for what you use at the end of the month.
That way, if you're not a heavy voice user one month, you don't end up paying a whole
bunch of money into a voice line that you don't need.
On top of that, it's contract free.
That's right.
No contract, no early termination fees.
You only pay for what you use.
It's a flat rate of $6 a month.
You can have as many phones on that line as you want, sharing the pooled minutes, and
then you buy your phone.
When you buy that phone, it's contract free.
You own that phone.
That's probably the top five things I love about Ting, but it gets even better from there.
If you go over to linux.ting.com, you'll save $25 off your first month or $25 off a first
device if you are not bringing a device, and they're doing something that's kind of fun.
It only goes on until the end of October.
October 31st, they're getting a little Willy Wonka up in here.
Ting has these new really cool pouches that they're shipping out devices in, and they're
reusable.
You could actually just use it to carry your recharging stuff for the car or whatever.
They're really nice devices or cases, and in these cases, they have golden tickets.
No kidding.
There's going to be three tickets that go in the cases that get sent out, and there's
going to be three digital tickets.
When you buy a device from Ting between now and October 31st, there could be a golden
ticket, and that golden ticket will get you a year of Ting service for free.
If you're already considering switching to Ting, why not do it now?
You could potentially end up with a year of service for free if you order between now
and October 31st, but those of you who are considering ordering online may be bringing
your own device, and don't worry, my friends, Ting has stashed three tickets aside for you
as well.
They'll also be giving out three tickets to anybody who does a digital order.
There's going to be digital tickets, and they'll be given to random people who go through the
bring your own device process before October 31st.
Pretty fun, pretty cool, and it's another neat way that Ting sort of makes it even more
fun to switch, and right now, I think it's better time than ever because there's a good
chance you could get a year of Ting for free.
When you combine that with the fact that they have early termination relief program, you
can get up to $75 per line off.
You just buy your phone, port your number, then submit your claim, and they'll give you
up to $75 for the early termination and the fact that you're going to get $25 off your
first device or your first month if you bring a device when you go to linux.ting.com.
My friends, it has literally never been a better time to switch to Ting.
Start saving right now.
Go use that calculator right there to calculate your savings.
I think you'll be pretty impressed.
If you ever have any problems, anything you ever need sorted out, just give them a call.
1-855-846-4389.
A real personal answer to the phone and a real personal take care of your problem.
They claim responsibility and they own that for you.
They really get it solved.
I really appreciate that.
That's so awesome, and I love the fact that for the golden ticket program, it doesn't
matter how you come into the program.
Whether or not you're bringing your own device, you can go digital, or if you actually are
purchasing a device through them, then you get a real ticket.
That's awesome.
Everybody wins.
So go over to linux.ting.com, tell Ting, thanks for supporting Linux Unplugged, and then go
get yourself some great service and a fantastic phone.
Linux.ting.com, and thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
They get a winner bell for being awesome supporters.
All right Matt, so I wanted to continue in the vein of digging through some follow-up
which will bring us to our main topic this week.
We had a really good post in the subreddit, linuxactionshow.reddit.com this week from
raccoon1215, and the post was titled, I use old, crusty Debian Stable, and I love it.
This is such a great post, I want to just read a couple of highlights to kind of kick
us off here.
He said, I was inspired by the recent discussion on Linux Unplugged and I thought I would talk
about my desktop and server distro of choice, Debian Stable, technically CrunchBang, and
why I prefer it to, say, the way of Arch doing things, i.e. bleeding edge.
You kids and your fancy new shiny gooys and your Unity and your Cinnamon with your Gnome
and your KDE, my desktop was bland, gray, and that's the way I like it.
And for reference, here's my default settings of my desktop.
It's a very nice looking, very clean looking desktop, minimal for sure.
He says it is bland, it is gray, and here's another example of it with like Conkey and
doing some awesome stuff.
Oh yeah.
I mean, it looks really nice.
It is definitely a very good looking desktop.
He goes on to say, on a separate point, I don't want my desktop and Window Manager to
change on me.
Chris brought up the example of running a system update and having Gnome update from
3.8 to 3.10.
If such a drastic change happened to me, I would panic.
I don't want that to happen.
To quote RMS, get it out of here, which is right there.
He goes on to say, yes, packages are old and they don't and won't ever get updated until
the next version of Debian, but that's a good thing.
I don't want some program I use every day to suddenly change its behavior.
It should be predictable.
I don't want the init system to suddenly change to systemd, even if it does look awesome,
until the next release cycle.
In addition to that, sometimes old packages are just better than newer ones.
Sometimes newer versions of things lose functionality.
In conclusion, if I had to sum it all up, it would be this, unplanned change is bad
and Debian understands this.
Well, I think he's finding something that works well for him and he's someone that
probably likes, well, not probably, he definitely likes his experience predictable.
He wants to wake up and know that even after an update and everything that's going on,
everything is going to look and feel as it did.
Everything is going to operate the way he expects it to.
I think that's awesome for him.
I guess so.
I totally see that.
To me, it smacks a little bit of being afraid of upstream.
People I think, I don't know.
I'm like him to a lesser degree.
Yeah, and I can see that.
I can see that.
I'm not near as extreme.
There are some things I just really want a hell of a lot.
I want to get the arch into the arch repos and see some of the latest, greatest stuff.
I do.
So, I think I called it, there's an old school way.
This was Earthy Pornstar, I just read the nick, Earthy Pornstar.
Earthy Pornstar commented that I called it the old school way or people who haven't gone
rolling haven't tried it in years, I believe were comments I recently made.
He says it's not just about updates breaking stuff, it's about general stability, compatibility
and functionality.
He goes on, and I thought this was an interesting comment, I, like all Linux desktop users,
am clearly downright insane for not using OS X as a daily driver desktop.
Yeah, Apple Inc is evil and all of that, but if we look at this from a factual, architectural
and even practical viewpoint, there is no comparison.
All the best parts of Macintosh plus BSD Unix, all highly polished, highly stable workstation
quality because obviously OS X only runs on Macs, therefore Apple can write close to 100%
of the drivers.
He goes on to say the Linux, he says, oh actually I wanted to point this out, he says, a resulting
in old school workstation stability that is downright perfection to be honest, I don't
know if I agree with that.
I wouldn't say perfection, I would say an expected experience would probably be the
kindest I could say.
Yeah, okay, good way to put it, right?
Yeah, that's a good way to put it.
His point here is that OS X has apps and it has this Unix architecture, but I think that
is true to an extent and I think we have to, even as Linux fans, have to acknowledge that
there is a really good compelling solution on the Mac side, right?
But it comes at not only a premium price that not everyone's willing to pay, but it also
comes at a limited set of options.
Basically on the Mac side, you can either do it or you can't do it, right?
True, yeah, I would say that's true because I mean in the past on my wife's Mac for example,
the adventures of trying to get HP printers to work or not work or will this update break
it?
That's not perfection.
I quite honestly get greater stability out of any one of my Linux computers than we see
on the OS X, quite honestly.
That being said, that's with drivers.
I would also say it's very boring.
It's extraordinarily boring.
You really can't do a whole ton of tweaking with it.
The only reason that I ever find myself in front of one is if I need something software
specific that I'm not getting on Linux and that would be it.
I'll always use that over using Windows because I really can't stand it.
Here's the point and this is funny because it shows you there's several different ways
to think about this because I take his last point here and I see it a completely different
way.
He says, the Linux desktop is easily still a good five years behind Windows and OS X.
Without LTS, Linux wouldn't even be in the ballpark.
So let's take the five-year thing and really look at this logically.
Factually speaking, when Windows 7 first came out and I had my mom's ton of peripherals that
I wanted to see what would work, 80 to 85% of them would not work because there were
not compatible drivers.
Fact.
Linux, all of them worked.
No, I wasn't running Linux on our computer.
Another thing, we look at wireless drivers.
Drivers specifically would be a big thing there.
Also just overall stability.
Even in Windows 8, it's more stable than it is in the past but it's not that awesome.
I think you're right in terms of drivers and kernel stability.
I think what he's talking about is because I think in this context, he's talking about
certain applications perhaps like Final Cut and Photoshop and things like that that are
just way ahead that are only available for Mac or Windows.
That's factually true but that should be stated as such, not that the platform is five years
behind but the fact that the companies that produce software for those platforms, it's
just non-existent.
That's fair.
Here's where I see the disconnect is because his argument is that the LTS Linux is out
there and LTS is canonical term but Red Hat Enterprise, SUSE Enterprise, all of these enterprise
grade distros, they are a picture of time.
They're like when we look out into space and we see planets come back into us, the reflection
of light from millions of years ago.
It does not represent the true state of the Linux desktop.
In a sense, in a way, you could argue that LTS also holds Linux back because as we are
rapidly evolving at a pace that is way beyond what commercial software evolves at, as we
are rapidly evolving, that is lost by these LTS snapshots.
That is a benefit in the enterprise and that is a benefit for folks that want Debian stable.
That is a good thing but in terms of actually pushing the envelope forward, seeing where
the innovation is in the Linux desktop, you lose it a little bit.
You lose it in the forest because you can't see it.
I think in a sense, LTS is actually doing the opposite of what his argument is.
It has a role.
It obviously has a role but I actually think for desktop users that are savvy enough, people
who are comfortable with Linux, I think using an LTS is shortchanging yourself.
I don't agree with that.
I think that it basically comes down to two happy mediums.
I would not want to be in a world where we only had an LTS because I think that would
be incredibly limiting nor would I want to be in a world where we only had rolling releases
and bleeding edge stuff either.
I think you need both because honestly, if I'm going to put one of my family members
on a Linux distro, it's going to be something long term and something I have to screw with,
quite frankly.
I don't want to roll updates for them.
I don't want them doing anything to it other than letting me manage it when I have time
and that's a long term release.
For myself, I'll probably take a bleeding edge option.
Okay, so let me jump from there and then we'll roll into mumble folks here in a sec too.
For you and I who are hardy enough and of course millions of other people who are hardy
enough to sort of tuck and roll when something happens in our rolling distribution, I think
we are benefiting Linux more so in the long run.
If we zoom out and we look at what's happening to Ubuntu, there could be an argument at least
on the desktop side.
Maybe they're about to be a shooting star on mobile or whatever the future of these
converged devices, maybe they'll come out on top as like a shooting star of that category.
That maybe is yet to be seen, but if we accept that a lot more people these days are less
satisfied with the Ubuntu desktop and that in some regards is in a decline, watching
the events around Ubuntu unfold, I believe once again is teaching us that something who
anyone who has watched Linux for a long time has probably noticed and like myself refuses
to probably fully accept that maybe all of them, at least not most of them in the grand
scheme of things, most distros die or change for the worse and yet many Linux users are
still they remain afraid of the raw Linux experience without the protection of their
distro masters.
They fear total system havoc without some bearded gatekeeper at the repo preventing
mass chaos from entering their system via a system update and they believe that only
the distros can protect them from this, the great distro masters, you know, and the thing
is Matt is four months now into the arch experiment using arch as my daily driver in production
and play and yeah, we just had Skype crash on us on an arch rig.
Is that because of arch?
I don't think so.
I think it's because Skype is crap.
Skype hasn't updated in months, but using it as my daily driver, it's taught me a really
big lesson and it's not about how elite arch is and it's not about how wikis can actually
not suck.
Those are lessons I did learn, but that's not what I'm talking about.
What I did learn is that upstream is amazing.
The near real time work that is being done is inspiring and encouraging me as the host
of the Linux action show to push on.
It is fun to watch and a joy to use and all of that is lost when you live inside this
distro box and I think there could be a case to be made that if you like me enjoy toying
with your computer more than actually playing video games and perhaps using a rolling Linux
distro, it's better for Linux and it's better for all that upstream code, it's in everyone's
best interest if we all live outside the box and we live a little closer to upstream.
If we can bear it, if we can be exposed to the bumps that come along with that.
I would agree with that.
Yeah, I think the more people that are living on the bleeding edge, the better because that
just of course as bug reports come out and things like that, it's making a better experience
so that when the next long term release comes along on another distro or whatever that is,
it's better for everybody.
It's a great ecosystem to live in.
I think that's awesome and it's something that we miss in a Windows or OS X world.
You're talking about very limited testers and what not.
I think you lose it just kind of even just living in the distro box.
I'll give you two examples that applied to me this week.
Two new apps that have rolled out, both covered by OMG Ubuntu which is ironic because you
can't really use either one of them in Ubuntu.
First is Corebird, it is a really, really, really nice Twitter client that is completely
designed for GNOME 3, minimal, does exactly what you need, has great features, has notification
support, but if you want to install it on Ubuntu, you're kind of out of luck if you're
on 13.04 because it requires GNOME 3.10.
If you want to install it on Ubuntu 13.10, then you got to go get the GNOME 3.10 PPAs,
install those first and then break your Unity installation and then install Corebird, right?
That's one app.
That's one new app that's coming out that is really interesting to follow.
That new app that's coming out, Polari, an awesome new IRC app for GNOME which again
is like IRC, totally follows the GNOME design, looks absolutely, incredibly amazing.
I have it installed right now on my Archbox, can't get it on Ubuntu.
Right, exactly.
And this is what I'm talking about where I enjoy watching these new stars be born and
as soon as I see a news article on it on my rolling distro, I go get it and I have it
installed and now I get to play with it.
And I think that – and see, you're the type of person that really values that experience.
Right.
But there are a lot of people out there that don't and a lot of people there that do.
And so I think there's going to be a balance there.
I think that as the people that really want that leading edge experience, they'll test
these apps and they'll just get better and better and better and by the time they do
roll down to an Ubuntu type distribution, the people that are wanting to remain in that
space will also be able to enjoy it.
It's kind of like paying for cable and getting your TV now versus waiting for it to end up
on Netflix.
Yeah.
It really is.
There's no right answer.
It's just I think everybody's kind of got their –
Yeah, it's interesting.
It's a good analogy.
Or it's like –
Yeah.
You know, it's funny.
It's like on Usenet Blu-ray movies of stuff like two months not even released yet will
show up on Usenet.
It's like, wow, really?
It's like you could get it –
Yeah.
Handycam.
And I don't know.
I mean, maybe I'm wrong here.
And we can ask.
I'm totally up to mumble room.
Chime in.
But I feel like if Polari and Corebird have more users using them, then those apps get
better and then we have a better chance of fighting the proprietary commercial desktops.
But when we live inside these cages where our bearded masters make sure everything's
perfect for us, we don't really push the envelope forward as fast as we could.
Your thoughts, mumble room?
Okay.
See, the thing is, since I guess I'm the only one talking here, the thing is it depends
on what your situation is, what context you're using Linux in.
If you want to take the risk of only upstream packages or you want a more stable solution
for it.
So while the upstream philosophy and the arch philosophy applies to some people, it may
not apply to other people.
So again, you have to look at your situation.
It does not actually matter what philosophy you drive your Linux box with.
It matters what that box does for you.
Finally, there are still risks to getting upstream.
And so you have to make a choice whether you want the latest and greatest and whether you
want just another, a new IRC client, or are you happy with your old one and you can take
the safe option of not breaking your desktop.
Right.
I agree.
And so I think what I'm talking about is the category of people that listen to this show.
The people who are a little more savvy, a little more comfortable.
And I would say like how many, haven't all of us seen the scenario where you have a problem
with like say X chat and you submit a bug and then it gets marked as it's not our problem,
it's downstream.
Invalid.
Yeah.
We've all seen this.
I guess if I wanted to type in and say something, when I was distro hopping, I was fine with
getting the latest and greatest on a distro.
But now anymore, I just want to install something and let it sit.
If I want a newer package of a software, I will usually go search for that Debian file
or that RPM file and get it myself rather than relying on the distributions or a repository.
That only gets you so far though, because pretty soon you run into some sort of like
Gnome 3.10 dependency or you know, you eventually require your underlying system to be current
to take advantage of the new apps.
Eventually, but I do upgrade often enough to where that shouldn't be a problem.
Like once every maybe six to eight months.
Yeah, okay.
Yeah.
Those distro snapshots in a way are a figment of our Slackware past.
Yeah, they are, I think.
I think that's exactly what it is.
Like we have security updates and functionality updates, but it's not exactly how today is
best utilized.
That's what I'm thinking.
And if I wanted to, I could on my laptop switch to the tumble read repository and get the
latest packages.
Right.
Oh yeah.
I run tumble read and I run rawhide.
Right.
It doesn't have to be Arch.
It could be rawhide.
Yeah.
It could be tumble read for sure.
I do daily Ubuntu, like for the, before you guys done your Ubuntu review, I was running
daily for a week just to make sure that I knew exactly what I was trying to get to.
I guess part of my argument might be though is when you look at distros, there's some
distros that patch kind of heavily and there's some distros that don't patch very heavily.
And that's where you starting to get into the blame game is when you have a distribution
who patches a lot.
Maybe they changed the way their whole notification system works.
And so every app that wants to use the notification system has to have some sort of tweak applied.
Right.
That's the only, that's the only thing where I kind of, I guess, I guess what I wanted
to, the point I wanted to get across is I feel like I was a person who I for a long
time believed that if we couldn't make a Ubuntu a success, it wasn't possible for Linux to
be a success, not because it wasn't good enough, but because you needed to have a corporation
behind it with a little bit of money that, you know, a company like valve could call
up.
You needed to have a community organized around it.
You needed to have a good, you needed to have a good established base with a good reputation.
And I thought, you know, there's really not another distro while there's other really
good distros and even better distros like they, none of them have all of that stuff
and are also targeted at the desktop and cloud, et cetera, et cetera.
And, and what I realized over the last four months is like Arch isn't really a distro.
It is just straight upstream with a bunch of great scripts and, and some, and some shuffling
around it.
Yeah.
It feels almost like a roll your own.
For sure.
All right.
All the other distros.
Yeah.
Right.
But what that has shown me is like just what the community itself is producing is pretty
great.
Well, the distros, all the other ones with corporate backing are pretty much server or
corporate desktop based distros like Novell and Red Hat.
Ubuntu is the only desktop, you know, distro, but the reality is they actually make their
money on cloud.
You're right.
Yeah.
Now, when you, now I was thinking when you back, back when you said notification, that's
why I stick to like the standard desktop environment, like KDE or even the GNOME 3.10.
I don't go towards Cinnamon or towards a Unity just because, you know, they're the biggest
ones out there, GNOME and KDE, or even XFCE out there, then they tend to use the standard
components for notifications and such.
Right.
libnotify.
Yeah.
See, the thing I was saying about Ubuntu is that there are still disadvantages to having
a super popular Linux distribution because there was a post in the Linux subreddit where
a man said Microsoft Word deserves to die because it captured the market.
So what I'm saying is that you need what Ubuntu has established is a monopoly.
And so that has its own disadvantages that may not be looked at in several places, meaning
if Ubuntu is, if you have one OS that is the king and it has 80 percent market share or
70 percent market share, then everybody, regardless of the OS's flaws and merits, has to develop
for that.
Right.
And so that restricts them.
That restricts the market.
I don't know if they've reached that.
I don't know if they have reached that.
And I think the thing that kind of made me think that was, and I could be, I could be
way off the mark on this, but to me the thing that kind of brought that home to me was if
Ubuntu had reached that monopoly point where you must write for Ubuntu, kind of like the
reason I put our videos on YouTube is because if you don't put them on YouTube then there's
thousands of people who won't see them and I hate it, but that's where I put them.
And there are a lot of advantages to being on YouTube, even if I have to fight them constantly.
I think that when Valve chose to create Steam OS, that was Valve making a vote of no confidence
in the long-term viability of Ubuntu on the desktop.
And the reason I say that is because if you're going to hyper-focus on making the best thing
possible, you don't really need the baggage of creating your own OS, right?
I mean, they never had to have Steam OS when Windows was around and the Mac was around.
And then it was like, I think maybe Gabe was sitting back, smoking a cigar and thinking,
man, am I going to bet the whole farm on this canonical clown show?
Or am I going to just take the great work they've done so far and create my own, you
know, direction?
Right.
And I believe that them going with Steam OS proves that they do not hold that monopoly.
Yeah, but certainly, I was thinking this whole time, like, okay, what if the canonical patch
is a kernel so much that it eventually ends up like, let's say, Android?
I think that Valve did Steam OS just because of the brand, because most people don't even
know about Linux.
Yeah, you could be right.
It's the same about Chromebooks.
Chromebooks are because Chrome is so popular and people know about it.
I agree.
Though I do think, though, if we just had a world where maybe, you know, Ubuntu's market
dominance was so clearly established that they might just say, well, they've got that
part taken care of.
See, it might be, though.
See, the thing is, Steam not putting confidence into Ubuntu might not just indicate that Ubuntu
is not as popular.
It might just indicate that Canonical is very much a clown show and they have no idea where
they're going.
It does not reflect, I think, on their popularity and dominance on the Linux desktop environment.
I disagree with that a little.
I would say that the whole thing of them taking on Steam OS might be because Ubuntu is focusing
on mobile.
They're focusing on the tablet and they're not focusing on the desktop as much.
Well, Steam, they want to focus on the desktop because that makes sense where mobile makes
no sense to Valve.
No, that's what I'm saying, actually.
I don't know.
I believe I heard somewhere where Valve wants to get into the mobile market.
Yeah, I'm still surprised they haven't.
Yeah, but see, the thing is that-
They're going to get into mobile.
They're going to go into that little thing.
I say you've got the NVIDIA shield and that, so there's definitely a gaming market for
mobile devices.
And that's Android.
Well, if they wanted to do Linux, choosing Ubuntu is not exactly choosing Linux any longer
because Ubuntu doesn't patch upstream like all the other distributions do.
They are Ubuntu and are siloed as themselves.
They can't benefit or give back to the other rest of the community.
So if they chose Ubuntu, then they would be kind of locked into Ubuntu.
But they did choose Ubuntu.
They're just tripping off the top layer.
Exactly.
See, the thing is that does not mean Ubuntu is not popular.
It just says there are other factors.
I'm saying unless you're using something like Unity, I don't think you're locked into Ubuntu
just yet.
But again, like I said, the whole lock into Unity, Ubuntu thing with Unity, that's why
I use KDE because that's pretty universal across whatever distro I use.
Well, they're even saying screw Kubuntu, screw Zubuntu, screw Ubuntu, they're themselves.
They don't want to help them with their other derivatives.
What Ubuntu does quite well is it takes Debian testing and freezes it.
So it gives you a fairly up-to-date platform to work with.
No, Debian is old.
It's stable.
It rocks.
No, that's what Ubuntu does.
It takes Debian testing, freezes it for six months, and then you can work on it.
So you get quite an up-to-date platform that's stable.
Debian's testing is also stable, too.
It's not like a bleeding heads distro.
But it's constantly changing.
All right.
Okay.
So I want to change the conversation for a second.
I want to play a mental exercise, and I'm going to toss it to Matt first, and then I'll
toss it to the mumble room.
I'm not saying it's going to happen.
I mean, Ubuntu still could pull it out.
You never know.
But let's say, well, fast forward three years down the road, SteamOS has been shipped for
a year, all the other distros have gotten better at what they do, and Ubuntu has continued
to decline.
Who is the new dominant distro?
What do you think, Matt?
What is the distro that pulls ahead, and why?
As much as I hate to admit it, and as much as I want to say, oh, it's going to be Fedora,
or, oh, it's going to be OpenSUSE.
Oh, I thought you would say Fedora, actually.
No, I can't.
I mean, realistically, if I'm looking at Ubuntu's targeting of new users, I hate to admit it,
and yes, I'm not a fan, but I'm going to say Linux Mint, because they do have their
Debian stuff on the back burner for just such an occasion.
If Ubuntu does a poo-poo, they're going to go with their Debian release, and that's what
they're going to do.
And I think that they have enough stuff going on internalized that they could make that
switch work.
They're not ready yet.
Would it be better for everybody, though, if it was like Mangero or Antegros, like somebody
that...
Oh, it would be awesome, but I think that we...
People have to remember, part of why Linux works is because it is not, the kernel is
not a democracy.
What about elementary OS?
Elementary OS, again, you got these community-based distributions, that's great, but they come
and go, quite honestly.
I've seen a lot of community distros come and go, and at least with a corporate-backed
distribution, as much as I don't like a lot of them, you have something identifiable.
You can spot, okay, it looks like they're going to go downhill, or it looks like they're
going to pull the plug.
Okay, all right, but could the problem with Mint be, as much as I have respect for Clem
and all that he's done and all he continues to do, if Clem gets really super burned out,
what happens to Mint?
I mean, you've got one guy, right, whereas OpenSUSE is an entire company, there's an
entire team, you know, people come and go, right, and Fedora has got the backing of Red
Hat.
You've got these, Mint and elementary OS, they all suffer from a very, very short bench.
No, that's true, but here's the problem, though, is that you have to look at...
Fedora doesn't target users in any universe.
OpenSUSE, again, great distribution for the enterprise, not for the new user.
It's just not.
The tools provided are not targeting grandma.
Linux Mint is.
That does not mean in its current state that they don't still have some of those community
issues, but I see enough interest, resources, and I mean financial resources being dumped
in their general direction to where I think at some point, if Ubuntu did go south, I could
see some sort of a structure stepping in or perhaps even being formed around it.
I think that...
Okay, Mumble Room, let me ask you this question and whoever wants to chime in, answer it.
So I think there's a couple of ways we could take this.
I want to ask you guys, is it possible we could have a three or four year, three years
down the road, three years down the road, Manjaro continues to evolve and they've really
got something where they've got a good combination of up-to-date packages, but certain snapshotting
of key components to make things stable.
Could Manjaro pull ahead as a lead distro candidate?
I don't think Manjaro has the corporate backing or the money behind them to make that happen.
It's completely community and granted Mint is completely community too, but I mean their
sponsorship is up the wazoo.
It is.
Yeah.
That's almost better, isn't it?
Well, the thing with Ubuntu, Ubuntu isn't brilliant, but what Ubuntu is extremely good
at is marketing.
I don't think there's another distro that is as good at marketing as Ubuntu is.
Elementary got close with their countdown, but I agree.
When you search for past stuff, Canonical can capture the headlines, especially for
the Edge campaign, they captured the headlines.
Yeah.
They're a PR machine.
They can do marketing like no one else.
They're really good at it.
I was thinking, Mint I think would probably pull out front, but I got a funny feeling
that Kubuntu might do quite well because that's got quite a lot of backing.
That I like.
Yeah.
That I would like.
I see.
I can see that.
What is... Kubuntu has a new backing.
Yeah.
They have a corporate sponsor now.
Kubuntu's got blue systems.
Yeah.
That's a big deal.
It's a completely separate operating system now.
I know it's still based on Ubuntu, but the KDE fellows have very little...
Right.
There's some heat there as well.
They're leveraging the... Kubuntu will continue to leverage the big advances we're going to
see in QT and the big adoption we're going to see in QT because of mobile.
That's the other thing about... That could play a big part in three years is as mobile
continues to influence the direction of Linux, QT is going to continue to become a more and
more dominant framework that people use.
I wouldn't be surprised if KDE distros do pull ahead because of that, right?
Yeah.
One thing-
Didn't that say that the default is king?
Right.
Yeah.
How is Kubuntu default?
It may be.
Well, they have a huge corporate sponsor in blue systems, but for blue systems, I think
that's a means to an end because their goal is for Netrunner, which is a derivative of
Kubuntu.
They live and die with Kubuntu.
If anything, my choice would be SUSE.
Because it's got a good mix of corporate backing and community or what?
Yes, and they can PR the hell out of themselves.
Yeah.
You know what?
The SUSE camp is really good at PR outreach.
They've got support, but they're not up to the snuff yet.
Well, I mean, think about it like Matt, before a SUSE release, you and I usually get an email
from somebody at the team who tells us what's new.
They usually send us pre-release ISO links for us to download so that way we can get
it before the mirrors get smashed and they'll give us a chance for our review.
That stuff's-
And the other thing-
But for their audience, I would say so.
But for the people that have Ubuntu targets, not even close.
No, I agree.
Yeah.
For us, oh yeah.
For geeks, they're awesome.
God, they're great.
They're all over the place.
Absolutely.
It's about not just a single thing.
It's going to be a combination of things.
It's going to be good PR.
It's going to be low barrier to entry, like do you need to know anything about Linux to
get into it?
Your grandmas, your lifetime Windows users and things like that, if it isn't simple for
them to just pop in a disk, install it, and then it's easy for them to understand.
I think OpenSUSE, maybe not all of us like it, but OpenSUSE has Yast, and when you're
a Windows user, you want the control panel.
You want to be able to bring up the control panel and go add, remove software, detect
your hardware.
Well, I mean, that's what Yast does.
And I'm not saying that SUSE couldn't pull it off.
I'm not saying that at all.
I'm just saying we're focusing on, well, it's this, we'll know it's this, we'll know it's
this.
And it's really just a combination of things.
Right now Ubuntu just has a stranglehold on that.
But SUSE has all the combinations.
They have the corporate backing.
They have the build service, which is bringing in a whole bunch of new software.
They have the gallery and ladies and gentlemen, probably the number one thing for me right
now, they have Tumbleweed.
So you can also be rolling, right?
I mean, it seems to me like OpenSUSE has got a pretty good collection of a lot of the things
I like.
But the problem is at the end of the day, I can't imagine using Linux now without Pacman.
Yeah.
So that's my thing.
But OpenSUSE is definitely my fallback.
Yeah, but that's going to be your advanced users.
Yeah.
They have Greg.
He's straight up next in line to Linus.
He's a straight up kernel.
He's our kernel master.
Oh yeah.
And he's at SUSE.
Oh yeah, for sure.
They can support the hell out of SUSE for the user if need be.
I'm going to use the M word here.
But one thing SUSE has backing it too is an agreement with Microsoft.
Oh yeah, they do.
Yeah.
In fact, they're OpenSUSE.
They have an OpenSUSE week or they have like a SUSE week coming up, you know, like a conference
and Microsoft's one of the top sponsors.
I completely forgot about their enterprise desktop.
Right.
And I have to say one of my favorite things about OpenSUSE would be the build service
that people could set their software on.
Right.
I'm going to chuck something out there.
How about an Android Chrome OS hybrid?
I mean, if Google actually ends up sort of producing that where you can run Android apps.
I feel like Google has too much skin in the game to be a trusted platform provider like
that.
My system controlled by Java.
I don't think they're going to do that.
It's Java script.
It's different.
No, but Android is Java.
It would succeed because of Google, but it wouldn't be good.
Hm.
Well, I mean, if we're talking a hybrid that works the same way that Ubuntu's, quote,
convergence would, the Android part would still be Java, but the Chrome OS part would
not.
There has to be no Android Java.
It's not Java.
It's JavaScript.
Like car is like...
Chrome OS is JavaScript.
It's too complicated.
Android is Java.
Yep.
Yes.
All right.
Well, now we're going down the Android path.
We're going to close out, but I just leave you with this.
I wanted to make the case that if you have the stomach for it, and there's no judgment
if you don't have the stomach for it, but if you have the stomach for it, maybe consider
going with one of the rolling releases from whichever distro provides it just to kind
of...
It is really exciting to be on the edge and see things that are coming out that like core
Bird and Polari that are so cool and to play with them and you know how great it is to
get Gnome 3.10.
I mean, the Gnome project, let's be honest, it has been really, really hard to use Gnome
for a while and with Gnome 3.8, it got there and Gnome 3.10, they made it even better and
Gnome 3.10.1 is really looking good.
I look at this and I go, this is it.
We're getting there again and KDE 4 series, man, they are just...
I love their plan to make KDE 4 just rock solid where they work on 5.
Both Gnome 3 and KDE 4, I feel like, are once again getting to that point we were before
we had the big upset, before we killed Gnome 2 and moved to Gnome 3.
I feel like we're getting back to that...
We're not there just yet, but we are probably within one or two releases to being back to
that level of awesomeness and it's got nothing to do with any particular distribution and
that's what's so awesome about it.
There you go.
All right.
So again, I think at the end of the day, it's about what suits you best.
But yes, Ars does have a very good advantage on this, but again, what suits you best?
Because Gnome and all the other upstream packages are working, they're in beta, they're in alpha
and they're still working.
If they break, then that's where the trouble starts and they don't, which is a good thing,
but if they do, then you have to deal with it.
That's the cost you pay.
But I feel like it's helping because I fully figure that if that happens, then I'll submit
the bug thing, I'll watch the bug report and I'll participate in that part because that's
what I can do, right?
I can either donate money, but I'm too broke to do that, so I'm going to donate my time
to submit bug reports and then plus for me, it also works out, I can talk about it on
the show and stuff like that, but I think it's an interesting position for us to be
in to maybe not have a direct influence on the future of our desktop, but at least help
push it in the right direction as a user, which is way more, which is just so more empowering
than you get on Windows and Mac and when we go back to that email where you said, well,
the Mac is great for this and that, it's like these number one things, being tuned into
the open source community, being able to have an impact on the desktop, being able to choose
these things where we can move around, those are indispensable features for me that only
Linux provides, the Mac can, no matter what Apple ships in the next version of Mac OS
10, they will never be able to ship that, they can't, right?
That's true, although Apple is a master of copying various Ubuntu features and I could
make a list for the person to send in the email if they'd like that.
Yeah, I think the copying goes both ways in some cases, but yeah.
But it's very visual up front, front and center experiences that they copy, not back in.
Now they just need to copy the App Store a little more and they'll really have something.
All right, Mumble Room, well thanks guys, you guys were great today and I'm gonna wrap
it up with an email from G H, he wanted to write in in defense of KDE.
He says, Chris and Matt, how contradictory is it for people to leave Windows or Apple
because they're tired of their intrinsic limitations?
Only then to move to Linux and choose the most limiting working environments like GNOME
or Unity.
Wouldn't it be more logical to move to an environment, say, KDE, that gives you the
most options to configure in any way you want?
Spock would nod in agreement.
For me, choosing between GNOME and Unity and say the others versus KDE is like choosing
for the same price of zero dollars between an F-150 and a sovereign class enterprise.
And guys, you're choosing the truck because you find the spaceship too complicated to
use and it has too many options and the truck can still take you places and has technology
I can understand and use without too much effort.
I assure you that if an option to choose was real, you'd pick the enterprise even if it
took you the rest of your life to figure it out.
Your friend, G H.
Well, I heard from Mavura and she was very clear in saying, Captain, the communications
are not working because false audio doesn't play well with the KDE sound system.
So once I get my communications up on the Starship, but the radio in my truck seems
to work pretty well.
I also would point out, I would also point out that Gene Roddenberry went to great pains
to work with his designers to make sure that the enterprise was clean and streamlined because
Gene believed that technology had become so perfected that to truly enhance human life,
it would be natural and comfortable to use.
I'm just pointing that out.
So however that is natural and comfortable for you is how you should use it, right Matt?
That's right.
Who needs to hear anything with headphones?
That's so GNOME.
Yeah, that's for GNOME users, whatever, whatever.
I guess if I want to have a modern sound experience, I do need false audio.
I don't want some antiquated poppy back and forth crap that every other, yeah, no.
Matt, I have in my hot little hand, right here, my Synology box that arrived, the Disk
Station Synology, and as experienced, running Linux, supports iSCSI file servers, backup,
surveillance cams.
It's the DS412+.
I think we'll do a review this Sunday on the Linux Action Show.
Oh, nice.
It has four, four terabyte drives in it, running Linux.
All right everyone, well thank you for joining us for Linux Unplugged.
Don't forget we're live on Tuesdays at 2 p.m. and you can email us by hitting the contact
link at the top of our website.
We'd love to have you.
Also check out our subreddit over at linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
All right everyone, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Hey Matt, I'll see you on Sunday.
Sounds good, see you then.
All right everyone, thank you, and we'll see you right back here on Tuesday.