I think, Kev, the reason Wimpy's not here is because we did our time change last weekend, and you do yours next week.
Yeah, oh boy. Oh boy.
Okay, what's happening, Wes? Will you break it down? We're falling...
I don't know, Chris. How can I know? This is an arcane system. It makes no sense.
Hold on, are you serious? You don't know?
Okay, we're falling back.
Does that mean it gets darker earlier or lighter earlier?
Dammit, just tell me which one it is, Wes.
This is too much fun.
No, come on, Wes! I've been trying to figure this out for...
It gets darker earlier.
Okay, thank you. Okay, I've been trying to figure this out for two days.
Yeah, that also gets lighter earlier.
So, you know, it's already... this is a problem. This is a real problem. It already gets dark way too early.
And I gotta be honest with you guys, I start getting sleepy as soon as it gets dark.
Oh, I know. It's like, well, eight o'clock, I guess it's bedtime.
Yeah, it is a big problem. It is a...
I screw getting lighter earlier. Screw that. I don't need it to get lighter earlier.
Then I just feel pressure to wake up earlier.
Well, and sometimes, as soon as it's... I do, actually. I usually get up around 530. It's usually when I'm up.
I like X-Metal's point here.
What is that?
Maybe J.B. Time should just be agnostic.
Just make UTC the thing you've pinned to.
All the best places use UTC.
We're on UTC now.
Hello, Wendy!
Hello.
Hey, do you want...
I've just been caught out by TimeMath. I'm very sorry.
Yes, we were kind of thinking that might be the case.
I just wanted to do a little, when we get into the show, a little Ubuntu Mate 15.10 yak-a-yak, if you would, with us.
I think that'd be very nice.
Well, that'd be delightful. I'll look forward to it.
And somehow I'm driving all the way to Liverpool in a couple of days' time. I mean, how did this happen?
Oh, by the way, who's calling shotgun? I think Mark should sit in the front and I'll sit in the back so I can write my presentation.
All-time shotgun.
Sure, sure, sure. You can do shotgun to Laura's and then sit in the back.
No, I want to sit in the back. I want to sit in the back the whole time so that you're my chauffeur all the way to Liverpool.
Yeah.
I don't want to have to sit with the workers.
Let me work this out. Let me work this out. I'm just going to extrapolate here.
Would you like me to wear leather driving gloves and a peaked cap?
Wear whatever the hell you like.
We're playing dress-up, don't mind.
You just want to look like Miss Daisy in the back of my car, is that right?
Only on the weekends.
All I heard was leather.
Oh, boy.
Oh, hello, Chris.
I've decided I'm going to move. I've got to move somewhere where it's sunny. Where can I go where it's sunnier right now? Where do I got to go?
Australia.
Australia?
Sunnyvale.
That's what I was thinking, Australia.
Where it's sunny right now.
Yeah.
Six months of sun in the South Pole.
Yeah, I could do that, yeah. Then I could be more productive. Then I could be more productive. That's what I was thinking.
You're looking at a talk show that's ready.
It is nice, sunny, and 70 degrees out.
Where are you?
I got to go. That's ridiculous.
Looks familiar. He's yelling at me in IRC.
What?
I live in Texas, man, and it's sunny all day from 6 a.m. to 9 p.m.
Well, it would be 9 p.m. still, really, because the thing is I can feel my productivity is going to start falling off.
It's time to hibernate soon.
Well, because our time zone change is going to make it darker sooner, and something with me, I think it's probably because I don't get good sleep or something.
As soon as it starts getting dark or whatever, I'm an old man. As soon as it starts getting dark, I start falling asleep.
I start getting tired. My energy drops way off.
It's the release of melatonin that does that.
I know. I'm 33. I know. I mean, I'm not actually that old, but I don't know what it is.
It's been for the last two years.
I remember when I was 33.
Now, listen. You mock. You mock, but it is so bad. I thought there was something wrong with me.
Well, there might be. Don't discount me.
Okay. All right. Because for the last couple of years...
We had a horse and a trap when I was 33.
For the last couple of years, I was like, why am I falling asleep at like 6 o'clock, 6.30 at night?
What is wrong with me?
And then as it started getting lighter out, I started staying up later.
And then I started staying up later.
And then I'm up at 11 o'clock at night, and I'm feeling just fine.
And in the middle of summer, I'm like, oh, because there's sunlight.
And then as soon as it starts getting...
You guys, I'm starting to get tired around 7.30 when the sun set.
It is ridiculous.
So basically, I've got from 5.30...
From about really 6... Well, really, who's going to get out of the house?
So from about 7.30 a.m. to about 7 o'clock p.m., that's my window of opportunity right there to do anything.
And if it doesn't get done in that time period, it's not getting done.
We need to get you some nice solar temperature lights in your rover.
The truth is, I just got too much work. I need to work till 11 o'clock.
That's how my life is structured.
I have a job that expects me to be available till 11, and I can't make it past 7.30.
Actually, 8.30, really.
Yeah, so I tell you, maybe I'll get one of those satellites.
Yeah, there you go.
You would think being in a studio full of lights...
The ones up in a constellation are the ones attached to the side of your house.
No, like, you know, those seasonal affective disorder lights that, like, give you...
I've got Hughes lights.
This is not as cool as I thought it would be.
No, in fact, one of the things that's really kind of neat with these Hughes lights is, check this out.
Now, Wes, tell me this doesn't actually feel a little bit different.
Tell me you don't notice a little difference when I do this.
I'm going to hit the button here. It's called Energize.
Ooh, suddenly I'm awake, alert, ready for a podcast.
It does feel a little more like...look, don't you feel energized?
Yeah, this is a great feeling.
I didn't hear the energize sound.
All right, so here's the difference.
All right, so here's before right here, right?
See, there's before, and here's after.
Boom.
Now I need to open a browser.
Yeah, you do, you do. See, before...
Hang on, hang on.
That's kind of boring, right? It's kind of sleepy.
Sad, sleepy Chris.
Yeah.
Does that only work with a cell phone?
All right, go on, go on, do it again, do it again.
Okay, so here's sleepy mode.
This is what we're going to start the show with.
Now here is energize mode. Boom.
Boom. You see that? Big difference, big difference.
It basically...and I have other modes too, like...
Oh, right, okay.
Here's concentrate, which I don't like as much.
Oh, that's kind of intense.
Yeah, here's sunset.
Yeah, now it just got warm in here, didn't it?
Day is done.
This is Greece.
Oh, it's green. That's weird.
God, I can actually see you, Chris.
This is unnatural. I don't normally do that.
Sorry, there, that's better.
I think it's fixed.
Put the curtain back up. Yeah, that sounds good.
All right.
So what does Philips Hues run on?
Just a mobile phone app or...?
Well, no, actually...
Actually, they have...
They even have, like, a Python API for it.
Like, pretty much anything.
There's all kinds of things you can use to set it,
but the consumer out-of-the-box expectation is a mobile device.
Oh, I see.
So do you have to firmware update your lights?
Not the lights themselves, but the controller, yeah.
I don't know if it was the hues,
but I saw Matthew Garrett talking about
how one of the lights he has has Netcat on it,
which is pretty disturbing.
I don't know about these.
I mean, it does have a little controller,
and it does need updates from time to time.
You know, they're pretty obvious for a studio use.
Having color control over your lights is pretty obvious.
Without you having to go fiddle with the gels?
You know, I was talking to Benjamin Karenza.
Did I say his name?
Karenza?
Karenza.
Karenza, right.
That's right, Benjamin Karenza, thank you.
And he was talking about how you could tie in
his Glucosio app,
which checks for, like, your blood sugar levels and whatnot,
with hues lights
to change the light of the hues
depending on your blood sugar.
Karenza, yeah.
We just need to record you saying it correct once,
and you can just have that as a clip ready to go.
I know! I've got a frickin' soundboard!
And also, whilst you're on form there
with correct pronunciation, go on,
do un-ter-gos just once.
Un-ter-gos.
You gave it!
Creative commons, everyone.
Creative commons!
I've never installed gnu-slash-lux.
I just need to replace all these Richard Stallman clips
with me saying things correctly.
That's all I need to do, and that'll solve the problem.
This is
Linux Unplugged, episode 116
for October 27th, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly
Linux talk show that's ready to
head out and find the sunshine.
My name is Chris. My name is Wes.
I'm just saying I get sleepy in the fall, Wes.
That's all I'm saying. I do, too. Maybe after this
we'll take a nap. Actually,
you did bring us Red Bulls before the show.
I'm doing my part. I'm doing my part. We gotta have
a show somehow. It's been a long time since I've had Red
Bull, too, so when you crack it open, it's got that
distinct Red Bull smell.
Yes, it does. But we are well caffeinated
for today's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We're gonna get into, well, a few things.
First of all, we're gonna chat with Wimpy
about some of the new things in Ubuntu Mate
15.10. I'm looking forward to that.
Big win for the EFF that benefits
Linux users. We're gonna chat about that.
Why Intel x86 platform
is gonna be, just basically,
we gotta write it off. We gotta write it off.
We're done. I love me some x86 CPUs.
We gotta write them off, you guys. You think I'm kidding?
Actually, a really, really compelling
report just came out on why we have to do that and why Linux
users are in the best position to take advantage of that.
It's from the guy who created Cube OS.
And then later on after that,
we're gonna, right here,
right now, we're gonna admit
that Richard Stallman was right. In what may become
a reoccurring segment at this point,
he nailed it. RMS nailed it.
This week, a judge declared that
because an iOS user does
not own their software,
Apple can be legally compelled to unlock
the device. Because,
by Apple's very own EULA, that user
doesn't own their device. They don't own
their device. Apple owns their device. The OS
that runs on their device. And so because of that,
Apple has to unlock it.
Wow, is that not a huge
red flag, and exactly what Richard Stallman
warned us about, and exactly something
that Linux users should be thinking about.
And then after all of that,
some really sleek new
hardware could be coming out for Linux users.
I believe, now I've been working
on this. I believe it's pronounced
YaoMei.
Sounds good, Chris. Damn it, Wes.
YaoMei. And they have something really
interesting up their sleeves. So before we get into
all of that, let's bring in the Mumble Room. Time
appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Good morning.
Hello. Hello.
Hi. Hi. Hi. So,
you guys may or may not recall, a couple
of weeks ago, we played
the Linux Foundation's The World Without
Linux episode. Let's
play their second one that just came out, and
then we're going to play Critics.
So we're going to mystery science this thing. You ready?
So here it is, The World Without Linux
episode number two, by the way, with a
real serious guitar intro.
Alright.
Road trips are the best, but
I think we are totally lost.
Don't fret, dude. I brought a trusty map.
Dude. So, a map.
All I have to do is convert inches into
miles and cross-reference our perceived location
with the mile markers on the road.
Uh, my bad.
Map goes out the window. Don't worry.
As a backup, I printed out directions.
These two aren't going to make it.
Broken up by the end of the series.
You take a left on...
flight right on... right.
Now... What in the world are you saying?
Sorry. The printer cut off the directions
on the side. Ah, MapQuest.
I hope you never, ever go
away.
Okay, well, I think U-turn.
Wait, U-turn? I was supposed to make it U-turn?
No, U-turn. Wait, are you saying
U-turn or you should turn?
Right. Are you saying right as
correct or turn right?
Stop. Wait, are you saying stop it
or stop the car?
A world without Linux
would mean a world without direction.
We are
so lost.
When do you think we'll get there?
Alright, let's see. No, I'm going to do this. Okay, so if a train leaves New York
at three o'clock. Okay, wait. Carry the one.
You want miles, not kilometers, right?
Okay, the way it looks to me, we're going to be there by...
Halloween.
A world without Linux is hard to imagine.
Thanks to the hundreds of thousands of
individuals and companies who support Linux,
so we don't have to.
Learn more and help support Linux
today.
Wait, that sign says Bermuda Triangle Street
ahead. Finally, some good news.
Oh, I know, right?
Sounds tropical.
Oh, hashtag world without Linux.
So what do you think, Wes?
Are you impressed by the world without Linux
series so far? There really wasn't very much
of Linux in it, so I guess that's good.
You know... Chris.
Yes, yeah, go ahead, Buffy.
Is this a cultural difference
between you guys and us, or is that
just not funny in any
way shape or form?
No, I think you're right there, Buffy.
It's pretty much not funny, Buffy. Not only is
it not funny, but I don't get the premise.
Like, if she has printed out directions,
what did she print them from?
Probably the Internet, and then he references MapQuest.
Which is probably running Linux.
And I think the fundamental, and maybe I'm overthinking this, but I think the other
fundamental thing is like, it sort of assumes
that something wouldn't come up in its place, like
a BSD or something like that. I love the
idea, though, and I love the basic
idea that they're trying to convey. That's the
part I should say. I love that. I love the idea
they're trying to convey is Linux makes the world
easier in a way you don't even realize.
Spotlighting how it builds all the common infrastructure.
Do you think maybe these
promotions
are not aimed at us?
Yeah, exactly. Yeah, exactly. Exactly correct.
Do you think this is more suitable for my
mum when I want to explain what Linux
is and what it's done for the world?
I do think so. I think it's kind of fun.
I'm glad they're putting it out there, and
you know, I've noticed that the first episode
did get a little bit of attention. Yeah, it did.
I think if I
showed this to my mum, she'd say,
that's nice, dear, and that
would be it. Yeah,
there's an element of that as well.
It didn't make a big connection to
the part Linux plays, really.
No. No, I guess you have to...
There's a huge amount that goes into providing the real-time
directions. You kind of have to infer that Linux would
be providing solutions for all those things
but if you don't know anything about Linux...
Debbie Downer and all that, but it just
seems like a complete waste of time.
The other
question that has to be asked is
is that being created under Linux?
Yeah, right, exactly. I don't think it is.
Was that contracted for a designer
using a Mac? Yeah.
I don't know, so I'm torn.
Part of me really likes them getting the word out, and
part of me likes the idea of sort of showing how Linux
has made our modern lives easier, but part of me
thinks it's a little off-tone
because you have to kind of know how Linux fills in
the gaps in order to get it in the first place, and if you know how
Linux fills in the gaps, it's not resonating with you.
And number two is... I probably think it was
probably made on a Mac.
My thoughts. Hey, you know what?
Speaking of things that are probably not made on Macs,
OggCamp 15 this weekend!
October 31st and
November 1st in Liverpool,
which is a little
bit of a commute from here. Just a little bit of a commute.
So I don't think I'll be making it, but I bet a few
folks in the... I've got a boat and everything. I know, I could.
Put the rover.
Yeah, just put the rover on a ferry and call it good.
Put some pontoons on it. What else
do I need? So anybody want to
chat about OggCamp and kind of tell us what to expect
if people are in the area? Maybe they could make it.
Go ahead. Yeah, so
this is, I don't know,
like the eighth, seventh one?
I've lost count.
And something like that.
And we do them every year.
They're community-run events.
It's an unconference,
and we've moved around the country a few times.
We've run them in Liverpool a few times because
one of the organisers lives near there,
and we've got a really great deal on a venue.
It's at Liverpool John Moores University.
31st of October,
1st of November, so that's this weekend as we're
recording.
And people come along. It's not necessarily
a Linux or open source
or FOSS conference.
It's free culture,
open hardware hacking.
There's some Linux people there.
I bet there's a fair amount of Linux people there.
Yeah, there is.
But it's not
distro-specific, so while
Ubuntu is one of the sponsors, Fedora
is another sponsor, and
Martin can tell you one of the other
sponsors in a minute.
Yeah, we have a bunch of sponsors who
help fund the event, but the key thing is it's free
to attend, so you can
buy a ticket if you want to,
if you want to pay and donate a little bit that
helps run the event,
or you can just have a ticket for free.
We don't differentiate.
That's a cool system.
But the thing is
most years, the years when we started
doing this community funded,
it turns out that the community
turned out to be one of the biggest
sponsors voluntarily.
So people just voluntarily
gave £5, £10, whatever they could,
and that was
comparable or higher than
the corporate sponsorships we got
from big name
brands, which I thought was really nice and really
shows off the way that the conference runs.
And if people want to come along, come along to
Liverpool John Moores University.
If you go to ogcamp.org,
you'll find out all the details, the schedule, and
if you've got something to talk about, bring that along
and do a long form talk
or we've got lightning talks as well.
Cool. That's exactly
the kind of event
that I think is really in that sweet spot. So that
sounds really cool. Ogcamp.org, and I'd love
it if you guys showed up and told us
a little about how it went next week. So Wimpy,
you had a little deets on one of the
potential sponsors here. Is this the one
listed here at the bottom of the page?
No, at the top of the page.
So Entroware, who
are the Platinum sponsor this year,
they are also
a hardware partner
for Ubuntu Mate. Right, right.
So Entroware
is sort of the UK's answer to
System76. So if you want a
computer that is designed
to run Linux, then
Entroware is the place that you go.
And at Ogcamp this year,
they're the Platinum sponsor, I think the only Platinum
sponsor. They're going to be
showing off their new Skylake
equipped systems
at the event. They've also
donated one of their
new as yet unreleased models
to the raffle. So there's a £600
laptop up for grabs
in the raffle, and
I can exclusively
reveal that Entroware are also
a Valve partner, and they will be
showing off their Steam Machine at
this year's Ogcamp, and so you can come along
and have a play with Entroware's
Steam Machine. So yeah. That's exciting.
And this is great
for me personally, because I know these
people via email
and Telegram and what have you, but I've
never met them in person, so this is an opportunity
for me to meet the
guys at Entroware for the first time.
So this is a perfect
example of what Entroware's all about. It's about
bringing people together from the
community to have a chat,
have a meal, and have
some fun, and do
good things. Really cool.
I'm glad that they're doing that. And
Ogcamp.org is
now, is there any chance at any
point that this thing would ever
be live streamed?
We've recorded
talks in
the past, and in fact we've
had some people record
talks and send them to us.
One notable one was
Stephen Fry,
who sent us a talk that we
played to the audience at
Ogcamp a few years ago, which
was really nice, and he talked about Software Freedom and
GNU and all that good stuff.
We tend to not live stream
because we just
don't have enough people and
infrastructure and stuff to do it.
You know what would be amazing? You know what would be an amazing goal?
It's probably impossible, but how cool would it be
for Ogcamp 16 if Jupyter Broadcasting could go
and we could live stream it for you?
That would be amazing.
Put that in the budget, Chris.
I just gotta take care of a few things.
I just would love to.
That's not a bad idea, actually.
It's a really great idea, and
I know of at least
half a dozen podcasters in the UK that
could help with your accommodation whilst you're out.
That would be fun. That would be a lot of fun.
Well, let's talk more. I think that'd be really cool.
Alright, so
Wimpy, while we're talking about Ubuntu Mate
too, guess what? As the part of the big release,
all the big 15.10 releases came out,
and the one that we follow really closely on
the show is Ubuntu Mate Edition.
15.10 is out, and
I like the press kit page that was put together,
and it looks like a ton of stuff.
Obviously, the really big feature is
Mate Desktop 1.10.
Also, the new...
I know that you worked really hard on the new welcome screen,
so, Wimpy, where do you want to start with some of
the new stuff that's in Ubuntu Mate, because it looks like
a killer release.
Well, I think so, but then I'm
biased, aren't I?
Well, I think... I mean, I'm telling you realistically,
I mean, one of the reasons people might
ask and wonder why do I follow it closely
on this podcast, why don't I follow Kubuntu
or Zubuntu,
which has been around for longer,
because, honestly, to me,
I feel like I've been watching a lot of different
flavors for a long time, a lot of different
distributions for a really, really long time,
and there is really some
great things you're doing here, so I think this is one
of the standouts, and so that's why I like to cover here
on the show.
I'm biased as well. I think it really is
a fantastic desktop for anybody that
wants to game under Linux
because the Mate desktop has very
low overhead, but you're getting a very high-quality,
very modern-looking desktop, or anybody that just
wants a very simple, straightforward desktop that
works the way they expect that has low resource
usage. But still looks really good. Yeah.
And it's friendly to use. It's very friendly to use.
So I'm biased as well.
Well, thank you very much for the kind words.
That's very gracious of you.
Yeah, so we've got the
Mate Desktop 1.10, and you
touched on the Steam stuff there.
So there's a couple of things
where the planets have aligned there.
I think
Foronix either today or yesterday
published an article about the different
desktop environments and their performance
with running games
under Linux. And Mate was up there
in the top couple
of desktops for sort of gaming
performance. It makes sense.
And then you marry that with
the Ubuntu 15.10 base,
which of course has got Steam
Controller support out of
the box. And then what
we've done with Ubuntu Mate
Welcome, which has got a one-click
installer for Steam.
And you have an environment
that can, with one
click, be your desktop
gaming environment. So
yeah, there's a few things that
come together in a very sort of last minute
timely fashion. But you know,
it's nice to see all of those
things being pulled together.
But I suppose Ubuntu Mate Welcome
is more than people
realize. I see people sort of
immediately hitting close because
these sort of welcome screens
traditionally have been a bit anemic.
You know, just a bunch of links
to websites and Ubuntu
Mate Welcome is not that.
It actually does things.
You know, it gives you some help
through the initial post
install configuration
and can install,
not right now, definitely for
16.04, but now
at least a good proportion of
the software you would want to install on a
computer. You know, if you've used a computer
regardless of operating system,
you're probably familiar with things
like Dropbox and Google Chrome
or Spider
Oak 1 or a whole heap of other things.
And Ubuntu Mate
Welcome's got one click installers for
all of those and many others besides.
And we'll expand on that
selection slightly, not
overly, maybe about
20 titles or so in the next
release just to sort of make that
the place you can go
once you've installed. And also it's asynchronous.
I don't think anyone's picked up
on this, but you can go down that
link, that list and hit install, install,
install, install. Oh, I love that. That's wonderful.
Thank you for that. So
is this also sort of
a...
Is this sort of an answer to
the software center that isn't a software
center? It isn't an app store. It's
almost something better because
it's actually more in line with
what users actually need.
Every single time I give someone a new Linux desktop
and it baffles
me to this day,
the hugest concept gap that they have
is how to acquire new software.
Definitely. Because in their minds, I gave
just this, just
Monday, I gave somebody a new Linux laptop
and his first thought was
he wanted to go download Scrivener for the writing month
that's coming up. Download,
he just went to Scrivener's website
and immediately started looking for a download link
and a download in exe. And it
just does not register
at all how it should be done. And I think
so an app store is actually too much.
It is overshoot.
They have
a category of applications they just
want to get up and running with pretty quickly
and then they pretty much never really go
back and change it again.
Most people, that's what they're doing. They're using the computer
to use these applications. That few functions, right?
If you nail it with the welcome screen,
you almost negate the
need to have a really well robust
app store. I mean, it doesn't
completely replace it, but for
a good decent chunk of users,
it negates the need as much.
Yeah, for a good chunk of people
it certainly fills a need.
And that's what it's designed to do.
So,
Matt Hartley actually helped with the
software selection in Ubuntu
Marte Welcome. So, he helped
identify the applications and
what they were alternative or equivalent
to. So, some of the apps you'll
find in there says this
is an alternative to. So, GIMP
says it's an alternative to Photoshop.
That's nice.
Say it's equivalent.
It's an alternative to. But we've done as
much as we can to these
applications to make them the best they
can be. So, in the example of GIMP,
it doesn't just install GIMP. It installs
GIMP and a series of
plugins including CMYK
support. Oh, that's very polished.
There's a little bit of tweaking that goes on
there. So, when you choose
to install Chromium. So, there's a little
tick box that says hide proprietary
software. If you're looking at the
internet section and you click that,
Chrome disappears and
Chromium appears in its place.
But when you install Chromium,
it installs Chromium
and all of the
supported multimedia extensions
for Chromium are available.
So, it does an awful lot behind the
scenes. It does a lot of the heavy lifting.
And, you know, it also brings some things
in that probably need a bit of promoting. So,
things like VeraCrypt which is now the
successor to TrueCrypt.
Now that TrueCrypt have been through its NCC
group, you know, validations
and they've signed it off and the guys
at VeraCrypt have really
improved the cryptography
and some of the
key generation in VeraCrypt.
I think that is
now a genuine
alternative to TrueCrypt. So, there's a one-click
installer, you know, for that. For those
people that have got TrueCrypt
volumes that really need to
stop using TrueCrypt now,
there's a solution for you to
import your TrueCrypt volume, bring it up
to date with the latest stuff.
Makes it nice and easy to move over.
Yeah, yeah. So,
it does a whole heap of things
and as you say, you know,
for most people this will...
So, I haven't
cooked this up, you know,
out of thin air. This is actually made
by talking to actual people
that use the distribution or
use other operating systems and trying
to understand what they need.
And it is more geared towards people
who just need a helping hand to get
started, but that
asynchronous technique
is also convenient for someone like
me who when I install a new machine,
I can just go down the list,
install, install, install, install, install,
walk away, make a cup of tea and come
back and all my stuff's installed.
So, this is...
I mean, that's just the welcome screen,
but there's also one of the things that you
I saw also updated was
MateTweak, which I think is
kind of maybe a nice point to underscore
because I don't know if people realize when
they install it, you can go in here and you can actually
turn on a whole bunch of more stuff and tweak
a whole bunch of stuff. So, not to stop the welcome
screen, but I also wanted you to touch on the tweak screen
or the new tweak app or the updates to the tweak app
too. Yeah. So,
MateTweak is
distribution agnostic.
I forked it from Mint Desktop.
So, it's a utility that
is shipped in Mint Desktop.
I forked it from there and then
stripped out all of the Mint
stuff and then made it
distribution agnostic. So,
it'll run on any distribution. So, it's
not pinned to Debian or Ubuntu.
It runs on Arch just fine and
some people stuck it in the AUR.
But this enables you to
one click
activate compiz, for example.
Right. So, just like
Ubuntu used to do back in the day,
you used to go into those extra options
and turn on
extra animations and
compiz would come on. There's a drop down to
enable compiz and it's also got
a facility to
somewhat
reproduce the look and feel of
other desktop environments
outside of the Linux world and within.
So, you've got a theme
called Redmond, which looks
much like Windows XP.
A theme called Cupertino,
which looks like Mac OS X.
And then
within there, I've
changed the layout slightly. I've improved
the way the UI works.
So, now there's the
enable indicators, which enables
the app indicator capabilities of
Ubuntu underneath the hood. Very nice.
If you want app indicator support, it's a tick box
away. Or the advanced menu.
The advanced menu again is
forked from the Mint utilities.
That's the Mint menu, which again
I've forked and made distribution
agnostic. So, this is
something you can install on any
distribution running Marte and
it gives you that Mint desktop
that I've sort of stripped out all of the bits
that are specific to Mint
and made it something that you can run
anywhere. And that's
those two utilities are sort of those
sort of value add
that give sort of Ubuntu Marte
some of its identity, you know,
that distinguish it from
the other distributions.
Right. Very much so.
And it makes me
wonder. The next thing that
comes to mind is why I'd love to have somebody
have all these things but not have to worry about them
upgrading their distro in nine months.
What is the likelihood that any of this stuff ever
makes it any further back down to sort of like
an LTS release? Is that even possible?
Well, definitely
it's going to be in 16.04.
So, going forward. All right. So, I
guess I'd have to wait. So, if somebody
today wanted to set up an LTS
laptop, they'd kind of have to either
kind of wait or go
with 15.10 and then update.
Well,
you've got a number of options. There is
an Ubuntu Marte 14.04 release
which is based on the
Ubuntu LTS release strategy.
Those two utilities
that you're looking at there have been
backported. So, Ubuntu Marte
Welcome and Marte Tweak have been
backported to 14.04.
So, if you want them, they're there.
Now, the thing is
I didn't
appreciate this at the time, but
the gap between
Ubuntu Marte 14.04
and 15.10 is
vast. So,
my advice is if you're
interested in trying out Ubuntu Marte
today, install
15.10 because
the best version
we've made, the most polished
version we've made,
and one of the other things we've worked
on in this release is that you can
distribution release
upgrade. So, I've upgraded
all of my machines that I was on
15.04 to
15.10 using the internal
upgrade. I worked with the Ubuntu
foundations team to make sure
that that stuff worked right. So,
if you install 15.10 today,
I will personally guarantee
you can upgrade to 16.04
in April.
Wow. Wimpy will fix it for you if it breaks.
Yeah, well, I mean, even if
you didn't mention that, I was just going to say it seems like a pretty
safe bet that since the gap between
15.10 and 16.04 is small,
it should be fine.
Yeah, it's one to one. You should be able to upgrade pretty safely.
So, it seems like this would be the one to jump in at.
But for me,
I've recently rediscovered
my love affair with Bluetooth.
So, something the Mate
team have been working on for a while
now is helping
the new maintainer of Blue
Man 2
to fruition.
That's great.
So, Blue Man 2 also features
in 15.10. And
Ubuntu Mate is not the only
flavor to take advantage of
Blue Man 2.
The underlying stack
has been upgraded as well to
Blue's 5.35
rather than an extremely old
version of Blue's 4. So,
consequently, I'm now able to
do Bluetooth
sharing
over network sharing
and connecting to
headsets and speakers and stuff.
Very recently, things I've become
more and more...
I've wanted more and more as I've sometimes
been in the rover without connectivity
and I just want to move a file from
my phone to the desktop. I just
want to move that file between these two devices and I
just have Bluetooth as my available option.
That should be easy. Yeah, that should be.
So, I know...
It also feels like we are now
really reaching the point where
14.04, even with its updates,
even the point updates, 14.04 is
beginning to feel very old.
And I...
You know, we have a machine here
in studio now that is dual
booting and one of the systems it's booting is Ubuntu
15.10. And I think I'm going
to stay there for a while and go
to 16.04 because I don't think I can go back.
Who's clicking there, Wes? Who is that?
Who's clickalickin'? Who's clickalackin'?
That's
Swift. All right, Swift.
Maybe Swift needs to move up to the
staging area for a minute. Sorry
about that. So, what I was
just saying is I
just very recently went through this debate as I was
setting up this machine here in the
studio thinking, well, I might as well just stay at 15.10 for a while.
Just hang out there. Yeah, check out there.
And then go to 16.04. That'd be better than this.
Generally, 15.10 is a really solid release.
Yeah, that was my experience in the review testing
that we did. There's an awful lot of
effort, but you know, behind the scenes, having
some involvement with some of the
people at Canonical now and
being able to see what goes on
sort of behind the scenes on a
day-to-day basis. Yeah.
To say that
whilst visually on
the surface, people might not appreciate it.
And you didn't get
grossed out. I'll give you
an example. If you look
at it on the surface, you might not
think Ubuntu Software Center has
changed, but I know it has.
So, at the back end,
Ubuntu Software Center has actually
seen some
bug fixing and improvements
that you won't
appreciate, you know, through
the UI because the version
number is the same, but if you go and look at
the change logs, you can actually see that the
Ubuntu Desktop team have been working on this.
Well, that's a statement right there. I haven't heard one before.
There's a whole heap of things like
that that I've now got an insight to
and an appreciation of.
You know, that has been... I didn't previously
have. That has been a universal
experience of mine every time we've gone in
and worked with any... a lot of these
companies that work in this field is that there's
a lot of work and things that get done
that they are, A, just not
very good at communicating because they don't
have the time, they don't see the need, or the people who
would be communicating don't see the need or aren't connected to the
people making the change. Or there's legal reasons
a lot of the times, too, that they can't say anything.
Or, you know, there's thousands.
But every time we go in there, it's like, wow, you guys
are really working really hard, even though from the
outside we don't see it all the time. It's universally
really much been the case, and I'm
usually very impressed.
Speaking of impressed, very impressed
by Ubuntu Mate 15.10, I think
that's becoming the default recommendation.
If somebody wants to
try Linux, I think this is the
go-to, especially if they're coming
from a Windows or Mac
desktop, even. Yeah, definitely.
It's very approachable. Yeah. I mean, unless
there's a specific reason they would need
Gnome 3 or Unity, just to me seems
if there's not a specific reason for that,
because even on a brand new machine
they're going to have a good performance. Yeah, definitely.
And all the apps they could want.
Personally, if
Ubuntu Mate is the gateway
drug for people to find Linux,
I'd be perfectly happy to be
that gateway distribution
that people find Linux through.
There you go. Very noble of you. Well said.
If you use Ubuntu Mate
and you like it, and then it whets
your palate and you want to go on and find
other stuff, then great.
Job well done, I think, if that's
the position we hold in
the Ubuntu distro community.
So if you give it a try,
let us know. linuxactionshow.reddit.com
and find episode 116.
And I wanted to also give Symonk2
a chance to mention about his
excitement for 16.04.
Go ahead.
Yeah, I was actually, I think I'm actually
really, really excited for 16.04
because I don't know if, I think it was Tech Republic
that posted an article, and I kind of agree
with this, where
16.04 is probably going to
be a very exciting release, because
well, specifically for Ubuntu
Unity, because
Unity 8 is going to come around the corner.
I don't know if it's going to be 16.04 or what their
plans are, but I think this
it's going to start to pick up pace
not only with Ubuntu
Unity, but with other
flavors.
So I really think this will be
one of the... We'll see.
Or is 16.04 going to
be relatively simple and straightforward
but yet with some nice features, and
16.10 is going to blow your freaking mind.
Yeah, probably. Something around there
or within the next couple of years
I think it'll drastically change.
Stay tuned and find out.
I love it. Keep watching this show.
Okay, so we have some
we have a big win for Linux users to
get into. We still have the Intel discussion to talk
about. Also, we have to
discuss this, you don't own your
operating system, therefore it can be decrypted
and the new Linux laptop
and we have some emails to
get into, so I'm going to take a second here. I'm going to tell you
all about Linux Academy. Yeah, I
don't want to talk to you about Linux Academy right now. Go to
linuxacademy.com
to get our special Linux Unplugged discount
and then give a tour, if you will,
of their different features. I think you'll be pretty impressed.
It's Linux users that got together with
developers and teachers to make something really great.
And it's not... Oh, here's what I love
about Linux Academy. It's not just an
attempt at covering Linux and open source stuff.
It is truly what they are passionate about.
They have step-by-step video
courses, comprehensive
study guides, and the
courses as well have come with instructor
help, so you're not on your own necessarily.
You can contact a real human being
instructor and get help. There's a great community
stacked full of Jupyter Broadcasting members.
The courses come with their own lab servers.
Seven plus Linux distributions you get to choose
from because they get that there's different distros you might need
to learn on. You can keep track of
your progress as you go and they've been rolling out
brand new features. Rather than just
checking solutions, you'll now get instant feedback.
So you don't have to just try something, submit it,
and see how it does and get scored. You can get immediate
feedback when performing exercises.
And then you can know if you need to
make a change and do it correctly.
There's a new learning tool that's part of Linux Academy
membership at no additional cost that really adds
some nice functionality. Like they're applying this
new tool to build performance-based practice exams
for search, such as the
RHCSA and the Linux Foundation
search. Now those Red Hat certifications
are a serious thing that people
really get stressed out about.
And spend a lot of time and effort trying to get.
Yeah, so the fact that they're building this performance-based practice
exam I think is really
slick, really well done.
And it's for finally for
people that are Linux users that have certain
high expectations of
what is being taught to them
and not just like this basic stuff that's coming from
somebody who's just doing a professional
read, but actually somebody who wrote
sat down and wrote the material instructors that are familiar
with it when you need help. Scenario-based
labs, you actually work with this stuff in a
production live environment.
A real lab server where you can SSH into and do
the actual work. I think it's
really nice. And they also launched their professional
development certification platform.
It's a new set of tests that are very targeted
and a lot different than professional certification.
So there's a lot of new ways
to challenge yourself. There's also tools
available when you have limited availability that
automatically adjust the courseware to match your
availability. You combine that with the
video streams. It's really pretty
neat. And then, last but not least,
you can deep dive into single topics with their nuggets.
You go there two to sixty minutes long,
learn something really simple, like
how to use IP tables, how to use
rsync, how to use Samba,
how to set up Samba for this or that, just
really specific topics. And it's really
nice because they're all really quick or
at least very specific. And I
really think you should check out their lab systems.
It's really cool. The fact that
it comes with the lab is a nice feature
too because if you're doing some of the AWS courses,
you don't have to worry about setting up all that stuff.
They'll take care of all of that for you as
part of the integrated lab platform.
It's really cool. No surprise, AWS
builds. That's a big thing. Yeah, that has
bit me. LinuxAcademy.com
slash Unplugged. Go check them out. And a big
thank you Linux Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
You guys are rockin'.
And that new October update is huge.
Huge. If you sign up, you can go read more about
it and go check out their community section
as well. It's very nice.
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged. Thanks
Linux Academy. Alright, so
BRTMR wrote into
the show. He says, I was not satisfied
with podcatchers for the command line, so I
built my own. And it's called PodFox.
Now, I don't know how, how do you catch your
podcast right now, Wes? How do you catch your podcast?
How many podcasts do you subscribe to, Wes?
Oh, maybe on the order of
ten. Okay, yeah,
that's actually almost exactly where I'm at.
How do you download them? Are you
familiar with curl? Are you
serious? Well, no, actually I use
ARIA 2, but it is in the terminal.
That's usually how it goes
for me. Really? Yes. Okay, so this might
be perfect for you. So PodFox is a podcatcher
for the terminal. I'm loving this logo here.
Yeah, that is good, right? That is good.
It's a work in progress, but it
has got a nice, simple directory structure.
Every podcast is identified with
its own short name. I think you were checking this
out a little bit ago. What do you think about
something like this? I mean,
you're doing a dozen shows manually?
That does sound crazy
now that I think about it, but yeah, that's what I have
been doing. Have you tried BashPod or two? I have
not actually, no. Okay, okay. So maybe I should
give PodFox a shot here. Wow. I mean, I like
Python. It looks neatly implemented.
I thought for sure your answer is going to be on your
phone. Oh, yeah?
Well, actually, no, I do it the reverse. I usually download it on my
computer and stick it in my sync thing folder, and then it
syncs to my phone. So tell me, IRC,
how do you, IRC room, what do you
use? Like, what's the app name or the tool you
use to download your podcast? And then Mumble Room,
I'm curious, is anybody in the
Mumble Room also using the command line right now
to download your podcast?
Stay with me, brothers. You used
to, Poppy? What do you use? Okay, how did you
do what you use now? There was a tool called
HPodder. Oh, yes.
HPodder was good. It was written in Haskell,
I think, which is why it's called HPodder. I used
to use that, but now, actually,
I have an iPad
1 that is pretty much useless
for anything because no apps
work on it anymore and there's no software updates.
So I just have it sat there with the Apple
podcast app running, and
it downloads my podcast from iTunes, and I sit
and listen, and that's the only thing it
does. I guess it has a decent enough
speaker, too, right? Yeah, exactly.
That's not too bad. Yeah, okay, so
sort of a mobile setup there.
Do you see they have a TechSnap as one of the example
URLs here? No, I didn't see that. Are you serious?
It looks like it. That's really funny.
Where do I go to see that? Go down to
import and then, yeah, you're right,
the TechSnap MP3 feed. I love them already.
Well, I'm glad I came across them. That's just
funny. No, I was just checking this out.
Oh, well, he did submit it to the Linux Action Show
subreddit, so that makes sense. That makes sense. That does make sense.
The TechSnap MP3
feed, that's a popular
feed. Yeah, that's some great stuff there. That's a good
commuter show, I gotta say. If you haven't listened to the TechSnap
show, you throw that, I mean, you could look at Alan
Jude's face if you want, but... See, for me, it's his
voice. It keeps me calm when you're sitting in traffic.
Right? Especially when he's talking about
ZFS. Yep. Which is a lot.
Alright, so
anyways, moving on.
So, okay, YouTube, I'm seeing
YouTube DL.
What are podcasts as looks for me? Somebody kick him
out of here. Rekai says he streams
all on YouTube, BeyondPod on
Android. Hmm.
Anybody else in the mumble room have a shout out for
the podcatching software they use?
Pocketcasts.
Yeah, Pocketcasts is one of my favorites.
I totally agree. Oh, yeah, Wimpy, that's what you
use for the 20
podcasts you subscribe to.
Yep, Pocketcasts, and occasionally
I send those via Chromecast,
but almost exclusively through
Pocketcasts. Yeah, and on the
internet phones, the
Overcast from the Marco Arment is
really good. It's free now. And
one of the nice things, this is,
if you get a, and Pocketcast does this too,
if you get a podcast player
for your phone, it's really nice to have it sync
with a web player. Oh, yeah. Because when I,
if I've been driving and the podcast gets
really interesting and I park, I often times
want to go in and finish it on my computer speakers,
which are usually pretty nice, and listen to the podcast
there. So to have the podcast
mobile app sync with the web app is
really nice. Oh, that sounds like a feature I would like.
Yeah, it is. So you should check out Pocketcasts.
Or Overcast if you want to get
an internet phone. Yeah,
so there you go.
Apparently we woke up Alan.
Now Alan's in the chat room. Sorry, Alan, we love
you. Everybody say TechSnap is
awesome. And
CFS Rock's in the chat room. All right,
so you can go check it out. So moving on
from there, Wes, you caught
this one today. This came out today
as we're recording. It is a
release or a media alert.
Media alert, media alert.
Hold on, we should do this legit style.
Do you want to do this legit style? Let's do it. All right, here we go.
It's a media alert, everybody.
All right, from the Electronic Frontier Foundation,
a media alert is coming in here
that is actually a pretty big deal.
It's actually good news.
I started the day with bad news because CISA
is raging through the US right now.
And net neutrality just got a piss in the
EU. So I was like, I was just nothing
but bad news this morning. But today
the EFF made a post that says
the Librarian of Congress has granted security
researchers and others the right to inspect
and modify the software
in their cars and other vehicles
despite protests from vehicle manufacturers.
They would protest. Well, this has
become a big deal that we've
those of us who
have grumbled about the proprietary software
in our cars have been talking about for a while
but really came to light with the Volkswagen
stuff.
So the fact that this Volkswagen
scandal with the cover-ups
is really sort of
forced this issue through, I think.
And this is a big, big win for
the end user. They say this
access control rule is supposed to...
This is what the manufacturers were using
to block access. They say this
access control rule is supposed to protect
against harmful and unlawful copying.
So the EFF staff attorney.
But as we've seen in recent Volkswagen scandal
where VW was caught manipulating some tests
it can be used instead to hide wrongdoing
hidden in computer code.
The EFF also won an exemption
for users who want to play video games
after the publisher cuts off support.
Yeah. For example
some players may
need to modify an old video game so it
doesn't... They say... Yeah, some players
may need to modify... Oh yeah, because this is where you're not
getting in trouble for now. Some players may need to modify
an old video game so it doesn't perform a
check with the authentication server that has
been shut down. The librarian also
granted the EFF's petition to renew previous
exemption to jailbreak smartphones
and extend that to other mobile devices including
tablets and
smart watches. It's really upsetting
to me that we have to get this as an exception
that's occasionally granted by the Librarian
of Congress, but I'm still very glad that it's
continuing to be the case. It's like a subtle
win for digital ownership
that we kind of subscribe to. Yeah,
it's like a continued win of something
we should already just have. Yes, exactly. That should be
enshrined and we shouldn't have to get it renewed every
so often. But, thank you EFF.
Yeah, I guess they...
I mean, what this really is, is it's
sort of... It's sort of
working around the rules that the
proprietary software vendors try
to put in there, which we are going to be talking more about
in a moment, so let's not go
too far down there. While we're in
the things that Wes came across that
made us scratch our head this week category, because I think
you also sent this in this morning
when we were chatting.
This is a real interesting
piece on the invisiblethings.org
blog, which is
also where you would find
Kube's OS.
And I...
I'm just going to read it to you, and then we'll
see what to make of it. So, today I'm really seeing
this first paper. Finally, you can see the PDF or
EPUB here. As mentioned, this paper
is mostly a survey of the various problems
and attacks presented against the x86
platform over the last
10 years. And,
uh, boy is
it. It is, uh,
it is, it is basically
a, uh, it is a
litany list of issues with x86
that basically, to me, look like it
condemned the platform, because there's so many
different vulnerabilities built in.
So, they start with the BIOS, the root
trust of everything, bad SSMs,
then they go on and talk about
UEFI, they talk about some of the stuff
Intel's built in for management, and then
from there it's networking devices, of course
USB devices, the graphics subsystem,
disk controllers, audio cards, microphone speakers,
cameras, embedded controllers, Intel management engines.
The bottom line is
specifically Intel x86
based machines
are just extremely, extremely
vulnerable. No ways about it.
Is that essentially what you got from it, too? Yes.
I mean, I think a lot of what they're talking about as well is just the
amount, you know, the instruction architecture
is not necessarily bad. I mean,
it might be old and crufty now. People have different
opinions on that, but the amount of
microcode and other things that runs without
the running operating systems knowledge
or intervention in any way has
made it so that efforts, you know,
from the open source community to make
secure kernels that are running on
verified hardware,
you can never trust it now. It's similar to what we see
in cell phones. Yeah, it's very
much like that baseband that has its own...
They can reach right into memory and, you know,
stops the regular processor in its tracks.
So, let's just...
We'll just roll with the theory here that
x86 is a very vulnerable platform.
You know who I wouldn't want to necessarily
be right now?
I wouldn't want to be Windows. That's because they're
really, really tied to this. I feel like
this is something that Linux is going to be much better
at rolling with if... I don't know what we'd roll
to, but let's just, you know, we're just going with this
theory here. If this is really a big deal,
it seems like this
would be something much quicker for Linux
to respond to than it would be for Windows
or Apple to respond to. Right. Assuming that, you know, we could
get the headwind to change major
architecture that is used by, you know,
the computing public. Yeah. I think you're right.
Yeah. What do you think, Wimpy? Is it possible?
Is it all in the hands of the
distros or could it just be a...
Maybe like... Maybe one big distro
comes out and says, all right, we're releasing for
this laptop and they, you know, who knows how it could
happen? There could be... There could be... There could be
something there, but what are your thoughts?
Well, all the big
distributions are making their
platforms available
for other architectures.
But when you look at Distro Watch,
there's 800 some
Linux distributions almost
exclusively aimed at, you know,
PC, the Intel chipset.
Of those, there's
about 20 or so that are
aimed at ARM platforms.
And
if you're a distribution maintainer,
it's very difficult for you
to differentiate yourself
from everybody else if you've got eight other
distributions to,
you know, compete against in
air quotes. But
if there's only 20
distributions on ARM,
for example, or
half that on PowerPC, and
PowerPC is still a thing. You know, people
think of the old PowerPC on the G4s,
but you can buy,
you know, new PowerPC
based equipment. You know, there's
the Amiga 1,
X1000, X5000, and
X500 devices.
Then, you know, if you're
building for those architectures, then
you're also, you know, just
hedging your bets for the future because
the trend is ARM
is becoming the consumer
chip platform.
And, you know, you
still want a foot in the Intel
camp for serious gaming and
professional workstations. You can't
ignore that. And obviously, at the moment,
despite the energy efficiency
of ARM, you want Intel in the data
center. But
you, as a distribution
maintainer, you can't not
be looking at those
alternate architectures.
I do agree to an extent.
It's an interesting, so it's an interesting
thought that you put forward is that ARM is going to
become the consumer platform. And
kind of the concession that you're making there
when you say that is
consumers don't need a lot of CPU
power.
Well, they need some hardware acceleration
for things for
media consumption. And
they need some degree
3D performance for casual gaming.
And it's only when
you're into the serious gaming
arena and professional work
stations that you actually need to
step out of the ARM arena where
that isn't yet.
And it could well be. I mean, I think it will.
I mean, I think you look at some of the latest generation of
CPUs and GPUs coming out for ARM.
I have to say, I think most
of the ARM stuff is driven by economy
at the moment rather than technology.
And I think ARM is far more capable
than
people are paying for. So I think
it could well be the next
platform. I really do
think it's a contender.
But we should be
gearing up our distributions
to support these
platforms. So just
thinking, you know, if you're being myopic
and saying, oh, well, I'm laser focused
on
Intel 64-bit.
Well, I tell
you what, you're missing a trick there.
There's what is it that I think
in February, the Raspberry Pi
Foundation said they'd sold
5 million Raspberry Pis in
two years. You know, if you
extrapolate the numbers out, they must be
clearing and approaching
7 million by now.
Right now, there are
two Linux
desktop operating systems, soon
to be a third in the guise of
Lubuntu, desktop operating
systems available for the Raspberry Pi
2. So
do you want to be
competing against 800
distributions on Intel or do
you want to be one of the three
with 7 million devices?
Yeah,
you need to be
gearing up to, and
like I say, PowerPC isn't dead.
PowerPC is massive in the data center.
This is what's driving these
new IBM
mainframes.
Yeah, that actually all rings
pretty true. Let's be clear, they're not PowerPC, they're Power.
Well, it's, yeah,
the architecture. The Power architecture, yeah.
Yes, the linearity, yeah.
And also, there's still a pretty healthy...
It has very similar problems to the x86.
There's still also, I mean,
a crap ton of literally PowerPC
desktop machines on eBay. There's still
a crap ton of those things getting sold.
So, and I don't know
if we could really walk away from this conversation without admitting
that ARM probably is riddled with its own issues, too.
It's not like ARM is some sort of savior platform that
doesn't have security vulnerabilities, and not to mention
it's always going to come down to implementation.
And you have to trust whoever's manufacturing
them anyway. Right, yeah. And when you have physical
access to a device, it doesn't
matter what the CPU architecture is, there's
going to be vulnerabilities. Because all
these ARM chips, all these ARM systems also
have USB buses, so is there
the same vulnerability there? But
I think all the underlying points that
Wimpy just made, and the point that I'm trying to make, too,
is that Linux
is specifically at a
just technical advantage to roll with this.
I think Wimpy underscores a good point, though, that
really just out of the box, good to go
consumer-focused distros that anybody
could use, we're really lacking
that right now. And I hadn't
really thought about it, because when I think about it, I think
of Raspbian, and I think
of Arch, and that's what I run on the Raspberry
Pi's. I don't really think about it.
And unless
you're up to speed with Arch, you've
got to augment that into a desktop
distribution right now. You've
got Raspbian,
Ubuntu, Mate, and
soon, Lubuntu.
And then you've got things like
RISCOS, and you've got other distributions. There are other
distributions out there, but they're not desktop
focused, end user
focused. And whilst the Raspberry Pi 2
is just about capable
of being a desktop replacement,
it's not about
what's there now. For example,
Odroid, if you buy
an Odroid and an eMMC
chip with
Ubuntu pre-installed as your
Linux distribution rather than Android,
when you plug that in and boot
it, it's Ubuntu
with the Mate desktop. Now, it's not
Ubuntu-Mate, but it is Ubuntu
and the Mate desktop.
And they've got
the fortunate position that
their GPU has also got open
source drivers, so you've got all of that
3D stuff all accelerated out
of the box. And Raspberry Pi
is very, very close to
delivering their
accelerated drivers
for X. So I think
Linux 4.4 is targeted
for the initial version that doesn't have
all of the 3D acceleration yet, but
it's coming. So
this is why I've ported every
Ubuntu flavor to the Raspberry Pi 2,
because when that driver
is available, every Ubuntu
version is ready to go.
I agree
with you. When the horsepower gets there,
I think you could see there's
machines here in the studio I could even see replacing
to a certain degree. And it seems like
we're only on the start of that. The desktop
computer revolution really
gave Intel the funds to
work on their fabrication technique. That's true.
That's what we're going to see now in the ARM fabs.
Yeah, and the phones are definitely, they're really adding a lot of
fuel to that development fire. Apple pays all that money
to get those A9s manufactured.
That investment gets pushed up. And Samsung
is building a lot of those, so that's
not all lost. Even when they're building the Apple chips,
they can't all be lost R&D.
They have that machinery, right?
I don't know. They learn from this.
Right, exactly. And so
I would say for me, it's
nowhere near ready.
I mean like, I
yeah, I mean I just can't even
see it for years for me. But I could see
it for my kids already.
And I could see it for
a lot of people in a lot of different
work roles very soon if not already.
So it's very cool.
Alright, so I want to move on from this.
And I want to discuss this EULA situation
that is
very uncomfortable because it's a bad, bad precedent.
And I think it's one that
might be a good talking point for us that are discussing
with users. Why would you want to maybe use
Linux over Windows 10?
Why would you want to maybe use
the Ubuntu phone over Android?
Or something like that. Well, this might
be the number one talking point from here on out
I would think. But first,
I want to tell you about our friends at Digital Ocean.
That's where I have my servers.
Back in the day, before Digital Ocean,
I was all about
Proxmox.
I was all about Proxmox. If I needed a server,
I'd spin up a Proxmox VM. Have you ever
messed with Proxmox? Only a little bit.
Yeah. But I've heard some good things. And you probably mess with
VirtualBox. Oh yeah, definitely.
That's so, you know, like, okay, so what would I
I would go get like my best Core i7 PC
and I'd put a bunch of RAM in it
and a bunch of hard drives in it of various
quality. And I would put that in my garage
and that would be how I would do my virtualization.
Frankenstein monster virtualizer.
Yeah, and that worked for basically always about
a year before for some reason it completely
blew up. And now
now I'm like big time. Now I'm
like, I walk in, I'm like a boss. I'm like, yeah, I have
infrastructure in the cloud. I have data
centers in New York, San Francisco, Singapore,
Amsterdam, London,
Germany, and I just got an API.
Got a new one up in Toronto. Yeah, I got it. It's straightforward
that API.
You know, and one click deployment of
things like GitLab,
Docker, one of the first
to deploy Docker. Wow, Chris.
My data center is, my data center
is Digital Ocean. Yeah, I know. It's
a big surprise. Digital Ocean, if you use the promo
code DOUNPLUGGED, you can get a $10 credit
and you can try out Digital Ocean two months
for free. The $5 rigs,
Wes, I'm telling you, I think just about every
time you come in here, you sit
down and log into a droplet in some form or another.
Yeah, that's pretty much true. Is that Quazl core
there running off of it? It sure is.
Yeah, I got my Quazl core running off of Digital Ocean
Droplet too. Seriously, if you use IRC
for work or for communications,
you should be looking at Quazl and Quazl core
and put Quazl core on Digital Ocean Droplet.
Worth $5 right there. Oh yeah, and it's
real easy to get set up. It is. It just
always runs. It's just right there for you. Trust me.
It makes, you know,
what you'll do if you do that is you'll be
like, why did we ever use anything
but IRC? Why is Twitter a thing?
Why is Slack a thing?
Why are we even using email?
Really, why are we not using IRC for
all the things? Anyways, there's
a lot of different things like sync thing, own cloud,
like I mentioned earlier, GitLab,
BitTorrent sync. We do a big
distribution for BitTorrent sync for our
own filter show. Lots of people sync from
that. All powered by Digital Ocean Droplets.
It's really a cool system. And one of the
really nice things if you need like a backend storage
rig, there is some really cool solutions
when you use private networking with Digital Ocean.
The data sent between machines on the
private networking doesn't go against your transfer. Even though
you get a terabyte of transfer, you can use private
network and do like backend caching,
proxying, or a backend file server.
And they have a really good interface to manage all of this.
So for $5 a month, you can get 512
megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD,
one CPU, and a terabyte of transfer.
Digital Ocean is nuts, son. They're crazy.
I want you to go check them out. And they now also
have floating IPs.
So that way when you go big,
when you're like, when you're Ubuntu Mate
and you're like, you're going big, you know,
or you want to be
fancy and you want to have a big launch day, they got
floating IPs.
You can scale out however you need. Just move it around.
It floats. It floats.
That's fancy. You know what? Things in the cloud float.
Yeah. What I like about Digital Ocean
too, it's all running on top of Linux. They use KVM
as the virtualization platform,
which some other providers out there that you
may have heard of before are kind of kicking themselves for.
No kidding. They're kind of like, I wish I would have gone KVM.
The best thing about KVM, you get that, you get your
own kernel right there, you know? You get
all the new fancy kernel features. You want cgroups,
you want IP tables, like whatever you want.
It's right there. And that means they're able to
roll out the newer distros way before
other guys do, which is really cool.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUG
to support the show and get a $10 credit
and a big thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
Linux Unplugged. You guys rock.
Alright, so just let's talk about
this from a general Linux perspective.
The DOJ dismisses Apple's argument
against encrypting iOS. And to Apple's
credit, they have been fighting this
case trying to say that
they, you know, it'll do them harm
if they have to unlock it. They say they can't unlock
anything iOS 8 or above.
However,
the federal court is not agreeing.
The US government rejected Apple's argument in federal court
that unlocking iOS devices for police
would damage the tech giant's public image
because they've done it before.
Boom. Apple designed, manufactured,
and sold the phone that is subject to the search warrant,
the government told US magistrate
Judge James. But this is only
the beginning of Apple's relationship to the phone
and this matter. Apple owns
the software and runs the phone, their argument
is. And the software is thwarting
the execution of the warrant. The
software is thwarting the execution of the warrant.
In the Justice Department's filing in the case
involving the iPhone discovered on the suspect,
he's indicted for a drug
possession, meth.
And this is an ongoing battle.
Apple filed a brief saying in most
cases now and in the future it would be impossible
for it to extract encrypted data
from an iOS device.
But they dismiss the
argument, says Apple's asserts,
Apple's burden is not provable since they've done this
before. And
they also say,
moving ahead here, they say
Apple
should be able to unlock
it. The government's argument is essentially that Apple
has never really objected to this case and the fact that they
have set up guidelines by which they'll comply
doesn't stop them from objecting to any particular
case. But they have the ability to do it here and
clearly the judge was concerned.
Apple also warned
that if we're forced to routinely decrypt data from law enforcement
its employees could theoretically be subpoenaed in every
case to provide expert testimony.
They cited a previous case
where an actual employee
who did the decrypting ended up getting hauled into court
because he then saw the evidence.
So just like the technician
that had to do the decrypting.
Wow. Yeah.
So there's several things Apple's trying to fight against.
Having to do future decrypting,
having to
bring its employees into court
if they do the decrypting.
And now this argument
that Apple's software licensing agreement
specifies that iOS software is licensed
not sold, quote unquote. And that users
are merely granted a quote
limited non-exclusive license
to use the iOS software.
So in their argument because it's the software
preventing the decryption and Apple owns the software
not the user, Apple must decrypt it
because the users don't own the software.
Yeah I like how they came back and said that you know
well you guys have been claiming for so long now that
it's your software that you just licensed in it
so you can't have both sides of it.
Proprietary software is not ethical.
Yeah you know what else makes me think of?
Malicious functionality perverting
free software. That program
although it may be attractive
is really a trap.
I think all of those statements are correct.
All of those statements. He's right.
RMS is right.
I mean
this
blows my mind. Their argument is literally
that because you don't own the software
you license the software
the manufacturer should be able to decrypt it.
And they might actually get this.
They might actually win on that argument.
They might actually be able to convince the judge of that.
Maybe Apple
will take their security claims seriously
enough and change their licensing agreement.
Probably not though.
That would be I guess the best
direct fix right? Right.
I mean they've already got the encryption going on
you know 8 and 9 but.
But doesn't this seem like the biggest argument
like out of all of the arguments
doesn't this
really fundamentally prove why it's important to
own your own software? Yes I think so.
Like this is like to me seems like the biggest
the biggest bullet point for that.
And
there was a post that I caught recently
titled Richard Stallman is the hero the internet
needs. And a few bullet points.
He warned of the growing danger
of DRM and the great story
The Right to Read in 1997.
He warned about DRM in 97.
He refuses to own a cell phone on the grounds
that it might be used as a tracking or covert listening
device. Slightly paranoid but
looks increasingly possible. Stallman considers
cloud computing. Increasingly. Yeah.
Stallman considers cloud computing dangerous
in 2008. He thought this would sound
like an alarmist. Now nobody trusts the cloud.
He always held the proprietary
software could not be trusted. Windows 10
shaded behavior proves that point.
You mean the Windows 10 I'm running here
in the studio Chris?
Yeah.
But he was right. He has been right.
He's been consistently on the ball there.
Yeah. So I don't know
does anybody in the Mumba Room have thoughts
on the EULAs and not owning the
software and the ramifications that maybe we're
just now beginning to understand?
I'm still
reading the Windows proper.
Go ahead North Ranger.
Well if
the idea behind
copyright is for the benefit of the public
to secure for authors a limited
time. There's
really no limits at this point as far as the government
is concerned. Yeah exactly. That's a good point.
Yeah. Yeah. OK. Now I know two other people
who else want to speak up. I caught that.
Next go ahead and whoever goes first
can have it.
That's not a very good system is it?
Free for all. All right. This is
unplugged after all.
Go ahead. Let Sean go first.
All right Sean go ahead.
I was just saying like given the fact
that basically all
software is licensed do we really
own any of it?
Yeah. I mean I guess you'd have to look into
the individual EULAs for open source software
but I think if you have the code and you can modify
it functionally you own it.
It's at least closer to our
pre-software definition of ownership than
what you get with a Apple
or Windows style license. And Casey you
were next?
Was it Sean that was next?
Sorry I can't see your names guys. The screen is too small for me.
I'm an old man now. No. No. It was
me. Actually
the EULA for Windows
10 I plan on going over with
and then looking at it. It's pretty
horrendous when you see that
oh we can use
subject and
the body email to
just return user
input. It's really bad.
Yeah. That is a particular nasty one.
And Heavens you want to get a chance to jump in too.
Go ahead.
Oh we can't hear you.
Wow. While he's getting his
mic fixed I would say in the future
I look forward to the day when the DOJ
holds Richard Storman
into court and says
that he has to
speak for the fact that
he created the license and all the stuff on
my machine is licensed under GPL.
And so he's responsible
for the software that's on my machine.
There you go. There you go. That's a good twist.
I like that. Heavens one more chance.
Did you get your mic working?
Going once? Going twice? I wonder what happened
over there. What happened over there? Maybe pulse
audio. That's what everybody always goes to right? Everybody always has to
blame pulse audio. All right.
Well Heavens I'll give you a chance to
troubleshoot that for a second. It was just a
thought provoking piece and I wanted to just
kind of call it out because I think it underscores something a lot of us
Linux and open source enthusiasts have
been talking about for a long time. I'll tell you
about something else I've been talking about. That's Ting
my mobile service provider. Ting is
mobile that makes sense. It's only pay for what you use
wireless. It's your minutes, your messages, your
megabytes. They add them up. Whatever bucket you fall into
that's all you pay. It's six dollars
for the line. A great control panel.
Really enthusiastic customer service.
And really good selection of devices
too. All these are unlocked so you
own them outright. You can go to
linux.ting.com.
You know Chris I was doing the math yesterday
trying to get my parents to switch to Ting.
I looked at the last
year their bill. They would save an average of
sixty two dollars a month if they switched to Ting.
That's a nice savings. These are real world figures.
I did it yesterday. Yeah when you go to linux.ting.com
they have a savings calculator there on the front page.
Makes it really easy. Yeah you just plug it in there.
So would they be getting more of a smartphone
device or more of a feature phone device?
Well this is on their current feature phone trend.
Maybe not the most
current. So they're cool with feature phones?
Yeah and Ting works great with that.
They've been on another provider who
their phones will just work right with Ting.
They won't have to change anything.
Yeah the feature phone prices are ridiculous.
And then of course I love right here that you can
get the Moto X second gen for two ninety nine unlocked.
The Moto Nexus 6
or you can get the LG 5X.
Right when they're ready to go to that next level
Ting's got it all right there. You own the device
outright. It's nice. It's nice.
Including my S6 Edge.
Yeah so you can check them out at linux.ting.com
I love their customer service.
I love the way their control panel works.
It makes it really easy to manage my account.
It's really easy also to pick between GSM
and CDMA so you can pick and choose which one's
better in your area. And if you're a little savvy
with Wi-Fi it's going to blow your mind
with the savings. Blow your mind.
Check it out.
Go to linux.ting.com and a big thanks to Ting
for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Okay Evans did you get your mic working?
Did you get it fixed? Going once?
Yes I believe I did.
Yeah you're a little over
you're a little hot but you're good.
You're coming in now.
What did you want to add on before we wrap up?
Sounds good.
It really just applies
to Apple's product.
Apple software or possibly the Apple hardware.
So if we have a hardware module
which we own ourselves
which they do not own
but their operating system APIs
call, we could have
our own owned
decryption keys.
Kind of like little, you know, cookie or whatever.
Or the SIM card.
That would be nice. It would come down to the user owning
the hardware and then just installing their OS on it.
Which they would use.
And then they would bypass
the ULS agreement for us using
their software or their OS.
That's an interesting idea. That is interesting.
I wonder if that would ever actually happen. Ever happen, yeah.
You know, so speaking of hardware
Yaomei I think is how you say it.
They have been pondering a Linux laptop for a while
and now the folks over at
OMG Ubuntu say it's going to happen.
Their long rumored Linux laptop has been
kicked around and we've covered it once before
in its earliest stage. It looks like
it's going to be a 12.5 inch display
and then another with a 13.3
inch display.
The model with the 12.5 inch screen will be manufactured by
Inventek, who also makes laptops
for Acer and Toshiba and HP.
With an initial order of 250,000
units. A slightly larger device is being
made by Compella Electronics.
They also supposedly manufacture some
Apple devices and various PlayStation, Xbox
and Nintendo game consoles.
And Yaomei is supposedly placing a
300,000 order unit with them.
Now this would be shipping with their
own version of Linux they say?
Oh interesting. Hopefully with
not too much added tree stuff.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And no word even
if it'd be shipping anywhere specifically.
According to the same sources
they'll be priced cheaply but offer high
performance. I like that. Just like the
company's smartphones.
So probably
going to debut in China I would imagine
but maybe eventually make it over here. Is anybody interested
to see what Yaomei could do? Actually
I don't think anybody in here was last time we talked
about it. Has anybody changed their mind?
No. Seems to be more popular
online though. We've gotten people sending to the show
that are definitely looking forward to it. I mean I'm interested.
I don't know that I would necessarily get one
but I feel like there's a couple
you know 13, 14 inch laptops that people
can look at. But really
like 90% of the laptop field is boring
15 inch
over you know it's like 5 pounds. It doesn't
have a great resolution. If you're coming into the laptop market
today with a 12.5 inch or
13 inch laptop you are
probably targeting the MacBook Air
right? Right. And so then when
you say that I think
light, thin, but decent
performance. Right. But if you could
just offer me a few things that the MacBook doesn't
like a couple more ports would be nice. Better
Linux compatibility? Absolutely that would be
nice. Then maybe you got
something here. And it might be nice to invest
you know maybe not but it's nice to see clearly
you know the Asus and Acer's of the world
they have some stuff for us but they're
not really supporting our crowd very much.
We might be able to support a new company who
will leverage that. Yeah System76 has
a laptop in this space. There's the Dell
XPS. Then you can also go get yourself a
ThinkPad. But
maybe it will be terrible
I don't know. But there's still room here I think.
No I think there is still room here for this.
You put a really nice screen on there. You put a decent CPU
in there and maybe some PCI Express
storage. At the right price point?
Yeah. I could be interested in that.
I'm not really in the market right now. My XPS
13 does the job but I could be interested in that.
Yeah. I don't know.
Anybody remember I'm interested now? Anybody?
Come on.
I can't believe it. You guys what do you got?
You're all a bunch of ThinkPad users. No you're just all a bunch of
ThinkPad users.
The problem is
chances are it's going to only be available in
China. Probably have some wacky version
of Linux that doesn't contribute upstream
at all. And so
if I wanted to wipe that and put
something else like Ubuntu Mate or
Ubuntu proper I
would probably find the wireless doesn't work or
the touchpad skitty or whatever.
And I don't want to have
to buy something from China.
Find it doesn't work and then end up putting it in a drawer
or chucking it on eBay. I would rather know that it works
which is why I'm veering towards
a ThinkPad or a Dell XPS.
At least they contribute upstream.
My question would really be is it going to be more Chromebook
than it is Linux laptop.
And you know what I just kind of
remembered incidentally
is I believe my
Chromebook from 2015 was supposed to arrive in September.
It is now October.
Remember how I
backed that?
I'm sure it's coming soon.
I was told it was. Maybe it's on the doorstep right now.
Maybe. It would still be late.
I would really
like to do that. All right Swift you want to talk about ThinkPads
go ahead.
Yeah my thing about the whole
ThinkPads thing is while
the recent ones I keep hearing
about the whole Superfish issue
the classic ones are really nice.
The only thing I would say is the resolution
is an issue.
I'm currently in front of an X201
right now and I love this machine.
Yeah I think that's
about what I hear all the time.
That seems to be a pretty fair assessment.
Wimpy you have a Librem 13. Tell me what do you think?
Well I have the better version
of the Librem 13 in that I
actually have one that you can buy today
and it works and
is running stuff. Yeah.
Do you like that hardware?
Well I do now that I've
helped fix the touchpad driver
in the Linux kernel. Yes it works very
nicely. But
what's interesting about the Librem 13 I have some
involvement with them. So hello
everyone from
Purism. You'll know me
from the guy that sent you the kernel patches.
But
it's a long time coming
so they're just shipping the Librem
13 and
Entraware who I spoke about
earlier who have been shipping that hardware
platform since almost
the start of this year
have already revved on
that platform and are just about
to release their new version
based on
Skylake and that's coming
out next week or the week after.
That's going to be nice.
Yeah and
I just don't get this
Purism thing.
Honestly that and
this YaoMei Linux laptop.
I think this YaoMei Linux laptop
or however you pronounce it is a total non story
for any actual users.
I don't think it's going to be a product that we
really get our hands on.
Well maybe not in the US
and maybe not in Europe but it could be a thing in China.
But even then they won't even probably know it runs Linux.
Well do they care?
No. They just want something to replace Windows XP
don't they? Yeah.
Our first computer. Not even necessarily
something to replace XP.
There's a giant market of people who've never
even owned a computer at
all out in the burbs and beyond
in China that have
never had a computer. Yeah absolutely
for them. For those people something like this that
can get on the internet is a fantastic device.
Very much. I agree.
And I wait
with anticipation for my Librem so I can
give it a shot. I have been thinking
it would be. Oh oh
oh. Yikes.
Did you hear that? There's a little voice.
How much did you pay for that?
I don't remember. It was during their crowdfunding
and that was
I think over a year ago now. I can't remember.
Chris believed in it?
Maybe it wasn't a year ago. Maybe it was the beginning
of the year.
Really if I wasn't going to
you know a lot of times
a lot of times I will
buy something specifically so
I can have it for review on the show.
And that does fall into the category of
this from a news
standpoint is an interesting topic
and it's really nice to be able to contribute
some actual genuine
observations on the product in
the shows. So for me that pushes it
over the line. If I didn't have that I don't
think I'd push it over the line.
But it's fair enough.
I think the latest update
from crowd supply said that
the Librem 13 would ship in late
October.
The 15.
Oh right. Maybe you order the 13.
No the 15 is October 19th
it says here.
OK. So today
is October 27th.
All I'll say is that
the Librem
is about three times over
the price of where you
can get it elsewhere.
And
if you want... Yeah but you get hardware kill switches
though Wimpy. Remember?
Have you
actually seen those?
Well
we'll see. We'll see. The jury is out.
We'll see. Well Chris look
you know if you want
to review another
hardware platform then I know
Entroware would be interested
in hooking you up with one of their new Skylake
devices. Oh they should email me. That sounds fun.
I would not mind a Skylake device. That sounds cool.
Well all right. I know my
quest. I feel like this quest
this quest for like a laptop
that would be available in the stores you walk
in and that thing runs Linux it's just...
It's impossible. We're so close but yet
so far away. Like there's really great
places now to go get good devices
like Entroware System 76
and even Dell has
Linux too. Right? Does Dell start
shipping that again? I can't keep track of what they do with Linux.
But in theory they will. OK. So there
are... But you have to know.
That's the thing. You have to know.
Just spend a significant time investment
in getting all that out. You know what else
you have to know? You ready for this Wes?
linuxactionshow.reddit.com
That's where you go to give feedback to this show
or jupyterbroadcasting.com
slash contact. You can choose Linux unplugged
from the drop down. We'd love to get your
feedback. Yes we do. Join us live
jblive.tv. We do this show Tuesdays
jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get it in your
local time zone. It's 2pm pacific
usually when we start. We usually start a little bit before that.
You know just for funsies.
Wes anywhere you want people to check you out online?
Not this week. But there should be some
stuff coming. Mysterious.
Follow the network at jupyter signal for live stream
announcements and things like that. Linux
Action Show on Sunday this week. Moving
to Sunday this week
to make room for some stuff. So check
out Linux Action Show on Sunday instead of Friday.
And see you right back here next week everybody.
Alright
Wes we're all done. We're out of here. We're done.
Mission accomplished.
Yes it was. Thanks everybody.
Thank you everyone.
Sorry for being a grumpy
old sod about Nebrum.
No no it's fine. It's good.
I'm sure you'll have fun
reviewing the device. Oh well we'll see.
Linux communities survive on
grump. So it's needed.
I think people
have gotten a little too
sensitive about criticism.
Just saying there's people out there that get a little too sensitive
about it. Sometimes criticism can be well
placed. So criticize Chris as much as you
want. He takes it very well. Oh my god don't
they. Oh brilliant.
If there is seriously
people just criticize me constantly.
They really do. And that's how you got so good.
Oh sure. That's why you moved away
from IRC. Why you moved away from
Telegram.
No kidding. No that's
not true. I'm in IRC all the time. But yeah
it is
very true. And you know honestly
there's just tools to tune it out
too if it gets ridiculous. That's really what
it's about is like you know
there are there are there are plugins to
you know just turn off comments when you don't
want to see them. And there's there's all kinds of things you can
do but you just got to walk the line because you don't want to overdo
it either. JBDotless.com JBDotless.com
I wasn't I wasn't trying to enroll
myself into your twit filter. I was
I was just trying to
provide some
level headed. I suppose
I'm just
forewarning you.
Yeah.
Oh man.
There's a little bit of a bummer.
It's a bit of a bummer. And you know what
else is if if if you
if you if you had paid
for the
for the Librem 13 what
you can get for it elsewhere and what
you know what you pay for it elsewhere
it's a good machine.
But it's like three times more
expensive through Librem
and they're trying to pitch this as like
an Apple type
product and it just isn't that.
So yeah.
It's well you know fundamentally how
does a brand new company
compete with a 30 year old company
at manufacturing. How do you even do that fundamentally.
Even if it's well and
the other thing is is that Pureism have tried to
pitch that they know they're doing all of this manufacturing
themselves and that's not the case either.
So you know it's
a little bit smoke and mirrors.
Mm hmm.
So Chris can I criticize
you for being so negative on the
Xiaomi laptop.
Sure. Yeah that's fine. Yeah you think
you think it has a you think it has a good chance of becoming
big. Well I
won't make any
prophecy but this company has been doing
great phones and
they really it seems like they really
have a great price to performance
ratio and also their devices
are always very well thought out
and they are also a very big manufacturer
of phones. So I think they have
quite some experience and I was actually hopeful
that they might shake up things a little bit.
Well you should have said that in the show.
That's a good you know I hope
and I agree. I think probably
if you could I would I would criticize our takeaway
on is it could be big for
for thousands and thousands of people but
just not for us. I mean that's that's jaded
Americans. Yeah. The problem is
getting into the U.S. market I think
for a lot of these products.
Not really. The Chinese market
is gigantic
and that's
this we like we
get this in Ubuntu we get like
when is it coming to the U.S. when is it coming
to the U.S. and there's like 300 million
people in the U.S. or whatever your
population is but there's a shit ton of
people over in China as well
and those people are
people who are actually buying devices
who don't
currently have a device and
or don't currently have a laptop and so
there's a gigantic untapped
market over that side
of the planet. And that middle that middle class over there is
expanding you know I mean there's
there is a lot there's a lot of
growth potential over there right now. Yeah. When
when Apple's profits in just China
dwarf Samsung
and Motorola and LG
and everybody else combined
you know that's a big market.
Yeah. Also China has one seventh
of the world's population so
yeah and so it could be
I'm really excited for my Chinese MacBook Air.
Yeah. Yeah. So exactly
it could be a Chinese MacBook Air exactly
and it could eventually make its way over.
Exactly like a MacBook Air. Well that picture
might literally be a MacBook Air.
I don't know. Yeah. Well you know I'm curious
if. Yeah that's the funny thing.
I saw a comment before
it was really funny
in IRC I saw a comment that said
that they could just
ship from China a
MacBook that has an Apple logo
that just runs elementary OS.
I thought that was funny. But I'm
bummed.
What's new mate?
I have been looking at
new phones like you know
looking at what alternative devices
are there out there and the
Xiaomi phones look
really nice. They're
nice mid to high range
high end like you're talking like
three gig of RAM rather than two.
They look with 4G
chipsets and decent resolution
screen and multiple
SIM slots and all that kind of stuff for
a really decent price
point like $180 or something like that.
Yeah I know. But you have to get rid of the software
if you've used one and the Chinese software
on there oh man.
Right. Probably wipe it and put
cyanogen or something else on there.
Anyway.
It almost reminds me of that Windows firmware
thing with the
I don't know that it was
Windows something
with the BIOS or something like
that with the firmware that something
was in there. I saw I heard
on a previous show I don't know if it was Linux Action
Show or Linux Unplugged or something like that
but I heard about
Windows loading something
onto your oh yes it was
for the OEM or the OEM
laptops where the manufacturer
or someone could put
special firmware on your
on your
on your device whenever you installed
Windows on the if you reinstall
Windows it would automatically install those applications
again. Yeah.
It kind of reminds me of that. Yeah.
Yeah. Again.
I think we should go with What's New Mate
or Mate. That sounds good to me. I think I like it.
It was a good conversation.
Thank you Wimpy for making it in here on the
and thank you Poppy for paying Wimpy.
No thank you.
Thank you very much. I'm just Popey's
he summoned you
we were going to
well it was either that or sick the whole chat room on you
and so we figured that was probably more more efficient
to anything. Well yeah. Yeah.
So thank you for making it. And thank
you guys for being here. Yeah.
And so chat room don't forget I mentioned it right
at the end of the show but we're going to do Linux Action Show on
Sunday. Sunday.
Probably 10 a.m. or regular time. Yeah.
So OK. All right.
Bye Mumble Room. Thank you for being here.
When do you change your clocks? Is it
Saturday night Sunday morning.
Oh my God. Oh my God.
Is that a thing. Could I possibly
have you change this weekend.
Oh why did I have to.
On the one day we moved back to Sunday.
Oh my God.
Oh my God. It's horrible.
That could not have gotten more worse.
Just set it back an hour. Yeah.
That is horrible.
Just do it early on Saturday.
You know what makes it even more complicated
is Noah is traveling across time zones right now.
And he will be traveling
while we're doing the show across time zones.
Oh that's going to be disaster.
Holy crap.