Oh my god, Wes.
You're waiting for WWDC.
You know it.
You're waiting for WWDC
to see what the new MacBook Pros
are gonna look like, aren't you?
I'm hoping it's just all touch bar.
It's just one giant touch bar, Chris,
and then that's it.
No more keyboard, no more track pad.
It's the touch pad.
Wow.
I mean, cause I'm really done
with this whole Linux thing anyway, you know.
I want that, I want something stable.
And it makes sense, you know, Dan's on the Mac,
so that way when you guys are doing TechSnap,
you're on a common platform.
Yep.
That makes a lot of sense.
And you know that OS X is like the homeboy for Skype.
That's just where it shines.
Right, that's his predominantly used platform.
And then, of course, the studio here
is switching all to Macs.
Yes.
So, you know, we just recently made a transition to Linux,
and now that we've made that transition,
obviously we'll be making a transition to Mac OS.
So.
Like when that new Mac Pro comes out.
Right, so when you consider the fact
that the studio's gonna be on the Macs,
Dan's on a Mac, you should probably get a Mac.
And I plan to release a Jupyter broadcasting touch bar app.
Oh.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, a touch bar app.
So it's got like, it's got the, right on there,
right on the touch bar.
Yeah, that's one of the buttons.
Some Stallman things.
Yeah, yep, just three things actually.
Stallman, the DING, obviously.
Obviously.
Of course.
And then just a button that loads our webpage.
You just push that button and it just loads our webpage.
Oh yeah, jzlive.tv, right there.
Yeah, cause you know, nobody's buying keyboards
with the custom buttons anymore,
but touch bar apps, people be desperate for those.
And with all the switching over to Macs,
it just seems to make a lot of sense.
And you can monetize.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 199 for May 30th, 2017.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's been trying out so many different projects this week.
It might be time for a nuke and pave.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
I hope this is one of those episodes
where people will walk away
and they're going to want to try at least something
that we talked about today,
because goodness knows I have,
I have been trying out some really great projects this week
and I got just a couple of them that we're going to share.
I've also got like a whole list of things
I could talk about for future episodes,
but we'll get into all of that
because before we can get there,
there are some big updates in the open source community
and in Linux that we want to talk about.
I've been going through the list today, Wes,
and I was like, geez, how do we even,
how do we even sort through these things?
So what I've tried to do this week
is we're going to start with some of like
the official newsy stuff.
And then I'm going to gush about our community
for a little bit.
Then we're going to replace Evernote once and for all.
Yes!
And all your other apps.
Those of you who need to improve your focus,
well, there's a GNOME extension for you.
And finally, we'll solve the problem
of old smartphones not getting update.
Then we'll talk a little bit about Chaos Bot,
the huge improvements coming to the Plasma desktop.
And then finally, finally, my friends,
you can stop hating Docker now
and we can all have a little fun with KiteMatic.
I'll drink to that.
Yeah, buddy, yeah, buddy.
Speaking of which, Wes brought us in some IPAs this week.
And these are some serious ones,
some local brews from Seattle
because beer matters in Seattle, it says.
That's right, it does.
I like that, that's pretty good.
That's pretty good.
When it rains as much as it does here,
you gotta have something to lift your spirits.
Wes, you know, really though, you're a gentleman
because you've had a heck of a weekend.
It's true.
You did the thing this weekend
that I hope I never ever have to do, and that's move.
I hate moving.
It's really the worst.
I mean, there's so much excitement and other things,
but you can't get there
because of all the other bullshit right in the way.
Yeah, not only is it just tons of physical work
and disruption to your life,
it is so much coordinating of little details
that are extremely obnoxious.
And then it is so many things not coming through
that you then just have to like,
well, we're rolling with that bunch.
Exactly, yes.
We're gonna roll with that bunch.
So it's really cool.
Not only am I glad you could make it,
but it's really cool that you're able to
bring us in a couple of local brews.
The worst part is I don't even have internet yet
at the new place.
So it's like the backwoods.
So are you like tethering or what are you doing?
Yes, I did buy myself a new Unifi access point.
Oh, cool.
So that's set up.
I got it piggybacking on one of those Xfinity Wi-Fi's,
but it's so slow.
So yeah, I've just been tethering, which is.
Yeah, yeah, I know what that is.
Because it's one of those things you have to schedule
and then they're gonna be there, of course,
between 8 a.m. and noon or something like that.
So good luck.
Yeah, I'm like, well, how are you gonna work from home
if you don't yet have internet to wait for the guy
to show up to install the internet?
So go ahead, take advantage of the JB1 connection
while you're here, Wes.
It's so sweet.
Yes, yes.
Well, we do have some news, quote unquote,
to get into this week, but before we do,
we gotta bring in our log.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, hello, hello, hello.
Woo, but now, you know what, I swear,
if we did a little pre-planning,
our virtual log there could do like a little harmonious,
hello, hello, hello, hello.
We just gotta tune it.
Yeah, yeah.
Hello.
Hello, some lads.
And then we'll put like an auto-tune filter on there.
That would be amazing.
If anybody knows that's possible with the X32,
at Chris Elias, let me know.
All right, so let's start with a semi-serious story
that's not really getting a lot of discussion
in any of the Jupiter broadcasting shows
or any of our friends really,
it's not really huge to those of us
that are just daily desktop Linux users,
but it's something that I think
is worth making people aware of,
and it's a seven-year-old Samba flaw
that allows attackers to access
thousands of Samba systems remotely.
It's a CVE-2017-74-94, and it affects all versions of Samba
that are newer than Samba 3.50,
which was released in 2010.
Ouch.
Yeah, all versions onward are vulnerable
to remote code execution vulnerability,
allowing a malicious client to upload a shared library
to a writable share,
and then cause the server to load and execute it.
Yep, pretty much exactly what you don't want to happen.
Now, this story didn't get a ton of attention
until WannaCry came along,
and then everybody was like,
well, if this could happen with WannaCry,
maybe it could happen with SambaCry.
It didn't take off, but they tried to make it SambaCry.
They tried to, and you know, the thing is,
is by the time we're hearing about this,
the reality is that your distro
has already sent out patches.
So I was talking with some people who are like,
people I know who are casual Linux users,
and they'd had some problems with their work computers,
and they'd been like told that,
oh yeah, no, Linux is usually more secure,
and they were kind of like asking me about this and this,
and they'd heard about WannaCry,
and so I was having to try to explain this,
and it really struck me that like, yeah, you're right.
You know, if you just like, the update thing,
a bunch of you, update comes up, you hit update,
you're probably gonna be fine,
but really it seems like where this is gonna bite us
is like everything in the Linux ecosystem
is all of those embedded devices
that will never, ever get patched,
or if they do, how many people are ever going
to actually update that firmware?
Yep, and that's why I wanted to include it
as a discussion piece,
because I think that is the part that matters,
is the reality is many of us probably have routers
that have Samba built in,
because we got a USB port, you can hook a USB.
Exactly, yeah, there's a lot of those.
Yeah, there's so much Samba out there in the wild.
In fact, it's one of the little statistics
that the Samba, I always shouldn't say little,
I don't mean to demean it,
it's one of the statistics that the Samba project
is very proud of, is that Samba is one
of the most widely deployed open source projects.
DVRs use it, and some applications have Samba baked in.
So the issue, the flaw, I guess,
is really in the way Samba handled shared libraries.
So the remote attacker could use
the Samba arbitrary module loading vulnerability
to upload a shared library to a writable share,
and then cause the server to load the malicious code
and run it.
Just one line of code is required
to execute malicious code on the affected system.
And then, of course, when it's an open source thing,
I mean, this happens with Windows,
but it happens at a really kind of amazing rate
with open source stuff.
Metasploit and others already have created
penetration testing frameworks to take advantage
of this exploit. Of course.
Just like within days, like just within days.
I will say, that is kind of handy, though.
I'm always, you know, whenever these comes out,
sometimes it's not easy to be able to repro on your side.
And I'm always kind of curious, you know, like,
hey, is this like, am I vulnerable?
How do I test that?
So it's nice if you can get an easy to use framework
and you're like, yep, I just hacked myself.
All right, great. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Samba's already issued patches,
so that's sort of how this,
the information doesn't get really released
until the upstream projects have had a chance
to look at the vulnerability and potentially come up
with a fix, and they usually have a timeline.
So you're saying we live in the age
of responsible disclosure?
I believe this is generally how it goes these days.
Yeah, not always, and sometimes projects
don't meet the timeline that they're given
and it gets disclosed.
That generally happens, though, more with Microsoft
than it is with open source projects tend to get it,
they tend to get it done in remarkable time, actually.
But anyways, the issue isn't so much
how fast the upstream project gets it done,
it's actually the issue is how fast the distributions
get it out the door.
Or if you're using a distribution that's still maintained.
So Samba has patched versions 4.64, 4.5.10, and 4.4.14.
Now, you might notice that three dots
are missing in that list,
and so after a couple of days of discussion,
Good Guy Samba decided to actually also,
I kind of love those problems,
Good Guy Samba also decided to release patches
for Samba 3.0.37, 3.2.15, and 3.3.14.
So even though they're no longer officially supported
by the Samba team, they decided to release patches.
That's really nice.
They're clearly very busy,
so if you appreciate the work they're doing here,
maybe go help them redesign their website.
Oh, man, yeah, you know,
somebody who used to go to that Samba project,
it's so funny, when you first get into this stuff,
at least for me, when I didn't have any idea,
I got, one of the ways I got into Linux
was through the Samba project.
Yeah, you're like, oh, suddenly I don't have to have
this horrible Windows file server?
Yeah, yeah, and we were, that's funny,
you and I were just talking about remote profiles
in the pre-show, we were hosting a bunch
of terminal servers users' remote roaming profiles,
which caused a ton of open connections
to the NT4 server when users would log in.
Right, anytime anyone logs in.
Yeah, and so when you have 700 users logging in at once
across 120 terminal servers,
it causes a massive, massive issue,
and Samba was capable of handling that load,
NT4 and even Windows 2000 were not,
and so I got in as a way to solve problems
we were having, limits we were having
with our Windows servers in many areas,
in network proxying, but in storage,
and Samba was part of that storage solution,
so for me, obviously, the place to get the best
documentation was gonna be Samba.org.
Obviously, you go to Samba.
Right from the source.
And they did have great documentation for a long time,
but it's so funny now, a decade later,
no way in hell would I do that.
I would go look up the documentation
that was the most current, that was the most applicable.
If it was Arch, I would go to the Arch Wiki.
If it's Ubuntu, I would go whatever resources
were Ubuntu-specific or Fedorae.
I would go to a distro-specific outlet,
and I would make sure that the date was relevant
and all of this stuff.
It's a totally different approach.
Now understanding the complexities of the ecosystem
that I would take, and so the Samba website,
even back then, it really hasn't changed much.
It was horrible back then, and it's still pretty awful.
It's got a little better, but it's still pretty bad.
Anyways, so go patch your Samba, guys.
Don't be like a bunch of Windows XP users sitting around.
Yeah, it does affect Samba 4.3.11 XMM.
Now, let's talk a little bit about the community
for a second here.
Oh.
A few weeks ago, we talked about Caster Soundboard.
I'm giving you updates on it.
Caster Soundboard has been driving
all of the sound effects in this week's show,
and last week's as well, and all of the shows,
and holy crap is it great.
It is really something that,
if you ever needed a soundboard for anything,
for a presentation you're giving
or for a podcast you're recording,
holy shit is it great.
And one of the things they've done
is they've implemented remote control support,
the open sound control protocol into Caster Soundboard,
and so Oscar wrote this amazing how-to
on how to remotely control the Caster Soundboard
using an Android, or I think iOS,
but using an Android device.
Yeah, iOS too, yep.
And really look at this thing.
Like first of all, it's amazing you can do this,
but second of all, the amount of work and passion
that is going into this Caster Soundboard is.
This is some documentation too.
Like, not only just making the features, but then.
It's super good documentation.
Yes, I know, with really good layout,
and screenshots, and structure,
and easy to follow and understand,
and JB references throughout.
I just, I can't believe what I'm seeing here.
And also the Python visualizer that we use
for User Air and Linux Action News,
also been getting some love from the community.
Huge improvements coming.
I've already heard from other podcasts
that are thinking about trying it.
It seems like a great tool for audio podcasts,
it really does.
It's so awesome that anything we can do,
working with the OBS project, or doing projects like this
to make media production under Linux better,
just really excites me.
And so to see the community just,
like this, where we're at with Caster Soundboard
would never have happened without the community.
And now I really think that Linux podcasters,
and other platforms, you can use it on other OSs too,
are really gonna have an amazing tool going forward.
And then to combine it with documentation like this.
And the thing is, is like being able to control
the soundboard from your remote system.
Here he has an example of on a Galaxy Tab 4,
like imagine you have like an old tablet sitting around.
Wes could have a tablet there.
We've talked about this before,
but Wes could have a tablet there on the table
and say he went to a conference.
He could come back with a few sound clips loaded up,
and you could kick him off as we're talking about it.
Wouldn't have to do any post editing,
or any, just have it right cued up.
That would be amazing.
Yeah, or if we're doing like a,
if we're doing like a, more of like a morning zoo show
where we had a lot of sound effects,
you could have access to the board,
I could have access to the board.
It would really be cool.
Anyways, thank you to Oscar for making that awesome write up
and thank you to the whole community
for working on the caster soundboard.
You can get it at github.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
Also, it's just great to see that repo grow,
you know, the organization.
Yeah, yeah, let's go look at some of the, let's go.
Can we get to a.
We talk a lot about open source on the network.
So it's cool to see some open source stuff in the network.
101 commits.
Nice.
Yeah, 13 contributors.
That's actually awesome.
How do you, okay, insights.
Here we go.
So let's get some graphs on it.
What does that tell us?
Cause you know, it's all been,
it's all been relatively recent, right?
So, so let's take a look at some of these stats.
So looking at just like at the last month
from April 30th to May 30th, we've closed 20 issues,
13 new issues, merged 25 poll requests.
Gosh, look at these guys involved with this.
This is so awesome.
13 authors, 71 commits, 156 files, 12,980 additions,
and 1,642 deletions.
Thank you everybody who's been involved
with Caster Soundboard.
It is such a cool project.
Thank you to Oscar for doing that right up.
That looks, looks kind of amazing.
It really does.
It's pretty cool to see that, Wes.
It's pretty cool.
Also, I want to mention,
speaking of community involvement,
Linux Unplugged has a Reddit now.
You can go to reddit.com slash R slash Linux Unplugged
to submit stuff in here.
I want to say thank you to Reg Gaster.
I'll be talking about one of the things
you submitted here in a little bit this week.
Also, this is a cool one.
Didn't really think it was worth putting in the show,
but Chaotic Kernel submitted this GPS share utility,
which is a utility that lets you share
your GPS device location information
over the local network, and it's written in Rust.
So it replaces some cloud provider stuff
if you just want to do like a small little GPS sharing thing.
That's pretty neat.
Mm-hmm.
And you know we have a soft spot for Rust.
That's right.
Also, if you didn't know, like you know,
say you're Popey and you haven't been here for a while,
welcome back, Popey.
It's good to see you.
Welcome.
Hello, sir.
Hello, hello, hello.
Hello.
Hey, you smell great.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I do, actually.
I do.
All confirmed.
It's mostly IPA I smell like,
but anyways, it does smell delicious.
Popey, I know it's been a little while,
so I didn't know, I don't know if you're aware,
but we're almost episode 200.
Good Lord.
I know, I don't.
It's shocking.
Is that metric or imperial?
No, no, I measured it with both systems,
and it checks out.
It actually checks out.
It's the one number where the two systems converge.
It's beautiful.
I've actually constructed a lab
where I'm watching the decay of an atom
just to confirm, because I can't believe it,
but so far it seems to check out.
And as is proper style,
I don't really have anything prepared for 200 itself,
which is next week.
Oh my God!
Oh my God.
So we don't really have anything planned.
Except a great show, as usual.
Yeah, of course.
Duh.
Come on, Chris.
But what is coming up here soon is America's birthday.
The greatest day in the world.
Which we will be taking over and renaming.
Deluxe Unplugged's birthday.
So for the fourth.
How old is America now?
Hey Wes, Google that real quick.
Hey, let's see.
Alexa, how old is America?
Let's see what she says.
What'd she say?
240 years old.
Oh, she knows.
And don't we look just fine for that?
Okay, let's see if Siri knows.
How old is America?
Okay, I found this on the web for how old is America.
Totally worthless.
Oh my God.
Way to go, Siri.
I love how it starts being like,
listen, I don't really know.
So here's where I got it.
You shouldn't trust me, but this is the thing.
It's so couchy.
Yeah, can't wait to put that in a tube.
That's gonna be a real successful product, Apple.
Go ahead, put that in a tube.
All right, so let's ask the Google Assistant
just really quickly.
Okay, Google.
How old is America?
United States of America was founded in 1776.
Well, so she didn't really answer the-
You're making me do the math here?
Yeah, so the-
Come on, Googs.
So the Echo is the only one that successfully
really answered the question.
And also, did you notice though
that they all allowed me to say America?
They never, like none of them got confused.
Well, actually, hold on, maybe that was.
How old is the United States of America?
Okay, I found this on the web.
Nope, Siri's dumb either way, it doesn't matter.
It doesn't, nope, Siri's just stupid.
So anyways, for America's birthday,
and for America's birthday,
and for Linux Unplugs 200 episode,
which will be 200-ish,
we're gonna have a barbecue here in the studio.
I've only heard from like three people
that are gonna make it.
So right now it's you, me, the beard,
and three other people that are getting burgers and dogs.
And maybe we should do like a chicken.
Oh, Wes, you were gonna do ribs.
Yeah.
The Wes, gosh guys, if you want the Wes Payne ribs,
you should probably come to the studio.
That's true.
I mean, we can do other things too, I'm open to ideas.
I just wanted, I thought we needed
some sort of non-standard grill item, something special.
Yeah, yeah, so if you're gonna make it,
let me know, at ChrisLAS,
or, this is where I was building,
join our new official Jupiter Broadcasting Telegram group.
It's official now.
It is.
Are you in there?
You're in there, aren't you?
Yeah, it's pretty crazy these days.
It is pretty crazy.
But it's crazy like in a good way.
It's like when Twitter was good.
I'm still kinda trying to figure out
exactly how to use a Telegram group, you know?
I use it like I use Twitter.
I really do.
You should ask, you should ask.
It's like somewhere between Twitter and IRC and.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Bit.ly, bit.ly slash jbtelegram.
Bit.ly slash jbtelegram.
Wimpy, you're in a few groups.
How do you manage all of that?
Well, the first thing you do is,
every time you join a group, you mute notifications.
Yeah, absolutely, yes.
And yeah, I don't know how to use Twitter,
but I think what you're driving at
is how I should use Twitter,
which is you don't read everything.
Obviously, you read everything
in the Ubuntu Podcast Telegram group.
Obviously.
Because it's all excellent content.
But the other groups, you read what you can see
whilst you're in there,
and then when you wake up in the morning,
you just fly by the 500 notifications that you've missed.
Yeah, yeah.
And that's sort of, I dip in.
It's like a river, and I dip in for a swim,
and then I dip out.
And pinned messages can be nice.
Yes, that's true.
So, Popey, what happened when you asked Mycroft
how old America is?
Should we find out?
Yeah, yeah, oh yes, yes.
Mycroft, how old is America?
Not as old as England, so it doesn't matter.
That is pretty much on point.
All right, good, very good, thank you.
Yeah, Mycroft makes a good point.
This weekend, the village I lived in
celebrated our 900th birthday.
Wow.
Now listen.
Yeah.
And you don't look a day over 799.
We've got some old trees in my neck of the woods.
Does that count?
Can I, no, no, no, it doesn't, does it?
Well, very good.
Bit.ly slash jbtelegram.
Oh my gosh, guys, there's so many things
I wanna talk about today.
Let's mention real quickly before we go crazy.
Wimpy, how do you feel about talking,
teasing a little bit about your recent shenanigans
with eGPU testing?
Are you ready or do you wanna save it for a little longer?
I can tease some stuff.
Yeah, do, okay, so hold on a second.
Let me do a little teasing here.
Let me tease DigitalOcean.
DigitalOcean.com, go over there,
create your account, and use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
It's one word, it's lowercase, it's easy,
you put it together, you smoosh it together,
you create the account, and you get a $10 credit
when you apply DOUNPLUGGED.
Now, once you've got the account set up,
I'm not gonna tell you how to do your business.
But if I were you, if I were you,
take a couple of things we've talked about
and just say the last two weeks on this show.
Just take what your favorite one
and try it out on a DigitalOcean Droplet.
It's so fast, it's so easy to use.
The interface is super simple.
The SSD storage is lightning fast.
Faster than lightning.
I don't even know how fast it is, it's too fast.
I'm making pew-pew, right?
I'm making pew-pew, it's like pew-pew fast,
that's how fast it is.
Presidentially fast.
I don't really know what that means.
I don't know what that means either.
That's how fast it is.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
They have an API that's really easy to integrate
with desktop applets for your Linux desktop
or for Android applications or your own code.
I really like it for that.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Earlier, you were talking about how
you wouldn't really go to the Samba website.
And you were like, I'd go to some distro,
I'd go to the Arch Wiki.
I think you were just trying to be polite though,
because in reality, you would go check out
the DigitalOcean documentation.
I sure would.
In fact, check out this post from May 26th.
How to use GPG encryption in signed messages.
This is an example of a DigitalOcean how-to
that crushes it, because it's not necessarily
specific to DigitalOcean.
I don't mean to tell them something
that maybe they're not aware of,
but guys, I could read this and use this anywhere.
But go over there, check it out.
It's a great guide on how to use GPG on Linux.
It's not even, look at this, look at this.
It's not even distro-specific.
This guide works for Ubuntu, Debian,
CentOS, and Fedora.
Fedora.
Fedora?
Fedora, is that how you say it?
I'm not sure.
You know, if Matthew ever stopped by the show,
he might remember.
Oh yeah, he could tell us.
Anyways, go over to DigitalOcean.com.
They got great tutorials.
They have a really great dashboard.
They have a service that's super, super nice.
Not only do you get up and going in no time,
which is what they like to emphasize,
but the pricing's amazing,
because they have $5 rigs a month,
they have hourly pricing,
they have a bunch of different distros
you can choose from,
and one of my favorite features
is they have an HTML5 console
that works on everything from your tablet
to your Linux desktop,
and there's a lot of stuff you can do
when you get access to that console.
A lot of stuff you can do.
DigitalOcean.com, you go over there,
take advantage of all of that stuff.
Plus, if you're in a team, they support that.
40 gigabit connections to the hypervisors,
highly available block storage
when you need to grow your rig,
monitoring, alerting, when you wanna look like a boss
and know about things before your clients even do.
DigitalOcean.com.
Playing around or putting it in production.
Try it out and just use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
And thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
So Wes, one of the things that I'm thinking
more and more about these days
is a future where I buy a really light and thin laptop
that is using an embedded Intel GPU.
Right.
That is supported under Wayland really well.
And mind you, I'm thinking about this, too, as like.
Because you wanna run Trisco, right?
That's the motivation here.
I wanna run Wayland is what I wanna run.
And I want it to run smoothly.
And I'm really trying to think about
how to do this in the future
where maybe I'm taking a rig
between the studio and the RV a lot.
And one of the things that's jumped out at me
is if we could really nail external GPUs right,
so I could have a laptop that is thin, light, and portable,
but when I need to edit
or I wanna play video games from time to time,
I can buy a box that's a PCI3, like Thunderbolt,
or what, a Thunderbolt 3, that's what it is.
Thunderbolt 3 connected device.
You put a GPU in there.
Then I could hook it up to a laptop.
I could have a lot more horsepower.
But beyond that, I could take this one video card
that I spent all my monies on, this one video card,
and I could move it between my laptop
or a desktop that has Thunderbolt 3
or another laptop or your laptop.
And it's like you invest once in a great graphics card
and then the three or four times a month that I need it,
I've got a plug-in go-to graphics card.
And all the other time,
I've got a super portable, lightweight,
great battery life laptop.
So Wimpy stopped by that official bit.ly
slash JB Telegram group the other day
and was teasing me with a little information
that he's gleaned.
So you've been doing some testing, Wimpy,
on eGPUs, external GPUs, over what,
like Thunderbolt 3 USB-C style connections?
That's right, yeah.
So I've got a Razer Core,
which is the box of tricks that is the external enclosure.
And I've got an Nvidia card in that.
And I've been putting it through its paces
on a number of computers I have
that are Thunderbolt 3 enabled
to see does it work and how well it works.
And this is on modern Linux, like version what?
Well, I've tested Ubuntu 16.04 and upwards.
Okay, so stuff that's easily available.
So like I don't have to be running
some crazy development version of Linux
to get support for this.
No, you can, so in the Ubuntu world,
you will need Ubuntu 16.04.2,
which comes pre-shipped with the hardware enablement stack.
Ah, okay, okay.
And if you don't have,
if you've just upgraded from.0 or.1 of 16.04,
then you have to enable the hardware enablement stack
and that will do the good stuff that you need.
So there must be a downside, right?
I mean, there must be a downside to having an external GPU.
There must be something that is inconvenient about it
other than, I mean, I'm just trying to fathom,
like what would be, I imagine you can't hot swap it, right?
So you can't just be running an X session
and going about your business
and just connect this thing to your computer
and all of a sudden be connected to your eGPU, right?
Yeah, you can do that.
You can hot plug the GPU.
No, see, the folks at Dell told me
that wasn't a possibility.
Well, you can do it under Windows.
It's built into, well, in Windows with additional drivers
on the Razer laptops, it's doable.
You can hot plug the GPU.
And if you know the right incantations,
you can then bring that GPU up
without having to do anything.
The best route that I've got is you can hot plug it,
then use Nvidia settings to switch to that GPU.
And then you have to log out and log back in.
And that's like the safest way
to handle it.
That's not so bad.
So you don't need to do a full reboot.
You can, you know, log out, log in, so that works.
Now, Bash, you had a question in the mobile room.
Go ahead.
I think it was about cost.
Mostly just bringing out,
you were talking about some of the downsides.
I was mostly just talking about cost of them.
Yeah, cause it's like a $500 box.
US greenbacks, right Wimpy?
Yeah, yeah, the Razer Core itself was 499 pounds.
And then you've obviously got to put the GPU
in that as well.
So yes, expensive.
Or, you know, the way that I did this was with Bitcoin.
So the combined cost of the core and the card
was half a Bitcoin.
Yeah, yeah.
And it's crazy to think that you can get something
as expensive of that for a fraction of a Bitcoin now.
It's just mental.
Yeah, I mean, it looks like it's well built.
I mean, it looks like it's a good metal body.
It looks like it's like a solid piece of equipment.
Does it feel good?
The Razer Core is extremely well constructed.
Integrated power supply?
Yeah, it's a 500 watt integrated power supply.
It's got fancy glowy, glowy lights and all of that carry on.
I'm not into all of that, but if you like your things
flashing and blinking at you, you can do all of that.
Is it loud?
No, not really.
When it's just in general use, it's barely audible.
If you're playing a game, then yes, the fans kick up.
I think you can negate that to some extent
by buying graphics cards with different cooling strategies
and what have you on them.
But maybe that's a downside for some.
My experience is that any gaming PC that's competent
makes some degree of fan noise.
So have you been able to accomplish my dream world
of having several machines that have this Thunderbolt 3
connection and essentially have one great GPU
that you can move between them?
That's exactly what I've got.
So I've now got a hot stinking GPU
that I can move between four devices at will.
Wow, and it just works under Linux fairly well.
Yeah, there's one caveat, which is right now
in the Linux kernel, it doesn't support
the Thunderbolt security profiles.
So consequently, it will only work on a computer
where you can disable the Thunderbolt security model
or enable what's known as legacy mode.
Once you've done that, it works.
But as I was doing some research,
there's fixes coming for that fairly soon in Linux.
So you can actually keep that enabled
in something that you want enabled, right?
Because this is a device you're plugging
into the bus of your computer.
And that's a BIOS, so you have to have a BIOS.
It's a BIOS setting at the moment.
So I've got three laptops that supported that in the BIOS
and one that doesn't.
So I've got one laptop that's got Thunderbolt port
where you've seen it, it's that HP Spectre.
It's got Thunderbolt ports coming out the Wazoo,
but I can't use this device on it
because Linux just doesn't see it.
Well, it sees it, but it doesn't know how to manage it.
So when those new kernel patches drop,
I shall be testing that with interest.
But the performance games are considerable.
You know, like significant.
So I've got an intro where Athena,
which has got a GTX 980M in it.
And if you're familiar, there's a Unigine
have got a new benchmark tool called Superposition.
And this was recommended to me by Pedro Matos
from Linux Gamecast, because by and large,
this tests the GPU performance
rather than taxing the CPU overly.
So you get a fairly fair comparison of the GPU performance.
I know there are other factors,
but as best as you can manage,
this is a good reflection of GPU performance.
So that 980M can run the Superposition benchmark,
which the default settings are medium 1080p,
and it can conk out a consistent 45 frames per second.
And then when I stick my Razer Core
into the various laptops, that goes up to,
well, on the least performing device
at 80 frames per second and the highest performing
at 107 frames per second.
And this is a really graphical intensive benchmark.
And the gaming for Linux community,
gaming on Linux, they have a benchmark forum.
And in there, they're currently running a,
run the ultra test using Unigine Superposition
and post your benchmarks.
And one of my systems with the Razer Core attached
is the number two placed.
Wow.
Box in that list and top placed.
What was the host system?
Mine.
It was the Entraware host system?
No, my one was a Skull Canyon NUC
with the Razer Core. A NUC, a NUC.
Yeah. Ooh.
Yeah.
I do want one of those, those look sweet.
So you hooked it up, you hooked this eGPU up to a NUC
and you ranked number two in the benchmarking positions
on Linux gaming.
Yeah, uncomfortably number two.
So this has got a 1080Ti, this Razer Core.
And the number one position that it's behind
is a Ryzen 1700 with an 1080Ti on a 16X bus.
And I'm only just slightly behind.
Wow.
So it shifts some data, yeah.
So we've defined good enough.
Well, to me it suggests that perhaps, hmm.
So you're telling me that these, yeah,
cause you're comparing this to machines that have,
you are comparing this to other systems
that have these video cards snapped
into like a 16X PCI slot.
Yeah, yeah.
And my Skull Canyon is four PCI lanes
are exposed over the Thunderbolt port,
but they're shared with the NVMe drive
and several other components on the board.
So it's not dedicated for lanes by any means,
but it's still right up there.
Wow.
Well, will we hear more on the Ubuntu podcast?
Yes, on Thursday this week, Ubuntu podcast is out
and we discuss this at the top of the show.
Ah, attaboy.
I'm looking forward to it.
Me too.
I will follow this topic with much interest
because it seems like it could unlock
both portability and a lot of power.
I'm very excited.
Mr. Popey, it's good to have you back.
I noticed recently you've been tweeting away these days
and I followed the story you were, where was it?
Where was it?
Hold on, wait for it, wait for it.
What to expect and not to expect from Linux Universal Packages
which is the next story in the show.
So I kind of wanted to get your thoughts
on the state of Universal Packages and whatnot.
What do you think, Popey?
Uh-oh.
This post from The New Stack
that I think you tweeted a few days ago, if I remember.
I can't, I can't, that's how it showed up in my list.
Yeah.
What was your takeaway?
Yeah, so it's Bruce Bifield who spoke to a bunch of people
who are involved in these new packaging systems.
Yeah, so look at Bruce.
You know, Bruce should come on this show too.
Yeah, that would be awesome.
That would be really good.
Okay, anyway, sorry.
He spoke to us about snaps and he spoke to people
from the Flatpak project and AppImage
and also people from traditional distros
like our good friend Richard from OpenSUSE
to get everyone's hot take on what the new packaging formats
mean for Linux desktop.
And yeah, I think it's fairly fair and balanced
and covers everyone's perspective.
I don't think everyone agrees on this,
but yeah, I think it's pretty fair.
Yeah, and Wes and I were just chatting recently
as in like 45 minutes ago about Visual Studio Code
just recently announced that they have a snap available.
Right.
That's pretty cool.
And I also saw like a Qt-based Flatpak manager
that people are working on.
It's like a graphical Qt-based Flatpak manager.
So the Universal Package March,
even though we're not talking about it as much these days,
is continuing, it continues on.
So yeah, check out the new stack.
Although, I mean, people mention it as wars,
but I really don't think the people who work on it
see it as war as such.
Yeah, okay.
I think we're all working on our own thing,
but the Flatpak developers are working on a great way
to deliver the GNOME experience and GNOME applications
to their users and tailoring it specifically
for their needs.
AppImage developers are working on their system
for making sure that it's super easy for people
to just download a file and then run it
and get the application.
And we're working on our unique selling points
that make ours slightly different.
So I think they've all got their own selling points
and they're all slightly different.
I don't think we're all really seeing each other as war.
I think you're underselling Snap's competitive advantage
in this space.
So I would phrase it as this.
Flatpaks are a reinvention of PPAs that nobody needs
and ain't nobody got time for that.
AppImage is what's already being done on Mac OS
and then developers have to create things like Sparkle,
which are their backassword workarounds
to get users to update their applications
after they've already been dropped onto their file system.
And Snap package brings us sort of the best of both worlds
where we can have a centralized store and an index
where it's easy for users to search, it's easy to install.
And on top of that, it's particularly well suited
for not only server side, but graphical applications.
So in my opinion, if one of them could win out,
I would absolutely want it to be Snaps
based on all lessons we've learned
from all other operating systems
and things we've tried on Linux before.
After that, I'd want it to be AppImage
because at the end of the day,
I just want the damn application.
And then the very number three on my list
would be Flatpaks because honestly, I think PPAs suck.
Beside outside of a limited scope for testing applications,
for users to maybe like beta test applications
before they're put in the repo or something like that,
PPAs are fine.
But as a way to distribute software to everybody
in the world and then have random people who have lives
and they maybe have children and a job
to then maintain a repo, it's ridiculous.
And Flatpaks don't seem to solve
that particular problem at all.
And Snaps do, and also AppImages do.
Out of any of them though,
if any of them take off, I'd be happy.
I would be satisfied if any of them are successful.
It just seems to me that right now,
things have slowed to a crawl.
And I don't know what exactly I was expecting,
but I was-
Has slowed in what way?
I mean, we spend all our days talking to developers
about what they want.
So like, we developed Snappy and SnapCraft,
and we think we know what developers need,
but because we are essentially a company full of engineers,
but we speak to developers who create things
in new and interesting and different ways.
And these can be proprietary software vendors
who just want to get their code out there to Linux users,
or they could be open source software developers,
or they could be proprietary companies
who are making open source software
like Microsoft with Visual Studio Code.
And some of those people have very specific requirements.
So what we're doing is spending time listening to them
to find out what it is they want.
I'll tell you what I was, I'll tell you,
the only way I can answer your question is tell,
I can tell you what I was hoping for by about now-ish was,
so say Visual Studio Code is announced as a Snap package.
Hooray, that's great.
You go to download Visual Studio Code for Linux
and nowhere on their website
does it mention that as a possibility.
It's not a download link.
It's not like, hey, by the way,
if you're a Snap package user,
they've obviously, they can't be bothered
to update their website.
You're talking about the marketing level and the...
Well, I'm sorry, so let's just do a little less.
So let's just Visual Studio Code.
So you want to go get Visual Studio Code.
Let's just say you want to get Visual Studio Code for Linux.
So I'm gonna Google search Visual Studio Code for Linux.
I would imagine this is how most people would find this.
And then I'm gonna go, I'm gonna,
well, boy, that's not the right link.
The first link's no good.
The second link's what you want.
It's code.visualstudio.com slash download.
And then when you go to that,
I don't know why it's not loading,
but when you go to that, they have devs and they have RPMs.
You can download and things like that,
but they don't have a Snap package
or they don't have a link.
I understand.
And that was the benchmark
I was hoping we would be at by now.
And that really depends on the developer
because some developers have embraced it fully
and some, I could point you at a website
where you go to download the application
and the first thing it says is go and get the Snap
rather than here's Windows, here's Mac,
and Linux, and oh, by the way, there's a Snap.
So it really depends on the developer.
And some of them are at an early stage.
So Visual Studio Code only recently landed in the store.
And you think about the size of the company
behind Visual Studio Code,
these companies don't move super fast.
Whereas little agile developers
who throw their code on GitHub
and just wanna get it out there,
they will accept a pull request that says,
here's how you install a Snap
and you can just provide a pull request
and fix it for them.
Like cost a soundboard, for example.
Yeah, and that's nice.
I guess it's starting to feel like
we're not landing on a universal package format,
we're landing on a couple of universal package formats,
which is not the right fucking thing, it's not.
Because what I want is,
oh, you wanna develop software for Linux,
you use X to distribute software.
And I don't even want it to be like a,
let me go read an internet war
about which particular one is better.
Let me go read a bunch of users' comments
about why Flatpak isn't the next PPA,
and then I'll go base my decision off of that.
I just want it to be so fucking obvious
that if you're gonna make software,
it's like, you're stupid if you don't release it this way.
That's what I want.
Right, like from hearing some of your discussions
with Michael and Coder,
that seems to be like, if it's not that,
then you really lose a lot of people
who can't put that much time in for a niche platform.
Yeah.
And for some developers,
packaging is like the least interesting thing.
Yeah, exactly.
That's, I think, what Wes is saying is like,
I barely even wanna waste my time on Linux to begin with.
Oh, it's Electron?
I'm not even gonna bother to make the Linux version.
Like, these people, as they start to like,
well, maybe I should target Linux.
Maybe I should publish.
And then they start to actually invest time.
The last thing we want is,
oh, but I can't figure out how to distribute the damn thing.
Right, which is exactly why today,
if you go to insights.avante.com,
our most recent blog post is about build.snapgraph.io.
We wanna make it easier,
so you don't have to learn the intricacies
of packaging devs or RPMs
or whatever weird esoteric format it is.
You just blop a YAML file in the master branch
of your project, hook it up to build.snapgraph.io,
and every time you land an update, it goes in the store.
So you just don't have to worry about it.
Yeah, nice, nice.
It just goes in for you.
That is nice.
So do you think that it's a give the market time
kind of thing, let the universal package...
I don't wanna call it a war because I...
So we go back.
So this is why...
This, Popeye, I think is why it gets described as a war
is because to get to the goal that I stated earlier,
rather passionately,
you kinda have to have one thing win out.
And that's where the war context comes from.
But if you take the more practical approach
and say, well,
Flatpak is a great way to distribute a lot of software
and snap packages are gonna be a great way to distribute
a lot of software and app image.
Well, then shit, that isn't actually what people want.
But at the same time,
it is the more realistic thing of what's gonna happen.
But on a daily basis, when I'm talking to a developer,
a typical developer will be writing something
either in Go or Rust or with Node.js,
it might be electronic, it might not.
It might be a command line tool.
It might be some amazing utility
that gathers system metrics and puts it in a central place
and you get a lovely web-based dashboard.
Is app image the right way to distribute that software
and deliver updates to their users
on a thing that runs on a remote server?
No, is Flatpak the right thing to do that?
No, it snaps, yes.
So there are certain situations where you can just
really easily show a developer,
this is the right tool for the job
to distribute your software to as many users as possible
and make sure that they're all running
the very latest version of the software as possible.
And each of the others have their niche as well.
So if I was talking to a GNOME application developer,
if I could find one, there aren't actually that many.
When you look at how many projects there are on GitHub
or Bitbucket or GitLab,
there aren't actually that many GNOME native projects.
Most of them I would imagine are known
to the GNOME upstream developers.
So they know who their target audience is.
We're looking at everyone outside that bubble, right?
Which is a huge number of people.
Which is why I think snap packages
have probably the best long-term chance
because you are solving real problems
with distributing server-side software,
which is an obvious strength that Linux
and particularly Ubuntu have.
And so people will get familiar with that package format
on the server side, right?
Yep.
And then by the time you're looking at distributing software
for the desktop, you're like, well, we're already doing snaps
for the server side of this, so why not?
Like if I'm Nullius and I'm making my Nullius server
and I'm making the Nullius for the desktop,
well, if I start distributing Nullius server
in a snap package and I get really familiar
and I have say 15,000 users downloading my snap package,
then it seems like it would just be the next obvious choice
to then use snap package format for the desktop client
that we start officially supporting.
Yeah, I mean, I think in that case, right,
the biggest hurdle is getting the build chains
and familiarity with the packaging format and all that.
So if you've already done that hurdle
and it works on the desktop, then yeah, why not?
Yeah, and I guess I suppose at the end of the day,
if I can install support, if I get support for flat packs
by installing GNOME and whatever distro I'm on,
I have a pretty good chance I can install snap support
and app image is sort of the way it works
and you can just get it.
So what you're saying is we need snap
to be distributed in an app image and then it'll be fine.
No, I'm just saying like the end result
is if I only have to install these
or if I only have to install these two things to get this,
it's not that bad as an end user experience.
It's not so bad.
Yeah, that's true.
I wanna give a little attention to standard notes.
Joey over at OMG Ubuntu wrote about this eight hours ago
and holy crap, if it doesn't just look great.
So it's a simple note killer, really.
I teased it as an Evernote killer
but it's really a simple note killer
which is even better in some sense
and it's totally open source.
It does have a server side component
although you can run the server yourself
but you can get a free sync account.
So calm down, calm down.
I know.
And when you do that, you get end to end encryption
and it encrypts on your device
before it uploads to their system.
So that means you don't have to worry
about them sharing it with like a government request
or something like that if you're super paranoid.
It also means if you lose your password,
you're totally screwed.
So make sure you don't lose your key
because it's encrypted on your end.
It's AES-256 encryption.
They have Mac and Windows, iOS and Android apps
as well as their Linux app.
Automatic sync with no limit on data.
It has web access and if you decide to pay,
you get some nice stuff along with like a new like dark theme
and fancy stuff like that.
You get what's called an extended account.
Oh.
Ooh.
How extended?
Well, it's so extended it unlocks access
to additional features like the ability
to go back in time on your notes.
Up to 100 years.
Which feels pretty optimistic.
I'm not sure what that means.
Like I'm never gonna test them on that.
I'm never gonna test them on that.
You give me, you know what,
you give me a good solid 50 years
and I'm never gonna, I'm never gonna question.
See if your kids are still using it.
Yeah, yeah, they're really gonna care.
And performs real time backups of your notes
to drop Bizzle and Goog drives if you want that.
Also with that extended account,
you get access to additional editors like a markdown editor.
So this is where it becomes relevant.
Markdown editor, that's pretty cool.
So it's standard note.
You could host it all yourself like an animal
or you could pay a slight gentleman's fee
and get access to their extended.
I will say I like the note or the name.
It sounds so antiquated in a way.
Standard, it's like Standard Oil but standard notes.
Actually, I particularly like that.
I got a question for you.
If you're trying to get in the zone,
you may be writing a little code.
For me, it's editing or it's writing.
Sometimes in the past, what I used to do
is I used to play a podcast, maybe like the Ubuntu podcast.
But those guys, they're making such great points.
It turns out it's so good now, you have to listen,
even if you're trying to ignore them.
It's distracting.
So I have to find something else.
So I've been trying stupid Spotify playlists.
I've been trying all these different things
to try to give myself some background noise.
So that way my lizard brain can relax and I can focus.
What do you do?
You know, I'll put things like public radio or some podcasts.
Some NPR that talks like this all the time.
Yes, exactly, because it's all the same tone.
There's no dynamic range there.
Perhaps you should check out Focacil.
It improves your focus and increases your productivity.
Sounds like a prescription drug.
Yeah, I know, right?
Focacil.
Yeah, I'll take that, sure.
It's a gnome extension.
I don't normally share gnome extensions on this show,
but this is just too good to pass up.
It is a gnome extension that plays different nature sounds.
So it's like a white noise or sound machine type.
Oh, you could do rain, you can do wind,
you can do the vibes of the earth,
you can do people chatter, you can do system hums.
It comes with some built-in sounds.
Of course, you can add your own by dropping them in there.
Just make sure you're ready to edit the JSON file.
And it just needs to be MP3.
And then you get a slider built into the gnome menu.
In fact, I have the extension right here.
Yeah, I can't really see it.
I got a screenshot of it though.
And it provides you with background noise.
Do we get a sample of what that noise sounds like?
Do you have that set up?
I have, I couldn't get it.
I apparently I'm missing the dependency,
but they do have a sample.
They do have one here you can listen to.
Here, I'll turn it up a little bit so you can.
Right?
Are you feeling focused?
Very nice.
Yeah, man.
Yeah, super focused right now.
Focused on getting out of here.
Here's the people chatter, which would be the last one
I'd ever use.
It's like you're working in a coffee shop,
but without the coffee.
Here's the nature of the earth sounds.
And this is right there in the film show.
I'm sorry, Wes.
I don't mean to make fun of it, but out
of all of the extensions I've ever seen,
that has to be both the most useful and most hilarious
extension ever.
Can I share?
I want to share something with you real quick
before we move on.
Just a little secret.
I've talked about it before in my vlog.
It's MyNoise.net.
And let me share with you one of my favorite go to bed.
This is when I park Lady Jupes at a rest stop
and the semi-trucks are idling really loud.
I put this on my Bluetooth speaker,
and this is what I listen to.
MyNoise.net I like it so much I'm a patron.
Wow, I could listen to that for hours.
I know.
It's really great.
And they have so much more.
You want to check out another one?
This is rain on a tent.
Wow.
Isn't that great?
Isn't that so great?
So what do the sliders do there?
Well, oh, thank you for asking.
Thank you for asking.
Because what you're actually hearing
is not a single audio stream.
You're actually hearing a seven channel audio stream
being composed in real time in your browser.
And so you can, in real time, tweak different elements
of the stream.
Now, this isn't a particularly good one.
So let's go back.
So for example, of course, I have my favorite one.
I have it bookmarked so that way I can fire it up at any time.
So you see how I have these different ones tweaked?
So if I were to move some of these dials,
I can add more sound effects.
So here's more interface sound effects.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, and here's another one.
And I can pull that away because I found it.
Let's hear it right in the engine room.
And here's like a, this one is kind of interesting.
This is like a more like a 60s sci-fi sound.
Oh, yeah.
Look at that.
It's like beats.
Yeah, and then here's another one that I think is.
Isn't that interesting?
And here's one that I have completely turned off
because it distracts my fiance.
And you can mix it all in real time in your browser.
And they have also, they have ones
that other people have created.
And they have all kinds of stuff.
They have so many interesting different sound effects
you can get.
So that is a real thing.
And I do find it helps me focus.
Having it as an extension in the GNOME desktop, though?
No, I don't think so.
I'm going to install that one after the show.
Post Market OS, aiming for a 10-year lifecycle
for smartphones.
I love this project because why the hell can't we do this?
If you go get a PC from 2007, and you
put a basic, minimal Linux, you put that,
or something classy like Ubuntu Mate on there,
you're going to get a real nice system where
you can do basic computing tasks.
A 2007 PC could surf the web.
It could read emails.
It could listen to podcasts.
It could do IRC chat.
It really would be fine.
And it would even be able to get security updates.
But even a three- or four-year-old Android device,
screw you.
And part of this is because Android's architecture
is in some ways really based on forking the entire code
base for each and every single device out there
that these OEMs come up with.
And there's things like LineageOS,
which do provide even weekly updates, but they're really
based on Android, which means they're always catching up
to whatever Google's doing.
And it's not really great for the root cause of the problem.
So post-market OS thinks they have a solution.
Now, this is just early days, big dreams here.
But they're going to bend an existing Linux distribution
to run on smartphones.
Bend it, Wes.
They're going to apply the necessary changes as small
patches, Wes, upstream, Wes, where it makes sense, Wes.
It's an Alpine Linux-based distribution
called post-market OS, which each phone will
have only one unique package.
All other packages will be shared amongst the devices.
Wow.
Popey, can I ask you what you think of a project like this?
Sounds like Ubuntu Touch.
What do you think?
It's Alpine Linux, and they're not even
going to try to make it all that fancy with a touch UI,
I don't think, right now.
I think they're just going to basically try
to throw some Linux on there and give you some updates
and get some basic use out of the machine.
Do we need another one of these?
Part of me says yes.
It does feel like we have these.
Well, I guess we need one successful one.
Well, I do feel like we should be
able to get more than three or four years out of these devices.
So part of me says yes.
Oh, I completely agree.
Yeah.
Who else is going to solve this problem if not the Linux
community, though?
You know what I mean?
So you're saying that Tizen isn't going to do it?
Maybe.
I end our updates on ChaosBot.
This is so fun.
The beard found this one.
We might talk about this more on news area,
depending where it goes.
It's a social coding experiment, and it's pretty neat.
It's ChaosBot.
It's an experiment to see what happens
when absolute direction of a software project
is turned over completely to the open source community.
So here's how it works.
You fork the code, and you make any changes
that you want to make.
Have at it.
You open up a pull request.
If there is general approval from the community,
the pull request will be merged automatically by ChaosBot.
ChaosBot will automatically update its own code
with changes and then restart itself.
And then the process repeats itself.
Here's some things they feel like this might accomplish.
Number one, it could provide some useful service to people.
And number two, it could be malicious.
Yep.
Number three, it could recreate itself
in a different programming language.
Very likely.
And number four, probably the most likely,
it could break itself and die.
There's no set purpose.
It's up to the community.
Have at it.
I think it's kind of interesting.
What do you think, Wes?
Can we see some interesting results from this?
I mean, it's interesting just as an idea.
And yes, it does seem like it's either going to break,
or the internet is going to evolve itself
another malicious bot.
I'd like to see it.
So go contribute.
Yeah, help it not be evil.
Be part of the chaos.
Go make it download Jupiter Broadcasting Podcast.
Oh, yeah, that's what we need.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
All right, linux.ting.com.
Go there to sign up.
Switch to Ting.
It's mobile done differently.
In fact, if mobile had to start all over again,
this is how they would do it.
The average Ting bill is just $23 per phone per month.
$23 per phone per month.
It's because Ting does mobile differently.
It's $6 for your line.
And then it's just your usage on top
of that for your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes.
You pay for what you use.
However much you talk, however much you text,
and however much data you use, that's what you pay for.
They have nationwide coverage.
There's no contracts.
There's no quote unquote agreements.
And they have a really nice control panel
that gives you your usage, that lets
you turn specific features on and off,
set usage alerts.
They have great customer service.
And one of my favorite features, and I've
been a Ting customer for like two and a half, three years,
two and a half years at least, two and a half years,
and like eight, I don't know, a long time now.
One of my favorite features is they
have a CDMA and a GSM network.
A CDMA and a GSM network means you
can pick whichever one works better in your area.
Or it also means if you inherit a device,
you've got something sitting around,
you can bring it over to Ting, try it out,
and then if it works well for you, switch.
That's what I did.
Now, like I said, it's been a while.
But I had an EVO 4G sitting around on my desk.
So I thought, well, what the heck, why not?
So I took it.
It used to be like a Sprint device or something.
It had a CDMA radio.
And it had WiMAX, which was going
to be the next big wireless technology, was WiMAX.
And I took it out of the desk.
And I thought, well, I'll try it out on Ting.
And I switched it over to Ting.
And I was like, well, holy shit, why
am I not just doing this all the time for all the things?
This is just fine.
It works great.
And it matches my mobile usage perfectly.
And then from that point on, I've switched everything over.
Now I've got multiple devices.
And I'm super, super happy.
Linux.ting.com, go there to get $25 off a device.
Or if you bring a device, get $25 in service credit.
Linux.ting.com.
And a huge thank you to Ting for sponsoring
the Unplugged program.
So I've been having some troubles with Gnome,
which I outlined in user error.
There, that was the sentence I was trying to get out.
And it's mostly around performance.
It's actually been getting me today, during this show,
while we were recording.
We had to stop and restart because Gnome crashed on us.
And for some reason, and I don't really understand why,
and I'm starting to suspect maybe it's a graphics driver
issue, is when Gnome crashes, it also
kills our audio and OBS for like 15 to 30 seconds.
It's just a real bugger.
And so it's within this context that I'm
very, very excited about the new Plasma 5.10 release.
And this guy from the Plasma team over there
has a video about it.
And I thought maybe we'd cover it.
He covers it all right here, the new features
of the Plasma desktop.
After a few months of intensive work,
the KDE community is pleased to announce Plasma 5.10, which
brings many improvements and features to your desktop.
Due to the popular demand, we've changed a folder view
as the default desktop, which allows users
to put whatever files or folders they want on their desktop.
Spring loading in folder view makes drag and drop
files powerful and quick.
When you search in KRunner, it can now
list non-installed applications in the software center.
The icon size in the vertical task manager
is now configurable to support more and more popular
vertical panel usage cases.
Speaking of the task manager, it's
gained options for middle mouse click
so you can group and ungroup applications.
Places jump list actions are available to the file manager
launchers.
So Dolphin and task manager gives you
quick access to locations like your downloads
and your pictures.
The audio volume applet has a handy menu
on each device, which you can use to set the default
or switch the output to a different port.
Interactive notifications now support a context menu
on previews, giving you access to actions
such as open the containing folder, copy, and open with.
It is now possible to resize widgets on the desktop
by dragging on their edges and moving them with Alt-Left-Click,
just like a regular window.
Plasma menu launchers gained a new category
for often used documents and applications.
Lock screen has gained support for media controls,
so you can switch between your favorite songs
without the need to unlock your desktop.
Discover Software Center has gained provisional back ends
for flat packs and snap packages.
It's now possible to use the virtual keyboard on the login
and lock screen.
If you enjoy using Plasma, please
consider donating to KDE so we can work together.
Man, I am so glad I recorded that video because I really
had to go to the bathroom during the show
and I was not sure what I was going to do.
I was not sure how I was going to take a pee during this show
because it's live.
But that was how I did it right there.
And it was with that that also gave us a chance to share
with you all the new features.
Now, I actually thought it was worth playing the video too
because it really, to me, illustrates
a continued steady stream of improved Plasma desktop
releases over and over again.
Yeah, I was shocked this last week or last yesterday.
Yesterday?
It's all a blur.
I hate the internet, dude.
The internet makes everything go by so fast.
Anyways, so yesterday when Linux Action News came out,
Joe told me that he's planning to, well, he's considering,
I shouldn't say planning.
Joe Resington is considering switching to the Plasma desktop
from XFCE.
Is this your doing or is this organic?
No, no, he's just been looking at it.
And it really is because I think they've
had about five or six solid releases after the other that
have been better than the one before it.
And they're adding features that are legitimately useful.
So imagine you get a Plasma desktop notification
that a file has changed in a directory from one of your sync
software.
Well, now you can right click on that thing
and open up the folder.
Just look at it.
Nice.
It's nice.
Yeah, that's very convenient.
Anyways, the Plasma desktop is just
getting better and better.
So I've been thinking about switching back again.
Can't even finish that whole sentence, can you?
I just feel like such a jerk.
But the reality is, so I outlined it in user 10,
but there is a performance issue with GNOME 3 on systems
that you run for, say, more than 20 days.
That's been about, at least for me, and this is with the Nvidia
9-series graphics cards.
I get about 20 days before I start
getting about 15 frames per second when I open up.
Ooh.
The Activities window on GNOME.
And it's really stuttery, and it's really noticeable.
And you combine that with other little problems,
like the fact that GNOME 3 is crashing on our OBS rig.
Or yesterday, I was copying a bunch of files, and X crashes.
And it just screws up my whole system.
And I can't do anything, because I know Nautilus is still
copying files, because the process is still running.
But X is unusable.
I love GNOME, but I'm having so many problems in the last,
say, two months with it.
The one common thread is all of them are on Nvidia systems.
So I actually am willing to consider that it's Nvidia,
not GNOME.
But it's got me wondering if maybe I shouldn't just switch
back to Plasma for a little bit.
And so this new release, it looks pretty good.
And if nothing else, it's continued solid improvement
in the right direction.
And Qt seems to have a good future in front of it, too.
So anyways, congrats to the Plasma folks.
Yeah, that's great.
They seem to have a good release.
Yeah, what would it take for you to try it, Wes?
Not a lot, I don't think.
I mean, I'm down.
It looks like a good release.
I could give it an install.
But you've got GNOME there.
I do, yeah.
It's running GNOME.
If you were just doing an install tomorrow,
would you hit GNOME, or would you do Plasma?
You'd probably do GNOME, wouldn't you?
I would, mostly because I've got a real minimal GNOME setup
with just a couple of extensions and a theme.
And it works OK, and it gets out of my way.
Especially, I only use, what, six applications.
And so just hitting the old super key,
and typing my thing, and then it starts up.
That said, I really like Kwin.
Kwin is great.
And I think if I put in enough time,
just really sunk my teeth into Plasma.
So I figured it minimally, I think it would work.
I tried to do that, and I ran into usability issues, I guess.
Wimby, have you seen any of this stuff
I'm talking about with GNOME 3 performance?
I don't know if you had a chance to hit User Air,
but essentially the activities pop-up area and whatnot
is noticeably slower and slower.
And then if you run it on Wayland, it's really bad.
Really?
I've not tested GNOME 3 extensively enough recently
to encounter that.
I've been running it a little bit
for these external GPU tests and comparisons,
but I've not had a system up for 20 days
or anything like that.
What is your opinion of the,
how would you describe the perceptual difference
of a system, say, the Mate desktop,
where the interface is being rendered by the CPU
versus where the interface is being rendered by Comp is?
How would you describe the difference there?
Well, if you take a Mate and you switch between the two,
there's no real difference in the speed
at which things pop up and render, so.
I disagree in the, to me, I perceive a difference
in the way the windows move around,
the way the windows draw on the screen.
To me, there's- Oh, yeah.
Yeah, definitely, yes.
What do you describe?
That's what I'm talking about.
What do you describe that?
What do you describe that difference as?
Well, I mean, the first thing is,
is that reduced all the lack of screen tearing,
so you just get this sense of- Smoothness.
Yeah, there's a smoothness to it, yeah,
a fluidity and a consistency.
And actually, I would say that as good as Comp is
and Comp to now at eradicating screen tear,
until you've seen something run on Mir and Wayland,
you don't realize just how good the pixel pushing are
in those technologies by comparison,
because they're a level up again.
I feel like, see, that is exactly how I feel
like when I switch between the GNOME Shell,
like there's just the GNOME 3 desktop
and anything that uses K1,
but obviously the Plasma desktop.
That's, that is my, like that level of like,
I've just stepped up in the way that,
and I keep coming back to like these things,
like I mentioned it with the text editor earlier,
it's like, do these things actually matter?
Or are they just like nerd things
that I've decided that matter?
And I think it depends on the person.
And I think-
No, I think they do matter, don't they?
I hope so, because they matter to me an awful lot.
But you're asking like, is this like the old compiling
your software for your CPU thing, right?
Does it really matter?
Or is it like a 0.05% difference?
Yeah, that's a good way to think about it,
because to me, it feels like it matters a lot
because I notice it, and if I notice it, then it matters.
Yeah, and I know, I probably said before,
I'm a big film fan, and when I'm watching YouTube videos,
for example, or any sort of video playback,
and I see that it's dodging around
and that the image is tearing and all the rest of it,
it drives me bananas.
Now, not everyone sees it, but it's not just like video.
It's simple things like, in some cases,
scrolling up and down a webpage, for example,
can be really stuttery,
and you can actually lose your spot in the text,
because you can't maintain a consistent view
on where the text is scrolling to,
so you lose sight of that, and that's frustrating.
So I think it's something that people will appreciate
and will notice. It feels good that you say that.
It feels good that you say that.
It feels good that the chat room is agreeing with me,
because this is something that I've commented on
in my past reviews and gotten a lot of like,
shut the kind of stuff up. Chris, you're crazy.
Yeah, I'm just like, okay, all right, maybe it is just me,
because that stuff does really matter to me,
and so that's where I'm at.
Those kinds of things are where I'm at with GNOME right now,
is that sort of, I'm getting that stuttering,
a do, do, do, do, do, do.
I can make the motion with my hand,
but I can't really describe it to you.
It's rough, it is rough.
I had to watch the hand thing.
It's rough, just don't. You saw it.
Yeah, you should be glad that you didn't see that.
Thank you, thank you, Wes.
So I don't know where this brings me,
but Plasma 5.10 is out, and I'm considering,
once Arch gets it updated,
I'm considering rolling it out.
I have been also experimenting with a new way
to try out my Plasma, and I want to talk to you guys
about the application I've been using to do it.
Whoa.
And why I think it's really exciting
that it's coming to Linux.
I tried out, for the first time ever.
Let me guess, let me guess.
It's a Soos running on Windows.
That doesn't even exist yet.
And here we are.
It is May 30th, 2017.
Build was forever ago,
and we still have no information
about what version of OpenSUSE,
or how that's gonna work exactly.
My only conclusion is,
is that Microsoft hasn't given the projects any information,
and they have no idea when this thing's actually gonna ship,
so they can't tell us what version they're gonna ship,
because they don't know yet.
Side rant.
Side rant. Sorry, go on.
Anyways.
No, I tried out the new Plasma desktop in Docker.
I know, I know.
I'm sorry if I just triggered any of you haters out there.
I apologize.
And it was so easy.
It was so, it was so smooth.
I have to tell you about it.
It was an app that I just, actually it was funny.
I thought it was only available for Mac and Windows,
and I was really bummed.
In fact, I told the beard, I was like,
"'Shit, Rekai.
"'If this came out for Linux,
"'I'd make a whole episode about this.
"'This is so awesome.'"
And then Rekai did a little digging around,
and he found a Linux port.
Woo!
So I'll tell you all about it,
but first I'll tell you about our friends at Linux Academy.
Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged,
and sign up for a free seven day trial.
Not only will you support the show,
but you get the seven day free trial,
you get to try out the Linux Academy platform,
which is built around learning more about Linux.
Get the essentials around Linux,
but also get all of the cool technologies
that are gonna make you real money around Linux.
You know, stuff like OpenStack, Azure, AWS.
Oh, AWS, how you have burned me in the past.
When I was first playing around with AWS,
I logged in, put all the credit card information in there,
created a system.
Like a sucker.
And then got busy for 24 or 25 days,
and didn't realize that they were billing me
just for having a system.
You're like, I'll just transcode that,
and I'll spin up this queue.
I wish.
I didn't do anything with it for like 25 days.
I had no idea they were billing me.
And that's what I, you know, like,
I walked away, oh yeah, okay.
That was my first lesson, is that this is very expensive.
That was my first lesson.
And Linux Academy, they just do all that spin up for you
as part of your subscription.
So you don't get that particular lesson.
You actually learn how to use the systems.
They got video courses, self-paced,
in-depth video courses, hands-on labs,
which really are scenario based,
which give you a real experience.
Instructor mentoring with real human beings
that are happy to advise and answer questions.
Course schedulers that you can set a time frame
and you can actually set to it
and make sure you meet your learning goals.
And of course, if you're going for certs,
they got courses created specifically
to prepare you for those exams.
And then when you're busy, not only do they have nuggets,
which are like deep dives into single topics,
but they have an availability planner
that'll help you create a content plan
around your cray-cray schedule.
Just get started.
Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
and sign up for a free seven day trial.
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the Unplugged program.
So this is a bit of a gimped tutorial.
I was planning to walk you through this
a little more in-depth for this episode.
Did a whole bunch of stuff on a couple of machines
up in my office and then came down to the studio
to show it to you.
And it turns out that Docker services are offline.
Yeah, Docker, that thing that enterprises use
that is supposedly the next big wave in Linux technologies.
Yeah, it's down, the Docker Hub is down,
404 for all images.
I can't really demonstrate this to you fully,
but let me just kind of set it up for you.
So the piece of software I want to talk about today
that makes Docker approachable and usable,
it makes using Docker easier than using VirtualBox.
So if you've ever even flirted with VirtualBox
or VMware Workstation, this is easier than that.
And there's a lot of great Docker images
you can take advantage of right now.
Containers that you can just search for
and install right away.
Things that, I mean everything, guys.
Stuff from like Usenet indexers and downloaders
to NGINX servers, Minecraft servers.
Like it's just so much stuff is available in Docker.
Basically all of the world's great open source software
is available in a Docker container.
And if you've had your head in the sand around Docker,
this is your opportunity to really take advantage of it.
It's called Kitematic.
And they'll tell you it's available for Mac OS
and Windows 7.
I don't know, I suppose it probably is good for them.
To me it sort of sniffs of an Electron app,
but I'm not quite sure.
We'll get to how you can get it on Linux here in a second.
But it's a one click install to get Docker containers
running on your system.
And it gives you a gooey configuration
to set up things like X11 forwarding.
It gives you a configuration to set up your network hosting.
It has a really nice output for the log.
Of course it has integration with the hub
so you can just search for stuff
and automatically download it to your system and get going.
It makes it easier, it's also, it's great
because it doesn't surplant the Docker CLI
so you can use it in conjunction with the Docker command line.
Now, I guess you don't really need to care
about any of that stuff.
Really what you need to know is it's a really simple gooey
to just look at all of the great Docker containers
and essentially get them running on your system
with just a couple of clicks.
And before today's episode,
I thought this was only really available for Mac and Windows.
Turns out, pretty straightforward
to get it working on Linux.
There's a deb available, put out there.
It works best on recent Ubuntu's,
but there's also an AUR repository.
Nice, wow.
Yeah.
I gotta say, I've heard of this.
I've had people at work and other places who are like.
Mac users have told me about it.
Yeah, oh, a ton of Mac users.
They love this, which, admittedly,
Docker's a little harder to use on Mac,
so this goes, it's a little more useful, I think,
for those platforms than it is on Linux.
But for anyone who's wanting to play with Docker,
intimidated by the constantly changing Docker ecosystem,
it really does, I think, bridge the gap
to make it like, I can start playing with this.
Well, it takes Docker from an idea to,
I want to try, I want to run a Minecraft server.
And if that's what you want,
I want to run a Minecraft server.
You launch KiteMatic, you type in Minecraft,
and within 45 seconds, you're running a Minecraft server.
And I think that's pretty sweet.
For Arch, they have KiteMatic,
which uses straight up Docker,
and then they have KiteMatic Git,
which is not only a Git version of KiteMatic,
but also uses the Git version of Docker.
And so there's just a couple of things you have to do
on your GNU slash Linux box before you can use this,
and I've outlined them in the show notes.
It's essentially, you complete the post installation scripts
that I have linked in the show notes.
It's make sure you have a Docker group,
make sure you start the Docker service,
basic things like that.
And at least on Arch, where I was testing this,
I had to run KiteMatic with pseudo privileges,
otherwise it can't create the containers it needs.
And once the Docker service has started,
you run pseudo KiteMatic, you get a graphical interface
for deploying really all of the great Docker hub images,
and so I was trying out the Plasma 5.10 desktop
using Docker, and it was great.
That's awesome.
It was super cool, dude,
because didn't even have to bother with a VM,
didn't have to bother with downloading an ISO,
I just was able to take advantage
of the native performance of my workstation.
Anyways, KiteMatic is, if you look around online,
it looks like it's just something for Macs and maybe Windows,
but us Linux users can get it too,
and I have a link to how to set that up in the desktop.
And if you've never really thought about messing around
with Docker before, it kind of makes it approachable,
kind of makes it real, makes it real,
and they have two different containers
for neon spin of Plasma.
They have KDE Neon Plasma,
which is sort of just the base Plasma desktop,
and they have KDE Neon All.
Both of these are containers available,
and All is like the entire software,
so it's like a four gig image,
and then just the Plasma desktop is like a two gig image.
There you have it.
You can go fly a kite.
Go fly a kite, Wes.
Go fly a kite, Matic.
Go fly a kite, Matic, Wes.
I don't know, I'm working on my slam.
It's not very good, it's not very good.
I'm sorry, I apologize about that.
I forgive you.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Anyways, it's pretty neat, and it was one of these
where I felt like, ah, screw the damn Mac users
and the damn Windows users.
Docker's supposed to be a Linux technology,
and here they have this GUI that makes it super easy
to pick out the Docker containers you want
and just deploy them on your system.
How dare they?
This is our technology.
This is our thing, and then Rika was like,
actually, I found this link here,
and yeah, you can make it work on Linux.
That's awesome.
I actually had not done that either,
and so I'd seen it, and I was like,
well, yeah, I guess I'll just keep figuring out
the Docker CLI.
Yeah, and it's fine.
It works, and this doesn't necessarily supplant it.
You can still use both.
I'll have links to all of that in the show notes.
Go to jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Look for Linux Unplugged 199,
and you'll find links to that,
plus the Razer core that Wimpy talked about,
the Samba vulnerability we mentioned,
that crazy GNOME extension if you want it,
and also the rest of that Plasma 5 video
that I used to take a leak.
All of that over at jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Just look for episode 199, and just a slight reminder,
we do have that barbecue coming up.
We'd love to have you come hang out at the studio
for the 4th of July.
That'd be pretty cool.
Oh my gosh.
Do it.
Also, you can join us in the mumble room.
Just do a bang mumble over at jblive.tv,
and we'll see you back here next Tuesday!
We'll see you back here next Tuesday!
Oh, thank you everybody!
jbtitles.com, let's go name this thing.
Let's go name this thing.
Varatunda, it was good to see you again, man.
Good to see you, good to see you.
Good to see you.
Oh, absolutely.
Mr. Lou, we didn't hear from you this week,
but good to see you too.
Zub cereal, good to see you.
And we have Robot the Arm.
Roboter, something like that.
Good to see you too, man.
It's awesome to see all these people.
And then we had a couple people filter in
during the show.
It was good.
It was nice getting a chance to listen to the show, Chris.
Jb Titles, Jb Titles, Docker Apocalypse,
Go Fly Kite Matic, Keddie Makes Plasma Great Again,
a package for your package.
Oh, I like that one.
No, you don't.
No Samba, No Cry, that's not bad either.
That's kind of clever.
Yeah, that is pretty clever.
I get that, I get that.
Do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, boom, boom, boom.
So Mr. Wimpy, are you doing the eGPU thing
separate from the review of the laptop
that you and I were discussing?
Because I've been waiting for that one too.
I want to hear that.
Yeah, yeah, so the eGPU is this Thursday
and the laptop review is the following Thursday.
Man, I have to wait even longer.
I'm looking forward to that, I'm looking forward to that.
So Wimpy, are you doing any of these tests
that you're running, are you going to be comparing them
at all to Windows performance and let's say
how much of the third of the bus is being used, et cetera?
So I can't compare with Windows
because I just don't do Windows.
So not even interested in making that comparison
because it's personally meaningless.
In terms of like things like GPU utilization on the bus,
then yes, I've actually, although we don't talk about that
when we were discussing it today,
but yes, I did make a note of how saturated
the GPU was under load.
And I've looked at what other people have done
with measuring the comparative performance deltas.
I haven't done it myself
because I have no means of making this test.
I don't have a desktop PC with Thunderbolt
that I can mount the graphics card on the bus
and then plug it into the core on a Thunderbolt port.
So I can't do that test to see what the,
you know, relative performance differences.
So other people have done those performance tests
and they're interesting
because some people have been more thorough than others.
And what you learn is that you will see banded around
numbers of like, you'll get a 20 to 30% reduction
in performance when you use an external GPU.
Wow, really that much?
But well, but it depends, right?
So it depends on the game.
It depends on the CPU requirements of the game.
And interestingly, as you drive up the resolution
that you're running the GPU at,
the higher you drive the resolution,
the closer the delta gets to the installed speed.
So when you're doing 4K gaming,
that delta is like 5%, not 20%.
Wow.
So, and this is because you're pushing the GPU harder
and you know, the bus speed is irrelevant at that point.
But all I was interested in was, does it run well?
And I define well, as can I run it on my 2K display
with everything pushed to ultra or high
or whatever the maximum settings is
and it run at a decent frame rate.
And the answer to that question is yes.
Yeah, one of the things from one of the people
that I saw that did an eGPU test on Windows
was that there's a difference between
hooking the eGPU up to a, let's say a desktop system
and running the display off of the desktop system
and then utilizing the display out on the eGPU
instead of the desktop system.
Yeah.
So I'm not sure if they're aware of that.
I have done that one.
So I have done the drive the external display solely
and also reflect the display to whatever the laptop screen
is because you can do either.
And there is a slight performance penalty
of directing the display to the laptop screen
but it's almost immeasurable for most titles
is in the realm of a couple of percent in my testing
unless this is 1080p screen.
And of course, if you're an Intel graphics user,
if you can even get within, I mean,
if you can even play the games with decent settings,
that's a pretty big win.
Well, we're talking about the difference
between running some of these games
at like barely 20 frames per second
to over 100 frames per second.
Exactly, exactly.
And this is 20 frames per second at low
versus 100 frames at everything dialed up.
What was the out of the box config?
Was it pretty extensive or pretty plug and play?
It was really easy.
The core itself, it's just got a magnetic release
to pull the chassis out of the casing.
One thumbscrew to where the card goes in,
plug the card in just like you plug it into the bus on a PC,
thumbscrew in, close it.
So that whole process takes about 30 seconds.
And then you just plug in power to the GPU
and then you plug a Thunderbolt port
between the GPU and the computer.
Come on, I mean, it is somewhat remarkable
that in this day and age, something like this,
an external graphics card by a vendor like NVIDIA,
you know, the graphics cards in NVIDIA,
the enclosure is by Razer and you're connecting
over a technology created by Intel
and you just plug it into Linux and it's working?
Like this is not something that would have happened
five, six, seven, eight years ago.
This is a huge piece of equipment
that you are externalizing and just connecting
to your PCI bus and it's just working and it's no big deal.