My son is currently going back and forth between believing in Santa Claus versus not like he has a pretty good theory his theory
It's pretty solid. He thinks that Santa Claus is real. It's just that Santa Claus is Amazon
So if you ask him Dylan, who is Santa Claus Amazon?
I know and he recognizes the Amazon wrapping paper and that's usually what dads know all the presents from dad come in
Yeah, when he's a father Amazon will have reindeer shaped drone, right? Yeah
They will
with custom 3d printed boxes and
Man, Amazon needs 3d printed boxes. That would be great
If the reindeer drones don't happen, I'm protesting. Yeah, that's that'll be a missed opportunity
Wimpy you should market that patent that and then sell it
Faisal yeah, I just sell for you for a good deal like $500,000 or something like that. I
Just want my unlimited credits on my fire TV. That is that is brilliant
That is that is eating up my spare change. Did I did I tell you I can't did I said?
I might have mentioned it on there that I cancelled my Nexus player order
And I don't blame you. I'm gonna get a fire. I read the reviews on the Nexus player and it just sounds
It sounds like a total miss. I think on
Okay. Yeah, I thought I remembered saying something. Yeah, so now the fire TV is really terrific and some advice
You gave me a couple of a few weeks back now
I was asking about controllers for Steam on Linux and you recommended the wired Xbox 360 controller
Compatible with the fire TV you can plug the USB in of it. You just plug it in you just plug the
Xbox 360 360 USB controller in and all the buttons are mapped
It works exactly like the official Amazon controller, but it's half the price and it's stonking good
So I'm using that on the fire TV for gaming that is winning
Yeah
Arbilis is right like you have the Google TV now the Nexus Q and the Nexus player and all of these three products have been
In my opinion, I'm sure people like the Google TV is used by people still in it and loved but in my opinion
it fails on a couple of critical points that would really bug me and you know
The number one thing that jumped out me in especially a couple of the reviews
Complained about the same type of lagging us in the same kinds of areas and it's exactly the kind of stuff that drives me
crazy
I'm the guy that will yeah, you know back before the set-top boxes like the Roku could could handle decent performance
I was the guy that would just build an XBMC machine
But in because I needed a PC powerful enough to just not have a laggy system
Because who wants to sit down with the TV and like then wait for their computer
Yeah, quite. Well, the the fire TV is really really slick. It's very responsive
In all respects. I mean it does some really neat things as well
So the first thing is when it arrives it's pre-configured with your account credentials. That's nice
So like a nice touch that yeah nice touch. Yeah
But it's a bit like oh, I didn't expect that but then when you start watching TV episodes and things like that
It will pre download the next in the series. It stores them. It stores them. Yeah
Yeah, so when you then say I want to watch the next episode of Battlestar Galacta
It's just instant because it's already there and it means that you know, the fast-forward and rewind stuff is really responsive
I like that kind of hybrid streaming download approach
So I assume you could probably stream immediately right you could go in there and if you had not ever watched say like I don't
Know 24 and you went to go watch season 1 episode 1 and 24 it would play immediately, right?
But then you would just start down. Yeah, that is so but but it will pull it down faster than you're watching it
So eventually you're you're playing it off the local device rather than off the stream
And then it will be grabbing the next one if it thinks that this is something that you're you know into and watching
That I got it I got that's it, you know
I'm what I'm doing is I got a couple of TVs that I like a lot
I don't I feel like a TV buying a TV is like a huge decision too, which is a little silly
But I have a couple of TVs that I like a lot that I have bookmarked to see if they go on Black Friday sale
And if they do I'm gonna get an Amazon fire TV with it
Yeah, I'm really impressed
We've ditched the Roku in the front room now and I'm now looking at the fire TV stick to replace the other Roku in the bedroom
Did you guys see they announced their tier pricing for bit torrent sink?
No, yeah. Yeah, it's a thing. They're doing a tiered pricing thing. Let me go look it up real quick. I think I saw us. What what?
I'll stop using bit torrent sink and start and use sink thing because that's
That's horrible. I'm looking it up now. Maybe it was a prank before I
They're still gonna release like a
Solid free version everything that you have now you're gonna get to keep you won't lose anything
All right, so that was the thing I saw that wasn't me just being crazy
What the hell?
Are you guys seeing this?
Yeah, what do you think of this? What do you think about this sucks?
At the moment, I've got probably 200 gigabytes. Well, I think I think yeah, I published all the unfiltered supporters
Files and every single episode is usually one to two gigabytes minimum
And you know, there's a lot of episodes and then yeah, I know it really so that shit, isn't it?
Okay, so I'm gonna have to bite the bullet on the sink thing and get over the rather clunky trust relationship model
I promise
That pulse that pulse model doesn't work for me. I can't add each listener individual
No, no, it doesn't work for you and then it's a pain in the what sits for me because I've got
Bit sync on all of the laptops and desktops and the NAS and a couple of servers out, you know providers
So I've probably got at least a dozen to 14 things and just that is going to be a mess because that's a 28-way
Key exchange which is doesn't scale really does it?
Way to add add keys from like the command line because in theory what you could do is
When someone subscribes to like the unfiltered stuff you could send them an email it like it could and that could be automated
They could add their key and then you could have just a back end that automatically adds it to
The sink thing. So yeah, so okay. So sink is gonna be
Pro is gonna be forty nine dollar. I'm sorry forty dollars a year
Gives you unlimited files
Yeah, she's boy. This is rough, right?
Some people call it bait and swing folders as well though. This is rubbish. Oh
I've got because in lieu of in lieu of selective sync. I've got lots of sync folders, right?
That's how you thought my torrent sink. Yeah. Yeah
It isn't
Looking more like 96 euros a year from from what I'm looking at here
Isn't isn't bit torrent sink
distributed
Well, it's decentralized. It's the the way the files are shared is decentralized
It's basically it's basically they're they're nobbling their software to get money out of us
Well, this is this is why they're never open sourced
It isn't that technically be illegal because you think other people's resources to get money. No, I mean this is not
You launch a beta it's free during the beta and then when you are done with the beta you charge
I mean, that's not too uncommon
Chris what if you use an old version for
for our filter on content? Yeah, I suppose you could stick but the thing is is if the clients update
I've noticed on bit torrent sink that can be an issue if the server falls too far behind some of the clients
At least it happened to me once
It became a problem and I and some people couldn't get files anymore
So another one looking good now, maybe yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So yeah, another one to look a C file if you've not used that
Sparkle share. Yeah, and of course if you want to pay a spider oak
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's really packing it in for the holidays. My name is Chris
And my name is Matt. Hey there Matt
So rumor has it you were just chowing down on a little bacon before we got started today
I was I was
You know, I got up here about 15 till logged in about 10 till and I'm like cramming bacon down my face
But the cool through it you were still doing your thing. So I was like, oh cool. I got time to eat
I had some meatballs while you're having your bacon. It's like it's Sunday. It's like we're our Sunday routine on Tuesday
Oh, so I have a I have a lot to cover today. I'm really excited about today's show
So we are following up with Charlie from Sunday's Linux action show and he's brought some of the students and they're all huddled around a laptop
Right now and we're gonna talk to them about their experiences with Linux really looking forward to that
We've got some great emails to read this week
There's some thought-provoking questions and potentially some big changes coming to the Jupiter broadcasting website and
No towards the end of the show. I'm gonna play a preview clip of
Interview that will be playing on Sunday's Linux action show with Mark Shuttleworth and the topic is Jermaine
To this show. It's something we've been talking about a lot lately the tone of dialogue in the open source community around all the recent
Systemd debates and Debbie and all that kind of stuff. I wanted to ask Mark Shuttleworth what he thought about it and
Got his a brief summary of his thoughts
We go into greater detail in the Sunday interview
We're gonna play a clip of that because it felt like it fit pretty well
With the topic that we have been recently discussing here on the show
So that'll be towards the end of the show a lot of the stuff that we've been talking about
With the topic that we have been recently discussing here on the show. So that'll be towards the end of the show a lot to do today
So Matt, you know what we got to do. You guys start with that email got to start with that
He's good. So Jesse writes in and he has a question for our guest today
so I will start with our first email that pertains to Charlie and
Charlie I I'll read this to you and then I'll give you a chance to respond and it goes a little something like this
Jesse says hello there Chris Madden obviously now Charlie I saw your latest episode of the Linux action show episode
340 with Charlie raising your rising your
And I was just wondering how would you introduce Linux and open source to a school district that still uses Windows XP and power PC
Versions of OS 10 and they can't really afford new hardware or software
Due to politicians stealing money from the state budget
Thanks for your hard time and all your hard work and any ideas
So Charlie if somebody's in a really budget restricted environment, maybe they couldn't buy laptops for students
And can't really afford to buy new hardware
Is there somewhere where you would give them advice to start on rolling out Linux and open source in a district?
Oh, sorry Charlie I had you turned down go ahead Charlie. Oh, yeah, no problem. Thanks again for having us on the show today
This is just so much fun. Yeah, you know, that's that that's tough, you know being in a school, you know
You've worked in a school. We've we've you know both been there when you know budgets and resources are restricted
What I could offer up is
Probably just starting small
Right in the past, you know really are some of our first implementations on the desktop or with Zubuntu
Just simply because the interface was lightweight and we could take advantage of lower-end hardware
But also I think you know more germane to this is a discussion of just starting, you know in a very small fashion
You know when we've we've scaled up to thousands of machines in the desktop, but if we didn't start there
We built on very small successes, you know in many cases we installed
You know some flavor of Linux on just a few machines, you know
Maybe just a teacher's set in a classroom or perhaps even just a single lab
Very good. Yeah, that makes a lot of sense
It requires patience, but you start small and you build up after successes
You get some successes under your belt prove that it's worth everybody's time prove
It's worth whatever little budget is available and then build on top of that. That's great advice
Yeah, absolutely
And it helps also just you know to bring teachers on board and and staff and and of course students too
You know, we often forget that we want to get students excited about technology
And I think that's an important part of the equation as well. Yeah, great point
All right. So there you go. Jesse. There's some great starting points from Charlie and I wish you the best of luck sir
And you know when I tried to get Linux deployed in my work environment
It was fundamentally critical to have these mini successes. It started small and then I built on top of that
And it doesn't have to be a school district. It can be any kind of environment like that
So Bugsbane the third writes in and maybe this is one we can open up to the whole mumble room
He says I've been using Linux for over a decade and I love it
While I can't write a line of code to save my life over the years
I've gotten very used to setting up networks compiling code triaging bugs, etc
I have no formal qualifications, but I've learned a lot
Now I'd like to use all of that training to get a job, but I have no idea where to start
Entry job levels entry jobs seem to be overqualified
We have requirements where you've been a network administrator for many years or you're a developer
And currently not having a job
I don't have a lot of money to spend on getting certifications or training to become a coder
So where would you or anyone in the audience recommend someone start?
And so the question is if you have a good sense of Linux
Maybe you've been using it for a while, but you don't have anything on that resume
How could you get in and get started?
And I have I'll start with my idea and then anybody that wants to jump in please do so
I would if you're all if you're all if you are unemployed
Consider the fact that you might have something in excess that a lot of people don't have
And it's not necessarily money. It's time
And you might consider starting at the ground floor somewhere and just on a volunteer basis to see if they need help
And then perhaps make yourself invaluable and they might consider hiring you
That would be one way I know that's easier said than done
Matt, what do you think?
What about like just trying to get your foot in the door and maybe trying to get somebody's attention?
Is it got to be like, do you need to know somebody?
Is that is he screwed if he doesn't know somebody?
No, you hit the nail on the head with volunteering
Both pretty much everything I've ever done in my life
I started at some capacity of working for free
And I think that volunteering for a worthwhile organization makes a lot of sense
Because not only do you have something very strong to put on your resume later
But you also showed that you weren't watching Oprah all day on television
You're actually doing something productive, right?
Getting work experience
Exactly. It's truly it
I mean, that's you know, I've been self-employed for years
And so for me, it's like I can't fathom not having you know
If I'm not in the middle of a project, I'll go make one
And I think the same thing applies here
If you could find a need, go fill it, figure it out
You know, just get out there and try stuff
I love it. That's great advice
Anybody in the mumbler want to jump in with anything before we move on?
I think that's probably good stuff right there
But if anybody else has any pointers of something that got them a gig
We'd love to hear it
I'd just like to echo Chris that absolutely volunteering is the way to go
You know, open source by its very nature is participatory
And really the best way to demonstrate your skills is to get out and volunteer
Be active in projects and programs and demonstrate what you got
Nailed it. All right
I'd also say that there's sometimes where I've talked to people who said that they didn't have enough experience
Because the job listings required something so absurd that it's not even possible
But a lot of the times these employers are looking for people who are willing to try anyway
Yeah, I've heard that before too
Yeah, so they'll set up an experience
It's like you have to have three years of experience for this
And two years experience for this
But they don't actually want that
They're kind of like
Sometimes they'll have it where it's kind of a deterrent for someone who's not motivated enough to try
They don't want them working for them anyway
So if you don't have the experience but you go there and say
And you can prove that you can do it anyway
They'll hire you
That's a great point
From their perspective they're like we're either going to get somebody who's really determined
And willing to go the extra mile for us
Or B, we'll get really lucky and get somebody who's super qualified
And we won't have to pay them very much
And on top of that
Once you're in the negotiations for the job
If they're going to give it to you and you didn't meet all the qualifications
They can be like well
You know we were looking for somebody who had 15 years as a DBA
And 25 years as a VB programmer
So we're going to go ahead and cut off about 10K from what we listed in the job application
But you got the job, congratulations
You know that's another reason they do it
They make up these impossible qualifications
And when you don't meet them they can kind of reduce their commitment
We want you to have like 10 years of VB experience
And also speak Chinese
Yeah, yeah
Have you been working with
We need somebody who's been working with Linux for 35 years
Can you do that for us?
Yeah, no I can't
Lies
Yes, lies exactly
Alright I'll tell you about something that's not a lie
That's saving a little bit of money from Ting
That's my mobile service provider and Matt's mobile service provider
And that's our first sponsor this week
Go to linux.ting.com
Linux
Yeah you get to put Linux in there
Linux.ting.com
Head over there
Check out the Ting website
By going to that URL
You automatically are going to save 25 bucks
If you pull the trigger and get a Ting device
Or if you got a compatible Ting device
You're going to save 25
Or you're going to get 25 dollars in Ting credit
Which could be like almost 2 months of service
It's kind of crazy
So why Ting?
Right
Why Switch?
Why go through the hassle of moving over?
Well first of all they make that switch pretty painless
They've got an early termination relief program
So if you're in a contract now
They'll pay up to 75 dollars per line and you have to get cancelled
If you're not in a contract
Well then this is a better time than ever to move over
Because you only pay for what you use
It's just your minutes, your messages and your megabytes
That's all you pay
You just take that
Add it up
That's it
It's 6 dollars for the lines
You can have as many lines as you want
It's a flat 6 dollars
You can turn them on and off when you need them
And then you just pay for your usage
It doesn't matter if it's a data device or a smart phone
No contracts
No early termination fee
An incredible, incredible dashboard
And no whole customer service when you call them at 1855-TING-FTW
A real person answers the phone
Just got a call between 8am and 8pm on business hours
They're not animals
But go to linux.ting.com and try out that savings calculator right there on the screen
You click that
Go in there
Put in your current usage information
Like for example
Let's just
I don't even remember what I used to use anymore
But let's just say I use
Yeah right
Let's say I use 300 minutes
I'm not a big talker
And 200 text messages
Well
I mean maybe
I really would probably use Hangouts to be honest with you
So I don't know
But let's say it's 200 messages right
And the megabytes
Let's say it's about
Let's say this month I think I'm probably about 3 gigabytes
And before taxes
That would be normally what?
150 dollars for that cell phone bill?
Oh not 450
150 dollars
Now you go into the Ting savings calculator
If you've got multiple lines
You put that in there
You put your actual usage in there
And you can calculate the savings
And see how much you would save
They can do some data scraping as well
But just at that
Which is a fairly moderate plan
You probably are using more than that
A lot of you
You'd save 2,000 dollars
And if you're using less
You'd save even more
That's what's so great about the Ting model
It's so sweet
Go over there right now
Linux.ting.com
Check them out
See why Ting is mobile
That makes sense
And when you're playing around with that savings calculator
Don't be surprised if it brings a tear to your eye
When you see that money
You're like gosh
That's a laptop I could buy every couple of years
And also I think this is pretty cool
They've been spotlighting different Ting customers on the Ting blog
And they've got an adorable new baby
Oh look at that girl with those pretty blue eyes
Let's go over to the Ting blog
And check out the Ting customers
Their app pics
Information about Ting
Their blog post about their consumer reports rating
That was excellent
They've got all the kinds of good info
Gives you some behind the scenes information about Ting
It kind of gives you a better idea of where your money is going
And I think that's all pretty important to a lot of us
Linux.ting.com
Get a 25 dollar discount on your first Ting device
With no contract
No early termination fee
You own that phone
Like your computer
You know
I know
It's crazy
And it's not actually
You know what's funny
Is people outside the US
Like some of our listeners
Live in areas where the cell phone system
Makes a lot more sense
And they hear this stuff
And they're like wait a minute
You guys pay subsidies
You realize you pay more in the long run
You realize they're scamming you
And I don't know if you heard
But Verizon just like extended the early termination fee
Even further out now
And with a higher rate
Like they just keep getting worse
They're not getting any better
Linux.ting.com
Go make a difference for yourself
And go vote with your wallet
Linux.ting.com
And a big thank you to Ting
For sponsoring
Linux Unplugged
Okay
Just a couple more emails to get to
This is
You know when we started the Linux Unplugged show
The initial concept for Linux Unplugged
Was actually going to be
Just 100% emails
I remember that
You remember that
Yeah right
Like I was like Matt
We get too many emails
We should have a show
Where we just read emails
So that's why we do emails
At the beginning of the show
Because that's the heritage
Of Linux Unplugged
It's like okay
This is bad
These emails are just sitting in the inbox
And now we still have the same problem
But we at least get to some of them
So that's good
Alright
Mandaray writes in
With yet another System D survey
This is up to you
Dear audience
But he wanted to let us know
That he's created another System D survey
Unlike the one we ran previously
This one aims to figure out
What groups of users
Are in favor of System D
And which are against it
And who is a vocal
And who is
You know
All the kind of nuances around that
He says hopefully
He wants to find more discussion around it
He's already compiled
Some of the interesting information
Not only about System D
But other topics too
Which might be worth discussing
In future episodes
However
Because he's kind of running this on his own
We haven't talked about it anywhere
He's only gotten about
240 participants so far
So I have a link in the show notes
If you'd like to take yet another
System D survey
That also asks some other questions
And you never know
We might get some good weekly
Conversation out of it
For a little bit
So thanks to Mandaray
For writing that
It's a Google form
You know these Google forms
Are actually really handy
If you haven't checked them out
Because they output all of the results
I mean you know me
I'm not like Mr. Google over here
But they output all of the results
Right into a spreadsheet
And that's just undeniably handy
In fact we have one
That I'm going to talk about
At the end of the show
For us
So I'll have a link to his survey
In the show notes
If you guys want to try it
Cool
Yeah
And maybe we can dig
Through the results later
Alright
Here's the big one
That I've been waiting to get to
I know Rotten Corpse
Is going to have some stuff
To talk about that
So I'll give him a chance
To jump in first
Once I read this one
So on Coda Radio yesterday
I mentioned that
I have
I have a dream Matt
I have a dream
You have a dream
Of going into the Jupiter Broadcasting
WordPress directory
Typing rm-rf star
And hitting enter
I want
I'm done with WordPress
It's great
It's super sweet
If you run a blog
Anything like that
Great open source project
I don't want to use WordPress anymore
I don't need a CMS
I don't want a CMS
All I want to do
Is put an HTML5 video
Up on a webpage
With some download links
And some text that tells you
What that video is about
That's all I want Matt
I want to take a flat markdown file
I want to drop in a directory
And I want that to publish
Up on the web
I don't want a database
I don't want nothing dynamic
None of it
Reach it
Static HTML
Simple easy
Boom shakalaka
I hear you
So on Coda Radio 129
I went on
About my fantasy
Of replacing WordPress
With something more
Quote unquote
Sane as
It was written here
Up in this
Subreddit post
So here's the
There's a bunch of great suggestions
In this post
Of what Jupiter Broadcasting
Could do
To move away from WordPress
Let me tell you
What I'm thinking about here
Because I'd love to get the audience
I'm sure there's some people out
That have done this kind of thing
I really want something
Very simple
That would allow us to import
Somehow
I don't know how we would do it
All of the back catalog
Of the existing post
So we could go
Pull in
All of the previous shows
Not mess with all the time stamps
Keep all the tags
Something that could extract it
From the MySQL WordPress database
And put it into this new system
So that's one thing
I want to get done
I'm thinking like
After the holidays
So not like right now
Probably after New Years
And put this all
Put this
I'm trying to put something together
And I'm looking for people's
Suggestions right now
On how we could pull off
What we could use
And any tools that might be useful
In a transition like this
It's really early day stuff
Just starting to think about it
But Rotten Corps
You were looking at PicoCMS
I know
I think Alan is using PicoCMS
To run the bsdnow.tv site
And he says
It essentially does
Kind of what I was talking about
They run the whole site
Off of markdown files
And some CSS tweaks, right?
Yeah
It's not just
It's not limited to just markdown
But it does
It does have a lot of
Focus on markdown
So what do you think?
Am I crazy?
No, actually for JB
It makes a lot of sense
Because the biggest bottleneck
For a CMS
Is the constant checking
The database for the content
And if it's just
For the episodes
You don't need to go back
And change the show notes
Because once the show's out
The show's out
So a static file
Would make perfect sense
For JB
And the entire structure
Would make sense to each other
Pico looks really good
I'm also looking at Pelican
But so far
Pico is kind of like
The front runner
But there are many other options
That I'm looking at
A few suggestions people gave
Were actually
Have been discontinued
Oh, really?
So there's
About half of the ones
That were suggested
Were not viable
But Pico does look like
A good option
Now, MB
You've done some migrations
I noticed you mentioned
mate-desktop.org
And ubuntu-mate.org
You mentioned those as reference
Have you migrated those
Specific sites from WordPress
Or what's that been like for you?
So, yeah
So I migrated my own site
From WordPress
To Nicola
Which is a static site generator
A couple of years ago
And Nicola has a
WordPress migration tool
So you can migrate
All your pages and blog posts
And it also has
Well, no
You don't need to use Nicola
For this
Within WordPress
You can export
All your comments
As XML
And then you can load
Those into Disqus
And then you can link
Your static site
Generated with Nicola
To the Disqus account
Where your comments
Have been imported
And retain all of your
Comment history as well
So I migrated my own site
To Nicola
Because I wanted
A static site generator
I wanted a really easy way
To deploy the website
And I spend a lot of time
In the shell
And I just wanted
To be able to open up
My text editor
Bashing some words
And publish
And everything for my site
Is done in Markdown
So if you look at
The Ubuntu Mate website
That is all Markdown
That's rendered into HTML
By Nicola
And you just manage
A theme
That is then applied
To the Markdown
So I found Nicola
To be really great
And I actually use
BitSync as my
Deployment mechanism
So my sites are in BitSync
And you edit the Markdown
And then I touch a file
In there to say publish
And a cron job on the server
Looks for the published file
Runs the Nicola
Static site generation
And then R syncs
The generated site
To the web group
I was thinking of maybe
I mean BitTorrent sync
Is pretty sweet too
I was thinking of like
A GitHub
Like a git deployment
Like check in, check out
Push kind of thing
Yeah, I know
I've used things like that
Too complicated?
It's a bit of a
Well, for my own sites
It is, although as it happens
The mate-desktop.org
Website is powered by Nicola
And that's in git hub
And periodically the server
Checks out the git hub
And rebuilds the site
And deploys it
So that's familiar for
For the developers
Who know the git workflow
For my own stuff
It's currently in BitSync
But I'm going to put
The Mate desktop
The Ubuntu Mate site
Into either Git or Bazaar
So that I can get some
Translators involved
Because Nicola has also got
Multilingual facilities as well
So you can do translations
I like the WordPress
Conversion built in
Yeah, go ahead
What I would recommend is
Setting up a Gitolite server
On your DigitalOcean droplet
And this is what I do in fact
And you push a change
And you can have Gitolite
Call a hook
And that hook could be
To rebuild the static site
Okay, oh this is exciting
Okay, so how do you handle
Like changes to like
So if you
How do you like for example
In Jupyter Broadcasting
Let's say we had a thumbnail
And we want to change
Thumbnail on one of the
On one of the stills
How do you regenerate
Like a front page
What generates that
Is the Nicola software
Taking care of that
What's doing that part
Yeah, yeah
So the way Nicola works
Is it knows the hashes
Of all of the source files
And it knows the hashes
Of all of the configuration
And the files that get generated
So if for example
You change an asset
Every page where that asset
Is used will automatically
Be generated
So when I did that deployment
Of Ubuntu Marte
A couple of weeks ago
The release part was running
Nicola
And it's two commands
Nicola build
Which builds all of the pages
And pulls in all of the assets
And then Nicola deploy
Which is then
Calls a script of your own
To actually push it somewhere
And what I've done is
I've added a couple of
Extra deployment pieces
Which are scripts
That automatically
Sim link the ISO images
And stuff like that
And does it handle things
Like responsive design
And stuff like that
Or is that a little tricky
It does
Yeah, go and open
Ubuntu Marte.org on your phone
And have a look
It's automatic
Yeah, it actually works
On the browser too, yeah
So the way that that's handled
Is I've cheated
And Nicola supports
Bootstrap
One of the themes
So I just went to Boot Swatch
Found a theme that was
Broadly what I wanted
And then just tweaked it
And then I got all the benefits
Of Bootstrap and Boot Swatch
I didn't have to do much work
That's pretty great
That's a lot of great
It sounds a lot
Up our alley
And does it do
I'm sure
Sorry
Does it do any feed generation
Or anything like that
For RSS feeds
Yeah, it generates
RSS feeds
And it can do
Podcast stuff
And a whole bunch
Of other things
And it's not limited
To Markdown either
So it also supports
Restructured text
And BB code
And just about every kind
Of text render
You can imagine
Really?
Yeah, all of those
And so on the
Marte Desktop.org website
The front page
Is actually
Restructured text
Because I needed
Some of the facilities
Of restructured text
But all of the other pages
Are Markdown
That's cool
So this is sounding
Pretty doable
I wonder
But I'm sure
What Nicola does
Is not that different
From what a lot
Of the other static site
Generators do
But what you get
Of course
Is you get some real
Security benefits
Because you're not running
An interpreted language
On your web server
So you can't be exploited
And the other thing
You can do
Is then trivially
Hook it up
To your CDN
To cache
All of the assets
Like your CSS
And your JavaScript
Exactly
So I then integrate
My sites
With Cloudflare
And that absorbs
Gobs of bandwidth
That I don't have
To serve out
Through my own servers
That is excellent
And my
Really ultimate
Envision
I don't know
When this would ever be done
But the file
Comes out of
The editing software
Whatever it is
At this point in time
And it's then
Ran through
We currently have
A pretty nice
Bash script
That Rekai's put together
To handle all
Of our encoding
And metadata tagging
And the different versions
Of all the different files
And the, you know
It spits them all out
It would be amazing
Then to have something
Like that
That would
Then take a
Markdown file, right?
And put it somewhere
Where it could get
Absorbed onto the website
And upload these files
To the CDN
Really have it be
The point where
You export out
Of the editing application
You run the bash script
And from that point
Everything is kind of
On autopilot
And it just reduces
Human error
It makes it faster
And the end goal
Would really be
To give us
More time
And more resources
Available to do other things
So that way we don't have
To sit there and babysit
The computer
As it goes through
These tasks
And sit there and upload
It to the FTP
We don't need to do that
It could all be automated
But the key part
I really want to do
Is I want to make sure
The whole web
Posting process
Could be automated as well
And that
You know
It doesn't have to go
And it gets published
On its own
After that
So we'll see
Yeah so
So if you've already
Got an investment
In some scripts
That do some of those
Deployment activities
You can continue
To leverage those
And just integrate
Those as the deployment
Commands within
Nicola
So in the configuration
File it can run
Any number of commands
As part of the deployment
And I've got
Half a dozen shell scripts
That get executed
In my deployment
And I've got
Half a dozen shell scripts
That get executed
In my deployment
One to deposit
The files
In the right place
And then a few other
Bits and pieces
To link up ISO links
And torrents
And stuff like that
So not dissimilar
From what you would
Want to do
With media
And it can be automated
Because cron
Is your friend
Yeah
Wow
I just
Touch a file
And how long
Have you had so far
How long have you
Been using it
In production
On my own
Personal site
For two years
Okay wow
On the mart
A desktop website
For about a year
And obviously
I've been to Marte
Just about five months
So what do you think
Rodden
I think that there's
A now potential battle
Between Nicola and Pico
Good alright
There you go
And if
Out there in the audience
If anybody has some suggestions
There's already a thread
Going in the subreddit
You can toss in
Or you can leave a comment
In the feedback thread
For this episode
It's not that we're
Going to do right away
But it's definitely something
I want to start thinking
About now
So when we do it
We do it right
Oh totally
Well I actually
Threw something to you
In the Skype message in there
So I think it's called Jekyll
It's something I've looked at
In the past
It's very similar to what
You guys were talking about earlier
RSS imports the whole package
Yep yep that's another one
I've heard of too
Yeah Jekyll's looking good
Yeah there's
And Ghost is another one
I've seen a lot of
Common mentions
Yeah so some
Some really interesting
Way more options out there
Than I thought
When I came up with this
Apparently
I'm nowhere near
The first person
To ever think of this idea
Not surprising
Not surprising at all
And you know
I think a big part of that
Is that's why I think
I'm going to mention
Our next sponsor
Over digitalocean.com
I could easily see us
Using a droplet to manage
The deployment
Or take care of
Some testing
In fact there's so many
Amazing things you could use
Digitalocean for
Because you get
Great performance
Great price
And unlimited access
To the machine
Check it out
Digitalocean is a simple
Cloud hosting provider
Dedicated to offering
The most intuitive
And easy way for you
To spin up your own
Cloud server
You get root access
To that bad mamma jamma
HTML5 console access
I know you like that
But you get a
30 second
Benchmark
And it's only 35 seconds
I mean seriously
Like our audience
It's ridiculous
I mean now if you can
If you can get it below 40
You really
The benchmark is
35 seconds
That's when you should
Be tweeting at Chris
If you get it under
35 seconds now
And for $5 a month
You're going to get
512 megabytes of RAM
A 20 gigabyte SSD
One CPU
And a terabyte of
Blazing fast transfer
This connected to
Data centers
All over the world
In New York
San Francisco
Singapore
It's got to be
The best looking
Data centers
I've ever seen
And I know that seems
Like a weird thing
To comment on
But guys
I've been in
A lot of data centers
And they never look as good
It's just
Oh man
I feel like
I want to go back
And just appreciate
A well designed
Data center
Because now that
It's no longer my problem
Oh it's just
It's gorgeous
But it's
It's that interface
That really stands out
I mean it's not just
Their data centers
That look great
It's their interface
They can replicate
The functionality
With their straightforward
API
You can write some scripts
Snap it into your
Puppet management infrastructure
Use one of the
Many applications
Built by the community
They've got all of it
That control panel rocks
And the community support
Around it rocks
DNS management
One click deployment
Of GitLab
You know like
For example
If we were going to
Actually start
When we released an episode
Deploying that
To the website
Via Git
You
You absolutely bet
It would be on a
Self hosted instance
Up on Digital Ocean
No question about it
Not only does that dashboard
Make Git up and going
Super fast and straightforward
Doesn't make
Give me any pause
So I just get right in
Friction free
But it also means that
I'm going to have a
Blazing fast machine
Because Digital Ocean
Has SSDs throughout
They've got great bandwidth
Incredible SSD speeds
It really makes a difference
And it's
It's just all those little things
At every single level
That make them
So incredible
But I also know that
If I ever get stuck
Digital Ocean has
The best tutorials
On the web
And they're getting
Even better
Because Digital Ocean
Is willing to pay
For them
Because they understand
The importance of them
In fact
If you write a tutorial
For Digital Ocean
You could get paid
Up to $200
And they have an editor
That works with you too
So it's not like
It's all on you
And they've had
Such success there
They've opened up
An editing position
So here's what
I want you to do
I want you to try out
Digital Ocean
You can try it for
Two months
For free
To see what I've
Been talking about
Use our promo code
For November
Okay?
You get a $10 credit
You apply that to your account
In fact, I need to go in there
And do that right now
This is another thing
I like a lot about it
Is that you pre-fund the account
And they just send you
A message
Hey
You need to add more funds
This is how I have it set up
I'm sure you could probably
Have it set up multiple ways
So I go in there right now
If I was trying out
Digital Ocean
I put the promo code in
Unplug November
And I get a $10 credit
I think I might go do that
I could be trying it out
Right now
Try it out
Go over there
Get a $5 rig
See what you can do
Because if you need to upgrade
To a beefier box
The pricing tier
Is crazy straight forward
You just go look at the
Pricing plans
Okay, that's easy
That's another $5
That makes sense
Right?
And you could even do
Hourly pricing
So if you just need to
Scale up for a little while
And add some additional capacity
Or you're doing some testing
For a day
Or it's a launch day
Or maybe you're going to do
A gaming server
For a few hours
Hourly pricing
Right?
Because you've got
These snapshots
You can just spin it up
When you need it
For a little while
And then shut it down
For you
To DigitalOcean
For sponsoring
The Linux unplugged program
DigitalOcean.com
Unplugged November
When you check out
I always have like
Whenever now we're talking
About big projects
Somebody's like
Oh, I know what we're going to do
We're going to spin it up
On a DigitalOcean droplet
Is this an excuse
To have a droplet?
That's like me now
It's like I'm ridiculous
Totally
Okay, so I'm pretty excited
So we've been talking with Charlie
And Charlie's there
I'm assuming
I'm picturing it right now
It's a classroom
Probably a whiteboard
And there's like one laptop
In the middle
And like all of these kids
And students
And teachers
And I don't know
Who else?
Maybe Superman
I don't know
Are all sitting around
This laptop to talk to us
So I thought
Charlie told us something
That really struck me
Like wow
This blows my mind
As a previous school
District employee
Some of the students
I'm not sure how many
Maybe it's all
Have root access
To their boxes
And some of the students
Are involved in the help desk
And troubleshooting
Like they get tickets
They go in there
And close tickets
And so Charlie
You could be my eyes
And ears
And hands for me
And pick maybe
A help desk representative
I'd love to ask somebody
I'll start
Here's the question
And then Charlie
I'll let you pick the person
What is a typical
Help desk call
For a student IT person?
What kind of troubleshooting
Do they have to do?
Sure
That's a great question
And I'm looking at
Four gentlemen
That are with me here
And I'm going to let
One of our
Students answer
That question for you
Great
I'm curious
Hello
My name is Taylor
Hey Taylor
How's it going?
So what kind of questions
Are you wondering?
Well give me like
A common problem
You run into
Just usually general things
Like why isn't this page loading
And stuff like that
Because I mean
They're not going to go
Too above and beyond
The normal student population
You know what I mean?
Yeah
Well I wonder
Do you ever get people
To throw their hands up
And say I don't know
How this Linux stuff works
What's going on here
This is Linux
And I don't get it?
Actually when we first distributed them
We ran them all through tutorials
When the new freshmen come in
We run them through tutorials
When a new student enrolls
Same deal going on
And they're welcome to stop by
With any questions
Or leave a ticket
If they can't get down here
That's great
And do you run Linux
At home now too
Or are you running
Something else at home?
I used to have my one computer
Triple booted
But yeah
I got a new drive
And it's just running
Mac OS X E70 right now
I caught you
It's okay
We still love you Taylor
Oh no
We won't hold it against you
It's okay
So Taylor
When you go out there
Do you have like
Do you get assigned a ticket
And this is Taylor's ticket
And you have to resolve it
And is that tied
In any kind of curriculum?
Well it's tied into the course
It's an honors weighted course
And the whole ticket system deal
Is basically everybody
That has admin privileges
To view the tickets
That are open
They can assign it to themselves
Or transfer it to somebody else
And you just basically answer
If you assign it to yourself
Or you transfer it to somebody else
If you can't necessarily
Figure it out on your own
Okay that sounds pretty reasonable
Sounds like a pretty good system
Is there ever a time
Where you're troubleshooting
Some of this stuff
And this is Taylor
Or anybody that wants to answer this
Is there ever a time
When you're troubleshooting
This kind of stuff
And you think gosh
If it wasn't Linux
This would be a lot easier
Or do you find it sometimes
Is easier to do some troubleshooting
Because it is Linux
Both are things that do come up
With the wall that you hit
When you're trying to find
Something that would be
Maybe easier
There's always alternatives
Stuff like that
Play on Linux to run
Windows applications
If we need to
Stuff like that
That's pretty cool
So you're getting into
Some of the wine stuff too
And how has that worked for you?
The students seem to be
Pretty pleased with it
And it basically gets us around
Obstacles that
They want to use a certain program
And it's only supported
On Windows and Mac
They download the Windows version
And then they just open it up in there
And it does the rest for them
Yeah, that is kind of a nice thing
And I wonder if
And anybody's free to answer this too
How do you guys manage user logins?
Because one of the nice things
About a Windows mobile lab
Or a Windows lab of computers
On the desk
Or whatever it might be
Is it's Windows
But you can tie it into a domain
And it's easy to have one account
Across all the computers
And so is there a standard student login?
Or how are you managing
All of those user accounts
On all of these laptops?
Yeah, actually I'm going to turn that over
To one of my staff
To jump in for a moment
I'll let him introduce himself
And take that question
My name is Chad
Hey Chad
So on the actual laptops themselves
Well as part of the rollout
Every student kind of just
Resets the local password
On the user
And then we actually
Don't even know what they are
And then as far as like
Any services that we provide
As a district
We actually have
Active directory accounts for people
So we do centrally manage those
But that doesn't give them access
To the laptop
It's a separate username and password
Sure, that makes sense
And I suppose as long as
You have root access
You could always get in there
And flip their password
To something you need
If you need to log in as them
Have you ever walked up to a laptop
And been shocked or surprised
By something installed
That maybe came from a repo
That you didn't expect
Like they didn't have to go out
And find it on the web
They just
Somebody came down
They knew Linux
And they installed stuff
Or is this
Is this so different
Than what people are used to
That that almost never happens
I'm looking to the student team
To answer that
So I think you get two different
Two different answers
From the staff and the students
So Taylor
Do you want to take that
Or Nick or somebody
Okay Taylor
Taylor is going to jump in
So were you ever surprised
By anything you saw installed
Well just aesthetic wise
I've seen some freaky wallpapers
For one
Yeah
And I've seen one or two students
That like
Have actually tried to
Like reinstall Ubuntu
Or actually try and install
Windows itself
And they just completely
Messed up everything
Because of it
Yeah that doesn't surprise me
You know I could see them
Like well I'll take this home
And I'll put Windows on
So I can play my games
Or something like that
And then they mess it all up
Yeah okay that makes sense
Okay
I know you
I should
Chris I should add
Just really quickly again
We absolutely encourage
Our students to explore
And tinker with the machines
There is an acceptable
Use policy
There is a mobile policy
That our students do sign
The one thing that we ask
Them not to do
Is to reformat
And reimage the machine
That's one of the boundaries
That we put up
And there's various reasons
For that
You know we have software
That's installed
And there are some
Unique mechanisms
Here at the high school
There's other unique items
That are specific
To the high school
That we need to
Make sure are maintained
On the boxes
So we do put
That barrier up
And that's really more
Of a functional barrier
Because we do have
Certain expectations
Of what's on
The machine itself
You know also our
Filtering software
For example
You know in a perfect world
We would remove
Those restrictions
But there's still the
You know the quote unquote
Business of education
That we have to get done
Inside the school
Sure that makes sense
That's available
For learning
I'm curious
I'm picturing
My environment
Right I'm picturing
A setup like this
Who drives forward
It's who comes
Who pulls everybody together
And says alright
It's been a few years
We deployed
Zubuntu
Or whatever
12.04
14.04
Whatever it is
Who's the person
That now leads
The initiative to say
We've got to update
The Linux deployment tool kit
And we've got to get
The next version
Of all of the applications
And the next version
Of the operating system
On all of these laptops
Who has that initiative
Is that something
That's driven from IT
Is that something that comes
From the student body
That says look
We need these things
How does that work
In this setup
Yeah in our case
That's driven by IT
You know we look at
We'd like to stay on
Long term support releases
You know I mentioned
In the past
We actually started
The elementary level
With Zubuntu
On 12.04
Our current implementation
Here at the high school
Is pretty close to stock
Ubuntu 14.04
Long term support
We actually do use Unity
But yeah at some point
We'll look at that
You know my team
And I will sit down
And decide well
It's time to you know
To rev and move up
To the latest long term
Support release
We're pretty happy
With 14.04 right now
We're not seeing
Any roadblocks
But you know likely
When the next long term
Support comes out
We'll look at that again
And build a fresh image
Now of course
In the intermediate time
As there's applications
That we need
We'll rev those
As need be
We pulled back
All of the one to one
Machines this past summer
And re-imaged them
Up to 14.04
Long term support
But again it's really
Driven by you know
The OS reps
You mentioned
You're running Unity
What's the reaction
Been to Unity
From this
From the student body
I think I'm going to
Let the students
Answer that
We have two
Just to give you a sense
Of who's with us today
We have two of our current
Help desk students
Two current students
Here at Penn Manor
And I also have
Three of our Vanguard
Help desk students
These are three individuals
That have
That actually just
Graduated last year
So they're here as well
But I think for the reaction
To the Unity interface
Nick would you like
To take that
Sure
You want to jump in
And take
Hi I'm Nick
And a lot of the students
Here actually kind of
Do like the laptops
But some are complaining
Because they are
So used to Windows
Or Mac
And they can't play
Their games on here
So they keep coming down
But it's something that
We can actually
Really do without
Installing a GUI
Or a different sub
That they can use
But overall
A lot of students
Do like them
Because it gives them
The opportunity to
Bring the laptop home
Work on stuff for school
And then bring it back
Without having to be back
A couple of days or weeks
That makes a lot of sense
So Charlie I know you have
Sounds like you have
A good range of experience
There
Here's my question
You know
Here you are
A very large
What I find fascinating
About this is
It's a very large
Concentrated Linux deployment
Of similar hardware
With a specific
Use case in mind
And I'm curious
And maybe people might
Ask what is Linux lacking
That would make
Your job easier
What have you gone
Oh man
If we just had this
Or if we could just do this
XYZ would be easier
Or we could get this
Better accomplished
What's been lacking
For this initiative
That you've maybe
Worked around
It's not insolvable
But it's maybe
Not the best case
Yeah I think
Four of us kind of
Jumped up and thought
The same thing together
I'm going to introduce you
To another member
Of my staff
Take it away Alex
Hi my name is Alex
I will say
Two things that
Could be improved
From the feedback
From the students
First is that
Since the students
Get to take
The computers home
They already have
Equipment at home
Printers especially
Different network setups
And it's the lack of
Drivers for many
Devices they run at home
Sometimes they have to
Come to us
And help them
To install the drivers
That they can
Do themselves
The second one
Is there's a lack
Of polish on the GUI
For most of the programs
And that from students
That are used to
Carrying their
Android phones
Or iPhones
The interface
Sells a lot
That's a really good point
Yeah they see it
As a polish thing
That's a good point
And the drivers
I could see
Being an issue
Actually if you don't mind
Chris
If you don't mind
I was looking at
Some of the other students
Again current
And past students
Does anybody else
Want to add to that
What are their
Impediments of
People are shaking their heads
Any other ideas
The fact that we can't
Actually print from these
Because we can't
Drive our support
For printing
Yeah that's another
Road block
That we bump into
Although that's not terrible
I mean it's gotten better
Over the years I think
But it's still problematic
I think you know
To add to that
You know we hear a lot
From students and parents
You know that
That just are very unfamiliar
With Linux
And they run into
Road blocks
When they're trying to
Install their home printers
And other devices
So that's pretty common
And have you
Guys experimented all
With something like
Google Cloud Print
Or something like that
That sort of normalizes
The print driver
Where print rendering
Is done on a separate box
Because I mean that's
A lot of times
How network printing works
But Google Cloud Print
I know you're not big
On a lot of the Google services
But Google Cloud Print
Might resolve the issue
For home users
Yeah we haven't really
Explored that
But it's not out of the question
I mean it always could be
Something we look at
Down the road
My team is all kind of
Collectively nodding heads
Up and down
Yeah
I wonder
Have you seen
Or heard of students
Maybe not a lot
But have you heard
Of some students
That were sort of encouraged
Maybe motivated
To use Linux
On their home computer
Yeah actually Nick
Go ahead
Jump in
Last year actually
When I decided to
Join this
My Windows 7 laptop
Was being corrupted
And it wasn't working
So I decided to actually
Install Linux on here
And actually worked out
For the better
I kind of actually prefer
That over Windows 7
Right now
Because it seems to be
Very unstable
That's awesome
Windows 7 was unstable
Yeah
Right yeah
Well that's
That's great
And so
I want to
We're going to
We're going to keep
Pulling ahead here
On some of
The rest of the show
But you guys
Feel free to jump in
On any insights you have
On any of the
Rest of the topics
For today
I guess
My final question is
What's next
Charlie you mentioned
Getting down the rest
Of the school district
What kind of initiatives
Are next for this
Kind of huge project
Yeah I think in our
In our immediate future
We're having discussions
About expanding our
One to one program
To the middle levels
Currently
The only students
That are carrying laptops
As part of the one to one
Are in high school
That's grades 9 through 12
So we're beginning
These planning stages
For rolling that out
To grades 7 and 8
For next year
You know I think
You know beyond that
You know I'm beginning
To think longer range
You know what does this
Look like for an elementary
Implementation
You know but that's
Just the operational
Side of the house
I think that you know
Ideally
What I look forward to
Is just watching
Our teachers and our students
And the interesting
Creative uses
That they have
For the laptops
I mean the whole reason
Is because
It's a learning initiative
You know again
We talk a lot about it
From the technical perspective
And it's very interesting
And you know
And exciting
But at the same time
I think the learning
Opportunities for our kids
I mean that's really
What gets me excited
And I just can't wait
To see what neat things
Our students begin producing
And finding and discovering
You know everything
From coding
To painting and drawing
Applications
To what they do
With the 3D programs
You know I'm just
Really looking forward
To what our kids do
And what they can produce
And build
And you know projects
Yeah absolutely
And I think it's
There's also maybe
Some long term advantages
On being on
The Linux ecosystem
Being on
Getting familiar
With these interfaces
These program names
How they work
It seems like
We are rapidly approaching
A time where
The Raspberry Pi
And devices like it
Could become
Consumerized, productized
And be very accessible
To low cost deployments
Like a school deployment
And the best part about that
In the case of the Raspberry Pi
Is it's fundamentally
Different hardware
Than your desktop PC
But you can still run
The same Unity desktop
The same you know
Firefox applications
And LibreOffice
And all of this stuff
And the school
Would in theory
When these devices
Are powerful enough
If they're not already
Would be able to jump in
And start deploying those
And the cost savings
Like it just seems like
It will continue
To pay off over time
But I guess here's
My really last question
For you Charlie is
You know down the road
You win the lottery
Or a lot of folks
On the IT staff
Win the lottery
Change over happens
Maybe 5, 10 years
Does this initiative
Continue on on its own
Does it have enough momentum
Or if the stars
That are pushing it
Sort of fade
Will the initiative
Begin to fade
And that dominant
Narrative from the parents
And perhaps new faculty members
Who come in from
Other school districts
Come and say
Well this isn't Windows
Where is Office
Windows 10 just came out
It's amazing
You know these kinds of
These kinds of
Will always be
Outside external pressures
That are always constantly
When new eyes come in
Reassessing your project
Reassessing what you're
Doing here
Constantly questioning it
And I wonder
Is this something
That can hold up
To scrutiny long term
Say if some of the
Key drivers behind it
Were to go away
Yeah I think
I think it can
And I think a large reason
Or really to that point
We've been building
To this point
This isn't just something
That we woke up one day
And we decided
Hey we're going to roll out
Not only A a one to one
But also B we're going to
Do it on Linux
You know we've been
Building on experiences
And successes
For well over a decade
You know we started
Again with
With a huge deployment
Of well actually
Started small
But built up a huge
You know a huge infrastructure
Based around open source
And Linux
And demonstrated that
It's not only the cost savings
But it can work
And that open source
Works well
In an enterprise environment
In schools
So I think that you know
Culturally it's
It's really been
Threaded into our DNA
And into our philosophy
Here at Penn Manor
At this school
And I really don't see that
Unraveling any time soon
Because we've demonstrated
That it's a fantastic
Learning model
Model for education
And one that saves
A truckload of money
You know now
Who knows down the future
I mean we would be remiss
If we were not constantly
Re-evaluating technology
Both open source
And proprietary
My team and I
Have a fundamental belief
And we
Our fundamental philosophy
Is obviously you know
Turn toward open source
But we continue to evaluate
And see if there are
Better solutions
And at this point
I don't see anything
In the near to long term
Future that is better
Than a full open source
Implementation for us
From an operational
And more importantly
An educational perspective
Right that makes
No sense
I mean it
Fundamentally at the end
Of the day
Is the best tool
For the job
It's not just one thing
There's a lot of
Aspects to it
Well that's
That's great to hear
And Charlie I've heard
From you know
A lot of people think
This is a great initiative
So major compliments
To the whole team over there
All the students
And everybody
It's really awesome
And it's I don't know
To be honest
It's sort of
It's brought back
My optimism about it
Because it's something
I'd seen fade away
So it's really good
It's people motivated
To get into technology
So everyone over there
Please continue to huddle
Around the laptop
And join us for the remainder
Of the show
And feel free to jump in
Just flag us
If you want to say something
Because I'd love to hear
Your insights on any
Of this stuff
So if somebody has something
They want to contribute
Just raise your hand
And I'll have Charlie ping me
So before we get into
Our next topic
Which is I'm really
I think I'm really happy
With the way our chat
With Mark Shalloworth turned out
I recorded it yesterday
On Monday at 10 a.m.
I did it off air
Because I wanted to ask him
A few things that I wanted him
To feel comfortable
Not having a live audience
Answering them
Because I wanted to go
A little bit deeper
Than the typical
Mark Shalloworth interview goes
And I called him out
On a couple of things
That I think are misconceptions
And he did a really good job
Of addressing them
So I really encourage you
To tune into Sundays
The upcoming Linux action show
Because we covered some ground
That I think a lot of interviews
Have danced around
But nobody's asked Mark
Some of the direct questions
The preview I'm going to play
In today's show
Is Mark's thoughts
In light of
The Debian community upsets
So this is very pertinent
To the discussions
We've had on this show
And I think it actually
Would be pertinent
For some of the students
That are listening right now
On how conflict resolution
Has to kind of work
In the open source community
Before we get to that, though
I want to thank our next sponsor
And that's Linux Academy
This is a great opportunity
For you to go
Bring your skill level up
A little bit
And have something
On that resume
You know, we had an email earlier
Asking about something
That Jesse, I believe it was
That wanted to go out
And try to get something
On the resume
Try to put something
On the books to show
That he's been expanding
His skill set
And that the unemployment time
Has been well spent
Well, Linux Academy
Might be a good way to do that
Because if you go to
LinuxAcademy.com
Slash unplugged
If you go over there right now
You'll get our special discount
That's
LinuxAcademy.com
Slash unplugged
You'll save 33%
On the quarter
And it's a really
Amazing service
It's training
For Linux users
By Linux users
And it's everything
Under that umbrella
DevOps
AWS
OpenStack
Virtualization
Basic command line stuff
Grep
R-Sync
It's everything
Under the umbrella
All of it
And it's done by people
Who truly know
The subject matter
They're not generalists
They're experts
They're expert trainers
They're programmers
It's really
Exactly what
The market's been waiting for
And I think that's why
They're seeing so much success
So go to
LinuxAcademy.com
Slash unplugged
To get started
You have
A lot of free guides
You can read them offline
A lot of the stuff
Is available in
Podcast-like formats
You can listen in the car
And continue to learn
You know, after you're done
With your JV content, of course
And labs come
With their own servers
Just that alone
Is amazing
You get to a point
In the courseware
Where you need to
Actually implement something
They spin up a VM
For you
Give you a public IP address
Give you logins
You can assign roles
You can work in teams
It's so cool
And they do it automatically
From any seven
Of the
Or more now
Of the Linux distributions
And when you choose
Those Linux distributions
All of the courseware
Automatically adjusts
To match that distro
So if you're moving
Between distros
Or curious how
The other side lives
It's a great way
To do this
They have some great
OpenStack courses
They have great
Puppet courses
All of it
Just go over there
And learn a little something
I hear from folks
All the time
They've gone over there
And said, jeez
I had no idea
How much content was available
I've heard you mention
Some of them
But I had no idea
The sheer amount
You could spend years
On the internet
And I need to enter
In my gnome password
Go over there right now
Linuxacademy.com
Slash unplug
Get the 33% discount
Try out a few
Of their courseware
The reason I mentioned Puppet
Is because they just
Refreshed the Puppet stuff
And I think if you've got
More than a couple of servers
Now
Or more than a couple of VPSs
This might be something
That's worth looking into
Maybe you want to
Dip your toe into
Android development
Or OpenStack
Maybe you're one of those
Quote, unquote, DevOps
People all of a sudden
Did you just find yourself out
Did you just find out
Your DevOps
Because I think people
Will learn
Oh wait, this is kind of
A DevOps position
Maybe there's more
I need to learn
Go over there right now
Try it out
And they also have
Scenario-based training
So that way you'll actually
Implement everything from
Setting up the web server
Configuring the security
Getting the CDN caching
Deploying to the website
All of it
It's scenario-based training
So when you walk away
From the course
You've already done the work
It's not
When you go to do it
In a live production environment
It won't be the first time
You've ever done it
That kind of confidence
Is invaluable
They've got in-depth resources
Over at Linux Academy
They've got live Q&A streams
They've got a community
That can help you get going
If you stall out a little bit
If you've got to move into AWS
Go take some of their courses first
If you're managing a PHP server
Go take some of their courses
The list goes, Git
If you've heard us talk about Git
And you have no idea
What it is or how it works
Or you kind of have a rough idea
But you've never actually used it
In a practical use case
They've got a course on it
You want to start doing
Your backups with rsync
They've got a course on it
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Go check them out
I'm telling you
Game changer
It's a game changer
Because it's the difference
Between when you hear
Your general technologist
Talk about open source and Linux
And they just butcher it
And when you hear
Linux users talk about Linux stuff
It's that kind of difference
Because it's by the people
That know the material
Through and through
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Go check it
It's just
You know what I've noticed?
All three of the sponsors
In this show
Have the best dashboards
In the industry
When you log into Linux Academy
All of the courseware is broken out
How long it's going to take
And don't even get me started
On their learning plans
Because the learning plans
You just tell them
Hey, I've got this much time this week
And it automatically generates
Custom courseware
For that availability
How slick is that?
It's the best of breed of technology
With the best kind of backing
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Go become part of that vibrant community
And a big thank you to Linux Academy
For sponsoring the unplugged program
Love it so hard
All right
Before we jump in
If anybody has anything
They want to mention
Feel free
Otherwise I'm going to play
A little bit of the
Mark Shelworth interview
We're doing a little bit
Of a tight show today
Because after the show
If you're listening live
Stick around
We're going to go through
And try to find out
The best moments
For 2014
My hope is
If we get that done
And I think we can
We've got a good showing today
And I'll also
Put the link in the show notes
So if you're listening
Afterwards on the download
But there's a moment
You think might be good
For the best of
I will have a link
To the form in the show notes
It just has a few questions
You can fill them out
And I would really
Appreciate the help
You don't actually
Have to be here live
I feel like it's more productive
If we're all here live
Collaborating at the same time
We'll get a good chunk
Of it done
But I have the sense
That we should give
The download audience
A chance to chime in as well
To the show notes
If there was a best moment
In Jupiter Broadcasting's
2014 run
Help us fill that out
My goal is
If we get it all pulled off
We get all the moments noted
Which is the hardest part
Of a best of
Best ofs you'd think
Are less work
Because you don't have to
Show up and do a show
But it is way more work
Than doing an actual show
Going through
Especially when you have
As big of a back catalog
As we do
So it's a lot of help
If you have a moment
In your recent memory
And you want to go
Let us know about it
I'll have a link
In the show notes
I'd really appreciate it
But we're going to do it
And all right
So let me shift gears
Let me shift over
To the Mark Shuttleworth interview
I was talking to Mark
About a lot of things
And I wanted to get his take
On essentially if the tone
Of conversation
Has been getting
More and more hostile
And why is that?
Why is the tone
As bad as it is?
And what can we do?
These are a couple of questions
That I started to ask Mark
And he jumped in with
I thought some pretty good
Commentary on the topic
So here's just a couple
Of minute pull out
From the whole interview
Which we'll have
In Sunday's
Linux action show
Just tell people
To stop
And ask them
Why they're involved
And what they're involved in
Right?
If you're just here
To be a talking head
Then
And you're just going to
Bring opinions
To the table
Then you need to
Back off
Because we're trying
To get stuff done here
Do you think it's the result
Of the size of the communities
Now that there's
Now there's just
So many people involved
That there's just not as many
People actually producing code?
Well, no
I think it's
I think it's more
Got to do with the fact
That it's so easy
To contribute an opinion
Because of
Because of the evolution
Of sort of
The social thing
Right, right
So it used to be
That if you wanted
To have an opinion
On how Debian did something
You needed to show up
You needed to become
A Debian developer
You needed to go through
A process that essentially
Gave you a sophisticated understanding
Of how all the parts
Fit together
And who's contributing what
And who's responsible for what
And get a sense
Of the culture
Because now you can just
You can just throw comments
At LWN
On Slashdot
Or somewhere else
Right
So I think that's
The real issue
And it's the same thing
With Gamergate
Right
It's this
It's that
In a sense
It's so cheap
Just to throw another opinion
On the fire
And in some ways
It's rewarding
To put out an opinion
That's somehow polarized
And so as a result
We get a lot of
Polarizing opinions
It's not
Not surprising
Right
But I do think
We have to
We have to be willing
To defend our communities
For it
And continue to invest
In building a clear
Constructive conversation
For people
Who want to
Get stuff done
And that's why
We
I think
Continue to
To just
You know
Steamroller forward
Not just with Unity
And Ubuntu
But actually across
Huge tracts
Of
Free software
Right
Because people feel
They can come there
Be part of that conversation
And get stuff done
Yeah
We have an incredible
Community council
That are very thoughtful
And supportive
And also
You know
We
We don't fool ourselves
That you can have a technical
Meritocratic decision
By 500 people
Right
You take a decision
As to the three people
Who need to make a decision
And then
Yeah
They get on
And do it
Right
So what do you think guys?
I'll start
Let's start at the bottom there
Wimpy
Is it just
Is it that comments
Are cheap
And that anybody
Can have an opinion
And that's what's moved
The tone forward
Or is it
The beliefs
Of how technology
Should be implemented
And it's really coming down
To more of a
Philosophical difference?
What
What do you
What's your sense of it
Wimpy?
I think that it's
The first thing
I think that it is
Far too easy
For people
To contribute
Comments
To a wide
Audience
That don't
Necessarily
Understand all
Of the technical merits
Of the discussion
And repeat
Sound bites
And clips
That they've picked up
From
Other places
Elsewhere
It's
So it's sort of like
Opinions
Are
Sort of like
A dime a dozen
Everybody's got one
I want to ask
But sometimes
Sometimes not their own
They're
They're repackaging
Other people's opinions
Not necessarily
Technically accurate
Opinions
And passing them off
As their own
Boy
You see that in political debates
All the time
Right?
Yeah
And you've
And you've identified
A few
Problems with the quality
Of this
Of you know
Pinging backwards and forwards
And citing each other
Over
System D
Rotten Corpse
Do you have the sense though
That
Some of it is also
That maybe there's
Less technically savvy people
Involved now
And they're not understanding
The nuances
Of the discussion?
Well that
That goes with the
Repackaging as well
But the problem is that
The
The people who
Are
Providing those
Repackaging
Opinions
They don't know
As well
So there's a lot of people
Who are talking about
They don't understand
The
The topic
The technical part of the topic
But then they're acting like
They do
And then spreading more
Misinformation that is
Then spread again
And it just
You know
It just
Rolls
Keeps rolling on
Becomes bigger and bigger
Web wizard
Break it down for me
You say
You would argue
One is because of the other
What do you mean?
So basically
When you go in
You look at this
And you say
Look at these
These opinions
Are that way
And then there's these arguments
And then we have to argue it out
Between
You know
500 people
3 people
Whatever
It's
It comes down to
Well
I'm arguing this
Because of this reason
And
I know my reason is right
There's nothing that makes it wrong
So therefore
You must be wrong
And the other person
Has nothing wrong
With their argument either
But they're thinking
The exact same thing
There's nothing wrong
With my argument
You must be wrong
And this is
And then you go
And you have each other
And you're both insistent
That the other is wrong
Because there's nothing wrong
With my argument
Urban
Do you feel like
People have to pass a test
Before they can give
Their opinions online
On technical issues?
Like a technical
Qualifications test?
No
I'm not that far
But I think that
People should give
And need to give
Their opinions
But only if they know
What they're talking about
If they don't have
A technical background
To
To say about
Any systems
They should
Shut up
About system D
I think everybody
Thinks they know
What they're talking about
Right?
That's part of the problem
Because everybody thinks
They've got it figured out
All right, Lionhead
I want to ask you a question
You and I
We sit here almost
Every morning
On Tech Talk today
And we talk about
Technology news
We are one of these
Commentators that
Mark is talking about
Are we, Lionhead
You and I
Part of the problem?
No
I don't really think so
Because
At least for myself
I know my limitations
And I try to
Angle my point of view
From what I actually do know
And if I don't know something
I completely acknowledge that
Yeah, so
There is that kind of
View as well
Know your own limits
Kind of thing
Before you jump in
Yeah
That's a good point
You know
And something else
Mark says in the interview
Is that
Part of it is
Human psychology
It can be kind of satisfying
To go online
And drop a big wisdom bomb
When everybody knows
What they're talking about
Right?
Yeah
And drop a big wisdom bomb
When everybody
Be like
Boom, here's my point
Look at me
I thought of this
You know
And it's sort of a
Satisfying kind of feeling
A sensation for some people
And so it's a little
Human nature to do it too
To jump in on something
We all care about
And also
The thing about the
The three people
Versus 500 people
Is not the argument
Of opinion versus opinion
It's more of the argument
That three people
Having a discussion
Is a lot easier to compromise
Than 500 people
You know
Let's ask Charlie a question
I'm always extremely curious
How much of all
Of the inner turmoil
And drama
Inside these open source
Projects
Actually leaks out
Into real world
So Charlie
When you're talking about
Linux and open source
And people developing software
All over the world
Do you also say
And by the way
They fight a lot
Is there a disclaimer?
Do you say
Sometimes it's treacherous?
What's that look like?
How do you prepare people
That might be looking
Into the open source world
For the first time?
Or does it
Not even come up?
Well I think
I think it's a huge concern
Actually
I think part of my role
As an IT leader
For the district
For our organization
Is to
Well first off
I keep up with this
As much as I can
Again I'm not a developer
So some of the finer points
You know escape me
But
I think what's key
Is that from my
Perspective
I need to
Have at least
A finger in the pulse
So I can get a sense
As to whether or not
Projects are going to
Live or die
Sure
You know for us again
Everything that we do
I think about
From the enterprise
Perspective
You know so not just
The immediate
People that support this
You know over
Three five
Maybe even ten years
So you know I think
That the infighting
On a lot of projects
It does certainly
Concern me because
You know again
I've seen many
You know many projects
That you know were
Potentially killed
Or strangled by
You know a community
That just sometimes
Can't get their act together
Now I don't
That's not an indictment
You know I think that's also
A tremendous strength
Of open source
And developing software
In the open
You know so again
From my perspective
It's a big concern
I think what it doesn't do
Is it doesn't necessarily
Help you know schools
That you know by nature
Are not technical
You know they're looking
For fast easy simple
Fantastic educational solutions
So the minutia
Of technical arguments
You know it doesn't
Really help the conversation
So I don't know if that's
What you're looking for
In terms of that question
But that's my perspective on it
I didn't even think about it
In the fact of
If I'm looking for
An enterprise and I'm looking
To get something that
You know multi-year
Sustainability out of
Of course
Of course the drama
Of a community
Would be a concern
And it almost becomes
The responsibility of the person
That's trying to implement
That technology
At least have a bit
Of an understanding
Of how volatile the project is
Because in open source
You know it's not the mighty dollar
That drives that project
It's the passion
Of the contributors
In a lot of cases
So that makes so much sense
That that would be
That if you're sitting back
And watching a project
Right now
And you see a project
That's just falling apart
You're not going to want
To bet the farm
On that for five years
You're going to try to find
Maybe something else
That's maybe a little stable
Maybe a little
A little more tame
Well ironically
You would have thought
That would be Debian
You know
You would have thought
That was Debian to a T
But watching them fall apart
It even happens there too
I mean not fall apart
That's kind of
Putting it over the top
But obviously
They've been having issues
And that's critical too
Because education
Again I'm speaking specifically
From education
But you know
Educational leaders
I mean they
They have limited dollars
To begin with
And it doesn't
You know
By the same token
But you know
With when you're betting
On open source projects
In general
It's not as if
You know
We can just turn
To another vendor
And say hey
Help support this
You know
We are
One of the downsides
Of our current position
Is that
You know
I can't just
Easily go out
And get support
For the projects
And programs
That we have in place here
Now I'm incredibly fortunate
To have a phenomenal team
Of technologists
You know
Because they're just
Great technologists
But you know
If I didn't have
That internal support
I would be at the mercy
Of vendors
And again
That's an incredibly precarious
And dangerous position
For a school district
Or any organization
That can't turn to
You know
Somebody or something
For support
Absolutely
Rotten Corps
You have a question
For Charlie
Go ahead
Yeah I was wondering
Do you find it more
There's
Based on when you
Started doing this
Do you
Is it more recently
Have you noticed
A difference
In Debian
Or anything
In particular
Linux community
Based on before
Because at
At one point
Like Debian has not changed
How they do anything
They caught
There's a lot of people
Leaving and coming and going
And there's hundreds of people
Working on Debian
And people leave
Because of different
You know
Opinions
But now that they can
Make it public
And that media people
Pick it up
Do you think that has
Any effector
For the
The perception
That people have
For this
Yeah
Just kind of
Thinking out loud
Yeah and I guess
It
You know it's tough
And I'm not as
You know
Up to speed
On those specific
Arguments and discussions
You know I think
I guess the key is
You know just
The tone of these
Again these tend to be
Incredibly technical
You know
Sometimes vanity
Discussions
Very much
And you know
I just
It doesn't help
You know it just doesn't
It just doesn't help
You know the
The tech industry itself
Finds itself fighting
All the time
Over
You know Apple
Versus Microsoft
You know iOS
Versus Android
You know I think
What we do in
Our industry
Again just
In fighting
Doesn't add to
It just doesn't add
To you know
To anything
For technical leaders
So again without
Knowing all of the
You know all the details
The arguments
Yeah I just
I just think it
Makes it more difficult
You know I think we should
All be focused on
Working together
In these programs
And trying to minimize
You know the
The strife
Yeah preach it
Alright Charlie can
Will you do me a favor
Give it
Give everybody down
I'll give you a countdown
And when I get to one
Hold down the
Push to talk
And have everybody in the room
Say
Linux unplugged alright
In three
Two
One
Linux unplugged
We gotta try that again
Come on whole group
Three
Two
We totally have to try that again
He's gonna give us a countdown
To screaming
Linux unplugged
Yeah we wanna get
The whole room in there
The whole room
Let's see if we can just
Break the whole thing in
Three
Two
One
Linux unplugged
That's pretty good
Alright thanks guys
Alright well
We'll wrap it up right there
I think
We gotta get out of here
Cause we got some
Thanksgiving shenanigans
Here in the U.S.
To prepare for
Matt we're gonna have
A great show on Sunday
We got not only
The Shuttleworth interview
We got all our other
Regular stuff
Are you ready
I'm so ready
Yes
Alright you bring it
I'll make sure that
I know
Don't worry Matt
I'll get bacon
I can handle that
Alright so those of you
Watching live
Please do stick around
We're gonna do
Our best of summary
Don't forget Linux Unplugged
Is typically live on Tuesdays
At 2pm pacific
Over at jblive.tv
Jupiterbroadcasting.com
Slash calendar
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
For the feedback
Jupiterbroadcasting.com
Slash contact
Drop that down
Choose Linux Unplugged
And send it in
We need it
Alright everybody
Thanks so much
For tuning this week's episode
Of Linux Unplugged
See you right back here
See you
Bye
Well that was fun, thanks everybody.
It was a little tricky making one laptop work for everybody in the room but I think it turned
out okay and we had a good discussion.
So that was nice.
So we're gonna sort of shut down here and switch over to our best of thing but let's
go over to the JB Titles real quick and pick ourselves a title before we do that.
We got some business to take care of before we run and I don't know man, I didn't see
a lot of title suggestions.
Repackage your opinion, that's pretty good.
I kind of like that.
Cool kids use Linux.
JBTitles.com, JBTitles.com, er buddy boat.
Know your technical limits.
That's pretty good.
Yeah, know your limits is good.
Unplugged education, I like that.
That's good too.
Unplugged, I'm gonna give that a boat right now.
Good one Keller.
Let's see, let's see, let's see.
What's that?
Unplugged education?
Unplugging education.
Oh, I suppose, yeah.
Yeah, like get rid of that thing.
Get it out of here.
Yeah, maybe we could just get, maybe we could just loan Charlie out to different school
districts.
That'd be cool, right?
Yeah.
That was neat they were able to join us during the school day over there.
That was awesome.
It's got to be getting close to the end of the day for them, right?
I would think so.
East Coast, they're 511 over there.
Yeah, oh boy.
Well, a big thank you to them for joining us.
That was really cool.
Yeah.
All right, JBtelus.com, we'll go pick a title and then get, did you guys hear about this
Sony hack?
Matt, have you heard about this?
Yes.
Where they replaced, it's Sony Pictures.
I guess it's the movie arm, but like this has got to be a Windows vulnerability they're
taking advantage of here because it's full screen images and holding data for ransom,
taking over Twitter accounts, replacing Google Play apps.
This is a massive breach and it's of course the week we take TechSnap up.
Oh man.
Well in hindsight though, it'll allow more things to develop over time and you can come
back to it.
We do like them deets.
That's a good point.
Yeah.
All right, JBtitles.com, unplugged education.
I do like it, but I could see the negative connotation.
Repackage your opinions would be good too though.
Linux powered schools.
Cool kids use Linux.
School of Linux, cool kids use Linux again.
Open source education.
Linux in schools is cool.
Boy, I would have loved to have been a student back when that was going on.
That would have been so neat.
All right, last chance and then we're going to run.
Last chance and unplugged education is racking up the top, but there's still a chance.
Everybody go over there and boat.
Repackage your education.
Boat.
Nice.
Oh, yes.
Boat, boat, boat.
I think he's done, the school sounds really interesting.
Yeah.
I agree.
I wish my school did that.
No kidding.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean the best you're going to get-
I'm still in school, so I have a chance to change it.
The best you're usually going to get in school is freaking Chromebooks.
Yeah.
I would have loved to have anything remotely relevant to computer class.
I don't think it really counts to your entire, your entire school.
Your entire hour of the class is Mavis Beacon.
Or Organ Trail.
Or Organ Trail on an old Mac.
Now, don't doubt Organ Trail.
That's how I learned about dysentery.
Come on now.
Exactly.
I learned how to do punch cards in computer science at school.
Oh, wait.
Boom.
Static.
Well, now, that's been a really useful skill set that you've been able to bring forward.
Yeah.
Even when I was taught it, it was about 20 years out of date, I think.
Oh, wow.
Did you have hanging chads?
Yeah.
Did you ever, like, drop all your punch cards and get them all mixed up?
Oh, God.
Yeah.
Done that.
And also, we had the paper tape as well, which, frankly, it's only practical application is
removing fingerprints.
Wow.
I was going to say, the last person that I heard that actually used to tape drive to
go and take it, well, sorry, a regular paper tape with punch holes in it was my teacher,
and she's nearly 16 now.
Yeah.
It's an older generation thing for sure.
I'm not that old.
Like I say, it was well out of date when I was at school, but this was the quality of
computer education.
I want to find one just to experiment with it.
Yeah.
It'll be kind of fun.
My father-in-law has still got one from the mainframe systems he used to operate at Heinz,
so yeah, maybe I'll dig that out at Christmas and take some photos.
Well, schools have got slightly better.
Their only perception of Linux in books at the moment is Ubuntu.
Yeah.
That's a de facto screenshot for every single one I've seen.
I wonder if, yeah, I mean, hmm.
Redhead desktop's pretty popular too.
Okay.
I can see Ubuntu, and especially with the Edubuntu spin and Zubuntu, being pretty useful
for schools.
Yeah.
And Ubuntu Monte.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
In fact, Wimpy, we were going to-
Nice plug.
Yeah.
There was a...
You were telling me about a pretty big deployment of...
In fact, that was something I was going to ask Charlie if they've played with Linux terminal
services at all.
Yes.
When I was.
That's what I used.
Yeah.
There's a few in the embryonic stages at the moment, and I can't really say too much about
it at the moment because it might happen and it might not, and if it looks like it's definitely
going to happen, I shall be sure to fill you in on the details.
But here's a little teaser.
The Ex2Go Gathering was sponsored by IBM.
Hmm.
Really?
IBM?
And they like those PowerPC things, and they contracted Canonical to port Ubuntu to PowerPC
recently.
Oh, wow.
Oh, I didn't realize that.
You know, that would have been a good answer for the emailer who was saying, how do I repurpose
these old XP and PowerPC Macs as maybe Linux terminal services?