What I want to start with is this article opensource.com that's talking about smart
GIMP tricks. I'm wondering if anyone in the mumble room or otherwise does a lot with GIMP.
I know rottencorpse you do a lot of graphic design but I'm not sure if you use GIMP or not.
Maybe rottencorpse isn't here. Anyone use GIMP? I use it to crop pictures
and I actually there's a there's a processing service that we print all of our promotional
material from Ultispeed so we have you know our cards and we have flyers and table tents
and stuff like that and a lot of that stuff gets sent out over GIMP but because Inkscape will
export to to a PNG and then they want silly little compressed formats that you know that
are far so I use it to essentially to reprocess image files and occasionally I'll crop a picture
or you know or change something like that but anyone use GIMP extensively?
I don't use it extensively but I do see a great use for it as that kind of go-to utility you know
pretty much any Linux install that you have you have GIMP you know that you can use it for those
base needs yeah also sometimes it does the job very well I've used it a lot to render pdfs
before sending it to a printer kind of sure kind of like what you do yeah yeah yeah for you know
and I did see actually it was it was interesting of all places I was watching True TV unless you
watch True TV do you ever watch like forensic files and the new detectives and stuff like that?
I have not but it sounds interesting. I tell you what it's a double-edged sword because on one hand
I start to think I can get away with anything because I'm like oh you moron how did you not
know about DNA and then on the other hand I realized that that's from like 10 years ago
and so you know 10 years ago that whatever the technology is that we have today to catch people
probably won't become very prevalent for another 10 years and so you know I'm judging people based
on their information 10 years ago but I was watching the other night and GIMP actually
made an appearance and they were talking about how they were changing the contrast of this photo to
bring out certain elements in it and you know the little announcer guy he's got this you know deep
voice and he's like so the photo analysts use the GNU image manipulation program which is a
professional program released for free and has that has amazing power and part of me was like
okay so I actually don't know a lot of you know super photo professionals or image professionals
that use GIMP on the other hand I'm really happy that there's a public perception at least in that
particular TV show that it's this very high-powered tool and is available for free. Right those shows
get so much wrong it's nice that at least they're getting it wrong in our direction for once. Well
yeah it was kind of cool but so anyway so I saw the GIMP and then you posted this story and I'm
like maybe I'm a little out of touch maybe there are a ton of people that are using GIMP nowadays
and in the chat room you know I should point out in the chat room there's a ton of people that are
using GIMP obviously Odyssey Westrup he actually and Odyssey you should you should maybe join us
if you have the ability to jump and mumble but Westrup he's a graphics designer so he uses
does a lot of graphics design and he does all of it in open source and we've actually had him do a
couple of stuff from us for us as a company AltaSpeed that is and I've had him do some
personal stuff for me and I know that he uses all open source software GIMP and Inkscape and
Corita and and and that that's actually how he does the majority of his workflow.
So but anyone use any other open source graphics utilities anyone ever used Inkscape?
I used Inkscape. What do you use it for? I used to use it not so much anymore but when I ran my
business somebody needed something done like a brochure or something like that it was great for
doing page layouts. Okay. I actually preferred it over Scribus. No kidding.
One of the Ubuntu phone community developers created a toolkit in Inkscape for doing user
interface design mock-ups so it's got all of the all of the kind of elements that you would need
to create you know an application whatever application you like as little elements in
a giant Inkscape document and you just drag the bits around duplicate them move around line them
all up and then you know design your application that way it's really really cool. I tell you what
one of the things that I have come to love about Inkscape itself is because it's a vector graph
program you know I can I can start out with a you know 500 by 500 800 by 800 or whatever it is
a canvas and and design a graphic you know you know asset and then I can take that graphic asset
and I can say all right well I need to blow that up to the size of a banner or a poster or we're
going to wrap a car or a via service vehicle and how are we going to do that well we can take that
that vector graphic and it scales you know essentially and definitely and you can combine
one graphic art from the other so I'll give you an example we actually are launching
a cloud-based wi-fi for the hospitality industry so essentially they pay us pay us a monthly fee
and we bring in a bunch of equipment and set it up and we manage all of that remotely and one of
the things is that there is a tent that goes inside of the room and that tent has connection
details and contact information if if they have so if they have trouble with their wi-fi they
can call a 1-800 number and somebody will walk them through how to restart their computer and
turn on the lights all the stuff that I wouldn't want to do right and then if it exceeds that level
then it gets elevated to us and so we we got a a free for use essentially a wi-fi vector graphic
and we were able to bring that into Inkscape and take our existing car that we already had
designed and put in then we had this wi-fi logo and because it's it's a vector graphic
all of the transparency carried over all of the you know I could change the color to match the
color scheme that we had it's just incredible and and the fact that I can do all that with open
source software is incredible to me you know and it it it changes the way that you can approach
a project because I can essentially use the internet and people on the internet that are
doing creative things and combine those all for for a single purpose and it's awesome it is I've
used it a little bit of work myself mostly for I'll have a automated tool that will output a
graph maybe of like data structure relations and how they're you know foreign key kind of stuff
and Inkscape will just import the pdf and you can modify it before shipping it out or putting it on
the wiki for documentation that's awesome yeah and and you know we actually we I think the I
can't remember the program that we used for our original logo design the one that everyone
comments on but but we took but after that we took that imported it and and Inkscape actually
has the ability to look at a graphic asset and trace it out and then fill it with a blank color
and so we essentially stripped all of the you know fancy filters and stuff off of it and turn it back
into you know a vector and then we were able to recolor it and build it back up from there so that
was that was pretty neat yeah it was pretty cool open source yeah it was awesome this is linux
unplugged episode 128 for january 19th 2016 welcome to linux unplugged your weekly talk
show that's brought to you this week from the sprawling metropolis of the frozen tundra
my name is noah my name is wes hey wes how are you i'm doing great how about yourself well
once again the the uh the lovely world of the internet has connected us your ip packets isn't
it wonderful it is and we and we get to chat and talk about linux which is coincidentally my
favorite thing to talk about so i want to start out by talking about why it is uh wes and i are
pretending to be chris this week and that's because chris is on his way to scale he is in
jb rover 2 which if you haven't seen head over to twitter.com and check out at chris las it is it
is crazy cool he got a like an amazing rv wes have you seen pictures of this thing yeah it is a beast
it's incredible it is incredible it it is like a luxury home on wheels and i like anyone who sees
it is going to be jealous they're gonna i would live in a camper if that's what my camper looked
like that's how cool it is but like a roving jb party bus exactly oh that's good oh that's really
good that's a better name than that's a better name than rover 2 the rover party bus not to
pitch that to him anyway he's on the road as we speak making his way down to scale if you're not
familiar with what scale is it's a southern california linux expo and chris is going to
be attending this year and hanging out uh and and covering some of the community aspects and
this that and the other and uh because of the way that uh the time it's going to take him to travel
he's not available on tuesday and so he has let wes and i sit in the big chair and do the show
this week so we are going to talk this week starting uh with a reddit thread a follow-up
from the linux action show and basically um reg regia regia i don't exactly know how to pronounce
that um posted in the linux action uh in the linux action show subreddit which is of course
reddit.com slash r slash linux action show and he says no it hit on something about unity and he
says i wish i i think he's quoting me it says i wish abuntu would just use gnome and go back to
trying to contribute useful bits and then he um links to an imager image of uh of uh apparently
a star trek episode um now i have a few extensions oh he's showing his desktop now i have a few
extensions installed but the way i use gnome it isn't much different than how somebody else would
use unity i keep the dash on it all sides i have those pesky tray apps in the corner and so on
this is close to how i work with unity and osx etc i'm puzzled to why gnome gets treated like
the redheaded stepchild sometimes now uh now i know that once in a while gnome the gnome dev team
decides to head off the deep and make the file manager work like an old school finder by default
but hey let's override users pre-existing settings that's that's not very good is it
but overall gnome just keeps getting better and better now west you're the one that actually
brought this to my attention what was your immediate thought when you read this and and
was and you know if you when you watched the show and and thought about how all that ties together
well you know i i too am a gnome user uh i definitely prefer it but i can understand
why canonical wants to be developing their own desktop environment you know with their
plans for convergence with uh the big move to unity 8 i think a lot will depend on what that
looks like when it's shipped and when everyone's using it uh but at the end of the day i think
people do you know like yourself like many desktop users a lot of people i know at work who sit next
to me are using unity and it seems to work for them and i also think the that while that gnome
is different uh there does seem to be a significant portion of people who use gnome not dissimilar to
unity you know with the with the doc on the side kind of you know you hit your super key and you're
finding applications it's it's not that different so i guess my you know i'm one of the few people
that actually and i i responded this in the reddit too i'm one of the few people that actually like
unity um i actually have unity on the laptop i'm using right now and i have it on the desktop
that i'm using to send the stream to chris that becomes particularly evident when um
you have multi monitors that exceed three if you have more than three monitors
i just think that unity it comes off more polished than gnome does oftentimes and chris
would would vehemently disagree with this he he would tell you that he would point out a thousand
different things that that that um that point to why gnome is a more polished desktop environment
but i see things like you know the multi-monitor support the fact that i can choose
a display and only that display has my you know launcher bar and activity stay and i can put that
on any of the displays doesn't necessarily have to be the quote unquote primary um i can set up
how i want i can set up because oftentimes the quote unquote primary monitor is the one that's
right in the center of me and i have two auxiliary monitors off to the left and right and then three
auxiliary monitors up on top and that's not a that's not a usual use case but it's my use case
and in in that instance i i think that unity just shines a little bit and the other thing is too is
i feel like there are a lot of things that just feel that make unity feel more cohesive than gnome
and i'll give you an example so on guake for example i get weird i'm not sure it could be a
bug but i get a weird thing where when i bring down guake it doesn't it the transparency doesn't
necessarily go over the um this the the menu at the side do you use guake wes you know i have in
the past but uh i usually just have a terminal open kind of in the corner somewhere anyway so
i use it currently yeah so i so i i like to have whatever i'm doing and this is the one thing i
think that gnome got right is have everything in full screen and take up the whole screen
and the exception to that is the terminal because oftentimes the terminal is my connection to
another machine exactly and then my screen is whatever i'm doing to that machine and so i bring
the terminal down i do some work i put it back up i you know reorganize figure out what i'm going to
do next bring the terminal back down and i feel like um i i just i think that gnome uh it does not
feel as native to me when i install an app and have you know that like that that menu that guake
for example come down it just doesn't feel as native to me as it does in in something like
unity and i i see other little things that just feel like pieces that have been put together and
on one hand i really appreciate that because that is essentially the heart of linux right
everyone does something very very well and we bring all those pieces together
and it makes for a cohesive experience um and for whatever reason i just there are there are
there are a number of little things that just make me think that gnome is missing and so i'm
actually one of the people that like unity that said there are there are some there are some key
issues that irritate the heck out of me so i had a client that actually was using a bantu gnome
because that's the first thing everyone's going to say is i don't know why everyone's i don't know
why no is hating on gnome it's available with a bantu it's a it's a it's a blessed uh you know
i forget the terminology not not a flavor but a um you know a flavor uh the gnome environment and
he installed a bunch of gnome and what would happen was if you would full screen a flash
video in firefox and then uns full screen it and then go back to refull screen it it wouldn't ref
it wouldn't go back into full screen a second time you'd have to restart his computer or at least log
out to make that happen again now some people are going to blame firefox some people are going to
blame gnome some people are going to blame a bantu but the problem didn't occur in chrome inside of
a bantu gnome and the problem didn't occur in firefox in a bantu unity and the problem didn't
occur in any other distro i can tell you've tried this yeah well yeah we troubleshot the heck out of
it let me tell you because i and so basically what i came to i came to the conclusion that
at least in in in some esoteric use cases because canonical is focusing so much on their own desktop
everything works really really well in unity and so if you're going to use a bantu you're probably
your best choice is to go with uh is to go with unity because that's their quote-unquote default
desktop and so what i think is is interesting is we have this illusion of choice that you can pick
any desktop but really you you start to you start to have compromises and the further down the list
you go the the the less popular of a desktop you choose the more problems i find that exist and so
you know i i can't count the number of issues i've had with uh cinnamon when i try to install
it on a bunch of now on a like on mint it works just fine but you try and install the cinnamon
desktop on top of a bantu and i have all sorts of weird weird issues that i don't really want to
work through and so so i i and i don't know and so that that was kind of my response on reddit
and i'm wondering what you think of that response i think that's fair uh i would like to hear what
our mumble room has to say let's uh introduce those fine fellows hello hello hello oh there's
tons of people in here so mumble room uh you guys all use linux right yes sir what's that question
what's that question lunix gnu slash linux yeah gnu slash linux um so wimpy i'm interested
to some degree to get your perception because a bantu mate is is one of those uh is one of
those distros where i i have not to the best of my knowledge found a single thing that when as
when using a bunch of mate where it makes me feel like i'm on a on on an alternative desktop from
a from standard bantu everything just worked i mean literally everything just works in fact so
much so that i actually all of the production machines that i have here in grand forks um with
the exception the one i'm on now but all the rest of them are actually running a bunch to mate because
it runs lighter than it does with unity and i'm wondering you know what kind of considerations
went into that and and and how you guys feel about that and um and how that plays out well
well a bantu mate is just a bantu in fact it is a bantu um when you when when when you boil it down
you simply i say simply it's taken a year and a half to do you you remove
unity and you put the mate desktop on top but then you keep all of the bantu tools and integrations
that already exist underneath the hood which is what gives you all of that stability and just
works goodness of a bantu on a traditional desktop environment so and one of the reasons why
mate is lighter than um unity is that it's based on gnome 2 with all of the old compatibility stuff
from gnome 1 removed and all of the underpinnings upgraded to the latest versions of all the recent
technologies um and it's all written in c so it's a very lightweight implementation by you know by
comparison to what it was um when it was gnome 2 in its sort of last versions so um it's kind of
happenstance in some respect that respects that mate has now come out as a lightweight desktop
alternative outstanding um anyone else have have uh have thoughts or opinions on desktop environments
and good i i'm sorry my audio is terrible i'm in america for scale um uh so there's a few things
one whenever anyone says i'm one of the few people who like unity i want to slap them because there
are millions of people who use unity watch out at scale watch out at scale no one yeah and and
you know saying i'm one of the few people what actually is the case is there are a few really
negative uh people who don't like it and who are very vocal and there's a vast number of people
who use it and aren't vocal so you know saying you're one of the few people you should actually
say i'm one of the majority you like unity to be fair um so the the original question you know from
the guy posted on reddit was about you know why don't we just use gnome you could use that same
argument about every single desktop why don't you just all pack up and go home and use something
else is effectively what you're saying and every single desktop has their own um niche that they
want to fulfill or use cases that they um address that others don't like you know for example
elementary have their um uh niche with it's not so much a niche i would like to have a you know
well-designed pretty robust you know functional desktop uh that sounds like a reasonable thing
and and so you know that i think it's unreasonable to suggest that the people who are working on
those things should throw that away and use something else instead um you might just as well
say why didn't katie give up and switch to no it may it's a it's a nonsensical argument from my
point of view that's fair um so basically and i admit that this is a horrible horrible thing to
to base a generalization on but there was a i am admitting that up front but there is there it was
a couple months ago maybe even a year ago that we did a poll um a straw poll and to find out
what desktop environment people were using and i was shocked at how many people didn't vote for
unity and and and gnome shot way to the top and and unity was down there and i guess i've had
that correct or incorrect or correct um perception that uh that unity just wasn't preferred by a lot
of the people that the you know that that are aware of other desktop environments that are out
there and i fully admit that you that you know work you know working in the space that you work
in you're going to have a much much much more realistic perception you know what actually
biased biased and you should throw away my opinion completely and you should only listen to people
who are outside of this bubble um because they weren't their opinion won't be tarnished you know
potentially is one side of it but the flip side is any of these um polls are deeply flawed the same
way that they're bearing uh using distro watch is your measure exactly the same it's ridiculous and
people who who place any importance on something which is basically um a poll which can be shared
amongst a subreddit which massively skews the numbers for any one distro plus or minus when
in fact the actual people who use and like a particular desktop or user interface or application
or whatever are ultimately never going to see that poll my mum uses Ubuntu and has used Ubuntu
for years she will never see that poll and never click on anything in that poll same that's exactly
the point i was i was thinking is that however many millions of people in china use the Ubuntu
desktop they're never going to see this because the thing's written in english for one so it's
just ludicrous we in particular also are a community of you know linux enthusiasts and
people who like customization i think some of unity's strengths is that it can be widely
deployed and people it's pretty easy for people to just get it you know the icons are right there
on the left you hit the super key things just work so it has a lot going for it like like you
said you know your mom can use it my mom uses it it's it's great well and we also have unity is
actually the default desktop on well not the default test that was the only desktop uh on the
on all of our kiosk machines that we deploy and so basically if you think about the target audience
there it's we're taking people from all walks of tech of the technical spectrum and saying that
no matter who walks in if they sit down and they want to check their email print a boarding pass
or check the weather they're going to be able to accomplish those things quickly easily and
without complaining to the front desk because of course if they complain then we lose the contract
and what we found is that little bar on the side of unity which by the way requires no tweaking
and requires no extensions which means we don't have to update anything it becomes is is incredibly
useful in a situation like that and so i agree that the average person walking around the street
is going to sit down and have no trouble using unity and i think i even started out by saying
i phrased it you know poorly but the the gist of the message was it's my personal belief that that
unity is a more polished desktop than gnome is um but uh but for whatever reason and maybe it is
just that people are are terribly vocal i guess there is a there is there is a perception from
from some people that uh there's a perception from some people that that the that the unity
of desktop is inferior correct or incorrect well that's different it's like any any individual
like any reddit consumer uh is entitled to have their opinion and it's perfectly fine for someone
to say unity is inferior because of these xyz reasons in the same way that someone might not like
enlightenment or someone might not like kde because it doesn't work their workflow or the
apps don't look right or you know for whatever reason it's perfectly fine for people to have their
opinions you know and like buttholes everyone's got the problem is when you try and extrapolate
from a poll on a random website somewhere and make bold assertive statements about whether
something is right or wrong or whether something is good or bad based on a button clicked by a
bunch of random people on the internet it makes no sense whatsoever to me but that's just me
no i think that's completely fair um all right well i want to talk about a piece of feedback
that we got in and this comes to us from do cake and do cake writes in and he says greetings i
was hoping that maybe some of the technical savvy people might be able to help point me in the right
direction to resolve my crisis i may have just made a potentially costly mistake we nuked and paved
a friend's brand new lenovo yoga 500 with linux without booting into windows to first disable
secure boot explicitly he didn't want to accept the eula and so we successfully booted into the
usb key a bunch of mate 1510 a bunch of with unity 1504 so we thought we would just go ahead we
installed both a bunch of mate 1510 and then installed a bunch of with unity 1404 after
booting we were faced with a very plain and daunting boot prompt and he gives a screenshot
i get a screen with boot options of which the hard drive if i select any of these it just reprompts
me to the same screen i imagine that i need to go into the system that has a secure boot signature
that is find such a distro install it disable secure boot then reinstall our preferred system
i thought a bunch who would be a candidate but apparently not is this the correct way which
distros would work we have tried installing into a bantu unity 1504 which is supposed to have the
appropriate signature but after install and reboot we get the above given that windows has been
obliterated at this point what options do i have unfortunately he's leaving in just over a week so
if the conclusion ends up being install windows to do this i'll take it but i'd rather not if anyone
has any tips thanks do cake so i hate and i use that word strongly i hate windows and secure boot
it has become a nightmare to get linux onto machines sometimes and i had a guy that we
actually ended up returning his computer back to best buy and he bought a different model
because we simply and i fully admit i'll put this disclaimer out it's probably because i'm an idiot
i fully admit that there's probably some of you out there that know exactly what buttons to click
and exactly how to get it to install but i couldn't i couldn't get it to work and it uh it
it drove me nuts and so i'm curious is there anyone there is there anyone out there that knows
how to do this because the only way i'm aware of is to actually boot into windows go into the
troubleshooting menu reboot into the the uefi settings and then disable uh secure boot or turn
on um legacy boot or or whatever they call it is different in different manufacturers but
does anyone know of another way to do that i might have an idea um if it's a lonovo then
there might be like a little button on the side of the pc you press that button and it'll ask you
if you want to uh your boot options go into the bios and that's where the secure boot should be
located and just check turned it off from there yeah yeah we did that's what i that's what i did
in my laptop i i got a lenovo uh y510 p laptop that well the motherboard fried but anyway it
came with windows 8 with secure boot uefi and all the stuff so i just pressed that button went into
the bios shut all that off and linux installed just great yeah and we did the same thing on on
angela's yoga too uh yoga too we angela's yoga too as well we'll say it that way um but she had
that little button and yeah that was super slick to get into the boot menu but the thing that was
confusing to me is they're able to get into somewhat of a uefi setting or bios setting
because they're able to change the boot order so i would think that there'd be something inside of
those uefi settings to to to turn it off um it does kind of look like they were trying to
it does kind of look like the one thing they might want to check as well just in general if
they want to use it one too uh you know if they got it installed obviously secure boot is working
to the point where they could boot into it uh and it kind of just looks like the efi entry
right get set there should be like a you know linux manager the same way there's a windows
manager exactly so i can actually answer that for you yeah please okay so depending on what
model of computer it is like or sorry not model what make it is like hp lenovo uh etc there's a
different key when you're booting up and you get their splash screen that you gotta hit uh to get
into the uefi and then usually there's a setting in there to disable secure boot or in some cases
you can even go as far as to go into legacy bios mode and then that bypasses all the uefi nonsense
uh okay and and chat room is telling us that on lenovo f1 will get us in to make that change
yeah and on toshiba it's usually delete uh f10 on hp and uh i can't remember what it is for asus
all right well that's that gives him something to try anyway but uh you know i'll reiterate again i
think it's been a real pain i i've tried a couple different times to you know it's gotten to the
point where i'm almost more likely now to buy a used machine that previously had windows 7 on it
and just uh and wipe that off rather than um you know rather than go with a new machine because
it's just such a pain and that's sad really because it it's seriously going to decrease the
amount of people that are willing to give linux a shot i am nervous as heck now to recommend that
somebody try to install linux whereas before i'd be like well let's try and do a boot worst case
scenario we just uninstall it and redo your partition now i'm petrified to do even that
yeah i was just helping my brother with his new laptop and uh you know i had i walked him through
over the phone how to disable secure boot and even he's fairly technical but he even asked me
like oh is it is it okay that we have this off you know just the name scares people to even try to
follow that kind of instruction you know that's such a good point and they have these stupid
idiotic messages that pop up too that say things like you're disabling secure boot your computer
may be pro you may be susceptible to unsigned firmware and cause damage and no no it won't
because we've used computers with unsigned with with unsecured bios i hate using that word
for the last 20 years and we've never had a problem so in this case it does also seem like
the at the same time they rolled out that quick boot where it doesn't always load the keyboard
and other drivers right at the exact that plays right into it you know on its own secure boots
okay especially for enterprises and places where you do want that extra you know key security to
only boot your kernel but it doesn't work as well in this case you know i've worked in a decent
amount of enterprises i mean they're going to be somewhat limited in grand forks north dakota i've
never walked into an enterprise that was concerned about uh which kernel was booting i just it just
seems like a problem that never existed and and the the thing is like you're onto something with
that um it doesn't recognize keyboard input just to load into the bios of the ufi man you can't
even do that anymore you know because it boots so fast with that stupid uh you know fast boot
or whatever where it doesn't completely shut down just a pain um lucas z writes in and he says i
heard yesterday about friend os friend os it looks like this and he links us a youtube video
so it's an amiga workbench in the browser powered by linux pack and they're releasing the public
beta as open source this week it will be able to run on both html5 and native applications
and then he links us to their website i'm wondering if anyone in the chat or in the
mumble room has heard about this or played with it nobody nobody has played with friend os well
let's let's take a look um so it looks actually pretty neat anytime you start combining an
operating system and a uh and a browser i i get excited wes have you seen this i think you were
the one that linked it actually only just a little bit what do you think it was kind of
interesting uh honestly i wish they had a few more screenshots the video is okay but more
screenshots a little bit more it's kind of a little salesy at this point yeah yeah it really
is a lot a lot of a lot of stock uh stock photos and stuff like that well anyway um look at that
3d earth yeah exactly exactly well nonetheless i it still excites me and the and it would be
something that might be neat to get a review on a little bit later but um basically my understanding
is um that that uh that you like again you like this is email so do you get an amiga workbench
inside the browser and um have you used anything similar to this before you know i don't think i
have hmm anyone in the mumble room used anything similar to this or have an idea what we could
expect if if you know when they when they release their public beta and we play with it nobody
it's quiet in here this isn't popular um well um hmm that's no good so uh i guess what we'll do is
we'll just we'll keep our eye on it and um when they release the public beta and we get to play
with it we will uh we'll take a look at it and see what we think and maybe by that time i guess
once i guess that that is what the uh um what the catalyst of conversation is right is actually
getting to play with something if you can't really see what it is i suppose um yes they had the other
two in uh an article but it's not in english so i could not read it yeah yeah i try you know i
tried to use that's another thing too is google translate has been has been super crazy well i'll
tell you what what else is crazy is chris is on his way to uh scale now i don't know how many
people i haven't i haven't heard what the final numbers of people that bought the um the the the
shirt to support the trip from scale but at this point whether you support it or not you can come
visit chris hang out with him he's going to be at scale i believe he's arriving tomorrow night
and you can track him the entire way there jupiterbroadcasting.com slash rover dash two and
he has um oh he updated it oh that's cool um you can live track him to find out exactly where he
is and you can go beat on his door and uh and and and say hello and people did that last time
and he actually invited him right onto the air so i don't know if you remember that west we are
sitting here we're doing the show and all of a sudden we have a third person there uh that was
joining us um from it was awesome yeah it was it was really cool we got to talk to him and and they
got to be on the air and and essentially do the show and and the chat room is officially renaming
unofficially renaming chris's rv as the jb party bus i don't know if that's actually going to go
over well or not or if he's going to keep it rover 2 but i'm in favor of the jb pb that's i'm down
with it yes you have to say yes yeah yeah so we'll talk to him but you can follow him on uh
on jupiterbroadcasting.com so i think both do both the links both rover and rover to work
i think they do i'm going to jb rover slash rover and that seems to still work so i think that's
working you know i actually attend all of the major conferences and i've tried every cell phone
vendor out there practically i've had a verizon phone i've had an at&t phone and i can tell you
without a doubt the most reliable connection that you're going to get at a conference like scale
that's full of congestion is from ting now ting is a trendsetter of the of the of the mobile sphere
if you go into any cell phone shop uh today you'll see that they have all of these uh gimmicks for
no contract phones and and uh and at&t has done away with their two-year contract and and they
have all this prepaid stuff and you know who started all of that ting did uh with ting you're
only going to pay for what you use so we have contract employees that come in here for a week
at a time or two weeks for a time or a month at a time and we have them do things like wiring
buildings and pulling cat 5 and and and doing punch down block tests and if we're doing a if
we're doing an equipment swap for you know a hotel they have a bunch of new machines they don't have
to have any real technical skills they just have to be able to unbox computers put them in the place
of the old ones and then our techs will go through and actually do the imaging and configure that
kind of stuff so they have to do very basic things but we need to be able to get a hold of those guys
and the way that we do that is we outfit them with a phone from ting now because they're working on
site in a place that we manage the wi-fi they're on wi-fi 100 of the time we very nice we use
telegram for all of our texts and we use sip for all of our phone calls so west the deal is they're
not really using any of ting service we need that we needed to fall back to a phone service we needed
to hold back to internet in case they're not available or they they you know they go off site
for a little bit but for the most picking up supplies at the store they have a question to
ask you got it you know they've got service you've got it but for the most part we're only paying
six bucks a month for those phones now now that alone would be enough for you to get your drop
your current provider and come over to ting but because you're a linux unblocked audience they're
going to give you 25 off your first device your first month first month of service and all you
have to do to get that is visit and i think we can all agree here this is the coolest url on the web
linux.ting.com linux.ting.com and you can buy something for yourself for me i actually bought
a a unlocked gsm phone off of ebay and was able to use that 25 towards my first month of service
and if you're only using six to ten dollars you're going to get the first month or two for free it's
not going to cost you anything they're going to give you that so linux.ting.com and pick yourself
out something nice and thank you so much to ting for sponsoring the the linux unplugged so let's
see if this is more popular it better be i have had servers on my brain this week and for a number
of different reasons and so i i immediately gravitated towards this article um that says
the if it loads there we go um ocean the linux web server that fits in your pocket ocean may look
like a smartphone but in fact it's a fully functional linux powered web server that fits
in your pocket you want a web do you want a portable linux powered web server look no further
than ocean ocean has been designed for the ground up for profit for for portability and features
integrated battery that allows you to run web and bluetooth applications in place where direct power
is limited the device is approximately the size of an iphone 6 and can easily fit in your pocket
because it packs the power of the linux operating system the default is debian but you can install
your own ocean can be used for a variety of functions deploying web applications frameworks
such as node.js ruby on rails building a custom router a internet of things hub ibeacon eddystone
or prototyping the device can also act as a battery pack for iphones and android devices
and holds enough power to recharge an iphone 6 1.3 times it has the following specs a one gigahertz
arm processor cortex a7 one gigabyte of ddr3 480 megahertz ram 16 gigabytes of an internal micro sd
storage four gigabytes internal flash chip one usb 2.0 and 3.0 port 8211 bgn wi-fi and bluetooth
4.0 it also supports qi wireless charging and a 4200 milliamp internal battery which is good
of two days of continuous cpu usage and as the chat room is pointing out it is kind of like
a raspberry pi the the difference to me is i really like arm devices and i think that it's
it's a really competitive alternative platform to x86 but every time i talk to raspberry or people
the arm enthusiasts that are interested in um all arm devices a lot of them seem to rail against the
raspberry pi and they say basically it's kind of like a toy it's not really a serious device so
i guess the thing that makes us stand out in my mind is it seems like from the ground up it's
designed to be a production grade server just a very very limited very very low power uh
low power uh low power consumption low resources uh production it also has kind of the slick
branding in the case which i could see you know helping its marketability like you don't want to
buy something with an exposed circuit board and put it together exactly you just want to like drop
it in your studio and use it for you know recording things when you're working with your friends or
whatever exactly and you know as and from and again if taking that marketing perspective one
thing further when i go into a client i say if i tell them i want to install something called a
raspberry pi they're gonna look at me sideways right now if i tell them expect food exactly now
if i now if i tell them i want to install the ocean micro web server you know and then they go
to a website and it has flashy little spinning around graphics and it has little bullet points
that talk about specifications that they don't really understand that kind of stuff impresses
people um but the you know i was i was looking around the other day and i was thinking you know
we have so many little tiny things you know we have a we have a resource site that our employees
go to to and it has um links to the to these incredibly long urls like for example drivers
for hp you have to click like seven different links to get deep enough into their site before
you can actually type in the model number that you want it spits out the driver links once you
find that link it's not so bad so we have that hot link to a resource site and we have things
like the another example would be the hp lip driver um all of that stuff is linked it doesn't
require a lot of power i don't even necessarily need you know a you know an even you know a big
server would probably be too much and too much overhead all i really need is a little tiny thing
that serves up a tiny little html page and i was actually looking for inexpensive uh low-powered
servers and then you drop this on me and i'm like you know what this is it this is exactly what i
was looking for a couple nights ago and um i can think of a ton of uses i don't know what if you
had one of these west what would you be using it for no i'm imagining like you could take it with
you uh you know maybe you're if you're out car camping maybe you're out somewhere else and you
want to play like a game with all your friends uh and you already have kind of like stuff set up you
could use this as a as a little server that you know you host all the download files on you can
host shared files to drag and drop between them as you're working how about the mumble room what
do you guys have uh what do you guys have ideas for i know freso you can probably think of a
thousand things to uh to host on a tiny little web server hey we could start hosting uh i thought it
would be nice to use it for like a wildlife camera or something or a surveillance system
yeah yeah so if especially if we paired that with a like a like a gsm card unlocked gsm
card with a unlocked hotspot from ting you know for five bucks a month or six bucks a month you
could have a hotspot capability and put that thing online and have it be a cellular server
they both run off a battery right so that would be that would be kind of neat how about uh how
about uh freso are you still here yep yep you got any ideas of what you could do with the tiny
little pocket website i have tons of ideas actually i could probably use one today to
collect some data and but here's the thing i am very destructive with this kind of devices and
this is why i love the raspberry pi is because i can destroy one and getting a new one cost me
just five bucks right and i literally just a couple hours ago accidentally shot a raspberry
pie with a twin too i'm not even joking you say um i think it's still working it still sent the
data back to uh my tablet so um i think it's still alive um but i can do this because a replacement
cost me five bucks i'm not too worried about it that being said um if i had uh a 50 server
i would probably not be as willing to experiment with it uh which is the big downside for me um
um that being said if you play with a lot of iot uh stuff and you need a hub this is perfect yeah
yeah no it really is um i can think of it good my my first thought one i i saw that also on the
internet my first thought was i could use a nokia n9 for that he's doing the same thing besides i
have no usb port but the rest i have it okay well i don't it's a rather expensive tool when i say
when you look at the prices so you can have much cheaper thing to do the same thing i think
i don't think price is the only factor i mean there are plenty of people who you know look at
how many people buy apple max right right so the price is not the single factor uh it you know as
a geek on a limited budget yeah sure it may be uh how the price range or your budget for whatever
like uh homebrew project but if you're a professional and you want to take along a
server to a demo um you know to a to a company that won't let you plug your laptop into their
network i've had plenty of those occasions that's a great use case you know want to demo something
you can just slap the little server down on the middle of the table turn it on and say right
connect your laptops to that and uh and you can you know i'll show you my my web application demo
written in node or whatever running off that little box that's a great that's a great point
because there's so many things run on windows these days that you might not you know might
be way more work to try to get your demo running on a windows laptop that your business provides
you than it would be just to stick it on a little linux box you don't need you know load balancing
you just need an nginx server right and for me like right now i'm sat in a hotel away from home
uh it would be ideal for me to have a little server with me here as well sometimes there's
some things that i want to run uh on a server rather than having to use the rubbish hotel wi-fi
to deploy out to the cloud i could just deploy it on a little local server sat here and having
it as a little box that has a battery in it is just nicer you know it's it's not it's not as
gnarly as having a raspberry pi yeah okay i could get a raspberry pi in a nice case but i'd also
need a battery and bluetooth and a wireless dongle and you know adding all those things together
together and get it sometimes a pretty box outweighs uh yeah the hackability of putting
a bunch of good values together and if they support it well that might be enough you know
that you know that well if this thing breaks i can reasonably get it replaced or serviced or
you know rather than oh well it's on me to buy the new hard drive and figure out why the solder
joints aren't working then you know there are there are other you know out of the box solutions
that i use too you know one of examples is every place that we do work and we usually try to keep
at least one box that we can ssh into so that we can get into the network to do various things
then from there we can do you know we can you know do a skin or ping a specific ip or whatever
we like to have at least one box sitting on the inside now normally that's not a problem because
if they're paying us to come do the network infrastructure usually they have at least one
uh at least one at least one server i'll say that i that that's not true in every place especially
in the hospitality industry because a lot of that's cloud based but most of the the the enterprise
networks we have one server but this would be a great place to actually put you know like a
single device behind the firewall by the way i have been updated from the field that the name
of the of the new rig is not rover not rover 2 it is lady jupiter whoa yeah yeah lady jupiter
that's the name of that beautiful beautiful rv so uh there you go um so yeah so i have had servers
on my brain servers on my mind all week this week and all week last week and i actually just got
done setting up a couple of the in-house stuff here for ultispeed and one of the things i was
doing was i it was last week or the week before i was working with a client who wanted to set up
content hosting and basically what they were they wanted to do is they had three different uh three
different things that they wanted to run three different independent servers that they wanted
to run and so we were talking about you know we could buy a server and virtualize all three of
those little mini servers um and the the the price point was going to be three thousand dollars to
buy that server and then we started talking about it well here's you have to consider a couple of
things one is you're going to purchase that server and and you're going to you know have to front
that first three thousand dollars and then you're going to have to they were going to be on a two
year upgrade cycle so every two years they're going to spend another three thousand dollars
and throw the last one away so basically that means they're paying you know one and a half
thousand dollars a year to maintain this to maintain this architecture uh then there's no
redundancy so if they have to do upgrades if they have to do if we have to do repairs they're going
to have to take that server offline for a couple of hours unless of course we could buy a backup
server but then you're spending another three thousand dollars on the backup server so now
we're up to three thousand dollars a year and repairs and maintenance aren't going to be
covered so they're going to contract that out to us now the good news for me is we charge two
hundred dollars a month per server to do that so i would have been happy yeah i would have been
thrilled if they would have decided to to buy the server and then pay us a monthly fee to maintain
it um but in but anyway we broke all that cost down divided it by you know their monthly cost and
said this is what it's going to cost you per month to run a server and then we looked at what it costs
to run that same to do all the same things they wanted to do on digital ocean and actually one
other thing i forgot there was also pricing in there for a backup internet connection because of
the if the if the fiber line that fed the building ever went down then they would have a backup
connection that was going to be another 50 bucks a month i think and so we looked at the cost of
the digital ocean droplet 480 a year that's what it was going to cost them for everything all
included they were going to have practically no downtime they were no longer going to be
responsible for the upgrades there was going to be no ongoing maintenance because it's going to
be handled by a professional that lives and sleeps in the data center 24 hours a day seven days a
week and they eat and breathe this stuff that's gremlins right little data center yeah well they
they're minions actually you know the little yellow minions yeah so basically more sense
basically after they got done working for uh uh for the for the evil henchmen in despicable me 2
then they actually went to work for digital ocean they're the ones that actually maintain
the servers and the server infrastructure they they do it all day long and they do a fantastic
job now because of the complicated setup that we had it was going to cost us about you know roughly
40 a month or so to to do all that but if you're just running a basic web server kind of like some
of the tasks we were talking about on this uh on this ocean uh server if you're just running uh you
know a basic web server or a basic database server man we switched our entire ticketing system over
to a uh to a five dollar a month droplet on digital ocean and it i mean it freaking flies
like it is wow yeah it's it's far and away better than the system that we were using before and it
runs on a cheaper droplet and we're accomplishing all that for five bucks a month and here's the
best part wes digital ocean is going to give you 10 credit if you use the promo code d o unplugged
so you're getting dollars 10 bucks and so basically you get the first two months free and
because uh there's no requirement to keep going if you decide after the first two months you don't
want to use it anymore you just power the server down and close your account and that's the end of
it but you won't do that because it's an addiction i my name it is my name is noah and i'm an addict
i'm addicted to digital ocean droplets i spin them up constantly i spin them i was playing with have
you ever have you ever played with the um i'm probably throwing away a linux action show idea
but have you ever played with pong no i think i think it's i think the name is pong let me let
me look but basically it is a it is a load balancer uh for linux and uh i'm probably
pronouncing that wrong and everyone is probably uh everyone that knows it is probably thinking
of it i'm trying to look at i'm really taking over for chris last then yeah yeah oh yeah no no
no not not quite that but here we go here we go it is it is called i'm pulling the name up now
it is called like it doesn't have the name but but anyway there is a there is a program i'm gonna
i'll look it up and i'll throw it in the show notes and basically it is a very very simple
load balancer so you set it up on one digital ocean droplet and basically what happens is
anytime your pound that's the name of pound p-o-u-n-d pound is great yeah and so basically
you set it up you have three servers and you have your your server and your backup server and then
you have your load bounce bouncing server that has pound running and basically what happens is
anytime that server one goes down it automatically sends all of the traffic to server two but it gets
even better let's say you had a uh let's say you had one server that had a lot of really good
resources and then you had your other server from a couple of years ago that didn't have so many good
resources you can actually set set it up so that you have a a weighted key so out of every 10 users
that connect six of them will go to the good hardware and four of them will go to the poor
hardware and you can set it up like that to to distribute the load over you know obviously i'm
using the example i'm using two but you could have three or four or five and we actually set that up
on our ticketing system so that if our main ticketing computer ever goes down it automatically
fails back to a back over digital ocean droplet and god forbid anything ever happened to digital
ocean themselves it automatically fails back to an on-site backup on our premise and god forbid
anything happens to both those two at the same time it'll fail back to a to a backup of a backup
server that sits in my house nice yeah so this actually i like you said i probably just blew a
perfectly good linux action show episode talking about that right now but it is super super cool
and and here's here's my challenge if somebody goes and tries this they can put this to the test
you can set pound up in 30 seconds it's that fast i mean the configuration file is like
12 lines and and and you have it up and running and it works and it's absolutely amazing
uh so if you want something useful to use that ten dollars digital ocean credit for that's that's
what i would look at um i want to go over to this article that comes to us from rs technica and
this is about um having confidence in linux to do the things that we have sourced to basically
other devices and the article says i've noticed lately that rather than replacing a router every
time it literally stops working i've needed to act earlier swapping new gear because an old
router could no longer keep up with the increasing internet speeds available in the area um and he
says uh a lot of you are probably muttering to yourself pf sense sure that might be what you're
thinking about or smooth ball or untangled i've played with all of the firewall distros out there
but i decided to go with a more basic more old school approach a plain cli only install of a
buntu server that has a few ip tables rules and he talks about basically how he set his linux box up
to act as a firewall slash router and before i go on with what i think about this what do you think
wes i thought i thought this was a great article um it may not be applicable for everyone not
everyone wants to learn and write their own ip tables rule set but i mean there are things like
you know ufw uh and another firewall firewall d things that'll help you set your firewall rules
but it's a great example of how you you know if you want a good project you want something just
kind of deep dive on understand networking and routing a little bit better here's a really
helpful guide i love the graphs he has here just kind of outlaying what performance he got a big
one for me is a lot of people want to set up vpns on their router but a lot of those little crappy
not even smartphone quality arm chips in the routers are not going to do the kind of crypto
that you want but something x86 based probably has a nice instruction set for it exactly now
anyone in the mumba room use uh use any sort of uh linux firewall distro any distro at all
does firewalls or routers open wrt count sure let's talk about it um what is it that drew you to open
wrt well frankly i was just too scared to leave the stock firmware on their tp link but i mean
it's not the link or anything but still so it i i bought the router with the specific intention
of throwing an open source software on there also happened to be about the same time that bsd was
thrown on a tp link by alan there you go um the model down so what i what i have my my basic
problem with all of the different firewall distros out there and i've admitted numerous times that i
am incredibly happy with router os and it's a it's a it's an operating system that is sold
uh by microtech and put onto microtech devices and i am able to get an enterprise grade uh
security gateway firewall router for like 40 and they work amazing we have them in production we
have the most i've had that i've seen personally is 2000 users connected at one time and it didn't
miss a beat and the nice yeah i mean it's it's an amazing i mean to be fair that wasn't the 40
dollar one that was a couple hundred dollars but but the operating system is the same on all of
them it's just that you get a better processor and a little bit more memory and and um and it
becomes rack mountable and stuff like that and you get more interface ports too but my basic
concern with all of these things is that linux has been capable for a long long time at doing a lot of
this stuff and we for whatever reason don't have confidence in its ability to do something as simple
as ip routing and there is a company out there called cumulus networks and they basically what
they do is they believe that linux is good enough as a router so it's it's basically exactly what
these guys have done or what this guy is talking about is using linux to do your routing and and
firewall stuff the the problem that they ran into though and where their solution is that the
switching fiber inside of a lot of the a lot of the network cards that you put in to a computer
isn't fast enough when you handle very very large networks if you have a lot of traffic going through
the the integrated network card or even a pci network card isn't going to be fast enough and so
they have um you know and i this is well over my head i admit that but my understanding is that
they have um they have special switching fiber that is on the same level that you would get
if you went with something like a juniper networks or a cisco um or a microtech or or hp or what have
you um to do your routing and but they both the author of this article and cumulus network share
a belief that i have subscribed to now since it's been explained to me and that is that
linux is often more than enough to do a lot of the tasks that we want it to do we just don't trust
it because it doesn't have a pretty web ui and you know you know we just talked about in the
mumble room about how we don't trust stock firmware on a tp link which is smart by the way
um because they're kind of a lower end uh device but what and so basically what he did was he took
better open source firmware and put it on you know reasonable hardware and got a very usable experience
on it and my question is what if we could do that with everything but instead of using something
like open wrt that only runs on a specific set of devices what if we just used an actual operating
system which i think is kind of what this what the author is talking about what do you think
yeah i think it has a great you know the one one thing i like that would work with pf sense or other
things as well as there is the split between your core routing and firewall and your wireless ap
i think that's i think that's very helpful i think that makes you can probably upgrade you
know your wireless ap a couple times well you still have the same server set up to do your
routing yeah uh it also lets you host more open wrt works for this too one thing i do like about
open wrt is that it has a built-in package manager yeah yeah so i use it at home for instance and uh
i wanted to have two i my work still uses pptp as a vpn even though it's broken even though it's
terrible um but i wanted to be able to have two separate connections to work from two separate
devices uh by default a lot of routers will not be able to nap that correctly sure open dwt you
just install one package and bam it works perfectly so you get that same kind of power but
you can do that it's just an ip tables module and if you had you know it's like a bun too it's even
easier it's just like a mod probe away right so i think that's what you get is like if you want to
customize and you really want the power to tune things and understand what's happening then then
why not how about the mumba room anyone in support or against of using linux as a router or edge
device i think it makes the device um much more flexible and if you have um some spare resources
on it um that you could use otherwise you can uh plus um i think tools like pf science and
other uh routing specific disk shows they come with all this stuff that you could possibly need
for the most complex router you will ever build in your ride in your life right whereas if you
just use the room to server and all you need is um ip tables you have this super simple setup for
your super simple task which makes it a lot easier to manage that's interesting i i i guess i have
become i guess i started in the networking world in cisco where nothing is easy to manage because
everything is and you know the thing is about cisco is it's great hardware it does a great job
once you learn how to configure it but the configuration syntax is not similar to anything
else because they have their own commands and it's its own syntax and it doesn't work on anything
else and so if you start configuring routers that way i guess everything seems like a step up from
that at least from a usability standpoint but um you know one of the things that we do i should
ask you first anyone else have any other thoughts about about routers well if you take if you take
the fritz boxes for example they are running linux or the asus routers they are running linux
and for the asus routers they are open source enhancements available really tell me more about
that i've seen asus routers that like best buy i didn't know that they were running anything open
source though so i can't tell you what model i have but i switched i took a an open source
replacement of the stock firmware which is open source too and there are some enhancements with it
that's awesome you know one of the things that i found is if we let employees stay in the same
environment as us routers they they do better with them in the field so for example we had a program
what i shouldn't say had we have a program called professional development and basically if there's
equipment in the shop that's not actively being used or isn't actively assigned to a ticket to go
out and to be deployed they can take that equipment home as long as it's returned in the
same condition it went out with and play with it and it was actually the company i worked for
before had a similar program and it really really helped me because i wasn't going to be
able to uh it has put my hands on a on a ten thousand dollar uh core router or core switch
but unless the company bought it for for a client and then i was able to play with it for a little
bit and so we have let employees do that and take their equipment home and basically what we're doing
is i can teach somebody how to set up ip tables on a router and i can give them written instructions
so they can go through and do it but the the biggest thing that they lack is communication
the biggest thing that they lack is confidence in the field if they walk out into the field
and they go to a client and the client says i need you to forward uh i need you to create this
firewall rule that accepts packets from this or i need you to create this nat rule that sends
packets to this internal ip and they can think to themselves and go i've done that a thousand
times at home when i was forwarding my web server playing with my ssh and even though that stuff is
meaningless in the grand scheme of of what we make money off of it's valuable because they're
developing skills and so i found that to be a really cost-effective way to boost their confidence
when they're in the field so they not only do they know what they're doing but they feel like
they know what they're doing and they know that they know what they're doing and that's really
helpful and i was talking to an employee yesterday and he was talking about how he had some lack of
confidence when it came to administrating servers and so what we ended up doing with him is we signed
him up on a website called linux academy slash unplugged and we were able to get the course
because we used linux academy.com slash unplugged we got the course for a third of the cost and what
we ended up it ended up costing us like 15 bucks and we sent him through doing the uh the red hat
seven so he could learn how to do a lot of the red hat administration and he came back to me
a couple days ago and said you know i uh i well he he came to me yesterday is when when he finished
and and said to me you know that you know we signed up for that course and i sat up last night
i was kind of goofing around with it and playing with it it was awesome and i i now you know i kind
of had an idea of of how to do this that or the other but now i have been told by an instructor
an instructor by somebody of authority that this is the appropriate and acceptable way to do this
and so you don't you're not embarrassed about is this the right way to do this or is this just
kind of the way i've always done it and so you know i can get the job done but is it technically
correct you know that what you're doing is correct and and and um and so for him he actually signed
up for his own subscription he told me today that he has his own subscription to linux academy
and he's going to continue on uh to learn other things because he sees it like like a subscription
to netflix it's like entertainment and i'll tell you something about knowledge knowledge is the one
thing that people can't take away from you it doesn't matter what doesn't matter what life
throws at you you can get arrested you can be uh you know everything short of being killed
you can lose a lot of stuff in life but nobody can ever ever ever take away things that you've
learned they can't take away your education they can't take away your knowledge so for 20 bucks a
month um and actually even less have used linuxacademy.com slash unplugged you can get a
course and you can learn things that nobody will ever be able to take away from you
and to me that just seems like an incredibly valuable way and it's a huge return on investment
and not only that i've learned one of my favorite things to do is i memorize useless trivia facts
like i memorize things that you do now i do and it's really dumb it's so stupid but it's fun
because it's fun to do in a crowd when you sit down in front of a bunch of people and you you
quote some esoteric uh uh fact and and and and then you act as if like everyone should know it
or you say it in a way that everyone should know it and then everyone looks at like man that guy's
really smart he's that guy's how did he know that how did he know that yeah yeah if you're ever
around me in person then and you see me do that you like don't say anything don't you dare ruin
it wes but you can know never okay but you can know for yourself like that is that that's noah
doing his thing that's him uh doing that trivia thing where he does that thing where he pretends
that everyone should know but really he knows that nobody else knows and he knows it i think
it's fun game great way to get that trivia is linux academy.com slash unplugged if you want to
support jupiter broadcasting we could really really use your support you know chris i don't
i i don't even know i can't even put into words that from the time the man wakes up in the morning
till the time he goes to bed even if he's doing other things in the back of his mind he is thinking
about shows about content about what his audience wants and how did and how did yeah you see you've
been around him so you understand and what and and how to best deliver that and the problem that
he keeps coming up against is to do more things to do things better requires capital and the problem
is we find all of these little excuses of why we don't want to of of why we can't or why we shouldn't
support this that or the other and and that's what i hear from people um you know for the for
from the people they're saying well i'm not contributing because xyz and i just i want to
ask people to look at it like you'd look at any other source of entertainment you don't maybe
don't agree with everything that's ever said on netflix or maybe you don't agree with everything
that's ever said on uh hulu but you still contribute to those services because they're providing
valuable content to you and again we're going back to that whole knowledge is power thing
if man if if i if i charged the if i if i build out the amount of time the amount of information
that i give that we give on on linux action show in this week on linux unplugged and if chris did
the same thing and and build that out as a consultation service rather than just putting
it on the internet for free now we'd be rolling rolling in cash so you should consider that yeah
i should maybe i've maybe we've attacked this whole thing the wrong way maybe that's what we
should do we should just start doing online yeah online consultation you pay you call in we take
your credit card number and then we'll walk you through all this stuff and i'll start doing how
tos and he and chris can chris can fix your arch box because i want nothing to do with that and
yeah we'd make tons of money but no and we give all that to you to you for free and and right now
we could use your help at at at patreon.com today and every person that signs up even if it's just
a couple bucks if the more people that sign up every dollar you put towards patreon.com slash
slash today is a dollar that says i listen to jupiter broadcasting i find the content that you
guys make valuable and i appreciate what you're doing doesn't have to be a lot of money um you
know you can you can divide that up with you know a lot of people if they if if a bunch of people
just contributed a dollar it would it would add up to a ton so that's my plea if there's anyone
out there that that especially now that we're getting into like tax return time if we can i
don't know if it's possible to do a one-time donation on on patreon.com today but you can
do that on the jupiter broadcasting site but we would really really appreciate your support because
honestly when things like scale come up it's the first the first wave is excitement of this is
going to be amazing we're going to do this and it's going to be exciting and then it's immediately
followed with a wave of panic of how in the world are we going to pull this off um and that would
help alleviate that so i want to talk about um gnome defining a clear set of core apps for the
desktop and you see this article wes yes i did so of course you did because you posted it
but um and so basically um they are talking about how cheese is now a core app and g-ed
is going to be coming soon as a core app and i think to some degree this goes back to what we
were talking about about um having a cohesive desktop experience right and i'm interested in
in in what the future holds with that because i think if we can start even if we maintain our
freedom so you know anyone can write an app anyone can install any app they want but if we can get
to a point where there are some apps that are just these are the these are the apps that are
going to be installed these are the apps that are going to work these are the apps that we're going
to understand that are going to be there and everyone else can understand that are going to
be there when people write themes when people design changes so for example take my quake
example that i used at the beginning of the show if if quake became a core app for gnome
um what we could do is say that the people that make the dock on the side would be aware of the
fact that this terminal is going to drop down and how do we make that look nice with the terminal
drop down how do we make that a cohesive experience and of course we're not talking
about stopping anyone else from adding apps in we're just talking about having a defined set
that these apps are going to be there these apps are going to be available and one of the
main reasons i use the vi text editor is because i can i can know without a shadow of a doubt it's
going to be available on every machine i ever use everywhere it is it's everywhere and it becomes
omnipresent like that then you end up using it what are your thoughts wes yeah i agree i mean i
think i think gnome is rapidly becoming one of those desktops you know unity as well but where
we can just put people in front of them they look polished they look like a 21st century desktop
and one thing that people come to expect from the other operating systems is a kind of consistency
internal consistency and uh you know between when you sit down at one computer you sit down the next
computer you know you'll be able to do a certain amount of things they look this way it's the same
kind of interaction so hopefully this goes at least some extent to making gnome that kind of
environment where you're like oh yeah well cheese is here yet it will be there are things where
you're just like okay it works it's all gnome and if you for the power users of course you can still
install whatever replacement app you want it's still linux but hopefully these will be nice and
polished i think like elementary is doing a similar thing with their apps right so it's
good to see no i'm doing it for sure mumble room what do you guys think you guys are killing us
today you guys i i didn't even know that g edit was not a core app i mean it's a i always had it
yeah yeah the article is to be believed that gg edit will be soon and it's funny because
here's how you know g edit is doing it right because it is so entrenched in my mind as a
native app to to to gnome there's it is so much a core app in my head anyway that when i was doing
the linux action show a couple weeks ago i i inadvertently said was talking about how i didn't
like uh i didn't like the the text editor in kde because you had to bring part of the the kde
desktop in and i almost said well and g edit it just worked and then it dawned on me the g and g
edit is obviously you know and then then my brain caught up with my mouth and and it's like but it
is it is so well integrated and it does so well and the the thing is about something like g edit
is that it's such a simple program like what really is there to be done to make it a core app
i mean do we all just have to agree that it's a core app and it it it's just not that complicated
of an app you know anyone else i am glad i am glad to see that the the color app uh color manager
will be there because yeah i think that like what we were talking about you know professional
graphics earlier i think professional color management is something you need if you want to
have linux as a production platform sure and no the uh the point you were making earlier in the
show uh about the polish that unity shows on an ubuntu desktop or that cinnamon might show on
a mint desktop you know i i think extending your core apps is a key part of how these
desktop desktop environments are going to show more polish yeah having a complete settings suite
uh for whether it's gnome or unity or kde and having good default apps and good baked in apps
is critical to that yeah yeah it's going to become more cohesive right yeah exactly yeah
i think so anyone else before i wrap i think the gnome apps they are awesome i very much agree
but i don't know how about the speed of development i think they're really slow in development
all right anyone else yeah actually i think this is where kde of all desktop shines because they
pretty much have a core app for anything that you want to do that is true you know you're right
about that if i'm not i i haven't personally switched to kde i've never used it for any
extensive amount of time but you are onto something uh when you say that they have a
core app for almost everything it does feel like they natively have thought of almost everything
doesn't it it's a complete whole you know experience it is it is that's true you're
right about that um and i i don't know what it is i think i think basically it comes down to a long
long long long time ago um when i was first getting into linux one of the guys that was
teaching me about linux was like kde is the desktop that you use if you're not a real power
user and gnome is that i know i know it's it's a it's a huge trolly thing it's hugely biased but
at the time i was like 12 or 13 years old and i'm like well i want to be the smart one so i'll use
gnome and i just i never really used anything after that peer pressure look what happened yeah
i think it made a mark on me well because i'd been using kde prior to that as it kind of played
with it because it looked more like windows and it made me more comfortable and um yeah and then
my desktop got you know got crapped on and i was like oh well it's not a respected desktop and i
want to be a good hacker so then i switched to no stuck with me ever since all right anyone else
i just want to say you sounded like a very impressionable teenager uh well i guess there
was that but not either here or there that'll put this episode of the linux linux unplugged in the
books before we get out of here let's thank a couple of our producers producer rotten corpse
of course blaster for running the mumble room for us we really appreciate having west thanks west for
joining us thank you for being here too no it's a pleasure to talk with you it's always fun we'll
see you right back here next week guys and hopefully hair will be back
so
all right bang suggest bang suggest um so and while we're doing that i want to go as the out
uh as the um the post show i want to look at this uh phoenix os um how deeply have you looked at
this west only briefly yeah so basically this goes back to talking about exactly what i don't like
android on the yeah yeah exactly uh but kind of proves me wrong actually as i'm looking at
this screenshot you know what this looks like to me west it looks like an android operating system
that is properly scaled to meet the requirements of a desktop platform it doesn't look that bad
actually although they do call it a rom still even for x86 which is a little weird but uh it
doesn't look bad yeah uh no it's it it doesn't look bad and it you know what it really reminds
me of is it reminds me of like a little bit of a souped up better looking version of windows
you know you've got the two drives and they have space and then you have the you know the navigation
on the side which i guess is to some degree what some of the linux file managers look like but yeah
it's kind of like windows no mixed i don't know i gotta tell you west this of all the things i
want to install on my computer this is darn near the bottom like i agree yeah i just nothing about
this is really i don't know a mumble room if you guys are thinking that any of these are and west
said it uh what concerns me about this about os is like this is they're managed and developed
like android roms unless like a true linux is true i mean do you want to download just one big
system image of random bits from the internet even if some of it's based on it yeah this is
a zip file uh and then you run a program that will create a usb for you i know yeah i don't
mind that i i would be willing to trust the developer uh on that i think they would be
shooting themselves in the foot if they would include anything malicious in there so what i
see as a bigger issue is that those uh attempts to make android work on a desktop uh kind of
come and go and if i do install something i want uh something that i can that i will know will
stick around right uh because i don't feel like reinstalling something uh six months from now
uh because what i initially installed doesn't have support anymore i'm assuming it would just
update apps separately um when it's not a system update as well yeah yeah it looks like that looks
like well it looks like it updates to the google play store doesn't it well my thing is is what uh
frechel said about trusting the developers i mean you know we trusted lenovo not to put spyware on
computers by default that happened yeah yeah it did it's interesting to try to build up from android
to a complete desktop rather than take a desktop and try to make it mobile you know i i think that
that has a better chance of working to be honest with you i think you're i think it might be true
but it's not it's not neither is a good solution but i think that scaling up is is has is more
has is more viable than scaling down probably at least for the majority of uh simple users not in
a disrespectful way just people who don't you know like you need the web you need your main apps and
that's it yeah i i don't know i nothing nothing about this is is uh is uh there's been a ton of
attempts to strip the linux down to like something small and lightweight there was one peppermint i
think was one right yeah it was mostly browser based um and didn't really have you know concept
of an app store is like like android has it because you still need native apps like no matter
how hard firefox the mozilla guys tried to push firefox as html5 and that's all you ever need
right now that's not the case you know i want to play some high-end 3d game then you need something
lower level than html5 you know it's just not ready for that yet right but but i i can see
some value in in people pushing the boundaries with android on the desktop um i i don't know i
i'm i'm referred to i don't i think it needs to be someone bigger and someone more committed to
do that though because there will always be these little projects that pop up all over the place and
then they disappear a few months later or a year later and you've got to wipe it reinstall something
else i don't know i mean i'm not i'm not sure i'm following you are like so linux couldn't get
much more stripped down i mean you have things like dsl that are like what 50 megs i mean how
much smaller do we really think we want an operating system to get well i personally
don't care for that you know i'm not i'm not what i'm saying is that people have tried to make
like you know very very small lightweight um distros that the users then want to add loads
of stuff the box about right yeah right right right but it's but can we agree that it makes
more sense to start with almost nothing and add all the junk that you want back on that is that
is a that is a more viable option than starting than starting with something like you know windows
xp and saying i'm gonna find a way to fit this on a phone there's just too there's just too much
there to fit into a phone to get down to to shave off well that's exactly what we're doing you know
we're starting with nothing and adding things like mere and unity 8 specific application so
yeah i agree with you that it's better to start from nothing and and build up uh totally good
also no on that friend os um earlier i think cm2 set in um the irc chat that's enclosed beta right
now so that's why no one was talking about it yeah yeah i here's here i've learned i've learned
uh i've learned a couple of things today i've learned that one uh seven hours is still not
enough time to uh to properly prep a show i've learned i've learned that everyone will telegram
you at the worst possible time right when you're trying to do something and so essentially you'll
get nothing done for the about the hour leading up to the show because you'll be putting out
random fires you sound more and more like chris every day being chris lasovitch is that it yeah
no it's just it's it's funny it's like and the thing is if i wasn't there if i didn't see it
myself i would never ever believe how many like his phone will be silent almost perfectly for
like an hour and then right before he goes on here or he'll sit down to do something and the second
his his butt hits the seat boom somebody starts telegraphing boom the irc goes off boom his phone
starts ringing boom the alarm the smoke alarm goes up boom the oven blows up boom his truck
blows up like everything happens at the worst possible time and if i hadn't seen it myself and
it's and it's it is like clockwork i could set my watch i would i'll know when a show is going to
start because everything in the studio will start going wrong but it'll only go wrong right when he
sits down after he's done with the show then everything returns to silent normal and it's
funny yeah and it's funny because like for the most part i managed to skirt that except it must