There hasn't been a version since March 11th, 2017,
but today, well, a couple days ago,
WindowMaker 0.95.9 was released.
And you remember Next, that Next desktop?
Yeah, I mean, from ages ago, before Apple got good?
Yeah.
Gigi, you were just shopping Next boxes, weren't you?
Yeah, so I was, after reading the new update
for WindowMaker, which, when are they gonna hit 1.0?
That's gonna be an amazing release.
But I was looking at old Next machines
and $800 on eBay for a full Next station right now.
Did you catch the age or the vintage of that machine?
1991 was the release date of that machine.
25 megahertz, Motorola 80, I forgot the exact CPU,
but yeah, 25 megahertz.
25 megahertz.
Originally sold for $5,000.
That's a steal of a deal, man.
I think you gotta get it.
I wonder if you could run Linux on that thing.
Oh, hello, friends, and welcome into your weekly Linux talk
show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hey there, Wes.
Hello.
We have a really fun episode today.
We're hanging out with some killers, some memory killers.
So you've probably heard the term out of memory manager,
and you've probably also heard that Linux isn't always
that great in a low memory situation.
And you might wonder why, because one
of the very first things I learned about Linux
is that kernel will start to kill processes to survive,
and I thought that was so cool.
But it seems like it's used so sparingly.
And if you're on the desktop and you run out of memory,
you get in a 10% memory zone, you'll
notice that your desktop just starts to thrash
and sometimes never really fully recovers until you reboot.
Yeah, I've certainly been there, right?
You see the mouse move every once in a while,
but ultimately you just have to hold the power button down.
And you're thinking, I'm sitting here
on a supercomputer-grade operating system,
and this is happening.
What the heck?
Well, one of the first projects to try to solve this
will be Fedora, on the desktop at least.
There's lots of solutions, but Fedora
is one of the first distros to ship something
enabled by default. It's called Early Out of Memory Manager,
and we'll talk about it in a little bit.
And we've set up two boxes, a Fedora 31 box and a Fedora 32
preview box.
We're going to slam them into low memory conditions,
absolutely punish them, and we'll
show you how Fedora 32 handles that situation a lot
better than 31 does.
It's kind of exciting.
You like this?
This is a real-world improvement,
and the nice part is it's all enabled by default in 32,
so you don't have to do anything.
Nope.
And so I loaded up a 31 machine over here.
Wes has a 32 machine over there.
We've come up with the same way to stress them at the same time,
and then it'll just be a versus, and we'll
see how 32 and 31 compare.
I know which one I'd rather have.
That'll be in a little bit.
We'll also have some community news and some housekeeping,
but before we get to any of that,
I'm going to say hello to Alex and Cheezy.
How are you guys doing?
Hello, internet friends.
How are you?
Hello, hello.
I forgot my water, Wes.
Wes, I forgot.
Wes, will you do me a favor and grab my water?
Thank you.
And while you do that, I will say
time-appropriate greetings, Virtual Lug.
Hello, Mumble Room.
Hey, hey.
Hello.
Bienvenido.
I hope you stay.
Got it in there.
We got 21 people on air today, and 35 people total.
We'll sum up in the Quiet Listening.
Thank you, Wes.
I got to drink the water during the show,
or else my mouth sounds really annoying,
and then people have to listen to me smacking my lips.
And Joe will complain.
There's that, too.
All right, well, before we get to abusing our Fedora installs,
let's cover some community news.
Besides WindowMaker, there are other things happening.
Microsoft has announced essentially its own version
of SE Linux.
You're probably familiar with the LSM, the Linux Security
Module.
You have things like AppArmor, SE Linux.
And there's others, actually, I wasn't really aware of.
But like everything in Linux.
Once you make it a module, people
are going to write modules.
And there's multiple versions of something.
So Microsoft's is named the Integrity Policy Enforcement,
or IPE for short, as they like to say.
And it is indeed a full-fledged LSM,
which is an optional add-on for Linux kernels.
It's not necessarily mandatory.
It's if you want these security features.
According to the docs just released on Monday,
IPE is Microsoft's attempt to solve the code integrity
problem for Linux.
Mostly because they deploy a whole bunch of Linux on Azure,
they want to make sure it's secure.
Go figure.
So on Linux systems where IPE is enabled,
system administrators can create a list of binaries
that are allowed to execute.
And then they can add verification attributes
to the kernel that can check each binary before allowing
it to run.
Little things it needs to make sure of per binary.
And if the binary has been altered by an attacker,
well, then IPE can just block the execution
of that malicious code altogether.
If that sounds like a lot of hoops to jump through,
well, Microsoft says IPE is not intended
for general purpose computing.
The IPE LSM, say that twice, was designed
for a very specific use case where security is paramount.
And administrators need to be in full control
of what runs on their systems.
And that's where you want to start
monitoring every single executable that runs.
Examples of this include things like embedded systems, maybe
like your network firewall running in Azure,
or Linux servers running strict and immutable configurations
where you need to verify and make sure really
that nothing changes once you've deployed it.
I have pretty good faith that Microsoft could pull something
like this off overall.
And like SE Linux, they have a permissive mode
and an enforce mode.
So you could put it in permissive, log what breaks,
and then try to fix that before you turn it on.
I'm curious to what just your off the top reaction
is to Microsoft creating essentially an SE Linux
alternative.
Yeah, it's interesting to see them working at scale
like this.
I mean, they have a lot of experience with enterprises
and also working with governments
where you have a lot of strict controls
that you have to meet.
Clearly, none of the other systems
allowed them to really target exactly the certain use cases
and scenarios that they had.
So it's kind of great to see them contributing this backup
in a way that surely other systems are
going to be able to use.
Right.
I'm going to go with that.
But I really don't know what to make of it.
I hate the not invented here stuff.
But at the same time, I have faith
that Microsoft is probably pretty
familiar with their deployment scenarios
and deems this necessary.
And they're not going to just go off and create something
that's not necessary.
And I mean, we already had multiple versions
right of Map Armor and SE Linux.
So you weren't really going to get your one true tool anyway.
I took a kind of a quick look at what
IPE is designed around.
It seems to be very much oriented around.
Your system essentially has to be immutable.
It has to be paired with something like DM Verity.
It has a lot of specific things that
are very useful for embedded devices and things like that.
But I also think that this is likely
going to be structured as what's known as a minor LSM that
can be stacked on top of a so-called major LSM,
like SE Linux, for example, is a major LSM.
So in the LSM framework, there are
limited stacking capabilities.
I know that Canonical has been pushing very hard for making
what are so-called major LSMs to stack,
like App Armor and SE Linux stacking on each other,
aside of the complexity disaster that I personally
think that will cause.
And I also don't think anyone is going to reasonably be OK
with such a configuration ever existing in production
because it would make it a total nightmare to debug and analyze.
Minor LSM stacking on top of major LSMs
is actually quite common, like Yama on top of SE Linux
or SMAC or App Armor and things like that.
So I think we will see that things that
need to exist within the LSM framework that support
very specific use cases, if they aren't considered quote unquote
major and are considered complementary to the major LSMs,
which at this point are SE Linux, App Armor, and SMAC,
we'll probably see this be used actually
in more than just the embedded space.
It seems like a pretty streamlined, minimal approach
right now as well.
So you could see adoption there.
I want to just bring up another story that is probably somewhat
applicable to our audience.
This isn't getting a lot of coverage.
It's getting covered in a couple of places.
I'm hoping WRT has a pretty important security advisory.
Essentially, the short version is
there was a flaw that caused the package manager to ignore
the SHA256 checksums embedded in the signed repository index.
In other words, effectively bypassing
integrity checking of the downloaded.ipk artifacts.
Not good.
Obviously, very easy for an attacker
to exploit that if they could just put up a bogus package.
So worth an update.
Now I wanted to bring it up here because I'm
curious if the Mumba Room or Cheese or Alex or yourself,
Wes, if you guys are still using OpenWRT,
if you're using something else, is OpenWRT still the project
to go with for these kind of jobs?
Somebody want to educate me because just kind of re-looking
at my setup at home.
And I would love to have a Linux operating system
that I could put on a piece of hardware.
So I'd love to not have to run a full-fledged machine
if I can avoid it.
And I'd just like to have a dynamic DNS server.
I'd like to have a little firewall capability.
I'd love to have a WireGuard VPN UI.
Is OpenWRT the way to go?
The juggernaut in this space is PFSense.
And I think most people will kind of make that trade-off
that, OK, it's not Linux.
It's BSD instead, based on.
But it's been the go-to for people
looking to solve that and scratch that itch
that you've just mentioned.
You want something that's open source,
is free, is really flexible, has all the power
of the enterprise, can do multiple WANs.
It can do dynamic DNS.
Now, PFSense can't yet do WireGuard,
which actually about two months ago
led me to switch to something called OpenSense.
There was a whole bunch of licensing drama,
which Wes and Jim covered in great detail on TechSnap
around PFSense, which led OpenSense
to come into existence.
And I've actually found it to be quite a nice little upgrade.
I think we'll talk more about that on self-hosted, too,
because I will try that one.
There are various similar sort of solutions based on Linux,
like IPFire is one that comes to mind.
But I just roll myself on Linux.
I know you know how to run DNS mask,
so you can get a lot of that stuff
if you're willing to set up the config files yourself.
So legitimately have been considering that.
It's less work than you think.
I know a lot of people that just have
a bunch of random IP tables rules on their Linux box,
and then they say, yeah, that's good enough to be my firewall.
Personally, I don't object to having a firewall with a UI
so I can see what is easily available
and what isn't available.
But Brent and I actually recorded an extras not long ago
talking about his setup and how you separate Wi-Fi
from the firewall, all that kind of stuff.
And he's still running, I think, Tomato
as a version of DDWRT on some 10-year-old embedded thing.
So something that Alex and I want
to focus on for a couple of episodes in Self-Hosted,
starting with next week's episode,
is some of the basics of fundamental good networking,
fundamentally getting good, strong Wi-Fi
throughout your entire place, that kind of stuff.
So check out Self-Hosted for that.
Now, Colonel, you're a daily driver, if you'll allow it,
of OpenWRT?
Yeah, so I run the OpenWRT for friends and family,
because trying to slot in an actual real router
or something like a PF Sense scares the dickens out of them.
They want that little consumer-grade all-in-one unit.
And so for them, I put that on there
because it's more secure and easier
to manage than half a dozen different types of web
UIs and all this other.
And they just like it better.
One of the things that I think you have to consider
is that a lot of these smaller devices and less power-hungry
devices are going to be running an embedded OpenWRT, DDWRT
tomato or various different projects out there.
In fact, the GL Inet Slate that you have runs OpenWRT
and, as you know, has WireGuard built in.
The GL Inet, I think it's the MT300 that I have,
it's the baby brother to yours, also runs OpenWRT.
And a lot of the Netgear Nighthawk routers
support OpenWRT straight down the box.
Oh, really?
I didn't know that.
I think it's one of those things that depends on the level
of security.
I mean, the way that I've always felt about it
is that if you really want all the configurations, everything
at your fingertips, then go with PFSense.
If you want something that's a little more consumer-grade
nicer generally than your manufacturer's UI,
then go with something like OpenWRT.
And you get a slew of packages.
There's a ton of stuff available there.
I mean, if you wanted to set up an IRC server on your router,
you could.
Well, like you said, I have it on the Slate.
And I really just think it's the perfect spot for OpenWRT
because they have provided a bit of a skin average user
GUI that just shows you if you're on a Wi-Fi connection,
if you're on a Wi-Fi, if you're repeating LAN.
Because it's kind of designed as a travel router
that you'd take with you to a hotel or something.
And so it has a really nice GUI that just gives you
that status and where you can program
what the button on the side of the case does.
And you can give it all these kinds of functions
like initiate and close a WireGuard VPN
by just clicking a button on the side of the case.
You can assign it to a function, which is neat.
Then they have the advanced UI, where you can actually
manage interfaces and see data about what's being transferred.
And then on top of that, you can also terminal into it.
They have a web UI, or you can just turn on SSH.
And then, yeah, you're essentially on a Linux system.
It does feel limited.
It does feel like I would like something
a little more advanced.
But at the same time, I was concerned
I would not be able to use the Slate
as a full-time, quote unquote, router.
But it has been totally fine.
And OpenWRT works great on there.
But it's a very unmanaged version of it.
It's not something I'm maintaining, really,
other than just doing OEM updates.
So is that something that you use primarily
for LadyJuice connections when you're on the road, or like?
All the time.
It's always it picks and chooses between the best.
Sometimes I have to coax it.
It could be a little better at that.
But at my home base, I have an ethernet connection.
And then when I'm on the road, I'm
either on Wi-Fi or some Wi-Fi somewhere.
And I can pick and choose between them.
But what's nice is the LAN IPs, everything behind the net
always stays the same.
Nice and simple.
It's just the external connection that changes.
And the devices on the LAN are none the smarter.
What I like that you can toggle features super easily.
So if you wanted to, say, do DNS over TLS or something
like that, it's literally just flick a switch in the UI,
and you're off and running that.
So it's great.
It does make that really easy.
And it was really easy to just sort of get in there
and turn off the DNS stuff when I wanted to go with PyHole.
All that's very simple.
One thing I want you to investigate,
this is self-hosted show research,
but one thing I want to investigate
is site-to-site WireGuard VPNs from the slate
to an OpenSense instance.
Now, I used OpenVPN from PFSense to PFSense
for a couple of years, and that worked really, really well.
I haven't yet managed to have two OpenSense systems
to do a site-to-site.
So I'd be curious to get your take on that, Chris.
Wonder how it would do that behind the double-grade net,
the double-enterprise-grade carrier-grade net.
Maybe if I had a droplet in between that
did like the go-between, so I WireGuard out from the RV
behind the double-carrier-grade net
into the digital ocean droplet,
and then the digital ocean droplet connects
into the other land that I'm bridging to.
I don't know, there's probably a way I could do it.
Some sort of network tomfoolery.
We'll figure it out.
We did deep dive at one time,
and that double net really is a complicator
for that kind of stuff.
It's just tricky.
Sometimes it works when you're lucky.
It's gosh-darn tricky.
Even software that's designed to get around double nets
still sometimes with that double-carrier-grade net
still has issues.
That's how you gotta say it, too.
All right, it's time for a little housekeeping here
on the old Unplugged podcast.
Keep things fresh, keep you informed on what's going on.
You know, you gotta clean yourself from time to time
for you guys, you know.
First and foremost, check out the recent Brunch with Brent.
Daniel Foray, the founder of Elementary OS,
sits down with Brent for brunch,
and it was a really great Linux origin story.
It's fantastic, so definitely go check that out.
You can find that at extras.show.
Slash 68, is it, Wes?
I'm gonna say 68.
Going once, yes, got it right.
Ha ha ha, pretty great.
You know, rumor has it, there's a lot of great brunches now.
You could probably just go there
and click on that brunch tag and see them all.
That sounds like a nice way, yeah.
You know you wanna escape the world outside?
Have some brunch, just continuous brunch
for several days in a row.
I liked it so much I slapped my leg.
I went, yeah, slapping my leg, Wes.
Yee-haw, woo, woo.
Now you know we do this here show live.
We've got a great mumble room,
and we're all hanging out here
having ourselves a virtual lug, and you can be part of it.
If you're like me, you're not actually making it to a lug.
You know it'd probably be good for you,
but you're not going, you know.
Sometimes they're not near.
Sometimes you got a couple options
and you're still not going.
Like Wes and I, we have options and we still don't go.
We should go.
About twice a year, I might go to one.
But usually it's not one that's in my neighborhood.
So it's, anyways, I'm getting off.
I had too many Red Bulls.
Lugs can be hard.
It is, that's what I'm trying to say.
When you have to meet in meet space
because you gotta like take the time and get there.
And here we are, look at this.
We're hanging out with 37 other Linux users right now.
37 other Linux users.
And the thing is is we're all chatting
in between the shows.
You know like maybe we had to take a break
a couple of minutes ago
because we got disconnected from a couple of people.
So we're just chatting.
I mean, you could be part of that.
It really is, it's great.
It's good for the Linux soul.
We do this show live, jblive.tv on Tuesdays, 2 p.m.
Nope, it's been a little while.
Noon, Pacific.
But you can get that converted
at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
You can also find that Mumble Room info
if you just go Google search Jupiter Colony Mumble.
Or if you get in the IRC room, you can do Bang Mumble.
That makes it easy.
I just mentioned that because we'd love to see you.
Also, the conversation continues after the show
at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash telegram.
How we doing on numbers there, cheese?
Do we get, we're over 1,700 now?
Yeah, we're like 1,736 I think was the last.
No, it's slowed, it's slowed.
It slowed a little bit, but 1,700 people.
I've never asked the number.
I've never cared.
But then I got this stupid idea of getting it to 2,000.
And now I care.
It's stuck in your head.
It's dumb.
We will get there.
You're not gonna hear me stop complaining about it
till it gets to 2,000.
So let's just get it over with.
Please, for my sake.
Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash telegram.
Get over there and get involved.
You know, you get links to stuff, you know?
You can talk to Wes Payne in there probably,
you know, if he's around.
Sure can.
Just make sure you add him at really weird times.
You're welcome, Wes.
All right, that's all the house.
I'm gonna get out of there
before I wreck somebody else's day.
Don't, don't add Wes at weird times.
So I'm feeling a little silly
because I just love this idea,
thanks to Carl who suggested it in the post show last week.
And that was just punishing the heck out of Fedora 32
and seeing how it handles it differently
than a Linux system in the past.
Now, as you know, there is this out of memory manager
that we've talked about, the OOM.
And there's different, well, you may not know this part
because I didn't know all of this until recently.
There's many out of memory managers
out there on the market.
One created by Facebook, others created by other folks,
ones that may be better for the desktop long-term.
But easy, I'm sorry, early OOM
is a very easy one to implement.
So that's an easy way to remember that
because early OOM is kind of a simple,
straightforward out of memory manager
that lives in user space versus kernel space.
And that's a pretty significant differentiator
because the kernel memory space killer,
I don't know if I'm properly giving it
full characterization, but it sort of has a bad reputation
and it doesn't really get invoked
until your system is already wrecked.
Yeah, I mean, we've talked before on the show
about Facebook's efforts.
They actually have their own daemon to do this
in user space and added some pressure stall metrics
to the kernel to help that work.
Early OOM does not take advantage of that,
but it has a similar goal.
It's basically, as Facebook acknowledged
when they released their version,
the in-kernel solution, it works sometimes,
but we've all seen those situations.
They've seen the situations where you have a live lock
and your system, it is technically still doing work.
It's swapping stuff back and forth from disk,
but you're not gonna get anywhere.
Yeah, we'll do a live demonstration in a moment.
But the way early OOM or OOM works
is if both your RAM and swap go below 10% free,
then early OOM issues a SIG term to the process
with the largest OOM score.
So this must be something that the kernel is watching
or that this is always watching the background
and it's assigning certain weights to processes.
Yeah, and you can also influence that
both in the kernel version
and then early OOM has its own config file.
So if you wanna change that from 10% to maybe 5%
or something like that,
you can tune it separately for both RAM and swap.
Yeah, now this is turned on by default now in Fedora 32,
only for the workstation version.
The other spins, you could turn it on.
It's in the repo and it's just a,
essentially a command to turn it on.
And there are other options out there.
So when Fedora 32 does release,
you'll probably hear conversations about,
well, why didn't they go with no hang?
That's early OOM on steroids
and it's got all these cool features or OOM or OOM,
or why didn't they use the Facebook backed one?
That's got the Facebook pockets.
It's gonna be the most well-developed and financed one.
So there'll be some debate
about why they went with early OOM.
But I think the simplest way to understand it
is it's just very simple, it's stable, it's tiny,
it's written in C,
which is a good choice for like embedded systems
that might have low memory.
And it has a small set of dependencies
and can work with much older kernels
than a lot of these other killers.
Yeah, I mean, so Facebook's the OMD,
theirs looks very flexible.
You can write plugins that execute your own custom code
with hooks into the daemon
to really configure how you want precise control
over this application.
That sounds like it would work really well
for an application that you're designing
and custom hosting yourself,
but for a wide array of desktop uses.
I mean, when I've been playing with it,
the config file is just a few lines
and it's basically just specifying the command line options.
The system dunit file is very nicely documented
and also sort of explains what's going on.
So it'll take anyone who needs to mess with it
all of a few minutes
to understand exactly what's happening.
I think if I was looking towards the future
and I'm thinking about like the ultimate Linux workstation OS,
it's something that has built-in snapshots
and it's something that has one of these
early memory killers.
But I wonder if maybe my perfect scenario
wouldn't be No Hang.
Not only is it nice and configurable,
but it seems like its real goal
is to sort of preemptively keep your system responsive.
So it sort of kicks in even sooner and a little smarter
of following a certain rule set.
I think maybe that's the one that's a little more tuned
for the desktop as well.
Whereas early OOM is O-O-M,
I just try to cover my bases,
is also perfectly I'd say usable on the server as well.
It's a little brutal, it's a little hard handed,
but it's usable on the server as well.
So let's try it.
You wanna try it?
Ooh.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah, well, I figured it'd be fun
to actually experiment with it
and see what the differences are.
So what Wes and I did here
to try to keep a low memory situation,
there's a few ways you can play with this,
is we have set up identical VMs.
He's running Fedora 32,
the latest preview or beta, whatever.
Is it actually beta yet?
It is beta.
Oh, is it?
Good, perfect.
Thanks, Carl.
This is fun because both Ubuntu 20.04 and Fedora 32
are really close
and they both have really cool new features.
So I think this is one of the reasons
we wanted to dive into this right now
because you could obviously do an entire episode on this.
So what we did is we set up identical VMs in KVM
and each assigned exactly eight gigabytes of RAM
and otherwise pretty basic installs,
fully up to date on both sides.
We have three terminal windows open under Gnome Shell.
I'm using Gnome Shell Classic.
So are you on Gnome Shell Classic as well?
Okay, that's one thing I didn't think to check.
So we're both on Gnome Shell Classic.
I have Firefox open with NetData running,
as does Wes, and three terminals.
So what we're gonna do,
it turns out it is so easy to thrash a Linux box.
It is so easy.
What we're gonna do is we're just gonna simply
tail slash dev slash zero.
And that will fill up memory pretty quickly,
depending on how much memory you have.
If you have a system with like 64 gigs of RAM,
it'll take a little while.
If you don't, if you're like me
and you only have eight gigs of RAM,
it goes pretty quick.
Sure does.
So now what we're going to observe when we run this
is how these two different systems react.
Will either one of them remain usable
in a low memory condition and how will they perform?
So I'm on 31, Wes is on 32.
Do you have your tail dev zero ready, sir?
Yeah, let's do it.
All right, you ready?
Three, two, one, go.
Okay, my memory usage is,
I'm watching a NetData, it's climbing quickly.
Oh boy.
I also have top running.
We both have top going up and I just maxed out.
Wow, that went quick.
Are you still running over there?
I was just at the top.
Okay, it looks like my NetData metrics
are going a little slow, but I can-
My Firefox is totally frozen.
Okay, and my thing is killed.
So it just terminated the tail command.
Really?
Yep, and I'm seeing here in the early OOM logs
that you can configure it so it'll print out
all the metrics it sees and it just went,
oh, nothing's left.
Everything's frozen.
My system is totally locked up.
Every terminal window is locked up,
Firefox is locked up.
Well, I think I'm just going to get some work done.
I mean, while you're, you know.
Wow, that's a significant,
yeah, you can use Firefox right now?
Yeah, well, I mean, my-
What's your memory usage?
My tail command, it just all dropped back down.
Mine is unmodable now.
Even my terminals have frozen.
Top is frozen, everything's frozen.
You weren't trying to use that system, were you, Chris?
Wow.
Is it going to come back?
This is a pretty significant difference.
Imagine like on a Raspberry Pi
where you've only got two or four gigs of RAM, right?
Because this is just eight gigs.
That's not an uncommon amount of RAM.
I just did it again.
And it seems to just sort of replicate the same behavior.
You just lapped me?
He just lapped me?
Wow, it's totally locked up.
Now imagine if I had set this limit, you know,
like to like 1% for your, or less,
then you might get into a similar situation
where you could live lock.
So you probably-
Shouldn't my kernel killer kick in now though?
Sometimes.
It's interesting because we've actually run this test
before and usually the kernel killer does kick in now.
We, in our prep, we ran through this
and a couple of different takes to make it reproducible.
And usually by now, ah, there it goes.
Here we go.
All my terminal process,
all three terminal windows were just killed.
And now Firefox is starting to come back to life.
So that's another difference.
Oh, it's sluggish.
In my case, all of my terminals stayed open.
Oh my God, one, 1000, two,
three seconds for a tab to open.
Oh man, it is brutal.
It's picking up now.
It's starting to pick up.
It's acting a little better now.
Oh man, it's still sluggish.
It's taking a solid second for those tabs to close.
So-
This system is thrashed.
For me, it was just the tail command that got killed.
So all the rest of my terminals stayed open
and I can still see the logs.
Wow.
Yeah, for me, it killed all my terminal windows.
It didn't just go for the tail command.
It just, it just was brutal.
That's a significant difference.
You can actually turn that on in 31 and 30 as well.
It's, you don't have to wait for 32.
Yeah, it's already, it's already packaged.
You can find it on Debian systems as well.
It's really easy to get going.
I wonder if there will be instructions
on how to get that working on 2004
and other distros like Manjaro.
I mean, it must be simple, right, to get it set up.
There's probably an ArchWiki on it.
That is really significant.
You could have probably run that a whole other time too.
You just didn't do it right away,
but you probably could have lapped me three times.
I think so.
And your system, and that's the other thing is
not only does it recover quicker,
but it's more responsive when it does recover.
You know, there was still some sluggishness
just after it got killed as the system
was sort of catching up and it looked like net data
maybe lost some of its data or at least dropped its caches
to be nice to the system under pressure.
Yeah, look at this.
I have a gap in my, in my metrics log.
Starting at 12.50 and going to almost 12.50, 3.30.
So for about three minutes there.
Yeah, okay, so I have a little gap,
but it's a much smaller gap.
I have a three and a half minute gap in my logging.
How long was your gap?
Do you still have it on your chart there?
I was like 10 seconds.
Really?
That shows you the difference right there.
It's, that's, huh.
That's a fun little experiment.
I think, I think we are looking at such an awesome
Linux desktop future when you look at the speed
at which Manjaro is humming along now
and how solid Ubuntu has been.
And now with Wimpy at the lead of the desktop there,
like, you know, that's going in good directions.
2004 integrating snapshots is fantastic.
Fedora 32 integrating not only the latest
gnome shell improvements, but also this cool little trick
is going to make it a really solid workstation.
All of these are just getting to be such good workstation
OSs, which is what I really care about.
Well, it's these exact sort of corner cases, you know,
as we saw the kernel killer does eventually work.
And you don't get into this sort of situation every day.
It's nice that we've reached the level where this is,
these are the problems that we can work on now
because we have solid foundations underneath
and can, you know, add a little more levels of polish.
Well, and imagine that scenario on the server for a moment.
You know, your server is essentially unresponsive
that entire time.
That's, that's horrible.
Yeah, and that's where some of the options
that you'll find too for either preferring to kill programs
or to totally not kill programs might be especially useful
if you're like, well, don't ever kill my logging program,
but yeah, you can shoot this application
that we have to reboot sometimes.
It seems the Red Hat developer, Chris Murphy,
was the proponent to include this early gnome killer
in Fedora 32.
And that's one killer I can get behind, you know?
I had a whole intro that I was going to do
that was such a bad joke, I dropped it.
But I was, I'm going to tell you now that I've, you know.
Lay it on me.
Today we make nice with a killer.
No, not Hans Reiser.
Ha!
Too soon or are we good?
Is that okay now?
I can't ever tell.
I think you should, you need to use some Reiser FS.
Yeah, I should.
It's probably great.
I'm not sure that was funny even five years ago.
Damn it, Alex.
Millions of unread users are really upset
with you about now.
Hey, I used Reiser FS on a bank check imaging system
back in the day because you needed a file system
that was really good with small files,
lots of small files, and I believe I needed support
for extended attributes.
So that's how I both got going with Reiser FS and XFS.
Back in the day, back in the day.
So we will have links for all the stuff
about the different out of memory managers,
including ones that I think are pretty cool.
Maybe a little more server focused.
Yeah, I would give No Hang and Try
if you just want to go try one of these out
because it also has desktop notifications integrated,
which you can also get for early OOM.
It looks like you might need another component there.
Oh yeah, that's something we didn't even touch on,
but that's something they're looking at
is giving you a notification mechanism via your desktop
to say, hey, I just had to go kill something
in the background.
It does make a journal entry.
And so you could actually just look at the journal
for that stuff.
But if you're not looking at your journal,
which you're probably not, it's nice to get a notification.
Good old D-Bus.
Well, it's just one of those like first class
sort of entities where you should tell the user
what's going on with their system.
That's a good point.
So if you don't have the desktop application,
you have to refer to the logs to see what was killed.
And if you're running on a low memory box
and say you're trying to, I don't know,
edit video and encode video,
and it's eating up all your RAM,
is it by default just going to kill the tasks
that's eating up the most RAM
like it did with the tail command?
How does it pick which app or which process to kill
whenever you're running these out of memory errors?
I don't remember the exact particular,
so I could be wrong about this,
but I believe it works off of determining
the memory pressure through PSI
along with the OOM score that is associated with it.
It also takes into account priorities.
If you set a priority for a process ID,
it does take that into account as well.
You can, however, configure early OOM
to have different specific priorities,
or like, for example, if you're doing video encoding
and you know that's intensive and you don't want it to die,
you can have early OOM try very hard to ignore it
and try to do something else
to relieve the pressure as needed.
We went a lot back and forth
in the workstation working group
about how to configure this and how to deal with this.
I know that we had to implement
in the configuration workaround specifically for Chrome
because Chrome does somewhat bad things
for how it sets up its child processes.
But yeah, so the exact details, not sure,
but I think that kind of gives you the gist of it.
And also one last thing, Chris.
Chris Murphy, who's actually doing this,
who suggested all this
and kind of leads the workstation working group,
he does not work for Red Hat.
That's a different Chris Murphy.
Oh, then I emailed the wrong guy.
Yeah, you probably did.
Oh, well, there you go.
It's hard tracking people down online.
Sometimes you get it wrong.
Well, hopefully Chris Murphy will pass my email along.
I was also curious,
is this going to be implemented into Fedora server
when it rolls out as well?
Because I could definitely see this being useful on,
like Chris was saying, low-end servers,
a droplet with limited resources.
I personally wanted to.
The problem was that we kind of ran out of time
in terms of turning this into like a full,
all Fedora edition system-wide change.
It's pretty simple to enable though.
It is simple to enable.
Honestly, my suggestion is,
if you want to see this in Fedora server,
drop an email or something
to the Fedora server working group
to let them know that you're interested in this.
And that, like,
cause the main reason it didn't get done
was that there was nobody from this server,
nobody on the server team
particularly expressed any interest
cause they didn't hear of anybody who wanted it.
So, I mean, I obviously believe
that it would be useful across all the variants.
Wouldn't something maybe like Facebook's OOMD
make more sense?
Because that's really kind of designed for data centers.
That was some of the argument as well.
Some of the issue with using Facebook's OOMD
or O-O-M-D or whatever,
is that it is a lot more aggressive than early OOM.
And depending on what type of workloads
you put into a server,
that may not be great.
That being said,
one of the other reasons why we didn't do OOMD
is because it's in the process
of being reworked completely.
One of the, they're working with the SystemD folks upstream
to re-implement it as a service
that's more tightly integrated
with SystemD service management facilities.
Facebook themselves heavily leveraged this
and their contributors to SystemD upstream,
as well as into the Fedora project.
So they're working on making this
a more comprehensive solution,
better integrated with the service management capabilities
within SystemD and exposing a better interface
for desktops and other things to take advantage of it.
And if that pans out the way that we all hope it does,
we'll probably see within my guess is about a year or so,
we will look at transitioning from early OOM to that.
We're not there yet,
but I think it's fascinating that this development,
there's these parallel solutions and development
to make Linux handle low memory solutions better,
or situations I should say.
And the thing that's interesting about them,
and this is where my mind was going,
is that they're user space, right?
They're all user space solutions,
but there definitely seems to be a need here.
And I think we just demonstrated
there's a real benefit on the desktop.
Yeah, absolutely.
But you could easily see how that
would apply to the server too.
Yeah, I mean, the end of it was that we all just gave up
waiting for the kernel to solve the problem.
So, I mean, if you really, really look at it,
all of this is just a way to try to make
the kernel OOM behavior happen more deterministically,
more repeatably, more reliably,
and more in a manner that a user expects.
And potentially maybe as if you have a user space solution,
then maybe the kernel one can be,
it's okay that it's so much more conservative
and heavy handed because it's kind of a backup.
It's a parachute to your glider.
Exactly.
Maybe, we'll see.
I could say, and that would be,
and the thing that's nice about the user space one,
although it's so Linux to have multiple solutions
to do the same thing.
I'm sure other operating systems,
they just have one and they just implement it.
At the same time, it's clear that there's nice uses for it.
Like OMD or UMD from Facebook is great for the server,
but NoHang looks like it's gonna be
a lot better for the desktop.
And there are different use cases there.
And so it's so perfectly Linux
that there are multiple ones,
but we'll get to some common ground.
There'll probably be some easy way
to swap these all out too, right?
Well, yeah, I mean, they're just a single binary
and oftentimes that run.
So just stop the service, start the service to the new one.
It's a user space thing.
Exactly.
It's a very powerful user space thing,
but yeah, I think it's fascinating.
And I might always now run a desktop with one, I think.
I think that's my takeaway from this.
It's a little bit of a paradigm shift in that sense
is why not?
Why not?
I mean, would you implement it on your,
say if you were to go back into your Neon installer?
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, you might need to do a little tuning perhaps
if you have some applications that are memory hogs
and end up getting killed, but that's easy to do.
Like it probably might not make as much sense
on the OBS machine.
And we also don't see those problems there.
So it probably does make more sense to write it
for a machine where you've got
perhaps a little more dynamic workload,
where you do see large changes in how much RAM is used,
like a web browser.
Yeah, and specifically my laptop.
Yeah.
With three electron apps open and.
At least.
Yeah, it's on a good day.
So there is one other case
where you might want to think about
for using early OOM or any other user space
out of memory management solution.
It's if you know that you're doing a workload
which dynamically spawns lots of threads
and those threads can at any given time spike
and use lots of memory
and you don't really have a good way
of immediately dealing with that
or otherwise controlling it within the application itself.
So for example,
if you are dynamically letting video encoders
just run wild on your computer,
that's probably an avenue where you,
if you cannot do any control in the application itself,
which thankfully most of them let you,
that is something where early OOM would benefit.
But another is if you're compiling code,
killing threads for out of control compilations
doesn't necessarily bring down the whole compilation process.
In most cases, it causes it to reschedule them
or do something different.
So, you know, it depends,
but like when you consider these workloads,
you also have to consider, you know,
what is the modeling for how these processes
and how the memory allocation is going to go.
Right, and what are the consequences
for things getting killed
in terms of how that work can continue?
For sure.
Yes, absolutely.
Yeah, that is definitely the other side
to this double-edged sword.
I think that's what makes it so interesting
to see it as a new default too,
is sort of the workstation team saying
this works well enough that let's push it out.
Yeah, and I think you'll see other distributions
pick it up, especially the ones
that want to be seen as performance focused.
Well, I could see this, you know,
the out of memory killer along with immutable systems,
you know, all kind of coming together under one umbrella
to maybe form the next, you know,
the next season of Linux distros and stuff,
you know, like what Silverblue is doing now
and being able to stack OOM right on top of that
would be, you know, a nice little...
All running on Wayland backed by flat pack
or app images or snaps, it's happening.
And the IRC XMN has a point about mobile devices
and yeah, I kind of want this for Android already.
Funny you should mention all of that.
So Silverblue, the goal with this
is like combined with low memory monitor and early OOM,
I believe that in the very near future,
Silverblue will also have this functionality active
and more tightly integrated.
And because of some of the stuff
that's going on in the flat pack side,
it can be slightly more intelligent
than your average application
about handling memory pressure situations.
Oh, and as far as Android goes, they already do this.
That's really one of the reasons
why there's been a lot of impetus
towards trying to fix this for desktop Linux
is because every other platform,
including the Android one already has something set up.
Well, that's the advantage to a unified focused
sort of sprint based, like we're gonna focus on this
and this and this and yeah,
the Mac does similar things, Windows does similar things.
Mini Mac though had a question that I bet
is on the mind of a lot of listeners.
So I wanted to let you jump in.
Thank you.
My question was how is swap involved in all this?
I mean, we're talking about a ROM now,
but we all have a little small swap partition.
Yeah, and I think there was some thought
in the design of this when it comes to swap
is it looks at your RAM and your swap.
And if they're less than 10% free
or if they're around that range,
that's when it'll generally kick in.
But one, I think Wes and correct me if I'm wrong,
but I think one of the tunables is you can say,
start sooner than 10% swap
because if I'm using that much swap,
then my system is already thrashing
way more than I would like it to be.
Yep, yeah, you can tune both of those separately.
Yeah, so you could go in there and say,
you know what, once I'm at 50% swap, start getting crazy.
Now that would probably be too much,
but by default, once your free swap goes below 10%,
that's when it starts kicking in
for both your swap and your RAM by default.
And part of the reason for setting that way
is that there are some people who are either putting anemic
or no swap at all,
and so we need to cover those grounds as well.
And people who have anemic swap,
this can cause interesting side effects.
So that's why we consider both free RAM and swap together
to make sure that we don't kick in unnecessarily aggressively.
Yeah, this is an example where sometimes
just blasting defaults and not letting the user change it
has some advantages because then you know
what their configuration is for things like swap.
You know it's exactly the amount of RAM
or maybe the distribution policy is 20% of the amount of RAM
or something, you just always know what that number is.
But this is a power user workstation OS
and we can tweak those things, thankfully.
Well, that's what I was just thinking
because with Android, I'm not very satisfied
with the version there because it seems
I have more stalls on Android
than I have on my Linux laptop.
So I want more knobs.
Yeah, very good point.
And I think it's gonna be there for you, Wes.
I think you will be able to.
Like I say, I mean, this changes everything
for me going forward.
I will forever going forward on my Linux boxes.
I mean, I'm gonna go start after the show installing it.
And now it's gonna be one of the things
like along with tweaking my fonts
and installing themes, Wes, and getting extensions,
I'll be installing an early memory out of memory killer
because that's how I roll.
That's pretty cool.
And I'm glad to see it getting turned on.
Now we'll see where it goes from here.
All right, now how about a couple of pics?
Not just one, but two pics.
Yes, please.
The first one, new shell.
It's a new type of shell.
Okay, all right, I'm gonna admit it.
I didn't put this one in,
so I hadn't really looked at this.
This looks pretty great.
You'll be pretty pleased to hear
that it's written in Rust, so.
What, what?
What was that, Wes?
Yeah, that's right, it's written in Rust.
Oh my gosh.
Yes, yes.
Yes, it is hammer time.
Very good.
It's got all kinds of smart support
for different formats and natively understand things
like XML, JSON, INI files, other configuration files.
And as you will see, if you visit their website,
when you run just the average old LS command,
instead of getting the normal sort of pure text LS output,
you get a lovely little table.
And new shell has a bunch of built-ins
to help you sort with that.
So instead of having to use flags to LS to configure,
like I only want to see things
that are this new or whatever,
you just sort of pipe it and say,
well, when the date is after this.
Oh, Wes, this is really cool.
Oh, I love what it does with PS and LS.
Oh my gosh, that, oh, that's so nice.
So it's basically making mcurses tables,
just a UI to just outline the data easier to see.
Well, but you can also interact with that data.
So you can filter on the different things.
You can load a JSON document into the exact same table
and use all the same tools to interact with it
and pipe it back out again
to traditional command line programs.
It's definitely, as I admit,
inspired by things like PowerShell, right?
That have these sort of rich objects behind the scenes.
And it's almost like a little subdomain
that you get with this rich capability in this new shell,
while still having access
to a somewhat traditional command line experience
to go do all the rest of the programs
that might not be supported by, you know,
what the additional superpowers.
Stay a while and listen.
And now one more.
And you know, this one's a hot market one
because it's just got a launchpad page.
Does it not have a homepage?
What's the matter with this thing?
It doesn't, I wasn't able to find one.
There might be one out there, but I wasn't able to find it.
All right, so tell me about Timekeeper Next.
So Timekeeper, Time KPR, which it was originally known as,
and then they changed the name a few times,
and now it's Timekeeper Next,
essentially allows you, you know, everyone's at home right now
and their kids are using their computers.
And likely, if you're listening to the show,
your kid is using a Linux-based computer.
You can install Timekeeper through a PPA currently.
It's also in the Arch repos,
but you can install a Timekeeper to keep track
of the time used on these desktop environments
on the computer for any other user on the system.
So say your kids log in and you want to allow them
to log in and use the machine through the certain hours,
or if you want to maybe allow them to use the machine,
they can't use it past midnight until 8 a.m. in the morning,
and then you only want them to have three hours
of computer access for the day.
You can set all this up on a per-user basis.
So it's a nice little way to kind of, you know,
keep your kids off of the computer a little bit
while you're stuck at home.
Yeah, or yourself.
Yeah, absolutely.
Honestly, I have a hard time.
Just in the last couple of days,
well, really yesterday and today,
I'm trying to get myself to move more
because I used to have this mindset
that I would just sit down and marathon a day
and just work, work, work, work, work, work, work, work,
all day long.
Yeah, it doesn't work.
Oh my God, like I get sore all over
in places I didn't know you would get sore.
Serious, like it's bad, so.
The sitting sore.
Yeah, well, and it's really, it's in my shoulders,
in my elbows, and in my wrists.
It's just getting, I'm getting like RSI, essentially,
is I think of what it is.
And so I gotta move around more.
And so something like that to help me just practice that
is always good.
So that's timekeeper next.
Yeah, I think for me, I would be tempted
just to go in and flip the switch and turn it off, though.
Yeah, I know.
If I was administrating it myself,
like it would have to be something like
I wasn't able to get in and turn off myself, you know?
I don't use like any of the digital wellbeing stuff
on my phone.
Here's the thing, you just change your root password
when you're drunk.
Get it all configured.
That is the best idea I've ever heard.
That's a Westpain pro tip right there.
Yeah, no doubt.
Yes, it is hammer time.
Hey, does anybody know if you can run OpenSense on ARM
hardware, like the Pine 64?
Because I think that'd make a, I was just thinking
about our firewall segment.
They did make a PF Sense box that was ARM-based.
From my understanding, it wasn't super great.
It was kind of limited on the throughput side.
Like you couldn't saturate the gigabit connections.
But yes, from my understanding,
there is already ARM hardware out there
running PF Sense and OpenSense.
I could sniff around.
We'll see.
Alex says he can do a low-power cheap setup,
so I'm waiting to see, but I'm just trying to think.
Yeah, 100 bucks.
100 bucks are used, I'm going to write a blog post
before the next self-hosted episode.
100 bucks, and you'll build an x86 system
that draws about 15 watts.
Okay, all right.
Okay, you got me with that, because I was going to say
my entire setup right now draws like 50 watts,
and I am so stinking proud of that.
That includes router, Wi-Fi, and switch, and now four Pi.
So it might be actually, I haven't actually checked it
since I added the fourth Pi, so.
But I'm going to shut down one of them, so it won't matter.
Yeah, I am, so.
You know who else is running a super inexpensive
and low-powered PF sense box is our buddy Tyler Condulo.
He runs a, I think it's a Wyze thin client.
Oh yeah.
As a PF sense box, yeah.
Wow, that's wild.
I remember those old boxes.
All right, well, I just have a quick disclaimer,
really quick, but I just want to get it out there.
Alex and I have decided together
that we're going to take things to the next level
in our self-hosted relationship,
and we have launched a Discord server.
I think you need the hallelujah.
Now, okay.
A beautiful baby server.
Now listen, if you don't use Discord already,
don't sign up on our account.
We're not trying to convert anyone to use Discord.
We're making a community there for people that use it,
selfhosted.show slash Discord.
I want to get the word out there,
because I know some of you already have Discord accounts
and you want to use it.
And something that Alex and I have talked about on the show
is trying to strike these balances from time to time.
We obviously lean towards hosting it yourself,
and we're very aware of ways we could do that
from IRC to Matrix.
But Discord is where the community is.
And so for the people that are there,
we have created a Discord server.
And Alex, do you have any other thoughts
you want to add to that?
Well, for some people, it's just like crazy
that the self-hosted show is using Discord.
I know, we're a pair of heathens, aren't we?
We knew that was coming though,
within 20 minutes of launching it.
It just boils down to pragmatism in the end.
I've written a blog post to try and outline
some of our thoughts in a bit more detail
as to how we came to that decision.
So blog.katyz.me is the first post on there at the moment.
And yeah, there'll be a link in the show notes.
It's a truly contentious issue.
It's why we're still on IRC for this show,
even though I think we'd probably have
maybe a thousand people in there if we were on Discord.
And you know, it's interesting
because it's just really, it's the audience.
I launched a Discord server for Unfilter recently.
It was like two weeks ago.
It took until this weekend, like two days ago.
Somebody said, hey, how come we're doing this on Discord?
But when we launched it for self-hosted,
it was within 20 minutes of launching it
that somebody said, what?
All about those expectations.
Yeah, and we're totally aware of that.
And that's something we'll address in self-hosted
if you check out self-hosted.
And also, if you start and go through our early episodes,
like we had one with Wendell very early on,
we really kind of get into our rationale there
about when it's absolutely vital to self-host
versus when you can make a compromise.
And I think that's important even just for Linux users.
It's not just a self-hosting thing.
It's also a software thing.
Linux isn't always the right solution.
Sometimes.
Now, it's true.
And I think when you judge someone for using Windows
or for Mac OS, in a way, what you're actually doing
is you're judging them for choosing something
that you did not choose.
You're sort of projecting a moral value onto them.
And then you're judging them for that projection
of a moral value that they never subscribed to.
And it's a complicated thing to judge people
for what they use because you're essentially shaming them
in your head or publicly for choosing something
you didn't choose.
And that is a slippery slope.
Well, and you know, it's rare that you actually understand
the complete context of all of those choices
that other people are making.
Yeah, very typical because it's very hard to, you know.
You may not understand them for your own choices.
Yeah, sometimes.
So I agree.
I think it's sometimes very, very likely
that Linux is gonna do a great job,
but it's not always the right tool.
And we shouldn't judge people for not using it.
I happen to like it a lot, but it's fine if you don't.
Really.
I stumbled into a conversation thread
on YouTube and on Reddit over the weekend
where somebody was being outed for running Windows
who was supposed to be like a Linux developer.
And they were outed for using Windows 10.
And I just felt like it was, like it's sort of old now.
It's like we kind of moved past all that.
It seems like it's one of those things
that people like to just hang on.
And I get being a purist,
but in that same vein, I think it's always just right
to use the tool that's good for the job,
that's perfect for the job, you know.
And when a lot of us came to this,
I mean, before you learned about licenses
and all of these things,
or maybe you came into computers
before the open source and free software movements,
computers are tools to do things.
We're excited about playing with them and using them.
And yes, I think for a lot of us,
once you discover open source and free software,
you're like, okay, this makes sense.
This is how we should try to be doing things for computers.
It's just a natural fit,
but there's still a whole bunch of tools out there
that are very useful in a huge range of fields.
And they're still great.
Yeah, well said.
It's funny because while we look at things like Fedora 32,
and we talk about Ubuntu 20.04,
it doesn't seem like I have this view,
but I truly do see this as sort of a post-distro show.
Like it's all great.
It's all good.
And it's just different kinds of good
for different use cases.
Like this show can get into Mint.
I can put myself in that head space
and I can appreciate things like time shift
and the way the updates are labeled out
or I can get myself in the head space of,
even we tried out Regolith recently.
I was like, actually kind of like this.
I get it.
And it's because when you step back and you remove
that sort of like, well, it should be like
this kind of thing.
And you just roll with kind of the awesome software
that it is.
It sort of doesn't really make sense
to have these different camps and tribes
in different distros,
cause they're all using the same upstream stuff.
They're all struggling with the same problems.
And often in almost, not all, but in a lot of cases,
maybe the majority of cases, behind the scenes,
the developers chat with each other.
They work on multiple projects.
It's not uncommon for them to work on several.
Especially in the open source world, right?
Where there's all these shared fundamentals.
Neil, what are the different distributions
you contribute to on a regular basis?
Oh boy, let's see.
Primarily I'm involved in Fedora and OpenSUSE,
but I also work in Magia, OpenMandriva.
A little tiny sliver in Debian.
I've got a little bit more than a sliver in Ubuntu.
I used to work on a couple of other distributions
like Unity and a few other,
Unity Linux and a couple of others.
I have done a little bit in Alpine, some in Void.
There was a little bit of time
where I was working with the Exervo people.
But Neil, some of those are competitors with Fedora,
you madman.
I'm sorry to break your heart, Chris, but for the most part,
all of us talk to each other and work with each other fairly often.
Some more than others.
There are some that like to live on their little islands.
But in general, at least within the larger distro communities,
to a great extent,
we do talk to each other and work with each other on common problems.
It's common software.
That's why the tribalism between the distros,
I think is sort of silly and that's why I call this a post-distro show
in that sense.
And I apply that same logic to judging people for other tools that they use.
I just don't think it really makes a lot of sense.
I do find a certain important moral value in free software,
but I don't need to have somebody else subscribe to that same moral value.
And just like I happen to like the Linux flavors I like,
but there's such a range and variety of different distros and Linux users
that it's fine.
Yeah, we just celebrate that.
We're all using the same stuff.
What is the purpose of this show of JB in general of what we're doing here?
It's to further the open source agenda, isn't it?
Absolutely.
Free software rules the world.
Yeah, and to help others find it and be part of a community.
And sometimes, to quote the orange one in the chat,
sometimes it's about using the best tool rather than the right tool.
Yeah, and I think Linux is the right tool for a lot of jobs.
And that's what we talk about here.
And for a lot of us, it's sufficient that it's all you need.
I had a great chat with Neil about Pagoo, a GitLab alternative.
We just dedicated an extras to that that came out this morning.
It's 14 minutes long, so it's just a quick one.
Extras.show slash 69.
If you are curious about a self-hosted GitLab alternative
that few projects are involved with these days, some less than before,
and then, of course, the free software is rolling out,
it's GitLab-like solution that we based on.
Pagoo?
Prager?
Pagger.
Troll.
Oh, am I trolling again?
Sometimes I do that.
All right, well, go find more of my work at chrislast.com.
Go find more of Wes at wespain.
And of course, at techsnap.systems.
What else should we plug?
At Cheese Bacon?
Is that your handle cheese?
Yeah, that's me on the Twitter, at Cheese Bacon.
There you go.
And of course, you can find us in the Telegram as well.
We'd love to have you join us live on Tuesday.
Get that converted at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash
calendar.
And you can always jump in that IRC.
It's irc.geekshed.net pound jupiterbroadcasting.
You don't want us to switch to Discord.
Use the IRC.
It's real easy.
Just go to jblive.tv to get the stream and IRC embedded right there.
Boom.
See you next Tuesday.
Bye.
Unplugged program.
All right, jbtitles.com.
Cool, bro.
Is the bot working?
Let's check.
I rebooted it earlier.
You snuck in there and rebooted it before we started.
Good thinking.
You know, you just got to reboot the bot.
You know what we need is a bot command that reboots itself.
Metabot.
Yeah, a master bot.
We need to start porting JBot to Discord right away.
It's not a horrible idea, actually.
Ideally, though, in the same crippled format.
We don't want to improve it too much.
Right, absolutely.
Something you have to kill from time to time.
It's troublesome personality.
What I think is interesting, too, is that, you know,
this talk about Discord and tools and so on and so forth,
we all know that Discord's using open source technologies
under the hood.
Oh, yeah.
They're written in Elixir.
Yeah, well, and you know, their servers
are all on the back end.
I know that's so true for so many services.
It's a tricky line there.
So first, I actually would have been
real interested if you guys had decided
to do like a JB network matrix to replace Geek Shed.
But one thing I know, I mean, I think
it'd be way more successful than the IRC server is.
But when it comes to things like Discord and Slack
and all of those, like, they're all proprietary solutions.
And I'm kind of stuck having to use them for various reasons
and like whatever.
Like, I grit my teeth and deal with it.
But the thing that annoys me more
is the fact that they're so bad at contributing back
to the community.
Like, they build lots of stuff.
They clearly do.
They build really innovative things.
But they don't, to some degree, share the wealth back
to the community to help build bigger and better solutions.
And that's the part that I get more annoyed
about more than anything else.
Hmm.
That's what I say there.
That doesn't sound good.
Until those engineers move on to another job with the skills
they picked up at Discord and build something else better,
maybe this time it will be open.
Who knows?
Possibly.
That's what I always hope for.
Well, I certainly picked up most of my skills
working on software that will never see the light of day
publicly for companies that are obviously
paying me money to do so.
And here I am contributing.
So it does happen.
Just maybe not quite in the ways we hope.
I would say you probably also picked up
a lot of hardware skills when you worked at the Apple store.
And now you're building home-assisted controlled
devices.
So we all kind of come full circle.
Alex, tell me about the printing factory
you've turned into over there.
Oh, my god.
I'm so bored of 3D printing.
I've printed nearly 300 face shields for medical workers
over the last seven days.
Ooh, very nice.
That's great, though.
About $500 in donations and lots and lots
of folks in local nursing homes and hospitals and stuff.
Very, very grateful.
So I'll be so happy when the big molds come online
and I can stop.
But for now, I think it's a valuable public service.
Do people come by and pick them up,
or do you have to deliver them?
Yep.
All hours of the day, I have given out
batches of 20 or 30 at a time.
They cost about $0.50 to make each.
And people generally seem to be donating about $1 each
to cover filament costs and electric and time
and that sort of stuff.
So it's been really great to see the community pull together.
That is really neat.
I'll drop the link to the blog post you wrote there, Alex.
I jumped on it, too, and had been printing them and was lucky
enough that the school donated their filament
from their 3D printer that's on the fritz
and also donated a ton of transparency sheets
for the actual face shield part.
But if anyone out there is interested,
I'd know, Neil, you have a 3D printer.
Jump on it.
You know what?
You guys just earned a taco.
Good job.
Yes.