This is Linux Unplugged, Episode 47 for July 1st, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's got all its updates applied
as it prepares to go offline and live in a cabin.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey Matt.
It is hot here now.
It's maybe not hot by like everybody's standards, but it's hot enough that we've got a brushfire
nearby.
I mean, that's hot, right?
Yeah, it's about 87 degrees in the studio today.
So it gets, and it gets wet.
It's like a wet hot, Matt.
It's like a humid kind of hot.
That's what makes it so miserable.
And of course I made my own predicament worse because I was barbecuing today.
So we had to close up all the windows in the studio because I didn't want to make the studio
smell like barbecue smoke.
And it was delicious.
I'm not going to lie.
It turned out, Rekai gave me like, here is a bag full of burgers that I made.
Why don't you cook them all?
It was like, he threw down the gauntlet and I'm like, I'm going to cook all these burgers
before Linux Unplugged.
And I did it.
And it was delicious.
And we had copious amounts of bacon.
And I made, I took some of the, this is kind of gross, but I took some of the bacon grease
sauce.
I took some of the, and made a sauce out of it with the barbecue.
It was just, it was just amazing all around, Matt.
That's all I'm trying to say.
Oh my goodness.
So we got.
Yeah, I kind of lucked out.
I pretty cool, pretty cool office.
Oh, nice.
Starting the show.
But it's still kind of warm.
So we got to just persevere.
I'm glad you took, I'm glad you took a wise precautions.
I, on the other hand, was not so wise.
But that's okay.
We've got a good show.
We're going to follow up first and then we're going to cover a couple of items, a few updates
on some big news that's happened on stories that we've covered recently.
And then after that, we're going to announce a new community, we're going to call it the
Jupiter Colony Review Draft, where we're looking to expand our distribution reviews and cover
more distributions.
And we want to collate a group of folks out there that would like to get involved in reviewing
a distribution and perhaps come on our show via mumble and share their thoughts.
Now this isn't going to be necessarily an easy job because you're going to have to download
the distribution, try it out and note down your thoughts.
And then work with our team.
But we want to expand the distributions that we're able to cover.
And so we're going to talk more about that in today's show, including where you can sign
up and draft yourself to be in our Jupiter Colony Review panel.
We're going to talk about that a little bit.
But first, Matt, this is something that's been kicking around.
We talk about this a lot on the live stream.
We haven't talked a lot about it in a show for a while, but the audience might be familiar
that you and I have struggled with audio issues under KDE.
It's been a struggle to being calm.
Oh, yeah, that's that's being kind.
Yeah, you're right.
It's inexcusable because it's not just like one particular hardware setup.
It's multiple hardware setups.
Right.
Come on.
And I got to and I want to qualify that I want to completely back that statement up
to because I've tried it on multiple systems with USB sound cards, on board sound cards,
HDMI sound cards, you name it, different machines with NVIDIA, ATI, Intel, all the all the whole
stack has been laptops, desktops, all of it.
And I've had issues with switching my audio settings and things like that.
So WiggleWaffles wrote into the subreddit and said, in previous installs of KDE, I haven't
really had any troubles with phonon, especially running it on a VM.
But since I dedicated to switching from dual booting with Arch and Windows 8 instead of
running Arch in a VM, sound on KDE has been a nightmare.
It works in the most basic sense of the term, but hooking up headphones is spotty.
The volume buttons on the keyboard adjust the HDMI audio even when it's not plugged
in.
And it's reset to 100 percent every time I reboot, blowing out my eardrums whenever
I get an error message.
And then he goes on to ask if there's a way to overcome this.
And then the discussions didn't go the way they usually go.
Usually I see a ton of people saying, well, I run KDE and I never have a problem.
And then I just kind of check out because I'm like, OK, well, I know I've had it on
like a dozen systems, I've had these problems.
But actually, just about everybody in here sort of chimed in and said, yeah, I've had
some problems, definitely had some problems, you know, it's really bad, et cetera, et cetera.
There's something going on.
I don't know if it's the way Phonon interacts with Pulse Audio.
I don't know.
It's exactly what it is, in my opinion, based on my experiences with it and actually experimenting
with it and just kind of troubleshooting, looking through the logs.
That's where the hang up is.
It's a one or it's either one or the other.
You don't do both, in my opinion.
OK, I have a suggestion because we can we can have a religious war about this or maybe
as a community, we could create a database of the hardware that people are trying it
on and the distributions and the versions of like Pulse and KDE and maybe we could come
up with some common threads and then as a group, we'd have something we could submit
as a bug report to the KDE folks so they could work on it.
Sounds interesting.
So I don't know if people in the subreddit would be interested in that.
Maybe we could work together and all sort of come together and try to narrow this thing
down and submit a bug and maybe we can fix this for other people because it's it's one
of these functionalities that when it doesn't work, it's infuriating.
It made me so frustrated because I got a new machine set up.
I got a brand new steam game and all I wanted to do was set my audio out to my speakers
and I probably spent two hours trying to make that work and I eventually gave up and it
made me just sit there and think, you know, why did I just do that?
I felt like I just wasted two hours of my life on something that shouldn't be a problem
at all.
And I think a lot of people have that experience and it can be very frustrating and it's something
I think if we all work together, instead of just banging our table about how upset it
makes us, maybe we can, as a group, figure out some commonalities.
Like something like that.
What do you think?
Yeah, it sounds interesting.
Worth a try?
Yeah, I think it's worth a try.
I'm skeptical.
I'm really skeptical.
It's because I, every time it's ever been brought up, it's always been, well, it's just
not an issue.
And if we can get past that and we can get something legitimate out there, then I'll
be able to stand behind it and say, okay, that's cool, let's evaluate.
That's why I'm thinking those of us that acknowledge it's a problem, we band together and figure
out what it is.
Because it seems like there's so many moving layers and it could even be versions of things
that make a difference.
Yeah.
I don't know, maybe it's more pronounced on Arch.
Who knows?
While we're...
Possible.
Let's shift gears.
Let's talk about KD a little more in the context of Mint 17, they just had the new release.
And producer of the show, Eric, has been trying out Mint 17 for a little while now and he's
kind of gone in and made us really kind of finely tune it to the way he likes it.
So Eric, what has been your impressions of using Mint now for a little while and what
was the first thing you had to change?
Well, I kind of went through it and the first thing I changed was the theme.
For some reason, the error theme for me is just way too bright.
So I changed it to one that you can download straight from the Get New Themes button called
AMAKAGE, wherever you pronounce that, I don't know.
So I've got that and then I got rid of oxygen.
The way I did that was I changed my widget style to Qt Curve and then I was able to install
on top of that, there's a Zekitwo, or Zekitwo, however you pronounce it.
I was able to download that and make that a theme for Qt Curve.
And on top of that, because Zekitwo, wherever it is pronounced it, it is available for GTK3
as well and GTK2.
So you get sort of the benefit of like the same benefit you get if you're using oxygen
only you can use the theme you want.
Correct.
Yeah, exactly.
And it gets rid of that glow that people are so upset about.
And not only that, but I have not, at least in this KDE setup, experienced the audio issues
that are prevalent in the Arch KDE setup.
I don't know what it is about that setup.
So you've had issues on the same machine and then you've loaded Mint and haven't had issues?
Correct.
I don't know how that is.
It's got something to do with the phonon and pulse audio implementation, but it's got to
be something with that.
Hmm.
That sounds like something that needs to be a little investigated into.
So overall, toolset, performance-wise, you like it?
You think you're going to stay here for a while?
I think I might stay with it.
And the reason being is that I have actually run it up against Kubuntu.
And with Kubuntu, I don't know what the problem is there, but it just seems sluggish.
Like if I go to open the system settings, Mint KDE, I don't have that problem.
It just pops up right away and I was actually blown away by that.
So I don't know what they've been doing.
That'll be because we're sending all your data to Amazon.
That's what it is.
Hey-oh.
I'm not talking about the Ubuntu.
I'm not talking about the Unity desktop.
I'm talking about the KDE implementation, Kubuntu.
Kubuntu.
Yeah.
I was trying to be funny.
Oh, okay.
Popey, any thoughts you want to share with the crowd on KDE from your end?
I know you've been playing with it recently.
Oh, man.
Why did you set me up like that?
I'm just curious.
I think KDE is a great desktop.
I just have sound problems.
Honestly, KDE and Bay can go very well together.
I got to say that.
Yeah.
Nice.
I know KDE.
I mean, Popey, that might not be a fair question because you're obviously a Unity guy, I'm
sure.
I'll bash it.
It's okay.
Well, you know, I use lots of different desktops and I've tried KDE in the past, the distant
past, and I've tried it recently this week.
And I find it incredibly painful to use and verbose and far too many settings and the
layout of the UI is unbelievably painful with like bits scattered all over the screen and
weird dialogues.
I find it a horrible mess.
Now, let me ask you, though, would you be willing to...
Oh, somebody has open mic, hot mic, close your mic, there we go.
Would you be willing to, you know, entertain the idea of you're just coming at it from
a different angle?
Like you come at it with a different set of expectations of what a desktop should be.
So these things that don't meet that set of expectations really stand out at you.
But if somebody else came at it with a different set of expectations, those things would be
expected and they'd be missed if they weren't there.
What do you think of that?
Yeah, probably.
I think if your expectations were, I'm a deeply technical user and I want to have absolute
control over every single pixel on my display and I want to be able to fiddle with every
possible setting that there is, sure, it's there for you.
But if you're someone who wants to turn the computer on and use it, I find it obtuse.
It just gets in the way and I was surprised how hard it was for me to find applications,
download updates, I just found it really got in the way and that's from someone who uses
Unity where everyone tells me that gets in the way of your workflow and it's hard to
use.
I'm lost for words.
Okay.
See, I like Unity too and I just like this also.
Honestly, I'm the type of person who cannot decide between a desktop environment.
I'm a total desktop.
Because I like them all.
I'm such a desktop hooker.
It's crazy.
Yeah, me too.
I'll load up Cinnamon for a couple of days and be like, this is it.
This is the perfect blend of classic and modern.
And then I'll be like, in Nome, I'll be like, oh, I'm in the future and it's finally working.
It's here.
And then I'm in KD and I'm like, I can do anything I want.
What is wrong with you people?
Why don't you just install iOS and just leave it alone?
It's a sickness, man.
Just get on and do your work.
Maybe there's a medication for it.
It's like some sort of OCD.
I don't know.
It's weird.
I don't know myself.
I'm compelled.
Although I do find myself in Nome pretty much all the time right now.
That's what my main DE is.
And the thing I love about Nome is I have several different machines with different
monitor sizes and I think Nome works great on my big 28-inch monitor and a 30-inch monitor
that I have.
I have one of those cinema displays that I bought used that Nome rocks that.
And then I've got a 14-inch screen that I've got Nome on and it rocks that too.
I mean, they all do good in that regard, but I just found that particularly works pretty
well.
I'm sorry.
I cut somebody off.
Did somebody want to add something before we move on?
Yeah.
I just wanted to say that I like KDE's functionality.
It's got a lot of awesome technical features like KDE Connect and the widgets and all these
things.
And it's so cool as far as functionality, but it looks awful.
Well, and I'm going to close the screenshots then and show you what I've got.
Yeah.
If you've got them handy, yeah.
If the...
Like what you said, I completely understand that how you could make KDE look good and
it's possible.
You just remove oxygen completely and it's fine.
Oxygen is hideous, but also there's a few things that I don't like about the configuration.
It's confusing.
You can configure everything, but you can start a configuration and then right click
something in that and there's another configuration on top of it.
Well, they've explained the logic behind that, but yeah, I think it's like, well, people
expect it in both places, so we put it in both places.
I agree.
And I am watching the Plasma Next and Plasma 5 stuff to see like, what are they doing there?
Because Jen's in his team, like, what is their vision?
And I like where they're going with it.
I still, I think it's going to take, I think the next version of KDE is going to come out
in a big way.
They're going to try to keep it the same so that way they don't disrupt the Apple cart,
right?
They don't tip whatever the saying is.
But I wouldn't be surprised if once this next version of KDE is out and they consider it
sort of stabilized, if that's when they really start iterating on some of the more rougher
edges I think.
I think it's going to be a little bit.
You know what they could do?
They could add more options.
Yes, I can understand, I can understand why, you know, people use various desktops.
I can see why people use Gnome, Gnome Shell.
I can see why people like Elementary and Mate and Cinnamon.
The one that I just can't fathom is KDE.
I just can't figure out what psychology brings people to use KDE on a daily basis and like
it.
I mean, it's unfathomable.
Maybe you'll change your mind once all the Ubuntu apps are written in Qt and you're looking
for something that's a really solid Qt-based desktop.
Oh, I see what you've done there.
No, no, no, no.
KDE not equal to Qt, Qt not equal to KDE.
I do, I do.
All right.
Well, look.
You trolley monster.
I'm sorry.
Look, before we move on, I should probably thank our first sponsor.
I wanted to talk about, did you guys hear there's huge, huge, huge news for CoreOS?
Huge news.
Like we were just, it's probably because they were on our show.
That's the only thing I can figure.
It's gotta be because they're on our show, but I don't know.
But first, let's take a little break and thank our first sponsor this week and that is the
great folks over at DigitalOcean.
Now, what the heck is DigitalOcean, my friends?
I will tell you DigitalOcean is simple cloud hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way to spin up a cloud server.
And most of you guys could probably get started in about 55 seconds, but if you're a pro and
I'm not trying to challenge you, I'm not trying to say, hey, it's the 4th of July, go have
a few drinks and then go spin up as many droplets as you can as fast as possible.
But if you were to infer that from this spot, I would understand.
But most people create a droplet in about 55 seconds and pricing plans start only $5
per month.
And that's what I've been using for months and months and months now.
And here's what you get for $5 a month, 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one blazing
fast CPU and a terabyte of transfer.
And DigitalOcean has data center locations all around the world, New York, San Francisco,
Singapore and Amsterdam, tier one bandwidth in those locations and amazing hardware providers.
All of this connected to SSD drives running on top of KVM with their incredible control
panel.
Their interface is simple.
Their control panel has got to be one of the most intuitive experiences I've ever used.
And the best part is, is power users can really get at that with their straightforward API.
And they have a great development community and there's tutorials that help you get set
up with things like GitLab and there's one click deployment for a lot of great applications
that I know our community uses the heck out of.
You can create a droplet in less than a minute.
You can do backups.
You can do transfers.
You can set up the perfect Linux server and then template that and then deploy that Linux
server whenever you need it again.
And DigitalOcean has hourly pricing, so if you want to take advantage of our special
promo code, you can get a $10 credit or use that for the hourly pricing.
Use the promo code.
Now it's probably going to be changing because it's July now.
I haven't gotten the official new one, but it'll probably be Unplugged July.
If I was a gambling man, I would say Unplugged July.
Unplugged June will still work too, of course, if you're listening to this right as we're
changing over.
But use the promo code Unplugged July.
That lets them know that you appreciate them supporting the Linux Unplugged show.
You want them to keep sponsoring.
That way that keeps us on the air, but it also gets you that $10 credit so you can try
out what I've been talking about for so long now and see how amazing it is to get your
own server that you have root control over up in the cloud connected to tier one bandwidth
sitting on top of SSD drives powered by KVM.
I mean really, DigitalOcean.com, and a really big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
Linux Unplugged.
I tell you what, Matt, I'm starting to feel a little bit like I have short timers.
Even though I'm only going to a cabin for two nights, as soon as this show's done, I'm
hitting the road.
I'm out of here.
I'm going.
You're packed.
You're like Fred Flintstone going down the road.
Totally.
Okay.
Check out the great news for CoreOS.
They just got eight million dollars in funding.
Eight million dollars.
So CoreOS, you guys know, we've just had them recently on the show.
We did a review of it as well.
They're the company that makes this, well now they're a company, that makes a scalable
version of Linux custom tailored for servers.
They just raised eight million dollars in a Series A funding round.
It's now offering support services for companies.
That's going to be their business model.
They call it a new commercial help service called CoreOS Managed Linux, which the company
describes as an OS as a service offering and they provide organizations with constant patches
and updates in case they don't want the responsibility, so they're going to manage that for you.
Sounds familiar.
And they're promising to help reduce the admin work for people deploying CoreOS.
The monthly charge will range from anywhere, forget this.
This is for companies that have big deployments.
Monthly charge ranges anywhere from a thousand to a hundred thousand dollars.
Wow.
For monthly.
That's a good business.
And so when Pulvey was asked about like who's your competitor here because this has got
to be a hot space, he says well one of them for sure is Red Hat.
Red Hat's project Atomic is a direct response to CoreOS he said.
And of course CoreOS relies heavily on Docker who's been working closely with Red Hat.
And of course Ubuntu and others too.
Huge news for CoreOS though, huge.
Eight million dollars for a Linux distro?
It's got to be because we just had them on the show, right?
Absolutely.
Clearly.
The last bump.
It was totally.
Yeah.
Oh you know what, hey here's another last bump.
I'm kidding of course but the creator project announced that they just didn't really announce
it.
They just reached their funding.
This is the really nice, really nice illustrator program for that KDE desktop that Pulvey loves
so much.
They just reached their goal of $15,000 in funding and they still have eight days to
go too.
So now if you want to back a winner you can.
And this is really one of the greatest open source desktop applications out there for
people who are artsy fartsy.
And yeah there's GIMP and yeah there's Inkscape.
This is something unique, something different.
And congratulations to them.
Again the last bump I'm sure, I'm sure.
And responding to pressure from the Linux action show OwnCloud 7 we've gotten more details
on the server to server syncing.
I remember I said on last, I'd love to get more details on how OwnCloud 7 is doing the
server to server syncing.
We got some details.
So I thought I'd give you guys an update on that too because to me this is the coolest
feature of OwnCloud 7.
So the server to server sharing allows you to mount a share from another OwnCloud instance
and seamlessly collaborate on shared files from within each of your own OwnCloud instances.
Essentially combining your private clouds into one single public cloud between you two.
You can even have the folder locally synced to a client like through the OwnCloud client
sync.
No need to create accounts on your other instances.
Just once it's all shared up you can connect to each other's own cloud.
They use the example of a class.
You can have your classmates connect to your own cloud server, send them a shared folder
link the usual way.
Instead of them having to visit your own cloud each time and log in, they can opt to click
to save to OwnCloud button and add a folder to their own OwnCloud instance.
And then they can add this folder to the list of locally synced folders and it will sync
between your own cloud instances as if it was on their own own cloud server.
Oh cool.
Right?
Yeah.
That sounds nice.
That's freaking awesome.
Yeah.
I mean they talk about performance improvements.
They talk about server to server syncing.
I am digging that.
I am thinking OwnCloud 7 is the one that this might be the time I switch.
I cannot wait to load it up into.
Clearly I'm spinning up another droplet.
I mean I think that's been settled.
There you go.
Right there right?
Yeah it could.
I've been thinking you know I've been really trying to figure out like photos for my wife
and I and music and then moving them between the two locations.
It's not as easy as it should be.
And there's not like there's like you could do BitTorrent sync but then you have to we
have to run individual you have to configure each client application on each machine.
So like let's say I'm using Rhythmbox I have to scan that BitTorrent sync folder and add
it as a library on every machine and the metadata might be tracked differently or the podcast
or whatever it is right.
It's just not very smooth but the promise of OwnCloud where it could it could offer
that one central library for you know even if it was just for business contacts and business
events and things like that that sounds extremely compelling and essentially what I use the
Google Apps for right now.
And then if it does file sync on top of that gets us off Dropbox for some of our fixed
assets because we have like a lot of our art and fixed visuals in Dropbox because it's
just so easy to deploy Dropbox and have it sync up on the production machines.
But if OwnCloud offers something there too it might solve a few problems.
I'm really excited about it.
And I wonder too like if there wouldn't be a bit of a contracting business and going
around and saying hello this is Chris's OwnCloud installation and would you like an internet
that actually works for you and offers file sync and gets your staff off of Dropbox.
Let me introduce you to my OwnCloud installation package for only a thousand dollars I'll deploy
OwnCloud for you and get all your users migrated off of Dropbox.
Like that could actually be like a legitimate thing people go around and make money off
of because OwnCloud is getting serious.
And then if you offer like server sync that's a perfect solution for businesses to have
a few offices.
A small business has one or two offices OwnCloud sync between them.
Money maker.
I mean like especially when you think about like dental offices, real estate offices,
anything that especially when you're dealing with the at home people as well as at work
people multiple offices.
Yeah there's a lot of opportunity there.
Yeah you know very much so I mean I'm thinking very much of my workflow but I could easily
see like a you know a small business owner that wants a sync of the most vital documents
and things like that at their own house for backup right.
I mean that seems legit.
So it sounds like a good option for a couple clients I have that it can save a lot of effort
for me as well.
The other thing so OwnCloud right now is I'm going to look at for my for my all inclusive
sync solution and then the other one I got experiment more with is sync thing.
I've played with it a little bit.
The thing I not love about sync thing is you have to authorize each device you're going
to sync with.
So distributing things like podcast files you know I can't authorize every viewer out
there that wants to sync the Linux action show HD folder.
That's just that'd be crazy.
I'd be doing that all day long.
But so BitTorrent sync seems like that's still the go to thing for that.
It doesn't replace sync thing in the terms of like content distribution.
So then if I'm going to be running an instance of BitTorrent sync anyways should I just go
all in on that and just simplify my life instead of running BitTorrent sync and OwnCloud or
BitTorrent sync and sync thing.
I got too many sync options.
So I'll figure it out eventually and then we'll make an episode out of it.
Solve two problems with what you know just boom two birds one stone that hey speaking
of solving problems let me tell you about our next sponsor and then we'll get into the
community announcement the Jupiter review panel but first let me tell you about the
great Canadians over at ting.com go to linux.ting.com why because it's linux.ting.com own that
URL that is ours let's represent the Linux users at ting now here's really why you want
to switch to ting no contract no early termination fee and you only pay for what you actually
use you don't pay into some big contract where you have to kind of guesstimate how many minutes
and how much data you might use and how many text messages you might send you just pay
for what you use and it was interesting on tech talk today I had an email from a cellular
wireless engineer and he's like the ting model from the perspective of a person who builds
and maintains these networks is the only model that makes sense long term it's the only one
that can work and I feel like I am living a bit in the future when I use ting because
it's all the things I need in a cellular service my data is there I have hotspot and tethering
included I get the pick of some of the greatest Android devices and iOS devices and or just
feature phones all available through ting it's a flat six dollars per month then just
my usage build on top of that all managed through an incredibly easy to use dashboard
but also provides real insights and this is a big thing for me these dashboards this is
2014 there is no excuse for the dashboards that some of these cell companies use they
are just trash and the great thing about ting is they also support industry standards too
so they works well on mobile works well on your desktop they also have featured like
integration with Amazon payments to pay for your cell phone bill which is a really nice
feature and it kind of shows you how ting is hip to a lot of these types of technologies
and it's refreshing it's one of the things I appreciate the most and that's why I actively
follow the ting blog because there's always good information even if you're not a ting
subscriber on the ting blog and it's always worth checking out over there because they've
often post videos that are behind the scenes it's fun to see the ting crew get insights
into how the company operates and check out their devices too because when you go to linux.ting.com
they're gonna take $25 off your first device if you've already got a device they'll take
$25 off your ting service I paid for more than my first month now I've got two phones
on my ting program and it's barely cracking $30 a month because we're really conscious
about how we do it we're on Wi-Fi a ton we use Viber and Skype for our phone calls and
the little bitsies that we do use phone calls for we just pay for when we use it I love
it it's just worked so well for me linux.ting.com take $25 off your first device get or $25
credit and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring linux unplugged okay so this is a fun initiative
that the production team's been wanting to do for a while it not only is it a way for
us to sort of increase the distributions that we cover and give attention to maybe some
of the smaller ones that we wouldn't normally want to load up and install just for like
a smaller distro but sometimes when you do that like you find a diamond in the rough
so we are announcing the Jupiter colony review draft and this is an initiative that will
eventually eventually establish a kind of a reoccurring group of folks but we're going
to kind of take baby steps at first rotten do you want to jump in here at this point
and kind of mention how we're going to launch this with the pre-selected group and why we're
doing it that way yeah so it's the first the first week we're going to do to make it easier
to kind of instead of having to vet everyone to join we're going to do a just a kind of
a testing purposes of getting people to just a pre-selection of a few people maybe like
a list less probably less than a dozen or so but just as many people as possible but
then we're going to have it where they can we come on to like a show to get everybody
does show together you get you just you play with the distro however you would normally
would take some things like that yet take some notes maybe even try to beat it beat
it up a little bit and see where you find some flaws and then we have a community discussion
about whether you know whether they say it's something that could be good for a new user
or just the bit the pros and cons of the distro itself yeah and do you want to go ahead and
announce the first one no go ahead i'll let you do it okay the first dish we're gonna
uh put in this little round table review thing is uh chaos yeah chaos has been on our list
for a while but we just haven't gotten to it so that'll be a good one for people to
give a go and uh yes yes yes yes it is it's considered a lean kde distribution at that
uh yes is that even possible wow in the sense of how many packages they allow in their system
so they only allow kde specific stuff and they have anything other than that they force
it off and they have that interesting design aesthetic as well which i've been interested
to try out so the idea here is uh we get a wide sampling of opinions on this you guys
can look at it and some folks will look at it from very technical aspects some people
look at it from the design aspect others will look at it from like a usability and things
like that we'll get a nice rounded set of opinions and then we can accumulate it into
sort of a concentrated review for the linux unplugged audience and honestly there's an
opportunity here down the road where if a few folks stood out as you know really solid
contributors maybe there'd be a role where you'd come on last and do dedicated review
segments of specific distribution so there's opportunity for expansion and growth here
but it's just something to start with for fun so embedded in the show notes we will
have the jupiter colony review draft if you would be interested in reviewing a distribution
for us we like rotten said we've already picked our first distribution and our first crew
so that way we just kind of get things rolling but after that we'll be pulling from our draft
list and you'll find that in the episode 47 show notes it'll be linked and embedded in
there and it's also it'll be in the irc chat room for those of you watching live so are
we going to do the review next week rotten yes next week okay so we'll have chaos on
the show yeah you know what's coming up down the road in fact i want to put the word out
there i'm thinking about on july 22nd i see well we have something already scheduled but
i on the production calendar but i'm thinking about potentially being live from oscon in
portland oregon on july 22nd so i want to put the word out there for the jupiter broadcasting
audience if there's folks out there who might be interested in meeting up at oscon on july
22nd that it's like that's a wednesday or no it's a tuesday so we and if it worked out
it'd be really fun to be able to do unplugged live from there so kind of putting a feeler
out there seeing what people think we were accepted at oscon as media so we could go
in there we'd have media badges we could do interviews and stuff like that so there's
some reasons to go down there but i'd really love to do it if we knew we're going to meet
up with some folks oh yeah all right rotten is there anything else we want to cover on
the community review the jupiter colony draft as it were um yeah the the draft is going
to be um it doesn't we first want to make sure people that if they're interested in
doing it they don't have to worry about having an extra computer or anything like that it's
just like kind of play with it you don't need to remove remove your existing distro or anything
like that so we're going to do something yeah it can be a virtual box like some things might
will provide a virtual box image to make it easier for people or other other times they
could just buy the i mean not buy but download the iso some things don't work very well in
virtual box so we figure that out on the way to go yeah it might be distribution dependent
yeah because like for example you can't really review a distribution like core os in virtual
box so there's some yeah we were bouncing it around we found some uh some people had
some questions about maybe um you know having a whether you should like run it all the week
or is it just something we can just kind of like jump in and play with and if that's enough
and essentially uh it's not you're not trying to ask people to just you know run live with
it in a week or anything just to kind of you know play play with it use it see if you can
break it kind of things yeah i mean it's really going to be results depending on what insights
the audience that member brings and if like then if they bring something that we're like
yeah that was a really great observation will you join us for the next review you know that's
the kind of system it's going to be where uh solid contributions will be noted and appreciated
and i love the idea too of then eventually establishing a pool of folks and saying okay
we're looking for everybody who has intel graphics because we want to try out this wayland
distribution you know or something like that because we if we built up a little pool we
could maybe do stuff that is a little bit harder for ourselves to do because maybe i
don't have a machine with dedicated intel graphics right so i couldn't do that review
of of something that runs mere or wayland uh but if we had a resource out there of folks
that wanted to participate and wanted to do these reviews you know essentially uh you
don't even have to have experience but if you've done blogging too you're probably a
great candidate if you've blogged a distro review uh and just it's something fun we want
to do i'm looking forward to it i think it could be a great idea i think it could be
a good way for matt and i discover a few distributions we hadn't really thought of trying before
and then you never know like maybe we'll take a look at it and end up switching maybe i
don't know i'm a little i'm a little skeptical yeah i don't know matt you seem skeptical
so anyways uh form is in the show notes if you guys want to fill that out uh also uh
just a little plugsies check out tech talk today um tomorrow's episode because i pre-recorded
because i'm going to a cabin tomorrow's episode is a retro look back at two operating systems
that almost dominated the market one of which i'm sure most of you've heard of one of which
i would bet most of you haven't heard of and it'll be surprising who was making it and
what it was based on so uh check out tech talk today it's a new show on the jupiter
broadcasting network a daily technology podcast where uh me and my closest mumble friends
discuss the tech news from perspectives of open source enthusiasts and linux users now
that doesn't necessarily mean that every story is a linux story but what it means is instead
of getting that typical silicon valley bias where it's very heavily google influenced
or apple influenced and linux and open source are very often not considered not part of
their perspective or not part of the discussion this has been something that we've talked
about on linux unplugged for a couple of episodes the quality of journalism especially those
coming at it from a linux perspective is pretty abysmal so uh one of the goals i have with
tech talk today is to have a platform for us to have discussions around the tech events
the tech news of the day and it's the stuff that actually is we're talking about you know
it's not just rattling off headlines it's things that are actually worth discussing
from a perspective of a linux user and i hope it's an i hope it's an interesting recipe
i'd like you guys to check it out episode 18 came out today we talked about microsoft
shutting down the no ip service which screwed a lot of jupiter broadcasting audience members
i saw a lot of complaints about that in the form or in the threads in a couple different
of our subreddits so we talked that's an issue we talked about in today's tech talk today
doesn't quite fit in linux unplugged or linux action show but it's an issue we could talk
about and then like i said tomorrow is the retrospective at the os's of futures past
and so i encourage you to check out tech talk today if you want more show but i think that's
everything we have for today i think we've gone through our list we kind of burned through
it pretty quick but i'm okay with that because that means i get to wrap up and head out to
a cabin so i'm not gonna complain man if you if you get my drift and it is hot i tell you
what i was gonna say oh it is hot off a costco thing of water in the back oh yeah oh i got
a big thing of water but i could use another one jeez louise i'll tell you what so all
right well thanks everybody for joining us on this week's episode of linux unplugged
you know linux unplugged is a great show to join us live because you can participate in
the mumble room you can participate in our chat room you get to help name the show just
join us won't you go over to jblive.tv we do it at 2 p.m pacific on a tuesday jblive.tv
jblive.info for the audio stream jupitabroadcasting.com calendar to have our robots convert that into
your time zone that's what you got to do you just show up live and rock it and uh take
part in our virtual lug we really like that and don't forget we also want your feedback
over to jupitabroadcasting.com contact and choose linux unplugged from the drop down
all right matt well i'll see you on sunday all right sir i'll see you then all right
everyone thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of linux unplugged see you right back
here next tuesday