You got something you want to hide or you just want to be a baller like this is it silk Guardian is an anti-forensic
LKM kill switch that waits for a change on your USB ports and
Then wipes your RAM and turns off your computer very much inspired by USB kill
I made this project because I feel that it could be implemented better than already is so you make it you build it
Three reasons why this project exists in case the po-po or other thugs come busting in I like that police are the first threat
You know this guy must be a US citizen
You don't want someone to retrieve documents from your computer via USB. That's true
Or installs on my back doors. Yeah, you don't want malware or back doors
You want to improve the security of your full disk encrypted home computer or server like maybe a Raspberry Pi actually that last one's kind
Of legit yeah, so there you go if you want to just destroy your machine in one go silk Guardian
I like that idea doesn't wipe the drive though. It just wipes the RAM, but I'm sure you could
Customize heck yeah, you could heck yeah, you could I think that I think that could be that could be brilliant
This is Linux unplugged episode
133 for February 23rd
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that might just be swimming in laptops
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello there Wes. Guess what we got a great show. Yes, we do
I'm really really looking forward to today's episode a
We're gonna have a chance to talk about something that everybody else in the press is talking about everybody
But they're getting it all wrong. They're getting it all wrong
We're gonna talk about the big quote-unquote mint hack the ISO breach
That has been getting a lot of attention since Linux action show on Sunday
Then later on in the show. I am very excited to share my first hands-on impressions with intro airs
Apollo laptop I
West you can attest to this the first thing I do when I see people's I shove it in their hands
Oh, yes, that's right. You didn't even have your bag set down yet
Give me your impressions I have in the
24 hours that I have had this laptop in my possession
I've been going around getting people's opinions asking them what they think I've got my opinions
I've set up my desktop the way. I like it. I'm gonna give you my first thoughts on
Their ultimate Linux laptop, so that's gonna be an interesting comparison from last week's episode
So we're gonna talk about the mint stuff. We also have a whole bunch of follow-ups including some ZFS things that are actually
pretty exciting a little bit of bumpy news for Ubuntu touches new fancy phone and
many other good things including
including some fun news from the community
So why don't we start there let's bring in that community time appropriate greetings virtual log
Okay, so we have a pretty good showing today
And I know some of you already drinking your beers in there
I want to be I want to first I want to welcome Graham because he made me think of this you reminded me Graham from
Linux voice and from a kick Kickstarter project. We're about to cover Graham welcome to Linux unplugged. Thank you very much
Thanks for having me so tell me about the beer you're drinking on the show today. Um it's a it's a local beer
It's from bath. I'm in Wiltshire in the UK and it used to be called barnstormer
Until they were sued by a company in the US who made a cider even with the beer with the same name
So it's now called Barnsley
Yeah, I still call it barnstormer in the pub. You know that is funny
It's pretty that's pretty appropriate because Wes and I are also drinking a local beer from Washington State where we're based out of called whistling
pig
It's a half of Ison. So yeah, I like it. Ours has got a 4.4 or 5.4 percent alcohol by volume
It's kind of avoid the litigation. I guess with that name. Yeah, right
They have and it says the Northwest original German style craft burr kind of a confused name. I think yeah
That's what it says there, but the Northwest original since 1992 folks. That's like saying you haven't heard
Shakespeare until you've heard in the original Klingon
It is but it's not a bad beer Washington to reinvent the traditional German style. Yeah
Exactly. So, okay. Well Graham, let's get started with something kind of exciting that you guys have going on because it's really we should give
It some attention right away. It's only got a few days left and it's getting close to the finish line. It's beep beep
Yar, what is this?
So, yeah, so we make a magazine we actually crowdfunded at the next magazine and over the last couple of years that we've been doing this
We really wanted to try and experiment with other things we can because we kind of do this on our own
One of the things we always wanted to do was write books for children
I've got kids a couple of us have got kids and I know this has become a bit of a thing now
But we still don't think that anybody's really tackled made computing fun and programming fun. And so we
Kick-started trying to kick-start a project to make a book that hopefully makes programming fun. The book is actually story-driven
It's got pirates and robots in it
and we hope to inadvertently secretly kind of insert bits of
programming law in there without the kids actually having to do any programming in the book itself a little brainwashing is never a bad thing I
In fact, I really love the video. I'm gonna play just a minute of it because I believe it's your daughter
Here's the super cute and I think the best person to introduce this idea is my eight-year-old daughter Eden
This is grace and this is Alan grace and Alan are just like my best friends. They love to learn
They like to push themselves and do cool things and they aren't afraid to try anything new
This is really cool. And I also you know, I remember I was pretty lucky
I when I was young ish, I had a book called how computers work and it was did you ever saw these but it was
Really well illustrated books that helps you break it down visually and just having something that was sort of approachable
That when I did have a little bit of curiosity
Helped me kind of take it further tips, too
Well, that's it. I I had those books with the source code and you remember they were like in the 80s
That's where you're gonna get it from of course
Was that was that input magazine by any chance I
Had a cool news. I had them as my barcode you could scan in with a barcode reader
That's pretty cool
Well, so we got we got just a few days left five days left on the Kickstarter looking for a pledge of total of
28,684 us greenbacks and currently at
16,903 us so if you guys want to check it out go look for bpbr
We'll have a link in the show notes, too
so
Graham anything else we should know about the the effort here
so is this gonna run kind of in long side the same sort of the same production team as Linux voice and sort of
Or since that's sort of like a sub project. How's exactly sort of situated? Well part of part of the money that
We're all really so busy making the magazine part of the money from the kick-starting campaign
But actually go to help us commission out more stuff for the magazine to give us some time to do the book
we're also going to do an interactive part to it so that at the end of each chapter you can actually
With your child if you want to go online and type in bits of code and kind of experiment with the characters in the book
To kind of augment the story in that way
Yeah, the idea is I mean the thing is that print publishing of magazines
It's it's pretty it's a pretty static business and in a way
We're trying to safeguard and kind of look into broaden our horizons a little bit as well. So we thought we'd give it a go
Well, best of luck to you and like you say at the bottom. It's not necessarily just for kids. No
Secretly secretly, it's my fantasy pirates and robots. Yeah, it's a good one
And with a little bit of a software ideology in there. I think it's pretty good
Well, best of luck and hopefully guys go check it out
Thanks. So Graham, you're absolutely welcome to stick around and chat with us during the rest of the show
I had something I wanted to talk about. I saw wimpy on Google Plus saying there's a mutiny afoot
For Ubuntu 1604 and it's it's wimpy now makes news
Apparently when he posts on Google Plus because pretty soon news outlets picked it up and covered mutiny the new unity style desktop layout for Ubuntu
1604 and then I very quickly noticed wimpy take to g-plus trying to make sure everybody understood it wasn't gonna be mandatory
It was just an option. So what is mutiny wimpy?
It's another user interface layout for Ubuntu. Okay, so those of you that been following the project main map may already know that you can
One-click to augment the user interface to look like Windows or Mac OS 10 and
Now we've added a look and feel that is a poor facsimile of unity
It's a functional facsimile. Yeah. Yeah, it does. It does work. Yeah
So it has it has the global the global menu and you have the dock down the side
And it kind of looks and works like unity
But really it's there to sort of showcase some of the new components that have been introduced into Ubuntu
Marte which are there for anyone to use in their panels to create a user interface that suits them
So that global menu can be put on any panel anywhere you'd like
I don't down the side is just an applet that can go into any panel so it can go top bottom left, right
You know, you can align it how you'd like and you can so that whole side panel is an applet
But the panel is a panel and then that the top right the icons are a big happening out there
Yeah, that's that's all in an applet. Okay, the Marte doc applet made by Robin Thompson
He started that about
6-9 months ago and I've been talking with him and I'm actually really pleased. He's at he's actually
Developing within the Ubuntu Marte team now. So whilst we're talking I can see a telegram group going with the Ubuntu Marte
Developers and they're they're feverishly
Working on on new stuff. So yes, it's worked really well and and I like the backdrop as well. Yes
I like that a lot to backdrop from one of the other developers
Yes, I like that a lot to backdrop from one of the Google Plus community members some ghost
67 and he's got a good YouTube channel as well with
distro reviews and insights
So I have had some additional time with Ubuntu Mate
1510 that shipped on the Apollo and I you know every time I use it every single time there
There are just like to this time around it was the fact that VLC was preset up installed as the default audio player
like, you know, it's just
There when I here's the difference for me between Ubuntu Mate and Ubuntu
Legitimately when I'm installing Ubuntu standard 1510 or 1604
It takes me like if I get a machine with Ubuntu 1604 on it
It takes me less time to wipe it and install anti-gross and then from the command line using your word
Install everything I need with one command
It takes me less time to do all of that than it does to set up the Ubuntu installation not the case
with with Ubuntu Mate and it's some of its because of mate tweak Mate tweak and
And you know some of its like the predefined looks that wimpy has or that, you know, the team has put together and
Yeah, it's it is a real feels like a tool
It whatever you want to use it
You just some of the things I just have to do already like for another example is install G
Debye the the graphical G Debye package installer when you download Debs
That's just the best way to install a deb if you want to gooey and it's already set up on a boot to Mate edition
So things like that are always really nice. So 1604
It is looking like a great release
And so I I kind of had a question about this isn't isn't elementary OS also working on a 1604 based
Release and how the hell do you get your hands on something like that? I
Guess there is a way there's instructions for the odd on launchpad to build the Loki ISO
But I think you need to have elementary OS already installed. So if anybody out in the chat room
We're out in the community is up for making me a Loki beta ISO so I could try it out. That would be fun
Yeah, I'm curious to see where they're going to because I haven't checked them out for what I've been thinking a lot about the elementary
OS project recently, right and they're just taking over Geary and yeah, they just took over Geary and have Pantheon mail now
they announced that this week and
I think part of it is because my son has
Been using elementary OS for almost a year now and it's really been flawless
Wow, and I just sat down and used his computer to set up
Some some minecraft mod manager. I can't remember what it's called now and you know, it was just a it's just a clean simple experience
I just I think
I
Don't know. I feel like
Maybe maybe it's worth another look. I've been I've been following on 1604 hotness
Yeah
So if somebody out there want to make me an ISO because they if they have elementary OS installed and follow the instructions
I'd be curious because I don't have elementary
installed speaking of some of our favorite distros just a real quick shout out to Antigros Antegoros and
What what do you say Wes? Hmm Antigros? Yeah, let's go with Antigros. Guess what Wes ZFS support out of the box
Whoa install they've redone their installer a whole bunch of new stuff. They're moving this over to stable
Wow, look at all those downloads who 52,000 384 downloads for since she's 0.12
It's interesting how they're almost focusing more on the installer than they are the distro itself
Since she's 0.14 development 148 days of developments 510 commits
46 bugs squashed look at the new installer there Wow
0.16 is looking real smooth and one of the new features is built-in ZFS support
You can install now
with ZFS work. Go ahead
Antegos is
Basically 90% essentially installer anyway. Yeah, I really it's good. Yeah, it really is
That's why I think it's actually kind of smart that they do this because otherwise it's essentially arch
Yeah, so I don't know I think that's pretty neat so they've obviously moved after Ubuntu made the news
But they must have been working on this already. Yeah, I would I would think so at least yeah, so this is cool
I think we're gonna have it you're gonna have in 1604
Which I guess would mean that Ubuntu Mate 1604 is gonna have ZFS support too
When is that gonna be available to me in any way if I do a installation?
What ZFS on Ubuntu Mate on the 1604 version?
Yeah, in just the same way it will be available on any Ubuntu flavor
All of the ZFS stuff is gonna be in the official archives, but that's not in the installer though, right? I don't think it's going to be in
Ubiquity now at least I've seen no evidence of that so far. Yeah, and we're in feature freeze now
so unless they do a feature freeze exception, I don't know but
I imagine it. Well, I don't know. Yeah, are you feeling good?
Maybe maybe if you use the minimal ISO, you know, you'd have to do a bit of fiddling you could use the minimal ISO
You know install that on the ZFS and then yeah install the right package for the desktop of your choice
I'm not thinking it's time to move your root file system over to ZFS
You could maybe make the argument for home or like a data partition, which you would set up maybe after installation anyways
But after your root partition or boot even
I'm not sure I'm ready to make that case yet. And if you are
You're gonna set up manually yourself. I'm not sure grub supports ZFS. So I don't think it could be used as um
Well, I guess you could just fun. He's a BSD has even better
Just fine. I've been using it for a long time. Oh, it does. How long is a long time?
I've been using it for two years at least a really well like a git version of like I like a fortune
Oh, yeah. Yeah. No. No, you definitely use a git version of grub, but you probably already are because
Yeah
That's true most distros are using a git check out
The question is does it support all the new features if you use less features than the latest you're probably okay
But if you're using a new grub, you're okay regardless. They support all the ZFS features
So are you saying you've been you've been booting off ZFS for two years?
Yes
Well, there you go. Even with slash boot even slash boot on ZFS
Oh, really and and how do you feel like performance overhead is for something like that? It's not bad. I
Wouldn't say you really notice very much. I mean I have a lot of RAM on my machines, so I'm not yeah
Okay. Well see that's that's me. That's interesting to me. That is interesting
And I know their work. They've just recently started working on it on BSD
So that's why I just didn't feel like I had a lot of testing right and it's another level if you expect any user
Who can use the installer to understand the file system?
So I feel like there's an argument there even if it works great. Yeah, huh? Well, look at that everybody
It's it's interesting 16 is the future. Yeah, it's the year of the Linux desktop
It is just depends on who you ask and what what desktop they're using. Yeah, I'm curious
I'm curious to see where elementary OS is going. I want to try that out
What what I agree with the kernel panic here computers have plenty of memory and CPU cycles. Yeah, that's well
I don't know. I don't know if I agree I could always use more
You know what else I could always use more of a good deal everybody do me a favor
Go check out ting linux ting comms the first sponsor this week
This is mobile. That really does make sense. In fact if
Aliens came to earth
They would look at all the other guys and they'd be like what the hell is the matter with you?
What are you doing? Why are you doing it that way?
And then they'd look at ting and go okay, and it's not just Kyra. They'd look at ting and they go
Oh that makes sense. That's how you should do it ting keeps rates simple
We don't make you pick a plan instead. You just use your phone as you normally would how much you use
Determines how much you pay each month. You can have as many devices as you want on one account
That's good
Because when you use more you pay less per minute message or megabyte of data
Your usage plus six dollars per active device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill
Simple that's what we mean when we say
Mobile that makes sense. So not only can you save earth from an alien invasion because they're pissed off about our mobile practices
By going to linux.ting.com, but you get $25 off a device
You get $25 in service credits if you have a compatible device and they have GSM and CDMA
So you just might moto II second-gen 99 bucks unlocked. No contract. Yeah
Yeah, they also have the tribute to which is a nice LG phone running Android. They got the Apple Internet phones
You know if you want to fight the FBI about those before. Yeah, here's a good one
I think this is like this this is this is the one I think I mean if you don't need like the
S6 or s7 or you don't need a nexus because they got the nexus is too. Yep
LG volt to 5-inch display tri-band LTE lollipop 5.1 show probably get an upgrade though
Yeah, but look at that's a nice phone. Of course lollipops not bad really 183 dollars. No contract nor the termination fee. That's nuts
LG's nexus 5 the og nexus 5 still in my pocket 215 bucks. Wow
Yeah, I know that's a really great phone still that is a really great phone the aqueous crystal
That's pretty nice the one plus one 290 or yeah 299 unlocked moto x they got all the great phones, right?
And they also have just the sim cards go over to linux.ting.com to support the show and while you're there
Do the savings calculator. That's fun. Do the same. Oh, yeah, kits and points. Yeah, that's a nice phone
Kitson points out that you could put cyanogen on that. That's true
You could put cyanogen on that volt shoot puts put cyanogen on that
You know ting has a really great community on reddit on their forums
They post YouTube videos where you can interact with them
The reason I bring this up is they're not gonna shame you if you want to put a some weird thing on your phone
Like they just want you to use their network and you know be a customer
I they won't not give you support because you did something different
No, I was straight up when I was trying out a boon to touch on ting. I was straight up honest with them
Yeah, I'm running a boon to touch and they're like, oh, that's awesome
Will you give us feedback on how that works on a network because we're watching that that was their response not
That's not an authorized phone operating system
But you're on violation of your terms of service like that's what they could have said, right?
No, they didn't say that linux.ting.com go there
Support the show and a big. Thank you to ting for sponsoring the Linux unplugged show
speaking of mobile devices
Mobile World Congress. Yeah, right now I'm not going on
This talks about it's the only thing in
In Barcelona, they have a fancy new phone over there at the Ubuntu booth that people have been checking out
I've been watching some videos of hands-on demos of it
And in fact, I posted in the chat room. I should probably go grab it real quick
But anyways people been looking at this new Mizzou Pro 5 and the verse says
Not good enough the verge talks about it being laggy the verge talks about it not responding to some interfaces
There's a good hardware design they say but they're worried that it's just too darn laggy
And I I think for you and I West that's kind of a big deal. Don't you think?
Your thoughts after you read something like this is
Is this just an issue because it's a pre-release phone or do you think this is something on a bigger picture level?
I don't know
It's hard to say I think I think there is a lot with the pre-release that you know
The fact that it runs that you've still got who punt you you've got you know
Real Linux right there on the phone a good-looking phone. The hardware looks nice. Yes. I think that's a lot
The hardware looks very nice and I'm gonna say Samsung's it's got one of Samsung's nice processors
Any know like a really good processor, right? It's got a really good camera in it
And I do think that there's probably a significant amount of you know
Optimization for touch for quick response times rather than throughput kind of stuff that you see especially on real Linux
So I'm sure there's a lot of tunables. I'm hopeful
Probably really curious to see when you know the final production models roll out
All right
So here's what I'm really looking forward to and this is where I'm willing to give it some
I mean, I'm really really sensitive to lag but XTA developers have a video of convergence in action
Here we go actual real-world original stuff from Ubuntu phone
It's getting better. It's getting more refined, but that's not the exciting thing. I'm going to show you the exciting thing
I'm going to show you is convergence. We've now connected the phone to a monitor and it's automatically switched into windowed mode
So we've got the full Ubuntu desktop here
One of the new things we've got is the switcher. So I push into the right edge
And I can select an application and here you see Libre office
And this is running so any app that can run on Linux
Will run on this well arm Linux
Another nice feature we have is when you switch from phone onto the desktop a hundred percent of status preserved
That's kind of nice right that's really nice
No, I want that right now that sort of changes my opinion on it a little bit
I know anybody in the chat room have any thoughts on Ubuntu touch or is actually using it right now
I'd love to hear from somebody who's been actively on it. I know wouldn't be weren't you trying it for a bit? I
Yeah, I've been using it for a while and
Later this year. I'm gonna
Have an extended period period where Ubuntu for devices is the only thing I use
So the verge really really panned the experience the verge seemed very dissatisfied in the article
They published today from Mobile World Congress. Do you have any kind of was that to do with them they?
the
Into user interface and the phone operating system or more the hardware. Well, I
You know, I mean it's on this. It's on this mu as profile that it has the snapdragon processor in it
You know, it's supposed to be pretty good hardware
Yeah, I don't know I don't know if they're Apple buys or not and when the last meizu device
Shipped with Ubuntu it
It
Took a couple of revs to iron out, you know, some of the kinks they I seem to have had some difficulty
You know getting all working smoothly. So maybe it's just you know, yeah
Yeah, and my accident in the Mamba room. You've been running it for a bit. What are your impressions?
I've been playing around with it. I've been trying to
trying to get it in a state where it does all things I'm doing with Android and I find
The the I really like the system and I really like the the sort of I don't want to use the word paradigms
Because it sounds rubbish
But you know the the the style they're going for with the swiping from the edges and and the general feel of the system
I really like it. But when I come to try and use the apps, I find that there's you know
If they're just not mature like the ones I'm using on Android are that's where it really falls down for me at the moment
I don't have the features which I just think oh
a pod catcher will have this or an audio book player will have this and then I go looking for them and
There's just they're missing that that feature that I use all the time
So this chicken and egg problem for sure and the mu s5 pro looks really really nice
Like I think it even has like a super high-end. I even be 20 something megapixel camera. I got really high-end camera
USB-c charging there. It looks like is that USB-c or mini? It looks like you
Use to be see it kind of looks like an iPhone to be honest. Yes, it does. It does but
Linux on your iPhone. Hey, that doesn't sound bad wide power button on the side
Oh, wow, look they have actually have it right there next to an iPhone
Yeah, so
Yeah, we'll see huh? We'll say meizu meizu not my zoo meizu. Thank you. Oh
Yes, wimpy. Tell me about the UK that you that is right the UI usability study that we'd mentioned you ended up participating in it
Do you have anything to share about that?
Well, yes, I was actually the first person to
Participate in that
Usability. Wow, that was a week and a half ago. I think I was there
So I'm not gonna go into too much detail because I'd be stealing show content from upcoming Ubuntu podcast
But I suppose I suppose the thing to take away from that is that
they are actually looking at the user experience of the phone and
The applications and not just the core apps that are being developed by canonical
But also some of the community contributed apps. So there is an effort to you know, try and
improve
the the
User experience across the board and did you say would you say why you were there that you witnessed?
Somebody giving pushback saying this doesn't make sense and then being receptive to that pushback
Absolutely. Oh, that's good to hear. Okay, you know, that's that goes a long way and then they can also say, you know
We've tested this
Speaking of testing
Wow, 100 million users are testing the hell out of telegram and I bring this up on Linux unplugged because
The secret is this is like one of the number one messaging apps now on Linux
Mm-hmm is telegram freaking telegram and you were looking at at a telegram alternative. Do you remember what that was called?
It was like an open source. I think you put it probably in our message thread. I believe I did they say check this out
Telegram now has 100 million monthly active users
350,000 news your sign up each freaking day and they are delivering
15 billion messages Wow daily 15 billion. That is that is really nuts
Yeah, and and it really has undoubtedly become one of the largest one of the largest Linux messaging programs
Did you find it there with just about it waiting for slack? Oh, jeez
That's what you get for not using matter most West
I know after that big that low latency maybe on some sort of server that do you think it would you think it would be
Faster is that is that a thing because you know, I could always use faster
That is something I could take
So anyways West had found a project that looks like it may have some relation to actor. I am actor
Yes, okay actor. I am and it looks like what West this has some relation to the telegram folks
Yeah, I believe it's being worked on at least by some people formerly associated with the telegram project
It's free secure photo and voice messages all under an Apache 2 license and they're talking about it
I believe so I have not verified that myself and they're talking about integrating signals protocol
Which I know a lot of people have spoken good things about it looks just like telegram. It really does
Huh, that's interesting
So if it has the same performance and maybe a better or more open back end
That would be interesting because one of my favorite things about telegram is it really just works. The question is is what?
what
Encryption. Yes, are they using daredevil and you know a quick trick to see how many users are actively on telegram at any given time
What's that? I
Don't hear you I do not sorry. Yes
Yes
The trick the trick is they use in at least an Android phones
They use the accounts and when you're going to your contacts app and you're going to export your contacts
It shows telegram as an option even though it will not export them
It will show the number of actual users registered in telegram. Yeah. Oh, ah
Interesting good catch. I also by the way just one more thing before we get off the telegram topic
I gave a quick mention during last that I was impressed that the linux mint project was communicating
Via the tub, there's a there's a group I subscribe to on telegram with security alert notifications
And I thought maybe I'd share that with the rest of you since I've gotten some questions about hey
What group did you subscribe to to to get those those alerts?
So let's see. It's a if you go to telegram me slash it sec alert
this subscribes you to a telegram group that is essentially a read-only group of
Well IT security alerts Wow, so like when Linux make got hacked
This was one of the first place and since then there's been like 18 other projects that have been hacked and there's been a notification
That's been posted on this telegram group. And so it's kind of a neat thing. I'll put a link in the chat room
And so this was one of the ways I found out about Linux mint being hacked over the weekend was by this group again
That's telegram me slash it sec alert and you know what? I'll throw a link in the show notes, too
So that way if you guys you guys want to cover that mumble or many other thoughts on the telegram or open source chat or secure
chat before we move on I
Just hope they finally get the back end free software, too
Yeah
That would be the big difference if actor has the the full client is open source like the back end is there they have a server
Pulled her in there. I like that. I like that. I think that's a good thing
Yeah
Yeah, yes, we did EKS we did EKS just joins the chat room. Hold on. Hold on just for EKS standby. I'm standby. This is
Yes
EKS we have reported that Anna gross is integrating ZFS in their installer but just reconfirming if you're just joining us live now on
The jblive.tv stream. It has been confirmed ZFS support has been added
Knowing Chris he will be reinstalling his machine right before the show next week
That's so stay tuned that is very possible. All right, so Linux mint
They got compromised over the weekend Clem took to the Linux mint blog and said hey
I've shut down the servers where this is happening at. Oh, by the way
Clem you're also your forum server god. Oh, okay. I'm gonna shut that server down. Okay now we have shut this server down
Oh, yeah, they replaced the MD five sums. Don't pay attention to the MD five sums. You download use these MD five sums. Oh
Boy, this just started getting out of control and shortly after that you started seeing everybody talking about it by Sunday afternoon
Everybody was talking about it. Uncle Leo was talking about it on Twitter
Oh dear Leo ed bot was taking shots at mint
Exaggerating the scope of the flaws ZD net got an exclusive interview with the attacker
And got all the details. We're gonna talk about all of that
And and we're not gonna sit here and rub Linux mint in the ground
It's more about it's really more about the meta discussion that needs to happen here
And maybe maybe towards the end if we could bring the discussion to a place and say where we can maybe answer the question
What could be done as a community to solve the problem of verifying the source and identity of an ISO?
And I know there's a lot of different ways we can accomplish this you can have you can have lots of different signatures
You can have there's MD five sums today all these things exist. But what if there was?
Maybe something centralized maybe it's distributed like through a blockchain some way to verify the identity identity of files
That was reliable and distributed. Oh, man, that could be pretty cool. So let's start talking about mint
What's happened since the Linux action show on Sunday?
and then maybe we can sort of end up with that bigger conversation about what could be a really cool long-term solution to this problem and
Maybe you'd host that solution to this problem that long-term so I know where I would a digital ocean droplet West
Come on, don't fool around use the promo code deal unplugged and get a $10 credit over a digital ocean com
It's a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering most intuitive and easy way for you get a super badass Linux rig in no time
They have all Linux machines run on KVM virtualizer with SSDs for the disk
IO you can get started less than 55 seconds and pricing plan start Oh
Five dollars a month five a month. That's right. Get your 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSDs
Because they're all SSDs a CPU that's super fast a terabyte of transfer and moa
Oh, what's more you ask their crazy great interface and super straightforward API that interface man
That is an innovation of humanity
Managing virtual machines with an interface like this. It's ridiculous. It should be illegal
It's so awesome. If the US government knew they'd be taxing them on their on their innovation
I'll tell you what else digital ocean supplies the back-end hosting for tons of open source projects that we know we love and we download
from every single day not to mention
The very mumble room we're talking to our virtual love no way. That's right
Digital oceans your place to go to spin up a Linux infrastructure when you need it. They got Debian's
They got the core OS is they got the fedoras the Ubuntu's
They've even got no free BSD
That's true. That's true. They have great tutorials to help you really take it up a notch
So, you know what you can look like a boost
They make it easy to take backups move them around wipe them and start over again when you screw something up real bad because you
Know you will that's what it's all about. And what I love about the pricing is it's
hourly
So you could really just go spin up a rig for like a few hours and try something cray-cray see if it goes
And if it don't go blow it away and if a go-go you keep it
Then we use I know and when you use the promo code deal unplugged
The decisions made for you because you get the $10 credits
You can go create your virtual server infrastructure on demand in less than 55 seconds for free for two months
Now if that's not boss mode, I don't know what is digital ocean comm and a big. Thank you to digital ocean
For sponsoring Linux unplugged
Okay
Before we get into the Linux mint story
I thought I would read a little bit from the CD net article and then I'll open up to the mumble room to kind of
Jump in but the hacker
Known as peace had a nice chitchat with that was Zach white talker
Or white taker Whitaker. Oh, I like my version a lot better West
Thanks that Zach white taker. He taker of white men. He comes in and he talks about
What this guy did to Linux mint and I don't understand
Zach apparently writes for security websites, but yet he talks about Linux like somebody who's never heard of it before but anyways
So the hacker responsible who goes by the name of peace told me in an encrypted chat
Probably telegram on Sunday that a few hundred Linux mint installs
Remained under their control a significant portion of the thousand-plus downloads during the day. Wow. How about that, huh?
Peace also claimed to have stolen an entire copy of the site's form not once but twice friends once on January 28th
Happy birthday, Chris. Mine was my birthday 26, but yeah and February 18th two days before the hack was confirmed
The hacker shared a portion of the form dump, which we verified to contain some personal identifiable info like birthdays profile pictures
passwords emails
those passwords also might not stay for very stay safe for very long because
Clem was using PHP pass to hash the passwords which has known flaws
It later emerged that the hacker had placed the full form dump on a dark web marketplace
Which that's what you do. Yeah, which he wanted, you know 85 bucks cuz well he needed 85 bucks
So he asked for it in Bitcoin peace was just jokey or I'm sorry poking around
The site in January when he found or say they found a vulnerability granting unauthorized access
The hacker also said they used credentials to log into the site's admin panel as Clem
But we're reluctant to explain how
It provided useful later on I could think of a few ways though on Saturday
The hacker replaced one of the 64-bit Linux distribution images
That's an ISO for those of you at home with one that was modified by adding a back door and later
Decided to replace all the mirrors for every downloadable version with the Linux on the site with their own version aka
Altered the site links to point to their versions the backdoor version isn't as difficult as you'd think piece in because oh, no
That's right. This is one of the things the author just threw in here. This is not a quote
From the hacker. This is a quote from
Zach Whitetaker here
Zach Whitetaker adds
The backdoor version isn't as difficult as you'd think because the code is open-source the hacker said it just took a few hours
To repack Linux that contained the backdoor. What does that have to do with being open-source?
It just means it's easy to do those closed source ISO files Chris. Yeah, I can't touch them
I just like this and this guy's like it's supposed to be a like a journalist that writes on this stuff all the time
Anyways, the hacker used their access to change legitimate checksums and used and which people then download to verify the integrity
checksums checked out peace said the first hacking episode start in late January, but peaked when
They started spreading the backdoor images early Saturday morning
They had no specific goal to their attack, but peace said that their motivation was essentially to build a botnet
Using this anomaly bit malware that we talked about in Linux action show
For now the hackers motive was just having access in general
But they did not rule out using the body to carry out data mining or many other nefarious means in the meantime the hackers botnet
Is still up and running, but the number of infected machines has dropped significantly since the news broke on Saturday
Peace confirmed Clem decided not to respond for comment to the article
Okay, dare Devlin so you think it's not a big deal at all not a big deal at all. Tell me why so I will say
Not a big deal at all because in one if criminal.org
was able to be at the our target and existence of much simpler less
feature
oriented website
Yes, it's okay to understand that the project like Linux Mint could be infected actually any project has
That same issue in the sense of there is a likelihood of having you know being a target
So this is number one or two
Most people how that use the the Linux Mint already have it installed. They're probably upgrading their packages
Which also means that if you already have it installed in your district properly roles
Which is usually something that Linux mix tends to do somewhat decently
We're not downloading as often
So they say thousands of people download the ISO they say a few hundred are still running the botnet
Yeah, a few hundred are still running the button at those thousands that downloaded like how many times have you downloaded because you couldn't find
That CD just out of laziness
I've downloaded
Yeah, out of laziness. You couldn't find that CD or that USB stick or that I so you did that. Yeah, I
That's not really
Okay, that's critical. I wouldn't call it critical for the amount of users living to me that has so Swift
You also think it's critical for the amount of users living to me that has so Swift
You also think this has sort of been blown out of proportion. It's not really good to go after Linux Mint
Yes, it's bad for the community in general. I mean we need to
Really look at this as being an opportunity. Yes to make improvements
But overall it's gonna be beneficial for the whole community
They're gonna see areas where their weaknesses and then patch those things and just do better and better over time, you know
Patrolling different channels about Linux and saying Linux Mint sucks
That's not gonna help anything and it makes me question a person's you know, really intent intentions
So I gotta tell you guys
I've definitely noticed they that the dogs are out
Yeah
And what's what's really kind of impressive about it is the dogs are out
Inside the Linux community and they're going after Linux Mint and Clem
most of it seems to be a bunch of cranky package maintainers who like are from Debbie and who've had like
Package name namespace issues and things like that
But there are a lot of people that are very upset pointing out a multitude of issues
Rodden corpse. What do you think?
I mean
Do you think this part of the reason why this is getting as much attention is because there are outstanding issues or with Linux Mint that
People still argue. Well, this is just another example of the overall problem
Yeah, there's like that you mentioned the package manager issues
I mean the namespace is a problem the priority control is a problem the fact that they you mean for the kernel updates
Oh dad their kernel base, but they have priority controls over their own packages
so if they have a package that is in your as in their repo and is updated in Ubuntu and
Linux Mint doesn't change that and doesn't you know recognize that the thing has been updated. You're not gonna get that update and
That's nothing to do with whether you have the same package or not
It's just they have a priority that is much higher than anything else
So even if you install a PPA sometimes the mint priority just overtakes it and you cannot get it installed unless you manually force it
So there's like weird little bugs like that that men is done that are like legitimate problems
But this overhyped thing about you know, they're it being insecure is
Just pretty much garbage. Well, okay. So Wes you have a laptop. Here's your work laptop
you run mint on it sort of a standard practice cinnamon edition as a matter of fact and
You watch this stuff
Let's talk here's a couple things on the top of my head that mint kind of gets tossed around for for not really
addressing some say they
Inappropriately just pull from the Ubuntu repos and sort of right on top of that their bandwidth their infrastructure, etc
They distribute now, of course, they make isos available that don't have this stuff
But they distribute isos with codecs and flash pre-installed which many distributions see fedora and others
So you can't actually do there seems to be no regard for that
Although an attempt is made to make an ISO available without them, but it exists nonetheless
There's also the the matter of sort of avoiding kernel updates as a matter of actual desktop policy
Then there's the there's the whole create your own X apps, etc, etc
When you look at all of this in whole are we seeing something here that is perhaps
Indicative of
Some
Things that are just not properly being taken care of and when you when you look at it as a as a Linux Mint user
Are you worried?
That their eyes off the ball on a few of these things they could have somebody come after them for legal issues when it comes
To the codecs. They've obviously got infrastructure problems with when it comes to the security. Why why why wasn't why weren't the MD?
Five sums properly signed. Why weren't they properly signed?
It's an easy thing to do that anybody that has a moderately large distribution would probably want to have done. They didn't even bother doing it
Right. Why wasn't why why were these things missed?
Does that bother you? I think it shows a lot of the and I don't I'm not gonna call them growing pains
But just Linux Mint has gained a lot in popularity since its early days like 13 or whatever, right?
And it really is, you know, you can't compared a lot to fedora or a bunch of these are both
Distributions with companies behind them Linux Mint is you know a volunteer team and not only are they focusing on you know
building
Well an operating system but building a whole skin for an operating system as well as these new X apps and all that
But they have to run all the infrastructure and I think it's showing that
You don't you know, it takes a lot to do that
And especially if your passion is I want to make I'm working on you know
Cinnamon a whole DE that they're building here. You probably don't have any cycles left as they're running a first-rate infrastructure. Hmm
but I guess I do it I guess I don't know if I
Yeah, I guess I guess like I mostly I guess I mostly agree. It feels like
It feels like it is a bit of a growing thing
But at the same time it feels like it's also just a lack of priority
I guess before I go too far
I think I think one of the things is maybe not serving Linux Mint at this point is
Clem has traditionally been anti media anti interview closed off
It doesn't doesn't do them as sort of a matter of policy for him personally
Good or bad what that is kind of left is it kind of left a lot of people to fill in the gaps about what?
Clem thinks about things
Until something like this happens and then all as we can do from the outside is go
Well, why didn't he have the why didn't he have the hashes signed?
Why was WordPress not bubble like we can all we can all sit here and play you know
Like hindsight's 2020 kind of thing
But I guess I don't want to bash on him for it
But I I do look at it and I go this may be indicative of larger problems
I think it is indicative of larger problems, and I think
If mitts gonna I guess if mitts gonna keep growing these are problems
They're gonna get you have to really reflect on how you build what you're doing. They're gonna be that scale exactly
That's the problem is well guess what now?
We're here or at the scale and these problems are and it's kind of things like Linux is great for letting you set up right like
He could build this website on a couple of servers that runs and distributes for his distribution
But once you're a popular Linux distribution you get a lot more attention than you do if you're just you know one of the ones
in the weeds and you start needing to like
Sky go after you that only went kits and I want you to jump in and share your thoughts on this so far
Actually, I think that a site like a distro watch could really help with something like this
They could host the checksums
They could even make it a little interface to where he could download the torrents or the ISOs
What happens when they get hacked?
And then everybody's compromised. I would hope that they would have better security. I would hope that about Linux mint
I mean this is this is probably a good question
Because I don't I don't think this is something unique to mint anybody could run into this issue
I would have if I started my own distro, right? I mean it could happen to JB
yeah, and so I feel like maybe that maybe we as a group could come up with a
Better solution something that is maybe I don't know
So I'm gonna start with Micah Lee Micah Lee he he wrote a blog post and a couple of things jumped out at me
He said it's also important to note that comparing the checksums of the file you downloaded with ones you see on a website
You download isn't secure either and this is always like we all check the checks on the trucks on
Even if you using Shaw 256 if a hacker can hack the website to modify the download link
They can modify the checksum at the same time to match the malicious download
The only solution to this problem is to use public key
cryptography and
I that seems to that seems to register with me is this is a wider problem that all distros have
When it comes to actually verifying the ISO that you get go ahead. Hmm
Well, no, not every distro tails
I think is the only one that actually one of the ones I remember that actually provides a PGP key to verify the guy
So far that makes sense. Yeah, you know other than that almost all projects never do most of the time
But don't other distros besides don't other distros besides tails also GPG sign wizard you're mentioning other distros do this as well, right?
Yeah
So the thing is near almost every distro I can think of off top of my head
That most people flock to is one that I you know, everyone uses the GPG key to sign their final ISO release
I mean it's built by the main, you know, the main build server and then it's pushed out
It's tested and then they sign it and say okay
Put it up there with the GPG key so that the mirrors will go and we'll only copy that specific file with
GPG key that we've signed and they know that GPG key, right?
And it would have been a huge thing if the mirrors had come back when this hell happened to mint and said hey
Your GPG key just changed. Is there a reason you know why right?
It would have it would have saved them so much trouble. It would have probably been alerted them immediately
Maybe I mean you're still relying on end-users to check and I think that's sort of the failing bit about it
It needs to be a system that almost checks itself sort of like how a bit torrent right and distributed so that it can check
Multiple and make sure that you know, well if you're the check some for this or the signature for this match as well from this
You have the solution just we need to get the OEMs to install a UE
UEFI key that actually, you know
Yeah, yeah
Secure boot everybody
God oh no
You probably right to which would be which would work as long as Clem didn't you know? Yeah
Yeah, that's true. I feel like that gets good at having that set
I
Think this is a good point for rolling these truths. I mean you're not installing all the time
Seriously, it won't be an issue at least for that long. Yeah, and well people reporting non-user centric bugs
Should be having more attention because usually those are not exposed
exposed it's like well, there is this thing what we're gonna keep it quiet because we want to fix it and
Things are forgotten. I think before we move on one thing. I wanted to just mention is
I was pretty damn surprised at how the Linux community has turned on mint
during this
One of the one of the more popular Linux weekly news threads right now is I don't think Linux mint is a is a
Pot as a professionally built distribution, and there's a whole
deep conversation going on right there and a
Lot of it is a bunch of people who just seemed to be upset from previous encounters and things like that kind of dogpiling
Right now, and it's I think it's a little unfortunate
I I think it's unfortunate that this happened, and I think that bad is on Clem, but I think at the same time
What he needs to do now, and if he did this I think if he just came you know
He's already been pretty transparent and straightforward and so now if just moving forward
He's very honest and transparent about what they're doing to resolve the issue
And how this isn't gonna happen again, and why they know it's not gonna happen again talk about your new infrastructure
Talk about what you're changing. That's all it takes right. Yeah
That's what it takes people will read it and be interested and you'll get you know you lose users
Yeah, but you'll get new users. You see yeah, yeah, yeah, I agree okay wizard you get the the final word here
No, I was just gonna say the main people that are pushing this
are a couple people that have a little bit of sour grapes because they've dealt with these projects before and
they have had disagreements and
Some of those people tend to think that if you don't follow their agreement, then you're you know you can't possibly be right
So there's just no everyone's jumping on everyone right now because everyone's going and saying ha ha I told you and
You know so a little for a little while. I think you're gonna see people jumping all over the place
Yeah, I think you're probably right, and you know that is sort of the price you pay when something like this happens, right?
That is sort of unfortunately the thing and that is why I broke my wordpress installation Sunday night upgrading wordpress
Because I didn't want to be the guy that was talking about this with a night
Please don't go pick on me because really I don't have enough time to work on this and you know
We need some white hack JB stuff here make sure I wonder if this is across Clem's mind because I've definitely talked about this on
Air there's several times. I thought I just need to drop wordpress. I don't have time
I mean, I think wordpress is a great super awesome project
And I don't have any problems with it
But I also like I'm not here to manage a website right and I I just I don't nobody is
nobody is here to manage a website everybody else has got something else to do and
The problem is that that means it just sort of sits and it's one of those things that really does need to be managed
Yeah, I was see I was thinking about going to ghost exactly see either remembers
I was but then the thing the issue was is they I started looking at all the features
We'd have to rebuild and I thought oh gosh well and the ghost download was just down for a little while they moved to Singapore
Okay, all right
All right, so Swift wraps it up with he says well Swift
Do you want to you could you want to just sort of say what you just said in the chat room sort of as our?
final thought on the topic
Yeah, I want to make it clear. I honestly trust Clem Linux mint has not lost my support at all
I'm sorry this happened, but it ultimately will be good for the latest community as a whole. I hope so
I hope that is a very good way to put it
That's a good final thought on the topic if you have any thoughts out there in the audience
Linux action show that reddit.com look for episode 133 lucky 133. Hey everybody. Give us your comments your feedback and
Let us know what you think about it. Yeah. Yes
I was just gonna say if I were Clem and I needed to brush up
You know make sure that I had really good infrastructure. I think I know where I would turn
Yeah, you know what make sure you got the skills West Linux Academy Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
Please go there support the show but also get one of the best discounts around to an incredible opportunity to learn more
Linux Academy comm slash unplugs where you go
Check it out seven plus distros to choose from look at this
two thousand three hundred and thirty three man look at that thirty three again
I'm just saying this is the this is the week to sign up. It's episode one hundred and thirty three they have
two thousand three hundred and thirty three self-paced courses thirty three my friends
It is the magic number. I invite you to go check it out at Linux Academy comm slash unplug step-by-step video courses
Downloadable comprehensive study guides comes with your own server spun up when you need it scenario based labs
You work in their advanced lab environments. They spin up when you need it that matches the distros
You've chosen earlier on instructor mentoring is available instructor mentoring is available did I mention?
Instructor mentoring is available. That's a big deal for the type of topics graded server exercises
Help you actually get over that testing anxiety
Redhat testing DevOps Ruby on rails Ruby anything Amazon web services Android anything
Linux anything open stack PHP Python. Oh my goodness. It goes on and on go check it out at Linux Academy comm
slash unplug try the practice exams enjoy the detailed notes and
The learning plans that automatically adjust to your available time
speaking of time
Check out those nuggets when you just want to spend two minutes. Maybe an hour. They got a whole range
You can go get a nugget
SSH tunneling bash aliases and escapes bash is oh
The command history shortcuts is going to but I think this one's really good bash the comma is your friend. Oh
That's true. That is very true
Administration with Tilda and of course they've been posting their live events there as well
Always new things coming out as part of your Linux Academy
membership Linux Academy comm slash unplugged in a big
Thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
But wait an all-episode for this
So I as you may have been aware
West
last week
after
445 days of waiting I had a chance to try out the purism Libra ultimate Linux laptop
And I don't know if you know what to get the timing right on this
So we're gonna go to the horse's mouth directly here for just for a moment
But my recollection goes down like this in the time since I backed the purism a
Company I'd never heard of called intro where has come around and it started shipping laptops preloaded by the way with Ubuntu Mate and
They have a couple of different products out there
We'll talk more about that in a sec, but the one that I want to talk about today is intro where's Apollo laptop
It's it's I think it starts a base price around 700 US greenbacks somewhere around there depending on the conversion rate
it is a 13-inch laptop and
I have it here in my hands and they sent me a version of the Apollo
pretty well spec'd to see how it stacks up to the Libra 15 and others in terms of build quality performance and
All of that so I have it here. They have had it for about 24 hours
And before we go any further I want to introduce Mike from intro where Mike welcome to Linux unplugged and tell the folks listening
What you do over there at intro where what is that title of yours?
I
Hi, I'm the co-founder of intro and we build Linux computers for the UK at the moment and soon
some of Europe and
The Apollo arrived on my doorstep
yesterday and
It is a 13-inch laptop
very similar in in sort of look to say a MacBook Air or
Or really the Apollo 15 only I'm sorry the Libra 15 only 13 inches very very very good build quality
And so Mike I'm just curious. I I don't actually think are you selling these in the US at the moment?
No, we're not selling in the US for a while
The reason why yours got a US keyboard layout is because we're going to be shipping them to some
EU countries because they also use that layout. Oh my gosh. I got you
So a little bit about the Apollo if you would give can you give me some background on how this computer came to be?
and
Any kind of interesting details about the Apollo?
Yeah, we started selling when his computer is about a year and a half ago, maybe two
We got a lot of requests for an ultrabook and we just found
An ODM in China where we could have them built and shipped over
It is it you make it sound so simple
But what I find to be remarkable about it, and this is something that every single person that I have
Put this in their hands and said
Is it feels really really sturdy really well built and?
And they also people often tell me it feels a little heavy which I think adds to that it feels well built right
And so I'm curious to how
It was a matter of finding the right builder was it what what is it that?
Entraware has been able to accomplish here when it comes to build quality that other vendors sort of in the space. Maybe haven't gotten to
Is it just happened to be the partner builds a good machine because I mean it seems feel wise it's it's pretty significantly well built
Yeah, so we approached a few people and these are one of the few that did solid build
So one of the few that did solid aluminium chassis
So we chose them obviously because they had to build quality and then the keyboard also
I don't know what the process was of selecting the keyboard, but versus some of the others the keyboard is pretty nice, too
And feels good in the hand the keys are actually translucent so the backlighting shines through
Which is nice and the fan?
Isn't running crazy loud the fan actually seems to properly cool the machine which was a nice surprise
When I took it out of the box
Was there any particular tricks you guys had to pull to make this thing work properly with Linux or was it all pretty easy?
Well the first the first revision we had there was a few problems with the farm
We had the mind out in the firmware, so that's no go yeah
I would I would agree so if there was definitely some problems with the fan if you ran into the same problems
I did so if I wipe the if I wipe the OS that this came loaded with will the fan still work fine
Or will it stop working normally no exactly the same as what it's doing now, so it's firmware level then it's totally hard
Well, that's awesome. So I got it so my first impressions of this are this is one of the most well-built laptops
I've ever held would you agree? Oh, yeah, I really want one now. Yeah, so it's got one
two USB 3.0 ports plus USB C. It's got an SD card slot reader full-size HDMI out and
Headphone jack and entry where was kind enough to include a USB
Ethernet box because there's no USB Ethernet on this it's got a 13 inch screen 1080p resolution on it two hard drives a
500 gigabyte spinning for the home and a 120 gigabyte SSD for the root
Yeah, two hard drives in a in a 13 inch laptop, too
Mike that's a pretty impressive spec a skylake Intel processor
And it's silent. I haven't heard it sound since I've been here. Yeah
That's a pretty impressive piece of hardware is the are the Apollo cells
Meeting your expectations
Yeah, they keep growing as we get more publicity on them because they are really good for the price
Yeah, I use a base $700 now the base $700
Yeah, I think has like an i3 and 4 gigs of RAM, but you just bring it up from there
And and then and then Mike could you talk a little bit about the choice to work with Ubuntu Mate?
What drove that and how's that going?
Well as approached by Martin about a year ago, and we just had a back-and-to when I was a big fan of the project
So it was obviously a good
Move to start shipping of our machines. Yeah, it feels fast
You know it's my first experience with it when you get a machine
You know with a nice fast skylake processor and plenty of RAM
And then you throw the Mate desktop on there with with the Ubuntu base
It feels really snappy so ready to go yeah, and the battery life
I don't have numbers yet, but the battery life has been pretty good
I think part of that is because the desktop environment just isn't really very demanding
So you feel like you get a nice performing computer with a very reasonable
Modern desktop plus you get someone like intro right here
We're like they're a company right so like if you have problems longer term
You know they're they're gonna be around to support them and to fix them
so the number one question Mike that everybody in the chat room wants and has is
How how how likely and possible is it for intro where to eventually start selling in the US is that a possibility for you guys?
Or is that just a lot of trouble?
There is a possibility, but we'll wait for we're gonna wait for a few more
A larger amount of orders before we start shipping over there. We're gonna
Make sure all of the you saw it first. Yeah, yeah, you get it nailed there that makes a lot to work on the JB group
Order yeah
There you go. Yeah group order this thing is
Boy, I can't wait to just keep trying it over the week
This is this is gonna be my main machine for the week seems like a great little just getting stuff done laptop
Yeah, I am really looking forward to putting it through its paces so far
It sounds like like it's silent and silent is a big deal for me, so I'm really happy about that and I a one thing
I may be continuing to troubleshoot, and I haven't I don't know if it's just the Wi-Fi here or what
But I've had a couple of Wi-Fi issues
Where the either the transfer rate has been real bad like I'm talking like I'm getting 2,000 millisecond pings
Or it just won't find the network, but I in both cases it actually could be interference
So I'm gonna take it out to a known good location where I only have one Wi-Fi access
point there's no other Wi-Fi accesses points around or access eyes and
See if I have any issues, but so far
I other than that and then with the ether adapter of course
I've had zero problems and Ubuntu Mate has been has been pretty great, too. I really like the design
It because it's a little bit smaller than the Librem it feels a little tighter
There's a notch where you put your finger that kind of is reminiscent of the way the Mac books do it
Yeah, which looks nice it really all it all comes together
It's it's it's got a bottom plate that could be removed with one two three four five six seven eight nine ten eleven twelve
Screws so you remove twelve little Phillips screws, and it looks like the bottom plate would come off
But it seems like such a good laptop like you show but a conference
And it's it's just a little different, and you've got it running Linux, and it works well. Yeah. Yeah, I really like it
I'm really really happy that the keys are
actually
The the letters are translucent so the backlit key light actually shines through the keys
Which is nice because otherwise it's kind of pointless to have the backlighting Mike is there anything else you want to add about the Apollo
Before we move on I know that's it very good sir and wimpy was there anything you wanted to add
Any thoughts I'd like to add yeah, yeah Mike's being far too modest
Mike has
Intro ship with a company that you'd be very interested in hearing about I think
Tell me more
So now partners
Val okay Mike now are you bearing the lead here hold on we have ourselves a little valve story
I got to hear it tell me about it
Yeah, so we're official valve partners, so we're gonna be building a steam machine shipping them out a few months
very cool I
Have you I've already begun testing come on now. Are you a gamer Mike?
We had one prototype
I'll count this year for people to use and
Got a good reaction so my you know Mike. I gotta say. I don't know a lot about entry where my
My initial impressions are is you guys are very clever?
So it just it just it struck me just in the name of this device
It's a pretty great device, and you went with the name Apollo
Which when I say Apollo West what's the next thing you think of fast? Oh you do well?
I don't know I think 13. I think Apollo 13. Oh 13 right and what is this?
13 inch yeah, it's a 13 inch laptop. It is it's brilliant. I mean it shows you a little bit of the
I I to me
I think it just it sort of demonstrates a little bit of the thought that goes into it is it's an Apollo
13 but of course the product name is just Apollo because
The 13 just sort of comes naturally part of it
And it makes you think what laptop to Chris get got that Apollo and how big was oh yeah?
I was 13 inches Apollo 13. That's clear and the 15 should be called Creed
No
No, nothing ever gets called Creed. That's that's that has been banned, but yeah, so I I think it's pretty good kids
And you you had something you wanted to add to go ahead sir
When you said Apollo, I actually thought art and illumination like the
Roman slash Greek God yeah, yeah, okay, all right, okay fine not everybody thinks
But it does have proper backlit key so
It elimination is accurate all right, okay fine fine all those are good. See it's a clever name
Nothing nonetheless. It is a clever name
So I have if you're listening to the audio version
And you're curious what the hell does this thing look like and probably a lot of you are listening to the audio version in the show
notes I have a link to an album I took up up on campsite and
I posted pictures of because I was like hey, you know what you know what makes a good background for photos
The freaking Pacific Northwest yes, it does. It's a pretty good-looking state so Washington is so I put that up there
And yes, it does have a an Ubuntu button actually it's a matte button
So that's pretty yeah, I like seeing you can customize that right on the website. That's great. Yeah
Yeah, and it's a it's a sticker, but it's a translucent sticker
So it doesn't block the light which which makes that attention to detail
So I'm right now. I'm running Ubuntu Mate 1510 or mate or whatever addition on there. I may stick with that I
I I I don't I don't know what exactly it is
But this particular hardware has made me also want to just see what it'd be like to have elementary OS on it
Just to kind of go all the way. I don't know though because the thing is is right now for testing Ubuntu mate makes such a great
Low-key desktop environment that it's like you just get all of the machines performance out of it
So I just don't know about it Wimpy you had one more comment go ahead
Um, yeah, the version of Ubuntu mate that you're running there is actually sort of Ubuntu mate 1512
Really?
Yeah, yeah
So what you've got there is Ubuntu mate 1510 and then I worked with Mike to get the mate
1.12 desktop on there rather than mate 1.10
Did that is because in mate 1.12 we introduced
in the control panels
two
Finger three finger touch configuration. Yes, and I do really appreciate that
Yeah, so that's why we've just given you a slightly custom version
But so if I reloaded the OS it might I might not get the the the trackpad configuration stuff
No, the the trackpad works on all OSs sure, but Barte didn't have
The UI touch options until just recently that is it actually
exceptionally nice because so it is a good sized trackpad and when you go into the
Mouse settings in in mate you can you can say two fingers down as a right-click or in the corner is a right-click
I want to scroll by touching the right side of the trackpad
I want to scroll by using two fingers like all of that is available for you. Wow. Yeah
Really nice. So that's good to know. Yeah, I think I might stick with it
I I just I really have very little reason to replace it once I have it all set up
It really works super good. The only thing I might want to play fine. Yeah, sorry
I was gonna say you'll be fine when you go with an turgos as well cuz I know Mike runs arch. Oh, really?
Okay, cool there and you know
I was also thinking 16 if I all the other thing I might do is might do the 1604 version of Ubuntu Mate
Yeah, yeah and just do that because that and that would likely still have the configuration options right for my trackpad
Yeah, that's all built into 1604. Boom. Boom. I loves it. I
Have not done the distro bands bounce the chat room was asking. So yeah, but I might buy by the time
I buy the time last comes around
I think if all goes as planned this will be my review for last and we'll compare it to the to the two
I might try to do some performance stuff
So if anybody has any questions or or even better yet
suggestions of ways to benchmark a system like this that actually produce information that we care about and
That is relevant. I would love to know that Linux actual at reddit comm you could link the benchmarks there
or something like that
Oh
Okay, so Wimpy I will absolutely have to have Loki if I want to try it on this machine. Why is that? Yeah for elementary
elementary is based on
1404 right which doesn't have Skylake support
Right, right and Loki's based on 1604
Yeah
Okay. All right. Well see 15 10 or better see somebody's got to make me a Loki
I said just cuz it looks like it looks like if you here's my thinking right you put that on here
And then you go to like a mall or somewhere you say you say look at the new Macbook. What do you think?
Shriner prankster and you know before before we before we walk away and say oh, it's a big Macbook ripoff
I want to actually make sure I'm clear I did when I look at it
I actually don't give the impression that it's trying to rip off from the Macbook what I get the impression of is
Aluminum makes pretty good material for this and when you make a 13-inch machine, there's only so much room
I actually in some ways that I would say there's potential the keyboard may be better than the Macbook keyboard
I'm gonna type some more and tell you the truth if that's I don't know about the trackpad
But the keyboard I think might be better and this this thing with with one two three USB ports
I think outclasses the Macbook in terms of connectivity plus a
Dedicated HDMI out port and an SD card slot reader this thing might outclass the Macbook and connectivity
But I'm not I'm not sure about that
And so I don't actually I think it's I think it's selling it short to say always copying the Macbook
I think what it is. It's taking design cues from a good design, but it also I think is
Its own product very much its own product and I'm I like it a lot
But that is my that's my first impression if you wanted to take check out some pictures go over to the show notes
And if you got ideas on things you want me to do to test it, let me know so skylake. It's got Intel graphics
So we'll see what happens. We got two. We got two drives in there
I
Mean a Linux action show dot reddit calm
That's also where you can go to submit content for this show or any other show we do
We appreciate that helps sort of form what we end up talking about West
Is there anything else we want to cover in today's episode of the unplug program? I don't think so
It's been a big show today. Oh my gosh, Wes, and I got to be the fool that edits. It's all together. Oh, man
It's for people who like to mess with computers. I am NOT looking forward to that West that is that is you know
Maybe it just comes out later this week once Rekha
Just put it out a few days Rekha. I left all the editing for you. Yeah, that's true. Hey, mr.
Producer q5 sis got his acceptance letter for Linux fest Northwest talk. That's awesome. That is super awesome. Of course, we're grads
We're gonna we're gonna get Wes at Linux fest Northwest. Oh, we're gonna have people up
Do you guys got to be there to Linux fest Northwest org be so cool to have people from the mumble room make it to?
That'd be super nice. All right, check us out on Tuesdays
We do the show live Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar JB live TV to watch that Linux action show at reddit comm to send us
Feedback Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact to send us in some emails. See you back here next Tuesday
Thank you for making it in I hope the project makes it are you guys gonna push forward if it doesn't quite clear
What's your what do you have? Are you formulating a plan B? Yeah, we may try and do something
Um, if it doesn't quite go through we'll see what happens. Yeah, I think that's a great idea regardless
But hopefully it makes you something animation. So cute. Yeah, like I love that. Yeah, great
Yeah
Sometimes the those crowdfunding projects break through towards the end as people get motivated so you never know. Yeah. All right
Cool, man. Thank you for being here
Thanks from both to me JB titles comm chat room. Everybody go boat or bang suggest comm
Let's pick our title it out and then we're gonna get the heck out of here
So I'm like, okay, even though this is the dumbest idea. I I should probably upgrade WordPress before I release last I
Mean cuz that's one more thing to do man. Well, and it's like well it takes a while to encode
So I've got like an hour here to play with and I'm like I could spend this hour upgrading my WordPress installation
And then I'm not I don't look like the world's biggest
Hypocrite right and even though in the show I'm like I I suffer from this problem, too
I just thought this would be a good idea a little follow-through. Yeah
And so I don't want JB to get hacked pretty solid idea a couple of things that really bit me in the ass
They come the compounded
So first of all, I had to struggle through getting final cut to work
Which was just a disaster required a ton of maintenance to get final cut to perform properly. I I got through that in coding
That's pretty solid. Not a big deal the WebM encoding a two hour and ten minute episode
WebM was literally going in real time
and so it basically took two hours and ten minutes to encode one WebM file which looks way worse than any of the
x264 files and is way larger and
On top of all that like getting through all the final cut problems. I decide okay. I'm gonna do this WordPress upgrade. I
Do the upgrade?
It goes pretty solid
except
One of the most critical plugins we have breaks. Oh
convert markdown to HTML and as you know Wes all of our show notes are written in markdown for all of our shows and
This ability to post the shows in markdown just broke on the JB site and I'm like, okay
I didn't I didn't need this. Nope. I don't I don't want this right now
And so I start looking into well, I'll just go get a new WordPress plugin
So I do the thing that everybody does I install like three different freaking plugins and the third plug-in. I try to activate
something
Happens and it just starts slamming the mysql database
Well that takes down the whole back end of the WordPress site. And so I'm like in the chair. I'm like Alan
Are you around Alan? No Alan. It's a Sunday afternoon. He's in Canada. I don't even know what he's doing
He's doing so in Canadian and he's totally a he's totally afk
The back end of the JB website is down. The files are finishing encoding as the site goes down
I'm like what is going on?
Of course the YouTube encoding is is chewing away now and I'm like come on
I can't get this side up. Eventually the mysql server starts responding again. I
Don't know why maybe just some sort of BSD magic. It finished deleting all of your data
Yeah, and so I log back in still no markdown plugins turns out in the new in the new WordPress
They want you to use jetpack and jetpack has a markdown kind of feature that you can use
Okay. Well so to use jetpack you have to activate jetpack
That's really so I installed the jetpack plug-in and I go to activate jetpack
Authentication failure
What I tried again
Authentication failure unable to activate what is going on? I started looking into it
They're like, yeah, if your mysql server is running real bad and having some performance issues
It causes enough of a delay that the sync doesn't work and you can't activate the plug-in
So because whatever's going on with the mysql server
I can't activate this plug-in which gives me markdown support so I can't post the show because now I need markdown support to support
So a long story short
I've now been manually converting markdown to HTML and just posting them shows is it which is not a big deal
But it it's it means that we have your workflow and we have this
Mismatch of stump some stuff in markdown and some stuff in HTML and it's just you don't go have a canonical copy
Yeah, so now he's gonna now he's gonna have to go fix that
I love you. Okay