So I wasn't even going to share this with you guys.
I'd seen this on the web, and we were
talking about pre-show material.
But the most interesting part about this new TCP bug
is the fact that Netflix discovered it.
Yeah, I wasn't really too into it, except for that part.
That is kind of, I guess I'm just sort of getting exhausted
on these.
But it's sort of like a new version of The Ping of Death.
Yeah, kind of.
I mean, you get some misconfigured TCP packets sent
your way, and in just the right case on an unpatched kernel,
well, you might actually have a full blown kernel panic.
So those are always unfortunate.
Obviously, that can lead to a denial of service attack
when all your boxes are crashed.
Yeah, and that's not great.
I think the impact has been a bit lessened
because most serious boxes in production out there
are behind various types of load balancers or other gateways.
And many of those, typically this is not a protocol flaw.
This is a flaw in Linux's implementation of the TCP stack.
And FreeBSD is also affected.
There's several other variants that aren't panics.
They're just slowdowns.
Did you guys catch its name?
Sack Panic.
I like it.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 306 for June 18, 2019.
Hello there, and welcome to Linux Unplugged,
your weekly Linux talk show that's getting its way
into the 300s.
Feels weird, Wes.
It sure does.
Feels weird.
Like, this show can't be 300 episodes long.
We're just hanging out.
We must be doing something right.
I don't know about that.
Or very, very wrong.
We're just very persistent.
Well, coming up on this week's episode,
we have some community news.
But we decided to do something you should never do this week.
We decided to live swap out a FreeNAS
system to Fedora, which we're calling
from FreeNAS to Fedora our journey of live swapping
a production system with a failed disk.
We went out into the Jupyter broadcasting server room,
brought our recording equipment, and documented our journey.
Not only that, we changed the whole darn network
here at the studio.
It's amazing we're here at all.
Yeah, we really did.
We ripped out the whole network, re-IPed everything,
and still managed to put a show together.
We actually had a lot of fun doing it.
We'll tell you about that in a little bit.
But before we go any further, got to say hello to Cheesy.
Hey, Chees.
Hey, what's going on?
Oh, you know, doing a podcast, hanging out.
Yeah, you guys have been hard at work
with that stuff for the last couple of days, too.
Yep, we got everything back up and on just in time
to say time-appropriate greetings, virtual lug.
Hello, Mumble Room.
Good morning.
Hello.
Hello, Brent, and Bruce, and Byte, and Neil, and MiniMech,
and Sean, and TechMav.
It's nice to have you all there as we go along.
And we start out with some community news.
And the big item that caught my attention,
there's many things we could talk about.
This has been another one of those weeks
where it's sort of like what we didn't put in the show
is almost as important as what we put in the show.
And I just thought, let's start with talking
about initial benchmarks of Microsoft's new WSL 2.
We're already starting to see it shipped
for the people that are subscribed to the Insiders
build if you really want to play with it.
Yeah.
And under some benchmarks, this is, of course,
according to Michael Eberle over at Ferronix,
he's been testing the subsystem.
And in not all instances is it actually faster.
It is in some, like with I-O.
Yeah, right.
So it has improved I-O. And that was
one of the big justifications for this whole re-architecture
of the subsystem.
It just wasn't cutting it before.
But unfortunately, in some other areas, we're not so lucky.
Yeah, looking at the benchmarks here,
there is certain kinds of workloads
where it's significantly even slower than WSL 1
and obviously slower than bare metal.
He compared it to 1804 bare metal and clear Linux bare metal.
And all of the benchmarks, as he always has,
are linked over on his site if you want to check them out.
I think it just means it's not the Linux killer
that everybody worries about.
It's just a practical tool to get your work done.
And there are already some interesting use cases for it,
Docker just posted a massive write-up
that we read so you don't have to.
And they write, Microsoft gave us an early build of the WSL 2
so that we could evaluate the technology
and see how it fit with our product.
And then we could give them our feedback about what's missing
or even broken.
We started prototyping different approaches.
And we're now ready to share a little bit
about what's coming in the next few months.
Docker Desktop Future.
Yeah, that's the title of this section.
OK, so before they had a Hyper-V based VM,
and that's going to be replaced by what they're calling
a WSL 2 integration package.
Which is still based on Hyper-V VM,
but it's like a different, more optimized new version.
Yeah, exactly.
So it provides all the same features
as the current Docker desktop VM.
So you can do Kubernetes, you can do proxy configuration,
you can access the Docker daemon from Windows,
and all sorts of bind mounts, all the usual Docker
sort of stuff.
In the past, that was it.
You couldn't really mess with the underlying VM.
You couldn't run additional stuff in the Linux OS
that was running inside of it.
With the WSL 2 integration, you'll
still experience all the niceties you have from Windows.
But you can run additional Linux programs inside,
and they can also talk to Docker.
So you can have the same Docker API running from a daemon,
running on a Hyper-V VM, using WSL 2, all unified together.
And they write, and a good example, a use case for this
is, a lot of your scripts that you've written on the Linux
side can just now be used, or on the Windows side
can be used to manage the Linux boxes, vice versa.
They also have a nice example of using Visual Studio Code
with that remote connector setup.
So you can go remote into WSL 2, and then use the Docker daemon
inside, build Docker containers, run them,
and then still manage it all from Windows.
That's nice and tidy for those Windows developers that never
want to be bothered with dirtying themselves,
actually installing real Linux.
Now they can use the days of having to manually configure
VirtualBox with NFS shares over the net.
Now they'll just use a Visual Studio Code remote to WSL.
Then package all up in a Docker container.
Good to go.
Microsoft loves Linux, don't you, though?
Never had to actually touch real Linux at all.
That's crazy.
It hurts so much.
I don't know.
It's all about making Linux a bit of a runtime.
I'm all for it.
So while we're talking about Docker containers
and universally running applications,
just a quick update from our friends at Canonical
that work on snaps.
First of all, they have new distro-branded landing pages.
So that way, if you're on Mint, or you're on Arch, or Fedora,
whatever it might be, they'll now
have specific instructions on how
to get up and going with some copy pasta
if you choose, which looks pretty nice, pretty simple.
I thought it was a little strange to me
the way they sort of branched it out per package, you know?
Yeah.
Because most of the time, there's
not that much different, right?
You kind of, once you've got everything bootstrapped.
Now I get it when you want to land,
like maybe you're trying to install your first snap,
and so everything's there, right there on that page
for the application that brought you there.
True.
But it just kind of felt weird.
It's like, well, how do you install that?
Like, don't I just use the snap command line wherever I am?
Yeah.
Yeah, once you've got that part done, yeah, you're right.
We'll have to ask.
Maybe there's somebody who might know.
Maybe we'll have to ask him.
Now, while we're talking about snaps,
there's another part to the story
that I think is a good heads up for those of you that
are Ubuntu desktop users.
In 1910 right now, in testing, they're
calling for some feedback on shipping the Chromium browser
as a snap.
They're transitioning from a deb to a snap for the browser.
And they're working on migrating your profile,
the Chrome driver stuff, so that way
they can have video acceleration.
There's several elements to this that
need to be banged on by end users,
including just general desktop browser integration.
Sounds great, though.
I mean, I think it's a good fit.
You think so?
I mean, I already run, like when I run Firefox,
I install it manually under my home directory.
Browsers move fast.
Yeah.
Plus, sandboxing is not a bad idea.
The browser is a dangerous environment.
Chrome already has its own sandboxing.
It does.
But you're right.
I do agree that the browser is a good candidate for software
that you can update sort of independently
from the operating system.
And when you look at like an LTS,
it makes even more sense potentially.
And they don't have that many capabilities, right?
Like they don't need to reach super far into your file system
and go crazy places.
So I think it would mesh well with the abilities
that SnapD already has to give access when needed.
Here's what we've got to do.
You know what we've got to do?
We've got to phone a friend, like millionaire style
right now.
We'll call up a friend who might know about Snap packages,
and we'll ask Wes's question.
So, Popey, are you there?
Oh, hello.
Hi.
Go ahead, Wes.
You have 20 seconds.
What was the motivation between the structure
of the distro-specific pages on the Snap,
not one per OS at the top level, but for every package?
Very good.
You got it.
Because the goal is that a normal person who's
looking to install Spotify doesn't
want to know lots of stuff.
They want to know, how do I get Spotify on the distro
that I'm on?
And the focus for those pages is tell them
exactly what they need to know to get
that application on the distro that they've chosen,
and nothing more.
Maybe a little bit extra if they scroll down the bottom.
But the distro-specific stuff is really
catering to those people who like
to follow blog posts that say, how to do this one thing?
And it tells them how to do that one thing,
and then they get out of there.
That's all self-contained.
So the first experience they land on, they got everything.
That makes sense.
Mr. Wimper, it's nice to see you here this evening.
Hello, sir.
Good evening.
Hi, Wimpy.
How are you?
Very well.
Surprisingly, still jet lagged.
But other than that, fine.
I'm not surprised.
With as much traveling as you've done,
it's got to catch up.
Eventually, it's going to catch up to you, right?
Yeah.
This is the week it catches up, apparently.
So the Atari VCS is going on sale for pre-order right now
for $250.
It's going to be a AMD Ryzen R1000 SoC design.
And this is coming out of details at E3 this week.
What do we think, Wimpy?
Are you skeptical of this box?
Or is it not a waste of my IndieGoGo money?
I'm very skeptical.
I'm sorry you've wasted your money.
You think so?
I'm kind of excited it's going to be a Ryzen box, because I'm
such a fanboy these days.
Yeah.
Is this past due yet?
Is it on time, or is it delayed?
It is delayed, yes.
It was delayed.
They delayed it a little bit ago because they
said they're going to move to the AMD A1 CPU and a Ryzen
processor.
And so that added delay to the process.
But that seems like it might be worth it.
Yeah, I don't know.
It seems like a lot of money for what it is.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, $250 isn't bad for the base price.
But to get something good that'll do 4K or something
like that, you start getting close to $800.
Plus, you get the look of the thing.
Ooh, black walnut.
Yeah, that's true.
It's got that nice retro look.
I do kind of like it.
Well, I just wanted to give everybody
an update that they are now taking pre-orders,
and they're talking about it at E3.
And they're saying, well, they're not really
saying specifically when it's going to ship,
but it looks like it will be this year.
If they're taking pre-orders, does that
mean they're fulfilling backers' pledges at the moment?
That's a great question, Wimpy.
That's a great question.
Ponzi.
Wow.
Have they shown any footage of any of the games
on the console yet?
There may be some from E3.
I haven't really gone spelunking.
Poby, I'm curious.
If you were going to bet on one, the Librem 5 or the Atari VCS,
you had to pick one.
Which one would you put your money on right now?
Oh, man.
Atari VCS.
Why would you do that to me?
Well, so the price point of the Atari VCS
is not remotely attractive to me.
I think I could probably go and dig
in the deserts of California and find
all the necessary Atari VCS cartridges
I want to for less than $250.
But I'd say the Atari VCS.
All right.
What about you, Wes?
I got to agree.
I mean.
OK.
All right, well, obviously I've put my money on the VCS.
It just seems like an easier target to hit.
Yeah.
Plus, you can load other OSes on there,
including they even say Windows now.
And if I could put Kodi on there,
it's only a little bit more than I paid for the Nvidia Shield.
So it's not great.
We'll see.
Do you still use your Nvidia Shield?
The heck out of it.
Yeah, I have two of them.
Still use them every day.
Oh, I have three of them.
Have you hooked up Steam?
I have done the GeForce streaming,
but I have not done any Steam streaming.
What's that like?
So this weekend, because I've only ever played the Android
games, because that's all my daughter's been interested in.
But I was going to go back and relook at GeForce now.
And then I noticed that a bunch of the games you see in there
all have Steam written underneath.
And the very first time you click on that,
it stands up a Steam on Windows install on their grid
computing platform.
And you sign in with your Steam credentials,
and it then installs the game that you've just selected.
And you run that over the Shield.
So that has become my new most favorite thing.
That's incredible.
And how would you say the performance and latency
and responsiveness and all that is?
Well, I'm fortunate in that I've got
a reasonable amount of bandwidth.
And I've always been impressed by the lack of apparent latency
that exists on the Shield over that whole GeForce
now streaming solution.
So for me, it's great.
I mean, the screen I have in the front room is very old.
So it's a 720p screen.
So it's not very high resolution.
And for that resolution, it's fantastic.
It's a lot of fun.
I'll have to look into that.
That sounds really neat.
Are you streaming that over wired or wireless connection?
Wired.
So in the front room, that's got a direct line
to the router, which is in the same room.
And then that goes out over the fiber.
Good setup.
Yeah, I have the one in the studio living room wired too
for that very reason.
Who needs a stadium when you've already got that set up?
No kidding.
I've pre-ordered Stadia as well though.
Yeah, did you?
Did you do the founders?
Yep.
Yeah.
I did it as well because first, I
want to be able to talk about it here on the show, number one.
But number two is it could give me
the ability to run a fully open source stack and have gaming.
All Intel graphics, for example, but still have gaming.
Yeah, absolutely.
And if that makes my workstation more stable,
I'd actually pay a monthly fee for that.
Yeah, I've been impressed with what
the Shield has been able to offer me.
And I was interested to see, well,
what can Google do in this space?
I'm not buying into the platform necessarily,
but the only way I'll know for sure is by finding out.
And so I've pre-ordered, and I should
be looking forward to trying it out later in the year.
Yeah, if it sucks, I'll say it.
So I don't have any reason to.
Absolutely.
I don't have any reason to.
Nope.
Yeah.
No, I'm just going to try it out.
And it does seem like if anybody would
need the technological background
and infrastructure to pull this off,
it would probably be Google.
They've got the scale.
And they've got motivation too.
So let's talk about something that I'd say
was probably the number one submitted, quote, unquote,
story to the show this week.
People are like, hey, did you see this Chris Christie?
And I appreciate that.
I actually kind of like to know what people are tracking.
And this was Linus Tech Tips' video on the System76 Thalia,
which they titled, A Really Weird PC,
The System76 Thalia Review.
It is currently, as we record this episode,
trending at number 44 on all of YouTube.
It has over a million views.
That's a big deal.
That sort of makes Emma's weight in customs
when she was hand delivering this.
That was quite a journey for her.
Yeah, she told that story on the show if you've missed it.
She's been out.
Rumor has it she got hurt.
We'll have to talk to her about that when she comes back.
We miss you Emma, we miss you.
Now let's talk about their review.
So Linus Tech Tips, we'll link to the entire video.
It's an 11 minute video.
We're just gonna play a couple of clips for you.
And it starts with the unboxing as many YouTube videos do.
So let's take a closer look at the box.
Once you get it out of the shockingly nerdy packaging,
the most striking features of the Thalia
are its wood green finish
and it's tantalizing silver power button
and accompanying white LED ring.
There's no sign of any front IO
to disrupt the clean design language they've gone with,
which means it's beautiful,
but also means unfortunately that we're stuck
with what we've got on the rear.
And back here is interesting.
So more of that clean at any cost approach.
The IO is cut directly out of the chassis.
That means no simple motherboard upgrade.
Although again, it does make for an uninterrupted
premium look that really screams Apple.
Even though when we pop the hood with these thumb screws,
we can see that this is clearly
a standard PC motherboard on the inside.
That power button is very legit.
It's just great.
Yeah, I want to push it right now.
I have a fun story.
So when we went and toured the factory,
I didn't say anything and nobody prompted me.
I just walked up and I started pushing the power button
of the demo unit that was unplugged.
So it was, you know, it wasn't hurting it.
And I just had this, I made this very satisfying, like nice.
And Carl, you know, the CEO, he was listening.
He was perched, wanted to see my reaction
because that power button is a particular point of pride
for them.
And so I liked that they honed in on that.
They do mention that the back plate is fixed,
although I think a motivated person
probably cut it open, but that's, you know, overall,
like it starts like kind of positive.
You're like, wow, this is pretty balanced so far.
As a non Linux user,
I want to poke around Pop OS a little bit.
Oh, now here we go to Pop OS.
How are they going to do this?
You first boot, it is super easy to encrypt your data.
Just enter a password and reboot.
That is pretty neat.
Then when you come back,
you're given the opportunity to set up your online accounts
for integration into the OS,
including access to your Google Drive cloud storage
right in the file manager.
Now we've actually seen Pop OS before
in our gaming on Linux update video.
And they continue,
and then we're gonna talk a little more about Pop OS,
but they continue.
One of its major departures from its parent Ubuntu
is Pop Shop, a ridiculously easy to use app store.
So it's actually ported over from elementary OS,
but with one key value add.
System 76 curates their own packages.
So if you ever need something basic,
like Steam for gaming or the latest Nvidia drivers,
it's just a click away.
Actually, for your graphics drivers,
it's easier than updating them on Windows.
Now, a couple of things strike me about this video,
because there's even more talking about Pop OS,
is Pop OS isn't going anywhere.
It's not going away.
It's here now for the long haul.
And I'm curious to hear what your reaction, Poby,
that is to that comparison of the parent operating system,
I believe as they put it, right?
The parent project or something like that.
What's your reaction?
I don't know what to say.
I mean, every derivative of Ubuntu,
which Pop OS is, has something that stands themselves apart
from Ubuntu.
Otherwise, there will be no point installing it, right?
And so their USP for Pop OS is the design language
they've used on the desktop
and simplicity of installing applications.
And we can learn from that.
And certainly you'll have noticed very recently,
we've talked about how it will be integrating
the Nvidia driver installer directly during the install.
So we've certainly learned
that that's a thing people really, really want,
and we should probably do that.
So, you know, we've learned something there.
That's great.
Wimby, when I heard that,
when they were talking specifically about the Pop Shop,
the thing that crossed my mind is,
I wonder what their reaction would be
to something like the software boutique
that Ubuntu MATE has that comes up
and has an extensive list of curated software.
What are your thoughts when you hear that?
It seems like you guys really hit on something
pretty important to users a while ago now.
Yeah, I'm really proud of what we did
with the software boutique.
I think we switched things up a little bit,
but I'm not sure what someone like Linux Tech Tips
would make of that,
because they're kind of accustomed to it, right?
If you go into any of the stores,
you have a full catalog of software in front of you.
You know, that's not been a problem.
In recent years, you know, you've got the Windows Store,
you've got the Mac OS Store,
you've got the equivalents on mobile.
It's novel to us on Linux
because we didn't used to have that ease of installation,
and we do now.
So I don't know how much that would resonate really.
Okay, fair enough actually, good point.
I suppose it is sort of become just expected.
You'd notice it more if it wasn't there.
Yeah, maybe.
I still really appreciate it.
They did touch on the open nature of the hardware as well.
The case and all of its accompanying bits and pieces,
open source, just like the operating system.
So there's literally a GitHub page
with the CAD files for everything that you see here,
and for its bigger brothers,
the Thelio Major and Thelio Massive.
But what impresses me overall about their entire coverage
is, again, it's really well shot,
it's really well written,
you should watch the entire video,
but they seem fairly balanced.
They also point out, you know,
the entire thing is an open source.
Now, that's not to say that every component
in the system is open source.
The motherboard, CPU, RAM, video card, storage devices,
and power supply are all proprietary in design
with the IP owned by the individual companies
that made them.
As it is, I mean, that's just how it works.
System76 will open a source as much as they can.
And they touched on something
that we've been trying to figure out internally,
because Wes is co-host on Coda Radio,
Michael Dominic picked up a Thelio station,
and was unable to use it for podcasting
because of fan noise.
And it's something-
We noticed it right away.
He's been experimenting with,
and they may have come onto something that Linus Tech Tips.
What we can also see in here
is they've done a pretty bang up job
with the cable management,
helped significantly by the generous real estate
provided under the main fascia,
which doesn't attempt to seal the computer
so much as it conceals.
There is a bit of concern from our end
about dust accumulation through the side panels
and the potential for noise to sneak out
from under the chassis using the air gap as an echo chamber.
Unfortunately, sure enough,
it does get a little loud
when the fans are running full tilt,
and it's not just whooshing air noise,
something that we generally don't complain about.
Rather, it's a kind of droning whine
that's a little bit harder to tune out.
Honestly, I think a Noctua or a Be Quiet fan swap
would help tremendously here.
That's a particularly challenging problem, though,
if that is just down to the case design,
if it's kind of making sound channels on the side,
because it's such a gorgeous case.
It's gonna take them a while to iterate on that.
So that could be why they've struggled
to have a super great response to the fan noise issue,
in my opinion, that's of course just my opinion.
Yeah, it is so pretty, it'd be such a shame
to have to go stick it in the closet somewhere
and not get to admire it on your desk.
Yeah, and so they also get to the price,
because you could build yourself a cheaper system,
or you could go buy a mass produced system that's cheaper,
and I think they did a decent job on honing in
on what kind of makes them special.
While the operating system itself may be free,
System76 does have paid staff
that actively develop their OS,
and that's to say nothing of the user support commitments
that come along with that.
Perhaps most crucially, though,
the Thelio chassis manufacturer and final assembly
are both done in Colorado by a team that's about our size,
so no mass production.
System76 says they want to improve
the situation in the future,
but for now, it means that the costs add up really quickly.
The team that's about our size,
which is kind of, that's poignant.
And then last but not least, they wrap it up.
You're paying for the case, US manufacturer,
operating system development,
and support from a small team of enthusiasts.
Now, whether the design and concept
of a well-integrated Linux desktop
is enough to make you pay the extra,
that's a choice I'll leave to you.
But overall, we think it's really cool
and a huge step in the right direction.
It's pretty good coverage for System76,
and it's good coverage for Pop!OS, too.
So we have ourselves another major desktop container.
I mean, they'll get there.
They're not there yet, but they're gonna get there.
It does make me feel a little bit better
about Mike's situation,
because he was having a heck of a time trying to fix it.
It's nice to know, you know,
it's unfortunately a common problem.
Maybe run it with the case off.
I don't know.
But good for them.
But weren't they also raving about Pop!OS
in one of their videos just recently,
where they were talking about gaming and stuff?
Yeah, it's a lot of coverage for Pop!OS.
And I appreciate it.
I think I initially was very, very critical of Pop!OS.
I still, I would love, what I would love,
is if Pop!OS was just a series of scripts or repositories
that you would add to a vanilla install of Ubuntu
that would make it pop,
and that would add a couple of things or whatever.
I feel like we already have too many distros,
but of course, you know what, I'm an old fart.
So of course I feel like that,
because I've seen, in my time,
I've seen so many distros come and go.
However, there is apparently
a pretty, an interested market in this distribution,
and I give them credit for cultivating that
and for adding some value to the OS,
like you hear people constantly talk about the install
or the encryption, the pop store,
the theme, these are all things that matter.
And credit to System76 for nailing those things.
And truth be told, they're just getting started, really.
So I feel, even though I started
fairly critical of the distribution,
and I still don't really see myself running anytime soon,
but I could, I could see myself in the future
if I went back to GNOME.
I'd probably give it a try.
It is interesting to see them actually,
I think there was some wonder
about how far they were gonna take this.
Was it gonna just be sort of glorified,
a few scripts on top, a custom theme?
But it seems like as they've had time
to develop it more out, they're actively working on it.
So it will be a long time project.
We're gonna see more updates,
and they're gonna continue to ship it.
She was stuck all day, Emma, in customs,
trying to get that machine to them.
She hand delivered that machine,
and then just had to walk away
and hope that the review went well.
And that was weeks ago, that was back during Linux Fest
that she did that.
She did that during Linux Fest and did that.
And now here we are quite a while later,
and that just got posted.
That kind of shows you their time window there,
but that's a lot of weeks of her sitting around wondering,
was it worth it?
Or did I just screw up?
And I think it was.
I think it was, yeah.
It's number 44 on all of YouTube right now.
That's a significant thing.
A tiny little Linux shop.
Yeah, I hope they get some sales out of it.
Absolutely.
All right, you know what we need to do?
We gotta do that housekeeping.
We gotta clean it up in here.
Yeah, we gotta clean up a little bit.
There's a few things to touch on this week.
First of all, first of all, I should mention,
we don't say this often enough,
but Linux Academy is hiring for remote positions right now,
including a Linux training architect,
a machine learning training architect,
a Python development training architect,
but also an Angular developer,
a full stack Node.js developer,
and Ruby on Rails developers,
multiple Ruby on Rails developers.
Those are full-time remote positions,
full benefits, everything.
There's also a position open in the lab platform.
There's a few things happening there
that are pretty interesting.
So if you haven't gone to linuxacademy.com
slash careers in a while,
I really suggest you do it
because there is some great positions open right now.
And I want to pass that along to you
because if you're in our audience,
you kind of have like a leg up in the process.
If you tell them I heard about it on Linux Unplugged,
that's gonna probably move you to the top of the stack.
Oh!
Yeah, that's a big deal
because that means you're actually interested in this stuff.
I want to also mention the Friday stream this week.
We played Who Wants to be a Millionaire?
It was Wes versus Ange.
I don't want to give it away, but it was tense.
She's a tough competition right there.
Tough competition.
Fridaystream.com slash seven.
It's a really good one.
That was a really fun one.
And then last but not least here in the old housekeeping,
we have a big batch of study group videos
that just got posted.
In the show notes,
I have a link to the playlist on YouTube.
This is Linux Permissions 101.
I think it is seven videos, I think, or six videos.
Yeah, we've got it down
to just sort of bite-sized components you can handle.
And it's really everything you've ever wanted to know
about Linux Permissions.
So nice.
It starts at the very basics and then works its way up.
And then by the end, you're doing really cool stuff
with ACLs and with UMass and set UIDs.
It's a good series of videos, six parts.
Each is consumable.
And we'll have a link to that in the show notes.
Just something we do to give back.
We have a lot of great opportunities.
We talk not only with training architects at Linux Academy,
but Elle is a networking machine.
And she goes out to events all the time.
And she meets people who are great presenters
who want to share their knowledge with our community,
their listeners often.
And so that's where a lot of this has come from,
is people that Elle has met.
She's our ambassador.
Yeah, she goes down, connects with these people,
and then brings them on to do a seminar or a webinar really.
And then we release it for free.
Because we're all about it.
We're all about it.
So check that out.
We'll have a link, linuxunplug.com slash, what is this, 306?
306.
linuxunplug.com slash 306.
All right, Mr. Payne, that abbreviated housekeeping
this week.
So we're going to talk about something you should never do.
Don't do it.
We just wanted to have something that
was more familiar to us.
We had a problem to solve.
And truthfully, we felt a little inadequate with the BSD.
And we had work to get done.
So Wes and I headed out to the Jupyter broadcasting server
room.
We're out here in the studio server room, AKA the garage,
to do something that you should never do.
Don't do what we're about to do.
We're going to take our perfectly functional, totally
fine, FreeNAS server, and we're going
to rip out the FreeNAS part and put Fedora 30 server in.
Yeah, you heard that right, Fedora 30.
Then we're going to try to import ZFS pools that Alan
created under FreeNAS into Fedora
after we get the ZFS support installed.
I know this sounds ridiculous.
Non-standard, maybe?
There's a couple of motivating factors, if you will.
Number one, this is a killer super micro server
with two six-core Xeon processors and 64 gigs of RAM.
And it's just sitting here doing nothing but FreeNAS.
Right.
Right now, it's just storage.
And I mean, that's great and arguably probably
the way you should do it.
But why are we going to let this server go to waste?
It's just if you're using that much power
and you've got to make all this noise, let's put it to work.
So there is one other consideration.
We've also run into an issue where a couple of times
we need to do some repairs.
And Wes and I are just not FreeBSD guys.
Surprise, surprise.
We're Linux guys.
And so we have a disk issue.
We need to swap out a disk and get a new disk online.
And quite frankly, we're just more comfortable
with the Linux command line.
And I think this is actually kind of an important thing.
When you put something in production,
you need to know how to use it, not maybe be so dependent
on, say, Alan Jude.
All right, we're rebooting.
We've just maybe completed installation.
Yeah, you're going to pop out the thumb drive.
So we use the Fedora server image, which is pretty nice.
Network install.
Yeah, the net install server image.
So it pulls down the packages from the repository
and gives you some options.
In fact, it might be the way I install Fedora from now on.
I mean, honestly, what?
That took all of 15 minutes once we got it set up and going?
It was a tiny image, well, 600 megabytes.
And then you could choose all of the desktops
if you want, from Zubuntu to Cinnamon,
or just the minimal installs.
It gives you an option.
And then it's off to the races.
So we'll boot up.
And then I think mission one is make sure our Fedora install
is sane and then get ZFS support installed.
And then we've got to go see about importing this pool.
All right, well, it's our first boot.
We'll be back in a moment.
I don't know why, but I just haven't
used a net install version of a distro ISO in, like, 10 years.
I mean, it just feels like it's been forever.
That's the only way I'm doing it from now on.
Seriously, it was so great.
First of all, way quicker to download.
Oh, yeah, very nice.
And Anaconda has this screen that you don't normally
see when you get the live desktop version
or when you get a specific spin.
You don't see this screen that comes up.
And the screen that comes up is the choice
you can install any of the spins of the desktops
right there from Anaconda.
So you can use this as a base ISO for a Fedora server,
for a Fedora desktop.
Yeah, I think we were both pretty impressed.
It was a surprisingly smooth installation.
I was.
I'm not normally an Anaconda fan.
No, and I'm normally not impressed by Grub.
I was impressed at Grub.
So Grub just came up on the first boot.
And one of the things I immediately noticed
is we're already on kernel 5.1, which
does confirm that the net install pulls down
the latest packages.
That's also nice.
Fresh Linux.
And one of the sort of interesting little side
anecdotes about this setup is we're connected to.
It's kind of a rickety setup.
The keyboard is a old Mac mechanical keyboard
because it's just the only one I had laying around
that I'm not using.
It's actually not that bad.
No, it's not.
Certainly better than modern Mac keyboards.
It's just the control and alt and stuff
is a little different.
And then it's connected to the very first LCD screen
I ever bought back in like 2000, 2001,
which I've just held onto all this time.
But there we are.
And look at that.
It does say web console.
So this does.
Cockpit is already up and running.
All right, I'm going to give it a log in.
You ready?
All right.
Yeah, there we go.
We're in.
All right, well, let's root around.
Oh, look at all them disks.
So it does see the disk.
Yep, OK.
Yeah, we're off to the races.
Good.
So now what we need to do is we need
to get kernel development packages installed.
And then we have to get the ZFS on Linux official GPG
key installed and the repository installed.
And then we can get this going.
So why don't we take a few minutes?
We'll do that, and then we'll come back.
I wasn't sure, like, would it be in this weird, funky state
because we had a bad disk.
I was sort of like, OK, great.
Yeah, we got Fedora installed.
Great.
Yeah, it can physically see the hard drives.
Who cares?
We've got to get ZFS working.
Well, it turns out we'll have links in the show notes.
That's pretty easy to do.
The ZFS on Linux upstream project
makes it all possible by putting a repo up,
by putting keys up, and then by putting documentation up
on how to do it.
No time at all.
Yeah, it was really, it was one of the fastest
parts of the whole setup was actually
getting ZFS working on Fedora.
It was completely painless.
But I wanted to know if we were going to actually
be able to import that pool since it was created
with an entirely different operating system using
a entirely different fork, or at least much older fork,
of ZFS.
And of course, we had that degraded disk as well,
or that dead disk.
We had a degraded pool as well.
We just got done installing all of the ZFS packages
from the ZFS on Linux project.
You've done the import command.
How has it gone?
What's happened?
We've got our data.
Now, there is one issue we're going
to have to solve right off the bat, and that's
setting the mount point because it's
defaulting to just the name of the pool
right under the root directory.
Previously, it had been under mount.
So we're going to have to tweak that a little bit
as we set up the rest of the stuff,
get things like NFS or SMB set up.
But otherwise, I mean, it imported with no errors.
That's pretty great.
So we went from a up-to-date FreeNAS install
and replaced that with Fedora 30 server, installed the ZFS
modules, and we're just picking right up where we left off.
One command in, and here we are.
And I would imagine that, I don't know for sure,
but I would figure that Fedora 30 could likely
be using a newer version of ZFS since we just
got the repository from the project directly.
I bet you're right.
And it's still fine.
It still worked.
Well, we'll solve that mount issue,
and then it's just a matter of standing up all the services
again.
So there was, I guess, a polite way
to say this is a unique heritage of this FreeNAS box.
You have to appreciate some background
before we continue here.
Blessed soul Alan Jude was out for Linux Fest Northwest
and, like a Canadian gentleman, went out there
and completely set up this killer box.
It's got two Intel Xeons that are six cores each that
supports all of the virtualization stuff
that you'd want.
And then it's got, what, 13 disks in it maybe?
Yeah, I think so.
Something like that, a mix of different sizes,
probably the smallest being six terabytes.
And then it has 64 gigabytes of RAM, some contributed by Alan,
some contributed by a TechSnap listener.
And it's just this monster of a system
we're not doing anything with.
And I looked at this and I thought, gosh,
if this was running Linux, I would be more comfortable
with actually deploying containers on this thing
and running other pieces of software on this.
But when Alan set it up, he had set it up really
to only ever be a back-end storage
box with a fairly complicated ZFS layout.
As you would imagine, he sub-volumed everything.
And there's also kind of a funky, like, swap partition
that went across all the disks for the FreeNAS itself.
So there's, like, some weird space allocated to that.
And then we had this mount issue.
Yeah, I mean, we just had to get it configured.
And FreeNAS had a sort of non-standard setup.
And it had been a mix of Alan administering things
on the FreeBSD command line and some of the FreeNAS defaults,
especially because this had actually
been a regular FreeNAS from IX Systems
that we then ported over to this new box.
So it was something of a hybrid monster.
Yeah, it had gone from a FreeNAS mini
into a super microchassis, which then Alan reconfigured it
from there.
And then we, from there, have converted it into a Fedora box.
But in the process, we sort of redid some things
to sort of align to how we kind of do things now,
including how we sort of set up the way the disk is set up
for the OS and whatnot.
So we had to do some stuff, tweak some of the mount point
settings and play with that.
There was also one other gotcha that we ran into that took us
a little bit to figure out.
I'll tell you about that after this part, though.
Fast forward a few more hours.
We have a pretty happy Fedora server right now.
And it's come down to the task of replacing that failed disk.
This is actually what started the entire process.
Yeah, this was the whole point.
This is the reason we started mucking around
with the FreeNAS system at all.
I mean, formerly FreeNAS system, of course.
Yeah, yeah.
Now it's FakeNAS.
That's what we're calling it.
So what step are you about to take right now?
All right, we've already removed and replaced physically
the failed disk with our new replacement desk.
And we've applied the same partitioning structure
that was on the previous desk.
Now we actually just need to replace it in the pool.
Right now, it's configured in a mirror setup.
So really, we're just going to put it in.
And CFS gets to copy all the data from the one existing
drive, and we will have two back in parity.
All right, let's fire it off.
This is the moment.
Oh, I love watching all the disk light up.
That's my favorite part.
It's like a Christmas tree.
It's done.
Well, at least it's returned us the command line.
Resilver in progress.
Ah.
Isn't that great?
I just love the ZFS management commands.
ZPool status just shows you always
exactly what you want to know.
Yeah, you can see the state is currently unavailable,
but it's working.
It tells you what it was.
And then I guess we'll have to go in
and we'll have to pull that one that's labeled as degraded
once we have this finished.
No, this will do it.
So that's going to replace it, and then it
should be healthfully online as soon
as that replacement's finished.
Well, let's toss to future us and see what happened.
Of course, this bad disk was the reason we even started.
So where is it at now?
Is it still resilvering?
It takes forever.
Yes, it is.
We're getting there 98% done, so it'll be done hopefully today.
Yeah, that particular disk is a Western Digital Red,
so it's not super fast.
And it's 6 terabytes, so it's going
to take a while to resilver.
There was two curveballs we hit that I was not expecting.
The first one is not too surprising, really,
in retrospect.
That is, we were installing to a USB device that sits on a USB
header inside the case.
This is something IX Systems does,
your OS is on a solid state.
I think it was, what, 16 gigabytes?
No, that one was four.
That was one of the difficulties of our initial replacement
technique.
I didn't realize we were, oh, jeez, yeah.
So we tried to get Fedora Server, which we actually
still got.
Totally worked just fine.
We got it within the four gigs on this little solid state USB
device.
The problem was, A, we were really low on space
after we started installing a few packages,
and B, it got like two megs a second write performance.
Ouch.
It was really bad.
So checking the key signatures on packages
would just take forever.
So we started just digging around the studio.
Because we have some equipment around here,
we thought, we must have an SSD somewhere.
So we dig around here and actually
could not find a spare SSD anywhere in the studio.
I guess that's good.
Means we're not wasting it.
Yeah, we don't have utilization here.
But I remembered we had an old Hackintosh
that towards the very end of its production line,
we put a 10,000 RPM, 320 gigabyte drive in it.
And then it only ran for like a couple of months,
and then we shut the system down.
And we converted off of it.
So I went in, I tore that machine open,
grabbed that disk out of the old Hackintosh,
and we kind of MacGyvered it into the FreeNAS box.
And so now we gave Fedora a 320 gigabyte, 10,000 RPM spinning
disk to work with.
But the system's really set up, and the data's
all across the RAID or the array.
So if the OS drive were to pop at some point in the future,
we'd have to reload it, but we wouldn't lose any data.
So we had that problem, took a little bit of MacGyvering
to solve that, because we needed some Molex power adapters
to convert to SATA.
And that wasn't so bad.
The one that really threw me for a twist
was we ran into essentially this issue.
And this is, again, I don't fully understand it.
So if you do, please feel free to write in
at linuxunplug.com slash contact and correct me.
But I couldn't use traditional NFS
to share out the ZFS volumes.
It would essentially stop at a mount point.
If you had sub-volumes that were mounted,
it would essentially stop at that mount point.
And it took us a little while to kind of root around.
And it even turns out that ZFS itself
has some NFS provisions built in.
And I was completely lost when it came to this aspect.
Yeah, so we ended up using the ZFS stuff.
You can just sort of set a property on your data set,
and then you may have to remount it.
I'm not clear on that exact particular.
But after that's done, it just shows up as an export list,
and you can mount it.
So we've got not everything's restored yet.
But I mean, we just need a few more commands,
and we'll have all your shares back.
Yeah, yeah.
So that was kind of funny, because the way it works
is I would mount the NFS share, and the directory structure
would be there.
But then I would get to the bottom level
where it was actually going into a sub-volume,
and it would just be empty, which
is where all the shows would be, or all the pictures would be.
So I'd have the directory structure,
but none of the data.
It's like, what happened?
Such a tease.
Did we lose it?
But we got it going.
We got it going, and it seems to be working pretty well.
And now, what we're going to do with this rig
is just have it run some local services.
We're in the process of finally replacing Dropbox,
and we're going to run some virtual machines on this.
And all of the main applications will run inside a container.
So the host operating system will be fairly unhinged
from future upgrades and stuff.
It'll be unimpeded, or whatever I'm trying to say.
What am I trying to say?
We just wanted to worry about it.
Yeah, we're not.
Most of our stuff will be running in containers.
This is not a bunch of apps and packages
we're going to have to worry about.
It's going to be a pretty clean base.
It's not that much data.
Yeah.
Not impaired.
Yeah, not impaired, whatever.
Not entangled, I don't know.
Not in long-term software commitments.
And then we're also going to set up WireGuard on that sucker,
so the host can get remote WireGuard services in
if they want to remotely control the mixer, things like that.
So that'll be on there.
It's already pretty nice.
Just got NetData installed before the show,
so I can watch as all the data is shuffling around
as it's resilvering, which is great.
It's pretty nice to have.
It feels like what I was, I'm such a nerd.
God, I was laying in bed talking to Hadea about the server.
I can't even believe I just.
Something tells me she's used to this.
And I was like, babe, you know, it's like I went out there
and found out we had a sports car in the garage.
And I thought it was like this little four-cylinder commuter.
Because we kind of forgot about the only, like, I mean,
I think you logged in for some reason
and happened to see the little blinking red light
on the Freenaz console, right?
Telling us like there might have been.
Otherwise, we just didn't think about it.
Sat there and ran.
It did its purpose really well.
I am kind of a believer in overbuilding your storage,
so that's what I did there.
But looking back at it, 64 gigs of RAM,
two six-core Xeon processors.
The thing's just begging to do more.
And not that I couldn't do it with FreeBSD or Freenaz.
Absolutely, we could have.
But I know how to do it with Linux.
It's just faster.
And we don't, I mean, we're not touching the system every day.
So it's nice to have something that's easy
and we don't have to relook up a bunch of man pages every time.
Yeah.
So we'll probably, well, eventually, I
imagine we'll spin up whatever our sync solution is
in a container.
We'll spin up a couple of other items
that I use internally for like processing news
and whatnot in containers.
And I'll move some of the things that I
have on the workstations in the studio now onto that server.
So that's what sort of the, and I'll just
do that gradually over time, probably
with some of the more urgent stuff.
And then I'll, like the syncing thing.
Because this new Dropbox has got to go.
This is just the final straw.
Dropbox has just crossed the line with this Electron stuff.
I will say it really did cement just why CFS is a great choice.
We could just port operating systems
and hardly had to think about it.
It's not that many other ways that we could have done this
and get all the other benefits.
It's a pretty dramatic switch.
We went from FreeBSD base with an old version of ZFS
to Fedora 30 with the absolute most recent version
on the most absolute recent Linux kernel.
Some would call us crazy.
Yeah, I've just really been enjoying Fedora 30.
You know, it's.
I would say, I mean, it honestly did feel vindicated.
It's hard to explain, but I feel like the whole process
was surprisingly pleasant because we run into several other issues.
All the stuff relating to Fedora and Fedora 30 server was great.
And that cockpit was up.
We've already done a bunch through that,
which was lovely as we were still trying to get everything set up
and only had console access.
It's just been a dream.
Really, I couldn't really ask for any more.
And it's funny because I've been running Fedora on the base
and then like Ubuntu in the containers and in the VMs.
That's just been my setup recently.
It's just been working really well for me.
And other people, different setups work.
But it reminded me of, I think it was right
when I first started listening to Jupiter broadcasting.
And it was before I'd ever used Fedora on the desktop.
I had, I think it was a Fedora 14, 15 on the server.
And it was one of my first and favorite Linux servers.
So it's nice to come home.
Yeah.
All right, Neil, I'm curious what you think.
I know you work a lot in the Red Hat space with ZFS.
Are we crazy?
Well, first of all, I thought that was really cool what you just said.
You were slightly crazy, but it was the good kind of crazy.
So I was OK with it.
I told Wes, I said, Wes, you know, I think we're officially
top gearing this thing right now.
I don't know, that other one was a pretty top gear event, too.
But with ZFS on Linux specifically, I think,
I'm not completely certain on this, that the kernel can't
see all the subvolumes.
So when it tries to evaluate all the things
that it exports through NFS, they won't work properly.
So that's why you need to use the ZFS built-in.
NFS share NFS feature on Linux.
In FreeBSD and other places, I think
it's all more tightly integrated so they can just do it normally.
And that makes sense, because when we switched over to that,
it did start working.
It just worked, yeah.
So now, it's not like ZFS has like their own implementation of NFS.
They're working with the kernel, right?
I can't answer that question confidently,
because it's been a long time since I've looked at that code.
That's just crazy to me.
That ZFS is huge.
That's massive.
And the fact that ZFS works the same way everywhere
is more of a testament to how much of an outsider file system
it is in most operating systems.
So it's developed very independently.
Right.
It comes with a bunch of extra stuff
so that it doesn't have to rely on what may or may not be there.
Right.
So a lot of these kinds of things have also
been relevant in macOS, for example,
because you can't really poke all the things the same way
that you can in FreeBSD and whatnot.
Yeah, it gave me a confidence.
It made me feel like, well, in the future,
if Fedora doesn't work out and we want to go to Ubuntu LTS,
I'm not going to have any problem getting my data.
It's just going to connect and import just fine.
It gave me a good sense of my data is safe.
Yeah.
And in respect to ZOL and all of these things,
Fedora and, of course, CentOS and RHEL
are first class test targets for ZFS on Linux.
So if it doesn't work in Fedora, it is pretty much a blocker,
because that is a problem.
Yeah, it was dead easy to set up, too.
It really couldn't have been easier.
Yeah, so making sure it works in CentOS and RHEL,
because, of course, enterprise people who want to use ZFS,
that matters.
But also using it in Fedora, that matters quite a fair bit,
especially since Fedora is very close to upstream
and the upstream kernels and stuff like that.
So it's a very big important point for that.
And to be clear, we went with Extended 4
on the root partition for the OS.
So the Fedora install is running on Extended 4,
and it is using a DKMS module to get ZFS working.
Yeah, well, I would have called you actually insane
if you had put ZFS on a root file system.
Yeah, we had some limit, some limit.
Don't think we didn't think about it.
I mean, it was a listed option.
We just didn't choose it.
Don't do it.
I'm just going to say this right now.
I have done it enough times.
Don't do it.
Unless you are running on CentOS where
you can use a precompiled kernel module that
works against the kernel API, it gets really unsafe very
easily.
Yeah.
Well, I'm just thrilled myself because I just
feel like I got a new tool to get work done.
Not that it wasn't always there, and I couldn't have done it,
but now I'm actually going to use it.
Yes, right.
And we were running some stuff on a personal workstation
of yours or other random machines,
so it's nice to have a proper place for it.
Yes, exactly.
So let me know if you think I'm crazy,
linuxunplug.com slash contact.
But before we get out of here, I want
to do just a couple of picks.
Right off the top, I got a couple command line
applications I love this week.
Speaking of command line love, speaking
of command line love, you should check out the Ubuntu podcast.
Do it.
And send them your ideas for command line applications.
Add Ubuntu podcast on the Twitters.
Here's a couple, guys.
You know what?
You are welcome to share these.
I share these with the Ubuntu podcast if you want them.
Because these are so good, everybody's
going to want these ones.
RGA is our first one.
It's like grep, but for PDFs, e-books, office documents,
zip files, tar.gz, et cetera.
You can grep even docx files, SQLite files, MKV files,
MP4 files.
Oh, yeah, all the things.
It's rip grep for everything or anything, something like that.
It's based off rip grep, which if you haven't used,
you really should.
Ah, OK, rip grep for everything.
Yeah, it's like a Rust implemented alternative grep
that's just super fast.
They've wrapped this here.
Wait, wait, wait, did you say rust?
Oh, yeah, of course, of course it is.
Of course.
Actually, I mean, the burnt sushi, the author
is a fascinating human with some really interesting stuff,
particularly about the implementation of how
the search engine algorithms work in something like grep.
So if you want to learn more, it's
not only a great implementation, it's a good learning
opportunity as well.
So this wraps that and lets it search in stuff like PDFs,
SQLite, all the things that you've been missing.
That could be really nice, to tell you the truth.
All right, so maybe searching things isn't your thing.
And since they're Rust, they're just each a little binary
you have to download, so no worries
about a complicated text.
Is there a way we could put that in a snap?
Yep.
All right.
Now, I love the fish shell, talk about it all the time.
I always encourage people to check it out.
The thing I love about the fish shell
is it does autocompletion for frequent commands.
But it's not perfect, because sometimes you
have different variations on commands,
or sometimes you have just commands
you only use very infrequently.
Wouldn't it be nice if you could bookmark commands
like you do URLs?
Well, friends, that's where Marker comes in.
It is a nice little application for your terminal
that lets you bookmark commands or entire command templates.
And here's the best part.
It lets you easily retrieve them with a real-time fuzzy language
matcher.
So you kind of just get in the ballpark
of what you're looking for.
It has a nice UI on the command line, again.
But it gives you a UI to select easily which command you wanted,
and then it'll execute it for you.
I could see this being really nice, too.
Maybe you have a team of sys admins,
and you have a shared toolkit for working with applications.
Oh, totally.
That's a great.
That would be a great use.
This is something I'm going to have to play with.
Yeah, you just need Python, like a semi-recent version
of Python, and Bash or Zshell.
And it'll work on Linux or Mac OS.
So there you go.
It's called Marker.
We'll have a link in the show notes for that, too,
which I feel like that'd be pretty handy for somebody
like me to have something like that on the server
that we just set up.
That's actually what I was saying.
I was like, oh, man, I could make you some defaults
for maybe a complicated little command or Python.
Something I do like once every six months.
Yeah, exactly.
You know, when the server has to have something done to it
or whatnot.
So anyways, check those out.
When we say the show notes, of course,
we mean in your podcast player or over at linuxunplug.com
slash 306.
Each episode is just slash right there.
Easy to find, easy to get to.
Mr. Payne, is there anything else
we need to mention before we get out of here?
No, I don't think so.
All right.
OK.
Easy peasy.
All right.
Cheesy, is there anything we need to cover before we leave?
You got anything for us?
Check out the new Telegram sticker pack.
Yeah.
Oh, it's so good.
Yep.
Or if you're not in the Telegram group, why not?
You go to broadcasting.com slash telegram.
That's right.
You should be.
All right.
Very good.
Thank you, Mr. Bacon.
Now, I also want to thank all of you for listening.
I appreciate every single one of you.
You're the most important.
No offense, Jase, but they are.
They are.
All of you.
This show has done so well over the years.
We really just are so thankful for every single one of you
for listening.
So thank you so much.
Thank you for subscribing.
Appreciate that.
That's really great.
We have a great community out there.
Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode
of the Unplugged program.
You are welcome, invited, and encouraged
to join us live next Tuesday over at jvlive.tv.
Get that time at jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
And of course, linuxunplugged.com slash subscribe
for the cleaned up, released version every Tuesday.
Thank you guys for listening.
Bye.
Yay!
I know I'm biased and I'm probably supposed to say this but we really have
the best audience it's incredible it really is and that's what's been so like
this has been the season of events where we've been traveling a lot in fact we're
about to travel again and just really the best freaking audience ever like
friends for life a number of incredible people at me and just continue to me
yeah it is wild it's great it's the best part of the job so thank you everybody
JBtoddles, JBtoddles, thank you to that Mumble Room for making it too really good to
have all you guys here jeez what are you talking about what's the matter no I'm
just saying I'm just saying after we get off the show I think I might hang
around on the jump on the old mums oh yeah oh yeah oh I got you so I got you
doing posts a little post hang up look plug mmm I like it yeah right you're
already suited up you got your microphone on yeah oh yeah you know it
all right JBtoddles.com let's go grab our title otherwise we'll all take your
voting rights away mmm so poppy how's the old feedback been on the distro
specific snap pages yeah other than getting for incorrectly using the
fedora go oh oh I noticed I was trying not to be mean about it or anything I
just said hey can you fix it please you know what I think it's a good idea I
like it I like it too you know but jeez you know you can't please the entire
in a poppy if you did it'd be a miracle worker hey I thought it was good I
didn't say anything awful about it that sentence is it's pretty solid I like
that has my audio gone funny again every now and then I think it's just packet
loss weird I mean from my side it's been everyone's been kind of cutting out a
little bit which has been odd because that doesn't normally happen
Leonard oh man that poor guy dude I'm not even talking to you from my Linux
machine right now because I'm hiding in a conference room are you are you
permitted to say that I think I think you have to like get clearance or
something poppy already knows this from the times that I've met him at various
events mainly snap sprints but I was in one OS I was gonna say I've never
actually seen him run Linux oh no no no at the the rally two years ago I think
the one in New York the whole time I brought my Linux laptop with me Noah
saw it and so did a couple of other people I have witnesses now hold on now
we're not we're not we're not come on we don't we don't we don't know a shame we
got a call for an end of this the tribalism you know like I feel like I
should walk around be like my name is Chris I'm a Linux user and I also have
an iPad you know like I have to just come I have to come holding your iPad so
they'll see I have to come clean about it I don't know no more down with the
tribal you see at home I have a MacBook I have I have numerous Linux machines
running all many different distros here's where I think it has validity
though like I think if you work in free software and open source or in that
space like then that should be your primary stack that should be your main
stack because that's your area but it would be ignorant not to ever try a
Windows or Mac because then you would have zero insights into how very popular
very commercial very successful commercial operating systems yeah you
have to what you have to do that