Oh
Man, I'm glad we got a head start on the show yesterday because I had the hugest time suck this morning. What was it?
So my dad very nicely for my birthday got me the let me look these things up. Have you seen the Logitech?
Harmony, are you familiar with you're familiar with Harmony remotes, right?
They like the the big remote that like oh, yes
And you can have like modes where it turns on your your your receiver and it turns on your sound bar
And it turns on your sub and it turns on your DVD player turns on your TV and changes the input to the DVD player
Or blu-ray, right? It's these very functional
It's a poor man's echo. No, I guess it kind of it was a little bit in some ways, wasn't it?
Wasn't it? Well, it's funny you say that so the
The harmony this is the latest and greatest in this and it's this is a hub
That has like a thousand irs blasters that it shoots out everywhere plus has a little
remote IR blasters that you can set up in your home a little naughty and they recently
announced echo support
So you could use this as the intermediate hardware between your echo and your televisions pretty neat
So you can say things like echo turn on the TV turn off the TV turn on the sound bar things like that
And so that anything it can control with IR you've suddenly got access. Yes
So then Chris got very interested in this hub
So it's so if you're curious so far, this is a logitech harmony hub
And you could all have to have if you're a masochist and just want to use your smartphone to control all the things
You could also use this
With your smartphone and it just it looks like this
It's a little unoffensive puck and what's nice about this particular puck is the entire the entire
Surface and all of the edges is made of IR blasters
So it just shoots off IR in like every direction
Which is very nice for getting to a lot of your devices and then it comes
With in the box one additional I remote IR blaster that you can set up
Yeah, it looks like the remote is kind of an optional thing
So you can buy the hub on its own for like 90 bucks, right?
Which MSRP from logitech or you can go up with like the touchscreen remotes and stuff
So this pushed enough of my buns I was like interesting but not enough that I was gonna spend my own money
But my dad said hey, I'd like to get you a birthday present back in January. All right
Well, this would be something I wouldn't buy for myself, but I'd like to try so good old dad
He did he got me one of these and I have I just left in the box since January because you know
I'm not like super excited about this. I'm curious about this. And so I thought well today will be the day
How long could this take?
I've got a half hour. You've set up things with the echo before I'm actually I'm kind of in a groove, right?
Because I've been setting up TP link power adapters and Belkin white Wiimos or whatever they are
Like I've been in a groove recently. So I'm like, yeah, you know what I can bust this out
Um
Dear God, this was literally one of the most brutal setups I've ever done in my life. It is so bad
So first of all it expect it
scans your whole network and tries to find anything that it thinks it might be able to pair with Bluetooth devices Wi-Fi devices and
So if you have multiples of any device, it course isn't very good at differentiating them
So I have two Nvidia shields in the RV. So it just has shield one shield two
I have no idea which one is is which then after it detects everything it it it
Calculates activities for me automatically like playing games and listening to music and then tries to create these dramatic
Formulas that you have to then go edit in this really awful app
So I spent 45 minutes fighting with the app trying to figure out how I could go in and change those. Yes
It was rough because I really all I want is turn on my TV turn on my soundbar wake up the shield
Well, you don't need like the whole I don't I'm in my theater right turn it on now it by default
It wants to turn on the TV select the input for me then turn on the soundbar select the input on the soundbar like I
Don't want any of that
I just want you to and then it's then after that point it assumes you're gonna use it as the actual remote for the television
And I don't want any of that and it and then it's just it's it's
Compounded because anytime you go through the app to change the setting it
Automatically plays a woman's voice over tutorial in the background
So you get to points where you start hearing the same thing over and over again, but they don't cash it locally
So if you're on a my fight connection, you're just you sit there wait
Voice in the rest of the UI does not respond until the voice overloads off of the internet every single time
So that's literally one of the worst things ever
Really awful Wow like nails in the eyeballs awful waiting for that every single time. This is the only way to configure it eyes
Yeah, yeah
Well, actually there's one more which I'll be getting to but I managed to get through all of this eventually and it's bad
And oh my and dear lord help yourself if you don't correctly put in the device. So I have a continue us TV
which is I
Silly me did continue with co co and ITU space us. Okay
That's no good. No, it's dot us not period like the ASCII dot
So you have to get on your mobile phone you have to put the ASCII dot in between continue and us
Which I just put a dash in there the first time I try to space
And it's a smart little device here, right?
Yeah, and then and then you have to get the model number just right which thank goodness. I scanned the RV
Manuals and paperwork so I was able to pull that up and that up because otherwise it's under the mount for the for the television
Ah, yep, you know, it's like yeah get it off the back your television. It's on a mount
I can't I'm not gonna unmount my television to get the model number so that so you got I go through all of this
Finally get it turning on the television and turning on the soundbar, which is all I want after an hour
Which is just I was I just I'm like, okay. I've got to go but now that I've gone this far. I
Must make sure it works with the echo
Otherwise what the hell was the point of all of this because I'm trying to set up a system
Where Hedia or the kids or myself can say echo?
Turn on the television and it turns on the soundbar and it turns on the TV and the soundbar is particularly hard to turn on
You have to get that remote in just the right spot
That's kind of tricky for like, you know four-year-old or three-year-old or five interest point six-year-old seven-year-old eight-year-old, you know
They're they're good, but they're not like they don't know the fact that there's this little IR surface on this
Otherwise large soundbar that you have to hit just right and those are exactly the kind of things you don't want your users to have
To know anything right and and if they wake up super early and they want to watch Steven Universe
Why come get dad at 5 a.m
When you know, so they can just say echo turn on the TV and then they can say echo start plex echo play Steven Universe
And it all happens automatically, but you have to have this device to make it all work
This is the grand vision after all Starship Enterprise on lady tubes
So I finally get it online. I finally get it controlling the devices. I
Go to scan the network with the echo. It doesn't see the Harmony Hub
So I you know, I'm looking up stuff
Okay, I have to have this particular version of the firmware on the Harmony Hub to be compatible with Alexa cancel. So
Sure enough that firmware the newest firmware or is it like one newest the absolute newest and I'm one release behind one release behind
But the real gotcha is how you update it now
I don't know if this is the only I don't know if this is the only way and I think it might not be
But at this point, I don't never use this thing. So I'm going purely off their documentation, right?
I just don't know what else to do and I don't really have the even the patience to Google it even further
But this is where Google has gotten me so far. It's a Logitech documentation
Download this DMG file to your computer. It says
Well, I'm on arch so I got to close all my stuff
I got a log out of slack where we're talking, you know planning the show
At least you can do this because you're on your yeah
Yeah, and I reboot in into Final Cut OS and I then I have to go back to that webpage through my same Google search
Hierarchy that I went through to get there because of course I didn't bookmark it and then I download the dumb DMG and I open
Up the installer and I run it and at the end the installer says the installation is finished
Would you like to move the installer to the trash? Yeah, okay fine
Then it gets in some sort of loop where it can't delete itself because the process is active
But then it wants to so after I just force close all of that
I I then have to this is such a crazy thing on the Mac
I don't I don't think people think about this if you because you know
I dip into the Mac OS to go do something like Jesus. This is how you do it
So after you use an installer because you're supposed to click and drag software on the Mac to install it like back in my old
Mac OS days, this is how you did it and a lot of people still distribute software that way, especially under DMGs
Yeah, sure, but not Logitech
No Logitech distributed an installer file which just dropped an application somewhere on my hard drive
But there's there's not like there's a menu entry that's updated
There's there's I don't know what name to invoke in Spotify search. It's not in the applications folder. What are you gonna do?
That's the whole thing. No, it's worse. Even if it's in the applications folder, what's it called? Yeah
What's the name of the app?
There's no way to know on the Mac and even if you sort by modified date
You don't get the right date because they've decompressed it from a file system image and they've copied to your file system
They preserve date and time so I can't even sort by modified time to find what the new application is
I don't know how Mac users do it. And so then I figure out well, okay, it's harmony something. So H. Nope
That's not there. Okay, Logitech L. Nope, not that's not there. Oh, they've called it my harmony
Now the app on the phone just called harmony, but of course on the computer, it's my heart a little more personal there
So I double-click my harmony dot app and yes, of course
It's not signed and then I'm greeted with before I can proceed to update the firmware on my hub
I'm greeted with the prompt to upgrade Silverlight
It's a Silverlight application. What it's a silver light. What? Yes. Yes. Yes. Okay. Okay. I say to myself fine
All right, you're on the frontiers of the digital world here
We're gonna press on and skip the Silverlight update and see if this thing works
So then I go to update the firmware and they've got this big button on the side
That says this big Silverlight pulsing button that says upgrade your harmony. I'm like
And I'm reading the website too, and I just double-checked the documentation
Documentation says click to upgrade your harmony button
To update the firmware, right?
so I click that button and
It takes me to a screen where it wants to upsell me on additional devices for my harmony with no firmware update
I'm like what so I go back to the documentation and I kid you not it says or
If after you click upgrade harmony, you don't get an upgrade click the sync button up in the right corner. What?
Sync button to update my firmware. Okay, so I click the sync button and it starts sinking mice
Well first it asked me if I want to log into logitech harmony and either use Facebook or Google to do it
Oh, yeah, great. Okay. So here you go. Click my Google thing now Google's got this too
They had it all don't worry sinks it starts syncing with the logitech servers sink and what you might ask
Well, apparently the first thing it sinks is the new firmware. So that's great. Although you don't really know this
It just says sinking and ever since upgrading firmware
So you don't really know it's doing that and then it syncs with the new firmware
And then it syncs all of your settings to the logitech servers and by sync all of my settings
It pulls down all of the wrong settings that I had just fixed on the damn thing before I decided to update
And refer to one revision back where nothing works
Even has the wrong TV model in there gets the new firmware breaks all my activities
So then I have to go through the activities app another brutal time to get the activities updated plug it back in and now it's all
working
Forty-five half way through I thought about it, but I just didn't want to give up
Yeah, I didn't want to give up and now now I'm there now. I've got it. So just never touch it again
Yeah, now I'm gonna go down the road and the IR blaster is gonna come off the mountain that'll break it
But other than that, how do you like it now that it's working?
I've only I literally only had it working for five minutes and I just get here
So tonight will be the true test
This is Linux Unplugged episode 185 for February 21st 2017
Oh
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that is currently and presently
Bursting at the seams with good news. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Wes
Hello, you know as I am I am just
Thrilled with today's lineup
I I am really looking forward to a chat that you and I are about to have sort of right at the top of the
Show and then sort of at the end of the show just really great clip from Linus on
Reflected on 25 years of working on the Linux kernel
We have some great project updates some big new features coming to all of us
Linux users some great news from the elementary folks and a hardware device
and
It's already it's already exciting but the hardware device that if Noah heard about this
Well, it would blow his mind. In fact, we better not tell him in fact
I've tried to avoid telling him I stuck it and unplugged so that way he may he might have missed it, right?
Because he's busy right now. He's busy right now and and you know, that's just sort of the tip of the iceberg
That's just sort of the tip I could sit here and tell you all day what we're gonna be talking about
We got some we got some really good gnome stuff to get some great plasma stuff. Oh, but Wes
We're gonna start the show with a big news
Big news story coming from the folks over at cute and Nvidia
So before we can get ourselves mentally prepared something we have to do there is a there is a there's one duty
We must perform and that's bringing in and welcoming our virtual log time appropriate greetings mumble room
Oh, hello there. Well, hello. Hello. So gentlemen
Upon us today is a great show
We I am every single story I am so thrilled to talk about and this first one is is gonna be good for those of us
On Linux that want to do a little 3d modeling just something I like to do from time to time playing with 3d studios
Blender things like that that I don't know. I don't have any idea what I'm doing
It's like an adult version of The Sims, right?
It is exactly a great way to play and so of course other people will find other reasons to find this great
But Nvidia is open sourcing and contributing to cute the Nvidia Drive design studio
Which is a designer friendly 3d UI authoring system. Mmm
It's now released with the name cute 3d studio or QT 3d studio
Depending on your preparation the contribution consists of several hundred thousand lines of source code
It consists of a runtime component designer friendly tooling and cute integration
Wow, this allows us to bring state-of-the-art 3d tooling to the whole cute ecosystem
And they say it's complementary to existing technology
They have a video here doesn't say much in the video
But it shows you a little bit of what the tool does it looks and the video is 3d so oh it is
Oh, are you being honest?
YouTube does that actually
They have 3d video and they have the AR video and so I'm gonna now I'm gonna look Wes now
Nah, oh a shame that looks like that looks like windows like when I guess that's an advantage of cute, right?
Yeah, you know also he's on a Wacom there. And did you see the news today that I think in kernel 411?
We're gonna have some specific Wacom tablet support latest gens of their tablet supported
It's great to see that continue
They've had good support do you or does anyone in the lug there know of an application on Linux where you could take?
Handwritten notes. I asked that because good question. I find my I find myself a pretty forgetful man
But if I write something down, I almost never even need to look at it again. There's something about the active
Yeah, you've got two notebooks. You literally have your laptop propped up on two notebooks
You have two different notebooks with you right now. Wow. So you probably do find it useful to write things
Yeah, I really I really enjoy using the written word
But ultimately I end up wanting it on a computer ranks. I want to search it
Maybe I won't tag that maybe I just want to archive it and I don't want paper
I was just telling you about how I was able to look up the model number of my TV because I have a system
I can go back and search for documents for the RV same thing
so I was really wondering if you or anybody in the virtual lug there knows of a
System in Linux where if you have an input device like a pen input device, maybe it's a tablet
Maybe it's you know on a touch screen or a Wacom or yeah
Is there any is there any note-taking application on Linux that accepts handwriting not necessarily recognizes it even would be nice
I don't know. That's a good question
Bumble room. Not sure really
Yeah, I've heard of well if anybody out there listening knows I'd sure like to external external. Hmm
Yeah, I've used external. I've also used draw with
Just a draw pad cheap
When I bought off a mono price is you can just write on it and it will actually show up and draw so you can
Do notes of my boarding? Oh, this is
Why is it external or external because to be normal so people in the chat room are calling a zurnal or something
Which I'm gonna look it up right now. Yeah zurnal. Okay zurnal. Oh
Look at this
This looks old as F. Yeah, it hasn't been updated since 2014, but that's all right if it works if it works
Yeah, if I can if I can build it. Do you think it could be in there?
You are do you think it? Oh, let's try it live on there. Let's look right now
Embarrass ourselves. Let's find out. Let's find out if it's in the a you are it isn't hey you are. Let's see if it bills
Look at the guy in GTK 3. Oh my gosh. I'm gonna try to get GTK 3 version
Just because we'd like to live dangerous reasons
Because I mean that's probably the only thing that really needs updated on the thing if it works and then there was another suggestion too
right
Yeah, and look at that look at that it's installing right now
You are so much. That's why I can't leave you arch. I can't leave you. I can't how do you daddy?
How do you how do you daddy give that up? I don't know how do you get that up pretty hard so okay there you go
Okay, I'm gonna. I'm gonna play around if I this why you know the Wacom tablets are not crazy cheap
But I don't they are also very good devices, and I could probably use an editing too, so they have such nice Linux support
Yeah, well they then the one that I've been looking at which is the more reasonable priced one is gonna be in 411
Everything isn't there you are even plasma, so this is a great story
This could be a runs Linux if we were had recorded Linux action show this week
This is a good deployment of plasma desktops in the Australian schools now
I don't know how many of them total looks like 34 classrooms two counseling rooms some teacher rooms and some labs
It's not like all of that island over there
I think it's just just these but it's also 75 teachers that use it and 700 students
There's a lot of exposure here. Yeah, it's a great user base in fact
There's been some good bugs that have been found already in this user base and fixed I
Thought this was really good, so this was an interview with Thomas who helped set all of this up
He's the he's the guy over there that sort of I think pushed us because he's an open-source software enthusiast
He's a teacher. He's a web developer and a father, but not particularly any specific order
He says although I bet there is he says that at least 75 teachers are going to work within the system and most of the
7700 students will won't be on their computers these gonna be like computers just for the teachers
And this is an interesting kind of breakdown that they have
So first let me tell you about the hardware that I'll tell you about the way
They're breaking down the systems for usage because there's he likes two things about plasma for this one the customizability
Let's the students go crazy and the kiosk mode which prevents them from going crazy, so I'll tell you more about that
But here is the hardware first in some systems in some rooms. They have like old triple EPCs. It's rough, right?
Yep, so they've been able to switch to more powerful Acer laptops some with four some with eight gigs of RAM nice
That's goes a long way. Yeah, and you know in my ten-year-old Linux test that I did on that ten-year-old PC
Plasma desktop the latest plasma desktop ran just fine with four gigs of RAM
32-bit would be a little rough to hang on the distro
But one of our computer labs just got an upgrade with new HP desktops and big Samsung screens
Everyone loves those and he says everything works like a charm
They did have some problems mirroring the displays to a projector without losing configured widgets
But a bug was fixed in plasma 592. Thanks to Marco Martin, which I want to stop right there
I don't know if you've ever been in a deployment where you have end users where there's a bug in the software that prevents it
Working correctly for your users if it's a commercial desktop like Windows
Your only hope is to wait for the maybe a service pack if it's something like this
But most likely the next version of the Windows release which could be years away
And in this scenario he was able to submit a bug and work with Marco Martin
To get this thing have an opportunity like, you know
You can rely on the open source community
Yeah, if you have enough resources you can hire developer to try to fix it yourself
yeah, there's a lot of there's a lot there are options at all that is an unbelievable level of
Freedom that you I think when we talk about freedom, we don't consider that level of freedom and by the way
Yes, they're using KD neon. So they're getting those updates. They're getting those updates nice fairly quickly
So here's the breakdown
They bet on plasma because they made it just kind of out of the box
And it's also pretty easy to customize it to make it look like Windows 7
Which is really important for the acceptance of the teachers. I have experienced this myself to specifically having put Linux in labs before
Making it look more when this is one of the reasons why we eventually I think
Either it was either known to at the time or it was X FCE
I can't remember we ended up spending some time making it look like Windows to
To increase the acceptance by the teachers there
I was I was honestly shocked and I'm sure this isn't the case everywhere
but in our little podunk town here in Arlington, Washington, I
Was shocked at the resistance I got from people who are educators, you know, you think they're about
learning and and knowledge and
Analysis and they were it was it was pure rejection for change
Sake alone because they weren't necessarily happy with the Windows machines. They were having lots of problems, but they they didn't it wasn't a change
Yeah
But they're also probably kind of old right so change is hard for them in some cases. Yes. Yeah, and definitely yes
I definitely had teachers where it was the case where change was hard and there's only so much change they can do at a time
and that's just something that's like
Scope of teeth like teaching and all that stuff already consumes enough of them that changing their
Operating system isn't necessarily something they want. Yeah, it's like any busy people age was
Yeah age was commonly higher than those cases. But honestly anybody had the mindset. I'm too busy to handle what I already have now
I can't take anything else and that was off that could even that it was even sometimes some of the younger teachers
But yeah, I have some sympathy but yeah
I can kind of understand too
But you know at the same time
Like it was a huge problem for us time wise because they were constantly getting messed up
It was a big problem for them because they were constantly being taken out of order because they weren't working appropriately
So we needed something to change sometimes you have to change isn't it? So making it more windows-like was a huge acceptance factor
So I buy it here when he says they went with plasma because they can make it more like Windows 7 in some ways
So they hadn't heard about chillin. Yeah. Yeah. What was the name of it? Yeah. Yeah
So he says the first hour working with students is all about 3d effects custom fonts widgets and custom themes
After a half hour every single student desktop looks completely different and the students start to see it as their own system
Totally now that clicked with me for a second
Because you know Dylan his laptop
He took it on when when we are able to start changing things the way he liked it like it turns out when I gave it
To my like I had every app he would want to use in his dock
And put it like a special background on there. He didn't like any of that stuff
He only wanted one icon in his dock
He wanted he wanted a very specific
Minecraft background and then he really kind of took more he took a lot more ownership of it now
I thought this was interesting though in the classrooms. It's different
It's absolutely necessary that everyone leaves the computer in a usable state for the next teacher
So that's a reason the plasma shell was also picked because of the kiosk mode
He says he's had to you know work a lot of bugs out with the plasma developers
But they've done an amazing job fixing all the bugs
Since like five dot eight and above they say he says they now have a desktop that is completely launched to make sure nobody accidentally removes
Or reconfigures important parts of the user interface
And I honestly it my solution back in the day to solve that problem was I had a GDM
Logout script or a camera was log out or log in I think was log out script
that just deleted the home directory and then would copy over from like a a
default template directory I had
To do shared home directories basically like they're trying to just do isolated instances. Yeah
Well in my case we did we did network home directory so when the student would log in they'd get it mounted in their home
directory
and then when they would log out I would delete the home directory and then I would copy over a template directory that was
From a tar file that I could then SCP to the to the lab machines to give them a new desktop
I just SCP to new tar file and log out log in you get the new desktop nice
If you you have the whole home directory isolated per student right even matter
It shouldn't matter as soon as they log out it all gets cleared away
Yeah
And and one of the reasons we are able to do the run of the reason we went this route is in the labs
We just had a lab account and all of the students use the same lab account which you can imagine how awful that was under windows
Yeah, yeah, I had to go and of course here comes you know hotshot Chris
Well, we got to get user accounts set up. Everybody's got to have their own logins
Oh my god, you want to talk about resistant to change, you know, I was like, okay
These are the labs students want to come in that's fine
But then the same time we've got to have some way to wipe these things out and make them usable
It's probably a little easier today when like 90% of what they do is just gonna be in a web browser
Other things yes school stuff. Yes you back then it was a lot more it was GIMP. It was LibreOffice
there's a lot more stuff that students expected and flash and browser plugins all had to be just right and if you
Anything got monkeyed with it was a mess for the students
So that was a that was a different time and now kiosk mode sounds like it would do a lot of the work for me
So when I was in high school
We also had Linux which was pretty which was pretty but I think a lot of the a lot of the teachers had had Macs
Or I think a couple Windows machines as well. So it was a mixed environment, but all the labs were Linux. Yeah
Yeah, well you had a mixed environment. It was an old gnome 2, but you know it worked well
And that was a Firefox still the days of open office
I think just when it had started, but that was working pretty well Firefox. Yep Wow
University was still using gnome 2 two years ago
Good good times. I didn't you know I didn't know it was that I thought we were kind of a weird off
Cuz you know this is a while ago now. Yeah, totally. I thought we were a little bit of a weirdo
Well, it's interesting reflecting back because at the time like
Right as I was graduating I kind of got into it
I think so that was before you know I'd compiled a few C programs and play with the bouncy
It's like you want to play games when I should be studying right?
Yeah, but it really did work well, and I hope they're still doing I should check back in on them
Yeah, I mean I tell you I've told the story before the show, but the couple of times Linux
What first time I thought Linux was interesting and a really and I realized oh
This is a really powerful OS was when I accidentally RM RF a running system
By my workstation in my classroom totally and I was like jeez
I not only not only was I impressed that I could even do that and I there was no like I don't you had to do
Tactic there was no there was just you just it just did it
And then the other thing that I was amazed by is that it took me about five minutes to realize what happened because open office
And gnome just kept running you know cuz they're in memory
Yep, and it wasn't until I went to go do something that wasn't a memory that I was like oh
That's I think we've all seen that you're like and I was like okay
This is a really cool system, but I didn't really do anything with it after that
But then and then and I've told I won't go into it
But we use Linux a few times to really save the day of network wise
Just change things for us, and then I was like okay. This is this is really screw now where screw Windows NT
This is this is what I was smiling one more actually two more quick plasma things, and then we'll get going here
This was just kind of an interesting at this point technology experiment
It's too bad none of our canonical friends are here to tell us how great this is because I'm not particularly impressed
But it's it's a good first step. I'll put it that way
So we've talked a lot about flat packs and app images and snap packages
And it looks like Alex has taken the challenge of putting all of plasma in a snap
So one single snap and you get the entire plasma desktop pretty neat idea
But you know snap is still kind of new and so he ran into some really interesting things
So first of all distributing binary builds would be less of a hassle for them testing is more accessible
Can try them in in various ways can lessen the impact of security issues and confined software, so these are good things
reasons to consider distributing with snap format
But there's two main challenges that it breaks down to snap software is mounted and changing paths that are different from the installation directory and
Confining plasma is a bit tricky because of how many actors are involved in a plasma session
some of the medium far-reaching access to system services right as it turns out problem one in particular is
By is biting plasma fairly hard not exactly a great surprise
You know when you relocate and install plasma. It isn't exactly something that they normally do in the past so
they had to essentially go through and figure out what dependencies would break when the
Session move when the installation path moves and for one of them for example one of them is like ex-wayland things like that have
To be refigured out
But the other thing that I found to be more interesting and wondering if this isn't going to be a really bigger problem and sort
Of limit the potential for confined applications
Confining plasma as a whole is fairly straightforward albeit a bit of a drag since it's basically a matter of figuring out
What is or isn't required to make things fly a lot of the logouts and logins is just basically what it takes
Fortunately snaps have a built-in mechanism to expose deba session services offered by them a full-blown plasma session has an enormous
Amount of services it offers on debus from the general purpose notification service to special interest plasma activity services
Being able to expose them effectively is a great help in tweaking confinement to get plasma to start to work with confinement a bunch of holes
Need to be poked in confinement that are outside the scope of the existing interface
Kaywin in particular is taking the role of a fairly central service in the plasma wayland world
So it needs far-reaching access so we can do its job
Unfortunately interfaces currently can only be built with snap these source tree itself
So we had to make an example interface which covers most of the core services relevant
But unless you build snap D. It wouldn't be easy to try because you'd have to be building the latest version
so in summary
There's a lingering question of whether confining like this makes sense at all
Putting all plasma into the same snap means this one snap will need lots of permissions and interaction with the host system
At the same time it also means that keeping confinement profiles up to date would be a
Continuous task and feat as there are so many things offered and used by one step
so it may be that the things things like large desktop environments all
One snap not gonna be not it's not gonna be really possible to say here's the plasma snap
You're probably gonna have to break it up into smaller components like a Kaywin snap and right now
I do think it's always good like it's painful when you run into these things
But I feel like it's usually helpful when you are forced to sort of enumerate exactly what access your stuff requires
Especially as we become more security conscious great community
I know I see that a lot with like deployments and stuff where you're like, oh, yeah
Well, I require all these things and suddenly when you have to specify them you understand really what your requirements and dependent
It is always good to always be looking at what those are and re-asking and I know the switch to Wayland has has invite some
of that definitely
So let's one more plasma thing and I wanted to I wanted to pick up from where we left off last week with you
So during the show last week you switched over to the plasma desktop for that's right
And we've also got the state of plasma that was posted at net runner net runner dash mag comm
Which will have linked in the show notes
So I I kind of wanted to go over your experience cover his experience because I've been I've been
I've been so impressed with the plasma desktop specifically five nine
That I've had a hard time articulating what's wrong with it
people said so what's not working still and I'm having a hard time articulating it because I'm
I'm not like in review mode. I'm just like in use mode on like I'm just a geek out mode
and so I haven't really had to turn on that part of my brain until I started really getting this question more and more and
So now I've slipped into more review mode of the plasma desktop
And so I've I've got some observations of things that I think should be improved
But there's still not major things and so I'm curious to hear what your experience has been so far
I've been pretty impressed. I think it's been a year or two since I really had like plasma Katie anything as my main desktop
Some things I like like I already use quassel and other other cute applications
So it was nice to kind of have that be my native environment, but I have been approaching it very much like what you said
Just install and the defaults work
I was kind of interested in exploring with that because that's really what I do a lot of the time with gnome at least on
like this laptop which we
Refresh for the show a lot that kind of thing
So I really just kind of installed Katie start or plasma started working with it
it took me a while to like get used to some of the trivial things just like the
Like the mouse cursor is a little bit different plus some of the applications
I use like I have a lot of like
Telegram or slack they didn't integrate quite as nicely or look quite as nice with with just the default theme as I found that they
Did with home really, but I have not I have not customized that much
So I'm kind of interested to hear so another part that I I like I've been unit using unity at work
Mostly just because I got my desktop refreshed there haven't taken the time to customize that either because you know get work done
But I have been thinking about either installing gnome or plasma so now plasma is on the list
but like one of the things I think unity does well is
Imitate a tiling desktop or give me some of those features a lot of times really what I want and
Cinnamon does this well is just like quadrants even just splitting half their screens
But especially quadrants just gives me enough flexibility when I have multiple terminals open
Have you played it all with like the dragging the window and snapping it to an edge?
That's fine, but especially when I'm on a trackpad
I really want so like unity you can do I forget what I did like control out to you can do the quad
It works nicely
Cinnamon, I think is the best it does the pretty native little keyboard. Yeah, and they're really simple
Yes, and and no more so okay
You get the sides you can't do quadrants which frustrates me or at least not without like g tile or other things like that
I feel like keyboard commands. That is definitely something you could set up in the plasma. Yeah, so I would that's one of the areas
I'd be appreciate feedback because I'd like to figure out the best ways to kind of get those because with that I
I think it's very workable. I've been impressed for a while before I got all the KD you like wallet stuff set up, right?
Yeah, I would have problems where it's like I switch between you know and then chrome breaks
So that was kind of frustrating for a while. I got that working
Really everything else has been top-notch. It's been smooth. No crashes. I'm very impressed with Kaywin everything
So you know this you know yes
You do you notice like the way when like the dragging the windows it feels a little different than known yes
It definitely feels different. Yeah
Everything's like a little bit
Smoother or it feels like it
It has more effect in it, but not in this not in a slow way
I don't know the showy way not in a showy way showy and I also have turned the speed of mine up
One notch too. I've so they're a little bit faster on my system, but um
it does it in a way where it feels like a
Like a solid system. It feels solid it does feel solid so I would also say like on here
I'm running it with four gigs of RAM as well. It runs. Just right. No problem
I experienced my first two crashes today for the first time and they weren't major the first one was actually almost sort of pleasant
I know it's a funny thing to say but the the
Panel faded out my widgets faded out my background faded out faded to black for a few seconds for one second really and then faded
Back, I think that was a crash and then and then and then about a couple minutes later. I
I had it they cut out and cut back clunk clunk, and I think it was because I had done updates
But I hadn't rebooted yet. I'm not sure so that's something I have to check
I still haven't even checked on it, so I wanted to read this state of the state of the plasma
I didn't want to read the whole thing just a couple of notes because I thought this first part really resonated with my past
Experience and I also you know before I get into this
I mean, I'm a little on tangents today cuz West got me this kickstart energy drink. That's right. I did
People sometimes say God you guys talk too much about solace or
Geez you guys been talking a lot about plasma recently
And there's that undercurrent of arch just all the time. Yeah, yeah sure sure so I have I think what it is is a
misunderstanding of the philosophy that I've begun to adopt for this show, and I haven't articulated it because I I don't often I
Don't often talk about these things right
But I believe I think one of the I think one of the number one things missing from tech
journalism
Would you know I've gone on plenty of tirades man?
I think it's just like journalism don't you one of the things I think is just the worst is
We come out with these big huge reviews of stuff like and I love like my favorite whipping boy is is the Windows 10
Cortana is gonna change everything Windows 10 is so amazing this this this this well
Where's all the follow-up reviews about Cortana and how useful it is where's all the follow-up the ones that really mean the most?
Where is it? Where is it a year after using it and so my?
Myself my philosophy is first of all this is a weekly show
So we got to have something to talk about every week and the second of all what I what we're what I'm trying to do
to in this in some sense is
Create a story arc of our experience with these things
So that way if you are a weekly listener
Every week you are getting an update in the story of our usage of these sort of like as for you Star Trek fans
It's like the difference between TNG and deep space 9
We're more deep space not exactly Linux action shows more TNG. You don't always get the little encapsulated
It's not the yeah, right you don't get the full review type thing
But you get dialogue with the creators you get our chats about daily use yeah, yeah
And so that's why we're talking about plasma again because in a few weeks
Maybe I won't be using anymore, and I won't be talking about it
But for right now that's part of the story of the show
And then we're gonna take just so we'll just take a couple of minutes and talk about it, so
He had something here that I thought was really pointed because it's essentially been my feelings
He says since 2014 plasma has kept me in
entertained and disappointed in equal in equal measures at some point
I had crowned my fate. I had it crowned as my favorite desktop
And then it started going downhill steeply and fast struggling to recover not helping was the slew of bugs and regressions across the distro space
Which exasperated the quality of plasma and what it could show to the world I?
Think that's so right on that is so right on with what was wrong with the plasma desktop for a long time
It is so freaking right on and you know that was you guys have even heard me come on the show my gal
I'm using plasma again. It's great, and then a few weeks later. I'm back on them. Yep
and
And that is exactly where I've been at
And I think neon is playing a huge role in showing us
How other distributions have gotten so damn close, but what neon is doing is really light touch it touches same defaults
And here's your packages. Here's your packages. Here's your packages
Oh, and yeah, yeah happens to be the folks behind the desktop are pretty relevant to the project itself
So that helps plot and you know one of the things I have found by switching over to it again after using gnome for a long
Time now is the plasma retains some of the functionality that's disappeared from gnome based systems
Including just like trivial things like being able to create new files using the right-click menu
Being able to right-click and it just built in I don't have to go find like some script on the internet and put it in
My action systems. It's just I right-click in a folder. I go to the actions menu. It says open terminal here
I use that I love that I use that 30 times a day every day
I use that because I have I organize things for different shows and different folders on my file system
And I'm constantly open up a terminal in that folder and doing work in it 30 times a day
I do that it is so nice to have that I can't even tell explain to you how nice that is and it's it's these little
Things that we just used to take for granted that have just started to disappear on some of our other desktops
That plasma still has they still have kept those traditions
So would part of this you say that maybe is plasma targeting like a loftier goal
And so gnome has an easier time of reaching what their
Deliverable is and as more gnome has a narrower goal or a nor. Yeah, right
It's like it's a simpler thing to reach and yeah, right there
They are kind of pursuing a more minimal path plasma
You know gnome has just a you you copy something you paste it
You don't get notifications about nothing about that whereas the plasma desktop has like one of the best clipboard managers
I've ever seen or used anywhere on any on any OS
And they're like yeah, we're gonna make this the super badass clipboard manager
It can be or yeah, we're gonna have the best one of the things that impressed me right away was that clipboard bit
Yeah, and the screenshot tool is like all of it's like some of their best stuff like
The calendar even just be able to click on the yes
I like great count
It's very useful the way that all cups props crops up
And I have a bunch of different time zones now that show up for me really simply I like that a lot
Now I'm gonna get to some criticisms that I've observed, but I'm just trying to articulate the differences having having spent
Over a year on gnome 3. Maybe it's been. I don't know how long have I been on arch
To three years now three years. Yeah
There are some issues that I have also observed
They're not bad bad anymore. This is the one that bugs me the most
Some windows open at rather odd default sizes with less than the full width of the drawn elements
And I have I have a 2k resolution screen
So this is really really obnoxious because they open like 640 by 480 size
Which then truncates a portion of the window to the right and there's no automatic wrapping or rendering of window content
So you can literally miss critical elements of the UI or by that study exists, right?
Yeah, and then they have awkward scroll scroll bars that aren't centered with the element. They'll actually be scrolling and
Then if you just look at the screenshot here on the left
workspace
Workspace desktop effects and screen edge options all the same size icon then screen locking a different size icon then virtual desktops a distance
Different size square icon then accessibility around icon and then activities three dots
So this is just this one screen shows you this really bad mismatch that they have going on UI wise like they've gone
So they've come so far
But yet they have these consistent inconsistencies throughout the UI same thing with like the open and save dialogue
consistently opens
Way smaller than I need it to be again a 2k resolution. The first thing I always do I click and drag it better
Thank God that the K win drag
Effectance and look is so smooth and nice because I sure do it a lot
do it a lot and then the second thing I do is I expand the
Modified the kind and the name columns because they're never long enough because I they don't they don't resize when you redrag the UI
They stay that same small 640 by 480 size and you have to go redrag those and this adds three seconds to every file save
And open process. What's the point of that? It's ridiculous. It's again consistent inconsistency
There's other small things. I
Think if you use the default theme breeze and you use it in the light mode you
You you really run into a lot more problems if you go breeze dark it solves a lot of issues
So for example with the default theme the menu is slightly transparent and the description descriptor text under icons is so light
You can barely read it. If you go dark theme, it looks fine
There's a lot of little wigglies in this article that we're gonna link to in the show notes too that he ran into it
If you use dark theme, it's fine
Here's another one. That's a little odd when you're playing music when you click on the volume icon
It's a really nice widget you get live album art track information other desktops do this as well
But this one's really nice because it's got these big play controls, but they just look
Awful, they don't even render correctly. There's displacement in the play circle
It's it's just small stuff. You know the functionality is there. It's the way it's implemented is great
It works with like Spotify and my Google Play desktop client that I have and it's really nice
It just it's the UI of it's just a little awful. It was the only problem
There's just little things like that, but from where they were these things are minor enough now
That in my opinion even as somebody who gets a little annoyed by these things
To have this workstation class
desktop environment
That offers all of this functionality that seems to be running as well as it does is
Totally worth like these small little nuance issues that I think eventually probably even get worked out
That's kind of in my take oh, and oh, okay?
first of all the wallpapers the wallpaper setting thing is the worst of the of the system setting applets because I
Have a folder with like 200 wallpaper images in it that I'd like to rotate through and you have to add them one by one
And then there's no live preview even though a lot of the other settings do have live preview
There's no live preview for wallpaper
So it's like basic functionality stuff, and then I think the thing that most new users of the plasma desktop run into it
It's the thing that I should probably lead with the number one issue with plasma is this
Download new stuff from the internet screen that comes up when you want to add a theme a color scheme a plasma widget
It's one of the best and worst features of the plasma desktop is instead of like having to go in your web browser and find
A tar file and download it and then go and like drag it into like a dot folder somewhere like an animal
the plasma desktop says hey would you like to just
Download new widgets directly from our directory on the internet and it pulls down new add-ons or new widgets or new themes
but the reality is most of them are broken many of them have to lead you to an external website which sort of nullifies the
entire point of using an applet like this and
many of them do not work at all especially when it comes to the widgets and when it comes to the themes a
lot of them are incompatible with current versions of plasma and
It's just simply that no one in the project and I've I've gotten some fairly good confirmation on this
No one in the project has the time to go through and weed this thing out
It's a problem nobody wants to tackle, but it's one of the most unique things about the plasma desktop
And it's one of the first things I think a lot of new users try and it's one of the first things that breaks and doesn't
Work correctly which doesn't give you a great impression
Yeah, so there's there are there are some of these some of these problems like you often get a prompt that says
This is a this downloaded an HTML file which indicates
It's a link to a website instead of the actual download
Would you like to open the site with a browser instead and then it opens up your browser?
And then it usually takes you like KD look or something like that. It's vague what you're even supposed to do
It's just a really bad experience
So there's there's issues. There's definitely issues
I tell you I tell you what if you're willing to live with things like that
I think it's a pretty good desktop environment was I think you should give it another week
Have you messed at all with the launcher? No I have not so alt space
Will will launch krunner nice. Yeah, it's basically you'll do anything that the nicest launchers do
So you can you couldn't you can get and you can actually pass commands into you can see you can start console with button stuff happening
It's really nice, so player. I'd say take the week to play with play with that
Are you using a dark theme yes, okay? Good a breeze yes, all right? Well good good good you good there
Yeah, so play around with that you got KD wallet set up
I'll play more with some of the keyboard shortcuts see if I can make that I know you can do yeah
I'm sure I can yeah
Like one of the I think one of the things I had to do which I thought was kind of weird is I had to
Go in and set up like the keys. I always use to switch between virtual desktops. Yes
I was surprised that wasn't set up. Yes exactly wasn't that yep? I'll do some deep dive
Hey, when let's you do a lot of stuff, and there's there is like there's like an action
Area you can go in and create even things to do from yeah, I mean it's
It's pretty nice
Yeah, you can also
Here's a chat room saying there's a krunner widget you can put on the desktops you can see like applications
There's also one thing that do you use that at work that laptop?
Yeah, you might find I've never cared to use it
And I I struggle to really justify the even the feature
But it has activities and you could create a home activity and a work activity and they're like they're essentially totally different plasma desktops
That's kind of interesting you can have different widgets backgrounds panel layouts. Yeah
Console profiles all that stuff. It's kind of cool. So yeah, well. I'd be curious. Oh my god. You're right pixel pimp
Geez yeah, then and then of course. Oh my god. Yes, Katie a connect. Yeah, awesome. Oh, you have a setup
I have not installed. I've used it before even on gnome. I have not installed it this time around so maybe I'll do that
I I want to try it so bad. I'm half tempted to
To use my Nexus 6p again. Oh yeah, right does anybody know of a
What's a way what I mean, what is the what is the equivalent to find my phone find my friends on on?
Android
Find my friends is yeah, you don't tell you know what I'm talking about
Do you mean find your phone? No find my friends, which is is uses the same thing?
But you can you can set up friends where you can share location
I've never used that but you could use ways to do something similar. Yeah, no no it's it's always on tracking
Yeah, ways does that though? I think oh really stake and like there's a mode you can put ways
I don't want to be deprecated at this point, but there was a time like at least four years ago where that was a thing
So I have the kids phone, which is just like a shared phone
They have I have my phone and a deals phone, and we can all look each other's location up. Which is really cool
Okay, I see I feel like there's a way with Google Maps though or something
Go have it always on
Go ahead SK. You had something to say
Yeah, if you use the
Device manager app on Android, and you you have to have the whatever
Android devices you have on your
Account like my scrap draw gmail I can see them and I can also add like my wife's
Account also oh so and so I can so what it does is allows you to be able to see where those devices are you can
Lock them from remote if you yeah, you all the things you know, but she would have to then be on Android, too
So there's actually a cross-platform thing with the Google app
But I guess Android has that built-in so as long as you have play services in the Google app you can
Enable location history and then share the location histories and that's always on we see that I actually use that on iOS
I would be I'll have to play with that because I so all right, so
So what what is the app that you use on the iPhone? I?
Think it's just called Google is what they call the Google app. Oh wait really huh? Yeah, okay? Yeah, that's right
Yeah, okay, yeah, that's my location history continuously with that and there is actually a sharing feature boy
I have what it's one thing about using I know this is a this I this is an arbitrary line
But for some reason I just get creeped out about using a Google location tracking app like this just creeps me out
Yeah, it is interesting sometimes to review this cool
Though because they have a great dashboard for dealing with all your personalized data like that, and you can I know
Your trips throughout the day. Yeah, I know no I know yeah, yeah, I know I just worry about I worry about years and years and years
And years and years of analysis of my location data like I'm not worried about right now
I'm worried about like 10 years of using something like this. Yeah, what kind of in what kind of things can they inferred?
What kind of things could be subpoenaed?
That's my only concern really like Jimmy John's yeah, right
Yeah, and and what happens what happens to CEOs from our one CEO?
Yeah, sure that is a very good concern. Did they make a partnership with my health insurance company?
Because you know from that data they can derive also how fast I go sure yeah if I'm walking if you're walking
I think it's subpoena any of those applications, so it's really just I feel like Apple is putting your data there
I feel like Apple has demonstrated a willingness though to not participate in some cases so has Google absolutely yeah
I know that's why I say it's an arbitrary line. I've drawn. It's a pretty arbitrary line
I just would rather what I would really rather do is roll it on my own and have an app that just works on either
Platform, but I've experimented a little bit with that and they tend to be really crappy you guys and really really bad on battery life
Even though they're integrated well. Yeah, what do you have like busy polling for your stuff? Yeah, ah?
Huh interesting well the altera says that Google has recently made an announcement about this well
We should probably move on because this is not really
Yeah, yeah, yeah trusted contacts app will let you share your locations and emergencies not it's kind of not what I want
But huh you know let's why don't we before we get going let's let's let's talk about ting you know what this would be a great
Time this just kind of makes sense linux.ting.com if you want a mobile service provider
that's not playing games with you and announcing services turning services off and
Wearing gimmicky jackets you just go pay for what you use
This is really brilliant because it's just six dollars for the line and your usage on top of that
So you don't have to worry about getting a set amount of minutes or a set amount of data a set amount of text messages
And you don't have to worry about adding additional lines if you need something for a monitoring device or a family member or a tablet
It's just six dollars in your usage. I often have it. It's just I think I'm actually out now
But I have in the past and I guess I have to order some more
I've just had ting sims around and I've had a tablet that the kids were playing with and when Pokemon go was super popular
And this is just like hey, let's all go out as a family and walk around the trails and catch Pokemon
So but you got to have data connection. Yes, you do so
We get all set up and then that dawns on me. What do I do?
I better probably like buy a plan where you have to get a two-year contract like 10 gigs a month
I think it's not a contract a commitment a commitment. Oh, there we go. We change the word sure did yeah
Yeah, no none of that. I put the ting sim in an Android tablet that I already had
There's a what just it was a Wi-Fi device that had an empty sim slot and we had we had data for the day
In fact, I just left it in there for a while because it's six dollars a month. I was like, well, maybe we'll do it
Again, we didn't do it again
We didn't do it again, but I was so thankful
I didn't bother like going down like because I have been there with friends in the past
I've been to the game myself like here get this free tablet after an 18 month a commitment. Don't worry
It's not a contract, but it's a commitment. It's an agreement to be our customer
You know there recently the other big guy the other big duopoly guy announced more plans for more money
That's right
And I find it fascinating because if you look at the way ting customers save money
The average ting line is twenty three dollars per device. So that's that's your data your minutes. Your message is
$23
so when when like Verizon's like announcing
$140 plans and 80 even $80 plans
It just blows my mind. Let's see. That's not my cable bill
Yeah, should be better than that. Yeah, I mean I I guess there's people that will buy like a $12 cup of coffee
Right and meanwhile, I'm like, yeah
It's too much money for coffee, right?
So I get I you know the other day I accidentally ended up paying 40 bucks for pizza
I've never paid that much for pizza, but I went to a round table
I walked in there and I had the kids with me and I got two larges the next thing I know I'm $46 done
I'm like what I gotta I gotta down this for 15 bucks. Yeah, right. They don't care the kids don't care
Like this is this is the problem with these guys and this is why they can come up with different gimmicks
They can announce different services with different things or different ways of destroying net neutrality
They can come up with these different gimmicks and they can call it freeloading or whatever. They call it
What do they call it back during that trial?
What do they call that where they offer you if they offer you like the ability to stream YouTube for free and then they call
It like a good thing. What's that called though?
Well, they have a name for it. Yes, they do. Oh, yeah. What is that?
What they all have different names though, don't they? Yeah, like T-mobile. Oh my god T-mobiles is so prevalent
They advertise it all the time. Yeah, the IRC's probably already got it. Yeah, it's this it's this it's this it's this
It's this cliche. It's this cliche gimmicky way of calling
Basically binge. Well, yeah, no badge on yeah
But what they're doing is like that they're like pro right they pay the bill or something for it
And it's just gonna destroy net neutrality, right? It's gonna here's what it's gonna do
Is it's gonna give YouTube an absolute monopoly
Because if you want to watch Jupiter broadcasting shows and you don't want to go against your data
Guess what you've got to do. You got to watch it on YouTube
You can't watch it from our website, which doesn't get takedowns from
Python bots it is available in HTML 5 WebM doesn't track you and
Then and yet guess what because they're free jacking this thing, but in the back door, that's what I call it
they're gonna they're gonna give YouTube a monopoly and
That these gimmicks these bench on gimmicks and there's all this data these
This is a smokescreen to get you to buy in in the million the mean
I mean meanwhile, you're paying for more than you would originally use anyways, I
definitely was
It really gets me fired up
Linux dot ting comm go there save twenty five dollars off a device or if you bring one and they got CDMA energy or her
You can just get a twenty five dollar service credit which probably pay for more than your first month
And I didn't even have time to tell you about their great control panel or awesome customer service Linux dot ting dot com
So speaking of Linux Linux 4.10 brings in a new feature. That sounds really cool
Hey, yo, but for all I know it could be bunk
It is virtual GPU support this release adds support for the Intel GVT dash G for KVM a full GPU
Virtualization solution with mediated pass-through starting with fourth generation Intel core processor
So has well
Pretty large. That's a pretty large market devices. That really got my attention there. This feature is based on the new VVF IO
mediated device framework and
So this is this so unlike direct pass-through
Alternatives the mediated framework allows for KVM KVM GT by the way to offer a complete virtualized GPU with full GPU
features to each one of the virtualized guests
This could be huge fire OBS in the cloud
William are you moon there? Is this a development you were actually following?
Kind of I don't actually necessarily plan to use it
But it's definitely cool to be able to have new device types that you can virtualize and share
So you could have a bunch of KVM instances using one GPU instead of having to have an individual GPU
On the back end is the video is the video hardware
Accelerating these these virtual. Yes, that's what that's partitioning being done inside of the GPU to allow each instance to run
I don't know how good the like quality of service type stuff is
At this point for it say Intel interesting
I know AMD also this release has something similar right if I'm not mistaken or landed on four nine
Might have been four nine, but it also could have been four ten
I kind of forget but yeah Intel and AMD should have this capability in for ten
This is so so people been wanting this for a long time
It could be big for a lot of different kind of virtualized solutions
You know there's definitely times wonder what this could mean for Windows 2 and you're not going to do much gaming with an Intel graphics
But could mean some graphics right would I guess it would depend on the driver
Actually nice if you're like say DigitalOcean and you want to provide GPU instances, right?
Right because then you don't have to buy an entire GPU per VM
Which would be kind of costly per month right partition it down?
Yeah, and so you can have cheaper GPU instances right our needs were really
We just needed some accelerated video support for OBS or OBS to work up in on a DigitalOcean droplet
Yeah, that's right. Yeah, that could provide this too
Yeah, suddenly you just have the base support or like even if it makes you are like virtualized desktop suddenly not I think for
OBS and I think for like virtual desktop type stuff. Yeah, this could be great
Yeah, and you could do a bunch of open GL exactly all your browser stuff then works
Honestly wonder what it could also mean for video playback in VMs for like desktop sessions. I wonder if video play a VDI, right? Yeah
I'm excited about that, but that's there's of course
There's a crap ton of other stuff in for ten
But that just seemed like a good one that people might want to know about there's a whole list of stuff
Is there anything else you wanted? There's a couple of things like improved write back management
Oh, this should hopefully without having to switch your IO scheduler
You should be able to get some like less, you know, you're writing to a USB Drive. You're copying a giant file
It should have less interruptions now on your day-to-day desktop usage
I also thought it was interesting that you can now attach an eBPF program to C groups
So you can use this eBPF program to it's the Berkeley packet filter, right?
So you can use this to filter packets drop things that kind of stuff now
You can easily apply it to all your programs in a C group. That's huge. So that could be big for containers
Seems like it
Hmm. Yep
And in the same vein better support now for the Nexus 5 and 6. Oh really 6p here
There's a bunch of driver updates basically in all of the hardware categories
But specifically in USB and camera again getting another big round of updates
Isn't it great how often just a new kernel comes out?
You can install it run it BAM all of these updates some of this stuff like I say again with commercial desktops
You'd have to wait for the entire right next version
So cool speaking of next versions of things known
3.24 is entering beta final release is expected on March double deuce
With one day delay the beta release of the upcoming gnome dot 3.4 desktop environments finally here for public testing
We got a revamped gnome control center landing in this one with updated user printer and online accounts keyboard and mouse and Bluetooth panels
Also a sharing framework to make it easier for users to share things with other apps to other various online services
I'm curious about that one furthermore gnome music app gets a tag editing and own cloud integration
Next cloud will be available via online accounts panel gnome photos will import your photos
Epiphany web browser got a lot of new features and a revamp design and gnome calendar brings the week view and
And gnome software will handle snap and apt URLs now hey yeah, and of course a flat back and it looks like models file manager
promises to let users browse files as root
There's also there's another big feature coming that I'll mention here in a second, but I wanted to segue and say
1704 of ubuntu will be the first ubuntu in a very long time
That will actually ship with current gnome what which has been a big criticism for a while
Yeah, so annoying yeah, the upcoming beta of you know Ubuntu gnome 1704
Is already showing the promise, but there is a bit of a caveat not all of gnome 324 will be in it
This is I'm sure there's a great reason, but this is so Ubuntu
This is so Ubuntu the latest version of many core gnome apps will be available including gnome calendar
Totem and gnome diss others are earlier versions because there is no recent update available like gnome weather or Ubuntu
Ops to include an older
aka patched version
Like Nautilus gnome software aka Ubuntu software is also stuck to the older version of the gnome 322 version
Though it's a much more recent build than the 320 release that shipped a 1604 1610 and yes
They'll include flat pack support and snap URL support in it now. This is the big feature that I
Haven't a lot of people talk about is the nightlight feature in gnome 3.24. This could be pretty badass
It's a as you kind of could probably guess from the name
It says it's a new setting that automatically adjusts the color temperature and brightness of your display
Depending on the time of day to help reduce eye strain and help promote natural sleep cycles
You probably familiar with a lot of we've talked about a lot of different apps flux redshift, etc
Yeah, and so now it's built right in yeah, no nightlight reduces the amount of blue light the display admits becomes warmer
And the overall brightness is reduced
It is one of those things where it's like I can install no and just not have to configure that you know
Yeah, the less things I can configure it just that's nice. I think it's kind of a cool thing
Yeah, and there's been some extensions to do this and while we're on before we move off of gnome. I wanted to put a call-out and
I'm gonna probably have to mention this again, too
but the gnome conference Gwadek in Manchester is coming up the 28th and the
Second through the 2nd of August Gwadek brings together free software enthusiast professionals from all over the world
It's six days of talks demos discussion parties games and more six days. That's awesome
Yeah, and I I would be willing to go get my passport and go
And I got an invite to do so
and I just I can't really figure out how to make the money work because you know my hack to go into these events
Is I take I live in an RV and I take you drive there. Yeah
That doesn't work so well when it's in Manchester, so I don't think I know the RV over Chris
Yeah, I don't think I think that's probably way expensive. I don't I don't I don't think I can make it
I just don't think I can swing it. I would love to go
I would first of all your job audience is to just all start saying you're going and just force them to go
No
I want what I'm hoping is maybe somebody legitimately wants to cover it for us
Because I could probably get you press coverage if you're really willing to work with us
I can't pay you for it
But if you just want to work with us and do some recording for us and probably just audio
I bet we could probably get you in this press if you're willing to officially work with JB
I maybe be my eyes and ears on the ground
God, I would love to go because I've never been to an event outside the US like this
It's never I mean the only other country outside the US I've gone to is Canada
So that would be awesome, but not this year
I don't think if I had more time to plan, but July when you own a small business July is not that far away
So if you can make it a Gwadek the 20th of July through the 2nd of August
You don't have to go the whole time
I suppose but you could go a good portion to find it out find out you can go to
2017 dot Gwadek org will have a link in the show notes. I'd love to get an maybe a couple eyes and ears on the ground
even
The JB perspective yeah really get some I think this sounds like a fascinating conference
It sounds like a hell of an event for six days
It's got to be a party, so I would love to I would love to get a sense of that
also congratulations to our friends over at elementary they successfully
Funded their open or their new pay what you want app center initiative right? Oh, this is great
yeah, so they're gonna be going to Denver and doing a
Rush over there to put to put this thing all together
And then I'm sure we'll eventually get our hands on it
And get a chance to review it and see where they've come up with but I for those of us like myself who think this is
An interesting idea at least even if it's not gonna be a huge thing that right takes over to Linux software distribution
But even if it's just something that we get to try out in a corner of Linux
I think it's I think it's a fascinating worthy effort, and so I'm really happy to hear they got funding
It's nice to see yeah
It's nice to see the community a community backing them and what I keep doing and you know this isn't this is there
They've had some success now their community is coming through a couple of it has come through a couple of times now
It's pretty cool to see that too. We need that in the open-source world word West word
Oh my gosh
We have so much more to get to and tech snaps coming up, so you know what I want to talk about
Something that I think is gonna change Noah's life
Something that I wouldn't be surprised if you have stacked on that little stack of notebooks and laptops you have there
West so let's take a moment and I think Linux Academy for sponsoring the show go to Linux Academy comm
Unplugged to sign up for their platform to learn more about Linux with labs with hands-on scenarios
Instructor mentoring real human beings core schedulers you can pick a time frame that fits your schedule and learning goals
Learning paths which are series of courses and content planned by instructors their lab servers spin up on demand their video courses
Which are self-paced in-depth courses on every damn Linux cloud and DevOps topic
They have a great community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members comprehensive study guides you take with you audio
You can listen to on the go speaking of on the go
They got iOS and Android apps smart tools that really work with the particular session or lab
You're doing and I should probably mention it three times
But I think the human instructors are a huge component Linux Academy's been blowing up
And you can check out their Twitter feed to get a little sense of that
They've got a great guide on managing Docker containers with ansible up on their site now
And they've you know they're just expanding their content on a weekly basis so much your management
Just throw buzzwords at you Linux Academy's got those covered. Yeah, BAM containers. Yeah, I
configuration management if
If I worked in a place that offered any kind of budget for learning cuz you know Linux Academy's super straightforward
You can sign up for a seven-day free trial just to get a sense for it at Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
This would so be my go-to they have profiles that help you show your employer what you're doing or a potential employer
It's a great way to try out something new and with their lab servers
You can really get a sense of how it works so then when you go to use it in production
You know what the hell you're doing break it up Linux Academy. Don't break it exactly Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged
So it's the GPD pocket a 7-inch Ubuntu laptop. That's going up for crowdfunding on Indiegogo
That's right a 7-inch laptop. This thing is a little mental
It's got 128 gigabytes of storage 8 gigabytes of RAM it runs Ubuntu 1604
It's got an Intel Atom a Z
E8 750 cpu which is a quad core clock to 1.6 gigahertz, okay, yeah
7,000 milliamp battery which they estimate to be around 12 hours year right 802 11 AC Bluetooth a couple of us
type-c yeah, buddy and
Headphone jack hey you have to say that these days
You just have to look at that keyboard that when I saw that I went. Oh this might actually be legit right
Can you believe they got a QWERTY keyboard that size on the device that small?
If those are even slightly okay to use that is an incredible layout now obviously for you audio audience listeners
There's huge compromises the arrow keys are a mess the shift key is a disaster the caps key
They shouldn't even bother the key travel is incredibly shallow
Yeah, but but still damn look at that thing look at that
They really cool just to pull out of your pocket and be able to use ten times more useful than a tablet
I dare say plus. Yeah, it has you see that full HD resolution. Yeah, yeah, yeah, and so down and and it's got it
I say earlier. It's got an SD card slot, so you could you could expand storage. Just like on the go
It's essentially a seven inch laptop
They don't have a great they don't have a great video
But it does show you like some of the some of the different side
It it almost looks like it looks like a baby Mac. It kind of does yeah. Yep it is
This is really something I
Actually, I am extremely excited. I believe the 12-hour battery life given that processor that processor draws almost no power really well
Okay, and I guess the screen isn't huge so it'll be a little slow
But there are other laptops based on it that are somewhat. Okay, so it would fit in your coat pocket
Yeah, that's the nice or a purse. That's the real draw. Yeah
Has a full keyboard has a you know what exactly yeah, what do you think of that another mouse though?
What do you think of that there?
It is compared to a Macbook if you're looking at the video whoa, what do you think of that nubbin mouse for it's essentially like?
the the
Lenovo nipple yeah, I've always been a fan of those so I mean I do use a regular trackpad
But I think I could get by just fine with that the only thing with the nipple though is it's in a weird place
Because on most other things it's where like the F and the G and the H right it's a little
Down at the spacebar, which is yeah, you're gonna have to retrain your muscle memory a bit yeah
But for me, I think I would primarily end up using this as a terminal type interface
You know where I've got the full keyboard power, and if I've got my keyboard shortcuts for most things pay now
this is a crowdfunder and
So this I like to take a little bit of a skeptical view they've already popped their goal
They're 709 percent of a 200,000 goal they got 1.4 million US greenbacks right now backed by
3460 backers so they've
Hopefully got a good shot the thing that I'm not loving is a lot of these photos are mock-ups with
Gimped in screens that are so badly gimped in that we could tell yeah, and like this one
These are just plastic keys are not even it's not even a real keyboard in fact in the most of these promos
It's not that's not a real functional unit that one's not none of these are actually
all of these all of these are gimped in and
That's it looks like
It looks like Safari on Facebook
So it's that you know and like this one this one doesn't have any ports like these are not these are not productive
Those are kind of strange like the key travel looks or the keys themselves even look huge
Yeah, what the mock-up 3d thing look yeah, the 3d render looks good
But it it kind of looks like it just kind of looks like it's I would really like to see real physical units now
They looks like it's gonna be a brick though a little bit. It's kind of thick yeah
And they say you know it's gonna be about seven hundred and ninety bucks. I guess
Wait, I know you get two of them for seven hundred ninety damn. Yeah exactly. It's like 400 each
I think for the promo price yeah, it's for the prompt for the promo price you get it estimated June 2017 geez if I had the
Money, I would buy this for Noah wait. They don't even have a real unit, and they're planning to ship by June
They must I mean see this is I feel like they must not be native English speakers because they're not being clear on some of
this stuff
How because we're they gonna get a?
Anyways, they're gonna get a what well the screen look at the IPS the the PPI on the screen
It's an IPS display with a three hundred and twenty three
PPI
This is probably just a phone screen though more or less or a tablet. It's gonna be yeah
These exist though. Yeah, but that's a I mean that that has to be that screen in the Nexus line
That would have to be an already manufactured display is what I'm getting yeah, I think it is though
It might be they're just bolted it on so you can get a 399 funding like right now
399 for a base unit 409 if you want it with a type-c you hub that's cool
Oh, huh look at them getting fancy look at them getting fancy you get then you'll get $200 off their final retail prices
What we will give you an incredible low price this perk we will provide a gpd pocket win 10 and type-c hub
Oh, you just get a hub I
See then you get $200 off the shipping unit yikes. It's confusing. Can I just say that I love?
the
Newfound prevalence of USBC yeah boy. Yeah pixel owner
I bet you do I sure do so they're their crowdfunding price looks like you get it for like 400 and then retail price is gonna
Be $5.99 US green are they close to being funded have they are either way they pop. Oh, that's great. Oh great
709 percent
1.4 million dollars of a wanted 200
200 seems like it was never gonna be so is this is this for you?
Or would you forever burn?
You know I don't know. I don't know if this is really for me
I think if I don't I basically I don't commute
Outside of I don't I mean I drive to the studio like I drive around, but I'm not like you're actually driving, right?
Yeah, you know time you get a laptop if I if I was on a train or a bus a lot
I think this I think I'd be a big candidate for this if I took a lot of public transit
Or I you know uber taxi that kind of thing or if I'm Noah
And I'm going to a lot of clients every day, and I could see it. Yeah put it in the table you need like
Especially with how good like things like the XPS 13 or where you're already at a pretty reasonable size for a bag
I mean, this is really I'm putting in my pocket. That's up
Yeah, because you can just carry it around that's a big game-changer
And I got some big pockets so they would be or a purse you know like or small
They're so jealous of Adidas purse like cuz I'll just like sometimes like can you just carry my wallet
This is so sweet. You got a big old phone. She just puts that in there
You know and this could be one more thing it'd be a little heavy, but if you needed to carry something around with you
She's eight gigs of RAM to is generous on a device like this
I could get by in 120 gigabytes of storage no problem. I think it's interesting they call it 128 gigs of ROM
Yeah, yeah
There's warning signs
They say the screen this must be a tablet because it's got a 300 not only does it have the 323 PPI
But it's got it's got Corning Gorilla Glass 3 and it's multi-touch
With a 16 by 10 aspect ratio wait wait this is touch. I didn't I didn't realize that either. That's what it says
That's what it says
Yeah, that's what it says
See you look at that screen. It does almost look at that
It almost looks like a tablet bolted on a little bit
You know it's kind of is why would it not be and that's what everybody wants anyway, right?
That's what with a keyboard that might make it more doable
It might make it possible to actually ship this thing because if they don't have that screen
If they don't have that screen this things that this thing's dead on arrival. There's no way they're gonna build it
Boy, that is screens are cheap, so I wouldn't be surprised. This is just not an issue. I don't know man
I don't know. I well so
It weighs point four hundred and eighty kilograms
It is tiny look at that guy holding it there in his hand that is I would I would love to get a device like that
Eventually I think still a pretty hefty thing though a pound. I have been yeah
I know I you know I think my 6p with a case sometimes it's almost about probably is you're right
I I only thing is I have been so burned
I have like a 30% success ratio with crowd funders, right?
I really help like you know blaster. I ordered like this brew it yourself brew kit never care never came never got
I'm still waiting on a Kickstarter from 2013. Yeah, yeah, oh, and then I got I think they're going to deliver
They keep telling us they're gonna deliver, so we'll see I'm kind of excited
Just to see if they actually pull it off this one. I got really burned on I ordered a
Really nice cast iron skillet though. It's a light cast iron skillet. That's awesome great for the RV
It's not super heavy, but it's supposed to be really high quality
Now it's changed to from the cast iron skillet. I get a $200 coupon
What?
Yeah, this is kind of what they're doing here, too
I just know you get a coupon for what to buy the to buy the $500 skillet
Oh my god the prices turned out to be a little more than they could afford
So they're here well, but now it's now
It's just another couple hundred dollars, and then they keep and I'm not gonna do it
But they keep sending me emails about it. Oh last chance last chance last chance yeah, whatever nope whatever
Alright, so I got to play this quote from Linus
so this is where we're gonna take out the show with this and
I I also I often have rants against the tech media
I think they're awful and Linus was asked to reflect on 25 years of releasing. I like this yeah
I thought it was pretty great digital ocean calm
Go there sign up support the show do unplugged apply to your account and get a $10 credit digital
Ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider
Dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up your own server like that you go there you get set up
And you're a boss in total boss mode great distributions to choose from preloaded applications one-click deployments
And then an interface to manage it that is booty full
Simple, but extremely powerful yeah such a thing actually exists go see it in the wild at digital ocean calm and use our promo
Code deal unplugged it's probably worth it just to see how you should design an interface to manage virtual servers all over the world yeah
They got data centers all over the world and use our promo code deal unplugged you get the $10 credit
You can buy up spin up a $5 rig run of two months absolutely for free or try out their hourly pricing get it really nice
I love two core rockin rig two gigs of RAM poof go try it out use the promo code deal unplugged and by the way
You know I was joking in our in our
chat I was joking like
Maybe it's time to replace our libs in downloads with this new digital ocean feature because this could be like set up a couple
Of droplets put this in front of it this could start changing the game for a lot of people
I I just starting to just sort of think about like how maybe different projects could use something like this especially on release day
Digital ocean has rolled out a load balancer service
you can scale your web apps and stuff of course the servers and
Improve availability across your entire infrastructure all just built right into the freaking digital ocean interface
Just a couple of clicks. You don't have to be like some sort of server maniac
Well, you don't got to be like this west guy over spinning up the LXD containers on systems all over the world to handle capacity
You can improve availability you can scale to traffic needs. It's very simple to set up. It's $20 a month
Hourly it's basically like
It's like pennies less than a penny. It's less than a penny. Yeah with additional bandwidth no additional bandwidth charges
It's available in all data center regions and of course
You can also use they're really straightforward API man. I love it. I know I'm a believer
I am a real it really is simple. It is really nice the way we've been able to integrate it with our workflow
Digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplugged and a big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring this here
Unplugged program so Linus was asked to reflect on the last 25 years of Linux, and he's like oh gosh
Well, I'll play the clip for you. He's like I get this question a lot. Let me tell you what I hate
I thought this was great
You've been releasing the Linux kernel for
25 years
You know, it's just an amazing amount of fortitude for anyone to do the same thing for 25 years
I understand you took a six-month break. It sounds like to do this git thing
but
It was actually more just two months
In a very short break for a minor minor effort, but
the last question is sort of you know, you got
almost
organizations that participate in all the different Linux foundation projects here that are creating code at
in almost every aspect of computing and these aren't just you know a
Fast following present. These are the core main projects for the automotive sector the telecom sector
What for you? Was there a moment where you thought aha?
This is huge. This is much bigger than maybe what you thought when you started was there
Can you imagine how many times you must get this question?
Oh, this has got to be one he gets like almost every time he does one of these things or any particular thing that you
I've answered that before there hasn't really been anything like that
There's been a couple of moments that took me by surprise
But the big moment was actually when it went from past being personal
Like and that was within six months of just releasing it
It was I don't even know the people working on sending me patches like know them personally. I mean, obviously
Now I know them by email, but but there's a ton of people
I've never met and just going past that initial personal phase where the project was just for me
I do want to kind of mention the whole
25 year thing
I'm a huge believer in
Just
The 99% sweat 1% I will 99% perspiration 1% inspiration thing
any technology project
the innovation that this
Industry talks about so much is bullshit
Innovation anybody can innovate don't don't do this big think different don't do these big
Innovation thing screw that it's meaningless
like it the
99% of it is
Get the work done, right and and there are I actually that's my least favorite part of the technology
Like new cycle is this constant
innovation
New ideas and this will revolutionize all that hype is is
That's not where the real work is. Yeah, the real work is in the details and I'm
obviously one of those people who just I
Like to concentrate on one project I don't like flitting from one idea to another and and
You need the people who just?
Flutter about and come up with ideas, but they're not the really useful ones
They're the ones who who they end up being the ones
Ideas the people who then do the work, so I hope you guys I mean that's
What anybody should take away from this talk is the people who actually do the work are the ones you should
Really listen to and it these days. I don't actually do the work anymore. I I merge other people's work, but I
like
Conferences to to be less about the
Visionary innovation thing and more about the day-to-day. What are my problems and how do I want to solve them?
That was pretty good. I like it. I did I I will link to the entire video
I did it I did enjoy that entire talk, but I thought that was kind of the newest stuff
We had heard from Linus was in that particular moment. You can watch the entire video
We have it embedded in the show notes. Thank you for joining us for 185 find Wes on the Twitter
Where do they go with at West Bay indeed you coffee maniac? I am at Chris LAS the network is at Jupiter signal
Thanks for joining us join us at jblive.tv next week
You could participate in the virtual lug hang out in our chat room and don't forget to give us your feedback at
The exact you show dot reddit.com. Thanks for being here. See you next Tuesday
Oh
Okay, Wes, do you want to see my old Bitcoin mining?
Yes, I do. Does it come with some Bitcoin?
So I was asking no I was asking Angela to send me photos because I was gonna rep about how long I've actually used
Kde so this is a photo of Angela from like 2008 and she's using an old busted CRT monitor
But what you can't tell there is she's using open office or star office
I can't remember what we use at the time on the on the plasma desktop
That's a man and this is her upset when she couldn't get her screensaver to unlock so she could log into the KD
It wasn't called plasma back then. It's just called the KD desktop. Yeah, but there it is the the first Bitcoin mining iteration
I had I had a Windows box
I tried it on and this here was I can't remember if it was Sousa based, but it was also a KDE desktop
I think that was like if the entire distro was the point of the entire distro was to mine Bitcoin
Wow, that's just what it did. Is that Windows on the right there? Yeah, and then this here is yeah
Well, this is a this way this machine ran through various different iterations
but I was always kind of switching depending on which one mind the Bitcoin and
Depending on how the testing was going to see what I liked about of course using the plasma desktop here
And others is you could put widgets on here. If you look below Wes
Ladies and gentlemen, there it is the very Dell
I reviewed just recently on the Linux action show in service as a Bitcoin mining rig
That machine has been through hell and I just booted it up recently. Look at that a retro look. Yeah
Yeah, you can see over here too. I had the Radeon drivers up so I could watch the CPU temperatures and same thing here
I'm watching the voltages and the temperatures and setting all of that
Yeah, boy, and that's how you got so rich today. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Oh boy. There you go
JB titles comms your daughter come there. We gotta go boat now. We gotta go boat. Thank you mumble room
Thank you very very much. You guys always the best assess. It was good to have you here now
Help me go pick a title won't you and then we got to get out of here cuz mr. Wes and Dan are gonna do
Turns out everything's broken and will infect your system. So, you know, we have to talk about that. Yeah, I recognize that crazy monitor
Yeah, okay. Yeah. Yeah, it's old too that you know, what's funny about that monitor
First this screen right here this KDS KDS, which I don't even think is around anymore
First LCD monitor I've ever bought VGA monitor
Power and VGA cord are integrated. I think I spent $300 and Angelo was so mad at me for spending that much money on a screen
So mad at me
Literally still using that monitor to this day. It's out in the garage hooked up to our Proxmox server. I
And I bought that I bought that when LCD screens when 15 inches was just when it got like the three four hundred
It might have been four hundred dollar price range 15 inches
Horrible refresh rate response time just the worst but the damn thing still I mean I haven't turned it on in weeks
But still works. All right plasma injection plasma pontifications. Did you like that deep space nine thing?
I think I love I realized we hadn't really explained why we sometimes talk about we just sort of got in defense mode of
We're gonna talk about this stuff, and I never really got into the reason why we do it