Wes, did you see that the Fedora 31 beta came out today?
Oh, no.
That's exciting.
I'm already jonesing for it.
But I was looking at it, something in there
has me a little nervous.
They're switching from cgroups1 to cgroups2.
Upgrade.
Don't really understand what that means.
And one of the things they say in there
is, if your tool expects cgroups1, it may break.
And I'm thinking, well, what tool is that?
Is that one of my tools?
I don't know.
You're going to have to read the docs, Chris.
I'm already looking forward to it, though.
I got the itch.
I got up this morning, and my laptop was like,
hey, can we upgrade?
And I'm like, no, laptop, it's a beta.
You know how it does that?
Right.
So then I'm moving along, and it's like, hey, Chris.
I'm like, what laptop?
And it's like, I'd like to do an upgrade to Fedora 31.
It's got that new gnome shell.
And I'm like, no, the beta just came out today, laptop.
Stop it.
Calm down.
Yeah.
And then I get to the studio today.
It's like, hey, Chris.
Hey, Chris, you got fast internet here.
You could do the update.
You won't leave me alone, Wes.
You know, I'm honestly very impressed
you've made it this far.
I don't want to do the beta.
I don't want to run a beta.
But my laptop won't shut up about it.
On your machine.
What?
Hello there, and welcome into Linux Unplugged, episode 319.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Hello.
Big show today.
Huge show.
We have not one but two guests joining us today
to explain various things that need explained,
and of course, we have some big community news to get into,
as well as some new releases of one of our favorite tools.
Oh, boy.
That's right.
We've got some other community events to share with you,
as well as some pics.
We've got, well, you could say like a whole rack of a show.
Like, it's not like a half rack of a show.
Big rack, yeah.
Yeah, it's a full rack.
So to really help us dig into all of this,
we really got to say hello over there to Mr. Cheese and Mr.
Alex.
Hey, guys.
Well, hello, guys.
Buongiorno.
Hey, make yourself comfortable.
Make sure you grab yourself a cup of water there.
Wes brought in water for everybody.
Of course.
And thanks for joining us.
And sparkling, by the way.
Sparkling.
Oh, really?
Nice, Wes.
Everybody's going to have the burps now, though.
Oh, whoops.
And also, time-appropriate greetings
to that mumble room.
Hello, virtual lug.
Hello.
Hello, hello, hello.
I'm noticing we not only have a nice showing there
in the main mumble room, but we've got a good show
in there in the quiet listening, the low-latency listening,
as we call it, there in the mumble room.
I think it's like one of the best low-latency, low-bandwidth
ways to listen to the show.
Like you're right here in studio with us, basically.
You do get a special studio mix.
And we're glad to see you there.
That's true.
Well, let's start things off with some community news
that I'm honestly a little shocked to start with.
Today, as we record, it's been announced
that Richard Stallman has resigned
as president and director of the Free Software Foundation
and from the MIT CSAIL?
Is that how we say it?
CSAIL.
CSAIL department over his comments
related to Jeffrey Epstein.
Huge.
First, in order of events, I saw the announcement about MIT.
And then I saw the announcement directly
from the Free Software Foundation.
They write, on September 16, 2019,
Richard M. Stallman, the founder and president
of the Free Software Foundation, resigned as president
and from its board of directors.
The board will be conducting a search for the new president
beginning immediately.
You can find more details on fsf.org when they know more.
This is huge.
And it's been also something of a bit of a fascination of mine
to watch the mainstream media begin to report this story.
It's connected to a huge scandal now.
And they refer to him as computer scientist
and open software advocate.
Oh, boy.
Wow.
He has resigned.
The scandal tied to Jeffrey Epstein
is related to $7.5 million in donations
that he gave to the MIT Media Lab, which
was far more than what was previously disclosed
than the group inside MIT was discussing this issue when
Richard Stallman made his views about some of the victims
clear.
Parts of that quote were then picked up by the media
after it was blogged about.
And it's really kind of over the last few days
since we recorded, it's turned into quite a firestorm.
Absolutely.
Kind of blew up, right?
We got insight into what seemed like indefensible remarks.
And Stallman has a long history, kind of brought that back
to light, too.
One of the things that I saw was it
was a new group of individuals that
were learning about his views on certain topics that didn't
previously know about that.
Some of us, we've gone to his website over the last decade
plus, we know what his views are on some of these things
and have considered it to be a little gross for a while.
But a new round of individuals over this last weekend,
really kind of starting the middle of last week,
discovered some of these things.
But I think what I believe is important to take here
from all of this is we shouldn't frame the conversation
as a reaction to comments that Richard Stallman made
about Jeffrey Epstein's victims.
This is really the end result of a pattern of behavior
over decades that has eventually led to some kind of response.
I think we all kind of knew this was likely
coming for Richard Stallman.
Those of us that have followed this for a while.
Right.
And I think you're right.
At least in the wider community, he's
mostly known for his fairly extreme philosophies
and ideas about free software, at least viewed that way
by many.
But there is this undercurrent.
And if you've been paying attention,
this has always been there.
Yeah, you followed this pretty closely for Linux headlines.
And there was a moment where it seemed like something was
going to have to give pretty soon.
Yeah, absolutely.
Well, over the weekend, both the Software Freedom Conservancy
made a statement saying that Richard Stallman shouldn't
have this position anymore.
And then the executive director of the Gnome Foundation
said that in his view, the foundations
could no longer have a formal relationship
if Richard Stallman was still there.
Wow.
Yeah, they write, we admire the work
that the Free Software Foundation staffers
and volunteers have done.
But we have reached a point concluding
that the greatest service to the mission of free software
is for Richard to step down from the SFF.
And if this doesn't happen, then they'll look at, as they write,
severing the historical ties between Gnome, Gnu,
and the Free Software Foundation.
And that would be the only path forward.
Wow.
Like, that was, I mean, something had to break here.
Absolutely.
And when I saw this happen, because this
was before Richard Stallman's announcements,
I thought to myself, the FSF is going to go down with Stallman.
The two are inseparable.
They are linked.
You can't have one without the other.
That certainly has seemed that way for years.
I was really shocked when I saw this.
But I think it's not super surprising.
Richard Stallman probably wants to take
whatever actions he thinks are best for the longevity
of the foundation.
And it's probably better for the community as a whole
if we don't have someone with this history representing us.
So I think Richard Stallman probably
knew that this was the best move he had to make.
There's a famous quote of Richard Stallman's
that I shared with the team when the news was announced.
And I kind of feel like it's appropriate to read it here
on the show, because it's like one of those prescient quotes
from the man himself, where there's that meme
that Richard Stallman was right.
Well, he even has a quote that sort of summarizes this.
Geeks like to think that they can ignore politics.
You can leave politics alone, but politics
won't leave you alone.
He's right.
And that's exactly what happened here.
I'm definitely along the same lines as you,
as far as it's been a discovery, a week of discovery
for a lot of people, where we knew after reading his blog,
there are questionable things in his blog.
I always had kind of a weird feeling about the guy myself,
but what he's done for the Free Software Foundation
and that movement has gotten it to where it is today.
I'm glad that he is willing to just step down and let
the Free Software Foundation continue with, quite frankly,
better leadership.
All right, well, moving on then.
Let's talk about something that's
pretty exciting for owners of the Raspberry Pi.
There is a first fully functional 64-bit OS
for the Raspberry Pi 4, because right now it's 32-bit only,
even though it's a 64-bit device.
But who it's from is a bit of a surprise, Wes.
Yeah, it's our friends over at Balena.
Now, if you don't remember.
Yeah, the Etcher people.
But it turns out they do a lot more than that, too.
Yes, that's very true.
OK, so if you don't remember, Balena OS
is an open source, minimal, Yocto Linux-based,
host operating system that's designed for containers.
It enables a fast and modern workflow
for many different embedded device types,
and now includes the Raspberry Pi 4.
Basically, they've got a system in place
to take modern workflows that you might be used to
on the server, building a new container image,
pushing that up to test, and then eventually into production
and make that work on embedded and IoT applications.
So now you can get the 64-bit goodness
and run side-by-side 32-bit and 64-bit Docker containers
on your Pi.
I kind of like this, because I'm using the Pi exclusively
right now to run Docker containers.
And I did kind of pine about not having a 64-bit OS when
I was loading it up to do server stuff.
And one of the things I didn't fully appreciate
when I bought the Raspberry Pi 4 is
I was buying a machine to run Raspbian,
and pretty much only Raspbian.
When you look at some of the things
that they had to overcome to even make this thing possible,
it's clear that it's going to take a long time
before most distros are supporting the Raspberry Pi 4.
Yeah, I mean, basically, there's been a lot of hardware changes,
and you're trying to move over to 64-bit.
So they had to improve stuff in Yocto for the board support
package changes, all that stuff for the Funarm platform,
and work with their bootloader.
Yeah, the bootloader, the way you initialize the graphics,
the way you initialize the PCI bus, all weird and different.
It's all different on the Pi 4.
So I'll be running Raspbian for a while, I think.
However, you and I very momentarily
did get CentOS running on the Raspberry Pi 4.
Yes, we did.
That was fun.
We had to get it working on a Raspberry Pi 3 first, right?
Isn't that what we did?
And then we patched the kernel on the SD card
and then booted it on the Raspberry Pi 4.
Thankfully, some kind of community member
out there had built an updated version,
but that was what you had to do before.
That's what they did.
Right, right, yeah.
It was kind of awesome, though, to have CentOS on a Pi 4.
But it was 32-bit as well.
So BalenaOS.
You know, it is neat to just see because they're leveraging
open source distributions and a bunch of the open source
Mobi-based tooling for Docker to build
their customized platform.
Yeah.
Let's talk about Nextcloud.
Nextcloud 17 is out, and there's some pretty nice features
in here.
The one that really jumps out to me is remote wipe.
All right, so if you permit downloading of documents
by a third party, you can now wipe the documents
from the devices after you're done collaborating.
So maybe you have a few sensitive things.
You want someone to assess a pre-release of something
and they don't need access afterwards,
Nextcloud can make it happen.
It is a little creepy, though, right?
I mean, once I download something,
kind of want to keep it.
Yeah, I don't see how it could work
without either a Nextcloud client installed
or you go back to the website and next time you revisit,
somehow it could remove those files.
But I think it's got to be tied into the client.
So it's only of certain probably usefulness.
However, definitely had a scenario one time
where a client had Dropbox where it
was one of those random implementations
where the staff just started using it to share files around.
And then they worked with a contractor who took off
and took off with the folder on their hard drive.
Yeah, I mean, really, that's the story here.
This is an enterprise-friendly feature
and might make it easier for some people to adopt it.
Yeah, they've also been trying to make a bit of a showcase
out of some of their larger government installations
and better support for two-factor authentication.
Now, during the initial sign-up and login process,
a user can set up two-factor authentication and more
services than ever are supported these days, like gateways
that use SMS.
Of course, you have your standard one-time password
services for like Google Authenticator or similar apps.
So they're really all in on the two-factor authentication
now with this release.
That's good to see.
It does look nice, because we're using Nextcloud these days.
Guess that means it's time to update, Wes.
I think it is.
It's time to update.
Well, let's take a moment and talk about something
a little different.
So in our community is an individual
who's an advocate for PowerShell.
DM is active in several communities,
and he's also the individual behind the PowerShell
on Linux website and Twitter account.
And I love his story.
And I wanted to share it with you
and why he thinks PowerShell, which
is a topic that's just like, what?
PowerShell?
Linux?
Bash is perfectly fine.
We talked about it when it came to Linux for the first time.
We knew it was out there, but I mean, I don't use it.
Even today, though, I was in a Telegram group
where he mentioned using PowerShell,
and somebody was like, blasphemy.
But like so many tools, out of necessity,
you discover something's quite useful.
In DM's case, he's a very clever individual,
and he manages a lot of boxes.
I manage over 20,000 VMs.
Yeah.
That's a lot of VMs.
And so saving time is extremely important.
And there's an element to this that I can really
fundamentally appreciate.
But I think maybe we start with PowerShell itself.
PowerShell's a bit of a different beast, isn't it?
It's not like Bash.
No, I mean, it comes from a different heritage, right?
It's not really a Unix tool.
It comes from the Windows world.
And you get to leverage a lot of the.NET platform.
So instead of throwing text around, you've got objects.
Yeah.
For me, I like Bash, and don't get me wrong.
But because it's very text-based,
it's the good thing about it, and it's also
the worst thing about it for me.
Because if you have to work with text,
and you need to figure out all these special commands,
and because PowerShell is, just like Python,
is object-oriented, you can do amazing, simple things.
So easily in one command.
That seems to be the core difference,
object-oriented versus text.
That seems pretty key to using PowerShell.
Well, yeah, right?
I mean, so imagine you've got a date,
and you want to go grab just the month part of that.
Well, you could probably whip up something
to split by whatever separator you're using,
and then grab the middle field or something.
But if you've got objects, well, there's
probably just a method that you call to get the month out
of it, right?
So it's more structured than text.
Now, there's an aspect to it that I can completely
appreciate as well, as somebody who was a desktop Linux
user managing Windows systems, and having
to deal with user account changes and other things
that just desperately, desperately need
to be automated, and trying to come up with a solution
and even some means to automate them across platforms.
Creating an Active Directory user
used to take 30 to 45 minutes because
of all this special stuff, like this all special configuration.
And using PowerShell, I kept saying,
we would hire 30 people, and then they
wouldn't pass their insurance selling exam,
and then we would fire half of them.
And then I would just spend hours creating these accounts
and then deleting them, which was crazy.
So then that's pretty much how I started with PowerShell.
I was like, I'm not going to spend hours.
It's funny.
There has to be a better way.
That is how it always goes, isn't it?
It's a necessity.
Yeah, absolutely.
And it's not all just for managing Microsoft systems.
It's not all just about making sure you can
create Active Directory users.
There's a big community out there.
The other day, I found out there's
a FreeNAS module for PowerShell.
Wow, really?
So now, all of a sudden, I have this FreeNAS box
that I use for my home lab and whatnot.
So all of a sudden, I'm like, I want to create a new volume.
Then I import this.
I download this module.
I import it, and then I have, like,
connect FreeNAS server or something.
I give it the name of the server, the credentials,
and poof, I'm connected.
And then I have other simple commands,
like, I don't know, new volume or whatever,
new FreeNAS volume.
I don't remember the exact command.
Right, but then you can start scripting
your own little environments and handy helpers.
Yeah, exactly.
So then you start at home, and then all of a sudden,
you take it.
And because the API is very similar between FreeNAS
and TrueNAS, you can use the same.
I think the same library supports TrueNAS.
And then you take it to work.
And then at my job, I have to administer
a bunch of different storage systems,
because the application we build integrates
with different SAN providers and stuff like that.
So I have to administer NetApps and Icelon
and all kinds of weird, like FreeNAS is not weird,
but other weird storage vendors.
So if they have PowerShell support, then all of a sudden,
from my Linux box, it's really easy for me
to automate the deployment of all this stuff,
because I have one interface, which is PowerShell,
and I have all these different modules.
One of the things that seems like it's a key differentiator
is PowerShell has these modules.
Yeah, right?
I mean, it's sort of built right in.
In Bash, you might automate things
by installing additional programs,
and then sort of tying those together.
But PowerShell is more like a programming language
in the sense that you've got these community
modules you can go find and use.
So whether it's FreeNAS or I know
DM was talking about Selenium drivers.
So if you want to go do a bunch of automating websites that
don't have APIs, well, you can do that with PowerShell too.
Yeah.
Not everything is golden, though.
Not everything is golden.
For example, a lot of the Active Directory modules
don't work on Linux yet.
I took it upon myself.
I keep talking to different people from Microsoft,
from all kinds of places, like, oh, I have this module.
Can you test it on Linux?
So I download it into my box.
And then I think one of the Azure SQL team
member at Microsoft, they have an official SQL server module.
So he said, hey, it works on core.
It should work on Linux.
I already know that's not true because sometimes there's
all kinds of little things that make you break.
So I downloaded the module.
I tried to import it.
It doesn't work.
It doesn't work because Linux file system is case sensitive
and Windows is not.
So then all of a sudden, this file
has a lowercase letter in it.
Boom, it doesn't break.
So then I created a PR, not a PR, an issue in their system.
And I'm trying to fix it.
DM makes the case that the more users on Linux,
the more priority it becomes for Microsoft.
And what's also great about this,
and this is something I really connected with Amon,
is it means fundamentally more people
can run Linux on the desktop.
I'm trying to make the PowerShell experience on Linux
much better so then more people won't
have to go to Windows to do their day job.
And I think that's probably, if Microsoft
was trying to extinguish Linux, there's
no way they would have open sourced this because it's
pretty much the tool that allows you to manage all these
Microsoft things without Windows.
It is really kind of.
I was thinking like, and we have an extended conversation
with DM that'll be out on Jupiter Extras,
but I was thinking when I was talking to him,
like, I would have killed for this.
Yes, right?
I mean, you can actually go interact with,
leverage a bunch of Windows environments
in a way that's native to them.
I think we're also made a little uncomfortable
because it has this different heritage, right?
Like, it comes from Microsoft, it's using Windows tools,
but it's an open source shell on top
of an open source kernel, right?
Like, what's not to like?
And that cat is out of the bag.
It's MIT licensed, it's out of the bag.
Also of note today, Microsoft open sourced
their C++ standard library.
Actually, it was technically yesterday,
they announced at a community conference
that they were releasing their C++ standard library code
as open source.
The STL code is now up on GitHub
and provided under the Apache 2 license.
Oh yeah, look at them go, more and more open source.
More and more all the time.
They say they hope this move will help developers
continue to keep the library compliant
in the fast-moving world of C++ standards.
And they hope it's a measure of payback
to the developer community.
Isn't that an interesting statement?
The first part's being like,
we're not doing a great job keeping up with the standards,
will you guys help us keep this going?
It's kind of an admission of that, isn't it?
Right, and then the other half is like,
but also, like here, we can all make this better.
You get to have all the code for the other stuff too.
I don't mind that.
No, honestly, it kind of makes sense, right?
That's part of the open source community
and the interactions.
We're all going to use the tooling
and if it is open, we can all make it better.
Yeah.
We have a few items in housekeeping for the episode.
It got messy in here.
Yeah, you know, I've been traveling.
Was it an East Washington over the weekend?
Just didn't have time, brought in a whole bunch of dirt.
I'm sorry about that.
So here's a few things we've got to take care of.
First and foremost, just a reminder,
Texas Cyber Summit coming up real soon now.
Texas Cyber Summit, October 10th through the 12th, 2019
at the Grand Hyatt.
San Antonio.
San Antones.
Wes and I'll be there.
What?
Hey Cheesy, are you going too, Cheesy?
Oh yeah, I'll be there.
Honestly, Cheesy being there, that's a reason to go
if you weren't already thinking about it.
Yeah, that's definitely enough.
Nice.
If you are going to be in the area
and you don't have a ticket, but you would like to go,
join our telegram group.
It's t.me forward slash TCS2019
and you might be able to score a ticket.
What is that again?
T.me slash what?
T.me, T.me slash TCS2019.
TCS, all right, very good.
Texas Cyber Summit.
There's a B new track too,
which if you're thinking about getting in the cyber industry,
that'd be a good one for you.
Right?
Don't forget, we also have the hacker birthday dinner meetup,
meetup.com slash super broadcasting.
It's all there.
So also, can we just take a moment,
ladies and gentlemen, a round of applause again.
Two new shows launched on the Jupiter Broadcasting Network.
Very, very, very excited to say
we are now into week two of Linux Headlines,
linuxheadlines.show.
Great show.
Oh man.
West, you're doing a bang up job.
No, you're doing a bang up job.
Drew killed it.
No, you are.
Drew killed it on Friday.
Drew killed it.
Fridays with Drew are my favorite.
He's so damn good.
How can he be so new and still that good?
I don't know.
We'll learn from him though.
I know.
So linuxheadlines.show, go check that out.
The things you need to know that's going on
on Linux and open source in three minutes or less
every weekday.
Yeah, I said every weekday.
I said that.
It's crazy.
linuxheadlines.show.
Also, it's finally here.
Self-hosted episode one.
The first one is out, self-hosted.show slash one.
Alex and I just get things kicked off in this episode.
And then coming up very soon, self-hosted.show,
our episode with Wendell.
Oh boy.
Great chat with Wendell.
It's all ready to go.
We'll be launching it soon.
Every fortnight over at self-hosted.show.
So go get episode one now
and stick around for episode two with Wendell.
Got a great chat, toured his studio, his servers,
his workstations, chat all about it.
It's pretty great.
So go check that out.
Self-hosted.show and linuxheadlines.show.
Man, so much going on.
Crazy.
And before you know it, it's Texas Cyber Summit.
Before you even know it, Wes.
All right.
That's the housekeeping.
Nicely done.
No, you did great.
I don't know, I think we've just come up with a thing.
So you and I had a chance last week to talk to Phil,
one of the co-founders of Mangero,
after they announced the new formation of their company.
Which was great.
Really exciting for them.
And we then thought, well, let's have
kind of like a Mangero celebration.
Stubble down.
And let's talk with Bernard,
one of the other co-founders this week,
because you and I had checked out the community additions,
which is one of the many things that Bernard's involved in,
as well as a few other things.
And just to really kind of recognize the moment
for Mangero.
They've moved into a new echelon of distributions.
There's a legal entity behind them.
They have a community.
They've formed partnerships with commercial organizations.
They're getting recognition on large YouTube platforms.
It's a big moment.
And so we really wanted to take the time
to both talk to Phil and Bernard.
Hello, thanks for having me.
Hello, sir.
So why don't we start off with a little bit of news.
There's a brand new, fresh release of Mangero
that's out just as we record.
What's your favorite thing about the new release?
Oh, it was quite busy for all of us
because we had to get a lot of different additions going.
Of course, the official ones, KD Plasma, XFC, and GNOME.
And I'm also in charge of some of the community additions.
So I was doing i3 and Cinnamon,
and they're all rolling now.
So yes, we have the 18.1.0 release.
Of course, it's just a snapshot,
not a real, I mean, it's not a real thing
with a rolling release.
But of course, we polish everything with the install media.
And so the installer works and stuff
with some new additions, of course,
with the new Flatpak and Snaps support
with Bau, our new tool.
And also Calamares had a recent update,
and we also offered a new Office Suite chooser.
So I want to talk about the community addition stuff
here in a moment,
but we got to do like the human stuff upfront.
So you got a new job.
Yeah, I do.
I mean, it's basically the job I've been doing
for five years already, but now it's a job.
It just used to be like kind of an oversized hobby for me.
I was doing other stuff.
I was in the music business as a singer,
but my hobby was taking a lot of time.
And so this is finally what I can now concentrate on.
Congratulations.
You mentioned it as an aside there,
but you're a bit of a known musician.
We did a little Googling, Bernard.
You have a bit of an online presence when it comes to music.
Show research, you know.
Oh yeah, that's true.
Yes, I've been quite active.
How did you end up being also pretty prominent
here in the open source community?
Oh, well, I always liked tweaking and analyzing stuff
and breaking stuff and putting it again together.
I actually started out with Atari when it was still a thing.
And so I found myself quite at home with Linux.
In between, I was of course using Windows
for everything I needed.
And then my main stoppers to switch over to Linux
were especially the music software, like music editing.
I mean, printed music editing and this kind of stuff.
But during the recent years,
we now have really software for everything I need.
So that was finally my opportunity to switch over to Linux.
So you come from a creative angle on all of this.
Yeah, you could say that.
It seems that that has also manifested
in you're one of the probably, I guess,
you're probably one of the prominent supporters
of the different community editions.
You know, I had an opportunity to chat with you off air
about the i3 and Cinnamon editions,
which I think you're the direct maintainer of.
So let's talk a little bit about that.
Is that a creative expression for you as well?
Yeah, it is.
I mean, I've styled the desktops.
I mean, i3 is a good example
because the way it comes from just the packages,
it's just totally naked and ugly and difficult to use.
And so it took quite a lot of creativity also
and tweaking and also about the optics
and theming is also a topic
in all of our editions, of course.
And so I took over Cinnamon
and i3 was kind of abandoned a few years ago.
And so that was really a good opportunity for me to,
yeah, also express my kind of my taste
and I like things to look nice
and to be also accessible
and also pretty on the surface.
Can you maybe go into a little more
about what's different about community editions?
I mean, you know, you're involved
and you're part of the core project.
So how is that different from one of your major releases?
Basically, traditionally in the Manjaro community,
it was like we had,
it used to be open box originally
where the core team like was maintaining a main edition
and then we had XFC and KDE came after that.
And then GNOME is more recent edition.
And the community editions were mostly just done
by one person.
So if you found a desktop environment that you would like
and then you would like offer it on the forum.
And if you were the first one who presented
then a desktop edition, then it was just your edition.
And yeah, it has also grown, I would say.
And nowadays it's like also the community editions
are maintained by members of the core team.
Oh, that's fascinating.
Yeah.
I look at the Cinnamon edition
and the i3 edition specifically
and I think they seem like passion projects to me.
But I do kind of wanna,
I wanna kind of examine that question
that Wes had there just a little bit further.
So I kind of, when I picture the Manjaro project,
I picture a default XFCE desktop.
But we were just chatting recently
and it seems depending on the time of month or day,
there's other additions like the plasma edition
that may actually be more popular.
Manjaro isn't necessarily defined by a single desktop.
So I guess, Bernard, in your opinion,
what defines Manjaro, especially for people
that are listening that maybe don't use it,
what defines it apart from Arch?
One important point is the usability, right?
I mean, i3 is a good example because as I already said,
it's very hard to use as it comes originally.
And so I've really tried to make it more accessible
to make it look pretty and run right out of the box
with everything available, all the shortcuts organized
and with a little introduction.
And I mean, Manjaro is mostly about the core system.
And as you can see, it's a huge variety
of just different desktops on top.
So the team, everybody together makes sure
that the core system runs well
and that the system is reliable.
And then it's just a question of putting any desktop
on top, basically.
And over the years, we have like also developed
our typical style.
It was also, we decided that it would be good
that when you open up a desktop on the first site,
you would be able to see, oh yes, this is a Manjaro edition.
So it's like the colors, it's the fonts.
So there is some branding element.
Yeah, you could say that.
It's not actually the same themes.
Yeah, because they don't necessarily work on every desktop,
but then we try to find kind of matching colors
and common wallpapers and that kind of stuff.
So do you feel like it would be a fair assessment
to say the difference from Arch is the brand,
the community, and the intention
that you put into the desktop?
And you can apply that to i3, Cinnamon, XFCE, or Plasma,
because what defines Manjaro isn't a desktop environment.
The mentality of presenting a desktop ready to go,
I would say.
I mean, Arch people are really keen on building everything
and styling everything the way everybody likes personally.
And we offer like one version that you could just start
using on an everyday basis.
And if you can live with how it looks like,
then you can just, you would never have to change anything.
And also, we put together a combination of packages,
like you have an image viewer, you have a music player,
you have an office suite, you have a mail program, a browser,
so that you have everything that you would normally need.
So my question is, now that things are changing a little bit,
it's becoming a real business, it's a full-time gig for you,
will there be some shifts in your priorities?
You've got a lot on your plate right now, especially with the community edition stuff.
Do you see a future where you kind of narrow the list a little bit
of what you're involved with?
I don't know.
I mean, at the moment, we are just starting out
and looking around a little bit where our direction is really going.
We are collecting ideas and I have the feeling
that the team is extremely motivated by our steps.
And we have a lot of discussions between not just the two of us, of course,
between the whole team, which is about something around 12 people or so.
And at the moment, it's also about finding out who likes to specialize in what
and where the strengths of everybody lie.
And I don't really think that we need to narrow down our offer at the moment.
It's not really what it's about.
I mean, the basic idea is to keep what we have running
and then to add what comes up.
It sort of strikes me that Manjaro is sort of the first to make it this far
with something that's based on Arch.
You could look at Arch much like Ubuntu looks at Debian
as a great base to build a product on top of.
And you're sort of first to this real estate. You're the first to this new land.
What happens next?
I mean, Arch has this reputation of being hard to build, hard to use, and hard to maintain.
And so that's somehow where we have grown into.
We have built our way of balancing the bleeding edge idea
with usability and continuity.
Of course, it's still a little bit of a balancing act,
but I think we have found our ground here very well now.
So that's probably why we are now in a position where we can really say,
okay, this is quite reliable and we can look back on several years now
where this has been running smoothly.
And one idea of incorporating was also that, as you can see with other projects,
that at a certain point it really gets very hard to do this
beside everything else you do.
As a hobby, it's just you really need to invest a lot of time, a lot of energy,
and to keep it with a certain amount of quality.
That's basically our motivation to find a way to really be able to focus on this.
I'm pretty excited about it because I think at some point I had just accepted the idea
that all of the next big distros that were ever going to happen had happened,
and now it was just a matter of, well, let's settle in and figure out how to make this work.
And then Manjaro comes along and proved me wrong, and I think it's just so fantastic.
I think we have absolutely room for more, and you guys are really committed to the project,
and it's getting recognized for what it's contributing and those paper cuts
that it's solving for end users, and it's just such a great thing to see this next step being taken.
And Bernard, I love the Community Editions.
I had a chance to play with Cinnamon and i3 over the weekend.
We'll have links in the show notes for those.
And I just love that that's even a thing, and that we can have a company where this kind of thing can go on,
and it can be a creative expression for you and all of that.
So thanks for coming on and just answering some of these questions.
It's just something I've been considering, and I don't know, man.
I'm just super happy for you guys.
Thanks for that.
Jeezy, you've been running Manjaro for a little while, haven't you?
Yeah, so I've got this Dell Inspiron 3000 Series 2-in-1.
It was my wife's old computer, and so it just got handed down to me.
The first thing I was going to do is load Linux on it.
Whenever I tried to load any distro on it, I would have a problem.
Because it's a 2-in-1, it has an accelerometer and a gyroscope in it.
So by default, and this was elementary, pop, fedora, I mean, any distribution that I tried,
those kernel modules would be enabled by default.
So my login screen would be flipped 180 degrees and then inverted,
as if it was in tablet mode and you would be entering information in tablet mode,
which, you know, is nothing that you can't with GNOME.
You can lock screen rotation now, and you can do other things that make it a little bit easier.
You can X, R, and R, you know, and set it back to normal.
You can go back in and blacklist those kernel modules.
But the one distro that has worked every single time out of the box,
doesn't matter which DEF tried, has been Manjaro.
I've never had those kernel modules loaded by default.
And for me, I mean, that's a pretty significant thing.
You know, that takes three steps out of just getting the machine working properly.
And, you know, so I've been using Manjaro off and on on that machine,
just I use it to test other distros, knowing that I'm going to have to rotate the screen,
I'm going to have to do a few tweaks, but then inevitably always go back to Xfce,
the Xfce variant of Manjaro on it.
And man, I really like it. It's been solid.
Like Bernard said, I love the fact that I still get that rolling release,
but I don't have to spend the time to set up Arch.
Not that there's anything wrong with that.
I mean, if I've been down that road, I've done that as well, right?
But to have a distro out of the box, bleeding edge, boom, here you go.
Yeah, it helps that they make such nice, you know, choices.
Like the defaults are good, so you don't have to change that much.
Yeah, it's tastefully done. Absolutely.
The fact that they've gone through and they've tried to mimic, you know,
those themes across all of the DEs and everything.
I think they've really done a great job.
I haven't tried all of the community additions.
I will now though, knowing that I didn't realize that Bernard was putting those together as well.
So I guess they're official community additions.
Ish, yeah.
I really love Manjaro too.
I'm a diehard Arch Linux user on the desktop,
and my laptop is running Manjaro.
And the implementation of XFCE that they have is the one that made me realize that XFCE is pretty great.
You know, I'm getting 10 to 12 hours worth of battery life on a T480.
The laptop's cool to the touch.
You know, it just works like Chi said.
And it's more than Arch for people that can't be bothered to install Arch, I think,
which is what it was always sold as.
I look at it a lot, although I'm going to try not to make this comparison.
But I look at it in some ways similar to Ubuntu to Debian.
Like I could get a decent Debian desktop going if I wanted to spend some time
changing all of the defaults and optimizing things a bit.
I could, you know, it's not much more work really than setting up Arch.
I mean, it is probably a little less, but it's kind of equivalent.
Or you could install Ubuntu and you have a pretty ready-to-go machine.
Like that's very much how Ubuntu started.
It was a refined selection of good desktop packages with some same defaults
synced to the GNOME release schedule.
And so it was a great way to get easy-to-use Debian.
That's what made it so successful initially.
And that fundamental recipe is kind of what they're applying here to Arch.
Well, one thing that I really like too is as an official version,
they have the Architect Edition.
So if you want to do the same thing you would do with Arch,
you can still do that with the Manjaro ISO,
which I think is cool that they offer that as an official version as well.
Well, congrats to them.
Very happy to see them turn this into something they can do sustainably.
What am I trying to say?
Sustainably, yeah, right.
I mean, it's a big deal.
Bernard had a successful singing career,
and now he's focusing on this Linux distribution full-time,
and it's cool that that actually exists.
So we have an app pick we want to get to,
and we have a headline that we pulled out of Linux headlines
to discuss a little bit more here in the show.
So let's do that one first.
Just one last thing here from the community news is we've got new kernels, Wes.
We've got one that's out now, kernel 5.3 came out this weekend.
And that's always fun.
I also kind of want to talk a little bit about 5.4.
But in 5.3, they added the ACRN hypervisor,
which I was hoping was pronounced acorn.
Acorn.
But I don't think it is.
Why would you not pronounce it acorn?
Why do we need another hypervisor?
What's so unique here?
Well, okay, so this is actually guest support for Linux.
So acorn is a hypervisor that's targeted at embedded and IoT applications,
but things like real-time and safety.
So if you've got things in your car or maybe in like factory-managed equipment
that, you know, people's lives are at stake.
Where it could be an embedded device and it uses virtualization
to run different OSs on it.
Yes, workload consolidation, right?
You can move lots of things.
Existing hypervisors, things that you might use in a data center,
not really set up or designed with those goals.
So this is supposed to be an open-source implementation of a reference stack,
basically, all managed by the Linux Foundation.
Of course, this patch set allows Linux to be booted on top of acorn.
So, hey, that's great.
That means more places that Linux will run.
I mean, if you're going to run an OS on your IoT device,
I'd rather it be Linux.
And I'd rather it be updatable and supported.
And if it's baked into the kernel, that means it actually might be possible.
Now, this is only bare-bones support, so we'll see what happens.
There's another patch in 5.3 that I thought didn't get enough attention.
You know, I don't know about you, Chris, but sometimes you have a high DPI screen,
and then you go and you, like, boot.
You boot Linux, and you can't read it, right?
You can't read anything, especially what happens if it doesn't boot up all the way?
Right.
There's a fix for that now.
Yeah.
Prefer a bigger font for high-resolution screens.
That's the name of the commit.
And, I mean, like, why would you not want that?
Everything you need to know is in the name of the commit.
So it will prefer a console font that is larger on high DPI display
so you can actually read it.
Yeah.
Now, for, like, 1920 by 1080 and below, nothing changes, no effect.
But if you're above that, there's a different font that's used.
So it seems like this should have happened ages ago, but as a terminal user, I'm glad.
I actually didn't supermind it.
Sometimes we get a little janky on how it would update on the screen,
but I kind of like fitting more stuff on the screen, you know?
I want more screens, and I want to fit more on them.
Yeah, but I don't always have my microscope right next to my display.
That's true.
Yeah, on the XPS 13, it was kind of ridiculous.
It was getting pretty bad, actually.
Well, so it's not out yet, but I kind of wanted to talk about something
that I thought was interesting about the 5.4 impending release.
So this next one has a bunch of neat stuff.
But what I think we're now seeing is, you recall just a few weeks ago
when the news came out that Microsoft was changing their positioning
on exFAT licensing and said, all right, have at it.
You can whip up some exFAT code.
You can submit to the kernel.
We will not pursue any patent infringement litigation.
Great. Hoorah.
And then there was this sort of side story about, oh, it turns out somebody
created some exFAT code.
It's not of great quality, but it will probably make it in the kernel pretty soon.
Who could that be?
Well, now we got a name on a commit, and that name ties back to Samsung.
Samsung.
So Samsung whipped this up for their Android devices, likely.
Of course.
Of substandard quality, which... You know, you just hack it together.
It's fine. Who cares?
They're just putting it on a cell phone that's going to millions of pockets.
It only costs $800.
Who cares, right?
And so that should be landing in its early quality status
in the 5.4 kernel, exFAT like that.
I'd love to see that land in Fedora 31.
Now, has there been time for quality improvements, or is this still...
No, no, no.
I mean, maybe.
You know, maybe.
I mean, honestly, if I were them, as soon as Microsoft made that announcement,
I would have been like, all right, get that guy back over here.
Get him working on it.
That's what I would have done.
I don't know.
But you're right.
I mean, it's nice to see, and now we can all use it finally.
It's out there.
Not that I needed it done.
I just had that experience.
So what happened was, is during our team sprint in the summer,
we had a bunch of great pictures, and I'm like,
well, let me pop in the old SD card here that's built into my ThinkPad.
Right, it's great.
Take advantage of that.
Because hashtag port options.
And I pop it in there, and I look like a fool
because my operating system, which was Fedora 30, could do nothing with it.
Nothing.
And I had the realization that, oh, yeah, I got to go install Fuse,
and I got this whole song and dance.
It sounds silly, but it's almost like being pulled back to old Linux.
You know, like these days, things just mostly just work.
Well, yeah.
And this is suddenly like, oh, right, Linux is like this sometimes.
Yeah, and so it would be kind of a remarkable thing
if in the next release, if in 31, it just worked.
Even if it was just read-only, I'd be fine with that.
Don't get me right.
Just let me import my damn pictures, please.
I want to stash them in my file system like a squirrel.
It is cool.
I mean, right, open source.
And now you know that if improvements are needed,
we've got the kernel infrastructure and development staff in place.
Well, I think this only helps the creatives that use Linux from day to day,
like Brent, you know, constantly pulling images from large SD cards
or creating video content, drone video.
I mean, anything like that.
I think this is a win for us for sure.
So tell us about ClipGrab.
Jeezy brings us an app pick this week that could be useful for those of you
that like offline media like I do.
Oh, so, yeah, I was digging around actually in the Manjaro repos last night,
and I came across ClipGrab, which is essentially a GUI version,
not necessarily a version of YouTube DL.
It's its own thing, but it's super nice.
I use it to pull down tutorial videos for different Adobe products and stuff like that
so that I can offline those and watch them separately on another device
while I'm actually going through them.
I love it, man.
ClipGrab, check it out.
It's worth the download, and it's super easy to use, dead simple to use.
You can pull down MP4, MP3, OGS, all different various formats.
Oh, this is just an app image.
Hey, Andy.
Yeah, it's an app image, and you can just download and run it, and yeah,
it can convert videos to MP3s if you want to like pop it on a podcast
while you're driving and you don't need the visuals.
That's pretty great.
Thanks, Jeezy.
There's so many options out there now for that kind of stuff.
I don't know how YouTube feels about it, but it seems clear that there's a need
and a demand for that kind of thing.
Absolutely.
You can find a link to that as well as everything else we've talked about
and the news stories and all of that over at linuxunplug.com slash 319.
And Wes, did you know we do this here show live?
Oh, yeah, every Tuesday.
It's probably a good thing you knew that because if you didn't,
we'd need to have a separate conversation.
Yeah, that's true.
It would be really awkward.
It would be weird.
How has my timing been so good all this time?
It's just lucky, I guess.
Go get more Wes over at TechSnap.systems, him and Jim Salter doing their thing.
That's right.
Over at TechSnap program.
Loving that every single week.
And do join us live.
If you want to know when, jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
You can also just follow us on the Twitters.
Oh, yeah, we tweet about it.
Yeah.
That's for sure.
I'm at Chris Elias.
I'm at Westpane.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
So go check that out.
Also, go check out our buddies' Ubuntu podcast.
Go check them out.
Oh, yeah.
Why not?
Always cutting out a good episode, those guys, every single week.
So go check them out.
And join us next time, linuxunplug.com slash 319.
Thanks so much for joining us.
And we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
It's an episode of transitions.
Think about this.
No kidding.
So we talk about Richard Stallman resigning.
We talk about PowerShell on Linux.
What?
And Manjaro becoming a legitimate business and like the top tier Linux distributions
shifting.
Like this episode really reflects a really kind of massive amount of change going on.
And it's like part exciting and part somber because it's, you know, the somber side, it's,
you know, seeing somebody like Richard Stallman who is so well known in our community and
the technical contributions he's made have been so important to...
I mean a passionate free software advocate and shaped their discourse for a long time.
Yeah.
And then also yet undeniably a troublesome personality for a long time that there was
going to be some kind of reckoning.
And it's just to see that thing, to see all of that go down while also seeing the nature
and basic use of free software and open source radically shifting with Microsoft and just
the massive, massive deployment of cloud infrastructure and all of the people that are
writing software for that.
And also at the same time Manjaro becoming a company to me seems to be a clear indicator
that there is still a market for desktop Linux.
Like I thought we were done with this.
I thought we were all done with this.
We'd had it, you know, everybody gave their shot.
The people that could make it work had usually other commercial backings to them like obvious
reasons why they were in the market.
And then Manjaro came along.
It's like an unexpected little bright star in the Linux constellation.
And it seems to validate the market a little bit.
It's not necessarily like a foregone conclusion.
It's not.
But it's a data point.
It's a signal.
Yeah.
It's exciting to watch too.
I mean it's not all that surprising Chris.
If you think about projects with their own self-commercial backing like elementary OS
being a thing and there's a number of other ones like I mean Endless is one of those
that are closer to the failed state than a lot of other ones.
But they're all almost every single desktop Linux distribution project that has existed
has either pivoted some other way or refocused or even pivoted back or something like that.
It's the fact that desktop Linux still exists today after almost what 20 years of ragging
and attempts and stuff like that I think kind of proves that there is some degree of staying
power but we probably just don't quite understand where the pieces fit just yet into making
it like broadly successful.
I think that's fair.
Yeah.
We'll keep trying.
I mean everyone from Red Hat to Endless to you know Manjaro and all the rest of them
will all keep working at it and we'll see what happens.
I think Manjaro too.
I think it's fascinating about it is it's not sold as super approachable for new Linux
users out of the box.
You know get mom and dad started using a computer.
It's a little bit more of a more sophisticated user's desktop.
Right.
Yeah.
You're a Linux user.
You want like a good solid desktop machine that you can use without a bunch of limitations.
Even the concept of how it does its updates is more of an advanced user's concept than
what people are used to when it comes to commercial operating systems.
I have a bit of a theory here and this is the rise of DevOps.
This is the rise of people using Linux at work and then thinking hmm this is quite good
on the server.
Why don't I give it a try on the desktop?
What's the worst that could happen?
Right.
And there is some nice advantages to the desktop being rolling because if you want fresh user
land applications.
I do.
And you want fresh whatever like for me it would be Gnome Shell if I was a Gnome Shell
user.
Such a sucker for that.
Got to get the latest XSE every four years.
You know there's some advantages.
Really what it is about getting fresh Chrome and fresh Firefox and new Thunderbird and
getting all of these applications that are just in a repository automatically updated.
When you come from Windows or Mac OS that's all luxury.
It's a yearly thing where you got to upgrade your operating system on Mac OS.
They do that every year.
Oh you mean it works just like the Play Store?
Yeah right.
So the advantages of rolling for somebody who's just using it as a workstation as long
as it doesn't break anything are pretty appealing.
They're hand holding in the right places.
Aren't you Mr. Fedora that wants to upgrade every nine months?
I think Fedora is a better cadence because you still get fresh applications but it's
not like rolling constantly.
And that to me is just a little bit slower and that's just the preference I like.
But I can totally appreciate the appeal for the desktop still.
I kind of miss it sometimes.
So the other thing on the flip side of this with the pure rolling environment, then the
major difficulty that you'll start having is how do you make sure everything stays working
more or less forever.
One of the reasons why most distributions have a cadence is so that they can have a
choke point or a break point in which they can make changes.
My experience with working in OpenSUSE of Tumbleweed and other rolling distributions
is that it gets extremely hard to make major changes without breaking people unless you
have those kinds of release points.
And so one of the challenges I'm watching out for to see how Manjaro handles it is that
how are they going to handle when they need to make a major change and then they have
to make sure that that works and it upgrades and it handles cleanly and as they grow as
a business because that's what they're going to do.
There's going to be people filing bug reports expecting some kind of assistance or help
or fixes or things like that.
You get into an interesting mess that you don't typically have as a community project
that doesn't have a commercial sponsor.
I don't know how they're going to handle this and I'm kind of playing the wait and see to
see how this will shake out.
So one of the reasons we don't really see rolling do this is because this is really,
really hard to do right in that commercial-ish context, even for home users, especially for
home users who don't necessarily have that same level of patience that maybe enterprise
users can be pushed back into.
I also feel that when people pay money, they feel like entitled and then if a rolling release
breaks after they paid for it in some way, shape or form, then the backlash is going
to be much bigger.
Well, maybe that's a market opportunity to sell us a service support contract.
I mean, maybe it kind of depends on how they set the expectation.
I think it's fascinating because it's not your typical distro to go for this kind of
thing.
Clearly, there's a community behind it.
And also of note, we're talking a lot about workstation, but a big part of the community
there is clearly gaming, too.
That's what's got so much attention on YouTube.
It's something to watch.
As I say, the end of summer is always interesting in open source land.