Samsung's quarterly earnings are out and their sales are falling flat. The S5 is not selling
very well, profits are down, shipments are down, like big too, like pretty big, like
pretty big drops. What do you think, Popey? Why is Samsung's sales falling through the
floor on their Samsung lines of phones?
Could it be that people now have, that we've reached a saturation point of smartphones
and there's nothing revolutionary in smartphones that they're making. All they're doing is
making them in different sizes.
But look at the activation counts. The activation counts are still going up for every month.
There's more Android activations than before.
But people don't necessarily want gigantic, very expensive phones. They want a smartphone.
And Samsung, do they have a range of low-end Android phones?
They also have the same phone coming out every single year now, it seems like.
Yeah, yeah, that's true. People got a little bored maybe. And plus TouchWiz has gotten
a bad rap.
And people still use their S4 and S3. They're still on contract too.
I think it's cheaper Android phones. I think that's what it is. I think part of the problem
is the same problem that Windows PC manufacturers have had.
Cheaper on lock phones.
Like if it's all kind of the same thing, then why don't I just buy the cheapest one? Especially
if I'm not savvy enough to know the difference between them.
Speaking of phones, did y'all hear about the signage in GitHub getting pulled down?
Yeah, what happened there?
It was something about the Broadcom drivers, wasn't it?
No, it was Qualcomm, wasn't it?
Yeah, Qualcomm. That's what it was. There you go. And Qualcomm released a statement
about that too, but I haven't read it yet.
They backed down and apologized.
Well, it was like a huge pull-down too, right? Like it was a massive DMCA takedown they
did. So yeah, I'm looking at it right now in Ferronix. Qualcomm has reversed this takedown
notice and allowed the 100 plus Git repositories to reappear. Qualcomm came under pressure
and likely looked at the reported files to realize they weren't all that confidential.
In fact, they probably didn't have anything to do with them. Just all bits being like
Android kernel source files and things from Cyanogenmod.
It was weird too because the files that they wanted to pull down are open sourced ones,
wasn't it?
Yeah.
Yeah, they all had the Linux Foundation comments up at the top.
Yeah. Yeah. That's the bogus thing about it. So did you also hear that now SoundCloud is
allowing EMC to do a content ID on SoundCloud files and issue essentially like the same
YouTube notice system on SoundCloud now?
Yeah. And if you protest it, you get told you're outlaw. And if you've got a pro account,
tough.
You've got GitHub that has to do DMCA takedowns for code. You've got YouTube and SoundCloud
that have to do takedowns for copyright. This is sucking.
SoundCloud has like mostly other people's audio on it. So it's kind of hard to not have,
you know.
Well, I mean, yeah.
It consists pretty much like almost the entire thing.
You could also see that if there's some d-bag who uploads like an entire CD to his SoundCloud
account or something like that. I mean, you could see there's a point there.
Yeah, but you know, people also do remixing and stuff like that too.
Yeah. And I guess we're kind of more familiar with it in the content sense, but this to
me really seemed like here's a real world like GitHub code now is the same things happening
where it's probably the same way it works with content ID is there is some third party
that Qualcomm contracts with to go out and find violations of their intellectual property
online, right? And then they issue out, they do the whole thing. They probably have legal
representation status. They issue the letter on behalf of Qualcomm. And it's like there's
a whole industry around this now. And now it applies to code too, I guess.
An open source by itself.
Yeah. Yeah. It's probably an open source Python script doing the scanning. Damn it. Yeah.
Dang it. And they're doing it from the Chromebooks. Okay. Okay. Now we're going to talk about
the KD thing in the show.
I'm saying nothing.
Can somebody... Okay, here's the thing. I struggle with how to even phrase and talk
about these things. Like here's why. Here, let me read this. Let me just pick out. Here's
the opening paragraph to the announcement. So here's the headline on KDE.org. KDE-KDEShips
Release Candidate of Plasma 5. The next paragraph says, KDE has today made available the candidate
for the first release of Plasma 5, the next generation desktop. This is one last chance
to test for bugs and check for problems for the final release next week. Okay. So here's
where I get a little confused. KDE has today made available the candidate for the first
release of Plasma 5, the next generation desktop. See what the problem is, is KDE is the group
and the community. Plasma 5 is the desktop. So, but then there is also something else
that's KDE. There's like, I don't know. I'm very, I'm kind of confused on like, there's
a couple...
There's a Frameworks and then there's a Plasma Therapies.
Right, right. So the Frameworks are Q... No, they're K... What are they called?
KF5 Frameworks, I think. KDE5.
Yeah, yeah. Right. Okay. So there's KDE5 Frameworks, then there's Plasma 5, and then there's KDE.
Okay. So KDE is the group. Right, right. Which is KDE5 basically though, right?
Yeah.
Right. Okay. So you have KDE the community, you have KDE5, the next set of like underlying
stuff, and then you have KDE Plasma desktop, or is it just Plasma? What's it called? Just
Plasma 5?
Plasma desktop.
Just Plasma.
Yeah.
Okay. Just Plasma. No KDE. It's very confusing for me for some reason. It should not be so
confusing.
Cygo pasted a picture earlier today about it. I think it was Cygo, where it's like equating
KDE to Microsoft, Plasma to Windows, and 5 to Windows 7.
Well, it's interesting that he did that, because my first thought was this feels a lot like
how Microsoft names products, and this feels a lot like the same kind of confusion that
I get when sometimes I'm trying to understand a Microsoft product line. And I also feel
like that same confusion and how Microsoft titles their products also translates into
their products. And interestingly enough, I feel that same way about KDE. So it's interesting
that Aaron made that same comparison, because in my mind, when I was trying to sort this
out earlier, the first thing that came to mind is, man, I feel like I'm reading something
from Microsoft right now.
Isn't that strange that KDE, one of the desktops that is kind of heralded for being Windows-like,
is kind of confusing you like Windows does?
Oh, man.
Check that link in the chat, Chris. It's got an Inga link, which makes it all perfectly
clear.
Yeah, you should be able to get all that installed in Arch right now, but I tried to, but I could
not for the life of me get it to work.
Yeah, I figure I'm going to wait a little bit. I've been trying out the new theme, so...
Because you've got to use the KDE unstable repo and everything to do it all.
Yeah, right now I've just been getting the next theme on top of KDE 4, the latest, and
that seems to be the safer bet. But I'm a little curious to try out the new hotness.
I really am. Something about it, man. I'm a fresh-coated hound. It's like, I don't know
it's like a pie in the window. And I just start, I'm walking down the street, pretty
soon the next thing you know I'm stealing pies out of old ladies' windows, also known
as unstable repos.
Okay, let me take a look at this. Imgur, Imgur, Imgur, Imgur.
Now, only if they could fix Phonon. That would be awesome.
Hey, there's Josh. Hey, Josh. Josh, join us in the mumble room if you want. Bang mumble
to get the server info. Okay, all right, so here you go. Here is the errands I go. KDE
is not your desktop. All right, so KDE is the organization, Plasma Desktop is the product,
and then 5 is the version. Makes sense, right? Very simple.
And you got Qt on top of that. So Qt 5 now too.
Now, is it irrational? Okay, so I'm just going to say like, you know, hey maybe if
this requires an infographic, maybe it's too complicated. Is that just me being dense?
Because I understand sometimes like I think I have like a bit of a disability or something
and this stuff doesn't click for me. So I know I'm just maybe seeing this the wrong
way.
No, I feel the same way. I mean, I looked at this and I was like, oh, oh, okay, and
then there's a piss take at the bottom. Now, go boot your Microsoft, start Mozilla, and
buy Adobe. You're some kind of idiot if you don't understand that KDE is the organization
and Plasma is the product. What kind of fool are you? I'm like, oh, all right then.
I guess. Okay, so back in the good old days, was it just straight up called KDE? And is
that where the confusion come from? Is that back in the day it was just KDE?
Yeah, because before there was a Plasma shell. That was it come about till KDE 4.
So didn't they change the game rules on us? And they're like, hey, why don't you guys
know the rules?
Yeah, they're complicating the shit out of this.
Before it was just KDE 2 or KDE 3, whatever, and it was Plasma at the KDE core.
That's all right. I mean, they could be worse. They could be pulling a fedora and like changing
their name and then changing their name back and then changing their name back to it, but
not meaning the same thing.
Wasn't there also the whole KDE software collection and malarkey? That confused me as well.
I think that's still a thing. I know, I think that's a thing still.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that says forget legalizing cannabis.
Pizza vending machines powered by Linux are the real crop of our future. My name is Chris
and Matt will be joining us a little bit. They're working out his audio right now. And
it's not only a hot day here in Washington. Let me tell you what, it is a special day,
a magical day, if you will, magical brownie day, sans magical brownies. They've legalized
cannabis here. And then you think that's what I would be excited about, but no, I have discovered
something called pizza vending machines. Go Google it. It's a real thing.
Now they don't run Linux yet. So I think what we need to do is start a community effort.
Maybe we could crowdsource a platform for vending machines. It's going to need a resizable
UI. So we'll have to talk about maybe what we're going to use there. Something for different
pizza vending machine form factors is what I'm saying. Different architectures. Put all
that in there. We'll get it out into the public. Then we'll send the proceeds to the different
open source projects that needs funding. Huh? Chris just laid it out for you. You guys can
take and run with it. I'm an idea guy. I'm putting that out there to the universe.
Well coming up on the show today, we've got a few follow up items news and email wise
that I want to talk to you guys about, including some epic funding, some Civ 5 solutions, a
little KDE and Plasma 5 talk, and then we're going to do a community review of KAOS. K-A-O-S.
A Lean KDE Distribution. We have a team now of folks that went through and kicked the
tires on this thing. I've got it running in a VM. We'll talk about it there. We'll talk
about it with them. See how it goes. And joining me as always is a fully stacked house. A great
lineup of mumble folks that are going to kick around the topics with us, including Joss
who has joined us before on the Linux Action Show, although I believe he was working with
Sousa at the time of Novell. Joss, refresh my memory. Last time we had you on the show,
were you working with OwnCloud yet? I'm pretty sure I wasn't yet because I only joined OwnCloud
April 1st of this year and I think it's been a while since I've been on the show. Well,
I'm really glad you could be here today because a couple of things we're going to talk about
are in your wheelhouse, so I'll be deferring to your expertise as we get to that kind of
stuff and we'll get a little update from you and see what you've been up to in a bit too,
okay? I'd be happy to help. All right, now go back to the World Cup. All right, so we'll
get to our emails first. Ben S. wrote in. He says, hey Chris and Matt. He said, hey
Ben. I love the show. I recently started a command line challenge of sorts. I wanted
to see if I could live in the command line with no graphical desktop of any kind. I started
about two days ago and it's going really well. I use Elinks for my web browsing, Seamless
for my music listening, and Vim for writing. The hardest part was getting my wireless set
up. What do you guys think? Is it possible to work in a command line with no desktop?
I thought about this for a minute for myself. In MumbleRoom, I'd be really curious to know
about you guys. I wonder, could anybody in the MumbleRoom live in the command line exclusively
for two days? Anybody? Yes. Poppy, come on. Without HTML? No. I lived in the command line
for two months while my Debian SID system had an X, broken X server. All right, all
right, heavens, all right. Holy smokes. All right, okay, we got to break this down. I
want to start with Poppy because I'm calling BS. Come on, Poppy. Do you know what? I bought
a deck, a vintage deck, VT100, specifically to do this, to have it sat on my desk and
be my main machine so I could have some of that retro smell coming from the valves inside
of that terminal. Well, I love the idea of a dedicated machine for it. I mean, I could
see that. Okay, all right, so heavens, when you were doing this for a while, did you listen
to podcasts? Did you just randomly Google stuff? How did that work? What was that like?
Well, I was using a command line audio player, and I was actually in my Gentoo compiling
days at the time as well, so my second partition was on Gentoo, and that pretty much took up
an entire two months of time while my Debian system was just kind of in maintenance.
Wow. I don't know. I kind of fall down with Wimpy. What do you think, Wimpy? Haven't we
worked towards perfecting the computer interface and the graphical desktop and building in
all these great video cards to get past this hassle?
I think so. I mean, I was brought up on Unix systems in the late 80s and early 90s where
this was your only option, and we were craving for something better, and now we've got something
better. So on your desktop, use a desktop environment or a decent tining window manager
to manage all of your terminals to your connections to your remote systems. I do all of my development
over SSH in the shell. That's perfectly fine, but why would you want to do that for your
email and your web browsing and your podcasting and all the other stuff when there are better
tools available now?
Well, you say there are better tools, but MUT is a fantastic email client. I actually
miss when I used to use MUT before I started using Gmail. I miss those days because I was
so fast with MUT. I could really manage my email super fast, and I already use IRSSI
for my IRC client. So all I need is GNU Screen or TMUX, and I've got two windows there, one
with my email, one with my IRC. All I need is a shell in another. Who needs a GUI?
I like the pine.
I kind of... What do you think, Riley? You think it's possible, in other words, but not
practical?
Yes, there are several CLI tools that you could use in TTY mode, and you could use different
TTY sessions for each one. I could have WeChat running in one TTY. You can have NPD running
in another and do stuff like that, but it's just not practical to say in age. Unless you
are trying to rebuild an extra or something.
Yeah, yeah. That's kind of how I feel about it. I look at it and I think, boy, I could...
If I didn't need to do podcasts, if I didn't need to do media production, if I didn't need
to show webpages, if I didn't have to edit video, if I didn't have to play video or have
to want to play video games, maybe... I don't know. I love the idea of having a fully set
up account on my DigitalOcean droplet that's ready to go, could operate at any time and
is a fold command line only environment, but I wouldn't want to live there.
Just out of curiosity, how do I sound over Skype? Because I suspect that this is not
an audio problem. I think it's a mobile problem.
Oh, you sound good now, Matt.
Much better.
You sound real good.
You sound really good.
Yeah. Wow, you sound really good, Matt.
Like normal.
Yeah. Well, good job. You guys fixed it. So good. Now Matt's joined us, I think. I think
he's gone now, but he has it fixed, so he'll be back. Anyways, I would like to know if
you could survive on the command line, so let us know in the thread in the subreddit
for this episode of Linux Unplugged. And let us know how it goes, Ben. Be sure you're sending
a follow-up if you ended up breaking, which I think you will.
All right. Colonel Linux, open mic, Colonel Linux. Open mic, Colonel Linux. Open mic.
All right. So I want to do a follow-up regarding my ButterFS stuff. I had failed to mention
during the Linux Action Show episode on ButterFS about recovering that and expanding and reclaiming
space and defragmenting. Samuel tweeted me and said, sorry if this story mentioned to
you, which it wasn't, running defraig in general or recompressing on ButterFS will duplicate
snapshots. So if you use ButterFS and you take snapshots, you need to be aware of that.
And I failed to mention that because I never really have gotten into ButterFS snapshots,
so it didn't really apply to me. That is a huge caveat because that could be a massive,
if you're trying to reclaim space and you have snap, first off, if you're trying to
reclaim space, maybe you should clean up your snapshots. But second thing is, that's just
a little gotcha that I wanted to make sure you guys knew about.
Hey, before we get into a couple of really great news items that just didn't make it
in the Linux Action Show this Sunday, really exciting stuff for a super, super important
open source project that we're big fans of here at the Jupyter Broadcasting Network.
But first, I want to thank our first sponsor and a brand new sponsor to Linux Unplugged.
We had them on How To Linux, and we decided to bench that for a bit so we could restructure
it. But it's such, our next sponsor is so great for you guys that I said, hey, come
over to Linux Unplugged. We'll work out the details. I want to make this offer available.
And Linux Academy said, yeah, you bet. So here's what I want you to do. Go over to linuxacademy.com
slash howto. They've got a summer of learning discount. They're going to take 33% off, so
you're only going to pay $50 for the quarter.
This is a service that's been built from the ground up by Linux enthusiasts and people
who are educators working together on a system that allows you to do self-paced training.
Go test yourself as you move along. They have seven plus Linux distributions available for
you to learn from. So you log in, you pick your course, you choose your Linux distribution.
The courseware automatically adapts to the Linux distribution you choose. So not only
is this awesome if you want to focus on a distro, but if you're also really familiar
with one particular distro and want to just sort of brush up on how the other side lives,
it can be extremely useful for that as well. And how cool is it that they'll adjust the
course material for you? As you go along, they'll have step-by-step video courses. You
can download those and listen to them offline. All of their material is available for you.
All the courseware is high quality. You can download and keep it for yourself. Test yourself.
See where you're at. Engage with the community. See what's worked for them. Take advantage
also of the AWS training courses they have. Go over to linuxacademy.com slash howto. It's
a limited time URL because I really said it's like, you guys, this is such a great offer.
We have to offer it to the Linux unplugged folks. So we just made this kind of switch
just the other day. So that's like an old school URL. If you want to be like a URL hipster,
which I'm sure you do, right? Go use it. Linuxacademy.com slash howto. You can also take a look at some
of their courses. They have the Linux plus exam, introduction to Linux on your desktop.
They also have different levels of the Linux LPIC exam. How to get a Linux job. Introduction
to Android development. Introduction to Python on Linux. Open stack essentials. Linux, for
example, novice to pro. Introduction to VMware ESXi. Configuring BIND 9. Configuring Ubuntu
NFS. Setting up VNC. The LAMP stack. Nagios. Learning R-Sync. Resolving the Heartbleed
plug. Samba 4 and Linux client and server. I just got an email about that today. All
of that stuff is available right now, including brand new courses for AWS. You want to become
a hybrid technologies expert on AWS? Boom. They've got a course for it. You want to be
an AWS certified developer or AWS certified SysOps administrator? Boom. They've got a
course for it. This is what I'm telling you. Linux Academy has got this covered. And what's
super cool about Linux Academy is you're going through the courseware. If you get to a point
in the lab where you need a server, they on the back end spin up the virtual infrastructure
required for you to do that course automatically. This is amazing when you're doing an AWS course
because you don't have to worry about the cost to Amazon. And one of the other things
that I think is truly exceptional about them is they've got this whole system all set up
where you can log in at any point and get a snapshot of exactly where you're at. And
while you're a member, you can take any other course. I don't know how they do it, but they
are adding content constantly. They're fleshing out the OpenStack stuff and the AWS stuff
like crazy right now. This has never been a better time to go over there because they're
giving you the discount for the entire summer. So go over to linuxacademy.com. Take your
skill sets up just to the next level. Make yourself maybe a little more employable. Make
yourself look a little better on that next review or charge a little more on that next
contract. Get your skill set up. You know you have the ability. Get your skill set up
there. You know you can do it. And you can do it when you have time. Linuxacademy.com
slash how to to get a 33% discount and a really big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring
Linux Unplugged.
I've been using the service now since they were a sponsor in Coderadio, and it's really
great. They also have team courses available. So if you're in a group and you guys want
to work together, they have a system available for that too. It's really a neat service.
Linuxacademy.com slash how to. For a limited time you can get the Summer of Learning discount.
Okay, so Epic Games funded some Blender development, not just funded by a little bit. This actually
makes Epic the second major game developer to fund Blender development period. This is
a huge contribution to the Blender project. They're majorly excited about it. They're
technically I think now the number one sponsor in terms of dollar amount to the Blender project,
which is awesome. And other contributors include Valve. Valve backed Blender earlier this year.
I guess specifically there's some export stuff that the Epic team wants to see Blender work
on.
I don't know if anybody in the Mumbroom knows any more about this, but I think it's pretty
interesting to see as some of these big game companies begin to move over to Linux and
look at it as a viable market, they're kind of looking at some of this infrastructure
project stuff that's not necessarily a video driver, it's not necessarily how the kernel
handles a game pad, but it's still pretty important to the gaming ecosystem and they're
making some investments. They're not like, hey, let's just invent our own thing. We'll
come up with a way and we'll create the way you should all be doing it. They're actually
going to these existing, well-respected, open source projects that have been established
for years and not trying to roll them, but just trying to work with them and contribute
to them. And it's great to see now Epic jump on this too.
Not to mention that they don't just do games, they also do a lot of movies as well. I think
they did something with the Curious Case of Benjamin Button. I'm not exactly for sure
on that. But they do some awesome video graphics as well.
The Blender project, yes, very much so. They're kind of all about that, I know. It's really
awesome and so it's good to see. In fact, I don't even know if gaming is a really heavy
focus for Blender outside of the context of just a few things like that, other than character
models and stuff like that.
Now, if they can have that quality of graphics inside games at 60 frames per second, then
I would truly be in heaven.
Oh my gosh, the Blender gaming engine? Don't even make me dream, man. That's crazy. That's
crazy.
It'd be beautiful.
I talked about some audio issues I was having, I think it was last week on Linux Unplugged
when we were talking about KD sound issues, and I managed to get them fixed. Turned out
to be a config issue with the default fragment size buffer in PulseAudio. Changed the default
value, which was way high, down to a millisecond setting of five, and now my Civ 5, which had
choppy audio, plays flawlessly.
So if you've had choppy audio in Civ 5 or XCOM, Enemy Unknown, any of those games, I
got a link in the show notes where you guys can go check that out and see how I fixed
it.
Now, this is the story, I'm really glad Joss is here, because I have a hard time with understanding
the way the KD naming system works, and thankfully we now have an infographic that Aaron Saigo
posted recently that tells us how it works.
So here it is, ladies and gentlemen, KDE, the project, is happy to announce that they
have shipped the release candidate of Plasma 5.
Now this is the first release of Plasma 5, the next generation desktop, this is the last
chance for you guys to test and file for bugs and check any problems before the release,
which is scheduled next week.
So you have Plasma 5, the desktop component, then you have KDE Next, aka KDE 5, sort of
the architecture component.
Joss is there anything you want to jump in on here on this story, are you trying it out,
are there any insights here you can share with the group?
Do you have a link to that image, because I'm kind of curious about it, because especially
KDE Next is something I've never heard about, so that's kind of new to me, which is rather
odd.
Okay.
I mean, the idea behind the next thing that I do know is that the developers currently
refer to an upcoming Plasma release as Plasma Next, but that is always referring to the
upcoming Plasma release, so after Plasma 5.0 is out, Plasma 5.1 will be referred to as
Plasma Next, which is kind of a code name, eternal code name for the next release.
And so, for example, if I have this timing right, the 5.1 release is already scheduled
for October 15th, a Tuesday, if things all go according to plan, if things work out the
way the project wants them to.
Okay, I hadn't seen that date yet, but, and I actually thought it would be coming next
month, so today, yeah, it's Tuesday, isn't it?
So it's last night actually, last night we pushed out Framework 5, so KDE Framework 5,
that's basically taken, well, we took our old KDE libraries, the KDE Platform, the KD
Libs, however you want to call it, and basically, well, divided it into two parts.
One part we said, okay, this we're going to upstream to Qt, we brought it back into the
toolkit, contributed it to the Qt project, which now has an open governance, so we can
actually contribute and work at it.
And the other part, we basically cut the little pieces with clear dependencies, we worked
on it, making a proper closed platform, et cetera, et cetera, basically modularizing
it, and that's frameworks.
So we call it frameworks because there are multiple little pieces, each of them called
a framework, that you can use in your applications, and they're explicitly targeting Qt developers,
all Qt developers, and not just KDE developers, because this was the main complaint about
the old KDE, right, you install, you know, KDE, as it used to be in the 3.5 and even
in the 4 series, and then you get all this stuff, well, we solved that.
Framework 5 means you just get what your application needs, applications are smaller, leaner, more
efficient, and a lot of it even went in Qt, so the whole thing got smaller quite a bit
as well.
So this is really a major release, and this is what Plasma is going to build on, and the
idea was actually I think that Plasma initially would release this month, but because it was
meant to build on frameworks, and frameworks got delayed by a month, the Plasma guys also
had to delay by a month, and I think it'll come out next month, but that's a wild guess,
and maybe the October date is correct, but I thought we would go earlier than that, honestly.
And when, so the way this is going to work is really most people probably won't see this
ship in a distribution they're going to use until maybe 5.1 is actually out, right?
I'm kind of hoping for that, honestly, because as I wrote pretty clearly in I think the last
time we released something from Plasma, it's pretty good, even for a 5.0 release, it's
pretty good.
It's nothing compared to KDE 4.0, right, I mean absolutely nothing, that was the first
version of Plasma we did, and we were literally pushing technological boundaries everywhere,
we were pushing the graphics cards, I mean OpenGL support on Linux just sucked back then,
and we basically couldn't really properly do the stuff we tried to do.
We were pushing Qt, we were basically taking a new technology, the graphics view on which
Plasma was built, and we were taking it to places where it really wasn't meant to go.
But now all that stuff is basically ready, what we're trying to do is pretty much these
days what Qt is built for, right, and all the problems with Xorg and the OpenGL support
have been mostly fixed, I mean still everybody's looking forward to Wayland on the developer
side.
Sure, I bet.
But, you know, a lot of the rough edges are out.
In a matter of speaking, yes.
In a matter of speaking perhaps, but for normal, you know, for the Plasma guys, Wayland is
really something they look forward.
So the first release, on one hand, I mean it's a first release, okay, we've ported from
Qt 4 to Qt 5, we ported from Platform 4, as we used to call it, to Frameworks 5, which
is brand new in itself.
So yeah, you will definitely bump into some rough edges here and there, but at the same
time, we fixed a couple of really fundamental issues that were holding us back, and you
couldn't place, I mean a lot of people complain about the placement of things, you know, like
it didn't look really right, icons were just the wrong size, they weren't aligned properly,
that was all because we simply couldn't get that done in Qt, and now we can.
So you will notice on one hand rough edges, but you will also notice that we're finally
building on something that can actually support what we're building.
So it's the groundwork in the early days, so does that mean like, it sounds like what
you're trying to say very politely is, don't judge the looks in 5.0 and 5.1.
No, certainly not, I mean there's a lot of work still being done on, you know, there's
a lot that was done, but there's still a lot done in the area of polish and also the looks,
I mean there's work on the new theme, but honestly the implementation of the theme in
the first version, well to call it hackish, is still a compliment, I mean it's really
put together like, okay, this kind of looks like what we want, but the way it's done is
very suboptimal.
So certainly when it comes to looks, it shows a direction, right, flatter, cleaner, less
lines, less icons, less this and that, that's the direction, that's clear, but it's not
a final look, not by a long shot.
It sounds like you're pretty excited about it though.
I am.
It's maybe a direction you want to see things going for a while?
Well it's a direction, I think that's a big keyword here.
When we did KDE 4.0, I mean that's quite a while ago, 6 years ago, but I remember that,
I mean I worked a lot on the promo and in general, you know, on the whole, yeah, writing
about it and everything and the cool thing about it was there was a very clear direction,
we were going somewhere and it was awesome, right?
I mean we didn't know that our technology and the whole Linux platform simply wouldn't
be able to, well, carry us into this beautiful new world, so to say.
So we were all very excited because we were really breaking a lot of technology barriers
and I blogged about this a few times, you know, some of the things we did back then,
I mean when Plasma was designed, it was designed to basically converge different user interfaces
with one technology, right?
So you would be able to build, and we did by the way build prototypes of this, you would
be able to build a widget that would run on a mobile phone and on a tablet and on a desktop
and on a television screen and it would have the same underlying code, just a very thin
layer of UI work would be different.
Today you still see projects, companies trying to build one user interface for all these
devices, surprise, it doesn't work, and you see other companies building completely different
user interface for each device, while seven, eight years ago when we drafted this, we already
did it right.
Now, yeah, it didn't exactly work out that way and that's a little frustrating maybe,
but now we can actually do it because the knowledge is there.
So yeah, you bet, I am excited and a lot of us are excited about this.
Well I recommend that if folks out there want to know more, check out where Katie is going,
Joss just posted part two a couple days ago, so check that out.
Yeah, let me share actually simply a link to my blog, because I put a bunch of links
in there that probably are all, I'll put them on IRC, I have no idea how to share in-
Yeah, no, toss them in IRC, that's perfect, I'll grab it.
Let's see, yeah, so this has links to an overview of Framework 5, it has a link to an article
that I wrote for linux.com, why it is a big deal for free software, because I think it
is another thing we didn't get to, but I think Framework 5 is actually really a big deal,
because right now there are half a million Qt developers out there, and I mean people
developing software of Qt, and there are more people developing software of Qt than almost
the total number of users of openSUSE and Fedora combined.
And that's a lot of people developing software of that, and Frameworks basically brings them
all in contact with open source free software, open contributor process, open governance,
basically they can, if they want to, and have the skills and knowledge, at least if you're
a developer you do, to get involved with free software, and I think that's really a big
thing.
Well, it sounds like Frameworks is stepping in the direction to give the development community
a lot of confidence too, like, they're going to have maybe a little more, if they want,
involvement.
Yes, I mean, can you imagine if only 1% of those half a million developers decides to,
I don't know, fix a couple of bugs in Framework, or add a few features, I mean that will, that
will, I mean, come on, that's 5000 people, that's just crazy, if that would happen that
would just turn everything around, right, that would basically bring more than increase
the number of people doing gooey stuff on the Linux desktop, it will increase the number
from a few hundred in total to thousands, I mean that's the order of magnitude.
Joss, you've been around for a while, what do you think if you were to put, you know,
your forecasters hat on, how long until, you know, Frameworks 5 has been out, Plasma desktop
has been out for a while, how long until, like, it's at critical mass, and it's actually
making a palatable difference where people look back and go, oh wow, this has really
taken off.
How far out is that, do you think?
Honestly, I think there are two scenarios.
If this direction stays, stays strong, and I think you need to have a clear direction
as a project, and honestly, KD, in my opinion, has been missing that in the last couple of
years, but if it stays with a clear direction and gets people together and say, you know,
I mean, this doesn't look good, we need to fix it, and we're just going to fix it, and
not, you know, do something fancy somewhere else, right, because this is the thing that
you see a lot in free software, people love building big stuff, and you ask them, you
know, I'm quoting Frank Harlitek actually here, the guy who started on Cloud, he has
very interesting opinions on this, also been on the board of KD, you know, and he always
says, you know, a lot of free software developers work like this, if you ask them for a house,
they'll build you a skyscraper, take out the top and say, look, you know, here's a house,
right, and this is the thing you can't really do.
If you care about the goal and getting something done, you can't do this.
So this, in my opinion, is one of the things that needs to change.
It's changing a bit, but maybe not enough, maybe, I don't know.
If it does change, you know, by the way, no, in my opinion, has gotten this one done, right,
they have a very clear vision, and they're implementing it, and it doesn't fit, they
say no, they're a little extreme, in my opinion, in it, but, you know, if we can find a middle
ground, then I think in a couple of years, you will really see a big difference.
I mean, this can bring hundreds of people, maybe even an order of magnitude increase
in people contributing to the KD project.
We already started on that road, since we started with frameworks, since we started
with some changes in our government.
We recently did a manifesto, manifesto.kde.org, and since then, we had like seven, eight projects
join us, including GCompre, which is downright a known project that decided to join KDE for,
you know, bringing software to multiple platforms like Android.
So if that continues, that could really make a huge difference, but the other scenario
is, of course, the bad one, in which we lose direction, and then, well, I mean, KDE will
still be a cool project, and it'll still continue, but it'll be where it is today.
The Linux desktop will be where it is today, which is, unfortunately, pretty much irrelevant.
It's cool for the people who use it, but let's be honest, what do we have, 0.7%?
It's not enough to move the general needle.
Exactly.
We haven't, and, you know, to move the needle, we need to really change a couple of things,
and that's not just technology, that's also people, and on that side of things, I honestly
don't know.
As far as I'm concerned, this is a 50-50 thing.
How much of, this is a question that kind of came from Heaven's Revenge, how much of
a compatibility break is there between the version 4 of KDE frameworks and whatever it's
called there, and the new versions of all that stuff?
Will applications, say, designed for KDE 4 desktop work okay on the Plasma 5 desktop?
I'm pretty sure there will be some quirks there, honestly.
I think the best thing is if applications move, and I think the plan is to start moving
soon for the KDE applications.
They are now on the three-month release cycle, four months, actually, I'm not entirely sure,
but I'm pretty sure they will start moving well before the end of the year.
A couple of them have been ported already, and it's actually going pretty quick.
I know that an initial port of Dolphin, the file manager, which is a pretty complex application
when you think about it, was done by someone not too familiar with the code in, I don't
know, a few weeks.
Okay.
And there was, yeah.
Yeah.
So it's not too bad?
No, no, no.
We have scripts that actually really do 99% of the work.
So I think we will be able to, basically, you will be able to run a full Framework 5
based desktop, you know, with Plasma and the KDE applications all on Qt 5, you know, probably
summer or the end of the year, next year.
I mean, some parts will take a little longer.
I know there are people about KDPim.
They don't expect to move that quick, but honestly, if I see how many people have been
joining development there in the last couple of months, I actually think there might be
a little too negative about their roadmap, but we will see.
Things might improve.
Well, Joss, it's great having you join us.
You're welcome to join us anytime and stick around for the whole show and chime in on
any topic we get to.
We're actually going to do a review of Chaos, K-A-O-S, here in a little bit, which is a
very heavily designed KDE distribution.
They've really taken a heavy hand to customizing it and making it a very unique experience.
So we're going to talk about that here in just a second.
Before we move to that, I want to thank our next sponsor of the Linux Unplugged podcast,
and that is DigitalOcean.
Go over to digitalocean.com.
Guess what?
Brand new promo code!
That's right, it's Unplugged July.
And when you use the promo code Unplugged July, you're going to get a $10 credit over
at DigitalOcean.
So what is DigitalOcean?
My friend, I am glad you asked, because you need to know.
Did you know you can have a Linux server up in the cloud that you have root access to
in just about 55 seconds?
That's right.
DigitalOcean plans to start only $5 per month for 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD,
one blazing fast CPU, and a terabyte of transfer connected to tier one data centers and tier
one bandwidth all over the world.
In fact, DigitalOcean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, and
Amsterdam.
Their interface is simple.
Their control panel is very intuitive and power users can replicate the control panel
on a much wider scale using their straightforward API.
And I think I've mentioned it before probably on the Unplugged show, but one of the things
I love the most, one of the things I love the most about DigitalOcean is this amazing
dashboard.
They have managed to somehow take the complexity of KVM and server provisioning and really
global data center management, DNS management, backup management, application deployment,
Docker image management, all of that, and wrapped it in an interface where you can spin
up a brand new server in less than 55 seconds.
They also have hourly pricing plans.
If you use our promo code, Unplugged July, that $10 credit will get you quite a distance
on their hourly pricing plans.
And one of the things that really stands out about DigitalOcean is they made an early investment
in SSDs.
They saw how this was going and they realized if we could take the flexibility that using
Linux and KVM gives us, match that up with incredibly performant disk IO, then that increases
our density so we can host way more systems, the users get more performance out of their
box because the CPUs aren't sitting around waiting for the disk IO, you don't have to
have these massive expensive rate arrays of spinning disks, SSDs deliver the performance
of an entire array, and if we could somehow wrap it all up in a very straightforward package
that's so easy, even if you're not a server administrator, you have no problem, you can
provision in 55 seconds, you get amazing hardware without even having to think about it.
They took all of that, all out there, brought it together, wrapped it up so intelligently,
so well done with real vision and purpose, and now DigitalOcean is blowing up.
Users love DigitalOcean, Linux enthusiasts love DigitalOcean, but do they have a special
promo code?
Don't think so.
Unplug July to get a $10 credit, check it out, some of the DigitalOcean locations also
have private networking, which is great for a web backend, maybe you want to have some
front-end web servers access a backend database server, and by the way, that private networking
doesn't count against your bandwidth, and it's all just a fixed cost, $5 pricing plans
go up from there, make a lot of sense, and you know exactly what you're going to get.
Go over to DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code unplug July when you check out to get
that $10 credit and see what I've been talking about.
DigitalOcean truly rocks, you guys will be really impressed what they can do.
DigitalOcean.com, and a really big thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux
Unplugged podcast, that's right, that's right, unplug July, crack it open.
Okay, so let's talk about chaos, K-A-O-S, K-A-O-S, I know we had a group of you in here
that did the review, I'm really looking forward to see what you guys said about it, Rotten
Corpse, do you want to kick it off and kind of introduce it, or do you want me to introduce
what the distro is?
I could do that too if you want.
Well, I can go ahead and give a quick introduction.
Chaos is an arch-based distro that is based solely around KDE, I might be mistaken but
I'm pretty sure they have a very strict requirement about the packages as in if it's not KDE compatible
it's not allowed in their repo.
It's not installed by default, I think it's allowed in their repo because I know they
have Chrome and a few other things in their repo.
Chrome is self-contained so I think it's more in the sense that they don't completely restrict
your ability to use it, but they don't promote the use of it.
They mention on their site in their repo they have Firefox 30, Chrome 37, Thunderbird 24,
and Adore 3.5, but that's about it.
It's arch-based but it's not like a derivative arch, it's kind of like its own thing.
They call themselves a tightly integrated rolling transparent distribution for the modern
desktop built from scratch with a specific focus, KDE and QT.
They also even come out and say their target audience is desktop and operating system enthusiasts.
Those desktop-aholics we were talking about last week, they don't consider this to be
a new user distribution necessarily.
They want it to be more of an enthusiast distribution.
The latest version in June, they just came out at the beginning of June, includes the
non-free NVIDIA driver, KDE 4.13.2, Linux kernel 3.14.6, and I think there's also an
update to 3.15 already, GLib of course, SystemD of course, Xorg Server 1.15.1, KWebKit 2.33,
QT530, you know, the good stuff, all your regular stuff, it's a modern up-to-date just
as of June distribution.
Rotten, where do you want to start?
Well, I kind of want to start with Popeye.
You want to start with Popeye?
Alright, that's kind of what I was thinking too, because I know Popeye kind of laid down
a few hints last week.
Oh, but before we get to that, Wimpy, you want to touch on the philosophy, I'll give
you a chance, go ahead.
Well, yeah, I've run it, I'm happy to chip in later, I was just going to say I really
like that it's super-focused, they've got a very clear vision on this, one desktop,
one architecture, and they're being laser-focused in that regard, and I also like very much
that it's an Arch derivative, so in terms of the philosophy and what I read about it,
I was suitably impressed.
Now is it an Arch derivative, or is it just using Pac-Man?
Well, no, it's their own version of Arch, so whilst it shares a lot of the core architecture
of Arch Linux, it is not in any way related to Arch Linux, they've taken the tools and
the packaging tools from Arch and they've made their own distribution around it.
Right, okay, so Popeye, let's start with you.
What was your impression of this distribution, where would you like to start on your journey
with Chaos?
So, I first of all tried it in a VM, and then I stuck it on a USB stick and installed it
on real hardware.
I used an Intel-based Toshiba laptop that's about five years old, it's Core 2 Duo with
three gig of RAM, and it also has a touch screen, but I didn't really test that part
of it.
I did the install, and when you say it's aimed at desktop enthusiasts, I'm taking that to
mean geeks, like, you know, I definitely would not give this to my mum, and I probably wouldn't
give it to any new-ish user, it really is quite technical, so some of the things I noticed
like for the install, for example, you mentioned the Nvidia non-free driver, like when you
first boot up, the first option is to boot into the installer, and the second option
just says Nvidia non-free, with no explanation of what that's all about.
At one point when I was booting, I got dropped to like a boot colon blank screen prompt,
as if it couldn't find the Linux kernel, which I thought was a bit offensive.
I then got smacked in the face with a box after the install was done, I mean I did do
the install, and it worked, but it's really but ugly, their installer, and I didn't enjoy
that process at all.
All the bits and pieces on the screen didn't line up right, and it felt over-complicated
and too busy and typical KDE.
There was a box that popped up after I installed that said, welcome to chaos, and then it said,
in need of the password file or package list, and then there was like six buttons on the
screen.
Actually, why smacked me in the face with that, it just seemed a bit weird.
And the package list, interestingly enough, is just a PDF, oh I'm sorry, it's just a text
file, it's a text file of just the install packages.
I'm sure to some technical users that might be useful, but that's not something I want
when I've just installed, I don't know.
And then I get onto the usual KDE annoyances, I don't know if these are KDE specific or
plasma specific, but this is what chaos did, most of the icons had no tooltip, so I had
no idea what they were.
And bear in mind, I hadn't used KDE for like five years, and none of the icons were obvious
what they were.
I couldn't see an icon that looked like a web browser, I had to find something called
Quapzilla, which I had never heard of, loads of weird dialogues, applications that when
I opened them they did nothing, or they popped up multiple dialogues over the top of everything
else and I just found it quite frustrating.
Once I got past that, and if I accept that as okay, I could then install some applications
and that was okay, but I found it slightly frustrating.
But once it was up, you know, suspend and restore works, update works, I can install
applications and it seemed okay.
What was your impression of the look?
So they've spent a lot of time working on this theme, it's one of the most unique looks
of KDE, like they have this special menu that is very heavily designed, did it work for
you?
Did it not?
No, I think it's disgusting, I absolutely don't like it at all.
But then I don't really like KDE, so there you go, it's gonna have a hard time pleasing
me.
Heaven's Revenge, did you have a chance to kick the tires?
What did you think?
Well, yes, I had enough chance to kick the tires and then I broke it yesterday and I'm
still actually trying to fix it.
How did it break?
What happened?
Oh, give me the story.
Walk me through.
Well, something is wrong with Pac-Man, even though I am an Arch kind of guy, I love Arch,
but it's going down the same road as Chakra, as in it does, it has forked and it is its
own project, so it is not just a customization of Arch, it is a fork.
I completely took away that custom bar at the bottom, I put the normal kicker or the
normal Lancelot menu back.
I kind of had to get used to Octopi, considering it's kind of weird.
But their Pac-Man, the Pac-Man package manager, it has a very interesting progress bar.
It's like a Pac-Man eating little dots as it goes across the screen.
Which is a setting, I have that on my Arch box too, it's fun.
I've never seen it before, but I've seen that in this, and it seems quite custom.
The file system structure is all just pretty much like Arch, they didn't change too much
of that.
I've missed too much of the AUR, I cannot access the AUR, even though they say it accesses
the CCR, but that's, no, screw it.
I also had a friend, which is a, well, going to be a, well, he's dabbling in Linux, so
I gave him a choice of three or four different Linux distributions by putting a few virtual
machines up and saying, here, do any of these catch your eye?
The thing is, is that with Chaos, since it is a custom distro, all the packages are custom
built for the actual distribution.
That means there is no wine, there is no Windows emulation layer, and there's no Steam, at
least in the repos.
If anything, you have to go and get it manually.
So he needed wine, he wanted to play N64 emulators that isn't available on the, so that was a
showstopper for him.
I found the package, or the Pac-Man log viewer to be quite interesting, because I've never
used Octopi before, because I'm not much of a Mangero fan, but you can kind of get used
to the package manager.
It is very user-friendly, but the distribution is not aimed at new users, it's aimed at people
who can break their system, and like me, is attempting to fix it again.
Right, right, that is true, it is kind of an odd mismatch.
And Riley had a question, I think probably for the group, about 32-bit.
Go ahead Riley.
Yeah, according to the website, they don't believe in 32-bit applications, like they
were saying, in this modern-day age of computers, they refuse to have 32-bit applications on
their system.
So that pretty much means that Steam will not be supported ever at all, and gaming is
pretty much out of the question.
They feel that to make the perfect desktop, they have to target a specific platform, the
way they phrase it.
Is they have to take it right?
And that's kind of like, we're not doing 32-bit because we only want to think about 64-bit,
was that kind of the reasoning?
Yeah, that's what it sounded like to me when I read the website.
It's unfortunate because I do believe in 64-bit, but our 32-bit past has still not completely
left us.
Hmm, I agree, I agree, Wimpy, I think I'm in sync with you.
They call the distribution chaos, but what they're really striving for is sort of absolute
control and not, maybe not necessarily control, but absolute, it's exactly what they want
it to be, it's exactly what they want to present.
Do you pick that up too, Wimpy?
Well, yeah, my point is that the tagline is a lean KDE distribution, which is an oxymoron
since it juxtaposes lean and KDE, and those two things are contradictory.
And my experiences with it were, when I first installed it, I installed it on some hardware
that only had 768 meg of RAM, and the installer spits out a warning to tell you that the installer
requires one and a half gig of RAM to run, and you can proceed if you like, but you need
to be fair warned that you need one and a half gig to install it.
So that was my first, like, hmm, really lean, I need one and a half gig of RAM, so.
Yeah, that's not so lean, I suppose.
No, so anyway, I got over that one, I went to a machine with more memory and got through
the installer.
What was your impression of the installer?
I've noticed the disk part, the disk partitioner is pretty interesting, right?
The way it really works is, you launch off, you hit the advanced button.
If you have a drive that has no partitions, you immediately have to go to the advanced
button, and then from there, it launches K Partition Manager, and then you partition
out the drive the way you want.
Then you go back into the installer, and then once you're in the installer, you have to
flag these partitions where you want them to be mount point wise using a different application,
and flag them again to be formatted.
Did you guys find that to be wonky?
I didn't have that.
Yeah, I did, because I was installing on a... I DD'd zeros to the disk before I started,
and that's exactly what I had.
I was a little bit... Well, to me, it wasn't obvious what I needed to do.
There was no disk that I could select, and I clicked the advanced button, and then I
was presented with KDE Partition Manager, and there's this whole disjointed partition
thing.
I may as well have just been using Fdisk at that point.
You really could.
You really could just use Fdisk and then go back in here.
So yeah, if you have a blank drive with no partition table, you get hit with this where
you have to go into a separate partitioning program.
Not a huge deal, but it's... It does partitioning on itself, but there's
a button that I can't remember where it is, but that installer does do partitioning.
I partitioned my drive in the installer, which was terrible.
All those buttons were grayed out for me.
If I've got a disk with no partition... Like not even a table written.
Yeah, exactly.
You had to initialize.
Yeah, you had to initialize.
You had to do it mandronically.
The other thing I noticed about the installer was the... Well, as Papi said, it's very
cluttered, but also the time zone selector is a massive on it.
My notes say here is this why it requires one and a half gig of RAM.
For those of you that haven't installed it, you get like a Google Earth view of the world.
I think it's marble embedded, right?
It's the KDE Marble.
Yeah.
Rubbish.
It's massively over-engineered for choosing a time zone.
Yeah.
They should have spent more time on the disk partitioner.
It's kind of hard to manage, too, and depending on your machine, it can be pretty clunky.
Now I think they get the benefit of it just being able to embed that because it's part
of the whole KDE desktop, and then they just take the coordinates that you click.
Once you get through the disk partitioner, you select that stuff there, you set your
swap up... After that, the installer's pretty much done, right?
Then it just writes it to disk, and you're off to the races.
Yeah, but the installer in itself is a bit strange because it doesn't install in a traditional
sense.
It copies the contents of the ISO image to the hard disk, and then installs a bootloader.
Right, yeah, so essentially exactly what you get in the live environment is what you get
on the installed machine, which feels a little cluttered, perhaps?
Not so much cluttered, but it doesn't feel right.
Yeah, it doesn't feel quite like an installation.
One area where Integros sort of shines here, again coming from the Arch roots, is you could
have a three-month-old ISO of Integros, but when you install it, it is pulling down the
absolute latest KDE or GNOME.
It is pulling down the absolute latest kernel, and so it is super fresh packages that are
being written to the disk.
If you call yourself a rolling release, that would be nice, but that can mean different
things.
And I'm not trying to be critical of the way Kaos does it, because I also, on the one hand,
really like the idea of somebody taking, kind of like Joss was talking about, a direction
with a KDE desktop and saying, this is our look.
I kind of applaud them for saying, we're only going to support 64-bit.
That eliminates a huge portion of the market, but they're okay with that.
They're obviously aware of that, and they've made that choice, and in some ways, I think
we need to see more KDE desktops where the people that are implementing it stop saying,
we can do everything, and start saying, we're only going to do these things.
And I think it's going to take years of doing that to make it really awesome.
Isn't that kind of a contradiction to the KDE project though?
Because they always want to do everything, which is a double-edged sword, it's great,
and also a negative.
Yeah, very true.
Once it was installed, I found there were some odd, strange applications that didn't
seem...
It seemed like if they were going for real polish, they've chosen some odd things to
throw in there, like apps that A, don't work, or do weird things, or pop up strange dialogues.
It seemed like that once they got the installer done, it was a bunch of applications thrown
in as well, just because they could.
Do you think that's a QT bias, where we only want to feature QT applications?
My install failed.
Bummer.
Darn it.
Well, that's no good.
Well, there you go.
I don't know, that could be for a number of reasons, who knows why that died, but there
you go.
Man, this is chaos.
The introduction or the inclusion of Kabzilla is okay.
It's a very unusual browser, but it's still WebKit based, so it's good.
And the one weird one is the appear.in website, which is a WebRTC Skype replacement bookmark
that is in the-
Oh, okay.
Yeah, I see that.
That's what that is.
Okay.
I see how they did it.
I see what they did there.
And then this, there we go.
Yeah, this launch is Quapzilla, Poppy's favorite browser of choice.
Oops.
Well, I did manage to find Chrome in their-
Repo.
In their package manager.
Once I figured out how to actually launch it, as I bitched and moaned about last week,
using their menu, just searching for the word update or upgrade, couldn't find the update
manager or whatever package management tool.
It was under add, remove programs, which seemed a bit bizarre to me.
This is the only Linux distribution on which I was able to actually look at every single
package and read every single one, except from the PBI listing of the PCBSD when it
first started making PBIs.
That's when there were so little amount of them there.
Because they have such a limited amount that one human can actually read through the whole
list in a reasonable amount of time.
I read all of the, yes, all of the packages and the repos.
Okay.
That's an interesting benchmark.
I like that.
I've never thought of that as a metric.
But, boy, interesting.
So it doesn't sound like anybody's necessarily coming out with a recommendation.
Anybody-
Well, I would say if you like KDE and you want a pure KDE desktop, then this might be
an option.
And if you're willing to forego the 32-bit stuff, you're missing Steam, Skype, Wine.
Some of the three annoyingly proprietary things that lots of people want, then, yeah, it's
okay.
It works.
And Flash, right?
No Flash.
Oh, who needs Flash?
Steve Jobs told us years ago we don't need that.
That's true.
We don't need that.
We don't need that Flash.
Yeah.
Actually, to me, all of those requirements are completely irrelevant to me.
So chaos is a potential option.
And Wimpy, you wanted to say not lean.
Yeah.
So some months ago, I did, I've mentioned this before, some resource consumption benchmarks
for Linux desktop environments.
And they were all conducted on Arch Linux.
And I've got some scripts that automate those tests.
So I thought, right, here we go.
Let's see how it's up to its lean statements.
So chaos, when I run my scripts, which is bring the system up, wait for all of this
auto-started applications to execute and wait for disk.io to settle, and then use PS mem
to gather the memory usage.
Very nice.
So chaos weighs in at 319 meg after first boot with no applications being launched, which
is okay.
But a full KDE 4.13.1 on stock Arch under the same conditions weighs in at 302 meg.
So only 17 meg, but leaner.
So it kind of raises the question, if the tagline is it's a lean KDE, but it's not as
lean as the parent OS, they're kind of missing the target on that one.
Well, Wimpy, I would say that it is quite lean in terms of CPU usage, as it is just
as, it is equally as efficient in CPU as Antardos is under GNOME or running GNOME.
The GNOME desktop, it's a little bit like 100 megs more when it comes to RAM consumption,
but the CPU usage, it's actually quite good.
I was surprised.
It's been pretty robust for me as well.
Mine's got an uptime of seven days on my laptop, and I've been updating it regularly and trying
out various applications.
So despite all the gripes and bitches and moans that I've said that I don't like KDE,
it's stable.
If nothing else, it works and the apps that do work, work fairly well.
Very good, and if you want to see sort of an inspired KDE design, it's worth checking
out from that standpoint, at least in maybe a VirtualBox instance.
Also for me, I've tried it before, it never really manages to quite grab me.
I look at it and go, oh, yeah, I do see what they're trying to go for.
Good for them.
And then I kind of go about my day, and I just use a more general purpose distribution.
But I respect it.
You can check it out at kaossx.us.
Yeah, go ahead, Evan.
Oh, well, I would say that it would be a good recommendation for anyone who is wanting to
learn the Pac-Man package manager, but doesn't want the complete, I'm going to go balls deep
in arch and get way over my head.
If you can run Antigros, then sure, that's okay.
Chaos is also another good alternative in order to just learn the Pac-Man package manager.
Yeah, or Manjaro, or Chakra, or Pentagross.
I had my Chakra days back when it was first created, and when it was first starting to
fork.
That's why when it went on that path of forking away from arch, I now stay clear of any distribution
that wants to fork from its parent.
Yeah, that's kind of, I mean, yeah, boy, that's a whole, all right, we'll save that for, I
think actually I want to do a future episode on that topic.
I got a couple of bits of business, and we can do some more closing thoughts on the review,
so Mumble Room, compose your thoughts for a second.
We have a couple of announcements, too, that I want to cover real quick, but first, I want
to thank the folks at Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged, linux.ting.com, that'll take
$25 off your first device, linux.ting.com.
Go own it!
I mean, why not?
They put Linux in the URL just for you guys.
Now what is Ting?
Ting is mobile that makes sense.
$6 a month, that's all you pay, and then it's just your usage.
Ting takes your megabytes, your minutes, your messages, adds them all up at the end of the
month, whatever bucket you fall into, that's what you pay.
Plus, no contract, thus, no early termination fee.
What?
I know.
It's actually how mobile should work.
Don't pay into some big old contract where they're trying to get a little off the top
from you every single month, just pay for what you use.
And every Ting plan includes all of the things you'd want, you got your built-in hotspot
and tethering, you just turn it on in the operating system and just pay for the usage.
You don't have to be in a family share plan, I think is what my last telco called it, you
don't have to be in a specific kind of plan to use the tethering feature that the vendor
built into the operating system.
You just turn it on and use it because you own the device.
In fact, Ting's perfectly happy if you just want to use them as a mobile ISP or make phone
calls all day long.
And of course, you can have multiple devices, it's just $6 per device.
Fact, too, is if you have multiple devices, it's a great way to save money.
It's a fantastic way because each device is only paying for your usage.
So your heavy talkers just pay for their talk, but the folks like myself who don't use a
lot of actual phone minutes, you don't end up paying for those people.
It works so well, we have a couple of phones here for the Jupiter Broadcasting crew, and
it's fantastic.
It's a perfect fit for us, and there's no way any other value would work for us.
It's perfect for us, but I think what really, at the end of the day, matters is it's super
easy for us to manage and keep track of exactly where we're at.
Ting Matches, they're an awesome online dashboard that gives you a clear indication of where
your bill is.
You can turn services on and off, deactivate, activate phones.
I've bought several phones from Ting all through the dashboard, all activated, deactivated
phones through them.
I can set up a call forwarding my voicemail options, and if I ever get stuck, Ting has
no hold customer support at 1-855-TING-FTW, anytime between 8 PM and 8 AM, and a real person
answers the phone.
They've also got help.ting.com and an awesome blog where they're posting stuff all the time
to get you updated on what the Ting crew is up to, apps you might want to check out, ways
to save money, all kinds of things, events, giveaways, they all have that at the Ting
blog.
Start by going to linux.ting.com, see what I'm talking about, get that $25 credit.
That paid for more than my first month.
That gives you an idea of the kind of value you can get, and check out that savings calculator.
Go to linux.ting.com, click what would you save, put your current bill in there, and
here's a tip.
Put what you're actually using right now, so the actual data, minutes, and text that
you're sending, and look at the difference.
For me, it's like $2,000 every two years.
It's a new laptop every two years just by switching to Ting, linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com,
and a really big thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Love it.
My mobile phone provider for well over a year now, Matt's too.
So coming up in just a few short weeks, I wanted to mention too, we're going to do another
community review.
So if you'd like to be involved with that, go over to the show notes.
We have a form you can fill out.
If you want to be drafted to do one of our community reviews, we'd love to hear from
you.
Go to the show notes for Linux Unplugged, scroll down towards the bottom.
You'll see the Jupiter Colony review draft, and just fill that out there, and we'll be
calling on more of you guys.
And Mumbroom, if you guys have more thoughts on Chaos, save it for the post show.
We'll get to that in just a little bit.
I wanted to just mention before we run too that I'm planning to go to OSCON in two weeks.
I'll probably be there July 22nd to the 23rd if all scheduling goes as planned.
OSCON 2014 runs from July 20th to the 24th, 2014 in Portland, Oregon.
And I'm going to be there if we're right dab, boom, in the middle of it if all of our timing
works out.
And I'd like to know if you're going to be there too.
We could do a little meetup, maybe have some beers, eat some burgers, high five, fist bump,
whatever you'd like to do.
Talk about Linux.
Just make sure you call it GNU slash Linux when you are talking to me in person.
I don't care about it on the internet, but if you're talking to me in person, you better
have GNU slash in that name.
OSCON coming up in two weeks, I'll be there July 22nd and 23rd if all goes as planned.
I think the 23rd?
It's all kind of up in the air, but I might finalize some of my plans depending on what
I hear from you guys.
So leave us a comment in the feedback thread if you're going to be there.
And then last but not least, a little piece of business from the community.
I'd love to get your own runs Linux again.
I've made a call out for these from time to time.
I haven't made one in a while.
I'd really like to get your runs Linux.
Now I'd like to have a picture, and even better, a video if possible.
I know that's asking a lot, but we feature right at the beginning of the Linux action
show every single week, so I'd like to give it a splash.
Make it nice.
Make it entertaining for the folks.
And I'd love to get communities runs Linux.
Could be your desktop.
Could be something a little more inventive than that.
Whatever it is, here's how you do it.
Take a picture, record a video if possible, and write up a brief description, and then
send it into the show.
You can go to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash contact, or if it's awesome, just submit it
right to the Linux action show subreddit, and the community will vote it up so we can
see that.
If you do a video, which I would really, really, really love.
If you do a video of your runs Linux, upload it to YouTube and just give us the link.
Now you don't have to send us a big video file.
And that makes it a lot easier to submit to the subreddit as well because it previews
the thumbnail and all that kind of stuff.
So I'd love to get your runs Linux.
We're going to do runs Linux from the people if I can get enough of these.
I'd like to get your guys' contributions and see what you're doing with your Linux.
It's not a Fosho award show quite, but it's still kind of fun.
And last but not least, go check out Tech Talk today over at jupyterbroadcasting.com,
our brand new technology talk show Monday through Thursday.
How crazy is that?
And you can also show up live for that as well and hang out with us.
We love that.
Man, that's a lot of stuff.
So we'd love to hear from you.
Let us know what you think about those things, and join us next week.
We do Linux Unplugged every single freaking Tuesday over at jupyterbroadcasting.com, 2
PM Pacific over at jblive.tv, jblive.info.
And of course, you can email us.
Just go over to jupyterbroadcasting.com, click that contact link, or join us in the feedback
thread or on the subreddit.
We'd like to get it there too.
And don't forget about the review draft and OSCON.
A lot of stuff I've asked from you guys.
It's a busy week for you.
I hope you're prepared for all that homework.
I think you can do it.
I trust you.
We're coming up to episode 50 soon.
So stay tuned.
There might be a few surprises in the works, maybe even starting this week.
You never know.
All right, everyone.
Well, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Be sure you join us next Tuesday.
And if we don't see you on Tuesday, we'll see you on Sunday for the Linux Action Show.
We've got a big show coming up.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Mumble Room, thanks, you guys.
Great review.
Any closing thoughts on the chaos now that we're in the post-show?
It sounds like chaos was chaos to install.
Yeah.
Yeah, I was about to say, when he said it was oxymoron, I was like, it's actually kind
of an apt, a great way to say that it's a little chaotic.
So yeah, well, they're working on something, but it's just like with a small team and stuff.
It's going to take a long time to get there.
I heard it's like KDU project always in flux and then chaos.
Wow.
I think it's wasted effort.
I'm not going to do it, dude.
I'm not going to do it.
You can't get me.
I think it's wasted effort.
God dang it.
Yeah.
Sounds like the review went well.
I expected Popey to bring out the knives a little more and start stabbing, but he kept
it dialed in.
Well, I did that last week and I got beaten up on the subreddit.
You're a car-e-fueling.
Yeah, you're right.
I just don't see the point when you don't include or allow 32-bit applications.
That does not make any sense whatsoever for a user.
It's because 32-bit sucks.
Screw that.
I actually like 64.
I don't want to do 32-bit.
Give me fucking 256.
The bigger the better, baby.
Give me a frigging Fi.
A frigging Fi co-processor or some shit.
All right, Eric.
How are you doing?
Did you survive?
What happened to you last night?
So my appendix decided it wanted to say, F you, bye-bye.
Oh, heck.
Are you okay?
Yeah.
Well, I just got home from the hospital.
They removed my appendix laparoscopically.
Right now I'm actually doing okay and a little pain from the incision, but otherwise I'm
fine.
Did they give you any good drugs?
Dude, I got hydros.
That'll do.
Okay.
So is anybody going to keep running chaos after today?
No.
I will not.
Do we have...
Do we already have some...
Oh, go ahead.
My biggest problem with it was it is super focused and very geared towards a specific
set of applications, which is good on the one hand, but on the other hand, it means
that there's fewer packages available in the repositories compared to Arch.
And that even includes some really useful command line shell utilities that you would
just install because it's just part of your standard tool bag.
And it was really frustrating to say, right, now I've got to go and find the source code
for this because the AUR doesn't work properly.
And then you find yourself looking at it and you're thinking, well, Anturgus' installer
is far superior.
They have KDE as an option.
And then you've got the entire Arch package repository at your disposal after the fact.
So why wouldn't you just go to Anturgus and tweak the theming?
Or if you don't want to use Arch, just use Chakra, or there's another one called Freeble
ware, too, that's been around for quite a while.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Yeah.
Frugalwares.
That's not so great either.
Have you read that recently?
How do you use Frugalware and Forever?
They've been around for quite a while.
So do we already have an idea kicking around for the next distro we're going to do a community
review of?
I'm loving it.
I think we should do another one.
What about Calculate?
Well, it hasn't been officially decided on, no.
Okay.
We've got a couple ideas, though.
Yeah, we have some ideas.
Okay.
We're going to announce it soon, so people can get on board.
Can I toss an idea into the hat?
I've never run this distro, but I heard some friends review it a couple of months back.
I think it's Semplice or Simplice.
Simplice, yeah.
Simplice Linux.
Yeah.
They really raved about it.
So if you want to pick one that might actually get some positive feedback, it might be worth
tossing that in the hat.
I actually do like Simplice.
Linux BBQ is another idea.
I like that one.
That's almost one I want to do.
Yeah.
We're going to need like six months to review that one, though.
Because we've got like 80 window managers and desktops.
That's true.
All right.
Well, I mean, Linux BBQ is actually kind of easy, because it's more designed to be like
a distro to be played with, not necessarily actually be used.
So they don't even want you to install it ever.
So it could be easier in that sense.
It definitely fills a need, though, because some of those tiling window managers I've
never used, and I'm thinking, yeah, you know, one weekend I'm just going to fire that up
and have a good old play.
But they don't do anything to them, so it's just the default setup, so that's what I want
to do.
Yeah.
That's the benefit.
That's what you want.
If you're going to learn these things, you need to start with a blank canvas and then,
you know, figure out how they're put together and what you can do with them.
All right.
So Chaos Theory is our current leading title.
You guys like Chaos Theory?
I like that.
That is perfect.
Okay.
All right.
Yeah.
Okay.
Very good.
Well, that was fun.
It's interesting, too, to hear your guys' thoughts on it, because I tried out Chaos
before.
I made it a spotlight one time or something like that on last, and so I went through the
installer once before and kicked the tires for a couple of hours, and I remember thinking
a lot of the things that you guys thought, so it's interesting to, I don't know, validating
is the right word, but it's like, okay, yeah, that thing that bugged me also bugged three,
four other people.
So it's like, I'm not totally OCD.
Maybe it gives you like a disconnect so it's not you bashing it as well.
Yeah.
I'll play good cop.
Sure.
Chaos hasn't been around for that long, though, has it?
The only one that's been around for a couple months.
No, no, because-
Back in the last year, I think, wasn't it?
Yeah.
I think I covered them almost six months ago or more.
I can't remember.
But we didn't do a full review, so.
Oh, gosh.
I thought it was newer than that.
It moves so fast.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, all you jerks go back to watching your sports ball.