This is Linux Unplugged Episode 7 for September 24th, 2013.
Hi everyone and welcome to Linux Unplugged, the weekly Linux podcast that keeps checking
the source of the Steam countdown page, hoping for hidden messages from Gabe. My name is
Chris. My name is Matt. Hey there, Matt. Welcome to Episode 7, buddy. Thanks. Fresh off of
the birthday weekend, too. Nice, man. Oh, I know. It's been great. It's just been one
big whirlwind of acting like a complete nutjob. It's been awesome. You know what? I'm acting
like a nutjob tonight. I'm going carb crazy. Right on. I'm going to gluten it up, man.
So right now, I'm drinking a gluten-free hard apple cider. I got to keep the gluten down
because tonight we're going with a pasta with an Alfredo sauce. If I'm rekt for tomorrow's
on filter, you know why. I got crazy. And I got to hook you up with some of the gluten-free
recipes we got. My wife's got this entire monster cookbook for people that really like
to eat. Okay, good. It's none of the sissy stuff. It's like food. We'll have to share.
We'll trade notes. Yeah, totally. Now, you know, coming up on this week's episode, we're
going to, of course, be talking about SteamOS, which was just announced by Valve yesterday.
We're in the calm between the storms. Tomorrow, another announcement comes. We'll be doing
some speculation on what those announcements could be. But today, I thought we'd kind of
take a snapshot of where we're at with the announcement of SteamOS. We'll do a little
speculation, but really, we're going to talk about what this could mean for Linux. We're
going to talk about what this means for gaming and really what this means for an open platform
in general. I think we're going to have a great episode. Plus, we're going to bring
in our mumble guys who are always thinking about this stuff, always debating, a good
round table in there. Great opinions and whatnot. I think it's going to be a really fun episode,
Matt. I know it is. And plus, then after this, I'm going to go gluten crazy. Now, you know.
All right. Well, so why don't we start with a little follow-up, as is per tradition, before
we get into the main show. I wanted to read an email that came in from Jacob. Now, Jacob
was referring to last week. We got kind of on the whole Android discussion and we called
it the Android problem, if you recall, Matt. I remember. Well, Jacob thought it was an
amazingly eye-opening episode and another way to look at Google. He says, one thing
to note, on iOS 7 Google Chrome now, he says, maybe this has already been implemented on
Android, there is a feature they ask if you want to turn on, which sends all of your internet
traffic to some Google services for them to then compress it and send along to your phone.
In light of recent events, i.e. Snowden, it would seem that they aren't just compressing
all that data. Just something to think about. Great show, by the way. I just subscribed
to the All Shows feed. Constantly refreshing, waiting for the next show to come out. So
yeah, I'm of a mixed opinion. So I talked about this a little bit yesterday on Code
Radio, Matt, but here's kind of where I'm at. I think you're going to appreciate the
zen-ness of my sort of final position here. So one of the things that kind of got me all
riled up was lack of updates, right? Google's bad original deals that sort of torpedoed
the future update possibilities of a platform, and you know, the way that some of the carriers
can go crazy. But thankfully, there's alternative carriers now that kind of solve some of that
problem. Where I'm at with Google now, it's like, I just kind of like treat Google like
I treat my Twitter stream. Not my out replies, but just the front page of Twitter. Like,
I just jump in, I just see what people are talking about, and then I jump out. I'm not
one of those people that needs to read the whole Twitter feed, right? Yeah, I'm kind
of the same way. I mean, like with Twitter, I literally use it as my email forward. I
pay very little attention about what's going on there. But I really do. I mean, I pay some
attention to Facebook, I pay most of my attention to Google+, Twitter, not so much. Which is
ironic being it's Google. I try to read all my replies on Twitter. Yeah, I generally do.
Direct messages, I don't pay any attention. Well, they're harder to find these days. So
that's how I'm going to treat Android. When an Android release comes out, and if it meets
the conditions of a platform that I want, I'll make a precision strike. I'll grab that
device, going in knowing that, hey, maybe I'm going to have update issues. Hey, maybe
this is going to have stuff bundled along with it. And if I want to fix that, I have
to take certain steps myself. I feel like doing that sort of is like this. It's an acknowledgement
of the limitations, and then just kind of deciding, all right, well, it still has enough
incentives that I'm going to go ahead and go forward with it. That's where I'm at.
For me, it's very app specific. When it comes to data, I'm naively ambivalent about the
whole thing. I tend to just live with my head in the clouds and figure, you know, if they're
going to want to know something badly about me, they're going to figure something out.
So I just don't get too excited about it. I mean, it irritates me, but I try not to
focus on it too much because it just depresses me. So I mean, quite honestly, I am conscientious
about what I'm searching for or what I'm doing on my phone. Definitely so. Even the apps
I install, I'm very conscientious about it. But I would say for the most part, I'm pretty
ambivalent about it. I don't think too much about it, although I am having an app specific
problem that perhaps we'll talk about at the end of the show. But outside of that, no,
I'm okay with it. I still like it better than iPhone.
Let's get to the app thing because I watched something happen over the weekend on the Play
Store that I was pretty disappointed in that I think is real low class of Google and Google
Play. So we'll talk about it at the end of the show if we have time. One more piece of
follow up to yesterday, or I'm sorry, Sunday's Linux action show. Blackout Worm on YouTube
was responding to, remember we had the email where the guy was like, gosh, I could switch
to Linux. It's just that I really need iTunes. And we were like, what does anybody quote
unquote need iTunes for? Well, see, and I had to ask my wife because I haven't a clue.
She's the iTunes diva in this house. So I had to ask her. I was like, well, can't you
do this over Wi-Fi? And she says, well, I think you could do something over iCloud.
But she says, I honestly just connected to my, she just does the USB thing. Yeah, that's
what my wife does too. And she just, she said, she told me, well, it works. Why would I change
it? So that's what I thought the reason was. And I was like, okay, they just don't know
about iCloud and the fact that iTunes thinking is probably going to go well. Well, Blackout
Worm wrote and he said, the only reason I would need iTunes on Linux is for streaming
TV shows. And this is, he echoed a point that we heard from a few folks who said, I bought
into the, you know, I'm a cord cutter and I bought into the buy and breaking bad or
whatever on iTunes. He says, Netflix and Amazon's library is peanuts compared to iTunes. iTunes
has a lot of exclusives, meaning shows that aren't and will probably never be released
on DVD or Blu-ray. As a Linux user, I really hate that there's little to no DRM support
here. Can't get it working, nor MP4s that I bought from my iPad. I really wish that
would change. As far as digital media goes, Linux is 10 years behind. Uh, no. It's just
they're not included in these closed systems. Yeah, I, yeah, I wouldn't even go, but the
whole 10 years behind thing, it's like, it really just depends on how you go about getting
your media. Well, and whose rules are you playing by? Are you playing, are you playing
by Apple's rules? Well then yeah, but of course they made that only work in iTunes. This is,
this is almost where I almost can see, ah, I hate going down this route, but, but you
know, I talk about sometimes, sometimes to me piracy, the piracy of content like TV shows
to me can, it almost feels like an act of civil disobedience in some sense because,
uh, yeah, it does in a lot of ways because artificial limitations that prevent you from
getting it because it's not actually affecting supply and demand. It's not actually affecting
a warehouse of goods. It's not, you know, it's not tangible. Um, you know, there's not
a tangible thing people can point you. So yeah, a lot of people, you know, so that,
that argument is, I think it's valid and the unfortunate part is about it is like when
you, when you pirate, you eliminate this DRM issue, the blackout worm, right? You eliminate
this incompatibility. Like you just throw it on a Plex server and then you have it on
every device everywhere at any time and the whole, all the problems are solved. And there's
like, there's this whole, and oftentimes it's higher resolution too, which is, you know,
a whole nother aspect to it. And so it's like, there's all these incentives and these deer,
all these walled off systems with DRM really to me just don't speak my language. They don't
speak a longterm solution to me.
Well, they're not very effective. Absolutely not. I don't think they're effective at all.
And I think that it really, it speaks to something when you can find that a pirating ecosystem
is actually more pleasant and usable than the official ecosystems that are authorized.
And I feel like as technology has changed so rapidly in the last five years, content
that like for example, blackout worm has purchased content that he bought on iTunes doesn't scale
to his evolving needs in a, in a changing technology platform environment. However,
content that he might've pirated, that's portable. That's, that's free. That's, you know, it's
going to move around however you want. It's just, it's, it's so dumb the way the system
works.
It is. And I also want to point out that Angelo was kind enough to point out that, yes, you
can actually sync over wifi. So his problem of needing that USB connection is really not
needed. You know, so Angelo, yeah, I understand. That's good to know. That's good. And so,
but I also understand that you know, pirating is not really a great option and it's not
necessarily an option that a lot of people want to do.
Well, and a lot of people can take more of a, I don't know, a looser, I've been known
to buy, we have what we call mom flicks and that's my mother-in-law who has approximately
15,000 DVDs and I'm probably low balling that. Um, any DVD, you know, so anything I want
I can rip. You know what I mean? It's like, it's a problem solved for me. So, you know,
it works out pretty well from that. So I have that option as well. And if it's not available
to me, then I probably don't need it that badly. You know?
I agree, Matt.
That was perfect.
I really, I really think also we just kind of need to put our big boy pants on and be
like, fine, you don't want to sell me your content. I'm not going to buy it. I mean,
we're willing to make that stance for open sourcing versus closed software. You know,
Photoshop, you don't want to make your software available for my platform. I'm not going to
buy it.
I was able to do that with everything except Dexter and Breaking Bad. I just, I had to
have that.
That's fair. That's fair. I guess, you know, there is always that sort of a cultural, um,
experience, right? Like I, I am a Star Trek, you know, there's, it doesn't matter. I would,
I would, there are hoops I would jump through and have jumped through for Star Trek. I mean,
I have bought all that crap on Blu-ray or, or convinced family members to get it for
me for the holidays.
Exactly. That's where it's at. Yep. It's, that's where it's at. Like get me Star Trek.
You could do no wrong.
Well, and to be honest with you, uh, this is again, another advantage to physical media
in the sense that it's easily backupable, breakable. Um, and then I throw it into an
MKV file and I'm, and I'm good to go. I encode it with x264 and it sits on my, on my server.
Um, and it also is a higher resolution because it's from Blu-ray.
That's right.
And, and then I use Plex to manage the sampling. So if I'm watching it on my HTC one, Plex
manages the downscaling for me.
And you don't have to worry about it. It's great. It just works really, really well.
And there's such great Blu-ray ripping software out there for Linux. It's like a no brainer.
Yeah. We did an episode a while back on last, um, on backing up that stuff. You know, the
thing that I'm, I'm really loving these days is, uh, make MKV. I just think that's where
I've been. I mean, Handbrake's great. Don't get me wrong, but I've just, I don't need
all that. You know, I just need it simple.
Yeah. Yeah. Uh, Ickmyre or he told me how to say it, but I can't help but say Ick. He
lives in Washington too. We just outed him. Sorry to do that on the air, uh, Ick. Anyways,
he suggests that we need, uh, uh, a JB Plex app. If anybody out there wants to make us
a JB Plex plugin, that would be awesome. Ickmyre, sorry. Uh, and Linux newbie said, did I mean
H two 64 and not X? No, I mean, so I mean, uh, H two 64 is, um, is, uh, everybody knows
what H two 64 is. X two 64 is an open source re-implementation of it. And it is so much
better. Like, and, and this is coming from somebody who initially on X two 64 was very
skeptical. I'm very skeptical on web M and VP eight. I'm hopeful for VP nine. I've also
been a doubter on, um, Theora.
I think Theora was, Theora has been garbage as long as I can remember. It's adorable,
but it's just garbage.
It's just not, it's just not a serious solution for distribution of media. And I think that's
one of the reasons why it struggled to take off. Um, and so, uh, but one of the things,
and I was initially a skeptic of X two 64. Oh, it's just a, you know, it's gonna, it's
a rip off. It's a clone. How can it, it's always going to be in catch up mode. Well,
I was totally wrong about that. Uh, H two 64 stagnates for the most part because of
the, a mass amount of interests that are involved with it. And X two 64 has managed to maintain
compatibility as needed. I mean, you do have to watch yourself, but, uh, the, everything
about it is better. The picture it delivers is superior to H two 64 it's open source code.
That's superior. Um, and the encoding times are better because it's more efficient at
taking advantage of multi-core, you know, my Bonobo, it will light up all four real
cores and all four virtual cores completely maxed out, uh, as it rips through video using
FFmpeg. Um, it's really great. So that's really awesome. Well, and I, and if memory serves
me, and it's been a while since I've tried it, uh, on Vorbis, you know, for the audio
stuff, I don't recall that being bad. No, no, Vorbis is fine. Yeah. Vorbis was great
for audio, but yeah, it was the video where we always had the, it was muddy or was choppy
or suffers from that. Not, not good, but not better enough than MP3. And since it's almost
the same to me. Yeah. All right. Well, so, uh, we got, we got some steam stuff. I mean,
this is, we knew we talked about it on Linux action show on Sunday. We said Monday, they're
going to announce this. I was watching the countdown that happened while we were recording
quarter radio. So my, my, my immediate, as the, uh, as the page went live reactions were
captured in Kota radio and it's funny. And I don't necessarily think this was, I don't
think this, I don't think this now, but at the time my first reaction was, Oh, this is
a huge slap in the face to Ubuntu. Right. That was my, my, my first immediate reaction
was, Oh, canonical thinks or a valve doesn't trust the canonical is going to deliver on
the desktop. They don't think they can hitch their boat that way or their, their car to
that wagon or to that horse. Well, you know, I think it's like the old saying, go, go is,
uh, you know, trust, but verify. And I think that's kind of what they did. Um, I think
they said, Oh yeah, no, we're, we're totally hip to you guys. But in, in addition to being
hip to you guys and being down with what you're doing, we're going to go ahead and do this
project over here just in case, you know? Well, and like so many people like to do there,
we believe they're going to base demoize off of Ubuntu, but before we get to all of that,
I want to thank our first sponsor this week, Ting.com. Ting, Matt, mobile that makes sense.
Yes, sir. Mobile that makes sense because Ting has no early termination fees, no contracts.
No contracts. Yes, that's right. No contracts. And you only pay for what you use. In fact,
let's just start with this this week. One of the things I love about Ting is their rates.
They break out your rates by minutes, text message and megabytes, and they bill you at
the end of the month for whatever bucket you fall into. So if you don't use your voice
very much, but you use a lot of data like I do, well then you end up paying an extremely
reasonable rate. I think my bill right now is around $14. It's incredible. And since
it's the way they base this is you can have multiple devices on one account with a pooled
amount of minutes. You just pay that $6. There's a flat $6 for the line. Bam, you've got a
line you own. Then from that point on, you only pay for what you use. So if that, if
that device sits on your desk for a month, you don't have to worry about the gadget guilt
of not using it. And Ting is making a lot of great new improvements. LTE lit up all
over the place. They have a goal of 200 million people covered by LTE coverage by the end
of 2013. They just turned on 34 new cities, tons of new coverage in Texas, and they just
got the Moto X. This is probably the Android phone to have now, which, shh, my HTC One
is in air shot. You don't want to make it jealous, Chris. I know, I know, Matt, but
this HTC One is looking really, really good. But if you're still considering something
else, maybe something a little of the larger variety like, oh, I don't know, the new Note
3. Well, good news because Ting has announced that the Note 3 will be hitting Ting. And
now Matt, you know, you know, when you have a big screen like that, this thing's going
to support a 5.7 inch screen. You ready for this? Three gigabytes of RAM and a 13 megapixel
camera. Let me put this in perspective. My main desktop computer, not, not the one I'm
on now, which has more RAM, but my main desktop has two gigabytes of RAM. I want to really
let that sink in for folks. I think people, if you haven't tried it on a large screen
device, that when you have, when you're taking a picture on something like the Note, the
screen is so big, you get such a good idea of what that picture is going to turn out
like and the framing of it. So, so, you know, man, Note 3 coming out, they just rolled out
the Note, I'm sorry, the Moto X. And the good news is, and it doesn't stop there, the LG
G2, the high-end Android smartphone that packs useful features and unique design with a 1080p
5.2 inch screen, 2.3 inch, or I'm sorry, 2.3 gigahertz quad core processor and a 3000
milliamp battery. They're going to have the G2 coming out on the Ting network as well.
That's also got Android 4.2. It's got a tri-band LTE antenna in that thing. And they've also
got some new refurbished feature phones. If you want something real straightforward, you'll
see those in early October.
Get something for the family, you know? And I have a real quick, super quick plug that
I want to do for Ting that I experienced and I talked about on the show last week. And
that was where I went a little bit over on my data. Not a lot, just a little bit. And
I'm thinking, OK, I'm probably going to get rolled into the next plan, no big deal. I'm
going to roll into the next bucket, rather. OK, that's fine. Guess what happens? I get
an email saying, hey, you went a little over. We're going to eat that cost, and we're not
going to charge you extra for it.
That's awesome, isn't it?
What's up with that, right?
They're awesome.
Whoa!
Yeah, they're awesome. And now they have an early termination fee relief program. So
if you're canceling a contract at your current provider, Ting will help you take the sting
out of that. You just go get your phone, port your number, then submit your ETF claim, and
it'll take up to $75 off your ETF. That's a great deal. They've also announced that they'll
be rolling out a new LTE hotspot, the Zing Mobile Hotspot MyFive 5000 LTE. Now, you combine
the Ting fantastic rates with an LTE hotspot, and the fact that you only pay for what you
use. So if you don't use it very much for a month or so, no big deal. That's a killer
deal. That's incredible. So go to linux.ting.com. Linux.ting.com will take $25 off your first
device or, if you want to bring your own device, well guess what? $25 off your first month.
Since the average Ting bill is like $21, it might mean your first month is free. And then
later on, if you decide you want to get the Moto X or you decide you want to do something
else, you can. You can grab it. And it's super easy to do through the Ting website to get
them all set up and get it activated. And you combine that with their super, super wonderful
customer support, 1-855-846-4389. You call in anytime between 8 a.m. and 8 p.m. Eastern
and a real person will answer the phone. That's just so great. That is so awesome. So go to
linux.ting.com. And thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. Big thank you. So there I
was, the end of Coder Radio, and Valve has to go and make a big announcement, Matt. And
the thing that struck me in this announcement, just like did not see it coming. And to your
credit, you totally, totally, totally called it at like the 36-minute mark in the Linux
action show last week. I'm going to play a clip. Steam box. And I think, you know, I
look at what the Ouya did. We've covered it a lot on Coder Radio. I look at what a lot
of these other companies are doing. I think Valve's the one that has the right approach.
And the fact that it'd be powered by Linux makes me ecstatic. Screw you, Xbox. Screw
you, Xbox. I'm getting the Steam box. You know, the more I think about it, the more
I'm thinking, keep going back to what he said about the whole embracing the PC culture and
the fact that you can expand on it. It's open and so on and so forth. What if the box is
essentially a gaming thin client for your existing computer? Because if you think about
it, it sounds dumb at first, but if you stop and think about it, it's like, okay, I've
got my Steam box. Okay. Wow. You know, I really want to upgrade that hardware. Yeah. But if
you have a box that doesn't care and it's pulling it in from, I'm not saying that's
what it is. I'm just saying it's a possibility. I would say you called it, Matt. You totally
called it. That's one of the key features of a Steam OS. Yes, that's right. Ladies and
gentlemen, Steam OS. So this was the teaser last year. We shipped a software feature called
Big Picture, a user interface, interface, interface tailored for televisions and K-pads.
This year we're working on even more ways to connect the dots, dots, dots, dots for customers
who want Steam in the living room. Soon we'll be adding your design process so you can help
us shape the future. Now here's what we've got. Steam OS, so far what we know is going
to be a platform by Valve that they're going to offer out for free for people to deploy
on their hardware. They can make Steam boxes. Uh, we don't know for sure yet, but we believe
that Steam and Valve will announce a reference platform that you should follow. It'll be
Nvidia based. It'll probably be of a mid-range spec and it'll be running Steam OS. Steam
OS primarily is going to be based off Ubuntu. It has, of course, a Valve spin on it. There's
already repos up online. There have been for a while. We actually covered them like five
weeks ago on the Linux Action Show. There's been repos that you could connect to. Um,
they have been building them out and they've been calling it Home Test, which has been
obviously short for people who have Steam OS installed at home or are getting updates.
This has been around since April. So this is all something they've been building. Of
course, they've been working with Nvidia a lot. They've been working with the different,
uh, um, different parties on, on getting like a debugger built for Linux. And I love those
things because that's going to ensure not that it just exists, but it exists and it
works really, really well. Right. So we've been, so we've been seeing Valve very subtly,
very intelligently move towards the living room. One of the things that, uh, is I think
of particular interest is, uh, 40% of all games on Steam feature some sort of, and by
the way, I mean Linux games, 40% of all Linux games on Steam support some type of, some
level of controller support. So that amounts to 70 to 72 games of the total that are available
for Linux right now have controller support. However, when big picture mode was launched
last September, 23.7% of games available on Steam were listed with full or partial controller
support. That was 382 games total on Steam of games that have launched on Steam since
big picture has been launched about 48.4% of all of the featured or all full fee, all
of the games have featured or have full feature or partial feature for controller support,
raising the total pop population of games on Steam to nearly 30% or 617 games in total
now on Steam have controller support. So they've been working on this for a while, right? As
a part of that critical infrastructure piece, then they announced, you know, we're going
to, we're going to also announce some AAA titles. Uh, we assume those will have controller
support and they say, Oh, and Hey, don't worry if you've got, if you've got a steam library
full of stuff, but it's on windows, we're going to stream that for you. Oh, and by the
way, don't forget, we've also just enabled family sharing and that's something I got
to hit you up on. I got to borrow some of those games. I got a 16 year old over here
more, you know, games will be needing, I'll tell you, but I'm excited for this cause now
I'm seeing it from his eyes and you know, seeing it from a whole new perspective of
the sense of discovery. And it's just so exciting to see this happen, you know? So my, uh, my,
my prediction is here that, uh, we're going to have ourselves, uh, pop may be, I don't
think so, but maybe a hardware pre-order tomorrow. I don't think so though. I think we're just
gonna see a reference design, but I think we're going to see some sort of maybe potential
partnership announced with Nvidia. To me, it seems logical that the streaming technology
they're talking about is the Nvidia shield technology, but I think so. I think you nailed
it. I think you called that one. I would completely agree with that. That's just making sense.
It ensures that five, you know, two, three years, five years down the road, whatever
it may be, there aren't going to be any conflicts or issues because the partnerships already
in place, they have an equal interest in keeping that stuff on par. So this is to me, there
are so many interesting aspects to talk about this from what's it going to mean for Linux?
What's it going to mean for other distros like arch and open Sousa and fedora? What's
it going to mean for developers? I mean, there's so many different angles we can talk about,
but before we move off from the launch day announcement and what was announced, I want
to open it up to the mumble room and say, guys, is there any aspect of the announcement
or something that came out in the news that was particularly noteworthy to you? Anything
around with, you know, what you hope to see tomorrow announced? I'll leave that to you
guys now, buddy. I was surprised by the of being able to use your windows games on Linux,
which people do leave their computers running in an office while they're in the living room.
So hey, right. You're going to have to have a machine running occupied to do that streaming
because theoretically the streaming processing will take place on the windows PC, but it's
over the land. So it's not like what online was trying to do so much. This is true. I
guess I'm just looking for if it has really good updating features, because I know a lot
of people don't want to deal with updates, especially on Linux. Right. Yeah, they'd have
they'd they'd have they'd have to have their own system wide updater that sort of took
care of steam updates, system updates, game updates. And I think, you know, we've had
we have I'll leave it up to the folks in the mumble room, but we've had folks in the mumble
room who have connected to some steam repos, pulled down some packages and seeing that
there is their own like valve updater in the repo. And it doesn't necessarily sound like
it has to be on Ubuntu 12.04 either could potentially work on 13.04 that now that could
be interesting, although that's going to be an interesting release, you know? Yeah, no.
All right. Well, so here's where I think we should take this chat. And I think this is
something first thing I think I want to talk about is. So envision I think we're going
to envision something like an XBMC almost style distro based on Ubuntu 12.04 boots up
right in the steam big picture mode. And, you know, we've seen we've seen that, you
know, Ubuntu has been valves focus since they started steam for Linux. They already have
a repository for it. I think this will be just something they'll make available to folks.
And I think that they'll say, we recommend these specs, we recommend this hardware, but
you can do more video, you can do more CPU. But what I want to ask you, Matt, is what
do you think this means for OpenSUSE? What do you think this means for Arch? Honestly,
nothing, because I think they cater to different groups of people. I think they cater to people
with different goal sets and different interests. You know, there's always that, you know, do
we need to worry about some sort of evil division or whatnot? Do you think they're going to
create so Michael Dominic suggested that perhaps they're going to Androidify only to be steamify.
It's going to be maybe they maybe they're going to use, you know, their own display
manager. Maybe they'll use mere. Maybe they'll use, you know, they're they're they're going
to kind of over time become their own integrated solution, a customized separate kind of. Oh,
I think so. I think, you know, just like, you know, as you said, Android Androidify,
I think, you know, you look at Android and then you'll also look at the fact that other
operating systems are actually finding their way into the world. Firefox, for example,
things like that. So going back to the steam OS, I think, will that affect other distros?
No, I don't. I think that there's enough non specific interest to that space that everything
will remain strong. And as it is, I know that means that I do predict a lot of the sky is
falling from news outlets and folks on blogs and whatnot. Everybody's going to be freaking
out. Oh my God, Ubuntu and steam and all these guys are just big poo poo heads and they're
ruining everything. And we're going to hear lots of that nonsense like we always do. But
it's not going to happen.
You know, so I'll play a little bit of this clip. I'll go back to something we played
on Sunday. Yeah. On the other hand, PC gaming seems to have been immune to this back up
because we actually didn't play this part in peace to sort of double down on that rather
than going that the way that they should have responded is very much to key off. And that
was a very seductive opportunity. I'll let him play this. So one of the things Gabe talked
about in his keynote is that locking down the ecosystem, integrating the stream line,
it has actually led to less innovation, which has led to the decline of the industry. Interesting
point. So he may not lock it down. It is very much to key off of the strength of, you know,
the openness of the systems we had and sort of double down on that rather than going going
the other way. So jumping forward, what are we looking at now? We're looking at steady
year over year unit declines in PC sales. And so I think, you know, I kind of I'm I'm
I'm filling in and connecting a lot of dots for that could lead me to be very disappointed
down the road. But to me, it sounds like one of the things that's turned them on about
Linux is the fact that it is this sort of it's the it's the Internet of operating systems
in the sense that it's this open, common, connected platform that anybody can put their
goods on and sell. And and I think what if if Valve is successful here, Valve will take
the term Linux and take the general public thinking around Linux, too. Oh, that scares
consumers and it's too hard. So we're not going to brand Linux like Google doesn't Brown
brand the Chromecast as the Linux Chromecast. They just it's Chromecast, right? Because
like we talked about last week, Linux is scary. Exactly. It is scary. No, I think it'll be
interesting to see what they do. I do believe that at some level they may end up using something
like mirror or they may end up using something that would arguably be, quote unquote, you
know, locked down in the sense that it's not as widely popular or something like Wayland
or whatnot. But that doesn't but that doesn't mean that they won't go and take this and
make this to where you can run it the way you want it. You can take their OS and run
it on any darn thing you please. I believe they'll make that possible. And they may even
just go do that through APIs. And if they're successful, if they're successful at doing
this, then they'll go from Linux is scary to Linux is the platform where there isn't
a special interest controlling it and I can sell my stuff. And it'll have to be something
snappier than that. It'll be Linux is the Internet of platforms or something ridiculous
like cloud or vlog or whatever. Sure. Tweet. But it'll be like I think we could actually
go from to like Linux is this place where people are going to go to sell their goods
potentially. We'll see. I don't know. Well, I think it could at least help with the image
of Linux quite a bit. One thing I've learned watching steam over a period of time, as well
as watching other games in general, there are two industries and technology that define
media formats and that define direction, porn and gaming. Right now, gaming is going with
Linux. All we got to do now is get porn on board worse. And it's good. Everybody's music.
And I wonder too, isn't sort of like the you know, like you're right, like maybe it's gaming
comes here first and then other industries join along. But yeah, there's those two defining
industries that really historically define everything. I mean, they literally take direction
of media. They take direction of technology, even DRM. Yeah. You know what? Porn is going
to have a hard time in stores. I actually have something. Yeah. Well, I just think if
Valve does get successful at boasting Steam and having Steam on Linux, I think most people's
opinion will be like, Linux is for gaming because Valve made it very successful. You
know what I mean? Yeah. It could change like the whole perception around it, couldn't it?
Because like it makes Linux more appealing to say the younger crowd because the younger
crowd obviously wants to have really awesome games and really awesome graphics at the same
time. Right. Well, and I think Valve is in a, I know, okay. So I guess here's the question
is so Valve has a lot of clout. Steam's a great platform. I went and I Wikipedia'd out
the numbers here. Here you go. Here's a little bit of, here's some math for you. Steam, we'll
put it this way. Xbox Live has 46 million active users as of February, 2013. Okay. Xbox
Live 46 million. PlayStation Network, if you combine all of the PlayStation consoles with
all of like the Vita handhelds and all the handhelds they've sold, PlayStation Network
is a hundred million active users. That's quite a bit. But Steam actually has a very
respectable 60 million active users. Wow. So if you get 60 million active users, you've
got some leverage there to incentivize game makers and you could do it across the entire
store. So you could say, all right, a big AAA developer, if you're willing to make the
game for our Steam box, we'll give you a higher cut of your sales across the entire Steam
store. Like Valve has some room here to, you know, lean on developers to create something
for Linux. So I think that's the key right there. I think if they say, look, you're already
on these other platforms, you make these, you know, you make the needed modifications
to come to us, we're going to give you a bigger piece of the pie. And oh, by the way, this
is essentially a brand new market because they're opening up in the living room. Big
deal. You know, it's a big deal. No doubt. They have excellent pull against, you know,
developers because they have a huge base to work off of. And a huge customer base with
a good history of willing to buy products. You combine that with their pushing forward
on a lot of the fundamental aspects of Linux support. So they've been sort of changing
that image already with making the game performance faster, delivering their own games to Linux.
Steam with a lot of the back end features of Steam, I mean, the elephant in the room
is this is all commercial, this is all DRM. But the plus sides for Linux to me seem really
quite obvious in this scenario. I mean, this is a huge, this will be huge for Linux because
it sounds like in everything we're reading and everything we can infer is this thing's
going to follow pretty closely to mainline Linux. And I think what you'd end up having
for better or for worse is a quote unquote official standard for what Steam compatibility
needs to look like. And it's not like the standard in the sense that we went to a board
and a board came up with a consensus that all distros will follow. But what it is is
that every distro that wants to make a Steam game work can look at how it works on the
Steam OS and then do whatever kind of silly hacks they have to do to make it work on Arch
or OpenSUSE. Just like, you know, I mean, we get pipeline, I mean, hell man, we can
go watch Silverlight DRMed Netflix videos now on Linux. The Linux community is amazing
and making things work under their distro that are not designed for their distro. So
as long as we have a model to follow, which the Steam OS will be this quote unquote game
standard base that will follow. This will be the Steam base that we all follow now and
then we can make whatever they get working there, we can replicate it on different environments.
Yeah.
Yeah, but Chris, I kind of feel like that it's then also very important that in the
upcoming announcements, there is going to be a Steam box because without a reference
implementation of the hardware, like a real reference implementation, it might not really
take off as much as we hope. And then it's all been all for nothing.
I agree. I think if, you know, okay, so here's the problem. So say they do a Google route
and they make a Nexus device, right? Well, who the hell is going to order anything but
the Steam valve box? No, I mean, that sucks all the air out of the room. So what they
really need is to work with companies like new egg and have like the new egg Steam box.
And we could have like a Linux action show Steam box. And then I, I agree that you need,
I hope, I hope that system 76 might do something like that because the, the only other device
we have seen is the piston and that thing costs a thousand dollars and that's just too
much. Well, isn't that the interesting thing is a company like system 76 could take a Steam
box and make one, but would anybody buy one? Could they make it cheap enough is really
the hard thing to come up with because Sony and expo and Microsoft sort of have this economy
of scale where they can make things cheap and then they can charge for licensing and
games and they can charge for Xbox live and whatnot. But what does Steve, what does valve
really have in their hardware? What if valve gave a system 76 or somebody else, you know,
they give them a cut. Hey, you get 10%, 20% of the purchase of every game and maybe go
ahead. Okay. With regard to that, we, if it is that steam bless one particular vendor
over another, then you would have people who don't know about Linux, don't know about companies
like system 76 and so forth that will eventually have to go to these companies to get their
stuff just as well as I think you might have a couple of quote unquote blessed vendors,
but it's going to be an ISO you can download, I think. Yeah, I'm sure it will be. It just
makes sense because it's as much coverage as possible. I mean, as far as getting back
to the steam box itself, one thing that we really need to remember too, is that if you're
married you generally have to consider what I like to call a front room real estate. Yeah.
And there's others on others. You have certain consoles that are, that have been blessed
to be there. They serve their purpose, but to add another console and then to have to
argue, well, we're now we're going to need a bigger cabinet or, well, we're going to
have to rearrange that. As silly as it may seem, that does come up. You know, it would
here anyway. And so that, you know, so size and proportion. And I think the question would
be asked, does it play Netflix? Does it play? Yeah, seriously. No, that's a legitimate question.
Does it play, does it play either games and or content that your spouse is into? On the
page, it states that they are talking to content providers. It's vague though. It's vague.
That could be a YouTube app for all we know. Right. Oh gosh. Yeah, no kidding. And we'll
just say, I can't answer your question about hardware costs. I mean, you've got the Linux
kernel, so it's pretty much adaptable to anything. So it's adaptable, but you still have to have
something that runs the games well. And so it's kind of hard for them to vet it. It's
not like the Xbox where you have this fixed platform. And so all the software vendors
sort of have a target hardware spec when they're designing the games. This thing needs to be
very powerful to accommodate almost any game stole price. And I think the streaming kind
of alleviates some of that. In fact, that gives them some flexibility, right? I also
think that because Valve was working with like Nvidia about drivers and stuff like that,
I do think they also need to work with AMD, but that's just my opinion. Oh, I'm sure they
will. I'm sure they will. I think they would have more or less standard specs that will
work with any game. And seeing that they have certain vendors who'd be blessed, like for
example, they're working with Nvidia, people would tend to work towards getting Nvidia
drivers working with their games. And you continue on that path. I think that Valve
just needs to really focus and make sure they get this on the dot is to have driver implementation,
correct? Yeah. Yeah. And because Valve has been doing business with Nvidia, they might
already have a deal for a chip they can put in their box for a very good price. They might.
I think price is crucial because they need to meet the price point of the PS4 and the
Xbox One in order to get that console market share to get it really going and soon. And
if they do that, then the developers will come to them to make the money. I don't think
that will be hard. I think the way this has to work out, and I mean, the way I'd like
to see it work out is if Valve could make a box where, you know, if I just fall ass
backwards into buying a Steam box, I land on this thing. Like give me something for
just the most simple basic consumer to go purchase. Maybe it's advertised in the Steam
store itself. Maybe I could even buy it through Steam. But then make it available for anyone
to build one. And the reason I think that is because like I was picturing pitching
this to an Xbox fan, and like I think the question they would ask is, well, what controller
can I use? And my answer would be like, well, Valve has a really great controller they spend
a lot of time coming up with, but actually any controller that works with Linux you can
use. If you want to use the 360 controller, you can. You want to use the PS4 controller,
go for it. And so I think, you know, they need like the one-click purchase box that
just comes with everything. That's the one you get at Christmas. That's the one that,
you know, a real average user gets. But then later they could start building their own
the next time they get one, or they could, you know, swap out the controller for their
favorite console controller. And I think if they can walk that line, I agree with the
Mumble Room. If they don't really have something in 2014 for me to buy, well then they better
work really damn close with a few OEMs to have something. And it better be like, it
better feel just like buying one from Valve.
The controller points a good one, but one controller I'd like to see is just the standard
keyboard and mouse because for me personally, I'm an RTS fan and I can't get that on a console.
I think that's going to have to. I mean, I think, I think they'd have to, they'd have
to probably, you know, hard code it not to work.
Yeah, and that's the beauty of it being Linux is that that's something they should embrace
that you can use a keyboard or mouse, you can use your preferred controller. And I think
at the end of the day, you know, that's great.
Which would be my preferred controller.
Yeah.
That's going to be, that's going to be one of their major curb appeals right there.
It is. Yeah. Because I was talking to my nephew about this. He's 16. He's like, well, can
I use, can I use my, can I use the controller that I use on my existing console? And I said,
probably. And he said, well, I'm on board. You know, he was good. He already has Steam
games. He's good.
What do you guys think about this streaming capability? Is this a band-aid or is this
like a long-term, okay, here's the way I see it. It could be a, a bullet point to address
the lack of AAA titles in the library, 200 Linux games, and only a handful of them are
the ones people are like totally clamoring for. Or, or it could be a long-term strategy
to say, kind of like Matt was saying in last, you know, this is really just a thin client.
And while yeah, you can play native games on it. If you want to use this thing for five,
five years, good on you. Just keep upgrading the video card in your PC and we'll just keep
streaming it for as long as you want. Is this a short-term thing or is this a long-term
thing?
I think it's both. There's going to be some people that are just going to really want
that thin client solution. And there's also some developers that will refuse to develop
on Linux until it's inevitable that that's the primary gaming platform. And then there's
going to be other developers that rush to support it. So I think it's really going to
be both solutions, short and long-term.
I do think that, I do think that they should probably work on trying to entice developers
and show that it's actually easier to work with Linux than it is to work with Windows.
Because the thing with Windows is that its kernel structure, yeah, it's very stable,
but it's not that fast and you don't get the good performance and you don't get to have
the capabilities that you do with Linux.
So I feel like NVIDIA has this entirely new technology, the streaming technology, developed.
And this is for them also a chance to make it like a standard.
So you agree it's going to be the NVIDIA streaming tech?
Yeah, because this is a chance for Valve as well as for NVIDIA.
Yeah, the consoles went with AMD so NVIDIA could really sell some units here.
And so I wonder then, if this is NVIDIA's streaming tech, it sounds like, I mean to
me, and I don't know where the squares with NVIDIA saying they're going to provide documentation
to the Novo project today, when you look at this, this to me seems like one of these features
that absolutely will require the proprietary NVIDIA driver.
It would.
It definitely will.
See, Alan in the chatroom thinks that streaming will never work, that it never works for games.
Now I don't know, I don't know, see, I'm of a slightly different opinion because for me,
I actually was able to play on live fairly successfully.
And on live was going to servers up in the cloud.
Now we don't know for sure, but I think everything points to the streaming is going to happen
over the LAN.
But where you're going to run into issues is everybody has really crappy Wi-Fi, right?
At least in average homes, nobody's got their Wi-Fi figured out.
There's a dozen different Wi-Fi APs just in range within my house.
So people who are not wired are going to constantly have problems, I would say.
Then it might scale down to 480p.
My answer to Alan, my answer to him saying that streaming won't work, I think on live
kind of failed just because they didn't have the coverage.
They didn't have all the servers in place as they do now.
I mean, I played on live for a while.
I mean, it wasn't good because I wasn't in like a closer coverage area, but if they had
more servers in like say one in Iowa or something like that, I would definitely be playing that
and it would have been great.
Yeah, and I think, you know, Cheeseburg in the burglary in the chat room makes a good
point.
You know, average Joe isn't probably going to be too impressed with the answer.
Yeah, I can play your games is, well, I actually take that back because if you're asking the
question, can it play game X, then you probably already have a PC and you already have that
game and you want to be able to play it.
So maybe actually.
But taking it into the living room gives you better two player ability.
You don't want to share your keyboard and mouse at your desk.
So you're assuming they can still play it back at the desk.
I would think it would take almost all the resources to just cause you're going to, I
mean the game has to, the game has to run.
I don't mean two player as in one person sitting at the desk and one person sitting
in the living room.
I'm talking about person a person B both watching the same TV in the living room.
Yeah.
Console style.
Cause it is a console.
Streaming is also an enticement to developers.
If their game doesn't play as well over streaming and steam picks up a momentum, then they're
going to want to develop natively for Linux so that it is competitive.
Yeah, totally.
Yeah.
I think that that would be the main point.
Most of the games that eventually, especially windows only games, you'll start to see a
dip in their games being played or being purchased because people want to use the steam box or
the steam OS because they can actually play it on larger screens and everything like that.
So eventually they would have to move over their games being played on Linux and will
actually be a win-win right.
Because in the other distros, we'll see how they got it working on steam OS and make it
work on their distro of choice.
Exactly.
And that's going to be huge.
Definitely.
You know, I almost wonder if we're going to see something to where maybe it's kind of
a hybrid to where, okay, you've got the, uh, you, you, maybe you've got like some local
resources cached on the console itself and then the rest of it's being streamed in toward
basically where, you know, kind of a minimizes congestion from valve.
You know, I think people, I think, I think people would actually prefer that.
I think people would prefer to be able to stream it from valve because then you could
have somebody playing on the PC and you could have somebody playing on that.
Yeah.
Well, and if you cash local resources, like you cash in your, you got your maps cached,
you got various, uh, things like rendering, right?
That's where the, and that's where the seat, that's where the GPU is going to have to really,
you know, the whole Nvidia thing comes into it.
So, I mean, if they can kind of find that balancing act where, you know, there's still
some, there's still some caching going on locally, you still got enough to where it's
not just raw data going back and forth like crazy.
It's basically just gameplay.
Right.
Um, you know, well, if you did it right, uh, and essentially what OnLive did, and this
is why I think you could almost do it over a LAN is OnLive took, uh, either X264 or H264
and forked it essentially and created their own video codec and they would actually render
it as video and stream the video to the OnLive device.
Which is what the shield does.
Yeah, exactly.
It takes it before it goes to the HDMI port on your graphics card, if I'm right.
So if you can, if you can support, you know, a one to four megabit transfer rate over your
home LAN, that's essentially all you need to be able to stream that video bit rate.
Cause you're not actually streaming the raw data of the vectors and all of that.
You're just streaming the end output video.
Right.
That's pretty much every network.
Yeah.
It maybe is a little, a little pushing it for broadband connections for some folks,
but I should work over that.
I should work even over wifi.
I would think so.
Yeah.
They can probably drop the resolution to 720 without too many people noticing too.
I think part of it that I'm reasonably, another reason why I'm kind of excited about it is
because it's Gabe and it's valve, right?
If this was EA or, you know, Activision, I don't know, some company saying they're going
to make their own box.
I'm like, okay, good.
Well.
I'll look forward to that bastardization hitting the market soon.
Because valve has a, because valve has a good track record with their, with their comments.
Well, yeah.
I mean, just Gabe, you know, just totally we sort of, sort of, I mean, it makes so much
sense with that.
Why he was saying what he was saying at that keynote, it's, he's laying it all out there
saying this is the rationale.
And then when, when the news hits you, you know, you have this total framework to, to,
to view it all.
And I mean, it was pretty, pretty brilliant.
It was good staging.
I'm curious to see where it all goes.
Yeah, I am too.
And I think whoever did their marketing did a really nice job.
I mean, it was presented in a way of, here's why I care.
Love me a good countdown.
Yeah, exactly.
Right.
It's excited.
You know, one thing that I find.
I think that at the end of the day, Valve should more or less focus on organizing themselves.
Remember that they are just a platform in order to sell games, make sure that the development
platform is good for the developers, probably get one or two blessed vendors for the hardware,
but mainly focus on getting their stuff ported over to Linux so that the developers are easy
to move, to make a transition across to, to Linux so that they can get their game sells.
Right.
Yeah.
And if it is that they can do that, the hardware aspect of it will come eventually, whether
people like it or not, they would still be able to get, whether it's System76 or Dell
for that matter might want to jump on board because they see that, hey, everybody wants
to play games on Steam and every, and Steam using Linux.
So we need to, in order to get in on this, we have to be able to supply people with what
they want.
Well, you have a, you have a, you're going to have a whole range of people who just want
to play some of these side scrolling platformers or they just want to play some of these lower
end games and they could just, and as long as they're happy with streaming too, if the
streaming actually works, you could take, you could take an old box and just load the
SteamOS on it and call it good.
And you know, it doesn't matter if it can't play all the games natively because the streaming's
there.
And it could be this great use.
And if they tie in kind of video media playback, like I'm talking local LAN playback, give
me a little MKV support, maybe even a little Netflix action, action, I'm putting this on
every TV in my house.
Exactly.
That's, I think that's kind of what they're aiming for.
I really do.
And I think by hitting, basically looking at what the other consoles did wrong and that's
of course, you know, Wii is targeting nothing but family use only and any serious gamers
laughing at it.
Xbox and PS3 completely alienates most family folks and definitely into more of the people
that really like to play games.
I think by hitting that middle ground, and I think they can by having the side scrollers
as well as the hardcore games, I think they're going to be able to hit all the nails in the
head.
Well, and I think too, you have to look at some of this stuff in the perspective of a
struggling middle class, an economy that is continuing to have to make tough choices about
what they spend their money on.
And if I've got a two or three year old machine that can run SteamOS just fine, assuming I'm
okay with streaming a portion of the high end games, then to me, it's almost a slam
dunk because I get a console out of reinvesting in hardware I already have.
That's always been a great sales pitch for Linux usage.
It's always been a fantastic use for it and now, now we actually have a console contender
and so Valve is throwing their hat into the console ring by not creating one console but
by creating a platform and then letting the community build around it.
I'm pretty excited about that.
Makes complete sense.
We're going to keep digging into this and as we get more information, maybe even get
our hands on SteamOS, we'll talk about it more in the Linux action show, Matt.
But I thought we should probably get to a couple of email items that came in.
Yeah, good plan.
And before we do that, I wanted to actually make a special mention.
So I would talk about this pretty much as frequently as I feel people will tolerate
and that is our affiliate system.
We have links at the bottom of the Jupiter Broadcasting website.
We also have Chrome and Firefox extensions.
This is why I'm bringing it up.
Ah, the topic of the day, yes.
We did an update and I think it's really only Chrome that bit us in the butt but we did
an update to both to support new sites and to also kind of handle the, properly handle
the way when people click on an affiliated link on somebody else's site to make sure
our link doesn't override it.
That required a re, re, I don't even really, I don't really think it changes much except
for the way it just reads the URLs.
And anyways, that requires a reauthorization.
We had a massive drop off, a huge, huge drop off.
And I almost wonder if people are, it's maybe they are aware of it but they don't know if
they already have the old one installed, like do they know how to go into extensions?
It's super subtle.
Yeah, you gotta hit like the little hamburger menu and then go down there and say re-enable.
What's that look like?
Maybe show us what a hamburger menu looks like.
The three line.
I don't have a shot of it.
Oh, you don't have a shot?
That's fine.
So it's up there in the upper right hand corner.
Yeah, exactly.
It's that, it's that three dot, that three line.
It's called, they call it the hamburger menu.
And in there you reauthorize it.
We had a huge drop off so our, our expenses are super tight when that goes away because
the way we do it is we have advertising that pays for a certain running amount and then
we have a good portion that comes from the affiliates and that sort of balances out where
our different revenues come from.
But if either one drops off significantly, it really hurts the production.
So if you would check that and make sure it's enabled and if you don't already have our
browser extension, well you can find a link to the bottom of Jupiter Broadcasting for
Chrome or Firefox and we'd really appreciate it if you grab that and help us.
We have huge plans for 2014 and I've been kind of discovering over the last couple of
weeks, there's a lot of local listeners, Matt.
Oh, oh, that reminds me.
Oh, so, okay.
So we have a lot of local listeners, which how cool would it be to do an unplugged with
a few people in studio?
Dude, that would be awesome, right?
Yeah.
Okay.
So this is, I probably should have brought this up to you off air, but I'm going to
throw this out there.
Okay.
One of the things we could do in a future where everything is, everybody has infinite
time and organization capabilities, you know, that future that we talk about all the time,
wouldn't it be fun to take a Tuesday and like go do something on location, do an unplugged
on location, and while we're doing that, record a segment for that Sunday's last, so sort
of kill two birds with one stone.
So we take a Tuesday, we do the unplugged show on location, maybe do like a meetup type
thing, and then, you know, I'll give you an example.
This was all while I was naked, I was in the shower, I think I had, I probably had soaked
my body, but I don't think I had put any shampoo on yet, so just that's about that stage in
the shower.
And why do I picture you with microphone in hand this entire time?
I don't know.
Yeah, well definitely.
I got a waterproof microphone, yeah, yeah.
And so I was thinking it'd be really cool if like, the scenario I came up with was a
beer tourie, because we, you know, we met folks that run their breweries on Linux.
I was thinking real world, local Washington implementations of Linux in their work environment,
something you know, not so much like, here's our Samba server, I mean that's cool, I mean
good on ya, but we can't really make a segment out of that.
But like if you got like a brewery running Linux or a farm running Linux, oh dude a farm
would be awesome.
Anything running Linux that we could go look at and shoot a segment for for last, I'd love
to do some on location stuff for last, just kind of kick things up a notch.
And then we would do like a meetup somewhere around there, and then that's when we do unplugged.
So we'd be like killing like, basically we take a Tuesday and just knock out unplugged
and a segment for last and just have a ton of fun.
I like that idea.
I think, I don't see any reason why we couldn't.
It's an example of some of the things I want to do, and there's some ways I want to facilitate
that, and I have some great ideas for 2014, but we really need folks' support, so if you
please click those affiliate links and grab those browser extensions, it helps us plan
for that kind of stuff.
Absolutely.
Otherwise we're going to have to start doing like a, you know, save the children PSAs and
stuff.
Today on Unplugged, instead of doing a show, we're just doing a pledge drive.
Seriously, yeah.
Just, we're just going to keep talking, we'll keep talking, you know what we'll do is we'd
talk about iPhones until people pledged, and then when people pledged, we could talk about
Linux, and then once the like timer had run out, we'd have to go back to iPhones.
Basically a torture technique.
Or it has us like rummaging around various dumpsters looking for food because you guys
aren't supporting us with our, yeah, I mean.
Yeah, we take last and convert it into a dumpster diving, dumpster diving action show.
Okay.
Hey, this could run Linux.
He sees out of the dumpster, right?
Oh my gosh.
Okay.
So it's up to you fellas.
We'll see.
We'll see what happens.
We'll see where it shakes out, man.
All right.
So I've been an Arch user for over a year now and I, and it's basically because of the
awesomeness of make package and make and PKG.
The problem I'm having is that I can't find a desktop environment I like.
Here's why.
I'm a typical user.
I'm not a typical user.
I don't think.
I spend 99% of my day jumping between terminal and web browser.
I don't like messing with my desktop.
I want to look decent, but basically out of the box and get out of the way.
I'm using Cinnamon right now, but I've tried elementary OS after your review and I really
like Pantheon.
Based on this, I'm leaning towards installing elementary and running Arch in a VM.
That said, he says, cause he maintains a couple of packages in the AUR.
Good on you, Matthew.
He said, that said, there are still some apps I require the latest versions of like Gex
and get, I'm sorry, and Tmux.
So I'm planning on just compiling the latest versions of those myself on site like elementary.
I realized this may not work for everyone, but the, for the dev ops, for dev ops, sys
admins like myself, who don't like to waste time tweaking the desktop, it's becoming the
ideal solution.
I mean, I think we kind of zeroed in and that's who elementary OS would be good for.
The part I don't agree with is, I mean, it sounds like maybe he needs like, you know,
Exmonad or awesome window manager.
I mean, it kind of does.
Yeah.
And that might be something for him to explore as well.
And I'd also chime in on the whole Arch in a VM, just do yourself a favor and do a separate
partition.
Honestly, you'll be so much happier.
Especially when you're doing from the AUR, you need to build, right?
I just, I have building in a VM is like, Oh, and just Arch in a VM in general, just getting
it set up.
It's actually massively simpler on a partition than it is in a VM.
Is it based on my experience?
LXDE, we've got a recommendation from Ick in the chat room that LXDE would be good.
I guess, I think that, I think that really I'm still, so I switched back to Gnome for
a couple of hours this week and decided to go back to KDE because KDE is, yeah, you know,
with all the extensions, I had, I had extension problems again and I just felt like, you know,
with KDE I can make it be what I want.
And even if it takes a little bit of tweaking.
So I think, I honestly think, I do see how the, maybe try to just experiment with getting
the Pantheon desktop running under Arch.
I know there's people out there working on that and see if that gets you where you want.
Then try out elementary OS.
Sure.
All right.
Jonathan writes in regarding windows.
I'm not sure where this fits, but I just wanted to send it to you guys.
I'm more or less left on windows in the windows world.
And I've been stuck in the XP era.
Every time I had to take a quick trip into the Microsoft pool, it left me with shivers,
viruses, stupid gooey's and infinite reboot bonanzas.
And he's come to an epiphany.
He said, I think I finally understand why windows has ruled the enterprise desktops
for so long, despite all of the shortcomings he just listed.
He says, I'm interning at a large IT company, which means someone else does all the rebooting
virus scans and whatnot.
In that setting, windows is very usable.
Only the bad UI is left to deal with.
And of course, IE.
And he's got a great point because in enterprise, IT pulls their hair out with all the problems
windows has.
And then the end users all la dee da dee da circus music's going on in their head.
They don't have a clue.
You know, early on was one of the motivations to getting windows out of my home is I, you
know, I, uh, I can't, I can't remember what OS Andrew's on.
I mean, this is probably windows 2000 before I switched her to, uh, open SUSE and KDE.
And I just, you know, I come home and she'd have windows problems, printing problems.
And I was just like, oh yeah, no, I don't want any more of this.
And for me, it was like, I was literally, I I'd already been running Linux for some
time, but I went exclusive Linux when I found out that I think it was a win FS.
You know, I was looking forward to that file system with all the neat features they're
babbling about.
That wasn't going to happen.
I'm like, that's it.
If I hear the word NTFS one more time, I'm going to shoot something.
I just, I couldn't handle it.
He also, uh, he needs some advice from you, Matt.
He says, I've been forced, uh, through this company to use internet Explorer exclusively.
I'm in need of some therapeutic tips to get that dirty feeling off me when the workday
is over.
Any advice?
Uh, kill it with fire.
Um, that's the first I actually burn.
Yeah, like get, try and find like an old IE five CD, you know, they used to come in packages,
get some of those, light them on fire, do a barbecue.
You know, that could help.
You know, I don't know, man.
That's, that's tough.
Spend some quality time with candlelit, candlelit Mozilla, you know, just kind of get it around
your monitor, get some, uh, Barry White going, you know, what I would do honestly too is
like sometimes you need to like relive how bad it used to be in IE land.
So like go like find a VM of like windows 98 with like three or something and then live
that for a day and then be like, wow, this new IE is great.
Great.
And it's not, that's the horrible part.
Uh, Kiwi in the chat room says that, uh, he could just drink heavily.
That could also.
Yeah, that works.
Yeah.
And the beer goggles in IE is looking pretty good.
There you go.
Uh, so we, we had an email that came in from Ritison, who is a Manjaro Linux user and he
wanted to talk about SteamOS versus Ubuntu Edge.
I started to get through it and he, you know, I was going to read it cause he says blast
is my favorite podcast of all time.
He looks forward to it every week.
And I thought, well, okay, I got to read this guy.
Strong.
Yeah.
Right.
But it's very long.
Uh, but what he says is he thinks it's an interesting correlation to look at sort of the, um, big
run up to Ubuntu Edge and then the court of immediate drop off where his valve is sort
of taken this different approach where they've started, um, very small, you know, make this
work better.
Uh, like Gabe called it the sweater, um, the sweater approach where they pull us one thread
and then just leads to the next red means the next thread and they've been making those
things better, whereas canonical is kind of like put everything out there, let's go, let's
do this by it.
We don't even have all the bits done yet.
Not all the infrastructure done yet, but if you, if you commit to this week, we can try,
we can get, try to get it done.
Uh, he says that he feels like, uh, that it requires large companies like valve who have
deep pockets to make this possible.
He says, I look forward to the crazy future of Linux, but I resent that it does take these
huge companies like Google and valve, you know, of course, Google with Android to push
her forward to public adoption sometimes.
However, I feel like Gabe understands that and respects the philosophy of open source
more than others.
And I actually use the word Linux on the steam OS announcement page, unlike certain popular
distro that makes no mention of Linux anywhere on their website or mobile OS, uh, I truly
feel steam OS is pure Linux's chance to gain market share and a user base.
It deserves, even if users are unaware that they're running it, which considering the
state of some computer users, knowledge comes to as no surprise, sorry for being so long,
but I'm really excited and keep up the great work.
A managerial user and you know, he's right, this could be, um, this could be like, uh,
this could, I don't know, I don't, I don't want to be too crazy, but you know, if you
look over history, the common platform eventually takes over.
Like you start with individual things like very purpose-built operating systems, very
purpose-built devices that really only do one thing.
And then as, as the general technology advances and becomes more powerful, uh, it just becomes
economically more viable to use that technology and to continue to create your own technology
every single time, uh, all, uh, you know, these individual platforms that we have now.
So it kind of, you know, I've always kind of seen a day and age where, um, these big
guys move on, Microsoft moves on, Apple moves on.
And what we're left with is a really healthy Linux ecosystem because Linux has kind of
taken over there.
Linux kind of moves into mobile, Linux moves into the living room, Linux moves into the
desktop and over time it's on the server, it's on the cloud, it's on the work, you know,
it's everywhere because as people leave that area or the, or the common generally available
platform becomes good enough, it just becomes almost crazy not to use it.
And uh, steam could be, steamOS could be the beginning of that takeover, not just from
a Tivo standpoint, but from a really large scale deployment standpoint of, of an ecosystem
where people are actually making money, people are actually developing and creating something
of extreme value.
And I'm, I'm really, really, really excited that it's Valve doing it and I'm, I'm really
interested to see the kind of opportunities we're going to have in last to cover this
because there's tons of potential for them to screw this thing up royally.
Oh yes, yes there is.
Right?
And we're going to be there to watch that happen if that does happen, but there's also
opportunities for like, what's the best way to build out a steam rig?
What's the cheapest steam rig you can buy?
What's the nicest steam rig you can build?
You know, it's endless possibilities, endless possibilities.
And then just watching adoption as well, because as we all know, uh, computers are nothing
more than how do I accomplish blank?
We really, most people don't really pay a lot of attention to what the OS is.
It's how do I do this?
How do I do that?
How do I Skype?
How do I browse the web?
How do I send an email?
How do I game?
And Valve is going to be sending the game.
And what I like about that is it's totally solving that problem at the same time.
Like you could be completely checked out of the whole steam ecosystem.
You could never buy a title.
You can never use steam OS.
You're still getting better kernel X.
You're still getting better Nvidia Y.
You're still getting all of these improvements that they're making that are going to hit
the rest of general Linux.
And that to me is also sort of like this everybody wins scenario here.
If it's successful.
Right?
I think it will be.
I think, and I think the advantage they have is that they don't have the pressures that
say Apple or Microsoft have from shareholders.
Now that's not, I don't know what steam, I don't know what Valve's exact corporate structure
is.
Last time I checked, I think they're privately held, which is if they are to stay that way,
you'll be happier because it's less headaches and you can go long game.
If once you go, once you go public, you're short game.
And so that limits your options.
So yes, I think in the long run they will be successful.
It may not happen all at once and may, they may have some bumps in the road.
They may even have some costly mistakes, but I think because they're taking that sweater
approach, it's going to work out for them.
Yeah.
Cause they're doing all of the really, you know, low level grunt work that has to be
done first and not just building the flashy presentation on top of all of that first.
Like they're doing the stuff that, you know, general consumers will never, ever, ever give
them credit for.
It's not sexy.
It's not going to win them over in, you know, the, in the general consumer markets.
Only the stuff that us Linux nerds care about, but it shows that they're taking the right
approach.
And here's something they won't do that Google did.
We've talked about how Android basically sold their souls to get themselves on various mobile,
with various mobile carriers and various phones.
And of course the carriers or the phones themselves would be bastardized with all the software
and stuff.
Valve won't do that.
The Valve stuff will remain here.
I believe that through and through that anyone they hook up with, they're not going, you're
not going to see lots of, Hey, get this new, you know, lots of the little icons appearing
all over your screen or any of that.
It's going to be great.
It's going to be really solid.
Wouldn't it be interesting to like, if Roku eventually rolled out a steam box, cause if
they can take the platform and they just have to put up, you know, you could have the Roku
maybe in three years, the Roku XL is got a, you know, a really good graphics processor
in it and it has the steam, steam OS on it or something like that.
I think so.
Well, and just to look historically at Roku and I'm probably partially correct on this
and I think I am, if I remember correctly, the guys behind Roku are actually the guys
behind replay TV.
These guys know what they're doing.
And Roku is Linux based already.
Yeah, it is Linux based and they, and they got it right.
So I think that, yeah, if they did hook up with Roku, that would be very wise of them.
Anybody could.
I mean, you could just take, I mean, if the boxy box was to come around, say that, you
know, we, the boxy box guys time traveled to the future and created their product.
Why not base boxy box on the steam box and if you could, you know, maybe if there's a
way to do video and all that kind of stuff, because sure, then you just get the advantage
of the steam library.
It's like, it's, it's like when you ship an Android tablet, you want to be able to put
the play store on there.
It's bingo.
Exactly.
All right, Matt.
Well, I think that'll wrap us up for this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Don't forget you can contact us by going to Jupiterbroadcasting.com and clicking that
contact link and choosing unplug from the dropdown or even better, start a thread on
our subreddit over at linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Join us on Sunday.
We've got a good show planned, Matt's going to help you secure your house with cameras
and Linux.
Oh yes.
On Sunday and we will be doing some more steamOS coverage and following that as well.
We'd love to hear from you.
You can also join us live on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv.
We kick that off at 2 p.m.
Pacific.
Hey, by the way, calendar page has been updated.
You can now select your time zone on the freaking calendar page.
Pow.
Makes it super easy.
Anywhere in the world, not just US.
That's right.
Hey Matt, have a great week.
I'll see you on Sunday.
Sounds good.
See you then.
All right, everyone.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll be back here next week.