This is Linux Unplugged Episode 18 for December 10th, 2013.
Hi everyone and welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux doc show that currently
has more raw computing power than the NSA.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
And I'm surrounded right now by, let me count them down, one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven screens.
Wow!
That's a lot of screens.
Yeah, that's a lot of computers right now, so we're in the middle of this big hardware
roundup where we're reviewing different gadgets from System76, different machines.
And I just hooked up today the Leopard Extreme.
I actually hooked it up late last night.
So they sent it to me with 64 gigabytes of RAM.
Oh!
You gotta love that, you know?
And I'm just going to tell you too, I decided to go for it.
I installed Arch on the Ultra Pro.
Nice, good choice.
Yeah, so I got KDE 4 with Arch and I actually went a different direction this time.
I had problems with Integros, like the, I don't know if it was the repos or what was
going on, the install wasn't working.
I love Integros, but it just wasn't working out.
What exactly were you experiencing?
Was it just not installing, like crashing?
It would get like, no, no, it was fine, it was fine.
It would get through like 70, 80% of the installation process and then it would just seem to start
timing out and pulling down a package.
I don't know if it was the Arch repo issue at the time or what it was.
So I jumped over and tried out Bridge Linux, which is sort of along the same vein as Integros
in the sense that they use straight Arch repos and they let you pick like your different
desktop and they let you choose KDE right out of the box, which is what I wanted.
It's definitely not quite as smooth as Integros, like it's a straight up command line installer,
but it has like an Ncurses interface.
Not bad.
It's a little more, it's definitely for more power users, it's not quite as user friendly
as Integros is, but I got it installed and now I have a completely current Arch installation
and it took about 25 minutes, so it was an interesting experiment because I'd never tried
it.
Yeah, it's interesting.
I'm going to have to check that out myself.
One of the other things I thought was kind of interesting, to overuse the word already,
is I also tried Manjaro, but Manjaro suffered from the same exact problem Integros did.
Did it really?
That's why I was thinking it might have been a repo issue.
It must be.
Yeah.
I mean, it's really hard to say exactly what was going on.
The only thing I've ever experienced as far as a Manjaro versus Integros situation was
that one Ethernet, that one Broadcom Ethernet driver issue to where Integros was not having
it and it couldn't install because, get this, it couldn't get to the Internet.
Of course, there was no detection on the wireless front and of course, you're not getting any
love on the Ethernet front.
It kind of means you can either go the long way through Canvas, personally it would just
be easier to install Arch at that point, but I just went with Manjaro on it and it worked
out okay.
Well, so I want to apologize up front.
I'm not really so sick anymore, like I feel fine, but I still have some junk in my throat
and it's fine unless I talk, which is not really…
That could be a problem.
Actually, when I think about it, it's kind of a problem.
So you might hear, I'll try to mute my mic from time to time, but I do have a little
junk in there.
That'll give you an opportunity to yammer on.
Yeah, that's true.
And you know, I have, it's not the best solution, people, but it's all I have to
work with is a little 100 proof peppermint schnapps.
You can see it's already working.
It's got the tongue feeling good.
So I'll be sipping on that as the cough comes up.
But I wanted to touch on something before we go on, Matt, because I have a little more
things to say on the System76 stuff, but of course, as is to be expected on the internet,
there was a critique and of course, Stowolf2 in our subreddit who saw it fit to post the
same thing twice in the thread, said that the whole show was more or less a big commercial
this time.
This is, he's talking about our System76 laptop special from season 29 episode 10 of
last that came out on Sunday.
I really hope it won't take that long before they're finished this because I have no interest
whatsoever with this kind of thing.
I really hope they got paid quite a bit.
I'm willing to go through a couple of them if it means shows will continue, but I cringe
myself the whole time wanking off a sponsor the whole episode this week.
So I think there's a bit of an assumption here that this was a paid.
Yeah.
And that's, well, first of all, there was no wanking that was happening to my knowledge,
at least I didn't get anything there.
But no, I would definitely say that this is based on the fact that we're celebrating and
reviewing hardware that is built to run Linux.
Yes, they are a sponsor.
Yes, I've also been using myself as have you been using these guys long before the Linux
eyes ever on the Linux action show.
So I've been promoting them way before I had anything to do with them.
So these are products and services, these are products we're actually excited about.
So at least from my perspective, and that's what we're doing.
That's exactly it.
There's no exchange of money.
When I asked to be sent these computers, we didn't tell them how to spec them or anything
like that.
We don't get to keep them.
I mean, God, that'd be awesome.
And I also would argue, I don't think we got necessarily preferential treatment either.
I think we, you know, there's just as they became available, they were sent to us.
Right.
Yeah.
And there was a waiting list.
And it really and you'll notice.
So the way the system 76 sponsorship works is system 76 sponsors a particular segment
and not the entire show and we move that segment sponsorship out of the system, the review
like we'll do next week when we're talking about the leopard extreme.
Absolutely.
And another thing that happened on Google Plus and I'm finally glad is taking place
is the old, well, they're rebranded such and such and whatnot.
And I'm really excited to see that Carl came out of the woodwork and actually address this
and I'll actually provide it maybe in the show notes as to what he responded to.
But he was actually talking about, you know, what makes them different, how, you know,
what system 76 does to actually ensure that they're compatible.
The custom bios, hand to hand.
Right.
The hardware keys for the function keys.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Right.
And in case of my bonobo, the modification so that the GPU would work properly under
Linux and not just under Ubuntu but all Linux, right?
Which was later on, I mean at the time I bought it to run Ubuntu but then later on I decided
to run Arch.
So there's all this stuff that they don't spend, because, you know, this is of no value
to you guys to sit there and for them to ramble on about all this stuff.
But this is all the stuff that's actually happening behind the scenes that make these
guys unique.
And I think it's pretty exciting.
So are they Clivo based?
Yes.
That's the base, right.
Yeah, they're based.
But there's a lot of extra stuff there you're not seeing.
But unfortunately it's easier a lot of times to, from an easy chair to point and go, it's
just rebranded.
So there's changes at the hardware level, but then there's also there's the support
angle of it, which for some folks matters a lot more than other folks.
What I come back to at the end of the day is the strongest statement we can make as
Linux users, and this is one of the reasons why even though I don't play all of them,
I often pick up a Steam game, is there is nothing more powerful than Linux users voting
with their wallet.
And in the Linux ecosystem, especially in the free software world, there's not always
a lot of opportunities to clearly make your voice be heard.
And the thing is, is one of the reasons why I've been buying, and they don't sponsor this
show, right?
Right.
Exactly.
They don't sponsor Unplugged.
I can say whatever I want.
But the truth is, the reason why I've been buying them for seven, eight years is because
that money goes into a company that then continues to push the desktop Linux agenda forward,
right?
Right.
And so the thing is, is I know, for example, a lot of people love Lenovo ThinkPads, and
they probably are, I don't actually, I haven't had one for a while, but they often are very
good hardware.
But the problem at the end of the day is that purchase is actually voting for the Windows
desktop, because they're not counting it as like an Ubuntu desktop machine.
They're not counting it like that.
Because on top of that, there's the aspect of the interaction with the community, with
the drivers, the Ubuntu forums, and all of that that I really respect.
I respect a company that actually follows the community and doesn't just get Linux,
but actually actively participates in it.
And it's not that I, no disparity for anybody that wants to buy a Lenovo.
You buy whatever hardware works best for you.
Everybody, I mean, I've got Macs in the studio, okay?
So I understand there's hardware out there that does what you need to do and you need
to buy it.
My point is, is that is a vote.
And that's like when I do decide to buy a Mac, that internally for me is a very long
process of reflection that I go through and I spend way more time than I should like specking
out a Hackintosh, trying to figure out how to not vote with my wallet, because that is
the most powerful vote.
And that's another reason why I like System76 quite a bit.
And all of that plays a factor into when I look at a System76 unit and I think, you know,
this is something for Linux and how good is it in that context?
And that's why for me, Ultra Pro, not only did it change my perspective on Ultrabooks,
because obviously somebody has the Bonobo, I'm kind of as much power as I can cram in
there.
But it also changed my perspective on Intel graphics, which I think in the long run is
going to be the biggest thing I carry forward from this review is just how far the Iris
graphics have come.
And again, the Linux games aren't the most demanding games on the market.
I really haven't seen anything that the 680 and my Bonobo can't just chew through without
ultimate settings.
So it's maybe not a fair test.
Maybe it wouldn't perform as well under Windows.
I don't know.
I didn't try.
But I loaded Half-Life 2 on this Ultra Pro under Arch using Steam and it was butter smooth.
I didn't even adjust any of the video settings.
I just wanted to get in game and see like could I get enough frame rates to actually
expect to be able to shoot somebody.
And it was like it was as if I was playing on an embedded video.
And I understand that Half-Life 2 is not, you know, it didn't just come out.
It's not the most current game.
But at the same time, the way I look at it is if you're looking at getting an Ultra
Book, gaming for you is probably not the first priority.
It's probably more like something you do on a social occasion.
And I think…
It's secondary, yeah.
Right.
It's something you might like to be able to do, but it's not going to decide the purchase.
And I feel like the embedded graphics are now at that level and that's extremely exciting
for me because Intel graphics are a cheap, they're low power.
If you consider the Intel chip too.
And also open source, the drivers, right?
So you have open source drivers, which is great.
And not only do we have open source drivers, but Intel has shown us that they will work
with the Linux kernel team one generation out.
So while one generation is on the market, before Haswell even hit the stores, they already
had drivers into the Linux kernel.
And to me, that's huge.
So I'm really excited to see where that goes.
And so they haven't paid for any special treatment.
We asked to be sent the hardware.
We wanted to check it out because in both Matt and I's opinion, this is the premier
Linux hardware vendor.
Well, in my own personal desktop computers and old, I mean, hell, I've got my laptop
behind me from 2008.
It's a system 76.
It still works.
I've got a pile of laptops in front of me from other companies that don't work any
longer.
So I think the quality is certainly reasonable in that regard.
And I've had good experiences with them coming from an old PC repair background and watching
people buy crap and then get all butthurt over it when their stuff doesn't work anymore.
I really value quality.
I don't want to, and that's not just the product, but also the service and the way I'm treated.
And that's a big part of it for me as well.
Yeah.
So on my Google Plus page, I posted some hardware porn of the intern of the leopard extreme.
And this is a really well-built computer.
And I'm looking at it as a Mac Pro competitor.
So the unit they sent me, 64 gigs of RAM and a six core Intel i7 processor.
What I want to try to figure out is a lot of, once I'm done editing a show, I hand it
off to FFmpeg on different computers throughout my house.
And through benchmarks, I've determined which computers are best at encoding which versions.
Some are better at shrinking video down and then putting out an iPod friendly format.
And some are better doing just straight encoding to 720p with no scaling.
And it's all-
Oh, that's interesting.
Yeah.
So you're saying that different machines actually specialize more so in different encoding techniques
than other machines.
Right.
Yeah.
And so I'm wondering where this thing falls down.
So what would be incredible, and I don't actually know if it can be accomplished, is if this
machine could make web and video encoding economical.
Because right now, what happens on the Jupiter Broadcasting website is I post a show and
I usually use the YouTube embed for sometimes a couple of days because the web and video
takes so long to encode that I often just don't get back to it till a couple of days
down the road.
So I can't use HTML5 video.
And so I'm hoping that this might be the machine that makes webM doable.
We'll see.
I don't know yet.
I got a lot of things I'm going to be throwing at it, but it's pretty cool.
I got it under my desk right now sitting right next to me.
And I got a nice Logitech G19 keyboard hooked up to it.
So I'm like, I'm full in.
Yeah.
I'm enjoying it.
All right, Matt.
Well, we got a couple of emails we should get into.
The first one is getting girls on Linux.
This was a response to some comments we made on a recent show.
Did you want to read this one?
Yeah.
Let's get over to that.
Girls on Linux.
Getting girls on Linux.
Okay.
Getting girls, which I think was a pickup from a topic we touched on last week.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I'm going to try not to butcher this here as we go.
As a female who discovered Linux in college, I wanted to add my own response to the questions
on how to get girls to use Linux.
Okay.
Interesting enough.
The most important reason for someone to switch – I'm reading word for word, so it's
going to be a little bit short.
The most important reason for someone to switch OS is not who will be doing their tech support.
So okay, I think basically what they're saying with that was regarding the tech support.
Okay.
Moving on to the next piece.
It is how – let me make that bigger so I can see it.
Hang on just a minute.
Probably reread that.
All right.
Let's try it again.
Let's see.
It is how they switch that will make their life easier.
Any female studying STEM in college – I studied physics and used tons of open source
software in my research – using Linux is a great way to separate yourself when applying
for research positions.
That's actually a really good point.
Okay.
It also offers some awesome creative outlets for other majors as well.
Liberal arts students should love the freedom and ideals that Linux offer to the user.
Most importantly, it can save them a ton of money, which is also true.
Great point.
Yeah.
Excellent point.
Okay.
I know it wasn't your intention to demean women.
However, let's stop focusing on women as outliers who need a different type of convincing
than men on why to use Linux.
The benefits of Linux apply to all genders equally.
I think that really summarizes in that last sentence.
Yeah.
I think this is something, too, that really resonated with me.
I kind of feel like it's insincere when a bunch of guys talk about how to get women
into technology.
That kind of seems like –
I can't speak for you, Chris, but I know talking with my wife, there is absolutely
a thing there.
Not because she's a woman, but because she looks at task management and various things
differently than I do because hold on to your hats, kids, because of gender.
I think it's interesting because at one end, what's going to draw women into technology?
It's going to be the same thing that draws men into technology, but when you look at
the actual end-use cases like in the home, my wife and I use technology very differently.
I would even say my wife's more effective with technology than I am in a lot of ways
because she does tend to work smarter.
I'm the guy that does multiple trips to bring groceries into the house when she will
find a way to do it in one or two trips.
There's definitely an effectiveness there, but I think at the end of the day, I see what
they're saying, but I definitely think that there are differences and they can be embraced
in a healthy, non-negative way.
One thing I wanted to clear up is I think there was a misunderstanding.
She said one of the things, what's going to make women switch is who's going to be their
tech support.
I didn't mean it as in women will switch to whatever the men will help them with.
What I mean is usually when you're switching to something new, you're going to have the
most success when other people in your immediate social group also use that same technology
so that way they can share experiences or provide insights when you get stuck somewhere.
I don't think it necessarily depends on, although in a sense, I guess that does mean who's going
to be the tech support.
But at the end of the day, honestly, if we want to really quit trying to be politically
correct and be honest with ourselves, there are some things, like I'm very good at certain
things that my wife's not good at.
My wife's very good at things that I'm not good at and they're not necessarily gender
specific, but some of them are.
Some of those things, like for instance, when it comes to actually planning out the layout
of our home, that was my wife.
You guys are like peanut butter and jelly.
I know, right?
I mean, at the end of the day, it's like I don't want to be too sensitive about this
because it just doesn't really add any value to it.
Yeah, I don't know.
It's a tough call.
I definitely hear what she's saying and she's got some great points.
I definitely like the benefits of all genders equally, but I think there are inherent differences
that we can embrace and do so in a positive way.
So moving on as a follow-up thread to the topic of swap partitions, we had a lot of
interesting facts.
I've got a couple I'll get to here.
Panda Brain wrote and he said in the debate last week, no one mentioned swap files.
Those are files that can be used for the same things as a swap partition is used for, i.e.
offloading content from memory and hibernation.
Unlike swap partitions, they can be created, removed, or resized on the fly.
There is no real disadvantage unless you use ButterFS, which just simply doesn't support
them.
You'll find more information about swap files in the always excellent Arch Wiki, and he
has a link to that.
So the swap partition thing, it's so funny.
Gosh.
Yeah, you really opened up a can of worms with that one.
If this was a Windows podcast, it would be our should I defragment my drive topic.
This is something Linux users pine over all the time, and you know what?
I think SSDs have made it even more... Now everybody's like, well, now I don't have very
much space.
I've only got 128 gigabytes of space.
Should I really give several gigabytes to my swap file?
What am I even using that for?
I've got eight gigs of RAM.
That's what everybody's thinking.
There are ways to take advantage of hibernation without the swap file.
But it probably requires a little bit of research.
You actually got to kind of plan out what your goals are and decide which approach is
best for you.
So yeah, there's a little bit of homework involved.
Yeah, yeah.
We're going to get to the topic of the swap file again, but I wanted to read some feedback
we got from Ray, which I had actually been meaning to personally write Ray back, but
I just haven't done it yet, so this will be the first time I've addressed him.
Ray wrote into the show and he said, hey Chris, I'm one of the golden ticket winners from
Ting.
I just wanted to say how happy I am I have switched to their service.
So I wanted to say thank you, Ray, for doing this.
This is an excellent point.
So Ting is sponsoring this episode of Linux Unplugged and I have to tell you, I am a big
fan of Ting.
I've been telling you about Ting for a while now and I think they're a great company.
It's not just that I like their service and it's not just that I like their pricey model
and it's not just that they have no contracts and no early termination fees and that I own
the phone and that hotspot and tethering are included.
And honestly, all of those things are what got me to switch to Ting, but they're not
what keeps me at Ting.
What keeps me at Ting is the fact that I'm, again, voting with my wallet and I'm giving
my money to a company that I'm really passionate about.
So Ray Roni says, I signed up through the last URL and I purchased a Nexus S with a
$25 discount.
Nice.
Yeah, you can get that same discount by going to linux.ting.com.
He says, the phone arrived sooner than I expected and I couldn't be happier after working out
a few bugs with tech support and later a new battery that cleared up some problems.
It's been a little tight on cash flow for a long time and I have an $85 phone that has
4G and it's near showroom-like condition plus a $400 credit that I will cover my cost for
my Ting plan for the next year.
He was on an Android 2.2.2 device before that his dog had slobbered up a little bit.
Whoa.
Yeah.
He said, I'd have been...
By the way, he got to use Nexus S, which is a really great way to save money when you're
switching to Ting.
He said, I would have been without a personal phone by the end of October if not taking
advantage of the deal and the affordable service.
I'm blessed with grateful and willing budgeting for my next device on Ting sometime next year,
maybe the Nexus 5.
So get started by going over to linux.ting.com.
Ting is mobile that makes sense.
They're my mobile service provider and Matt's mobile service provider.
Personally I've got the HTC One and the Nexus 5 on Ting service and it's awesome because
they have a great dashboard that lets me see exactly where each phone is at.
I can put one phone on suspend if I'm not going to use it for a little while.
There's tons of really nice things in the Ting dashboard, but really the great thing
about Ting is you only pay for what you use.
They take your messages, your minutes, and your megabytes and they add them all up at
the end of the month, whatever bucket you fall into.
That's just what they charge you for.
You want to turn on tethering for a little while, do it because son, it's only $6 a month
flat and then you only pay for what you use on top of that.
Average Ting bill is between $21 and $33 a month.
Think about that.
What are you paying right now on your smartphone?
Go over to linux.ting.com and click that how much would you save button right in the middle
of the page.
Put your current stuff in there.
Just put your bill in there.
I'm not judgy.
Just put your bill in there and see how much you're paying right now and compare that to
Ting because I've got Hotspot and tether, I've got an up to date Android phone that
is awesome that I own, that I only pay for what I use and I have no contract and there's
no early termination fee.
I'm truly in control and as these mobile devices become more popular, as this computing platform
becomes the norm, these are the little details that will matter the most.
You can get started by going to linux.ting.com and don't worry, if you're in a contract
right now, Ting has an early termination relief program and they'll take up to $75 per line
that you have to cancel.
It's super easy.
All you have to do is go over to Ting, get your phone, port your number and then submit
your ETF claim.
That's early termination fee.
Submit your ETF claim to Ting and they'll take care of you.
So, go get started by going to linux.ting.com and a huge thanks to Ting for sponsoring
Linux Unplugged and congratulations to Ray for becoming a golden ticket winner.
Isn't that awesome?
You know, it's so cool.
It is so cool and also, I don't want to steal thunder, but we have a little announcement
to make on the Fo' Show.
Somebody just got a whole bunch of service too.
Alright, so let's get back on this topic.
I got a big one.
I got a big one on swap files, Matt.
Are you ready for a little more?
I think I'm ready.
I can only imagine.
So, there's only one way to take a swap conversation and make it better and that's to bring in
ZRAM and Hibernate, right?
I mean, that's really going to take the next...
Oh no.
Oh boy.
That's just really over-complicating.
Oh my goodness.
Okay.
Alright, so Kevin writes in.
Hey Kevin.
He says, Hi Chris and Matt.
I'm glad you brought up the topic of swap.
Despite the beardiness of the topic, it's something I've been following since SSD price
drops and 2GB of RAM have made a swappable system not just possible, but perhaps desirable.
With the community having a greater experience about it, I wanted to toss around a few ideas
to the Jupyter broadcasting audience.
Alright, Matt, so I'm going to activate our Mumble Room for this one too so that way they
can answer.
Alright.
So, question number one and I pose this to the Mumble Room.
I've heard good things about ZRAM, but I don't want to spare a machine to test on it yet.
Has anyone replaced your swap file with ZRAM?
Will it work with Hibernation?
Is performance under heavy load better than disk-based swap?
Anyone in the Mumble Room tried ZRAM yet?
If only Ant was here.
I tried it on, I have an AC100, which is a Toshiba ARM-based laptop shipped with Android
and we replaced Android with Ubuntu and memory was a bit tight.
So we used ZRAM or ZRAM as we call it over here and really didn't notice any difference
at all.
It's fine.
And how much RAM do you think the system, do you remember how much it had in it, physical
RAM?
A gig.
Oh gosh, I have no idea.
Okay.
Two, five, six maybe.
It's either 512 or a gig because I remember looking at it, it's a Tegra 2-based system.
Yeah, it's pretty lean.
Yeah.
Okay.
The other thing to note is that ZRAM does not fix the Hibernation problem.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Okay.
This period does not fix it.
There is no way to currently hibernate, which does not require you to write to disk at some
point your contents of RAM.
Right.
Because you're powering down the RAM.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Another thing.
No, I don't get why there isn't some solution that creates like on Windows creates a Hibernation
file separate from swap if you don't wish to have a large swap file that matches the
amount of RAM you have.
Yeah, let's go.
Another thing I've been noticing just on my main machine is that ever since kernel 3.8
for some reason, ZRAM causes a kernel panic when enabled.
What?
And sometimes just randomly it'll kernel panic and I don't even know why.
What distro is this?
Any distro.
With anything after 3.8?
Anything after 3.8.
That is weird.
Linus, dammit.
No.
Okay, now here's, let's talk about swap files specifically.
So Kevin wants to know, is there a big difference between swap files and swap partitions?
If the system partition and swap are on the same disk, I can't see where an improvement
would be, especially since I could remove or add swap files with much less hassle than
a swap partition.
Now I have a theory, but has anybody actually tried swap files?
No.
All right, so here's my theory on the swap partition.
This is just a raw space that the kernel can write to.
And I gotta believe that is faster than going through the file system driver and whatever
it is, BotRFS extended for, I have to believe it is a much more direct connection when you
have a raw partition space that is just only for swap.
That would be my belief.
You would think so.
Yeah, I mean, you would think it would be a straighter shot anyhow.
Yeah.
All right, so he goes on to ask about USB 3.0 flash drives being cheap enough and maybe
storing swap on there.
No.
See, the one problem with USB is that it uses the CPU for the controller logic, so you're
gonna have CPU load for doing that.
I just don't think that's a good idea in general.
He said, it sounds like some of the Mumble members would go swappless if not for Hibernate,
and he includes a link where we can find out more information from the Debian Wiki.
How about that?
A plug for the Debian Wiki.
Woo!
On at least running Debian Hibernate without a official swap file.
So there you go.
All right, so he says, thanks for relieving my ramblings.
Well, Kevin, thank you for emailing in.
That was a good one, right?
Yeah, very good.
I thought that was a good little topic.
All right.
Really well thought out too, I think.
Yeah, it's funny how, like, there's just the semantics, you know, where you think about
these kind of things.
Like, honestly, when I was resetting up this Ultra Pro, I was like, should I make a swap
partition?
Right?
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
Unless you're running, like, openSUSE and you just import what you're working with.
Yeah, I mean, I decided to go for it, but yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Well, I wanted to remind everyone that we'll be doing a double recording on Tuesday the
17th, starting at 12 p.m.
So we're gonna start early.
Oh, boy.
Don't forget, man.
I almost, I actually forgot until I read that.
I got multiple entries in my phone as well as other, actually, both of my smartphones.
And they beep and squeal all day long, so I don't forget.
Yeah, you know, so, okay.
Here's what we're gonna do.
We're gonna start at 12 p.m. Pacific over at jblive.tv next week, on Tuesday the 17th.
We won't be live on the 24th, which is Christmas Eve.
So we're pre-recording.
And I'll tell you, this show, having no topics and just going off the cuff is fine for one
episode.
Yeah.
I don't know about two episodes.
It might devolve into another Star Trek review.
No, I'm kidding.
But show up and hang out in our mumble room.
You'll have more opportunities to do so.
So I'll go to that.
Matt, speaking of opportunity and things that you've been dealing with, I know, were you
dealing with car troubles earlier today?
Okay.
Yeah.
I mean, just keeping it real loose here.
Basically, I had, I known for some time, and I'm sure Ange and Chris have certainly heard
it as I'm pulling in or pulling out, my car likes to squeal like it's dying a horrible
painful death.
You know, I have a trusted mechanic, a very good guy here locally that I take it to top
of the line fella.
Well, anyway, shaving a few things off, even relying on a battery warranty, I'm looking
at just under $1,000.
Oh my gosh.
Yeah.
And it's like, I'm literally going to be delivering phone books to pay for it right
now.
So, you know, so you got to do the balance.
For the belt?
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
I need a new axle.
What?
I got all kinds of stuff.
I actually went, I went to, I had a second mechanic look at it to make sure.
And yeah, it's the real deal.
There's a number of things that are going to be, I'm going to see what the timing belt,
I think it's the other one or time.
Yeah.
Timing belt was the other one.
There's a number of things I'm looking at.
So yeah, so definitely been, you know, just one of those tough life lessons, but the good
news is, is it's going to be possible.
So that's what's awesome.
Man, I'll tell you what, so car problems and they have a great way of coming like at the
worst time ever.
Well, it's December, right?
I mean, clearly this is what you do.
Now do you have like a business that you can like say that the vehicles for the business
travel?
No, at one time, yes, but not anymore because I don't, because I don't work outside of the
house really.
I mean, I do kind of, but not really as much as I used to, I don't just mathematically
the count actually said it's easier to go this other way.
Rethinking that now, but no, I really can't.
So you know, it's just, it's just one of those things to where you just got to, you know,
stomach it and move on.
Yeah.
And so, you know, I mean for us, the biggest upset has been this whole Amazon affiliate
thing.
Yeah.
And it's been interesting because when I set up the Amazon affiliates program, I set up
like four or five of them.
I can't remember.
I set up like, I think it was four because I was going to do an affiliate ID for each
show.
Yeah.
And then I realized the way the Amazon system works is by traffic base.
So if you have everybody use one affiliate ID, you get, you know, better results, which
is totally legit.
Yeah.
So I had all these other accounts available.
So when they shut down our account, I still had these other ones.
So I thought, okay, let's see how these go.
Of course, they've all, they were all systematically shut down within a period of time, including
my wife's account, which is on her mom vault.com blog, completely unrelated to Jupiter broadcasting.
It's just her own personal blog where she sells.
If she talks about a mom product, a mommy product that she bought from Amazon, she'll
put a link to it with the affiliate ID, but it's like straight up like that's all she
uses it for.
Yeah.
It's not involved with our company at all.
And they still shut even that account down.
Really?
Is it based on, I wonder if they're like looking at address or what the hell, I mean, or last
name or I don't understand.
It's gotta be address, right?
Yeah.
It's gotta be, right?
I mean, cause you got your 10 versus SSN and all that.
I don't know.
I'll tell you, it comes kind of at a sucky time because so the, the early 2014 window
was we were going to start up, I have a townhouse that I own that is currently rented out.
And my, my idea was is I will take that townhouse and I will convert it into, I will ask the
renters to vacate and then I will convert it into a studio.
And part of that would also be hiring a full time person to operate the studio.
And then what I would do, and this is the part that I really want to do, and I, even
if we can't do the new studio, I still want to figure out a way to do this.
So I'm putting the call out to the Linux unplugged audience is I want to take Tuesdays and I
want to go on location to a company in the greater Seattle area that is using Linux.
Ah, yeah.
I mean, valve would be the dream, right?
Oh yeah, right.
Any company, any company.
And I want, I mean, I'm asking for a lot.
I mean, I realize this upfront, but what I want to do is I want to go there and here's
my thought, man, just totally, it's totally economical in terms of production senses.
I want to go down there on a Tuesday.
I want to spend the morning shooting a segment for the Linux action show.
And then I want to spend the afternoon doing a podcast from their office and maybe bring
in like their sys admin, right?
Bring in somebody who works with Linux onsite, have them sit down on microphone with us.
And you know, you could be there in person sometimes and sometimes you'd be on Skype,
whatever, whatever works for you that week.
We bring it all in and we'd have somebody back at the studio who could switch it.
So I'd Skype in.
Maybe I'd buy myself a Galago Ultra Pro and how you utilize this nice webcam.
Woo!
I like that.
So that's, that's my 2014 dream, so I don't know how we're going to pull that off, but
if you are in the Seattle area and you would like to have us come and burden your office
with our presence and abuse your bandwidth and ask you all kinds of personal probing
questions about your Linux infrastructure, email me chris at jupyterbroadcasting.com
because I want to start setting this stuff up.
I want to start doing Linux unplugged on location and then come back with something for last
on Sunday so we can, I mean, I think the opportunities here are great.
Like you'll get the behind the scenes story here on unplugged.
You'll get all of like the nitty gritties, the stuff that we don't tell you about on
last.
Just cause we'll call on last, we'll cut down and give you like, here it is, boom, boom,
boom.
Here's the information.
Here's the interview.
Here's what they're doing.
But on unplugged, we're going to do it right there on location.
We're going to bring their guys on.
They're going to chat with us and I think this could be a great opportunity.
So if you are in the greater Seattle area, Chris at jupyterbroadcasting.com, let me know
and maybe we'll do an episode on site in early 2014.
I don't know how, I don't know how we're going to pull that off.
Oh yeah, no kidding.
One way we're going to pull it off is we are rocking our, our teespring.
This is, we've exceeded my, my greatest expectations.
We're now at 722 of 499 that we needed to unlock it.
So this, I'm just mentioning it real quick.
You have five days and two hours left as of this recording to grab yourself a Jupiter
broadcasting limited 2014 shirt or hoodie or ladies tee.
Hello.
Oh, it says women's tee.
I think they should put ladies tee in there.
And I think they should say it that way with a little Barry White in the background.
Ladies tee.
Also, I've heard from, from our, from our Aussie viewers and folks in Florida, I'm not
kidding.
They're happy that we have a short sleeve option as well, just a straight up tee.
So if you want to get those, teespring.com slash Jupiter 2014.
And if you're listening to this six days from when it was posted, it's too late.
We won't have them anymore.
Before we get in and we got our mumble room back and I'm going to ask the mumble room
if Linux user groups are dead and Matt and I are going to share experiences with some
local Linux user groups who we both love, but we're going to talk about it first.
I want to thank our second sponsor this week and that is digital ocean.
Digital ocean is cloud hosting made simple.
They offer the most intuitive and easy way to spin up a cloud server.
Users can create a cloud server in 55 seconds and pricing plans start at only $5 per month.
Which gets you 512 megabytes of RAM, 20 gigs of SSD storage, one CPU and a terabyte of
transfer digital ocean has data centers in New York, San Francisco and Amsterdam.
Hey oh.
The interface is simple, intuitive.
The control panel lets you deploy a droplet super easy.
I have right now an arch server up.
Yes, I said arch.
It's kind of my personal experimentation and I'm going to keep pushing it, see how far
I can take it.
But one of the really cool things is if you want to try something out for a little bit,
digital ocean also offers hourly pricing.
Yes, hourly pricing.
If you want to spin up a cloud server.
I know and what's so awesome is you could create, so like take my arch machine that
I have right now that has BitTorrent sync and other goodies on there.
I have a backup snapshot of that.
I can redeploy that dozens of times if I want and only pay hourly and there's something
even better.
Listeners of Linux Unplugged can take advantage of a special offer Linux Unplugged December.
Linux Unplugged December will get you a $10 credit when you check out.
Use that promo code at $10 credit.
So if you're using the $5 machine like I am, well that will get you two months of that
$5 machine.
That's a pretty good deal and I invite you to take advantage of it because I didn't actually
fully appreciate how awesome digital ocean was until I spun up a server and I've really
been enjoying it.
Digital ocean also has a really good community and they in fact are trying to encourage that
sort of grow it a little bit and so right now they're offering those of you who want
to create articles or tutorials for their community.
If digital ocean selects the piece that you wrote, they'll give you a $50 credit.
You can follow the link in our show notes to find out more about that but if you think
about the baseline server is $5 a month, well if they give you a $50 credit, that's going
to get you going for quite a while and at $5 a month, I'm thinking about taking, so
right now I have an Arch server and one of the criticisms of Arch is that, oh it moves
too much and that's scary because apparently we're all scared of our computers.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to also take advantage of Docker, something we talk
about a lot and Matt, my thought is, is why not take Docker and spin it up on Arch and
create an Ubuntu LTS or a CentOS environment in that Docker instance, install things like
Zimbra or whatever sort of productivity suite I want.
It lives in this cocoon of protection, this cocoon of long-term support while it rides
on top of that wily and crazy ArchOS and of course DigitalOcean will let you spin up instances
with Docker ready to go, also the LAMP stock totally configured CentOS, Ubuntu, they got
a whole bunch on there, go check it out, go over to DigitalOcean.com, Linux Unplugged
December is your promo code to get that $10 credit, that way you can check it out for
a couple of months and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Huge thank you, I love those guys, I love the fact that you have all that freedom and
availability to actually really pick and choose the kind of lifestyle you want to lead in
the cloud.
And it's so nice for like software development and testing for the hourly pay as you go,
that's super easy.
All right, Mumble Room, are you back?
Are you here?
Yes, we are.
All right, so let's put your flame retardant pants on and let's have a frank conversation
about the state of Lugs.
Popey very pointedly asked the question on the pre-show, are Lugs dying?
And I think Matt and I both chimed up and said, with much respect and appreciation for
both our local Everett and Bellingham Lug, which by the way, our Bellingham Lug puts
on Linux Fest Northwest every year.
So much respect, but sometimes it kind of feels like it's last generation that's left
at these Lugs.
Like, for example, in the Everett Lug, they're kind of famous for these are the guys you
go to when you want to put Linux on a 486, right?
It's not the kind of stuff I'm interested in anymore.
I mean, I have a lot of respect for what they're trying to do and I think it's really cool.
And I kind of want a 486 running Linux in my house, but at the end of the day, to get
my work done, I'm looking at six core i7s, right?
So I wonder to you guys, I want to start maybe Popey, are you still here?
Do you want to share your thoughts on the state of Lugs?
Because you're really the one that kicked this conversation off.
Yeah, so this came from, I've been involved in the UK Linux user group scene for a few
years and I've been to my local Linux user groups.
There's three in a fairly small catchment area and when I first started going to them,
it was, there were lots of talks being given.
We would video the talks and we put them online and we'd get like 40 or 50 people in one
county Lug coming every month, once a month, and we'd debug people's issues, we'd chat
about various like salient newsworthy things that were going on.
When was this?
What year?
This would be probably about 10 or eight years ago, somewhere around about there.
And then over the years, I've kind of noticed it drop off a bit.
The amount of traffic in the various mailing lists on all the Lugs in the UK has tailed
off quite a lot.
I mean, Popey, don't you think maybe the internet is killing the Lug a little bit because we're
more connected now where we go off into our community silos and we just hyper interact
there?
Sure.
And I know when the Linux user group nearest me first started, it was one of these ones
that was a mailing list on the end of a dial up line so you might get a batch of mail every
couple of days or something when the guy dialed in and processed all the requests.
And now you can probably get an answer to your question before the modem has finished
negotiating the call.
So here's what I worry, though, is there really truly is something to that meat space connection.
When I go to Linux Fest Northwest or I go to PAX and I shake the hand of a Linux action
show listener or I don't know, does Brian2040 leave?
No, I'm still here.
Right.
Like Brian2040, he was a name in the chat room until one day he's driving my truck home
when I'm too sick to drive it, right?
And they become real people.
And that meat space connection, I think, is easy to sort of undervalue on the Internet.
And I worry that lugs brought like it like now with like laptops and all this, like lugs
seem like they could do more good than ever.
But I agree with Popeye.
It seems like they've faded big time.
Yeah, and I agree with you.
There is there is that element of personal interaction.
And I agree with you that there are some people of an older generation in our local lug.
But that works in both ways.
There's a guy who's recently had to go to hospital and spent time in hospital with a
netbook and found that he it was difficult for him to type.
So, you know, we rallied the troops and sent a mail to the lug and I guess the keyboard
they send him.
Yeah, that kind of stuff.
I feel like the reason why the lugs in my area are populated by the graybeards, the
older guys, is because they're more socially adjusted and they're more socially balanced
because they haven't been perverted by the easiness of the Internet that allows them
to create these fake social connections that don't truly connect them at a human level
to another person.
What the actual lugs do.
And I feel like we're losing something there.
If I may interject, because LinuxFast Northwest was like my first really big festival I went
to, at least in my experience.
And you know, from what I've heard and it's just it just in and that sort of environment
where it's more of a development festival almost, it feels like lugs are growing at
the same time.
A second ago, he's saying that lugs also were a place where you could actually get help.
And when it got to the point, honestly, like it's so easy to just help yourself now.
Right.
The Google factor.
How easy it is to take a USB stick and install it and boot you on it, like you get it done
in 20 minutes by yourself.
Right.
Whereas before you go to a lug to have somebody walk you through the Slackware installation.
Yeah, exactly.
So I don't really I don't really agree with you guys.
Because I'm one of the officers of the lug at UCLA, University of California, Los Angeles.
And at least in my experience, we hold install fest every quarter, we give talks and stuff.
And at least in the at least in our academic, like the realm of students and stuff, a lot
of people just are never introduced into Linux.
And then by the time they do in classes or whatever, they are introduced to such a cursory
level that they need an extra place to go to to get the kind of help they need.
So do you is the majority of your users group a fellow college students?
Yeah.
And then we also have professors and people from around the area.
Okay.
I think a lot of Los Angeles has scale, obviously, which I've been doing a couple times, it's
just an awesome conference.
But it does happen to be I mean, we have media temple and a lot of the big companies that
are very focused on open source software.
But it does seem that a lot of the focus is in the industry and isn't big companies.
As far as the community scale, and there's a couple other lugs around LA.
But we're definitely one of the biggest on the west side.
And we're still not very big.
But it I think it helps that we're part of university also.
So do you guys meet on a regular basis?
Yeah, so we have meetings every week.
Okay.
And how was the attendance like on those?
So we probably have seven or eight extremely active people who come to every meeting.
We have a lot of legacy users and one of the a lot of legacy members.
And we have a lot of people hang on to RSC, or I'll come to install fast and stuff.
But in terms of active is maybe 10 people.
So it's still not very many that come to every single meeting or whatever.
Go ahead.
I mean, I was gonna say, for the longest time, I actually hung out in the IRC of a Linux
user group that started out actually as an Ubuntu Loco.
They were Ubuntu Loco Kentucky, and then they went to Bluegrass Linux user group.
It was active for a while.
I went to a few meetings in 2011.
But it's really tapered off.
A lot of the major members moved down to Texas, I think.
And then I myself ended up moving out to Kansas.
Yeah, see, I found it moved the other way where I am.
There was a distinct move from geographically centered Linux user groups, like in the UK,
you have one per county, and I'm sure you have one per state or one per city in the
US.
It moved to a UK wide Ubuntu Loco.
Like I moved that way.
And a lot of people move that way, too.
And then there were various other distro specific groups as well, which kind of made the Locos,
the Lugs somewhat less populated and less utilized.
Geographically, I have to say, that's probably a lot easier to do in the UK than it would
be in the United States.
In my area, the user group in my area is very scarce.
So there was one Lug that was here for a couple of years, and it's been just disbanded, but
it's been replaced by a meetup group for just Linux users.
Yeah, that's the thing that hindered me from going to a lot of meetings is I was in Louisville,
Kentucky, and I was younger at the time, and most of the meetings were over in Lexington,
Kentucky, so a majority of the time, I couldn't make it.
Yeah, see, I'm in North Georgia, and of course, as a person that uses Linux that I know personally,
I mean, I don't know him, but Brian, he was probably like an hour from me, just to kind
of give you an example, it's just spread out all over the place.
Is there some value in a Linux user's group that exists virtually, like this Mumble Room
right now is as big as some Lug attendees are, right?
And the IRC is many times larger.
Right now, 367 people in the IRC right now are chatting about Linux related topics, way
bigger than a local Lug.
So is the amount of connectivity and the frequency of connectivity and the availability of information
and help, does that in some ways, I guess if the end goal is Linux adoption, if the
end goal is getting people using Linux, doesn't this new model where the Lug plays less of
a role still promote Linux on the desktop more?
I completely agree.
I remember that.
And the reason being is that in my area, there aren't very many even computer user groups,
let alone Linux user groups, or even, I was looking for an Ubuntu Loco for some time ago.
The closest one is over the Seattle area, and then there's another one that's in Boise,
Idaho.
That's the next closest.
Right.
That's just how it is here too.
There's like nothing computer-related groups like that.
Yeah, that's a big factor, especially in the US, is there's massive groups of areas that
don't have other technology enthusiast groups.
But at the same time, going back to the IRC thing, IRC has been around since like a dawn
of time.
So here in Kansas, the closest Linux user group to me is the Kansas City, Missouri one,
although that doesn't seem all that active.
It's more than that, I see.
It's like for me, I live in a huge city center, I live in Toronto, and I can't get to their
local user group because it's so packed and I'm on such a small time straight.
Interesting.
I also think that the idea that an online friendship, an online relationship is a lot
considered a lot more legitimate these days than it was 10 years ago.
True.
I remember some five, six years ago when Lug Radio, John O'Bacon, Stuart Langridge podcast
was going.
Right.
There's a guy in France, there's an IRC channel and it's still going now, hash lug radio on
free node, long after the podcast finished.
Podcast finished six years ago and the IRC channel is still there and people still come
in there and say, good morning, morning everyone, there's still a community around it.
And I remember Bruno, a guy from France who listened to the podcast and was always in
the IRC channel said, lug radio is my lug.
And this was five, six years ago, he saw this online virtual community as his Linux user
group, as the people he was empathic with that he could relate to.
This could be the Irish schnapps talking, but you guys literally are my lug.
Oh, I love you too.
I mean, same here.
You know, Chris, when you mentioned something earlier about, you know, when you met Brian
at the Linux Fest Northwest, you know, that kind of reminded me how earlier this year
I also helped Brian pack his stuff when he was moving from Southern Indiana down to Georgia.
Right.
Well, that is really the interesting thing is there are members in like our IRC chat
room that have been met up in real life.
Like Brian, didn't you meet up with Mail Hauler?
Twice, actually.
Met up with Tyler, Mail Hauler and his entire family and you, Angela, and Ty the Geek over
at Linux Fest.
So yeah, lots of people.
I mean, it is hard out going home for Brian too from Atlanta.
I actually plan on certain early this year saving up to get a plane ticket to head out
towards Linux Fest Northwest in April.
Oh, man.
Awesome.
See, this makes me want to get the studio started up because then we could have like
a spot for everybody to come hang out after Linux Fest Northwest.
That would be cool.
Yeah, I would love to go up there too.
Yeah, that would be a lot of fun.
What's happened to Lugs is that all the simple support stuff has gone online and now it's
just the dedicated users that go to these hyper-focused events like hackerspaces or
in their towns or these conventions.
See, hackerspaces are different though because hackers are like more like computer centric
focused.
So there's a big overlap there though, if I go to any of my hackspaces nearby, they're
the same kind of people like, you know, people who want to take things apart and make them
work the way they want to don't necessarily want to use devices the way that the manufacturer
intended.
They're the same kind of ethic that we have.
Yeah, it is.
So I totally agree with Popeye because at least in LA, we have DevOps LA meetups and
different infrastructure like industry type user groups and in many ways, I think those
have replaced the Lug movement because as more and more people want Linux professionals,
they kind of congregate within their own professional groups rather than these informal Lug type
situations.
Well, and it's interesting too as new Linux based technologies take off like Android online,
the communities solely seem to be forming online, right?
And very large ones like the XDA form.
Oh, Bruce Phoenix actually just had an awesome idea.
What if you got your new studio and turn it into a Jupiter broadcasting hackerspace?
Oh, that would be cool.
You know, we would have a garage so there is possibilities.
And you know, if you made that new studio, you could have a couple interns too.
All right, well, interesting thoughts.
You know, I'd love to hear also if anyone out in the download audience has experience
with a local Linux users group or runs one or is involved with one.
We'd love to hear what you think.
Go over to Jupiterbroadcasting.com and pop that contact link at the top of the site.
There is actually a Linux unplugged drop down there.
Any other closing thoughts you guys like on the Lug topic?
I have all I got to say is coming April, party at the J.B. studio.
Yeah, I agree.
All right, Matt.
Well, also, when it comes to things, well, I was going for most of this topic.
Well for me, all those groups, all those groups, they're more of the follow up from the old
school computer clubs that used to do the old hardware stuff and the old OS stuff.
I wouldn't discount them because of that, though.
Well, they never had the Internet back at that time.
No, I agree.
It was just being like invented.
But there is something about seeing somebody else do something in Linux that makes you
go, oh, I could do that when you see it happen.
I'll tell you this.
The reason I say this is because for years I went to clients and a few of these clients
I would have like the tech savvy guy or gal that worked there who was like the tech person
for the company.
And when she would see Compiz on my Linux machine, that was the coolest thing ever.
And that made her or him want to run Linux.
If I can say something, honestly, that kind of concept is what actually, because I'd say
my first experience with that was actually watching the Linux action show.
That's kind of how I got into it in the first place.
And now you're spinning out your own distro.
Yes.
Yeah, that's interesting.
So I think for myself, what really killed the whole Lug situation really comes down
to the following.
I poked in and out of the Bellingham Lug for a few years, just real occasional.
And I found it remarkable how it felt like Groundhog Day, no new faces, always the same
folks, great folks, awesome people.
But it was just the same thing over and over.
And honestly, it's like even online, it's hard to get that stale.
So for me, I stopped attending just because I was really not getting anything new from
it.
Everybody used OpenSUSE, and if you didn't, you weren't, or not OpenSUSE, but a SUSE
at the time.
It was very much an echo changer.
Yeah, I could see the echo chamber in the same old stories over and over again.
So that sounds like a Lug that's kind of given up on recruiting.
And they're kind of in a rut.
Because we've had an experience where this year we did a pretty heavy recruiting drive
with all the club fairs and stuff at our school.
It's basically just about you need to, because we're in a room in the bottom of the engineering
building and unless you know about us, unless you have discovery, no one's going to know
we're here.
I would say from what you're saying is that the Lug is most likely to live on the best
in a college campus.
Yeah, I would agree with that.
And the thing is, is the college campus doesn't really, as much as, I totally dig that Cognizant
was talking about a Lug and that's awesome, but to me it seems like it's only successful
because you kind of have a captive audience.
It's easy to message to them because they're all in one location and they're sort of already
there.
And you got people churned.
You got new faces at least.
Right.
Oh, great point.
Isn't that what a business would want if they want to hire people who know Linux?
And they want to team up with somebody who's attracting other young, fresh blood who are
coming through the colleges?
It's funny you mention that.
It's funny you mention that because that's one of the primary reasons we exist.
Our school is a typical high level CS department where they really don't teach a lot of practical
skills.
Because in CS and academic levels, almost like math, it's like math for computer programs.
And to teach, like for example, I've been doing a lot of work professionally with Puppet
and very different DevOps, vagrant stuff, type CS integration stuff.
And those are skills that I basically taught myself.
And I've gotten jobs because I've known these skills from teaching myself.
And when there's an interest group where we give talks about these things and we have
other people who are interested in them, like I've had, I'm not going to name names, I think
it's probably not the best thing, but we've had very massive companies come and trying
to partner directly with us and give sponsor talks and things to try and attract our members.
So they're looking for talent.
They're looking for hires?
Yeah.
So like I've gotten three jobs from, I don't know, I don't know if it's directly from the
Lug, but it's from just knowing these things and having that kind of interest.
That actually makes a lot of sense, right?
Because these companies don't know quite how to find these people.
And a Lug is something they can see, something they understand, something they can approach
and they can come to the Lug and say, we're looking for somebody who is talented NGINX
and et cetera, et cetera, right?
So this is something that is actually, I was talking to the Facebook recruiter and she
was telling me, okay, so Facebook has this position called production engineer.
And the reason this position exists is because the software engineers they hire don't know
enough about the infrastructure backbone to make the kind of decisions they have to make
about how will this application run in production.
And so a lot of what happens is a software engineer will end up learning a lot of these
skills after they've been on the job for a while and then transition to this role.
Well, another thing is if you remember at Linux Fest Northwest, Chris, that lots of
job recruiting people are also there like Dice.com was there.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's true.
That's a great point.
And I think part of that is because some of these companies have their foot in the old
world and they really haven't figured out how to approach a community.
Like if you think about it, like if you were trying to hire a sys admin or you're trying
to hire somebody to take care of your backend infrastructure, dude, I would totally troll
the Linux action show subreddit, but these companies haven't figured it out, right?
They haven't figured it out, but what they have figured out is Lugs and user conferences.
That's a great point.
I didn't even think about.
And now that I think about it, if I was going to hire somebody for like to handle the Jupiter
broadcasting backend, that's probably where I would look to actually.
Yeah, it makes a lot of sense.
Yeah, it does make a lot of sense.
I never even thought about the employment aspect.
And so, I mean, that's probably another argument for like, how do we figure out how to rejuvenate
the Lug and does it need to be rebooted?
Okay.
Let me ask.
Mumbo room.
Let me ask you this and Popey, I want to start with you because you're the one that brought
up the topic.
So I think you should get first shot at this.
Would a Google Hangout replace a Lug?
No, because the people that you want to get involved are highly opinionated and the kind
of people who wouldn't touch Google Hangouts with a barge pole.
Well, okay.
I'll give you that on the last part.
But let's look at the Ubuntu Developer Summits.
You guys have moved to these virtual summits and you're still getting a lot of stuff done.
There's a lot of discussions that are happening.
People are able to attend because they're able to just connect in.
You're seeing each other face to face.
I mean, there's productivity happening there.
Isn't it better than nothing?
Yeah, but UDS is a very different animal than Lugs.
And we all have Google accounts by virtue of the fact that we have a Google set up.
Oh, that's a good point.
Not everybody has a Google account.
But Lugs are the place where you find people who buy Android phones and then immediately
flash them so they don't ever have to connect to Google or the kinds of people who refuse
to have smartphones.
I'm not saying there's anything bad about that, but it's a different type of person
in a Lug.
All right.
Isn't that the problem?
Don't we need to reboot the Lug and make it more modernized that way guys like me who
want as I want a 12 core processor, maybe I want two of them in my box, I want 64 gigs
of RAM.
Why don't we reboot the Lug for that guy?
So you're saying that's exactly what to turn it into.
Having it turn into a hack fest type thing would be more similar to the old school's
Lug.
At the same time though, that's like Linux was for those people who wanted not to use
them.
Like it's for open and free software and not like hangouts.
Also, when you're in some person, all the creative juices happen a little bit better
and you're more competitive when you're in person versus just the internet.
That's interesting.
It makes you think better and harder about what the hell to counteract this guy's idea.
A few years ago on OMG Ubuntu, which is a popular blog you may have heard of, Benjamin
Humphrey who used to write for them wrote a post about neck beards and he got a massive
negative feedback from the community because he was basically having a pop at people in
the way that you're suggesting that we should move on and maybe we should involve younger
blood who want faster processors and the JavaScript and that kind of thing of today rather than
COBOL and mainframes and 26s.
You are blaming me for stereotyping when you are saying that all these people at Lugs are
old school mainframe COBOL guys and I'm saying that stereotyping of Lug, you are really sir.
Really sir.
What I'm saying is that he made that kind of suggestion and he got a lot of flack for
it and rightly so because what the reaction was actually that people, what you're doing
now and in the future is built on the shoulders of what the people did before you.
If those Lugs didn't exist three years ago, ten years ago, then your podcast wouldn't
exist.
Yeah, isn't that true?
Do you see what I mean?
Yeah, I do.
What's come out of this to me is that you need...
This podcast is almost like the recording of a huge Lug meeting.
I'd say a community though has to center itself around far more than just a Google Plus hangout.
There needs to be more substance to it.
But you've also got to have, you've got to close the loop locally like what's happening
at Cogsues College, so you need two separate things.
The online stuff is going to solve itself and happen and is happening right now, but
you need to close the loop locally.
I think you might be onto something there because going back to the Linux Fest Northwest,
it's like it is truly one thing to know these people and hear their voices, but to actually
shake their hand, see them as a human with their flaws and with their pluses that you
never knew about until you saw them personally.
Like I really, really love my truck, okay?
I really love my truck, and I gave the keys to my truck to Brian2040, and I think that
no other man, maybe with the exception of one or two other men, have ever driven my
truck and will never drive my truck.
I will make that point right now, will never drive my truck, but I gave it to Brian2040.
Part of it was because I knew him in the IRC, but then I met him and there's a connection
that is made.
And it's interesting, I think-
Get a room.
I remember Chris standing out there with a food box in his bathroom, but you also had
to point out you were violently ill as well, so-
I was quite sick.
My options were limited.
That is true.
I remember very clearly as Chris looks me dead in the eyes, deadpan serious, and says,
dude, I don't feel good.
And I was like, oh, okay.
I was like, no, Matt, really, I don't know what's going to happen, and I'm just like,
oh, crap.
Yeah, we were actually all concerned because Chris went out into his car and then it was
just nothing for like two hours.
Yeah.
It was funny.
He died.
I kept thinking like, I'll get better.
I'll get better.
I'll be all right.
I'll be okay.
But I will tell you that it wasn't for Angela coming in and basically looping all of us
together, because we're a bunch of trained monkeys going in circles.
She was the one that set us straight and made sure we got things done.
So I got to give props to her on that one, big time.
Big time.
I'll be all right.
It's just a flesh wound.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
Oh, yeah.
No, he was so...
I felt so bad.
I totally see the closing the loop argument.
But unfortunately, that's not a practical...
So people listening to us in the UK, they can't realistically attend Linux Fest Northwest
and shake our hands.
So I want to offer something to them.
I want to say to them that even though you're not visiting the Lug, you're still part of
an overall larger community.
Yeah.
Hugs for Lugs.
What you need is you need to start a fundraiser so you could take a trip with the family over
to the United Kingdom to have a meetup there.
Once I get the staying on the air thing figured out and the studio thing figured out and the
doing Linux action shows and Linux unplugged on location thing figured out, then it's the
travel to the UK thing I got to figure out.
So Chris, let me know when you're coming over to the UK so I can go to another country.
Ouch.
The poppy that hurts on the inside, deep down.
Wow.
We're Americans.
We like our little angry bubble.
All right.
We love our ignorance.
Okay.
Now, this is...
This is the...
Oh, boy.
These are the final thoughts.
You know, the Linux action show went down to the Ubuntu one conference back when they
did these things in the meet space and that was a good time.
That was actually a really good time.
So all right.
Any final thoughts, you guys on the Lug?
I know Ixl, you were thinking about...
Ixl, what you think about starting the Lug on your own?
I thought about it and kind of played around with the idea, but with me moving, there's
no real sense in doing it over here.
So I mean, if there's anybody else like in the chat room, I saw somebody else from the
Spokane area.
Oh, he just found spokane-linux.org.
How about that?
That's actually pretty cool.
All right.
Well, it's an interesting topic and it's one that I'd love to hear the audience sort of
at large.
Like, I wonder if maybe because we're living on the West Coast, we're right by...
I mean, I think I could get to Microsoft in 45 minutes if traffic was good.
You could throw rocks at them from the house.
So maybe they're interfering with my thought process just because of the proximity.
So if you are living out there and you have a rocking Lug, we'd love to hear about it.
And I know they're out there, like our Bellingham Lug puts on Linux Fest Northwest every single
year and those guys are awesome.
The Everett Lug is nearby and they're working out on some pretty cool stuff, but I'd love
to hear what you guys are doing.
So go over to jupitabroadcasting.com and pop that contact link and let us know what's happening
in your neck of the woods.
And don't forget, we're doing a double back, back-to-back special of Linux Unplugged next
week.
So join us for that.
We'd love to get you in the mumble room.
That'll be on the 17th starting at 12 p.m. Pacific over at jblive.tv.
Don't know what time that is in your local area?
That's okay.
It's okay.
We've got a jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar and it uses secret technology that automatically
converts it to your local time zone.
I don't even know how that's possible.
It's some sort of...
Munchkins and gremlins.
It's some sort of, yeah, exactly, right?
I think we've had munchkins and gremlins that have been working on our website named Hymer
16 and they are incredible.
All right, Matt, well coming up on Sunday, we'll have a look at the Leopard Extreme.
I'm punishing it right now as we speak.
So and I know we've got more to talk about too so I want everybody to go over to jupitabroadcasting.com
and go watch our last episode of Linux Action Show if you didn't catch that and then tune
in next week.
We've got a big one where I'm taking the Leopard Extreme, the real System76 Mac Pro competitor
and we'll see how it holds up to a production workload.
Definitely.
All right, Matt.
Well, I'll see you on Sunday, okay?
See you on Sunday.
Okay, everyone.
Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll see you on Sunday for the big show and we'll see you right back here on Tuesday
for the next episode of Linux Unplugged.
Thanks so much.
Take care.
Bye-bye.