So, Rotten Corpse is in here, let's, Rotten Corpse here.
So we're in the, you know, pre-show discussion thread, and I'm sitting there grousing about
the fact that I've done two installations of Ubuntu 16.04 today.
One the Mate flavor, and one regular flavor, and I'm downloading Kubuntu 16.04.
And I'm starting to grouse a little bit about the fact that I want Plasma 5.6 as my desktop,
and there's no reasonable way to get Plasma 5.6 on Ubuntu 16.04.
You have to use either A, Ubuntu 15.10, and then use Neon, or B, wait for the backports
packages to get updated for 15.10, and download it that way.
But there's really no way to get it for 16.04, because Neon is based on 15.10 right now,
so it expects 15.10 repos and 15.10 packages to be pre-installed, and 16.04, there's no
official way, there's no repo out there to get the Plasma 5.6 desktop.
So I'm sitting here grousing about this, and you know what Rodden Corp says to me?
He says, that's just a sign of a lack of patience.
I disagree.
I'm going to go farther than Rodden Corp's and say that Ubuntu and Canonical should probably
just focus on doing, you know, Unity on.
Oh, for, they absolutely, well that's what they do.
That's all they do.
Yeah, that's what they do.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, you know, even the community members that are now being supported and stuff, yeah,
see if they want to, you know, but outside of the project, I would go for that way.
No, here's where I think it's weird, is it's weird to me that something that's the latest
in development isn't available for something that's in the latest in development.
I understand why, right?
Oh, because we haven't had a chance to base it and test it.
It seems like, it just seems like such an old way of doing software, it feels so weird
that I want to install the latest version of Ubuntu and I don't get to install the latest
version of a Plasma desktop.
Like those two things, like I can't believe those two things coexist.
And if this is not, this is not an impossible problem to solve and other distributions have
solved this problem, some of them fundamentally from the way they're based and others just
using other tricks.
It just, it really kind of strikes me as having now, I'm not trying to make this an Arch versus
Ubuntu thing, but now being two years or plus deep into using Arch and then now using Ubuntu
leading up to our review, it really strikes me as a totally old way of doing things, much
like when you go back on a system that uses a really old init system like we're going
to talk about later today, right?
It really feels like a super, or like if you install a distribution that doesn't have a
gooey partitioner and you have to use F disk or CF disk, like that's fine.
And you know, okay, I kind of remember how to do that, but it seems like I shouldn't
have to do that anymore.
So it's not like, it's not a matter of impatience, it just seems like an old model, an old way
of delivering software on a system that is constant, like it's, if 1604 is like as cutting
edges you can get for Ubuntu and you still can't get cutting edge packages on it, I fundamentally
understand the mechanics and the reasons why, but to me it seems like we should have solved
this by now.
There's also another little detail, it's an understanding of marketing.
I mean, if you are going to try and have a bad experience, even though it's development
and you know it's development, you're going to talk bad about it.
And so they actually have something to protect versus the other, don't necessarily have
that protection.
I'm not even talking about canonical shipping anything or Ubuntu releasing anything.
I'm just simply coming down to, it's really weird to me that there are packages for some
Ubuntu systems that I can install on some systems.
Like for example, I almost guarantee you I could install a Kubuntu 15.10, get all the
prereqs that I need installed, install Neon, upgrade the son of a bitch to 1604 with Neon
still installed and I bet you it would run just fine.
Like if I just rejigger the approach, if I jump through these hoops appropriately, I
could trick the software into installing through the package manager.
I shouldn't have to do that though, it's weird.
I'm not talking about who's releasing what or what community is supporting what, I'm
talking about fundamentally this is an old way of managing your software on a Linux box.
It's just weird and it's good by the way that I'm bitching about this now, let me tell you
why.
Because I'm getting all of this out of my system before it comes time to actually do
the review.
So by the time I actually sit down and review Ubuntu 1604, this will be old news to me.
And it's honestly, it's because what I'm doing is because I'm testing the different desktops,
I keep redoing installations so I keep setting up from scratch with new installs and I tell
you what, it has been tedious.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 138 for March 29th, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's been installing distributions
all morning long.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hey there, Wes.
It has been an install fest here at the JB1 studio.
It always is.
That's true.
But it's really kicked up into high gear recently.
I've been going through and installing different iterations of Ubuntu 1604 for upcoming review.
Oh my gosh, I got thoughts on that.
But that's not actually what we're here to talk about today.
Coming up on the Unplugged program, we have a whole bunch of updates on some of our favorite
open source projects at the top of the show.
Then I'll give you my tale of ordering the new Ubuntu tablet, the first Ubuntu tablet
available for pre-order.
Have you seen this thing?
Yeah.
We're going to talk about that.
And then later on in the show, Wes, prepare your body, prepare yourself, Linux distributions
are old news.
We have two brand new Unix eyes, one that is actually based on Linux and one that says
Linux could learn a few things from us.
We're going to give you our thoughts on these two game changers, as they call themselves.
And then later on, towards the end of the show, I've got a little bit of a fast update.
And Wes, you will testify to this.
I had to write it down.
There's so much to cover.
Oh, it's complex.
Right?
I was pen and paper writing this down because I can remember it, you know?
So a lot in the show today.
A lot to cover.
But before we start any of that, we really can go no further without bringing in that
mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings there, virtual dog.
Hello.
Pip pip.
So I just mentioned a few seconds ago, so you probably heard me say it, that I was installing
me a whole lot of Ubuntu earlier today.
And I got to say, right here, I think the software boutique might be the best thing
to happen to Ubuntu since Ubuntu.
Wow.
Straight up, full stop.
The software boutique, I think it is now going on anything that is Ubuntu-based, regardless
if it is the Mate desktop environment or not.
And Wimpy, I wanted to ask you if you have considered releasing this, I know it must
rely on apt heavily and PPAs.
This could really be a thing.
I mean, this is a great tool.
And so it must be possible to use it on other Ubuntus, correct?
Yes.
It's all built using the same tools that power things like the Ubuntu software updater and
stuff like that.
So do I add it as a PPA if I'm on a different spin of Ubuntu, or how does that work?
Well, the software boutique is part and parcel of Ubuntu Mate welcome.
So if you install Ubuntu-Mate-welcome on any Ubuntu, it will just install.
Okay so Ubuntu, I'm doing it right now, it's welcome, see, okay, let's see here.
I have this on this neon machine, let's see, whoa, that's a whole lot of packages it wants
to pull down there.
Yeah, if you're on a KDE machine, it's going to need a lot of GTK dependencies.
It is though, I have to tell you, when I sit down and I set up a machine, I can launch
the software boutique, what I think is really great about it, Wimpy, is the application
choice is, I don't know if it was you that picked them or who, who picked the applications
that are featured?
So it was myself and Matt Hartley and Luke Corwell, who's the primary developer for software
boutique and welcome now.
You guys nailed it.
Interesting.
You guys totally nailed it.
It's just, it's the good stuff and it takes care of all of the clunky PPA stuff in the
background and it's just click, click, click, click and you're going, all right, so my installation
is done.
So now if I would, would I just run welcome or boutique?
I probably want to run the software.
So you can find either Ubuntu mate welcome or the software boutique in the control center
hopefully.
I mean it's KDE though so I don't know where you find it but from the terminal, you can
run Ubuntu dash mate dash welcome and then hang on, I'm going to give you the secret
source.
So it's Ubuntu dash mate dash welcome space, dash, dash, software dash only.
Ah, okay.
Type that in and it is launching and then yeah, okay, software.
Brilliant, brilliant, brilliant, brilliant.
Thank you.
So now I can make this rig even better.
Perfect.
I love it.
This is such a nice tool.
It's worth installing all those dependencies for me.
Maybe it should be in one of those app image containers.
Yeah, I described it as it makes installing Ubuntu easier than Antigros, which that's
really something.
That's a lot, yeah.
That's really something.
But I mean it's one click.
And that's the whole point.
You know, the whole point is this is supposed to be a low barrier of entry install system
of just the stuff you need for people new to Ubuntu or lazy people like me.
So I'm sure everyone in the mumble room and everyone that's listening has done this.
You have a collection of scripts that you can somewhere and when you install a new machine,
you then run a whole swathe of shell scripts which install this and that and configure
things where you want.
And this is taking all of those scripts of things I used to install and just putting
them in one place that anyone can use.
You're sharing them with everyone.
And how does it work?
Why does it work on both 1510 and 1604?
Because when I try to add a PPAs for one, it doesn't work for the other.
So how does that work exactly?
What are you doing on the back end?
So on the back end, there's a small database which is just a JSON file called applications.json.
It's very, you know, cleverly named.
And in there, it's a list of all of the applications and it has some properties in there.
So it will say something like this piece of software only works on I386 and I864 or this
piece of software is compatible with trusty Wiley and Xenial.
But then it will say on trusty and Wiley use this PPA on Xenial use the official archive.
And on this one, because I'm like on some neon hybrid, it says, OK, it's not available
for this one.
OK.
I try to install it.
The operating system that you're using should be Wiley, right?
What have you installed?
This here, this is a 1510 with neon and they changed some of the repo stuff.
Right.
OK.
So that will work as though it's Wiley.
Yeah.
So, for example, if there's stuff that hasn't been released for Xenial yet, you won't see
it in the 1604 version, but you will see it in the Wiley version.
Yeah.
And it looks like my GTK theme.
So whatever desktop theme I'm using, it looks it looks nice.
It looks actually really good under plasma to a surprise.
Yeah, it really isn't offensive.
It's really and if you run if you run welcome itself, there's a little button in the top
of welcome where it's going to also appear in the software boutique as well to say subscribe
to updates.
And what that does is that actually keeps your version of welcome and the software boutique
in step with the absolute latest stuff as new applications become available.
So when, for example, Oracle release VirtualBox Xenial, that will turn up in the software
boutique for you and other things like that will just sort of come online as the support
gets added.
Isn't that a nice tool when you're on a new distro like that and stuff isn't completely
ready at launch, that is just show up when it's ready.
I would argue that it shouldn't be a problem in the first place, but you know, that is
actually pretty good.
I would say that.
So I just wanted to say thank you because it was a heck of a tool for me today as I
was setting up three different Ubuntu rigs and now I just put it on a plasma desktop.
So there you go.
It works from all over.
You can use it anywhere.
Yeah, you really can.
You really can.
All right.
So before we go too much further, I should mention we are enjoying ourselves a Fremont
interurban do you think, Wes?
IPA.
Well, there you go.
Because beer matters.
So that's our – so if you in the lug there have yourself some beverage, you can crack
it open now.
There it is.
And that's what we'll be enjoying.
It is ranked at 86 which is pretty good, very good actually.
And it has a –
Just a few minutes south.
Yeah?
Really?
Down in Fremont in Seattle.
Oh, they've been that free.
You have been nailing the local beers lately.
I do what I can.
Are you doing that on purpose, Wes?
Maybe.
A little local flair.
You know what would be great?
We should treat the guys when they come out for Linux Fest.
Mm-hmm.
All right.
We'll save that for the Linux Fest talk coming up.
Let's do some updates.
This one caught both Wes and my attention today and we're like, okay, this might be
something worth talking about.
There is hubbub coming out from Mary Jo Foley over at All Things About Microsoft at the
ZDNet talking about day one of build Microsoft might announce an Ubuntu-based bash shell
running on top of Windows 10.
What?
Yeah.
It seems that bash on Ubuntu will figure in somehow.
Bash is a Linux shell, she mentions.
I don't know if you knew that.
Did you know that?
No.
I was going to ask.
I'm glad you said.
Stands for the born shell.
She says.
That's what she says right there.
Stands for, and it has plugins, she says.
Ooh.
I love it when Mary Jo, who I respect, is trying to cover a Linux technology.
That's right.
She just is so often.
That's good though.
She's doing a good job.
To employ text commands.
Yes.
I love that ability.
Thanks, Bash.
So as someone has noted on Twitter today, there's already ways of getting bash shell
of course running on Windows, which was news to Mary Jo, which of course as we all know
is Sigwin, but Microsoft has been brewing on something that goes a step beyond that.
In Redstone builds, which are new builds of Windows 10 spotted recently, there was a Linux
subsystem added to Windows 10, a Linux subsystem in the new builds of Windows 10, and so we
might find very soon at the build conference, which is, I don't know, coming up soon.
Doesn't really matter.
Coming up soon, the build 26 developer conference, we may see them launch Bash based on Ubuntu
on Windows 10.
Popey, are you switching?
From what to what?
Well now you can have your Ubuntu command line with your Windows 10 desktop environment.
What else do you need?
Cortana.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
So I could say to Cortana, RM minus RF slash.
I hope so.
I hope they, I mean if they're dumb enough to put that stupid Tay AI robot online, they
might be dumb enough to make it that easy.
You know, speaking, I mean, not to pile up on Microsoft right now, but can we just take
a minute and just talk about how out of touch they are?
Like the idea that the reason why, the idea that them putting a bash shell on Windows
is what's going to keep me developing on Windows is kind of adorable.
And it just shows how disconnected they are from what people actually want.
Much like this commercial about the Microsoft cloud helping the digital crimes unit fight,
you guessed it, cyber crime.
Check this thing out.
The biggest challenge for business today is not competition.
Okay, the biggest challenge is what?
Cyber crime.
You got it, buddy.
It's protecting customer trust.
Every day you read headlines about governments and businesses being hacked, emails compromised,
and intellectual property being stolen.
That is cyber crime and it affects each and every one of us.
So how do we fix this?
Cloud dude.
Oh.
Microsoft created the digital crimes unit to investigate and fight cyber crime.
They don't have any big screens right now.
They use the Microsoft cloud to visualize information so we can track down the criminals.
So they use the cloud to visualize information so they can track down criminals.
And what they're showing here is a huge screen, which is literally sitting in front of a huge
screen.
Do you see that?
Are these bigger or smaller than this Fox News giant screen?
They're about the same size.
But do you see what they literally are doing is they are literally standing in front of
a screen that is blocking their field of view, which is then in front of it another larger
screen that they probably literally cannot even see while they're doing pinch to zoom
on a cloud powered map because they have cloud.
We use the Microsoft cloud to visualize information so we can track down the criminals.
Using our advanced analytics tools, analysis that used to take days to run, we can now
see in real time.
And we're building what we learned back into the cloud to make...
So here's what else is really weird is you notice how they keep zooming in on the United
States.
Like they keep showing cities and stuff in the US like they're watching the United States
traffic.
But I guess, you know, when you have the cloud, you're everywhere.
Back into the cloud to make people and organizations safer.
When it comes to the cloud, trust and security are paramount.
Our passion is making life tougher for cybercriminals and making it safer for you and your customers.
Microsoft come run Ubuntu on our cloud.
Don't let that baby on the internet.
Like that's what's so great about the Microsoft cloud is that more and more it's used to run
Linux.
So yeah, have that at everybody.
Isn't that great?
Yep.
Yeah.
Honestly, the company that's got the most egregious terms of use and YOLO out there
that is totally designed to invade your privacy at the drop of a hat is trying to pitch their
cloud platform as the opposite of that.
Wimby, I would ask you this one basic question.
Where do you think they're getting all of the metrics that they use to visualize and
put back into the Microsoft cloud to hunt cybercrime?
Where do you suppose those metrics come from?
I can't imagine.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Hmm.
I wonder where that is.
They also have a new other upside, which is the telcos are moving to put their infrastructure
on quote unquote cloud.
And they're pretty much actually hiring a lot.
If you look at most of the mobile companies and telcos are hiring people for cloud development
of their infrastructure technology.
Yeah.
Cloud.
Okay.
We're not going to spend a lot of time on this, but there is a significant amount of
game news updates to do really briefly that we're just going to spend a couple of moments.
And the first one is partially because it takes me back to when I finally had to save
up my own money to get my own first Matrox graphic card.
And this Matrox graphics card had this expandable RAM module to go up to like eight megabytes
of RAM.
No way.
Or four megs maybe.
I can't remember.
That forever changed my gaming.
Tomb Raider.
And now it's coming to Linux again.
So much has happened.
I'm super excited about this game just because I've been wanting to play a Tomb Raider game.
Our captain is injured.
Have you heard from any of the others?
Nothing.
Takes me way back.
Our crew is exhausted.
It sure does.
I have a bad feeling about this.
So Tomb Raider is coming out for the Linux desktop soon.
And we don't have a date yet, but we have details in the show notes that say reboot
is going to hit Linux and Steam OS this spring is the guesstimated ship date, so stay tuned
for that.
Another game coming out, Two Worlds 3, which is in development, and Two Worlds 2 is coming
to Linux.
That's only a little confusing.
Right.
Two Worlds 3, which is likely to come to Linux, which is in development, and Two Worlds 2,
which is getting an engine remake, graphics assets, a new DLC is coming to Linux.
So that's a game coming.
And then another game that's actually hit public beta right now, hitting Linux within
the last week, is Darkest Dungeon, which is a roguelike turn-based RPG, which just got
its public beta.
And I will just give you a brief taste of what it's like.
There is a great horror beneath the manor, a crawling chaos that must be destroyed.
The task ahead is terrible, and weakness cannot be tolerated.
So that's Darkest Dungeon, and the public beta is out right now.
So there you go.
Oh, and one more, Payday 2, which has had a bit of controversy in the past, has hit
Steam OS and is going free for the rest of March to play online.
And they're doing it specifically to celebrate the Steam OS launch.
So if you want to throw a little love, nothing out of pocket, I don't think, to get Payday
2, at least not for the online play.
So there you go.
That concludes your Valve Steam game Linux proprietary gaming update.
Faster than ever.
Yeah.
I tried to bust through it super fast for those of you who don't care.
One more little thing, though, kind of gaming-related.
Ferronix has a pretty good comparison right now of AMD graphics cards versus Nvidia graphics
cards using Vulkan.
Oh, really?
Yeah, and early game reports on Vulkan coming in now.
So if you are curious about that, Ferronix has that.
You can go check that out.
Yeah, I want to play games.
I just want to play games.
But we've got to get real for a second.
I don't normally mention alpha releases as an open source, like, project follow-up thing,
but I am going to mention Fedora 24 alpha, which shipped today, and only because it sort
of codifies something that we already knew well in advance, and that is that Wayland
will not be shipping as default in Fedora 24.
They read here, we've decided not to make Wayland the next generation graphics stack
the default in Fedora 24 workstation.
However, Wayland remains available as an option, and the workstation team would greatly appreciate
your help in testing.
Our goal is one full release where the non-default Wayland option works seamlessly or reasonably
close to that, and at that point, we'll make Wayland the default with X11 as the fallback.
Here's my question, mumble room, does this mean we will not have a mainstream Linux distribution
shipping with Wayland in 2016, as in another year will pass without Wayland shipping as
the default on a mainstream distribution?
It's possible.
Yeah, I think it does mean that, doesn't it?
I think it just means we just clocked another year without Wayland.
Now, if Mir could close the gap, the year of Mir has been doing its work well.
If we use the year of 2016 to polish it up, obviously that's worth it.
I'm just pointing it out.
It's just worth maybe mentioning.
It's funny to realize that when it's still only March.
It's good for things like SteamOS, right?
I don't think it was ever going to be a problem for SteamOS.
They would have hung out on X probably for a while, but you're right, anytime you can
refine the process and get it better and get another year of driver development in.
That's probably good.
If we can make the switch that much better, more seamless.
Of course, there's going to be distros out there you could load.
Well, today.
Right, you could use it today.
We're only a week into NVIDIA supporting Wayland on their proprietary driver.
This is probably a good idea.
Also, if you go down to the alpha, you can get your hands on GNOME 3.20.
2.0.
Yeah, you get the new GNOME, which would be pretty nice, a good way to get that.
It looks like overall a pretty cool alpha, and they mentioned you may have some issues
with old themes.
But yeah, I just thought that was... I bet everyone, aw, okay, okay, yeah, okay, no Wayland,
no Wayland.
Also, speaking of updates from distributions, Arch has a doozy, which... Hey, Rekai, note
this one down, okay?
I better let Rekai know because we got some servers here we got to update.
Pac-Man needs to be updated on your Arch box before April 23rd, and I'm going to be too
busy at LinuxFest to remind you guys, so you got to stay on top of this yourself.
This is Chris helping you out right now.
In order to use the new hooks, the new fancy hooks, they say, we require all users to update
the latest Pac-Man 5.0.1 before April 23rd, 2016, which, by the way, guys, has been out
since February 23rd.
So get your freaking updates on.
Dash SYU already.
You're getting two months, so get on it, otherwise you're going to be in a world of hurt.
You're going to have to probably go download that stuff manually.
So there you go.
Oh, thanks.
Wait, really, Rekai?
Really?
Oh, he says he already did it.
Look at that, Rekai.
Good man.
Man, that guy, he gets an internet cookie.
Hello, everybody.
Well, that's the best I got for right now.
That's the best I got.
So there you go.
Go update your Arch boxes.
The first thing I thought of is, oh, no big deal, and then I looked over, you see that
machine we have running right there?
Yes, I do.
GNOME 3 desktop running on Arch, that runs OBS and VLC and NGINX and fancy stuff to do
internal RTSP streams.
I haven't updated that thing since like December, I think, maybe January.
What are you doing this afternoon?
Yeah.
Well, the problem is that I break it when I do the updates.
Then I have to be like, Rekai, come fix it.
I don't have time to fix OBS because it's usually the NGINX installer or something that
breaks.
You know what I need to do?
I need to shut that knockoff and move it over to a DigitalOcean droplet.
Oh, DigitalOcean, sponsor right here on the Linux unplugged program.
Here's our promo code DOUNPLUGGED over at DigitalOcean.
Use it.
See out there?
DOUNPLUGGED.
You got to turn off a knock and just go spin up a droplet.
Less than 55 seconds, you'll have a machine that's ready to go, and they start at only
$5 a month or 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one blazing fast CPU, and a terabyte
of transfer.
That's the starting price.
It only gets better from there.
It does, and they're all SSDs, and the bandwidth transfer just gets more.
It's a really great, simple-to-use cloud hosting service.
You can go spin up your own Linux rig.
They got Debian, Ubuntu, Fedora, FreeBSD if you want that.
They got CoreOS, because why not?
Go put it in a Docker container or a rocket thingy or whatever, Alex.
I don't care.
Just go do it, right?
Go do it.
You know, we've been seeing a lot of people saying, hey, do you guys want to create a
how-to guide on installing own cloud?
Just go over to DigitalOcean and just click the one-click deployment, and what's great
about it is like if you screw up your own cloud installation, like you just mess it
all up, you can go back and redeploy that base image again, and it's right back.
Own cloud installed.
Ubuntu's installed.
Good to go.
It's like, okay, that wasn't so bad.
Put your data back in.
Bob's your uncle.
They have a great interface, a really nice intuitive API that you can write around or
just take advantage of some of the open source code that's already out there, a community
tutorial section that is, honestly, it beats everybody out there, tons of really great
help out there.
So not only do they have the one-click applications, but if you just want to do a basic rig and
just set it up yourself or you want to build on top of it, really good tutorial.
So just use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED at a $10 credit, support the show, and spin yourself
up a droplet.
DigitalOcean.com, data centers all over the world.
Check them out at DigitalOcean.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED and a big thank you to DigitalOcean.
Thank you.
Hey, DO.
Thanks, man.
Thank you.
I'm pretty excited about this, only I have been pulling my hair out about this new Ubuntu
M10 tablet.
So there's two versions right now.
There's the HD version, the 1920 by 1080, and then there's a, quote, unquote, HD version,
which is more like 720p.
And I think it was announced yesterday for pre-order, coming from BQ.
It's the Ubuntu M10 Aquarius, Ubuntu edition, or whatever.
Going to have 16.04 on it, probably shipping in March, April-ish.
No.
No?
Not 16.04.
No.
Current build, it'll be OTA 10, which is based off Vivid, so that's 15.04, but we'll move
to 16.04 soon.
You know, they say 16.04 in the product marketing there.
Oh, dear.
But-
It's interesting, because I saw it say 15.10, actually.
Well, I'm talking about just right here in the imagery.
I don't know about in the actual specs.
You know, either way, I mean, that's sort of not the big point.
That's not the big story.
The big story is, it's our first crack at ordering an official Ubuntu tablet.
That's the story, right?
That's pretty exciting.
Poby, are you, tell me, do you have to buy it yourself, or are you just going to be getting
one, or how does that work?
So, for some, looking around me, I have a bunch of devices that I have been given, but
I do buy my own as well.
So I like to know what the consumer experience is.
So I have two machines side by side, and I have one that's running the latest stable
and one that's running unstable, so I can tell and compare and contrast.
So yeah, I'll probably end up buying myself one.
I might get one from work, but I'll probably buy myself one anyway.
I don't know what my problem is, but I can't get my order to go through.
I don't know if other people-
Actually, I heard from somebody else-
Bad credit, Chris.
Somebody else on Twitter is having this problem, but I put my order in, I put my shipping address,
I created my account, and then when I click on place order, the page just refreshes and
it goes from $299 to $799, or it actually goes from $299.90 to $799 price, and then
I hit proceed to check out just to see what happens, and it just – nothing happens.
It never proceeds.
I can't actually proceed to place an order, and I've tried for the last couple of days.
So I have not been able to order one yet, but I definitely want to get one.
I think it would be – I don't know.
Have you heard, Poppy, about how many there are?
Am I going to run out if I don't get an order in soon?
What's the word there?
I don't know, actually.
I don't know how many they're planning to manufacture.
Usually when it's a pre-order, the fact that you're ordering them means that they take
those numbers and manufacture a certain number for the demand, but no, I don't know.
I've not seen that problem at all.
So I've heard from only one other person that's having the problem.
This has got a 1.3 gigahertz quad-core MediaTek ARM processor in there, 10.1-inch screen,
8-megapixel camera, it looks like, and this is going to be the one that gives us convergence,
right?
This will be a tablet that you can hook up to a keyboard and mouse and have a full desktop
experience.
Oh, that's awesome.
Yep.
And you can either use the internal display or – it's got a mini HDMI port, so you can
just plug in an external display if you want a bigger display.
That's a big feature.
You can use internal or external.
That isn't being talked about that much.
Mini HDMI, you mean?
Well, just –
Yeah.
The convergence aspect of it, that's why I want to get my hands on it.
Right.
I want to try it.
Yeah.
I really want to try it because I think that's going to be –
That makes it a lot more interesting.
And plus, not only do I want to try it, but I'm sure it's going to be something that's
going to be iterated on for years, or at least for a while.
And so I want to see it as that process matures, as that experience matures.
And so that's why I want to get one, but for goodness sakes, I can't get the order in no
matter what I do.
I do not know.
Yeah.
I've also tried it in Chrome and Firefox.
I've tried it with no ad blocks turned on.
I'm just really happy they didn't cut the corners with the display in order to get at
that price point because when I saw that it was full HD, I'm like, oh, this is an absolute
buy.
Oh, really?
You're not worried about maybe applications that you don't want that aren't available
or something like that?
No.
That will be solved with time.
Yeah.
And plus, there's a lot of Linux apps that you might want to play with, right?
Anybody in the Mumble Room order one of these?
I have.
Oh, okay.
Wimpy, what was your reasoning?
Other than just obviously interest?
Yeah, also, I had the BQ5 phone, which I bought.
I've since given that to a friend of mine so that they can experiment with Ubuntu.
And I've been using the Nexus 4 and the Nexus 7.
And a bit like you were just saying, I want a proper device that's going to be supported
for some time.
And I'm really wanting to see how this works on the road as a portable device that I can
take with me and do useful things on.
Because I think, Popey, am I right about this, Firefox and LibreOffice are going to be installed
by default on these?
Maybe.
I don't know.
I remember reading at some point that those were going to be pre-installed applications.
So when you go into the windowed mode, you've got those sort of productivity tools.
Popey, how does that work?
Is it BQ that delivers the final image?
No, we build the image and it's exactly the same as it is for all the other devices.
We build the image, we do QA and then we pass it to BQ.
They do their QA and then they integrate that into their factory process.
So at the point when they manufacture the devices, the image that gets deployed onto
them is the image that we made.
And if that's true that LibreOffice and Firefox are going to be working on this, then that
also means that it's shipping applications that require XMirror to be fully functional
by default.
Correct?
Yes.
They use XMirror.
Yeah.
You got the same problem?
Except a different number.
So Wes just tried to buy it to see if he had the same problem I got and he has the same
problem only he got $599, I got $799.
We can't proceed with the checkout.
You're living in the filthy colonies and not over in enlightened Europe.
I'm sure, but it says worldwide delivery, right?
It says worldwide delivery, doesn't it?
Yeah.
Neither one of us can place an order.
So both of us are trying.
I've wondered if I should just buy the regular Aquarius and could find the image available.
Is that likely?
How's that going to work?
I know this is sort of looking into the crystal ball a little bit, but are there going to
be images I can download down the road and just install on it if I want to?
Yeah.
All our images are the same for all of the devices.
They're already available.
You can already go and-
Oh, they are?
They're not device-specific?
Yeah.
They are device-specific, but they're on the same server as all the other devices.
You could go rummage and find them.
They wouldn't be the final image because the final image isn't done yet, but you could
go and get the image.
I'm not guaranteeing that you could go and buy an Android version of that device and
flash it because that's somewhat out of our control.
If they put some lock on it or make it difficult to do, I don't know.
Or changed firmwares or something like that.
Right.
And that's beyond our control.
So we always say, if you buy the Ubuntu one, we know we can reflash that, but we just don't
know about the Android one.
But past experience, we have had people who bought the Android version of the BQ phones
and then asked BQ for the flashing tool that allows them to flash them to Ubuntu and BQ
have provided it.
So it's-
Wow.
That's a good time.
It's out of the realms of possibility.
They do have good support at BQ.
I like that.
I like hearing that.
I don't know.
Does anybody else have any thoughts or questions about the tablet before I just selfishly change
tracks for a moment?
No?
Okay.
If anyone can buy it, just plus one for Chris.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Maybe, Poby, you might be the best guy to ask.
Maybe somebody else might know.
How likely is it down the road that if I were to eventually wind up with a Nexus 5X that
I would be able to run Ubuntu Touch on that?
Right now, I'm looking at it.
It seems like the most powerful phone I could get to run Ubuntu Touch would be the OnePlus.
I don't really have any interest in the OnePlus.
I'd rather have a Nexus device.
Am I SOL theoretically down the road or is there likely eventually going to be a community
edition or maybe even official build for the newer Nexus I?
So it's a good question.
We've got a community porting campaign on at the moment.
And if you go to ubports.com, I think it is, ubports.com, there's like a wish list of devices
that people want ported to.
And the OnePlus One is only already done because that was done some months ago.
The guy who did that, Mario, who did that a while ago, and it turns out that the internals
of the OnePlus One and the Two and the OnePlus X are fairly similar.
So actually, he can reuse some of that work.
The devices that are wish lists that you'd really like probably aren't being ported because
A, he doesn't have the time and he's just one guy.
And B, he may not even have that device.
So he asks for donations if we want to give him, you know, chuck him a few dollars, then
he'll buy it.
Interesting.
And I know he has done that, like someone threw him some money.
So he went and bought a OnePlus X, and then I saw a message on Google Plus with a photo
of a OnePlus X running Ubuntu.
So you know, as soon as he has the device, he starts working on it.
But he has now a queue of devices to work on and he is only one guy.
If you know anyone who is familiar with porting, like cyanogen type porting from the XDA developers
type community, if they want to get involved and start porting to some of these other devices,
like Nexus devices, that would be awesome and put him in touch with Mario.
It seems-
5X is on there.
Not funded.
Yeah.
It seems like I'm having more and more conversations with people where they say, from now on I'm
only buying Nexus devices.
And that's not to put down like the OnePluses or the S7s or anything like that, but people
are just like, um.
That's about all I consider on it.
I mean, maybe a Moto X.
Yeah.
But I've been, it's funny how often I've been having this conversation.
And I think a lot of people are coming to this as they look at the smartphone market
is if you're going to go Android and you're technically savvy and you want direct security
updates from Google, you just go Nexus right now.
And so if Ubuntu, though I'll just say Touch, got to the point where it was, it got to the
point where if you, like where Linux used to be for laptops a decade ago where you could
take a pretty mainstream distro and if you got a fairly mainstream, well not even ten
years ago, five years ago, if you got a fairly mainstream laptop, you had a great shot of
getting Ubuntu to work on that, it'd be really something now.
If you got a Nexus device, you'd have a pretty great shot of knowing you'd also be able to
run Ubuntu on it.
Man.
That, it would be such a great place for Ubuntu to get to for those devices just, because
it'd just become another option to run on a Nexus device.
And it starts to make the Nexus device look less like a Google phone and more like a general
smartphone platform that you could just load all their OS's on.
And that's pretty neat.
Good hardware, good price.
More like traditional PC hardware where you can.
Exactly.
Something to standardize.
Decent hardware, good price.
Yeah.
I mean it's reasonable.
Kitson, you wanted to jump in.
Go ahead.
The reason that I will only purchase a Nexus device is because the support.
With a Nexus device, I know I'm getting at least two years of support.
And why am I going to spend, you know, $700 on a device that may or may not receive updates?
And then on top of that, like if I go to the Samsung Galaxy S website, I can't find out
if I purchased this device, how long they're actually going to support it.
It's not in.
They're not interested in committing to that.
No, no.
See, the interesting thing here is you've all been tainted by the problem of Android.
Is that the thing that has made you do that is the ecosystem around Android that's forced
you to all make that decision.
You shouldn't have had to make that decision.
You don't make that decision about laptops.
You don't buy a laptop because you're going to get a vanilla experience.
You nuke it and put whatever you want on it.
Right.
And that's something we're not doing.
We're putting the same image on all of the devices.
So the original BQE 4.5, the very first phone that we had, gets the same software updates
as the M10 that comes out next month.
And that's the same updates that the Meizu Pro 5 that comes out next month gets and the
next device and the next device and the Sony device and the OnePlus device.
And if it's ported to the Nexus X, 5X, then yeah, that gets it as well.
So it's the same software stack that all of them get.
Yes, exactly.
I think that's wonderful.
And that's the long term hope.
But in the short term, I think my Linux laptop from a few years ago analogy holds up here
because a lot of times people needed to still run Windows.
Still do.
They needed to run Windows.
This is going to be true with Nexus users.
They're going to still need to be able to run Android probably at least for the next
couple of years.
And so that's why you want a well-supported Android device, but you also want something
that can run Ubuntu and you really want a sweet spot there.
And so that's why I was...
That's where the Nexus...
Getting me all excited here, Chris.
Right?
Doesn't that sound right?
Yeah, it really does.
Yeah.
Because I want to run Marshmallow.
I don't want to not be able to run Marshmallow, but I also want to run the latest Ubuntu Touch
or whatever it's supposed to be.
I'm one of the rare people who will never get a Nexus phone again.
Why is that?
Because the Nexus phone completely lost power and the power button was faulty and broken.
Yeah, frustrating.
So the phone won't turn on at all.
It just does a boot loop forever.
I've had issues with every single phone eventually though.
But yeah, that is frustrating.
Yeah, but one of the things...
The reason I like it though is LG made that phone, but under the guise of what Google
told them to do.
If you look at LG's phones, those are awesome.
The ones that are just there.
Like the G4 and G5?
Yeah, the V10.
Pick an LG phone.
It's pretty cool.
And even if the crappy lower level $80 Leons are really impressive for their price.
And the best part, there is no bloatware in LG.
They don't do that stupid crap.
That most reasons...
Oh really?
That is nice.
You know, that's actually really cool to know.
Why don't I take a moment and mention Ting because they sell the LG Volt 2 for $66.
And LG has just announced they're going to ship Marshmallow for the Volt 2.
So go to linux.ting.com.
You'll get that for...
You'll get this device for $66.
It ships tomorrow.
No contract.
No early termination fee.
You only pay for what you use, flat $6 for the line.
That's Ting right there.
Linux.ting.com.
Go there to support this show.
They have a great selection of devices.
They have right now currently a post on the history of the Kodi project, which is awesome.
I love that they're getting into that.
It's super cool that my mobile carrier is writing a post about the history of Kodi.
I mean, I totally love that.
They get it.
They do.
And they also have the OnePlus 2.
They have the Nexus devices.
They also have the S7.
They just recently added the S7.
The OnePlus 2, $349.
You could load Cyanogen on that, no problem.
You could also load pretty much a lot of images.
I mean, it's the OnePlus.
$349.
You walk away.
You own it.
It's unlocked.
There's no contract.
Nice and clean.
You want to just go buy the Nexus 5X from the Google Play Store?
Do that.
And then just get the Ting SIM and just pop the SIM card in.
Easy peasy, my friends.
They have, from the SIM card, starting around $9, which you can get Prime on Amazon.
Woo!
I know.
But then you can't support the show.
Go to linux.ting.com at least.
Yeah, just go.
Go there.
All the way up to things like the Internet Phone 7.
Oh wait, they don't have that out yet.
The Internet Phone 6S.
Okay, they might have that.
The Samsung Galaxy S7.
All of that stuff.
They have a great lineup of phones.
They have great customer service.
They have an excellent control panel.
Find out why I've been using them for more than two years.
Linux.ting.com.
And that LG Volt 2, I mean, it's not like it's going to blow you away in specs.
But I mean, hell, a $66 smartphone with no contract, you pay what you use, and you get
freaking Marshmallow.
It's a great phone for people who haven't had a smartphone before, don't have a lot
of extra cash.
Or if you just need a budget Android device, but you want to have something that's secure.
I mean, that seems reasonable.
I don't know when LG is shipping it, but they announced shipping Marshmallow for the Volt
2, which is really cool.
That's awesome.
Yeah, linux.ting.com.
Go there to support the show.
And a big thanks to Ting.
I'm going to keep trying to get myself that Ubuntu tablet, too, because I really do want
to...
What?
Yeah, you got it.
I mean, I want to play with it when you get it.
I know.
Because if I get it, you get to play with it.
Exactly.
That's very true.
Okay.
So, have you guys heard of Stali?
Anybody in the mobile room heard of Stali Linux?
I think I'm saying that right?
Yeah.
Who said yes?
Rotten.
Oh, of course, Rotten.
Okay, Rotten.
How did you hear of this distro?
Seriously.
How did you hear of Stali?
I thought I'd have one on you.
ZDNet.
Isn't it?
Okay.
Well, this one is from Infoworld.
But yeah, okay.
Kind of same thing.
Stali promises to smash assumptions about Linux like a fricking wrecking ball.
And so they've put a wrecking ball picture in the post.
It's a distribution built with all statically linked binaries.
They say for speed and compactness.
Stali stands for static Linux, with static referring to how all binaries in the distribution
are statically linked against their libraries.
Stali's project head says – and by the way, he also currently works at BMW and is the
developer of DWM, window manager, believes that static linking works out better for most
common use cases.
The most obvious benefit in static binaries, have a smaller memory footprint and on disk
footprint.
I don't see how that's possible at all.
Static binaries also claim to be faster, although there's no real benchmarks yet.
And here's another doozy for you.
Here's another one.
Another way they're challenging the quote, unquote, directly from the article, traditional
Linux distribution, no package manager.
No repo, no package manager, instead all updates are pulled from upstream by way of Git.
Also no system D, no system D at all.
Stali has its own S-init utility, which is also statically linked –
Jason Kuznicki Synit.
Yeah.
Synit, which is also statically linked.
And also, by the way, kernel modules not supported because you would need to link them.
So this is Stali, the distribution that smashes assumptions like a wrecking ball about Linux
according to Infoworld.
But I mean, the ISO they provide now, it's like 34 megs, so that's easy.
Is that a full desktop environment too?
Well, no.
That's here.
Oh, just the command line?
So you have it installed right here?
Yeah.
And this is all you get?
Yep.
This is it?
This is how many programs are in slash bin.
Take a look there.
Is there the LS still on the screen?
You'll see that the file system they use is a little different.
That's one of their talking points, they don't use the file system standard.
Right.
Yeah.
They really don't.
Sys and share on the root, log on the root.
That's interesting.
Dev on the root.
Half the things are just symlinks to root.
Yes.
Var, user, and root, actually, the slash root directory.
Yeah, that was confusing at first.
Yeah.
Is all our symlinks to the root?
Yep.
What?
That is really weird.
It is really interesting kind of as a study of like a minimal Linux.
I wonder if I could show this on camera.
I don't know if this will show up.
Here, you guys, if you're watching the video, pause it and look at this crazy directory
structure.
I can't hold it for too long.
But it's just, it's really, you want to grab it?
That's really like something I've never seen before.
That is special and unique.
Wow.
So the completely statically linked distribution.
What are your thoughts having installed it and run it West?
Does it perform well?
It did boot very quickly.
I mean, there's not much going on.
I don't know.
I mean, it'd be interesting.
I could see it being useful for people who really need to, who want to build something
very minimal or very customized and really have a very good conception of exactly what's
running.
You know, if you're trying to craft this into some sort of embedded or like appliance-like
application, maybe this will, maybe this works well, especially if you already have like
something that's installed as a, you know, like something like an app image or a snap
package style system where it has all of it, it's statically linked or it has all of its
dependencies within itself already, then that might be a great way to just use this and
run it on that.
Did you see that everything for like all the system services and everything, the way you
start and stop everything is a single rc init file and there's an rc like shutdown file.
It's all in one file.
All of it.
Everything for simplicity.
That's the rc.exit power off.
Okay, Rod, what were your first thoughts when you read the headline?
I mean, can you see the argument for it?
Could you make a case for it?
Statically linked, yes.
I mean, in certain cases that makes sense.
The entire system, no.
It looked ridiculous.
But I laughed when I saw the bashing system thing and they're like making it called Senate.
That was just funny.
Yeah.
That is good, right?
That was a good one.
When I heard about it's only 34 ISOs, I was like, yeah, so tiny core is about the same.
And nano Linux is only 14.
Okay.
All right.
Derek Delvin, you've got a good point to make.
Go ahead.
So I'm going to defend them in the sense that statically linking has become more and more
common because hard drive space is not an issue anymore for shared libraries.
And bandwidth.
It fixes the problem of bandwidth and the problem of deployment is gone because suddenly
you just deploy this binary and it will execute.
So yeah, you don't need a package manager if you just executed.
And honestly, when you're going to look like Google, for example, Go programming language
doesn't even allow you to have shared libraries.
So is that that odd?
Probably not.
About the system, the part, well, if you are statically linking everything, then the other
components don't need to be initialized the same way because there's no dependencies to
initialize before.
So of course they're going to make something that, you know, that it's just different because
they don't need it even.
Moving on to the next point, you know, it's not much different than having, you know,
when you're an Android busy box, having your RC, having all the programs inside just with
the command line options that then inside the program splits them out.
So that's not that big of a deal and not that different anyway.
So honestly, it's a lovable goal.
Now on the file system directory splitting, I mean, in the end, all of the separation
was because you have to separate parts of the software like images here, resources there,
shared libraries there.
You don't have those things to care about anymore.
The assets can be embedded into the binary.
Then definitely yes.
And as a last point, compilers optimize better when they have accessible all of the source
code.
So technically, yes, it can be faster.
Yeah, it does seem to boot super fast and run super fast, right?
I mean, yeah.
So okay, so now continuing on this narrative, I've noticed the media, the print media, is
it has like a theme they're running with a lot recently.
And that is, this could teach Linux a lesson or Linux has something to learn from this.
Could this finally replace Linux?
And so to amp it up a little bit, here we go, you ready, ready, let's
Oh, rust, Redox OS could show Linux a new few tricks.
See what I'm saying?
You see how intense that is?
Yeah.
I'm scared for Linux.
Over the last several months, a team of developers has been busy doing exactly that using rust
to create Redox, Redox, Redox, Redox, that's what I think too, a full blown Unix like operating
system designed as a radical rethinking of the Linux approach.
Redox uses rust for its kernel level code to provide more memory safety considerations
and CLLs by default.
Redox uses a minimal set of syscalls and a deliberately smaller subset than Linux, gotta
get that in there, which avoids legacy bloat, gotta get that in there, gotta love that.
The OS also uses a microkernel by design to stay slender in contrast to Linux monolithic
kernel, and many of the OS's internal behaviors have also been rethought.
While Linux and Unix both use the notion of every item as a file, Redox goes a step further
and treats everything like a URL, so it's simple to register handlers for events and
provides a consistent manner to perform other kinds of abstractions.
Another radical break from Linux is that the software isn't licensed under the GPL, but
the entire project is MIT.
It's negative in the freedom dimension.
I feel like we've been seeing a lot of MIT projects lately.
I feel like we've been seeing a lot of going to teach Linux a lesson recently too.
And I wonder, Daredevil, you say you've looked into it, and you have some thoughts?
Because I know Rust is massively popular in the Mozilla crowd, it was recently voted one
of the most loved languages on Stack Exchange.
So tell me a little bit about what you've been following.
So Rust does provide some safeties that might help mitigating some issues on kernel development,
so I'll give them that.
But it still implies that they're good developers in the first place.
I don't know if they are or not, so I'm not making any statement, I'm just saying it implies
that they're good developers.
Then you're going to have to go to the next level.
Actually, Linux kernel is a hybrid kernel because of the way it loads modules, and especially
when you're considering KDBus that it's being implemented, so there's that part too as well.
Moving on to the argument that Linux is complicated, they're saying that Unix philosophy is right,
the implementation are the things that are not working, they're claiming their website
anyways.
Which means that they're going to implement most of the things in a familiar Unix way,
they're just going to change some of the little details that are in Linux because legacy.
So with that perspective in mind, I think there's people that are actually right now
doing a bolder move when it comes to kernel development, they're actually saying, let's
get away with all of these separation and multiple users, I think they're crazy, but
there's talks about this and people actually working on projects, which actually go to
differentiate themselves.
And on MIT, that's all to say that the GPL is the whole reason Linux succeeds, because
all of these companies fund Linux.
Look, who's funding them?
No one.
I'm going to answer just who.
So Alex Voda, he's saying, oh man, this is crap reporting.
I hope he doesn't mean mine, because I agree.
What I'm poking fun at is the narrative of the media that they are taking projects like
this and they're using it to say, this is what's going to teach Linux a lesson to generate
clicks.
And I think that's a really interesting trick they're trying to play there.
Wes, you've actually downloaded and installed it just there, or running a live image?
Yes, I'm running it in VirtualBox right here.
And yep, nope.
So they have a 28 meg installer, right?
You just like it finds your devices.
It looked like it was using the same terminology as dev, SDA, hit yes, installed, I rebooted.
It started up booting into a, you know, kind of familiar kernel looking startup, identifying
all the devices, AHCI, that kind of stuff.
Started the graphical environment.
I've got it running here.
Wait, there's a, you're telling me, you're telling me in a 28 meg?
Well, it did.
Yeah, I guess it must all be contained.
A 28 megabyte download, it has a GUI environment too?
But the mouse doesn't work.
Oh, it looks nice though.
I know.
It's got a, it's got a file manager down there.
It's got a calculator, a terminal, a sound controller.
And it started up, you know, I just logged in and it had to, had a terminal anyway.
It's another hold it up to the camera edition there.
But you can see here, Wes, you want, you want to take it and yeah, as you can see there,
there's the desktop environment with a sort of like your standard start bar down at the
bottom.
Boy, that is damn impressive.
That is really, and that loaded pretty fast from VirtualBox too.
Hmm.
That was just in the time Daredevil was talking, I got it installed.
Yeah.
I get it.
I have a, I have a sense about, about Rust.
I really do.
I don't want to, I don't want to talk out of my butt too much more about it.
So I think I want to move on from the topic, but you know, I was looking through some of
the upcoming talks, the sessions that are going to be at Linux Fest Northwest.
Oh, exciting.
Rust's Community Automation, and they talk about this, they say this talk will discuss
the implementation details as well as the social motivation and effects of the customized
infrastructure and workflow practices which allow a small core team to have such significant
impact.
They talk about Rust being a system programming language that runs blazingly fast, prevents
segfaults, and guarantees thread safety.
Behind the scenes, Rust is also a community that nurtures new contributors, consistently
enforces its code of conduct, and maintains a high quality code base.
This is a talk at Linux Fest coming up on the 24th in room CC236, and damn, that looks
at 1230.
Oh, I did just see something.
They're working on ZFS support.
No!
Yup.
Says work in progress, right?
So like, probably doesn't work, but that would be kind of cool.
Oh man, that's a mind bender.
So I, you know, I know-
Really giving it to Linux there.
Boy, 1230.
I don't know if I'd be able to attend that since I'm going to be on the air, but that
seems like-
Yeah, let Noah do it.
Yeah.
No, maybe.
I would be really interested in going to that.
That Rust community automation talk might be really interesting.
Why don't we start talking a little bit about Linux Fest Northwest 2016 real quickly because
that actually leads perfectly into my next couple of things that I want to update you
guys on.
First of all, you know what we've got to talk about though?
Let's get real.
Let's get serious.
Let's talk about Linux Academy.
When you're ready to get serious about extending your education, about learning a new platform,
about bringing your career up to the next level, or just challenging yourself, LinuxAcademy.com
slash Unplugged, get our discount and go check out the Linux Academy platform.
Seven plus distros you choose from.
They automatically adjust the courseware and the distros they spin up when you need them
on demand, including, by the way, when you're doing AWS courseware, they'll spin those instances
up for you.
What?
I know, man.
It's a really cool platform.
Tons of cool features, tons of courseware focused on the different aspects built around
Linux that run on top of Linux or Linux itself.
They have systems and tools available if you don't have a lot of time, and if you want
to go get some of the top high-grade courses and certifications, Linux Academy has the
courseware on it.
They just recently did another OpenStack certification courseware.
They've got awesome courseware on the Red Hat certified stuff.
If you need scenario-based labs so that way you know exactly what you're doing when you
go do it in production, they've got courseware on that.
If you want instructor mentoring, they've got a Help Instructors available if you want
that.
They've got live streams.
They've got a community stack full of Jupyter broadcasting members.
I love it, but more than all, more than all of it, I love that there was a company out
there that said, Linux is an amazing platform, and none of the educational sites out there
are doing it justice.
They're all treating it as a stupid feature that they've got to check the box, and they
ship some crappy courseware alongside their Adobe After Effects courseware and their motion
…
Yeah, exactly.
It's just one more application to that.
It's one more thing.
I'm so sick and tired of that.
So the folks at Linux Academy who are passionate about Linux and open source themselves, educators
and developers, friends, they came together, they started the Linux Academy.
Now it's grown into a business where they're growing like crazy with new staff members
dedicated to all kinds of great things for your content, and they've built this platform
to help promote Linux and give people a real place to learn Linux by people that know and
love Linux themselves, linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
You see why it's such a great fit.
Go check them out and support the show by visiting that site, linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged.
Thank you, Linux Academy.
All right, so in 2018, when Jupyter Broadcasting is making Leo Laporte money, I mean, we're
talking not right now, something down the road, but when we're making Leo Laporte money
…
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
I'm going to fly everybody out in the mumbroom.
You mean in the year of the Linux desktop.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, where we've released Jupyter Broadcasting OS based on Ubuntu Mate.
That's where your wallpaper is the live stream all the time.
Yeah, yeah.
And every time you …
You're at Wayland.
I wish all of you guys, I wish you could all be at Linux Fest Northwest.
Maybe we could like bring the mumble room in at some point on the live stream.
That would be fun.
That would be cool to actually be able to do that because I feel like it's one of
the neater events, not just in Washington, but in the States and so I'd love it if
you guys can make it.
Maybe one day.
So I had a couple of things I wanted to cover real quickly.
If you didn't see this week's Linux action show briefly, I'll just mention Noah and
I have officially made a stash bet.
The stash bet is briefly, if he loses to Emma, he has to grow a mustache for six months and
he's not very good at it.
So that'd be embarrassing.
And he'll be visible every week.
I want him to win, but if he wins, I will shave my mustache in order to motivate him
to do it.
That's how dedicated I am to winning.
So that's the stash bet.
Just the mustache, not the beard.
Well, I don't know.
I doubt it because then I start getting carded and that is super annoying.
I hate getting carded.
It's your handsome young face.
Don't you look like an Amish person if you do that?
Yes, that is the problem.
I will very much look like an Amish person, a lot.
But I also want Noah to win by a large margin.
So I need a little help from you.
I really want to see you look like an Amish person.
I really want to see that.
Well, then Noah's got to win.
So here's what I figured out is we've got to change the game up a little bit.
I don't want to talk bad about our boy Noah, but I'm looking at the playing field and I'm
thinking Emma has got the cards stacked in her favor right now.
So I want to change it up.
And what I want to do is I want us to be able to go mobile.
I want us to be able to go around and go to different locations.
And so if people are listening to this and are going to make it to the Linux Fest and
you perhaps want to volunteer either helping with bringing a light if you have like an
LED light or if you want to hold a camera or if you have a microphone or something,
I don't know.
You can call me Chris at JupiterBroadcasting.com because what I want to do is I want to set
up two crews, one to follow Noah and his switching adventures and one to follow Emma and her switching
adventures as they go out into Bellingham and try to get as many people to switch to
Linux as possible.
And to give them the flexibility to do that, we're going to have to have people dedicated
to audio, lights, and camera, like an actual production crew, but there's no way we could
actually do that.
So I'm hoping people that are going, Chris at JupiterBroadcasting.com if maybe you want
to help out with that.
And something we're doing kind of different than we've ever done before, which I'm really
hoping will make a big difference in how much content we're producing is, Ham are you still
in there?
Hey Ham!
I think Ham left.
Ham is going to be, we're going to go out and pick him up in the Lady Jupiter about
a week before Linux Fest and he's going to be staying about four or five days, three
days after Linux Fest here at JB1 to help Rekai and I go through all of the content,
so all of the footage.
So hopefully now we're going to have another dedicated editor on hand to go through all
of the clips and stuff because we always have so much content more than we can ever process
or go through.
So that's kind of a big expense for us, but it's also kind of exciting to have basically
a game plan to what the hell we're going to actually do with all the footage we collect,
which is something we've never really done before.
That's awesome.
Yeah, so I feel like we're going into this Fest and maybe this might be something that
works in the future because a lot of times Linux Fest is where we just completely try
something new or big because it's local and if we really screw the pooch, we could actually
just drive to the studio, right?
When you're in North Carolina or you're in Pasadena, you can't do that.
So you get with Linux Fest, not only is it our largest, craziest, most expensive thing
we do every year, but it's also where we do the biggest experiments and that's everything
from like road trips to hauling crew out to hiring extra people and new equipment and
switching out stuff.
So that'll be really cool.
So we should have extra footage for that.
So if you want to volunteer, be part of our crew and it might just be something like holding
up a light and if you have stuff like that, like if you have really, really good high
end portable production equipment, let me know.
If you don't have high end stuff, don't let me know.
Chris got standards.
Yeah, I do.
You know what I do.
So one more thing, speaking of volunteers, if you're going to go to Linux Fest, I would
love reporters that go to these talks.
Like I was just talking about that Rust talk.
Go there.
Check it out.
You know, I'm hosting the live stream.
I'm interviewing people constantly at Linux Fest.
I sometimes don't even get a chance to eat, let alone go to the bathroom or go to an extra
session.
It's here, Mike, Chris.
I know.
I start getting sick sometimes, it's bad.
Yeah.
Usually Hadia or Angela spots me starting to get a little sick, like, all right, he's
got to take five.
Hey, he needs five.
And then somebody steps in.
But if you're going to go to some of these talks, I would love for you to report back,
come to the booth at Linux Fest, sit down and talk to us about these.
And maybe if you have a camera, you could get some video of it just to give us an idea.
You don't have to record the whole thing.
Just give me some B roll.
If you've got a phone with a decent camera on it, record a couple of seconds of the session.
And then maybe I could get a way to get it on the live stream.
Capture the experience.
Yeah.
So while you're talking about it, I could loop that a couple of times.
I'm not asking you to record it.
Come back and report.
Like, like, you know, radio or newspaper reporter style, you come back, report, tell me about
it.
And we'll scream it.
And we'll record those.
And we could put those in the shows and stuff like that if they're cool, or at least the
best one.
So I'm asking for some volunteers to help us with the switch recording and production.
And I'm asking for some volunteers to go to some of these sessions and then report back
for the ones we can't go to.
So I think that's going to be if I know that's asking a lot, but it's also gives you an opportunity
to just be involved in the process.
And if we get a couple people to help us, that's great.
Yeah.
Chris can yell at you and tell you to do stuff.
No.
That's not true.
In fact, you know what?
Honestly, if you're super helpful, you usually end up getting invited to parties and barbecues
and beer.
I mean, really, there is there is so much upside because, like, we are super nice to
the people that help us out.
So there's a there's a there's a ton of upside, as you will discover, Wes, as it is your first
Linux fest.
You will see it's quite the party.
Yeah, there's things that some people should go undercover and accept Noah's proposal to
switch to Linux.
Yes.
Right.
Or at least spread the word.
If you know family or friends in the Pacific Northwest, have them come help us.
Have them help us.
Heaven's forbid.
And you can also help us wherever you're at Teespring.com slash here's the thing.
We've mentioned it.
We announced it.
I launched it on last week's show.
I think we've sold around 60 out of 100 right now.
100 would probably pay for maybe me to go pick up ham or hotels like it's like it's really
expensive stuff.
But these are awesome shirts.
They got the last logo on the front, sort of classy style where a Star Trek communicator
badge would be.
You know what I'm talking about?
You know, can you visualize that?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, OK.
So right where the communicator badge would be at.
And then on the back, here's the thing.
Do you have a minute to talk about Linux?
And we got that.
I love that Linux.
It's just big.
Right on that.
You can't you can't miss it.
Look how sharp that S is with with red.
It looks like you're some sort of official or something like that.
We also got the hoodie here.
Just an insider tip.
Gray is gorgeous.
It is a it is a gorgeous kind of charcoal gray.
Red is bold and gets attention.
So if you don't have a red one, either way, people will be like just touching it.
And the long sleeve shirts, if you have if I don't know what your build is, but if your
build is similar to my build, the long sleeve shirts can be can be pretty can be pretty generous.
This is one of them.
This is one of the Jupiter broadcasting ones.
We have different sizes and you can get different colors.
I'm just saying, depending on your you if you're a medium, you are going to get lazy
with these shirts.
If it's an extra large, the way it's cut with the shoulders is still very generous and makes
you look like you have nice shoulders and still a figure.
And all people will see is the ladies love or the gentleman.
And then when they go, oh, who's that handsome or gorgeous individual?
And what is this Linux?
And you start the conversation.
So I'm just saying, here's the thing at Teespring dot com slash here's the thing.
And you know, Wes, I know I mentioned this once before, too, but we are doing a.
That's really what it looks like, folks.
I mean, that's exactly what it looks like here in the studio with all of the mystique,
the hat.
You just want to open it.
You can't.
Yeah.
No, I'm leaving it like that as a tease to myself and to the host.
Yeah, it's just there sitting there in the living room of the studio.
We're leaving it in the box until the crew gets here.
We are doing a big Linux build.
I talked about it last week.
I would love to know a well built.
I mean, I'm talking well built, economical case that I could buy two of that hold, you
know, at least probably six drives because we're going to have or maybe four drives.
That's all right.
Yeah.
We're going to have an SSD for the OS and then probably five drives and probably four
storage drives.
You don't want to read one of those SSDs.
Probably read zero.
Oh, yeah.
It's more about the speed because we're writing it.
All right.
That makes sense.
Yeah, we're writing uncompressed video.
And we may maybe one day.
So we're so if you I don't want to give away too much.
So this is a secret build.
But let's just say one day I would like this to be able to support 4K video bit rates and
it's going to be running Linux.
I'm just going to leave it at that.
That's your hint for what these builds are.
And we need a really nice presentable case that let's say we ended up building something
that was so awesome it actually showcased the features of Linux and we could take it
on the road and show it as an example of what Linux is capable of.
I would like a case that is presentable to people because I want to be able to sit down
the table and be like, yeah, this is the thing we use.
And I'll tell you more about it later.
But just a really nice presentable case that isn't too crazy expensive, that accommodates
good cooling quietly with a lot of drives.
That's my request.
LinuxActionShow.reddit.com.
Look for the feedback thread for 138.
And let me know.
Get to it, JB community.
I hope there's one out there because I haven't bought them yet.
And Chris has zero time.
Bitcoin is like up at 420 bucks right now.
So it's a good time to buy.
I'm just saying.
Yeah.
Wimpy, you have a suggestion.
Tell me about it.
Where did he go?
I don't hear you, Wimpy.
His mic is muted.
He linked to a Lincoln HP.
Oops.
There he's back.
Go ahead.
Go ahead, Wimpy.
Yeah.
They're end of life now.
But I've got two of the HP ProLiant microserver G7 in 54Ls.
And when I bought those, they were about 150 quid because you got a rebate on them.
It was quite good value.
And I've got five drives in there, one TFS and four in a RAID configuration.
They've also got the SATA connection on the back.
And I've had a four bay SATA drive hanging off the back of one of them in the past as
well.
Nice.
So if you want something that's low cost, but they're a proper case, they're a proper
pro grade case with proper fixtures and bolts and they look the business and they've got
the blue HP light that comes on the front.
I like them.
So they're cheap, they're not super powerful, but I can get 100 megasecond write speed through
my RAID array and that's spinning disks.
You were sick last week.
You had to jump out.
I did.
But I teased it a little bit.
I'm financing personally the hardware, so I had to buy it from Newegg directly because
I only really I don't have any money to my name except this is liquid in Bitcoin.
Yeah.
And so I got to spend Bitcoin to buy something and Newegg sells directly.
And if you buy if you buy directly from Newegg, you can use Bitcoin.
So what I did, Wimpy, just super recap, so people don't have to go back and listen either,
is we have a big build project.
We're going to switch some some internal functions over to Linux.
And so we needed six core processors and like 32 gigs of RAM.
And so all of that is we're going to assemble that, deploy Linux on it, and then put them
in production and make some series of episodes out of it.
Got the motherboards and the processors and stuff, you're looking for the cases.
And I figured I would wait again until Bitcoin kind of creep back up.
It's creeped back up to the 420 range.
Get some good value there.
Yeah.
And so if there's a nice case that's not crazy expensive that's sold by Newegg directly.
I just linked in the chat Fractal Design R5, the Define R5 is awesome and it's $90.
Oh, I've looked at that before.
The Fractal, huh?
It's very understated.
It doesn't.
You can also get a window version too if you want.
I don't really want a window.
No, I just you know what I would really I really think I got the first link.
It's got like a more marketing thing so you can see like all the ridiculous amount of
bays it has and it's got support for like extended GPUs and stuff.
Extended so I would really think that is three by five drives.
That does look classy.
I'll give it that classy is actually maybe actually the good way is maybe a good way
to go.
I actually have the R4 of this and it's awesome.
Kind of want one now.
I think what we're going to build is going to be something unique in media broadcasting
and especially online media broadcasting.
It'd be neat to turn this into like to do it this way and turn it kind of into a recipe.
I think so too.
Right?
Like here, get this.
Here's the software.
Well, the reason this is awesome, you can remove the bays and put them in different
configurations if you want to.
I've seen that.
Yeah.
Okay.
That is really cool.
Boy, that does look like a really nice case.
And that's on Newegg?
Yeah.
All right.
I will check that one out and I will put a link to that in the show notes if you guys
want to check that one out too because that does look really cool.
And there's also YouTube reviews coming in.
Yeah.
And so I would really love when we're done to have something that I don't know how we
would publish it but basically it would be a recipe like you said or it's difficult Wes
because it literally changes every three to six months.
Well, of course.
So I don't know exactly how to work it but almost something that you could reproduce
yourself and then sit down and accomplish a lot of what we do using all open source
tools.
I don't know yet.
We'll see.
But anyways, and I might be jumping ahead too because one of the things is, one of the
reasons why I'm being kind of secretive is we're going to build it and see how far we
get.
Right.
See what we have to work with.
Yeah.
And we're going to try to push it as far as we can.
And so I'm really excited about it.
And that's why, you know, that's just like part of what we're doing.
Like that's not even really Fest related but since everybody's out here we're going to
take advantage of it during Linux Fest and get everything done at the same time.
It's really cool.
Oh, I'm excited.
I am too.
I mean, the design stuff looks pretty cool.
I'll put a link to that in the show notes.
And let me see.
Where was that?
Oh boy.
We got YouTube videos too.
I'll put a link to the YouTube review from hardware conducts, hardware conducts in the
show notes as well.
Okay.
Any other closing thoughts from the moment before we wrap up guys?
Oh, you hear that?
Could you imagine?
Could you imagine you're sitting like at your local library at a Linux meeting and you ask
that question and nobody actually said anything?
That never happens.
There's always some guy who's got something to add.
Well.
Hello some guy.
Actually.
Are you guys serious?
Are you serious?
Are you just joshing with me?
Because that's what actually.
On the other hand.
Oh no.
Okay.
All right.
Very good.
You got it.
Yeah.
The thing is.
So here's the thing.
Oh no.
I almost forgot.
No.
Here's the other thing.
I'm getting this out of here.
I'm cutting you guys off.
And I almost forgot.
That brings us to the end of this week's episode of Linux Uploads.
The show that never ends.
We just got trolled there.
We just got trolled.
I know.
By our own Mumble Room.
We still got Poe Show coming up.
We still got.
It's a show that will end.
All right.
Well thank you for joining us.
Check the calendar.
Jupiterbroadcasting.com.
Slash calendar.
April is a crazy month.
You never know if things change.
I don't know.
Hopefully not.
Hopefully things just get even better.
But check it out at Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar where we convert it to your
own time zone because that crap seems to be hard for everybody to figure out.
jblive.tv is where we do it live.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com is where you go to give us feedback.
And you could also send me an email about any of the stuff I just talked about, Chris,
at Jupiterbroadcasting.com or at Chris Elias on Twitter would be even better.
See you next week.
I just want the new LTS with the new plasma desktop that actually I, there's no way I'm
the only person that wants this, right?
Sounds nice.
It sounds like the new 16.4 LTS, which is damn near release.
I know like a week or two after it's out, it's going to be available.
I grok that.
I want to try it now before release.
I understand that if I wait two weeks, but here's the reason why is I'm setting up my
machine now and I, if I like it, I don't want to reinstall.
I don't want to worry about this.
Yeah.
You want to test things out, feel the water.
If I, I'm going to do the review and if I like the desktop, that's going to become my
new permanent setup.
So I don't want to wait two weeks after the release because that doesn't really work for
me for this particular use case.
And what bugs me about it is, again, I'm not trying to make this an Archibuntu thing, but
on Arch, this problem is does literally does not exist.
Uh, yesterday I had plasma five, five, today I have plasma five, six, nothing else has
changed.
Like it's not a big deal.
I didn't have to change my release of arch and it's, it's so refreshing is it is so refreshing
to know that I, it just, it just, when it's, when they have it in the stable repo, which
was like a few, like a week afterwards, I got it.
There's probably other distros that make it just as easy like that.
Um, open suits is about to release their new builds probably like a couple of days or
so.
And then people who already have installed, we'll just update and get it.
Right?
Yeah.
That's beautiful.
That's all I'm asking for.
They keep everything the same name.
So it's like plasma five dash desktop.
So regardless of what version it is, it gets updated.
Yeah.
Five, six, one's already out on arch, which is, and so cause of what I'm, what I've done
is I've re since someone, uh, when I, I have not reloaded the Apollo since I got the factory
image, which came with 1510 and a couple of updates to support the track pad.
And I just wanted to review the machine for a while as it comes from the factory.
And now with 1604 getting here, uh, and plasma five, six and all this, I've decided to reload
the Apollo and try a few different things out.
And uh, what I would like to do is land on a final installation for the Apollo that I
just, I run for a while and I would like to try to run it for a couple of years.
I'm trying to find an installation that will be a multi-year installation for me.
That's quite the task.
Yeah, I know.
So it's either gotta be, it's either gotta be 1604 with a snap packages and Docker containers.
So you can run up-to-date things.
Right.
Or, uh, with, and I want, I want, and the other thing is I want the neon repos because
I always want to continue to get an up-to-date plasma desktop, which is, this is lining up
to be the perfect solution for me because the, all the pieces are beginning to be there.
But the last thing that I need to be able to do is, uh, I need to be able to keep it
updating constantly, keep it updating, always rolling, always going right.
And just for the desktop, just for some of the core applications, I think 1604 can do
that.
I know I can do it in Arch and I know I can go for multi-year installations in Arch.
This will be the first multi-year Ubuntu installation for me in a very, very, very long time.
There was a period of time where I was like four, five, six upgrades deep in an installation.
Wow.
And, and, or it probably wasn't six, it was probably like four.
Uh, it was a long time ago though.
Uh, and I have not been, I have not stuck with an Ubuntu, with the exception of a server
installation for a long time.
So I really would like, I would really love to pull this off because I would, I would
love to demo that installation during my review of 1604 in LAS.
But to get there, I gotta be able to get five, six installed now.
So my thought is maybe I will try installing Kabutu 15.10 instead, with the Plasma desktop,
right?
Get it just how you like.
Upgrade to, uh, Neon and then upgrade from that to 1604.
Interesting.
I kind of like to watch that.
I think it's, I think it would be the perfect blend because you still see, uh, you still
see a lot of stuff released for Ubuntu.
Yes.
Quote unquote.
Like anything you go download these days, anything that requires a download.
Linux support, it's Ubuntu support.
Yeah, it's pretty much, you're going to get an Ubuntu package.
If you're lucky, you're going to get 32, 64 bit options, right?
And they're devs.
Maybe an RPM.
Yeah.
And then, and then, and then if there, if there's somebody who actually knows Linux
users, there's also probably a Targesi.
And then that's really something.
And that Targesi will have both 32 and 64 builds in that thing, and it's a big download.
So that's, that's the software distribution on Linux right now.
And the, uh, the reality is, as somebody who is trying to understand things from an end
user's perspective, and also as somebody who wants to sort of sometimes jump in on some
of those commercially supported applications, there are advantages to having a machine running
Ubuntu because that would be my machine.
I try it on.
Oh, okay.
This is an Ubuntu thing.
I'll go try it on the Apollo.
And like, it makes a lot of sense.
Plus, you know, for games or whatever, whatever.
It makes sense to have an Ubuntu machine.
And if snap packages can make it possible for me to get new apps on an older installation,
this is really something I'm willing to give a shot because I think it'd be beneficial
for, boy, that's loud out there.
I think it'd be beneficial for the shows.
Did you ever look into doing the, uh, Tumbleweed option with KDE Krypton or Gnome Next as,
uh, the, uh, the desktop and then using OpenBuild to get your apps?
Yeah, you know, uh, I, the thing is, is for me, uh, I, uh, I don't particularly enjoy
using SUSE.
I think it's really a fantastically well-engineered distro with a lot of really good technology
around it.
Um, but I, you know, I had, uh, a dozen, maybe, maybe more, uh, SUSE Enterprise servers and
SUSE Enterprise desktops that I've managed in the past and I used SUSE throughout when
I did that.
Uh, so I spent some time with it and a lot has changed.
You know, uh, Zipper looks like a pretty competent tool, but I also find myself often getting
a little overwhelmed working with it, uh, especially some of the tools and stuff.
And so with my, with the way I look at, uh, SUSE, like any of the, uh, Tumbleweed or Leap
or whatever is they seem to be on a pretty good track and they seem to be pretty sharp.
So I bet, uh, sooner or later those things that I find rough will probably be smoothed
over.
So I just kind of keep an eye on it.
But for me, it's not really what I, I'm either going to go with an Arch or a Fedora or, uh,
an Ubuntu installation, not really likely to go with anything else.
Maybe Debian rolling, maybe, but probably not.
Well, I mean, I wouldn't go Debian rolling more than OpenSUSE because Debian rolling
is more like, you know, untested stuff.
Like they're, they're, they're tested, but yeah, it's probably something based off Debian
too.
I like Debian.
That's why I say Debian.
I really liked Debian.
I was like, oh, that's why I like Ubuntu actually, because I like Debian and then Ubuntu got
it better.
So, hey-o.
OpenSUSE's Leap is really interesting because, uh, they said there was going to be like not
very many releases or whatever for the backend.
They're going to do like, you know, once a year type thing and they can't, they've implied
that in the beginning.
Uh, they've already got, uh, updated to Plasma 5.5 for Leap and Plasma 5.6 is going to Tumbleweed
pretty soon.
What they mean is that the underlying structure, stuff like system D and the kernel are not
going to be updated on a regular basis, like, you know, like a weekly or whatever.
Um, but the desktops and the software that writes on top of that, uh, can be updated
on a regular, uh, pretty fast basis.
What I'm referring to is what they actually said of we don't have any plans, but we're
looking at like a one year release cycle.
I'm not talking about like what they could do or couldn't or like what they're doing
now.
I'm saying like what they said, they basically said we don't know exactly what we're doing,
but now they've essentially changed to the point where they do know and what they're
doing is awesome.
So it's basically just a, uh, base for the core system.
It's like a slower version of Tumbleweed at this point.
Right.
Um, there is, I don't know if you guys know, if anybody knows which one I'm talking about,
but there is, uh, there's a couple of, there's a thread on, on, on our Linux or somewhere
where our Brown is answering a lot of people's common questions about OpenSUSE or confusions.
Do you know what I'm talking about?
Where he talks about like, yeah, software doing it.
He's doing it in both the, our Linux and Linux, actually show separate.
Yeah.
But there's one like that's just like really recent in the last couple of days.
Is that what you're talking about?
Both of them.
Yeah.
He's doing on both.
Uh, he made a, he made an article about the, what, what's, what, what's, uh, what's good
about OpenSUSE and stuff like that.
So, uh, it's kind of like those threads are devolving from that article.
I think what I find fascinating about the threads is not any one particular specific
confusion or a problem, but just how, how brilliantly they demonstrate how complicated
some of the systems and tools are in, in the distro.
Um, there's, there's so many things in there where, uh, his response is, well, that's not
really the way we recommend people do it.
Or we've never actually documented this to be the way you should do.
We've never actually stated this or that's the way we used to do it.
But now we, there's a lot of that, uh, there's just a lot of ways of doing a few different
things in there that those threads, I think, I think our Brown maybe gets, uh, he gets,
they are so focused on the technology and the engineering, but they're not zooming out
and actually listening to the meta thing that people are saying.
The bigger thing that people are saying is that it's too complicated.
It's too confusing.
You guys are still, you guys are talking about tumbleweed and leap and I, and, and, and I'm,
I'm still grasping to fully understand it.
Uh, I mean, I do understand it, but I can quickly get them confused.
I can quickly misunderstand like, uh, Wes right now, not to put you on the spot, but
right now, if you wanted to get KDE 5.6, would you install tumbleweed or leap?
Tumbleweed.
Cause that's the rolling one?
Yes.
Okay.
I think that's the one I would say too, but I could get it in leap too, right?
Rotten?
Not yet.
No.
Okay.
You see, I don't follow.
I don't know.
And you know, I don't, I don't know.
I mean, I know I started to complain about Ubuntu software management, but this is very
confusing to me too.
Uh, it's just, it's stable and tumbleweeds the rolling.
Right.
I, I still though, I, I don't know, uh, quite to understand what to expect from which when
it comes to like, well, if I want five, six today, I'm sure a few Google searches would
resolve it for me.
I'm not, I'm not saying it's an impossible question to answer.
What I'm, what I'm implying is that it's still just a little confusing and people only
care so much when what they already have works well for them.
And so if it's too, if, if the on-ramp is, is too much of a climb, uh, I got other stuff
to do.
I think is what a lot of people feel and think.
Well, if you wanted to get five, six right now in OpenSUSE, it's just install tumbleweed
and activate Krypton, which is the like next version.
So you get to use the beta stuff before it's officially released as builds.
So it's, it's still not, it's not like it's like untested stuff, but it's kind of like
Would that mean that I would then get like five, seven or like five, six, one before
you get five, six, you get five, six, you get, you get the continuous branch of five,
six until KDE releases their latest version, uh, or like the latest betas of the next build.
So you'd get five, seven at some point with Krypton, but it wouldn't be like immediate.
Okay.
And heavens is also pointing out a blog post over at news.openSUSE.org that talks about
the different choices for KDE.
I mean, I understand, I do get it, uh, but at the same time, like it does take, it takes,
I know this sounds really, this is the problem is I think they, they, they underestimate
the cognitive load that just keeping track of what the hell they're doing takes.
And I know they're like, oh, that's, it's really simple.
It's simple to them because you're the guys that dreamed it up.
That's why it's simple to you.
You use it every day.
And if you look at the threads, uh, he's so good at actually specifically addressing the
questions and saying how he should do it that he's, I don't know if he's grokking the overall
issue there.
My, that's just my impressions from afar.
I'm going to kind of give them an excuse on, we are used to following how Ubuntu does it.
And Ubuntu is somewhat similar to Debian and, um, other distros have picked up names that
are already used in the cycles or the way other distros cycle.
So we are used to seeing that cycle pattern and it's easier to recognize.
So actually what they described in here is not that different is that the naming conventions
are not, you know, easily to correlate.
So you say, think tumbleweed and you use leap and then it's like you usually you are used
to having, is this unstable or untested or experimental and you know, you did the notion
of forward, you know, and unfortunately our brain in a way and added to that when they
are coming up with the other distros, which are, you know, dinosaurs in the distros community,
you're having the sensation that they have to show what they have different and they
end up having to explain much more than the other distro.
When you go and you pick up Debian, you say, I picked up Debian and you maybe mentioned
one thing because everyone assumes all of the rest of the luggage that Debian already
built over the years.
When you say, I'm going to pick openSUSE that you kind of have to say, you know, because
these, these and that and that, and suddenly you're explaining too many things and it seems
confused, but it's just because of the time that they are arriving as a visible thing.
That's when people, when you say I'm running Debian, they think you're running the oldest
possible crap you could possibly do.
So that's not even, that's not the issue of the naming thing.
I think it's because they have terrible marketing.
Like they, they have a lot of cool technology and just fundamentally the way that the software
and tools that they have are amazing.
They have, they have, the open QA system is amazing and if you just, if you, if you look
at it and see how it works, it will blow you away, but it's really hard to figure out how
it works because it's the most complicated website to go through you could imagine.
Like it makes, it makes a folder structure like, you know, those, those websites where
it's just like a directory of files.
It makes that seem easier to navigate because there, you have to, you have to know that
you had to click a particular link in this, like they have an order where you want to
see a result for one of the tests.
You click the name of the, the test, the date of the test, then you go into which package
you want to see, which version of the test, then you have to click a link for let's say
a Gnome test.
Then you have to click an icon to show a video of that test and the, it's just kind of hard
to get to where you're going.
But once you find it and you realize that this thing is doing an automatic test, showing
a video, highlighting different elements of the test, like testing the deck, the desktop
loading, running, opening applications, playing audio sounds, playing music, watching videos
and it's doing this automatically, that is amazing.
So here's my, here's my, kind of my thoughts on this for, for SUSE as a desktop.
Open SUSE Leap or Tumbleweed.
I think the biggest, the biggest distro besides maybe Fedora that would benefit from XGG apps
or universal app installers or however we're going to get there, it would be SUSE.
Because at the end of the day, it comes down to, it's really got to be dead simple for
people to get software installed to do work.
If I want to convince people like Michael Dominic from Coderadio, he's doing a Linux
testing experiment.
Yeah, the last few, the last like three or four weeks of Coderadio, he's been reporting
on his experiences of switching to Ubuntu.
And he went to Ubuntu because he would, he wants to know, he just needs a path to know
how to download and install software and it needs to work reliably because he's simply
using this to code.
He's writing Android apps right now and he just needs a workstation to develop on.
And the timing is perfect because his Mac died and he needed to pick something himself
on his own, install it and get rolling.
And it's not that SUSE doesn't have the tools or the build service or the great software.
The issue really comes down to the workflow that an average web dev might sit down, like
we just looked at that Stack Overflow survey, a huge percentage of the developers are, consider
themselves to be web devs.
Okay, well if they're web devs, then they could web dev on Linux.
They don't have to web dev on a Mac or Windows.
So they, but they need a workflow that is reliable and reproducible for damn near every
single application for Linux they download from the web.
Ubuntu delivers that right now simply by market adoption.
But if XDG apps came along and you could take that one download and you could run it on
Fedora, Ubuntu or SUSE, then all of a sudden that barrier, that wall that's been around
SUSE, the software availability of commercial applications, things like Sublime Text and
Telegram and Herupad and some of the SIP clients that we have attempted to install, all of
that stuff that has been traditionally so hard to get on SUSE, even though there's all
these different methods to get software on there, that wall would fall because every
application would be available for SUSE all of a sudden packaged that way.
And then all of the technical merits of the distribution would be way more important,
right?
It becomes way more important.
But right now, the fundamental box you've got to check is can I get my job done?
And for some of us, that box is absolutely checked.
But for a lot of noobs out there, because that workflow is not consistent, how you get
that Sublime Text, how you get that Herupad or how you get that Telegram download or that
Google Chrome link, because I'm a brand new user, right?
When I go download Google Chrome, we watch Chase do this.
He goes to the Google Chrome website and he looks for a download link.
It never even crosses his mind to look in a repository or a software website, never
crosses his mind, because he's literally been using Windows for 20 years, right?
So he goes and downloads the deb file for Google Chrome and installs it on his desktop,
just like Michael Dominic did that night when he had to reload his Dell machine in the middle
of the night from a thumb drive and he didn't have anybody to call on.
He knew that he needed to go get Google Chrome to do half his workload, so he went and downloaded
that deb file from the website, and that's an expected workflow.
And with these new universal applications, we could reproduce that same exact thing.
It's not ideal.
That's how I want to get my software, but that's how they want to get their software.
And until that's going to be available, I don't see Sousa getting a ton of traction
because there's too much of a barrier for that kind of thing, for Sousa right now.
And there's lots of work around, and if you go post a question in Reddit, there's going
to be somebody super smart that'll give you the exact command or maybe two commands to
run on the command line to fix it.
But that's not a way to solve the problem.
That's not going to work at scale.
Wes, there is a big old long thing, gosh, I wish I would have printed this out.
I feel like I want to read this, but it's really long.
It's from R Brown at OpenSousa, and he is writing here at the KDE mailing list.
And I don't know if you guys have seen this.
It's how to handle KDE not respecting your distros requirements.
And it's in response to some packaging issues and about GNOME releases.
And I think it's really interesting.
We almost don't even know the rest of the discussion to read some of the interesting
points that he makes here.
He says, while I strongly agree with the sentiment that KDE should choose its own path, I think
it's somewhat enlightening to consider that the competitive field KDE has to operate in.
While in my last email I pointed out KDE is the default in only one out of the Distro
Watch top 10 and two out of the Distro Watch top 25, GNOME is the default in three out
of the top 10 and seven out of the top 25.
GNOME is the default option in all enterprise Linux distributions.
GTK and other GNOME apps and technologies provide the foundation of the default choice
of another four of the top 25 distributions.
QT provides the foundation of only one of the other top 25 default desktops.
The remaining 11 either do not have a default or opt for lightweight options like LXD or
XFCE, et cetera.
Or to put it another way, GNOME and its stack is at least three times more popular with
distributions than KDE and its stack.
We've seen this trend mirrored even within OpenSUSE.
Even as KDE with the default option for our installer, over recent years we've transitioned
from a strong majority KDE distribution to one where KDE is now used by less than 50%
of our user base.
Why all the doom and gloom?
Because I think it's important we be realistic about where we are before we can improve things.
Doing the same as the other guys is not a viable option when they have the dominant
position.
They already have all the buy-in from the wider ecosystem of distributions who put them
first.
They can afford to make questionable choices.
It seems no matter how questionable their choices may have already been, it's not negatively
impacting their adoption rates compared to KDE.
KDE has to be better, smarter, leaner to compete.
It needs to be easier for packages and packagers to work with than the alternatives, easier
to put together, easier to maintain, and easier to track changes.
I personally think the whole Plasma Application Frameworks Qt split has dramatically increased
the workload of distribution packagers here for little to no benefit for users, although
I do recognize it makes it easier to develop.
Look at the applications.
Are they all necessary?
Does KDE need to offer an office suite when almost everyone really just uses LibreOffice
these days?
Is Scrooge a worthy competitor to GNU Cache?
Does KDE really need two text editors?
There's a duplication even among KDE's own web application offerings.
Never mind when we put up against the backdrop of distributions are wanting to offer.
I think there's room for streamlining there.
And I know it's painful to suggest, but right now KDE is the biggest, heaviest desktop-oriented
software stack for Linux distributions.
All of the competition, even GNOME, is smaller, leaner, and therefore more readily integratable
into distributions.
But maybe going on a diet isn't an option.
If KDE wants to remain technically large and continue to provide such a broad offering,
then at least it has to do a better job of selling itself to distributions.
In addition to the clear technical information regarding dependencies and such, distributions
need clear information about why users should adopt KDE in order to parrot that to their
users.
What are KDE's selling points?
What are the hooks which make KDE better than the rest?
I fear KDE is currently making the same mistake I saw OpenSUSE make in the past by only trying
to sell itself on technical merit and mostly letting software speak for itself.
As I understand why, I've been saying for years that Qt is a superior platform for desktop
and desktop application developments from GTK, but that being true hasn't changed how
many distributions put their faith into which desktop stack first.
Testing through software capability only speaks to a very narrow market, and problems with
software quality erode that market dreadfully quickly.
And I think it's safe to say that KDE has had some severe problems with software quality
lately.
And I do not think that putting all of the responsibility of testing onto a distribution
is a sensible strategy to turn that around.
Is there more KDE can do to make sure its offerings are well tested before distributions
have to find a way to make all of the parts work together?
KDE needs to make it very easy for distributions to sell the premise, the promise, and the
benefits of using KDE to their users.
Where possible, that should be more meaningful than just a bunch of screenshots and feature
descriptions.
People should have an idea of what the KDE project is trying to achieve and therefore
be able to buy into that concept by using your software.
Right now, I don't see much information available to help weave such a story.
That's my two cents anyway.
Man, that's a great post.
Wow.
Yeah, it's really good.
There's a few parts that I massively disagree of saying, and it's incredibly heavy.
But as far as the fact that GTK and Gnome have such a huge lead as far as users, that's
totally true.
Even when Gnome does incredibly stupid things, it doesn't seem to stop anything.