This is Linux Unplugged Episode 40 for May 13th, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that just hit its distinguished
forties. My name is Chris. My name is Matt. Hey there, Matt. Forty weeks, buddy, right
in a row, too. Man. I mean, it's no Coderadio 100 or TechSnap 160, whatever, but I'm a little
proud of it, because this is just a little idea we have. We're like, hey, we've got too
much show every week. Let's do another show. Right. Here we are 40 weeks later. I think
it's turned out pretty good. Not to pat ourselves on our own back or anything like that. No.
It's going to be a fun show today, too. We're introducing a new segment in this week, so
I'll tell you about that in just a second. Of course, we've got our feedback like we
always do, and two developers from the LXQT project have joined us to discuss our first
look that we had over the weekend at LXQT, just at their first major beta. We're going
to chat with them in a little bit. Then we'll get to that new segment. So that new segment
I mentioned, we're going to call it the Mumble Roundtable. Right now, I've submitted a link
to our chat room, and they are voting on what should be the roundtable's topic. I've proposed
two topics. I don't pick the topic. The live stream picks the topic. Right now, the two
topics we have proposed to them is the orange box that Canonical announced today. It is
an Ubuntu cluster in a box. It's a pretty cool concept, and it's made up of like 10
NUCs in a box, 10 Intel NUCs in a box, and it's a pretty neat deal. Also, the second
topic that is being voted on, so there's two choices. Choice number two, antivirus pioneer
Alan Solomon thinks that antivirus is dead, and he says he switched to Linux instead.
So whichever one is the winning topic towards the end of the show will be our open roundtable
discussion that we'll get to. So I'm looking forward to that to kind of give our virtual
lug a chance to stretch out a little bit and pontificate on a good topic. But, Matt, before
we get to that, we should probably start with the feedback, because there was something
that, man.
Oh, boy.
Chief of the Broadcasting was off the air basically yesterday for Chrome users.
Yeah, what was up with that?
Case of the Mondays. So Mark writes in, and he says, hey, I can get an old malware warning.
I'm running Ubuntu 14.04 with XFCE and Chromium. I like that he's giving us the XFCE, like,
just so you know. I'm getting a malware error in Chromium, but I'm running on it. OK. Tried
to download the HD video version of Last 3.11, and I got a malware warning from Chromium.
Probably a bug, but I thought I should let you know about it. Love the show. Now, we
got a lot of emails like this, but Mark had a good, concise email. And Mark also was kind
enough to include a screenshot. So if you didn't get to enjoy this error that was happening
to us yesterday, there it is. It says, the website ahead contains malware.
Oh, boy.
It says, Chromium has blocked access. Now, if you read carefully, it actually says, Chromium
has blocked access to www.podtrack.com. It actually wasn't a problem with the Jupyter
Broadcasting website. It was a problem with the download stat tracking service we use.
PodTrack's kind of like the gold standard in legitimate podcast statistic download counts.
As good of a service there is, it's pretty much PodTrack. Now, the problem was their
whole domain got blacklisted by the Google anti-malware whatever it is, and so every
podcaster that uses PodTrack had their downloads unavailable to Chromium users and then Chrome
users and then eventually Firefox and eventually Safari and other browsers later in the day
all got their downloads blocked. I mean, this is not only taking out Jupyter Broadcasting,
but it took out Twit, it took out NPR, the Nerdist, the Discovery Networks. All of those
guys that use PodTrack were nailed by this. Now, our awesome web developer, Aaron, was
able to, about midway in the day, I said, all right, I call uncle. Aaron, can you please
go in there and just pull all the PodTrack links from our site? Because this also affected
the HTML5 video player. So even just trying to stream video from our website, the only
thing that worked was the live stream. And Lynn this morning, earlier this morning, PodTrack
sends an email. He says, hi, Chris. Dear Chris, yesterday we discovered an issue with the
PodTrack domain that impacts some non-iTunes podcast users. Yeah, like everyone using Chrome.
It's like, come on, really guys?
Yeah. You know, for those idiots that don't use iTunes, the Chrome browser blocked PodTrack.com
domain reporting it as malware, followed later by Firefox and Safari as they use the same
malware list as Google. At the same time, Chrome's diagnostic page said there's no reports
of malware for this domain in the last 90 days. And for more than eight years, we have
not seen a browser return the domain as malware. They scanned the servers ourselves and we
didn't find any malware. We requested a review from Google and sometime between 1 a.m. and
7 a.m. Eastern today, so that's this morning, Chrome and other browsers corrected their
listing of PodTrack.com domain and the services are working in all browsers again. So we essentially
just didn't have, so for the first half of the day we didn't have downloads, for the
second half of the day and into today we didn't have any tracking. So not a great day for
us and not a great day for podcast listeners either. And in a way too, doesn't it show
you how dangerous it can be to consolidate power like that on the web? Because even though
that anti-malware tool does a lot of good and it saves a lot of Windows users' butts,
it also can go very badly. And in this case, it essentially took an entire industry, the
Google malware system took an entire industry off the air. Now did PodTrack have a legitimate
malware? They claim not, but maybe they did. I mean they do use IIS after all, so it seems
entirely conceivable they did have something. But the end result for me was like, oh well
sorry, all of our listeners and downloaders are getting this big old scary error that
makes it look like the Jupiter Broadcasting website has malware on it. So it's not a good
experience all around. And I hope that Google, this isn't the first time we've seen something
like this happen, I think this is maybe the largest scale outage that the Google anti-malware
service has caused, and it's not a great experience. So I apologize to you guys out there who are
trying to download the Linux Action Show or the FoShow on Monday or Coda Radio and got
that error. Monday's a big day for us, so I know it affected a lot of folks out there,
I apologize about that. But it should all be resolved now. And the RSS feeds, for the
most part, weren't impacted as far as I know. So if you ever want to just bypass it, just
subscribe in your favorite RSS client, maybe it's G Potter or Miro or whatever it is, and
that might have solved the problem.
All right Matt, next email comes in from Gargan, I think, Jarjan?
Gargan, okay.
Well I'm not, I apologize, I'm not getting that one right. He has a little follow-up
on our fragmentation time bomb discussion. He says he feels that fragmentation isn't
really an issue. Consider Qt and GTK, so what? You have them both on Windows and even OS
again. Does using Qt on iOS fragment iOS? Not one bit. It's still iOS, a well-defined
target for developers with a semi-stable API. Look at the toolkits that Windows has. Microsoft
foundation classes, the Windows template library, Smart Win++, the Object Windows library,
Windows Forms, Windows Presentation Foundation, Qt, GTK+, Swing, and WX Widgets, all on Windows.
The problem is a fragmented core. Examples would be the multitude of glibc, unstable
kernel driver API, systemd, sysv, upstart, glib, mesa, kairo, gstreamer, pulseaudio,
and versions that compromise, or all versions that compromise the bedrock of the OS. So
I was arguing yesterday that, yeah, the core is stable. He's saying, no it's not. It doesn't
matter what's happening up in user land. Let them use whatever toolkits they want. What
really matters is we have stable APIs and ABIs to target. And that's something we've
heard from driver developers for years too. Do you think, Matt, maybe I was a little off
the mark? Maybe I was misrepresenting how fragmented the Linux core is?
I don't think so. I definitely see what they're saying. And I definitely agree with it to
an extent. But I also think that because we're so freewheeling that we don't really have
a dominant anything in the ecosystem. And I think that's probably kind of where a lot
of people find frustration, including yourself. I think that's kind of the frustration we
have. So I half agree with him. But at the same time, I also think that we do need to
kind of, in user land, kind of figure out what we're doing, at least with the dominant
distributions. And then everybody else can just do whatever they want.
That being said, our biggest problem is we have half the camp that adamantly loves the
fact that we have no dominant anything. And then we have the other half the camp that
hates it. And as long as we have that, I don't ever see this getting resolved. I think it's
always going to be a good effort.
Always wasted effort, Matt, until it gets resolved. Yeah. And you know, it's kind of
like evolution in a sense. Like eventually dominant strains and implementations stand
out in a way. And eventually, it's a lot messier. It takes a lot longer. I think it eventually
gets worked out. And I think things like system D, and I think the kernel API thing is a valid
complaint. But I don't think it's as valid as it used to be. So I think it's over time,
it is actually just kind of improving upon itself.
Nico writes in. He says, thanks for the great show. I really like it, but. And there's always
a but, Matt.
Always the but.
I was extremely disappointed with your discussion on Menjia in episode 39. I almost never write
any kind of comments to anybody, but this just got me so sad that I just have to write
this one. Now, he specifically laid out what he didn't like. I wouldn't went ahead and
cut it because these emails that we're getting these days are just way too long. So I'm editing
a little bit. So I just I wanted to kind of just touch on some of his core points. He
says, first of all, what I was the most disappointed with was that you guys obviously did no research
on the subject yourself. You just let the Mamba room tell you what they think about
Menjia and maybe it's OK, but by doing so, you sure made it sound a whole lot more difficult
and strange than it really is. And I must say, I don't I do not even understand half
of what the complaints were. So long story short, do your own research. I think he's
going to give any specifics. I mean, it's basically he just did exactly what he said
the Mamba. Well, I kind of cut some of it to make it. I mean, the one thing like he
took the most issue with was our discussion around packages and and like some of the how
some of the weird packages in the repos and stuff like that night. I just saw him based
into discussion. I mean, it's he loses right there. I mean, it's far as I'm that's not
even a debate now. I mean, that's not to say it's not a nice distribution from other aspects
of it, but that's that's through years and years of banging my face into RPM distros.
That's that's well researched. Yeah, I mean, I do see your point there. I mean, I don't
know, man. I mean, maybe we should put it on the schedule down the road in a few weeks.
Maybe we should throw Miji on our machines and just kind of, you know, see what we maybe
maybe, you know, like because I was pretty sure when we took the arts challenge, I was
going to be like Mr. Nose up near. This is stupid. Yeah, I know. And I'm speaking exclusively
of packaging worth with arch. I had no experience with the packaging. Yeah, that's true. I mean,
we do know magic dust to make RPM suck less. And they maybe they do. I don't know. There
is you are PMI in there. Yeah. Well, you know, I mean, I think it's worth a try. Sure. Yeah,
I see what you're saying, though. Like arch is a fully different piece. But you're you've
been down the RPM alley before, you know, what's at the end of that looking distro.
I mean, I'm not not negating that at all. I think they did a lot of things right. But
at the end of the day, for me, it's more than appearance packages, packages, packages. I
I could have the ugliest desktop in the world. But if I got the packages I need, I'm happy.
You know, that's just me. Yeah, I you know what? You make a lot of sense. And so let's
give it some thought. Maybe you and I can do a little collab after Sunday on Sunday's
last and figure out if there's a spot where we can slip in a Miji review and you know,
but I kind of I kind of see your point, too. Like we have I got a certain time you've been
around the block enough that you kind of learn like, you know, sometimes there's just no
change in a distro. I don't know. We'll see. I don't mean I don't want to make it so heavy.
So you and I will talk on Sunday. Maybe we'll decide to schedule it in the last and we'll
do it. I have a feeling we're going to do it, but we'll talk about it. All right. With
our rights in, he says, Hey, there, Chris and Matt. Love the show. I'm writing in for
an idea of how to Linux for how to Linux. Now, we get a lot of these, but I just thought
I'd take this opportunity to kind of update everybody on where we're at with how to Linux
is I'm writing in on an idea for the show. My idea is using a digital ocean droplet and
install a light desktop on it using X to go and X RDP server on a thin client to connect
to the droplet over the Internet. You could have local sound, print and drive forwarding.
I realize it's not a simple how to, but I'd love to see your approach to the task. Cheers
for an interesting idea. Turning a digital ocean droplet into essentially a remote cloud
desktop server. So I'm going to give you guys an update on where we're at with how to Linux.
But first, why don't I give a thanks to our first sponsor? And that is Digital Ocean.
Digital Ocean is simple cloud hosting. And I got to tell you guys, we got a great brand
new promo code for the month of May. Guess what it is? Unplugged May. Unplugged May will
get you a ten dollar credit so you can try out digital ocean for two months for free.
If you get the five dollar, you don't know what digital ocean is. Digital Ocean is a
simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way to
spin up a cloud server. Now, you're like, oh, sure. Sure, Chris. Sure. I got a tweet
this week. I think our new record is thirty seven seconds. Thirty seven seconds. Now,
most digital ocean users can spin up a cloud server in about fifty five seconds or so.
Not our audience. Our audience is now thirty seven seconds. But here's the best part. Pricing
plan started only five dollars a month for five hundred twelve megabytes of RAM, a twenty
gigabyte SSD, one CPU and a terabyte of transfer for five dollars. That's a you know exactly
how much you're going to pay. It's a fixed cost. It's not going to scale up for CPU usage.
You know, you're not going to get you're not going to get charged one price for two hundred
gigabytes of transfer and a different price for nine hundred gigabytes of transfer. You
get a terabyte. It's included with that. And Digital Ocean has data center locations in
New York, San Francisco, Singapore and Amsterdam. Their interface is simple. Their control panel
is super intuitive and power users can replicate this control panel on a larger scale with
their straightforward API. I have heard so many awesome stories of what our audience
is using Digital Ocean for. So go over there, use the promo code for the month of May. Unplugged
May. One word, unplugged May will get you that ten dollar credit. You can try out a
Digital Ocean droplet for two months, even if you only use it for two months or just
increase your own skill set. Work on something that you've been wanting to do. Scratch that
itch. Try out that thing. They've got a great image backup system. So if you screw something
up, just take a snapshot first. Revert right back. You get tier one bandwidth. It's all
sitting on top of SSD drives with, I got to tell you, some of the best data center locations
in the world. DigitalOcean.com. Use the promo code unplugged May to get that ten dollar
credit. Go check them out and see what you can do. A really big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. Every month I find something new to do with my droplet
and in this Sunday's last, I think we're going to be scratching an itch for you guys or at
least we're going to make something itch and you're going to want to scratch it. So keep
Digital Ocean in mind when we start talking about some server stuff on Sunday. DigitalOcean.com
and use the promo code unplugged May and a really big thank you to those guys. Really
appreciate them sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show and there's so many cool things you can
do with it and you know what? It's all built on top of Linux so that's pretty cool too,
right? So now you're supporting a company that also runs on top of Linux using KVM and
all kinds of stuff. They really get their users. I think that's the big takeaway. It's
just awesome. Now we have joining us two developers from the LXQT project. Now I know them by
their mumble names but maybe we'll get to know their actual names. Starting first is
Jay Lanch. Am I saying that right? That's Jerome Leclanche. Jay Leclanche. Jerome, welcome
to Linux Unplugged and we also have PC Man joining us. And PC Man, what's your first
name? PC Man? My name is in Chinese. My name is Hongren Yu. So I use this ID for short.
And you're talking to us from Taiwan, right? Yes, I'm from Taiwan. And Jerome is in Cambridge
I believe. So we got a 10 o'clock and a 5 a.m. are here with us. So I really appreciate
you guys joining us. We're going to keep it brief since it is so after hours and the connection
is a little shaky but the one thing that really struck me is LXQT as we looked at it on Sunday
on the Linux action show, kind of looks like it's almost for a lot of users, Matt said
he might be one of them, ready to use today. How far along do you guys see yourself? I
don't know who's maybe the best person to ask. PC Man, what is your role at the LXQT
project? Melanie, I'm responsible for the file manager.
Oh okay. And some other parts, yeah. And Jay Lanch, what is your role at the LXQT project?
I do mostly system administration and UX but PC Man is underselling himself. He's really
the guy who built the original LXD Qt project before we merged with Razer Qt. Well, big
respect because I think the work is remarkable already. So PC Man, I'll start with you then.
How far along do you consider it right now? Is this sort of halfway baked? Is this five
percent baked? Is it almost done? Where do you see it at right now in your opinion?
It's not completely finished now. We still need some more translations and artwork and
there are some remaining bugs but actually it's already working and use it daily.
How are you guys seeing response from a user base? Are you seeing people circle around
and get excited? We've had a really huge uptake from our recent
release. You got to understand that before it was LXQT, it was Razer Qt. Razer Qt already
had its own kind of community. LXQT really is the continuation of that. It was just kind
of on the back burner for a while. So are you guys, being honest with me, are
you on a Qt holy war or is this one of these things that you were looking at it from a
practical standpoint. You said, I like the direction Qt is going in. I think we could
build a compelling desktop around it. This is a major going from a GTK based desktop
switching over to Qt, merging two popular projects. Is there a larger motivation there
PC Man? Yes, actually we are. One of the reasons is
the GTK3. When we try to port LXDE to GTK3, we encounter many problems and some APIs are
changed and some even with different behavior and the themes are changed too. So actually
it's not very backward compatible. So was the sense that it was moving away from
being a toolkit for all and maybe a toolkit specific for the GNOME desktop and since you
weren't necessarily interested in creating the GNOME desktop, you needed to move something
that gave you more flexibility and a quote unquote freedom? Am I grokking?
Pretty much correct. This is pretty much what we've seen from a lot of GTK developers who
feel that GTK is becoming way too GNOME centric. This was the experience of the LXDE desktop
but on the Razer side of things, we just like Qt. We've always been Qt developers and we
want to continue being Qt developers. So it was kind of just two projects with the same
goals. Right. And you guys seem to be positioning
the desktop in a pretty good spot. There's a lot of people who are seeing these trends
that are interested in Qt development and I think that's a big one. I think people that
are looking to switch to Linux that are interested in Qt development but they're also interested
in having a more minimal desktop experience. And when you guys decided to go forward with
the merger, was it with this sort of 50,000 foot view of, well, this is the way the landscape
is going and so we should make this merger or was it, this is what I want to do and now
just by happenstance, you guys seem to be in this really great position for the desktop?
I'll take this one. Basically, when we decided to merge, the LXDE Qt project was just getting
started and it was based on a lot of Razer Qt parts and on the side of Razer Qt, we had
a lot of problem developer wise. We had about four or five active developers and it kept
cycling between people leaving the project and people joining the project so we never
really had a solid team. So the merger was really from a need of having more activity
and was really successful in that sense. How many people are working on the LX Qt project
at this point? I would say about a dozen but as I said, we've had a lot of uptake recently.
Any talks of like a commercial sponsor who might provide funding for some full-time development?
You guys been approached? No approach? No?
We've not really had, I mean, some people contacted us not directly for sponsoring but
we're definitely open to it and a couple of our community members want to fund the project
as well. Great. The other really great use I could see
for LXQt are enterprise desktops where they want a cute environment and they don't necessarily
need Gnome 3 or full KDE. These are just business class machines. Perhaps a more traditional
interface is actually a performance or I guess a productivity improvement. It's a good thing
for productivity to be a little more classical. To me, I could seriously see commercial entities
getting interested in wanting to encourage LXQt's development because imagine a CentOS
based distribution around the LXQt desktop. It's like this is your iron solid bullet proof
desktop that looks and works a lot like your old XP machine did but this is now you guys
are a Qt development shop. This is a made up scenario but here's your Qt development
shop. Here's a great desktop that works for you.
Then of course, it's for enthusiast users who want to eek the most performance for games
and things like that but still want to feel like they're not totally stuck in the 90s.
I think it's a very interesting project, guys. Was there anything you wanted to mention or
touch on from our review that we did on Sunday or any follow up before I let you guys go?
I wanted to say I really liked the review. I watched it yesterday. I really liked the
review. The KDE system settings, you were talking about system settings, having three
or four different system settings and you actually reviewed the KDE system settings
not the actual LXQt one.
It's hard to tell when you do it on an Ubuntu installation. At the same time, I also felt
like LXQt was sort of like, hey, whatever you want to use to configure. I didn't feel
like I was being forced to use a specific set of configuration tools too. Is that intentional
or is that just where things are at right now?
What do you mean?
Well, for example, it seemed to me like, and I don't know if this was just the PPA archive
that I was pulling it from, but if I wanted to use the KDE settings to configure something,
it seemed to work. It seemed to allow it for what I was doing at least. I was just curious
if I know there's a modular aspect to LXQt. Is that the modular you mean? I can use this
as my default file manager. I use this as my default configuration program for my whatever.
Or will there be a very specific set of LXQt configuration tools that as the desktop matures,
those are the ones you use regardless?
Okay, it's modular, but it's not that modular as you think because part of this is because
the design of Qt. When you run some KDE programs, you will notice that they do not apply the
setting from your Qt config because they have their own module and doing this. KDE guys
have their own platform plugin to improve integration with KDE, so their programs sometimes
do not load the settings from Qt config, so you will have inconsistent settings among
the Qt program sometimes, and it's hard to solve. We suffer from a similar problem because
independent Qt programs sometimes load different settings than yours. We implemented Qt plugin
to solve this, so there are still some limitations and some settings only apply to our desktop
session, so not all of the tools can be used outside LXQt, but we will do our best to make
it.
All right, that makes sense. I understand how that could happen. Yeah, it seems like
that, and that's probably something in a few years it'll get worked out on the Qt side.
All right, guys. Well, thank you very much for coming on the show today. I really appreciate
it. I know the times are a little crazy where you guys are at, and all over the world too
at that, especially PC man. I really appreciate it, and keep up the awesome work on the Pac-Man
file manager or the PC file manager. Anyways, that is a great file manager, and I'm loving
the Qt implementation, so great work on that. Matt, I've got a little question I want to
toss towards the audience that's going to help inform this Sunday's Linux action show.
In fact, it's a bit of a survey. It's something I want to talk about. We've talked before
on the Linux action show about building the ultimate Linux home server, and in the past
our builds have always been Ubuntu-based, 1204 and 1210, somewhere in there, and so
now that we're over at JB1, we've been sort of building out a new server infrastructure.
We've got a free NAS here. It's a free NAS mini from IX Systems. Then we have in front
of that a Proxmox machine. It's running multiple different instances, and I'm going to go into
more detail on the big show, of Linux in front of that free NAS VM, and we're loading up
different services on there, and I kind of want to ask the audience what makes your perfect
Linux server. If you're going to load on your house or something like that, so I just put
the link to the survey in the chat room if people want to fill that out, and while they're
doing that, while they're answering the questions, it's a pretty quick survey, while they're
answering those questions, I want to tell you about our second sponsor this week, and
that is Ting. What is Ting? Ting is mobile. It makes sense. It's my mobile service provider
and Matt's mobile service provider, and you know what we love about Ting? You only pay
for what you use. I know it sounds insane. It sounds impossible. There's no way you only
pay for what you use, but that's what's great about Ting. It's $6 a month for every line
you have, and then just any applicable taxes, and your usage on top of that. I know. You're
like, Chris, that's too good of a deal, and I'd be like, well, listener, how come you
don't trust me by this point, but if you don't believe me, maybe you'd believe Kyra.
Ting keeps rates simple. We don't make you pick a plan. Instead, you just use your phone
as you normally would. How much you use determines how much you pay each month. You can have
as many devices as you want on one account. That's good, because when you use more, you
pay less per minute, message, or megabyte of data. Your usage plus $6 per active device
on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill. Simple. That's what we mean when we
say mobile. That makes sense.
One of the great things about Ting too is the Ting dashboard. As I've been a customer
now for well over a year, I really, really appreciate this. The other thing that's really
great about Ting is they're great at just blogging about what they're working on, what
they're thinking about the industry as a whole. As somebody who follows this stuff, I like
to be an informed consumer. I think this is one of also my favorite features. They had
an interview with one of their sysadmins on their blog about how Ting uses data to make
sure that when they make a rate change, everybody is getting a good return on that change. I
think it's a really interesting and fascinating way that they do this. You can watch that
over on their blog. They're also helping out with budget tips. This is something they think
about a lot. They've got a new guy in who's doing blogs on finance tips and things like
that in general. Of course, it includes saving money on your Ting account. Go over to linux.ting.com.
That lets them know you heard about it right here on the Linux Unplugged show. I'll also
get you $25 off. If you want to grab a Ting phone, they'll take $25 off your first phone
if you already have a phone. If you're just going to switch over and you're going to port
your phone, you're going to BYOD, they'll take $25 off your first month or they'll give
you $25 credit that paid for more than my first month. Ting has a whole range of devices.
They have the Sanyo 3810 Red starting at $52. You own this phone outright. Then you're only
paying for your usage on top of that. You can get a feature phone, one of the best feature
phones out there. These Sanyos are amazing with these really cool front displays where
the clock shows through for $52. It's yours. You own it. It's not subsidized. There's no
contract and there's no early termination fee. They've got a whole range of really great
devices. Go over to linux.ting.com. Also try out that savings calculator. One of the things
I realized is for about a year, I was saying, oh yeah, my cell phone bill was about $125.
And Ann's just like, actually, you know your cell phone bill was $140 a month? When I plugged
in my old cell phone bill to the savings calculator, it came out to $2,200 over two years that
I'm saving. That's a new computer every two years right there just by switching to Ting.
I could buy myself a fully loaded Ultra Pro every two years by switching to Ting. That
was a massive statement because I realized I kind of was willing to make some sacrifices.
I was willing to kind of get into a bad deal because I was honestly a little distracted
by the shiny nature of smartphones and how cool they were. And then I got a couple years
into it and I said, wait, what am I, $140 a month? What am I doing? I didn't even realize
that's what I was spending. It didn't really click with me. I didn't realize it was that
much money. And now looking back at it, what was I wasting my money on? I didn't get my
value out of that. Linux.ting.com, go get the value out of your mobile service plan
and a really big thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. And by the way, no hold customer
service. How awesome is that? You don't have to, if you call in between 8 a.m. or 8 p.m.
Eastern time, you don't have to hold. And you know what? I really appreciate that. I
really do. All right, Matt, I want to talk about the perfect home server. So here's what
I've asked the audience and hopefully they're filling these out right now. So you're building
a brand new Linux home server. You're using everything you've learned or heard about over
the recent years. You're starting from scratch. What would you start with? So, oh, well, goodbye
Matt. What would you start with is what I asked the audience. And so I put out the call.
They're doing the survey right now. Hello, are you back? I am back. I have no idea what
happened. I think, I don't know. Maybe the gremlins infected Skype. I don't know what
happened. So I've asked the audience to go out and fill out that survey right now. This
will help inform the Linux action show on Sunday. I'll incorporate some of their feedback.
See what we get. I'm kind of curious what people, also I left a spot in there to just
kind of describe your dream setup and all those kinds of things. So go out there, fill
out that form. It's the perfect home server. And I'd be really curious to see what you
guys would do and see if it lines up with, oh, we're already getting some results in
right now. And by the way, you can see the results that I set in the form to allow people
to see the results. So open media vault, looks like I'm getting an open media vault. Sabnzb,
Plex, Subsonic. Oh yeah, Subsonic's a good one. I should have put that in the check box.
BitTorrent Sync, File and Network Services, Couch Potato. So we're getting a lot. And
also I asked folks if they would just avoid building a LAN server and maybe just do like
a VPS, like a digital ocean droplet. But we'll see. We'll see where folks go on this. I'm
kind of curious because what we've got set up here now at JB1 is a Proxmox rig sitting
on an i7 box with some internal storage and then some NFS storage. And it's pretty neat
because we set up an arch server. Yes, an arch server. I'm going to talk about more
of that on Sunday while we're doing that. We set up an arch server and then we, you
know, to save ourselves time down the road, made a template of it. And now we can just
deploy these arch boxes. And so I've got one arch machine that's limited to two cores.
And that way, like if it's doing things like BitTorrent Sync or Sab NZB Usenet downloads,
it can't go too crazy. And then we've got an encoder box on there that's for Rekai to
bang on for doing like a show encodings. And I just like, I said, just have at it. Do whatever
you want. You get eight cores. You can use up as much. When Rekai wants to take over
the rig, like he just logs into this one virtual machine that I set up for him and he gets
full control of all of the resources. And it's this cool way to kind of provision stuff
from one machine that, you know, isn't necessarily busy all the time. So why not? And what's
really kind of, I did some testing on the machine with only two cores assigned to it
and limited memory. We did an encode of this week's fo show and we were getting about 22
frames per second. When we switched to the encoding machine and with the eight cores
available and more RAM, it went up to 122 frames. We gained a hundred frames per second
improvement on the encoding speed. So now we've got an arch box. We're doing, and this
is even like optimized FFmpeg scripts yet. This is just the basic boxes. But now we're
going to start doing multi machine encoding using this Proxmox VM. And I thought, no way
are you going to encode inside a VM. That's crazy. You can't do that. Can't be done. No,
but it's actually, it's working okay. It could be a little faster, but beggars can't be choosers,
man. We, you know, you only, you only get so many. Yeah. All right. Well, I got a new
segment I want to introduce here in just a second, but before we do that, I want to just
mention we just got a few days left on the Koda radio, 100 hoodie and t-shirt teespring.com
slash CR 100. We've sold 154. There is six days, four hours, 14 minutes and 23 seconds
remaining until this shirt is no longer available. The hoodie, if you're in a cold area, might
be the way to go. It is hot, is over 80 degrees at JB one right now, 80 degrees Fahrenheit.
And so I'm looking at these red and orange Koda radio hoodies. Ange tells me the one
that's selling the best is this kind of dark gray is doing really well. So go to teespring.com
slash CR 100. Grab the limited Koda radio 100 shirt only available for a few more days
just to celebrate Koda radio and hitting a hundred episodes in a row too. Maybe one day
we'll have a Linux unplugged t-shirt up there, Matt. Nice. I'd love that. I can only dream.
So go get it while you can at teespring.com slash CR 100. No, we're not making a bunch
of money. This isn't a fundraiser shirt. We just did a limit of a hundred and we just
wanted something for the fans to be able to grab it. And I wanted some new shirts because
it's getting hot out there. So this isn't like any big money raiser, but it's still
a fun way to kind of celebrate. You know what I mean? All right, Matt. Well, it's time for
us to own up. We got to look at the results. Hazel Bishop's new longer lasting lipstick.
The only lipstick I found that stays on beautifully all around the clock. Now that wasn't what
I was talking about at all. I don't know where that came from. You know, I have been considering
changing my lipstick. All around the clock, Matt. All around the clock. No, actually what
it's really time for is our all hands on board round table. We asked the live stream before
we started, which topic would you like our round table to discuss? The antivirus pioneer
Alan Solomon who thinks antivirus is dead and now he switched to Linux or the orange
box, a $12,000 Ubuntu cluster. Now, Matt, what can you say about our audience when I
do a poll? What usually ends up happening, Matt? What do you usually get when we ask
our audience? What do you guys think about something? You know, I'm going to probably
roll off the hardware. I could be wrong. Yeah, I think we should because this is a
50-50 split right here. Our first one falls on its face. I said we would go with whichever
one polled ahead. 220 votes. You know what? I'm going to put that in the chat room. I'm
going to put it to a vote right now. We can have one person tip the scale. If you go to
right now live stream, go to strawpoll.me, slash 16-87-395. Go over there and tip it
one way and then that'll be our topic. They're both really interesting. However, I personally
think the Ubuntu one is slightly more interesting, but that's just me. All right, here we go.
The poll has been tipped to the Ubuntu orange box, 113 votes out of 223 votes. Ubuntu orange
box got 51% of the votes and the Antivirus guy got 49% of the votes. All right, Mumble
Room, so why don't we let Popey go first? Popey, can you tell us what the orange box
is and why it looks so damn cool? So it's a box that was designed by Canonical and built
by a company called Tranquil PC in the UK. It's got a bunch of Intel NUCs inside, which
are i5 computers that are passively cooled. It's got a gigabyte switch and the idea is
that you could use it as basically a cloud in a box. You could carry it around. It goes
in a flight case and you could cart it to a location and build a cloud locally, a private
cloud, no NSA snooping for you. And yeah, you're off and running with one box, one bright
orange box. So it has what, like 10 NUCs stuffed inside this orange box and then it has a gigabit
switch integrated in this box and a USB hub, right? Yeah, it's impressive actually. We
saw it in the office a couple of months ago. Well, I saw it in the office and a bunch of
us were kind of peering in because they had the lid off and it was quite impressively
built. The guys at Tranquil PC have done a really nice job building this thing and I
know that at the time when they built it, I think it was a one off. Well, more than
one off because I saw two of them in the office. Well, so here's the specs. Okay, so it's 10
Intel NUCs, specifically the Ivy Bridge D53427RKE model, rolls off the tongue, with an i5-3427U
CPU. It's got an HD 4000 graphics, 16 gigs of RAM in each NUC, a 20 gigabyte SSD, Intel
Gigabit NIC, and then they've got a D-Link gigabit switch in there with VLAN set up.
All 10 nodes are internally connected to that gigabit switch in aggregate. This micro cluster
effectively fields 40 cores, 160 gigabytes of RAM, 1.2 gigabytes of solid state storage,
and is connected over internal gigabit network. A single fan quietly cools the power supply
while all other nodes are passively cooled by aluminum heat sinks spanning the side of
the chassis. And then the first node, which is called node zero in the box, also has an
Intel Centrino Advanced N6235 Wi-Fi adapter, a two terabyte spinning hard drive, USB and
HDMI ports are wired and accessible from the rear of the box, and access to the USB and
HDMI of nodes one through nine are accessible under the unit. It also has six gigabit LAN
ports all connected to that internal switch that the NUCs are all connected to, which
is hooked up right there at the rear of the panel.
Doesn't that just sound amazing?
Yeah, it really-
Sounds like a lot of fun.
Like I've, you know, I've had some fun with the NUC recently, and I can tell you it's
a serious machine. You know, it's-
Yeah, so 10 of them must be 10 times the amount of fun, surely.
All right, so round table, mumble room, anybody in here, what do you guys think? Could you
see a use for an orange box like this? Could it be like, think about this, maybe like a
portable data center? I think this is pretty exciting. Anybody think this is bogus? Anybody
not excited by this?
Actually, I could think of several applications for something like this. For instance, you
know, for a doctor's office record keeping offsite, you know, that kind of thing. It
definitely has a use.
And I could see like two, like you could do everything working together in like one big
cluster or you could have one machine's the web server, one machine's the database server,
one machine's the file server, right? You could-
One's the Quazel server.
One's the Quazel server, exactly. I think this is a pretty compelling idea. And I think
it's interesting to kind of demonstrate maybe in a way how you could have extremely high
powered servers in a very small little container like this. You think about it, like the price
isn't that crazy. So it starts at, what, 7,500 euros and then depending on how you configure
it, the price is going to go up in there. But I mean, you can get a Mac Pro for that
price, right? And this is 10 machines in one box.
Yeah, Mark Shuttleworth unveiled it at the OpenStack conference in his keynote today.
And yeah, it's certainly had a lot of attention as a result.
Yeah, so there is an OpenStack thing going on right now. So I guess this was sort of
the big, this was the big show for Canonical, wasn't it?
One of them, yeah.
Oh, is there something else going on there?
Yeah, so Mark has a lot of the times he does a big tech demo or announces some new product.
And I think he gave two things away. One was the orange box and another was the fact that
there's the most powerful machine on the planet, the most powerful computer on the planet in
China happens to run Ubuntu on OpenStack, which is quite cool, really.
That is quite cool. Although I think we covered that in the Linux action show, so Mark should
watch last. That's all I'm saying. All right, hold on. I think I have the keynote that you
linked us earlier. Let's see if it'll play. I don't know if I have the audio from it or
not because I had to hook this machine up during the show. But it was pretty funny because
Mark was on stage revealing this orange box and he had it under a big curtain, like a
big sheet. So there's this big black sheet on stage with Mark Shuttleworth and he's walking
around it. He's not really drawing a lot of attention to it. And then at one point when
he introduces the orange box, when he starts talking about it, he pulls off the sheet and
then it's like, huzzah, here it is. It was a pretty good moment.
He loves the big reveal.
We'll have the keynote linked in the show notes. And Popeye was nice enough to give
us right to the time index so you can watch that big reveal since I didn't have it set
up for the show today. I apologize. Yeah, but I think it's a pretty neat thing. I mean,
the antivirus thing is a cool story too, but I felt like the antivirus thing is we already
kind of knew that. That guy was just saying stuff we already knew. Look at that, master
HDMI. That's so cool.
Here's the mirror to our question though. Can it play Minecraft?
I think it could. I think it could. Although it is-
Oh man, think how many Minecraft servers you could have inside that one box.
The problem is that HD4000 might be your limiting factor. I don't know.
What is a server? You could have a cluster of Minecraft servers in that box.
I'm thinking this is our new encoding rig, right? We just-
There you go.
That's not what I was thinking.
Yeah, we do a little GNU parallel scripting and go in there and get ffmpeg running across
all 10 NUCs and then it spits out a file in two seconds.
Oh man, I totally want one of those down.
Yeah. I find it compelling that it's just that single fan in the back too. They've obviously
taken every NUC. They're not even getting NUCs in the cases. They're like motherboard
NUCs mounted inside this thing.
They're all out of the boxes and they're all mounted on the side. There's a picture on
the Tranquil PC side of it upside down with the bottom off so you can see inside. All
the NUCs are mounted along, there's five on each side, I think, and they're mounted so
that the heat is dissipated through the outside of the case.
I was trying to find that on their website, but I don't see it. Yeah, because I saw that
on one of the Ubuntu announcement pages, but I don't see it on the Tranquil PC site. When
you saw this, does it look like they're actually buying full straight up NUCs from Intel and
then pulling them out of the boxes or does Intel sell them to OEMs just as the boards?
Did you get a sense?
I don't know. Tranquil PC build them. We contracted them to build them and they deal with all
that kind of stuff. I don't know whether they have someone sat there with a screwdriver
taking them out of the cases or whether they have a deal with Intel. I really don't know.
I like the idea though. I do like the idea that just a whole bunch of guys are at Canonical
and they get a big shipment of these things and they sit there and just take them out
of the box and they hook them up to this thing. I think that's a kind of funny idea.
I'll tell you what, there's a whole pile of empty NUC boxes you can chuck on eBay if you
wanted to.
Well, I'm showing this picture, this image from a NUC right now. You know what? Rekai,
our production pipeline guy calls it the glue for the studio. It's like when you need to
hook two things up, you need a box in one place, you just stick a NUC there and it's
the perfect glue because it's small, it's tiny in terms of the space it takes up on
the table is actually beneficial but also the amount of power it draws and the sound
it makes is all very minimal. HDMI out is very nice. They've been really good rigs and
I love the idea too of not just having multiple cores but having multiple machines and then
having the ability to either have them all work together independently. I think it's
kind of a neat deal.
Now I know what I want. Now I want one, Matt.
Oh boy.
I think System76 should get on there and then give us a review unit. That'd be great. You
know what? Tranquil PC if you guys want to send us a review unit. I'm just saying Linux
Action should take a look at that.
You okay with that?
Yeah, we could take a look at that. That'd be fine.
Sure.
I wouldn't mind. All right. Well, before we go, before we wrap up today's show, I'd like
to make a special request that you guys get out there. Oh, go ahead, Crash, if you had
something you wanted to add. I just saw that you flagged me.
I was just, I looked up the CPU that they have in those NUCs on the Intel Arc side.
Yeah, are you about to?
I noticed that they're actually one of the fully-enabled Intel CPUs. They've got all
the virtual machine stuff and all the directed IO and all that sort of thing as well. So
you think about for an office, like a small office that needs to run a bunch of machines,
you could stick one of those in there. They're not going to be ultra-fast VMs.
You specifically saw the-
You could run 20 virtual machines on it.
Right. You specifically saw it has VTXD support?
Yeah, it's got everything. I'm just going to look on the site now.
So the VTXD support's nice because then that means you can give direct access to hardware
to the virtual machine, which is really nice for storage and stuff. So that's really cool.
All right, well, there you go. We'll have links to all that stuff as well as the specs
listed out. And if you're curious about that antivirus guy who switched to Linux, we also
have that linked in the show notes. And I do want to ask you, if you do me a solid,
help us make this Sunday's Linux action show even better.
If you go over to the show notes, I have a link to the perfect home server form you can
fill out at home and let us know what you would. And add your own descriptions and things
like that and submit that. I'll be going over that. We're going to do, on Sunday, and now
I am having some free NAS problems right now. In fact, if anybody is familiar with how to,
on a free NAS box, just do a one-to-one swap out of a failed hard drive, I had my last
non-Western Digital Red drive in my free NAS rig, died yesterday or the day before. I got
the overnight drive replacement, I put the drive in, and free NAS does not have any interface
for just doing a swap of a drive. It still thinks the drive that died is still attached
to the pool, and so the pool is still all screwed up and the machine is locking up.
It's a free NAS catastrophe. So if anybody out there has any ideas or tips, I'd appreciate
that. Or if there's anything else you want to comment or give us a topic to chew on,
go over to jupitabroadcasting.com and click that contact link, and then choose Linux Unplugged
from the dropdown and send in your feedback to us. We'd love to start out the show with
a little bit of that. You can also go over to our subreddit, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
And don't forget, you can also join us live over at jblive.tv. We do this show Tuesdays
at 2 p.m. Pacific. You can get that converted to your local time zone by going over to jupitabroadcasting.com
slash calendar. Alright, Matt, so here's what you've got to get thinking about, alright?
You're thinking about what it would take to have Matt Hartley's perfect home server. Like
is it Plex on there, right? Yeah, I'm going to have to think about that. I have a couple
ideas. Yeah, so we'll talk about that on Sunday. We'll get the audience's ideas, and on top
of that, you'll see what we've come up with here at JB1 for the new setup. We've got some
pretty cool stuff we're doing, and it's kind of nuts how awesome this technology's gotten.
So we'll cover the perfect arch server on Sunday show, our ideas, plus the community's
ideas. So go over to the show notes for Linux Unplugged 40, find that Google Doc form, and
fill it out for us if you would. Alright, everyone, well thanks so much for tuning this
week's episode of Linux Unplugged. If we don't see you on Sunday for the big show, we'll
see you right back here next Tuesday. Bye, everybody!