Dang it, my Rona hair is getting ridiculous.
God, it's just in my face constantly.
You just need to glue it down.
But then it gets all gnarly,
and it gets all hard and greasy.
Chris, last dreads, I think, is what's about to happen.
So then I go for the nothing in the hair thing,
so that way it doesn't get greasy,
but then it's just all over the place.
And when it's like poking me in my eyes and my forehead,
I can't focus.
And everybody says, you'll get used to it.
Well, guess what?
It's been like a solid month, and I'm not used to it,
so I don't think I'm ever gonna get used to it.
My damn hair needs to get cut,
but I just, I haven't got it.
You know, there's like,
there's better reasons to go out during a pandemic,
and my own vanity doesn't seem like a good enough reason,
so I just haven't done it,
but now it is driving me crazy.
Well, if it starts to affect your productivity.
That's usually the way I talk myself into everything.
Right, that's why you need ice cream tonight.
Hello, friends, and welcome into episode 364
of your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hey, Wes.
Hello.
Nice to see you there.
Hello, cheese.
Hello, Drew.
Hello, internet.
Hello.
Nice to see you there.
Everybody really dressed down from last week.
Like last week, everybody was excited and they dressed up.
Biologist in your shorts.
It's hot this week.
That's true, that's true.
Well, we have a big episode.
We're gonna get into some community news,
and then we're gonna discuss the past, present,
and future of Linux on the ARM platform,
which has become of a little more interest recently
with Apple's news, but additionally,
there's just some significant things that are in the works,
even within the last couple of days
as we record this episode,
that we thought the timing was right to do that.
So we'll get to that in just a moment,
but before we do that, time-appropriate greetings,
Mumble Room.
Hello.
Happy Linux Tuesday.
31 people hanging out in that Mumble today.
Beautiful.
That is pretty great.
Hello, everybody.
Good to have you there,
and say hello to the new terminal on Chrome OS,
which is shipping in Chrome OS 84.
It's been completely revamped as a system web app,
and it adds a new settings menu
and a bunch of customization.
I think Chrome OS just got really serious
about the Linux terminal.
Yeah, right, it's even got tabs built right in.
Well, now you know they're serious, Wes.
Tabs, you say?
That's how power users get work done, Chris.
Oh, man, could you imagine the meeting
where they're discussing the new power users
they're gonna add to Chrome OS,
and you know, like, tabs was on the whiteboard.
I will say, you know, this continues to make me
more and more curious about Chrome OS,
in that having a usable, configurable terminal
is probably one of the things I would want
if I was gonna actually be using it day to day.
Yeah, and they invested pretty heavily
in the Crostini environment,
and have added significant functionality to it over time,
and now they're improving the user interface to that.
It seems to be a fairly significant through line
of continued investment in the Linux environment
for Chrome OS, and I think the message here is,
this could be your simple, no-hassle,
plug right into your corporate environment
development machine, and that sounds ludicrous,
unless your corporation uses Google Apps,
and all of a sudden, this thing's plugging right in.
It's got your calendar, it's got your inbox,
it's got your cloud storage, it does your Google meetings,
and it's got a terminal.
Right, you can go, you know, hop onto your Google Cloud VPS
and start getting work done.
Oh, what a Google Cloud future it is, Wes.
And it's just, I think, remarkable,
because it's a clear strategy
that has been adopted by Microsoft.
Their manifestation of it is WSL,
which is a much more sophisticated implementation,
but Google is able to take a few shortcuts here
since they're using the Linux kernel,
and so they're able to sort of respond
competitively very quickly.
It's interesting to see them converge
on similar ideas, though.
Yeah, and I wonder, just because we are gonna be talking
about ARM today, I wonder how this impacts the Mac platform.
They seem to be getting further away
from making it possible to run Linux applications
outside of virtualization.
Right.
And there does seem to be, in the latest builds of Big Sur,
there does seem to be specific OS improvements
to enable Linux virtualization.
Did you see that?
Yeah, isn't that interesting?
But, I mean, it does make sense.
You gotta have Docker, you gotta have things like,
you know, developer productivity tools
if you're gonna have developers use your platform.
How much do you think it's about Docker?
Right, right, yeah, yeah.
It's probably mostly about being able
to run Docker containers really easily.
But then you may see other lightweight virtualization suites
that sit on top of a set of APIs that Apple's creating
to make Linux virtualization easier.
If it works smooth enough, I suppose,
you might not even notice.
Yeah, yeah.
All right, well, let's shift gears to Manjaro.
This week, there was an announcement
in the change of the team composition,
and it happened in a fairly public way,
and it appears to involve the use of finances
and community-contributed funds.
And so that always gets everybody's attention.
And Philip is joining us from the Manjaro project
to walk us through his side of what happened
and kind of get a better understanding
of the greater context here.
So Phil, I don't know if my characterization is correct,
but it seems to me that there was a disagreement in the use
of funds to buy a fairly high-end laptop
for a maintainer on the project, not yourself.
And it seems that there was a process that was followed.
That process didn't work out, and so then the decision
was made by yourself to proceed anyways
with the purchase of the laptop, which
led to a disagreement that fairly rapidly went public,
maybe before the conversation was even complete.
And now people don't really know what to believe.
Well, the laptop is for a community developer who
is mostly based in Germany, and he is presenting Manjaro
at several trade shows.
So everybody in Germany at least know him,
and the laptop was actually about 1K.
And we added two hard drives because he
has a special backup system.
And he extended the RAMs because he is simply
doing all the testing and installs several Manjaros
on his machine, and he needs that.
And it looked like you guys took a look
at doing an 18-month contract with a cloud provider
to do the builds.
And you look at the cost, and it sort of just
works out to just end up buying the laptop, plus then
the developer has a machine to actually use as well.
So I think that totally makes sense
and seems like a pretty reasonable laptop
for a development workstation, especially one that's
showcasing the distribution at events once they resume.
I guess what a lot of people seem
to be thinking something foul happened
is with the stepping outside the process for the purchase.
So I'll tell you my interpretation
of it from an outsider, and then you tell me where I land.
But I looked at this situation, and I said, well, it
seems maybe there's some personal things going on
between some team members, so that could
have some influence here.
But is it possible that the project created
a very rather convoluted process to handle expenses,
and then that process failed?
And then as a project leader, you
decided, well, this is a necessary expense
for the good of the project.
Is that essentially the events that happened?
Essentially, kind of.
But Matthew's also here.
He is one of the community developers,
and he can also show you his side.
It was accepted by the whole team.
We talked about it, and even the guy who didn't approve it
also agreed on the laptop itself,
but slightly disagreed with the additional configuration.
So there was a process, but not like everybody on the team
can discuss with him.
So we said, it doesn't work like that.
And since I started the project, it's
really important also to me to have the developers give
their goods so they can develop.
Matthew, for example, has a laptop not working,
and he's still in the team.
And we are now currently looking for a working laptop also
for him.
So a lot of purges will happen, and the process
is currently due.
And Matthew can tell you about what the community board will
do for the next thing.
I mean, that actually tracks pretty closely
with what I would think would happen,
is sometimes a process is created for the project,
and that process doesn't necessarily
serve the project's end goals.
And so it needs to be modified.
Tell me if I'm wrong here, but I think maybe where
the breakdown was is instead of modifying the process to make
it possible for the purchase to happen via process,
the process was just sort of bypassed,
which is sometimes necessary when
you don't have a lot of time and a lot of energy to mess around.
But that seems to be sort of like the core problem there
is the process wasn't really serving the project
as you saw it.
And it sounds like what you're sort of saying there,
and maybe I'm misunderstanding, but it
sounds like you're saying there's maybe a new process that's
being developed now.
Yes.
Since I'm more part of the company,
I give Matthew more or less the freedom
to decide what he thinks for the community project.
And yes, we will see how that works out.
The funds are secured now.
Everything is safe and sound.
And we can only move forward from now on.
And it seems like this probably means long term you'll
have a better representation of what it actually costs
to run a team of developers.
Exactly.
We will be more visible.
And also the team members who are not known yet
might appear in podcasts, shows, YouTube channels, whatever.
It depends also what to do.
Mati is joining us as well.
Yes, I'm here.
Hello, sir.
So do you want to chat at all about what you kind of have
in mind?
I know it's super early days and still,
but it sounds like maybe a new process will be put in place.
Any insights you can share?
One thing I would like to say about what happened,
I think it's a bit misleading or a misconception
to say that the process was bypassed
or that the process was convoluted.
Because I think the problem with the previous way
that things were processed wasn't so much
that it was convoluted, but it was kind of unclear
for the team.
And it was mostly run by the developer who left our team.
And now we're coming together as a team to make a new process.
So we're making sure that everybody is on board
with how the things work.
And everybody knows what to do.
Which should be a lot more sustainable, I would imagine.
I think this, in long term, or actually not very long,
it's going to lead to a better process about this.
I think that's probably what Jonathan wanted anyway.
Fair point.
Is there a plan to communicate the expectations
to the Manjaro user base?
Because I have to imagine part of this
is people are getting a snapshot of a conversation,
essentially one side of a conversation,
that is being responded to.
And I wonder now you must be thinking
it'd be good to get ahead of this for the next time.
Yeah, it's going to be better when
we have finalized the process and decided
how we're going to do it.
Then we can make it public and show that how
the process actually works.
I think there's going to be much more transparency
with the project and the use of the donation funds.
Yeah, I'm glad to see that.
Whatever we can get to a sustainable place
so the project is healthy, continues, and can actually
use the resources that it has.
That's what I think everyone in the community wants to see.
So we'll have links in the show notes
to the announcement and both sides of the discussion.
Also, the item itself, you talk about transparency,
to your credit, is on Open Collective.
The expenses documented there.
The process has been, I would say, somewhat transparent
just in that regard.
It seems like these situations, I've been on the side of,
so somebody comes out and starts talking
before something's supposed to be public,
and they end up setting the narrative.
And the language that they use sets
the tone of the conversation that happens on Reddit
and in Telegram groups and on IRC rooms and wherever else.
And it then becomes the onus of the other party
to either defend themselves or just remain silent,
which is usually my trick.
And that's a difficult position to respond from.
So I really appreciate you guys willing to just come
on the show and just answer any question I throw in your face
and respond to it genuinely because I
know you've probably been getting
a lot of negative criticism.
And I appreciate your transparency
in just doing this part of this process.
And when I said convoluted, I didn't mean it as an insult.
I just meant when you're beginning
and you're starting up as a project,
you have an idea of how things will work,
and you create a process and chains of command and whatnot
that maybe a year or two into it or whatever it might be,
you realize with hindsight, well, that structure
doesn't really make sense.
That's not really how this works.
And so at some point, there has to be a change.
And generally, it's some kind of event like this
that forces that change.
And sometimes people do get their feelings hurt.
And it really sucks to be on that side of it.
So I appreciate that position.
And I appreciate you coming on the show, guys.
And we'll keep an eye on the situation.
And best of luck, Philipp.
Is there anything else you want to chat,
like any teases of future developments
that you want to get out there or hardware sneak peeks?
Well, we're working on several projects.
So currently on the PinePhone, in winter,
we might have our own community edition.
Then a new mini PC with an Ryzen CPU will come.
And of course, more Ryzen CPUs based laptops from Tuxedo
and under and other partners.
So how much is known about this mini PC?
How much can we share that you and I've
talked about this mini PC?
Because that seems pretty exciting, is it?
Is it pretty locked in as likely to happen?
Well, we have a new partner in China
and is one of the biggest manufacturers of mini PCs.
We will sell it in Amazon, US, and EU
and have it there when it's ready.
So we will see.
To recap, I'm really excited because this
is a Ryzen-based system that's smaller
than a Mac mini that has some really nice performance
characteristics.
And it's going to be available to buy on Amazon preloaded
with Manjaro.
That's so cool.
That's a pretty big deal.
Wow.
I mean, here in the States, that's like, well, OK.
That's a possibility.
All of a sudden, it's like, hmm.
I mean, I look at, we have a couple of machines
in the studio here that are getting seriously old.
Like, the recording machine actually
had a hard drive problem over the weekend
that I was able to recover and mark the blocks bad.
But that's the beginning of the end.
And I think, OK, it's time to replace this machine.
Something like that that I could order on Amazon when
the computer dies and I can have in a couple of days?
Game changer.
And it would fit nicely in the studio.
We don't need a giant tower in here.
No.
It's something low profile we could have under the table.
Anyways, again, thank you guys for joining us.
And keep us posted on future developments,
because it seems like there's a lot going on
and some cool hardware in the works.
So thank you very much.
And I just, by the way, recently reloaded my workstation
upstairs with Manjaro Gnome Edition.
It had started as Manjaro XFCE.
Then I switched over to Plasma.
Of course you did.
And then I switched over to Gnome Shell.
And then over the weekend, because I was in here just
like doing computer stuff, I was doing an update
on my workstation.
And I was doing it in retro CRT, because it's awesome.
You just feel like a badass admin.
And watching your packages go by on a cool retro CRT screen
is great.
During the actual installation of the packages,
Gnome Shell crashed on me, dropped back
to the login screen, killed my terminal session
that was running the update.
So I see I'm not even going to mess with it.
I drop to the shell, do like the Control-Alt-F2 or whatever.
I get on just the full screen shell.
I log in, Pacman SYU, all packages up to date.
No, they're not, because I was watching them install, right?
So I do a Pacman clean cache, thinking like,
just clean everything out, redownload all the packages.
Let's just start over again.
We're just going to hit Go again.
Does the whole operation.
Takes a minute cleaning stuff up.
Do the Pacman SYU.
No updates available.
So now what do I do, right?
Because I know it's not done.
But Pacman's pretty convinced it's done.
Switch to Fedora and DNF.
It's funny you say that, because that legit,
when I reached for the thumb drive,
and I had the thumb drive in my hand,
I'm like, what do I flash this with?
And I thought, you know, DNF, this wouldn't have happened.
But this is what I get for doing updates
in a cool retro GPU accelerated terminal.
Let's be honest, I should know better.
So I can't 100% blame Pacman in this case.
So I decided I got no other option.
I've got to reboot.
And sure enough, the system just does not come up.
And I'm thinking, do I try to recover here?
Do I just switch to Fedora?
And I just decided, I don't want to do upgrades of distros.
I just want to keep my packages up to date.
I just want fresh packages.
So I decided to stick with Manjaro again for a bit.
Oh, and then honestly, this sounds really lazy of me,
because flat packs and snaps are not hard.
But I just kind of like having one package
manager for everything.
It is nice.
I mean, it's just slightly simpler
when you have such wide support in your package management.
And there's a bunch of crap I got
to install that's like Slack and Telegram.
And now I even have a reason why I have to have Teams and Outlook.
Well, I use the web app.
But it's bad.
It's getting to the point now where
I have so many weird apps.
Big old mess of software.
I think it's more stuff that's outside the repo that's
in the repo these days that I use on a regular basis.
And so it's just nice to have one package.
So I just went to GNOME Shell, Manjaro edition,
and loaded it up there.
And it's great.
It's nice.
Isn't that nice?
I mean, if you had a traditional Archbox,
you'd have to reinstall, which might take you a bit.
But with Manjaro.
Yeah, I still have to load a bunch of stuff.
But I really don't mind the default configuration.
I, of course, turn it into dark mode.
Naturally.
Although I'm starting to get a little done with dark mode.
That's a topic for a future show.
I know.
But when you go all in on dark mode for so long, it starts to.
That's like your personal brand.
Well, I'm still using it.
As you can clearly see, everything in front of us
is currently in dark mode.
I thought that was going to be a new handle, dark mode Chris.
The dark tipper.
Anyways, so yeah, it's back up.
It's a fresh install.
It feels good.
I do like doing that from time to time anyways.
But it was funny to sit there with literally the thumb drive
in my hand and go, hmm.
It's a big moment of decision.
All the power right there.
And then I run through this.
I would totally go to Fedora for DNF.
And then I'm like, but then I have
to install a dozen flat packs and all that kind of stuff.
And it's just not that it's impossible.
It's a lot.
Sounds like you need a better FS underneath there
for your snapshots.
I did actually choose better FS this time
through for my main partitions.
I've never really done that with an arch install.
So yeah, it's all better FS.
It's all of the disks.
And there's a lot of disks in that box.
It's got like six attached disks.
I'm looking forward to whatever updates we get down the road
here in a couple of months.
It's pretty great so far.
I actually like it a lot.
I like that you've built this strange machine that
seems to just constantly be stress testing Linux.
I know.
It's a weird configuration, and you keep finding these fun
little bugs.
And then like a jerk, I just insist
on having two vertical monitors, which
I don't think any developer of Linux desktop
has because it is always so wonky.
Anyways, that's my update.
It was one of those Sundays where
I came in for the LUP lug predominantly
because it happens every Sunday.
Hey-o.
So I came in a couple hours early and was like, well,
I'll just bang out a couple of things real quick.
And literally up until like two minutes after the LUP lug
started, I was still fixing the various computer
stuff around the studio.
And then I hung out in the LUP lug for like, I don't know,
two hours, hour 45.
Once you start, it's hard to stop.
It is.
You get sucked in.
All right.
Well, let's do a little housekeeping real quick,
and then we'll get the show back in gear
because we do have a lot to get to still, big show.
So really, really quick, I do just
want to mention the LUP lug is on Sundays at noon Pacific.
It's on our calendar at jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
So you can just kind of get our live times.
And you never know.
There may be new live shows popping up
on that calendar soon.
So do check it from time to time.
Also, you are welcome to join this show live.
Please do.
We do it Tuesdays at noon Pacific,
which is 3 PM Eastern.
You got any other time zones you just
want to randomly throw out there?
We should just pick.
3 AM if you're in China.
I don't know how you knew that.
It's just so funny.
And we'd love to have you join us if you can.
And then you can participate in the mumble as well,
or the chat room, or just watch however you like.
And you can get all of that at jblive.tv.
And we also have that full screen IRC.
If you just want to jump in our chat room really easy,
lazy style, go to bit.ly slash Jupiter chat.
And that is all the housekeeping I have.
Nice and tidy today.
Quick and easy.
All right, well, let's talk about ARM.
Let's specifically talk about the past, the present,
and the future of Linux on ARM.
I think this is a little more convoluted than I expected.
As we record this episode, convoluted is my word today.
Did you notice that?
Yeah, it is.
As we record this episode, Intel has
announced a major restructuring of the corporation.
And they've also announced that they
will be delaying, again, their 7 nanometer process, which
is kind of embarrassing because they couldn't really
get 10 nanometer down for more than a couple of lines.
And so they were essentially punting that problem
by going straight to 7.
We'll have 7.
And now they can't hit 7.
Meanwhile, TMC is ramping up for 5 nanometer production
for the new Apple chips and some other ARM CPUs.
Right, and of course, there's all the intricacies
around what do those sizes really mean
and the differences in the processes.
But just continued failure on the Intel side
is just a trend that they don't want to see
and a lot of people aren't happy with.
And the massive restructuring they've announced
has people leaving the company.
It has new people in charge of different operations.
Intel is in a vulnerable position right now
because while we won't talk about it a lot,
there's also the AMD platform now
and how competitive that has become.
And we will talk about RISC-V in a little bit,
but there's also that in the background
as well as the open-power PC architecture which
has actually picked up.
So there's a lot of downward pressure
on Intel combined with their own failures.
And of course, this is all in the shadow
of Apple announcing the switch of their entire Mac line
over to ARM CPUs, which early benchmarks would
seem to indicate are actually fairly impressive.
And that's just their early dev kit stuff.
So where does this leave Linux?
And I think to appreciate it, you
have to understand the history of ARM, which
was founded in Cambridge, UK and was sold to SoftBank
many years later, but we'll get to all that in a moment.
The early days of ARM are actually kind of quaint.
It started as the official Acorn RISC machine
in October of 1983.
That is a long time ago, especially in computer time.
You think of the x86 platform as the old legacy platform
because it's from the 80s.
But yeah, it started as the Acorn RISC machine in 83.
But the first samples of ARM silicon
that worked properly when received by a customer.
Who wants that?
I know.
April 26, 1985.
And there's a post from 1988 where
some people are talking about getting the machine working.
It's such a trip to go back to 1988
and read what I think was probably an old Usenet post
that has been saved by Google Groups.
The first ARM application was really
like a second tier processor inside a BBC Micro, where
it helped with simulation software
to finish development of other chips
and also sped up CAD designs.
That's a trend you see to this day,
just little helpful ARM CPUs on board.
And an interesting little historical anecdote here
is in the late 80s, Apple and VLSI technology
started working with Acorn on a newer version of what
became the ARM Core.
And in 1990, Acorn spun off that design team
into a company named Advanced RISC Machines Limited,
which became obviously the ARM Holdings parent company
eventually, which then eventually sold to SoftBank.
The new Apple ARM work eventually
evolved into the ARM6 platform, which was released in 1992.
And Apple used the ARM6-based ARM610 CPU
and system on a chip as a basis for the Newton.
Wow.
It's like a weird parallel history here.
Yeah.
The first time around.
If the Newton had been successful,
they may have stuck with it.
But what I think most people probably are aware of,
but maybe don't fully appreciate about ARM,
is it's really a set of specs and licenses
that ARM Holdings and now SoftBank,
and potentially maybe one day Nvidia,
who's looking to buy them now, sell.
And that really became the business for them in 1994,
when they had that proven CPU that worked in the Newton
at 233 megahertz.
They could sell a slightly faster one
to customers as a license.
They do actually sell chips, too.
That actually is something that they do.
But licensing is really what picked up for them
as a business in 1994.
And now you see all these different vendors out there
that have an implementation of ARM.
As far as Linux is concerned, really,
ARM came to the masses via Debian 2.2, which was released
on August 15, 2000.
ARM for Arch, or Arch Linux on ARM,
came out in March 11, 2002.
Wow, that is way earlier than I would have expected.
Yeah, and then you see just a lot of development
across a lot of different Linux distros from there.
That isn't necessarily the first time Linux developers
had their hands on ARM boxes.
I can find interviews with Linux developers going back
to 1994, where they had custom builds of early Linux kernels
that were working on ARM.
But as far as a mainstream distro,
it appears to be Debian 2.2, which is pretty cool.
That is really neat.
It's been a long time now since 2000.
Here we are, and we're still kind of working it out.
20 years later.
We've covered three decades.
Now there's two more since.
Wow.
Yeah, yeah, how about that?
By 2005, 98% of all mobile phones
had at least one type of ARM processor in them, 98%.
By 2010, producers of chips based on ARM architectures
reported shipments of 6.1 billion ARM-based processors,
which is 95% of all smartphones, 35%
of all digital televisions, and 10% of all mobile computers.
How about that?
Yeah, and since then, they've kind of gone everywhere, right?
What device sitting around you doesn't have an ARM chip in it?
And of course, one of our favorite little projects,
the Raspberry Pi Model B, was released in February 2012,
followed by a simpler and cheaper Model A later on.
So that's when the Raspberry Pi came to the masses.
And then things kind of took a whole new development track.
At this point, 2020, we've had so many different vendors
of ARM systems that you can't just say ARM
and mean you could just take this image
and run it on anything.
Right, that's been one of the big problems.
But the Pi really did sort of pave the way
for the concept of a super cheap board that students,
enthusiasts, integrators could buy.
Right, it was actually an end-user platform
instead of something that you would take as an integrator
to build into your own product.
Here I am now running it as even a server for home use.
That was it.
It's a general-use platform, or almost.
A lot like Linux.
And it really just took things to the next level.
And Cheesy and I were chatting about this last night
and about just sort of how now we've
sort of set the stage for a whole new generation
of devices that really span the range
of different capabilities.
My only other forte really into Linux and ARM,
aside from the Raspberry Pi, were the WRT-54G routers
back in the day, flashing those with DDWRT, or Tomato,
or Letty, or one of those others.
But one thing that I find really cool,
specifically about the Raspberry Pi
and how it enabled a lot of us Linux users
to get something, an inexpensive board
that we could tinker with, I think what that's doing now
is it's opening doors for a lot of us
to really become more maker-oriented as well.
Because along with the Raspberry Pi,
you've got GPIO, DSI now, SPI, I2C.
So you've got a way to really attach
a bunch of different elements onto this machine
and really do something, I think,
that we haven't been able to do with Linux
and our general desktops for quite a while.
There's just a ton of boards out there now, right?
So I mean, since the Raspberry Pi,
you've had everybody kind of come on board.
Obviously, one of my favorites is Pine64.
They tend to be mainly RockChip.
They were founded by TL Lim, the same guy
that did the Popcorn Hour series of media players,
which back in the day, again, like Chris had mentioned,
a lot of your set-top boxes and stuff like that
have ARM chips in them, and still to this day, they do.
BeagleBone, I think, needs a mention.
The Asus Tinker Board, the Onion Omega 2,
the Libre Computer, I mean, there's just tons.
Like, the market has really exploded.
So there's no reason that you can't get
into one of these ARM boards and work on it,
develop for it, tinker with it.
And I suspect that now we're going to, we already have,
but even more so, we're going to venture into ARM CPUs
in data centers, like AWS's new Graviton.
I think you're gonna see more complete products, too.
Like, look at the PineBook Pro.
That is sort of bringing together so much stuff
that we have been seeing develop over the last 20, 30 years.
And it's a genuine product that by version two or three,
I'm gonna be recommending to just about everybody I know.
It's great because I think, in a way,
it showed me that this really,
there really is something to it.
I don't know if it's for all tasks,
but there really is something to Linux on ARM.
And I know you've had a chance to kind of like,
actually open the thing up and take a look at it
from more of like, modifying the hardware standpoint.
Did it hold up to that process?
I purchased the original PineBook
that had the ISO keyboard.
So I switched it over to ANC.
I bought the top case, which was super inexpensive.
I think it was like 15 bucks or something.
But doing so meant that essentially,
you had to disassemble the entire laptop
aside from the screen.
Oh, go figure.
So once I disassembled the laptop,
you know, it was super easy getting into it.
I would say maybe 25 screws, maybe 25 screws completely.
And as you open it up, I mean, really the largest portion
of the inside of that laptop is the battery,
like a lot of laptops these days.
But the motherboard, for lack of better terms,
is a quarter or a third the size.
Is there room for more battery in there, do you think?
I would say no.
I would say there's no room for an extra battery.
I did add the NVMe adapter.
I haven't popped in an NVMe drive yet,
because I still think there's some issues
with U-Boot and booting directly to the NVMe drive.
You could leave the eMMC in there to boot off of, right?
Right, and so that's the idea, right,
is you could boot off of that and then throw it to the NVMe.
And that's totally worth it, dude.
That would haul, that'd be awesome.
Yeah, I mean, I think that's when you would start
to see the limitations of the hardware itself, right,
as compared to the current eMMC that it uses.
Yeah.
Why don't we talk about the future a little bit?
Stay awhile and listen.
And Dalton from the Ubiports Project
is joining us to chat a little bit about,
I wanted to really kind of get a handle, Dalton,
on what some of the challenges are for the ARM platform,
kind of going forward,
what some of the significant barriers still are.
I alluded to like all of the different hardware versions
and whatnot, but I know you've kind of probably
gotten a pretty close look at this
being part of the Ubiports Project.
I would imagine a bit.
Yeah, for sure.
So one of the things about ARM
and what makes it complicated to develop on
is that ARM products are designed to be this vertically
integrated full stack thing.
You know, most phones that are out today,
you have Samsung who buys their chips from Qualcomm.
Qualcomm gives them this blessed version of Linux
that works on that Qualcomm chip,
and then Samsung takes it and makes their product out of it.
And it's not like the mainline Linux,
and it's not like any Linux distribution,
it's Samsung's, well in most cases, Android
that's going to run on that hardware device eventually.
And that makes things more difficult
when we are a third-party software vendor.
Sure.
What we expect and what a lot of our users expect
is the horizontal platform that x86 has become,
where you take Ubuntu, period,
and you boot that on whatever computer you want to.
You can boot it on my Dell XPS,
my Ryzen 7 workstation downstairs,
all the way back to some Core 2 Duo machine from 2008.
Where we're going now is people are seeing,
especially server vendors,
don't want to be that vertical integrator.
Dell doesn't want to make, well, maybe they do,
but Dell probably doesn't want to make Dell Linux
for the Dell EMC server platform, right?
Right, and they're selling to customers
who sort of expect this plug and play, just,
they're going to put on their own operating system
and configure it afterwards.
They're going to want to put Ubuntu on the server
for lack of a better option.
And I think that's kind of where we come
into ARM Server Ready,
which is a set of technologies,
a specification and a certification by ARM Holdings.
So this is really cool.
I didn't know about this Dalton
until you educated me on it.
And as luck would have it on July 20th of this year,
a VMware developer who works in the bootloader area
for the ARM platform held a video stream
about Server Ready.
We'll have a link to that in the show notes,
but you guys know me.
I grabbed you a couple of essential clips
and here's his definition of Server Ready.
Server Ready is about making boring infrastructure.
Boring in a sense where I can buy an HPE
or Dell server today,
and I don't have to ask myself
whether it will run an operating system
that can also run on my laptop.
So that's kind of the definition of boring.
Boring means that I don't have to retrain my IT staff.
Boring means that you don't need any new skill sets
in OEMs or ODMs to design platform solutions around chips.
Boring means that software developers
can continue doing what it is they do best,
and they don't have to completely
kind of change the worldview.
So Server Ready seems like it could have some potential
if it's implemented correctly.
Neil, I wanted to give you a chance to jump in
on that particular topic,
because I know you have thoughts.
This isn't worth the paper it was printed on.
Server Ready certification boils down into two parts.
The first part is implementing a ARM-based system
that follows the Server-based system architecture, or SBSA.
And this essentially mandates that it should behave
somewhat similarly to how modern x86 machines do
with UEFI exposing an ACPI-like interface,
all these sorts of things like that,
like PCIe support is actually like specified in there.
That is fine and dandy.
You're not really going to see
anything that's in an approachable price range
supporting SBSA.
So where you're typically gonna see this is
in rack mount servers and stuff like that.
So the developer from VMware,
he addresses, because he agrees,
the issue right now is that it's for very high cost systems,
server grade systems,
but he makes the case, and I'll play his clip,
that for the developers that are gonna be
writing applications for these future high-end ARM servers,
they need something within their comfort level
to develop on.
But I'll play it and then, Neil, I'll let you respond.
There are folks in the audience who don't care about IoT,
don't care about small board computers,
and might actually not really like the Raspberry Pi.
Why would any of you care?
Well, because there are no good client platforms today
to build a good mass of developers.
If I want folks to build from my Xeon E7,
they can do it on a $200 laptop.
If I want something to build for a Thunder X3,
whenever that comes out,
what am I gonna use?
And I think some of the pressure here will be that
cloud providers will offer a discounted rate,
well, like Amazon already does,
if you run on their ARM system.
The problem with this is, quite frankly,
you're not gonna see anything
that isn't vertically integrated for this space either.
So let's talk about, for example, Apple,
which is the silver elephant in the room.
They will follow SBSA
because that is how they're going to design it.
However, it doesn't matter.
You are not gonna be able to take advantage of it.
They do SBSA not because it makes things easier for you
as a developer or consumer,
but it makes it easier for them
to transition the macOS platform from X86 to ARM
without having to retool the plumbing layers
because the plumbing layers will behave the same.
For some context, Jeremy from System76 is here,
and I also emailed Carl, the CEO of System76,
and I said, just your personal thoughts,
not like a company position, but your personal thoughts
on ARM because Carl thinks a lot about this stuff.
And by the way, great brunch with Brent.
So go check out brunch with Brent.
That's well worth listening.
Carl got me thinking about how I view choice in Linux
and how it's the true competitive strength.
It's a good chat.
But I asked him about ARM,
and he said that he doesn't really find it very exciting.
He said device-specific OS images are pain,
hard, and limit hackability,
especially without good documentation.
The architecture he thinks makes sense
for a lock-in device maker like Apple.
I like that term, lock-in device maker.
Remember that one for me, okay, Wes?
I know it's sourcing my memory to you on that.
He says, so for like a company like Apple
or perhaps an entry-level performance machine,
but System76 cares about performance hackability
and users easily running whatever they want.
So that's kind of how I think about it.
Now, of course, that's a great position for him to take,
but that's, as an end user, how I think about it.
I mean, it's your device.
You want to do stuff with it.
That's it.
He says, I am excited to see where RISC-V goes, though.
We'll talk about that in a moment,
but Jeremy, I saw you tweeting recently
about moving some fancy stuff over to ARM machines possibly,
and I'm just curious about your thoughts on this.
Yeah, so I agree with Carl,
and I think what Neil has said is completely correct.
What we want to see as Linux users and Linux developers,
we really want to see the high-performance chips
run mainline Linux.
We want to see something like the Huawei trips
or the Qualcomm chips that are being used
in top-of-the-line mobile phones
that are able to do 4K video from YouTube,
which the Pinebook Pro can't right now,
and we're simply not seeing that.
Apple and what they're going to have,
that is not going to run desktop Linux.
So for us who are outside of the server space
and the developers who really want to have a platform
like you get from an x86 laptop,
there was some hope.
There was some hope when Windows was pushing Windows on ARM
because things would have been more like PC
on those ARM platforms.
Now, unfortunately, they had mandatory secure boot,
but that's something that can be worked around.
Microsoft does sign other distributions,
but I think we're kind of doomed
with the way ARM is right now
because ARM Holdings prefers
that they have value add being done
by every single SOC vendor.
So they will produce the minimal,
absolute minimal instruction set,
and then the SOC vendor will add a whole bunch
of memory addresses and memory map devices
to do things like acceleration.
And those accelerations are, in many cases,
important to running a desktop operating system.
So having support for that means,
often you have to run a specific kernel
for that specific device,
which is what we see in the Android space.
So my hope is that RISC-V doesn't run down the same path.
And I'm really hoping that there is a general purpose,
very well-defined thing,
such as what we have in the x86 world,
which is we have ACPI, we have UEFI, we have PCI,
and these standards allow you to do hardware discovery
in a very generic way.
Yeah, that really speaks true to me.
The fundamental just nature of the way
these CPUs are designed and the value add
that's created by the parties involved,
it fundamentally means they're always gonna have
unique properties.
So I kind of look at this, though,
acknowledging all of that in a perspective of
things do change, and imagine a world, Dalton,
where Nvidia buys the ARM holdings from SoftBank,
which is the current rumor that's being reported on,
and structures change a little bit.
Apple releases extremely successful ARM-based MacBooks,
at least from a performance standpoint,
and Windows OEMs, like they have historically now
for 30 years, follow suit and release high-end HP
and Dell laptops that are based on ARM running Windows.
In this scenario, with Server Ready,
you could see just that market pressure
creating more adoption, combined with the fact
that it's kind of close on the Raspberry Pi 4 right now.
What are your thoughts?
Yeah, that's absolutely correct.
And as the talk that you'll link to kind of goes into,
there have been Qualcomm ARM laptops
and mobile processors, or mobile devices,
that use a variation of ACPI or something similar to it.
But at the moment, they only run custom
Windows on Snapdragon images.
But I see that going in the direction that we want,
where devices that ship with Windows on ARM
can boot enough, just out of the box,
to say, I have all of this hardware,
Linux, please look for your drivers
for all of this hardware.
I mean, we want the ARM vendors to be putting
all those drivers in the kernel too,
but it'd also just be nice if we could know
that we need those drivers to be available
in order to use the hardware
that we're currently booting Linux on.
No kidding.
So I see a future where these fundamental problems
that Neil and Jeremy have touched on are not solved,
because it's sort of now, 30 years in,
it's what the platform is.
Right, and someone has to pay for it.
Yeah, exactly.
As Neil said.
And I think, ultimately, you could see a moderation of it
if there is enough competitive pressure brought by RISC
or PowerPC, you know, I mean, a man can dream.
But I don't think it's ever gonna be fully solved
in the ARM ecosystem, which is why I kind of fall down
with Jeremy and Carl and Neil and sort of saying,
we really kind of need a different solution.
But what I like about what Dalton is touching on here
is that doesn't mean the ARM ecosystem goes away.
That's never gonna happen now at this point.
And so if there is something we can do
to apply some kind of pressure,
some sort of at least standards that we can expect,
it would make life so much easier
for Linux on the ARM platform and for Windows
and for server vendors and for developers.
I'm just tired of downloading the wrong ARM build
or something.
Yeah, I think that's really kind of,
really kind of has gotten all of us a little bitter about it
is like, let's just solve this now.
And, you know, like I would love to be able to just,
when the Raspberry Pi 5 comes out,
I'd love to be able to just assume
I can put the current build of CentOS on it.
Like I don't have to wait for somebody in the community
to create some special fancy boot system.
It'll just work.
Same with Ubuntu and Fedora.
And I mentioned CentOS because that's really
what I tried last go around.
And we're just not there,
but maybe in a future we could.
I'll play the last clip from that presentation
that touches on this,
and then we'll link for the rest in the show notes.
Far as OS support for those, you know,
for example, in Linux, it's non-existent.
Nobody has done that work.
Within NetBSD and OpenBSD today are probably
the best operating systems in terms of support
for the platform using ACPI bindings.
So some of the biggest challenges
is in the way how USB is wired up.
Due to the Silicon bug,
the PCI Express root complex can only address three gigabytes.
Well, the Raspberry Pi comes in a four gigabyte flavor.
Because of that, there needs to be a way
by which the firmware can communicate
to the operating system that it shouldn't use
the full four gigabytes for DMA.
In other words, it's still a ways off
before it's gonna be there
is really what's the reality of it.
It's a fascinating talk to watch though.
I mean, just some of the technology
and the clever things going on
to make this work as much as it is so far.
And I think maybe ultimately,
the other thing that's really nice about it
is just to see people addressing this
and starting this conversation.
It really will kind of,
we'll kind of see the results will be driven by
what the predominant uses for Linux on ARM end up being,
which is probably gonna be data center and IoT.
Something tells me if I were just to guess.
Thank you, guys.
It doesn't seem like the silver bolt we were hoping,
but you could see a Raspberry Pi four or five one day
getting support for it
because it's just small things,
just small things now at this point,
but small things that persist.
Hey, Wes Payne.
What do you say we do an app picker too
before we get out of here?
Oh, an app picker you say?
I do say, Wes.
I do say.
I do say it, Wes.
I do.
I want to talk about TU uptime,
T uptime, top time.
I like top time.
No, it's gotta be T uptime, right?
It's gotta be.
I think cheese decides he found.
It doesn't matter, Wes.
Who cares?
It's a cool utility.
I'm going with top time.
Top time?
You guys are crazy.
Just sounds good.
Top time.
It just don't matter.
It don't matter.
It's a tool to report the historical
and statistical real time of your system
between restarts.
Yeah, you know, we're all familiar with uptime.
You just find out how long the system's been online,
but what if you're interested in a longer term behavior?
How long was it online?
When was it last restarted?
And history about previous runs.
And what was the load during that time?
It looks like as well, which is great.
Want that.
Reminds me of a classic command
that doesn't give you nearly as much information,
but this is great because you get all the load info too.
And it's a super easy command
because once you get it installed,
it's just T uptime, which has got to be,
I can't believe I'm the one advocating for that.
You guys are trolling me right now, aren't you?
That's what's happening.
You all know how to say it.
Well, don't worry, Chris.
Top time is available in the AUR.
Top time.
Even with you right now.
And then we have one more bonus pick,
which I think we've mentioned before,
but recently came handy.
So I want to mention it again is SETUI.
S-T-U-I, which is a terminal based CPU stress
and monitoring utility,
or as Wes Payne calls it, SETUI.
Well, now you're just putting words in my mouth.
I'm pretty sure I've heard you call it that though.
I thought that one was SETUI.
Yeah, that's how I would do it, I think.
No, I'm pretty sure you said SETUI, so.
Stewie?
Stop time and SETUI.
All right, well that brings us
to the end of this week's broadcast.
Thank you so much for tuning in.
Don't forget, we'd love your feedback
at linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
You can also join the conversation in our telegram group.
That's at jupitabroadcasting.com slash telegram.
Links and more information like that talk
are all available at linuxunplugged.com slash 364.
He's at Wes Payne, I'm at Chris Ellis.
The show is at Linux Unplugged.
And that's probably all I have to relay to you.
When are we going to be back here?
Oh, you want me to say when we're going to be back?
You want me to say it?
All right, we'll see you right back here next Tuesday!
We love you quads!
Dalton, we didn't get a chance to talk about it in the main show, but I'm just curious
if you have any project updates while you're here.
Oh, well, everything's going pretty decently on the PinePhone.
We got all the, fingers crossed, all of the PinePhone UbiPorts Edition devices have shipped
out and are arriving in people's houses now.
Hey, hey, congratulations.
That's a big moment.
That's a bit of a wait off.
Big thanks to Pine64 for that.
On the device, there's still some of the basics to get going and it's been pretty exciting
and it's made me learn a lot about what most integrators do on the ARM platform and really
let me bring the perspective that I had today.
Because before this, I only knew the Android perspective of the world, which simplifies
a lot of that out for you.
That's an interesting insight and I can totally see that.
That's a pretty solved problem at this point on the Android side.
To a point, yeah.
Oh yeah?
Only to a point, huh?
Yeah, okay.
Why am I not surprised?