All right, I got a question for you anybody in the mumble room or anybody in the chat room
Trying out pale moon. I don't know I guess after this whole chromium download a binary in the background thing
I'm kind of just keeping my eyes open and
I've known about pale moon for a while
It's an open source Firefox web browser, and it's available for Linux and other operating systems that probably exist
But I can't confirm their existence
So if you like everything about Firefox
But you want to independently develop source with carefree selected features and optimizations to maximize the browser speed stability and user experience
pale moon
anybody trying it in the mumble room I
I've tried out pale moon for a while
But there were a few of my plugins that just straight-up wouldn't work with this so I had to go back to Firefox
Oh really Romeo, which ones and do you remember which ones in particular stood out to you um I off the top of my head
I think that it may have been you block origin, but I'm not a hundred percent on that
Pursuit of men says he can't watch Netflix on it rotten corpse. Did you try it out at one point?
Well, yeah, I've tried out pretty much every everything like ice weasel ice cat everything that's based on Firefox
Just to see the difference in the stuff, and they're pretty much all the same
They're pretty much Firefox with slight tweaks. Branding removed obviously. Yeah, it's still Firefox. Yeah, like it doesn't matter
Okay, the only the only thing I actually hate right now about Firefox is why I'm not using it is uh
That stupid pocket crap they believe that is what that that's what that's what makes you stop using Firefox is the only thing
Firefox is the pocket integration what about decent process isolation I?
Think the process isolation is awesome. Have you ever used tried electrolysis?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, all right fine fine. I'm not gonna get it. I'm not going down this conversation again
I've done too many episodes where people have told me about all the stuff that Firefox is gonna do one day
Firefox is great. It's great. No yeah, it's great. You can get it right now. You can use it today
It's just ready to go. It's production-ready. That's why it's included with every single Firefox installed by default
Electrolysis for a few weeks of nightly when first came out, but Chris on this one
First came out
I'm going to point out
What about what about your computer you're recording shows on
Yeah
No, I mean like on my on my personal laptop that I like my XPS 13. Yeah sure why not
Have fun with it
But on the machine that I'm just you know on the machines that I'm displaying
Webpages on for shows and and things like that. I just Chrome. I just feel like is the best bet still I hate it
This is Linux unplugged episode 99 for June 30th
You
Welcome to Linux unplugged your
Weekly Linux talk show that wonders perhaps somewhere out there is there a beer keg and an air conditioner combo
My name is Chris and today is a hot day in the studio
It's 90 degrees as we record episode 99 somehow that almost feels appropriate. I'm not even gonna complain
It should be hot on episode 99 now coming up on this week's episode of the unplugged program
We're going to talk about Cisco buying our favorite DNS service open DNS
We're also talking about Linux Mint 17.2 being released a new cinnamon edition of that as well as valves
huge news regarding steam machines and
Pulse video is it going to be the pulse audio for Linux's video woes that rumor is circulating around the web this week
We'll be discussing that as well as the next meetup for the Jupiter broadcasting crew and a little bit more in fact
I know you guys usually you'll have to just you'll just have to grant me this one
Sometimes I love to talk about video gaming under Linux because I feel like there's so much potential here
It's such a good system and games need an open platform
So that way artists can express their passion and Linux and open source are so perfect for that
So this week I'm gonna raise all I will resist the temptations
But I have to share at least one amazing game that I've been it's a category of games that I've been waiting to come
To Linux for a long time that have been severely lacking. I won't spend a lot of time on it
But as a little treat to myself, I'm also gonna talk about one of my new favorite games
It's come to Linux and I really want you to try it
I won't spend too much time, but you got to give it to me
You got to give me but first we have some interesting follow-up on some stories
We've been covering in the unplugged program. And so I want to bring in our virtual log time appropriate greetings mama room
Hello
Hello now Popey, I hope you'll forgive me I got half of this of the mix, right?
I've had a lot of beer today, but I didn't have any curry. There's a local brewery nearby
I stopped by while I was prepping the show. They didn't serve curry though
In fact when I asked them about curry, they looked at me like I was a crazy person
Outrage I know I know so yeah, you'll have to forgive me. I didn't have any beer in Korea
I just had the beer part, but it was lovely it is like it is almost 90 here at the studio today
which means it's like five or seven or ten more degrees in the studio as we record and
I was like
I really really really really want to do an episode outside and my goal was to do episode 100
As a meetup if possible and then holy crap
Linux fest came up and and self came up and BSD gan came up and now OSCON's just a little bit of ways and
episode 100 just snuck up on me
but
If you would if you're out there if you're listening to this episode and you're in the Pacific Northwest area and would like to come
To the Jupiter broadcasting studio for episode 100 shoot me an email Chris at Jupiter broadcasting comm in cc
Angela Jupiter broadcasting comm and for episode 100 we could do a mini meetup here in the studio
It is an open invitation to any of you who'd like to join me next Tuesday around one o'clock
Pacific time if you'd like to come in studio and hang out
Join me just shoot an email Chris at Jupiter broadcasting comm and if enough of you show up
I'll do some barbecuing maybe and also this week. Please forgive the air conditioner in the background
It is hot in here. So why don't we start with OSCON?
I just gave it kind of a mention and
We're gonna be there the crew Noel is gonna be like a reduce crew. It's gonna be Noah and I we're gonna be getting clips
For unplugged and Linux action show we'll be at OSCON on the 22nd OSCON itself runs July 20th through the 24th
It's gonna be in Portland, Oregon. And here's the big bit
It's the last OSCON in Portland. I know I
Think they're moving to like, Texas
But I'm a little sad
Because you know, I can just take the train down to Portland, but I think it's a smart move
They've spent a lot of time in Portland and Portland is an amazing area
But Texas has really seen some serious development. And so it's good. It's a good opportunity
I've been getting a lot of emails from listeners asking me to come down to the Texas area over
Really? It's been ramping up over the last couple of years and now it's a steady drumbeat come down to Texas come down to Texas
Come down to Texas. And so I think OSCON is also getting that same drumbeat and is responding
So Noah and I were talking about this because we've enjoyed the fact that you know
It's sort of like it's great to be able to these conventions that are in our backyard
And when you can take a train ride down to Portland, how do you beat that?
So we decided since this is gonna be the last OSCON in Portland going from the 20th to the 24th
We're gonna have a little get-together
We're gonna have a little party to celebrate it because this why not right because gives you folks in the Portland area
Even if you're not going to OSCON a chance to catch up with us
We'll talk Linux and open source about all the things that excite us. We'll get together
We'll have some good food. And if you are gonna make it to OSCON, you can say hi to us at the conference
We're gonna be there Wednesday, July 22nd
We're gonna be there Wednesday, July 22nd, and then we're gonna go out to dinner at 5 p.m. Right now
We have all the details at meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting. We're gonna go to spirit of 77
It's a bar that has a big area
So if enough of you sign up at meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting for this one, I got it linked in the show notes
We can reserve the top floor
They have a dedicated area for large groups and it's just a handful of you are gonna make it
Then we'll just hang out in the bar area down below either way. It's gonna work out great
So our plan is on Wednesday
July 22nd to be at OSCON in Portland Oregon at the exposition center got all the details on the meetup page and then we'll go
out to dinner at 5 p.m
And we'll be at
Spirit of 77 now that may change those details may change the best way to stay informed
That is be the meetup at the meetup page because if we get a bunch of you to go to the meetup page that are
Under 21 we might want to change the location. That's why you need to go there and represent so we can let the
Location know how many people are going to show up
So let's go to OSCON if you're gonna be there use our promo code Linux
You'll get a 20% discount on your ticket and let's have a party
It'll be good to see all of you guys and it'll be a belated episode 100 celebration in the meantime
You're welcome to show up here next week. Just shoot me an email Chris at Jupiter broadcasting.com show up in studio
we'll hang out I got a mic you can chat about stuff and
Maybe eat some barbecue Chris at Jupiterbroadcasting.com if you want to be here next week meetup.com
Jupiter broadcasting if you want to join us for dinner while we're in Portland on the 22nd. How about all that?
I'm really looking forward to all of that. It's it's good to get out especially when it's nice
I want to get out and about maybe get a little physical activity in now. Mr. Corpse. Are you still listening?
Come back if you're not in here
And join us when you get a moment, Mr. Corpse come back into the mumble room because I want to talk about
So OS solo s now remember we covered this a little bit ago the dame change
We interviewed the developer and all of this and they have their first daily
ISO available after all of their big transition all of their big work. This is the follow-up to that
We have the results the fruits of that labor
It's available now for you to go download and try it out that you have the bungee desktop featured right here in a nutshell
It's built directly from the latest unstable development material
now it's brand spanking new and it's available at the
High high price of zero dollars, so you can go check it out. We'll have a link in the show notes. It's solo s
s o l u s dash project comm
They have their new daily iso, and I'm just excited
I wanted to give them a little follow-up since we've been watching the project since they left mr.
Corpse did you have any anything to add to the solo s release or anything from the project that you've heard?
No, I mean I've used it and they're they're actually changing some kind dependencies with a
With some like the gnome and GTK stuff they're doing. So they're actually moving to clutter. Oh, really is the base. Yeah
I'm not sure exactly how like how much like they said they said that they were they their old dependency was limiting in them
So they're going to change to clutter to be able to
Benefit from the clutter development instead of doing it completely by themselves
It's neat to see these these distros continue on and so I wanted to give them a brief mention since we did have them on the show
Before and I love it's an interesting. It's another take on the gtk3 desktop
It doesn't have you know, I think gtk3 and and gtk is I love the way those applications look
I'm still a huge fan. I think cute cute is great, too
But maybe you are not a huge fan of the way the gnome project has sort of moved forward
You're not a huge fan of how they've implemented that vision and you'd like to see another take on it
Check them out
solo s dash project comm level link in the show notes and congrats to them for getting their first iso
You know when they were on the show, they said they were going to do it
but at that time it was um
You know it was in the in the in the in the shadow of a big name change controversy a little bit of a little
Bit of a mix up it seemed a little ambitious
And so to hear that passion actually translate to an actual release is really cool to follow up on a few weeks later
So check it out now. I got to tell you about something else that I want to follow up on
That's our first sponsor this week digital ocean man. Has this been an amazing resource for jupiter broadcasting
It started as a recommendation really as as as one of our hosts
He said hey, you know i've been using this for my clients and it's a solid solution
I'm using them so much. I want to talk about it in the show all the time. Maybe they'd make a good sponsor
Man was mr. Dominic right digital ocean is perfect for the jupiter broadcasting audience
First of all, let's start with the fact that their entire infrastructure is built on linux powered by the best virtualizer out there kvm
That's right. Digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy to use
intuitive and easy way to spin up your own cloud server
Now, what does that really mean? That means you can go get a linux rig up in the cloud now
What's the cloud that's somebody else's computer in this case?
It's digital oceans computers the best data centers in the world with the best ios the all ssd infrastructure running on top of linux
Yeah, that's the route i'm gonna take thanks and you can get started in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans start only
Five dollars a month. That's less than one trip to mcdonald's for the entire month or starbucks
Really? I pay for more than that in a couple of energy drinks and it's five dollars for the entire month
And then I get you 512 megabytes of ram a 20 gigabyte ssd one cpu and a terabyte of transfer a terabyte
Digital ocean has really got this figured out. So they decided okay, we're gonna go ssd only
We're gonna base it on linux and kvm and then there's gonna be these technologies that we're gonna work really closely with
fedora
Yeah
Core os free bsd docker, right?
They work directly upstream with these projects to make sure they can integrate it at the base level with the digital ocean platform
And I love that because they are really contributing back or another example is they there's projects that don't even directly impact them
But they feel are important to open source. So they invest there
Elementary os is moving off of source port source forge because digital ocean is donating the bandwidth to make hosting free for them
So is ghost they're getting off the source for ghost is an amazing blogging platform that i'm recommending to people all the time small businesses
And people just want to have their own personal blog check out ghost
And now they're able to get away from source forge. Thanks to digital ocean
They didn't have to do that. That doesn't sell more vpss for digital ocean
They did that because that's the right thing for open source. That's awesome
You guys that's why they built the entire infrastructure on open source because they get it
And man is their interface amazing super intuitive
And you can replicate the functionality of their control panel with their really fantastic api. They've recently revved it and it's better than ever
it's
Maybe even a great one to cut your teeth on if you want to do a little programming
And the best part is if you're never going to get to that point where you're going to do any development around their api
Their community has created so many fantastic applications ones that will integrate into your linux desktop
There are ppas available for ubuntu. There are applications in the arch user repository for managing your digital ocean droplets right out of the box
Managing your digital ocean droplets right now
You could integrate it into your existing lifestyle because there's ios and android apps today that all take advantage of this api
It's that good. It's really a nice system and it's all starting at five dollars a month
Go over to digital ocean.com. But here is the best part use our promo code do unplugged
That's one word lowercase do unplugged
You'll get a ten dollar credit with that ten dollar credit. You try out that five dollar rigs two months two months
two months
Absolutely free
What a great opportunity to play with core os
Have you heard about freebsd how it's a cohesive system about how it has ports about how it has great documentation
Is that legit? Is it the right technology for your business?
Try it out on digital ocean droplet two months absolutely for free
Just use our promo code do unplugged
Is fedora 22 really the next best fedora try it out two months absolutely for free on a digital ocean droplet
Out on a public ip with incredible bandwidth and a fantastic performance
Digital ocean.com use the promo code do unplugged seriously from testing to production to learning
Digital ocean has got it covered digital ocean.com do unplugged and a big. Thank you digital ocean for sponsoring
the linux unplugged program
Check it out
All right
So, uh, let's cover a couple more things before we get into the topic that i'm really really really itching to talk to you
Guys about but I want to give a nod to the mint
Mint project linux mint 17.2 cinnamon edition has been released and it came out today
I don't have any current plans to review it
But that may change one of the things that's interesting about this release is it's supported until
I wonder how they do that probably some sort of uh, i'm sure they just
That's probably some sort of magic, uh, so i've talked about 14.04. Yeah, I know I know I that was that was the joke
Thank you. Thank you. Nice
Uh, so lots of improvements to cinnamon. I mean, this is really a uh, performance improvement to cinnamon multi-monitor support has been improved
Lots of cleanup and performance. Um, I don't really have a lot to add here in my opinion the bigger story about mint
And I mean no disrespect to the project because I think this is a totally valid track to take
The most interesting thing about mint is that it's getting boring
I mean really though like it. Uh, it's got it's
You know, it's like the good stuff about ubuntu with some more modern desktop takes on it and some refinements
And it's fine
it works good and it's exactly like
it continues to be a great option for a lot of people I just
The more it goes down this path
The less and less it appeals to me when mint started
It was ubuntu plus codecs and other nice things. It was it was all the stuff you did to ubuntu
Already done for you in a really tasteful clean well-designed way
And then as it moved forward it stayed along that path and it deviated and cinnamon came up and mattei came up and these things
Came up was but they still kind of made sense for the overall. It's ubuntu
but better
I I think it's it's still that but uh, I
I don't know. I mean
For some reason as it's gone down more of the tried and true path
And it and it and it's not pushing. It's almost like it's gotten a little tired
Like mint's a little tired right now, and it doesn't want to push the edges anymore
It just wants to continue to build what it knows to be good the world that it's created continues to be okay
And it wants to refine and iterate on that
And I think maybe
That's not all that appealing to me
Mumble room. What are your thoughts?
So my perspective on this is mint as my understanding when I used it
Was that they do take a lot of the feedback from the community and what the community team's
What the community team's important as like the first thing to be solved
and I can tell you that uh, you could pretty much complain in the irc quote unquote and
See results in the next week or in the next release about what you just complained. So maybe
The stagnation comes from a type of user base that wants some consolidation in some aspects and because they are doing something slightly different
And perhaps they're stretching a little bit on what they can actually do and so they're just trying to focus that on a little
While until they develop the new concept and it's ready enough to roll out
So and so I wanted to give you a chance to jump in too
um, so speaking of of
Linux mint in 17.2 one of the things that they implemented for the cinnamon desktop
2.6 is making it better accessible for those with visual impairments and blind users
So it's um, it's begun work. There's still some some work to be done, but it's it's getting it's going in the right direction
Yeah, I agree now poppy maybe you know, uh, let's let's look at uh
There was a really cool video of mere eight and the new tasks which are coming out
A lot of changes are coming boring could be good, right?
Well, you know your perspective your opening gambit with this was mint's become boring and uh, not really interested in that anymore
But for me for me, i'm sure it's valid for lots of people
Right, but you said that was a good thing for me
You said that the the fact that linux mint has got to that stage where it's now boring and it's putting out boring releases
Is a good thing for linux mint yet?
The most recent once you release you I don't actually think it is a good thing because it was boring
I I actually do anything exciting. I actually would argue. No, I I think maybe you're mischaracterizing
I I don't actually think long term. This is a good thing for mint. I think long term
This is a sign that mint is tired
This is a sign that mint isn't going to truly innovate much more and that mint is building out its its base its world
It's its island its embassy
And I think when you say that's going to make it isn't going to innovate anymore. What what like truly innovative things?
They've they've added a backup tool. Yeah
I mean I understand
Yeah, okay. All right. Okay. I understand your inclination to downplay what they've done
But then I think if you know, I'm not I'm not downplaying what they've done. I'm just saying
I can't reconcile the fact that you say boring is
Is bad for mint? Well, come on now you're arguing two things. Which one do you want to argue here?
Let's say let's say I I I don't think boring is good for mint
I think long term boring is bad for mint
I think the more people in my audience to stop caring about mint
The more people long term that stop getting referred to mint the more momentum over long time that lament loses
And eventually mint sort of goes into obscurity
I think the stability is good
a lot of people want something that isn't going to throw a new desktop at them something that isn't going to
Move things around and yeah and something that they know that they can upgrade and they'll get the latest push and lever office
The latest kernel the latest this and that the latest toolkits
The latest mate or cinnamon or whatever they choose they get all that latest stuff
But they know that when they boot the machine up the next day, it's going to look exactly the same as it did yesterday
Yeah, absolutely little polish. Yeah, and you know a lot of people who want that. Yeah, and those people buy macs and windows
But I think the important thing is that to show the user
um
How how to use their computer, right?
So they don't want to they don't want a desktop to always be changing
They want a desktop to kind of stay stagnant for a little while and I mean what what what if a desktop changes every week?
or every month
That's kind of kind of kind of put a wrench in the user now. Let's come on now. Come on now
Let's have a rational serious discussion about this and not let's not argue the outlier scenarios
Here's the reality if you're a consumer who values stability and long-term support you're going to buy it
You're going to buy windows or macos because those that's what the reputation is. Come on. Let's be honest
If you're a linux user, then you know about things like rel you know about things like ubuntu lts
You you understand this game you're already in here
I think sometimes what we get caught up in is we pretend like we're marketing to some sort of pretend user
Who's never going to be a linux user at least not this generation around?
And so what we do is we get caught up on designing these systems that are amazing for this person
That doesn't actually exist because in in reality those people buy based on brand loyalty
That's what it comes down to what brand do I trust? I trust dell. I trust hp. I trust apple. I trust microsoft
I trust best buy. I don't trust mint. I don't know what the hell that is
I don't know what a mint box is. I don't trust that
I don't buy that if I want stability if I want something that's going to work for five years
I don't buy that I buy a computer that gets windows 10 or I buy a macintosh
And that's the reality and we can all pretend like that's not the reality because it makes us feel better
But the truth of the matter is the market tells us that's the reality
So that what we have to acknowledge is there is a certain demographic that uses the linux desktop in mass. That's developers. That's enthusiasts
That's technical people. That's advocates. That's us. That's this audience and for those people mint is boring
And those are the people that like like noah who buy laptops and ssds to convert people because that's the reality of where we're at
Right now those people will be the people that recommend things like abutu and mint and there's only so many people
They're going to continue to recommend a distribution that is basically tired and sleepy
Why do you think I would actually do this more just because they're stagnant because you know, I don't have to maintain that too much
I think people would use people who
Get help from noah are using ubuntu are using mint not because they trust the brand
They do it because they trust noah and that's how it's been for a very long
Noah and altus speed is a brand. I mean rethink about the way you think about brands
Noah is a brand to his clients. His company is a brand and they trust that brand
So noah can give them this thing called ubuntu that they've never heard about because they trust brand noah, right?
They're not trusting ubuntu when he gives them an ubuntu laptop
Just like they're not trusting linux mint and if they didn't have noah
They would buy something that's a mac or they would buy something that runs windows plain and simple
Well, okay, I agree with that completely but this I guess puts the weight on
our shoulders because we
are technically because mint is not trying to push a brand
And make mint be the next big big thing. They are just trying to make the best operating system
That's the most user friendly, right?
Right, which means sometimes the releases will get boring because they need to focus on bug fixing
Rather than adding features, right? But this puts the weight on our shoulders to be the brand so
Uh people who I recommend ubuntu or mint to they will trust me that this will work
I think and I want to make this clear
I think long term it is not a sustainable course for a distribution be it ubuntu or mint to be boring
I think short term
It is extremely prudent to have a boring arm of your distribution and maybe to have the primary focus of your distribution
To be known as stable and boring because linux itself is undergoing
We're about to talk about a rumor coming up that could fundamentally change the way video is routed under linux, right?
Linux itself is going under a lot of changes systemd containers butter fs
And then on the ubuntu side the biggest desktop distribution out there the conversion to unity 8 and mere and all of this
Is the biggest amount of change we have ever witnessed at one time under the linux desktop
And so it makes a lot of sense for the market to respond by having these distributions
That are sort of a safe refuge from all of that
But I think they will meet a time there will come a time when unity 8 or unity 9 is pretty effing solid, right?
And containers are the way we're distributing software and there's all these things that have caught up and snapshots
Are part of your kernel update because you're using butter fs everywhere
There's all these developments are going to crop up faster than we expect them to and these distributions are going to look like
1990s technologies and they're going to have to realize that they have stuck in an old way of doing things
And they're going to have to find a way to modernize and the funny thing is
Is the one that all of them are looking to is ubuntu?
And it's the one that outwardly with its lts releases and and it's very boring unity releases for many releases
Now is the one champion a boring release is okay
And then they're the ones they are going to be the very ones that do the switcheroo on us and be like boom
Everything new is great use the new stuff new is good innovation is good
Everybody go this direction and the entire focus is going to change on all of us and distributions like mid
They're gonna be like wait a minute. I thought I thought stole old stable and tired and true was good
And it's all going to change out from underneath them and then when that happens
Their stability and their boringness is going to become a detriment to them and no longer their primary market advantage
They have a temporary market advantage today
But they need to be looking forward to the future because it's all going to change I believe a year or two down the road
Well, except for men already established that they're going to be continuing with more lts
They're not going to stick to 1404. They're going to go to 1604 as well
So they're going to get the new technology. They're just doing it in two year cycle instead of a six month cycle
I think it's I don't think that'll work long term. I think it'll work now
You know what I think we are running into this
The same issue that node was in as node.js
Um for a while now is that when node.js was new and they were just adding features constantly people were complaining
Oh, we can't use this in production because with every other there are too many changes
So they slowed down as the uh industry wanted and they slowed down the production that
adding features and focused on fixing bugs and
It was kind of more sustained for production and then people started complaining
Oh, no, we want faster development and more features and they had a fork and io.js was made and
That didn't work either and now they merged together and we have node and
uh
io
Merging to a single project right and like there is no perfect solution to this that will work for everyone
it's about finding balance, but this is
not just about finding balance for
Users or and but also
about finding balance for developers, right because
Because developers can put themselves in a situation where they keep adding features with every release
And now they have a backlog of you know, 24 months of the feature development
And no bug fixes, right? So
This means that once in a while you will have to focus on fixing bugs and have a few boring releases
I actually I you know the the chaos of all of this is
Is the best part, right?
Uh it to me in a way knowing that this is all going in a certain direction
but today
Revelling in the in the in all of the different approaches and all of the different actually very valid ideas and reasonings
Is is sort of awesome. Uh, I I find it to be sort of like
When you when you are in the thick of it
It is perhaps a bit maddening but when you zoom out
It's it seems so obvious and almost intentional in the long run, uh rotten corpse
I want to give you a chance to say to sort of go at my windows comparison here
Yeah, I was just going to say that the windows and mac thing about this where people buy because they just they're they're picking a brand
They probably don't really care they're looking at money and if or they're looking at their hatred of windows. So
I don't know man
I think people are I think the general user is afraid of technology and I think brands help them make a decision
In the lack of other other information to proceed with
Sure, but with with windows, they don't really make that decision
Anyway, even now they contact someone they know that knows computers because they don't know the difference between this dell laptop or this acer laptop
Or this other acer laptop and so on. So
But my point is is that the the linux thing the reason why we're people not buying linux is because
Either you have no option at all or you have a laptop that's ridiculously overpriced
Like their libram, which is like fifteen hundred dollars or something. No, no one's gonna do that
But no one who's like in that field, I mean, but for now as of like what two months ago
There's now that dell laptop is 250. That's a perfectly reasonable price that anybody who doesn't really know anything about it could totally buy
Yeah, yeah, and and uh, and I agree, uh that that's a good start. Um, go ahead sunsel
You want to come in also about the brands thing?
Yeah, just to add on to what robin corpse is like most people don't even know what linux is
And you can now unless you're in the you know, the the tech area or you you you're you use it and you you recommend it
To your friends and family or whatever
Yeah
But other people who don't live in this sphere that we live in a lot of people don't know what linux is
Like for example, like in my school. I mentioned linux to people like what is that? Is that a terminal?
Is that is that just a black window with words?
That's if you want if you want any if you want to just that's why it's I mean, that's why it's called chrome os
That's why it's called chromecast not linux cast not linux os on the chromebook. It's not called the linux book
It's called the chromebook. It's not called it's not called linux a mobile. It's called android
Right
People just don't you know know what's going on and I think if people were more aware or kind of what?
Or they want to be more aware. I think that would kind of help the issue
See and this is the this is where uh, I don't think this is ever ever ever going to change
And maybe it's because i've been doing the linux action show for nine years and it's never changed in that nine years
Maybe it's because linus torvald said that linux is successful when people don't know they're using linux
and so it's even at the very top of linux and maybe it's because um
Companies are motivated to brand things as their very own even even when that company is a company like canonical
They want to brand it as their own and not call it linux
They want to call it a bunt or they want to call it android
This is the natural inclination of the commercial entities that are involved with linux
So maybe it's one of those three reasons I think the community and I think the public at large will never ever ever ever ever
Except linux as a brand as anything but a technical thing because these three major interests it is in their best interest
To rebrand these things to rebrand these technologies to own these technologies to make them look bigger and better and to be honest
Open source makes that possible. It's kind of the beautiful thing about it
Is it is a general technology enabling platform that allows people to create products services and all kinds of other things around it
And so people like google and people like all other companies like samsung can take it and call whatever they can call it tyson
They don't have to call it linux
Well, but that means that the general public is never going to trust the name linux
And so we cannot expect that things like linux mint are ever going to be applicable to an average user. That is a bullshit fantasy
That's why I call it mint and not linux man
Well, yeah, well, let's let's let's let's pause this for a second if you were to actually make money off of something called
linux
Wouldn't you then have to apply for use of the trademarked?
Name, yeah, that's all foundation. Yes. Yeah, this makes it a lot more complicated because you can call it
linux, whatever like if you are not making money off of it, i'm guessing it's fine, but
Linux as far as I know is a trademark that you're right foundation
Correct, correct. And so it's in those companies best interest not to use a trademark name even exactly. Yeah
So it's never going to happen. It's never going to be a generally public thing, but you know what?
That's okay, because linux doesn't need that that gives that gives other platforms like ubuntu like github
That gives other platforms like ubuntu like android a chance to shine and then that gives us
The knowledge of knowing well linux powers all these things so become an expert in linux and you understand all of these things
I mean, it's a good thing
If we take ego out of it
But see we have ego
All wrapped up in this because we want to convince other people to use the technology that we use we want to advocate for it
So we want things like linux mint because that gives us the idea that we could advocate to average users
They could use this and so we hold it up there as this iconic idea
The average person coming over because in reality it makes us feel better. But the truth is that's not how it's going to work
I just want to make that point mention. That's why that's why that's my super sorry not to interrupt you rotten
But I just want to complete my thoughts so it doesn't sound like i'm just rambling
That's why it's my super long answer to poppy
Why I think it's not necessarily long term a good idea for it to be boring
Because I think if you're honest about who the market is here
It's people that listen to this show
Honestly and what they're going to recommend and they're going to recommend
Things that excite them things that to them seem like an idea that has momentum things to them that seem like have a future
Seem to definitely not. Yes. Yes. Absolutely. I'm not i'm not saying i'm not saying rolling but seem
But things that feel like they're going to be around for a while
Always recommended boring this shows that could be l that could be why couldn't that be a bunch of matte?
Why can't that be a bunch of matte?
I don't want to explain to someone once some icon moved to some other
Place in the menu and they can't find it anymore with boring this shows
You know if some icon is in one place and if you want to go to settings
It will always be the same spot because that's what boring this shows do don't listen is sometimes good
Don't misinterpret my words for advocating rolling release for everybody. That's not what i'm saying
I'm saying there's distributions out there like today
There's distributions out there like ubuntu 1404 and ubuntu matte and and mint and they are serving a purpose today
Today
Today and i'm not i'm not trying to discourage anybody from using them today
See, here's the thing. I stopped this is not even about rolling
I stopped recommending ubuntu to people when unity first came out just because
Because things were moving around and I know this is always the issue
It's not an issue for me because I always can do things through the terminal. I don't care where the icons are, right?
But for a lot of users
Some icon
Being moved somewhere else
It's a big deal because now they will spend five minutes looking for it. Yeah, and it's it's frustrating. So I recommend this shows that are
By many in this community
Considered boring now. I want to give daredevil in the final thought and uh, because i'm happy to uh,
i'm happy to just put my thoughts in episode 99 and I will replay this clip in two three years and uh,
And see where things stand now, but uh daredevil you wanted to uh get a point in so i'll let you have our closing thought
So apparently they are selling mint boxes and they have their user base
They are one of the few distributions that has a system to get feedback from the users and do
Like there is that even the other users can see the feedback because just the software center alone
That has the ratings and the comments you can have a perception
Just by using the system of what is changing or what where people want change
So from those things I think mint has enough data to make their own decisions
I think it's too much of us to say that it's boring or it's not going to be good
Just based on what we're seeing as not using the distro because apparently they have other things going on that we're just not aware of
Just yet. I mean
How much are they selling off mint boxes which type of users are acquiring these mint boxes
Why are these companies deciding to partnership to make mint boxes in the first place?
So all of this information might actually be
Contraproductive to what are we are saying right here right now just because we don't know how that's going on. Hmm. I don't know
I uh, I I think the uh, I think the evidence is in the fact that canonical refelt refocused on the desktop
And I refocused on mobile and gave up on the desktop even though there's vendors out there shipping it
But i'll you know what i'll leave it at this uh linux action show at reddit.com. We'll have a feedback thread for 99
Let me know your thoughts. I think
It is uh, I think it's a great release. I think the guys like clem
I think he is one of the most respectable people in the open source community
And I think the mint project is one of the most respectable distributions. It's a classy distribution
I think what they're focusing on right now is exactly what the community needs right now
And I bet if anybody like clem is clever enough as the tide turns down the future
Like I think it will clem is clever enough to turn with it
I don't think the mint project is any long-term risk. I just don't think it excites me right now
I don't find it particularly compelling
And I wouldn't be too surprised to find that to be the audience of or the opinion of most of our audience
But maybe i'm wrong
I want to talk about our sponsor first and then we'll get into the topic that I think is maybe the biggest deal of the week
It's not strictly even linux related
Um, yeah, no, well, no, it's not strictly linux related, but it probably impacts all of us
So, uh, I want to uh, take a minute though and talk about ting go to linux.ting.com
Linux.ting.com to support this show and boy today's the last day
So if you're listening right now and you've been on the fence about ting
Make the move. Here's how I would make the decision to be honest
You just got to go with your gut but go to linux.ting.com and then click that savings calculator
Here's the difference about ting
You only pay for what you use. It's a flat six dollars
It's tax and then your usage on top of that your minutes your messages your megabytes ting adds them all up
That's what you pay for
And they have a gsm network and a cdma network. They're huge
So that means if you get a device that's good like a nexus 5 or any complement complement, you know any device any nexus
Well, I would go with the nexus 5
But really any android device is dual sim or any any gsm any device that has cdma and gsm sims in it
Then you have the flexibility of moving between cdma and gsm
Now for me, that's particularly appealing because I attend conferences. I want to go on road trips
I like the idea of picking the network. That's the strongest
But maybe you have really strong gsm or cdma and you can just pick a single phone
You have a lot of flexibility with ting and as power users
Having those kinds of flexibility those kinds of options is really nice and not only does ting have no whole customer service
So you're not going to get stuck in a call queue in a call tree
Which we know we've got more we've got better things to do than play than play that game
You call them right now call them right now 1855 ting ftw
If you're listening live you could call them right now because they they have they have no whole customer service during business hours on the east
coast
I've never actually needed to use that they have a really good online community a really really really good dashboard and they have apps for android
and ios
Which you can like set up device usage alerts. You can turn devices on and off
Oh, that's the other neat thing. So like if you want to get like a ting myfi go to linux.ting.com
ending today
50 off a device or if you're gonna get like a myfi they're gonna give you a 50 service credit do this do this
Go get the myfi and get 50 of data credit because here's the thing you're only paying for what you use
So it's flat six dollars and then you get a myfi device and they've got like tri-band devices
They got gsm devices if you've got one and you just want to go get a nine dollar sim
Ting will give you a nine dollar gsm sim
You can put an existing myfi device if it's unlocked. Oh, and by the way ting devices are unlocked. Yeah
Yeah, all their devices are unlocked. So anyways, you can get a myfi device you go to linux.ting.com
You get a fifth dollar discount
You know, I think for the myfi instead of giving you money off the device itself
They give you service credit
But oh my god, dude
That is gonna last you months and here's the best part about ting
You can go into the android app or their dashboard on their website and you can just turn the device off
Like if you're not going to use it for a month or two, then you don't pay for anything
But like worst case scenario if you accidentally forget to turn the device off like you accidentally leave it on but you don't use it
You're out six dollars. It's a six dollar hot spot
I would pay six dollars just to have the internet available all the time like hey guys you want wi-fi
Yeah, I got a hot spot right there. Like I could always be the guy that's got wi-fi
Like six dollar freaking hot spot a month and you get a fifty dollars worth of credit when you go to linux.ting.com
Now that's that's only good till the end of today and then it's a twenty five dollar credit
That probably still lasts you more than two three months
I don't know. It's up to you. It depends on your usage and then you can go get great phones
I got the best phones everything from like seventy dollar feature phone sixty dollar feature phones all the way up to the best androids
Like the s6 linux 6 the moto x2 all unlocked
linux.ting.com also supports the linux unplugged program
Would you like to see us do another 99 episodes? linux.ting.com
Go to linux.ting.com and a big big thank you to ting and by the way ting's not just doing this all to wireless
They're not just changing up the wireless industry
They're also bringing fiber internet out there, which is really neat go check out their blog for their fiber internet service initiative
Could you imagine like the ting model to fiber internet?
Yeah, they're trying to do it linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program
All right. So let's talk about oh
Man, I can't even believe I have to say this out loud. This actually bothers me quite a bit
Cisco is buying open DNS for
635 million dollars with the deal to close in the first quarter of
Open DNS has its special to me open DNS is a service that you can go to to help filter out porn gambling sites
Malware all from afar
You just set your DNS up to the open DNS servers and you can create an account and you can set up a client if you
If you have a dynamic IP address and it automatically filters these things and as a parent, this is such a great solution
I don't have to worry about putting you know parental controls on each individual computer
I set it at the router to use open DNS and I filter it there or as a as a client
Contractor I could go into my clients and be like, yeah, you want me to block malware and viruses?
I could do some global filtering. Let me set your up DNA your upstream DNS to open DNS
It's such a cool service. And in fact, not only do I have like that connection to it
But in terms of traffic to the Jupiter broadcasting website and the YouTube channel on YouTube alone
I our coverage just seem let me I'll pull it up right now
Let's see. It's in here somewhere open DNS
178,000 people watch my video on open DNS and way more downloaded on open DNS
I covered I did a coverage of open DNS on December 19th 2008. This is extremely embarrassing
I mean, this is extremely embarrassing
But I'm gonna play it for you because I want you to know how near and dear open DNS is to my heart
But this is the most embarrassing thing I've ever played on this show in this episode of an in-depth look
I'm gonna go deep into open DNS and maybe why you should be using open DNS for your network
The alternate title for this episode was is hey, look at open DNS. How awesome is this? How come I never knew about this?
Open DNS in this episode of an in-depth. Look I'm going to assume that most of you probably know what DNS is
If you don't hit the pause button and then go Wikipedia DNS and then come back
Quick summaries that helps you resolve IP addresses to names if you browse the web you're using it if you send emails you're using it
So I've always just used the DNS provided to me by my ISP who happens to be Comcast which you know, sure
I thought DNS was DNS. No big deal then
Lately, there's been some talk about open DNS and how it was patched against against a vulnerability
that had come out that a lot of the main ISPs hadn't patched against yet some poisoning issues where someone could type in a
URL and a
Poisoned DNS server could give you a bad record and send you to a site that was either bogus or a phishing site or something
like that and
That kind of piqued my interest. So I thought well, I'll go check out this open DNS thing. See what this is about
So I jumped to open DNS org and the thing that immediately struck me right away is they put their DNS IP
addresses their IP addresses right there at the bottom of the page
So there was no hoops to jump through no account to sign up if I wanted to start using open DNS
I could and it was fairly evident to me pretty quickly that one of the advantages to doing that would be open DNS seems to have
regional DNS servers which for me I'm in the Seattle area and they have a data center here in Seattle and
they have a bunch of one other ones around the United States and they're adding them around the world and
So it was fast. I wouldn't say I noticed a huge difference, but it did seem to me that my name resolution was
Snappier, so I stuck with that for a couple of weeks thought hey, this is neat
Then it kind of struck me
I went back to open DNS his website and I saw that there was an option to make an account and I thought okay
Well, what does this account do? What's the benefit and I I had some assumptions that I didn't really quite understand it
So I went and I created an account at open DNS and I learned quite a few things now
I my day job is I'm an IT consultant and one of the things I have a lot of issues with is
Phishing and viruses and malware sites that my clients accidentally stumble upon
Open DNS has the ability once you create an account you give it your IP address that your DNS queries will be coming from
So in my case, I configured my router
and I said router use these DNS servers instead of the Comcast DNS servers and
Then I went to open DNS. They said okay open DNS
Here's my IP address now like most of you on a DSL or cable modem or some sort of home broadband
Your IP address is dynamic it changes
Not an issue open DNS makes a client available for Windows Mac and Linux
That you can load on your machine and it basically goes back and reports to open DNS when you have a new IP address
So they automatically get the update and they always know what network number you're coming from
Once they have your IP address you can do things like enable filtering
Maybe you're a parent and you don't want your children going to sites that aren't appropriate for children
Or maybe like you're like me and you only have adults in the house
You don't care what they do, but you do want to protect against malware and phishing sites. So I have mine crew
Oh, wow, I can't really imagine a time when I only had adults in the house
I'm gonna stop right there cuz the chat room is dying
But that gives you the basic summary of open DNS if you want to watch the rest of the video go screw yourself
I'm not gonna tell you even how to find it
If you don't know how to find that then you'd probably don't even need to bother
It's horrible and that was embarrassing
But I really have a deep connection to open DNS and so today when I read the news that mother effing Cisco
Was buying open DNS. I'm had a little bit of a mental breakdown
I love open DNS. I have so many clients in the past that are still using open DNS
Well, hold on don't give away the secret sauce
I have to wonder is this the beginning of the end of open DNS or am I overreacting can someone in the mumble room?
Talk me down. What do you guys think? It's just go buy an open DNS gonna be awful. I
Can say I don't care. Oh really tell me why the DNS was already awful
Oh, yeah open DNS baby has ads everywhere. They overtake service if something fails
They give you this massive
Ad infested garbage portal where there's other services like open Nick, which is much better
Oh do any of this stuff open DNS does I don't care that they're buying something that is trash anyway
I love it
So anybody that thinks that I only have yes-men working with me reference that moment right there because I totally disagree
I think that open DNS
Put a really friendly face on something that was completely unapproachable to the masses and it was something that I could show the average user
How to go manage?
Yeah, it used to be good in 2008. It is not now
All right, well you're making me feel better at least if nothing else I love it I still think it's okay
All right mountain dev you want to also could chime in on open Nick go ahead, sir
Mountain oh good. I'm using open Nick and it's working pretty well, but open DNS. They used to offer free
free
Dynamic DNS service and they quit doing that a long time ago, too
Wow, all right, okay ham radio Layden Layden get please jump in
All right, Chris. Well, I totally agree with you. I love open DNS. I've used it open DNS
I love open DNS. I've used it open DNS for years. I I have configured all of the
My clients computers whenever I work on a computer for a client. I always search them over to open DNS
There you go. Hey go eat even if they don't use the filtering. I always search them over to open DNS
I've been using open DNS from myself for years my family for years. I've used the filtering
I think it's great, and I love them cash you seven if you you you say you give it to everybody
Have you tried anything else?
Damn it no
All right, so you make actually I'm super you actually I was seriously kind of going
I would get on the bump train that was gonna
I had an express pass to bum town and you were actually making me feel a lot better about this
So apparently there's other things to try out there
But Corky says I love open DNS Chris last and so do hundreds of other system
It's Corky. How come the hell you're never in the chat in the mobile room damn it
Damn, I could use your backup right now, but I you know what I will give open Nick a shot
I'll switch it over here now
Also, we have covered on the tech snap program if you have watched there are times when using Google DNS and open DNS and open
Nick aren't necessarily the best
Sometimes now this is less and less and less and less of a problem
But sometimes CDNs have a hard time figuring out where you're coming from when you use these global DNS services
So anyways, I won't I won't I won't talk over my paygrade
But Alan goes into more details in tech snap and you can do some searching around the web
Wait for that. Oh, okay. I got to give our Rekha a plug here
He says because this Rekha PD has always got a good got sound advice
He says I gave up on open DNS when the redirect failed DNS resolutions to their custom search page. Yeah
Yeah, the custom search stuff is total crap. I ain't when when rotten mentioned that I kind of had to agree
Oh, but I'm a conscious that open Nick doesn't have any kind of filtering. Is that true run?
It doesn't have any filtering that by default you can you can do filtering
All right, so I can say a box porn block malware block gambling. I'm not that level
So it doesn't do what open DNS does it all then?
No, most people don't even use open DNS for that. They use it to get it off of their ISP or to not use Google or stuff like that
No, no, it is to provide network-wide prevention of porn and spam and malware. I
Don't know. I haven't tried I've never tried to filter my DNS. So I've don't I've not even tried to do open Nick
So it's because you never want to stop having porn displayed on your screen. That's why
I always
Hope we can I ask you a personal question because you you're closer than I am and I'm more I'm much further away from this
But have you considered parental filtering and if you have have you considered open DNS?
So I actually use open DNS my my router
Or my the the box that connects me to the Internet actually has those the open DNS as the default
DNS
servers
So my kids around the house have iPads Android tablets, you know
computers and they all default to whatever the router gives them which is right DNS same is set to
You know block all the naughty stuff, but there I mean, I'm not I'm not using that as a replacement for being a good parent
You know and also it doesn't work in some situations like they can still read the comments on YouTube
They sure to visit right pretty crappy if there's crap on YouTube. It doesn't prevent that right does not replace parent
Where I notice it is if I want to go to one of those websites. I have to change the DNS settings on my own
In order to override my own control. Are you concerned at all about two things one?
Are you concerned about Cisco mucking this up? That's the first one
No, because I think open DNS came along because there was a need for them to exist
And if Cisco screw it up someone else come along and replace it. That's nice. I like that
Okay, here's what can I tell you what actually freaks me out about this and I'm wondering if this scares you too
I don't like any other solution for Linux and I want my kids to use Linux, but I don't want them
I mean I need to have some I just want to protect them like from really nasty stuff and I
Felt like open DNS struck that balance of me having some filtering
But allowing not having to worry about installing nanny software on Linux and this twitch is gonna suck
So are you worried about that at all? Let's be realistic like what you know, what are you trying to hide them from rotten.com or?
You pawn calm
Yeah
what exactly you're trying to protect them from because the fact is that most people are either most children are more vulnerable to
things like
Members of their own family. I'm not accusing you Chris, but they're more likely to be
Attacked by a member of their own family or it would be in a chat situation
so something like someone connecting to them on Instagram or
What's app or something which won't be blocked by any of these tools?
So they are almost a hundred percent ineffectual there
They make you feel better, but they actually don't do that much good at all wise very wise in a go-go
You want to make a mention about a proxy server here?
Well, it's the proxy server seems to be the best between both rules because it blocks sub directories of certain websites and it
Can it blocks domains and it caches stuff depending on how you got set up so you can bring down the uses and filter bad sites
Yeah, I like that. Um, you're right. That just takes more work and
It makes me want to use pf sense, which isn't Linux based, but you're right. That would be a great solution
Rekha says open Nick has DNS blacklisting. There's also Norton connect safe DNS servers that have filtering against porn
You know what? There's gonna be a lot of porn filtering stuff out there. So there's a lot of solutions
I'm sure and that but that's that's less of my worry like my daughter recently
I mean, she's got an iPhone and recently she signed up for
Instagram and I didn't know this at the time and we thought we'd educated her in the school do a good
internet safety thing, but you know, she took her phone to
Theater where she was performing and backstage with all the other kids. They were all talking about their Instagram accounts
So she set up an Instagram account now
She's in a completely different network on as a guest on their Wi-Fi where they don't use open DNS
So any controls that I implement in a home right useless because she's sat on someone else's net and that's gonna be more and more
The case, isn't it?
Right
Yeah, good point. Yeah, that's that's the reality, especially
for kids is it's gonna be on these mobile devices and
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. All right. You guys have made me feel a lot better about that. Thanks guys. That was nice
That was like I feel like that was a good session for Chris. That was really good. Why don't we?
Let's break it up. Let's change gears. Let's talk about gaming really quick. I can't believe it
Valve says that the pre-orders for the steam machines and the controller have sold out valve is sold out of the controllers as of today
and the steam machines, which are supposed to launch on November 10th, which could be a really good sign for
gamers and Linux
Because there's a lot of things that are moving in this area right now a lot of interesting developments around Vulcan around metal
around DirectX 11 around
Crossover bringing DirectX 11 and DirectX 12. I mean so much is happening right now in the gaming space
So it is critical that the steam machines start to make some movement around the game
So it is critical that the steam machines start to make some movement here and the fact that they're sold out. I
Think is a good sign, but rotten corpse. You're disappointed by it. Tell me why?
I'm disappointed about the news because I neglected to get a controller
Okay, I
Ordered the controller in the link, you know
This is what Chris does and you guys all think all
By the way, all of you jerks out there to think I just buy stuff because I their toys screw you
I hate you. I bought this so that way I could talk about it
I want to try to talk about it as soon as possible on the Linux action show in Linux unplugged
So I pre-ordered the controller and the link. I'm not a big gamer, but I want to have an opinion on them
So hopefully those will arrive we will see and I will have it a review soon
I I don't know if valve can make the ultimate controller, but we'll see Mountain Dev. You say it's disappointing perhaps
Why do you think so?
Well, it might be because they underestimated not a people that would buy the controller
Ah, ah
Perhaps perhaps I think it builds a bit of a buzz
Exactly that it gives it press by saying hey we sold out
So even more people are talking about it's even more people are wanting it
So then when they get the nut and there's not the only shipment they're ever gonna do
So it's just gonna get more pressure for the next time that they do it
Exactly exactly and here's exactly here. Now if you want to think who wants to take bets
Let's let's let's get a poll going chat room do this
Will this thing will it ship the smack zero will it ship yes or no somebody saw the straw poll right now?
Smack zero will it ship yes or no also known it was previously known as the steam boy
It is a handheld steam machine. Are you seeing this thing if you're watching the video version? It's great. It's precious
It's got an AMD embedded g-series system on the chip graphics
It's got the egg water based CPU and of course got some built-in Radeon graphics with four gigabytes of RAM
32 gigabytes of memory and an SD card slot yeah
It's got a 5 inch touchscreen with a 720p bad boy resolution and also configurable tactile gamepads HDMI output Wi-Fi
connectivity and
4g mobile connectivity in the pro model it is a handheld steam
Machine, and I would cast my vote as never ship straw poll somebody in the chat room go make it will the smack zero ship
Yes, or no
Rekai says yes, what'll happen is Ben heck will just put a PC in a
There you go, it's done. Oh yeah, just watch Ben Hicks YouTube channel, and he puts everything in tiny boxes job done
Yeah, that is the whole try and battery power the steam link with some form of display what we need to do
Go ahead
Obviously, I think the best solution is just to get like make the Nvidia shield work with the right stuff
Yeah, that would be nice. You got the pretty much the exact same thing
But also a you know a full controller and not that weird game gear looking thing so micro 89 has his ear to the news
Here he says pricing comes out in August with possible launch mid 2016
I would kind of want I feel like if this doesn't ship
We should do a segment on how to build one somehow. There's got to be a way. This is got to be doable now
I think it's called some what it was called on the pie to basically do Nvidia streaming
Exactly or actually you could do steam streaming you could just like if there was some way to get the pie to do steam link
Or something like that
You'd have a you'd basically have all that you need to have to get this thing to work all right
So I teased it earlier just before we get out of the gaming all together
I know you guys a lot of you out there
Don't care about gaming that much if you would just like a nice casual fun game
It's a little exhilarating kind of gets the adrenaline going
Doesn't have a lot to it doesn't have a lot of setup doesn't have a lot of story
It's a racing game. It's called distance. It's the game. You never knew you wanted on Linux, but it's here now
I've been playing it for a couple of weeks. It's I think still kind of in the early stages
Distance is a survival racing game that combines intense action of arcade racing with the exploration of atmospheric world now
I'll show you what that means here in a second what I actually do is I crank up
This is kind of embarrassing I crank up deadmau5 in the background, and I play this game
But here I'll play a little bit on the video version for you to see it's a really intense racing game in the future
And it's a lot of fun
And it does have a great built-in soundtrack as well as you can see here you're driving around you get booster you get thrusters
You got to make jumps the tracks are very futuristic and crazy, and you get points for making additional moves
And it's multiplayer, which is a lot of fun, and it's right now. It's available on Steam. It's called distance and
It is playable. Here's the other thing. I like a lot about it is it's playable on my XPS 13 in 4k
resolution on the iris
5500 and it scales up very nicely up to my dedicated desktop with an NVIDIA 770 or
7780 something in a graphic series, so it plays very nicely on a wide range of Linux desktops
You may even be able to play this one with the open source graphics
I've experimented a little bit the open source graphics at a 1080p resolution
It was still able to play this game
So this is one of these games that is nice to kind of actually
Still get a little enjoyment about it out of your video card without having a little proprietary driver
But if you do load the proprietary driver, then you get things like 4k resolution
Or you get things like on the NVIDIA machine like you get the music bumping you get the high resolution stuff going
It's it scales up pretty well, and it's a nice intense game
It's called distance, and it's available on the Steam store right now
And it's my current favorite along with this and race the Sun they both are have a similar feel to it and
Gammon on Linux just did a write-up, and they said and I agree they said it's the one of the best Linux games
You don't know about
That you need
That you need right now distance, and I have no idea how much it cost doesn't matter
It's worth it. Go check it out. It's on Steam. It's not open source. It's not free
It's just to give yourself a good time for a few minutes
And you don't have to even have crazy-ass graphics you can get by with on the Intel graphics, which
20 bucks 20 bucks. Thank you. Wow would you were you looking it up while I was talking about it?
Yes, dude nice producer in
Very well done sir very well done
Oh
Reek I suggest we should do a photo versus distance
I agree that should be the next photo for sure is a or maybe not the next but the next versus is distance
It's a good game Linux. It's funny. We've got first-person shooters. We got tons of tactical games
We got lots of pixel games pixel art games
But we don't have a lot of racing games and so this is actually pretty decent one $22 if you're Canadian so Sean's PC
Nice backup producer and Sean thank you from the Canadian perspective
I know that seems like a lot, but you're also contributing to the development, and it is truly a fun game
And the fact that they're developing it in it with Linux support and parity
I think is worth supporting at least me and and for me that's worth backing, but it's up to you check it out
We'll have a link in this show notes now or yeah completeness. It's $14.99 in proper British money. Oh
That is quite proper actually. Thank you, sir. Wow look at that good tertiary producing mr.. Popey tertiary producing
All
Right I got one last topic. It's only a rumor
We don't do rumors a lot like the Mac guys those SOBs they get like that's that's their bread and butter in fact
They don't even have facts. They have rumors and intentions and and mysticism and in Linux
We have like mailing lists and code and discussions out in the open. It's all very very real
It's all very concrete very rarely
Are there rumors about a feature coming to the Linux desktop?
It literally could change everything and it's called get ready for this
pulse video
Pulse video
We're gonna talk about that in just a minute, but first I gotta tell you about our last sponsor Linux Academy
Go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged to get our
33% discount now Linux Academy is basically a better idea than Jupiter broadcasting. I'm gonna be honest with you
It's what I should have done
If I could do over I might have gone this route when I when we started going out when we started developing how to Linux
I realized there is a serious opportunity here, but here's the thing I'm not an educator. I'm not educator well obviously
I'm not I'm not a college professor. I can't teach people stuff
I can talk a lot barely most the time about 5050 depends if I've gone to a brewery before I've done a show
But most the time I am NOT the best educator. I'm an enthusiast. I'm passionate about Linux. I'm passionate about open-source
I watch the trends
That's where Linux Academy closed the gap see they took these open-source enthusiasts for Linux and oh and all of this and
they paired them up with the educators and they paired up with with developers and they created the Linux Academy platform and
That gives them the secret sauce that sites like Linda and the other crap sites that they cover everything
but it's not their life passion so they don't go as deep as you need them to go as
You want them to go as deep as you go right?
That's the problem isn't it is you go deeper than all these other people go because this is your passion
This is your hobby. This is what you think about
These other sites is a checkbox. It's a checkbox for them to say they have courses on Red Hat certification
It's insulting
I'm not going to spend my hard-earned money on a site where a Linux of course is a checkbox to them
I want to spend my hard-earned money on excite where Linux is and open-source is all they do because that's what they care about
That's why the Linux Academy has things like their foundation grant where they're going to give
$5,000 to open-source projects they have self-paced courses you can go take over
1,500 courses where you can pick your Linux distribution 7 plus distros all of the courseware changes all of the VPS is that they'll
Spin up on-demand for you change to match that distribution
So now you're based labs that way you'll work with the real serious awesome open-source technology
Hands-on when you go out there, and you go into the employment place you've worked with this stuff
What does that mean?
That means you have the confidence that means that the first time you have to go work with an nginx config file in the real
World isn't when you're on the job. It's when you're on a Linux Academy VPS
It means the first time you've ever learned open stack isn't on the job
It's when you're on Linux Academy, and you have instructor help to back you up you have an awesome community
That to be honest at this point the debt the deck is stacked for you guys
It's full of Jupiter broadcasting community members
So they're there to really cheer you on and I get emails from them about they taking that they take this courseware
And then they go get these certifications and Linux Academy has the best stuff on Docker open stack virtual box VMware KVM
And of course the AWS entire stack all of the Red Hat stuff that you need to go get a serious job or to get
That next notch on the review they've got it and then last but not least if you're an old salt
They've got these nuggets
I love this when you're in between courses go check out these nuggets a single how to the walks you through doing specific tasks
They don't belong necessarily in an entire course. You know it could be two to sixteen minutes long
it's like boom deep dive on this topic get better on this thing that you've been meaning to do and
expand on it
Everything from like backup snapshots all this stuff in just a nugget
It's so slick and you can get started right now go to linuxacademy.com
Slash unplug get our 33% discount and just enjoy it for a little while
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and a big
Thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program you guys are awesome and keep up the great work
Now the grousing about pulse audio hasn't even died down yet
But it looks like the billions may have been spilled on Paul's video now
Ferronix is purporting
There may be an announcement imminent concerning some of the pulse video project details now an open-source contributor at Red Hat
Christian Schaller has worked on G streamer in the past he's also worked on gnome and transcording apps other multimedia projects
He seems ready
To announce Paul's video now the reason why this came out is on the gnome planet feed
Seemingly by mistake a link to a blog post with a password
Protecting it named introducing pulse video hit the RSS feed
When you refresh it also says fedora workstation next steps introducing pinnows now when you look around
There's no other references to pinnows when searching the github or the old get repository, but there is some references to pulse video. Oh
Oh, well actually it looks like there's an announcement right now as we read this right now
Pinnows has been announced for a while. This is Wow breaking right now hold on. Let's break it out you guys
This is incredible happening right now on the show. Holy smokes. Oh my god
That's not it at all get out of here. It's this one
Oh
Box news alert pinnows is linux video what pulse audio is for audio just a few hours after this story
It's been announced pulse video is ready to go for fedora workstation to improve linux video support
In a new blog post to display one of the original goals of pinnows was to provide the same level of advanced hardware handling for video
That pulse audio provides for audio for those of you have been around for a while
You might remember how you once upon a time could only have one application using a sound card at a time
Pulse audio properly fix that well pinnows will allow you to share your video camera between multiple
Applications and also provide an easy API to do so
Holy shit
This could be huge for Jupiter broadcasting
This oh my god this could enable an entire generation of applications that are competitive with Wirecast if
If this is done, right? Wow, this is a huge deal. This is happening right now
I mean
So this is interesting because one of the things that the Jupiter broadcasting mostly me is trying to figure out is
If we continue to raise funds at patreon.com slash today
I kind of want to do what poppy is doing or I'm not no sorry poppy
You guys all look the same
well
I kind of want to do what wimpy is doing and and I want to contribute some of the extra funds and not really extra but
I want to contribute some of the funds to open source projects that we are migrating to so almost on a monthly basis
We replace some sort of proprietary component in our chain with an open source component
And as we do that, I I feel like I should contribute to them and I should and I should help enable their development
This is this is exactly what we need. This is huge for us. So um
So most of you out there think of QuickTime as this POS
desktop application that is just atrocious and
And then don't even don't even get me started on the browser plug-in on Windows
It's just awful in reality the QuickTime API and the subsystem on OS 10 is amazing
It's what enables Final Cut and Wirecast and motion and I movie and and pixelmator and all of these and core and core
Graphics and core audio and all of these things that are available on OS 10
They're actually really good that by bypassing have this horrible reputation Oh QuickTime such a piece of shit, but actually
They're incredible on the OS 10 platform. This is exactly what OS 10 is available
This is exactly what has kept some of our video production
ie Wirecast on OS 10 is one subsystem that could bring in all of the inputs and then make it available to the
applications and if and OBS has just started to make this available by using the hell out of FFmpeg and if we could have
Something like pulse audio. That's for video
This could bring Linux ahead by five years in media production if they can actually pull it off
I'm really excited about this in a go-go. What do you think I?
Think in some cases it just could go really badly like just now I have was using pulse audio my speakers were going through my
My my output was going through my inputs going back into my microphone input
So if this is made by the same people who made pulse audio, it's that's I think that's gonna happen, but with video instead. I
Think it's not made by the same people who made pulse audio. Yeah, and that's why they didn't call it pulse video, right?
Right and Christian Challa has has worked on Gstreamer for a long time and he's worked in media production on Linux for a long time
So I trust that guy to do the right thing. So
Go ahead
They look at the clothes. No, they said pulse audio style as in just like the same goals of what they were doing
Yeah, yeah, the comparisons are from a developer standpoint use of the API not from an end-user
mute standpoint
Right. They say video frame
Passing will be done via file descriptors and separate apps and processes will be communicated via D bus
Pinos will make it easier to switch cameras and applications and for the same camera source to be used by multiple apps simultaneously
There will be support for multiple types of video inputs G streamer integration and some audio support. So it's really nothing like pulse audio
Yeah, and if it's an extension I've used the screen recording features of the dome 3 and they're excellent
So if that was extended to have more inputs and outputs and a better interface, I think that's great. Oh
my god, I
Mean I feel like this if it's done, right because here's pulse audio is getting pretty good. It's I
Can't stand here and tell you that it's it's better than what's on Windows or OS 10 maybe
But I I definitely have had a lot of problems with it for the last month. It's been pretty good
So I can't get I can't get crazy here
But a lot of times people have asked me what would it take to move some of your editing and some of your final production
steps over to Linux and I've always said
It doesn't matter if we get Lightworks. It doesn't matter if we have FM peg because we don't have this fundamental piping system
This fundamental piping of the camera inputs the normalization of the camera subsystem that you know
Right now on Linux if you want to switch between cameras video for Linux is your best friend
But you still have to write so many esoteric different kind of accommodations for different cameras
And it's just it's it is a you think Android fragmentation is bad
You have never witnessed anything like video management under Linux and if there could be a subsystem that comes along
like QuickTime does and and core video does under OS 10 and
normalizes all of this and enables a new generation of applications where developers can focus on managing the input from this pulse video
Pino system if they can work focus on that and not focus on writing all this esoteric side code
It could really help Linux catch up super fast
I have felt that without this system Linux has a five to ten year gap to be truly competitive
If this over the next couple of years can actually become something usable it could dramatically close that gap
because this is the underlying pinning system that really makes media production possible on OS 10 and
You don't really understand how that is how in critical it is until you actually do video media production
and then you realize why people choose Macs over Windows and Linux and and
Windows doesn't have something like this it has it has something kind of similar. It doesn't have this and and
This is a big deal. I'm very excited. So I'm gonna follow this
I would love rotten if you wouldn't mind Martin noting down
Maybe we can get some interviews with these people and follow it because this could be a huge deal
Really excited kind of neat that the story broke why we're recording the show too because it could be long-term
Right here. We are in episode 99 and it could be a long-term
Long-term the big technology shift that helps us move everything over to Linux
Maybe or maybe I'm just getting too excited
But I it could be also says here that it should enable better screen casting support within gnome 3
Video support for desktop sandboxes. Hello Wayland and many other potential use cases
So those of us who have wondered how the hell we can do screen casting and screenshots under Wayland because of all the sandboxing
This could also provide the solutions for that
Which is great for those of us who want to make how-to's and document things like that
So I'm pretty excited mumble room last chance any final thoughts on this before we wrap up for the day. I
Think pulse audio gets a bad rap
Lot more than it deserves and it does a lot of cool things that if we didn't have pulse
I would be incredibly disappointed. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, you know like to be honest
We had individual application volume control support well before Microsoft ever shipped that
Yeah, Chris, I think your comparison to
To to the Mac and to I already forgot the name of it having a brain fart
Pinos or whatever Pinos P I N O S
So, I think you know that comparison I think is very apt, you know, we have not only FFmpeg
We have G streamer as well and those tools are getting really good
So being able to plug in and out of this. Yes. Yes. It's gonna be very critical. Yes
Yes, this is coming along when FFmpeg is getting really well in pulse audio is stabilizing exactly
So to make the point
You made a point about how Linux is forever changing. This is a good example of that change
Yes, yeah. Yeah
Going back to our mint discussion you mean good points and so a good point
Well put way to bring it all back together
This is a good reason to hang out on mint or
Mattei for a little while because this stuff does just keep on changing. All right. Well, I
Well, maybe we'll leave it right there. Hold on. No, no, no, no, no, hold on. We'll leave it right there
So if you would like to join us live and make an excellent at a closing point like Sun Soul just did
Join us over at jblive.tv. We do this show live at 2 p.m
Pacific over jblive.tv go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone
Maybe next week. I'll have a quieter air conditioner. So there won't be that background Starship hum
Just picture me on the bridge of the USS Enterprise won't you and that'll explain the hum
Linux action show at reddit.com contribute to this show give us links
Also, there'll be a feedback thread for episode 99 and don't forget email me if you want to hang out
For episode 100 in studio and meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting for our OSCON meetup and remember promo code Linux
If you're gonna buy a ticket for OSCON, I everybody thanks so much to this week's episode of Linux unplugged
See you right back here next week
Yeah, you know what I wonder what'll haunt that pinos project is
Internally, they probably did consider it to be pulse video because internally they recognize that pulse audio was the example of an open source project
Has huge ambitions and over time gets refined and works out the bugs and ends up being maybe better than what the commercial offerings have
And so if you have that rationale it makes a lot of sense to call the next iteration for video pulse video
But then internally so you could see how they would stage things like that
Because we have prototype names for shows that we're developing in-house that we don't launch with those names
But that's what we refer to it as and and that's how we all think about it
But we wouldn't publicly call it that just like they wouldn't publicly call it Paul's video
They want to call it pinos, but their draft blog post called it Paul Paul's video
The the draft URL called it Paul's video and that's what for Onyx picked up on and now that's what we're calling it
and you got to wonder if a little bit if they could rewind the clock if they would just
Opt to never have the the meme Paul's video out in the public at all
Oh our jb title site is down. Oh, no. Oh, no
How are we gonna pick a title if our title site is down? Are we capable of coming up with a title on our own?
Yeah, someone suggested parents action show which made me chuckle. That was pretty good. But would you watch that?
Anyway, it's loading for me
We can we can make we can make a title
breaking linux
Check out these nuggets. Thanks. It's a good one
Compulsive video still works. Yeah, there you go repulsive video
Should we do something around the pulse video pinot stuff since that's breaking news or should we do something around open dns?
Uh, or we should do something around boring distributions. We had some good discussions in this episode
Wait
What boring district distros go the distance like that jimotowns.com
Oh is the voting not working? Maybe that just means we're having more traffic than normal
I hope that's what that means
Oh, yeah, oh boy. Oh boy
Oh boy. Oh man, that's no good
so
Server error. How awful was that video? I played of my in-depth look
Like do I seem really do I do I present a lot differently? Is it a huge difference? Oh, that's a big difference
Big difference more confidence. Oh, yeah, yeah, huh?
It sounds like I would have said the same thing
I feel like I would have said the same thing you would have you would have but you you sounded like uh,
a lot less confident and
You yeah, it was like every other youtube video of someone just blurting stuff out unprepared in front of a camera
yeah, you did actually you could you sound a different dude just like the
Uh, not just what you said and how you approached it
But like I don't know for some reason you sound like your voice is deeper now or something
Well, you know puberty and all
Oh, there you go change of the years, yeah
Yeah, you know what's super embarrassing is uh, like people who get into radio
They would they would do these kinds
They would do this kind of learning on like some obscure small little radio station in some small town
Nobody'd ever hear about it. And then by the time they make it to national they're good
But uh when you do it on the internet
I mean my entire you can watch my entire learning arc just by watching our old shows. It's embarrassing. It's all out there
Oh, thank you. We got
All right. So voting is now fixed jbtitles.com
And like what do you do right because you can't really pull it down because that's the back catalog which gets quite a bit of play
But like there are people out there that are meeting chris for the first time and they're meeting that version of chris
That's not the version. I want them to meet
First of all, he weighs like 45 pounds more than I do and second of all, he apparently says um a lot
He's he hasn't gotten into the flow of the rant yet
But the first version of chris that I met was unboxing a digital photo frame nice I remember that chris access point. Yes
Yes
It's uh similar to paul's video which got out on the internet and uh, no one can take it right
It's the same as open source, isn't it? You're right about that. Oh, that doesn't make me feel any better though
Not at all. Yeah, I remember that kodak picture frame. That was horrible
Was it terrible when you actually set it up?
No, it was okay. It was okay. I know you had to um use a vista vm. Oh good old vista
I do remember some of that. Yeah. All right. So how are the titles shaking out now that we got the boats. Let's see
Uh, let's see
Finger on the pulse of video. That's not bad. That's not bad opening dns from the past is boring better
Not so minty fresh turn and I kind of like finger on the pulse of video, but it's a little obscure. Don't you think?
Yeah, but uh, it's also not what it's called either so
Well, there's that
All right chat room, come on, we gotta get together everybody go there concentrate your votes
We gotta go in the meantime. I want you to think about one thing and one thing only that is
Mustache
What's driving me crazy is that photo right there zoom in on that
It's one of those cops in a black uniform with a mustache and you just look like an absolute clown freak
That works for murdering terrorists that jack our food and water. I think you're a big joke
Oh, you got a mustache i'll just worship you as long as you got a mustache. It's okay. Nothing against mustaches
It always makes me feel better
Uh ham, did you want to ask me now? Or did you want to ask off the air? Off the air is fine. Okay. All right
So jbtitles.com jbtitles.com jibber jibber jibber jibber jibber finger on the pulse of video is boring better
I don't think I want to do is boring better rotten just it's a good one
But I feel like it's territory the unplugged show has kind of analyzed before maybe with a new angle today
But if you're looking at it without knowing the context of the discussion, you might be judgy
I feel like that's why I also just suggested pinot noir
I like that. All right. Okay
Uh is finger on the pulse of video
Uh, I kind of like finger on the pulse of video. I think we're gonna go with finger on the pulse of video
How do we beat that? How do you beat that right?
Not so many first pretty good
With wine. I like it
Yeah, I do like that too. Um, all right
Will somebody go out there and try the new linux mint 17.2 and then give us a review next week?
Does anybody in the mobile room mind doing that?
Anybody want to take that nobody going once
Going twice. Thank you, sir. Who is that? Who said that who we got that's romeo romeo. Thank you romeo anybody else
Anybody else i'll give it a go if no one's dead ubi you you give it a go
Wow, give it a go. What's the worst that can happen?
Poppy you get you get sucked in by the boringness
Poppy
I grabbed the uh torrents earlier on today and uh, I was sharing seeding like a good man
And uh, yeah, so i've got them locally. I might as well give it a go. All right, so
I just started using it sun's all okay. All right. So would you guys let's how about next tuesday?
Since you know, I mean we I talked my mouth off about the barbecue so I can do it there what?
I'm going to the to the barbecue if that's next tuesday, you're going to be here. You're going to show up
I mean i'm in portland and there's a bus that goes straight up to seattle. So good man. That would be amazing
All right, so email me so I know though because if I get like two or three people to email me
I'll i'll get some food. Otherwise, i'm not going to buy food
I've already emailed you about it. Awesome. So, uh, great
Yeah, so we'll talk about mint because I feel like we probably deserve to give it, you know a fair shake
Because you know, they've done some good work there and I just kind of s'd all over it
And uh, and we'll have some barbecues. That'll be fun 100 is gonna be awesome. I like it
All right. Thanks mumble room. Thanks for being here. I appreciate it. I can't I can't wait to watch all the food
Welcome to linux unplugged episode 99 where today we're going to be talking about text editors freestyle. What do you think?
Guess what i've tried yesterday
What'd you try yesterday
I have tried emacs among other things, uh, because i've also tried atom the text editor from
Uh the guys over at github
Um, i've tried sublime text 3 which is currently in alpha i've tried. Um,
Sublime text 2 which everybody seems to love and i'm an avid
vim user
So I have a lot to say about text editing right now
So what is your favorite choice now?
um
See this is a really
tough question to answer because
I am
not a fan of
Vim style editing or vi style editing if that's what you want to call it
What I do like is my specific vim setup
so
I wouldn't mind moving to a different text editor if
It could provide me with what I already have and what I already like about my vim setup
that being said
Transitioning to anything else is always kind of weird. So i've been
Every few months jumping around to different text editors and trying stuff out just just to see what all the different
have you tried light table because it seems to be that light table you can really have your own configuration like
You have in vima. So once you have your light table, uh configuration, you will never change it, I guess
It's well
It's light table the one that brackets is using
Now if you want to change it, you have to go to vim.com
Light table the one that brackets is using
No, no, this was an independent crowdfunded project that is open source, I think
Well, it is open source that I know
I'm looking at the website of light table right now and here's the issue that I see already
Is that it doesn't stand out in any way
Well, it stand out becomes it comes into very basic settings and you have to push your settings afterward and create your own
Workflow, I guess. Oh, that's true about every text editor every ever made
Yeah, not that now what about nano though?
Nano is cool
Because I mean like everybody talks about vim and emacs and sublime text, but I hardly ever hear about nano
So it's like nano the the newbie text editor or or what do you guys think about nano? Because I use nano quite often
Okay, so here's the thing. Nano is awesome. If you just need to edit a config
If you have your thousand lines of code file that you've been working on for a few months and you have to navigate around it
Just to find the function that you want to work on today
Nano is not as good because
While basic features are there. It's not as powerful and not as extendable as
Anything else that you could be using
I would come I would agree with you
Nano is great though. Um, like if you're going to have one text editor on on your system
You don't actually write a lot of stuff. You just edit configs
nano
Perfectly fine
Perfect fun
So the best best command line editor, what would you say
Vim okay
Or emacs, okay
How about gooey a gedit sublime text or I forget what the name of the kde one is
But what about what do you think for gooey?
gven
So the text editor from kde, huh
Uh, no, no. No, he said he said gooey version of vim
Uh, I do like kate. I do really like kate. I wish there was a
Bigger community around it that creates plugins for it because kate is awesome
And i'm already a kde user. I would love to spend time. Um
more time in kate
that being said
Are we being stopped now or what's going on?
No, he agrees with you
Ah, ah, okay. I let me have a sip of coffee
While he's drinking his coffee I would like to also point out that kate is awesome
Except for the fact that it has missing features and the only way to do them is to
The plugin system for kate is not that good and it's not
very extensible
Now she uses plugins g edit's got plugins and g edit also has
uh developer plugin packages and extra plugin packages that are easy to get from the
Uh ubuntu software center or from the arch user repository, right? But by default g edit requires you to add everything
just that is true like just like emacs and just like vim you have to
You have to specify exactly what features you want and things like that where kate has a lot of cool things built in by default
Such as emit, um, uh block block editing, which is cool
uh, but then you know, there's other things I so use sublime text because um,
Well, there's nothing else that is remotely
As useful to me without having stupid bloat like adam
Wait, wait, wait. What's the stupid bloat in adam because as far as I can tell chromium atom
Is it not chromium it's something else it's it's based on chromium
Isn't it? No way kid or something like that. No, it's chromium. It's literally chromium
It even says it on their website that it is
Atom is based on chromium embedded framework. I actually have research into these when
Brackets came about and pretty much it is a special build of chromium which strips out a couple features and makes a basic shell
Out of chromium so that you can start writing. Uh, the kind of the shell
Component and the browser component so you it's pretty much just the html javascript whatever but it's chromium. That's overall
Um, yeah, there's that
So what about genie just throw another gdk editor in the ground?
It's cool, but it's very
um lacking in features
Yeah, and it's still gdk too. I think huh? Yes
I don't care what toolkit it is as long as it works
Yeah, that's an argument
I don't think
No one like no one has ever gone excited over genie. I've talked to people who use it because it's good
but it's not like
Anybody has ever had this
devout
Uh love for for genie like people have for vim emacs or sublime
Wasn't wimpy talking last week about genie
Yes, he uses genie, but he also uses more than just genie. So
Yeah, so most of us probably
I mean
But it's it's
Genie is like gedit by default with cool extra features, but still
still very limited
Okay, genie my perspective is a very simple ide
It's perfect in paten because it does symbol searching it integrates that and gives you auto completion of symbols already seen
But other than that is not that appealing to change it
You probably want to use genie when you don't want to make much changes and you want something simple
But other than that, honestly talking about editors when in the discussion there's things like sublime
Evim or emacs genie simply does not hold water
So with text editors, is there one text editor that is the best you should always use it virtually
No matter what you're doing or is it similar to like paint programs where you have gimp which is super powerful?
Or then you have pinta which you might want to just use if you have like a simple, you know
Want to resize image or so because that's not a good comparison this this
The editor of conversation is more like the distro conversation there
Most of them are all great for different for like for different preferences people
No emacs and vim both have great features. And yes, you're going to
So you're going to just go not just because not but not because i'm an emacs guys
But it's more like when looking at infrastructure alone what actually one is capable versus the other
Yes, people have managed to make vim to work with things that you know, and it's kind of amazing that it actually works
But looking at alone at the infrastructure that allows to plug in things to change things by a plug-in interface
Emacs is more powerful one thing or not being you a vim user that performs vim style and vim works better for you or not
Architecturally emacs is a superior editor period. There's no argument
Not as much
With every aspect of supply can be modified with a plug-in
Okay, here's my issue with sublime and atom is that I don't really see a difference on the text level editor. Yeah
Whatever atom is using from itself. It might be
Answer the phone
Yeah
Uh ham answer the phone
Oh
Hi guys, thanks for all hi, can I come back to me to start the show now you guys did good though
That was solid. That was awesome. But it is now time to start the show. You should do that
Let's do that every pre-show. We'll call it the we'll call oh my god
What if we put a podcast within a podcast?
Like the mumble action show and you guys just show up in the pre-show and you have a show
And then we'll just put that in there and we should do that you show up next week and do it again
We'll do it every time until you stop showing up. Okay
Okay. Well, if the mumble community is going to uh do a show you have to accept the fact that once in a while
There's going to be a special episode
exclusively about feces
I hope so. I hope so
Oh, yeah, we should call it mumble unplugged, right? It should be mumble unplugged. It'll be during the pre-show
It'll be like our warm-up show
It's like, you know how like when before a band comes out, you know
You have a pre-show they're like you guys could be like it could be the mumble action show or the mumble
It should be mumble unplugged or maybe chris unplugged because my mic's off and you guys get to have the show
I don't get to say anything. Apparently according to zfs for the win
I can't use the soundboard either because apparently the soundboard equals commentary. Um
I didn't know but I think I agree the more you know the more you know
I guess it does add a little context, uh to the uh show and so out of that that's how we go
That's how we roll. I'll respect that. I won't I won't use the soundboard
I'll mute my mic and you guys can have mumble unplugged and then I think we should probably call it mumble unplugged
And it's the unplugged mumble show in the in the unplugged show. It's meta
It's like it's perfect. It's it's perfect for our community