let's see should we do a tech story of the of the week before we get into any
Linux stuff hmm let's see here let's see here scanning scanning jiffy launches a
new gif maker tool hey hey big news everybody hey I use that today she's
really dude did she really listen listen it's integrated into Facebook Messenger
and my mom sent me a gift so I had to send something and the value of this is
negative. This is Linux Unplugged episode 207 for July 25th 2017
Welcome to Linux Unplugged with your host freshly back from Montana my name is
Chris Mr. West is actually in route I think he's battling some sort of
five-headed monster in Seattle traffic but back from last week because you
demanded more beard is Mr. Rekai himself hello beard hey guys hey so you'll be
sitting in for with with us at least for a little while especially it's kind of
perfect since apparently we can only fit two hosts and then one has to pop out
anyways we got a really really fun show I a new season is upon me after years
and years of running arch I'm beginning a new journey I'm distro hopping for the
first time in years we'll talk about where I've landed initially and the kind
of things I'm getting into new release it's really great so much works got into
it kick the tires we're talking about it just a little bit on the show also huge
news today breaking as we go on air we'll cover that fedoras got some big
news we kind of hinted at it when we talked last what two weeks ago about
fedora 26 guess wasn't last week mm-hmm then there's a vulnerability that's
actually a problem with Windows MSI files still manages to screw up your
Linux box still but yeah yeah it's it's actually kind of adorable it's not a big
deal but we're still gonna talk about it then we're gonna talk about what they
say is the most beautiful Linux distribution ever no other distro is
more beautiful and it's based on the plasma desktop I'm in yeah yeah so we'll
be talking about that plus adapting gnome for ADHD users like myself it's
true I have to admit it you may have noticed it yourself and of course my my
just my I was gonna say my perilous journey but I hope at the other end of
it will be a golden rainbow as I switch from arch I'll tell you why I'm what I'm
going to but before we go any further I've missed him you probably miss him by
now it's our virtual log time appropriate greetings mumble room hello
everybody good to see you in there good to hear from all of you music to my
ears yeah good group in there too good to see everybody so I got I gotta say
right now even though he's not here I just want to say at the top of the show
before I forget thank you to Wes for filling in and thank you to the beard
for stopping by and and people like you I'm not exactly sure why turns out when
we get you off the show the show just gets better I think they just like you
in general we put you on user and they like you we put you on Linux unplugged
and they like you so that's okay I'll launch like 15 shows maybe they can tell
maybe they can tell the impressiveness of the beard through the podcast like
you know maybe it like shows up on like something adds a certain warmth to the
broad that's what it is dude so anyways thank you guys for filling it how did it
go did it go okay pretty smooth did the soundboard machine crash on you guys no
because when I got back like the soundboard stuff was all reset I think I
might have restarted the app okay well I managed to restore the soundboard files
and it's just fine like hmm I wonder what happened but yeah otherwise place
was in pretty good shape I gotta say shows went out on time the trains kept
running I'm just gonna take off more often good in fact I just posted about
what two three hours ago the Montana fix it is the vlog post of my trip to
Montana ended up going down there with Noah and his family and had a great time
and hit a technical snafu which of course no one I had to spring into
action to solve so that sort of ended up in the vlog too unexpectedly it's pretty
I think it's a pretty good vlog I think it sets the bar now for the vlog it's
vlog 48 the Montana fix you can just find it over at Jupiter broadcasting
comm and while we're doing kind of admin II stuff here at the top of the show
probably worth mentioning that we've announced the winner of the XPS 13
developer edition sweepstakes in user air 18 indie there's some other big
announcements in there there are user air 18 and I begin the conversation it's
a really good conversation we have mr. chase Nunes stopped by and he gives us
his perspective of somebody who watches Linux from afar and we talk about some
I think compelling Linux II stuff in that episode like really good good yeah
I really enjoyed having chase on there yeah me too and it was like the
conversation was great because you and I we have our long held positions on some
of these topics and Chase is coming at it with a fresh eye and because he's
dabbled with a certain amount of understanding so it makes for a really
interesting he's a noob that knows things yeah he's an informed a noob
exactly and without bias so it brings a fresh interesting perspective to it so
that's user air 18 plus the winner of the XPS 13 sweepstakes which is pretty
cool all right so you let's start with the big news that I was teasing this is
what really is it's it's like tangently Linux related definitely affects us
Linux users and it's the big news from Adobe today as we go on air that they
are and announcing the end of life for the flash player I don't get like crazy
excited it's 2020 isn't this like the third time they've announced that though
feels like it is this one though has a different weight to it so they're first
of all they're being specific they say specifically we will stop updating and
distributing the flash player at the end of 2020 and encourage content creators
to migrate any existing flash content to new open formats like they mentioned
HTML 5 and WebGL earlier Adobe will continue to support flash on a number
of major OS's and browsers that currently support flash content through
the planned end of life this will include issuing regular security patches
maintaining OS's brow and browser compatibility and adding feature
capabilities as needed now there was a there was a line here that they said
Adobe will continue to support flash on a number of major OS's and browsers so
I was like is Linux in that list and it is it is it is it is actually it is
actually in that list Linux x86 is in that list so we will continue to get
updates 32 and I think just 60 the real question is is the ending of Adobe
handling that also going to be the end of like pepper flash because that's
handled by Google mm-hmm well so the chromium blog announced I went so I
went a little digging I was like well what's WebKit got to say what's
chromium got to say and what's Mozilla I haven't I haven't seen any post from
Mozilla yet but I did get a couple from chromium and WebKit and so they sort of
they have like a nice guy sort of like yay flash is dead they're like flash
really helped pioneer our rich web experience also it's an 80% usage
decline dropping like a rock well that's that's still not quite answering pepper
flash though because chromium did flash through the native stuff right pepper
flashes Google I don't know I so it sounds like they're going to continue to
Chrome will increasingly require here's what here's what they say so chrome
itself this is of course on the chromium blog so it's a little confusing but
chrome itself will increasingly require explicit permission from users to run
flash content until it is completely removed at the end of 2020 that makes
sense so that's at least the chrome story of course I actually already ran
into that where I couldn't figure out why a website wouldn't work but it turned
out that flash was disabled in that website by default oh and the chrome do
that for you yes but it also didn't tell me that I needed to allow it so I had to
go digging to find the setting so Safari's been starting to do that too I
believe and so WebKit sort of where Google had like this really really nice
sort of flash has helped enrich the web for years WebKit had more of a dance on
its grave kind of approach it's interesting to see the different tones
and in the projects and in fact they sort of promote the fact that they've
essentially been pushing this direction since 2010 and highlight the fact that
they've been making flash harder and harder to use in WebKit essentially
well really they've been they've been pushing this direction since they
launched the iPhone yeah yeah without flash mm-hmm yeah they actually kind of
call that out here they say they say Apple users have have experienced the
web without flash for some time iPhone iPad and iPod touch have never supported
flash for the Mac the transition from flash began in 2010 when flash no longer
was pre-installed today if users install flash it remains off by default Safari
requires explicit approval on each website before running the flash plug-in
interesting so what do you think of him then yeah well so what do you think
poppy I think it's surprising it took this long it's sad that there's loads of
little games and stuff that won't work and any more but yeah goodbye good
riddance agreed hmm bashful fruit you have a comment about 2007 as in this
should have happened in 2007 pretty much I mean they were in denial for three
years it sounds like I mean you could already see the writing on the wall and
the way it sparked up in the developer community at the beginning yeah although
you know you talk to folks and they'll tell you that flash is still best at X
and you know like it's true nothing fully replaces its entire set of
capabilities and and it seems to be the most capable live stream player like
we've played around with a lot with that what are your thoughts on that because I
know you know I think it's mostly able to be replaced now yeah stuff like video
JS and right you know kind of stuff yeah but that's what that's like in the last
how long has that been good a year a year or two yeah yeah oh you think too
maybe a year yeah yeah so to me it's like it's we're getting there but
there's still areas there's still like parts of it that aren't quite there yet
but I think with the announcement of the end of flash that it's gonna accelerate
those those things that are missing mm-hmm also the the announcement of DRM
for HTML 5 although that upsets a lot of people will probably probably helped
right I sure this in interesting that is a silver lining I suppose because that
was the one big thing for live streaming that was missing is the ability to do
DRM yeah yeah I suppose you could put that way
bashful robot you think it's gonna be like IP v6 well yeah no one's really
gonna touch it until they have to or until there's a better alternative which
you know everyone mentioned it's taken this long and maybe it's because there
isn't something there but until you have to do it no one's gonna do it it's extra
work it's debt I don't agree like most of the the major things that have used
flash have already transitioned to HTML 5 like YouTube and Twitch they're they're
massive and they didn't have to switch to HTML 5 but they did one twitch still
is heavily in flash this is why we're gonna transition Jupiter broadcasting
over to silver light it's an obvious direction of the future right I mean
silver lights really the streaming platform a choice for users you know
what I hate is frickin dependency hell hate it and I'm gonna be honest it's one
of the reasons I was initially drawn to Debian is because the app get command
would figure out tons this is back and this is back before yum and DNF where
you would just go raw dog and rpm onto a redhat box and then go figure out all
the dependencies yourself and use rpm just it was awful and now you just use
Docker well yeah and Debian went a step further but it's still one system
there's things like the depend specifically on other things you know
you could use Apache and PHP for example here and when we talked last don't I
can't do that I gotta remember when we talked two weeks ago about fedora 26 we
discussed a little bit with Matthew Miller a bolt Ron which as the name kind
of sounds is kind of like bolt on it's it's a modular server system that
they're working where you could have individual components of fedora be
replaced or upgraded without causing this crazy-ass dependency help and I
wasn't quite sure how this worked but Langdon white did a post over at fedora
magazine org that gives us some of the technical details of how fedora is
going to be pulling this off so the fedora modularity working group yes
there is such a thing has an objective and the objective is to generically work
towards modularity its crux is to allow users to safely access the right
versions of what they want so imagine some hotshot web developer needs a very
specific version of whatever they use Ruby on rails I don't I you know I you
can you can imagine your own scenario the working group took the requirement
that they they they took on the requirement to impact fedora infrastructure
user base and package community as little as possible the group also wanted
to increase the quality and reliability of fedora itself the distribution and
drastically increase the automation and speed of delivery I think this is one
of the reasons why rawhide is getting to a more usable point too as a result the
group didn't treat this as a greenfield experiment sort of like how butter fs
was created instead they took a rational approach that took years towards working
towards something like you know I mean they instead of taking like that kind of
which is like a more rational approach instead of working for years they took a
more rational approach and they just tried to keep the tool sets pretty
minimal and implement them as they need and then make slight adjustments to
existing systems and that eventually in totality provides something new the
result is a package set that can be sort of thought of as virtualized separate
repositories that's how they're doing this so this is in other words the
client tooling treats the traditional flat repo as if it was a set of repos
that are only enabled when you want that version of a component virtualizing out
the repos is I think and package set is pretty smart and so bolt on or bolt Ron
sorry is sort of this NF is this this effort this initiative and they have
stuff ready to try right now and they're looking for feedback I think this to me
is a pretty important part of if you if you're going to use the package
management system to deliver software this is what has to be fixed if you're
if you're good if you're not using Docker or flat pack or snaps and you
want to deliver software to a server distribution or something like that this
is what you got to fix but I kind of feel like it might be it's sort of like
fixing the barn door after the cows have gotten home speaking of the barn door
mr. West pain is joining us hello hello so we were just going over bolt Ron the
modular server preview of fedora it's getting out there and they're asking
people to try it out right now the whole idea is you know they're gonna do
virtualized repositories and package set so you can overlay like very specific
things and upgrade individual components without dragging the entire OS of
dependencies with you I love it I gotta say like we when we talked about it on
the earlier show I was excited but after having read about it a little bit in
between I'm this seems like it's gonna be great I kind of tried it yet but I
kind of want to pick wimpy's brain but I'm gonna ask you first right on since
you just sat down isn't this kind of solving last year's problem isn't kind
of the future snaps and flat packs for this kind of thing or Docker even
possibly um but I some of those seem like they they fit different use cases
this kind of excited me in a way that kind of more reminded me of things like
Nix OS and where does it give some more flexibility on the you know the open
source sort of how we craft the bulk of our packages and I mean maybe we'll go
to a place where everything is in a snap and that such but it seems like that
it's certainly going to take a long time and is in many ways kind of a drastic
shift in other ways not but this seems like it's a little bit more you know it
would let me maybe much more easily install three different versions of Ruby
or something right exactly but without like having a snap for each one which
would maybe break more of my you know current deployment strategies okay all
right so that's good that's good I like that that's okay now you got me
reconsidering I kind of wanted to so mr. wimpy I believe is a pretty big fan of a
universal package formats like snap and I'm wondering if you think there's space
for both like major reinnovation in how the underlying OS handles packages for
software delivery and universal package formats on top of that that's a lot
of questions I think I think Voltron is probably a result of the fact that
Flatpak is not ideally suited for distributing command-line applications
languages and services and things like that so I think it's it's not competing
with Flatpak in that regard it's complementing what what Flatpak offers
hmm okay fair enough anybody else want to jump in on the mobile room before we
move on I I look at it as in the back of my mind I run this fantasy scenario
where Chris last runs Fedora for a year and he runs it on the desktop and on the
server this guy's crazy obviously not real Chris last cuz that'd be crazy but
if he was gonna do it this would probably be a something like this and a
Fedora OS trees stuff would probably be a good way to pull it off yeah I if you
want to read more about it and try it out you can find a link to the Fedora
magazine in the show notes so there was a vulnerability going around that uses
Windows MSI files to exploit the Linux desktop well what that seems crazy see
this is what happens when a boon to switches to gnome if they hadn't no I'm
kidding yeah right so it's called bad taste and this is this is so funny I
want to talk about it obviously you know if you don't know if you've noticed but
I'm not covering on vulnerabilities as much these days because by the time we
talk about it it's old news everybody knows there's been the disclosure and
everybody but this is a fun one so this is a vulnerability that actually resides
in Nautilus gnome files but it's exploited by MSI files so it's kind of
funny the third-party thumbnail er that's bundled in with gnome files tries
to look into an MSI file and extract out like a thumbnail and somebody was poking
around and discovered that they could hide malicious VB scripts inside the
names of MSI files when the user accesses a folder on his or her computer
where the malicious MSI files just saved you don't even click on it it's just you
go to that folder so maybe you know yeah somebody downloads something I heard a
story recently about somebody's mom or aunt that was trying to watch streaming
movies and kept downloading exe's and if it weren't for on being on Linux they
would have been infected oh yeah so you can have these things just show up in
your downloads folder when you don't even expect it especially for average
users so the gnome files would try to automatically parse that file to
extract an icon from its contents and they would display that in your window
but the problem is once you parse that MSI file looking for the icon the
thumbnail er script also reads the file name and executes the code found within
there you go so it's there's little tricks you can do right now like you go
to new thing the user share thumbnail er's file if you want but I think that
was just that was our that was the funny exploit of the week MSI files that are
screwing over gnome files users that's I mean yeah you'd see that you'd be like
well whatever okay that I don't even have to scan that now everybody proceed
to be scared freak out and I've seen a number of these kind of things though
where specifically different file types that we're trying to create previews
from or sound or window it happens to Windows too we are not alone but it does
seem to be the act of parsing a file but I you know I suppose anytime when you
have an a program executing code and it's taking input if you're not super
careful about the sanity of that input it's just something like you know how
they'll mark downloaded files sometimes or you know don't let you run down but
even if the file isn't marked executable because the Nautilus thumbnail
I was proposing is like you do we need like some you know in the metadata on
this file that we need to specify something that the system then like
don't thumbnail don't preview don't don't interact with unless approved I
mean a really obvious stupid hack would be just disabled thumb nailing on the
quote-unquote downloads folder containerized thumbnail generation you
know that's actually the route it would go to like a whole fake file system
would mount up a Linux system would be spawned X would be started your browser
be executed the file be downloaded man that sounds very Apple II yeah that's
pretty much an Apple would do and it might just work oh man that is so there
you go that is your cyber attack of the week everybody you could just use
dolphin oh or sonar I'm sure we also be a or the command line yeah just use LS
because those inferior ones aren't capable of generating thumbnails that's
true I guess it could it could happen there too although I have not seen this
story for dolphin I don't you know what I don't I don't ever have my
directory in big icon view anyways I'm always list view I need as much
information in there yeah totally that's how I roll that is how you know if you
if you're like me if you like a lot of information you might like ting huh go
to Linux dot ting comm they give you all the information you need right there in
their dashboard they hide nothing from you one of the things that made it
really simple for me with our business account is I can name the lines in the
web interface and then on our bill reporting everywhere throughout the UI
and the apps on the phones those nicknames show up and when you have
multiple lines and why wouldn't you it's six dollars for a line so it makes
giving phones out to staff and family members economical especially if you
already have a CDMA or GSM device to check their BYOD page then it's just
your usage it's six dollars for the line whatever uncle Sam's cut is and then
your usage it's brilliant so if you got like the beard over there on the Wi-Fi I
mean like that's forget he pays for me that's like that's very true actually
and if I didn't have like beard labeled and I know I just look at that I see
beard never uses hardly any data like you know maybe makes a couple of calls
it's not a big deal it's not a big deal and I love that about ting because it's
approachable for small businesses it's perfect for families and it scales to
large businesses you can get started by going to Linux dot ting comm take $25
off a device or save $25 if you bring one check out their Twitter page to at
ting FTW they're doing a giveaway right now of the moto e4s and $250
in credit which would last a really long time since the average bills $23 a line
when you add everything up also great deal right now on the moto g5 plus this
is a CDMA and GSM phone so it's really nice on ting since they have both
networks you can pick what works better two hundred and seventy four dollars you
can get it unlocked it's new it's a great Android like they just made like
small tweaks to Android they're generally good and it's a solid well
built phone from Motorola for $274 no contract nor the termination fee you can
get started by going to linux.ting.com to get it at that price or bring your
own device linux.ting.com thanks to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program
damn that's a good URL mm-hmm linux.ting.com so I was looking at the
world's most beautiful Linux distribution ever staring at it really
it's a little uncomfortable about it this is one of those things where I've
never heard anybody say it out loud before so now I'm gonna be the first
guy to say it out loud I'm gonna sound like a jerk or you'll be the taste
maker for this I hope so I think it's nitrex what do you think nitrex n-i-t-r-u-x
nitrex nitrex nitrex anybody in the mumble room checked out nitrex the
world's most beautiful Linux to distribution ever that's apparently
according to this review they say it's a Linux distribution focused on design it
introduces the Nomad desktop which is built on top of KDE Plasma 5 and cute
it's based on Ubuntu actually Ubuntu 17.10 to be in specific and it is
obviously because of that still under development although they say it's close
enough this is a quote from the devs it's close enough to a rolling release
model I am
that's that's no that isn't that no that is using the beta of Ubuntu does not
make it does not make a rolling release that is not how that works that's not
the math I agree okay all right we don't need to we don't need to go okay so it
does say I mean you're like focused on portable universal app format really
you're gonna disagree and say that using the beta is like I mean if you go from
beta to beta to beta like some sort of hooker then yeah it's are they saying
they're not doing that because you know when they say they're using the beta
they could just be moving to the next beta when they have the the freeze man
that sounds like the kind of desktop I want to roll but then I don't get why
they just wouldn't be using Debian unstable as their base yeah yeah that's
well because a bunch of does a lot of hard work that's why they got those
repos man they have you seen how fast those repos are I'd love to re-host you
those repo I'd love to just reuse those repos are you over here crapping on
Debian now ouch I just it's funny how many distros are coming up based on 1710
when 1804 is clearly around the corner and and aren't you excited so clearly
the better way to go one thing I noticed about this is they're saying it's a
reincarnation of the old district I didn't even know they had yeah they had
an old one based on 1510 back in the day oh yeah they stopped development because
of a problem with system D and network manager they gave up I don't mean to
laugh at them because you know because they were using beta for that they were using system
they were using system during the system D transition they were you on the beta
huh which was like you mean they were on the rolling release is that what you
know they were on they were on the they're they're rolling beta ish thing
that was like right before the transition happened so it just started
it was boy that was a bad time I say they were beta testers yeah only they're
trying to build a distro at the same time it's kind of confusing to have an
ex.org which is like almost nix or an ex OS org it's really simple to be fair to
be fair even people that just normally use their desktops have problems with
network manager I feel like what this really is and they're not saying it is I
think it's neon I think it's repackaged neon with a nice theme because they say
the current version of nitrix is based on the dev branch of Ubuntu on top of
that we're getting continuous updates to plasma provided by neon devs for which
we enabled both git repositories and finally our homebrewed software like
nomad desktop all right you know what I mean I think it's I think it's it's if
you are a cute fan and you like the plasma desktop are looking for maybe a
different take on it it might be worth the look I mean we're having some fun
here but you know maybe something it's a hybrid concept maybe something that's
lighter than full KDE but isn't LXQT that's not finished yet well I mean it's
how I'm saying it's lighter when it adds more stuff and also you KDE plasma is
not heavy at all so that's oh there's a separation between plasma and the rest
of KDE now is my point so yeah cuz KDE is a community in a project not plasma
well so it's sort of like why I sit around and fantasize about what the
budgie desktop might be once Aiki stops fixing absolutely everything else in the
distro and focuses on the new I want my new desktop damn it well I I hear budgies
complete Chris well no it turns out that there as when a distro grows there's
there are things that legitimately need to be replaced and so I understand you
know some fine plumbing is being done but I do fantasize about it about a
desktop that Aiki and team have worked on that is cute based but not plasma 5
itself but still uses kwin and GTK apps look like first-class citizens it just
seems like a perfect world and this actually looking at the screenshots I
gotta say it's pretty it kind of very flashy website I actually used nitrates
a little bit oh give me the new version oh yeah tell me what you think it is
interesting you know and those things that they're doing there the
customizations they're doing are kind of interesting like one of the most
annoying things for plasma for me is the notification structure because it
doesn't keep track of a history of notifications anymore and that is
incredibly irritating and has been for over a year for me and to the point
where there's like a telegram group for it and there's big bug threads for it
and all this other stuff anyway they built their own solution to that and I
think they did it pretty well it's there's some bugs in it is in the
structure because they kind of built all their system tray everything that's like
a system tray widget would go into this new system tray they built so their
notifications are stored into that so that it's pretty cool overall but it
feels like a like a Mac elementary style like menu launcher and then then Mac
everything else so they have like global menu and if the dock installed by
default and things like that so it's interesting concepts and I do like the
fact that they have they've built some cool stuff one of the things that I
wish that plasma distros had was a more cute based graphical firewall
and they built one for their nomad thing it's called the nomad firewall and it's
basically a system settings module that is front-end GUI for ufw interested you
know do you have you happen to seen what the licenses for that that particular
one I haven't looked at that no but they seem to be gpl3 on everything I've seen
boy it's I'm still kind of trying to figure out where this this is nice but
yeah without with the world that has Alex cute what do you think would be with
the world that has Alex cute where does this fit I'm not sure where that this
fits in it I can't tell enough from the website as to what it is exactly yeah it
seems like when if it's if it's something on top of neon or kabuto or
whatever does seem to be their own custom desktop I don't want to say it's
an entire environment but it's not a stiff it's not the typical plasma shell
I will yeah I will say that at least from what they showed their their
settings interface looks way better than Katie I think it is the Katie one it is
the same I think it is it's just different yeah they the icons are way
clear and then they're the borders between each segment are more I guess
it's just more clearly defined yeah the borders are more defined the hover
effect isn't doesn't it doesn't have that same margin padding structure so it
looks awkward but like there's certain things about it that are really cool and
there's other parts that it looked like they there it's not finished yet and it
is it looks looks like it's on a beta so there's this the interesting thing about
it is it feels like an enthusiast that doesn't want to edit anything that wants
a Mac approach so like you can start with this Mac approach and then customize
it however you want because it does seem to be built on plasma I looked at the
widgets and they're all very they they all seem to be plasma widgets so it
looks like they took plasma and then like made modifications to plasma itself
and then also installed the latte dock and some other things so oh and the the
menu that's in nitrix is as a custom menu they built is a custom applet so
that they are doing some modifications to plasma but it does feel like plasma
and it seems like they're doing an Ubuntu like rolling beta thing with the
neon packages on top of it which is kind of interesting and also to me kind of
scary to me because the those packages are made for the 1604 release of the
stack so it's kind of you know that could be a problem you know if any of
you looked at Alex cute seriously I was like actually this I was just gonna say
this story is making me want to give it another go cuz it's been it's been since
it was in it was earlier in an early stage of development since I looked at
it I haven't looked at it you've got an LXQ expert in the chat room at the
moment I was actually gonna suggest that maybe Simon should chime in it's you
know from from his perspective of somebody who works with Alex cute what
he thinks about this distro and Simon could can I throw a random tech question
at you too I is Kaywin in LXQ does that part of and how can you explain that to
is that like advice if I set up LXQ on my system can I use Kaywin as a
back-end window manager or whatever I believe you can I've done it in a VM
just to test but I mainly use it with open box in fact I'm running Alex cute
on my system right now with open box that's right yeah so yeah I can use
Kaywin on the back ends like I said I played around with it in a VM the main
reason why why somebody would want to use Kaywin with Alex cute is for Wayland
support and the only reason why why yeah the only reason why Alex cute hasn't
gone to 1.0 yet is Alex cute 1.0 is Wayland complete that's why that that
hasn't gone to 1.0 and we don't have any we don't have an ETA for you know I've
recently been doing some upstream Alex cute development and we don't have an
ETA for 1.0 but I know they're gonna do what was it that is I think it was 0.12
they're gonna do upstream within the next month or two okay okay well I guess
I'd put this out there to the audience if anybody's tried nitrix and wants to
write in and tell us what it's like mm-hmm no I it's like for me though I
like I think my time would probably be spent better with Alex cute you know
this I don't really want to bring it up again but this approach is kind of the
approach I was talking about when we were talking about pop OS I feel like
this is an approach that makes more sense they're doing significant
customization but they're basing it on top of the right distribution instead of
spinning it off into its own thing yeah from what I can tell I don't know if
it's a if it's a fork of plasma or if it's just something that sits on top of
plasma with some themes that's I haven't been able to tell that from looking at
the website I based on what I've experienced it looks like it's just
sitting on top yeah that's my guess too by looking at it it is the difference
there's the things I've used on it it just seemed like it's on top but there's
there are there are things that are customized that are not plasma at all
but it seems like they've they they changed it looks like they're just
replacing applets I wouldn't necessarily compare it with
neon because neon is is like plasma on top of the LTS Ubuntu and they're
trying to do I believe like a whole different experience with this and like
I said neon is just from what I can tell it's a it's a plasma testing ground
right I think the reason the only reason the neon thing comes up is that they say
specifically that they use neon packages okay gotcha so it's an it's an
interesting the desktop but they're doing things that are cool that they're
basing on an existing distro with some existing packages already built for them
then just making modifications but at the same time they are using a beta
release of a distro that's that's a weird it's if you're gonna provide a
package that's like all set up for you out of the box why would you base it on
a rolling beta thing that and then that that's sort of something I don't know why
would they do why would they not do it on you you know why would they not wait
for 1804 or why not 1704 I mean I'm just curious to see why if there's something
new in 1710 that they that they need or something along those lines there is one
more thing I wanted to point out that it's really cool that they have a they
built a custom module for system D inside of system settings so you can
make all your modifications to system D straight in the system setting so that's
pretty cool that's pretty nice all right so we got to put it I got to put the
call out there to see what people think I I'm tempted tempted but I got a
greater story to tell today and I'm already on a journey I can't I can't
deviate now otherwise I might give it a look myself this is where the community
can help you guys give me a hard time about slackwear last week actually was
thinking about taking a slackwear challenge you should I was thinking
about it it's just I'm really on a journey right now like I'm like on a I'm
on a path to a new distro for our production equipment is that and all my
all my systems upstairs my laptop and so I'm on a journey of a process of
elimination right now and I don't want to I don't want to get too distracted
you know Chris cuz I can distro hop for days girls last time people told you to
take a journey you ended up switching the entire studio to that distro so
maybe you should take another journey well see this is the thing this is why
I'm taking it slowly and methodically so I'll tell you more about it later but
first stretch your middle fingers out for a moment because it may be time to
point them once again in NVIDIA's general direction I don't maybe you guys
can talk me down from the ledge here but an NVIDIA developer who works on the
Linux graphic side so Aaron you shout out to Aaron Platner I think is I think
that's his name thank you for your hard work and now please accept this accept
this plea from your humble Linux podcast please consider supporting x wayland it
appears right now that NVIDIA has no plans to support applications running
under x wayland with the NVIDIA proprietary graphics driver which to me
seems like a bad thing since that's pretty much almost anything that's using
the proprietary driver today and it's not like we're gonna get games rebuilt
with Wayland support tomorrow and I just the amount of applications that would be
f'd in the a you might say seems great unless I'm misunderstanding the dramatic
impact this is going to have well doesn't that mean that Alex QT 1.0 won't
work on NVIDIA as long as you're in under Wayland with k-win right I don't
know because it's no because that would be innate no because that'd be talking
way anything that communicates Wayland will be good anything that's talking X
anything is talking through X Wayland that's sort of X translation
translation compatibility layer it seems like and this is oh man check out
architect oh every single time we talk about this oh everybody always brings up
AMD you know I actually think that NVIDIA position is a good position
because at some point you need to just make a hard break and stop supporting
legacy stuff all of the games that have ever been written ever well then you can
just go run them on X maybe one of my misunderstanding here this I guess yeah I
guess I mean so the thing is right it's like if they're not doing this thing but
no one's making any Linux gamer uninstall their X server I think X is
gonna be abandoned at some point anyway so those games will eventually not work
anyway well I don't know I mean well I'm sure are we that X isn't gonna be
around for another 10 I'm sure something still be around I'm just saying like
eventually if the argument is the things that are gonna be that currently
available are not gonna be available like well that will happen eventually
anyway I'm sure there'll be one distro just like didn't de novo that does that
doesn't use a system D that'll continue to use X until the end of time but I
think it's pretty clear that the future is Wayland well the chat room and
everybody listening right now shutting up their podcast player will tell you
the future is AMD and open-source drivers the problem is there are millions
of GTX cards already bought and paid for and one of the reasons people like to
use Linux is because they get value out of their existing hardware and now all
of a sudden we're gonna come along and say hey welcome to Linux go get an AMD card
I don't think that's gonna work so I appreciate that maybe AMD has a better
path forward driver wise but it's it's like that's like telling people have
battery life issues to switch to Cyanogen mod or whatever also just
because the Nvidia proprietary drivers won't support X-Wayland doesn't mean
that something like Novio won't that's that's fair oh by the way a real-time
update here in the show Simon just chiming in saying the next version of
LXQt release will have nice things like high DPI support that's really great and
tons of more polishing including compatibility with the latest Qt that is
awesome I I will be checking that out so what do you think bashful fruit is there
gonna be like a groundswell to fix this problem I don't necessarily think it'll
be a groundswell is more of making a smart ass client that someone will just
fork it and go back because they didn't want to keep go to the new one well
rumor has it the Debian project is working on rootless X right so maybe we
just solved the problem of X's security issues and you could be sitting there
running Wayland all day long and then when it comes time to game you just
launched rootless X somehow and switch over to a different different terminal
exactly I mean that's that's a hack but it would seems like would something
prevent you from running Wayland and a rootless X server on another console at
the same time I actually don't know that one technically seems like that would be
a plausible fix yeah becomes almost compliance like in some ways I just
can't really understand can anybody I mean so is it are we doing all of this
work I mean if we set the security stuff aside are we doing all of this so that
way we have tear-free flash video because I just I'm gonna just mention
we're gonna be flashing gonna be dead before we're all using Wayland that's my
prediction that's for sure I think it's more tear-free anything GPU accelerated
ever yeah I get tear I get tearing it is hard though I will say I mean like
especially when we were you know niche to begin with and then after like 20
years of X we're like yeah all right people are kind of supporting us now
great mm-hmm so it's probably gonna be a long time huh so anyways I guess you
know it's not time to get the pitchforks yet because it seems like the the Wayland
the big switch to Wayland I don't know I think 2020 would be optimistic I just I
just don't see it at this point yeah I would say five years probably yeah and
so it this might be a non-issue there might be other ways to run these
applications there may be some sort of compatibility layer that has a stable
API set created by a company that's experienced in this area that works in
open-source who knows who knows there may be other solutions to this problem
maybe in video will become open source at some point who knows maybe mark
shuttleworth can sit down with Aaron Platner over at Nvidia and espouse the
great benefits of mirror and it'll just get we'll just get this ball rolling so
wimpy I'm glad you are here sir because for about an hour and a half before the
show I got to play around with the latest alpha of Ubuntu Mate 1710 holy
smokes holy smokes and I have a couple questions couple couple grave concerns
and a few observations so that I am very very much looking forward to talking to
because holy cow what a release there may be some patreon leaks involved I
mean it's it's some good stuff I know prepare your bodies prepare your minds
West have you ever been into a candle store that's like super strong with
smells yeah and you know how they have those jars of coffee and you sniff that
jar of coffee and it resets the palate digital ocean comm go over to digital
ocean comm and use our promo code deal unplugged after you've created your
account once you sign up you go in there like a boss you make your account and
then you apply that promo code deal unplugged and you get a $10 credit it's
like digital oceans like here here's a credit card with ten dollars on it go
cray now that's nice because they have a five dollar a month rig which you could
run two months for absolutely free or go the even more like sophisticated on top
of it route and do their hourly yeah so great I'm even I don't even know what
the like lower prices are cuz like three cents an hour like I'm like that's
better that's fine that's I've literally only need it for a couple of hours that
is it's so fast it's so so stinking fast it was a actually a topic of
conversation recently just how how stinking fast there their systems are
because first of all it's SSDs throughout everything and it's massively
taken advantage of I'll just put it that way then they have Linux as the host
system we all love that KVM for the virtualizer 40 gigabit networks to
ensure uptime and throughput highly available block storage you can get your
systems deployed in seconds the entire stack or just a base system monitoring
alerting so you can collect metrics and monitor performance and get alerts so
you can look like a ten-person team even when you're one or two people the
pre-built open source apps to are done right it's not like magic config scripts
that don't make any sense it's like if you hired a really good sysadmin you
went in there and he built a system and then they took an image of it I wonder I
wonder and then you top that all off with a really great documentation
incredibly straightforward pricing dashboard they even offer images for
those crazy BSD folks yeah I know I know they even they have the audacity to work
with the projects upstream to can you imagine such a thing that's insane
providing free hosting for many in the open source community and giving API so
you can tie stuff directly into your workflow I won't be having it Rekai
that's crazy talk digital ocean calm use the promo code do unplugged and a big
thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the unplug program and thanks
to you out in the audience for using do unplugged when you do sign up apply to
your account do unplugged man it is super useful I was on a network over the
weekend that was not so friendly for a little bit so I had to do some you know
tunneling over DNS what was that was perfect I didn't want to mess with the
servers I already had new do droplet boom back online yep yep yep so there is
there's a lot to cover in Ubuntu land these days and so you could say thank
you if you if you're not an Ubuntu fan because I could have made this entire
show about it so I'm saving really the best right now and I want to talk about
Ubuntu Mate 1710 they're actually I think a new alpha release just came out
today I'm I'm being sneaky on patreon two days two oh oh in two days oh okay the
paint the patrons got the release notes early access but the download it's gonna
be on Thursday oh teasing teasing wow so this is a huge release the the I would
say the number one thing that stood out to me when I tried it is how tight the
the mutiny tweak option is when you run the Ubuntu or the Mate tweak and you go
into the different layouts and you choose mutiny I mean it it really looked
like unity 7 with after I made a few small tweaks and I turned on compass I
was pretty much I was pretty much it back in unity 7 so it that was the map
that was the mode that I played around with with this new release the most I
think my favorite feature wimpy and I didn't even notice it until I went to do
it was the complete super key support which I didn't realize how much that
have bugged me until I tapped it and it worked and I went oh yeah that used to
be a problem yeah oh that's that's huge for me too wow that yeah and and me you
know that's not there by accident right but it's funny though because it's one
of those things where it's not just touching one project to make that work
right yeah I mean there are so many people that have been involved in making
that happen so in earlier releases the Marte menu which used to be called the
advanced menu in Marte tweak had super key support but it was like super key
support in a lot of the smaller desktop environments and launches in that you
could press super to open a menu but it swallowed the super key so if you had
any other key bindings that used the super key they just didn't work out so
Aiki obviously cooked up Budgie and then he Budgie the brisk menu for Marte yeah
and we I added a goal in there to add super key support and somebody from the
community stepped in Victor Carra I think his name is or Carra I'm sorry
Victor if I've butchered your name and he actually landed the fixes in brisk to
make it work but then he went around and started adding the same patches to the
Marte menu and when he started doing that he realized that the underlying
libraries weren't implemented properly and Marte settings demon wasn't doing
the right thing and Marte doc applet wasn't doing the right thing so he has
been laying down patches all over the place so that super key works but more
importantly if you've got other key bindings they work as well and it sounds
like such a simple thing but it's been a heap of work and I'm I'm really indebted
to him because he's turned Marte from a thing that had kind of janky super key
support to to real first-class super key support and it makes a huge difference
to the way I use my computer now because I just mash super key type enter and I
am off I think there's several more systems that will now be on this next
release I think is a direct result I can't tell you to me it's like if for
some reason it's muscle memory smash super key ter enter and that has to be
smashed you know delicate nothing it's I'd command this thing okay so I know
something else has been getting polished really for several releases is the
heads-up display which was one of the really kind of cool features when I was
using unity heavily I drifted away from using it but I do remember during my
heyday of using unity 7 the HUD was handy and for those of you that aren't
familiar I I think at least in the unity world essentially it was this tool that
you could execute with a keyboard command and like alt super or whatever
whatever I can't remember what the command was and I think just all okay
alt and I think it talked D bus and it would read all of the menus on an
application over D bus and then it would expose them as a command like so you
could type in if you wanted to do file export you could just type in export
into the HUD and it would just pull it up instead of having to dig around so
you didn't have to take your hand off the keyboard to use the menus mm-hmm is
it would be am I getting this right and is that what's coming or at least
getting even better in Matei yeah so we we started that journey in Ubuntu Mate
1610 and it was not ready so we we pulled it and in this cycle it's now
ready for use so this works hand-in-glove with the global menus that have also
been reworked and it means that yes just as you've described you can open your
application and in in Ubuntu Mate it's a slightly different keyboard
combination it's super alt to activate the HUD although Victor is determined he
tells me to make the necessary changes throughout the various places so that
you could activate it with just alt as well so he's he's like a dog with a bone
at this at the moment chasing these issues down but this is a really
powerful feature and it's one that I really valued what I obviously been
using unity for quite a while on a day-to-day basis and have recently
switched back to Marte on my main machine and one of the features I loved
was the HUD particularly like editing podcasts and you're in audacity and you
want to find the appropriate effects and filters using the HUD makes actually
digging out those effects and filters really fast oh yeah and also in things
like libre office and GIMP where you know image processing things are
scattered to the four corners of the UI you know it's really useful for just
quickly accessing stuff so I love that yeah yeah me too in fact I was just
sitting here thinking about how handy that is when I'm on air cuz it makes
things so friggin quick also improvements to indicator support which
is something that seems like it's a lot of work on every release what is there
still work to be done on indicators no we're done now this congrats yeah that
is good just in time to really I mean this is yeah this is looking like one of
those releases where if I was if I was really if I was really a big fan of
unity and I wanted a home to move to that reminded me a lot of it and that
workflow with the mate tweak tool you just it's like one drop down away you
choose mutiny and also I turned on compass is my compositor and it it
really felt a lot like home because we have a I was doing an AB test cuz I have
a unity 7 system right here that I'm running mumble on to talk to you guys
and so I ran it on the system right next to it my main presenter machine and was
doing sort of an AB and it's it's pretty great it's close yeah it'll get closer
in time as well but it's it's done without sacrificing some of the more
traditional things about about a bunta mate that I liked so I it was a really
it was a pretty salt I have to ask you that would be grave concern over this
one grave concern okay Firefox 50 what is going on here can you just somebody I
mean this is one of these 54 is out now this is one of those things who it could
who it canonicals in charge of this this is just this this is what happens in the
in the dev cycle you'll find that packages that are being revved you know
regularly in the in the released it is your fault I tease I tease I install
chrome immediately anyway so it's fine as does everyone else yeah yeah that
software but yeah okay well that's what you know you're that user are you oh the
best browser ever I was gonna give it a go but it was it was it was so old I was
like why does this feel so slow like Firefox has gotten fat oh oh that's what
so then I just you know what here's my tip for you
Ubuntu dash but a dash welcome space tack be you hit that right boom software
boutique flies right open cue up a couple of things and you go to the main
screen the new I like that cue animation that it does there's like there's like
a yeah there's like it's just tops it really is like I I opened up I knew I
went in there I saw the internet section there was chromium there was a brave did
fail to install a live bug report there but I figure that probably that'll
probably work later on I do want to give brave ago mm-hmm and then and then I use
that a lot now really are you liking it yeah I it's the only browser I use on my
phone and I'm using it about 50% of the time on my desktop now huh all right I'm
gonna give it a go come back to there's anybody to some that they remove ads
from specific websites and put their own ads in no I like that feature why
because it removes all of the privacy invading ads and replaces them with
sanitized versions hmm so people don't worry about the privacy guarding you
know capabilities getting rid of all sorts of stuff that's buried in pages
that you you really don't want so there's no need for things like privacy
badger and stuff like that yeah but then there's all of the idea that the ads
being put in are their ads and not the people who you're going to the website
for and they don't get anything for it yeah I've signed up to their scheme to
pay pay back the money to the sites that I want to support right hmm yeah that
scheme that sounds interesting it's almost like they thought about this
before they implemented it the browsers of today are broken they've been
overtaken by a barrage of sneaky and annoying ads trackers that follow your
habits and cookies that build profiles and all sorts of other internet clutter
that's taking precedence over the content that you want to see in fact
these useless bites can take up to a whopping 50% of page load times with a
third of it anxiously trying to learn more about you to make matters worse
some ad blockers are even letting the ads through and large advertisers pay
them but do you really want a leaky ad blocker it's because of these very
reasons that we developed brave a new browser that kicks internet crud to the
curb and makes it faster safer and better to surf the web than your
current browser
with brave everything you need is built right in
we integrated technology that automatically blocks trackers annoying
ads and shields everything that can cramp your style and destruct your
privacy wow I don't want you can expect increased speeds nearly two times faster
on laptops and up to four times faster on mobile so there you go that's the
pitch on brave it's it's a Mozilla project so that's you know sort of
interesting it's not no it's not it's the guy from Moses the founders of
Mozilla founded this okay I see that was the confusion so is it web kit based
then yes I think it's linked it's a bit more complex than that but yes
essentially well now I'm like I'm like half as excited but I'll still get with
a go I was way more excited when I thought it was Mozilla realizing that
the Firefox was dead and they were starting a new product and that they
were gonna revitalize gecko and a new more competitive browser but now that's
what they're already doing the Firefox though yeah that's what the web
extensions are for that's what servos for yeah yeah yeah and web extensions
are coming in three releases like they're gonna be like the the main thing
in three releases right now you can already use them and they've already got
electrolysis out and all this other stuff it's good yeah you should use
Firefox already has all these things Chrome you know I really am so I'm so
depressed about this topic I don't think I want to talk about it much check out
Linux action news 11 I mean we covered a story it's just it's devastating
devastating for Firefox it's just so sad it's so sad and there's just nothing
they can do about it because it's you know and I make this I make this pitch a
lot here on the show but as open source enthusiasts we are a particular kind of
techie crowd and we are particularly susceptible to getting into arguments
about things on their technical merits and we are less capable often I don't
know I'm trying to put this nicer but we are less likely to have a better
understanding of market dynamics and the market dynamics are such that a monopoly
in search and in web services is contributing billions of dollars worth
of advertising space ie the top of YouTube Google search Gmail calendar
all the Google's premier products if you are not running Chrome constantly nag you
to upgrade to Chrome and that's the terminology they use is upgrade to Chrome
and they do Google Google Docs works better offline if you upgrade to Chrome
Google Calendar works offline if you upgrade to Chrome having problems
watching this video this is why I've seen this one on YouTube are you having
problems watching this video try upgrading to Chrome can you imagine how
many users must fall for that that's interesting see I use Firefox to work
but I don't I only use it really for like for working so I don't watch
YouTube I don't check my personal email or any of those so I don't see that
that's it's literally invaluable ad space because Google doesn't sell that
to any Adsense customer only and and the thing is is that Firefox isn't
competing against Internet Explorer anymore mm-hmm when when Firefox was
truly taking over they were being innovative and competitive in a way that
the consumer base was hungry for the issue is is that like the beard just
jokingly said oh that's nice you know it also has that is Chrome Google has not
stood still at all they are not the stagnant monopoly that Internet Explorer
was they are hungry as hell to shape the web and they are moving at a breakneck
pace continuing to outpace Firefox and finally say that Firefox's release
schedule is fast know what I just mean is in oh I'm sorry I mean they're
continuing to get more users to like they're they're they're down velocity
yeah their momentum with their momentum is continuing to grow and they're
continuing to develop the product like it's it's just not the same not like
what IE was right yeah exactly they have a vested interest in getting as many
users as possible so it's just you know it's just a plus Firefox had a had a had
a had an unlikely ally in the US justice system which was beating
Microsoft over the head about bundling IE which slowed things down yeah I mean
it's it's harder the the argument between Chrome and Firefox is really
hard because both are very good browsers to use and it's purely a technical
aspect that but see brave would be new and shiny and a chance at new branding
and I mean look at the attention Braves getting already like if this was a
Mozilla project they're only getting attention because of the ad thing if
most if Firefox did the same thing and added an ad thing it would be the same
effect well there is a big problem with Braves though it doesn't work on porn
sites that's the big problem oh really why is that everything just is black
because it blocks everything so I'm told right these websites my friends that
tell me I know a lot of unsavory characters use brain for that's what
Firefox focus is for well maybe they'll just start working in 2022 when these
drop flash okay hold on I'd actually now this works so you use brave for
everything else and you use focus for porn and oh wow hey so I guess a flash
flash update again another real-time update here on the show breaking news
mr. wimpy reports that brave is now installable via the software boutique
good job with me that was like you're welcome so there's a bit of a patreon
leak rumors are spreading and you know I just I wanted to give you an
opportunity to address the rampant speculation that the Ubuntu matei
project is moving to github that just seems seems like that's just rampant
speculation yeah we have in fact we've moved all of our projects to github
wow we're integrated to the max now we've also got slack going for the core
team and we're expanding the team quite considerably so at the moment we've got
Etienne who's come in he's been doing good work behind the scenes for some
time and he's now heading up the QA team and there and whilst I'm here having an
evening of podcasting they're busy doing the ISO testing for the new release
thank you so really good yeah we've got a lot of improvements that streamline
our processes and there'll be more tooling just coming along just to make
sure I'm clear though this means the project is essentially migrating from
launchpad right we have moved the few packages that we were maintaining on
launchpad to github and that isn't required to be a flavor to be on
launchpad well we need to have our bug tracker on launchpad and what have you
and that's still there okay you know so that's more about if there's a bug
reported we're able to close the bug by uploading new package directly in
launchpad but in terms of source code hosting that's all on github now that
makes plus there's also the mirroring to launchpad thing no we've we've just
exported everything to github the only thing that we've left on launchpad are
the seeds because they have to be there and do you do you suppose that this
might lead to more more contributors to the project people that me that's yeah
yeah without a doubt we've already seen it with the day after we migrated we
just dumped you know just might run a load of migration scripts and moved
everything over and we knew there was a load of like URLs and things that needed
changing in the code before we could repackage them and the next morning
there was a load of pull requests where people had just come in and changed all
of those URLs for us and that's the github effect right so yeah you know
open source code hosting and all the rest of it github is where most of the
eyeballs are and you get more drive-by commits there it's as simple as that
yeah it makes sense that does and if they if it leads to more open source it
seems to me a net to be a good thing and if it leads to more people writing
open source then in that it's a good thing this seems would be like it's oh
go ahead I was just gonna say it's it's so much better now that it's on github
because it's a lot easier to just do a pretty much everything because like just
by creating a launchpad account and trying to commit to a contribute to a
project is so difficult that most people just give up I've had an account with
launchpad for I don't know like ten years I think I've used it maybe yeah
okay so this is just my impression I'm not saying this is wimpy's position but
to me what looking at this alpha I mean it's a freaking alpha it first of all I
don't really I don't know it's so damned it's to feel so damn ready I it sort of
blows my mind but this feels like this is the release it's really like this is
ready for the masses it's ready for people look at unity refugees I mean
this really feels like it's polished to the next level for this desktop release
yeah so it has been a ton of work it's been three months we literally started
working on this the day after 1704 was released we were the first people to
commit anything to 1717 awesome and it's been late nights and long nights for
three months and we've pretty much landed at this point everything that we
wanted to get on the desktop for the final release that's three months from
now so we're done in terms of features except we've got another three months so
now we're going to go and circle back to something so you will you will have heard
the news about our new software boutique which is not in this release it's the
old one slightly refreshed so now work will start on finishing up the new
software boutique and there's a few other little skunk work projects that
some of the other project they're helping us with and they should trickle
along between now and October so we're kind of done with the desktop and now
we're going to really start adding some more polish and improvements on top of
what we've got here that's a good position to be here that's going to make
for a this release so it sounds so damn good you should have saved it for the LTS
no kidding I guess this is just we're one step away right so I've not been
doing you know the flavors in a bunty for very long but I have done one LTS
before and I remember what it was like when we were making 1510 and then the
effort that was involved to get 10 to 1604 yeah and that was hard work and I
realized that really 1710 needs to be your 1804 and then it's all about
improving the quality and the stability in that 1804 cycle that's landing those
last few features but really making sure it's solid yeah totally that is that's
gonna make for a good song and we're well ahead of where we wanted to be
because this time last year we were transitioning from GTK 2 to GTK 3 and I
had originally planned we would finish that GTK 3 transition about now about
this time but we finished that last October so we we got like a cycle ahead
of ourselves so I'm really an Ubuntu Marte now is really starting to be the
desktop platform that I wanted to use because simple things like super key and
and the HUD and global menus I don't use the global menus myself but I know lots
of people like those these were all things that were niggling at me that I
knew weren't quite right and it wasn't perfect and it's really feeling like
it's falling into place now and it's all coming together and the indicator
support it's got the same indicators that you'd expect to find in Unity 7 so
everything that you'd expect to find in a unity desktop you'll find here now so
I'm really pleased with how it's shaping up yeah it really comes through as a
great release just even trying out the the latest that I got the daily build
and it was it was pretty great if you you know if you want to know about this
stuff first the people who support the Ubuntu Mate project learn about it from
the horses fingers I guess patreon.com slash Ubuntu underscore Mate I'll have a
link in the show notes too if you want to support the project not only do you
get news but you help help the news keep on coming yeah there is there's a poll
over there right now about which video player should be the default in Ubuntu
Mate obviously it should be GnomeMPV it is the greatest just saying with in my
humble opinion I completely agree well when we voted let me go yes yes I did
yes I did good yeah yes we need more GnomeMPV needs more love it's such a
team GnomeMPV yeah it is a great media player and it's somebody who does a lot
of media editing and work and then also uses that really pushes it for unfilter
it's just such MPV such a great tool are you saying GnomeMPV or just MPV well
MPV in general and if you're gonna use GnomeMPV if you're gonna use a
wrapper around it GnomeMPV is the way to go it really is great okay I was just
wondering like is it I've always never noticed the reason why would somebody
want to use GnomeMPV versus MPV like it's just you could just right-click
and load the video with MPV so I'm just curious if the I could tell you why I
because I'll go ahead with me well I was gonna say I like it because it adds the
typical interfaces to manipulate it that you'd expect to be there yeah the users
doesn't feel like an odd duck right but I like it because so I use it exclusively
to play back all of the crazy types of file formats we have for unfilter clips
it's just a whole range that we get stuff in whatever you can real player I
mean I'm telling you it's a whole range and then that's an MPV thing right right
no I know but let me just say so the nice thing about GnomeMPV is it gives
you a super clean minimal but always available play bar indicator pause
button I can only see where the play position is and it is one of the it's
probably one of the best designed gnomes in the sense that it's almost nothing to
it except for just barely what you need and it's just enough that I can look
down I know exactly where it's at play wise and if I want to go full screen
it's like f11 or you know a click away or whatever it is so it's kind of like a
perfect balance for me in that sense so I guess it's more like it's a user in
our user experience is easier to get you because you don't have to learn all the
specific shortcuts that MPV there's that and it's like I while I'm playing
something on the stream I can't keep putting my mouse over the video to see
where the play positions that have that display over the video because that's
tacky so having it just below the video where I can still see where the play
positions at but don't have to show anything on screen makes for a better
presentation okay I understand there's always weird you know use cases I always
have a weird one so it's very much a tool it's where it's regular MPV works
great if I'm gonna put on some you know MP MPV file and just watch it for an
hour yeah like if I'm gonna do a live stream I just MPV and then the URL I
don't bother with dome MPV like if it's because and there's really MPV I in my
opinion has done such a good job at giving you information that is readable
on the command line output when you use it from the command line that even if
you're not like a pro user you can see like it's trying to fix it'll try to
fix a video and audio sync for you and tell you what it offsets it's using like
it's just brilliant there's another thing that I found in recently MPV does
that a lot of people don't you think that they would do this but you can take
videos that are like awkwardly slowed down or have weird cropping issues and
you can like resume and recrop I use that all the time automatically yeah I
use all the time yeah that's really nice VLC is a great tool as well we do use
that in production here at studio but you know if I could only have I'm on an
island and I can only have one package MPV or no MPV all the way mm-hmm it's
it's so great all right so I there's a couple more things I want to talk about
before we wrap up for the day and we also have I think we have I think we're
gonna get some more Alex cute info out of Simon in the post show yeah more to
come a more to come but I want to take a moment and I want to talk about
something else I take on that desert island with me and that's the Linux
Academy then I could sit there and train my mind Linux Academy calm slash
unplugged go there to support the show and sign up for a free seven-day trial
Linux Academy comm slash unplug a platform by Linux I'll say it again a
platform a platform you see I got a little pop there a little bit a platform
by Linux enthusiasts for Linux enthusiasts people that wanted to spread
the adoption of Linux and kind of began to think about this project from there
then got together with real-world educators people with experience
developers that came together as a group like a holy trinity you might say I mean
they probably wouldn't say that but I might say that of Linux education and
they built a system they started and they started in a reasonable like
approachable like actually accomplishable product and then it just
took off like wildfire and they've been able to grow it and it just adds so much
value to the platform if you've been a subscriber now for like a year you've
just seen it take off like nuts self-paced in-depth video courses
hands-on scenario based labs to give you real experience on servers you get to
SSH into those bad boys and use them like you really would and man is that
nice because it gives you confidence to actually work with the stuff oh you're
busy yeah I know about that they have a course schedule that worked with your
busy time to make it all fit in there they have learning paths too if you just
want to go into a specific career track maybe you've got some type of type of
certain mind well they also have courses created specifically to prepare you for
that they also have a vibrant community that's packed full of Jupiter broadcasting
members and study tools that you can download offline and take with you and
iOS and Android apps if you have some downtime and want to do a little study
gosh that's cool yeah that's really cool Linux Academy calm slash unplugged
go there to sign up get a free seven-day trial and support the show and then dig
in and I think probably you know I gotta say my favorite feature is the human
beings the instructor mentoring like the actual help because that's that's really
what takes them up to the next level because instead of just throwing on
Linux as a feature that they have as well as plumbing and Adobe After Effects
and Final Cut oh and then they have your Linux stuff over here and your
developer stuff because you got to have those checkboxes you got to check those
boxes then they're not gonna have anybody passionate about that stuff in
their company that's not like their core focus that's not what their missions
about so Linux Academy they focus on Linux open source and all the stuff
around it which means they can hire people professionally well not just
professionally trained but passionate yeah passionate about it means you can
count on them that you know they know what they're doing and if you get stuck
or you know it just sometimes you need two or three different ways of hearing
something to learn it the other way that the other way that it manifests
itself in a way that is valuable to customers is that since they're
following trends because they're enthusiasts they they're on to stuff
that is valuable like when containerization started becoming a
thing Linux Academy was having court it was having the best courseware on it and
the stuff like you could immediately go and apply to a job kind of stuff really
practical good stuff always giving you value Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
sign up for a free seven-day trial and support the show this is a great post
and it got me missing gnome already and it was from a metanova over in the
unplugged subreddit Linux unplug dot reddit comm and he says greetings
unplugged I recently have made the switch back to arch and gnome 3 and for
the most part I'm pretty happy with the switch however I'm distracted easily huh
what would you say oh I'm sorry you distracted you weren't listening and so
I try to do my best to adapt my desktop environment to account for this my
biggest problem with gnome or good gnome as you say is that the activities window
overview is really disorienting for me I use dash to dock for switching windows
but I still have problems when I open the overview to launch applications
seeing every single window I have whoosh onto the screen is really distracting it
can really knock me out of my flow well I could see that like you know your
telegram window comes up and you see you got a shit ton of chats that you haven't
answered in 15 minutes or with slack or the IRC or your email what was that oh
the easiest solution to this problem is to use another application launcher like
no I'm doing anyways it goes through his goals here to sort of make gnome a less
distracting UI and I it dawned on me that this was the problem I ran into when I
switched to plasma for a while is that there was just so many things for me to
play with widgets that tell me my CPU stuff and my new messages and there's
different ways to set up the panels a ton yeah he's doing he's doing a plea
for help he says does anyone in the unplugged family to fam the unplugged
fam know about this is there an extension I'm missing I like that
alternatively if anyone here is familiar with developing gnome extensions
creating extensions that hides window previews and activities etc it'd be
greatly appreciated ultimately I'm looking for an activities
tweaker or other ideas and experiences that the audience has had and we have a
link to metanova's thread if you want to toss in there what about us are you do
suffer because you you probably get in cut type of work that requires that you
get into a flow and maintain that flow for a while do you suffer from
distracted UI you know thankfully not especially not on on gnome I don't
usually you know if I if I am even using dash to dock it's hidden so there's
always the problem of notifications but that's you know usually a per app thing
so as long as I'm you know divide my screen in half I got a terminal I have a
web browser I can get in the groove hmm but I do know you mean like playing with
plasma in the past especially for me when it might be something that like
I've been using it over ages now so it might just be used to anything that
would have distracted me as a new user I think that's probably part of it
ww you seem like a nice rational gentleman do you have the problem of
distracting UI right now no not really cuz and like I don't have any like any
background wallpaper forget about asking me for what's it look cool because I
have a billion windows up I have tabs yeah so tabs is pretty much my life
yeah I know what the beard solution is full screen all the things oh yeah if you
just run everything full screen then you can only look at one thing at a time I
don't have we ever talked about that the fact that you're a full screen maniac I
don't think so he's all in on the full screen every app I have is full screen
yeah I have like 20 to 30 apps oh yeah and then you know Chris ever a split and
and then like my browser that has 200 tabs yeah so I can only ever see one
thing at a time so I'm never distracted that is a it's an intense way to
operate but you do seem to make it work for you for me like I get claustrophobic
in that setup like I'm like I gotta I gotta be able to like I need an overview
and all I need windows that's for me I need to be able to move stuff around I
just oh yeah see I agree with architect if you can see your background you're
just being lazy all right that's it that's not a bad note to end it on I'll
just I just want to talk really quickly then about this journey that I'm
starting it's it's fun for me and I won't go on and on about it so I put it
at the end of the show but it's something it's different for me
personally with my Linux use in a long time is I'm I'm making I've talked about
this on user a little bit so I'll just give you the cliff notes I'm switching
away from Antigros and arch love arch I think it's a great great great desktop
workstation OS super stable despite what all the haters say Antigros has been
difficult for me recently and they it's a good project it's a great way to get
your hands on but I just have I just constantly having package
keys package key problems that prevent me from updating my system and it's only
about a five minute fix each time but it happens about once a month now and when
you multiply that across like five systems it gets frustrating and it's
even the same commands to fix it and all that stuff but it just feels like well I
don't want it I like the project a lot but it's it's just what happens is is it
makes me skip updating which is that only makes it worse that's when you
start going down a slippery slope with arch and you start you start not
updating and you start running into problems so it's kind of changes the
value proposition for the whole thing in some ways the other thing that's been a
big change for me is post Linux action show I don't do desktop app pics and a
project spotlight and a distribution pic like I don't have the pics and so I
don't have to try out so the pics look we talked about one app that week but
we tried five or six other ones other contenders so it means installing five
or six or seven or eight or sometimes ten different things to try out which
one really works and which one is generally available to the audience and
applicable and the AUR was just a slam dunk if you want to try out all the
different yeah it's always there and so it made it it literally made it was
part of my workflow you know go into the AUR find the application try it out
review it for the show probably uninstall it maybe not and that will you
know rinse repeat every single week and now I don't really have like I've kind
of have my stable set of applications I use I'm just getting my work done now
I'm not I'm not like sitting there trying to find new stuff constantly and I
don't know so it's changed it's changed what I need from my distributions
package manager to write and I would say like when you first switched to arch you
know snaps were not flat pack they're not in the place that they used they
aren't they weren't even a thing yeah so you have a lot more options even on you
know it wasn't a thing yeah right so there's also that's the other thing is
is there's like I was experimenting with solace and there was software I wanted
that wasn't available I was like oh yeah talker mm-hmm and I'm gonna have a whole
system running if you want one of the things that so it's funny cuz now I'm on
the other end of this one of the things that's that's true is for me is I don't
I wonder if it tells me right here I don't I don't make it a priority to
update yeah so there's 231 package updates for the OBS machine I don't make
it a practice to constantly upgrade the OBS machine because that makes a
production machine less reliable I need newer versions of everything underlying
OBS and I need newest versions of OBS but I don't need my gnome shell to
change I don't really need my new tools to change my kernel updates unless you
know except for security I don't I mean everything's working as it is in fact we
have some customized drivers for these capture cards so an LTS is starting to
make a lot more sense to me than it used to you're just gonna make Noah's day
aren't you you're making the what I like to call the Rekai to Noah transition
yeah right exactly how so well cuz I like the bleeding edge of everything and
Noah likes the LTS so you're making the transition from one to the other yeah I
don't see this it makes sense on the production equipment but it sounds
boring snot for my desktop it just really it's like it sounds like it's
sucking some of the fun out of using Linux but I think you're also some maybe
in a place where you're very busy and you're doing a lot more content
production yeah that makes it this is what I was thinking too I mean you can
always leave have you heard of the Church of neon oh you know I that's so
that's the other that's the other wrinkle isn't it because you've we've
got we've got a true blue gnome desktop coming from Ubuntu very soon and I'm
very interested in that we just talked about the super slick snot stuff in
Ubuntu Mate that really makes it a contender then you you do have the
plasma desktop as well I just like the whole field is open to me again I feel
myself I'm beginning to distro hop in a way that I haven't done for two and a
half two and a half three years so I've I've been trying out right now I've been
trying out mostly Ubuntu based stuff because I keep thinking if I'm gonna go
this route it seems like I should probably rebase on Ubuntu but there's
like this I key on my shoulder that keeps talking about all the cool shit
that solace is doing about how clear boot manager would be great for us for
you some production here and and then fedoras got this fedora workstation OS
tree release that they're working on and I'm like oh my goodness so many good
options it's it's it's so much harder than it ever has been to pick a
distribution right now and then Rika is saying slackware off in the corner you're
so that's why I was gonna do a slackware challenge but I'm right in the middle I'm
in the throes of this like my guess is Chris is gonna he's not gonna be able to
decide and he's gonna compromise and end up on a boot to budgie there we go well
that's reasonable what do you think bashful that might be a good way to go
huh yeah I'm kind of a little one-sided on this you use it as a dick you could
speak from as a from the perspective of a daily user over there you get you get
you get your work done every single day right and you're running you're running
it on the last release right now I don't know but I mean you're using it every
day as a daily driver yeah I'm running 1704 and I'm actually running it at work
too so and that's over a remote session as well and I haven't really had any
issues with it at all I got it another option is nitricks good callback good
callback nitricks I see budgie is a great desktop but it's so why would I
switch to that just so that way I can switch again in a year or whatever like
I don't know yeah but you're gonna run into that with almost any destroy you
pop in if you're not entirely happy no I just I just mean like that I think that
desktops gonna be going through a transition where right now it seems like
the time to you know get in on gnome 3 if things are shaping up like Mike Mike
Mike when's the last time we crashed it's been it's been like two weeks right
since we've had a gnome 3 crash yeah so the last time the last round of updates
I did manage to apply did seem to improve stability so that's good yeah
until the next issue crops well there's that there is that yeah so anyways my
distro my distro hopping ways have returned like it and of course it's
happening fun it has to be happening right around the 1710 release cycle too
so and you know you say that that that's a reason not to use budgie but don't you
think that gnome is probably about to go through a huge transition as well no I
think GTK 4 is gonna be more evolutionary well I was more talking
about the effect that Ubuntu might have on gnome oh boy well so far I like all
those effects I gotta say I mean I'm really this is this is the thing is what
I was trying to boom to mate and I rebooted this system like I realized as
I was hitting the restart button like I really like gnome like I really like
gnome 3 it's really good it's just I don't like it when it runs like dog poo
and crashes a lot but other than that I really like alright Chris you can run
gnome on your desktop upstairs and then down here in the studio we'll run Katie
everywhere well okay so if you're gonna go this is then we can have both then
we can wrap this up we got it we got a move we got to wrap it up for the day
but if just just if you take it to its practical logical conclusion why not go
Ubuntu LTS with unity 7 because this is this is a seriously this other than the
few problems we've had with the sound interface this this this mobile system
that's running unity 7 and Ubuntu is like 100% yeah yeah and I guess by the
time that it's end of life will probably have moved on to something else and
we've even done a couple of update batches on this thing so it's managed to
take its updates and not shit the bed and it runs until we have some cocky
many reason to reboot it and I mean it's just been rock-solid and unity 7 opens
windows real nice it has nice like borders to grab my windows to resize
them all the things I like about a desktop maybe 87 on some stuff too it
does randomly inexplicably spin up our GPU though that is true that did start
happening that did start happening I've been getting a lot of crap for saying
nice things about unity people are really angry that all of a sudden I have
positive things to say about unity now that it's end of life and it's I think
it's I think it's funny because if you look at the the majority of the
community that the transition has been much more positive for unity now that
things like all of the features that unity had that people didn't even know
existed they're going oh wow that's great you know too bad unity's dead now
like well yeah good job yeah but those same people just you know a couple
months ago we're crapping on unity because why is it moved to do in their
own of course anti canonical rhetoric yeah just this is the canonical hate and
then that's I don't I never understood then and I always they're always pointed
out how unity has a lot of cool features and now that it's gone it's kind of it's
kind of sad in a way it's still there like it's a saying it's like no that's
gonna mean I mean as far as like the innovation is all dead like the fact
that the HUD the concept of the HUD is just being is was abandoned and then
people and other people were trying to like rebuild everything and bring back
the global menu and like what the global menu has like every single gold menu
implementation so far has these weird massive holes like the CSDs don't work
and well I'm kind of not in a bunch of math a 1710 might drop canonical will
bring some of those improvements to know and make it a desktop that I like
more because I don't really like no right now yeah yeah that's I am not
ruling out plasma either so it's supposedly not changing that much except
for like already made extensions well initially but who knows what they're
gonna do down the road I think it's I think it's I think it's too obvious I
think it's not about it's not about changing the direction of gnome because
that's sort of the whole point of making this switch was to not have to to be
that to be that to be that player now you're now the idea is you ride with
upstream and you can spend your time fixing so we got to go we let Dan know
we're just gonna be five minutes so here's the thing the hard stuff isn't
getting done in open source and a lot of us know it a lot of us know that the
stuff that's really really tough to fix requires people that are working in
teams that have a coordinated development standards practice that maybe
have a PMO that's managing the things they're working on and telling them
instead of them choosing by what happens to fit their fancy the really hard stuff
is they underline stuff like the hundreds of bugs and Bluetooth and
things like that that require a real development focus and team to work on
them and that's an area where canonical can really and is already adding a ton
of value without having to fork the file manager or anything like that and I think
that is fundamentally going to be the long long term impact to the gnome
desktop isn't so much about them dictating the design future of gnome 3
but more about letting the gnome project make a great desktop making
modifications via the extension systems where it's appropriate and working on
the underlying underpinning stuff that makes using like a Bluetooth speaker
with your Linux box actually usable and that's I think going to be the big
benefit end of rant there's just a quickie well I I agree with that but I
also think that the fact that Ubuntu is settling on gnome now lets you work
better with upstream while also making changes so it's more like it's not
necessarily you're changing the direction of gnome it's you're just
helping improve the gnome experience right which is I think what was why some
people it's though some of the unity haters didn't like unity yeah is the
mixed resources thing oh we got a we got a fire fair unity 7 was way unity itself
was way better for not with a gnome for years like a gnome for three to four
years was utter garbage yeah all right well there you know what on that positive
note because that's you know that is that is a story for another time we could
you know we were thinking about it we should do like a history edition like a
gather around story version where we go back through the good and bad old days
of all of this but not for today that is a project for future Linux unplugged if
you'd like to participate in the conversation join us live on Tuesdays
over jblive.tv we do it at 2 p.m. Pacific you can get it converted your
local time at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar we also have the sub
reddit Linux unplug dot reddit comm the contact page at Jupiter broadcasting
comm slash contact the winner of the Dell sweepstakes in user air what is it
18 yep user air 18 go check that out great episode with mr. chase follow the
network at Jupiter signal Oh special outtakes were just posted for patrons
to over patreon comm slash Jupiter signal tons of stuff we'll see you right
back here next Tuesday
let's go pick a title before we get a mumble room thank you very much Simon
had a couple of I know he had several points you want to get in about Alex
cute so let me say this really quick go over to JB titles calm let's see if we
can't make our quickest title pick yet that way Dan and West can get started
ASAP Simon you wanted to jump in there real quick on a couple of things that
was yeah so alpha 2 is gonna be released on Thursday and both me and and bashful
robot we're doing the checklist tracking so so we're we're just wondering if
anybody can help test you you know if you're if you're installing boot to
Montana machine or if you're installing you know the other flavors are kaboom
to which they have I believe they have the latest plasma on this release you
have the little into the boom to next flavor which it's the experimental
image and you have a boon to budgie and we do chillin so if you install any of
those on your machine if you happen to do that within the next day or two it'd
be great if you could at least you know let us know that it works that sort of
thing because we're right now in a lane sort of like a testing phase for alpha
2 return of the distro hopper I think Chris switches to BSD we should save
that one in case that ever actually happened I doubt it but boy so many
people since I've mentioned this are like dude you should try out BSD and I'm
like uh-huh I think I would rather run slack where then run BSD maybe I'm not
sure BSD is like the greatest thing you should possibly want if you don't want
to run a desktop swap your hosting duties there Chris yeah I mean I could
fill in now yeah let's see scratch by a thumbnail keeping keep killing flash I
still think return of the distro hopper might be better so long and thanks for
all the flash yeah that's good too but I've already that was taken by chromium
you know I want to you know maybe one day somebody you know what
somebody actually pitched it to me as somebody actually suggested I should
switch to BSD so that way when I use Linux it's emulated and it's consistent
and so I'll have a more stable Linux experience because I'll be using an
emulated Linux experience under BSD there you go somebody around here made
that argument this neck of the woods and I that one really got me JB titles.com I
think we're gonna go with return of the distro hopper just in like that in the
order of expedience here flash dance you know I get a flash dance is good too I
gotta say wimpy made me happy and then he immediately made me sad what happened
because he's talked about moving Ubuntu mate to github yeah and he moved
everything to github except for the part that I hate about launchpad the bug
tracker oh yeah that bit of infrastructure you can you can raise
issues on github that's no problem we'll deal with issues in github okay that's
fine as well oh that's a good trackers are open but we need we also need the
one in launchpad to actually close project milestones and stuff yeah you're
welcome that's brilliant just just work on Chris explaining needs a stable
operating system for his production machine point him at the he'll walk in
with the green one and mate will be on every system