All right, well this has forced my hand.
I have no option at this point.
I'm going with the emergency pre-show topic.
Initiating emergency pre-show topic sequence.
Ladies and gentlemen, Microsoft is delighted to announce
Windows Server 2019 is going into full preview mode
and one of its headlining features is more Linux.
What?
Yeah, the improved and ready to go Windows subsystem
for Linux will be moved up to the server series
and they're introducing a new type of virtual machine
designed specifically to run Linux instances.
They'll also be shipping it with OpenSSH, Curl, TAR
and other common Unix and Linux commands
all pre-built into the shiny new Windows Server 2019.
Wow.
There you go, Wes.
I don't know how I feel about that.
So how long do you have to wait
before you can spin one of these bad boys up, Chris?
We'll just go grab the latest Ubuntu ISO
and get started now, Wes.
Oh!
Hmm, this is Linux Unplugged, episode 241.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged,
Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly Linux talk show
that's now recording in four individual stereo tracks.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Boy, do we have a heck of a show coming up today.
So not only do I have a couple of select moments from scale,
I went down and got 170 individual clips
and I'm playing one interview.
That is choice.
Hand-selected, hand-crafted,
my favorite moment from my trip to scale,
it's my first episode back.
But before we get there,
we have a huge batch of community news,
open source projects that are coming back,
big desktop releases,
some plumbing that's getting some major updates
and a cool trick to make Firefox, Firefox?
Firefox!
Do you have Firefox?
Yeah, I sure do.
It's all my facts.
I'm checking the service that checks Firefox facts.
I don't, everything is ruined.
I don't know.
Actually, no, it's a trick to get more performance
out of Firefox.
That's all.
I'm sorry.
It's nothing more than that.
Also, a pretty well-known company
is open sourcing all of the things.
They just announced it today and they're rolling it out.
A handy firewall utility for the Linux desktop,
a better way to stream Spotify on Linux,
and then we'll wrap it all up
with a couple of choice choice app picks.
That's solid, right?
Wow, I'm excited.
That's a lot of show.
Stop wasting our time.
Let's get to it, Chris, but there's a couple of things.
You're right.
First of all, we gotta say
time-appropriate greetings to that mumble room.
Hello, mumble!
What's up?
Hello.
Good afternoon.
Hello, it's good to be with you guys.
I missed you last week,
so thank you for hanging out with Noah and Wes
while they did the show
and thank you to Noah for hosting.
No kidding.
Of course, Ask Noah is coming up in just a little bit.
But did you see this story
that we're gonna start with this week?
I mean, it just had to start with this story.
LG has announced that they're re-open sourcing webOS.
Let's go back in time a little bit.
You remember this HP acquired Palm in 2010,
and then there was this whole webOS
on the touchpad thing that was short-lived,
and then around 2012 is when HP announced
that they would publish the webOS source code
as open webOS.
webOS was then acquired a little bit later on
by LG Electronics,
where they've actually been using it
for at least a few years now
on smartphone TVs, IoT devices,
and other LG devices.
I actually saw it, I think, on like a CES fridge.
And LG has announced that they're gonna work
in cooperation with South Korean's government agency
that's involved with technology
to make webOS a sustainable open platform
that is available for an open connectivity architecture.
They're looking to commercialize it as an open source
platform.
This is part of LG's announcement this morning.
And it's up, it's up on GitHub,
and I think it's sort of a semi-quasi-Android competitor.
It's part of this play to just have a company
offering a solution that isn't US-based,
that isn't Google.
Right, that seems like the main thing.
Otherwise, it's all still very veiled and enterprise-y.
It doesn't seem really like,
it's good that they're open sourced,
that part is great, but it doesn't feel like
it's really, you know, there's not a great README,
there's a whole bunch of components.
Really, it's not something we would use,
but maybe you're right, like there'll be some vendors
that think, okay.
Yeah, it just won't die.
It just won't go, and great, you know what?
God bless it, I think that's wonderful.
Good on them.
Can't kill Linux.
Just keep going.
And you know, we all have said,
I mean, it's cliche to say,
ah, webOS is one of the good ones.
But it's, maybe this bears that out,
because it just simply won't go away.
And I tried to get one of those touchpads.
I tried to do this whole thing.
It was a total waste of money.
But I have heard that their implementation on LG TVs
is one of the better smart TV OSes out there.
It is interesting going and looking through here,
like PulseAudio integrations,
Wayland extensions for webOS.
Yeah, yeah, isn't that something?
WebOS won't die, Wes.
It just won't die.
GNOME 3.28, also another big news item this week,
incorporating 25,000 changes.
Don't know how many of those are translations,
but a lot of changes.
And 838 contributions, or individual contributors,
make up the 3.28 release.
And it's got a couple of features that I'm a huge fan of.
First feature, it seems simple,
but if you think about it,
it's actually gonna make working day-to-day really fast.
The version of files in GNOME 3.28
now has a starred feature, where you can star files.
And then on the left-hand places area, you go to starred,
and it's just the files that you've starred.
This is great, because they've taken away desktop icons,
so it sort of comes at just the right time,
where you still have a kind of a workflow
for quick access to files,
and then when you're done with them,
you just pop that star off.
But that's not the big feature.
The one that I really like to see,
and I can't wait to see where they're gonna go next,
is Boxes, the VM front-end
that is one of my favorites on Linux,
now has the ability, using the new Box Assistant,
to download ISOs that you want right off the web.
So you wanna try out Tumbleweed to try out GNOME 3.28,
you just click the thing, it'll pull it down right there.
Wow, that's slick.
Yeah, Debian testing's in there,
NetBSD's in there, it's awesome.
Kind of makes it, changes the feel of it
from somewhat of a, not quite power tool,
but helper tool when you already understand
how the virtualization works
to something a little more user-friendly.
Totally, totally.
So that's the new Boxes feature,
and the Photos app has gotten some updates.
So new version of GNOME, I'm not running it,
I did try it for a bit.
You are, what are you running,
some sort of quasi-hybrid Plasma GNOME setup over there?
I do have both on here, yes I do.
Which one are you in right now?
Right now it's GNOME, I needed to test out on this side,
but normally it's been Plasma for the past couple weeks.
The reason why I even knew that
is because your machine's been running crazy hot all day
as the Evolution Data Server's been losing its crap, so.
Yes it has.
Woo!
Yeah, yeah, there's only a really, at this point in time,
that we're recording a couple of choice ways
to get GNOME 3.2.8.
Anybody in the Mumble Room by any chance
actually on the new version of GNOME, GNOME 3.2.8?
Like a Tumbleweed user in there by chance?
I didn't think so.
I bet you if Gabriel was in there, he'd say yes.
But I've been pretty happy with Plasma,
just got a whole batch of updates installed today.
So the Plasma adventure for me continues on
and I'm pretty happy with it.
Levi too, Levi the dog is pretty happy with it.
There's also a feature in GNOME 3.2.8 that Levi really likes.
It's support for Thunderbolt 3 security models.
And this is the accumulation of work
that's been done by Red Hat now for quite a while.
I first saw Joey over at OMG Ubuntu report about it
on December 14th, 2017.
And it was a project called Bolt.
And what it does is it adds some security protections
around Thunderbolt devices.
So unlike USB, Thunderbolt 3 allows a wide access
to devices on your memory bus, on your PCI bus,
just like Firewire did.
So it's speculated that you could hook up
a malicious Thunderbolt device.
It actually, I don't know if it's been proven
with Thunderbolt.
I know it has with Firewire.
But in theory, because it's the same essential technologies
the way it's on the PCI bus, you, as you know,
probably could hook up a device to Thunderbolt
and you could read what's on the PCI bus lane,
the PCI lanes, which is contents of memory,
the things that are being sent to the CPU.
It's like you're an IO port right on the PCI bus.
And so to mitigate against malicious uses of this,
there are Thunderbolt 3 security levels,
which has been supported at the kernel level
for quite a while.
But as you're probably guessing right now,
hasn't been implemented in user space.
This is where Red Hat's project Bolt stepped up.
Their developers were working on this project Bolt
to clearly handle Thunderbolt security levels
at the Linux desktop while keeping it user-friendly.
So what they've essentially done here
is they've provided a D-Bus API to list
all of the Thunderbolt devices, enroll them,
which means authorize and then store
which ones have been authorized in a local database,
and then forget them when they've been removed,
so that way there's not like an error message all the time,
and emit an alert to the user if a new device
has been connected or when that device
has been removed as well.
And during the enrollment, devices can be set
to automatically be authorized as soon as they're connected.
And so there needed to be a way to communicate this
that was at least somewhat agnostic, so they used D-Bus.
And now with GNOME 3.2.8, they've built in the front end
to display all this information to the end user.
So in GNOME 3.2.8, you'll click down on your status menu
and you'll actually see a Bolt message.
It'll say something like scanning peripheral,
and you'll see peripheral secure.
You'll see messages now in the status menu
when you hook up Thunderbolt 3 devices,
and that's because of this work to create this D-Bus API.
And this is more and more important now,
the devices like laptops have these USB-C ports,
which are also Thunderbolt devices,
so it's a little gray now to the end user
what they're actually plugging in.
Yeah, this seems like a surprising case
where a Linux desktop is actually
kind of ahead of the curve.
These devices are only now sort of picking up steam,
so it's great that we'll have this at least in one desktop
integrated right away.
Yep, yep, yep, I agree.
And that means it's gonna land in the next version
of Fedora, and it's already in Tumbleweed,
and it means it's gonna be in Ubuntu 18.04.
Wow.
So that takes care of a large,
low-hanging amount of GNOME fruit.
So pretty happy to see that.
And it's an example of kind of a behind-the-scenes project
that Red Hat sort of is famously known
for working on on the desktop,
even though they don't make a ton of money on the desktop.
You know what I mean?
This Bolt stuff and baking into GNOME
is specifically to benefit the desktop.
Right, I wonder, I mean, is that just enough?
There's enough people at Red Hat
who use GNOME on the desktop?
And I mean, if you're using USB
or Thunderbolt 3 peripherals on your work laptop,
you probably want them to be secure.
Or it's possible that multibillion-dollar corporations
play super long games,
and maybe they are seeding a garden
that they hope in another five years or so
is gonna bear a kind of fruit
that they can package up and start selling.
I like that idea. Possibly, who knows?
I mean, you just look at some of the stuff like Bolt,
which is a significant development,
and PipeWire, which you guys talked about again last week,
which is a significant amount of development,
and again, specifically for the desktop.
Perhaps all these people at Red Hat,
and maybe this is the case, actually,
perhaps they're all doing it on their free time.
Perhaps it's not Red Hat-financed.
I don't know, maybe somebody involved could let me know.
But it leaves us on the outside scratching our heads,
going, well, why is this company
that doesn't generate revenue from the desktop
expending quite a bit of development time?
Right, I mean, obviously we're happy
about a lot of these things,
but it does make you wonder, how sustainable is it?
Will it keep happening? I hope so.
It must be sustainable because they're doing more of it.
It feels like it's not declining, it's increasing.
So I would really like, where is it all going?
Do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do, do.
Geek Dad signing off right there in the chat room.
So we're back on the IRC for this show.
Yes, we are.
And I met Geek Dad, I hope he doesn't mind
me sharing his story a little bit,
but he gets to come to scale, he's a full-time dad,
and he's one of those dads that works really hard at it,
and he gets to come out to go to scale once a year,
and he's been going for quite a while.
And he was pretty fired up, he tracked me on the way down.
We were gonna try to meet up,
but I was driving like a maniac, so it didn't work out.
But when we got to scale, he created the Telegram group,
got everybody organized, he went over
and made the reservations at the Brazilian Meat restaurant
for our nice evening meetup.
I mean, just a super great guy.
And so, yeah, that's Geek Dad going on there.
He's gotta go pick up the kiddos.
So if you wanna join us live, we do this show on Tuesdays,
go to jblive.tv on a Tuesday, and you can get
the specific time at jupitabroadcasting.com
slash calendar, whoop, whoop.
I got my squeaky.
We gotta name the chair.
Chat room, name, bank suggest titles,
because I don't think you've given us a single title yet,
and name my chair.
What do we call it, the squeaky chair?
Yeah, this is where you really make the difference
in the show.
Because it really does, you know,
it makes a guest appearance in all the shows.
It's the third host, it is the third host.
And it's the best of them all, too.
I know, and it knows it.
So eloquent.
It knows it, too.
It makes us do things, but we'll leave it at that.
Let's take a moment and thank Ting
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Go to linux.ting.com, that's what my chair did,
and that's how my chair pays just what it uses
for mobile.
It's $6 a month for your individual line,
and then your usage on top of that.
So for example, if you're on Telegram
or another messaging platform,
you may not ever use or hardly use any text messages.
I think legitimately now.
The last text message I used was when Twitter
wanted to give me one of their crappy two-factors
and made me sign in and they sent me a text message first.
One text message last month.
Totally not worth paying for hundreds of text messages.
I didn't make a phone call last month.
I mean, I did make a couple of FaceTime calls,
and I did use Telegram and Slack calling,
but that's what I love about Ting,
is that's how I prefer to communicate,
so I pay for that stuff.
Now why?
That's how I can have three phones and pay 40 bucks a month.
It's $6 for the line, and then you just pay
for what you use, however many minutes,
messages, and megabytes.
Nationwide coverage, no contracts, Ting's got you covered.
They have CDMA and GSM, and if you wanna just pick up
a Ting SIM, it's $9.
If you go to linux.ting.com, they'll take $25 off a device,
and if you have a CDMA device or a GSM device
that is compatible, just check their BYOD page,
they'll give you $25 in service credit.
It's so nice, it's so nice.
My favorite combo when I'm running Android
is a Nexus or Pixel phone on the Ting network.
It's this completely clean, nobody in between me
and my phone, I get stock updates from Android,
Ting has zero incentive to get involved
in reflashing my phone with a Ting experience
so they have no reason to slow down the updates.
Yeah, but how will I get all my custom music
from the Ting music store, Chris?
Right, and of course, the Ting video streaming service
that has exclusive Ting content.
Oh man, I hate that stuff.
It's like you get to live in a parallel world
where it all just makes sense and you don't hate yourself.
Yeah, where they had to do it right.
That's what I love about it.
Linux.ting.com, support the show and get $25 in credit.
Linux.ting.com.
What do you guys say we take a moment
and my chair really wants to share a story
about the plumbing of our desktops.
GStreamer is the framework that really
just kept on chugging.
I don't know, I mean, I first started talking
about GStreamer back in the Lunduke days
of Linux Action Show.
I mean, it's been a really, really long time
that it came about and I have not seen
many multimedia frameworks that have stayed relevant
and continue to get additional usage.
So we just were talking about PipeWire.
PipeWire is plugging into GStreamer.
Like it's something that they're actively developing
for our Wayland future and GStreamer is a big part of that.
And so I thought, well, it's obviously
still a relevant technology.
Even as plasma users use it, what's coming up?
So the new version, a new major release came out this week
and it adds some pretty fundamental features
that, holy crap, is gonna make live streaming
JB shows a lot easier.
But first of all is WebRTC support.
Nice.
Uh-huh, baked in to fricking GStreamer
will be real time audio and video streaming
in and to and from web browsers.
The whole pipeline now, from your browser
down to your multimedia framework
is gonna be WebRTC aware.
I think that's a big deal.
That's huge.
Video for Linux support, including encoding support,
stable element names and faster device probing,
which means things like OBS may be able to bring
certain GStreamer devices in now.
I think that's gonna be really nice.
I'm skipping a few other ones, RTSP 2.0 support,
QuickTime Muxer support, a new pre-fill recording mode
that allows editors to import into Adobe Premiere
and Final Cut Pro QuickTime files
while they're still being written to,
which think about that.
Think about how fast those editors have to work
if they're editing files that are still being written to.
And then for you binary NVIDIA users,
a new plugin for hardware accelerated video decoding
using the NVIDIA API.
And back to live streaming,
Adaptive Dash Trick Play support,
which is also a big deal.
There's also some GStreamer C sharp bindings
that have made their way in there
and some Rust bindings that are now being baked in.
The chair approves.
It sure does.
This is fancy and I mean, there's like a lot,
I feel like a lot of people don't necessarily
use GStreamer directly unless they are doing
some of this plumbing or maybe involved
in video production, audio production work.
Yeah, you're watching a video or listening to an MP3,
you don't have any thought about the backend
of decoding that audio that's happening in GStreamer.
But it really is, it's got its fingers everywhere.
So these improvements can just be benefited,
anything that uses it and then uses the new release, boom.
And having a common API like this makes developing
good multimedia applications on the Linux desktop possible
because you have an API to develop against
and they're also releasing binaries for Android,
iOS, Mac 10 and Windows in the next few days.
Wow.
Yeah, it makes it an actual viable API to write against.
iOS binaries, fancy.
I wonder what that means.
I wonder if that means you bundle it in
with your application.
I would assume so, yeah.
So in the backend you're using GStreamer
and the user is none the wiser on an iPhone.
That's awesome.
We talked about Firefox 59 on Linux Action News this week.
There's a few things that I really like about it.
Their screenshot tool is actually getting pretty useful.
Let's you like mark it up now
and copy it right to the clipboard,
which is great for when you just wanna drop it in Telegram.
And they have some new blocking features,
but none of that matters, none of that matters
because it's not about making it much faster.
Windows and Mac users got something
that us Linux users didn't get this time around.
And I can't have that.
What?
So we gotta write that wrong.
We have got to write that wrong, right?
There is this cool new feature called
off main thread painting.
You can just tell by the name you want that.
I want it right now.
It's not on the main thread and it involves painting,
which probably means drawing my thing.
Slow.
Yeah.
And on Linux, unfortunately,
it has to be turned on manually.
You go to, what is it?
It's about colon config
and then search for layers.omtp.enabled
and set that to true,
which I did that about a day ago
and haven't really had any problems.
I don't know if I noticed any massive performance changes
either.
So you're not getting the Linux unplugged certified.
This is your hack to make kind of thing.
This is just, you've been warned.
You may or may not want to turn it on,
but I seem to feel like it is worth it
because so far I haven't had any noticeable downsides
and there is documented benchmarks that show
it is significantly faster
when you draw the webpage off the main thread.
It leaves the UI more responsive and other things like that.
So it seems like a no-brainer.
My chair approves.
I think Levi approves.
I think he approves, yeah.
We have a special in guest dog this week
who has made Wes his friend.
Levi just decided this week that this was the episode
he wants to sit in Wes's lap.
And Wes thought he had a choice in the matter.
I assumed I did, but nope.
Nope, I am just a chair today.
Studio dog.
Levi is actually the co-host.
Yeah.
You know, he missed you.
Oh, I missed him too.
You know, we were in California and he missed you.
So there's a company that I've bumped into a few times
and you hear about them every now and then
when it comes to funding.
It's Private Internet Access.
And they've been sponsoring several open source projects.
And of course they run Linux for their VPN infrastructure.
And they're self-labeled longtime supporters
of free and open source software.
Well today, they've started the process
of open sourcing their software.
And over the next six months,
they're gonna release all of the code
for their client-side applications,
as well as libraries and extensions as open source.
They go on to say they're extremely grateful
to the free and open source software community
for creating the foundations of the internet as we know it.
And while we may be late to the party,
we are looking forward to furthering our work
with a movement that aligns with our own passions
on our own personal and professional levels.
That resonates with me, actually.
Absolutely.
I feel a lot of the same feels there.
They say we believe that the shift to open source
is a right move for a privacy-focused business.
Completely agree with that.
And recognize that code transparency is key.
We appreciate that our code may not be perfect,
coming at it with a little bit of a humble attitude.
And we hope that the wider FOSS community
will get involved, provide feedback,
feature requests, bug fixes,
and generally help provide a greater service
to the wider privacy movement.
Today, we're opening up the first of many repositories,
the Chrome extension that allows our users
to access our network of proxies from their web browser.
The Chrome extension also boasts
additional privacy and security features,
such as disabling your microphone and camera,
blocking flash and IP discovery through WebRTC,
and it also can automatically block ads.
Fancy.
So they're opening that up.
They also have a private internet access chat room
on Freenode, if you want to go to chat.freenode.net
and go into private internet access for there.
And they say, yeah, our long-term goal
is to release all of our code into the open.
That's fantastic.
I mean, especially as a company that sells a service
that's really just backend infrastructure to run VPNs,
it makes complete sense to be able to do this.
And so, of course their code's not perfect.
It's always just been proprietary before.
This is fantastic.
And I'm sure it will get them more open source
advocates and users.
I'm definitely gonna take another look.
JJ, you've looked at private internet access before.
I've heard about it on various podcasts and stuff.
My question would be, how would this spec up
versus ProtonVPN?
I don't know.
I was thinking about, I wonder how it compares to AirVPN,
which has been my VPN provider of choice for quite a while
now, for a couple of years, which I was able to sign up
anonymously using Bitcoin.
And I've never provided them with a username or location.
And they have a ton of servers to choose from.
And they will generate open VPN profiles and all those things
that I really like.
But they're not open source.
And I kind of think that that really
is sort of a nice differentiator.
And they're smart to identify that.
It's very savvy to identify that as a differentiator
for their market.
And Duck Who in the chat room says
he just subscribed yesterday.
Either way, it's a good move.
It's smart of them.
Wes and I in the, well, before the hire,
it's our pre-pre-pre-show, I guess, technically,
because we weren't on the air yet.
But Wes and I were just recently kind of discussing WireGuard,
going back to Tink VPNs.
What do we want to do?
We both kind of have a need for a VPN service.
But we more like want to bridge lands together.
So we're both kind of on the fence.
I've been leaning more towards Tink myself.
What about you?
Where did you fall down on that?
I've actually still have Tink deployed pretty successfully,
bridging some lands and that.
Oh, you are still using it.
I am.
It's not as pervasive on my network as it once was.
So now it's kind of just using that and not
as much for the mesh functionality, which
is why, really, I was thinking about replacing it.
I've been thinking about giving WireGuard a more real try.
I've used it for some point-to-point stuff.
But I thought it'd be fun to try to get a larger installation.
Yeah.
Anybody in the Mumba room got an active VPN account
that they're pretty happy with, a service
that they like that works well with Linux?
And there's different needs, right?
Very much so.
There's rerouting to get around, say, region blocks.
And then there is just trying to bridge land.
So there's different uses, which I kind of have the former.
That's what mine is.
Right.
Yeah, sometimes you need to go on.
But you have the most experience with OpenVPN,
which is still working for me.
I have it set up on a VPS.
Yeah.
Yeah, I know a lot of people in the audience do that, too.
Levi prefers that.
Levi likes to just set it up on a DigitalOcean droplet
in the London data center.
And then he VPNs into that.
That's Levi the dog's trick.
Isn't that, Levi?
Yeah, that's a good point.
All right, Wes.
Well, speaking of VPSs, let's talk about this really quick.
DigitalOcean.
Oh.
Well, how perfect was that?
It's almost like I didn't actually plan that.
I wish we were that savvy.
I wish we planned the show to that level of a fine detail.
First, we'll talk about VPSs.
And then we'll get Mitt Free to say that he runs his own VPS.
And then we'll segue.
Nope.
It's just because these things are very useful.
That's why it comes up.
DigitalOcean.
It's simplicity at scale.
And they have a very special offer for limited time,
hot off the presses.
That's the presses when people make those noises.
Don't worry.
They're open source presses.
That's right.
Absolutely.
do.co slash unplugged.
If you have a new account and you go to that URL,
if you sign up for a new account and go to that URL,
you can get a limited time $100 credit for 60 days.
Oh, this is a great way to play around with DigitalOcean
because everything on DigitalOcean is wicked fast.
So you can go build a crazy, super powerful system
or build something and just get that $100
like for the full 60 days.
I mean, you could really just fine tune it.
They also have new flexible droplets, mix and match,
depending on what your application needs.
So yeah, you could also play around with that.
And I go to this all the time.
Like when I want to experiment with something,
what I love about DigitalOcean is
I'm able to think about who is the audience?
Is it me?
Is it the audience themselves?
Is it somebody in an area where I could spin up
the server in their location?
That's what I love.
Then there's this ability to transfer ownership.
So after I've created it, I can give it off to somebody.
We use that between Noah and I all the freaking time.
It's really useful, especially when we just
spin up infrastructure for an on-location gig.
We use it for one weekend.
And he has the image.
You can send it over here.
It's a super powerful system.
And they have team accounts.
So you have all of this great functionality.
And they manage to deliver it all in a really easy
to use dashboard.
It's super straightforward for pros or beginners.
A documented API.
And then SSDs for everything.
40 gigabit connections coming into the hypervisors.
Eight data centers all over the world.
And for a limited time, a $100 credit
when you go to dio.co slash unplugged.
I just waved the paper around, basically saying,
enough said right there.
Enough said right there.
I'll mention this, because this is boss level stuff.
You may have heard of Cloudflare.
You may have heard of NGINX.
And there's a possibility, a remote chance
you've heard of Ubuntu.
What about putting all those things together?
They have a guide on how to host a website using Cloudflare
and NGINX on Ubuntu 16.04.
So Cloudflare is a service that sits
between the visitor and the website.
And it's a CDN, as well as DDoS mitigation.
It's also a great way to do SSL acceleration
if you have a whole bunch of domains
and you want to put an SSL cert in front of all of it.
It's a really handy service.
NGINX is a very popular web server
for a lot of good reasons.
You combine all that stuff together,
and they've got an awesome guide on how to do it.
They've got really good stuff over there, dio.co slash
unplugged.
They also do a great job of supporting open source projects.
Yeah, they do.
Boom.
In fact, if I could give them any recommendations,
it would be maybe promote that a little more.
I know they do it just because they want to give back.
But there is some entire projects
where their entire infrastructure runs on D.O.
And they don't pay a cent, and it's pretty cool.
So are you familiar with the application for Mac OS
called Little Snitch?
Oh, yeah.
I think I've seen some people using that.
Yeah.
It's a handy little application that runs in the background,
and it creates an outbound firewall.
And it then gives the user some kind of notification,
either through the native notification system
or a custom notification dialogue,
that X, Y, Z application, Chrome,
is trying to connect outbound on this port to this address.
Do you want to allow it?
And one of the things that's interesting
is, say, you have software that checks
into some sort of remote server every time you launch it.
You will discover it very quickly with applications
like Little Snitch, and you'll discover, oh,
every time I run Lightworks, it's checking in
with edit share servers, for better or for worse.
But it's nice to know it's happening.
And you can also make the decision
to allow it or block it with Little Snitch.
And I've probably gotten, over the years,
a handful of questions.
Hey, is there anything like that for GNU slash Linux?
Anybody got something like that?
Because I would love to have something
like that for GNU slash Linux.
And I always say, get it out of here.
Get it out of here.
Right.
You'll have to roll it yourself, get some IP tables,
commands, and a whole bunch of scripting.
Yeah, yeah.
But you know what?
We have an app pick for you this week.
People have been saying, Chris, more app picks.
Missed the app picks from Linux Action Show.
Well, guess what?
We've been slipping them in here.
We just haven't been calling them app picks.
But this week, we got two of them for you.
And the first one is called OpenSnitch.
OpenSnitch is a GNU slash Linux port of the Little Snitch
application firewall.
And just like its Mac cousin, it gives you
a graphical notification saying, hey,
Telnet is trying to connect out on ports blah, blah, blah
to destination IP blah, blah, blah.
Would you like to block this temporarily?
Would you like to block this forever?
Would you like to allow it?
And the thing that's wonderful about this
is you can just run it for short periods of time
and get an idea of what your system is doing.
And it's incredibly insightful.
It, in my personal opinion, gets really obnoxious
after a while because everything is going outbound these days.
When Little Snitch was first conceived,
not nearly as many things connected out to the internet.
But it's still very useful.
It's called OpenSnitch, OpenSnitch.io.
And you're going to have to build it
if you're on one of the more common distros except for Arch.
Arch, there is an AUR entry.
Surprise, surprise.
But we're not talking anything major.
They have the commands you can run to sudo apt install or DNF
install the dependencies.
And then it's really just a Python setup install.
It's really not a big deal.
So it's not like you're going to be spending all day getting
the software built. And it is in the AUR
if you want to just install OpenSnitch dash git.
Anyways, OpenSnitch.d gets installed.
And then there's a cute front end that talks to OpenSnitch.d.
And then there's like a rule process.
And it's kind of a nice system.
It's an application level firewall,
meaning it works while it's running.
And it will detect and alert the user for every single outgoing
connection that gets created, which is very nice.
It can be extremely effective to detect and block
unwanted connections, which is also really helpful when you're
just in certain situations and scenarios.
Maybe you're on a certain unknown network.
Right, not trusted. Or you're just trying
to evaluate some new software.
And it's using underlying good standard Linux firewall stuff,
like AP tables extensions or NFs or whatever
you have on your system.
It's not like it's some crazy homebrew firewall.
Right, yeah, exactly.
It's just using the stuff in the Linux kernel.
And once a connection is detected,
the software relies on ftrace kernel extensions
to track which PID is causing the connection.
So it can actually tell you which particular process
on your Linux box is trying to make that outbound connection.
Nice.
Which is really great when something comes like,
I didn't even know that was running in the background.
So that's open snitch.
And we'll have a link to that in the show notes.
And then, Wes, you found this one.
And I figured, why would you want this?
But then I remembered that Spotify actually
has this feature where any Spotify client can control
any other Spotify client on your account.
And that's when this next app pick really clicked for me.
It's Spotify D.
An open source Spotify client that runs as a Unix demon.
So just like regular Spotify, it's headless freaking Spotify.
It streams music, just like the official client.
But it's lightweight.
Doesn't have that whole web UI wrapper around it.
It supports the Spotify Connect protocol,
which makes it just show up as any other Spotify
device that you can control.
The only downside is it does require a Spotify premium
account, which I happen to have because we use it
in the family quite a bit.
I'm not a proud Spotify user.
I actually hem and haw a little bit about putting this here
because I know a lot of people are like, Spotify?
You know what I like about Spotify, though?
I always tell myself, they're streaming
the music using Augworbus.
So at least you can play it on Linux.
And we're in kind of an awkward situation, right?
We talk about Slack.
We talk about other things.
As much as we love and want to support open source software,
we all get in our lives done.
And sometimes that means running whatever
you happen to already have.
Or maybe you're sharing an account with your spouse
or whatever else.
I mean, the thing is not only do we
have shared playlists, which is great,
but I just don't care enough about music.
Like when I first got a computer and CDs were still a thing,
I curated a collection.
And I was really OCD about all of my tag information.
And I would rip complete albums and make sure all of the stuff
and I'd run it through like, Music Brains Picard
and all that kind of stuff to try to make it.
Yeah, and then a couple of machine migrations,
everything gets ruined.
Or I'd try out, I'd install the new version of Rhythmbox,
and it blanked out all of my ID3 tags one time.
And I'm like, well, I'm never going to do that again.
And I just sort of had to just divorce myself
from caring about my music collection.
And now I just embrace the streaming service.
And honestly, if Spotify went out of business tomorrow,
I would give zero shits.
I would just sign up for something else.
A different one.
So it's with that kind of pragmatist mindset
that I use Spotify.
And so when you come at me with an open source Spotify
headless client that I could potentially
run here in the studio, I'm all about it.
I think this is great.
Yeah, especially if you already have like a media center
machine that's hooked up to a sound system or otherwise,
this would be perfect.
Totally.
Yeah, that's great.
It does require the also packages get installed,
which then talks to Pulse.
But that's the typical shit show of Linux audio,
not too surprising there.
It also supports D-Bus, which means
it can be controlled by some generic media playback
controllers like Player CTL or your desktop environments
that have like the playback controls in the volume slider,
like modern desktops, still can control this sucker too.
So you don't really need the Spotify.
Wow.
See, this is awesome.
So this might be just the way I get Spotify from now on.
And you may want to as well.
You can find a link to that in the show notes.
Yeah, that's true.
Vera Tundis says in the chat room,
she says, but Chris, that's what media servers are for, like MB.
So I got an excuse for that too.
I got all in on Sub Zero, I think it was, or Subsonic.
Subsonic, yeah.
And there was a whole bunch of shenanigans
about them going commercial.
And the project had a bunch of bad blood.
And I paid for it on two separate occasions
and got screwed.
And so it's not a good enough reason, but I just gave up.
I still manage my video collection
like I used to manage my TV, or my music collection.
I still manage my TV and my movies like that.
I gave up on the music a long time ago.
It's just a shame.
It's especially hard with discovery and other things too.
And the streaming services just make it so simple.
Yeah, yeah.
That's just, you sit down, especially with Android TV
and stuff like that.
I know.
Anybody in the Mumble Room, the exact opposite,
where you're super meticulous about your music library,
you only listen to local audio.
Angela's like that.
Angela only listens to local.
Is that right?
No streaming.
She's just local audio.
She still sings it via the wire to her phone.
Yeah, it's impressive, normally.
What's that, Mini?
I started to back up my whole CD collection, which
is about 400 or 500 CDs.
I have to flag a copy and then normally have 192 OGD copies
for my phone and for my router.
So when I'm at home, I stream via router.
So that works great.
What client are you using on Android to play Hogs?
On Android, I don't have an Android phone.
I use the Yola Sailfish phone.
So there is no problem.
OK, OK, all right.
Nice.
Nice answer, dude.
Yeah.
Shut Chris up right there.
And I knew that too, when I think about it.
I knew it.
I never had that question.
Is that true?
Does Android don't have Android in OGD?
No, I mean, there's like VLC and whatnot.
That should be default now.
I don't know.
The open source music media player, I don't think,
is even the default anymore.
But I have a dozen different apps that will play Hogs.
But I don't like any of them enough
to listen to all my music that way.
Isn't it interesting that it's hard to find
a really good music player?
I mean, there are thousands for Linux boxes,
but a really good one?
I found Lollipop for GDK Gno, which is cool.
CMOS on the terminal is great.
But otherwise, it's really hard to find
really cool, good music players.
I mean, most of us are satisfied with the results of VLC,
I guess.
But what if you have a large collection?
See, that's one of the other reasons I end up using Spotify,
is because it's also a jukebox, like of the old style jukebox.
You know, you guys all know Arm Rock.
Just like after years, just after years,
just released a new version recently.
I didn't, I missed that.
Yeah, I don't know if it's a beta or what, but yeah.
So it's still a thing.
But I think with SSDs too, and a lot of my main machines
are laptops these days, I just don't
have a lot of room for gigabytes and gigabytes of music.
If I had unlimited budget, unlimited time,
I would prefer to have everything in Flax.
And I would prefer to have it all local.
Anyway, Spotify D, we'll have a link up on the show notes.
You know, if you want to give us an app, or a story,
or a project that you think we should know about,
hit us up on the subreddit.
It's still going, linuxunplugged.reddit.com,
linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
And in the next, I'm not sure what the scheduling is,
but it's very soon there's going to be back end
changes for the RSS feeds and stuff like that
coming to this show, because we're doing a whole project.
We've got a whole project coming up.
And this show is going to be rolled up into all of that.
I don't think you'll have to do anything.
I guess the one thing I would say is if, by accident,
when we forward the RSS feed, if we trigger an extra download
or something like that, I apologize.
We're sorry.
Here's what I do expect to have happen.
This is why I'm giving you the heads up.
There will be a cleaning of the feeds
simply because we're switching feed services.
That's one of the things we're doing,
is we're migrating off a feed burner, which
is sort of like this zombie Google service.
And we're moving to a small shop that
is dedicated to hosting podcast RSS feeds called FeedPress.
And we're going to have a cool new URLs, too.
So check this out.
If you go to, they're not all set up,
but this one is feed.jupiter.zone
slash allshows.
That is the allshows RSS feed.
So we're going to have a new domain for all of our feeds,
feed.jupiter.zone and then slash feed name.
So it'll be like allshows, lup, super easy stuff.
And the issue with that is that migration process
is not super clean.
I can forward, I can do like a redirect.
I can redirect people to the new feed,
but I can't import the old items.
Incompatible.
So if you are an archivist, you got a few days, maybe,
to try to pull everything down in the feed.
That's your warning, because it'll be a reset clean feed,
then they'll be updated from there,
but there's going to be a clean break when
we move to the new feed service.
You won't have to resub, because I'll do a redirect at the URL
level, but the actual items in the RSS feed will be reset.
And that also will prevent triggering redownloads, too.
So it's also a good thing.
So yeah, that's your public.
But be prepared for changes.
Yeah, be prepared.
Also, just keep an eye out for that kind of stuff.
Just a general Linux Unplugged service
announcement for your better podcast experience.
Now, I did just get back from scale.
And like I said in the intro, I got a lot of clips, over 170,
and talked to a lot of people.
But I knew when I came back from scale this year
that I really wanted to just do the best job possible,
just giving you what you need to know about the event,
and not overdoing it with 15 interviews,
and multiple episodes, and all of that,
like not bogging down the show with it.
It's harder to do than it sounds like,
because there's so much going on at scale.
And so I got there on Thursday.
I got there Wednesday, but the scale starts Thursday,
and it goes till Sunday.
And there's stuff going on all day, every day.
And you're learning and meeting people every single day.
Plus, it's a multi-thousand dollar investment for us,
cost-wise, as a company, to go down there.
Noah's down there, and he's taking time off of AltaSpeed,
so it's a personal investment for him, too.
And so you have this drive to come back and just make
it all scale all the time.
Because we've spent a lot of energy and time in this.
But this trip was really the trip
where I internalized why I go to these things.
And it wasn't about the pressure of making a show out of it.
It was about going there, talking to people,
learning, getting insights from the audience,
figuring out new things to look into, meeting new companies.
That's why I went, not to come back
with all of these interviews about the latest, craziest
things that I saw on the expo floor.
But I did pick one.
I did pick one interview that I wanted to play for you guys,
because it's from someone who has been doing this
for quite a while.
He is one of the co-founders.
He's the Scale Conference chair.
Elon is a longtime member of this community.
And he works at Datadog.
He is, as he puts it, a recovering sys admin.
And he had some interesting things to say.
So I did pull that interview.
I sat down with him at the expo floor
while he was in the thick of things
and just did a brain dump with him.
And I wanted to play a little bit of that, a little bit
of the expo floor for you, just to sort of cap off
my trip to scale.
So before we get there, I want to thank Linux Academy
for sponsoring the show and making what we do possible
and for creating a platform to help Linux users learn more
about Linux.
It's a way to get access to advanced training tools
that increase your skills and encourage critical thinking
around everything related to Linux, a full-featured training
library with everything you need to know,
with full-time human beings that are available to help.
And one of my favorite features is real, hands-on labs
and exercises.
They deploy real environments, and then you
take scenario-based labs on them, hands-ons,
from anywheres at any times.
Hands-on scenario-based labs give you
experience on real environments that Linux Academy has
curated for you.
And that is huge for me because I genuinely learn by doing.
Yeah, sometimes you can't supplant that.
You can answer all the multiple choice questions you want,
but if you haven't been on that server.
And I can't test.
I can't test unless I've done it and I've seen it.
I cannot test.
There's no exam I'm passing.
And I say that having learned that the really hard and
expensive way a couple of times.
And that was just something I learned about myself.
And that's one of the things I really
appreciate about Linux Academy is it's built around that.
But even more importantly, it's built for your busy, busy life.
You can pick a course and set a time frame,
and it'll fit your schedule and your learning goals.
They have practice exams and quizzes
to help you prep for when you're going to go take that test.
And they have a community that's full of Jupyter broadcasting
that are forking, customizing, and randomizing study flash
cards to help you up your game.
And then they have study tools that you can download offline
and listen to.
So if you're like Eric and I and you're
in a bandwidth limited environment,
they can accommodate that too.
And if you're on the go, maybe you're in the tube
and you got some downtime while you're commuting,
they got iOS and Android apps as well.
It's pretty great.
In fact, you might say it's the best.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there, support the show, and sign up
for a free seven day trial.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Dooblaloo, dooblaloo, dooblaloo.
So yeah, let's go to scale.
You want to go back to California about a week ago?
Let's teleport, get right there.
Much faster than going by RV, right?
Can we still take Levi?
We're definitely taking Levi.
You have to take Levi.
He's the tour guide.
There was something that Scale has done,
and they really refined it this year.
It's not their first crack at it.
But if you're going to scale, I think
it's one of the things you might really like
is they have these track sessions.
So Ubicon, for example, was a track.
It's all Ubuntu all the time.
And then there was several other tracks.
Like one of the more popular ones was the Postgres track
for people that just wanted to implement and deploy Postgres
in their day-to-day work lives.
And so the goal here with partitioning
is sort of without having to do a lot of changes,
you can implement this within Postgres on the same system,
and then get a lot of benefits.
One of the tracks that was going on all day yesterday
and appears to be going on all day today
is people that are trying to get work done with PostSQL,
Postgres.
And so this one is like a performance track.
And this room, room 106, will be about Postgres all day long.
The other one that really blew my mind,
Noah and I specifically wanted to go out and see
how deep can we go into the under-workings of Linux.
And so we set out to find the USB subsystems track.
So the question is, is there a one-to-one core session?
That's like a hardcore session in there.
People are following along on their laptops with the slides.
It's like down to details.
Yeah, it's, yeah.
Like, I started to get a little overwhelmed
within a couple of minutes.
But it's fascinating, too, like the kind of stuff
they have to worry about.
It's a room full of people trying
to figure out how to make accessories on Linux.
And I'm glad there's people doing that so that people
like you and me don't have to.
No kidding.
And you heard in the background, there's babies there.
There's families there.
There's even dogs there.
They said, you know, we could probably get Levi a pass.
That's amazing.
It really was pretty great.
But Levi had other things to do that day.
And you get the sense that you could go there and really
sort of walk away with knowledge to ship something.
Like, that USB subsystem one really went deep into like,
here's how you troubleshoot when you're
trying to build a product and you need it to identify itself
to the Linux subsystem.
Like, here's some of the things you can look into
if this isn't working for you.
Like, really like stuff you walk away with.
Actual practical tips that you're going to need.
Quote unquote, actionable items, if you will.
But of course, one of my favorite things
of any conference we ever go to, because the energy's always
high and people always have their best foot forward,
is the Expo Hall.
And Noah and I are walking around with our media badges.
So we got to go in a little early.
You can hear them vacuuming the carpet now.
They're still getting everything ready.
We were able to sneak in as media a little early
before the crowds in here.
And it's still this noisy in here.
Yeah.
Yeah, there's the Ubuntu booth next to Chef.
Howdy, howdy.
Now, this is more my speed.
We got a Videoland booth, Datadog.
I've been wanting to talk to Datadog.
This is nice.
The Expo Hall at scale is always really fantastic.
And it looks like they've spread it back out again a little bit
from what it was last year.
There's Fedora.
Hey, Fedora.
Fedora's looking good.
Fedora has a booth.
Adobe has a booth.
Ubuntu has a booth.
Yeah, really nice.
Microsoft had a hell of a booth with Surface tablets there
and lights everywhere and nice chairs.
Git had a booth, like lots of folks have booths.
And then lots of companies that I didn't even recognize
had booths.
It's interesting how many of these company names
I don't even recognize.
I think a handful of these companies
did not exist two years ago at scale.
Oh, yeah?
I mean, do you recognize some of these, like TwitSlock,
Skilly Dab, Tindy?
I recognize GumGum.
GoBot, Uncoded.
I don't recognize these companies.
I cover this stuff every day and I don't recognize
these companies.
It's like they've just come up out of nowhere
based on some of the technology that's in Linux now.
Yeah, I think there's a lot of startup companies
and a lot of venture capitalist money that's coming around,
people trying to get off the ground.
Well, you just put it in a container
and you can get funded.
You know, we're joking about it, but that's kind of the reality
is that some of the recent advancements
that we've covered just as just topics of conversation
in this show are now fundamental building blocks
for entire businesses that are like getting VC funding
and have a business model.
And they're using namespaces in the Linux kernel, right?
And it's not to say they're not legitimate
because they are solving, in some cases,
real business needs.
It's just crazy walking around and seeing
all these companies that don't even recognize the name
because traditionally, going to these conferences
for many years now, I've been going to these things
even before JB when I was in high school, I started going.
And that was an unfortunate long time ago.
That was a while ago.
And back in the day, it was a much more limited spread.
You had some big names.
You had the people you expected to see.
Well, that's just it.
So that was 18, 19 years ago.
And through that time, really until just the last few years,
it was company names you already knew.
Every single company name you already knew.
Now it's a whole bunch of new companies
that are even possible.
They're like micro companies because of the technology
that they're based on.
So we were walking around the floor
and we bumped into Elon,
who is one of the co-chairs of Scale.
Elon Rubinovich.
So I'm the conference chair for Scale
and one of the co-founders.
And I had a lot of things to talk to him about.
We had a long-ranging conversation
from where he thinks Linux is going in 2018.
And I got the sense, he said something to me that struck me
and that's what led to my next question.
And he said, the core team of us here at Scale,
we take vacation at work so that way we can go to work
and work harder than we even work.
Right.
And I'm watching him run around
and I'm looking at his schedule
and in one hour from our conversation,
the Expo Hall opens up.
One hour immediately after that,
they need to be out there taking the wrap off of the food
that's in the middle of the Expo Hall.
One hour after that, he needs to make sure
that the event in the D room is so,
like he just has like all of this stuff he's doing.
Plus he was emailing back and forth
with all of these companies, including Jupiter Broadcasting
months before the event even kicks off,
which he's doing on his own personal time.
And he doesn't take a profit from any of this.
He doesn't make a buck off this thing.
I mean, he gets community stature
and he gets connections and networking.
But at the end of the day, he's doing it
because he wants to and he loves it.
Like that's very impressive.
I'm like, is it that?
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Like, so what is it?
What drives you?
Is this your contribution to open source instead of code?
So yeah, a lot of us are where we are in our careers
because of where open source,
because of how we were involved in open source
in the early days.
You know, my first time I needed Linux,
we needed to share a home internet connection.
And I was like, oh, somebody told me
about this IP tables thing and IP chains, sorry,
at the time and went to a local lug
and got help from some, made a bunch of friends
and they helped me at an install fest
to like getting started in open source and Linux, right?
And that was amazing.
And then over the years I thought, well, how do I,
you know, how do I give back?
That like really kicked off my career
and the career of a lot of folks here.
And so being involved in community activities like this
is one way of giving back.
So whether it's the kids track that we run on Saturdays
where we have folks from six all the way up to 18
giving talks about how they use Linux at open source
and start to get the next generation excited about STEM.
Or it's the install, like we have a Linux new user,
Linux training that's a full day session
where you come in at the start of the day with a,
basically it's a more organized install fest
and we take you through, get your systems installed,
train you all the way up,
or even just the regular talks that we have.
Like all of these are ways that people can get
trained up on Linux and open source
and further their own career.
We have a very popular jobs board and jobs bop
and you look around the room and most of the companies
are recruiting in some way or another.
So yeah, I think this is definitely a way to give back.
I would say, I would also say that participation
in open source is done, whether it's with scale
or with other things has been very, very kind to me.
Maybe I don't, you know, I don't take a salary
from anything we do around scale or Texas Linux Fest
or the other groups I'm involved with.
But I would say, I don't think I would have,
I've had any of my last two jobs if it wasn't for,
you know, having done, having built the skills
and the connections that I get to make
as part of running something like this, so.
And they really do hustle.
That he mentioned in there really briefly,
the birds of a feather session.
These boffs are also something that has become
a more and more common element of these events.
I really started seeing them become a common element
in the BSD meetups.
The BSD community started doing these
and I saw it kind of quickly spread from there
to the Linux community and one of the places I saw it
actually come from BSD to the Linux community
was at Linux Fest Northwest, surprisingly enough.
And now almost all of these events
are doing these boff sessions.
And it's, the idea is, I'll give you an example.
So you might know Randall Schwartz from Floss Weekly
on the Twit network.
He's there and he and I were chatting
and we were talking about what else but Perl and Dart.
And so we started going back and forth about Perl and Dart
and he started saying, yeah, you know what I'm doing
is I'm doing a birds of feather session on Dart.
So if you want to learn more, just come here
and we're just other people that are working on Dart.
We're just getting together and we're just hanging out
and talking about Dart.
And they sit around for two hours and they build stuff
and they fix stuff and they debate stuff
and these are becoming more and more common.
And they're kind of a cool unplanned aspect
that's sort of organically grown up in these conferences
that don't require like somebody to put together
a whole stack of presentations and propose a letter
where they recommend what they want to talk,
where they suggest what they want to talk about
and get accepted.
It's just simple.
Low maintenance, easy going.
And you probably find people who are actually
just as passionate.
There's so much to like at these conferences.
You can find zero in on some people
who are excited about what you are.
Yeah, so it was nice to go.
I'm glad we went.
It also makes me look forward to Linux Fest Northwest
where we'll be there.
We're thinking about maybe trying to do a live show
from there.
We're kind of getting all that kind of worked out still.
But yeah, I really had a great time
and it did seem like they were definitely
trying to make a contribution back to open source
doing that.
So many things, so many events to go to every year.
And I understand not everybody can go
and not everybody has an excuse to go like I do.
But if you can make it, it will sort of change,
it'll change you a little bit.
It really reifies what the community is.
We spend so much time on all these open source apps
around IRC and all of that's awesome.
But seeing people face to face
and getting the sense of just how excited they are
and how nice everyone is, it's totally different.
Yeah, yeah.
Putting a face to the disembodied voice.
There we go.
Yeah, it is.
You know, it is like you get to check in with people.
Like, you know, William's often in the mumble room
and William was there.
So we got to hang out with William.
He got to hang out with Levi.
William got to hang out with Levi as well.
That's awesome.
Yeah, he was Levi approved as a matter of fact.
So that's always pretty good, you know,
put names to faces like Geek Dad in the chat room.
And yeah, and it just is, it's a rare chance
to get to talk to a bunch of like-minded folks
about stuff that everybody's really excited about.
And you get to do it without the internet drama
or the internet angst that all conversations
seem to have now online.
Now all of that's gone when you meet somebody in person.
You know, like my favorite story I've shared it before
is Ryan who, tech helper, he's known as tech helper.
And he was not my biggest fan initially.
And we met up in person and we became friends.
And two years ago, he let me borrow his Cadillac
when we went to scale.
So that way I had transportation
because I brought Lady Joops
and I had to park it away from the conference.
And this year, just without even asking him,
because I was just crazy busy.
I was doing all this stuff without even saying a word.
The guy sends me a telegram out of the blue and says,
hey, would you like to borrow my car again?
That's wild.
And it's like, you know, go from somebody who's like,
yeah, kind of a troll to now like,
hey, would you like to borrow my car?
Because we meet in person.
And I guess I just, I can't put enough emphasis
on this one really kind of cliche point.
And that is meeting people in person
is completely, totally different than meeting them online.
Online, we have these two-dimensional personas
that we put out there.
And then we interact with these two-dimensional personas.
When I first started getting on the internet
and you had to dial up and connect to it,
you connected with a handle, a name,
a screen name or a nickname.
And so nothing had my name attached to it
and nothing had your name attached to it.
And so things just weren't quite as serious
because it wasn't coming from a real person
with their name and identity attached to it.
It was from some anonymous douchebag on the internet.
And so it didn't quite matter as much.
But now with social networking
and all these other platforms,
we're all using our real names.
We all have our real faces on there.
And so now it's Chris Fisher and Donald Trump.
It's like these real people
that are making these statements on these.
And so we take these statements so much more seriously.
But there's still these two-dimensional, low context,
low information statements that we interpret so much
and trigger our own emotional baggage.
And it creates this total hostile dialogue online.
And then you add in the total dumpster fuel fire
that is clickbait journalism and ad-based clicks
that just really make
for a horrible, horrible hostile discussion online.
And you just bypass all of that
when you meet up with people in person.
All that baggage is gone.
And it's just-
Wait, are you saying
you don't take seriously Captain Snorlax?
That's one person you always take seriously.
Okay, cool.
Says the guy with the handle called Rotten.
Or my nickname?
Yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
Although one person I always take quite seriously is Popey.
Hello, Popey.
Hello.
It's good to see you.
How are you?
Good, good.
We've missed you.
I missed you at scale, but I'm glad you're here.
Yeah, sorry I couldn't make that.
I may be hanging out with your better half soon though.
So that'll be good.
That'll be fun.
Yeah, I'm tracking his flight.
He's nearly landed.
He's gonna be there soon.
So that's not confidential.
We can say that he's-
Yeah, yeah, sure.
Yeah, Wimpy's landing in Seattle
probably in the next few minutes, actually.
That's so exciting.
Yeah, yeah.
I don't think, he's gonna be too busy to come on the show,
but I'm gonna try to run down there
and buy him a beer at least, or 10,
because how often does Popey or Wimpy
actually make it to our area?
Well, it turns out more often than you'd expect.
Twice in the last month, weirdly.
Wow.
But, and that's probably just a limited time thing,
so I gotta take advantage of it while we can.
Yeah, well, Popey, you have anything to share
at the class before we get out of here today?
I was just about to wrap this thing up.
Michael Sunnell Rotten is a lovely person.
That's all I've got to share.
Okay, I agree.
Yeah. I agree.
Oh, hey, actually, Ubuntu Podcast is back.
Could share that, do a little plug skis.
Ubuntu Podcast returned and just had Will Cook on the show.
Yes, we did.
That's something.
We discussed the things that are happening for 1804,
some of the decisions that were made,
and some of the controversial things
that people have been talking about on the internet.
We would discuss that in episode two,
and turns out, episode three and four,
we just had Michael Sunnell on.
Oh.
Whoa.
See, it's a circle of plugs there.
A circle of podcasts.
Yeah, right?
Yeah.
Well, good, that's awesome.
I look forward to hearing that.
And the nice thing is, you know,
there's a pretty good chance then
when producer Michael goes on,
he's gonna have good audio.
So that's nice too.
I always appreciate that.
I typically do, yes.
Yeah, you do.
You do.
I don't have a soundboard with a ding in it,
but I would, if I did, I would.
There we go.
You just gotta get a bell.
There it is.
I'll just get you a bell.
I should just get you a bell.
Nothing beats the hard copy.
Yeah.
I do like having the physical bell right here,
and so do the kids.
It's a hit with the kids when they come into the studio.
They always gotta play with dad's bell.
Wait a minute.
All right, well, let's get out of here while we still can,
because I just think that just went in a bad direction.
You guys, thank you very much for being here.
We'd love to have you join us in the Mamba Room.
Go over to jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
for when we do this here show live,
because it's true, it's a live production.
It's one of the few, so why not get in while it's still live?
Yeah, savor it.
Yeah.
And you can get more Mumble information
if you go on irc.geekshed.net.
Do bang Mumble, and it'll give you the server information
so you can hang out in our virtual lug.
You can submit content ideas to linuxunplug.reddit.com,
and of course, go to jupiterbroadcasting.com slash contact,
and keep an eye out for those feed changes.
Maybe new things coming.
Lots happening.
And just a few more episodes of Tech Talk Today
for season one, techtalk.today,
and go get more Wes and Chris, techsnap.systems.
See you next week.
Bye.
And we'll see you next week.
Wimpy is currently traveling 536 miles per hour
with a Wi-Fi connection.
Isn't that amazing?
He's had a decent-ish connection this whole flight,
because I've seen him in Telegram the whole time.
So I know he's got at least some Wi-Fi.
What a time to live.
Yeah, it really is.
This is pretty great.
Look at this.
And I wonder how expensive that Wi-Fi is, too.
Look at this, you can retrace the whole flight.
Oh, that is neat.
This is great.
That is really cool.
There's a little bit where they estimated where the flight was,
where apparently Wimpy went offline for a bit.
And then he reconnects as he comes in over Canada.
Hey, how's my audio now?
Much better.
So what were you trying to tell us earlier?
Well, I was trying to tell you what I ended up doing,
because I have bookshelves full of CDs.
When I downsized to the trailer, I
had to put all of that in storage.
So I put it all in a tub, basically a tote.
But before I did, I ripped everything onto a one terabyte
hard drive, which is being straight from Plex.
Yeah, I was thinking about Plex.
So that's the direction I went, but I hardly ever use it
because I use Spotify all the time.
Sure.
Oh, that old story.
Oh, no, if there's a reason to repair all of your CDs
and stuff, it's legitimately to try
to get software to do gender recognition
and actually try to make some choices for you.
There's actually a piece of open source software,
which I've been using for you, and trying
to make it so that it can become a recommendation
system for new music.
So I'll let the bot go to YouTube.
Yeah, you know, I won't lie.
You've honed in on one of the things
that I do kind of use these services for
is to find me new music, because I don't really
put a very high priority on music.
I also am not actively discovering new music
like I used to.
And so the fact that these things have some kind
of algorithm to try to surface music is nice.
JBtitles.com.
Last FM does that pretty well.
Yeah, yeah.
So does Pandora.
If you start to put your music list on Last FM,
you normally get good recommendations.
You just have to squabble your music.
I wish it was back in a few.
Import a list or something.
That would be great, because I don't
like listening to the streaming services.
I'd rather have it on.
I'd rather have local media.
And then give me some suggestions off of this list
of artists.
Wouldn't it be great?
And here's the thing.
If you really enjoy listening to music
and really hate when you get interrupted,
at least keep some of them locally,
because there's always going to be that one moment where
you're going to be absolutely bored of not having local stuff.
If you'd like to have 30 minutes of no ads,
just watch this video.
Seriously.
It's a 30-second ad to get you to watch another ad.
The other thing about the streaming services
that's sort of like a sucky, secondary, first-world problem
is it's kind of like a shit show,
like how they all integrate with different devices
and like TV set-top boxes, lady tubes,
all these different things.
Some of them work with Spotify if you
use this particular incantation.
Some of them work with Google Music.
Some of them work with Pandora.
Some of them work with Amazon streaming music
if you use a different incantation.
It's really kind of all over the place.
It really is.
Yeah, right.
By the way, Chris, I'm not sure if you'll want this.
I can link it to the project I was talking
about, the general recognition project.
Sure, yeah.
Yeah, if that's a thing, I'd like to see it.
Put it in there if you don't mind, toss it in the IRC
so that other guys can see it, too.
By the way, related topic in regards to Linux,
well, Linux on mobile being Android at the moment,
what do you think Android P is going to be?
Well, it sounds like it's so far a UI overhaul, a lot
of small UI overhauls.
No, I mean the name.
Did you guys notice that all the UI elements
are basically Fuchsia OS?
Yes.
Yeah.
I thought that I had that same thought.
Oh, name?
Stratum.
What's something that P?
I bet it's going to be not a sweetie.
I think it's going to be like a healthy thing.
I think they're going to be the laziest thing ever.
Pancreas.
Because all of their stuff has been desserts or pastries.
It's just going to be pastry.
Oh, they're just going to call it Android pastry?
No, no, that's too generic.
That wouldn't be Google.
I think they're going to drop the sweets parfait.
Parfait is also really good.
I like parfait.
That's good.
I'm going to say pudding because I hope it's Android pudding.
I hope it's Android pudding.