Okay, I had a pre-show topic. I just thought since it's not directly Linux related, we
probably shouldn't do it in the main show, but I want to talk to you guys about it because
you got to wonder if there's going to be anything that changes for Linux. You have to hope not,
but everybody saw the news that Microsoft purchased Mojang for 2.5 billion and Notch
is on his way out the door already. And you know, you guys probably also saw because it
was grabbed in the last subreddit comments that Microsoft explicitly said they don't
have any plans to change Minecraft, to change where they deliver to Mac, PC, Xbox, PlayStation
and mobile. They didn't actually say Linux. Do you think I'm being paranoid?
Oh, it's definitely an elephant in the room.
They didn't thought about it.
I think that's the fuck Mark is going to write now.
But to be fair, I think Microsoft is trying to become what they were before, a software
company that means producing software for whatever it's selling.
So you think you think it would be silly for them to pull it up?
Yeah, I think so. Right. I hope so.
So the whole thing is if their goal and the only way to make what they're doing right
now totally Microsoft centric so that it can't run that on other operating systems would
be to actually undo what they've done that's good and what is to Java standard and to murder
it and do stupid things like instead of doing it from a canonical URL to something or canonical
connection to something, which is just assuming and going backwards from where you are and
then finding something else in the file system, they'd have to go and state some kind of awful
way to say, oh, look for the C drive.
So before we go like way down in the weeds, that's way down there.
Don't you think it's more likely that what would happen is Microsoft will continue to
deliver Minecraft as we know it today to all the places that Minecraft is shipped, but
then maybe in the future there could be like themed versions of Minecraft or specifically
Minecraft, I don't want to call them spin offs, but I can't think of a better term that
maybe would be exclusive to the Xbox platform or windows mobile first.
This is all about windows mobile.
Nothing else.
They need a great game for windows mobile.
They need the killer app for windows.
They need the number one seller on iOS.
And when, when like the kid goes into the phone shop with the parents and the parents
have got the money and they say, right, which phone do you want?
The question is, does it run Minecraft?
And you know, every kid in my kid's school, all the kids play Minecraft, all of them without
fail.
And when they go to like have a party over at someone's house, they sit there and pull
out their phones and do peer to peer playing Minecraft together.
I've seen the same thing.
And if you're the guy with the windows phone, you're like a loser.
You can't join in.
It's horrible peer pressure.
And it's the thing we teach our kids not to succumb to, but you know.
Yeah, I think it is.
So but how do you, it's okay.
So obviously outside of, I mean, do you really think they'd spend 2.5 Bill and buy something
that is so counter to the Microsoft culture, right?
Because Minecraft's all about how the community has embraced and extended it and built their
own servers.
It's a huge freaking Java app, right?
This is so counter to anything that is normally in the Microsoft realm of expertise.
So there's no way they're, they're doing all of this just to make a windows mobile port.
It has to be much bigger than that.
I mean, outside of even merchandising and things like that, I think, I think they've
got to make exclusives out of this property.
Well, it's like I've been saying, I think we're going to start seeing a new Microsoft.
I mean, this is the same.
I don't think it's new.
I think it's just the old Microsoft, the actual old Microsoft, the original one.
The original one was endorsing Apple like hell when it made sense for them.
They just grew too much and decided to take to their own hands.
Come on, they were planning to backstab them the entire time.
Yeah, I think so too.
I think, I mean, I see what your point is.
This would be a much more mature Microsoft, one that really is truly more interested in
just creating software for all platforms.
And maybe it'll be that.
Okay.
So let's, let's shift gears from this.
Doesn't this also kind of guarantee like more support's going to be going towards like mind
test and other open source Minecraft alternatives?
I hope so.
It could do, but it would, they would, they need to step up their game.
Yeah.
I mean, there's already other different like glowstone projects, all of this came out of
the big craft's bucket fiasco and it's already started and I think this has only improved
it and sped it up.
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, I think, I think like a Pope said, it's going to be, there's a long time to go.
And now if Microsoft does it right, they're going to have more money behind Minecraft.
Perhaps they could be, maybe they could make that even a better product even faster.
So there could be more competition for mind test to keep up with.
We'll see.
Stay tuned and find out.
Hopefully it doesn't mean anything bad for Linux users.
I don't think it will.
All right.
Yeah.
See, I didn't really think that was the main show topic, but I thought it was worth chatting
about just cause I know it's a popular game on Linux, you know, that's what my son plays
it on.
He has a, uh, well now I'm going to put it, I don't know if it'll play on the Chromebook.
I'm going to, I guess I could try get it so that my son can see it and see what he thinks.
Yeah.
I've got it.
No, it's the C seven 20, uh, yeah, that's Intel.
Uh, it's got, um, it's got an elementary OS on it right now, but he's got a HP laptop
at home that has enter gross on it that has Minecraft installed.
And that works really well for him.
And interestingly too, I didn't expect this, but he's taken much better to the track pads
on a laptop than a mouse because he started with touchscreen devices and then moved to
the computer.
He kind of graduated up to the computer.
And so the touch on the pad, on the touch pad, on the click pad made much more sense
to him than the mouse.
Now he's learned the mouse too, but I, he just almost immediately was able to translate
touchscreen to track pad, which I didn't quite expect cause it's not really a one-to-one
thing, but.
How old is he?
Five.
So Sam started off with a mouse and a keyboard, Minecraft, and then eventually I bought it
on the Xbox 360 and he now favors the controller.
He's no son of mine.
I mean, I'm a, I'm a, I'm a mouse and keyboard kind of guy, but he, yeah, he's, he's big,
you know, him and Sophie as well, who's 11, she's much prefers the controller now finds
it a lot more accurate.
And do they use the controller on the PC or are they sticking to the console?
They generally only use the console because they, they use the multiplayer thing with
the, what's the camera thing?
Connect.
Yeah.
And they, they chat to their friends.
So does that mean no custom servers?
Like how does that work on the console?
Are there.
They make their own servers and their friends, they invite their friends, they call parties.
And they're persistent worlds.
Yeah.
They come back to, there's like a hundred of them saved on the Xbox.
I don't know where they are.
They're in the cloud probably.
Yeah.
So they're hosted like on the Xbox live servers.
I guess so.
Yeah.
Huh.
So it's way easier than PC servers.
Yeah.
You don't have to worry about, you know, spinning up a VDS.
But you can only play with other, it's only other console custom worlds.
Yes.
Like you can't go console to PC.
Correct.
But there's a ton of people who have Xbox and Minecraft.
Yeah.
No, I think it's like a huge game on there.
I think, I think they looked at it as a huge game on iOS.
It's a huge game on, on the Xbox and they went, huh, you know what we should do?
We should probably own that.
And plus you see, you got Notch there.
He's like, yeah, I don't want to be part of a big company.
I don't want to do this anymore.
I mean, it was just sort of, I mean, wow.
I think it was the time was right.
He, I think he, I think it's pretty accurate what he was saying that he, you know, I don't
think that was a cop out.
And I think it was fair to say that he's not CEO material.
You can tell from his tweets and stuff, he likes just hacking around on stupid games
and stuff and playing Ludum Dare and, and, you know, entering competitions.
And that's not CEO material, CEOs don't do that.
So I can see why he wanted to sell it.
You know, two years ago or whatever he said, billion is my price and the only company who's
going to pay two billion for Minecraft is Microsoft.
Yeah.
With their nice overseas cash pile.
Blaster, are you a Minecraft player?
Yes.
I didn't know that.
And actually the, the server on the servers on Xbox live actually don't, they're not spun
up on Microsoft servers.
You actually host it on your console and then the party connects to you.
So your friends can't, you have to spin up your save and then some people have to come
and connect to you while you're online.
And then once you close Minecraft, it's offline.
Wow.
That's interesting.
That makes sense.
It works almost exactly like the mobile version.
Okay.
I like, see, I like the idea of a persistent world that people can be visiting all the
time.
That's, I think one of the coolest things when we had active, I don't know if they still
are active or not.
The Minecraft servers for Jupiter broadcast.
You just go in there.
Oh God, yeah.
They are totally active.
Yeah.
So you can go in there and there's just tons of people working on stuff.
So that's really cool.
My kids play on that as well and that's, that's another thing is having a game that your kids
can play, which is a safe environment.
Like if it's a curated server like Jupiter is where you know that the people aren't going
to mess about with your kids and you're not going to get dangerous people talking to them.
You can leave them playing on the PC for a while.
Yeah.
You know, it's cool when my kids come in and they say, Hey dad, do you want to play on
the JB server?
That's quite cool.
You know?
Yeah, it is really cool.
And I like the idea too that, I mean, I think sure you could make the argument that, you
know, it has to be maybe try to be balanced with, with other things, but at the same time
it's like, out of all the video games you could play for kids, Minecraft really seems
like it's gotta be not like, like super like healthier educational or something, but it
seems like it's, it's cultivating something like a creativity and building and problem
solving and, and, and, and resource management and all of these things that are actually
really good life skills.
Yeah.
Okay.
You know, you can try and make an argument for it in the same way that when I had a Sinclair
Spectrum back in 1980, I would try and make the argument that I was doing my homework.
Yeah.
Same thing goes with Minecraft.
It's educational mom.
Really.
Yeah.
But it's also, yeah.
Minecraft has a really cool server too.
Yeah.
Some of the stuff they have on there.
They have a really great server.
I love that my son learned about smelting and different types of trees from Minecraft.
That's quite cool.
That is really cool.
Hmm.
Well, the only thing I was thinking that maybe would change like the game, like I, I would,
if I was gonna look at my crystal ball, it seems like they're still going to ship to
all the same platforms.
They're probably not going to remove any features.
They'll probably make some things better and maybe make it more developer accessible.
But then you got to wonder if like years down the road, if there's just like really hard
things to measure that just never pan out.
Like this is a bad example, I think, but I'm working on the idea still like say like, say
like on Mojang's like five year roadmap, they have like this really awesome Twitch slash
YouTube live streaming integration.
I made the argument in tech talk today that potentially like maybe it was even going to
be server side where on the Linux server you'd have like this virtual camera that could live
stream multiple angles to different streaming services, right?
Well now that, now that Microsoft owns it, you know, they're not going to, they're not
going to integrate a feature that connects directly into Google's live streaming platform
or their, or Amazon's now either.
So there could be some things like that that would have been cross pollination because
Mojang was independent and didn't have any entrenched market interest that would influence
those types of decisions.
Now that freedom has been removed from them and there's going to be those types of biases
that will sort of form the future direction of what the game can and cannot do.
That's already happened once in the Twitch TV integration is Windows only.
Hmm.
Wow.
That sucks.
Yeah.
I mean, screw those guys, right?
I think that's more, I think that's more that they're using a third party library.
So whenever you bring in third party stuff that you haven't written, you're dependent
upon whatever platforms they support and the, whatever library they've used for Twitch
TV doesn't support anything other than Windows, I believe.
Yeah.
It's, it's because it's not Java at all.
I actually believe it's a DLL file.
Like it's brought down.
Oh sweet.
I love DLLs.
I know.
Sweet.
Isn't it a beautiful thing?
You know how I like, you know how I like my libraries?
Dynamic and lean.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's prepared to finally just
break down and invest in a caffeine IV.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey Matt.
Oh man.
I did one of these things where I, I had a couple of rough nights and then I was dumb
last night and I had too much to drink, Matt.
I had too much to drink and I woke up in the middle of the night with a hangover, like
in the middle of the night and I couldn't go back to sleep.
And it wasn't even that much.
I'm just a lightweight now, Matt.
What's that mean?
Does that mean I'm getting too old to drink?
I got to just stick to my prune juice.
You need the chat room there to like tell you all the things that you should have done
beforehand because that usually really helps.
That's true.
Especially like, you know, hey Chris, you need to drink more water.
Right.
You need HTML5.
You know, you need some other stuff.
Yeah.
You know, I do like to get, I do like the hindsight 2020 advice that the chat room is
so good at providing.
And they're doing it out of love.
I mean, it's a great thing.
It is.
All right, so we're going to do a show today out of love.
We got a lot of your feedback to get through this week.
Some really good stuff.
I've picked the best of the best.
And then Aaron Saigo took to Google Plus early one morning and said the community manager
role is a fraud and a farce.
And we'll break it down.
We'll talk about it.
I have a feeling that there may be some disagreements in the show today on that topic and we'll
bring in our mumble room.
And then after that, we're going to get into a few other topics time remaining and pertaining,
including potentially a little bit of info about some future changes coming to some Linux
distributions near you.
So we'll talk about all of that stuff as well as some additional links towards the end of
the show.
Got a lot of stuff to cover today.
I'm just going through it right now.
I'm looking at the papers and I'm thinking, dang, this is looking like a pretty busy week.
I think our news cycle has come back.
I think the news is starting to pick back up again.
In fact, we've seen some really big things go down this week.
So I think we're going to have a huge news segment on the Linux Action Show on Sunday.
But today, our duty is to focus on the feedback, to focus on the people.
And so Stefan writes in and he says, hey, Chris and Matt, I don't know if you have already
seen the leaked preview of Windows 9, but in case you didn't know, there's quite some,
let's call it progress in this hell of a stagnation that Microsoft calls Windows.
Anyways, to keep it short, they integrated multiple workspaces.
Oh, nice.
And when they finally developed something usable, however, you might think it looks
a little familiar.
My biggest concern is that I almost hear these F-ers at Microsoft, fanboys claim that Microsoft
opened up a whole new perspective of user experiences.
And I can predict that if you tell them multiple workspaces isn't something new because Apple
and Linux had this for years, they'll respond with, but Microsoft made it awesome and usable.
So have you seen this implementation of virtual desktops on Windows 9?
I have.
And just the interface as a whole, not just the implementation, but the interface as a
whole is the best box of Crayola crayons I've ever seen.
Yeah, it is very, yeah.
It looks like iOS 7 smacked Windows.
Absolutely.
We throw enough color at it, people are going to think it looks great.
And that, and just, I'm so blown away at how they come up with concepts.
I can't even wrap my brain around it.
I don't even, I don't even know.
I don't even know.
So I have it in the video version here.
You can see their dynamic workspaces, all a gnome and, or, and, and of course other desktops
as well.
I guess actually Mac OS 10 has dynamic workspaces as well.
And then you can see, you can drag the windows around and move them.
I, you know, I mean, I'm not going to use this because I don't use Windows.
I guess it's nice to have it for Windows users finally.
It is, I think what is interesting is like, remember how like Windows 8 came out and Microsoft's
all like, yeah, so the desktop's dead.
We have that classic interface, quote unquote, when you need it, but you should do everything
in the new modern UI.
That's the future.
And now this version of Windows is coming out and they're like, hey, so we know you
like the desktops.
We're going to give you more desktops.
You can in fact have unlimited desktops.
How about some desktops, everybody?
Exactly.
And it's like, and not only that, but we're going to borrow it.
We're going to, we're going to travel back in time and basically provide an implementation
that quite honestly looks a bit dated.
Yeah.
It looks actually a little clunky to me.
It's not very smooth.
It does.
It feels a little bit like a, a little bit like an early KDE, maybe two point something
kind of, you know, thrust up some cookies on top of something.
I don't know.
They need to add a little, a little, a little, a little animation factor in there.
Give it some, give it some jazz.
Right.
Put a little jazz in that desktop.
Microsoft Biz.
There you go.
Yeah.
Cause that's what makes it usable.
A spinning cube.
Yeah.
We'll add a spinning cube.
It is funny though.
So when they decide to reinvest in the desktop and sort of double down on it, what do they
do?
They go rip off features from Unix desktops.
Absolutely.
So there you go.
One stop shopping.
Redmond has indeed restarted their copy machines.
So yeah, I thought we'd just, it's always fun to kind of, you know, poke at my, poke
at Microsoft.
I mean, come on.
We had to.
It's so easy.
So Eric, you're here, right?
You're still here, Eric.
Good.
We have a question that is right up your alley.
So Scotty ZA writes in, he says, hello, I'm loving, with a U, all the JB awesomeness.
I have a new Dell PC on the way.
The first thing I'm going to do is drop kick Windows 8 and install some Ubuntu goodness
on there.
It's going to be the gnome variety of it.
The Dell came with, comes with a touch screen and I was wondering how the gnome touch, touch
gestures are and if there's anything I need to watch out for or things that could improve
the experience.
Pseudo thanks, Scotty ZA.
So Eric, I know you got a touch screen laptop.
You've been trying out gnome, KDE and Unity with it.
What are your thoughts with regards to gnome's sort of touch features that are there right
now?
Well, the gnome touch features that are there right now in 3.12 are not up to the par of
Unity yet.
So you can't resize your window.
You can't, you can drag your windows, but only from the title bar.
And I've noticed that gnome shell will tend to crash every now and then if you try that.
Oh, really?
Ouch.
Yeah.
So it's not up to par.
Gnome 3.14 coming out later this month, if not the beginning of next month, that should
solidify their touch screen.
So 3.14 right now though, in your experience so far, Unity is the champion when it comes
to full touch screen support.
Correct.
Yeah.
And you also, does gnome have an onscreen keyboard?
I do, but you'd have, I really don't know.
It's handy.
I'm sure you could get one.
I mean, the one that comes with Unity is pretty nice and it's really easy to use.
It's a standard one, so I think you could just load it anywhere.
But anyways, so it sounds like, so what?
You can close windows, maybe you could open the activities menu, but you're not going
to be resizing windows or dragging windows around or, and there's no right click or anything
like that?
Right.
There's no right click.
It's just, it doesn't work very well.
I mean, the best touch screen interfaces they have is the activities menu itself, but also
Right.
I would think so.
Yeah.
The activities menu itself is very touch screen friendly, but also the lock screen, but beyond
that the window management in 3.12 is not up to par, 3.14 is getting there, is going
to start to get there.
Okay.
And I know I asked you, but you've been trying it out too on KDE Plasma 4?
Plasma 4 and Plasma 5.
It's still not up to par.
They haven't done anything with multi-touch gestures or anything.
Okay.
And by the way, a little correction, Wikileaks pointed out in the chat room, GNOME 3.12 does
not have this, but GNOME 3.14 is going to have a long presses right click.
Okay.
Oh, okay.
Oh yes.
You know what?
I've read about that.
Right-o.
Yes.
I do recalls.
Do I hear music?
Oh yeah.
Hey, it's my daily collections call.
Of course, I'm not in collections, but somebody is that gave out my number.
So this is the default Sailfish OS ringtone.
Nice right?
I can dance to that.
Doesn't that sound good?
Yeah.
Sounds awesome.
And I've got a cool pirate ship in the background.
Oh, I wasn't able to answer it in time.
Darn.
I really like the Sailfish OS call interface, but it's a little funky because sometimes
you have to swipe in a certain direction to answer the call and if you're just late enough
it's that that that animation of making the swipe is just long enough that you miss the
call.
It's all right.
It's cool.
I'm just experimenting with it.
All right, Matt.
You know what else I'm experimenting with?
My mind over at linuxacademy.com go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged to get our special discount
deal linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
So I've told you a lot about Linux Academy, how they're always working on their courseware,
new features and things like that.
Today, I got an email from Anthony, the founder of linuxacademy.com and he says he's passing
along some of the new exciting things they're working on and it's really something.
He says, our new lab platform now allows the users to have four running Linux servers at
one time.
You can have any distribution you would like from a list as well as two public host names
for each server.
You can even assign each server a role.
Let's say you want to have a DB server and another one to be a DNS server.
You can now label those roles to help you remember which lab you're working with and
you can have people, you can work with other people now.
They have cool new learning and plans too that allow users to select daily availability
and based on that availability, a study plan is automatically created for them.
So you say, I have this much time available and they will generate a plan that you can
go through and learn something.
Learning plans will give you the lessons and quizzes and labs that are due on each day
as well as even send you email reminders that you have items due on that day.
Based on your availability, it will even give you a projected completion date of the course
with some extra time included for studying.
How freaking cool is that, right?
He says, we're also really excited to announce the immediate availability of a few extra
courses we've been working on.
Today we've announced Chef Fundamentals, CentOS 7 Enterprise updates as well as Apache Tomcat.
We've launched our deploy and manage open stack on Ubuntu and Icehouse which is 50%
complete and they're working on it right now.
We have a list of 14 upcoming courses throughout the remainder of the year.
He's going to send me updates when they've got them.
Isn't that awesome?
Sure, they're doing all this stuff.
You know, real servers with host names that you can have people publicly log in, these
automated coursewares, these learning plans, 350 new videos and content before the end
of the year, more scenario-based learning labs than ever before, all of these new additions,
no price increase.
You just get them as part of your Linux Academy subscription.
It just comes as part of the subscription.
Go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged right now.
You'll get that 33% discount.
That makes it a great deal.
You can go over there and learn courses on R-Sync and OpenStack and AWS, pick from any
of the seven plus Linux distributions.
The courseware will automatically adjust the documentation so that way it matches the distribution
you've chosen which is a really great way to also get up to speed on another distro
if you've taken on a job where you have to change your distro.
What a great way to get up to speed or if you know it's time to finally make that R-Sync
backup script, why not go take the R-Sync courseware?
And they're always adding new stuff as well as live videos and all that kind of stuff.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a really big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the Unplugged program.
You guys rock and great work you guys on the new updates.
That's crazy awesome.
I love the automated learning courses.
That's man.
If I...
They'll get you learning on.
Well, I'm just thinking like, you know, I could go in there and say, all right, I need
a learning plan and I've got, I've got, you know, this much time this week to do it.
I just, I love that.
I think that's a really great system.
All right.
So Alec writes in, we had a ton, a ton, a ton of email about our Assistant D discussion
and I think a couple of people felt like it was our first time.
Maybe they were kind of new to the show and they didn't realize that we've done past episodes
on this.
So they felt, some people wrote in and felt like we left some, some details out and sort
of jumped in mid conversation.
So I apologize if that is how you felt.
I would suggest maybe go check the Unplugged back catalogue.
We've done a couple of episodes on it with some really good discussion that does fill
in some of the background details.
But Alec wrote in, he says, hi Chris, Matt and chat room.
And I thought Alec had one of the more interesting anti-System D concerns.
Like, like he's not like opposed to System D, but he's bringing up a concern about System
D that I think maybe has some merit worth discussing, discussing outside of what we
normally hear about, you know, some of the other issues that we've discussed before.
He says, I want to chime in with my thoughts about the recent System D discussion.
As a system administrator, I like System D and its innovative new features like D-Bus
and socket activation.
Yeah.
You know what?
I agree with that.
But I have some concerns about its long-term viability.
From what I see, the main problem with System D is that it's a large attack surface, which
could lead to security problems in the future.
Also, because System D will be adopted by all Linux, I fear it could become a major
target for attackers.
In short, I think System D is a good thing for Linux right now.
But in the future, it could become insecure and unmaintainable.
And because more and more projects are starting to depend on System D, it could become a painful
process to move away from System D.
Thanks for all the awesome shows, Alec.
And I want to add to that, even outside of security, what about just code creep where
something gets to be such a massive project and it impacts so many distributions and so
many users whenever you change it, that it sort of becomes like this weight, this anchor
on Linux because you have this whole layer now that has to be updated and it has potentially
dramatic effects across the board.
Obviously, there's ways and updates that maybe would have very minimal impacts, but you have
to wonder if that could become a source of stagnation.
I wonder what you think, Matt.
Do you think there's a potential that maybe System D is going to make a large attack surface
for Linux, a common attack platform, or maybe an anchor that slows us down?
Or do you think the folks at Red Hat and people working on System D can stay on top of it?
I think at this point they can stay on top of it.
I think it's going to be something that they need to be vigilantly aware of and proactive
on because you never know, it could develop into what that concern addresses.
But I think at this point it's too early to tell and I don't see any point in borrowing
trouble.
I'm not saying to fall asleep at the wheel, but I'm just saying let's keep our eyes open.
But at the same time, let's go ahead and keep pushing forward.
It hasn't created any problems yet that are really significant that I'm aware of for my
personal use.
Others may have other gripes, I don't know.
For me personally, it's been great.
Okay, Daredevil.
And you think it's not about security, but something else?
Yes.
So we saw what happened, like Linux as the kernel is super complicated now to get in
as a maintainer or to start contributing.
It's famous for that.
That is kind of the problem that I find.
Not the security aspect, we can solve security aspects.
I mean, we've been solving them in multiple fronts and now there's even a specialized
group for it.
But I think companies getting a hold on who maintains System D now becomes more and more
parts being just company control.
Even though community always have a say, that's actually more dangerous than the security
aspect.
Yeah.
I think you have to look at the kernel and you say, yeah, the kernel is not a one to
one analog, but it is an interesting way to compare it to a large bit of code that obviously
impacts every Linux distribution and even mobile devices.
And yet we make that work, don't we?
We have that working.
I think it's in part because we have the right people on the job and I feel like right now
we have the right people on the job, but these things can change.
I do not know if I totally buy in with Alec on the... And I think Alec's not the only
one who's worried about the quote unquote System D lock in.
I'm not so worried about that really.
It's kind of a funny thing.
One of the reasons we all want a free and open platform is because we want to avoid
those problems and then we still worry about those problems even though it's open source
code with documented APIs and things like that.
So at some point we kind of just have to acknowledge we have to adopt a technology, but realize
that we can build our way out too if we need to.
I don't think it's as much lock in as people think.
All right, Fred, what do you think?
No, I just wanted to mention that I think there were these patches to get System D working
on BSD systems early days of System D and they were not accepted because the developers
thought they only wanted to target Linux and didn't accept patches for portability.
Very good.
And Blackout rightly points out... Sorry, I just mentioned I didn't want to lose track
of this.
Almost 600 people contribute to System D, 200 alone in the last 12 months.
So there's a lot of people that are working on System D.
I think that seems like a lot of eyeballs.
I mean, it seems like a lot of people have got their fingers on the pulse and are watching
what's going on.
To me, that's my perspective.
So here's what we did, is Producer Q5 says put together a simple System D opinion survey
that we put out for folks to go take advantage of and just plug through the questions and
just so we can get a little data to kind of see where everybody's coming from in this
... where their heads at... Jack, close your mic.
And so it's a simple System D opinion survey and it's up on the subreddit right now.
I'll have it linked in the show notes.
We've got quite a bit of responses.
Q5 is going to be releasing the results in the future.
And it's not like a definitive scientific study, but I think it'll be interesting to
see where people who have different opinions, where they all stand and what their experience
level is and things like that.
So we'll have that linked in the show notes and if you'd like to participate in the survey,
we'll talk about the results in an upcoming episode.
And also you can keep sending your System D feedback in if you've got something really
good.
We'll put it on there, but either way I'll even read it so that way we can just at least
incorporate it into our opinions.
Hey, speaking of producers, we just heard from Eric a little bit ago and I want to plug
something for Producer Michael aka RottenCorps.
YouGet Beta 2 is coming and available for beta testing and YouGet is a great downloader
for Linux.
We've covered it before in the Linux Action Show and RottenCorps is one of the developers
for it.
And they just put out a new beta for their brand new version coming out.
So we'll link to that in the show notes.
It's a great downloader, YouGet, and it's my preferred way if I download large ISO images
and I don't want to leave my browser running and I'm doing, I like, you know, if I'm not
doing the torrent, I generally do the torrent, but if for some reason I'm doing an HTTP download,
boom.
Boom.
There you go.
YouGet is where it goes, Matt, like a boss.
Nice.
Like a boss.
Hey, speaking of like a boss, I want to tell you about something else that's like a boss
and that's DigitalOcean.
Go over to DigitalOcean.com right now, DigitalOcean.com.
Not just walk, not just trot, but full on gallop because we've got a promo code that
will get you two months for free of a DigitalOcean droplet.
I know, it's crazy, if you use the promo code unplugged September, you're going to get armed
with a $10 credit.
Oh.
So you see that value there, you get, for $10 you get two months of DigitalOcean service.
Why?
Because they have pricing plans that start at only $5 per month.
That'll get you a 512 megabyte RAM droplet with a 20 gigabyte SSD, one blazing fast CPU,
and a terabyte of transfer connected to tier one bandwidth.
You don't know what DigitalOcean is?
My friend DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way to spin up a cloud server.
And they've got droplet centers everywhere, or maybe you call them data centers, I don't
know.
Say like, oh I don't know, New York, you heard of that?
You heard of New York, right?
San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London, and they're rolling out new features all the
time.
Their interface is crazy simple and intuitive.
Their control panel is very powerful, but if you want to even go beyond that, they've
got a straightforward API that you can take advantage of.
DigitalOcean has also recently rolled out IPv6 in some of their data centers, CoreOS,
private networking, it gets better and better and better.
One of the things I love about the private networking is not only does that allow you
to build the etcd cluster you're gonna need to configure your CoreOS rigs, but it also
allows you to have say, a front end web server with a back end database server that isn't
exposed to the internet, and the best part is, there's no charge for the transfer over
that private link.
That's how awesome DigitalOcean is.
Something else that's kind of cool, and another great reason to hold on to Unplug September,
you can also do hourly pricing over at DigitalOcean.
This is super useful if you're doing testing, and you need to do it up somewhere that actually
has decent performance, where a lot of people can get to it, and you can turn it on, turn
it off, take snapshots, deploy, redeploy.
This is a great use of their hourly pricing structure.
It's so awesome, and their control panel makes it crazy easy to just get up and going.
DigitalOcean.com.
Unplug September when you check out, and a big thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
Linux Unplugged.
I'll tell you, I keep spinning up droplets, I kind of say, oh, I really need to do that
one thing.
And I'll just spin up a droplet.
It's great.
Oh yeah.
Aaron Saigo lit the world on fire via Google Plus yesterday at 3.01 a.m.
I don't know why he's posting at 3.01 a.m., but that's what he was.
And I'm just going to read a few highlights, and then we can get into the meat and potatoes
of it here.
He says, here we go.
Flamethrowers on everyone.
Here's what I feel.
The community manager role that is increasingly common in the free software world is a fraud
and a farce.
The community manager role is a fraud and a farce, he says.
If your community has a quote-unquote manager, then it isn't being treated as a community
and probably isn't a community to begin with.
Community has an actual meaning that transcends a crowd.
Community is a structure derived from the self-determination of shared values.
Communities don't have managers, synthetic organizations do.
Nearly all community managers in free software ecosystems work for companies that own and
manage products that that community they are managing are built around, and that's not
a coincidence.
Communities, real ones, have facilitators and leaders of various forms and stripes.
It's okay if they do get paid, and if they're able to spend time and energy facilitating
and leading, but they damn sure are not managers of the community.
They are accountable to the community, selected by the community, and drive their influence
from the community consensus and can be replaced by the community at the community's behest.
Does that sound like the free software community managers you know?
I'd be fine in the situation if there's some honesty on the ground about this because then
we wouldn't be tainting the word community for those blessed souls who have managed to
actually erect the real deal.
There wouldn't be quite so many diluted individuals out there who think that they're a true stakeholder
with equitable rights and privileges in the actual community.
In summary, a community manager is really an audience handler, as in they handle you
as members of their audience, as part of their marketing program, and frankly, I've run out
of patience for this deception.
Get off my lawn.
Matt, I'll open the floor to you.
So I don't subscribe to his thoughts or his feed for obvious reasons, because personally,
so let's take a step back and let's go to this thing called Wikipedia and let's look
at what the term community is.
A community is a social unit of any size that shares common values.
Period.
Okay.
Why is it a problem to have a name of manager or facilitator or reach around guy or whatever
you want to call them that comes in and facilitates, I don't know, something we like to call communication
between a large mob of people and in some cases a company or in some cases, I don't
know, the developers.
Fun fact, developers and end users don't always speak the same language.
Sometimes it requires a manager to come in and help facilitate that line of communication.
His post was the biggest pile of drivel I've ever read in my entire life.
He's a nice guy.
I like him, but this pissed me off.
It was absolute nonsense.
Absolute crap.
I couldn't even wrap my head around it.
I'm hoping he was drunk because it's like, was he just up to a fight?
I mean, he's such a nice guy and I mean, I like the guy I do, but he's just so negative
about nothing.
It's like, oh my God, relax.
Take a pill.
Take your own.
Do something.
I do wonder, I think part of the problem is the term community manager can mean a lot
of different things to a lot of different groups and businesses, so you can't blanket
hate on just one term.
I mean, it might not be the right manager, might not be the right word.
So I'll take the opposite.
I'll play devil's advocate here and I don't know if it is fair to compare the community
of Jupiter Broadcasting to the community of, say, a well-established open source project.
I don't know if that's fair or not.
I would guess the Jupiter Broadcasting community size probably dwarfs many open source projects
that aren't super famous, right?
Easily.
Yeah.
So we have a huge community, huge, and I very consciously have chosen to, whenever we start
up a new aspect of the community somewhere, to generally sort of wind my involvement down.
I don't know if manage is the right... curate.
I'll curate the community there for a bit and then sort of wind myself down as I notice
certain personalities in the community sort of stand up and take on leadership roles.
Not even leadership roles so much as much as just... I don't know how to explain it.
I really don't.
But let's take this mumble room that we're all in right now.
This is something that Blaster, on his own initiative, went out and created and now he
is the operator of our mumble room.
I didn't set that up.
Blaster set that up and everybody knows that it's Blaster's creation here and that is,
in my opinion, community taking on their own leadership in a much more organic and real
way than when you have an artificial manager who really kind of more ends up playing PR
guy and try to smooth things over and a lot of times kind of keeps the community at arm's
length from the business.
So the business is allowed to make the decisions it needs to make to be a profitable business
and then the community manager ends up being the guy who tries to sell it to the community
and tells everybody we're having a great time and it's really because of your participation
that it's all working out.
Oh absolutely.
And that drives me crazy.
It does and that's the mark of a poor community manager.
If you're working on stuff like Operation Lightning Rod, which I've actually known people
that worked on an operation called Operation Lightning Rod as a community manager, it exists.
If you're in those situations, yeah, that's a bad situation to be in and that's honestly
a bad role to be in.
But at the end of the day, if something happens with Jupiter Broadcasting, generally speaking,
you or Angela or maybe even one of the producers will reach out to the community and say, hey,
by the way, we're going to do this, that and the other thing.
There's some information passed.
We have a more distributed system where there's producers and staff and generally speaking,
you take on that role a lot of it, especially it's like, hey, by the way, this is being
rescheduled or hey, we're going to be having this guest on or we're going to be doing that.
You're going to be making that communication happen.
You do need some kind of leadership in some fashion and sometimes it does fall to a person
that is hired for such a role.
It really just depends.
I do agree that when you get to a certain size, it does become easier to just make it
a person's responsibility because it can be one of the things that gets neglected and
also that sort of fits in better with how businesses are structured.
All right, well, this is your responsibility, Bob, and you're going to manage the community.
But I wonder if maybe there isn't a bit of a different approach that needs to be taken
when you are deriving some of your success from the fruits of labor of that community.
I think there needs to be a guide.
I think there needs to be like a community, like everybody gets together, including the
communities themselves to say, look, here's how not to be a D-bag when you're talking
to us.
Here's how to actually have like a level of, because a lot of times you are talking about
like let's say Red Hat and the Fedora project or whatever it may be.
You do need someone in between those things to actually make that conversation happen.
I've lived in this world for a long time.
You just do.
Let's toss it to Popey.
I'd like to hear your thoughts on this, Popey.
Go ahead.
I read Aaron's post and I can see an argument there that's worthwhile.
I can see how it could be misconstrued that someone who works for a corporate entity who
tries to rally people around and basically do their bidding for them for free is not
a pleasant person to be, right?
And I can see how there's a good argument for that being not an appropriate person in
a community.
It's not a community person, but I would flip that around and say that I would say a company
who is comprised of a bunch of people who aren't necessarily close to the community,
who have a product that is used by a wide community of people, there needs to be an
interface between them.
If you hire people in the company who have never worked in an open source company, you've
got to be able to interface those people to these random drive-by community contributors
and say, look, this guy who just fixed a typo in your code, he's trustworthy.
He's a good guy.
You should accept that contribution.
That person could serve as an advocate for the community.
Right.
Or it could be just a drive-by edit and they're gone and then you'll never see them again.
They were just scratching an itch because in their language, that word didn't make sense
so they fixed it, right?
But I do feel like the core argument that Aaron's getting at that there has been a quote
unquote perversion of what the term means and what that role does, I think for a lot
of companies, a lot of times companies grow and all of a sudden the community almost becomes,
their view of them changes and the community shifts from asset to liability.
And now it's like this thing we need to manage so that way they don't damage our public perception.
And it becomes like this distorted time of, it's not community management so much as keeping
the community sort of boxed and that's not a good thing.
I can see how that perception can happen because I've seen that happen and I've seen people
being labeled as the PR guy or the guy who fixes when there's a problem in the community.
From my perspective, that's not the role I play but I can see how that could be seen.
The problem is that a lot of people outside of a particular community, and obviously I'm
speaking from experience of the Ubuntu community, look in and only see someone with a public
face like Jono, for example, and only see his public blog posts and his public conversations
with people and think that's all he does.
Right, he doesn't see the day to day.
Right.
And the full calendar he had talking to, I'm not talking in the past tense as if he's dead
but just because he's known with the company.
The late Jono Bacon.
Yeah.
He had a calendar that was full of meetings with people inside the company making sure
that the community's needs were addressed and that any decision that was made in the
company was made with full thought and respect for what the community wanted.
And whatever name you give that role, yeah, manager, he's got people under him in the
company.
Okay, he's a manager.
He deals with the community a lot.
Yeah, okay.
Let's put the word community in there.
Right, right, right.
You can futz around with the job title but the fact is that he's a very pro community
guy who is doing his best to interface a corporate entity with a community of contributors who
are doing what they're doing willingly and they can walk away at any time and they do.
You know?
Right.
I object to Aaron's post mostly because I think he has a very blinkered view of the
term community manager and what a community manager is.
Bingo.
Yeah.
I mean, I totally see it from the  when you come at it from the inside of how a business
works, like it makes so much more sense versus when you look at it from the outside where
you just kind of end up seeing them continually play that PR buffer zone.
And I look at this and I think there is a lot of ways you can parse this.
There's a lot of ways you can change around the terms but I wanted to give Daredevilin
a chance to kind of get in because I know he's had a couple thoughts on this.
So Daredevilin, is that  is the semantics of this something you wanted to touch on?
Yes, because I don't think even the term is applied to the community.
I also think that the post is actually looking at the community creating and forming itself
around the company when actually a lot of times the companies go and join the communities
that already exist.
And it's like making the post is under the impression that the community is dependent
on the company when it's most of the time the other way around.
It can always go on their own and suddenly there's no point.
And I see the manager to be actually a manager for the company as like Poppy pointed out.
I completely agree.
And I get people PM me on IRC and say, hey, I've seen this winter phone thing, I'd
like to help out.
What can I do?
And my response, I'm the right person they should come to because I can point them in
the right direction, right?
Is that a community manager?
Well, that's not what my business card says but that's arguably what I'm doing.
People are coming to me and saying, hey, I'd like to contribute.
And I say, well, what do you know?
What do you want  what are you so passionate about?
What do you want to contribute to?
And these are people who have lives, they've got other jobs, they've got families, they've
got other stuff they need to be doing, but they're willing to contribute to a product
that's made by a corporation.
And if they're willing to do that, yeah, they can walk away at any time.
If they're willing to do that and they want to contribute, then it makes sense for the
company to have someone who is a point of contact for them, someone who can facilitate
that conversation and find the bugs that that person can fix or poke the right people inside
the company in order to fast-track a bug through or release a piece of software or whatever
it is.
That's what the community manager does.
It's not like running around the streets grabbing press-ganging people off the streets
and putting an Emacs in front of them and saying, you code for me now, that's your
job now and you work for me, bitch.
That's not what a community manager is.
The last time I held the position, no.
I wanted to give Eric a chance to chime in because Eric, I know that you've done a lot
of work with community management and taken training in it specifically.
Do you agree with Aaron's point that the term community is sort of being muddy down here?
It's getting sort of distorted by these corporations and it's sort of devaluing the term community
and what it actually means.
Do you think that's an issue?
I think it depends on the corporation.
Basically you've got a lot of volunteer management going on or community management as it's called.
You still have to have somebody who's acting as a liaison between the community and the
company.
When that person becomes a PR person, that's where it's getting a little fuzzy.
The person does have to inspire the community to do better things but at the same time they
also need to be putting the community toward the vision of the company and saying this
is kind of what we have in mind.
Do you guys like this?
And here's why we think this is a good idea.
So there's a lot to it.
There's a lot to it more than being a PR guy.
A lot to it more than just talking to the community.
It's a lot of trying to vision cast as I call it the vision of the company to the community
at large.
That's a huge part.
And also getting them involved in company events as well.
The community manager in the past in Ubuntu would send out all the invites and figure
out who were the kind of people that you needed at an Ubuntu developer summit and would send
out invites to like 100 people to get them along and get them involved in conversations
and planning about what's happening in the next release.
And I've just had to do this.
I've invited a bunch of people to come to a sprint in Washington to help us form Ubuntu
phone.
And these are people, yeah, they're giving up their own time to come along and help us
figure out what a free software phone should look like in the future.
And you need someone to do the crappy work of figuring out what flights they can go on
working out what their visa requirements.
Trust me, I've had to do this.
So yeah, this is exactly what a community manager does.
It's nowhere near as nefarious as Aaron makes it out to be.
It might be in some companies, but not in my experience.
Yeah, I guess that's the difference is when you get assigned community manager as your
job title, what do they have in mind for you?
Is your job to, you know, mollify the community and keep them from sending hate mail to the
company?
Or is it to get the most out of the community that you can to, you know, get as many of
those people involved in actually forwarding the project along or what?
I would say the latter, Alan.
I would say all the above it's different with each company, what their why they decided
they needed a community manager.
That's why it's not black and white, because it is literally different for every single
case.
It's ambiguous.
It's become a buzzword for a job title that could mean anything from I remember when the
first time I heard it, it was when a company hired someone to manage like a forum about
something.
Yeah, see, this is this is the part of Aaron's post that I the registers with me is this
has actually bothered these kinds of things have bothered me for a while.
Alan, since you're here, would you would you can you give us an overview of how this works
for FreeBSD?
You guys have assigned liaisons?
Is that how it works?
Not really.
Like there are certain people who volunteer to try to be that matchmaker type person like
Popey was describing.
There's I think it's FreeBSD help and a couple of their Twitter accounts that when they see
somebody tweet having this problem with FreeBSD or whatever, they'll, you know, be like, hey,
well, does this help?
You know, make sure you file a PR or oh, that thing you're asking about.
Well, why don't you talk to this person who's the guy that worked on that most recently
or whatever, kind of like Popey was describing.
But you know, the FreeBSD foundation doesn't pay someone to to do that.
Gotcha.
All right.
Well, I wanted to get I want I want to cover Mark Shuttleworth's response because I actually
really liked his response to Aaron's post.
And as you'd expect, I'm one of Aaron's provocative Google Plus posts.
The comments were about a mile long and just as I was about to abort because I was getting
a little burned out on the comments, I saw Mark Shuttleworth's dragon and I had to read
his post.
So we'll we'll read what Mark Shuttleworth had to say.
But first, I want to thank Ting over to Linux.Ting.com.
That's right.
Linux.Ting.com.
That'll take twenty five dollars off your first Ting device.
If you already got a Ting compatible device, they'll give you a twenty five dollar credit.
That's also a great option to go if you're going to get one of their dedicated data units,
like a little LTE hotspot device.
So what is Ting?
Well, Ting is truly mobile that is different.
No contract, no early termination fee, and you only pay for what you use.
Flat six dollars for the line, plus the taxes the man's going to take.
And then it's just your usage.
Ting takes your minutes, your messages, your megabytes, they add them all up at the end
of the month, whatever bucket you fall into.
That's what you pay.
It's so much better than paying for the amount of minutes and data and text you may or may
not use.
That's such a freaking rip off.
And the best part is to like if you if you've been feeling what a rip off that is and you're
like, OK, it's time to do something differently.
You can go over to Linux.Ting.com, try out their savings calculator, get an idea of what
you'll save over like the two year contract period that you'll be getting away from.
And if you're ready to make the jump but you're still in the contract, well Ting has an early
termination relief program, Ting.com slash ETF, where they'll help pay seventy five dollars
per line that you have to get canceled.
That just sort of supercharges your transition over to Ting.
And if you are an Apple user and you have an iPhone 5S or 5C, Ting has launched the
countdown to when you can bring the 5S or 5C over to the Ting network, which is a great
option if you are on that device now because you can take it and just get even more use
out of it.
And if you're thinking about getting perhaps a different phone down the road, you could
take this iPhone and convert it over to Ting and then just pay for what you use.
What a great opportunity.
What a great way to get value out of it.
I've got the Nexus 5 on the Ting network, too.
Matt's got the Note 2.
They both absolutely rock.
I love the Ting network paired with the Ting devices and you own them outright.
They're yours.
You never have to worry about getting screwed in a contract.
They have an amazing dashboard.
No hold customer service at one eight five five Ting FTW any time between 8 a.m. or
8 p.m., East Coast time, and a real person answers the phone.
Linux.ting.com.
Linux.ting.com will give you $25 credit if you've got a compatible device like the iPhone
5S, 5S or 5C or any of the devices available on the Ting store.
Lots of good stuff.
Linux.ting.com.
Check them out.
Maybe even give them a call.
See just how great that customer service is.
And a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring.
Linux Unplugged.
Okay, guys, let's parse Mark Shuttleworth's response to Aaron Seigo.
Mark Shuttleworth wrote, from my perspective, the great people in this kind of role really
love the people and the project and help unblock things which would otherwise cause a project
to stagnate.
It's perfectly possible to stick a fraudulent label on a job, yes, there are companies that
think they can get people to work for them if they have a manager for those people.
But those cases usually don't work out very well.
By contrast, invest in people who love both the goals of a huge project and the opportunity
to work with folks who can only participate part-time and some magic happens.
That's worth investing in, in my opinion.
I like that he leaves the H off.
Mark's like, I'm not going to put H in that.
So Jono, Michael, David, Daniel and others are wonderful to work with and I'm very proud
of the things they've done and the things they've enabled to get done by others.
Whatever label people might try to attach to them, those are my heroes.
He said something in this post, pretty short, but something that I think is perhaps the
most, the most realistic like day-to-day task that a good community advocate or manager
or organizer has to do is a lot of times an open source project, there's a lot of people
in your community who come and go, they can't contribute a lot of hours and if they are
on a regular basis, it's very limited.
And so because of their time constraints, they need an enabler to help them when they
do have the time.
So that is a critical role that that community manager, whatever you want to call it, could
play.
And at the end of the day, that is truly about enabling people in your community to help
work with you and it really is a two-way street in that case and that, that kind of thing
I think is a great example of a good role a community manager can have.
Any closing thoughts you guys on this before we wrap up?
Well that just tells me that Kynockle has a great idea of where they want to go with
the community and, or at least Mark Shelworth does and since he is the dictator as it were,
then sure.
Well and of course Aaron did reply to Mark if you guys want to see Aaron's response to
Mark it's further down in the comments, what were you going to say Matt?
I was basically just going to point out, when we see things like this, two things that,
you know, first of all, when you start off with just a really ugly title like that, you
know, fraud and all this stuff, you've lost me already.
So even if he has like relevant points throughout the article, you lost me at the title.
Just ugly, ugly stuff.
The end point that people need to remember with stuff like this is that, you know, it's
apples and oranges with every company, every community.
There are some real d-bags that are just total placeholders in certain companies and they
exist and I realize this, but there's a lot of times where these people are doing this
stuff because they actually started out as members of the community that were perhaps
brought in to fill a void and they have a really unfortunate title.
Oh no, it's got the word manager in it.
Maybe we can call him the community advocate or the community hug guy or something.
I don't know.
But whatever makes people feel warm and fuzzy, but at the end of the day, they have a critical
role if it's a company you want to do business with or if it's community that you want to
be part of.
If it's not, go away.
Yeah.
That would be my message.
I walk away mostly thinking, you know, you can't make it black and white, but I still
remain slightly skeptical of the position.
I think in my case, it's I wait and see, actions speak louder than words, and I'll treat each
case individually.
There you go.
Yeah.
Because like I said, there are some exceptions.
There's some real d-bags.
I'm not debating that at all.
There really are.
I mean, I don't think anybody's going to debate on that topic.
I think we all pretty much agree.
The internet is full of d-bags.
Matt, so that's going to wrap up the show today.
Actually, we do have a post-show topic.
So if you're going to be listening after the music, stick around for that.
I'm curious to hear what you think about this next topic coming up.
Matt, on Sunday, I got two different topics that I'm brewing right now to see which one
completes.
Whichever one finishes first will be the one we roll with on Sunday, but I like both of
them as much.
So we'll eventually do both of them, but I'm not sure which one we're going to do first.
Tune in on Sunday and find out with us.
JBLive.tv, Sunday, 10 a.m., or just come back here next Tuesday, jblive.tv.
We do this show in the afternoons, jupitabroadcasting.com, slash, calendar, to get it in your local time
zone.
All right, Matt.
Well, I'll see you on Sunday, okay?
All right, see you then.
All right, everyone.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
You see a lot of companies out there right now that are sort of in this transition phase,
like Amazon's really developing into something interesting, too.
Like with the Fire Phone and the tablets, and they seem to be having some success with
the Fire Tablets, and we don't really know, but they seem to be.
Yeah, Fire Phone seems to be flopping, and I think part of that is because it's only
available on AT&T.
But then you've got the Fire TV, which, from all accounts, seems to be a pretty credible
product.
I wanted to pick one up one day myself.
Also Android-based, right?
And then you've got folks like Apple that are slowly turning up this TV stuff.
It's really in this weird phase where they're entering into watches, they're entering into
TVs, and they're entering into home automation stuff, which we've really just seen the very
beginnings of.
And I'm just kind of watching all of this because you all are kind of working against
each other, and because of that, none of it really appeals to me, because I don't want
to be stranded in one person's ecosystem, or one company's ecosystem.
This is why the watches don't appeal to me, because I don't want to have to buy a watch
that they're not going to buy a specific phone.
That's no fun to me.
Well, and that's why I was glad to jump ship from Apple when I did.
And I think the Android wear has the advantage of you can move it between different Android
devices, but I don't even like that restriction, which kind of means I'm screwed, I think,
unless I'm just happy with something like the Pebble, and that's not really a compelling
device to me personally, although I know Chase really likes his.
But I kind of want to want this stuff, because I do want some of the convenience they offer.
At the same time, I'm just so sick of the lock-in.
Yeah.
I can wait.
I think so.
Yeah, and a lot of people in the new world would say, why give up your freedom like
that?
WikiLeaks says, Google is a disgusting ad-selling hypocrite company that pretends not to be
evil when their entire business is based on having and using your personal information.
Ouch.
I don't know if they're hypocrites.
I think they're kind of upfront about that.
Yeah, they are.
They are.
That's all you like is.
I guess we're all kind of negative on the watch thing.
Really?
Nobody in here wants a watch?
I wouldn't mind an Android one, but I mean, I'm not going to spend that much money on
a watch.
I just want the dummy watch.
Something that is able to receive a few instructions from something remote, and I don't think a
watch having processing capabilities is going to be of really any good use.
I think it's kind of a device to use as a gateway to any other company or place that
you are in, and just maybe some very simple functionality, but mostly a receiving device.
I think what I want is something I could do messaging, and the problem is that, and it
doesn't want advanced messaging, you just want something that does voice dictation or
voice notes.
Where would you use that?
Seriously, where would you use voice dictation on a watch?
What do you mean?
When I'm driving.
Right.
So why would you not use your phone?
Well normally I have my phone in my pocket, which is just kind of like, you know, right
there anyway.
So yeah, I could just grab it.
The thing is, when I'm driving, sometimes I have like the phone in a spot where my audio
is actually connected to a Bluetooth system, and so then I'm using a different microphone
that doesn't work as well for the dictation, whereas if the mic was built into the watch
and I could speak more clearly into it, I think it would work better.
Okay.
What are you on about?
You won't be driving for too long.
Yeah.
I mean, okay, so this is the other thing where I don't want to get all like Zen Master about
it, but like I think we've already crossed a threshold with our smartphones.
Okay.
I think, okay, all right.
I don't, you guys feel like, like do you guys go to restaurants and stuff and like you look
around and everybody's got their face in their phone and maybe it's getting, it's going on,
it's gone a little too far and that, and that sometimes like, do you get the sensation that
maybe people are like avoiding like being alone with their thoughts for 30 seconds and
don't jumping in their phone so that way they don't have to deal with, you know, being a
human being or something like that.
Like it, I have watched the progression over the last five years where like, I remember
a time where it was kind of considered inappropriate to have your phone at the dinner table in
a restaurant and that was kind of like considered bad taste.
And now I go out and everybody's buried in it and it happens everywhere I go.
I do it.
My friends do it.
My family does it.
Everybody's got their faces buried in these phones and I'm thinking, geez, we already
are so distracted that we don't even look up and just like look up at the moon one day.
We're always looking at our phones.
And so I, I worry that these watches and especially things like Google Glass take it so much further
that it, it actually isn't maybe healthy for the way our minds process information and
it could leave us like, I think over sensitized or overexposed to this stuff.
I don't, for example, particularly want Google Now notifications on my watch.
In fact, I'm thinking about turning Google Now off.
So then that sort of pretty much makes an Android wear useless.
Well, when I look at it, I see two things.
I see one that modern work environment and people have to relocate.
It's kind of why those gadgets feel a gap that it's right there.
It's like people are going to another state to, or living in another country for large
periods of time.
And those devices do feel a gap that they have.
That's a real gap.
That's the real modern world.
And that's when you find most people, but people that are just on the local, sharing
with people that they know and live nearby, it seems that when some time passes, they
eventually start gradually decreasing the usage, especially among friends.
That has been my experience is like people got just bloated.
It was new.
It was shiny.
Yeah.
I could see that.
But if you're dealing with some with actual remote relationships, then it feels a gap.
So you will find that and also like when you go to do a restaurant, you're kind of already
doing something that it's remote.
Gradually with age, people technically, depending on the country, of course, but culturally
also start moving to eating at home, eating with family, eating with friends.
It's not so much the restaurant thing either.
So I wonder if these watches will, could these watches become podcast clients?
Could this be a way to listen to podcasts where you don't have to bring your phone if
you want to go on a walk?
I would be all down.
Well, of course you have to have your phone with these phones, with these watches, right?
All of them require your phone.
What happens if they don't, they can't operate on their own just with minimum functionality,
local functionality?
I think they would like just timekeeping and whatnot.
Well, and maybe media playback.
Like if you could, if you could, you know, put a Bluetooth headphone in or whatever and
listen to a podcast while you're on a walk and not need your phone, I would love that.
I think this will actually push further for mesh networks of Wi-Fi networks.
Oh man.
Wouldn't that be bad-ass if everybody's watch formed a secured mesh network?
Well, why not just do that now with phones, right?
Again, well, we go back to that.
Because you're wasting battery or something important.
That's true.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
At least your phone available for as a communications device.
Yeah.
And also like we're now at the current stage of software as a service that companies do
have an incentive of having you connected at all times, not just through data plans
of telecom because ultimately a lot of other things will start to factor in like because
the amount of devices is also huge and the expansion is not as quickly if you're relying
on just the telephone operators.
True.
Last time I had a watch, they were called Swatch and you know, and before that it was
a calculator watch.
Yeah.
I think that was the 80s.
I'm just not a real watch guy.
I do kind of feel like actually there's a point to that.
Like I kind of feel like maybe I was, I think when the smartphone came out, I was like,
oh finally I don't have to wear a watch.
Right?
I mean, I don't know.
It's just something else for me to break.
I don't know.
Well, there's that and charge every night.
Don't forget that.
Oh gosh.
No kidding.
There is the problem with that as well.
That's it.
I really.
I'm back with chargers and your desk is in place, workplace being filled with those.
Chargers everywhere is what you're saying.
Yeah.
But then it's actually not as easy.
So when you take the watch off, like in the case of the Apple watch, it like doesn't,
it deauthorizes your capability for payments.
It doesn't track your health stats.
Like it becomes significantly less useful when you take it off your body, which you
have to do at least once a day.
Yeah.
When the hell are we going to get decent batteries?
What do you want to pay when you're sleeping though?
People are trying on the battery front.
Yeah.
Whatever happened to that one battery that was actually a capacitor invented by a teenager
that lasts like for all day, if not more.
He was murdered by the oil industry and then they destroyed the, no I'm kidding.
No, no, no.
Him and water car guy went up to another point.
So you know, you asked what would you, why would you want to wear your watch at night?
I track with a Fitbit, I track my quality of sleep.
So I know how I'm doing with my sleep apnea.
And so I actually, a crucial part of the Fitbit is the functionality I use for it while I'm
sleeping.
It's actually, I probably would consider that more important than the step tracking for
me.
So you were saying that there are people who are sat in restaurants out of the house who
can't stop with the digital connectivity.
Oh yeah.
You don't see this?
You're doing it in your sleep.
Everywhere.
I'm not staring at a screen though and I'm not distracted by it.
It's different.
It's more actually what I like about it.
Yeah, that's different.
That's completely different.
Well, cause my point is like it's passive tracking and you go in and get the data when
you want, but these phones and these watches are active, require your attention, distract
you from the fact that something's bad in your mind that you're not paying attention
to or you know, they're like these bursts of like indulgence on let me take a selfie and
make sure I get some likes.
I was kind of pulling your plunker a bit.
But I can see what you're saying.
I was at a wedding a couple of weeks ago and it was in the middle of nowhere and there
was no cell reception at all and there was no wifi.
Nobody had their phone out other than for taking photos of the bride and groom.
The rest of the time everyone was talking, dancing, drinking, having fun.
Wow.
Nobody had their phone out.
It was amazing.
It was the best wedding.
Aside from the fact it was a fabulous steak, it was the best wedding I've been to for a
long time.
We are now reactivating the wifi.
You may now turn your smartphones back on and everybody got quiet.
Shouldn't have a faraday cage over places so you don't connect to anthem.
No, we have trees into the countryside.
That'll work.
That'll do it up here too sometimes.
I was in the ER and I couldn't make a phone call out.
That is a weird thing.
The deal is okay, I need to open a company that just sets up a signal blockers for weddings
and events.
Yeah.
No, they have those already.
We have a post-show topic.
This is an interesting one.
In fact, I didn't put it in the main show because I've noticed almost zero discussion
online about it.
It seems like nobody gives a crap and I care.
So I just wanted to ask.
It's probably important.
Usually it's the stupid crap that everybody gets all testy over.
Right.
Yeah.
Like you two albums being auto-downloaded to phones and things like that.
Exactly.
It's like, oh my God.
Chris, can I just say that I personally guarantee if you buy an Ubuntu phone, we won't force
you to buy one.
Yeah, thank you.
All right.
Deal.
So speaking of buying stuff, Micro Focus has bought AttachMate for $2.3 billion.
Of course, AttachMate is the company that owns SUSE Linux.
Oh, that is kind of a big deal.
Don't you think?
I think so.
Although, SUSE Linux is what percentage of AttachMate though?
Not that much, but I suppose it's still, yes, it matters.
Well, I don't know.
That's what my concern is, is maybe it doesn't matter to them because they make their money
off mainframes and writing cold ball apps.
That's where they make their money.
Check the name.
OpenSUSE has.
Visual cold ball.
That's interesting.
Yeah.
OpenSUSE have posted their response to say basically nothing changes.
Okay.
Good.
I mean, it seems like it would be complimentary to a mainframe business.
I mean, they've got a good strong position there in the market.
Well, yeah, AttachMate group owns SUSE, Novell, and AttachMate.
AttachMate is based in Seattle, Novell is based in Provo, Utah, and SUSE is based in
Germany.
So it's kind of an interesting thing they just picked up.
So they say, yeah, no changes for SUSE are planned.
The business structure and leadership remain.
There's no need for any action taken.
Commitment to open source remains passionately committed to open innovation.
Commitment to open SUSE is fully committed to being a sponsor and supporter of open highly
independent.
I'll just kind of boilerplate.
Yeah.
Well, it sounds like AttachMate bought Novell and then it turns out that didn't make them
any money.
Right.
And so then they had to sell because they had to pay back those loans.
Yeah.
Well, and they sold off a bunch of patents.
So.
Ah, there you go.
There you go.
All right.
Yeah.
So there you go.
There really was not much to say, is there?
It just seems to be really kind of a non big deal.
Yeah.
As long as business continues for the SUSE project, I think everybody's happy.
Do you think the the constant sale of Novell and SUSE devalues the SUSE brand?
Yeah, I think it's weird, too.
I think it's weird that it keeps getting shoved, you know, pushed around like a hooker.
It's everybody thinks that they can make money with it, but it turns out they can't.
Well, but that kind of makes it sound like SUSE is a loser.
Well, she sounds more like a hooker with a PayPal swipe.
I don't know.
You know, at the end of the day, everybody wants to be the next Red Hat because Red Hat
made billions.
Right.
And.
Yeah.
You know, though, I mean, for all we know, it has nothing to do with SUSE.
Maybe SUSE is the only thing that makes any money at all.
Yeah.
In this case, it's it's, you know, a line item that's kind of buried in there.
Well, you know, SUSE is way bigger than Red Hat over in Europe.
I mean, way bigger.
Yeah.
So if you're if you're putting a SAP ERP system in, you're either going to if you're going
to put it on Linux, you're either going to put it on Red Hat or SUSE.
If you're in the US, that's probably Red Hat.
If you're in Europe, possibly SUSE.
Do you.
So, yeah, it could be some big iron.
You asked me, but you didn't answer the question yourself.
Do you think it devalues the SUSE brand?
I think it kind of does.
It does kind of.
It's like the blue headed step chart or the green headed step chart keeps getting pushed
around.
It feels like sloppy seconds to me.
Well, yes.
And the other thing is, it's like when you're trying to pick an enterprise platform to base
like your entire server infrastructure on, stability of the company is a major component.
In fact, some people will pick the stability of the company, IBM or Microsoft, over the
stability of the actual software product.
Right.
That's scary.
Yeah.
And so when you see this keep moving around, it starts to cast doubts because you never
know if the next time it changes hands, if that'll be the time they decide to end it.
Right.
You just never know.
And maybe that would never be the case.
I don't know.
And I actually think the enterprise products are really good product, too.
So it seems like it should be a moneymaker.
But I think this damn Ubuntu LTS thing came around and sort of ate their lunch in the
cloud.
Yeah.
Big time.
Son of a gun.
All right.
So it's interesting to look at Linux's version of long term support and see how different
it is from what companies actually look for.
There's a dig.
It turns out that companies actually want like insane levels of long term support.
Yeah.
Like they want to stick with one version for 10 years.
Well, Red Hat Enterprise, Linux, and CentOS are around for like fricking ever because
they have their long term support.
Well, they're almost five years, I think.
No, more than that.
We're talking like seven or eight.
Well, FreeBSD does five, but CentOS is about the same.
But Zinus is basically making their version of FreeBSD that has 10 plus years of support.
Yeah.
Which is insane.
I think that's meant to compete with HPUX and all that other stuff.
Well, it's specifically to replace the product they already have, which was scope.
Yeah.
So you can actually pay for what they call extended life support on Red Hat.
Well, you actually get patches for 13 years, but you got to pay out the butt for it.
Like $5,000 per server or something like that.
Is that actually a radio button on their web page?
The butt charge.
I like GNU news is good news.
I also like community D debate.
I like all of the system D references.
Man, the people who disagreed with our overall end opinion on our system D discussion, I
were really upset by that.
Did you guys see what we had?
I haven't gone back in there, but that feedback thread is like a record setter for Linux unplugged
in the subreddit.
Does it make me evil that I actually popped popcorn for that when I was reading it?
That's what I should do.
I did too.
I literally did, because I just found it so amusing.
I didn't mean to insult anybody.
Just the interesting views, I was just like, okay.
I don't know what these people think my background is, but I've managed servers for a really
long time, and I think system D is a great advancement for server management.
When I see these server guys that go in there like, I don't want it for my server, I'm like,
are you kidding?
I want it for my servers.
What are you smoking?
Yeah, I just don't get it.
All right, so I'm going to refresh the vote page, and I mean, I understand, honestly,
I don't want to force anything on anybody.
If they want to use OpenRC or whatever, have at it.
I'm fine with it.
Well, here's the problem.
Everyone always gets so fired up about it.
What they really need to be talking about is...