I watched Mad Dog's 50 Years of Unix and Linux Advances talk.
It's great, wasn't it?
That room was so full, it was standing room only.
Yeah, that looked like it was a good talk.
And he made a great point
that if we're gonna call it GNU slash Linux,
we should probably also call it GNU slash Linux,
MIT slash Linux, BSD slash Linux,
insert license here because it's all,
the user land now is full of so many different licenses
that it might be time to update that whole naming thing.
I think I called that a couple of years ago,
isn't it system D slash Linux now?
This is Linux Unplugged episode 287 for February 5th, 2019.
Oh, hi there and welcome to Linux Unplugged,
your weekly Linux talk show
that's hunkered down in a windstorm.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And Wes, you're hunkered down in a snowstorm,
but that's not what we're here to talk about today.
No, no, we have some community news,
including everyone's favorite media player
getting a major update and everyone's favorite desktop.
Well, at least that's what the stats would tell us.
Gnome Shell is getting a major speed boost.
We'll talk a little about open source cryptocurrency crashes,
some big updates in housekeeping,
and then a FOSDEM check-in.
Not only do we have a couple of choice moments from FOSDEM,
but the one and only good smelling Popey joins us.
There's nobody else that smells as good as Popey does.
And he joins us this week to talk about FOSDEM,
maybe his lightning talk and other observations.
In fact, we've got a mumble room full of people,
so we'll see, perhaps they have some experiences as well.
But later on in the show,
something Wes and I've been wanting to do
for a good long while now,
but we've never really had the opportunity,
just never really came up in the cycle of things
until this week.
PiHole, everyone's favorite network-wide ad blocker,
has a big update, version 4.2 this week.
So we're gonna kick the tires,
give you a rundown of PiHole,
how it works, what makes it tick,
the open source projects it's using
to accomplish what it does,
and Wes's experiences giving it a go,
and how you can also install it
and other things besides the Raspberry Pi.
And then we'll wrap it all up
with another excellent pick, as we do.
But before we go any further,
you know what we gots to do.
We gotta bring in that virtual lug time.
Appropriate greetings.
Hello.
We have quite the show today,
so it's appropriate that we have quite the showing.
We have Brent, Bruce, Cubicle Nate,
Dan Rabbit, Foursquare,
Popey, Sean, Skull, TechMav,
ThisGeekTweets, William on his iPhone XS Max,
and Mr. Martin Wimpress,
all joining us in our virtual lug today.
We have the first study group after the show today,
so stick around, guys, and learn some YAML.
I think it's gonna be a great episode.
Yeah, first you get to goof off with us here on Unplugged,
and then we can get some serious studying done.
I think it's gonna be good.
I really do, because we've gotten a lot of interest.
We set up a meetup.
We got people voting on topics.
I'm just gonna say I'm pretty excited, Wes.
Pretty, pretty excited.
Now, I'm in, I think it's like a desert, Palm Desert.
I'm in some desert area in California.
It's like, yeah, it's like Palm Desert.
And you are up at the studio
where we are both in very different weather conditions.
So if you hear a bunch of crazy sounds in my background,
it's not me like throwing things at the dog or wife.
It is a big windstorm,
like 40, 50, 65 mile per hour winds
that are coming at us in three different directions.
We're like in the center of this valley
where all this wind is being funneled in
from the polar vortex, and it's just, it's what it is.
It's gonna be in the background a little bit this week.
Not ideal podcasting weather.
It turns out that is a thing.
Yeah, but I mean, thankfully,
now that Joe is our full-time editor,
anything that sounds weird, you can just blame on Joe.
It's not my fault.
You know, it's not my fault.
He must've just missed it in the edit.
Fix everything in post.
How are you and how are the doggies holding up
in the snow there you have in the Pacific Northwest?
Oh, they're having a great time.
Actually, they really like the snow.
Do they love it?
We went on a big hike on Sunday,
and it was just as the snow was starting to hit.
So we left, trail was clear,
just a nice kind of soggy Pacific Northwest day
by the time we got back covered in snow.
Oh man, dogs playing in the snow, along with kids,
one of the most adorable things ever.
And they get so tired, right?
And then they just take naps later.
It's great, you can get some work done.
It's the best, it is the best.
All right, well, we gotta start the show out
with the breaking news this week.
This is CNN Breaking News.
That's right, right here on the show,
developing as we record,
the plus is being dropped from GTK.
What do you think of this, Wes?
Beg your first, what are you learning now, Wes,
while you're on the scene?
Well, there's kind of a gnarly little commit diff here,
mostly because you have to rebalance
all the careful equal signs
you've placed underneath the titles.
Yeah, yeah, this commit is great
because it's basically the same thing
that's always been there,
but it's just everything without the plus.
So they've removed the plus from everything
and it's a pretty huge commit.
And can I just be the first to say, congratulations?
Congratulations to the GTK team for making this move.
It is high time that the plus dies.
It goes away, it needs to be done.
I find it offensive, I find it revolting,
and I am happy to see it go.
I think this is a move for the user.
This is a move for usability.
And clearly now we should all switch
to Gnome and the GTK stack.
Your thoughts?
It's nice to see them taking things so seriously.
I actually do, I am somewhat serious about that though.
Like I do think it is a much more user-friendly facing look.
I know it's a weird thing to comment on,
but it makes it, when it's GTK+,
I don't know, it's just something about it.
It's a little more techy.
It's sort of like, what does the plus mean?
What's happening here?
GTK at least is some sort of just like
a normal three-letter acronym.
And our lives will never be the same.
Everything has changed.
The story continues to develop.
So you're pleased to see the plus go away from GTK, right?
Oh, I hated it.
I just thought, I was so bothered by the plus, you know?
Okay, what's your opinion on Pop OS?
Wait, is it, wait, the inter-capping,
the underscore or the exclamation mark, which part of it?
Sorry, I wasn't clear.
What's your opinion on Pop OS?
I just wish they'd change it to a dash
instead of an underscore, and then I'd be fine.
That's the thing.
You see, the underscore is part
of the overall brand strategy.
You see, the underscore is representative
of the System76 name,
and they like to have that underscore throughout.
So it's not going away.
It's not going away.
And I think my thoughts on that are clear, actually.
Now, there's everybody's favorite media player,
although I happen to love MPV,
but I did have love for many years for VLC.
Now it's like, we're still, we're still on good terms.
I still haven't installed on my machine,
but it's not my default media player.
Maybe that'll change, though.
If this is coming out of FOSDEM this week,
we'll be talking more about FOSDEM in a moment,
but the lead developer, Jean-Baptiste,
has announced some solid details around version 4.0,
which, among many things, will be sporting a new playlist,
redone user interfaces, a new video output architecture,
which supports VR.
Thank you.
I'm sure Wimpy's been waiting for that.
And the removal of some old platforms.
Oh, yeah, that includes stuff in there,
like 360 degree video,
which I'm sure you're all using 3D audio to go along,
support for the desktop VR head-mounted display,
so stuff like the HTC Vive and Oculus,
and just a whole bunch of stuff for various things,
like better HDR support.
Yeah.
I mean, that I actually kind of think is pretty great,
but probably the most user-facing change
is the new interface.
There will be GNOME and KDE adaptations of it,
but my understanding is this new user interface
is using QML, and it looks very clean.
It looks a lot, actually, like GNOME MPV in some regards.
It's got a transparent play bar down at the bottom.
The playlist looks different.
It's an overlay that you can see through it,
and along with all of the standard GTK and Qt versions,
they'll also make sure it works with client-side decorations,
server-side decorations, Wayland, and X11 as well.
So when you think about what it takes now
to be a full-class, full-fledged desktop Linux application,
this is kind of insane.
You gotta have a Qt version, a GTK version,
an X version, and a Wayland version.
You gotta support server-side decorations
and client-side decorations.
Now, you don't have to,
but every time you don't support one of those,
somebody on one of the distros on one Linux desktop
is gonna be making a compromise.
Oh, yeah, see, I was just thinking to myself there,
like, it's like they're really taking this seriously.
Doesn't the show, like, the project's doing,
must be doing pretty great if they're doing all these things,
but yeah, the flip side is exactly what you're saying.
That's a lot to do.
It is a lot to do.
And, Poppy, I'm wondering, do you think I'm exaggerating
what it takes to be a full-fledged Linux desktop,
or do you think that's the reality of it right now
if you wanna support all that stuff?
I think VLC's in a very particular position
in that they're used everywhere.
It's used on Mac and Windows
and every single Linux distribution,
and they have a lot of work to make it look good
and consistent across all of those platforms,
and I think they do a great job.
I'm also interested to point out
that you can, of course, track VLC
from the Edge channel in the Snap Store,
and you'll get daily builds of version four,
so when this stuff lands,
you'll get it right on your desktop
directly from the developers.
There it is.
That's some good sauce.
So, Dan, what are your thoughts on something like this?
I think this is the problem,
and I honestly think this is something
that elementary OS could aim to solve.
If you really wanna be a full-fledged
Linux desktop application,
there's so many different camps
you need to make sure you make happy.
Qt, GTK, client-side, server-side, Wayland, X11,
and that's not even getting into the actual look
and design of the application.
You know, I remember a long time ago
having a conversation with the CEO over at Yorba
and telling him, you know, this is the future
that the quote-unquote Linux desktop is going toward.
It's not a unified thing.
Like, the Linux desktop is not a platform.
The Linux is a kernel,
and there are so many different desktops.
I think that as application developers,
you should pick a camp,
and cross-platform development is super expensive,
super difficult to do right,
and for most application developers, it's not worth it.
Just write for the distro you use
and be happy that you have a set of users
that like the thing that you made.
Yeah, I feel like what's gonna happen
is developers will look at all the options
and go, eeny, meeny, miny, electron,
and they'll just ship everything with electron.
It'll be like, all right, good enough.
Everybody's happy.
The right answer.
Jesus.
Actually, it's interesting you should say that.
I know we'll come to FOSDEM later,
but there was an interesting talk
about using Go and HTML
to build lean desktop applications
rather than, it was a counterpoint
to big fat electron apps,
and they were talking about how you can use Go
as your runtime and HTML for rendering,
and so there are people exploring different ways
to make cross-platform applications that are not electron.
Oh, give it a couple of years, Go,
plus FFmpeg, plus another interpreted language,
plus a toolkit.
It'll be as fat as mustard before too long.
Yeah, I mean, that's where you get, eventually,
when you want all of the things.
Yeah, hmm.
Well, that does sound promising.
I mean, I think the idea is obviously proven out,
and so now how do we make it as palatable as possible
becomes the next challenge,
and hopefully they can figure it out.
But the thing I didn't hear in all of that was Rust,
so not really convinced.
I've seen Rust on the desktop, a desktop.
Oh yeah?
It was something on Gnome, or?
No, it's Pop OS again.
Oh, okay.
Good, right.
They're trailblazing with the stylized name
and the use of Rust and everything.
That's true, they are.
In fact, there's some Rust fans there at that System76.
That's a good point.
Now, the Gnome shell on the other side of the,
I don't know, on the other side of what,
I guess, I felt like, oh yeah,
because we're talking QML.
There's a lot of good performance fixes coming to Gnome.
The work around Mudder has seen a lot of bug fixes
and performance fixes.
There's different camps involved.
Obviously, canonicals help tackle stutter,
latency, CPU issues within Gnome shell.
That's been, we've seen that trickling in
over the last couple of months,
and I got a hands-on experience with it on Ubuntu 19.04,
and I noticed I actually just could proceed with it.
It is a perceivable performance improvement.
That's the kind of, I mean,
that's the level we're talking about here.
When you can start to perceive it,
that means a lot of things have had to go into that
to actually make that.
Does it also mean, though,
that they kind of needed that sizable of a change?
Ah, yeah.
Yeah, maybe somebody can talk me out of this funk,
but I look at this and I think,
A, very appreciative of this work.
They're doing the people's work here with this stuff.
There's also a developer over at Endless recently
that submitted some performance fixes upstream.
There's multiple camps now doing the people's work,
but it's still really not there,
and the fundamental issue is still that architecture
where it's a lot of things riding on a single process,
from mutter to extensions.
It's just an architecture issue,
and it is definitely appreciated that it is faster
and that it is a better end user experience,
and I'll take that, and I will happily use that,
but I can't help but have this sinking feeling
in the back of my head.
It's still not a workstation-grade desktop.
It still feels very consumer.
I don't know what the right word I'm looking for there,
because I wouldn't even say consumer.
If the architecture is fundamentally busted,
what does it really matter
if it's getting near 60 frames per second animation?
I mean, it matters, but it's kind of like saying
that you have really great appliances,
and you redid your kitchen counters and cabinetry
in your home, but your foundation is crumbling.
I mean, I guess it depends on who it matters for,
and I guess it seems like it has bad foundations to us now,
but at one time, it was probably fine.
I mean, we were just kind of talking the other day
about how just running on a laptop, GNOME does pretty well,
and honestly, on my ThinkPad,
I've had way more plasma desktop crashes
than I have GNOME crashes.
Oh, really?
Yeah, oh yeah, I mean, not major crashes,
but just this morning, I was working on show prep,
and all the title bars disappeared, and I couldn't Alt-Tab.
I couldn't change which window was selected anymore,
and I just had to log out and log back in.
Your server-side decorations died.
It just, yeah, totally gone, yeah.
Whereas with GNOME, by and large, it kind of just worked,
but you're right.
It obviously is running into limitations of its design now,
but maybe it worked for a while,
and it's also probably difficult, too,
because I think we ended up using the older versions of GNOME
in workstation-type things.
It had been really proved out.
It would kind of fit in that space,
and obviously, GNOME's kind of targeting something else now.
I think you're being a little unfair.
There are millions of people right now using GNOME
as their workstation platform.
They're running it for either gaming for consumers,
but also tons of developers have developer-oriented things,
IDEs, Android Studio, Atom, VS Code,
all these kind of applications they're using
on a daily basis to do development on a Linux desktop.
They might not be developing for a Linux desktop.
They might be developing Java business applications,
or they might be developing Android apps,
but there definitely are many, many people using
GNOME Desktop as a workstation machine on a daily basis,
and they get on just fine.
Yeah, I think I have to acknowledge that that's fact,
so there's no getting around that.
It's sort of one of those confidence issues.
It'd be just like if I had a beautiful car,
you open up the hood,
and it was just a mess underneath the hood.
It would betray my confidence in that vehicle
to really carry me the distance.
You probably have other objectives too, right?
Like you don't really care, for instance,
if like the swarm animation got a little more fluid.
You want a desktop that you know is rock solid,
won't crash, and won't ever lose your work.
I've had so few crashes in GNOME Shell.
Like I am the epitome of that person
who leaves their machine on all the time,
like days and days and days and days and days.
I have very long uptime on my GNOME Shell desktop
with multiple screens with very long running applications
that eat tons and tons of memory,
and I almost never restart GNOME Shell,
almost never log out, almost never reboot,
and I cannot remember the last crash that I had.
The most annoying things I have
are actually things to do with the things beneath that,
like the NVIDIA driver.
Like Ubuntu, not Ubuntu, GNOME itself,
it's actually more rock solid now
than I've ever seen it before.
Huh, okay.
You know, you're making me wanna stick with it even more,
which really gets under my skin
because that's gonna make Westpain's prediction,
it's gonna, I mean, I think I still have like a month
to like, to get out of this,
but it's not trending in the right direction.
I have been really impressed.
Now, I haven't gone all cray-cray
with like external video cards and multiple monitors
and stuff like that.
The real pressure test, right?
Right, that's what,
that was where my love affair with plasma started.
It's not that I don't like it still,
it's just that I started to hit up against a set of cracks
that I hadn't encountered before.
And that, so far, I have not fully, fully tested.
I've done a brief test where I hooked up to all the screens
and things seemed like they were working well
and I went, okay, cool.
And I, you know, three hours later, I was done.
Like, but I need to spend days with it still.
So I have a feeling that's gonna happen.
I should write a book about the perpetual distro hopper
and desktop hopper
because I've been doing this now since the 90s
and I don't, I don't know.
I mean, I'm pretty much sticking
with the Ubuntu base these days.
You know, I've slowed down my base hopping
where I was on Arch for a while
and then I came back to Ubuntu.
And like, if I ever jumped again,
it might, you know,
like say like something like Debian or something,
I feel like it would be a good five-year run.
Like I'm slowing down the base,
but the desktops, I'm still at like a six to nine month clip.
How long have we been on plasma, Wes?
I guess it's been since Linux Fest last year.
So it's almost been a year that I made it for plasma.
Now you do seem tempted every now and again
when we review a particularly good Fedora workstation,
I will say.
I think it's been longer than a year
because we were with you in Seattle this time last year
when you did the plasma challenge
and that's when Papi switched.
Right.
Yeah, that's when I did it on the plane
and I still have that same install.
Okay. Okay.
So that is a pretty good run for me.
That's a pretty good run actually.
So I don't have to really beat up on myself
for trying out Gnome again
because that would be a reasonable thing to do
after a period of time is to try out Gnome again
and see if it.
And there it is.
There's the personal acceptance
and where's your protection is about to come true.
Yeah, there's the self-justification.
Job done.
Thank you, gentlemen.
All right.
Well, we've got to talk Bitcoin.
Oh no, please no.
Yeah.
Just, you know, I don't know what you guys make of this.
Is it done now?
So it's around 3,400 US greenbacks
is the average price of Bitcoin.
But if you look at the trading volumes on cryptocurrency
exchanges, they've dipped to new lows in January,
according to an analysis that was published on the 4th.
So that would be yesterday.
Since the beginning of the year,
the digital currency exchanges have reportedly registered
lower trading volumes, marking new lows
that have not been recorded since 2017.
Since 2017 is kind of forever in the Bitcoin world.
That has been a long, long time.
Can I just say I enjoy not having
to talk about it all the time?
That has been nice.
Yeah, you're right.
Coinbase also chimed in and says they're experiencing lows
which they haven't seen since May of 2017.
So what does that tell us?
Is the cryptocurrency hype dead
and we're just seeing like the base market at play here now?
Or is the whole idea kind of over?
I think the more interesting metric
is the cost of Ethereum over the last say 14 months.
Because when the whole crypto boom happened
and people were off buying GPUs
like they were going out of fashion
and driving up the cost of GPUs,
they were mining Ethereum in order
to turn Ethereum into Bitcoin ultimately,
because you can still mine Ethereum on not ASICs.
And that's dropped in price from about $1,400
to a touch over $100 in the same period.
I wonder, so this Geek Tweets,
do you think if we had a killer app all of a sudden
spring up that used Bitcoin, it'd be better off?
You think the issue is that there just isn't really
any sign of a resurgence coming to Bitcoin's aid here?
I don't think there is in terms of financial transactions,
but if there is an application for it then potentially,
but I don't really see one at the moment.
It worked well for me like doing
some actual financial transactions
way back when it was like $200 a coin.
And you know, maybe it was like fast enough
you could get through.
I paid for some like seed boxes and stuff with it
and that was fine.
But these days there's just,
other payment methods have gotten better.
Credit card processing is a little faster.
It's hard to say that there is a killer app out there
besides all the other sort of like distributed
ledger research the bigger companies are doing.
But yeah, I think it's in part that the cost
to get your Bitcoin transaction approved fast
got kind of high as the network got really busy.
But also there's like a dozen different ways now
to easily send cash directly between people,
at least here in the States.
And I think it's even better in some countries
outside the States.
Like for example, the cash application
or Google Pay or Apple Pay,
make it very simple now to just use a messaging system
and send somebody some money.
And that direct person to person transfer,
which is behind the scenes,
really probably ACH transfers between banks
and all kinds of complicated things.
Complicated fronting to make it seem like it shows up.
Right.
That's gotta be happening,
which isn't necessary with Bitcoin.
But the banks are willing to operate at that risk level
and they're willing to do all the behind the scenes work
to make it seem very seamless.
From our perspective with using the cash app,
I could send a hundred bucks to Hadia
in two minutes and she could transfer to her account
in two minutes after that.
And it's essentially as good as using Bitcoin
in that regard.
So you have that downward pressure for consumers,
plus you have the challenges they hit as the network grew,
and then some of the challenges they continue to have
just as the cryptocurrency market matures.
And it really kind of just comes down to your perspective.
If you bought into Bitcoin when it was $11,
when I came to Bitcoin, it was between $2 and $11.
And that's when we started covering it
on the TechSnap program.
And so if you bought in at $11,
then $3,400 is still a pretty fantastic return.
It's not $21,000, but it's still pretty fantastic.
Yeah, the last time I actually paid for Bitcoin,
like bought Bitcoin, I was paying $100 a coin.
So even that is a good return on today's prices.
But I don't think it's gonna last for much longer.
I think it's on the edge of capitulating completely.
Well, Skoll Leader, what do you think?
Maybe the currency goes away,
but the blockchain technology sticks around?
Yeah, I think that most businesses are looking at blockchain,
especially with IoT, as a method of exchange.
And I think that's what's going to stay.
I think Bitcoin is a store of value.
It's just, it's untenable.
The higher it got, the more transactions cost,
the longer it took.
But blockchain is for doing transaction.
I think that's where it's going to be.
Yeah, I could definitely see that.
I think that I could see all kinds of different uses
for business for the blockchain and forks of it,
essentially, it'll be blockchain technology
with their own twist on it.
Yeah, smart contracts, as you're pointing out, Poppy,
I could clearly see that.
Or just between companies
that don't necessarily trust each other.
There's a lot of value in being able to have a document
that they can rely on.
It almost writes its own checks in that case,
at least I think.
So, Dan, I was thinking about it in the context
of taking online payments.
To me, I always thought the ideal situation would be
is if Bitcoin was a successful,
not only just a transfer mechanism,
is what I was going to call it,
but also if it was a stable store of value.
So say it was pegged at $100 US,
and it was that way for five years,
and you knew for five years, one Bitcoin was $100.
I actually thought this would be the perfect way
for open source projects to take in donations
from different currencies,
convert it to one common currency,
and then cash it out in whatever country they're at.
And same with things like app stores.
Do you think that's a legitimate use
for something like a cryptocurrency,
assuming some of those things are standardized
and normalized?
I think some of the big problems we have
is just not technology, but it's also on the legal side.
And so something that we get from a payment processor
like Stripe isn't just the ability to process credit cards,
but they also keep track of things like
which countries are on the US sanctions list
that we're not allowed to do business with,
when the government's going to come after us.
So it's stuff that we have to be really careful with
on the legal side,
and just solving the technology piece
doesn't really help us as a business stay
in the kind of legal area we need to be in.
Right, fair enough.
And when you have things like GDPR and other countries
that are thinking about adopting policies like GDPR,
it's nice to know that there's companies
whose business it is, is to navigate that kind of thing
and make sure that you're not going to get in trouble.
Makes sense, because that's not your core competency.
You've got a distribution to build, you know?
And we don't want to be lawyers.
We don't want to have a big legal team
and do all these kind of things.
So it is really nice to offload that off
onto another team that does want to be in that business.
And it keeps us writing software
instead of doing all these other things.
Right, fair enough.
Well, so you've got to imagine it's things like that
and a million others that are applying downward pressure.
And we just have to wait and see where things fall.
I think ultimately there's a use for the technology.
I think the current price even is ridiculous.
And maybe that's because I've been coming in forever now.
And so I've seen it when it was very cheap,
but to me, really a ridiculous price right now.
And I could see it falling much, much further.
But even if Bitcoins were only worth a few dollars
or a hundred dollars, there's still a market for them.
Some of it's illegal, but there's still a market for them.
And so I don't think they're going away completely.
I want to do a FOSDM check-in
and we got to talk about Pi-Hole.
So let's do a moment of housekeeping first,
just here about midway through the show.
This is a tricky one.
I've never really done this on air before.
Ooh, a big wind, big winds are hitting me right now.
I've never done this on air before,
but I'm going to ask if a few of you
wouldn't kindly mind updating our Wikipedia entry.
It's pretty out of date now.
And there's probably more source material coming soon
that could go on there, like new logos
and descriptions of our hosts,
like Jim and Jason that have joined recently
and Elle, who we just met last week.
So there's a lot of stuff
that we don't have source material for to use from.
So unless you happen to just know it all, I understand.
And don't worry, we are working on that,
but yeah, if you have a free time, free moment,
a free second, a reason to edit Wikipedia
and would like to update some of that stuff that you know,
I'd appreciate that.
Because as you know,
I'm not supposed to be the one to update the entry,
which is understandable, but also kind of silly
because I could just write all that stuff.
I could just write all this stuff that's not on our website,
that's needs to be on our website, but that's cool.
I understand that's how the system works.
Also, looking for somebody who might be interested
in continuing the development of our Roku application.
It seems Roku as a platform is continuing to grow
and our application is very old.
And it is an open source project
that is up on our Jupiter broadcasting GitHub.
Sibo Jar has donated his time so far to maintain it,
but I don't even think he has a Roku anymore.
And we would definitely love to have somebody
help us update that and then, you know,
maybe we would submit it to the store.
I don't really know how that process works,
but that's something that Wes and I are thinking about
is maybe, you know, we have a community maintained
open source Roku app that other podcast networks
could also use to host their shows
or get their shows up on Roku
because that's the thing people like to do.
You know, and a lot of times you just need to like,
sort of, you know, it might have like a tiny little theme
or skin to it and then it's basically implementing
whatever video player they ship in their SDK
and pointing it at one of our URLs.
Yeah, we also have JSON feeds and stuff
that we didn't have before when that application
was originally written.
So maybe there's a different way, I don't know.
So that's just something to think about.
If you want to participate in that, keep in mind,
we also have an art refresh coming to our shows.
So if you do maintain a JB related application,
keep that in mind.
And if you want to get the new art when it is ready,
you can contact Angela or you can join
our Jupiter broadcasting telegram group
for Jupiter developers, which we have linked in the show notes
that Jupiter Dev Telegram,
which I think Wes you're in there, I'm in there.
I sure am. So if you want to work with us
on updating an application or have one that you maintain,
do be aware that new art is coming in the near future
and you'll need to grab that stuff because it's good stuff.
Yeah, but now's a good time to go figure out
like, yeah, what platform should we be on?
What are we missing now and how do we make it happen?
I have been thinking about that.
I have been wondering what other platforms we should get on.
We've gotten, everybody has now, but we're on Spotify
like everybody else is now,
which is kind of cool, I suppose.
And I don't think they re-host.
Have you guys considered using BitChute yet?
I can't remember if we actually got around
to testing or not.
It has been discussed, absolutely,
but I can't remember if we actually got around
to testing it.
I might circle back to BitChute.
And of course we have the PeerTube instance as well.
And now another bit, one more thing.
Well, actually we have two more things,
but something that we just open sourced,
Mr. Wes Payne, software developer and podcaster
and man about town has released FM,
which is a simple script that takes in an RTMP stream
from anything that you can get an RTMP stream from,
and then we'll re-stream the audio of that
to an ice cast server.
Wes, why don't you tell people like how we have this set up,
why we have this set up, like the way it's running,
like all of the, like any of the kind of details
it'd be cool to share, because this is a neat stuff.
You know, I was just, I was just pleased to know
that besides being able to send an RTMP stream,
well, FFFPEG can receive one.
So you don't have to set up a complicated stateful server
to handle all that stuff.
We ran into this problem because, well,
we used to do a lot of video shows.
That's not really the case anymore.
Maybe that will change, we will see.
So our main streaming rig is all set up to operate
around OBS and sending video streams up to scale engine
and YouTube and everywhere else that you can find us.
Turns out we also like to have an audio stream,
especially since we're doing so many audio shows.
Unfortunately, the various things and codecs that play
over in RTMP world, not so friendly over in ice cast.
So we needed a little bridge to connect
our already existing ice cast server
with our live streams from scale engine.
So that's what FM does, it's not super complicated,
but if anyone else runs into that situation,
it might be handy, it just runs on a little Docker file,
runs in a loop, and then once we start a live stream,
scale engine says an RTMP push over to FM.
Yes, it's actually, it's really simple and straightforward
in that West put it all up in a container.
We have it up on a digital ocean droplet
that we run for other things.
So it doesn't take a ton of resources.
It's basically as much as like a VLC would pulling
in a video stream, and then it's stripping the audio
and sending it back out.
And we have that streaming at jblive.fm.
And what's great is it's actually,
I think in most cases ahead of the video streams
because of the way the whole RTMP streaming order
works over at scale engine, like it's the first feed
for jblive.fm, so now our audio streams,
like I think our lowest delay stream.
It'll be right there with RTMP, they'll be real close,
but everything else will be behind.
Yeah, that's pretty great.
And it works great in the mobile web browser too, jblive.fm.
And if you for some reason ever need to take audio
off of the RTMP stream and restream it,
go grab West's open source code.
We have it up on github.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
All right, that's a lot of stuff,
but we're trying to figure out a way to talk about
some of the open source projects we're beginning to release
in a way that doesn't drag down the show,
but still lets you know they're out there,
because what's the point of releasing them
if we don't tell you?
So hopefully this format works.
I suppose in the future, if it was some massive project,
we might dedicate a show to it,
but right now we'll put it in the housekeeping section.
And last but not least, we have the votes open
for a March study group.
We've gotten so many good meetup signups, feedback,
people already beginning to vote
because we've released it earlier.
Like there's just so much feedback already coming in
before we even held the first study group
that we decided we try another one in March
and let you vote on what the topic's gonna be.
There's a couple in there that are really good.
So I'll have a link to that in the show notes
at linuxunplugged.com slash 287.
You know, I see Vim, the improved editor.
That's an option.
I vote for that already,
just so we can finally get you to learn.
The bastard.
How come there's not one on Nano in there?
I should go create a Nano Essentials course.
You have fun with that.
It'd probably be the least viewed course on the platform.
Yeah, there's some good things in here.
Visual Studio Code Essentials course, surely.
Yeah, that would be good, wouldn't it?
The first step when setting up a Linux studio
is to set your editor back to Nano
after Wes Payne's been in there changing things to Vim.
Like I wouldn't notice.
Yeah, there's also LXC and LXD.
Deep dive in here.
Big Data Essentials, if you wanna wrap your head
around that, or DevOps Essentials.
But the one that I'm kinda hoping people vote for
is either Linux, I'm not gonna, I don't wanna sway it,
but I'm just gonna say there's a Git Quick Start
and a Linux Operating System Fundamentals in there.
We'll be doing future study groups on.
And those study groups will be taking place
after Linux Unplugged.
It's not in the show.
It's just, it's not part of the show.
If you wanna join us, go to meetup.com
slash Jupiter Broadcasting for the details on that.
All right, well that's the housekeeping.
So, oh, you know, while we're just talking
about network stuff, Mr. Wes Payne
has been on the Coder Radio program
while I have been in Texas and killing it.
I just think you've been doing a great job.
So if you haven't checked out Coder Radio, coder.show.
Go listen to the last few episodes.
I think the last one was your guys' best episode, Wes.
I think it was a really good one.
Oh, well, thank you.
Having lots of fun chatting with Mike
and getting to pick his weird Floridian brain.
Yeah, yeah, it is that, isn't it?
All right, well, let's talk a little bit
about FOSDEM 2019.
It was something that I had really, really, really
high hopes of attending.
And it did not work out for multiple reasons.
But I did manage to catch a flavor of FOSDEM
by watching the live streams.
Good morning, everyone.
I hope you can all find a seat somewhere.
There's plenty of them available.
So welcome to FOSDEM 2019.
It's a bit more snowy than we expected.
I hope you all got here safely.
But yeah, at least some of you made it, so that's good.
Some of you, like Mr. Popey, made it.
It was a pretty big crowd, it looked like,
from the streams that I saw, Popey.
And I don't know if you got any idea
of how many people attended.
Lots, thousands.
The main room is called Janssen,
and that's where all the keynotes happen.
And the reported capacity for that room
is like 1,400 people, and it was people sat all up and down
all the stairs, so every chair was full.
They were like demanding people move into the middle
of the rows so that everyone could get a seat.
And then there were people spilling out all over the floor,
like people coming in all through all the talks
and sitting all over the floor.
It was a ton of people there, and every room was busy.
Some of them, obviously most of the rooms
are much smaller than that, and it got to the point
where some of the rooms were just rammed all day.
There's like a DNS room, and it was just full
all day, every day.
And if you go to a room, there are people queuing
to get in, waiting to get in.
If someone goes out to the toilet,
they're like busting to get in.
But the good news is every room was live-streamed,
so if you couldn't get in the room,
you could stand outside and get your phone out
or your laptop out, and there were people just standing
around watching live streams or huddled around a laptop
to watch a stream of a room they're standing next to.
It was quite amazing.
Wow, that is an impressive feat.
That is.
I feel like I have a bond now with them,
because I was doing a lot of that online,
and they are also posting a lot of these talks.
It takes a while to get all of them out there,
but they've already posted a whole bunch,
which we will have linked in the notes.
The way they do it is the speaker gets an email
after their talk, and the speaker gets to review it,
and once they review it, it goes live shortly after that.
But it's pretty much all automated.
It's pretty amazing the way they've got it working now.
It's really, really good.
So is it too much?
Is it too big?
Is it too many things?
Like, looking at the schedule,
it just seems there's so much FOMO,
because you can't make it to any of that stuff.
You can only make it to one thing at a time,
and then you add the crowds and how packed the rooms are.
Is it too much?
I think they, I mean, they constantly have to think about
what venue they use, and it is a sizable venue.
There's 63 tracks, 43 dev rooms,
and then there's exhibition space as well with 65 stands.
So there's a lot of space taken up,
and they use a lot of rooms spread across loads of buildings.
You have to hurry from one room to another,
and all you get embedded in one room
for a talk that you want to see in three hours' time,
but you get in there early in order to sit through two talks,
and then, and you might even be watching a talk
from another room while you're waiting for the talk
that you actually want to see coming up.
I mean, it's a bit ludicrous,
but that's mitigated by all the live streaming
and the recorded video that's published afterwards.
So they have an app, so you can sit there
and tag all the things that you want to go and see,
and it will remind you when they're coming,
or it's got a little map,
and it will navigate you to the room you want to go to.
So it's just so well run, really, really well done,
and it's all community run by an organizing committee.
It's not a corporate event by any stretch.
They have a few sponsors.
The university itself in Solbosch in Brussels
is the main sponsor.
Google and Red Hat also sponsor at a high tier,
and then there's like 10 other sponsors, including us.
But it's a major event, and you walk the halls,
and as I'm walking along,
you get that little flutter of celebrity.
You see all your friends,
but also you see loads of other people
from the open source world,
anyone you can name, not just the Uber celebrities
who've been around for years and years,
like John Mad Dog Hall,
but you can see Leonard Pottering,
and people from other podcasts,
and developers who work on that favorite project
that you have.
There's so many people go to this event, yes,
and I'm sure they do their absolute best
to get people in the rooms, but it is very difficult.
So that was gonna be my next question was,
is the MeetSpace meetings,
is it very valuable?
Because I know you're a great person
to ask that question to,
because you've gone to so many different Linux events
in different countries,
and literally all around the world,
and so I'm wondering how this kind of stacks up
that sort of MeetSpace value
compared to some of the other events.
It's great.
It's got one of the better social calendars of any,
because there's opportunity
to talk to so many different people.
I mean, there's also opportunity
to miss conversations with people,
because there are so many people there.
It's not like there's only one person
that you're likely to want to talk to.
I missed conversations with so many people.
I had great meetings with people from the KDE community
and people from the GNOME community,
and bumped into my old boss who now works at GitLab,
and you bump into podcasters who you haven't seen for years,
and it was just lovely to meet up with those people
in corridors and just bump into them,
and people would come up to me and shake my hand.
In fact, it became a running joke of Fosdian with my friends,
because people came up to me and were like,
oh, you're Alan Pope, aren't you?
And I'd shake my hands, really like the podcast,
and to the point where that is now something
my friends say to me in real life.
Oh, you're that podcaster, aren't you?
Just to take the mix.
I have no idea what you're talking about.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, totally.
But it's a great event.
It's so well run, and the facilities are great.
There's food and drink nearby,
and there's public transport.
You can get a tram or a bus,
or if you have to, you can get an Uber.
And there are even little Lime scooters
you can jump on and scoot around the place.
It's really worth going.
And there's so many great talks as well.
So they have tracks for loads of different subjects,
but obviously there's keynotes
that are definitely worth seeing.
And there was one at the very start
with Bradley Coon and Karen Sandler talking about,
is it possible to live a life of only using free software?
And talking about the challenges that come with,
you know, if you work for a company
that mandate you shouldn't demand
that anyone has to use proprietary software,
that you should only use free software if you possibly can.
You know, it's quite a challenge to do that,
and I'm sure many people appreciate that.
And there are other talks like the Tor project
gave a talk about the state of Tor,
and the Matrix project talked about
how Matrix is being adopted by French government,
and they're using it internally,
and the amount of changes they've had to make,
and user interface changes to Matrix
in order to facilitate that.
And it's, yeah, there's so many talks,
but the great thing is, because it's archived,
I can queue them up and sit and watch them later.
True.
I'll link to the John Mad Dog one,
because that would look like just,
I watched the whole thing live.
It was 50 years of Unix and Linux advances.
And it's really poignant right now,
especially in the age of the cloud.
I don't know if I 100% agree with all of his conclusions,
but if he isn't just one of the best speakers
in our community.
Right, that was like sitting around the campfire
with granddad telling you stories of the last 50 years,
but the grandchildren being like 2,000 of them in the room.
And it was very well received, that talk.
Yeah, I think it's one of my favorite random moments
that's ever happened to me still,
is when I was at Linux Fest Northwest many years ago,
while we were live on air,
the guys around the booth funneled John Mad Dog Hall
down to sit next to me.
And I just got this completely unplanned,
unexpected interview with John Mad Dog.
And it was just great.
I just really enjoyed the conversation.
And I noted in his talk that he said he's going
to stop traveling around to these events in 2025.
So there's only a few more years of this.
So I will have that linked in the show notes.
Also, I'll have linked in the show notes,
Mr. Popey did a lightning talk.
So you were in the lightning talk track.
What was that like, being involved in that process?
So that is interesting,
because like most conferences I go to,
lightning talks is like they set aside a portion
of a day for lightning talks.
But no, not FOSDEM, it's like all day, both days,
Saturday and Sunday, solid lightning talks all day.
And so there's a constant change.
There's like your 15 minute talk
and then five minutes changeover.
15 minute talk, five minutes changeover.
And they are strict, super strict.
There's a clock, like a little, I don't know if it's Arduino
or Raspberry Pi based digital clock on the desk,
which faces both you as the speaker
and it faces the audience.
So everyone knows whether you're going to overrun or not,
and they don't let it happen.
So it's very much kept to time.
And so I went in the room that I was going to be in,
that I was giving my talk in a few talks ahead of time.
So I was well prepared and I could make sure my slides worked
and laptop worked and all that kind of stuff.
And I learned some things.
For example, there was a lightning talk
about an application called Monica
that I had never heard of.
And I'm sure most people haven't heard of it.
And it's a thing I totally need
and I never knew I needed it.
It's like a personal relationship manager, they call it.
It's a database in which you can put all your memories,
like remembering who that cousin is married to
and what the names of their children are.
And when was the last time you went out with this person
and when's so-and-so's anniversary
and all those things that you try and keep in your head
and you forget.
And you know, like when you get old, you forget that stuff.
And it's all local, it's all stored internally.
It's never meant to be shared.
It's not like Facebook, it's not social network.
It's just a little bit.
And I'd never heard of this.
And the guy gave a lightning talk before I went on.
And I was like, this is fantastic.
This is exactly why I come to FOSDEM
because learn about stuff
that I would never discover otherwise, it was brilliant.
And then I gave a lightning talk and it was all right.
So yeah, it was good.
Now, do you have to, so you have to,
for the lightning talks,
is it like you have to stick to the 15 minutes no more?
Is it 10 minutes?
Yeah, it's 15 minutes and then a five-minute changeover.
So you got an ability way to get off the stage
and get back on and the next one to get on.
I burned through my slides in about 10 minutes
and left time for questions
because whenever I talk about snaps and SnapCraft,
there are always questions.
It's never like, oh, that was interesting.
And then everyone gets up and leaves.
What's the most common,
like when you're in a group setting,
what's the most common one?
So usually there's something about security,
something about the fact that you're bundling libraries in
and who's responsible for security.
So that question came up.
There was a question this time
about parallel installs of snaps,
like having multiple snaps of different versions
on the system.
And I didn't realize that that feature
has actually landed like this weekend.
So I said, oh, it's coming and it's actually all right.
That worked out.
And then there was the inevitable question I always get
is how does this compare to Flatpak?
Which like, please, could you compare this to Flatpak?
And I had two and a half minutes left on the clock
and I was like, no,
I'm not gonna compare them in two and a half minutes.
So yeah, I kind of ducked that one,
but it was really, really good.
Really, really good.
That does make me wanna make sure I try to get it
to a FOSDEM 2020.
Wow, 2020, geez, that's crazy.
Yeah, it's the 20th one next year, I think.
Joe always says it's the worst time of year to travel though
because everybody's sick.
Did you manage to avoid the con crud?
I haven't come down with anything yet.
I did notice a few likely patient zeros
who were kind enough not to shake my hand
and they realized they were patient zero
and didn't wanna spread it.
But you know, it's very difficult
when you're in a room full of people.
But the travel, I went on the Eurostar.
So I just get a train from my place to London,
which is like 45 minutes and then cross London,
it's like 20 minutes on the underground
and then get on the Eurostar
and it's a train direct from London
all the way through the Channel Tunnel,
through France, into Belgium,
get out, quick cab ride or bus or tram
and you're at the hotel, it's fantastic.
It's a great way, if you're coming from where my house,
it's great.
If you're coming from where you are, Chris,
maybe not so much.
Yeah, no, no, it's not.
It's a slight distance difference, I guess.
It's also important to understand
that Joe is something of a delicate flower
when it comes to conference attendance
and getting sick and being concerned about getting sick.
So you need to bear that in mind as well.
Hey, as the boss, I gotta respect the fact
that the man wants to make sure his voice is functional
because I got a lot of shows that go out of business
if he's too sick.
Also, he is a bit taller than me
and he is a bit cramped on the Eurostar
unless you're able to play a little bit extra.
Actually, the fact that Chris has never met Joe,
it's gonna be interesting to see that first encounter
when Chris is staring squarely at Joe's navel
when they meet for the first time.
Yes.
Brent, you had a great question to ask Poppy.
Yeah, my question actually was
with Linux Fest Northwest coming up.
I know it's the 20th anniversary
and I just wondered if you think that the rooms
will be just as packed with how it's the 20th anniversary
and how that's gonna affect sort of that closeness
that it feels like at Linux Fest Northwest.
That's one for you, Chris.
I've never been to Linux Fest Northwest.
This is my first time.
You'll be able to answer, won't you, soon?
Yeah, yeah, totally.
I think what your answer would be,
and I'm just gonna guess,
it would be great if we could remember to go back to this,
but I think what your answer would be, Poppy,
is that the size is much more manageable
at Linux Fest Northwest.
You can find a seat,
you can make your way to a talk in time,
but there's just also not gonna be necessarily
all of the same selection.
And that's the tricky part about some of these
is the thing about FOSDEM is it's kind of a unique event
in the sense that there's some folks
that only make the trip to FOSDEM,
just like there's some folks
that only make the trip to Linux Fest
or only make the trip to Scale.
That's why they're all unique.
Same with all the different events.
So I bet that would be your takeaway,
but I might be wrong.
I don't wanna put words in your mouth.
Yeah, Chris, I think the crux of my question
is judging by how last year was pretty full
and this year there's, only in this chat room,
there's a bunch of people coming
for the first time from overseas.
I know, we're freaking a big crowd this year.
Is that an indicator of what might happen, right?
I mean, I hope so.
The Bellingham Technical College is a large campus
and they've been very generous.
Perhaps they'd open up more space, more space in the future.
You know what they need to do
is they need to adopt a policy like FOSDEM has.
Out of all of the events I've gone to,
I've never heard this line before.
Please also make sure to clean up after yourselves.
Like, that's, that's fantastic.
Yeah, us nerds, we're not always the cleanliest people,
are we?
Yeah, and because you can buy beer and Club Marte,
there's always glasses clinking around
as people are like moving in and out of the room.
As people put the glass down on the floor,
there's nowhere else to put it.
I've just put an image in IRC
you might want to have a look at.
It's, you can find this yourself
if you do an online search for FOSDEM Richard Stallman
preaching to the converted, I think the image is called.
And it's a panorama of the main room, Jansen.
And so that room, that photo,
if you go and find it is from 2005 and it's Richard Stallman.
I was there, I'm right at the back of that picture.
And when Mad Dog was there this year,
you imagine every single one of those seats full.
This room isn't full in 2005, all of that full
and people all the way up the stairs either side
and sat around the front as well.
It was mad.
I will put a link to the 2005 photo in the show notes
so people want to compare.
Yeah, you're right, that's a good point.
I think when it's a community event,
it also leaves room for slight rough edges.
Going back to the cleanup thing, I laugh,
but they have a real community attitude about it.
We have to pack up tomorrow in about two hours time.
We have to be out of the buildings
come nine o'clock tomorrow evening.
So there's not a lot of time to do the cleanup.
If you do the bulk of the work,
that leaves less work for us.
So we'd be very grateful if you would do that.
It's not only is it something
that you just wouldn't really hear in the States,
like there's their general attitude about the event.
It's not the same attitude that you have here in the States.
So it's different in that regard,
but it really does have that community feeling to it,
even watching from afar.
So thank you, Mr. Proby for the recap.
I love living vicariously through you.
I wish I could have made it.
Well, I would encourage your listeners,
if you get an opportunity next year,
you might want to book early to avoid disappointment.
You don't have to pay for tickets, by the way,
it's completely free event.
You can, it's just got to pay for your travel
and accommodation, but book early,
because I suspect it's going to be even more full next year.
So you might want to make sure you can get accommodation
and all that stuff at a time
and look out for the announcement
when that comes later in the year.
Very good.
Let's take a moment in the show now
and talk about the new release of Pi-Hole.
Pi-Hole version 4.2 is now available with shared memory,
new blocking modes, and much, much more.
And Mr. Wes and I were chatting before the show.
We said, this is it.
This is now our chance.
Talk about Pi-Hole.
And you did a deep dive, Wes.
You went all in into the Pi-Hole.
Oh yeah, I'm stuck down in there now.
It's running on my laptop.
It's running on my network.
I can't escape.
So did you really?
Okay, so you did a laptop install.
I mean, not to throw us off course here,
but maybe that's not a bad place to start.
Like this isn't actually something
you have to install on a Raspberry Pi.
I think everybody knows that,
but this is proof positive right here.
Yeah, it's kind of a little bit different of a project
because it doesn't come on like an SD card
that you just flash and stick into your Pi.
It's really just an installer script.
So they have a set of supported operating systems.
And honestly, it's pretty wide.
Raspbian, Ubuntu, Fedora, Debian, CentOS even.
And on most of those, they also support ARM.
So whether you wanna use the script
on your Raspberry Pi or on your server,
it doesn't really matter.
It just sets everything up the same.
Yeah, so Pi-Hole is a network-wide
DNS-based advertising blocking appliance.
It uses several different technologies like DNS mask,
which is a lightweight DNS server.
It can also do DHCP.
Uses curl for transferring data
with different URL syntaxes between things.
HTTP D for the web server to manage it.
PHP, which is the web interface I believe is written in.
And the admin dashboard is based on admin LTE.
All of that sits on top of Linux.
Using these open-source technologies
to intercept DNS requests and use what's called,
I think the Pi-Hole comes from DNS black-holing of things.
Wes, that's where the name comes from.
It's essentially a DNS black-hole
for things like ad sites and malware and whatnot.
Yeah, exactly.
So usually what you do is you install on a Pi
or in a VM or a container.
Or sync-holing, sync-holing.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
And so once you've done that,
you usually update your router to push a DHCP option
that says like, hey, go use this for DNS.
Or you could obviously go manually edit
your DNS configuration on whatever client you wanna use.
Right, you do have to adjust your client DNS.
That's a good point to mention, right?
Because otherwise, if you're not doing it the DHCP level,
then you need to go adjust the DNS
at anything that you want to use this thing.
Yeah, exactly.
Go point it at whatever IP you've given
wherever you installed it.
And then from there, it's got a modified,
a forked version of DNS mask that it's using
to go block all these things you can load in.
Honestly, the web UI, it's pretty decent.
They've got these fun little glowing counters.
So every time it blocks a new request,
you get, you see that kind of count up
and you're like, oh yeah, more ads that got killed.
And it makes it easy too.
Like you could do this, obviously,
I mean, I run DNS mask.
I'm sure many of our listeners do for exactly those things,
DHCP, DNS, but their forked version's got some improvements.
And with the web UI, it makes it really easy
to go manage what block list you're using,
kind of tweak that.
Cause maybe you, maybe you're really privacy conscious
and you want to block every single thing from Facebook,
all their IP space, anything,
even remotely associated with it.
That works for some people, but kind of would hurt,
you know, if your kids are on there
or your family members, that's not gonna work.
Yeah, well, if you use like, for example,
there's a bunch of default lists
that you can subscribe to during the installation.
And when you subscribe to just those defaults,
there's even parts of YouTube that don't render quite right.
And there's not as much of a direct action as you can take
when you're using an ad blocker in your web browser,
cause you could just go to the toolbar
and turn it off for a brief moment.
Then the broken webpage renders properly.
When you do it at the network level,
there's a little more work involved to fix that.
But the advantage is A, you don't have to install
ad blocking software on the individual end machines,
but B, it's also preventing tracking and advertising
on any of the devices on your network.
So a smart television, your phones, your tablets,
things that aren't web browsers
that you can't install ad blocking extensions into
can also be protected.
And that's even more important now with smart televisions
that basically ship from every manufacturer
that monitor what you do.
That's really nice.
And it's not 100% peace of mind,
but it's a bit more peace of mind.
Well, that's a great point.
I wouldn't, you know, I'm not gonna remove
any of the like application specific ad blockers.
Cause kinda like you said, you know,
because they block it at a DNS level,
you do sometimes see a space that was made for an ad
that was supposed to be there, but doesn't load.
So you don't see the ad, but it's not quite as seamless
as some of the fancy ad blockers we have today.
But with all the changes we've seen,
browsers making some moves to make that harder,
it's a nice fallback that you can have
at the edge of your network.
And like I said, if you just have,
if you just have like a stock router
that you got from your ISP,
and you're not already managing your DNS and DHCP,
and you're all interested, this is a great first step.
Cause it's all the same technology under the hood
with a nice interface to manage it.
And even if the ad blocking isn't perfect,
it still does those other services.
So you only have something to gain.
And there is a moderate performance improvement
if you switch from checking a DNS lookup
across the internet versus checking for that DNS lookup
on your local LAN.
It's just a faster response time.
And DNS mass will start to catch those things.
And then when another machine looks up google.com,
it doesn't go all the way out to the internet or your ISP
or Google DNS, it can just get it from your
local DNS mass server.
But I guess the skeptic in me
would be listening to this right now.
And I would challenge this, Wes, I would say,
why not just use something like my own local files,
like Etsy host and others where I could,
I could create my own sinkholes.
And I could essentially do what Pi-hole is doing
just using my local configs.
Yeah, you certainly could,
but I honestly, I don't see you doing that.
Whereas using the GUI for Pi-hole, you probably would.
And you're always gonna have devices,
maybe you're just trying out a new distro
or you've opened something in incognito tab
and you forgot to enable the specific ad blocker extension
in incognito, will you still get all the benefits?
So you could still do it, but like they have it pretty easy.
People have a lot of scripts out there
that have compatible blocking lists.
And actually, Poppy makes a great point.
You can also add whitelists if you're having trouble
or you always wanna know like all the requests to work,
always allow those.
Yeah, I use Pi-hole at home.
And one of the things we do is send out
some marketing emails and we use a third party service.
And unfortunately that's blocked by Pi-hole
because for some reason people think that's spam.
And I need to see those.
And so I just whitelist that service on my Pi-hole
so that I can see it.
But the thing you won't do, I mean, you could,
you could just go and put like these big lists
of blocked hosts in your Etsy host file and you're done.
Right, you could do that.
But you've got to keep that up to date
and Pi-hole has an automatic update system, right?
Also Pi-hole has a really nice reporting system.
So you can actually see the top blocked domains,
the top rated domains, top clients on your network.
So I can see which machines on my network
are doing the most DNS requests and where they're going.
And I can make decisions that can affect the decisions
I make about the software that I install
or services that I enable and what extra things
I might want to take belt and braces to block.
I think it's an amazing project and the guys behind it
have the absolute best intentions for it.
It's just such a wholesome project, it's fantastic.
I love it.
That's a great point.
It is, I mean, kind of, it's just DNS mask on steroids,
but with a whole bunch of supporting community members
and a lot of active development.
Chris, you also found, so like part of that is
they've been working part of this update
is using shared memory to make exporting
all the statistics they gather more efficient.
And then they're implementing a Rust API
to just be able to grab that.
Part of that means you can also have things
like this neat little GTK control panel you found
that'll show you all the things that you're blocking.
Yeah, right there on your desktop,
you can get the stats from your Pi-hole system.
Oh, really?
Yeah, isn't that neat?
Yeah, it's a GTK Python app.
I had no idea.
I'm logged into the web admin tool
and I look at the pretty graphs
and I see spikes at certain times of the day
when I know I've got cron jobs
that are doing loads of busy stuff
and I can see when the kids come home
because all their devices, IP addresses start showing up
and I can see they're all using YouTube
and Snapchat and Instagram and all that kind of stuff.
I just love it.
And the web admin tool is nice.
It's good enough, that's all you need.
I just, I dropped a link to it in the IRC,
but I'll also, I'll put a link to it in the show notes.
Awesome, I'm totally getting that.
Now, the other thing that I was curious about
is we've gotten a lot of emails from the audience
about using this in a FreeNAS VM or on a PF
or doing like a KVM box with PF sense in a VM,
FreeNAS in a VM and Pi-Hole in a VM.
And each one of these, obviously,
each one of these use cases,
they're not using a Raspberry Pi at all,
but they're taking advantage of the automated installation
where it walks you through
how to get all the subscriptions,
how to just set all that up.
And obviously they're taking advantage of the updates.
And it's still a very much like an appliance.
So you don't have to run it on a Raspberry Pi,
but you can just get the image
and then flash it to the Raspberry Pi.
But they've also now started shipping it
as a Docker container as well.
That's what I'm using to run it on my laptop.
And honestly, it works pretty well.
You gotta go fiddle with a few environmental variables
and supply those with your like,
the IP address of the machine that Docker is running on,
stuff like that.
But honestly, they have decent instructions
and it just works.
Now do be aware,
they've only recently got the cadence switch
so that when new releases come out,
new Docker builds are available,
but the Docker files aren't that complicated.
You can build it yourself.
And the kind of the question
when you look at all of those emails that came in,
the core of it is,
could this work for an enterprise LAN?
And when you look at the underlying technology
like DNS mask and whatnot,
it absolutely holds up.
It really just depends on the resources
of the machines you deploy it on.
You could absolutely use this
to provide ad blocking and malware blocking
across an entire LAN of employees.
I think you could certainly test it out
on a subset of your estate,
like try out on the techies first
and then add this to your DHCP leases
for some parts of your user base
and slowly roll it out.
And as you add departments,
you'd find,
oh, well, so-and-so in accounts
needs access to this thing
and we need to add a white list for that.
So I certainly think if you rolled it out
in a managed way,
you could use something like this, definitely.
Yeah, you could just,
initially a handful of users
where you switch their DNS manually
and just see how that goes for even one lease cycle
of the DHCP lease.
You could just see what happens.
And the admin is really easy.
While I've been talking to you,
I remembered, oh, I haven't updated it for a while.
So I just SSHed into my Pi
and ran Pi-hole-up
and it's updated while I'm talking to you.
It's brilliant.
That's cool.
So what do you think, Wes,
after trying it out for the show,
are you gonna stick with it at the home network?
Yeah, I think so.
I mean, I really don't see why not.
I've been doing some rebuilding in the home network anyway,
simplifying things.
And I like having, right now,
my DNS and routing stuff
is a little too commingled for my tastes.
And if I can have an appliance that does the same thing,
I'm in.
Mm, I like that.
We'll have some of Wes's notes
linked in our Linux Unplug blog,
which is linked up at the top of linuxunplug.com site.
And he's got information here
about versions that they officially support
that aren't on Raspberry Pi on there,
whitelist, blacklist information,
how to run the Docker container,
how to add additional block lists,
how to just grab the PyHole installer
and run it on your own Linux, all of that.
So that, as well as additional resources,
are linked in the show notes.
And please do let us know your experiences with it.
I know it's been around for a while.
It's on us that we haven't talked about it, really.
That's our bad.
And so this was our chance to do it.
Let us know your experiences, linuxunplug.com slash contact.
And I don't know, Mr. Payne,
is there anything else we should relay about PyHole
and the new version 4.2?
No, it's really easy.
If you're interested in trying it out,
there's no reason not to.
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
Yeah, it gets the Linux Unplug seal of approval.
And I have a sense we'll be talking about more
in the post-show.
But I do wanna head out of here with an app pick.
It's great to see it if you've decided to spend the money,
like Mr. Wimper's has, on a nice, fancy Nvidia card.
And you look over at the folks on Windows
and you see them with their graphical overclocking tools.
And you think to yourself, why?
Why can't I have that?
I am green with envy.
Well, I have good news for you
because that is a new tool designed
to let you manage your fans, your CPU,
I guess the GPU of your Nvidia card under Linux.
And it's literally called Green with Envy.
And Joey has a great write-up with some screenshots
over at omgabuntu.co.uk if you wanna check it out.
You'll generally get general CPU stats,
I'm sorry, GPU stats, power, clock information,
like the rate, GPU temperature, the fan speed.
You can set up custom fan profiles.
You can view historical data.
And yes, yes, you can overclock.
Finally, Mr. Wimperis, are you gonna give this a go?
No, cause it's easier to do through the API and the script.
Oh, okay.
So I've already put the effort in.
Yeah, I've got a script and yeah.
I mean, certainly having a GUI is a great thing, right?
Because when you buy the Nvidia cards
and you get your Windows drivers from insert name
of board partner of Nvidia,
they have their own skin on top of the drivers
and their own overclocking utilities.
And they're all pushing the same parameters around.
It's all about clock speed, memory frequency,
fan profile and power limit.
They're basically the four things that you can tweak.
So, and you can do that through Nvidia settings
and Nvidia SMI and stuff like that.
But having a GUI, which reproduces the custom UIs
that you see on these board partners, Windows drivers
is no bad thing.
And it's a little bit more computing parity
for Linux users.
Yep.
Completely agree.
I don't actually think I'm going to do it,
but I'd love to see it.
Oh, you should totally do it.
Really?
Oh, I'm squeezing tons more performance
out of my 1080 Ti with this.
Really?
It's astonishing.
Yeah, I've got over a gigahertz memory clock uplift
on my 1080 Ti.
And I think between 350 and 500 megahertz core clock,
and that requires that you up the power limit.
So the power governor for Nvidia cards is quite constrained.
And so you push the power limit up,
which means you can push more juice into the card
in order to support those clock and memory frequencies.
And then of course, to do that,
you then need to configure the fan profile
to make sure you don't burn the thing out.
So yeah, all the tools are there.
Not even sure if my GPU doc has a fan.
So what I have discovered is if you've got
mobile Nvidia things,
so the sort of the M series from the nine,
you know, the nine series and the 10 series
and the max Q stuff.
So far, I've only got a few of those available to me.
So far, you're not able to overclock those.
Even if you turn on all the magic bits
to strictly enable that,
when you actually try and poke at those values,
they all come back as their read only
and you can't actually change them.
So question for the audience,
have you got a max Q or a mobile series Nvidia chipset
and have you figured out how to overclock it?
If so, come and join us next week and tell us how.
Tell us how to do that.
That would be really good to know.
Well, all right.
So hey, while I've got you for a moment,
I saw there was a flash update
over on the Ubuntu podcast feeds,
a flash podcast with a very important announcement
about a community meetup on March 16th, that's a Saturday.
What do people need to know?
Yeah, we're breaking with tradition a little bit
this year on the Ubuntu podcast
and we're gonna have a listener get together
ahead of the next season to have a chat with the listeners,
find out what they like, what they like to hear more of
and use their feedback to go into our curry meetup
where we decide what we're gonna do for the coming year.
So yeah, it's gonna be in Reading in the UK on March 16th.
If you go to, oh goodness,
if you go to ubuntupodcast.org
and look at the most recent episode,
all of the links to where you need to go to sign up
and register to that event are there,
but we're currently sorting out the final location
at the moment and details will be posted soon.
Very good.
Speaking of March, we will be at scale,
scale 17X, March 7th through the 10th.
Mr. Payne, Al and myself will be there.
Any of your friends from Canonical
going to scale this year, gentlemen?
Maybe. Yes.
Yes, certainly people are going.
We're just trying to figure out who is going.
We'll let you know.
Oh, very good.
Well, there you have it.
Last minute updates here on the Unplugged program.
We start with breaking news
and we end with in-development last minute updates.
So ubuntupodcast.org for more information on that.
Go join Wes Payne and Jim Salter
on the revamped TechSnap show Better Than Ever
with new details about ZFS rebasing on Linux
and much, much more.
Where can they find you on Twitter, Mr. Payne?
I'm at Wes Payne.
Beautiful, I am at Chris LAS.
The whole network is at Jupiter Signal.
If you're listening live, stick around
because we're about to kick off
our first ever study group.
I am super excited about that.
If you want to know more about when we're doing those
and other kinds of meetups online or in person,
you can go to meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting
for all of those.
Thank you so much for joining us
and we'll see you back here next Tuesday.
I really do appreciate your time with us.
well thank you everybody for joining us thank you mumble room for being here
enjoyed that show that was amazing and boy look at the size of that mumble room
it's just warms my heart it's huge it's great so the link that Martin couldn't
remember is get together dot community it's a website that Michael Hall ex
community manager at the canonical and now works for the Linux Foundation on
Ajax foundry he has created this in his spare time it's like a an alternative
free software alternative to meet up oh that's great that is really really good
what is it again get together dot community have you seen I I don't know
if you how much you've plugged around in the Linux fest Northwest website but
that is a whole event system that was created by the open Sousa folks like
it's a whole CMS for events it's MIT licensed and it's up on github Wow yeah
it's called OS EM and it's on the open Sousa github reports the open source
event manager an event management tool tailored to free and open source
software conferences so it does like the the speaker papers so all of us that
have submitted talks it's you're using that system for people that are just
registering to go the whole thing's an open source platform it's pretty neat