So, it doesn't really fit in with the show, but does anybody have a way they've been impacted
by this Amazon AWS outage that's going on right now?
As we record, AWS and its related services are down for many people.
Chadron's been talking about it for the whole show, pre-show.
I have my customers.
Who had customers?
What happened?
I have a bunch of customers that use AWS to host their PBXs, or dialers, or CRMs in.
Yeah, I think that happened to Ting.
Ting was knocked off.
Their call center was knocked offline for a bit.
They're still able to do web chat and email support.
Yeah, it's interesting.
You can actually see 5,000 calls dropped down to about 3,000 calls, and you're just like,
what just happened?
Yeah, every time this happens, I really am just sort of shocked at the massive dependence
on Amazon.
It is the underlying infrastructure for a lot of the services I use.
Just before the show started, I was trying to get a screenshot for the show notes, and
I tried two different imaging sites that were offline because of AWS being down.
We get asked all the time why we don't host our switch because our switch is all cloud-based
and Amazon.
This is why we actually have our own data centers and our own cloud infrastructure
around ourselves.
Really?
Even though this only happens like once every year, a couple of years, you still feel like
it's worth it, huh?
If your telecom went down once or twice a year because of this, or had problems routing
to the customer...
Yeah, telecom.
Boy, that's a tough choice.
Yeah, you're right.
Telecom and medical, just the cost differential there is, I got to imagine, I mean, thousands
and thousands of dollars a month just for a data center.
Not really.
I mean...
Shut your face.
I'm serious.
When you map it out for the amount of bandwidth, I mean, we're connecting to 10Git connections,
you just can't compare...
AWS, if I went to them and said, I want 30 or right now, it takes about 30 to 40 images
to run each site.
I want 30 images and I want a 10Git connection.
It doesn't, you know, even buying hard $40,000 worth of hardware every year isn't going to...
Yeah, you know, that does add up.
I agree.
That does make sense.
Hmm.
I wonder, I wonder every time this happens, I think to myself, is this the time that people
are going to start looking at other options?
You know, you have to think too, like, even just differentiating a bit.
So not going all crazy and just saying like, no more Amazon, I'm done with Amazon forever,
but just saying, well, I'm going to put some backup resources on DigitalOcean or I'm going
to put some additional storage on ScaleEngine.
It seems like, it just seems like this is...
Every time this happens, I have this conversation and everybody goes, yep, yep, that's the way
to do it.
Yep, yep, yep.
And then another AWS outage happens and here we are, nobody's done it.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 186 for February 28, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that has so much breaking news this
week, you might as well just call me Shep Smith.
My name is actually Chris.
Hey, Shep.
This is Wes.
Thanks, Wes.
Thanks for going with it.
What's your new name now?
I kind of lost steam and then I realized, if I go as Shep, do I have to try to do an
accent?
Oh, yeah.
Okay, maybe I'll spare everybody that then.
We do have a really great episode.
So much stuff has happened literally as we're recording today and I'm not even talking about
the big AWS outage, no, no, no, we have big news stories on items and gadgets and projects
that we love.
Oh my.
Yeah, really.
And all of them are like things that everybody's been buzzing about this week.
So we'll jump into that, get those all banged out for you guys right away so you'll get
your veggies right up front.
Ooh, tasty.
Then we're going to reignite the debate.
Is swap on modern systems actually necessary?
I kind of felt like we had this settled and then Red Hat released this big old document.
Red Hat weighs in with their official documentation and advisories.
Those guys.
Oh my goodness.
And then later on in the show, Telegram, some perhaps shenanigans afoot.
It looks like what was once promised to be open source may actually be closed up.
Now they haven't said anything officially, but the tea leaves look bad.
We'll cover that if you're a Telegram user, it's going to be relevant to your interest.
And then Noah warned us all, but an internet connected teddy bear has leaked millions of
voice messages and passwords.
We'll tell you what went wrong, what the fundamental issue is with this particular type of approach,
and the details, and also the horribly awkward video that walks users through setting up
the worst security ever.
Oh, I'm excited.
And then Wes, I think this might all just be for me.
So I hope the audience enjoys this, but at the end of the show, we're going to have some
fun with G-Streamer.
I recently just went on a big G-Streamer purge on my main Archbox.
Get it out of here.
I'll talk about the problems it's causing, I'll talk about how you can fix it if you're
having your G-Streamer woes on Arch right now.
And then Wes has been playing around with some really cool stuff powered by G-Streamer,
which maybe, maybe will make me kick that dirty old FFM peg to the curb.
I'm kidding.
I love FFM pegs.
Everyone does.
All right.
Before we get into all of our breaking news, let's bring in that mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings, mumble room.
Hello.
Wow.
Yeah.
That's how you do it.
I like that.
Nice one.
That was really good.
All right, guys.
Let's start off with our breaking news.
This is the one that people have been talking about maybe almost number two in the chat
room today.
It is the Raspberry Pi Zero W. A $10 computer with with it and Bluetooth built right in.
Raspberry Pi Zero W. The W signifies exactly what is new.
Wireless connectivity.
I thought it was for Wes.
I'm sorry, buddy.
One gigahertz single core Broadcom like the old one, 512 megabytes of RAM, a 40 pin header,
just like its predecessor.
But it adds an 802.11n and Bluetooth 4.0 to the existing Zero design.
Now that's pretty nice because the original Zero will stay cheap at $5.
And then the W with its fancy Wifi and Bluetooth, $10.
The Raspberry Pi Foundation is also offering a new injection molded case.
And I got a picture of it here.
It does look really slick, actually.
Yeah, look at that.
Yeah.
So just to recap, the new features are one gigahertz single core CPU, 512 megabytes of
RAM, a mini HDMI port, a micro USB on the go port, micro USB power, HAT compatible 40
pin header.
Is that hat?
Do you actually say it hat?
Is it pronounced hat?
I don't know.
Yeah, composite video and reset headers and a CSI camera connector as well as now 802.11n
wireless LAN and Bluetooth 4.0.
And then of course the official case to accompany it.
That is really great.
This is for me, I've been recently discussing with Mr. Michael Dominic on the Coderadio
program about different use cases for embedded devices like this and I've come up with a
few that just require something really simple that could connect to a couple of sensors,
have a web server and this could be perfect for what I have in mind.
I'm really tempted to order one even though I don't actually have the use case yet.
Yeah, totally.
I'm wondering if I just find it.
For $10, what's the harm?
And then you have it when you have a spare Saturday or something, not that that ever
happens, but if you do, you can actually work on it.
True, and Mr. Gogo in the chat room points out that this is great for digital signage.
Oh yeah.
I can think of a lot of things where it's less work, you put it on Wi-Fi, put it somewhere
and just be done.
They rolled out new distributors too, so it sounds like there's actual availability for
this, which is nice.
Remember how it used to be different?
They've really gotten their act together when it comes to availability.
You can get this stuff.
You don't have to go to weird providers that you're uncomfortable giving them their credit
card number and you're like, is this ever going to show up in my house?
This is really great.
Anybody in the mobile room have any thoughts on this story before we move on?
Elf into the room, the Pi 3 is getting Wi-Fi.
So is the Pi 3 getting Wi-Fi finally?
If this was getting Wi-Fi, why does the Pi 3 not have Wi-Fi?
Maybe the update's coming soon.
Maybe the... ooh, Rotten Corpse's Red Book prediction right there.
Good job.
Write it down.
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
So everybody mark it in your minds.
Episode 186, producer Michael says that the Raspberry Pi 3 update is imminent with Wi-Fi.
Bold prediction, sir.
All right, so XMetal says that he agrees.
For $10, it's an order now, find use later device.
Not bad.
Pi 3 has Wi-Fi with arch arm Chris Lass.
All right.
There you go.
Thanks.
Boom.
And this is the story that sort of had me sort of sat back in my chair and go, what
is going on here?
Is this a bad sign?
Is this a good sign?
Mozilla has made its first strategic acquisition, and it's acquired Pocket.
Now Pocket is the read it later service that they bundled into Firefox.
It's some controversy.
Yes, definitely.
And when I first... my cynical take on this story when I first saw it was, well, this
is Mozilla trying to save face.
They didn't want to back down, they didn't want to pull it, they probably had a contract
in place.
Yeah, probably.
So this was their way of saving face.
But then I sort of rethought it a little bit, and I actually think this could be a pretty
clever purchase for them, because Pocket has supposedly 10 million monthly active users.
Ten million is not a...
That's a good number.
That's our peanuts.
That includes advertising deals, existing deals, premium subscriptions with credit cards
attached, analytics for publishers.
It seems to me like that could be a good business for Mozilla to have for revenue generation.
And I'm certainly more comfortable with it as something under them as compared with this
other party that may or may not share their values that they're working with.
Yeah, and Mozilla says they're going to open source the bits and pieces.
They say that it's going to run as a wholly owned subsidiary of the Mozilla Corporation,
and they'll continue at least for the next year to run things sort of as they have been,
as they are.
I used to use Pocket for a while, and it was a fine service.
The read it later functionality is good to have.
And I enjoy their... They do pretty good little translations for easy reading, mobile
view or whatever.
I wonder, W.W., you have any thoughts on this before I get into the Verge coverage specifically?
I'm hoping that this is a way to mitigate any kind of Yahoo buyout that could possibly
be taking place.
So we'll see, because I know Firefox has a clause to get out if they don't agree.
So this may be a way to diversify and have more cash flow if they need to.
What do you mean, buyout from Yahoo?
Yahoo has been long in talks of being bought out, and since Firefox is primarily dependent
upon them for cash flow, and yeah, they need-
Verizon be buying Yahoo.
Right.
It sounded like you were saying Yahoo was buying Firefox or Mozilla, and I was-
No, no, no.
Now here's what I want to just really... Because this is a trend that I've been noticing from
the Verge recently.
We covered it a couple of weeks ago too.
There are routine jabs at open source anything in the Verge coverage.
So this is from Casey Newton, at Casey Newton on Twitter, posted at the Verge, and here's
a couple of things that I highlighted in the article that felt like they didn't need to
be there and just simply are there to attack and disparage Mozilla.
I'm trying to think of the motivation behind that, because even if you're a devout Chrome
user or Microsoft Edge user or Safari user, it benefits the web, and it's pretty easy
to understand how an open source browser that's always pushing for web standards is beneficial
to the entire web.
Even if it's not the browser for you.
Right.
Yeah.
And so either this is a super shallow technologist who doesn't properly understand the technology
they're writing about, or there's some sort of fanboy that is biased against open source,
and I see this a lot at the Verge.
So here's a piece that I'm just, here's like a little paragraph.
Best known, speaking about Mozilla, for its Firefox web browser, Mozilla has faltered
in the mobile era, spending years on its failed Firefox phone project and waiting until 2016
to release Firefox and iOS globally.
Meanwhile, the slow decline of desktop web, which is just stated as a fact, has made Mozilla's
broader future uncertain.
They have millions of active users.
That is an unfounded statement that is just speculation on the part of the author.
The author later writes, after talking about the purchase of Pocket, and unlike Mozilla's
existing mobile products, people seem to actually enjoy using Pocket.
The implication being that the people don't enjoy using any of Mozilla's products.
And that's why they had to buy Pocket, because you see nobody likes to use Mozilla's stuff,
according to this author.
And then he takes in a quote that kind of implies that, by a Mozilla person.
It's, it's, what was it, do you remember like a week or two ago we covered something else
from the Verge that was taking just unnecessary pot shots at open source?
What was it?
It's escaping me.
We'll have to check.
If anybody in the chat remembers, maybe mention it, but I don't understand why this coverage
has to be like this.
I mean, there's parts of the article that are fine.
You just don't need to, you know, just report on it as a neutral reporting agency.
Maybe the stinger like, unlike Mozilla's existing mobile products, people seem to enjoy using
it.
First of all, you're projecting people's enjoyment of Pocket versus Firefox, and the two are
so incomparable it is not even funny.
Because Firefox is competing, especially on iOS, which is what this author is referring
to, Firefox is competing against the incumbent Safari, which will always be the default web
browser.
No other app can launch Firefox unless the developer has specifically programmed their
application to send URL links to Firefox, which is not ever going to be in the default
iOS system.
It's never going to be in any of Apple's apps, and it's never going to be in any of the trendy
apps either that are all in with Apple.
So it is such an unfair comparison to compare the usage of mobile Firefox and iOS to Pocket,
which is a completely different category of application, and it only competes with Safari's
Read It Later service, which has only been around for one iOS version and is lightly
used.
It is such an incomprehensible comparison, but yet this author takes the time to draw
the comparison after taking a shot at Firefox for failing in the mobile era, which the mobile
era would seem to imply the last eight years, perhaps nine years.
So Firefox has been in a state of failure for nine years, according to this author,
and they waited, they quote-unquote waited until 2016 to release Firefox on iOS, which
is, guess what, shocker everybody, not using the gecko rendering engine.
It's not a real product.
That's why they waited, because they didn't want to water down their brand, didn't want
to water down their product, but eventually they bowed to the user base on iOS and released
something that sits around the WebKit engine.
Surprise, surprise.
Apple didn't even allow you to make a separate browser other than Safari for like five years
anyway.
I actually think Chrome, for example, on iOS is pretty great, it's pretty great.
So I can understand that you could say it's not a success on iOS, but to compete against
Safari and Chrome, it's a ridiculous comparison to make it to the read it later service.
And I don't get why The Verge is like doing this more and more.
It seems odd to me because it's the two things that I find odd about, and then we're gonna
wrap up on this topic.
It's odd to me that they're taking unnecessary pot shots, perhaps just to fill out the article.
But then at the same time, why are the authors choosing to cover these subject materials
that they appear to loathe in the first place?
They're choosing to cover open source related stories, but yet they apparently loathe that
at the same time.
So they understand perhaps that there is some sort of demand and they can get a certain
click through threshold by covering these news stories, but yet they almost resent having
to do it.
I hate this.
All right, there you go.
That's hopefully the only rant for this show, we'll see, but geez, it just gets me fired
up, The Verge these days, gets me fired up.
You're on The Verge, Verge.
You're on The Verge.
So this has me excited, AMD's Ryzen really looks great.
I can't wait to see some people posting like Linux builds based around this.
And there is something that I think is interesting to note, if you're looking at pre-ordering,
getting ready to do a new build, you're gonna wanna run a distribution that'll have a newer
version of Linux, version 4.10 specifically.
Now this is posted by Michael Larrell over at Foronix, and he sets it up like this.
Maybe I'm reading too much into this, but he says, I haven't received any communication
from AMD about any review samples or the like.
Okay, I don't need to know that as the reader.
You don't need to communicate, guess what?
Jupyter Broadcasting has not been in communication with AMD about review samples.
Haven't offered to send us things.
Should I disclose that for every company that I haven't been in communication about?
That implies to me that he's been trying and not getting the recognition that he thinks
he deserves.
So then he goes on to say, after a comma, so I'm not under any NDA for the upcoming
AMD Ryzen launch on 2nd March, and thankfully received some information from a reliable
source this weekend regarding Ryzen support Linux requirements.
Jeez, is he drunk when he wrote this?
Sorry Michael, but jeez.
I mean, good on you if you were actually.
So he says, here they are.
Like because they are not working with me and giving me a review unit, because they
haven't given me a review unit, I haven't had to sign an NDA, and because I don't have
an NDA, I'm gonna spill the beans on what I know.
But if you had given me a review unit and I had signed the NDA, I wouldn't be posting
this right now, is essentially what he's saying.
So is he saying that his news coverage can be bought simply with free product reviews?
Because Michael, that's not really the message you want to send, man, as somebody who does
product reviews.
So he goes on to say.
So it kind of sounds like extortion.
Yeah, it does, right?
It's like public shaming a little bit.
Come on, dude.
So he says, but here's the good juicy bits.
You need Linux 4.10 because according to this trusted confidant, a good point for AMD testing
and usage was 4.10, so the Linux 4.11 cycle's gonna have some updates, but 4.10 I guess
has some code that AMD.
I can't really decipher the hint, but essentially he says if you're using Ubuntu 16.10, if you
want to go by this marker, or 16.04.2, so you're on the LTS, but you have the new hardware
enablement and all that jazz, you'll have a good base state for AMD Ryzen.
So either if you're going by the Ubuntu releases, that's what you need to be in, or you just
need to be on a distro running kernel 4.10.
Easy peasy, right?
Easy peasy.
By the time the hardware ships, that'll be easier said than done.
I mean, wait, is that, it'll be, that'll actually, hmm.
Right.
So if you've got 16.10, 16.04.2, and you're on Fedora, I think 5.26 is gonna have kernel
4.10 soon by the time the product's shipping.
So a lot of the major distros are gonna be close to 4.10 or on 4.10 if you're on a current
distro.
Yep.
And hey, if you're chomping at the bit to buy the processor on release day, then just
compile a new kernel, you'll be fine.
I kinda am.
I'm not going to, but I am actually fairly impressed with what AMD has to offer here.
I think they've actually got a pretty good product that's gonna be really competitive
in a way that AMD, in my personal opinion, has not been competitive to the i7 and i5s.
I feel like we're at an inflection point where things are kinda questionable for Intel, they've
had some slowness, or...
This is Intel's Firefox moment, and this is AMD's Chrome moment.
Yeah.
It may not go that way at all, but it's interesting.
I kinda want it to, because competition in this space is critical for really competitive
laptops and desktop PCs that can be high performance, and Intel has...
They're really pushing the die size and all of that.
They've really done a lot of work there, but at the same time, they just announced the
next couple of releases, there's not gonna be a die size change, if I'm correct, I'm
not sure.
But it hasn't gone the way they expected.
And maybe a little kick in the arse might lube up the machinery there at Intel.
Anybody in the moment room have thoughts on Ryzen before we move on?
Because I've seen a lot of people talking about it on the subreddit and the chatroom,
so I gotta figure somebody in here has a thought on it.
I'm still waiting for actual benchmarks from PCpern and other tech places that don't just
do pure synthetic benchmarks before I decide.
I'm really excited for...
I'm hesitantly excited about the stuff I hear that I want real proof before I decide.
You know what's...
Oh, go ahead.
Unfortunately, I can't provide any information because I received a review unit, and I'm
under NDA.
Such a tease.
Also, A and B, hey, you know, I could use some Ryzen parts, please.
There is...
You're right.
I totally agree with you, WW.
I haven't seen a lot of the non-synthetic stuff yet.
But what does give me sort of like a positive indicator is they're being really responsive
to other reviewers besides Michael.
They are letting them get in and dig into the systems.
They're not doing the whole, we can't talk about that yet, we can't show you that yet.
They're...
And they're honestly like letting people get hands-on with the hardware in certain cases
in a way that in the past, they haven't.
They've been a little more hands-off, a little more distant.
And I think that's a good indicator.
Hopefully, they've really got something exciting to show.
I hope so, Wes.
I hope so.
Speaking of things that are exciting, Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there and sign up for a free seven-day trial and support this here show.
Do it.
Wes, what's the most important asset?
What's your most valuable asset?
It's your mind.
Oh, I have one of those.
Yeah, you know what?
I was just sitting here thinking about this too, Wes.
What if you go out into space one day and you're out there for years and years and years?
Your body would shrivel away.
Sure.
But you'd be like a jellyfish.
You'd still have your mind, right?
Yup.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
You go there, you sign up for a free seven-day trial, you enrich your mind.
You know what jellyfish Wes is excited to learn about?
What's that?
Oh, yeah.
Very important in space.
And you know, I'll tell you, especially when you've got a lot of systems to keep running
and they have been like life support, they've been partnering directly with chefs or for
a great new set of courses and you have instructor mentoring when you need it.
They've got labs to give you hands-on training.
They have a great community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting whether you're an experienced
sys admin or new to the world of Linux, Azure and AWS, OpenStack and DevOps, a sharp skill
set is an absolute necessity to succeed.
Meet Linux Academy, an online Linux and cloud training platform that uses self-paced video
courses and hands-on labs to give you real-world experience for a wide range of skills.
Train for your certification, learn the latest DevOps tools and grow your skill set to do
better work.
Linux Academy is not just a video library.
Our scenario-based server labs and quiz system allow you to learn hands-on.
We also have full-time human instructors who answer questions and help you earn that certification
or promotion at work.
We add new training every week so you'll always be up to date on the latest tech.
Sys admins of every experience level use Linux Academy to stay on the bleeding edge of the
Linux ecosystem.
You should too.
Yeah, that's legit right there.
That bleeding edge part is legit.
Even when I'm not out in the quote-unquote industry, I'm still hoping for that day that
Elon comes on, knocks on my door and says, I'd like to take you to Mars, and I need your
mind.
And I'm going to go invest in my mind at linuxacademy.com slash unplug, sign up for a free seven-day
trial, dig around in there.
Even if you're busy, they have course schedulers that will work with your time frame.
They'll customize some work, customize some lessons, and I think one of the other things
you could probably dig into, even if you're like me, I run my own business and I got three
kids.
I understand that you can be busy, but you know what's great is these nuggets, just little
tiny bits of wisdom.
You jump in, it's one topic, you do a deep dive, and you're done.
In the time you could have watched a few silly videos on YouTube, you could learn something
completely new about Linux, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, and a big thank you to Linux
Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
The debate rages on like dis-defragging.
Do we really need a swap partition on modern systems?
And I thought we'd kind of, here was my advice.
If you're on a desktop with lots of RAM, you probably don't.
If you're on a laptop and you want to hibernate, you probably do.
That was sort of my...
Those are the obvious kind of corner edge cases on the spectrum.
Yeah, yeah, and then these guys, maybe you've heard of them over at this company called
Red Hat.
I don't know if you're familiar with this.
This Red Hat company comes along, noobs I think, I think they compete with Canonical,
and they came in here and they said, well, ha ha ha, well here's a couple of caveats.
They actually wrote this whole article telling you about how you should and why you should
use swap, and then it says at the bottom, but can I run without swap, Red Hat?
Can I do it?
Is further tuning possible?
And Red Hat's official stance, systems without swap can make sense and are supported by Red
Hat.
Just be sure the behavior of such a system under memory pressure is what you want in
most environments.
A little bit of swap does make sense.
Yeah, I can see that.
Yeah, that's where I've kind of come at too.
How are you running swap on that system you're on right now?
I don't actually know.
That's a good question.
Let's, yes, so there you go, there you go.
And I can do swap off.
I could do swap off right now and I think I'd be fine because I've still got 3.6 gigabytes
of RAM.
Nice.
Yeah.
But the reason why I actually wanted to link to this in the show notes for those of you
at home is they've essentially done one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine
or so, eight bullet points, really eight, that tell you the parameters and where swap
might or might not work for you.
And this one I thought was interesting.
If you design your applications to regularly use swap, make sure to use faster devices
like SSDs starting with Red Hat Enterprise 7.1.
You can do swap on, dash, dash, discard, which can be used to send trimmed SSD devices to
discard the device contents on swap on.
So it's some good tips there too.
So I don't know.
You thought, what do you think, Wes, when you're building a system swap?
Yeah, I usually do, but I could see doing it on a desktop, but it would probably depend
on, you know, maybe do some tests if you feel adventurous.
I could see it like, I wouldn't care here, you know, if like, all right, well, the out
of memory killer comes by and kills my Chrome session, which is probably one of the things,
but I'm generally not doing anything.
I habitually, you know, colon W and Vim all the time.
So I'm not that worried about programs being killed and things dying.
But say if you're like, you know, you're the beard and you're working on editing the show,
it might be worth just a couple of gigs of swap to make sure that that situation doesn't
really happen.
One of the things I think about too is how fast certain types of storage have gotten
now where you can get nearly a gigabyte or 900 megabytes or even 300 megabytes of throughput.
Swap is a little less expensive than it used to be.
Somebody in the moment wanted to jump in with their thoughts on the swap.
Swap on.
You know, one of the things you could do too, is you, go ahead.
I've never, okay, so ever since like elementary 12.04 and other, like going to KDE Plasma,
I've never seen swap used on like the swap partition or swap file used at all.
Zero.
And I have never tweaked it.
And I'm like, maybe you just don't have enough to do.
You're not working hard enough.
Yeah.
You're just not swapping right.
That's what she said.
The thing is, it's like I'm going to be redoing my system really soon and I'm going to be
putting an SSD in and I want that to last me as long as I can for several different
reasons.
So I don't want to use swap on that drive if it's going to be wearing it out, causing
problems or, or should I just be moving it?
And I can never find an answer to any good swap like questions like, okay, is the double
thing still valid?
Like double your RAM size, you know, there needs to be a hard drive.
No, no.
I don't think so.
It depends on the RAM.
It depends on what your RAM is.
If you have like four gigs of RAM, maybe, but you can even get away with that.
I would say like a hundred percent what your RAM is until you get to like 16 or more than
you can just do half of that and just stay at eight.
Yeah.
I actually just do like two gigs these days, really.
And I'll tell you, the only time I would do more is if I wanted to be able to hold the
contents of RAM during hibernation or something like that.
I tell you really, I have it mostly out of legacy.
I have it so that way for me, it feels like it's my, my bumper in the bowling lane that
I, if I go a little crazy, which I sometimes do, I'm not going to, the gnome desktop, and
I haven't hit it with plasma yet, but boy is it crap when you run out of memory and
you don't have swap.
It is, it is, it is not, and it, especially if you're using Chrome, oh, it just is the
most frustrating.
You're right in the middle of work.
Everything starts locking up.
Clicks are taking forever to get registered.
It becomes practically, everything starts timing out.
This tab's died, this tab's died, this tab's died, this application is not responding.
It is a train wreck.
It's a dumpster fire.
So should we get an option where, you know, you hit that memory seal and instead of like
add a memory killer, it just reboot?
You know what, you know, and, and, and I, yeah, really, you know what I think is faster,
you know, with an SSD.
We have an option.
It's called swap.
Is it, isn't Ubuntu switching to swap files instead of a swap partition?
This is another thing you can do is instead of dedicating like a whole partition to it,
you could switch to a swap file, which more and more distros are doing and might make
sense because then you have sort of the best of both worlds.
You don't, you don't necessarily lose a lot of hard drive space and you give, you make
a swap file.
I'm not sure if you have to preallocate the space with a swap file or not.
I don't know exactly how.
You don't.
Okay.
Well, that definitely seems like that could be the way to go.
Yeah, that's what I use.
I don't know about hibernation on a swap file.
Good question.
No.
Popeye in the chat room says no.
So that's sort of a bummer.
But on the desktop,
Well, he says no and yes.
Oh.
If only there was some sort of communication method we could use in which we could speak
more clearly and rapidly.
I don't know.
I don't think that's a thing.
Oh, okay.
Wait, have you tried IRC?
Hmm.
All right.
So I, that's something we'll have to leave a bit of.
I was hoping we could just finally stop talking about this, but like with the disty fragging
topic too, it just keeps coming back.
There's a good chat, I mean a good thread in the subreddit though, if you kind of want
some guidelines to follow.
You have any other thoughts on it?
No.
I think that's it.
All right.
Well, then I suppose without other people inputting, it is time to move on, wink, wink.
I think isn't Popeye like at Mobile World Congress or something right now?
What's going on right now?
The canonical folks are over there doing all, there's an interview with Mark Schultz.
I hear that you're in the mobile space sometimes.
From time to time.
Yeah, from time to time.
Now, we have a story coming up that, I don't know, I don't want us to get all riled up
because we got a lot of fans of Telegram in the audience.
So I know this is a big deal.
I know this can get people upset.
So before we jump into the Telegram story, I want to talk about this 11-year-old flaw
that has been patched, but I just want to put it out there so people know what's up.
A security researcher at Google found a use after free hole within Linux, speaking of
memory usage.
This particular flaw is of interest because it appears to be situational.
It only showed up in kernels built with a certain configuration option, which was config
IP DCCP enabled.
Unfortunately, many people, or I'm sorry, popular Linux distributions have enabled this
option by default.
A new Linux update has since patched the vulnerability, although the exploit is present in Linux kernels
since 2005.
It uses heap spraying methods to execute arbitrary code inside the kernel, which allows the attacker
to escalate permissions.
So you can think of it like this.
An attacker could hijack a low permissions account, maybe a remote services listening
that has limited privileges, like a database service or a web server, your NGINX user,
something like that.
If there's a flaw in NGINX, it just takes one other piece of software that's perhaps
on your system running in the background under a less privileged user.
Or even your own user account on your desktop that is a standard user, and maybe something
happens like inside the web browser, the attacker can use your basic privileges of that account
and then escalate from there.
That's by very definition a local escalation bug.
When you combine it with other types of attacks, it's sort of the island hopping approach that
you guys and we used to talk about in TechSnap.
And it is definitely worth patching, but you don't really have to worry because some distributions
don't really need to be patched.
Most distributions that do, Debian 7, Debian 8, for example, have been fixed.
Stretch and SID have yet to be patched.
Only one version of SUSE is affected.
And if you have SE Linux, well, you can mitigate this problem pretty much all together.
So it's not like it's a huge problem, but it's been around for 11 years, so it probably
does by just the very nature impact a lot of people.
So I just wanted to give a little breaking news PSA update before we got into this whole
Telegram thing.
Because the Telegram thing is not exactly breaking news.
That kind of ends our breaking news section of the show.
And thanks, Shep, for stopping by.
I've enjoyed Telegram for, I don't know, since it was an early, early beta stage.
It's a great chat application for collaborating with groups or individuals.
One of the things that I really appreciate is a very serviceable desktop Linux client.
They have great mobile clients, good bot support, lots of fun features like stupid stickers
and whatnot.
And a big part of using Telegram is using it on mobile.
In fact, you have to have a freaking mobile number to even use it.
I hate that.
And this is where we run into a problem.
Essentially it looks like Telegram for Android is essentially a closed sourced application
now.
According to the repository in the Telegram website, the Android client is covered by
the GPL license.
However, since early October 2016, there has been many releases but no updates of the source
code.
Everyone involved so far is pretty much not responding.
The original author hasn't responded, the Telegram chat support doesn't respond, the
Twitter account doesn't respond to the questions, other individuals like the face of Telegram,
the spokesperson of Telegram doesn't respond, and there's really no other contact method
for Telegram other than a physical mailing address.
Is it time to really start seriously considering wire?
Does this concern you or is this wire or signal, I guess?
You concerned about this at all?
I mean it's very disheartening.
I have not investigated it very much.
I know like Telegram has never been like the perfect messenger, at least in my eyes.
I agree.
We've talked about the problems before, but it has been that mix of like, it's not stagnant
like Hangouts and wrapped up in this, you know, other...
It does feel like stagnation is beginning to set in.
Because when I first picked it up, it was like changing all the time and it's always
been very snappy, fast, supports file uploads very well, all those kinds of things, plus
all the stickers and the font and all that.
Part of me is grateful that they haven't gone down the rabbit hole of video and audio and
trying to be like all in all...
They're not another Snapchat clone.
Yeah, because it, you know, focus on text chatting.
There's other applications that can do video and audio, but when I say stagnation at the
same time, like there are still things about it that kind of bug me that I'm surprised
they haven't fixed.
Like, my big one is freaking global status.
Allow me to set my status to DND for goodness sakes.
And the more things I have coming in Telegram, I have, you know, a bot that sends me something
in Telegram.
I check it, but now all of a sudden I'm shown online and I get 15 telegrams.
Literally, that's what happens to me.
And if I could just go in there and say DND for a little while and let me read through
my telegrams and just catch up, it would just be very useful for somebody like myself.
Those kinds of things are...
There are companies out there like Slack who've really nailed DND.
Yes.
I mean, it's like the best implementation I have found and Telegram could just wholesale
rip that off and they just don't.
Mr. Tonell, you were going to say something.
Yes, I was going to say that Wire is already a good alternative now and it's even gotten
better from a recent announcement.
What do you mean by good?
Like, well, it's a good option because...
Like, how's the desktop app for Linux?
It's fine.
I mean...
Is it better than Telegram?
At first, does it do the audio and video stuff on the desktop?
Yes, it does.
Yeah, okay.
It has the audio and video stuff and the video stuff is actually surprisingly well-made.
I expect it to kind of underperform because of the WebRTC approach, but it's almost flawless.
It's got an app image.
I'm installing it right now.
Are you?
Downloading it.
I got an app image and they also got like a regular tar.
My hesitation here is...
So like, for example, Linux Fest Northwest, just around the corner, when everybody is
working, everybody we're working with has Telegram.
And it's not even just like our team.
It's people that we meet up with or other people that are coming to Linux Fest and all
of a sudden we want to start coordinating with.
Everybody has Telegram.
And for a while, it was in that spot, right?
It was like, hey, open source, yeah, not perfect, they have their own crypto, there's problems,
but it was that beautiful combination of like functional, we have people who use it and
open source.
The network, I think, like interacting with the network, you can still build your own
client.
Right.
There's QtGram on the desktop and others.
The protocols, the APIs are open for the client side, but the server has never been open.
So I'm not really surprised that this is happening.
I'm more surprised that people are being bothered by it rather than questioning, oh, this is
happening.
Well, their server has also been proprietary the entire time.
True.
And their encryption is weird and homebrew.
Right.
Exactly.
And no one's audited it because they've not allowed it to be audited.
The Wire, though, like Wire uses already audited encryption algorithms.
They're actually announced recently that they're going to be open sourcing their server.
So they're going to be completely open source.
And they haven't set a license yet, but everything other than that, everything that you can check
the license on is GPLed.
Yeah.
Here's my problem.
This is me becoming more salty in my old age.
I've been around long enough to know that you can have the best technology and still
not succeed at all.
I mean, look at Linux versus Windows for so many years.
Really what I feel like the issue is, is user base.
It is user adoption and user base.
And it is simpler for people not to care, and it is simpler for companies to slowly
add the features that their competitors have.
System is so entrenched that we really need almost to reboot this whole problem.
And I think Google is working on something called RCS messaging.
Are you familiar with RCS messaging?
No, I'm not.
Yeah, I'm not either.
But it's a messaging system that's designed to move beyond SMS to take advantage of more
modern cellular networks.
It's more of a standard.
Google is a big part behind it.
You can go to jibe.google.com.
RCS stands for Rich Communication Services.
And the idea is to standardize a way to have messaging across phones and across carriers
that allow you to do things like high-resolution photos, videos, large files, group chat.
Knowing messages have been read, you can make video calls.
And it's not like a Hangouts app.
It would be literally built into the text messaging application of all of the phones.
So it would be a new standard that carriers and other type telcos could have.
And Google is, while not  like it's weird.
Google is like all-in in some cases because they've got their management layer talking
to the other management layers of carriers, like they've managed to convince Sprint
and some other carriers outside the US to take on RCS.
At the same time, they're not really pushing it very hard on a software front.
Now they're going to be  eventually I suppose.
And they're going to update the Android Messages client to be the RCS client for Android.
But I don't really understand how that plays into their greater messaging strategy with
Allo and Hangouts and  it's just very confusing.
But if the industry can sort this out and Apple and Google and everybody and Microsoft
and Android and everybody can  Samsung and get along with RCS, we may have something
that's more sophisticated.
But you know it's not going to be encrypted like the way we need.
It's not going to be end-to-end, definitely.
It might be encrypted but the carriers are going to have the keys, guaranteed.
We know how much we love those carriers.
So it could help the average user but for us like users that want something beyond that,
Wire has got a  I think we as a technical community are exceedingly bad at estimating
how much of an uphill climb a company like Wire has because we look at it from  we
weigh the technical merits heavier than we should.
Because the average user doesn't even consider the technical merits.
We literally are not even a consideration in their decision process.
They are absolutely irrelevant to them.
But we can't get beyond it because we understand technically this is a superior thing and so
we should be using this thing and yet the market continues to use things like Skype
and Telegram and all the other messaging platforms.
I would really love to see people switch over to Wire.
I could see maybe a revolution taking over here at JB but you know I look at somebody
like Noah and he puts his entire life in Telegram.
I cannot describe to you.
You just have to be around Noah and witness how Telegram is integrated with his task list,
his to-do items, all of his family, all of his friends, all of his work, everything goes
through Telegram.
When Noah has to take notes for a show, he sends it to himself in a Telegram message.
When Noah has to remember to do something for a client, he sends it to himself in a
Telegram message.
When somebody needs tech support from Noah, he gets them to install Telegram first so
they can chat.
I mean so there are people out there.
That is quite the adoption.
Yeah.
Yeah and then he's in like a dozen group chats.
I don't know how he managed that.
I think he's insane.
Yeah.
Well that's, we know that to be true.
All right.
Mumble room.
Any final thoughts before we move on from messaging?
Yeah I don't think Google is going to get the carrier, the cellular carriers to switch
over to a new standard in lieu of SMS in the back end because it would require such a massive
hardware update.
They're going to have to do it over the IP side.
Yeah.
Well I think that is exactly what the intent is.
SMS messaging, the way it is distributed and routed between carriers is very much a hack.
I don't know enough anymore but it was explained to me by a friend of mine that works for a
carrier, how crazy they have to set this up to get messaging to work between the different
carriers.
And it's out of bound messaging gateways and it's so limited.
Oh yeah.
Monkey, you would probably actually be kind of familiar with it.
Yeah.
I mean do you want to expand on that at all?
I mean the whole SMS craze, I mean even iPhone isn't using SMS anymore and we get subpoenas
all the time for messaging in the back end.
It doesn't exist because they were on an iPhone using the iMessenger which doesn't use SMS.
It uses iMessenger which is an IP based solution.
And so when you start having conversations with people, yeah I'm using SMS, no you're
not.
You're using a third party application which is going over the IP.
And that's maybe coming up with new standard from Google's perspective is a good idea.
I just think it's a waste of time.
That kind of bums me out.
But maybe long term something like Wire can be something that at least a larger percentage
of users adopt.
If you're thinking about ditching Telegram and trying out something like Signal or Wire
or something else, Facebook Messenger obviously, this is a project that may be of interest
to you.
It's the Telegram history dump.
It backs up your Telegram chat logs.
It just kind of requires a few things to be installed like the Telegram CLI client which
is actually kind of cool.
Have you ever used that?
Yeah it is cool.
One of the things that's creepy about it is it constantly logs who's in and out so you
can constantly see who's coming on and offline if people turn that status on.
It supports incremental backups which sounds pretty nice.
And it has a separate YAML formatted configuration file so Pope could geek out on that all the
time.
You don't just need to get a snap of this.
Just need to snap it up.
So it's on GitHub so I'll just link to it in the show notes or it's telegram-history-dump
on the GitHub.
So how's it going over there?
Pretty well.
Yeah?
Did you get your app image of Wire?
Yeah.
I'm running.
Can I see what the UI looks like?
Do you mind sharing with the class?
I haven't...
Wow, that's quite the background over there on the side.
So it's... is it an Electron app?
Why is your webcam on?
Oh, I was testing.
Oh, OK.
Thanks for later.
Oh, look at you, really?
Oh yeah, that's going to be a fun demo.
We got to get moving, huh?
All right.
Well, I'll play with that after.
So you're playing with a bot right now in the Wire?
Yeah.
That was the first thing.
Auto the bot.
Hey, I'm Auto, a robot sent by Wire to talk to you through the app.
That's OK.
Hi, Auto.
You know what?
I'm getting kind of excited about Wire.
I'm getting kind of excited.
If you're thinking about switching up the whole thing, maybe you're ready to try messaging
on a mobile device and you're going to be using data, you're not going to be using text
messages.
You're going to use something like Wire or Telegram.
Ting is such a great carrier for you because if you don't use text messages, you just don't
pay for them.
It's so awesome.
It's pay for what you use wireless, six dollars for a line.
And then your minutes, your messages and your megabytes, add that up and that's pretty much
just what you pay.
They go in there, they have, go to, do me a favor actually, go to linux.ting.com.
Not only does that save you 25 bucks, either in service credits or off a device, but it
lets them know you heard about it here, which kind of keeps us on the air.
Anyways, you go to linux.ting.com, click on what would you save and you can dig around
on this chart and get a really good idea of what your Ting cost is going to be.
Your Ting cost.
Right now, I think even with the beard traveling, even with the beard traveling, like our, because
he has a JB phone with him that's on Ting, we have three lines and his is one of them.
I mean, we have, gosh, maybe we actually have more than that now, now that I think about
it.
Wow.
You know, it really doesn't up our nominal cost because I think our cost this month was
like 45 bucks or something.
And that's with, I think now we have four lines active all the time and we turn some
lines on and off too, so that's another nice thing about Ting.
You would have a hard time finding a plan for one person for that much on another carrier.
I know.
And it's so nice too, especially like in a company where we're all kind of technical,
we're always on Wi-Fi all the time.
I also thought it was kind of nice that Ting did a blog post that kind of resonated with
me.
Why buying last year's flagship phone is the smarter choice?
And I've been thinking too about people that have been emailing into the show about their
phones, which we don't really talk about much on the show anymore, but I've been thinking
that more and more like the 5X is that price point gets to where the 5X is at.
You get something like the 5X directly from Google Play, you get Android updates, in fact
you get, unbelievably, you get more functionality with the 5X than you do with the 6P right
now.
I don't know if you know about this, but the latest, if you're in the beta channel, the
latest Android updates coming down to the 5X give you the gesture swipes that you can
do on the fingerprint reader to like check notifications and stuff.
So you can, yeah, there's like different finger gestures on the fingerprint reader that will
interact with your display, which is really nice when you're holding the phone in your
hand and the fingerprint reader's on the back.
You can just whoop.
It's very nice.
6P doesn't get it.
No fair.
The 5X gets it.
There's something to be said for that 5X.
It's a sturdy phone, it's not metal.
That also means that when you drop it, it doesn't dent.
That's kind of nice.
It's a great price.
The back comes off, you can replace the battery.
I don't know if you're supposed to do that, but I've done it.
It happened.
Don't question it.
I used to do it on my 5.
It's just kind of a nice sweet spot because then you also get the updates directly from
the Googs.
Then you go over to Ting, you bring a device like that, you get it from the Play Store,
you can put it on GSM or CDMA, so you get to take advantage of either one of Ting's
networks.
And if you bring a device, you just get $25 in service credit.
And if you don't use a lot of text messages or mobile minutes or data if you're on Wi-Fi,
that $25 service credit would potentially get you for a couple of months.
It's ridiculous.
It's such a nice setup.
So check them out.
Go to linux.ting.com.
That lets them know you heard about it here and saves you some monies.
Linux.ting.com.
How's that pixel working out?
Still pretty happy?
Yeah, actually I'm very happy with it.
Hmm.
Pretty nice.
It's not quite like as it is now.
It's last year's.
The only thing that kind of makes me...
I don't know.
What is it?
I don't know, man.
I just, you know...
Basically, I've been on the iPhone.
Right.
It's fine.
But every mobile operating system starts to get on my nerves after a while.
Yeah.
That is...
This time around, I just haven't invested that much.
Like I haven't super customized it.
Yeah.
Just use it for like core things.
Because I get that same point where I'm like, this is just not the platform for me.
Yeah.
And it's interesting because I'm going further and I'm deeper in.
Like now it's like there is maybe a handful of applications in the past I'd have to re-log
into.
But now, it's probably a good solid 15 applications.
Like just an example, all my TP-Link power adapters, the DJI Phantom, the Amazon Echo,
the Harmony Logitech remote that I have, the Wemo power adapters, all of those, all of
the information, all of the configuration for all of those stupid things is on this
stupid phone.
And it makes switching harder and harder and harder.
You're bought in.
It almost makes me want to get out just because now they've tried to get me in.
Yeah.
Like I almost, a visceral response, I want to get out of here.
I want to get out of here.
But I should focus on more dramatic things.
These Internet of Things devices, they're not just part of a lock-in system.
They're not just making me more dependent on apps.
They're also making us more vulnerable.
And there's one that's sort of like the worst case scenario because it affects the children.
And to set up this product for you, I'm going to play their commercial.
It's called Cloud Pets.
Saying goodbye can be hard.
The ones you love seem so far.
Now staying in touch is easy and fun with Cloud Pets.
Just record a message.
I hope you had a good day at school.
I miss you.
And send to the cloud.
You know, let's stop right here.
Before we go any further, yes, this company was hacked.
All of their users' information was exposed online, including their actual conversations
when they use this product.
Full-fledged, not by one attacker, not by two, not by three, but by at least four separate
attackers that can be identified potentially more.
The company was notified not once, not twice, not three times, four times the company was
notified and they did nothing.
No password on their database.
Their Amazon Web Services was left wide open with public URLs for all of the files.
No.
Yeah.
So as we watch this, bear that in mind.
With Cloud Pets.
Just record a message.
I hope you had a good day at school.
I miss you.
Let's stop right there.
You know what drives me crazy about this type of advertising?
The only time daddy is away from his little girl is when he is out at a hotel bringing
home the bacon and mommy and the little girl are at home.
This type of advertising is so basic.
It's so insulting and this already, this company's got me upset.
I hope you had a good day at school.
I miss you.
And send to the cloud.
In just seconds, it floats down to the app on your smart device, allowing you to send
the message to the Cloud Pet.
I hope you had a good day at school.
I miss you.
It's a message you can hug.
If you didn't catch that, that message you can hug doesn't even get sent directly to
the bear.
They couldn't put a Raspberry Pi Zero in this thing.
You have to separately like...
So the mom in the background, of course, she's at home with the little girl because dad's
out at home.
She's the caring parent.
She has to download it on her iPad and then upload it to this stupid bear.
It's not even...
It's amazing.
And then the little girl hugs the message out of the bear.
Now squeeze puppy's paw to send one back.
Night daddy, I love you.
Cloud Pets makes you feel like the ones you love are always near.
Hi, this is grandma.
See you real soon.
The Cloud Pets app uses Bluetooth technology to send your messages.
Hi, this is grandma.
See you real soon.
In other words, some parent or caretaker has to be near the damn bear and constantly uploading
these files when they could just play the message on the iPad.
Hi, grandma.
Whether you're all the way on the other side of the world...
I miss you guys.
I'll be home soon.
And this is the most insulting because it's a service member and he's all earnest and
he's all sad and I'll be home soon.
And of course, it's stereotypical white family, moms in the middle, two kids next to what
looks like the fakest fireplace.
It's faker than my green screen fireplace.
And it's the perfect family, which is an impossible standard, which then service members look
at these types of advertising and they look at this impossible standard and they judge
themselves by this and go, oh geez, we really don't have our shit together.
Again, this kind of basic advertising is so insulting to have then expose everybody's
information is just...
I miss you guys.
I'll be home soon.
Or very close by.
Good morning, sunshine.
Make sure you eat your breakfast.
That's the last thing I want, a lecture toy.
I know.
So this is the really dirty details about this.
It is definitely the worst case scenario cloud device ever.
This is more than two million voice recordings exposed of children and their parents, along
with email addresses and passwords of over 820,000 user accounts.
Clouds not only that, but cloud pets data was also held for ransom.
The customer data was left unprotected from December 25th, 2016 to January 8th in a publicly
available database that wasn't protected by any password or firewall.
The creator of I've Been Pwned said that its exposed data was accessed multiple times by
many third parties, including hackers, who used and stole customer emails and hash passwords
from cloud pets database.
In early January, cyber criminals were actively scanning the internet for badly configured
Mongo databases and guess what?
Cloud pets was one of them.
Their database was actually overwritten twice.
They didn't fix it then.
The toy maker was allegedly notified four times that its customer data was online and
available for anyone to have their hands on, yet the data remained up for almost a week,
with evidence suggesting the data was stolen on multiple occasions.
Cloud pets blog has not been updated to reflect this.
In fact, it hasn't even been updated since 2015.
So if you're a cloud pets customer, you essentially have, unless you're listening to the show
or reading these blogs, have no idea this has happened.
Look, we hacked them again, but get all the bears to spit out a security warning.
So it's kind of funny because AWS is out today, right?
And that's part of AWS is part of the story.
So you had the MongoDB database.
And that's where you got like the URLs and session IDs and user information.
But spiral toys, the parent company used Amazon hosted services that required no authorization
to store any of the recordings or profile pictures or the children's names and the relations
to the parents and friends and family and pets and all of that is like a worst case
scenario Internet of Things hack.
And it's such a stupid product.
And the other problem is not only is the company unresponsive, but check out their tutorial
video on getting started.
Sybil looks like Sybil looks like she is she is deeply she and I don't I'm just saying
she looks like she's a deeply tortured woman.
I don't know what's going on.
But watch how Sybil tells us to set up a password email ready and choose a password and watch
this Q W E and good Q W E confirmed and good in their official tutorial video with Sybil
the tutorial host.
They recommend a three character password Q W E and in fact tested by some security
researchers.
Their application allows a single digit password.
If you so choose.
Well I mean the children got to think of the children all this makes me sick and it's funny
because we're recording this in the middle of an AWS outage and as part of this outage
people on Twitter are really going on and on about how their Internet of Things devices
are not responding right now which is just my bear is broken.
Yeah because if this than that it depends on AWS and if it's just it's incredible.
It is incredible that it is 2017 and a company like this exists where they just throw this
crap online and don't bother securing it.
But what's to stop them if they can get manufacturing that's crazy cheap if they can take advantage
of people's smart devices that have Wi-Fi and Bluetooth they just have to throw together
some Web services.
It's a lot cheaper if you don't bother to secure your things properly.
You don't have to even hire a sysadmin if you don't right.
You know what you put a Docker image up online that's a big deal.
Pretty bad.
So you think there's like a market niche after this for like super secure cloud bear because
maybe we should go into business.
I don't I don't like being a like a naysayer of all cloud things because you're looking
at a man who is pretty pretty satisfied with the echo product.
I just today set up another smart thing.
You're a cloud child.
I've been using the harmony right remote with it with the echo to turn my television and
soundbar on and off since our last episode.
It's actually pretty great.
I don't have any idea where some of those remotes are right now.
I think I just put them away in a drawer.
It's the best thing ever.
It is literally the best thing ever when you when you sit down on your couch and you bark
at the echo to just turn on your television and it turns on the television the soundbar
and the Nvidia shield.
Mind blowing.
Great.
That's been fun.
You know what.
And today I put a heater on it.
I put a heater in the RV on this so now I can just tell the echo and turn the heater
on or off.
I'm cold.
I can actually tell I can actually tell this echo to turn it off at the RV at home.
So before I leave I can have the heater turn on.
Which saves power.
I don't have to leave it running all day.
But it's toasty warm when you get home.
So I don't want to be like this all cloud all innovative things.
I'm not all Noah on this.
I'm not all Alan Jude on this.
I have a middle ground where I think there's a room there's room for products that are
well maintained.
There's room for a product like like the transactional update products from Canonical there's room
for that kind of stuff.
But you see this and it's just so disheartening that we're in the majority I feel like we're
never going to get it right.
Yeah right.
And that's the thing is like the more things we have like this than the less faith we have
in the entire marketplace.
And there's unfortunately not enough pressure to make companies behave good.
And they can just disappear.
They sell a product.
You got to do it right.
Go to DigitalOcean.com and do it right.
Use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED after you create an account and you get a ten dollar credit
DigitalOcean.com sign up then use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED simple cloud hosting provider
and they have if you are totally a noob they have a fantastic beautiful easy to use interface
and they have one click deployments of systems that are updated.
They partner with upstream providers.
They make sure it's configured right and then they back it up with really clear really really
well done documentation.
So you can deploy a system that is configured properly that does get updated or you can
build it from scratch.
Go to DigitalOcean.com and try it.
One of the things I love about their web UI is the HTML5 console.
Not only is that just a handy feature to have but the way DigitalOcean has implemented it
there is some quote unquote power user features that you can take advantage of that really
up the flexibility of a DigitalOcean droplet.
Try it out.
Use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
They got data centers all over the world.
They got an API that will make you fall in love with the concept of APIs.
You're like Chris you always talk about APIs and I say where the hell have you been.
Seriously what where have you been.
But if you want to see an API done well you go over to DigitalOcean.
They have an intuitive API.
They have utilities where you can just get right to work with it.
They have libraries and frameworks and they got everything up the wazoo.
I mean they got a wazoo even for it.
It's incredible.
I actually I don't know for sure but I suspect that their own tools like the interface to
their website and all of that shenanigans must use the API.
It's so well done.
We use it every single day here at Jupiter Broadcasting for our DigitalOcean droplets.
We turn on the things and we turn off the things all day long using the API.
Even though their website is great I don't even have to log in.
I do with a bot in our IRC chat room.
You can deploy a new machine in seconds.
All of their systems use SSDs from the five dollar a month rig all the way up to the ones
with gigabytes of RAM.
They have 40 gigabit connections coming into the hypervisor.
You can have team accounts.
They have highly available block storage and the pricing is ridiculous for three cents
an hour.
And remember we'll give you a ten dollar credit when you use the promo code D1Plugged for
three cents an hour.
Two gigs of RAM a two core processor 40 gigabyte SSD and three terabytes of transfer.
They've also just launched their new load balancer service which is online and working
right now.
And it makes you look like a boss.
Load balancers by DigitalOcean integrated in with their control panel 20 bucks a month.
Boo yeah.
Ridiculous.
DigitalOcean.com use our promo code D1Plugged after you sign up and a big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Now I like the idea of you know those like coin machines you throw your coins in they
sort them and give you money back.
What about those but you just get like an AWS credit card you know.
You're like hey I took my change and now I got servers.
I love it.
You know I've been I've been grousing off the air for the last couple of weeks that
the fine folks that package up G streamer for Arch Linux move the old buggy unsupported
G streamer 0.10 into the A U R. And that means every time I do an update I'm sitting there
trying to build G streamer it makes my A U R updates take way longer on most my systems
not all but most my system it fails to build anyways depending on your A U R client sometimes
that stops the entire update process.
It's a bad experience and if you've been running into this and I've seen people grousing about
it in our chat room check to see if anything actually depends on G streamer 0.10 because
it's old it's buggy it's unmaintained.
You might just want to install all of it.
I have the uninstall command just to take it all out in the show notes if you do and
you have your or substitute your own package manager and after I did this purge things
were running much better in my updates much smoother and it made me think about G streamer
a little bit as something that I've been following now for almost a decade I think.
It has sort of a reputation as well that's how I watch videos on GNOME.
Why do I need G streamer building in the A U R it's that thing I use to watch my video
but it actually has some pretty pretty as they say dope functionality Wes and I'm kind
of curious about some of the playing you've done recently because it sounds like you've
been kicking things around using G streamer and winning victories impressing the ladies
and showing friends how it's done.
Tell me all about it.
I just I was just kind of rekindle I would have been playing with it maybe six months
ago eight months ago and I've been playing with it more recently work just because it
can do it has first class support for RTP and other things so you can use it to receive
like media from say a SIP call but it also does RTMP which is something we do a lot here.
Yeah we do.
That's how we send our video stream up to DigitalOcean from DigitalOcean to ScaleEngine
and YouTube and it just it just impresses me like there are some issues we've seen some
security things where you know like hey G streamer runs and it supports these weird things
and then that can cause you know it's not well tested or you have a bunch of like the
bad set of plugins that aren't good quality but and I'm also a big fan of FM pick but
I love that it has this like.
Server side component to it.
Well it has a server side component and it has like this notion of pipelines which is
very powerful and composable.
So like FM pick works great there's a lot of options but it's not quite as composable
or as clear, concise, well it's more concise but it's less like G streamer really has this
much like a Unix command line model where you can just take different pieces stick them
together build complex pipelines hey maybe you want to do like a video wall with four
pictures up on a screen and a timestamp yeah G streamer does it all.
I have a graphic up on the screen that kind of attempts to illustrate this a little bit
because you can have like one of the pipes could be to a media player the other pipe
could be to a streaming server the other pipe could be to a real-time video editor which
is kind of a cool concept.
The other thing with the latest G streamer I think it's like 1.10 or something like that
they support Microsoft smooth streaming are you familiar with smooth streaming?
No I'm not.
So this is interesting to anybody who's on sort of a crappy connection smooth streaming
is adaptive bitrate in real time so as your connection goes up it can stream a higher
bitrate and it's not just bitrate it can also adapt resolution so it can change to from
to an HD picture down you know way down to whatever you have support for and G streamer
has added support for that and that kind of got my attention because that's something
I know that the live stream they've been looking for that scale engines working on that YouTube
offers that somehow but I think you have to manually choose it kind of.
So this is interesting G streamer is is so much more it's kind of like and boy this
is a risky comparison to make but it has elements of QuickTime.
People really commonly think of QuickTime is just that really shitty video player especially
on Windows.
I never really fought with it on Windows but I've heard horror stories and this it's just
that's like that's the tip of the iceberg that's like the totem or the movie player
on Gnome.
The QuickTime plumbing and and and pipe system is what makes video editing on OS X better
than pretty much all of the other platforms QuickTime and core animation and and the accelerated
graphics capabilities that plug into the QuickTime pipeline system are are really the secret
sauce of video editing and and motion compositing and work like that on OS X that if you don't
use G streamer on Linux you have to cobble together with different libraries yourself
and each editor in each or you know maybe Splendor whatever has to either find another
stack create their stack out of a collection of libraries or use G streamer.
What kind of stuff were you streaming around with?
I was doing the screencast or what?
Yeah doing that I've seen some projects and I played with a little bit like doing like
a video wall where you decompose a video into different segments and then send those each
to a different computer attached like a pie attached to different TVs.
So are you streaming right now from this machine because I saw your webcam was on earlier was
earlier but I can be what is going on over there so what are you using what what software
do you use on the desktop there to start the stream?
G streamer.
Okay so it's just a command command line yeah and you just say G streamer grab my webcam
yeah and then send my webcam to yeah I have a URL if you want oh really where do I find
this URL all right go to we'll open up maybe MPV because it'll be an RTMP stream all right
oh oh all right all right let's do this right now here I'm gonna should I put is it okay
to put up on the you okay with the URL being public yeah it's just westpain.com oh look
at you I just needed I was just a droplet that I had a DNS name for.
RTMP first RTMP oh right of course RTMP wes dot anything or westpain.com slash live slash
test slash live slash test okay let's see if it works all right video stream discovered
after having already parsed oh I like that I don't know what that means but I like it
survey says oh some red some red oh oh we got it oh there it is hey that's me there's
Wes's face there it is yeah we are but like at the same time if I want I could switch
it to sending my desktop we could be sending this so does the desktop show up as a virtual
camera or how does that so I'm gonna try lighting you whoa boom there we go now I'm so now you're
lit let's see if that looks better on the stream here see what the delay it looks like
about it's probably and then I hit cancel because I was gonna switch oh okay let's do
this all right this is fast oh boom and it's down so it's about about a seven second eight
second delay there yeah and probably some of that is this I'm doing like a ton of things
and this is doing h264 conversion yeah yeah I believe you can get it to do like the quick
sync or other types of hardware offloading but I do you have the IRC on this yeah I'd
be curious to see what the if you paste it with the command you don't have to put the
whole URL for your server in there but I'd be curious to see what the command looks like
just so I can get an idea of how complicated that is because that's pretty nice Wes just
to have that built into gstreamer right there yeah seems like something I mean you can do
the same thing with ffmpeg there's a lot of overlap there so if that's your preferred
tool that's usually what I use but it's neat and it exposes some options that you might
not otherwise have and it makes it really neat to see like you saw some of those diagrams
there like if you want to do like a whole bunch of multiplexing into one thing and then
mix it and send it gstreamer it's a nice tool I was just thinking about how I would have
maybe used this back when I was working in IT and I could totally see setting up a like
a link on an intranet and I would say at this time let's go here and it would be a stream
of my desktop and we could do like a tutorial or a walkthrough yeah totally could you also
is it pretty straightforward to set up audio capture yes I don't have that working right
now sure yes so that seems like another like a headset it'd be a really nice way to do
like tutorials internally or something it really well that's a great idea mm-hmm way
of the future way of the future I'm gonna look more into it because I'm curious about
smooth stream I mean I know it's a Microsoft technology but if it's something if it works
well yeah I mean I really like the idea of it why not why can't why can't the player
in the server talk and say okay this is looks like a first rate support for what people
do with like dash or HLS yes so without it just having to like actually switch I don't
know exactly I don't know if exactly like with HLS it's kind of a hack because we essentially
do is have all of these different bitrate streams and you encapsulate them in a playlist
and then you throw them at somebody as fast as possible and it's possible to jump from
one one playlist stream to the other but most clients don't get that right and it all depends
on how good the client is if this is like you get one stream and this is my understanding
because I was looking at how flow soft has implemented and the way they do it is it's
one stream and you you connect to this stream and it adjusts the resolution and bitrate
in a range that they have set up for that stream so they predefined a range of what
the smooth stream can can fluctuate between and then you just connect to that one URL
interesting like a nice client experience yes yes could be a game you have to play with
some more game changer as they say Wes well interesting so where did you learn where did
you learn all these shenanigans about G streamer you can find like they have a G streamer cheat
sheet there's a lot of bloggers one thing I will say is the documentation could be improved
there's a lot of stuff there's a lot of documentation for that old zero dot one zero release so
some things have changed there's different command line options different parameters
to the plugins watch out for that but the 1.0 1.10 version can pretty much do all the
same stuff so you just have to tweak it a little bit very nice very nice thanks Wes
also Mr. Gogo in the chat room points out that the blog post about that teddy bear breach
yes is really good including more details about the company's response and I have that
linked in the show notes if you want to read more and they have other videos that are also
just as horrible all of that's linked up in the show notes you can go check that out go
to Jupiterbroadcasting.com and look for episode 186 of your unplugged program thank you for
joining us you know if you'd like to attend live head over to jblive.tv on a Tuesday when
my friend visit Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get that converted to your local
time and yes you can participate in our virtual lug you just need a working microphone a headsets
preferred and mumble an open source chat client what yep you join our chat room do bang mumble
get all the info feedback Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash contact or linuxactionshow.reddit.com
a great place for stories to find more of Wes on the tech snap program find more of
me youtube.com slash Chris Fisher I'm going to have a behind the scenes edition of this
here show there see you next week.
So you know what's a real son of a bitch last week as I said Australia instead of Austria
that's a real son of a bitch and I think the problem is is that I think the same thing
so it's fine it's fine I think in part the problem is is that I'm probably dyslexic but
I think the other thing is is that I'm not when I'm on the air my primary focus isn't
reading it's talking yeah right it's a different thing and it's talking about what I'm reading
and it it gets me more often than I'd like and then the other thing that compounds is
we don't edit very heavily so it's not like I go back and edit for content right like
if it was user air I would probably affix that because that's I did do that you would
have caught it but in this show I'm like no it's it's live to tape oh man it gets me
you know the thing is is then you also have to multiply it by volume because I do so many
shows and I've been doing them for so long like this just there's so many out there where
I've done this you can't win I cannot win nope I cannot so even track so as long as
everybody sets their expectations remembers that I am a simple man who can only do so
many things the things you say they'll probably start with the right letters so and you know
what else you know what else it's theater of the mind it's mad libs podcasting everybody
and you know it might be fun for the viewer we'll just try to make more mistakes and just
see if you guys can catch them watch out