Well, Chris, did you hear someone posted a native in kernel patch set for wire guard to open BSD?
Is that possible? Yeah, you know actually they've been working with upstream with with Jason
They've learned a lot from the Linux kernel implementation and they've got the right licensing in place
So yeah, I mean it hasn't been accepted
I don't know if it ever will be
But it actually might be simpler than Linux because turns out open BSD already had good crypto
Hello friends and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello Wes
It's episode 354 and I think it's too big of a show way too big. We're not being very responsible today
I know we needed to get one of those vehicles behind us with the sign that flashes that says
Oversized show just go around us on the internet. There's too much to cover today
We have a bunch of great community news. It turns out this is one of those weird weeks
That only 2020 brings us these days where Microsoft is going to dominate a large portion of our community news section
Say what? I know it's not just gonna stop there
We have a bunch of other things to get into including
Philip is here from Manjaro. Hello, Philip. Thank you for joining us again. Hello. Hello
So stay on the line there Phil because we're gonna be talking about some Manjaro hardware here in a moment
But before we go any further, I gotta say a big hello to drew and cheese who are also here today. Hello guys. Hello
Hello. Oh, hello gentlemen cheese. You're looking fabulous today. I like this new beaded sweatshirt. You've got here
Did you hand bead this thing hand beaded and hand sequined? I'd never seen a hoodie made out of beads before
It's really pretty impressive. This is one of those times. I wish we are a video show
And of course a huge time appropriate greetings to that mumble room. Hello virtual lug. Hello
Hello who let the eagle in the lug? Oh my gosh ridiculous. Well, I didn't want you to get lonely
Yeah, it is nice to have a pet eagle. I gotta say it is it is pretty pretty sweet
We have some strange news to start with
Everybody take a moment prepare yourselves because today is Microsoft build and we have a build
blast of Microsoft news for you
It starts with a Microsoft executive recently saying we got it wrong on open source
Microsoft's Brad Smith acknowledges they were wrong in past remarks made by Balmer and other executives
Brad Smith has served as the president of Microsoft since 2015. He held a virtual talk slash Fireside Chatskies
During that there was a quote that Michael liberal at pharaonic scrapped
Microsoft was on the wrong side of history when open source exploded at the beginning of the century
And I can say that about me personally
The good news is that if life is long enough, you can learn that you need to change
Today Microsoft is the single largest contributor to open source projects in the world when it comes to business
When we look at GitHub, we see it as the home for open source development
Now we see our responsibility as its steward to make it a secure productive home for developers
How does that make you feel when you read that? Do you feel like they get it? They actually get it this time
I mean, you know Brad Smith is is high up there and it does seem like their workforce gets it
So at this point the executives sort of have to play catch up, you know, all the best talent that they want to hire
Those are folks that want to be involved in are involved in open source
And you heard that little business reference in there
I think really what they picked up on is hey, this is working for our bottom line
Yeah, indeed
So build like I said happening right now Microsoft's annual developer conference
And there's been a couple of bombshells that apply to the Linux world
Let's start with the biggest the one that made me go. Holy crap
There was some hints going around about this that a developer on Twitter named Alex happened to mention
And notice and took some screenshots of some weird DirectX stuff that seemed like it was being baked into WSL
But he didn't know what was going on behind the scenes
And today we learned that Microsoft, Sachi Nadella himself up on stage actually announced that WSL
The Windows subsystem for Linux on Windows 10 will include GPU compute support and full GUI application support
And there's even some DirectX magic happening here to support certain DirectX calls on your WSL applications
This is full fledged graphics supports
And their initial prototypes right now are even using Wayland as some of the windowing technology
To make it possible to run full fledged Linux GUI applications with GPU acceleration via WSL
They're going to beat us to Wayland on the desktop. Oh, no
It turns out how they're accomplishing this is essentially making this technology on par with what Windows applications can achieve
Graphics performance wise will link to the developer post where Microsoft explains all of this
But essentially for a while now Microsoft has been baking in para virtualized GPU support into the core of Windows
And Windows drivers including requiring all of the OEMs to support this
Think about this for a moment
This has been a long term project actually in part to support HoloLens of all things
And launching with WSL 2 and WDDM version 2.9 which is part of the Windows display driver model
They're going to expand the reach of GPUs to Linux guests using this para virtualization technology that Windows itself is already using
So it's the same pipeline Windows is using for graphics rendering now being opened up to the WSL
And it's one part Windows software but it's also one part Linux kernel software
Yeah, they've made a new kernel driver DXG kernel brand new and it basically exposes a little device slash dev slash DXG
To the user mode Linux running in your virtual machine there
And it's got an iOctal that basically mimics the native WDDM stuff that happens on the Windows side
And it sits there on the bus between the virtual machine and the host and just sort of forwards those calls along
So once you're in Linux, I mean, you just get the full capabilities that you would get in Windows
And there's not a whole bunch of throttling, it's not like the Linux has some sort of second tier access to the hardware
It competes just the same as any native Windows application
Yeah, like Bruce in the chat room puts it, so now you can play your Steam games using Proton on Linux on Windows
And as Jill very accurately and acutely puts it, there's really no need for VMware on Windows to run Linux with the full GPU anymore
Applications that are running inside of the Linux environment have the same access to the GPU as native applications on Windows
There's not a partitioning of resources between Linux and Windows or limits that are imposed on the Linux applications
None of that exists, the sharing is completely dynamic just based on what application needs what
Also sort of interesting from the open source perspective, not really the open source perspective but just the targeting Linux at Microsoft perspective
Is they've added stuff like DXCore and D3D12 to Linux, so this is like DirectX driver code now running on Linux
But it's compiled from the Windows codebase, the same codebase that they make the DLL for Windows
That's what they make the.so file for Linux on
Although it seems that their kernel, while it shares some of the same names as Windows components
The kernel driver they've created is a clean room implementation that will be GPO
Nice to see, now of course you know we mentioned Proton and I had the same thought but
Probably what a lot of this is targeted to especially right now before the full you know the GUI stuff comes into WSL
Well it's machine learning
Yeah those kind of jobs and stuff like that
And I think it's also about reassuring certain OEMs that if you wanted to continue to invest in DirectX
You've got still a Windows Avenue here as long as they're running it under WSL
And they do address the question around Vulkan in this post
And they say they're still exploring how to best support Vulkan in the Windows subsystem for Linux
Although it seems like they're looking at basically adding stuff to Mesa that implements OpenCL and OpenGL
And some of those technologies on top of DX12
So this is like the reverse of the shims that we've been using to get DX implemented on those
They just flipped the script on us Wes
What?
On one hand it's really nice to see that Microsoft is giving more prominence to Linux as a whole even in their conferences
But like my principal worry about this is that it'll continue to suck the oxygen out of further advancing the Linux platform
In favor of just well Windows is good enough so we'll just do that and then all the crap that we have to run on Linux will just run on Linux on Windows
And it's a very very dangerous and bad path for the success of free and open source computing
Because if people in large droves actually do embrace this attitude
Like I don't want to bring up an old dead meme but it's embrace extend extinguish in a very very real way
Yeah I see others in the chat room saying the same exact thing they're echoing the embrace and extend extinguish
I think it's the other way around though is I think this is a dramatic reaction to trying to shore up what has been a pretty lacking aspect of their quote unquote workstation desktop OS
And I think they've looked at what sold a whole bunch of MacBooks few years ago when a bunch of people bought MacBooks for development in the cloud
And they're looking at that going well a rich command line a good terminal
And now moving towards the future machine learning and being able to use the GPL for the GPU I should say for compute
Is a big part of what's going to make the future workstation for developers I think they're making that calculus as a reactionary move
And I think the problem here is because of the nature of the GPL because of the nature of Linux as sort of a unifying technology platform that anybody can kind of build on
And then bring their final value to make it a complete product
I think that's an unstoppable force and it eventually will continue to consume the desktop
It'll just be a 10 15 it's the it's the multi 20 year multi decade saga
But when you zoom this thing out and you go 5 10 15 years down the road it's not a Windows future
This is a stop the bleeding kind of move right now Windows itself and the NT kernel has a limited long term potential
Windows 10 is sort of the big last hurrah for that platform and in a way what they're essentially doing is just making Linux the de facto runtime
If you target Linux you can run it on the cloud you can run it on Android you can run it on Windows you can run on Linux desktops
You can run it on ARM you can run on everything that's in everyone's pockets
And I think that is just too big that's bigger than any one product is bigger than any one company
And this is sort of just attempting to become at least competitive with the kind of workstation you get out of the box with Linux or Mac OS
It's almost Microsoft sort of just selling you know fancy developer tooling on top of Linux like here's this whole OS
But but really it's just a wrapper around Linux to smooth that experience and let you play games on the side
That's it we're taking what you know we're taking what you like and we're just going to shave off some of those rough edges
Why even concern yourself with leaving the Windows experience
But I don't think it will supersede Linux as a whole because it's just utilizing part of Linux which has already been so successful
That doesn't mean it's not extremely clever and I think the company that's most at risk is Apple
This is clearly going after the developer market in a very aggressive way and I think it's going at the heart of what made Mac OS good
Because they've taken Windows 10 now and they're doing this iterative update process they're trying to make it a stable OS with WSL with all these new features
It's not us Linux users that should be concerned. It's Apple
If this was really the way that you know Microsoft was going towards us like they're trying to stave the bleeding and trying to recover a little bit and attack Apple more
Why not invest in wine. Why not build up that part like essentially what Valve has been doing to beef up the GPU and and and the hot pads for supporting video games
Why not do the same for the rest of the stuff that Microsoft tends to care about which is productivity and and things of that nature
I've been wondering about that myself if that would be something we start seeing them do
But I think instead you'll see them just start targeting the platform
I've recently for the first time used teams on Linux Have you ever tried that
It's not bad It's actually not bad on Linux
They've done a decent job of creating the teams application for Linux
It lacks some of the features like background blur right and it did take them a while to add that support
But you saw it there as a bug and I think that that's part of their process
Right they have ways to get feedback about products
And when they saw that oh yeah there there are a bunch of Linux users out there who maybe wants not the right word but need to use our software and want a native ish version
Let's make it for them I have this Chris last dot com slash consulting where I'm doing the podcast consulting for folks
And I had a client who is interested in working with me for a serious chunk of hours
But the requirement to work with them was I had to use teams because everyone on their team is using that
And I was like OK I didn't realize that until like the call was supposed to start
And so I was like I bet this is in the managerial repos
And so I did I did a quick search there was teams I did a dash teams and hit enter and within 30 seconds I had Microsoft teams installed
I click the link and I selected my audio source and I was done and I've used it three times since then and it's worked perfectly fine
I think the only thing I can say to that is yeah exactly
There's also called a couple of other Microsoft things before we move on to manager which I want to talk about next
They also officially today released the Windows Terminal which was announced at build 2019
And has become official with 1.0 at build 2020
This is their open source terminal application where you can have in one tab the Windows command line
And then in another tab any Linux distro you want and you can have four or five tabs open with different Linux distros in each tab
It's a very well done piece of software it's something Wes and I were very impressed with when we tried Windows 10
I hope it doesn't get too good or might be better than our native terminals I mean it's already graphically accelerated
It's got a ton of customization options and of course first class emoji support right there
You know it's one of these new breed of sort of Windows apps that have been reimagined in this Microsoft loves open source future
So I imagine this be a lot of new workflows going on
Well you and I met a couple of the individuals behind the project at WSL Conf and the people behind the project from what we could tell
They came to Microsoft after this new open source kind of attitude so they came with this whole fresh perspective
I mean I've known people who worked at Microsoft for a very long time because it's here in my backyard
I've had family and friends that have worked there and there was an old way of looking at a Windows first world
And then there's been a shift since then and they joined the company since that shift
And they came in with that open source first mentality and then they built this terminal
And it's just a fascinating story
But last but not least in all of this because there's actually even more
Microsoft announced a built in package manager for Windows now
And this one's interesting the company today announced the Windows package manager
I knew they would do this I felt like Windows needed this
It's a new native package manager that will be built into Windows 10
With the new win get or wing it if you want to be silly about it command Windows package manager automatically gets the latest version of an app you want to download
Validates its authenticity I mean you want that too and installs it on your machine
So as an example you can install the latest version of that Windows terminal we were just talking about
Just by running win get one word install terminal
And that just pulls down the latest version from the Microsoft store and sets it up for you
Yeah so when I read this at first I was like oh so it's it's a command line front end to the Windows store
That's not very exciting but no the company will also allow users to download apps from third party repositories
Which I think is the key thing to actually making a package manager useful
Yes right it's a little more it's generic tooling in that sense and not just tightly tied to their proprietary infrastructure
Yeah command line front end of the store is boring but a legitimate package manager that also can pull from the store
Okay that's interesting the Windows package manager supports Windows 10 version 1709
So you need to build 1709 or later and it will come pre-installed with Windows 10's desktop app installer
Once that reaches version 1.0
It seems nice for automation too you know we'll tie this into some of your scripts and setups
And instead of relying on third party tools well you just do it all with the Windows stuff built in
This speaks to the larger point that you made about Microsoft looking at the landscape of Mac OS maybe
What sold a bunch of Macbooks well brew sold a bunch of Macbooks so let's just copy brew and have our own thing
I think that's it I think what you're seeing here with this package manager is Microsoft looking at Linux workstations
And Mac workstations and saying what works how do we do a modern take on that and build that into Windows
And where I sit as a Linux user it feels like it takes four freaking ever for this stuff to land in the operating system
It could have been there for years but to Windows users this stuff's coming at a rapid pace
They said it from a totally different perspective
Definitely big changes I mean it's interesting just from the velocity aspect to see how much stuff Microsoft's able to get done
And in the new Windows 10 world of you know frequent and smaller updates actually push this out to people
I think as Linux users we're going to have to get comfortable with a new reality where there's a lot of people on Windows that are playing in our space
And we need to be inviting and understanding and help them when they're ready to make a transition to a fuller Linux system
Because if we're lucky we can set a good example we can make it look like a friendly place and we can encourage them to move to a richer fuller Linux ecosystem
I mean that's just it all right you got Windows from your you know enterprise supplied workstation at work
And oh hey you were able to start playing around with this Linux stuff
Well now when you go home maybe you want to try putting some stuff on a Raspberry Pi and doing home automation
We've got the tools for you yeah exactly we got to set our defensiveness aside as much as we can
And just try to help these new users be successful so that way they become part of the greater community and further the cause
And I think it won't be for everyone I mean every user of the system won't be thinking like that but we'll be able to get some of them
All right I know that's a lot of Microsoft news and a Linux podcast but today's build and that concludes our build blast
And we move on now to some new hardware the mangero book AMD Ryzen running a Ryzen 5 series which is a 3600 I believe
Phil help me sort this out because I was thinking when mangero announced a Ryzen system it was going to be the 4000 series
But looks like we have maybe an interim release hardware here
Well it's like you have a normal desktop CPU flagged into your laptop so you can even change the Ryzen later on
If you have a different CPU simply swap it to a powerful one
Oh so this is like one of those workstation killer laptops
Something like that this is a standard M4 CPU and you can simply swap it out
There's a powerful cooling system so it works so we have a smaller version but you can also put in a Ryzen 9 up to 3900 12 core
So we've got a whole range of systems here we mean we've had you on recently talking about Intel based systems now we have an AMD Ryzen system
There was talk recently about a ultrabook style mangero system it would also be Ryzen based so how do we keep all of this straight now
Well we have several vendors so this one is the computer shop from Belgium and they said hey we're looking also into the Ryzen plate and said okay let's go for that
And we said yes why not and we promoted for them
And so are they doing the bulk of the heavy lifting for getting the OS to run on there or is it because at this point the hardware is so well supported there's not a lot of heavy lifting to do
Well we test with them the main developer of their shop is also using mangero so he is testing with us and we give him some pointers to get his hardware supported
So yeah it's a win-win situation that he is so active in distributing mangero on his machines
So I see kind of a split now in the strategies because some distros have one laptop and it's like the KDE neon laptop
There's one machine you can get it when they update it they update it infrequently but it's that one box
Mangero seems to be going the approach of working with multiple vendors with multiple different laptops
Are you concerned at all about that getting confusing
Normally not we have tuxedo laptops where we have the complete branding then we have mangero computer from Belgium which is also doing some kind of branding for us
And having more vendors than only one you have more options and with this vendor from Belgium you can sell also to the US and Canada without the taxes
So we get a discount of 21% of each automatically
Oh that's pretty significant actually so you are in a sense trying a different model here and I couldn't be more for it
I think it's great to see some just stick with one piece of hardware and they iterate it infrequently and there's that choice
And then you have the mangero approach where there's several vendors which might work better for different customers with different machine options
I absolutely for a very long time and long time listeners of mine will know this I was a fan of the battle station laptop
I would haul these hunkers to my clients and then I would just plug in and I would have the power I needed of a desktop in a laptop
These days and I think kind of like yourself I'm more of portability first because you know I end up on a plane or I'm carrying a machine around at home and work every day
So it sounds like they'll just be multiple options for different types of users
Well Phil I got you here let's just do a quick update on the mangero project itself I saw a bunch of updates come out recently for my workstation
How are things in the land of mangero generally
It's pretty good we're working on getting the updates for the 20.0 releases out so the first point release went out there as well
And we found some issues we fixed them and we hopefully will also update the new KDE packages as they come out soon
I love that I'm running plasma on my mangero workstation and I just I just love it
I told the story recently on the show but it's so nice having one package manager for everything
Even my stupid printer drivers were in the AUR and then you combine that with the curation that happens at the project level on top of ARJ
I was initially skeptical but as an end user I have just absolutely loved it and I'm going to keep an eye on these hardware choices
Will you let us know when the 4000 series Ryzen box gets close
As soon as some vendor has a 4000 series then I'll let you know of course
Oh I'm excited already
Yeah I mean everybody is that's what everybody is and truthfully in our testing the Intel 10th generation CPU based systems are also very competitive
So it's a good time there's lots of lots of choice
Well thanks for coming on Phil and updating us on this it looks like a serious machine for anybody who needs workstation performance from a mobile rig
Yeah and the 10 generation of Intel we will have some new laptops soon also from the UK and Germany so stay tuned for those as well
Thank you sir
Now on the other end of the price spectrum but also well supported by managerial are the pine devices and recently as in since the last show
That's my definition of recently I'll take it
Yeah the pine tab had a pretty significant update with dates on shipping and also other new features like unless I missed this and cheesy maybe you can correct me
The last time I saw information about the pine tab I didn't see this keyboard attached with it
Well yeah they've always had the idea of magnetic keyboard in play for the pine tab
He was in November when they were initially kind of talking about it and there were dev units out there
I know Marius from reports had gotten one the magnets on the keyboard case weren't very strong
So they were having issues with those so I think they reengineered where those were placed and use stronger magnets
I mean it seems like a great little tablet to get it kicked off there's already some videos out there of the pine tab running Ubuntu touch
You know from reports with the five six kernel in it Lima graphics drivers seems like a solid little machine six thousand milliamp battery full size USB 2.0 socket
Does have two gigs of DDR3 RAM which is a little low but it's definitely not a killer for a small tablet like that 10 inch 720 IPS display 64 gigs of EMMC flash storage
But you can expand this and I thought that this was super cool so they have an optional M.2 adapter that you can open up
Apparently with one screw you can take the back off tab toss in this M.2 adapter so you can add in your NVMe SSD even an LTE module
They're talking about LoRa modules a lot of interesting stuff
Yeah that really stood out to me cheese it just because you know they mentioned a little bit like some of this is for aimed at personal users
But some of this is aimed also maybe at commercial applications like LoRa support which is that low bandwidth but long range wireless protocol
So wouldn't a pine tab especially at that price be something just flash on your like commercial thing give it to your employees
They've got it there in the truck with them they when they need to go service something that'd be awesome
Precisely and the one thing that does seem to be kind of a hiccup with that adapter though is that you can populate it with two modules
So you can populate it with the LTE module for example or a LoRa module which isn't quite out yet and say an SSD but you can only use one at a time
But I mean you got to think that this is a $99 price tag with a $20 keyboard upgrade that's really a pretty awesome deal
There's a lot of cool stuff that actually came out of this update so the pine phone itself they're going to be adding a QI wireless charging that attaches via the pogo pins
They're exploring adding a another 5,000 milliamp battery to the back of the case to give you you know more runtime
The keyboard that they've talked about for the pine phones kind of been put on hold but that's going to be coming around eventually whenever you know this kind of COVID thing has died off
And I think that really comes down to they need some in-person visits which you really can't do right now with these factories
So until that opens back up you know they won't be kind of going down the keyboard route for a little bit
A couple of things jump out at me first of all $20 for a magnetic backlit keyboard is crazy and when you compare that to the $300 entry price for the new Apple iPad keyboard
The other thing I really like to see is adding QI wireless to the pine phone is a big deal because there are millions of QI wireless devices already out in the market made by some of the biggest manufacturers in the mobile industry
You know they've said that there's going to be compatibility there so any QI wireless devices that you already have or charging mats that you already have will work
It's a genius idea that they added the pogo pins so that you can easily you know make these additional devices that you can attach to the pine phone
As far as software I tried the latest UbiPorts I still don't have a SIM for it it is getting better
In the video they released it looks like UbiPorts was designed for a tablet
I think that really kind of crosses that convergence area where everyone's been talking about
The tablet itself is also supposed to support display out I don't know if that's USB OTG how exactly they're going to handle that but should be interesting
I got a question for you you said that they have the same quad core a64 system on a chip is that which is that just essentially the rock pro 64 in there
Well it's similar they use the same CPU as in the normal Pinebook the original the 1080p so you have the same CPU in the phone in the Pinebook original and in the tab
And with that you have the possibilities to have the same hardware and us as vendors of the software we don't have to release multiple kernels
So it's easier for us to have one kernel for the Pine devices and to work on the phone on the tab and on the original
Yeah I bet as a developer you're very pleased to see that I want to be the guy here for a moment who just says you know set phasers to stun on your expectations
It's not going to be a performance powerhouse it's not going to shame the iPad Pro in that regard
But in price, customizability, tinkering, future expansion and potentially your preferred workflow this could be an unmatched value
I am very excited to see where they take this
I mean it's just the beginning right I mean this will be the you know the first try out and I'm sure it will evolve as a platform as it keeps going
Very cool all right well let's do a little housekeeping we don't have a lot in this week's episode
I do want to mention that we'd love to have you join us live we have a great attendance today 33 people in the mumble room right now as we go
You can join us on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv and we convert that to your local time zone with the assistance of robots at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash live
And that's good because you don't want us doing it
I'll mess it up every time, every time
We also have the Luplug happening every Sunday and this is how I know some people skip housekeeping because they don't know about this
They show up in the telegram group and they're like isn't there some sort of lug thing yeah the Luplug
Sundays at noon pacific but we got that calendar so you can convert that stuff
Noon pacific which is the same exact time we do this here show only on Tuesdays so it's the same bat time just a different bat day Sundays
And we use our here mumble
Yeah easy peasy and it's a great way to practice your setup if you want to come join us live on Tuesday which you should
And you know Chris you did mention the telegram group and that's still happening going stronger than ever jupiterbroadcasting.com slash telegram
Yeah some say it's too strong I say they don't know what they're talking about
So we'd love to see you in there it's a great way to continue the conversation in between shows but also get us looking at something
Is there something in the open source world that you think needs our attention that's a great way to get it in front of us
So there you go also you know I'm going to plug right here linuxunplug.com slash contact
Get your feedback in ha how about that we love that feedback
How can we never plug that in the housekeeping West I don't know let's add that right now there you go
Well let's just do a quick old update on our pie holes pie hole 5.0 came out and we run pie hole here in the studio
I'm sure some of you run it yourselves but those that are not familiar pie hole is a network level ad blocking software
That is predominantly designed to run on a raspberry pie there is where you get the name obviously
But because we're maniacs we just run it on our big old x86 server in a container old school old school well actually kind of sort of I don't know
Or new school I don't know what's old is new again
So version 5.0 has landed and I thought well let's jump on the old server here at the studio and do an update right before the show
Because what could go wrong on the very thing I used to access the internet and nothing did it was very boring
I did a docker compose poll and then I did a docker compose up dash D and waited one minute impatiently
And then the new page loaded and I was running the next version and it was the most boring upgrade in network software history
It was just a good thing in my opinion
Yeah you know they do have some notes as a project that this is a one way upgrade so if you leave version 4.0 and you go to version 5.0
There ain't no going back except for your backups and yeah you probably should have some backups
But they also note that docker is a great way to run this because the upgrades I mean they're just a little safer
You don't have to worry about any intermittent state as long as the configs don't break
Well you've got a time tested image right there available
As far as 5.0 goes what I noticed pretty much immediately was improved graphics on the dashboard
For like my history charts of what's been blocked and whatnot and a little bit of more information in log and areas like that
But I think probably the biggest deal for me and why I went ahead with the upgrade
Was the custom host names from the web GUI now through local DNS records tab
This is where you can assign the host name to an IP address
Which I think Wes was the reason why we ended up not using PyHole for our DNS
Does that sound right to you because they didn't have this feature when we first deployed it
Yeah exactly you know it wasn't quite ready to do everything on the network
We had some other infrastructure options available to us at the time
Now that they have this well yeah why not just do it in PyHole because it really does have a pretty friendly GUI
Especially if you've been used to configuring things like DNS mask by hand in the command line
Yeah it is so nice when you just once or twice or three times a year want to go in and do that kind of stuff
It's really nice just to have a UI that sits on top of tried and true Linux technologies
It's not creating some weird implementation itself
Overall pretty solid release though I mean the update was done
I got in there and is one of those experiences where I was like hmm I don't notice a lot of differences
But what I have noticed is an improvement
Her device blocking is quite nice so you're able to block individual clients
So you have a teenager that wants to access Facebook between a certain time
You can do that now through the PyHole web interface
Yeah it's a pretty nice customization you know PyHole is one of those systems that by and large you sort of forget that it's running on your network
But for folks all stuck at home right now with a lot of diverse use cases
That might be causing some problems or maybe you don't need some of that blocking on your work computer that needs to get some stuff done
But you do want it to block out those things for your smart TV
Yeah very true I recently just did the math the back of the napkin math
And I looked at some paid for blocking services for the kids
I was actually kind of doing it on behalf of Angela for her because at the RV I have PyHole
But she wanted something for her network and we were just kind of doing the math
It's like if you look at it if you put this on a Raspberry Pi it doesn't need to be the latest Pi either
So you may have one already which changes the math or maybe you just buy a Raspberry Pi 3
For a very reasonable cost around $35 and then you load this image on there
When you look at it it's probably a grand total of an hour of investment of your time at $25 to $55 worth of hardware
So when we were done with that back of the napkin math 12 months or so you could kind of justify the cost of a subscription service
But by year two you were clearly saving money by deploying this yourself
I don't remember exactly how long ago we deployed PyHole on our machine here in the studio West
But I think we're getting close to that year mark now
Yeah and it's really been a good test that by and large nothing's broke you know
It's not that like sites mysteriously fail or all kinds of stuff just hangs when you expect it to load
So I've been pretty impressed
They've improved some other stuff there just as from the admin perspective too
They've got deep CNAME inspection which is pretty cool
So you can have multiple CNAME redirects you know when you've got a DNS name and it could be a whole chain of them
PyHole can now inspect that chain and determine if any of those are on your blacklist and then block that original request
And you mentioned better logging info one of those things is more information about why something was blocked
So now in the GUI you can go in find that something was blocked and if you're curious like what rule is blocking this
Maybe it is something that you don't want to be blocked it'll tell you just what that rule is
I do like that I always love seeing other notable features include quote unquote more efficient memory usage
Always love seeing that on a new software release because it makes it easier to run it on lower spec hardware
Which makes that whole cost calculation even easier
I think there's other things in here for those of us who subscribe to different blacklist
They've improved the parsing of imported blacklist
They have a gravity script that will now show how many domains were not able to be imported from that list too
And then give you some examples as to why they didn't import so you know where to start from
Which is exceptionally nice especially for people who are doing this casually and don't spend a lot of time
Managing these types of lists or even trying to block things at a DNS level
Yeah exactly it's an interesting blend I think because it is you know actually pretty nice for the power user
You can get in there and go into the command line you can customize the DNS mask or DNS FTL whatever they call it these days
You can customize all that stuff if you need to we've got some custom configs and host files entry setup
But if you just want to use this from a casual end-user perspective that works great too
Do you struggle with the morality of using something like this Wes? I've never had this problem with piehole
But when I use something in my browser, I've gotten a couple of hey, you know to use our website
Please whitelist us from your ad blocker
That is a little bit harder when you're using a network level blocker because it just you got to go login
You got to go add the URL it takes more time than just clicking something in your browser toolbar
There's a bit of a disconnect here when you're using this do you struggle with that at all because I kind of do
Yeah, I mean you are just sort of blanketly saying hey, I want as few ads as possible and that's pretty great from you know
The actual end-user experience, but we do have to acknowledge that many of our favorite sites on the internet
Well traditionally a lot of their revenue let's and the things they use to pay for their servers or pay for their staff
That does come from advertising. So it is a good workflow to get into maybe practice once you set this up
Like what does it look like to whitelist something? What are the sites I go to a lot and you know, especially right now
It's just it's just a good time if you have the resources available
Maybe go subscribe send some money to those sites that you turn off ads for that's a good point
Bloomberg just recently did a piece about piehole interestingly enough and
According to their research piehole is installed on only a hundred and forty thousand network
So we're not talking like, you know a plague that is impacting the advertising industry
But what are your thoughts on this Alex aka? Mr. Ironic Badger
Is this one of those situations where end-users are essentially robbing the creator of revenue?
I mean, I hate to put it at such dramatic terms, but that is kind of what we're talking about here
Yeah a little bit but then on the flip side you have websites that are designed entirely as ad revenue
Farms, you know all these ones that have 10 things about this thing that you don't really care about
They make you click through a 10 image slideshow instead of just writing the article properly
Also trying to browse some of these websites on mobile is just horrible
And there's no real good way to block ads on mobile
So for me piehole or ad guard home is is just a it's a necessity to get a decent mobile browsing experience these days
I completely agree, you know in lady dupes right now. I'm on a mobile connection
I get maybe if I'm lucky 4 megabits where I'm parked right now and having a network level ad blocker
That just prevents pre-rolls and prevents certain components from loading on the web page
Means I put less traffic on the cellular network
I've been subscribing to the New York Times for a couple of months now just to try and support proper journalism
And I think that is the way that we should go about this not forcing advertisements down our our throats really
Yeah, there is the tracking element to of this and I think in a way
It's users pushing back saying this isn't the right way to monetize and I don't mean to make this about this
But to your point the unfiltered podcast, I've relaunched it recently and I very intentionally am just crowdfunding
I've committed to no sponsors. No advertising. It is very much
Not a feasible way to monetize news in my opinion
I think it's fraught with problems when it when it requires tracking of clicks tracking of views tracking across multiple properties
It's fraught with so many user hostile issues that if you just took a more direct to audience approach would be completely avoidable
And I'm not trying to justify the use of ad blocking
But I do think in a sense it's users attempting to vote with their wallet
Well, right. I mean we haven't had a lot of feedback mechanisms and there's you can talk to individual sites
But there's no other real way to go yell at advertisers and marketers out there and we get that some of that stuff's needed
Sometimes it might even be useful rarely maybe but sometimes but we've just seen a relentless increase in tracking and fingerprinting
That's it was well said and it would be nice if you know
Maybe a little more than 140,000 of us were using this because it might send a very clear signal
Also, I want to mention this Bloomberg piece is worth reading because the other thing they talk about is the core developer now
Who's taken over the project recently will kind of semi recently in the last few years
He's got about five to 20 hours. He says to work on this thing between college and his project
Now there is a flourishing community here. So it's not all on one individual
But the elite dev for this project this piehole project that I think is it's one of those showcase open source projects
That even people who have no idea what Linux or a Raspberry Pi or open sources you can show them piehole and they love it
It's being created by somebody who's spending roughly roughly five to 20 hours depending on how busy he is at school
I think that's pretty humbling when you think about it. It's a guy who started this when he was in high school
Got involved with the project when he was in high school and now he's in college
And when science classes are busy, he's only got about five hours a week to spend on this thing
Yeah, I think that does underscore a little bit too of you know, this is an organic need
It's not some conspiracy to hurt websites and advertisers. It's just end users getting frustrated and doing what they can
All right. Well, let's cover a little feedback here on the show. I think that's a piehole for you
And now let's talk about a Linux Mint success story from Zachary
He writes I wanted to share a Linux Mint success story about my grandmother
She loves it. Her computer is a six-year-old HP all-in-one
It had all of the programs from Windows 8 and she hated Windows 8 didn't we all?
Yeah, you know, it was amazing Wes. It really was something the touchscreen worked intermittently
Oh, that's good took three minutes to boot
Oh my god, and she had a metered internet connection that Windows did not respect
Which she was constantly worried about going over her cab all the time
There were weekly printer issues then eventually the Windows key deactivated itself
So and not the key, but the actual like serial key. So she got the Windows watermark saying this is not a license copy
She stuck it out as long as she could but it got horribly slow unreliable
She desperately needed a new computer, but I convinced her to first try Linux Mint and she loves it
I do as well because computer problem calls went from weekly to only twice in the last year
Wow, isn't that the truth? I've noticed that as well
She likes it and says that it's easier to use than Windows ever was
I even forgot to show her how to shut the computer off
And so I called her and told her how to do it, but she said she'd already figured it out
Can you imagine how proud he must be of his grandma right now?
Oh my gosh, I know. He said like really you figured it out and she just said yeah
I mean it has a big red power symbol labeled shutdown. Of course I did
Obvious. How simple. Yeah, yeah that grandchild pride is real though
Camille writes in with a question that I get about once a day right now
So I'm very thankful for the opportunity to clear this up
It's about Pi Boot. He says hello in episode 347
You mentioned putting some info about booting from the USB drive with the Raspberry Pi 4
It's in the show notes you said, but I can't find it. Help please
Well, we'll link it again
And I'll say the guide we have linked here
You really only need to jump down to about midway where it talks about preparing your SD card
That's about where the guide is relevant today
But what this question is getting at is something that I think is fantastic
With Ubuntu 20.04 on the Raspberry Pi 4 and it's that you can run from an external USB drive
Now you do need the SD card
You got to have boot on the SD card
But the process is so simple
And once you do this the read and write access to the SD card is so limited that it's probably going to last forever
Right. I mean at that point it's basically okay
Anytime you boot it needs to read the RAMFS on the kernel
And then when you update and get a new kernel then it has to write you back
But that's about it
And what's nice is it's so much faster
And yes it's over USB 3.0
So huge caveat, past Chris would never ever ever ever recommend that you run your system from a USB drive ever
Don't do it
Current Chris has accepted this compromise in hopes that the USB code base has gotten more stable as time has proceeded
And so far, so far, current Chris has not been proven wrong
Yeah I mean USB has been adopted for so many things these days
And I think there are a lot of systems
I mean I've definitely been guilty of that before
Even running Windows off a USB drive once in a while
So it seems to just work
I hope so
Because I'm doing it
The way this works is you take the Pi image
And this may work for other distros as well
This is something I'm going to try
But you take the Pi image for your favorite distro
In this case I use 2004
But try it with others
It just really requires a more modern kernel
You take that image, you flash it to the SD card like you always would
Maybe using DD or using
I don't know
Do you do you?
Maybe you use Etcher
I'm not judging
Then get ready for this
Ready?
Take the USB drive
You plug it in
You flash the same image to the USB drive
I know
Revolutionary
You plug both devices in
You log in
You change the file system ID
To match the SD card on the USB drive
And from that point forward
Once the kernel loads up from the SD card
It sees that file system label
But from what we could tell essentially
It just the way that it's hard coded
It first attempts to boot from USB
Yeah, it seems to work out that
How the kernel chooses its boot devices
They both ended up having the same label
But it just picks the right one to start with
So we didn't even have to erase the label from the SD card
So that means too that in the worst case
Your USB dies
Well, you can still boot to repair things from the SD
Yeah, and we'll link to the guide that I used to do this
And like I said, start about midway down
And it's so much better
First of all, you reduce the wear and tear on the SD card
But these SD cards are slow
So slow
So slow, where I have USB 3 and an SSD
It's about as fast as you're going to get
In fact, I did some benchmarks just to test it
Because I wanted to get some real numbers
And from what I can roughly tell
It's about as fast as I could possibly get a Raspberry Pi 4 now
Without overclocking it
You know, and just from our own experiments
When you SSH into one of those things
And it's on the SD card and you launch something
Boy, can you tell
But running from the SSD
It just feels like you've SSHed into any old x86 VPS
Yeah, you'd have no idea it's a Raspberry Pi
You really wouldn't
You'd just think it's a VPS or a physical x86 box
And things just run
Yes, and so much stuff is supported on these systems
It's all been cross compiled, it works on ARM
It's great
Alright, well now Wes, you've got that brand new
Really nice looking Dell XPS 13
In your hot little hands for a review
And we got some feedback on the
Hey, include this in the review feedback that we asked for last week
And it came from Cory and he said for the XPS 13 review
I'd love to hear about using it with a generic install
Of Ubuntu 2004
He says, what changes has Dell made to the drivers?
Do they submit them upstream? How will this machine run
22.04 in two years?
You know, Cory, thank you for that feedback
Those are all definitely things I'll be checking out
Actually, a little spoiler right here
It came with 18.04 I think on there
Everything worked out of the box, WiFi was working
I just wanted to test it and I've been loving 20.04 so of course I overrode it
And stuck that on there
So far, no WiFi yet
I'm going to do some more testing, I'll definitely dig into what drivers are in use
And what you actually need to get this working
Unfortunately, it's like it's still new enough that that's a little bit tricky
Interesting
I'm glad you're trying that, a little early discovery there
The way my understanding of this process is
Dell is not creating drivers
And then creating a bastardized image
That ships on the XPS to make it work
They contract with Canonical
And Canonical developers
Make it work, they generate an image
And they certify it and they deliver that to Dell
And then Dell ships that on the XPS
What I'm saying here is, this isn't Dell hacking it into an image
It's the Canonical developers making it work
So it has a very, very good shot
That it's going to get upstreamed into mainline Ubuntu
And that is part of the arrangement
There is a licensing agreement that Dell
Pursues with Canonical
There is a revenue share for every laptop sold
And those support services are part of that agreement
That Dell makes with Canonical
The good news for Dell is that the Ubuntu developers themselves
Are doing some of the coding necessary to get things to work
Like maybe that WiFi
Or maybe that new fingerprint reader
The nice advantage for end users is
You're not having some third party OEM just slam jam code
Into your image where they've hard coded a PPA and you're good to go
You actually have the maintainers of the distribution
That are writing this
And Dell makes it always into the mainline ISO
But it has a very good shot
And it also is a revenue source for Canonical
Yeah absolutely, and I should note I was just using the same
Random 2004 USB stick I had laying around from our review
So that hadn't been updated and because I didn't have WiFi during the install
I actually haven't updated the thing yet
So it may be that I do some updates and everything just works
Yeah and on top of that, you know me, I'd be also interested in other distros as well
You know what you've got to do Wes, you've got to kegzak into some RAM disks
As if I won't be doing that already
Yeah I know, you've got to put at least some of the major ones
I'm sure Fedora 32 will be getting a run on there and Menjaro as well
One of Wes' most recent duties was
He was put in charge of hiring our new soundboard guy
Who just sits here
Too soon, he just did it too soon
Come on, we talked about this
I don't know what to do about this guy
But we do have some pics to get into
It's not the same now
We've got to get rid of this guy
Maybe one of our pics eventually will be a machine learning model that replaces him
I told you hiring a soundboard guy out of Bangladesh
Was going to be fraught with latency
I told you that
But doing this for a long time Wes, that's how these things work
Yeah you're right, in fact I think he's paying us
I don't know how that works
Well we have a couple of pics
This one was sent in by several individuals
I think the whole internet in a way that doesn't typically happen noticed this pic
But we'll give credit to Stephen because he actually used the contact form
Stephen wrote in and he says I just found this little tool that converts any USB thumb drive to a multi boot ISO stick
All you do once it's finished is copy over the ISO and reboot
It can hold numerous ISOs all at once
Also any normal files you might want just to use it as a USB stick
It's got a GitHub page and it's undergoing very rapid development
Alex N on Twitter also sent this in
Interestingly enough on my own accord I also found this one and tagged it
Everybody found this and it does seem like a super cool pic Wes
Oh yeah absolutely
Way back in the last days I think you guys talked about some hardware that could do this
You know a special USB stick that you could copy ISOs on
But talk about easy peasy when you're making these USB drives from ISOs all the time
Why even bother with Etcher when you can just use CP
Yeah it's like the last USB stick you need and you just throw the ISOs on there
And you're right I had I think it was a Zalman drive
Yeah that's what it was and that's pretty slick and kind of makes sense that you might do this in hardware
I'm really impressed I'm going to have to do some digging here in the repository to see how they're making this work
And just how slick it is because they even talk about having UFI support and legacy BIOS both working the same way
It presents you with a nice little menu that finds all your ISOs and lets you choose between them
Holy cow
Yeah you just now stick the USB disk in copy the ISO over
I mean I love this about my Zalman USB drive but it would do classic CD-ROM emulation
So it would actually show up to the host OS as an actual USB CD-ROM drive which is just too much
This is much simpler and you just copy them over and you're good to go
I think this is going to change my Linux distro hopping game forever
Big statement
I think you might be right
Well how can we top that that brings us to the end of this week's unplugged broadcast
We'd love to get your feedback at linuxunplugged.com slash contact
Please do and if there's anything else you want to know about that XPS before we do the official review let me know
It's coming soon and you can hit me up on Twitter I'm at ChrisLS, Wes
At Wes Payne
And go get yourself some cheese bacon cheesy
At cheese bacon
Oh it's magic and of course the show is at linuxunplugged on Twitter the network is at Jupiter signal
Thanks so much for tuning into this week's episode of the unplugged program
And I'll see you right back here next Tuesday
I found the WSL content really refreshing because I got to know the change from within Microsoft when it happened
So I was there with the Windows 7 to Windows 8 and Windows 8 to Windows 10
And you really notice the change from Baltimore to Nadella
And it's like day and night and people are still in the embrace, extend, distinguish mentality and I really can't hear it anymore
It's just so like tiring
So you were an employee of Microsoft?
It was a close contract, it was like subcontracting I did
They have lots of contractors
Yeah so I was teaching sales for the Microsoft employees and for the retail guys and stuff
So from what you witnessed personally you felt like the transition was legitimate internally
Yeah for sure absolutely
They had meetings, they had people flying out to Redmond and showing them Azure
And when the whole canonical stuff happened people started getting really curious
So I did some workshops because I was always Linux curious and did use it privately
And so I did some workshops for the sales guys that had to deal with Azure back then and stuff
So I mean I'm from a little country like I'm from Austria but you know small changes
Yeah I feel like my proximity to people at Microsoft gave me a bit of a view into the company that people maybe outside of this area don't have
Not only that but I will be honest that I now looking back at it feel like I was childishly irrationally angry at Microsoft
In the late 90s and the early aughts Microsoft was the greatest evil in the technology industry that I perceived
And the technology industry had the greatest potential for influence on mankind
You might even say they were a cancer
Yes and so it became my life's work to inform people about alternatives to Microsoft
And so when I had the opportunity to go down to Redmond because of some content we were covering in Koda Radio
I actually was contacted by some folks at Microsoft and asked to come down there
And when I sat down there and started chatting with folks that were Gentoo users and SUSE users and Fedora users and Windows users all around the same table
I went oh this is different this really is like something that's been multiple years at that point when I went in it was like five years in the works
And I just couldn't be intellectually and emotionally honest with myself without recognizing the cadence difference in everything they were saying to me
And the fact that a lot of the employees there were listening to our podcast because they're interested in what Linux users are thinking and doing and care about
Was also very telling because when I walked around there it was like I was kind of at a Linux conference like people knew me and I didn't know who they were
You know that awkward kind of like you know me and I don't know you but you know me that's weird and that was the Microsoft office
And I walked away from that and I brought my wife with me and I walked away and I remember talking to her and I'm like this isn't the Microsoft that I grew up with
Now we can all just circle up hold hands sing kubaya and just beat up on Oracle
Amen