What was that really easy clustering that was originally just on live CD? What was that called? There was a super dead simple
Clustering software for Linux for a while. There was only like in the two kernel two dot something kernel maybe and
You know you booted off a Debian live CD
you have a master controller and then you'd boot up all the other ones and say that they we should look for the master and
Then you could you could distribute tasks between all of them like the like they had a floating
Process table, I can't remember
Wonder what it was called. It was the coolest way to do clustered stuff, and it was so straight called heartbeat. No
It's not around anymore, so it's gonna be hard to find because it relied on stuff
That was like I think sunset a long time ago in the kernel
So it's probably gonna it's probably impossible to find it now. It's I'm so old
That's that's the problem well the reason I said yes at heartbeats because that articles from 2002
That's almost old enough. It's not a bailiff cluster
Nice tech man yeah, that would play rust that would play rust tech man that would definitely play was it mozziex
Was it open mozziex was that it I?
Think I just I think I just found it
Open mozziex. Yeah, and cluster not picks. That's the live CD thing I was talking about so this was originally for from mozziex in
2002 open mozziex was stable on Linux kernel 2.4.x for the x86 architecture
But porting it to the 2.6 kernel remained in the alpha stage and support for 64-bit
architecture only stayed in the 2.6 version on
July 15 2007 it was announced the open mozziex project would each it would reach end of life
Due to decreasing need for SSI clustering and low-cost multi-core processors becoming more available
but so this was particularly useful for running parallel applications, so this is another great way to build or
It would actually worked really well is if I had centralized storage I
had a couple of users that would just slam a samba server and
I could actually move that process around to a system that wasn't as busy. It was really cool
And you could just when you needed a system. You would just add it to the cluster by booting off of clustering optics
It would detect the cluster, and it would just get added as resources and when you were done
You would reboot it so at night. I could go reboot a whole bunch of systems into this
Gosh, this is so cool. Oh, man. It was clustering optics. Yeah. Yeah, okay. Well. It is a gen 2 derivative. I
I
Really had fun with that stuff
It'd be really cool to set that up again sometime. Yeah, that does sound fun kernel 2.6
No and 2.4 my time 2.4 if you want the good stuff
That's what an optics in that. This is what the KDE desktop look like back in the day look at that
That KDE one or two. I don't know I don't remember, but I do remember that digital clock
I had all of my KD desktop set to use that digital clock
You know this clock did you the one thing I'll say about this version of KD is this panel was rock-solid
I have my panel crash on plasma sometimes now and this panel never crashed like that
It's probably all just one process or something but
Boy that was a totally different time. Yeah, right. That's funny to think about last version was September 1st 2004
It is possible that you might be able to do it on modern kernels because apparently
OpenMozics was forked in their Linux PMI and is currently developed. Hmm OpenMozics auto-discovery new nodes automatically join the cluster cluster management tools OpenMozics user land and OpenMozics every node has root access to every other node via SSH
Yeah, that was the other thing I loved about is they just talked SSH
MFS DFS a to support every node can have a full-blown X or console only for more memory
So what is would you say is still in development?
Linux PMI, I think but Linux PMI, huh? Sounds like something else the website might
Yeah, Katie, too. Yeah, I think so a project with a lot of potential 2009. Yeah
a lot of potential
This is Linux unplugged episode 200 and 22 for November 7th
Oh, welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that survived Chris's new rust obsession, and I'm that Chris. Hello
My name is Wes, you know, you know beard
I kind of blame you because you kind of got me into rust so the beards here too, but you know
I'm not here next week. You can blame him. Oh, I gotta fill in for me. Okay, I'll be here. Anyway
All right. Yeah, I think he's playing rust over there right now in the corner despite that
We still managed to put together a pretty good show this week
It's it's gonna be packed with a lot of community news and a story too
We got a little anecdote that we that I think resulted in a pretty good app pick this week
Desktop environment. We don't often talk about very much and then Starcraft 2 for Linux
well
Well, we'll explain what's going on there
Dan's here from elementary OS tells what's going on with granite
Which I think is one of the coolest things about elementary OS and maybe you'll find out why and then
There's a spat herd around the community right now, and there's a lot of crazy speculation. Everybody's got conspiracy theories
I'm gonna give you a breakdown of
What's going on between the software Freedom Law Center and the software Freedom Law Center?
And the software Freedom Conservancy a hype free conspiracy free
Concise breakdown of what's going on and the projects will be impacted by this dispute
Why we actually care the actual open source projects the code that you and I all use on our day-to-day
Adventures what's actually getting screwed over by all this shenanigans. We'll get into that and then to make everybody feel better
We're gonna wrap it up with one badass-looking command-line utility that helps you straighten out
You stress the heck out of your Linux box and then visualizes the whole thing for you on the terminal so whoa yeah
I really like this tool
So we'll talk about that to kind of pick up the mood before we get out of here
But you know if if there was ever morale officers to be had it's those in our virtual lug time appropriate greetings mumble room
Hello
We will do our best to be guiding you through those morals. Oh, thanks morale's not morals
I
Thought you said more we'll take both actually no morals. You know what that's true. That's very true. I'll take that
I'll take it you guys can help us with both. That's probably very useful
So let's get into some interesting news
Just to sort of loosen us up a little bit because there could be ups and downs in this episode dramatic moments things that no one
saw coming
But in the meantime let's talk about Gladys a
Raspberry Pi powered intelligent open-source home
assistant
Yeah, okay, so Gladys is new
It's designed from the ground up to act as a central hub that interacts with a variety of smart
IOT that's Internet of Things devices. I know I'm sorry smart speakers other devices light bulbs
But it has a couple other tricks that a lot of your average assistants don't
and Gladys or Gladys can communicate with low-cost
433 megahertz door magnetic contacts and wireless motion sensors through RF
433 megahertz transmitters which and receivers which I was just thinking I believe that's the stuff that Noah really likes to oh
That's the stuff. He likes to install
and of course as all the other kind of fancy things and they have a they have a demo video where someone has a Bluetooth a
Bluetooth low-energy switch and they're able to activate a light and music scene by
Pressing that switch and then talks to the Raspberry Pi 3 and it implements their commands and you can see they do have a GUI
That's nice. It's definitely
For geeks because you put in your for your home for your parameters your home your address your city your postcode your longitude your latitude
You know those guys things that all average a home user setting up today's IOT devices have off the top of their head
I keep them just on my tattoo right here. Yeah, of course you do. Of course you do and they've got bots
that's the one thing I do like if you don't want to do anything else, you can just text it like a like a
Text message and Gladys bot will respond to it. I know you're pretty hyped about this, right?
We call you're probably gonna be deploying this. Oh, yeah, totally
100% definitely
Okay, all right, well I wanted to start with something weird but apparently nobody gives a shit about it
That's right. I mean you didn't bring no on the show. He'd love it
Yeah, maybe cuz it's talking his 433 megahertz RF. Well, and it's self-hosted
Yeah, Dan you play with any of these like like I got a couple of echoes you play with any of these kinds of things
I need like smart switches and stuff, but you know, not really just cuz I'm in an apartment
So there's not much modding that I feel comfortable doing here
Yeah, I think I think the smart switches are a good way to sort of dip your toe in there
It's useful for me in the winter when it's cold. I know I'm an old man, but I have my heaters on it
It's nice. It is nice. I think for this we just really have to see you know, duh
Is there any adoption or there are people doing novel things with it that are passionate about it until then?
Yeah, one of the the interesting things about this is you can expand it to add additional protocols by adding like the Z wave USB dong
Yeah, yeah
Yeah, this is I sort of put this actually in here a secret
I secretly put in here to just sort of test to see what the interest was because I'm thinking people are burning out pretty bad
On these is what my sense is and so I wanted to see how that would play out. I I
Think it is kind of the case. I think it is kind of me
I think it's but I what's interesting is I think it does have some mainstream broader appeal
Yeah, I think so
But also probably comes and goes and waves to you, you know people buy a bunch of it
They have it that you guys do it and then it's like you're done spending your money for a bit
You're done spending your money and like only so many new types of interactions come online and you know the certain rate
So at some point you're like, well, I turn all my lights and my heaters off and now the other thing is
Maybe the people that are buying this are doing it to make stuff easier
and so you go with the tools like your echoes and
Your home assistants and your hues and stuff like that that are all really easy to use because that's why you got it in the first
place
Right and geeks are like we want full-fledged solutions. And so it's not a real appealing market to us. Yeah
Have that said I find it to be a nice I find it to be and it is actually
How did I say that one of the reasons I've stuck with it more than more of the automation is because it's had a high
Degree of family appeal spousal approvals and children like my kids like they all get it
They all know how to use it and it works well with that for them
Which is one of the reasons why it's stuck
So, okay, maybe something more toward niche then what do you think about this guy's signal is now available as a standalone desktop app
It's an electron app, but but you can get on your your Linux or your your Mac's or your Windows now all of them
Yeah, and the setup process is kind of interesting. So you download it that gets their shipping as a deb right now
And you can't do jack with it until you have it set up on your mobile device, too
And then once you have signal configured on your mobile device
There's a process and signal where you add a new device and you scan a QR code and you just tell this app
Okay, I've set it up on my mobile device. I'm ready now. So it displays the QR code
You scan that with your phone and it links them up. It's pretty similar to telegram then
Well, no, no, so well, I mean in that it's useless until you set it up in your mobile device. Yes. Yeah
But what's different than telegram is it syncs all of your messages in your contacts?
From the other device not from the server
So once it's once you've paired them it then does this moment where it says alright, hold on there boss
I got to pull down all your contacts and all your messages and sync it to sync these two things up
Let me ping your device and so instead of having all this stuff sitting on telegram servers
It just blasts down to a new telegram install
This stuff has to sync between your your own encrypted device and before they do that they each set up a key
Yeah
They have a little they have a little chitchat back and forth to negotiate and then they and then they do the sync
so that was interesting but
You know, you're not gonna have your I
Ironically, I'd say it's not even nearly as doesn't feel nearly as integrated even as telegram does which is like some QT app that uses
Their own thing their own black magic. I'm disappointed that they don't have a snap and only sports distros that use apps. That's what they say
Yeah, Linux distribution supporting app like Ubuntu or Debian. Yeah, I bet you send a you are already actually
What do you guys think don't bother them about it when you install it on arch anybody the moment room a signal user
Are we all just a bunch of telegram bitches now? Everybody just all telegram. Yeah, we are we look at the telegram
No, buddy signal you do. Yeah, I do occasionally do
All right import your app MMS messages into it and actually have it as your default
Texting app on your phone so you can use it as your messenger
You can only you know, you can enable extra features for signal protocol to work its magic
But yeah, it's just a texting app. I just checked there are six different signal a you are Wow
Oh, so that's why do you use signal say over telegram is a different contacts you separating them out is a different features
You know, I don't use it a ton. I have a way more people on telegram
So I do use telegram as like day-to-day, but I have a couple people on signal and you know
I do I do have more trust for it and it's I do
So when I do have conversations, I'd like to keep private. That's my choice now heavens
Do you also have any other ones that you could compare it to are you just a signal user?
I've used telegram too, but not as much
Telegram is more of an app and signal is more of a replacement text messenger
Okay, fair enough. That's how I would compare it really they both have the same encryption features where you can enable
you know one-to-one communication, but
signal actually replaces the MMS app which or where a telegram is just a
third party
Program just another app on the phone. Yeah. Yeah, it really is
So in that context the signal would be more equivalent to hangouts, which you can do the same thing. Mm-hmm
I wish I bet you don't get that that integration on on the Apple iOS on that
Stone isn't even it's not even
That comparable either because hangouts doesn't exactly replace your MMS app even though it can
but it doesn't have
integrated encryption into it at least with a protocol which is
Vetted
It looks like a pretty nice app and they're steadily adding features
They just recently the beginning of October started beta testing read receipts
which is something that can be nice for some folks and then at the end of October you we got the desktop app and
Now they're working on expanding things like doing gif searches to include in text
You know the jiffy kind of stuff that people love all that kind of stuff
So they're they're slowly just checking off features that a lot of other systems have but what did impress me about it
Was I really felt it felt it felt more secure than telegram
It felt like it didn't feel like Vladimir Putin was reading my messages
Yeah, right when tell it every time I'm using telegram I go
Yeah, yeah Putin could read this one and this doesn't seem that exciting but the you know
The Chrome app version of it
I think that was off-putting to a lot of people and so having like real first-class
As long as you're willing to consider like John real but regardless having first-class desktop support
I think makes it a lot easier for me to make this the case to others that hey you should jump on here
so man speaking of
Crossover and Chrome. I mean speaking of Chrome Crossover has a Chrome OS version now Crossover office
Folks that always hacking away at wine and then yeah
They make their commercial their commercial version that I've I've almost bought every single version of now because they just think it's it's a nice
Way to manage your wine
Installs if nothing else and there's been other things that come along like gaming on Linux and other things
But nothing's nothing's nearly as good as crossover and now they're talking about a version for
Chromebooks
This is gonna be huge potentially if it if it even half works
They have a video should we risk it you want to do a little hope how to install
Oh, this is how you install crossover. I do like the music
Stage one had this music. We would be there. Oh
Yeah, we got it. We'll figure that out
You think we'd have do you think we could figure that out by the end of the show no no no if we're gonna do
The whole VM thing yeah, okay, but next time yeah, so anyways stay tuned for news on that because it's been announced
It's there. They have a beta right now. That's good. So does that change things for you?
No, make a Chromebook anymore if you know it, but it does it does probably make it more appealing for a lot of people
You know how we used to speculate is the Windows subsystem for Linux gonna keep some people on Windows
I know for a fact now it has I've heard from several Windows users who are considering switching
Yeah, and they were considering switching to Linux, and they're like I don't need to know I mean it does make sense
Right if you're just a casual. You don't really care you haven't bought into the whole
Open-source free software thing you don't use it you haven't so this realized what if this is that move
What if this is that move on Chrome OS? Yeah?
Maybe that means only the true Linux users will remain kind of see the writing on the wall for that like a mile away
You know
You know you I'm saying yeah, yeah, it's probably only gonna
I bet you only works on certain Chromebooks, so so you got it okay here you go
Here's the requirements has to be a Chromebook with an Intel processor. Oh you have to have Google Play services available and enabled for it
So that probably means a Chromebook that can run Android apps, right?
That might be how they're doing this
And then 200 megabytes of free disk space and 2 gigs of RAM and if you got if your Chromebook meets those
Requirements then you could potentially run Windows applications on your Chromebook
So speaking of messaging applications does anybody care that Skype has
made
Made that Skype for Linux version that new crazy Skype desktop version
That's now officially the main Skype desktop version
Oh yeah for Mac for Windows 10 real official Windows 8 Windows 7 and Linux are all now switching over to that
Electron version of Skype the one that we've been beta testing in the studio and
Sorry to report guys that the
Feature that I know you all wanted really badly in your Skype. It's been delayed on the desktop version
I hate to break it to you, but snapchat style stories
Didn't make it to the desktop version of sky. I know I know I know you wanted to have snapchat like stories in your Skype
I really did
Did they manage to port ads?
They did. I think they did manage. Yeah, they didn't have reliability
They hate that
Microsoft declined to say how many total active Skype users they have today so TechCrunch speculates
That means it's probably still around 300 million
But the company did give some details Microsoft said that Skype now has surpassed a billion downloads on Android
Geez generated 2 trillion minutes of video calls since 2006
I think half of those are text naps and today's users make up to 3 billion minutes of calls per day
3 billion you can multiply anything by the number of users you have it sounds pretty good
It's funny how how much more
This new version looks like and has the features of discord and slack. Yeah and slack there and they've been doing bots
They're doing bots too. They're really trying to everybody's trying to be so they've got their reactions
Everybody's trying to be slack and it's so annoying
Can't slack just be slack
Like like at least when matrix did it they did something unique there, you know
But like Skype if you go look at this
We'll have a link in the show notes you look at the screenshot in that article. It's what you would almost think
It's slack at first. Maybe someone wrote how to write an electron app. That's like scat slack and then
Everyone else is just like, all right, this is easy
Everybody's just looking at the source code to the slack app and going, you know, this is great about electron apps
It's all just right here. Let's just take it
I don't like the problem is that a lot of times people look at and they go oh, you know
This is the leading solution. Let's compete with that
And instead of looking at this is the problem that they tried to solve and that's how they came up with a new competitive
Product. Yeah. Yeah. Oh, you know what? I'd like here's how I'd like the Skype folks to think about it
Why do people want to use Skype over slack for video and audio calls and whatever reasons those are?
let's get really even better at those get even better because
slack is adding pretty decent web RTC video calling and
I if I if I wanted to just use slack with that had video calling I would just use slack and
So Skype needs to ask the questions to themselves
Why would somebody still choose to use Skype over slack now that it has those features and double down on that stuff?
they're just making they're just watering down their feature set and
Unfortunately, and I hate to be this guy so typical of me
Really just so disappointed in myself even but we all are don't worry
And you will you will you you have to back me up on this because you witnessed it firsthand
We have legitimately had considerably better audio and video performance under the old Windows version than we have
With the new Skype beta. Yeah, that's true
it pains me to say it but you are right like we tried for weeks to get video working properly in a way that didn't
Suck on tech snap and and then we eventually just for on a whim like well
Let's reboot into Windows 7 use the old version of Skype. See what happens and it was bulletproof
Ever since and it sounds better too. And that's really that that just pisses me off now. I wonder now
I don't I wonder which version Dan was using like I wonder if it's any better if it's the modern electron on both ends
Yeah
Probably I do find you to be better
So on Koda radio if both my Mike and I are on the electron version
It's better and if he's on like a non electron version
I have to reboot into an OS that has that okay version interesting and then it sounds better. It works better
The two do not still I don't think work as well together and I'm just you know
Just listening to with my ears recording these shows
I maybe other people getting different results, but for the my is my broadcaster bad ears of yours
Well, like a kid screaming them a lot. So they're not as good as I used to be
All right. Let's talk about a desktop environment that doesn't get as somebody put it enough love on this show recently and that's enlightenment
Enlightenment has a brand new release 22. How about that?
Did you even know did you even know after one year and 1500 patches?
200 tickets on their issue tracker and a whole bunch of new features. We get a little 22 and one of the headline features is
greatly improved Whalen support
Adding support for all kinds of stuff including some of the pointer stuff that was really broken and improved support for ex Wayland as well
Which is enlightenment was one of the first desktops to actually implement Wayland protocol support because of their compositor
Design they had I imagine that they had to have as well update their protocol support
In order to get up-to-date, but they were one of the first yep
Yep, they they definitely were and they just had they just had to get they had to get caught up essentially
They've made some improvements to how their windows tile and they have per window now pulse
Right there in these so you have your title bar where you have your application icon you have in the middle of the window
You have the name of the app and then you have your window controls like your maximize your minimize in your clothes on the far
Right, but on the far left next to like the icon
they put volume control for that specific application if
That's not if that's not the most brilliant thing. I've ever seen it brings it to me
I'm saying saying enlightenment 22. That's what's going on the studio machine
Systems reloading all these systems. It does actually make me want to try it next to go
I don't know if it would work an X to go but it if it if it did it would that would be pretty great
They've also worked. I remember their gadgets were really cool
they've been that they've improved the gadget infrastructure as they put it and
They've also created a improved GUI for like pseudo prompts and SSH password prompts. That's nice
Obviously, I'm not it. I'm not a daily user. So I can't speak authoritatively on it. But I
Mean, I'm a little enlightenment curious. Yeah, I am as well. Maybe I can install it on gentoo later
Yeah, if you ever get that gentoo working West, I'm sorry
Just one job. Just one. You know what West just just know it
No, it couldn't have said it better myself. No, okay. The FL is way faster to compile than the no more
Yeah, no kidding that actually be a shortcut when you get to that stage you should do that yeah, why not
Yeah, all right. Well, let's let's keep going here
I got a I got an app pick as it were based off of a little support call
I wound up in before the show so I thought why not share it with the whole class
You're so generous speaking of class Linux Academy comm slash unplugged go there and sign up for a free seven-day trial
It's a platform to learn all about Linux really any DevOps topic and then any of those huge platforms
Around Linux like like OpenStack or or AWS or Azure. There's just a big OpenStack summit and
Lots of news I almost put some of it in the show
But I figure if people are open stack curious
They could just go to Linux Academy Linux Academy comm slash unplugged you support the show you sign up for a free seven-day trial
They have a great system with hands-on scenario based labs. They have instructors real humans that can help you
They have a course scheduler when you're busy
learning paths with your series of courses and content planned by instructors and
Then they have a community that's full of your fellow Jupiter broadcasting listeners because they've been a sponsor for quite a while Linux Academy
Comm slash unplugged. It's a great platform. That's always getting better. They're always adding new value adding new content
Fixing up and improving and going back and rephrasing and based on feedback or addending things based on new commands. It's
It's a great system Linux Academy comm slash unplugged go there sign up free seven-day trial
You'll get a sense of the system also
Enjoy the offline content you can download and take some study guides with you and Android and iOS apps to listen and study on-the-go
an audio that you can kind of take in like an audiobook it's pretty nice system Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged you might say they paint a great picture in your mind
I do and speaking of painting a great picture the lady
My lady my lady friend came to me last night and said I tasked one of my employees
Her name is Christina with setting up an image editor on our front front workstation
Okay. Now Christina is a lifelong Windows user and the front workstation is an Ubuntu 1604
system with unity 7 on it and
I
Immediately my heart sunk because I'm like, oh god
how could this have possibly gone because what is she gonna do first she's gonna go to Google and
Best case scenario and no disrespect to the game project
But best case scenario is she somehow after all of her research online because this guy loves to research. She's very diligent
Mmm, she winds up at GIMP somehow figures out how to get GIMP installed on the Ubuntu box
And then they go to just they want to create some signage because they haven't marked they have a marketing thing coming up and they need
Some digital billboards. They just need to mock together some signs for it to show the artists what they want
That's all they're looking for. And so if they can they can paint would do the job, right? And of course as
Luck would have it they wound up at GIMP and they got GIMP installed to their credit which good work
I wish I could have had like a camera on that to see how all that went down
They got like a Linux badge. They can give them just like a good job. You've installed GIMP. That's a rite of passage
I actually was very impressed. So they got that installed and then they opened it and
That's where it didn't work out. I'm like whoa, and it's funny
You know what?
Their first reaction was and it was so classic it couldn't have been more classic because I had no influence on the conversation
Well, this is nothing like Photoshop
Oh, oh my god, damn it. Damn it. I'm like, come on. Come on. Okay
Well, have you heard of GIMP shop?
So I yeah skin. Yeah. Yeah, I I thought about it
I did but you know
there's another app I've mentioned it once before on the air and I think was years ago and
Linux action show and it's just such a great basic app and it's it's it's pinta
P I N T a and it's painting made simple and they have a PPA available for Ubuntu
So at first I had to try to install it through the software center
But it wasn't working for so, you know, you know what?
You know what is always the easiest is just give people commands have them open the terminal
It's just it's it's it's binary they type it in and it either works or it doesn't work and there's no like
What are you seeing on your screen?
Where is that button that like it's just describe where the menu and right did the prompt come back or did the prompt not come?
Back, that's all I have to know and so I I was able to with three commands
She got the PPA set up
We got a repos update and then she got it installed and they're up and working with with Pinta P I N T a
It's a free open source program for drawing and image editing and it's it's just powerful enough
It's more powerful. It's more like a paint net if you ever use paint on windows
I used to use that and it's more like paint net. It's got layer support. It's got histories. It's got tabs
It's got lots of basic image editing
and
It's just it's just really doesn't come with the cute dog picture because I don't think so
If you're looking for something simple as well, I'd also give a shout out to my paint. Yeah. Yes
My paints also really good, right? That was the other one that I had. I knew there was another one
I was forgetting my paint is also what I like
So my paint org is where you can find that one
And then yeah gimp shop as heaven mentioned is if you just want to use gimp
But just have the arranged in a way that makes it look more like Photoshop, which is something I've enjoyed
Because I had used Photoshop previously because my mom was a graphic artist
And so she's been using Photoshop literally since version 1 and so it was always in our household
Yeah, so I grew up with from version 1 and then I stopped using Photoshop
heavily around
But I still use it on and off frequently
With our JB has a creative cloud subscription and I still find it to be a better layout than GIMP
I probably you know, I'm probably equal in my usage there
And so if I could just make gimp look more like Photoshop, I think I'm gonna do it again
I think I'm gonna try to gimp shop it up again. I used to do it
I think I'm gonna do it again and I'm on unity. I'm gonna gimp shop it up. I'm going all in
Because a lot of people that know Photoshop know that Photoshop has plenty of obscure features that but they would probably never know
For years unless they were an expert and so they expect new features to pop up and gimp shop does give them that
experience of
discovery
And if you want something else that's advanced, that's not the GIMP then
There's also Krita. Yeah, which I think is maybe more for drawing but yeah
Yeah, I know that Albert likes create a lot
So there there's a lot of there's a lot of hubbub today about this Starcraft that came out for Linux Starcraft 2
Give me started on it. Yeah, it's just a headless thing
it's a headless thing, but it kind of it might be a cool way to run like
The Starcraft server remotely on a Linux box somewhere. Is that what I'm getting here? Well, that's I'm aware of it's the protocols
so as long as the protocols are
Network capable. Yeah, and not just
Local network capable then you should be able to run a Starcraft client on a remote server and have it
Relay all of the commands back and just play locally. He's so yeah, I'm pretty excited digital open digital
Yeah, right, right
Now we just need somebody to write an open source front end right to talk to that. I know
Yeah, can you play Starcraft 2 on Linux? I've never tried so don't know and under whiny. Oh you can
You can hashtag rust life. I
Don't know. All's I know is rust. I've been every free minute. I log into rest
There's a Starcraft 2 arch wiki entry. So that says something I'll save it for user
We're gonna have to talk about rust on user this week because I had such a hoot with wimpy and poppy last week
They got me they sucked me in and I came in at the right time and it's been a blast
So check out this the checkout user later this week for the I gotta I gotta start also poppy if you're listening to this
I think you might be a psychopath. Sorry
All right, moving on. We got a question that came
Oh
We go back for just a second sure sure I'm looking at the the downloads for the Starcraft 2. Yeah. Yeah, it's password
It's in a password protected file and the password is I agree to the EULA. Yeah
Yeah, I looked around too for licensing stuff and it was pretty I don't know people are pretty jacked up about it
I look down again. Okay, looks like under wine. It's platinum though. It is a parody good. Oh, it's the game is yeah
Oh, it is apparently under the AI and machine learning license
Well, I know where all my hard work hard-earned money is going which is a blizzard specific license
I tell you okay
I'll tell you if you boy if you want to if you want to try out a few life theories like
Should I have been a member of the collective should I've gone out on my own?
Could I live after the collapse? You should play rust Eric. It's a it's a good
It's just a good mental exercise and just try out a few different life scenarios
All right, so we got a question that came into the show and maybe Dan might help us with this one because I bet he
Has thoughts and I bet so he says guys what distro should I be using to get high DPI support on my laptop?
I recently bought a Dell XPS 15 and I've been having a hard time finding a distribution
That doesn't look like crap on my high DPI display
anything running XFC
Not that
What do you think though Dan because I know
High DPI is something that the elementary project has some opinions on and I
Recall one of my first out-of-the-box high DPI just working by default distros was elementary OS
So I'm gonna put that down for you as a recommendation
But high DPI thoughts in general is there things to look out for or things he can look for
yeah, I mean high DPI is pretty complicated right now actually and
I think the first big question to ask is are you gonna be using this with an external display is
If you are then you definitely want a distro that's running Wayland
Is mixing DPI's is not something that X does well
Definitely that is you'll get the weakest link in the chain basically on that external monitor and it's a bummer
Yeah, yeah, then the next question after that is
What scaling does your display attempt to do normally because Windows does?
of non integer scaling and so a lot of these manufacturers are putting out displays that are built for non integer scaling whereas
Most high DPI ready desktop environments in the Linux space right now only handle integer scaling
Wow, I barely even understand is that right the fractional scaling. Yeah, that's yeah
Yeah
So so if your display is looking for like a 1.25 or 1.5 scale
Like you're gonna have a pretty pretty bad time, right?
And unless like unity has some stuff for that like the latest gnome added some stuff for that
But that's still like you still probably want to be on Wayland for that and you're talking like the really latest version of gnome
Yeah, so if you get past those two things and you're like, oh
I'm only gonna do integer scaling on my laptop and I'm not gonna attach to an external display
Then you can pretty much go with anything. That's ggk3. Yeah
I have I will say I have pretty good success with elementary OS and I have great success with unity 7
You have to go manually do it in unity 7 like an animal
I have to squinted my screen and I that's where you have the magnifying glass in your in your desk drawer
Right for that
But the nice thing is you just hit the super key you type in display enter and then it's to the only slider on that
window is the one you need to move and you just slide it up to like a 2 in my case and
Mm-hmm looking good and I bet that's the case for the XPS 15 too. I bet it just be a 2
Remember for them they have to remember that it's the disc or desktop environment that does the DPI scaling not the distro, right?
Right. Yeah, that's important. Yes. Yes. Yeah, the question to what did say distro didn't it?
So you could yeah you yeah, you really need to focus more on the desktop environment. So the latest gnomes
plasma can do this to
an elementary
And and you know, I'm gonna be that guy miss a unity 7-2. Mm-hmm
Yeah, definitely unity 7 you got to kind of stick to that stuff for right now
And if anybody has any other tips, please leave a comment. Let us know
So Dan the real the really tough stuff about that though is you're gonna run into like apps like Steam that don't scale
Oh, you're like OBS or like a lot of the really important apps that you're gonna want don't support. I'd be I yet
Yeah, you know surprisingly my daily driver at home
I've wound up on a high DPI display and not didn't even really just that's the laptop I ended up taking home for a bit
and
That's really where it stands out the most is Steam
otherwise, it's pretty good like my day-to-day apps that I use Chrome and Firefox and the terminal and
My editors they all look really good now
so it's it's those things like Steam or it's old X applications that
Like an old Java app or something that just look like real hell. Yeah, or sometimes like some proprietary stuff
Like that the Dropbox UI doesn't look quite right
But it essentially looks right and telegram has support
You can go in there and you can tell telegram to zoom its UI up a little bit and then it looks then telegram looks
fine, too
So good luck. So Dan why we're chatting. Why don't we talk a little bit about the new release of granite and
And what's new there and and maybe I know we've talked before maybe even on this show about it
Maybe not but kind of like a quick recap of what the heck granite even is
Yeah, so if you're not familiar with what granite is
basically, we we had this problem when we started out where we're making a lot of apps with not a lot of people and
Realizing that we had a lot of common design patterns that we were spending a lot of time
Rewriting over and over and over again, so we made this library on granite and it's a companion library for GTK plus and GLI and
Granite basically is just a way for us to not repeat ourselves. It contains like common
utilities and widgets and
Design patterns that we've used all in our different apps that you can use in your apps, too
And it makes it really easy to write nice
elementary HIG compliant apps very quickly and so this has got a I got to imagine helped with the app store
Adoption that we talked app centered adoption. We talked about last week over 50 native applications
I mean a lot of them are maybe all of them using granite to get set up. I
Don't know if all of them are but but I'm sure like a fair number more
I don't have that stat actually handy, but I can tell you that we're over 60 apps now
Hey
Thanks, I think this is I think the reason why I've always praised this is because it's a
It's the easy button for developers. Yeah, it's it just it does a lot of the hard work that they don't really want to do
Yeah, okay
Maybe I could learn how to do this right and the thing is is like it takes care of UI
Elements that you don't have to worry about and by using these it looks consistent and well integrated with the rest of the entire
Operating system and so it looks like it's part of an ecosystem
So I really I really think that every distribution should have this I think
Canonical would have had this with unity 8 once they were done
I think Gnome
Started to go in this direction with gnome builder. They started down this path, but there's all there's there's so much work to be done
here and
Now we have an iterate another it of release. It's a 0.5 release of granite. What's what's new?
What's what do you what lessons have you guys learned recently? That's been sort of integrated into this release
So there's a there's a couple big things in this release. One of them was
Not only what's new but what we got rid of
There's a ton of stuff that we built out in granite that is now
Available in GTK or has become features of GTK. So we're able to pull out a bunch of stuff and make it way leaner code base
But we also went in and we redid the whole demo app
so it's way easier to find out like hey what utilities and widgets are actually supplied by granite and
Then with some new utilities for a date time though. We have a new relative date time utility
So you can give this utility a time and then it'll say oh that time
It'll give you a natural language string back like oh that's in five minutes. That's in three hours. That was yesterday
That was last week, you know
It'll give you like a natural language response. You can use in like your messaging app or scheduling or things like that
Nice. Yeah, I'm going through the post right now. It just looks looks so clean
I really like this demo app because as a as
As somebody who's maybe not familiar with what what all granite does bring you can just sit down here and basically tab through this
Application and see all the different stuff that it brings and it's the range is is pretty big
Actually, it's quite a bit quite a quite a lot of stuff
Do you I guess so this is 0.5 and I'm sure you're not gonna want to speculate about the future
But am I gonna someday see things on here?
like maybe like some sort of cloud related service on this tab or some kind of
Something that's unique to elementary OS like a like what other things?
Do you think down the road could be added to the sidebar of options that granite lets you integrate with your application?
Um, I mean, I guess the scope of granite is pretty big
Because it is just like whatever common widgets and utilities are in there
one of the one of the next widgets that I want to get in there is we built this sharing menu for
App Center so you can share links to apps and App Center
And so I really want to build that into a proper granite widget with a great API so that you can just say
like hey
I've got a string that's this many characters and it has a link and it's an image and then the popover will figure out like
Oh, like these are the social networks that accept all those parameters and then you know, like that's one widget
I really want to get in there. Very cool. I like that
Yeah
this is this is a nice write-up with with great pretty pictures too and I have it linked in the show notes if you guys
want to check it out and
I I would think it's got a it's got to help lead to the success of those 60 apps the fact that they're actually there
I mean if you stop and think about
The the hard work a lot of times on Linux is getting the UI right for developers
A lot of times we have a lot of really great applications and the UI is just a little rough
Well, I like it seems like that's kind of sometimes the barrier to like, okay
Well, I know how to make all the back end work
But to make it usable to you, I need to have like it doesn't have to be beautiful
But I just need a usable UI. So if this can make that trivial, that's awesome. Yeah, and it's not it's not electron, right?
See, that's the thing like that's that that would mean like, okay
Well, if I can just integrate this whatever else I was doing I don't have to jump to the electron band
Yeah, the other day. These are I mean correct down at the end. These are essentially GTK applications that are being produced
Yeah, it's all it's all GTK 3 and and yeah granite uses GTK behind the scenes
So it's they're all just GTK widgets that are kind of prefab
And one of the things that's super awesome
I think is that we've been able to get a developer ecosystem that's excited about
GTK CSS and providing like easy style classes for them to use
You'll see like a ton of the apps and App Center have nice brand colors
And they do interesting things with GTK CSS to look really nice. Mm-hmm
Well great work and nice post to good job on the write-up. It was a good read. So thank you very much
Thank you. Come on explain Matt. It's nice to pick your brain on that. Go ahead. Oh
Granite is built upon Fala, isn't it? Yeah, it is. Okay, and Valor is built upon GTK
So it might be an indirect, but that's why it's built upon GTK
But Valor really gives you a lot of power when it comes to scripting and it's ease of use
Doesn't it? Yeah, it's built. It's built purpose-built 4g object though. It feels really native to write
GTK with Vala
Hmm, that's what I've heard and I have looked into it before but I haven't bothered with it
You should give it another chance if you're familiar with C sharp
Then you'll be able to jump into it super easy. Like the syntax is buttery smooth
It's way easier than trying to write GTK with like C. Oh, yes G object all raw G object is
Brutal makes my eyes bleed. I
Every time we talk Vala, there's always some hater that comes along and talks bad about it
But every time I hear about it, it sounds like it sounds like a great way to go and it is a good intermediary
Yeah, exactly. And it's I mean the proof seems to be in the pudding more and more
There's some great apps and we've been talking about apps in the App Center
but of course elementary OS ships just with a bunch of great apps that are built around this and
Vala already installed out of the out of the ISO
So it's not just the things in the App Center
It's also the apps that have been getting shipped on and revved on now for years
Yeah, and the whole de to our desktop environment is all GTK 3 and Vala
I think I think we use more GTK in our desktop environment than gnome does these days. I
I
Now that I'm back on the 1604 bandwagon like never before I should I should give it another go, Dan
I should really take another look cuz damn if it doesn't all just look super appealing all the time
I like it and I'm liking 1604 a lot. It can't am I allowed to talk about that? Is that okay?
Okay, can I talk about well, so last week I I admitted that
after the whole 1710 excitement was over I ended up going back to
Ubuntu 1604 and then realizing that unity 7 was actually pretty great for my particular use case and
Then like a madman
Proceeded to just wipe all my systems and put up into and unity 7 with the exception of the OBS machine just because the capture
cards
and I'm all in and it's um
I'm loving it and I I think it's the new XFCE and
I
Thought I would get a truckload of shit for saying that last week
I was really expecting people to harp on me and I got a ton of people saying they were doing the same
Thing and they agreed really? Yeah way more than I expected. Yeah on all the all the feedback mechanisms. It was really
Surprising to me. It was like when I admitted that I like nano more than vim
I you know vim and I keep my vim skills active
But if I'm if I'm choosing I just prefer I prefer nano
I like the bottom area of nano where it just lays out the commands for me gotta hit them
I know that it prints. I just don't know how to use it. Oh, yeah. Yeah, and then of course and me
I'm a nanotech w that's I'm a nanotech w guy and I've been rocking that now for you know
Everybody always says here's the bullshit
Here's the bullshit emacs vim propaganda that you get fed as a sysadmin is every server you log into is always gonna have VI
So you just learn VI. Well, you know what? That's not true. Every server has vim first of all second of all
second of all it I have yet to meet a system that doesn't have like nano or pico or or
Joe or some other non vim editor. I just I don't I don't work on those systems
I know there's systems out there. I understand that I don't work on those systems. Sure. And so I've always had nano
I've always enjoyed it. I've always thought it's been pretty great
and so one day on the show I finally came out and I said I
Like nano and I'm a nano user and I got a ton of people that said I also like nano
and I'm not saying Vim's bad or emacs and
Now I'm saying this with unity
I like unity and I think it's pretty good and I'm gonna use it for a while
And I thought I thought it'd be the same thing
I get flamed ton of people came back ton of telling people came Joe Collins made a YouTube video about it on his YouTube channel
About how he's going to you know, he's sticking with 1604 in unity. There's something about the LTS releases is when you when you
When you become an LTS user West you realize that all the other releases are just beta tests for the LTS
And they can call it 1710, but it really should be called 1804 beta. Yeah, where's that ding soundboard effect? Oh, oh
Man, I don't know what's happened to me
I feel like I feel like I've had some sort of like a
Psychedelic Linux experience and I've come out on the other side of it as a changed man is what happened to me
You'll be back large drug in six months
Unity there's one gripe that I cannot accept that there's a lot of its desktop
Functionality is implemented in Python and that's against my morals
Yeah, I can you know, I can see it
I can see switching for moral reasons and I tell you what if if I felt like that ever caused it to be slow
Or pokey or crashy I'd probably bail but so far. Yeah, you wouldn't care what was making it slower crashy. You just get out
Oh, yeah, the old XFC menu. It was based on
Python no, it wasn't the XFC menu. It was that desktop that was recently implemented in C
But it wasn't Python before
Goodness gracious does anyone remember? No
Okay. Anyway, I might have been a budgie. It might have been the budgie men. Oh, yeah
It used to be a mint menu. Okay mint menu is based on Python
They re-implemented it in C and it was way faster. Sure. I think but he's bitten written in every language
Yeah, that's
Minimum and then you I can only hope unity goes down in flames, but I like nano
You know it as long as it's all small batch organically sourced 100% locally produced code
I'm okay with that. I would like to try unity and the new gnome with the Ubuntu shell. Yeah on the same system
I haven't done. Yeah, like do a little a B skis. Yes, that's I
Used unity at work all the time. I'm kind of like, okay. I wonder maybe I should try that
Try the new version out. See what that looks like. I feel like unity's faster having ran it on some of the same systems, but
Then again, what do I know? What do you what the hell do I know?
There's something about the fact that my doc isn't some extension
QML JavaScript, you know the quick like that doc here in unity. I don't know. It just feels really solid
It doesn't ever flicker. It doesn't ever
You saying you want to flicker in unity plug-in?
So I've just been on the gnome desktop long enough where my doc's just totally taking a shit. It's gone away and then I'm like
oh, so
Right. Okay, so I don't have that anymore
and then and then what it was is of course it was well gnome updated and the
Doc I had installed was from the repo but the repo package for the doc extension hadn't been updated yet
so I updated the gnome desktop the extension so then I had to uninstall the
Distros version of the extent of the extension then go to then then go then go to the gnome extensions website and
Install the extension separately see if you just don't install the doc extension then that's all right
But I take your point. I find it particularly useful just to have my sets of icons right there
I don't you know, I'm not a big doc guy. I doesn't have to be a bar. It doesn't have to be a doc
I don't care what you call it. Just call whatever you want
I can't don't have to get bigger when you hover on them
Microsoft got it right in Windows 7 when they added the quick launch down there. Yeah, they got it, right
and I
Ever since that I essentially try to get that and I just want I want my launcher and my searcher and I want my quick
launch icons and
That's what I go for and unity 7 does a pretty good job with that in a way that doesn't make me feel like I'm using
Windows at all, but still gives me that same kind of functionality. So it doesn't really make me think about it
That's what I like because that's the problem with mate and both with XFCE is like I'm like using Windows over here
I'm using Windows again
Digital ocean comm go over there and create an account and then use our promo code do
Unplugged you get a $10 credit and and with that $10 credit you could try their
object storage for two months for free so you can stack them and I don't know what maybe build some sort of
Media empire in like two months because with digital ocean you got their fast connection
You got their dashboard for days. You can deploy in seconds
everything's SSDs and you can choose the distro that best suits you or
Or even Alan Jude's free BSD and for me besides the object storage the block storage is it's just great
It's been around for a while and what I love about it
Is it shows up to the operating system as if it was just a block device?
So you can look in d-message you'll see it show up there and then you can go in FS tab and you can actually just
Mount it to a folder on your file system and it's just like dev
So can we install Gentoo on that thing? Is that our solution?
Boom boom, you know, I am thinking maybe you're not up for this challenge anymore
We'll see maybe you're the one that's supposed to be looking into that right now, that's true
Google that for us. Okay back to digital ocean digital ocean's also got monitoring and alerting and they have team support
Which is really great and then they got private networking
Which is fantastic because it doesn't count against your transfer when you use that private network
And that's great for like proxies or if you got a database or a backup server
Which I should probably do that. I should probably do that
I've got a new digital ocean droplet that has some pretty important data on there
So I even put that out on the public net just put put on the private one and then just let my droplets talk to
Each other digital ocean comm use our promo code do unplugged
Create the account apply that get the $10 credit and then you're off to the races digital ocean comm promo code do unplug
Hugged yeah, I wonder if you could do you think you could do you think you get that?
You think you get that gentoo working on a droplet. I'm right. I'll give it a shot
That's me. You could do that. Yeah, that would be pretty interesting. I would say it'd be interesting to try it
I was thinking of EM, but a triplet would be pretty dang cool
It'd be pretty cool. Okay, so
There is a story
That we're going there
We're gonna go to and I want to be really careful because this thing is gonna have big ramifications
and it's one of these stories that is very easily turned into clickbait and it's very easily gonna
It's gonna be it's be it'd be simple to set the tone of the conversation in the wrong direction
On this particular story and I think it's too important of a story for that, but I also I
Don't want to ignore important things that are going on just because I'm afraid of screwing up the discussion
so we're gonna start with
what's going on between the Software Freedom Law Center and
The Software Freedom Conservancy two separate projects. I'm gonna refer to them as Law Center and Conservancy just to try to get yeah
That's that's a good idea. Yeah, the background between these two organizations is the
They well by all public appearances seemed to be two cooperative organizations
In fact, the Law Center helped establish the Conservancy early on was involved with that process and provided counsel
So they've been working they had a publicly appeared to be working in tandem
for quite some time
I don't know exactly about the people running the two different organizations if they were working in tandem necessarily, but we'll get to that perhaps
on September 21st
Eben Moglen on the Software Freedom Law Center's blog posted a rather long post that addressed IRS
Service changes now under the Trump administration versus the Obama administration and it restructured
how
the Software Freedom Law Center could move around essentially provide services for open source projects and
in this they they say this is game-changing for them and that the
they have they've been waiting for these developments and that the gives them and their clients the best of both worlds that
essentially, there's a new market that's going to be opening up for the
Freedom Law Center, they don't really kind of give any more detail than that
But shortly after that, I think it was on the 27th of September
We have more details concise and accurate details in this week's Linux action news
The Law Center sent a trademark
Notice to not not to not to the Conservancy
but like the patent office saying or whatever the trademark office saying we're concerned that there's confusion between the Software Freedom Law Center and
The Software Freedom Conservancy and I agree there is there is some confusion between the names
It is hard to to keep them straight. That's why I'm trying to say Law Center and Conservancy
and
It appeared that perhaps the Law Center was sort of gearing itself up to become more competitive
Then on Friday, November 3rd fast forward to Friday, November 3rd the Software Freedom Conservancy the
Which I believe is probably Karen Sandler and Bradley Coon. I think is his last name probably co-wrote this
I'm not sure but it's the staff they have they have assigned the staff and
They write a month ago the Software Freedom Law Center the non the not-for-profit law firm which launched the Conservancy in
2006 took the step of filing a legal action in the United States Patent and Trademark Office seeking
cancellation of the Conservancy's trademark for our name the Software Freedom Conservancy
And they say in here that this is this is really weird because you know
We're all where the community has recently all come together and decided that we're all about taking every other approach first before legal action
that's what the Linux kernel enforcement statement was recently about and
They say yes, we sometimes disagree publicly about policy issues
But we're both sort of working for the same interests. So they were disappointed that
essentially public resources or community resources were being wasted on this action and it didn't really sound like there was any attempt to work with
Them it sounded like on September. Oh September 22nd that when when the petition was filed
That the process just started there was no communication before that is what is what the impression you would get by reading this
They say yesterday we provided an answer that defends the of the list of defenses that we plan to use
Now the element of this is this really something is this post was made
During an event that was being held by the law center that the the the people that are filing the petition
That's when this post went live was during this event and
My understanding is Karen was at that event. She she was there when this went public
Now the Conservancy is
home to about
46 member projects and you have to understand that this is
This isn't just membership. This is sort of like a governance a financial financial governance and
Copyright governance the copyright can be transferred in some cases and maybe all cases to the Conservancy
So this is an umbrella
Organization that is essentially home to some of the intellectual assets for these open source projects
And there's a bunch on their list core boots on the list
Debbie and copyright aggression project ether pad is on the list
That's where a bunch of closure projects are hosted get is on the list
The GPL compliance project for linux developers is on the list homebrew inkscape
There's a lot on this list. There's you know, it's a php my admin is on here outreach eqm you Samba
Some pretty important projects that this is essentially the home for this is the this is the legal structure for the copyright holder
Wine is also on that list
And so it's surprising that
That even Mowgli's organization who used to be part of the Free Software Foundation that ended about a year ago
Rather quietly that his organization who's funded by the linux foundation
Would be aggressively going after the Conservancy for trademark violation
When they helped them set up the organization in the first place
The law center helped launch the conservancy
in 2006 and they served as the Conservancy's law firm until 2011 and never had any trademark issue during this time
That seems pretty bizarre that seems pretty bizarre doesn't it
And people are raising all kinds of conspiracy theories because the law centers one of the law centers funders
Is the linux foundation and one of the linux foundation's biggest members is VMware and one of the companies that the Conservancy is actively going after
For GPL violation is VMware
So some people have drawn conspiracies there, although I wouldn't necessarily put any stock in any of that and I would say we should all definitely
Wait until way more information comes out because this really could come down to personality nuances
Between the people that run these different organizations because on Monday our rather bizarre post was made by the software freedom law center
By even Moglen's organization
And it's hostile. It's it's aggressive and it's
It feels like unnecessary like they would have been better saying nothing. I'll read a few highlights
So the law center responds to the blog post made by the Conservancy on Friday
And they write on Friday we were while we were putting on our annual conference at Columbia Law School a puff of near apocalyptic rhetoric about us was published
By the software freedom law center's former employees Karen Sandler
And Bradley Coon who now manage the Conservancy which was originally established and wholly funded by the law center and still bears our name
We were busy with our conference when this happened which seems to have been the point
We were glad to have the chance now after a little much needed rest to help everyone avoid unnecessary hyperventilation
And then they go into several different things
They claim that they attempted to make some contact they say we've asked intermediaries friends business associates comrades in the free software movement
Other alumni of the law center to stress to Bradley and Karen the importance of opening negotiations
One would think that this unless one would think this was unnecessary with people who talk so frequently about the importance of communication
And opening connections with respect to compliance
And enforcement but there when the shoe is on the other foot no efforts on our part have gotten us the slightest progress and bringing about discussions to resolve these differences
Friday's response to the Conservancy's management is grossly disproportionate and in view of their long maintained refusal to communicate with us irresponsible
The entire piece and all of the outrage hangs on one thing and that is supposedly Karen and Bradley always said they were too busy or always too busy these are direct quotes to have time to talk
Sometimes we were not with sometimes we have not even been offered so much as the courtesy of refusal
But when wouldn't a law center know that they should probably be talking to the lawyers of the Conservancy shouldn't be lawyer to lawyer shouldn't they be reaching out to the representation of the Conservancy not to Karen and Bradley directly
Well I'm not so sure because if they filed the trademark action I imagine that would involve the lawyers right like you don't have to call the other law firm if you file a petition in court court delivers
But if you're so hell-bent on establishing communication before this action wouldn't you have tried to reach out to the representation you would think so yeah yeah I don't know what do I know it's really you know me all right but this is
This is one of these messes that on the surface looks like the law center wants to be in a new market and essentially take over the Conservancy's gig which it felt like it wasn't capable of doing because of rules
That they as they put the Obama administration put into place that tied their hands and so it was necessary for them to create these umbrella organizations like the Conservancy out of out of these restrictive IRS rules
And now now that Trump's in and all these guys are out new guys are in these rules are gone and so we don't need the Conservancy anymore we don't need them
So let's just have everybody come back over here to law center and we'll be your representation will be your copyright holder will be your umbrella organization will be a one-stop shop everybody's happy the only problem is people don't understand it because the name differences
So let's just get them to change their name so we can compete it's what it seems like on surface to some people and that is dirty because the reality is the Conservancy the software freedom Conservancy
Should be something that is not subject to the political whims of the United States when when the when the political what they call it pendulum swings to the other side and different people come in running the IRS then what are we going to do
Then the Conservancy will matter and when you have projects like wine that have been around for decades they're going to they don't want to be swung around by the different politics of the US and and moved around all the time the Conservancy offers a stability
And a home that is safe and from that political turmoil it's part of the whole spirit of the open source projects that we want to support in this thing and the you know the thing is like the Conservancy and I'm I you know I really don't have a dog in this hunt but just going off recent news the Conservancy seems to have been working with Colonel developers to come up with this enforcement statement statement that everybody seems to like and the thrust of it was legal action as a last resort
Which having talked to people who write Colonel code that's what they want that's what the people who write the Colonel want is they want legal action as a last resort only to be initiated when other community efforts have failed.
That's what people making stuff want and if that and if that's what the Conservancy is also agreeing to then they seem to be representing the wishes of the Colonel developers and that seems to be a good thing in my estimation seems to be like the Conservancy had recently just made a good move and then.
Now this whole thing's breaking.
It's really it's really it's really interesting and I I don't want to speculate much because I think I feel like we've done plenty I've tried to represent what everybody's different theories are on this while still giving you the base fundamentals of when these things all went down.
I wouldn't I if I could give anybody any advice on this story don't participate in speculation online don't don't stoke these conspiracy fires because this stuff is all going to be an a long suit so super boring legal process that will eventually all be played out for us.
And it'll all be documented what exactly happened and we don't need to speculate if we're just patient the information of it'll eventually just tell the story the terror the story will tell itself and so I encourage all of us to try to tone down the speculation tone down the rhetoric or the clickbait.
What do you call it you know if you people are going to be incentivized to tweet and blog post and make YouTube videos about this story and I encourage people not to do it because it's it's a nothing story so far it could literally come down to personality conflicts at the end of the day and it could represent tearing up tons of open source projects.
So there's a lot of better stuff to talk about.
Yeah. But the thing is we can talk about it but we can also just wait it'll all play out in the courts and everything will be right there in public record for us to review and we don't have to speculate if we're just patient. So that would be my be my advice said my piece.
I think it's a fascinating story.
Yeah right. I mean it's certainly important but like there's going to be enough bad and maybe good coverage of it there's going to be plenty of drama and other things that come out of it for better or worse probably worse. And so we pay attention but we don't have to create a whole hype machine.
In the meantime I just hope the open source projects of these different organizations represent aren't screwed up with this I hope you know they're like their money isn't taking from from protecting or financing them or running them I hope that those funds don't have to be like redirected to fight this kind of thing like I hope nothing like that happens.
That's what I hope for. And then we just sit back and wait.
But if anybody in the number wanted to chime in you or have any questions because I know that was a lot to kind of unpack again I'll just make another plug for Linux action news because we did a much better job just breaking it down concisely and accurately.
But the development the response post wasn't out when we recorded Linux action news the software the law center the software freedom law centers post was wasn't posted until Monday.
Hmm. Yeah. Yeah. Wow. OK. Yeah. You good. You good. Yeah I'm good. You good. I'm good.
It's it's rough stuff. That's rough stuff. That's why I said we're going to have this really cool app pick at the end of the episode because this thing's not only is it look beautiful runs on the terminal but it helps you kick your Linux box.
Box boxes but there somewhere I can speak I swear we're kicking but that's what matters. But it's gonna be kicked. It's a way to stress test your system. I know we have someone in our discord room who has a new oryx on the way.
And so this will be a great pick for him because he can throw this on his new oryx and kick the tires.
And then I'll just show you. I'll show you anyways. So let's let's take a moment and thank Ting for sponsoring the unplugged program go to Linux.Ting.com Linux.Ting.com $25 off a device or if you bring a device they'll give you $25 in service credit.
Nice. CDMA and GSM networks. So you can probably bring a device.
I'm a GSM guy myself. I have been for a long time now.
But I started out on CDMA and there's nothing wrong with that.
See people when they listen like CDMA what does it matter with you guys. Guys in the Pacific Northwest we got a lot of trees.
So many trees.
CDMA can punch through those trees in a way that GSM just does not seem to. I can't I can't explain it. I'm not a I'm not Neil deGrasse Tyson.
I can't explain it. But I can tell you this. You can play around. You just go to Linux.Ting.com to try it out.
You pay for what you use six dollars a month for the line and then your usage and Uncle Sam's cut.
Whatever that might be in your area. He's got to always get his piece Wes.
But that's why he's going to pay his Ting bill.
You know what I'm saying though. That's why you got to start with the six dollar a month line.
Because that's just like that is at that price level where if I get that on a MiFi and I don't use it much one month I'm not feeling too guilty about that.
And the fact that I don't have to worry about how many minutes I may or may not use.
I love that. And they've got a great dashboard to manage it all. Tons of nice devices you can buy directly.
And then the best customer service in the whole industry. Check it out. Linux.Ting.com.
Big thanks to Ting for sponsoring the unplugged program.
All right. So it's stress terminal UI. It's kind of a it's kind of a complicated name.
So just shorten that to s t u i s dash t u i and it's nice looking.
Now I don't want to trigger I don't want to trigger heaven because it may be written in Python.
I didn't double check before I put it in. You install via pip. I'm sorry heaven.
I didn't mean to trigger you but I didn't realize that but it is a Python app.
But it's a command line Python app not a gooey Python app. So is that. Are you cooler with that.
Are we good. He's not talking to me now. You see that. That's how many he's cursing in the background.
It's funny so many won't talk to me now. Unbelievable.
So the stress terminal UI for your CPU is a great little way to.
Not only do you get CPU information but you get temperature and power usage information all visually graphed and represented for you.
You display the performance dips that are caused by thermal modeling monitoring.
Like you can actually see like when thermal when thermal like limits get hit you can really see it on this graph which is really cool for testing laptops.
That's why I mentioned the or interesting. Yeah that's not something a lot of other tools really highlight.
No you might see it like something like the XPS 13 or maybe the Gallego but you're I don't think you're going to see that on the Oryx at all.
You may not see it on other systems too but you can always try and find out.
And then they have a stress operation mode for really just running the CPU into the ground for as long as possible which I kind of like that too when I'm trying to get a laptop really hot to feel like get a sense of what the fan noise is like for a review.
It's pretty cool. And you can also turn off different areas that you don't want to see.
So if you just want a nice simple display and you have this is the thing that really I think makes it look the best is it has this fancy graph smoothing option.
And I just something about really smooth fancy graphs on the command on the command line dude.
You know what I'm all about it. I just can't help it.
You start putting pretty graphs like that on a command line all of a sudden it like it's like the future meets my childhood and I can't help but love it.
So S-TUI and it's available via PIP and it could be a fun way to kick tires on a VPS too. It doesn't have to be like a laptop.
Oh yeah. Super easy to get going. Here we go.
Oh dude it looks really good on there.
It does look really nice.
That's with the window all maximized like that it looks even better.
Purple bars.
I got to say this is probably one of the slickest looking end curses I've ever seen.
I'm going to have to take a look at the look at the source there.
They've done a really impressive job. That was actually what originally drew it to me and then I was like gosh I always am looking for ways.
I have like a I have like a little toolbox now of ways that I abuse review systems that are just like torture chamber tools.
Well you want to know. You know you only have a short time with the system.
I do. And I should give a I should give a plug to the open benchmark site and the Ferronix test suite because isn't that just the funniest thing.
You open that up and you go to the game section and sure enough if he's not keeping that thing pretty update to like most recent games.
As whole automated scripts will download it from steam and install it on your system and then play the game for a little bit and benchmark the whole damn thing like geez Louise.
If there isn't just an incredible incredible amount of work into that Ferronix test suite.
That's true. That's another way to bang on your system a little bit but this is just a nice quick way.
You could just load this if you got Python already on your system and it'd be easy to do on a VPS too.
Oh which I like that so and it just looks so good.
I should kind of a weird name.
Stewie?
I should put it on my yeah I should put it on my X to go system and just keep it going for a while and see how that does.
See how it see how it performs.
Boy that does seem like a nice way to like maybe benchmark some different VPS things.
Maybe it's just like a backwards Family Guy reference and it's just Stewie.
Terminal user interface.
Yeah let's do I do like Stewie. That's it. That's a good way.
Sounds like a user interface designed to stress the user.
Yeah we should that we already have that perfected.
So I think we're looking at the recording right now.
Yeah.
We're definitely so we're trying to come up with a way to do the Gentoo challenge.
We're going to we're going to really try to get it in the show.
We are going to try to get to this. We're going to try to get this in the show.
It's going to take forever man.
So but we have we have an approach we're working on.
I don't think we've totally nailed it down yet.
We were discussing the pre show.
So if you joined us live you kind of heard what our current thoughts are.
And so after the show Wes and I are going to compare notes and see which way we think would be the best to pull it off.
And then we have hopefully by next week's episode we'll have our game plan for the Gentoo.
I'm excited.
But I think what we should plan for for the focus of next week.
So it's not going to be the Gentoo review but we're going to tell you our plan for the Gentoo review next week.
See what we're doing here.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
I don't.
You know what what happened was.
Listen we'll call this a stage zero install.
Yeah that's right.
So here's the thing is this like New York thing happened and then like this Ubuntu 1710 thing happened and then next Tuesday the Fedora 27 lands.
So I feel like we're going to have to talk about Fedora.
That's next week.
Next week's episode we got to talk Fedora 27.
So I'm going to be installing that to give that a go.
Back on to Gnome for one week.
I don't know what system I want to take off of Unity though.
I've got to go through that whole thing now.
It's going to be rough.
It's going to be so rough.
You're going to hate it.
So if you get a chance Wes install Fedora 27 the next few days.
Yeah. All right.
Kick the tires a little bit.
We'll talk about it on next week's episode.
I always love installing a new Fedora release.
And that invite extends to the virtual lug and those of you listening on your own.
If you want to check out Fedora 27 before episode 223 kick the tires with us and then we'll all come back and compare notes and talk about it or listen along.
It'll be like a co-review.
You like that?
I like that a lot.
So we have a Discord room dedicated to this show now.
Go to Discord.me slash Jupiter Colony for the main link to the server.
And then once you get in there look for the Linux Unplugged channel.
And I'll mention in this because we're using this during our live shows.
So even if you can't make it live you can still go back after the show and see some of the stuff people talked about.
Some of the links people shared.
And you know maybe beat new community members too that might still be there.
It's like a live archive.
Yeah.
So it's kind of a cool way if you see something go by the video that you want or if you just want to check it in.
If you listen to the audio version you're like I want to just go see what the Discord room is talking about.
You can go over there.
We do still have that mumble room.
We're still doing mumble for the audio.
That's where our virtual lug still at is on our mumble server.
So still totally looking for people to join us there every single week.
Please. Yeah.
All right.
Guys is there anything else we want to include in this week's episode?
I don't think so.
Well very good.
Where should people find you throughout the week Mr. YS?
At Westpane.
You crazy SOB.
That's me.
Also check him out on the TechSnap program.
Oh please do.
What about you Beardsley?
Wrecked and done it.
There you go.
Nice and simple.
Easy peasy.
Find me tomorrow on the Unfilter Show.
Going to be a huge show.
Huge huge show.
You better be preparing right now.
And then I'm going to share a little rust shenanigans.
A little rust shenanigans in User Air.
So check out User Air this week if you're curious about that and it's a lot of fun.
Otherwise just grab our live time over on our calendar page and then join us next week if you can.
Otherwise grab the feed and we'll see you then.
I think it's wasted effort.
Who snuck him in there?
Let's figure out this, Todd.
We've got to get this thing figured out.
Oh gosh we do.
Come on now.
We've got to get this.
Let's get this thing printed out.
Let's get it out of here.
It's going to be dark here in just any minute.
Come on now.
Let's go.
JBtitles.com.
Perfect.
Fine.
I didn't get a hit of America compiling Gentoo.
Winner winner chicken dinner.
Ed is all you need.
Nice.
Dude where's my C?
The division inside open source.
A community divided.
Token Ring has been killing it with the titles today.
He's getting deep is what he's doing.
He's reaching deep into his emotions and he's coming out with these real winners.
I do want to do a Windows unplugged.
I'm not going to lie.
We could do it.
Conservient rust.
I was hoping we could just bang this out real quick.
I know.
I thought this would be a quick one.
I thought okay this is the week.
We're just going to be.
We came in with a lot of energy.
We get it.
But that didn't work.
That has already backfired I can tell.
I can already tell.
I'm burned out.
Yeah.
We're tapped out.
Well you and I need to go on a sabbatical for five years and then come back and do one
episode doing just one really good episode and then retire.
Right?
I'm in.
Yeah.
Done.
I don't think so.
I don't think it works.
Maybe I'll buy my own lady jubes.
Yeah.
There you go.
We'll go caravanning.
Yeah.
Caravan.
Actually the dream would be to caravan and still podcast.
That would be a lot of fun.
We'll just do road shows the whole time.
That sounds great.
Go around and do Linux meetups.
Either great or entirely exhausting.
Yeah.
We'd be both of those things.