Yeah, so I would give Google Domains a very solid try.
I don't think it offers all of the feature sets that something like a Hover does, but
they do straight up real simple mail forwarding.
You can do that.
To configure that, it's very easy to go right in there and set that up.
They definitely have made the process of setting your domain name, pointing it to somebody
else's DNS server, so like for what I did, for example, is I registered my domain name
and then I went over to DigitalOcean and I got the name server information from DigitalOcean
and it was very easy to plug that into my Google DNS account and point my domain to
my droplet.
So now I've got – I had a droplet that I hadn't assigned a domain name to for a long
time.
I was just going by IP because it was just for me, but now I'm going to share it with
Ange and I wanted something that she could just type in the domain name.
So I thought, okay, it's a good excuse to try out Google Domains.
So I went over to Google Domains because it just opened up to the U.S. public today.
I bought the domain.
The process is – it's very straightforward, just like you'd expect.
You essentially search for the domain.
You use your Google Wallet account to pay for it, so whatever funding source you have
for like the Play Store is the funding source you'll use to buy the domain.
Once that's set up, you go in there.
It's very simple, like five-button interface to manage it.
One nice thing is it lists all your domains in a nice list and the last item in the column
is how many days remaining on that registration, so you get a – it's really very straightforward
like how long you have.
Very clear.
It's very minimal.
And once you click into it, the fields are very basic.
There's some help.
But like all Google products, if you want to dig any deeper, like for example, when
I wanted to find out if I could get privacy for a.us domain, they have a learn more link.
Once you click that, of course, it sends you into the hell of Google help pages which just
go deeper and deeper and never really answer your question.
So just like all Google products, if you're comfortable, you'll be able to get something
done really quick.
But if you go outside their area that they have support for, it's – you hit a wall.
You're like, there's nobody you're going to call.
For example, and this is an ad for Hover, they're not a sponsor, but with Hover, they
are my domain name registrar and I had a very complicated thing happen that was like mistakes
on multiple registrars and I – there was like literally I was trapped between three
different registrars who had had like an internal database that disagreed with an external.
It was very complicated and one call to Hover resolved the entire thing whereas with Google,
I would have been kind of just out of luck I think.
I don't know exactly.
They say they have support, chat, phone or email support.
I haven't tried that yet.
I'm kind of skeptical but Google has been stepping that up recently so.
So is it just a registrar or can you actually manage your DNS zone files from within Google
domains?
You can go in and manage some of it.
So a pre-specified amount of stuff like your name servers, you can set up DNSSEC, your
registered hosts, you can add synthetic records to do common things like domain forwarding
or you can go to Google apps, custom resource records so like your type A domains, your
C names, your MX records, PDRs.
Oh, okay.
Okay, so you can.
Okay.
Yeah, you can set all that stuff up.
Very minimal interface.
I'd show it to you but it has all my IP info in it.
The pricing is very fair.
It was $12 for a.US domain, $20 I think for a.com – no, not 20.
It was very – Harold, you know what?
I'll search for one right now.
Let's see.
Give me a domain name.
Let's do Ubuntu Touch.
Let's see what we get.
All right.
One quick –
So here I can show you this UI.
So now it searches – it gives you a little frowny face for the UI – for the domains
that are not available.
So I get frowny faces for Ubuntu Touch.com and Ubuntu Touch.net but I get green smiley
faces for Ubuntu Touch.org and then it's also recommended Ubuntu Touch.equipment,
Ubuntu Touch.properties and Ubuntu Touch.systems.
So the Ubuntu Touch.org, $12 a year.
Ubuntu Touch.equipment and properties and systems are like 20, 30 and 20 a year.
And so it looks like.coms are about 12 bucks a year.
Same with.US.
One question I have is hover offers volume pricing.
So like the more domains you have on your account in hover, the less you pay for renewals
for all of your domains.
Yeah.
Does Google appear to offer anything like that?
I don't think so.
I don't – I haven't played with it long enough maybe to be able to fully answer that
but from the looks of it, you're just doing one domain at a time and it's just always
the same flat right every time.
You can add multiple domains.
There's like a cart but I don't think there's any discount but I could be wrong.
I gave – over the weekend I gave their latest testing ISO a spin.
And it's kind of slick.
So like one thing that's nice is it does some notifications that are pretty good.
And one of the things it'll do is it'll actually update the installer.
So I boot the live environment and I get a notification that comes up and says, hold
on a second, Antigros is updating the installer.
It updates –
Yeah, I just had that as well.
Yeah.
And it closes and reopens it so you get the latest installer which is pretty nice.
And –
That's good.
So I started with the KDE 4 implementation and when I was done, what I got was it's
KDE 4 but with Numix and kind of a GTK look.
And before you freak out because that sounds horrible, I am surprised at how not horrible
it is.
It flattens KDE out a little bit.
It takes away the blue glow and the very oxygen look of it.
You're going Numix icons.
It's kind of a GTK look to it but I actually think it's – I don't know if I'm going
to stick with that look but I was surprised how well they were able to take that and translate
it to KDE.
And the benefit was the GTK apps also looked – everything looked kind of at home.
It was kind of – I was like, wow.
You're giving me the itch.
Do you want a little bit of Arch Linux inside info?
Yes.
Of course.
So we had voting for new Arch Linux to use yesterday and one of the six trusted user
– we're the people that look after the community repository and moderate the AUR
and other stuff.
Look after backend infrastructure.
But one of the new to use is the maintainer for LXQT.
Oh, cool.
Yeah.
So I guess what's coming to Arch Linux into the official archive soon.
Yeah, no kidding.
And we'll probably have first class support.
That's great.
Yeah.
I know him quite well because he's on the old existing LXDE team and he's the guy that
does all of the package maintaining for LXDE for Lubuntu.
So he's come the other way.
So he's come from Ubuntu into Arch and I've just made the transition from Arch to Ubuntu.
So we've sort of passed each other in between there somewhere.
Poppy I was wondering, did you ever end up getting a new laptop?
I know that was on your shortlist.
No, I postponed it because my warranty on the ThinkPad X220 doesn't run out until next
year and the and I wanted to keep hold of it just to keep it going until it dies really
because I don't really need a new laptop.
I was wondering if you saw that new XPS 13 from Dell.
Yeah.
The new one looks awesome.
But also I like the new ThinkPads that have put back the old keyboard with the proper
keyboard.
It's a proper keyboard.
Yeah.
Too bad the latest unbelievably I couldn't believe it.
But I have to double check.
I could be wrong.
It seems so impossible to believe.
I would definitely double check this.
But I swear, after I saw the announcement of the new Lenovo's, I went look to the video
cards and their Intel 4800s.
How can that possibly?
Is that bad?
Yeah.
That's really bad.
Because I mean, like the Dell XPS is the Intel 5500 and when you get to 5000 and you're in
the Iris series graphics, it's a whole new category of Intel graphics.
Oh, I didn't realize that.
5000 years from when to 5500 is the new Broadwell chip.
Their Iris is 6000.
The Lenovo must be.
Oh, OK.
The Lenovo must not be.
So they're still based on the Aswell.
That seems odd though, right?
Well, no, because Broadwell isn't even shipping yet, technically.
Like it's just starting to come out now, like it was announced at CES.
Oh, so these laptops are all having, these laptops today shipping are with a processor
that's already been replaced, essentially.
Maybe a little bit, but.
Yeah, I guess it's gotten so good at this point, doesn't matter too much, though.
And Barton said there will be an Ubuntu version, so that's good.
Yeah.
So that's cool.
Did you guys all see Linus's rant on Google Plus that happened like back in December?
I missed it.
And I just wanted to read it real quick because I really hate HFS Plus a lot.
So there was this talk about, I love it.
It's this Google Plus thread and they're talking about a bug and a wild Linus Torvalds appears
with a great HFS rant.
He says, and he goes on to talk about how there's this bug, and he talks about how there's
issues with HFS.
He says, quite frankly, HFS Plus is probably the worst file system ever.
Christ, what shit it is.
NTFS used to have similar issues with canonicalizing UTF-8 using non-canonical representations
of slashes.
I think they at least fixed them.
The OS 10 problem seems to be fundamental.
He goes on to, which is like, okay, so fundamental problems, okay, all right.
So then the thread kind of gets hot, right?
And they start kind of, some people come in, come on, Linus, they're trying to call him
out.
Linus, then some people agree with him.
He comes back in to say, further in the common thread, the true horrors of HFS Plus are not
in how it's not a great file system, but in how it's actively designed to be a bad file
system by people who thought they had good ideas.
The case in sensitivity is just a horrible, horrible bad idea.
And Apple could have pushed fixing it back in that era.
They didn't.
They doubled down on a bad idea and they actively extended it very, very badly to Unicode.
Okay, so NTFS did some of the same, but Apple really took it to the next level with HFS
Plus.
There's some excuse for bad case in sensitivity in a legacy model.
We didn't know better.
But people who think Unicode equivalency comparisons are a good idea in a file system shouldn't
be allowed to play in that space.
Give them some paste and let them sit in the corner, eat it, and they'll be happy and they
won't be messing up your system.
He goes, and Apple lets these monkeys work on their file system, seriously?
It's not even a paste-eater quality thinking.
It's actually actively corrupting user data by design, Christ.
There are lots of good reasons not to move to ZFS though, cough Oracle, but they could
have pushed people to a case sensitive HFS, which would have then made it much easier
in the long run to migrate to anything else.
But no, this is not the choice Apple took.
There is a case sensitive option, but Apple actively hides it and doesn't support it.
The stupidity.
It burns.
Here's the thing though, when is Apple ever not doubled down on a bad idea?
Every time they've had an idea, they've always said, yeah, we're still doing this.
They've never admitted that they are wrong.
Yeah, they even found a way to ship a one button mouse that depending on what you do,
actually has six buttons.
So like, yeah, they've always just like, they won't admit when it's a bad idea.
I've got a Logitech mouse that's like that, but I love it.
Yeah.
I mean, it's not necessarily a horrible idea, but it does kind of feel like they, even there,
they won't admit they were wrong.
Yeah, that's true.
That there's use there.
All right.
So there you go.
Linus Torvalds rant segment over.
We should have a Linus Torvalds rant jingle, I guess.
Honestly, it's really too bad that Apple gave up on porting ZFS.
Yeah.
When Oracle, as soon as Oracle got involved, they're like, nope.
Yeah, that's exactly what happened.
It's like, well, if they had just held onto that and waited and then, oh look, open ZFS
and they could have used that and every Apple user would be a happy camper.
Yeah.
It's funny.
You know, I guess, I guess I just would, I would have expected Apple to keep working
with Oracle since Jobs and Larry Ellison were BFF, but I don't know.
So yeah.
I mean, it really is.
And the only reason why I really want to even bring it up is because we were talking last
week about how power users are getting sick of the Mac.
Well, I mean, what I like is I have been bitching about HFS for a few years now because of production
problems.
And now more and more people are talking about it and it's going to be more of these kinds
of things that'll come out.
Yeah.
HFS is horrible.
Horrible.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's barely finding the microphone
in all of this Pacific Northwest fog.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
Matt, is it foggy up in your neck of the woods like it is down here?
It's just lingering.
I haven't stuck my head outside yet, but I see sunshine coming through my blinds.
I think we're okay.
You are such a geek.
I am, right?
I haven't gone outside today.
I know.
I really haven't gone outside if I hadn't had to drive into the studio either.
So I guess.
I mean, I only go as far as the wifi allows.
Right.
That's a good point.
That's a safe bet.
Yeah.
It's been like this since last week.
We've been surrounded in a fog, but in this fog, we have that time to reflect on the state
of Linux, and we have a great show coming up for you today on the Linux Unplugged show.
So coming up, just a little bit, we're going to do some quick feedback this week.
And then I want to discuss the four best new Linux distributions, according to Jack Wallen
for 2015.
And at first, I came into this list, and I'm thinking, the four best lists.
These lists.
I read the list, and I'm like, hold on.
Hold on a second.
I think Jack's on to something.
These are some compelling distributions, and you might not have heard of a couple of them.
We're going to talk about that plus then, after we gave the Mac a good bashing last
week and in the pre-show.
It is only fair that we get a little real about some Linux issues, but I actually think
it's a really great thing.
And it's a list, yes, of problems, but of problems I think are addressable, and we'll
talk about that in the second half of the show.
So Matt.
Yeah.
We probably should get started.
Probably so.
I'll put everything aside, close my VLC window, stop watching YouTube, and maybe we'll take
a moment and welcome the Mumble crew to the Unplugged show.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Good morning.
Hello.
Hey.
Hi-oh.
So before I managed to hit record today, Popey admitted to the entire live stream that he's
switched over to Integra.
He's now a happy Integra user.
And I'm still gainfully employed.
I had to give you a hard time.
No, actually, I downloaded the latest Integra release.
They just actually got the testing ISO, but Wimpy reminded me they just released a new
stable ISO two days ago.
And I, Matt, I tried something that was crazy.
I did the KDE version of Integra, and when it installs, it's kind of a GTK-looking kind
of KDE.
Now, before you puke, it's Numix-themed, and it actually works.
It's sort of a flatter KDE.
It's still KDE, but with a slight GTK look.
And the result is both Qt and GTK apps look great on the desktop.
It's overall, it's really, it's really well done.
It's interesting.
I don't know if I like it a lot.
I don't know if I'm gonna stick with it, but I was pretty interested in it.
So anyways, go check out the latest Integra ISO, they just released them and-
Screenshots where it didn't happen.
Oh, okay, okay.
Actually, Chris, the installer is running right now on a spare laptop.
And I was surprised.
I like you, you mentioned earlier the auto update thing the installer has, and I went
through the installer and it looked really familiar and I've realized where they borrowed
some of the design from.
It looks exactly like the Ubuntu installer.
I actually, when I first reviewed Integra ISO, I made the mistake of assuming they had
forked the Ubuntu installer.
I was very-
Right, no, it's their own thing, isn't it?
Yeah.
And it's neat.
Like Popey says, when you boot up the live environment, it automatically updates so you
have the latest installer.
Not to mention, once installing all of the packages, they're the absolute latest version.
So if you're installing right now, you're gonna get kernel 3.18, which is crazy, and
it's great.
What were you gonna say, Wimpy?
I was gonna say that when they started making their installer, it was heavily influenced
on Ubiquiti and they actually had Ubiquiti's source in their tree as reference for quite
some time.
That was why I actually thought it was.
So in my review, I sort of matter-of-factly stated it was a fork of the Ubuntu installer
because I went to their Git repo and I saw the code for the Ubiquiti installer and then,
even once they made their own, they still took some assets and stuff.
So some of the files were actually named Ubuntu something.
And so I thought, well, dead ringer, it's just a fork, right?
I actually looked at the freaking code and I'm like, dead ringer.
And so I say it in the show and then I got a lot of people contacting me, including the
Anticross developers, like, no, actually, we wrote that from scratch and we're kind
of proud of it.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Yeah, it's good.
Yeah, it seems pretty nice.
It is really good.
Because the Ubuntu installer's really nice, too.
Give me the itch.
I know, I know, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
I had the itch, too.
I think they make a cream for that.
You know, there's a branding opportunity here.
Yeah, that's true.
That's very true.
Okay.
All right.
So anyways, just wanted to give those guys a plug because they do great work and Popi
reminded me a little bit before the show started and then I had a weekend adventure that I
forgot to share with everybody.
So let's cover another distribution that's been getting a lot of attention.
And I think it's a favorite around here, Ubuntu Mate, or Matai, or Matati, or Mate.
So Eric writes in.
He says, it's awesome.
And I thought this was a great story.
Different Eric, not producer Eric.
And he was struggling.
He was not super happy with the direction of Unity after 12.04.
He says, when it came out, Ubuntu 12.04, I was very excited.
And he says, but then Unity had to show its face and I quickly found out what garbage
it is and my unhappiness began.
I downgraded to Ubuntu 10.04 and I found I liked it more than 12.04.
I tried Gnome 3 before downgrading to see if it was any better than Unity, but Gnome
3 is such a pig with different makeup, only really stupid.
Sorry, Chris, I know you like Gnome 3, but I'm just channeling my Endel Tervalds here.
Of course, that sounds like he's trying an old version if he's doing it on 12.04.
I'm so disappointed by the direction of the Gnome team took.
It feels like it's different just for the sake of being different with absolutely nothing
redeeming for the power user.
Everything useful is turned off by default.
By the time you're done turning things on, the desktop sort of resembles Gnome 2.
So why bother, I asked myself.
I tried Mint 17 and I was less frustrated by Cinnamon, but it still felt like a skinned
Gnome 3.
Guys, I have been truly miserable since Ubuntu 12.04 and when I heard on your show about
Ubuntu Mate, there was a glimmer of hope.
I thought I'd give it a try.
Ubuntu Mate is what every Ubuntu since 12.04, including 12.04, should have been.
Mate is as fast and snappy as Gnome 2 was.
It's clean and I know where everything is, no need to search for anything.
Ubuntu Mate makes me feel like I spent the last few years in a nightmare and I finally
woke up.
I have my desktop, I have my apps like I did before, but now I have access to sites like
Netflix and apps like Steam.
No shitty UI, no crappy ads from Software Center suggesting what I should try, no random crashes
or UI elements disappearing, my system never uses more than a gigabyte of RAM.
I'm just so happy with Ubuntu, mate.
I'll just say it again, it's an effective desktop, yet I have way more than before.
Hopefully Windows 10 will do the same for Windows users that Mate did for Gnome and
just fix it while adding tons of more functionality.
Eric.
Wow, that's pretty steep praise there.
I should say so.
Yeah, it definitely feels like it.
Sliding inside.
Yes, yes.
You should be.
I think people will really appreciate that.
Eric, you take issue though with maybe basing it on a really old version of Gnome, right?
Yeah, basically 1204 has Gnome Shell 3.4, which is utter crap.
If he were to use a more current version, I'm sure he would have a better experience
because then you've got the client-side decorations, you've got the better...it's just better overall.
And like some Destros like Fedora are pre-shipping the Gnome Classic environment now, so it's
much...yeah.
True.
And you can obtain that in Ubuntu Gnome as well.
Wimpy, did you see our interview with the Mate developer on Sunday's Linux action show?
I did, yes.
What did you think about his comments on the transition to GTK 3?
Well, I obviously agree.
I'm deeply familiar with the difficulties we've had.
And although I've prepared that unofficial repository with Mate built against GTK 3 for
Arch users, and that when Mate 1.10 ships, I will push the GTK 3 versions into the official
Arch repositories, but they are very clearly tagged as experimental.
And the reason for that is that whilst they're working fine against GTK 3.14 at the moment,
as with every GTK 3 release, we can't be sure what's going to happen, change, and break
with 3.16.
So we're kind of hoping for the day that Gnome 4 comes along, and GTK 4 comes along, so that
then we have a stable API to target.
Wow.
Wow, I can't believe you're already hoping for GTK 4.
Meanwhile, I'm...wow.
It's imminent, I think.
I think it's imminent.
I think it's going to come soon.
And the other thing that...you asked Stefano about MIR support and Wayland support.
So Wayland support has been on our roadmap for some time, and definitely Stefano is very
keen to start work on Wayland, but quite recently, probably...I first heard about it around October
time last year, Canonical have started to commit MIR compatibility patches for GTK 3.
So if that continues and comes to fruition, technically, it should be possible through
GTK 3 to target Wayland and MIR.
And what we would need within the Marte team is somebody who's enthusiastic about actually
doing it, because it's a small team, and there's lots of jobs to be done.
So there's opportunity for somebody to come in there and own that.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it's dependent on Canonical finishing their work, actually adding the
support to GTK 3, but I should imagine that's going to happen given this push this year
for Unity Next.
Now to black out 24's question, and I don't know in the case of Wayland, but in the case
of Wayland or MIR, is there extra burden on the Marte project to do things like the compositor
or something like that?
Is there more work you'll have to do besides just toolkit stuff, or is the toolkit going
to bring most of that stuff for you?
Yeah.
Well, with regards to Wayland, this is one of the conversations I had last year.
GTK 3 alone is all we need to bring Wayland support to Marte.
We don't need to sit on top of Mutter or anything like that.
Nice.
Very fantastic.
Well, I'm really interested to see how that goes.
Do you think, is this going to be a transition that will be very, is there going to be a
big change for users when Marte goes to GTK 3, or is the theming going to hide a lot of
it?
Or what's that going to look like?
Could be a big change.
Not really.
If you install it now, you can install that unofficial repository now.
So if you run up a virtual machine with, do it the easy way, go with Antergis, seeing
as though you were talking about that earlier.
They have Marte support, and I know they have Marte support because I helped add it.
You can start with that, and then they use the official Arch repositories.
You can then add my unofficial repository, and it's designed to clean the upgrade from
the official repository.
So you could jump from Antergis with Marte 1.8 built against GTK 2 to GTK 3 for Marte
1.9, and you'd be able to see firsthand what it looks like, and by and large, it looks
very similar.
Interesting.
Yeah.
Almost the same.
I mean very close.
There's a few applications where because GTK 3 just implements things differently, it looks
a bit different.
So when there's tabs in things, the tabs are laid out a little bit differently, but by
and large, it looks very, very similar, and there are a few Arch users that are actually
running that GTK 3 version and have been running a GTK 3 version for about six months now.
So it is good enough as a daily driver.
I saw the write-up on how to do it, and I thought about it.
I think I even linked to it in the Linux Action Show show notes for Sunday, and I thought
about doing it just for the interview so that way I could run it, but I ran out of time.
But it looks interesting.
I think I'm going to try it soon.
See what I notice.
All right.
Yeah.
Okay.
You know what else you should all try soon?
Something that I love quite a bit, something that Matt and I use the heck out of.
In fact, a lot of the hosts here at the Jupiter Broadcasting use the heck out of, is Digital
Ocean.
Head over to digitalocean.com right now.
Go over there and check out Digital Ocean while you can, too, because I'll tell you
that.
Things are a-changing, my friends, in the world, and you can have your own server up
in the cloud.
Earlier today, Matt, today I was like Mr. Productive, Matt.
I don't know what it was.
Maybe I tried butter coffee.
Have you ever had butter coffee before?
Butter coffee?
No.
I was going to say maybe it was the fog.
But okay.
Maybe.
I just decided not to go outside, so I stayed inside and got a bunch of stuff done.
Right?
No.
I got my butter coffee.
That's coffee with a little bit of butter in it and coconut oil.
Yeah.
And then you immersion blend that, Matt, like a bouse.
You immersion blend that.
And then I decided, you know what?
Let's go out there and let's see if I can get a little work done.
So I tried out the new Google Domains, and I registered a domain and pointed it at my
Digital Ocean Droplet.
The Digital Ocean Droplet that I've been using for quite a while to do things like BitTorrent
Sync and my Quasal Core, you know, stuff that is just handy to have running in the background.
But I never really thought, I'll just set a couple things up.
I'll never really use this very long, so it's not a, you know, I don't need to register
a domain name.
Well, today I got that done.
Right.
This is the first Droplet that I ever created at Digital Ocean.
I went and registered a domain name for.
And now I feel official because they've all got domains.
It's really easy to set it up over at Digital Ocean because they have a DNS, part of their
control panel is a real nice DNS management system that makes it straightforward.
So here's what I want you to do.
I want you to remember our promo code, and then I'm going to tell you about Digital Ocean
because they're really awesome.
It's cool.
It's brand new.
And it's for the entire year of 2015.
So use it wisely, my friends.
D.O. Unplugged.
D.O.
Unplugged.
All one word.
Lowercase.
D.O.
Unplugged is our new promo code for Digital Ocean.
So what is Digital Ocean?
Go check them out right now.
It's simple cloud hosting that's really done right.
I've got several systems up there now because it's straightforward.
I get going in no time.
It's intuitive and really easy to spin up your own cloud server.
You can get started in less than 55 seconds.
The pricing plans start at only $5 a month for your own rig.
You get 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte of transfer.
These droplets are running on top of Linux using KVM, all riding on SSD drives across
the board.
Digital Ocean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam,
and London.
But it's really the interface.
And I really, just today, just today, like before the show, I literally like, before
I came down, so I probably was doing this 45 minutes ago, before I came down here, and
it's just, I didn't even worry about like, oh well I need to go on air, I need to start
the show up, because I know how straightforward and intuitive the Digital Ocean control panel
is.
So I know that once I get in there, it's just going to be boom, boom, and I'm done.
And it really is crazy straightforward.
And they've got this API, and they've done a few iterations of it now.
It's really clean.
It's a really elegant API that the community has embraced and built a ton of apps around.
You can take advantage of that today, right now, or you can write something for yourself.
They've got a great set of documentation for it as well.
Head over to Digital Ocean, check out their tutorials.
They've got the best tutorials on the web, and they'll even pay you to write for them.
They've got editors that can work with you, and they'll pay up to $200 for a piece you
write for their tutorials section.
So if there's something that you're an expert on, setting something up that you see a gap
and people are searching for that, you could go make a little cash on the side, and write
it up for Digital Ocean.
There's just great resources over there, digitalocean.com.
Go check it out.
DO1plugged is our new promo code to get the $10 credit.
You can try out the $5 rig two months for free.
DO1plugged.
It's a great deal.
Digitalocean.com.
And a big thank you to Digital Ocean for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
It's so neat to have.
I feel like I have my own server farm up in the sky.
I know, right?
I'm actually still in the process of bringing stuff over from other folks that I work with,
because I'm like, can you just move it over to DO, because then I can just do it, and
I can just get in there and get things done without having to monkey with whatever you
got going on over there.
It's great.
All right, guys.
Matt, I think you might have a suggestion.
I have one suggestion, but we really have never solved this problem for the audience.
Let's take one more crack at it.
We can always take submissions from the audience, too, but Dukaked wrote in, and he's looking
for an open source solution for remote support, so I think that takes out TeamViewer and a
few others.
Thanks for an amazing show, as always.
I wanted to ask you how you go about doing remote support and screen sharing and remote
control for users behind routers.
This is people like friends and family behind home routers and small businesses behind their
business routers and firewalls, with them probably using Windows.
The company I work for uses TeamViewer and Join.me, which work well for the purpose,
but I want a solution that's open source, not licensed, and has no subscription.
I'm considering connecting to a port forwarded SSH server, which might help, and then using
further forwarding to get into their machine over RDP, but there's got to be a simpler
way of doing this.
Is there a TeamViewer-like solution that I haven't heard of?
Thanks for any tips.
Keep our Sundays rockin'.
Dukaked.
What do you think, Matt, anything jumping out at you?
You know, he kind of hit the nail on the head as far as, if you want to go with an open
source solution, it is certainly doable, but it's going to require some work, some SSH,
some of this, a little bit of that, a little bit of forwarding, a little bit of IP magic.
There's nothing out of the box that I know of specifically that's going to do what he
wants that's open source, and I personally just happen to use TeamViewer or one of the
others, just whatever works at the time, so not off the top of my head, no.
Yeah, I was thinking maybe Chrome Remote Desktop, but again, that's not free.
And that's been kind of buggy sometimes.
I've had some issues, so.
Wimpy, is there a way to accomplish this with X2Go?
There is, yeah.
X2Go has desktop sharing feature.
Oh my gosh.
So even if I'm not using it for like remote terminal services style things, somebody could
remote control my sessions still using the X2Go client?
Yeah, yeah.
So I have this on my father-in-law's machine at his house, so he's got port forwarding
on his router to his laptop, and when he needs help, I X2Go into his machine on a shared
session and we talk through what he needs to do.
How does the IP mapping and stuff like that work, like when he's behind his router?
Does it universal plug and play that?
No, what I've done is I've put his MAC address in the DHCP server on the router so he always
gets the same IP on his laptop, so the port forwarding always works.
Ah, so you set up port forwarding, so that's one disadvantage, but if you have the ability
to set up port forwarding, how else would you do that, because you'd have to have a
piece of software on the remote client that's updating the firewall in real time with your,
you know.
The only other one I know is you can do reverse VNC connections, so I would have to configure
at my side the port forwarding, and I can set VNC to listen, and then the client, my
father-in-law, can establish a remote connection to me, and I see his screen on mine, and I
use that for tech support at work, so our customers at work can effectively send their
screen to us.
So I'm trying to think, Skype offers some remote control features, but again, it's pretty
buggy and it uses Skype.
Oh, it's horrible.
Yeah, I wouldn't use Skype.
Yeah, Skype's not open source, and VNC's really slow, and yeah, yeah.
I'm seeing Romania, R-E-M-M-I-N-A, mentioned by Kapi in the chat room.
Yeah, that was kind of where I was thinking, it's just one of those things where it requires
a little bit of massaging to get there, but yeah, that would work.
Right, and Bentley's reminding us that Universal Plug and Play will do the port forwarding,
but you have to have something that calls on Universal Plug and Play to do it.
And you have to have it enabled.
A lot of people don't.
Yeah.
And Bentley's here in the boardroom as well.
Yeah, no, I know.
I know.
We've already mentioned Universal Plug and Play twice, so I think, and I know, so we
know there's ways to do it, right?
Like if there was a way to trigger Universal Plug and Play using a remote client, I like,
I like honestly, if you have the ability, X2GO is going to give you unquestionably the
best performance, probably better performance than any commercial packages out there.
The only downside is you got to have the port forwarding set up.
That doesn't, I mean, that might be, if you're doing a small group of people, that might
be doable.
Yeah, I was wondering too if Jitsi, I don't know if Jitsi offers a remote screen control.
I think it's just remote screen sharing with Jitsi, so I don't think that would do it.
But if anybody out in the audience knows the feedback thread in the Linux Action Show subreddit
or go over to the contact page on Jupiter Broadcasting and let us know.
I would love a fully fledged open source remote control product because right now I'm doing
a mix of Splashtop, which is hit and miss, Chrome remote desktop, which is, so I like
literally Matt, sometimes I have Chrome remote desktop and, and Splashtop on the same rig
because at any given time, one of them doesn't work.
See and that's been it for me is that like on Ubuntu boxes, Splashtop is great.
On anything other than Ubuntu, Splashtop is a face to a brick wall as far as on the Linux
side of things.
So I tend to go like with TeamViewer and like maybe if I'm running something like Arch-based
or something like that, I generally have had better luck in that space.
Usually it's TeamViewer or Splashtop for myself.
Oh, you know one that we've talked about like three years ago on the show is Guacamole,
which is an HTML file.
Oh!
Or maybe it was like two years ago.
I remember we talked about Guacamole really briefly.
I do.
Yeah, that was briefly.
Yeah.
And so that's another one to check out is Guacamole at guac.dev or guac-dev.org or something
like that.
Anyways, that's a good one that came in.
Most of the WebRTC ones I can think of are all just like views you can't modify.
Yeah.
Because you wouldn't want the browser to be able to give someone remote control.
Guacamole.
I like the name.
It's a great question and it's, it's something at the towards the end of the show, major
problems on the Linux desktop 2015 edition.
One of the things he calls out is remote desktop support solutions like this.
So I think Ducaite kind of nailed it a little bit.
I think he's kind of right.
And I know there's other things out there you could obviously do.
Like for example, at first I thought I always needed, if they're on Linux boxes, I always
thought, oh, I need remote desktop support.
And then you know what I realized?
A lot of the times I can just SSH into the box, kill a process, update a thing, uninstall
a thing.
Exactly.
And then you log in nearly as often as I thought I did when you're escaping the bloat too.
So that if the, if the hangup is in fact, gooey based, a lot of times you can slide
in under the radar like that and deal with whatever the hangup is.
Yeah.
Get so, I'm not familiar with get so, but there's a suggestion coming from, oh yeah,
that's that.
I think that's the reverse VNC thing actually.
Yeah.
That's exactly it.
That's the, the, the client side of the reverse VNC.
Yeah.
I'm making notes as we go here cause some of these are really useful.
And I think that could be used to make a program to do this.
Oh, okay.
Thanks Bentley.
That's good.
So I guess there's, I guess you could string a few things together.
That's kind of my thought.
Yeah, that's definitely it.
Although the extra go stuff sounds really cool.
Yeah.
If you just, all you need is just access to that port.
So anyways, if you give us your, give us your experiences out there, send them into the
show and we'll follow them up as a feedback next week.
One thing I talked about today on tech talk today, and again, Chrome remote desktop hit
and miss, not open source, but they did just announce the Chrome remote desktop client
for iOS.
So now you could like use an iPad and run it into your Linux box and have remote control.
So that's kind of cool.
I don't know.
And you could also do on your phone.
And speaking of phones, why don't we mention our next sponsor, Ting, and then we'll get
into the top four distributions to look at for 2015.
Linux.ting.com is where you go to support the Linux Unplugged show.
Linux.ting.com.
Mobile that makes sense.
No contract, no other termination fee, and you only pay for what you use.
Flat six dollars, pay for what you use.
They just take your minutes, your messages, megabytes, add them all up.
That's what you pay.
It's really straightforward.
Linux.ting.com will also get you $25 off your first device.
If you have a Ting compatible device, they'll give you a $25 credit and they're adding GSM
support in February.
So Ting service is going to get even better and better.
And it's all still going to be pay for what you use.
You can still have hotspot and tethering.
They're still going to have no hold customer support.
And also, they're still going to rock some great tips.
Ting has always got great tips on their blog and they're doing Ting tips right now for
Android.
And here is a great tip for probably most of the audience is if you have a podcast catcher
on Android, they've done a roundup of not only great podcast clients, but how you can
set these up, fully animated GIFs so you can look at it on the smartphone itself, where
you need to go so that makes your podcast only download on Wi-Fi.
Hey, look at that Linux Action Show HD right there.
Look at that.
So that way, you only get the show, especially when you're downloading Linux Action Show
HD over Wi-Fi, right?
That's a nice tip.
And again, think about this.
This is a mobile carrier telling you how to save money.
And the reason they're doing that is they've based their business model not on incentivizing
you to keep buying the bigger and bigger packages.
Oh, you know what?
I might need four gigs.
Ah, four gigs isn't enough, honey.
We better go to six gigs.
Oh, you know what?
We're using six gigs a month now.
We better go to 10.
And then of course, you really end up using six, one month, four, one month, eight.
The next month.
Exactly.
It's a huge range because your life is different every single month.
So that's where Ting comes in, right?
So their model is you just pay for what you use and that doesn't cost them any more if
you use less or more.
So they don't mind telling you how to save money.
And that's why these blog posts are so handy.
So this is a great roundup of how to set up your podcast catcher to only download while
it's over Wi-Fi on your phone to make sure you don't get any surprise bills.
It's among a bunch of other great tips.
Start by going to linux.ting.com, try out their savings calculator, see how much money
you would save, I'm getting like $2,000 in savings now with their savings calculator.
It's crazy because I've been a Ting customer for like two years, got my Nexus 5 now and
I'm just paying for what I use.
Linux.ting.com.
And a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged Show.
And thank you to all of our listeners out there who go there, check out Ting's offerings
and resources.
You really are helping us stay on the air by doing that.
So we really appreciate you supporting our sponsors.
Okay, so Jack Wallin wrote a piece for linux.com saying the four best new Linux distributions
to watch in 2015, and I almost always pass over these top lists because usually they're
for clicks and I don't think they're necessarily bad, but not my style.
It's usually fluff.
Yeah, I kind of thought this was going to be the case with this one.
It's not necessarily not fluff, but it's good fluff, I guess.
So he says every year new Linux distributions pop up, something new and game changing.
So he's looking at some of the distributions for 2015.
And Mumbaroon, feel free to jump in if you disagree.
Number one distribution to look forward to, he says, is Evolvo S. Ironically, I got an
email this morning that was raving about Evolvo S. He says it's incredibly simple to use.
It's inspired by the Chrome OS desktop with a user-friendly interface that anyone can
sit down and use immediately.
The developers of Evolvo S have taken a page from Chrome OS design look and created the
Bungie desktop.
Bungie is not a fork of another desktop, but is built from the ground up.
And I'm pulling up a screenshot right here for those of you watching the video version.
It does look very nice.
So Evolvo S, number one.
Number two, Sparky Linux Game Over Edition.
It's based on Debian testing.
It's a rolling release distribution.
Sparky Linux Game Over Edition adds Steam, Steam Launcher, Wine, Play on Linux to Sora
along with standard gaming tools and services like Game Over Edition.
Also has in it the PSX emulator, the Kega Fusion and Sega Mega Drive Genesis emulators
and PSP emulator.
So it comes with a lot of great stuff.
And also really low resource desktops.
So there's one for you.
And then number three, Korora Linux.
Korora Linux is a Fedora remix.
We've talked about it before.
You can choose between KDE, Mate, Cinnamon, GNOME, Xfce desktops.
It includes a number of packages that Fedora can't ship.
It's based on, like the current one's based on Fedora 21.
So it includes things like Adobe Flash, Dropbox, Google Chrome, Google Earth, Google Talk plugin,
RPM Fusion repos pre-setup, VirtualBox, all based on Fedora.
It's like Fedora that's ready to use.
In addition to all of this, Korora includes packages called Flarp, I guess, or Phalarp
or whatever it is.
Phalarp?
Yeah, I don't know.
It makes installing drivers like the Nvidia graphics driver super easy.
I like that.
Yeah.
So that's Korora.
That sounds pretty badass.
That sounds pretty badass actually.
And there they have great, he has a great screenshot here.
Ozone OS.
We first heard about this on the Linux action show.
There's very little to see at the moment, but Ozone OS will be based on Fedora and will
have a Numix flavored spin.
It's from the Numix guys.
Oh, okay.
And it's going to be based on the GNOME desktop.
Totally Numix stuff.
What's even more interesting about this project is it's partnered with Nutrix, which sells
Numix themed desktop PCs, so you might be able to buy desktops already with this distribution
as well.
So four distributions, Evolvo OS, Sparky Linux, Game Over Edition, Korora, and Ozone OS.
All pretty different distributions.
I think they might have a shot.
Eric, do any of these excite your distro hopping bone that would make you want to maybe try
them out?
Well, not really the distro hopping bone, but one I would add to the list would be Kubuntu
4, because they will be shipping Plasma 5, so that's really kind of something to keep
an eye on, I think.
It's a game changer.
Yeah.
Derek Delvin, you feel like maybe a certain elementary OS is missing?
Yes.
Actually, in 2015, and I have some rumors from some of the devs that they're working
in making their desktop less tightly coupled with just specific Kubuntu, which could yield
good interesting results.
Hmm.
Like the elementary OS desktop environment, what is that called?
Luna, right?
Pantheon.
Oh, Pantheon.
Yeah, thank you.
Luna is one of the releases.
And there's also...
And in distribution-wise, there's also Deepin, which it's a Chinese company backing it up.
They have full-time developers working on it, and they're submitting code.
They actually have a very different desktop environment, basically multiple type of things,
but they have something unique coming out of there.
I feel like Karora should be getting more attention than it is.
You think?
Yeah.
Yeah, I do.
I think Fedora is compelling, but it's just not really usable without a lot of changes,
like number one, RPM fusion, and probably Dropbox and Flash.
Right.
But it's for someone that wants to open up the hood and get in there and actually do
things themselves, right?
I don't know.
I think Karora has some potential.
I've installed it, and I've been pretty impressed by it.
And it's close to a mainline distro, so you get all the benefits of a largely supported
big community distro, but with some niceties added to it.
I guess that was my question, but it's like, why does each feature have to have its own
different version of Linux?
Oh, Alan.
Well, no, I just mean even as a Linux user-
No, I think it's a fair question.
It's a fair question.
Honestly, I want that feature, but I want it on the Fedora that I'm used to or the
Ubuntu that I already have.
That's why the rest of us just run Arch, because then we just install Arch and then just install
whatever you want.
A lot of times it's because it's silly things, Alan.
It's like, well, this is based on this and this version of the desktop, which requires
this version of the toolkit.
And the main version of Ubuntu ships this version of the toolkit because they're shipping
this version of the desktop environment.
So therefore we're going to go off on our own direction.
It usually starts something simple like that, that is sort of-
Yeah, we've had similar complications on other systems with bundled software, and that's
why we've seen a lot of unbundling happening lately, getting everything out of the base
system as you can, so that the package repo determines what version of this toolkit you
get or what version of this that's going to work with that and so on.
I think my predictions is the top three distros for 2015 are Arch, Ubuntu Mate, and regular
Ubuntu, and followed by Fedora.
That's what I think the top three- I'm not saying in that order necessarily either, could
be a different order, but I mean these distros are great, but I think you just can't deny
the fact that every time we look at Arch numbers, they've exploded since the last time we looked
at Arch numbers.
So I think you got to figure that.
And Mate is obviously rocking people, like look at you Matt, you just switched over to
Ubuntu Mate.
Oh yeah, all my systems except for two.
I think I still have one running Arch proper, but everything else is running Ubuntu Mate,
so yeah.
Yeah.
For sure.
There you go.
Chatroom says Quora is not that great.
All right, I'll take the word.
I don't actively use it.
Well, and one thing I want to touch on in that article is that I think articles like
that are cool in the sense that maybe they bring a little limelight to distros we might
not have otherwise heard of, and they're cool to check out, you know?
Yeah, that's very true.
You know, I've heard some folks in the community talking about Evolvo S now to see this written
up here, and I haven't really been following Sparky Linux Game Over Edition because it's
called Sparky Linux.
Right?
Yeah.
Yeah, it does sound a little unusual.
It's like, okay.
Yeah, I know.
I know.
I'm just going to plug it because I already plugged it.
Linux says in the chatroom, no KDE Plasma 5 love, and yeah, you know, that's why I mentioned
Kabuntu is because they're going to have a Plasma 5 straight up starting in April, so
that'd be good.
Yeah, definitely.
Wimpy, what do you think?
Do you think Deepin should be getting some love?
Well, it's definitely interesting.
I installed it a few months ago to have a play because I'd heard good things about it,
and I have to say, if you've got a Mac switcher who's looking to go to a Linux platform, they're
going to feel very comfortable with Linux Deepin.
You need a fairly decent machine because it's composed to the hilt, but it's got some very
sexy transitions, and it's got a unique take on control panels and what have you.
It's a very tidily put together modern distribution that I have to say is different from everything
else out there.
Yeah.
It's not at all like GNOME 3.
It's not at all like KDE or KDE Plasma.
It's not at all like Unity.
You know, they've really done something different.
Huh.
Derek Devon, were you going to say something?
Were you adding something?
I was saying that it's not even looking like elementary.
He mentioned, you know, the Mac familiarity.
Yeah.
Yeah, you're right.
It is distinctive, and it's quite good.
If you've got a decent machine, it's worth a look.
Yeah, it does look very nice.
It looks like they don't do very many releases, but that's not necessarily a bad thing at
all.
And I know I've even looked at it before, but I cannot remember what it is based on.
I think it was Debian.
Yeah, it's definitely a Debian-based system.
I don't know if it's a bootstrap.
And I seem to remember their software manager was very creative, very colorful.
Yes.
We liked that a lot, didn't we?
We did.
Yeah.
Real robust.
The deep in store.
Yeah.
And the reason it's difficult to pin it down is because every time they have a release,
the UI is completely different.
So I don't know if they've settled on this current incarnation of the UI, but every version
of Deepin has been distinct from the last.
But maybe they've settled on this one now.
It'd be worth a review if you're doing a distro review.
Yeah, we should look at it again, because it's been a year, and they have a new release.
And Urban 120 in the chatroom says it's Ubuntu-based, and I believe Urban.
I trust them.
Makes sense.
Yeah.
And they have some of their own tools, like Deepin Movie Player, Deepin Music, Deepin
Shot, even.
And they actually look like decent tools, too, which is nice.
This is definitely worth another look, I think.
So I will put this on the list.
You're talking about my distro hopping bone.
This kind of itches my distro hopping bone a little bit.
I wonder which version of Ubuntu...
I bet, you know, if we did some digging, we could probably figure out exactly which version
it's based on.
LTS all day.
I would hope so.
I'm sure of it.
Yeah.
If it is, then...
I'm going to give it a go.
I think I might give it a go.
Yeah.
I'm going to give it a go.
Deepin...
And by the way, the URL that you at home would like to check out, linuxdeepin.com, linux-d-e-p-i-n.com
to check it out.
And you can download the 2013 or 2014 edition.
And let us know what you think.
We'd love to hear your thoughts.
I'm looking at the view package list right now, which just redirected me to distro watch.
Oh, okay.
I'll do some post-show digging, because it's been a little while since I've looked into
it, and it looks pretty good.
Okay.
We've got our last topic of the day to get into.
Major problems on the Linux desktop.
And at first, I thought, oh, great.
This is a troll.
You know, I do appreciate, boy, the snow is making my browser freak out, though.
I'll tell you that.
So it's got a snow background, which I do appreciate quite a bit.
And I do think the headline is not quite as provocative, major Linux problems on the desktop.
I think we've heard other headlines out there for these types of things that are much more
attention-grabbing.
So I think that's reasonable.
The snow, though, really puts it over the top for me.
But it is an epic write-up.
And it is a long-running release, too.
This is the 2015 edition.
And it's brutal.
So we're going to talk about that.
And I think, you know, maybe counter some of it, but acknowledge some of it, and maybe
not all bad.
Maybe not all bad.
First, I want to talk about something that's great.
And that's Linux Academy.
I'll shake it up.
Shake, shake, shake it up.
I think that's a song, actually.
LinuxAcademy.com.
Shake, shake, shake it.
Yeah.
Shake, shake it, right?
LinuxAcademy.com.
Hey, Matt.
Yeah.
Linux Academy just added some NGINX courses.
Now, we've talked about NGINX quite a bit on TechSnap.
And if you've heard us mention it, and you're like, what is it?
Why is it so great?
Why not go take some courseware?
Docker courses were recently updated.
Vagrant was recently updated.
Puppet stuff was recently updated.
I mean, it's really all the stuff that you really got to get current on.
And the great thing is that Linux Academy folks are super passionate about all this
material.
So they're the experts to go to.
They've got step-by-step video courses.
You'll be able to take advantage of this.
So once you go over to LinuxAcademy.com right now, unplugged is the slash you go to.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Get your 33% discount, which is a killer discount.
And then you get access to all of the content at Linux Academy.
Get your own server as the courseware requires it.
You choose from seven plus Linux distributions.
It'll spin up that virtual server.
It'll give you a public IP address and a DNS name, and you SSH into it to do all of your
management courseware.
And then, of course, when you've chosen, like, say you choose a CentOS rig to do your courseware
on.
Well, then, since that's your virtual machine, all of the courseware, all of the stuff automatically
adjusts to match that distribution.
You've got only a limited amount of time available.
Well, they've got learning plans.
You go in there and say, with sliders, Monday I have two hours, Tuesday I have one hour,
Wednesday I have no time.
I've got them filtered.
It's crazy.
I don't have any time Wednesdays.
Thursdays, well, TechSnap's kind of like going to school, so I'll just do one hour.
Fridays, I'll put in three hours.
Then it generates me a learning plan, automatically just fits that schedule for me, keeps me in
the loop.
Like, it'll send me a little reminder, like, hey, bro, you've got a quiz coming up tonight.
Don't forget to study.
Okay.
And I'll be like, thanks, Linux Academy.
It's great.
It keeps you right there.
You go back in.
You see how long the next section's gonna take.
They download this content and listen to it on the go like a podcast.
They have live streams where you can ask the educators questions directly.
They've got a community.
They'll get you going if you ever have a little bit of a bump.
It's a really cool system, you guys, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Why not start with the OpenStack Essentials?
Really.
Like OpenStack is such a fundamental technology in the industry, and if you don't know about
it, why not go just take the fundamentals courseware?
I hear from folks all the time that start with Linux Academy as a total noob on a topic
and take it all the way and go get certifications.
It's kind of a pretty neat phenomenon, and it's unbelievable.
There's folks that have gone to Linux Academy here in Washington state, some listeners of
our shows that have taken Linux Academy courseware and are now working at Amazon.
Linux Academy has a full set of AWS courseware, too, so you can go in there.
I heard from one of them recently who gave me some info that was really useful that helped
me correct something I made a mistake on, and he says, yeah, by the way, I got the job
thanks to my courseware at Linux Academy.
Nice.
Isn't that neat?
It's really cool to hear that.
Yeah, it's really cool.
Yeah, so go check it out yourself.
LinuxAcademy.com.
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
You guys are doing an awesome job.
They're adding new stuff like crazy, too.
Holidays didn't slow them down.
Okay, so this article is super, super, super long, and it is full of snow, but it is a
regularly updated article that is trying to be the most comprehensive list of problems
anywhere on the internet with the Linux desktop.
Now this person is not a Windows advocate.
He even says here, this is not a Windows versus Linux comparison.
He says, I want to make this crystal clear, Windows, in some regards, is worse than Linux,
and it's definitely not ready for the desktop, either.
So it's not, and this guy fixes bugs for the Linux kernel, for many of the desktop environments.
A long time developer.
And he writes in here, in different categories, the problems that are wrong with Linux.
So I'll just read a couple of them, okay guys?
And this isn't about bashing Linux, but I actually think, if we look at this list, it's
not such a bad idea to itemize the problems we have with Linux, because then we have a
central place to sort of acknowledge these problems and work on them, right?
And it definitely reads like an article that was written by someone with a clue.
I disagree with a number of points, and I think there's some cherry picking, but I think
it's worth looking at.
So he, of course, bashes on NVIDIA Optimus technology and AKI dynamic GPU switching.
Still not supported on Linux.
Open source driver limitations he bashes on.
He says, open source NVIDIA drivers not properly and fully support power management features
and fan speeds.
Mesa problems, of course.
You cannot easily mix proprietary drivers and open source drivers.
So you know, some things in the audio subsystem, he picks on the audio system, no reliable
sound.
He's referencing a lot of things here.
He complains like one of ours is too many layers of abstractions lead to situations
where you just cannot determine why his audio input and output is not working.
So you have also kernel drivers, also libraries into DMX, pulse the audio server to also library,
then pulse the backend into the application, six layers of audio redirection, and if you're
on KDE, it's seven layers of audio redirection because of phonon.
No reliable high definition audio support, things like above 96 kilohertz or greater
than 24 bits, pretty much unusable often on Linux.
No reliable system wide echo cancellation.
You might notice that from our mumble room sometimes.
On Windows and Mac OS, there's a system level echo cancellation that applications can take
advantage of.
Lots of slamming on X.
X is largely outdated, unsuitable, insecure.
X doesn't automatically switch between desktop resolutions if you have an application that
goes full screen and running and crashes for some reason.
X doesn't restore gamma properly if an application changes.
So if you play a Valve or a Wine game and experience a problem, you know, he's got a
command here that'll fix that.
Lots of complaints with X.
A huge section on X.
High DPI support is pretty much nonexistent at the X level.
Wayland, he's got complaints about Wayland.
Applications must implement their own window shadowing under Wayland because Wayland decorator
has no access to application subwindows.
Applications must implement their own font anti-aliasing, or the GTK or Qt toolkits must,
and there's no API for setting system wide font rendering.
He says most sane advanced window systems, windowing systems, have exactly this.
Windows, Android, Mac OS, you can all set system wide font rendering.
In Wayland, all clients read all applications are totally independent in this regard.
Applications read GUI toolkits must also implement their own DPI scaling.
Again, Wayland doesn't do that.
Wayland, even though there's a, even though it's version is above 1.0, is still largely
incomplete and not supported by proprietary Nvidia and AMD GPU drivers.
It's got a whole section on font rendering, the Linux kernel driver, problems stemming
from vast number of different Linux distributions.
It's a pretty long list of problems.
Well, and he does link, you know, he does provide citation for 99% of the stuff, and
so I'll give him props for that.
I think my only real gripe with it, because it's really well written, I mean, really,
I mean, it's very detailed.
A lot of work went into this.
Yeah, I mean, he actually cares and honestly knows what he's talking about, but I do feel
like there's someone that might need to just, whatever he's developing or working on, take
a break, dude.
Calm down.
It's not going to bite you.
It's okay.
And there's some stuff where it seems a little arbitrary and there's not enough information.
He says the new init system, system D has been utterly broken by design.
System D can and does segfault, crash, and freeze.
In the same world, init system should never crash.
And he even says in the comments that it's crashed for him.
And then his proof for this is, well, he Google searched system D segfault, and that's his
proof.
I've got system D running on nine systems on a pretty heavy production load right now.
And I've never had it.
They've never crashed period, let alone system D crash.
I've never had system D crash ever in two and a half years.
And if you look at his regressions link, great writer, I have no problem with who he linked
to specifically, but it doesn't actually prove anything.
It's just a citation.
And so it's kind of like, there's a lot of subjective stuff here.
It's like how, at the end of the day, if he's really this upset about it, let's maybe flip
this upside down and try and find solutions to it.
Okay, there's a lot of layer abstractions, there's a lot of layering stuff in Linux distributions
in general.
It's kind of the nature of the beast.
In 2015, computing holistically blows.
I don't care what platform you're on, and that's okay.
We don't have to, you don't have to make it your daily thing.
So I don't know.
I agree.
I look at this list and I think to myself, all right, some of these problems are legitimate
problems.
There's a lot of layer abstractions with X and stuff, but they don't really prevent an
average user from using the computer and they don't maybe even notice that if you're really
an average user.
No one knows.
If I park this in front of some random guy on the street, they don't care.
Yeah, DPI scaling, sure.
Yeah.
But yeah, sure.
There's a bunch of stuff like that.
It just makes it really hard to use a system where if you used a different operating system
would just work.
And it's really annoying, but at the same time, it's the kind of thing where a developer
can work around it and just decide they don't care, but it's the type of thing that you
can't convince your mom to live with it.
Well, and the toolkit does provide, like GTK and Qt can provide some, so if they're just
using, if it's a GTK app or Qt app, they'll still have the whatever the GTK and Qt systemwide
anti-aliasing setting is, but like over pulse audio, you know what, I'm just, it sucks.
It's just still not working.
I mean, like as soon as I try a KD desktop, it's not working.
If I'm on anything else, it's fine, but it's just, it's too much.
It's Alex, do you have something, do you have input on the audio frameworks?
Yes, I wanted to mention that the audio situation is very complicated.
I would, what I would like would be a port of the media kit from Haiku.
Media kit seems to be the best competitor to the sound solution on the Mac OS, which
is by far the best one so far on any computing.
I'll look into that.
That's interesting.
Dylan, you had a point on the Wayland and fonts issue.
Yes, actually the windows in their design, it's systemwide and everything, but also it's
worth noticing that whenever you're using anything else that is not the windows forms,
you also have issues.
Not to mention that actually it opened up an extremely dangerous vulnerability just because
they did it in that design or that model.
I remember the font bug, yes, where you could take, you could own a system with a font.
Yes, it's like with a browser at that point because you can send fonts via browser.
That was a good one.
You know, when I looked at his list here, I thought it was exactly what you said, Matt.
God, in a way, computers suck in 2015, and then I thought to myself, you know, I couldn't
use anything else.
I just can't use anything else.
That's just it.
Well, like his printer and scanner argument, that made me angry because I will tell you
any day of the week, you give me a printer and you hook me up on a windows box, I'll
drop the CD in, and then I'll take a trip up to visit Alan, and then I'll come back
and it'll still be installing the software, okay?
I'm just saying.
I didn't even read that because I just felt like, and also that's an old argument, well,
these don't work with a Macintosh, you can't, well then you buy the stuff that works with
what you use.
That's what, so that argument is crap.
If you bought a win modem back in the day and then decided to switch over to Linux and
the win modem didn't work, well, then you bought the wrong device or you shouldn't have
switched to Linux.
When you buy a printer, you check compatibility.
That just seems like a given.
Well, specifically when I bought my new printer, I bought one that was networked so that it
wouldn't matter, I didn't have to plug it into any machine.
Exactly, because then you don't care.
It also meant I didn't have to have that machine on when I wanted to print, because I wanted
to put the printer in my office downstairs and I didn't want to have to leave a computer
on.
Yep.
So, Zero, I was curious about your point regarding the NVIDIA driver.
So the thing with NVIDIA, it kind of piggybacks along with what you said about printers and
printers, you know, get hardware that works with what you use, a lot of people complain
that NVIDIA doesn't have good support using Linux, and that's mostly, especially Optimus
and things like that, that's because we have proprietary drivers that work well when they
work but can fail often from NVIDIA, who has time and time again shown that they really
don't care about Linux at all, you know, and got the finger from Linus Torvalds over
that.
That's true.
And the people who are trying to make these things work in Linux, who are reverse engineering
these things, you know, there aren't very many people like that because the people who
cared about freedom in the first place enough to potentially reverse engineer these things
just didn't buy NVIDIA in the first place.
Yeah.
Wimpy, you have a point regarding printers, I'd like to hear that.
Yeah, just like any bit of hardware, when you buy a printer these days, you should buy
a printer that supports your operating system, just like Alan said, and when I went shopping
for a new printer last year, I was able to find one that not only clearly had Linux support
but also supported Android, and that wasn't through the Google Cloud Print API, they actually,
this is a brother printer, and they actually have a printing app in the Google Play Store.
So you can even now, you know, find hardware that's compatible with your mobile devices
as well.
Yeah, very good point.
And Urban, I'll let you have the final word, because it's a great point, you can't necessarily
blame Linux if HP doesn't make a driver for a scanner, right?
I think that responsibility for drivers is entirely on the company that makes that hardware,
and it's not on Linux.
If HP doesn't do the drivers for Linux, screw them, we'll use something else.
That's right.
I mean, that's why I bought a brother laser printer for the Office, because it just had
great Linux support.
What I did is I just went and checked CUPS and saw the driver in CUPS, and I'm like,
okay, well then I know it'll work on everything that runs CUPS, and I'm good.
Yeah, that's just it.
At the FreeBSD Foundation, I've been trying to take that argument kind of the other way,
instead of being like, hey, this manufacturer doesn't make drivers for their device, screw
them, it's more like, well, why don't we get together a big group and demonstrate the demand
to them, and then they'll bother, and we'll give them the resources to help them build
the driver.
That's a good idea, too.
I like that.
That's excellent.
And that's how we have more 40 gigabit network drivers than other operating systems now, because
we demonstrated the need.
Well, and shops like Microsoft, they have huge departments dedicated to specific pieces
of hardware.
So they have, like for the Windows Server development team, on that team, there are
sub-hardware teams that work just with manufacturers on getting drivers into that version of Windows.
So there's a networking card department, a printer department, a storage department,
and they might even have sub-departments.
I mean, it's very structured, and all those teams do is work with vendors to get drivers
written and certified for Windows.
So the FreeBSD approach makes sense, because that's what the commercial shops have been
doing for a while.
So one last thing with this article, too, I want to point out that I wish he would have
addressed is that when it comes to legacy devices, such as an older printer, an older
scanner, including Canon products, you will find that Linux is quite supportive, whereas
newer versions of Windows will tell you to go F yourself.
You're on your own.
So, you know, just saying.
He's got a great bunch of stuff.
And the reason why I like it is it's hard, it's a little aggressive in its language,
but it's accurate, it's referenced for the most part, some of its conjecture, some of
its personal opinion, but some of its fact, and you can't deny it.
It's a pretty good citation, too.
I actually think it's not bad to, some people think I'm being negative.
I don't think it's bad to lose sight of shortcomings so that way we can focus on those and make
them even better, because there's opportunity if Linux shores these things up.
So the only way to do that is if we keep ourselves accountable.
Absolutely.
Well, and to his credit, when an adjustment is made or he discovers something that actually
counters a previous point, he will cross it out and actually update it.
So that's cool.
Yeah, very much.
All right.
And if you're not thick-skinned and you might be a little hard to read, I don't know, I
just wanted to say.
Put your big, warm pants on, you'll be all right.
Yeah.
Pour yourself a cold one.
Exactly.
Well, go on.
Okay, that's fair enough.
You can read it.
Throw it in your read later queue or something like that.
Oh, by the way, just fun to point out, he does, I just went off the whole list of problems
with Linux.
It might be fun to mention.
Here's a few things he thought was wrong with Windows.
Devastating Windows rot occurs.
No enforced file system and registry hierarchies.
Svshost.exe, no more needed to be said there.
Not a true safe mode, it's not legitimately a true safe mode.
No clean state option.
The user as a system administrator is bogus and most users just totally ignore UAC.
No good packaging mechanism, MSI is a fragile abomination.
No system-wide update mechanism, which includes third-party software.
Windows is extremely difficult to debug.
Windows boot problems are often fatal and unsolvable unless you reinstall from scratch.
Windows is hardware-dependent, especially when you're running from UEFI.
Windows updates are unreliable and they also waste disk space and there's no way to cleanly
upgrade your system.
There will be thousands of leftover files, etc.
So again, he's not saying Windows is great.
And I would agree with all that list.
Yeah.
He did a pretty good job, I think.
I mean, considering.
Yeah.
Alan, final thought on the topic?
Oh, I thought I heard Alan, but then I didn't.
Oh, I guess he left.
He said something in the mumble room and then he left.
He dropped his PSD microphone.
He's like, you know what?
Boom!
Yeah.
But Alan wanted me to mention before he left that TechSnap, episode 200 of the TechSnap
program is coming up just in a couple of weeks.
And if you've listened to TechSnap and something we've talked about, a story we've covered,
a question we've answered or anything like that has ever helped you at home on your network
or in your office, project, somewhere out there a little TechSnap advice has been helpful
for you.
So just send it into the TechSnap program, go over to jupitabroadcasting.com slash contact,
choose TechSnap from the dropdown and send in your story.
We're going to have a special episode 200 where we'll be reading through some of those
to celebrate.
So it's kind of amazing, 200 episodes in a row too.
Wow.
Which is nuts.
All right, guys.
Well, I just will wrap it up there.
I want to remind you that I'm looking for your personal runs Linux, either ones you
find, that's fine too, but I'd really love to see your setups.
Email them to linuxactionshow at jupitabroadcasting.com and put runs Linux in the subject line.
And if you need to send in a video, put that up on YouTube.
If you've got a picture, please put that up on Imgur and link that because I just pull
down the text.
I don't pull down attachments.
And I'd love to feature those in an upcoming Linux action show.
You can also submit ones you find out in the wild to linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com is also a great place to make this show and our other shows
even better and give feedback.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com, anything like a story, community engagement, an app pick,
runs Linux, anything like that on the subreddit, it's really welcome.
And it helps make everything better.
And don't forget you can join us live at jblive.tv, 2pm Pacific, jupitabroadcasting.com slash
calendar to get that in your local time zone and then you can hang out in our chat room,
join our open mumble room, and even title our show.
It's a lot to do, so join us, won't you?
All right Matt, well coming up on Sunday's Linux action show, we'll have a great show
and I've been following the news already, got a few stories I can't wait to talk about.
So join us on Sunday for that, so I'll see you then Matt.
See you then.
Okay everybody.
Well guess what?
That brings us to the end of this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Do join us, won't you?
And don't forget we've also got Android apps so you can watch Jupiter Broadcasting on the
go and jblive.info which is an audio only stream which works great when you're in the
car over 3G or maybe you're at your desk and they don't want you using video.
It's a great option, jblive.info.
Okay everybody, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll be right back here next Tuesday.
I don't know if there's been a series of videos.
We're going to be talking about the Ubuntu Touch Terminal Emulator.
It came out once before but we didn't talk about it on the show.
And this is the new multiple tab Ubuntu terminal that we might see ship in 1504.
And one of the things I would look at is the animation is pretty smooth, it's pretty slick,
it looks pretty good.
So watch as now he'll click this and there he zooms out and there's the different tabs.
So instead of tabs along the top you have sort of like a tab overview, sort of almost
like the Firefox tab overview page.
And you can see like the scroll action there looks real smooth, it's nice looking.
Looks like a nice equal product.
So just to be clear, this is the terminal for the phone that we happen to have made
sure it works on the desktop and tablet, Convergence, which is...
CONVERGENCE!
But it's not in the phone yet, it's in the store if you've got a phone and you can grab
the code, it's all open source, it's cool.
It's actually maintained by the same guy who made Cool Retro Terminal.
You know, I just gotta say, it's stuff like this that makes Linux so compelling.
This is just good!
Yeah, this is fun and I like the...
It's definitely not like desktop optimized, but I like that they didn't make it for the
desktop necessarily, but yet it's still functional.
So that's good.
And I saw it had a Retro Cool Terminal mode too, which is really neat.
Yeah, the little thing down the bottom, I don't know if you can see this, there's a
little pop-up menu and what we're planning for that is for it to be customizable.
So you can have a pop-up menu for Emacs and a pop-up menu for Vi and it has all your keyboard
shortcuts pre-filled in and you can define your own.
Oh, shut your mouth, that's cool!
That's great, guys.
JSON file or something, that's really quite cool.
I can't wait for that.
Did I just hear customizable and Ubuntu in the same sentence?
Oh boy.
Oh snap.
Sure snappage.
Get it back in your box.