Feel like pre-show should be Brent's department, you know, yeah, he is good at scouring strange and interesting things
Brent anything in the pre-show department this week. Well
Pre-shows give me sex. I think here I got a mouthful of trail mix. Check your folder
Open up your pre-show folder. I know you have a manila folder over there, right? I say that right West manila. Mm-hmm
Okay, thank you. It's actually vanilla manila. Well, he's got you've got the scented ones. Yeah, you just got the scratch and sniff envelopes
I know that
Hello friends and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes
Hello West
374 is brought to you by the all-new a cloud guru the leader in learning for cloud Linux and other modern tech skills
Hundreds of courses thousands of hands-on labs get certified get hired get learning a cloud guru comm
West today on the show
It's one of those where we adventure out into the server garage and we attempt to do something that we probably should have taken a few
More precautions before we even got started
That's for sure. I
Mean it was a while ago on the show a few weeks back
We have updated people on our setup with next cloud. It was a question that came into the show
362 of this podcast
So it's been a little bit
we reveal how much we were spending per month and I think people were shocked and so we set out on a mission to
tighten that up by quite a bit and
Update reconfigure and maybe come up with a damn near most perfect next cloud setup. I've ever seen that is fairly bulletproof
it's portable and
Something we're gonna recommend in a little bit
But we have a lot to do before we get there including some community news that I'm very excited about
So to help us analyze all of this it is our team of experts time-appropriate greeting virtual log
Was a good one, hey, you know 22 strong this week we've had more but I think maybe one of the better intros there
So hello everybody. Thanks for being here with us today
Why don't we start with a little KTE news because it's been a while since we've talked about the plasma desktop too long
The excellent plasma desktop and KD developers for more than a year have been working to evolve the default breeze theme
Which that work is being done by the KD visual design group and it's finally paying off with an initial breeze
Evolution breeze evolution is a modest refresh to the UI so far various subtle changes have landed around window shadows
sidebars and color alterations
More work on breeze evolution will continue leading up to its debut in KD plasma 5.21
Oh, I look forward to that also happening is some work on K wins Wayland virtual keyboard
Which now you're ready for this supports GTK applications that you didn't think that's what I was gonna say. Oh
That's neat. Yeah, we'll have a link to the blog post by
Nate who we've had on the show before that covers this and a bunch of other really cool stuff
Coming to the next update in KTE. It's such a nice solid performer these days
and I think we have slipped into a mistake of not talking about it very much and
So we wanted to write that wrong with kind of some really thought-provoking KTE discussion that came out of Academy 2020
Oh, yes at that annual KTE conference
Of course held virtually this year KD developer and the head Graham delivered a talk entitled visions of the future
About the possible future of KTE on commercial products
subtitled plasma sold on retail hardware
Lots of it the session concentrated on ways to make KTE applications and also the plasma desktop the default
environment on hardware sold to the general public
the proposal includes creating an official KD distribution with a hardware certification program and
Directly paying developers. Yeah, there's also another bombshell in here and I got some audio from the event
But we'll also link to the entire YouTube video Graham started by giving some context
the ideas that were to be presented was a follow-up on the entire KD accessibility and
Productivity goals that we talked to him about in 2017 and one of the objectives was to get plasma and KTE
applications ready to work on all kinds of hardware
well Graham thinks that this has been achieved and now it's time to move to the next step for KTE and that is
creating an official KTE
Operating system. I think what that next thing is is to create an official KTE OS
So you might ask why would we want to do this?
Well, the simplest reason is we have to if we want a direct relationship with hardware vendors
Because that's what they need they need an OS and that means working with distro partners or it means having our own OS and we
Love our distro partners. I do too, but having our own OS allows us to have our own relationship with them
And thankfully we already have one that OS is neon
Unfortunately neon is is a bit of a halfway product
It's mostly designed to showcase KTE software non KTE software can be very outdated and does not necessarily
Guarantee to work. It has a very small development team and most puzzlingly
We don't admit that KTE neon is an OS in our own messaging
On the other hand KTE neon is indeed enough of an OS that the slim book people ship it on their hardware and
Lots and lots of people use it as their daily driver on their own computers, including my wife. She loves it. It's really great
So I think it's time for us to finally admit that neon is a real OS and treat it as such
We can say that it's what we believe the reference implementation of KTE software ought to look like and promote it accordingly
You know just clean up our messaging a little bit many make this sounds similar to an initiative by the gnome folks
Doesn't it? Yeah, it's a little bit different
Yeah, indeed. It does. I mean it was years ago that gnome developers wanted to create a gnome OS
because they thought that they would be just
Good to have it its own OS but never appeared. Well, they're still kind of working on it
I heard them talking about it at this year's Gwadek
So it may still be coming there are isos out there. This does make me think sometimes when we talk about this, you know, we
Lament default settings at least occasionally and historically in some of these big desktop environments
And I wonder if some more of this vertical integration actually more, you know more fully shipping something that's considered an OS
I wonder if that will have any impact, you know, I'm sitting here right now reading this news off of a machine running KDE neon
I mean west you have even the foggiest guess of how old this install is older than 2018. Maybe 2017. No
No, it's getting close to three years. I'd say at least it's a pretty solid desktop as a pretty happy KDE neon user
I kind of wondered well
What would a more official KDE neon look like and nate has thoughts on that as well
First of all, it would have the latest kernels in it for hardware enablement purposes
It would probably have a method to have newer kernels in it than even its parent OS Ubuntu does
It would have more up-to-date third-party apps
If not from the repos then maybe from flat pack or snap or one of these
Generally new generation
app
Deployment mechanisms that we support it would have a lot more development resources, too
And this is sort of a call to action here. I think if you want to make this happen
Please please go ahead and help out
There's also the possibility that in case neon's Ubuntu base ever proves unsuitable for some reason
It could be rebased on another OS. I I think we can be fairly agnostic about that
And generally our new neon based KDE OS would just be more awesome in every way
That's that's what I think is the most important thing about it. I don't know about that new base OS
I really appreciate that. It's based on Ubuntu actually
I think Nate's a big OpenSUSE Leap fan
So I understand, but I I think that'd be
Really something if the project started being just a little more upfront. Yeah, this is actually the official OS
and this is what our developers are using and targeting and this is what we're working with hardware providers and
Nate also talked about a hardware certification program that would sort of go
Along with this and so there's several official goals. I think that they would foresee with an actual KDE OS
I think the end result of this would be pretty beneficial for us because
Because we would be able to work directly with hardware vendors in in a better way
Having neon has already allowed us to do this
And I think it's important that we continue to improve that offering so that we can improve our ability to work with hardware vendors
And I think there's also a very good chance as I mentioned earlier that
Making neon our own official reference implementation of KDE software would encourage other KDE
Distros to to up their game do a better job
Not to say that they do a bad job. Obviously I use a non
Neon distro and I think they do a great job, but there's always room for improvement everywhere
Right, and I think this is an example where competition
Potential to help everybody there is one concern I'd have about this and I'd be interested to know
What some of the developers using neon and creating neon think about this
Is it seems like it would take away this development playground where they can try things out
If it needs to all of a sudden be a quote-unquote
reference implementation
Then the burden of getting it right
And having it polished is a bit higher, isn't it? Yeah, right
I mean I think right now as we use KDE neon we kind of have a caveat of like well
You know, we don't really we shouldn't really treat it like it's stable
You probably shouldn't use it unless you're willing to have your desktop
Maybe possibly break and in practice
I don't think that's really happened or if it does happen it updates so frequently that the next day, you know
You've got an update fixing whatever small regression happened
but they probably still need a playground right like some sort of
A new area testing branch of if KDE neon itself becomes something more like stable
I have a question for a couple of you in the mumble room. Maybe I'll start with Brent and Carl
What are your thoughts on?
Almost more fragmentation in the Linux landscape if we start seeing different
Distros spin up into their quote-unquote own operating systems for hardware deals. Are you concerned at all about?
More distros more fragmentation more islands. That's a question that comes up often, isn't it?
And I I wonder if our energy like in developers will get spread out
It feels like we're a little thin already
So if we start going into all our own little projects around every single little technology
Is that going to cause some problems but maybe?
On the flip side, maybe it's a good thing. Maybe it means that hardware manufacturers
There's a lot more opportunity there than there was even a year or two ago
So maybe it's a maybe it's a good sign very true. It could be I really don't have a problem with it
I mean the way I look at it
It's people's free time and they can spend it how they want to and you know for a lot of them
It's their creative outlet
They're going to have opinions about the way they want to do things and I have no problem with that whatsoever
And at least for the moment, right? They are still based on the ubuntu base. So if anything maybe that just adds some
Draws some folks might use a different kde based distro over to the ubuntu world and you know more testers there
Mm-hmm. And if you think about it at that level
Well, then really it's getting pretty standardized stuff here. You have an ubuntu base. It's using system d
it uses a kernel of a certain version that has these certain features and
You start to realize it's not really all of that fragmented
I mean at that layer at that level things are actually becoming more and more consistent
Despite what some people would prefer
I'm going to keep listening for this haven't heard much from the
Kde neon folks, but would love to know their thoughts on this if this is something they'd be interested in pursuing and then
if it is
How do we as a community step up and support it and make it happen because i'd love to
To know that this kde neon install that I have here is the official
Kde plasma os and that it's going to be supported and around for a long time
That just kind of as an end user gives me a little more reassurance
I'm, not convinced. That's who neon is designed for right now, but uh, maybe that's the transition they can make
Maybe they're willing to take that transition
Linode.com slash unplugged get a
100.60 day credit on your new linode account. We'll have a link in the show notes or you just go to linode.com slash unplugged
They're the largest independent cloud provider full stop and they make it easy for anyone at any skill level to get started
No matter what technology stack you use linode can help your ideas come to life
If you just need a personal web server for a blog or a portfolio
Or maybe your business needs to scale to serve millions
Linode can help you with that and unlike entry-level hosting services that lock you into their platform
Linode gives you full back-end access to customize and control your server to fit your needs
They have a great dns manager simple to take backups one click app deployments
And if kubernetes is your speed to manage your infrastructure linode has you covered there
You can easily manage your kubernetes cluster with linode's fully managed container orchestration engine
Also a great way to learn if you want to learn cyber security or practice something before you have to do it in production
Linode has some great options there at great price points
But one of the things that I encourage you to look into is their s3 compatible object storage
If you're not familiar object storage is essentially an easy way for you to store and access data in the cloud
Without having to run a front-end file server. It's perfect for data. That doesn't change regularly
This is where we use it all the time for show assets that are essentially static
And what something is up in their s3 compatible object storage
It's really easy to get a url and share that file if you want or maybe even use something like that to power a static website
We use linode's powerful virtual servers to run our infrastructure our matrix server our encoding server our new next cloud server
All of it's on linode. My personal servers are on linode
Linode started in 2003 as one of the first companies to even get into what is now known as cloud computing three years before aws
Go check it out. See what i've been raving about and support one of our sponsors who's made our transition to independence possible
linode.com slash unplugged thanks to linode for sponsoring the show and thanks to everyone who supports our sponsors out there linode.com
unplugged
So let's talk a little more hardware this got me thinking this week nvidia unveiled a raspberry pi competitor
We've got hardware on the brain. And so I kind of wanted to just chat about this with you guys and just in time
A wild. Mr. Drew has snuck into the studio. Hello, drew. Hello, chris. Good to have you here
You know the state of disarray that our hardware is slowly devolving into here in the studio
It's all reached like the five year mark or something like that since we built it or maybe four year
I'm, not sure it runs 24 seven. So in computer years, it's a lot
and
Wes and I spent some time this weekend racking our brains on
on how to really kind of
attack this problem and
Figure out like should we should we build it differently? Should we say break the system up into six or seven individual components?
Or should we consolidate it down into one really super powerful rig?
I mean we've kicked around all the different scenarios and listener of the show mike f has sent us some hardware recently
Which is still coming. It's still inbound west. There's still more. Oh boy. Yeah, and one of the things he sent us
Is a batch like a lot
of pine 64
one gigabyte
Small boards, you know ones that are closer to the raspberry pi. They have the gpio ports
um, I don't think it's the rock pro 64, but it's
It's still a it's still a little pine board and we're not really even sure what we're going to do with all of them
You know, what do you do with like seven boards like that?
And so then I so I started thinking well
Maybe like we could use them as sensors, you know, like a temperature sensor out in the server room to check check in on that
So anyways, like it's we're in this weird hardware phase right now where we need to replace our recording machine
which currently runs, uh zubuntu
It might have actually been kubuntu converted to zubuntu for some reason and that runs reaper which records individual tracks for everyone in mumble and
For myself and wes and drew and then it also
So routes the audio out to remote people and remote guests
And then the other machine that's kind of falling apart on us is the obs machine
Which does the live stream and records any videos if we record video versions and captures all of that and puts it out?
and also makes our backup recording both of these machines are just completely falling apart and
I don't think these arm boards are where we need them yet
But it has started to enter our mind that maybe in the future
We're going to start replacing these x86 systems with these low power arm systems that could be freaking mounted to the table
Just put them up under the table right small lower power maybe fanless and if they're cheap easily replaceable sort of standardizable
So nvidia comes along
With their lowest priced arm small board computer to date
They're really kind of focusing this at the developer market robotics market. It's
For small tasks that need pretty high-end cpu and gpu for what you get in this form factor
It's called the jetson nano and it's already pretty cheap, but today they're introducing a $60 version
So their standard jetson nano was a hundred dollars, but now they're introducing a $60 version
That looks like it's priced pretty nice for what you actually get in something this size. Well, yeah, right? I mean it's $59
The usd and it's quite similar to the $99 full full board
But with just two gigs of system memory rather than four
So it's kind of in direct competition with the higher end raspberry pi models
But it has a more powerful tegra gpu and nvidia's extensive
gpu optimized software solutions if you're into that
Well, there's a lot of people that are basing their software around it and $60 gets you four cortex a57 cores at 1.43 gigahertz
like west said two gigs of ram you had micro sd
And there's 128 core maxwell gpu on this thing that has nvec
Which is their nvidia encoding and cuda capabilities?
It also has so you can get the data in and out of there pretty fast gigabit ethernet hdmi output and three
Usb 3.0 ports. Oh, isn't that fancy?
Now the arm cores on the raspberry pi 4 should probably perform a little bit better
But the jetson nano 2 gig has the much more capable gpu and I think you kind of hit on it there with the cuda
support
Sort of more similar to a board that you might run on a standard x86 environment
So if you just need to do this, maybe in the field
You've already got stuff optimized for the nvidia stack and you just want to run the same stack
But in a smaller lower power form factor, maybe this looks pretty interesting
Um, I can't help but feel the elephant in the room is apple has an arm announcement next week as we record this
on tuesday
Uh, we've been kicking around the whole arm development angle on coda radio, which by the way everybody
Coda radio is back. If you didn't know
Coda radio program
Coder dot show. Is it just me or is there a new one dropping today?
I think there's a new one dropping probably as we speak. So check it out coder dot show
It's back the last few episodes. I've managed to really piss off the seuss lizards
So I could use I could use a backup there if you want to catch up on the last couple of episodes
I'd love to hear your thoughts. But also we've been kicking around
arm as a development target and uh, all of this kind of plays into that and
I don't know wes. I feel like um, there is a change in the winds winter is coming potentially for a desktop linux
But oh you sweet summer child
I talk about it more in coda radius. Check it out. The coda radio program is back
and
it's
glorious business
All right
You know wes, um before we get into the next cloud stuff. What do you say? We just do a little spot of housekeeping
Yeah, let's do it it's high time in here it's kind of dusty
I know and you know something we should have been mentioning for a long time
But the jupiter broadcasting all shows feed is probably the way to go
Now if you look at it, we've kind of honed in on what jb covers and like coda radio, for example, you'd know it's back
It's in the all shows feed and there are things in the works
You don't want to miss anything new the all shows feed. You can just search for all jupiter broadcasting shows
In your podcast client or there is a link. Why waste all that time subscribing individually when it's a one stop shop also
Now that jupiter broadcasting is independent again
We are looking for some sponsors if you're looking to reach the perfect audience, you know, if you're out there, you know
This is a great audience to reach the best audience in podcasting and we have some opportunities
So email me chris at jupiter broadcasting dot com
And you may notice here on the old linux unplugged show. We try to keep the politics out
This is a technology area, but it is political season in the states
So it's never been a better time to check out unfilter unfilter dot show
It's not part of jupiter broadcasting so we don't talk about it here
But it is up and cranking to cover the people's history in real time
I'm doing live streams for each of the debates. They start 30 minutes before the debates and of course, we'll do a live stream
for the election night itself
All of that unfilter dot show check it out. It's back weekly and um, I think better than eva
Thanks, everybody who also has already joined over there and been hanging out with me in the discord
That was a lot of fun. We did the last debate. We're gonna do it again
And that's one of the nice things I like the setup. I just decided jb, you know
It's gonna it's got its focus and we're not gonna bring all of that stuff into it
So we don't that way we don't have to talk about it in the shows
We have a spot for it all the politics all of the world news all of that unfilter dot show go check it out
Okay, so we we had a bit of a next cloud conundrum pretty quickly
Our monthly storage bill was getting close to four hundred dollars a month and it's a pretty essential tool
It's how we pass around all of our raw recordings how we pass around our finished recordings
It's where we store our assets for things like well things like jingles like that housekeeping jingle. They're all stored in next cloud
Yeah, it's really integrated into the workflow at this point
And one of the things that we did when we built our last next cloud setup is we decided to base the backend storage on
object storage
Which allowed us to grow at infinitum, which we were intentionally doing that's how we got to like 400 gigs
Yeah, and we wanted something where we could just keep working and load it up
And then we could come back and clean it up and we knew that would be a job we'd have to do
But what was more important is that the daily productions wouldn't get held up by running out of storage
Which is where we'd always run into trouble with our previous
next cloud and own cloud implementations is eventually we'd run out of storage because we're constantly passing around
80 megabyte 100 megabyte files even larger when they're waves and video clips
so we needed something that wouldn't eat itself storage wise and
we knew at some point we'd have to come back and clean things up and
That is now we wanted to re-architect how we do next cloud
And what we've gone with if you'll allow the term here. I apologize ahead of time a hybrid cloud setup
I know I'm using the buzz terms. How dare you? I'm sorry Wes, but it's true
We've gone with the on-premises and in the cloud setup
And we've kind of arranged things in a way that we think is gonna work really good long term and keep the overall
monthly cost down and so that meant
Getting a space set up here on our local file server that runs arch that you guys will hear us talk about very often
It also has a next cloud instance on there
But there was a little bit of maintenance we had to do to get it to that point it
You know, it needed a little love just a bit
Yeah, and so good guy Wes came up on Sunday this last weekend
After I finished recording Linux action news Wes showed up and we had some killer food
Really good. I don't think I complimented you enough on the pork. It was
tremendous and
My wife got us some size and she got us some barbecued chicken and we sat down and we had one of those work and eat
Days, I mean, I think we did it in the wrong order and that we feasted first and then tried to get to work
But I mean we got to stuff done. We were a little sleepy
We had a little bit of food coma
But we had to we had to get the base server here in the studio ready
We had to prep it if you will so job one was take care of the base arch install before we loaded it up with
A bunch of data. So we set off into the Jupiter broadcasting high-security server garage
Okay job one is we got to prep this thing
So we got to do all of our due diligence make sure the OS is up to date. Uh-oh. So do that cuz it's been
Month or two
Do you just Pac-man so that way it's not all that you are too. I thought we might start there
So we are see what we're working against
Yeah, should we replace this?
Package name with some other package name. Yes
Core something with something core other something. Oh
Yeah, you tell Linux libs. That's probably not important. All right
New kernel new Linux LTS kernel coming in excellent
So we will also have to upgrade a new wire guy. Yep. New Zia new system D
There's probably gonna be a ZFS update in there to new Samba
Big question is what about Docker? Cuz yep new doc new Docker as well
Cuz this is just the base OS doesn't even get us the next club funny though
547 megabyte download net upgrade size 45 megabytes. Got a little arch
Shall it yeah, let's do it. I
Give us a hard time for being reckless. But in a way we were actually taking a fairly
Methodical approach here. We were first updating the base OS to make sure all of the host OS packages were up to date
We were on the latest version of Docker and you'll recall part of our bulletproof arch setup is this thing snapshots
Every time it does an upgrade and we're running now on the LTS kernel a change we made to the LTS
We're running now on the LTS kernel a change we made not too long ago that already pay dividends
This time around. Oh, yeah, and we wanted to just get all of that, right?
so you got to do all of that and then it's
Reboot time and you guys know how nerve-wracking this can be when you've done a big update and this one in particular
this one took a really really long time to shut down and then it booted up and
Somehow like the silent boot mode got turned back on or we never disabled it
And so we just sat there staring at a screen for what felt like
27 years
Take your 70s over there we go
I'm reminded that this is a pretty foolproof setup. We have with one major exception and that is
The entire OS runs off this one ten thousand rpm hard drive
So the data is all safe on a raid, but we have one OS drive
Chris you do have to factor in that we've conveniently located the OS drive on the exterior of the case for easy
Replacement in case that's necessary
Welcome to grab West. It's good to be here. Yeah
All right, sure turns off. Yeah, why are we going to power say oh, you know, this is one of my first LCD screens
I ever bought this monitors probably about 17 years old. You gotta say it's a nice aspect ratio
Yeah, it's the old aspect the old square aspect ratio. Yeah, it does make good for a console. It's kind of perfect. Yeah
All right system D firing up I see drives lighting up that's a good sign means it's probably talking ZFS
You're always watching for like all the signs, you know, okay drives are flashing. That's good. That's all the fans
They change their sound. That's a good sign. Yeah, maybe the you know, the display resolution changes and yeah, that does happen
You see the video driver load so it booted up. Eventually
We got the login screen and the first job for then really with this is like job two of just bringing
The arch server up to date now is make sure the ZFS pool mounted all our data is there
No, it did take a long time to reboot last time. We did this. I mean at least I come online
I could have to say Jim. Oh, hey
There we go. So I think we just we should just switch that, you know
We want to see the console scrolling by look at all the disk going well
Yeah, I thought I thought we did have that on
Let's log in and see if we have a sequel
I everything's online
And our containers
May still be loading actually, I think they're still loading
All right, we'll give it a minute we'll check back this next part
I would have messed up Wes if you weren't here
It was your idea that we should go kind of incrementally through the next cloud releases
I would have just gone whole hog to the latest version. You just love updates. I do. I just would have gone for it, but
You had a process you had a procedure and
We were ready to now tackle next cloud and get it all up-to-date
So that way we could have both the cloud version and our locally hosted version at the same exact version
We turn our attention to next cloud, which is
Version 17 dot something. It's a few releases behind
We want to go hands-on with this update because we want to make sure that we get this right
It appears we're gonna need to go in a bit of a stepped approach
We're gonna step up to version 18 and then to 19
18 and then to 19 or what has this work?
Yeah, sounds like you should really only go one major version at a time
At least I noticed some lines in the docs advising that I suggest we just go all the way to current but Wes wanted to be
careful, I know
So, okay
So if I understand we're gonna go 17 and we're gonna update to a supportive version of 17 and then to the release version
Whatever current version that is right now. Exactly
Okay
Let's give it a go. So first step is
Docker compose pull
You
You have to pull a specific. Yeah, we want to update and make sure we're grabbing the right image here
Okay, so how are you gonna make sure you pull the right version of this container since we're doing a pull?
Well, they've got a list of supported versions up on their github a few other places in the documentation and that includes supported Docker image releases
So we're just gonna use the tag for that version
Which is really just a simple update the YAML file make sure you've specified the exact version of the image you want and
You figured that out by doing what Wes? Well, I just headed over to their
Docker hub page and they had a big list and then they also I mean
There's a bunch of spots in their docs and on github that basically list like these are our supported releases
And then on the Docker hub page in particular
They've got a big list of all the tags that correspond if you want to use Apache or Alpine or FPM
You know all the various options of image flavors that they ship
They've basically got one for each of those for each of the supported versions
So go find the one that looks like the one you're already using except a newer version and slot that into your YAML
Yeah, and then it was just a matter of rinse and repeat we would update the Docker compose tag pull that version
We'd stop and start everything and then check to see if we could log in
Take it all down. Let's take it all down. Shut it all down. Oh, yeah
Okay
So really the only thing that's gonna have a major update is Redis because we just said pull whatever latest version of that is
But otherwise we've pulled tagged versions of everything
So now she just I say up it and leave it on the command line so we can see the output
See what happens. Yeah
Creating next cloud. Here we go
Okay
The check will be able to see if it loads on your phone, right
That's how we'll know because we didn't bring a computer out here
besides the server
Who needs it? Yeah, that's right out in the studio garage server room, okay
Configuration complete ready for startup
Set log level the debug turned on maintenance mode. We're upgrading hmm checking for app updates
That seems normal
Which seems to indicate a function in next cloud system if it's at that stage, that's a good sign
That's you, isn't it? Is that you? Oh, yeah, we can see your we can see your web browser in the debug log
You see all the stuff scrolling by is the login screen loads for Wes and we would do that each time as we step through
I think there was a mid 17 release and then the 18 release and then we had one last update to do or
Well, so we thought pretty confident. This is gonna work fine
Dang it. Why'd you say that?
Hahaha, did I just jinx us? All right
So we start her up
Let's do it a little console output
You know watching this array work away all these lights flash. It makes me kind of miss
Having that feedback aspect in my in my PC, right? You really feel it was working. Yeah, sorry
No way you get nothing right but with these like I know what's going on
Gives me a reassuring work. Okay. It looks like we're doing a
Lot of updates are these apps? It's updating. Yeah, these are up. These are it's updating a bunch of apps right now
That's what it's doing. Oh, well, I guess that's a good thing
Let's do an a code integrity check. Hey
Ready to handle connections
Break out the old test device there West. Let's see if next cloud loads
Come on, baby one more time. Yep
says update successful maintenance mode has been turned off and
And
Reset log level and it looks like it's loading pretty painless. I got to say
Every time we go through a process like this and it's pretty you know, essentially pain-free
I get a little more confident in next cloud, you know
So now it just needs to be like this for like another ten years and I'm gonna feel good. We'll finally be
No, actually, this is really good. Now. We just rinse repeat on the Linode version of the server. You're right
I mean kind of the test here is we're let's say occasional next cloud admins
Yeah, it's a small piece of our overall setup
So they doesn't get the attention that maybe it deserves right?
It's really nice for this to be simple clearly out of practice when I jinxed us and said that should be all good now
And because just about as we were done next cloud 20 came out
That timing yeah, yeah
But you know Wes we should talk about the bigger picture here
The bigger picture is what we've done is as thanks to you primarily is
We've spent the energy and time on getting both the hosted version of next cloud that's up in the cloud
That's costing way too much at this moment and our local version
Then you used a command to essentially use the sync system to pull a bunch of the data down from the cloud version to our local
Version, can you talk about that? Yeah next cloud CMD
I think it's called and it's just a built-in little one-shot command line client built into the standard next cloud client desktop application
And you don't have to have it configured for the desktop
I was a little worried about that since we were doing it on a mostly headless server
But thankfully it's arch
It was easy to get that client installed and then it accepts the credentials has got flags for it
Or you can do it sort of URL style, you know like user
Colon password at and then the HTTP address
So we just pointed that in with the right user to sync down all the stuff that we didn't want to keep up in the cloud
The stuff we needed to you know, we're gonna use day to day all the archival stuff
Well, we're just gonna move that right into the garage. And so we set up that sink
I think it was about
120 gigs of stuff or so
Yeah
And then it was a matter of cleaning up the cloud instance and you have to then
At least if you want to reclaim that space immediately
You need to run a command on the command line to essentially delete everything permanently
Yeah, you know you there's various setups the next cloud for keeping multiple versions hanging around and then also sort of defaults around like how long
Is stuff gonna be in the trash? When does it get expired out of there and just the trash get cleaned up?
So we just ran some commands in the command line
Inside the Docker container with the OCC command to just sort of clean all that up delete anything that anyone had in the trash
Delete any old versions hanging around and see how small we could get things and what we got it down to what like 30
40 gigs now, I think it's I think it's more like 50
But it was you know
Pretty good and that includes anything all the various users have uploaded as well as our sort of working team folder
Right and before we did the purge and moved everything down it was getting north of I mean because of all the undelete files
I think it was somewhere north of three four hundred gigabytes. It was getting pretty big. It was over 400 gigs
Yes, was it? Okay. Yeah, and that's why the cost was getting there so high and we knew that would eventually be an issue
And so what we're gonna do now is we're gonna just kind of rework our workflow a bit and only keep certain folders up in
The cloud and keep everything else
Locally and there's a lot of ways we can make that available to our users from Federation to just having two separate URLs
but
What really I think was nice here is that the next cloud project is publishing these Docker images
themselves and as a result they've taken the time to
note which ones are stable releases and they've given you instructions on which tags to use and
You can just tell it's a it's a first-class distribution
method for the project and I think that gave me kind of a sense of confidence in the method we're using to deploy next
cloud and
we also as part of this are moving from a digital ocean droplet to a Linode server and I
Don't know how much can we talk about that Wes because that's a tricky process since we're moving from object storage at
Do to object storage at the node? Yeah, and while the object storage has been handy
You know, it does have some tricks of its own one
It's not really like a regular file system and to the way it's set up with the way we're doing it next cloud currently
You don't have any of the regular file structure
that's all kept in the database and you just get a bunch of files with sort of
Database IDs for names all in one giant flat folder
So that's a little unintuitive at least at first and doesn't kind of match up exactly with how you have it stored regularly on disk
Right. So kind of step one is like we got to sync all that data from our previous s3 compatible storage provider over to our new
Yeah, and there's a couple of ways to do that, but there is specifically like an s3
Arcing compatible client right? Well, we're just using our clone which is so handy a great tool in general
I know it's a favorite over at self-hosted as well because it's so nice for interfacing with all kinds of different cloud
Clients and they've even got a very nice little home
Configuration CLI interface too. So if you're not familiar with the dot files and config, it'll walk you through that
You can choose who your provider is
They've got a lot of default support and then just enter your credentials right there as it prompts you nice
Yeah, our clones a great little way to also back up a website from the command line to say a Dropbox or Google Drive
As well, there's a couple of options there
So where are you going to use our clone to take data from one set of object storage to another set of object storage?
So that'll be the data back in and then it's a matter of moving the config which includes the docker compose and anywhere
that the docker
Composes set up to bind to for data and configuration. We'll have to make sure that we have similar mount points on the new host
We'll pull down the docker image and hopefully it'll connect to its previous configuration. It'll connect to the storage with new updated
object storage
URLs and in theory turn on although we're waiting to actually do it until this shows out because we don't want to screw things up
But we're ready. Well, and there's one more piece there, you know over a digital ocean
We were using a managed database, but we're gonna switch that, you know, we're not using this next cloud
We're using it for less stuff. So we're just gonna run a Postgres database locally on the host
So we've got to stand one of those up and make sure we've exported the database from the previous database host and move it over
Right, right the database part. We were going with the hosted solution
Which also will be a little bit of a cost savings and then that's an area where we're doing it kind of differently
We're doing a different implementation in our local LAN setup of next cloud
But it's all just implementation details at the end of the day the end users just see next cloud
And so I imagine we'll probably stay around the 50 60 gig range on our cloud version and we'll probably keep about 125 gigs
Or so and growing here on the archive version
Yeah, and you know now we've kind of worked out as well if we need to do occasional, you know
We've crewed a bunch of stuff up in the in the hosted version and need to move that down
We've got that workflow figured out
But here's what I kind of walked away with and I want to pass on to the audience if you're thinking about next cloud
Or how you might rearchitect your next cloud. I'm really happy with this setup. We've used it for over a year now and
Even when we kind of let things slip because well, honestly, we've been busy with a lot of things recently
It's been really crazy
And so next cloud just didn't get updated for a few releases and our data grew and more and more than it should
Yeah
And I think what I walked away with is not only did we learn how to do it better
But the setup with running next cloud in a container with using object storage with creating
These two different versions with an archive version and a cloud version
That is super fast and accessible to our team that works around the world
You know, that's one of the great advantages of the cloud version
But our long-term storage on a local more cost-effective storage medium is great for archival purposes
And also the requirements of that data just aren't as extreme
You know our editors aren't trying to download and upload those files as fast as possible
And that that combination I know it sounds crazy
But two next cloud servers when you're managing via containers and your storage back end is super flexible
Has been a bulletproof next cloud setup
We went from 17 to 17 and a half to 18 to 19 and now to 20 in a real relatively problem-free progression
It really wasn't very much trouble and we have modified these next cloud instances
We've themed them. We've installed a fair amount of apps. We use them quite a bit
There's a lot of storage there. There's a large database to track all of it
I mean you name it
We've put this thing through its paces
Yeah, and I mean it's been pretty good
Yeah, and I mean it's been pretty darn reliable even without us giving it as much care and attention as it might need
Which I think we touched on a little bit in the clips, which is yeah, we're occasional next cloud admins
We don't use it for all of the features. It has which are a lot impressively a lot these days
We're mostly just using it as a nice ui on some and some file syncing, but even there, you know
We can ignore it and it just keeps working
I mean, it sounds like hyperbole, but I really feel like this might be the perfect next cloud setup
Yeah, it is. It is pretty nice and especially coming as the casual sort of, you know
We got to do updates and oh gosh, we got to move this thing
It's nice not having to deal with as much
Miscellaneous system state, you know, it's at least constrained
We might not know everything about the ins and outs of how next cloud works or might have forgotten it since the last time
That we had to do a lot with next cloud
But there's a limit to how complicated it can be because it's just all containerized
We've got container images. We've got volumes and we've got a database and then, you know a whole bunch of files
But that's it. It's just some fundamental components and as long as we can deal with each of those
It's not that complicated xml in the chat room is asking. So what's the cost update now?
Well, we don't really know because we went from like nearly well, so I said over 400 gigs to
Like 40 or we're going to be around 50 gigs when we're all done
I just don't really know what that cost savings is because then at the same time
We're going to transition from do to lanode and so there'll be you know, just a different pricing structure there
So we'll give you an update after we've done it for a little bit
I say go forth. This is a linux unplugged approved a setup boom
it does look like you know if we were staying at do it would be significantly cheaper because I think that by default the
Spaces are about five dollars per month up to 250 gigs. So ours was going up because we'd sort of exceeded that
That's a pretty comfortable ceiling where we're at now though. Ah, yeah. Yeah, i'm sure i'm sure i'm sure it would be
I want to say a big. Thank you to our
Unplugged core contributors if you want to become a member of the show and get two
Special versions made available to you go to unplugged core.com
Not only do you help keep the show independent and keep an audience focused but we give a little thank you to you
There's two perks really for the membership when you become a contributor
You'll get an option for two different feeds and I guess in theory
If you're a maniac you could subscribe to both of them nothing's stopping you but I I guess I always envisioned you'd select one of them
Feed one is a limited ad
version of the show same full production
Just no ads
Tight sounds good easy to listen to while you're commuting
That's a great one. If you like the show a lot, but maybe just don't love the ads great feed
But if you have maybe a longer commute or you want more content
Even if it's not always 100 on topic or you want to just kind of feel like you're hanging out with the gang
We also make the full live stream available all of our screw-ups
The stuff that we cut from the show, which sometimes actual there's plenty. Yeah, like sometimes, you know
We try to keep the thing at a certain run length
And if I yap on too long we cut some of that stuff or anybody
Yaps too much we cut that but it's in the full live stream all our screw-ups everything that never made into the show plus the entire
pre and post show which is basically like a never show that is it like a whole nother show that
Never gets released
And it's just a thank you to those who help keep the show independent to keep us going unplugged core.com
We're about 60 of the way to a single sponsor like how much we'd make from a single sponsor in the show
That's really great. I mean i'm very happy with that. So thank you
I'd love one day to get that to 100 maybe and we'll just keep delivering. We'll just keep trying to earn that so
Uh, maybe you change your mind if you haven't done it yet, or if you can't we totally appreciate you just listening
Maybe take advantage of our sponsors when they work for you or maybe share the show with somebody. We really appreciate that
We're just glad you're listening. We just appreciate you sharing the show all of that
Even if you can't contribute financially, but if you can
You can then I think you know that this is a good investment. This is a good bet
unplugged core.com
Okay, wes
I've been promised that we have an email that presents the last text editor that we'll ever use
Should we get to it? Yeah, we probably should although actually this one came from our telegram group
Which is another place you can ping us with feedback
Although email is a little easier to sneak into the show with look at you
You took somebody and you put it all up into a slexy.org document here and uh made it like an email for me
I know how much you love talking about text editors. See what i'm saying. Yeah, you guys see what i'm saying about this wes, right?
You see what i'm saying. All right. Well, so jitty wrote in telegram lately
You've been mentioning text editors and listing some pics for editors on lup. He thinks perhaps i'm trying to replace nano
I assure you that is not the case
He says he goes on to say or they go on to say
I heard you praise nano on the latest episode who me no never which I use until I found
Micro it's probably the last terminal text editor you'll ever use
Very sane and easy to figure out with default hockey syntax highlighting right out of the box
And mouse support. It's kind of what nano should have been and it's written in go
I was surprised micro didn't come up even in conversation on lup
Also, I should add micro has a hotkey that exposes a host of other very powerful options
Which basically gives you a cross between vim and nano overall the best feature though in my opinion
Is the prompt that asks you if you meant to edit a file with sudo?
Which then runs sudo if you answer yes. Okay, that actually seriously sounds great. Jitty syntax highlighting
key combos similar to nano and vim and
That problem where I am I edit a file that I meant to do with sudo
But I just forgot that time and then I have to jump out is so frustrating
That uh, I think I might switch to micro
Wow, good work. Jitty, you know, this does look pretty nice. There's a ton of different editors, but that it's
Go means it should be fairly simple for you to get on your system and set up
And it does seem like it might be kind of a sweet spot for you chris where it's got some niceties
You know, maybe you're editing a random, um, you know a random configuration file some yaml something where some syntax highlighting will come in handy
But you obviously don't need all the complicated stuff in vs code or vim or something more full featured if it's just on a random server machine
Yeah, especially if you need something that's on the command line
Um, you want to take a shot at the pronunciation of this next one, you know, I think that's rain
Writing to us about the next generation of linux users. Yeah rain writes in the previous episode 372
You talked about the distro triforce and the next generation of linux users happily enough
I am one of them. So I thought i'd write in what a great idea
Uh, they go on to say i'm obviously still very new to linux
But I already am sticking to one distribution as I want things to work on my only school laptop just as predicted
During the show, um, which they say it was already quite difficult to convince my parents to let me use linux, by the way
But i'm currently using fedora
Uh, and I like the idea of dependencies thoroughly being checked
So, uh, that's pretty great listening to the show live and uh p.s
I'm looking forward to ms edge on linux as I currently have four different microsoft accounts for education and they're held to manage in a single browser
You know, that's the second bit of feedback
We got since last week where they where somebody's looking forward to edge on linux for various different use cases
I guess at this point I am too. Really? No, not really. I am just curious. It's been so long
It's interesting that they're you know, actually making it over to the linux world
I want to see what it looks like
Jordan writes in with the next cloud to-do system mentioned which kind of went well with today's, uh topic
Jordan writes. I recently finished sorting out a to-do list system for the wife and myself and I thought i'd throw it out there
The system has to be pretty cross-platform because my wife has an iphone and I have an android phone
And while we both use ubuntu on our laptops. I primarily use an imac at work
Oh, and well, I have a pine phone a pine tab and a pine book pro
So, you know i'm kind of all over the place and i'm trying to figure out how i'm going to do that
Kind of all over the place and I like to get work done on those too
The actual functionality we need out of such a system is really quite minimal
I think shared grocery list and you know a couple items with some due dates
Other characteristics are open source integration with the operating system and well no more web apps if possible
Nextcloud's cal dev based task apps fills out these requirements
Nicely it integrates with the reminders app on macos and ios and gnomes to do app through the internet online account setup
Without requiring any additional software on android. It's a bit more involved namely the next cloud app dav x5 and task.org
Which is a lot you have to put it all together, but it really isn't too bad
It kind of goes off the rails when you go from there
But the primary drawbacks are really the reminders app on both ios and macos lack support for subtasks and the kanban
Style boards like to do us now supports those aren't possible
but jordan says try out nextcloud to do system it could be the way to go and
I know I think I remember cheese mentioned he uses it drew
Do you use any kind of task management system or any of these things built into nextcloud? Uh, not in nextcloud
I just use google tasks. Oh, yeah, that's right. You're a google task guy, which does integrate with gnome to do
Just fyi, right? I was just going to mention that it does look at that. Yeah
James says should I be using memberful? I just signed up for patreon by is that a mistake?
I'm confused between patreon and memorable
So memorable is the white label service that we use for the core contributors. So if you want to support the show directly
That's where you become a core contributor unplugged core.com
If you want to support the network productions, that's where jupiter signal or the patreon comes in
I am frustrated that wes and I burned a lot of hours on that sunday that we talked about
Because I screwed up. I thought I could I thought I was gonna be able to offer a bundle of all of the membership shows
To the patrons. I'm still working on a solution for that
I thought i'd have it by now, but i'm trying to come up with something
It may end up being a substantial discount for a bundle. I'm not sure what it's
It's so much more stupid complicated than you'd think that's for sure
And then of course, we want to tie all of it into our automation system and production. So that way
Things go out on time for everybody when we release episodes and all of it. So it's a it's
It's a lot of a lot of layers to this dip but right now
In terms of just supporting the network helping us go independent keeping us going
There's really two avenues you can you can support your favorite show memberships and really appreciate that
And or you can support the entire network and that's done at jupiter signal now
That kind of goes towards future productions
Maybe shows that don't have sponsors that need to run for a while until a sponsor can land on them like
Which is currently the case for linux action news
That kind of thing the patreon enables it's not nearly enough revenue
But it's sort of like an emergency budget that we we have access to
And then if the revenues increase from there then we can leverage it for other things
But that's what we use right now
So we use patreon for to support the entire network productions at patreon.com slash jupiter signal
And then our individual shows have membership programs not all of them, but some of them
Those are linked at their respective websites like ours for examples
Is like we mentioned the uh core contributors at unpluggedcore.com
And uh, I just am very grateful for anybody who sticks in there, you know, one of the great things
About these shows is they are a regular reoccurring thing that happens in the community
You know, you can set your watch to them
And it allows for like-minded people to come together and talk about something
That has only really gotten better, right in 2020 has has brought a lot of bad things but
Linux and open source and free software is all still pretty great
And we really have a pretty smart sharp welcoming community. And so it's not just keeping the shows going but
It's also about creating that welcoming community for everyone and the rallying around that and you know, it's been a wild year
So I just really appreciate everybody's support
It's really been something wess. Um, why don't we do one pick and then we get the heck out of here? What do you say?
Oh boy throwing a wild pick out there. All right. What do you like?
Well, I know you've been talking about this file converter pick you kind of were hemming and hawing that that didn't get picked last time
Should we throw that one out there? Yeah, okay
File converter, you know, this is interesting because it's something we don't talk about on this show very much but sneaks into coder radio
Uh, and that's our friend web assembly. Someone took ffmpeg
Compiled it with web assembly and stuck it up on the web for you to use file converter. Digital
You upload your file, then you select your conversion type and then they're just throwing cpu power at this and it converts to a lot
Of stuff this must be up on github, right? Like we could grab this and host it ourselves possibly. Well, that's a good idea
Yeah, because this can't last forever, but this is a great idea. It looks really clean and simple
Give it a go if you need to convert a quick file file converter digital
It's been a while since we've had a website pick how westpain
Oh, and it makes me think of maybe um, you know things like web assembly. I'm not i'm not saying it's the best approach or
Even saying you should use it, but it's interesting to see and take some of these, you know
Very useful command line apps that you might otherwise have to go spin up a linux server
Learn how to use from the command line and instead just ship them right to the browser
Well, you can find me on the social medias if you like i'm at chris lass
I don't tweet a lot, but I do try to read everybody who tweets at me and reply to
Darn near all of them. I'm on twitter at chris lass as well, or you can email me chris at jupiter broadcasting.com
Westpain, have you decided to set up any social media presence? I know it's new. Yes, I suppose i'm over at westpain
Well, there you go
Breaking news, ladies and gentlemen, and uh drew. What about you over there drew at doom still drew of doom on twitter
You got it. Haha. Well done, sir proud of you
You can find our sponsor a cloud guru on social media as well youtube.com
Twitter or facebook. They're just at a slash a cloud guru. We'd love to have you join us live next tuesday
The show starts at noon pacific 3 p.m. Eastern
You can convert that to your time at jupiter broadcasting.com slash calendar
It uses the high-tech power of a google calendar in bed. I think I did
70 years ago
But it still converts it to your time and you can find us there. The show is at linux unplugged
But it still converts it to your time and you can find us there. The show is at linux unplugged on twitter if you want
to get
news and of course
Links to everything we talked about today linux unplugged.com
374 thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the unplugged program
And we'll see you right back here
next tuesday
So
Not a huge fan of the new next cloud 20 ui. Have you seen this true? I haven't no
It's like what would you call it a dashboard goat? You should probably look it up next cloud 20 new
It looks like kubernetes
Oh does it?
I totally get what they're going for
And if I used like all of the features of next cloud, it would be kind of nice to have like an outlook style
Today screen I do think there is there is use to it. But because I primarily use it as a means of file storage
It kind of just slows me down. It kind of just kind of it's one more thing
I have to dismiss it. Maybe I can turn it off. You're supposed to figure out how to actually do something in it
There are no clues no hints about what you're supposed to do once you're in the ui
You can get past it pretty quick. You probably can turn it off. I may even be able to customize it
Uh, but for me what I really want is I know if anybody knows how to do this
Is i'd like to set my home screen to be several folders deep into our into our team folder
That would be perfect for me. I only ever go into the web interface
Uh very very rarely
mostly because one i'm syncing to my desktop and
And two when I need things that are in there that are synced I can just
Log in using the gnome interface and it's right there in my file browser. So that is a nice thing
That is another nice reason to set it up. I'm never
In here like in the web interface unless I have to share it to somebody well because the web interface sucks