So, you know, as part of my job for these shows is I stay on top of the news.
And one of the things I found really handy about Google Now is it's getting a pretty
good sense of the news I like to read.
And this article showed up in my Google Now feed with wireless conversions on the Pro
5.
Ubuntu phone levels up.
And I thought to myself, oh, interesting.
I hope they have a video of it because I really want to see that.
I hope that there's something to watch so I can see an action.
So I come down here and I hit play and I think, that sounds familiar.
Sounds like a robot.
Try and connect it to my TV.
Sounds like some sort of AI.
If I knew more people were going to watch this video, I would have tidied my lounge.
Yeah, and maybe add a better mic, I mean, for goodness sake.
So really you're just in your room there, you hit a button on your Ubuntu phone and
this giant Microsoft display lights up.
Now what's with the Microsoft display?
Tell us the story about that.
That's a Miracast dongle.
There's like numerous companies that make Miracast dongles.
And it just happens to be that the first one that we got working was a Microsoft one because
I think that's the first one a developer happened to have nearby and it was cheap.
I think some LG TVs work as well.
So I bought one because he said that one works, so I bought one, plugged it into the TV, went
and got my phone and when I came back there was a Windows logo on my TV.
It's like, you know, we swallowed that pill too when we decided, well, I want a really
good game controller under Linux, so I'll get the Xboxes and even us, the most hardcore
Linux users, eventually buckled down and did it for the most part.
So yeah, it looks pretty good, how's the performance?
So there's a little bit of lag and it's noticeable if you, like on that video it's not very good
because my thumb is jittering across the display, but I did another video where it's a lot smoother
and I pick up a window with a mouse and drag it around and it's a lot easier.
Is that on your channel too?
Yes, the next video, I think.
But does that one have nearly 10,000 views?
That's the big question.
No.
That's all Chris is interested in.
Because it's not got some fat guy standing in front of a TV, that's why.
Okay, it's only got 2,700 views, yeah, okay.
Also the OMG Ubuntu effect helps.
So yeah, you just press a button and it scans your local network for Miracast devices and
it shows them all.
So it'll show your Sony TV or your Sanyo or Samsung or whatever TV, but it might not necessarily
connect to them.
But the cool thing is the log files are captured in Varlog like any standard Linux device and
you can grab those, the software is called Aethercast and you just grab the log from
there and file a bug on Launchpad and they'll work through all the devices to get others
working.
So you asked about performance.
It's a bit laggy, there's a bit of a delay and they're working on improving the encoding
and the performance and there's also some funky stuff that I don't fully understand
about how there's multiple channels that you can send data to the device.
There's like the video stream which shows the display and there's a separate channel
where you can tell it where the cursor is.
So rather than you sending an image of the desktop and an image of the cursor, you can
tell it the X, Y coordinates of the cursor and the dongle paints the cursor faster.
You don't get that perception of lag.
And this is, now do these two devices set up a Wi-Fi network between each other directly
or do they just have to be on the same LAN?
How does that work?
Dude, it's magic.
I have no idea how the hell this works.
I just press a button and this stuff appears.
You can tell the surprise in my voice when it works.
It was the first time I tested it.
Really?
Yeah, I watched the video like halfway through when I look up, I pan the phone up and look
at the screen, I'm like, oh, that worked then, okay then.
I love it when that kind of stuff happens.
And the nice thing is that unlike Chromecast, which is in a lot of things, or Apple's Airplay,
this Miracast, I mean there's a lot of devices out there that have it built in as just sort
of an industry standard, right?
My Sony TV, that TV actually has it built in, but it doesn't work yet.
There's some protocol thing.
Apparently it turns out that Miracast is a standard, but they all implement it differently.
Every single dongle is broken.
Surprise.
Yeah.
That's always how it goes.
You know what?
The Linux community has seen that before.
That is not, we're used to that.
Well, cool.
The good part is our part, the Ethercast part is free software.
It's on Launchpad.
That's awesome.
It's Miracast, so I think it's using some components from some other Miracast tools
that are around, so if people want to get it working on their TV, then that's the code
you need to hack on.
You know, it's funny because a lot of times in discussions with people, when we talked
about convergence, a lot of people, I think Matt was one of them, who was like, call me
when it's wireless.
If I have to sit down and put my phone into a dock, I'm done, and I always thought, whatever.
I want a dock.
I want a hardwired connection.
Sounds so great.
But there is something to the being able to just project your screen up onto a larger
screen on almost anywhere you go.
If this took off, you could just see an organization equipping their conference rooms with those
TVs that they know, or those dongles that they know are going to work with something
like this.
And now you have the ability to present in front of everybody immediately by sending
your screen up there.
Oh, that sounds great.
Yeah.
In fact, the first time I saw this, the first time I was at a sprint in Prague a few weeks
ago, and the first time I saw it was one of the Unity 8 developers did a demo.
We do like demos at our internal sprint, so we get everyone up to speed with what's going
on elsewhere in the company.
And he stood up and connected his phone, I say connected, you know, in the wireless way,
connected it to this dongle, which was connected to a projector.
So we're all watching this on a projector.
And we're thinking, wow, you could actually give a presentation directly from your device
because the phone becomes your mouse and keyboard.
If you click on a field, which is a an input field, the onscreen keyboard pops up on the
phone.
So you can just use the phone as a mouse and a keyboard.
It's not the easiest thing to do.
But if you wanted to give a presentation, you totally could do that.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, sure.
I've done that with some apps.
And you know, I know they think about it.
I have seen offices that have Apple TVs and have a Chromecast on hooked up to their devices.
But in the case of the Apple TV, that's a huge expense because the devices that are
capable of communicating with that have a massive premium, which is not always optimal
in the business place, or especially in the education market, which is a massive field
for this, a massive field for this.
And the Chromecast, the downside to that, the price is right.
And the availability is high.
But the dependency on a third-party service makes it unreliable and makes it problematic
for large institutions behind multi-level firewalls and things like that.
So something that is over your local Wi-Fi network, a industry standard to some degree,
and built into potential mobile devices, there is a lot of room for that still.
That's really cool.
I'm excited.
Check.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 149 for June 14, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that is reporting on the front lines
of the Linux packaging cold war.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Do you like that?
Oh, I like it a lot.
You know what I'm referring to.
I certainly do.
We're going to get into it.
I mean, it's unbelievable.
As if we had planned it.
Almost every week there is some big development in universal Linux packaging.
You know, that one installer for all distros.
Maybe someday we'll even be able to use them.
So Canonical is here this week with a huge bombshell announcement in this category.
So we're going to talk about that.
We're going to even try it right here on the show.
We've been trying it and give you our early hands-on.
Speaking of early hands-on, elementary OS has their new Loki beta out based on Ubuntu
16.04 and full of all of their new shiny.
There's also a few hints of things they may have coming.
We'll tell you all about that.
Our early impressions, because it is just a beta, so bear that in mind.
And then we have a bunch of epic open source project updates.
Stories that broke just in the last couple of days.
Extremely relevant to our interest.
So guess what?
We're going to cover them right here on the show.
We're going to do that right here.
The rumors of my vacation were false.
That's coming later.
I'm hanging in there for a few more weeks.
Are you strong?
Thinking back, thinking back, if I could have planned it, I would have left town like a
honeymoon after a wedding.
As soon as I wrapped up Lass's 10th anniversary, I would have left town, because boy could
I use it.
But I'll tell you what.
The fight goes on.
We continue to be on the front lines, just like our virtual lug.
Let's bring them in now.
Time appropriate greetings, virtual lug.
Hey guys.
Hello.
So I guess I made a comment last week, because Wimpy messaged me and was like, so are you
on vacation?
I'm like, no.
I need a vacation.
But no, I am not on vacation.
So if you were surprised that I'm here this week, I apologize for misstating.
Well, that's always a good surprise.
Yeah.
Thanks, Wes.
Thanks.
But I will be going on vacation the first week of July.
So Mr. Colonel will probably be sitting down with you on the show.
Oh.
Yeah.
And of course, it means I'll probably miss two weeks of Lass, too.
So we'll probably have a guest hosting there.
Hint, hint.
You may already know him.
Hmm.
So before we're here to talk about today, though, today we have some really big news.
We have what you might even say is breaking news.
I should break it out just for the special event, some CNN breaking news.
This is CNN breaking news.
Big stories.
Two big stories, really, to start the show off with.
Number one is that Nextcloud actually has some code shipping.
Nextcloud 9 is available, and enterprise functionality is going open source, well ahead of the July
promise, I guess, of the early July promise, I guess.
Nextcloud makes available Nextcloud version 9.
They're also releasing all enterprise functionality as open source, building on top of the open
source own cloud core and adding functionality and fixes.
This release provides a solid base for users to migrate to.
Hmm.
What do you think, Wes?
Yeah, they've got an Android app here they can get for free, too.
Are you surprised at how fast this came?
That is kind of fast.
I mean, just from what they were saying before, they didn't really hint at... I expected
it in a month or two, maybe, but hey, maybe I'm going to have to spin this up and just
play with it.
I'm sure there's not that much that's different, right, than the own cloud on YouTube, but
I'd be curious to see how it feels.
This release really has got to be about this new enterprise functionality, the new branding,
and I think it's got to be about momentum, too.
Right.
They need to start off their new project and really have a good, solid release and have
a platform they're built on.
What's your read on it, Daredevil?
Basically, I think it's a publicity stunt and smart because you just had a bad impact
new.
You have to bring new, fast impact news while still people are paying attention to what's
going on with you.
So it is sort of a building on the momentum thing and a smart one.
It shows a good instinct.
It shows that they got some savvy behind them.
We want that.
This next cloud thing's going to work out.
That's what I think.
I mean, look at them.
I'm tempted to go try it.
Is that a prediction?
I'm tempted.
I mean …
Oh, yeah.
Maybe we should get one up and running.
I just sort of got my head wrapped around the last release of OnCloud, so it seems almost
too soon to go to something else, but probably the sooner you switch, the better.
Traditionally though, the sooner you upgrade, probably the better.
I guess you don't want to go too many releases, I mean.
Right.
Probably true.
Get it over with.
Exactly.
All right.
Anybody else have thoughts on the new next cloud release before we move right along?
Got a couple other big stories.
I thought this one was interesting, just a sort of rebuttal to some discussion that was
out there regarding the slowdown of Steam machines.
Wait.
There's still Steam machines?
Slowdown.
I thought those were dead, Chris.
No.
They're still around, and in fact, that company, Valve, has got a good announcement, along
with Dell.
They've just pumped out a couple of more of these suckers, a couple of more of these.
They've upgraded them to Skylake.
These SOBs now got Skylake in them with DDR4 memory and some more NVIDIA GPUs.
It looks like they're sort of going at this with a pretty reasonable expectation.
This is, at least, I'm just reading the words from Chris Suffen, I think.
He's the senior marketing manager at Alienware.
This is a direct quote.
He said, we expect that the SteamOS catalog is going to strengthen at the end of the year.
What do you think, Wesley?
He knows stuff, doesn't he?
It sounds like he does.
What do you think he knows?
I'm not sure, but I'm really curious.
I think I have a hint, because this is a further comment.
He says, Vulkan will speed up transition for SteamOS to AAA content.
So maybe he thinks a lot of big games are going to be shipping with Vulkan support at
the end of the year.
That would be cool.
So is $8.99 the price point for you?
$7.49 is the low price for an i5.
Do you ever go for the low price?
GTX 960, 8 gigs of RAM.
You know, actually, Wes, so you're going to get two cores with an i5, and you're going
to get four cores with an i7, in reality.
They're both shipping with a GTX 960 GPU, both shipping with 8 gigabytes of RAM, both
shipping with 802.11 AC Wi-Fi, and I hope Ethernet.
One difference, though, is 500 gig hard drive in the cheaper one, one terabyte hard drive
in the bigger one.
But to be honest with you, I'm more likely to crack that thing open and put a SSD.
I assume it wouldn't be too hard to just replace that.
If I could.
I mean, part of me thinks, how great are these games under Linux if they're optimized for
more than two cores?
Is that a thing?
I mean, I have seen that it is a thing, but is it that common of a thing that it's worth
going from $750 to $900?
Maybe not.
Especially if I'm not really interested in a spinning-rest terabyte hard drive?
And you're going to do aftermarket modifications anyway.
But what do you think of that price, $7.49 for the entry?
A little steep, but if you really don't want to assemble something yourself, you want to
just have a dedicated appliance and you're in on your Steam library and you don't have
a lot of Windows-only games or the games you do like maybe will be here in the end of the
year, maybe it would work.
I don't know if the i5 is quad-core.
Is it?
I thought the i5 was dual-core with hyper-threading.
No, it's quad.
Well, then I definitely would just get the i5, I think.
So what's the i7?
Is it six-core?
It's quad with hyper-threading.
Oh, OK.
Yeah, I don't really think that's worth it, then.
So Wimpy, what do you think, you've got the Skylake, or not Skylake, the Skull Canyon,
is that what it is?
The really fancy, like more gamer edition, high-end NUC?
I'm drooling, Wimpy.
What are your thoughts?
It's exceeded expectations, I'm suitably impressed.
So it's got the Skylake i7-6770HQ, so that's a quad-core eight-thread CPU.
And it's got the Iris Pro 540, which I think is the top model at the moment.
And my last NUC, which I got in November last year, was the NUC that was the best at the
time, so it's the second best.
And this significantly outperforms it, just using the Iris Pro.
So the game that I'm most playing is Grid Autosport, and by comparison, that on the
old NUC would pump out around 35 frames per second average on low settings at 720p.
This new box can do 1080p medium graphics, about 55 frames per second peaks at 75 frames
per second, so significantly better.
But the reason I've got it, the project for the future, is it's got Thunderbolt, and I
want to experiment with an external GPU connected over Thunderbolt later in the year.
I would be very curious to see how that goes.
Honestly if that worked, I would be in almost instantaneously.
Because see, for example, I have not had as much success with Iris gaming.
I have played some games, but then there's like a new Formula One racing game that's
come out, AAA racing game, and it's punishing, even on the highest end Nvidia GPU, it's punishing.
So there's those edge cases from time to time where you feel limited by the Intel graphics,
but there's such edge cases that if I could plug in an external GPU case and then have
the capability of playing that game when I need it, but then have a quiet, I assume it's
really quiet, right?
Yeah, it's silent.
Yeah, see, I'm all about that.
Yeah, that modular, like, okay, boom.
I like this NUC.
It's tiny, but I've got 32 gigs of RAM in it, and it's DDR4, and I've got 128 gig M.2
SSD for the OS, and one 1 terabyte M.2 SSD for the home partition.
So it has HDMI, DisplayPort Mini, USB-C, USB 3.0, Ethernet, and that's it.
Oh, and there's a couple of front USB ports.
RAM, Wi-Fi, and Bluetooth, and a charging USB and Thunderbolt.
That's really everything you need, though.
Yeah, definitely.
Yeah, and the thing's tiny.
So if you're familiar with the old form factor NUC, it's a different size.
So if you think of the thinnest NUCs, it's like two of those side by side, but a bit
thinner, and it's got a nifty case.
So it goes for 650 US greenbacks on Newegg.
See that, I'm sold on.
You think that's a pretty good price?
That's not bad, right?
Actually, yeah, I suppose so, because it comes with the i7 processor, but I don't think it
comes with RAM.
Oh, right.
Yeah, that's a fair percentage.
So you'd have to get RAM and maybe a disk, but I actually, if the performance is there,
I think it's worth it to have, these days, especially in here, like that machine right
there, I would love to have it be silent.
So interesting, Wimpy.
I will, oh, look at that.
I will say, I'm pretty tempted by one of these.
Maybe not at the moment, because I just don't really need one, but down the road.
Down the road, yeah.
Yeah.
I hope they keep making these.
Skull Canyon.
Yeah, it's a nice device, I'm very impressed.
And if the external GPU worked, it would also make a pretty good...
Yeah, and the only thing about the external GPU, of course, is that you're looking at
like five gigabits per second over the Thunderbolt interface.
So when you compare that to PCI Express, it's a lot slower, so it's no good hooking up a
supremely powerful GPU, because it won't be able to saturate the bus.
So I need to do some sums there to figure out what GPU is sensible.
The chat room points out, too, that it's a mobile i7.
But really, Skylake, and really even past generation processors, the mobile processors,
just incredible.
I do notice, on the couple of desktops that we built for Linux Fest, there are desktop
machines that we're using for different functions that have six core processors.
That's the new sweet spot.
Six cores is so the sweet spot now.
I love it.
So I'm ready for mobile processors to get that.
Yeah, absolutely.
So the Intel NUC Skull Canyon.
I was thinking that was a good one.
Have you tried any Thunderbolt device, Wimpy?
Not yet, no.
I haven't got any Thunderbolt devices to plug into it, and I thought I'd wait for the 4.7
kernel to get shipped stable before I start experimenting with that.
Because I believe that's the version that's going to have all of the new Thunderbolt source
in it.
Oh, man.
So I'm going to turn off a couple of filters here on my mic just for a second so you guys
can hear.
I don't know if you can hear, but it probably sounds like rushing air.
Do you hear that?
Can you hear that in the background?
It is storming like crazy outside right now.
And I have some filters on my – here, I just tried to cut some of it out with my mic.
But it is – and if it's following what I believe to be the case, what's that – is
it Forecastio?
What is that website – what's that website that like Dark Cloud pulls – yeah, Forecast.io.
So if I go look at our current location, I think we are about to have like a huge thunderstorm
hit.
So it's –
Well, let's hope we keep power, everyone.
Yeah.
It could be – the show could be getting disrupted here in a moment because, you know, I feel
like these days, honestly, I feel like I live in a freaking rainforest.
I don't know what's up.
I don't anymore.
I just feel like – I feel like I live where it's constantly storming and rain forest.
So anyways, if you hear loud banging in the background or if we suddenly go away on the
live stream, it's because the storming is picking up.
It is the great flood.
Yeah.
It's raining like crazy.
Can you see out the window?
Oh, yeah.
Absolutely.
Can you see out there right now?
Yeah.
All right.
So we're going to move on.
I want to talk about – well, a couple of things that came out of Apple's WWDC keynote
that are worth mentioning for the open source community.
I always feel weird about this after it happens because WWDC comes around, and then it's
like this big awkward time for us Linux users.
Exactly.
Very well said.
I feel the same way.
Because sometimes some cool stuff is announced.
You're like –
But you don't want to feel that excited about it, but you're kind of interested, and you're
still –
So then sometimes you're like motivated to like – yeah, like bash it.
Because you want to like distance yourself from it.
Right.
Is that why you've been Googling butterFS so much, Chris?
Exactly.
So there's just a couple of things I wanted to mention that – well, one is a feature
that was announced at WWDC that we can already do on Linux.
I'll tell you about that.
And the other – I bet you can guess what this one is – is a solid response to a rather
infamous rant of mine.
But first, I'm going to tell you about our friends over at DigitalOcean.
Boy, speaking of storage, DigitalOcean has their block storage beta rolling out.
Noah got in on it.
Oh, did he?
Yeah, I'm not in on it.
I'm not yet either.
Oh, you got to tell me when you get in.
So DigitalOcean is a really easy, straightforward cloud hosting provider.
You want to go spin up a Linux rig that's a bare bones Linux rig, or one that's got
the entire application stack for whatever you might need.
Say you want to go experiment with Nextcloud, or say you want to try something like Sync
thing or BitTorrent Sync.
That's a great idea.
Yeah.
It's perfect for that.
But the price point starting at $5 a month, the price is easy to swallow, so you could
just experiment and test.
But then if you want to go into production, well, these systems are all backed by SSDs.
They have data centers all over the world.
They have tier one bandwidth.
They have 40 gigabit E connectors into the hypervisor, like the NUCs – or the NUCs
– the NICs – the NUCs.
Not the same thing.
Network interface cards.
40 gigabit E network interface cards.
I love that.
For $5 a month, you get 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte
of transfer.
And then they have the best interface to manage it on top of that.
A really slick, easy-to-use UI that's simple for beginners, but powerful enough for actual
experts.
That's like one of those unicorns that never actually seems to happen.
Whoa!
Lightning strike!
Lightning!
Digital ocean.
There we go.
Yeah.
Digital ocean.
Nailed it.
See, that's the cloud right there, responding to how awesome digital ocean is.
They really are awesome.
That's the power of the digital ocean cloud.
Just promise me something.
Come here, close.
You gotta do me a solid, okay?
You gotta use that promo code, DOUNPLUGGED.
That way I can pay for that lightning strike hole in the ceiling.
DOUNPLUGGED.
One word lowercase, $10 credit.
You got that?
Thank you.
That's all I ask for.
Chris needs you, folks.
DigitalOcean.com.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
That was funny, man, because I saw that lightning strike out of the corner of my eye, because
it's just right out of the window there.
So anyways, by the way, one other thing about DigitalOcean.
For those of you that are kernel Linux crazy, they do have a how to provision and manage
Docker with CentOS.
It's possible.
It's possible over at DigitalOcean.
But why?
Go check it out.
All right.
So I teased it just really quickly.
Did you guys, anybody in the Mumba room have a guess on what the news out of WWDC is that
I actually am kind of happy about?
Anybody have a guess?
Mumba room.
New file format system?
Yeah.
You got it.
The new APFS.
Apple's new file system, copy on write metadata, native file encryption, instant cloning, snapshots.
Don't call it ZFS.
It's not ZFS.
Don't call it ButterFS.
Although, you know what?
It's probably very closely more, it's probably more like ButterFS than ZFS.
It probably is.
Are they saying that it's not going to run well?
Bump bump.
Oh.
A couple of interesting things about this.
It is, they say, I don't know exactly what this means, but they say it is a 64-bit in
node numbering support system.
It has been designed specifically for SSDs and flash storage, not for spinning disk.
That's the part.
I don't quite know what they mean.
Perhaps this is a file system that presumes it will not be using the SATA interface to
talk to it.
Oh, wouldn't that be interesting?
Yeah.
Perhaps it'll just talk directly to the memory chips.
That's a possibility.
It also will not be available for a while, so it's not like it's rolling out anytime
soon, but here's the interesting tidbit for the open source community.
I normally wouldn't have actually even worth, I wouldn't have mentioned this in the past,
but since they actually delivered on Swift, in their documentation right now, they say,
just like they kind of promised in the past for other things, a developer preview of Apple's
file system was included in OS 10, or now it's supposed to call it Mac OS 10.12, it's
their own documentation, Wes.
Apple plans to document and publish APFS volume format when the Apple file system is released
in 27.
Now, they say an open source implementation is not available at this time, but when they
publish it in 2017, they plan to open source it.
Oh, neat.
Now, the question is, will it be something that already works with Linux, does it be
immediately useful, or something that just works on Mac OS X and does pretty much useless?
Yeah, well, probably the best case scenario will be you'll eventually be able to load
APFS support, like you can load HFS or NTFS support, right, because you know they're not
going to GPL it.
Yeah, the best it'll be is a Fuse module.
Yeah, exactly.
And that, I guess, will at least make compatibility a little easier for us Linux users that have
to interact with Mac users that somehow mistakenly formatted like a thumb drive or something
with this.
I mean, they can't GPL it.
It will pretty much make them make GPL the whole kernel.
Yeah, so you know that's not going to happen, but the fact that they are going to open source
is at least notable, and I believe they'll actually do it.
You don't think so?
What?
They said when they first announced FaceTime that they were going to open source, and they
never did because they got slapped with a lawsuit.
And so it is entirely possible that someone will slap them with a patent claim and say
that we own some part of that file system, you can't open source it, and then that shuts
that down.
So they've made all this big pronouncement, but they don't actually technically have to
do it if someone else comes along and tells them not to.
I bet the case with this though is they've been working on this for quite a few years.
I'm betting that they have been owning a lot of the IP of this as they've gone along because
their intention is for this to run from everything from the watch to the desktop and everything
in between.
So they're probably crossing their eyes and crossing the teeth.
No, you had it right first time.
Probably did.
I find it interesting.
Think different, Chris.
They're doing atomic file transactions.
They talk about snapshots and rollbacks.
These are all things I like.
Trim support.
So anyways.
I wonder how long until they think it's production ready, quote, unquote.
We can't get much worse than HFS, so they don't have a high bar.
That's a fair point.
Yeah.
Is there any indication how long this has been incubating for?
I don't know.
I think some people speculate.
The number I've heard kicked around is seven years.
Wow.
No, it has to be less just because I've been actually monitoring their hiring job boards
and they've been last three years hiring extensively kernel developers, which I am assuming some
of them will be for file system stuff.
So it's three years tops that I will claim.
Yeah.
I guess we might know if they open source it because in the case of Swift, when they
open source Swift, they include the entire commit log.
So we might know.
That's a good point.
That'd be interesting.
Yeah.
Oh, here comes more thunder.
So the other feature, I live streamed the keynote because I figure a lot of people that
listen to Jupyter broadcasting don't have Macs.
They have Linux rigs and the only official stream from Apple, it requires that you use
Safari.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
So lame.
But always somebody posts like an alternative RTMP stream somewhere.
So what I do is I always try to rebroadcast that so that people can just go to the JB live
page on whatever device they want because we're available on the TV, we're available
on their mobile, we're available on their web.
So I figure just make it easy for our audience that would just want to watch it.
Totally.
And so I do commentary along with the chat room and stuff.
And one of the things that everybody in the chat room seemed to universally love was this
new picture in picture feature of Mac OS X or whatever, Mac OS Sierra.
Did you see this?
Where any HTML5 video could be popped out and then you could drag it and it could stay
persistent on top of all applications across all desktops.
And fear not, that feature is already available in Linux via MPV.
Nice.
Mr. InnoGoGo made a link in the Linux Action Show subreddit where he just gives you the
command that you do in MPV and it can pop up into a little picture in picture window
like that and you can move it around.
He even shows how you can do it on Windows if you were so inclined.
I was going to say, one of the things we've got, I mean, window managers, man, we should
be able to get that down.
Right?
Yeah.
So that was like the one feature.
I was like, hmm, that's okay.
It's okay.
This one's cooler though, the MPV.
You don't need to use the window manager to do it.
Yeah.
Right.
I guess other than that, I mean, was there any other features that you heard about and
any by the mumble room?
Feel free to chime in to that.
You're like, oh, as a Linux user, I kind of, I kind of would like to have that.
I feel that they should totally, you know, since we still are dealing with X, maybe show
us what they're using.
That will be cool.
Actually useful maybe.
I don't know.
Yeah, I didn't, I didn't really, I don't want to go, I just want to make a comment.
I think the situation for Mac hardware right now is pretty poor.
It really is.
And I think there's an opportunity here for Linux because a lot of the things that drive
people to, originally, that drove people to Mac OS was a nice graphical interface with
a strong Unix underpinning, which is a lot like elementary OS, for example, or something
like that, or Ubuntu desktop, we're about to talk about, that people are now aware of
these alternatives.
And it allows you to buy from any hardware vendor you want.
And the problem is, in a lot of cases, Apple has set a pretty high bar for hardware quality,
but it's not an impossible bar to surpass.
And other, more and more manufacturers are doing so or getting close.
And the problem is, is legitimately, you look at some of Apple's high-end hardware right
now, like just as a thought experiment.
Let's say you decided you needed to get yourself a very high-end workstation from Apple.
Well, first of all, the first thing you'll notice when you go to buy from Apple is the
only thing they're really advertising is their iOS devices.
It's a little discouraging.
You can't really...
Oh, people still buy desktop computers?
Yeah.
So if we go look at the Mac, for example, and say we want to get the Mac Pro because
we want something that has more than four cores.
So I want something that has more than four cores, maybe because I have a large encoding
workflow, or there's all kinds of situations where you need a lot of CPU.
So if you want to get the Mac Pro right now, you are legitimately forced to use hardware
that came out like three years ago, and the starting price is $3,000.
Oh, man.
And that's with not a very competitive system.
This system is significantly less competitive than the computer I am showing it on right
now legitimately.
So if I wanted to go...I am displaying this on a quad-core...or I'm sorry, a six-core
Skylake system, and this is three generations old quad-core starting at $3,000.
Now what's even more egregious is, besides the 12 gigs of RAM and the only 256 gigabytes
of storage, what's actually the most egregious thing on this page is the AMD Fire Pro D300
GPU with two gigs of RAM.
It is an ancient, ancient graphics card.
And to upgrade, the best thing you can get is Fire D700s, which are like four-generation
old GPUs.
They were legitimately a generation old when this Mac Pro shipped.
And the best you can get is a four-generation old graphics card, two of them for $1,000.
That's crazy.
You'd think there would be a lot of professionals that want to do this, especially with like
machine learning, etc.
Like there's so many stuff where you really do want like a nice GPU for professional work.
I will claim that this is actually part of the smart move from Apple.
As a developer, what has screwed up Windows developers has been that they're constantly
shifting.
You don't have a stable platform.
People choose Ubuntu because they have the LTS and they can be sure that they target
that.
The fact that Apple doesn't go crazy on adopting new things so fast allows for someone to master
and craft for that platform and then sell on that platform, which means profitability.
I would argue that Windows XP and Windows 7 are pretty reliable targets as far as developer
platforms target.
But also, I think your argument would be probably easier to swallow if they reduce the price
over time.
They're still charging the original price when they launched that thing years ago.
And I think the core point here is your scenario may be okay for some developers, but I think
there's a group of people out there, even people who have enough money, who look at
that and say that is just unfair to the customer.
And I think I'm sorry, I'm so sorry, but in general, their platform does pay more.
You develop for Windows, the money you make, you develop for Android, the money you make
and you develop for iOS, the money you make, you do your math.
I think perhaps people like Leo Laporte are a harbinger of exactly what I'm talking about.
People who can afford to spend more but look at the commitment that Apple has to the Mac
platform and go, Apple is way more committed to the iOS platform and now to their new services
division and potentially to even building a car and they're not committed to their
desktop and hardware platform anymore as they have been in the past.
And so I can see very easily how people like Leo Laporte would look at that and go, well,
I don't want something from the Microsoft camp because I don't like what they're doing
with Windows and I don't like what Apple is doing with their hardware, so I'm just going
to go with Linux, I'll find a desktop eventually that works for me and it has to be a certain
enthusiast that's willing to do this, but I'll find a desktop environment that works
for me and I'll find a piece of hardware that works for me and I will now just manage that
marriage of hardware and software and not outsource it to Apple like I have in the past.
And I think that's exactly what's happening right now, I just think it's a slow trickle
that's going to speed up, especially as they continue to ignore their hardware.
They just did their only one big event a year, one that is for developers and they didn't
release a single piece of hardware for developers to use to develop for their platform.
They have all developers enough for us to buy hardware that has years old components
in it.
That's a pretty bad state.
I mean I know it has a cool Apple glowy logo on it, but at a certain point that brand attachment
only goes so far and the practical person in you goes, wow, I can go get a ThinkPad
or a Sputnik or a System76 or something.
That's where the System76 really starts looking attractive, or similar offerings.
Devices that people are targeting are also inferior devices anyway, aren't they?
That's kind of what the point is, it's like if I'm targeting this inferior device and
I can test it or run it in the developer machine I have right now, something's very wrong then.
I can target those devices that they're building right now, the phones and the TVs and whatever
the car system is, they're all going to be inferior and that's where the clients are.
So if me as a developer, I'm buying a Mac as a developer, I don't need the super fancy
thing, I need access to the platform.
I need better software tools, which is the services that they are improving.
I guess we'll just have to wait and see.
Pretty much.
So did you guys hear about this rumor that Samsung is going to completely dump Android?
Did you see this?
How could this be?
But apparently, this is from Fossbytes.com, so I don't know where they got their source.
But they claim that the plan is...
Oh, from the Korea Times.
Yeah, oh yeah, there you go, thank you, from the Korea Times.
They say that they did a launch in India, they sold lots of devices, millions of devices.
The devices are being very competitive, they've said, and they've had a low return rate, customers
are happy with the Tizen based phones.
And according to this, they seem to think it's a great opportunity to go from their
watches to the phones to their refrigerators to their television, Tizen, all the things.
They say they've had 64 million phones sold they're running Tizen, and that it's proving
to be very competitive.
That's a lot of phones, I mean, not globally, not to the whole phone market, but just as
a unit, that's interesting.
I wonder how well they really do work.
You think this is legit, Popey?
Yep, I called it, I've been saying this for a very long time, that what Samsung are doing
with their S apps is building a community and a familiarity with their applications
and their app ecosystem and locking people into their app ecosystem rather than the Android
ecosystem.
But doesn't that...
Normal people know two things, they know Apple phones and Samsung phones.
Yes, that's very true.
Normal people don't know about all those others.
And when you're on a Samsung phone, you have all these Samsung things.
My theory has been for some time that Samsung will just swap out the underneath and they'll
rebuild all their S apps for Tizen and the user won't care because they'll still be locked
into all the same S apps that they had on Android but on Tizen.
We can stop complaining about TouchWiz.
And if you look at a Tizen phone, it looks a lot like TouchWiz on Android.
But hasn't the S apps been universally rejected by users?
Don't people hate the S apps?
I don't know.
I mean, the places where these people who apparently have bought millions of Tizen phones
don't really have the option of all the G apps.
What's the size of the people that hate them versus the size of people who just use them
because they're there?
I don't even know.
I don't have the answer.
Yeah, default is game.
However, what I would say is I subscribe to a monthly mail that I get about the top 20
apps in the Tizen store and I get this email every month.
I signed up to be a developer on the Tizen store just so I can get this email.
And it tells me which of the apps.
And I've been looking at this for a year and it's the same 10 or 20 apps in the store for
like the last year.
Every so often a new one will come in, a new game or a new media player app or something.
But it's basically the same 20 apps.
So I don't think they have a massive developer community.
And I wouldn't be surprised if they're using the Android runtime to leverage Android applications.
That's what I was thinking.
So the number one app in there is WhatsApp and I'm pretty certain that's an Android app
and not actually a native Tizen app.
That's the response to the chatroom too.
Of course, if they can run Android apps, do you think they could even do the Play Store
API?
Is that possible?
It's possible.
How can you run Play Store API on another OS?
The Play Store is Java.
Tizen is JavaScript and HTML.
But everything all uses the Linux kernel all in the base anyway.
Android is pretty much Linux plus Java.
Tizen is Linux plus JavaScript.
So they can just shove the Android or at least their Java runtime in and it will be working.
I see.
How does this work?
It's not taking into account the display server either.
Tizen can use Wayland.
Just like Sailfish.
The Surface Flinger, a display server for Android.
Yeah, well, I guess they can.
I wouldn't want to use it.
I would more want to go the Sailfish way and do Wayland on the mobile platform anyway.
So heavens, there was a report just like a few days ago.
Just came out, said, mobile users are not really installing apps anymore.
They get five, six, seven apps that they use on a daily basis or frequently and then they
pretty much, they might install something but they never use it.
Do you think that factors into how Tizen could perhaps blow up larger than Android?
Because you say you think it could go bigger than Android.
Probably because of the developer base or the developers for JavaScript versus the enterprise
Java who have just migrated over to Android as a benefit, but I guess they could get even
bigger because one, JavaScript applications are all instant apps versus Android's new
Android M or what, N's instant app new feature.
Well, I think it's anyway, come on, Google's been pouring millions of dollars into JavaScript
execution better than Java can ever be and you know, lawsuit crap going on.
I think we look at it from too much of a technical possibility standpoint.
I think maybe outside the US this could happen, but I just don't ever see this happening to
... As long as Samsung in the US is trying to go against the iPhone, I don't see it happening.
Chris, can I just point out how many billions of people live outside the US?
Right.
You know, I could see this totally taking, that's exactly my point is maybe in terms
of scale, essentially they will have done this percentage wise just by doing this outside
the US.
But I don't think inside the US or any market I should say where they're commercially going
after iOS devices.
It just doesn't seem like that's going to be happening, that you can switch to a new
platform and be competitive.
Yeah.
I don't know.
It just doesn't seem like-
But to target the TV and Samsung TVs are more than the iOS or whatever other TV, well that's
a very compelling argument that nobody really has right now.
Sure target the TV, target the phones, target the cars, target the watches and see where
it takes them.
And they have their Chromebooks too.
So if they, you know, it's a step there.
That'd be interesting.
That would be interesting.
Maybe soon we'll be running a Tizen desktop fork thing right here on the show.
All right.
I'll get into that.
I would love to, like even if I had to import it, I'd love to get that.
It's funny because I say that I don't think Samsung will ever do this in the US.
Personally I'd love it if they do it.
It'd be fun to try.
I would love it.
Like from an enthusiast standpoint, I'd be like, yes please.
A large scale manufacturer who can build high quality products relatively and ship them
on a scale where I can actually go into a store and buy them.
Yeah.
That would be great.
But I don't know.
I just linked the Intel demonstrating Tizen on an Intel A7 Ultrabook in 2013.
All right Hawkins, would you like to have the last word on this one?
I just want to say that with Samsung, if we think back about the Nokia Symbian operating
system, which Samsung also had access to, they didn't do any development when they did
have access to the Symbian operating system.
It's true.
Yeah.
Maybe they're going to compete with Google in like the ad space and make Advertisen.
Ooh.
Ba-dump-bump.
And on that note, why don't we-
Let's move on.
Let's talk about Ting.
Whenever you get your device, be it a Tizen device, an Android device, an iOS device,
a feature phone, or even a Blackberry, heck I don't care, Ting is honey badger about this.
It's real simple.
They got CDMA and GSM and you pay for what you use.
So you get a SIM card, you put it in your device, and you pay for what you use.
It's $6 for the line.
You want to have 10 lines, it's $6.
You want to have one line, it's $6.
You just pay for your usage, there's no contract.
It's really this simple.
I can't even believe I... Even after all this time, I can't really believe it's that
simple.
Hopefully, hopefully you do and you're willing to try it because it really is a game changer.
I save over $2,000 a year by going to Ting.
Average Ting monthly bill per line, $23.
That's for your smartphone.
You know, they just take your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes, add them up
and that's what you pay.
You got CDMA and GSM to choose from and you can either buy a device from Ting directly,
which is unlocked and you own it, there's no contract.
Or you can bring a device and they'll give you a Ting credit if you go to linux.ting.com.
linux.ting.com will also take money off your first device.
They have great customer service.
You speak to real human beings.
They have a super nice dashboard that gives you features you never thought a mobile carrier
would give you right in the webpage.
I love that.
Same with the Android app too.
I don't use the Android app as much or there's also an iOS app, but that webpage, I just
love it.
I love it and I love the...
Everything you need to do is right there.
Just as an example, we have a couple of extra lines we turn on every now and then just when
we have people in town and we can disable them.
The process is very straightforward.
I love it.
The fact that we have CDMA and GSM means that when we're up north at Linux Fest Northwest,
we use the CDMA network and when we're down here in Arlington, we use the GSM network
and we get amazing service in both locations.
And you get to choose.
I love it.
Try going there right now.
Check them out.
linux.ting.com.
$6 per line.
That's nuts.
You can also call them at 1-855-TING-FTW.
Talk to a real human being.
It is mobile that makes sense.
linux.ting.com and up on their blog right now, they have an article about using Ting
for gamers which is really cool.
So we're going to talk about snap packages.
We got to talk about snap packages but first before we get into the snap package discussion
which this is huge news today, there's also a little bit of news this week, just something
I want to touch on before we run away with the rest of the show and that's the new Loki
beta that's out.
The elementary OS folks put out a beta of Loki.
It's totes early stuff here.
It is not meant for your daily driver.
You shouldn't use it if you are expecting a stable, reliable desktop.
It's really to give them feedback.
That's what this is about.
But it's something that's kind of interesting because it's sort of a closely watched distribution
because it doesn't do traditional betas and development in the sort of daily release tradition
that a lot of distributions do like when there's a new version of Ubuntu itself coming out
at any point in the development cycle, you could go get the latest ISO or you could go
jump in at Fedora Rahai at any point or Debian unstable, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
But that's not how elementary OS does it.
So when they actually put a flag down on the ground and say, OK, the beta is out.
You can go try it.
We had to give it a look.
And so besides reiterating that beta means beta, they say that they've shipped a new
set of toys for developers.
They've upgraded the notifications, better notifications.
No unsafe software sources.
But also there's a few things like a new app center or whatever they call it in there and
stuff like that.
Tell me about it, Wes.
What do you think?
What are your first impressions?
You've been running it this morning.
Yes, I have.
I'm doing it right here, doing all my show prep, et cetera, on it.
So far, mostly good.
I mean, there's like some small things you can tell that they're still working stuff
out like if there's no default associated thing with.deb files anymore.
So if you want to install those, you can't double click, you need to go into the terminal,
et cetera.
You can change that if you want to.
But I will say it installed easily, very quick.
It really didn't break anything.
It installed nicely on the three other operating systems I have here.
Loads really fast.
It has a very smooth graphical, not a lot of like you don't see the frame buffer terminal
or anything like that.
It really goes like right to the desktop, loads up.
And in typical elementary style, the animations are smooth.
Might not be a lot there.
But I admit for my own tastes, elementary is just enough different from GNOME that it's
like the commands are different and the shortcuts are different, like the layout, but it's similar.
But it's really nice.
And just all the little things, you can tell it's polished.
You can tell like every feature that they've put in, they really want to be nice and to
be complete.
So do you, when you're using it, do you have the sense that it is indeed a Ubuntu family
member, or does it feel like its own beast?
And so what I'm asking you is, do you sort of have the, do you sort of have the background
confidence knowing that you're using a desktop that's part of a larger ecosystem, or does
it feel like it's sort of off on its own island?
On the surface, I mean, it doesn't, there's not a lot of clues.
Here I am looking at the app center, and it's kind of just, it's very minimally, very minimally
branded.
It's just kind of, yeah.
But as more of a power user, I do appreciate that I can just open a terminal, apt-get is
right there.
I see that.
I see everything.
So this here is the, they call it the app center.
We don't have a visual of it because Wes's machine isn't hooked up to the capture.
So this is their own custom app that, or is it based on, is it based on GNOME software?
I'm not sure.
We should look into that.
I think it's actually based on GNOME software.
It does look similar, yeah.
Yeah, but it looks like it has much nicer categories, broader, yeah.
So that's a new feature for sure.
They have the app hub as well.
What is the app hub running?
It's a new thing that they're going to do, which is like the app center is going to be
like the store that you get.
The app hub is where everything is going to be provided from, and like a third-party store
type thing.
So that you push to the app hub, the app hub pushes packages to the app center that people
can install.
I see.
Wes, try going into the settings or switchboard or whatever they call it there, and check
out the new sharing settings in there.
I guess there's a couple other things, there's new online account plugins, printer support
replacing the old one, and there's also new mouse.
Oh yeah, here we go.
Yeah, so what do you see when you go into sharing?
The first thing is media libraries.
You can just choose to share music, videos, pictures.
They're all turned on by default.
Oh, cool.
All right.
Oh, no.
The whole thing is disabled if you enable it.
All of those are turned on by default.
Okay.
Have you checked out, have you gotten any new notifications?
I guess a new notification indicator was added to the panel.
You know, I have seen a few, and I'm waiting for some processes I'd run with pseudo to
complete.
They pop up a little like, oh, hey, your process is done.
That's nice, isn't it?
Yes.
It feels very slick.
Yeah.
I like how Fedora does that too.
I do.
But just for the terminal.
So where is their notification tray thingy at?
They say it goes up in the – oh, okay, yeah, oh, yeah, it's this little bell right
here, and it has a nice do not disturb toggle.
Have you seen that?
Yeah.
That seems like it will be very useful.
It's really clean looking.
It's nice.
Yeah, that's the thing.
It's like, you know, as someone who does like to tinker and I run Arch, etc., etc.,
I can see where some of these things might bug me or I might be like, I really wish I
had that feature or I could do it.
But if you just are using the computer or like especially kind of this laptop, I use
it for show stuff, but it's not my daily driver, so I don't do a lot of my main project
work, development, anything on it.
So if I just want to browse the web and have a laptop that connects to Wi-Fi and suspends
and comes back every time, it seems like it might not be a bad fit.
Yeah.
Anybody else have thoughts about elementary OS and the Mamba Room before we move along?
I'll probably –
Yeah, I think –
Yeah, go ahead.
That needs to be some – just one quick note.
If you're wanting to use PPAs, you need to install the App Repository tool.
Yes, you do.
That's a good point.
Because by default, they disabled it.
So there are some considerations like that for like power users that may be more inconvenient
than convenient for you.
That seems like a pretty clear message there, that it's not for power users.
Yeah.
Hmm.
And that's okay, too.
That's fine.
I mean, it's not really – not every distribution out there is – it needs to be for me.
No, right.
Absolutely.
Like I may not use it, but it might be something I could recommend for my mom to use, no problem.
Yeah.
My son is running the last release of elementary OS, and he's been running it for over a year.
Just totally solid.
And there are some times where like you need that – you might not like their aesthetic,
but they do have an aesthetic.
Yeah.
And there are some users, especially people who maybe are more designers or artists or
like who have an expectation from other operating systems that it is clean or it is simple or
it is just pretty in some way, and elementary might fit there, too.
Mm-hmm.
I think when you look at elements of it, I look at that and go, if I use my computers
differently, I would – I could see myself really being a good elementary OS user candidate
because I do like the consistent visual language that's just everywhere through the whole
thing.
I like that they take care of certain things like the sharing stuff there, like the notification
stuff there, the thought that goes into it, the very consistent – from the moment it
powers up to the desktop, it's very consistent feeling.
That is all indicative of a lot of intention.
Exactly.
And that intention, I respect a lot.
And so when I'm using something and it delights me in a way that I go, oh, wow, somebody really
thought about that, and I have just a brief moment of insight into, they must have really
agonized over this choice.
And I think to myself, I'm so appreciative that they did that.
I do enjoy using systems that make me feel that way.
And that's one of the reasons I like using GNOME because I often feel like there's things
in GNOME 3 that do that for me.
So there is a part of me that wishes I could be the perfect user for this.
But then, of course, the software availability would kill me, just kill me, because I would
want PPAs.
And I would want to add stuff all the time, and all that.
And I mean, you can't do it just for cars, right?
Yeah.
One install.
I feel like, though, that I'm obviously going against some of those intentions.
Right.
Are you going to break some things?
Are you going to have to – yeah, you're fighting the system.
Those very intentions I claim to think were great would seem to be in violation.
However, that all could be changing.
Right.
There are new things on the horizon.
There are things afoot.
Like we mentioned in the intro, there is apparently a Linux packaging cold war that we have been
on the front line.
Where do you stand?
Where do you stand in the war?
Are we being cray-cray?
Are we overstating it?
Or is there actually really some interesting developments?
All of those things are true.
By the way, links to the Loki beta if you guys want to grab it and let us know what
you think.
Have we had a couple of dropouts?
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Sorry, guys.
The storm is picking up.
Sorry about that.
Can you hear us okay, Wimpy?
Is it all right?
I can.
Good.
But I remember that you lost a load of stuff once.
Yeah.
We have a backup recording going.
Uh-huh.
I tell you what.
This new OBS rig has worked out unbelievably well.
I was just talking on the livestream like it runs 24-7 and never crashes.
It just runs, runs, runs.
And Wirecast could not live up to that.
It has shown itself to live up to a workload that Wirecast could never sustain.
That's awesome.
Wirecast is really to use it fully as a $1,000 product that's been around for a lot of years.
And OBS in terms of life cycle, they rebuilt it not too long ago.
It's still kind of new.
And yet when they seem to do releases, at least the versions we've installed so far
have been extremely reliable.
Maybe they don't have necessarily all the whizbang features I need at this moment.
But the fact that thing, I mean, it's probably been 20 days that it's ran solid.
It's really something.
And we had some issues on Sunday, and it wasn't that machine.
It was Comcast.
And when we do have problems, it tends to be Comcast.
Go figure.
Open source for the win.
Yeah.
Exactly.
It's really amazing.
It really is amazing.
And it helps that...
What a cool project.
It helps, too, that it is available on the Linux machines.
A solid operating system.
Yeah.
Because Linux is also very solid.
So I think a solid piece of software running on top of a solid operating system is just
a really great combo.
And thank you.
Really, the credit there for that system being as good as it is goes really to Rekai and
Noah, who stayed up all hours of the night, several nights in a row, making it work.
Right.
And failed components.
Yeah.
Googling like crazy.
So really the credit goes to the Beard and to Brown Bear.
But we shall move on to Canonical's big announcement, which may solve my software availability complaints
for elementary OS.
But first, let's mention Linux Academy.
In fact, go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
All of you right now, go there and test the link, because we had a bit of an outage the
other night.
Oh, no.
Yeah.
So help me test it.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Then dig around on their website.
They have 2,471 self-paced courses where you can obtain experience and learn as you go
with scenario-based labs that put you in the middle of everyday common tasks, instructor
mentoring when you need help, and graded server exercises that automatically grades your actions
so you can see how well you did, which is really nice.
Really, really nice, especially for those of us that don't test well.
They, of course, work on Python and, of course, Linux and all the technology around Linux
and Android and that DevOps category.
OpenStack, yep.
Yep.
That's a thing.
Python, Ruby.
AWS?
Oh, AWS.
Fo' show.
There's also something they're calling social cards, which—
What is this?
Tell me more.
I don't know.
My first thought was like, what?
Some cards?
What?
No.
They're like, you know, no cards for like learning.
And you can fork them and build upon them, and there's a reputation system built in.
Wow.
All of this now in Linux Academy.
They have a great community of people who are all super motivated, and tons of them
are Jupyter Broadcasting members, that are now going to be, well, if you want at least,
involved in the process of making these cards better.
They're doing a $200 Amazon gift card giveaway for like the first 10 best stacks or something,
so you can get in early.
What a cool community.
Yeah.
So get started by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
It comes with your own server, seven plus distros to choose from, modifies the courseware
and the server, spins it up on demand, enhanced learning plans, detailed, comprehensive notes
you can download and keep with you, and like I mentioned, instructor mentoring for topics
that most other online learning sites would completely gloss over.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Now I know we have talked a lot about universal software installation, and I hope the audience
is not worn out.
The sense I get is you all are sort of – the majority of you think, I've heard this one
before.
I don't have any sense that this is going to go anywhere.
Why are we talking about this?
That's kind of the general sense I've gotten back from the audience.
However, I have felt for a while now that there is really some serious momentum here,
more so than we've seen in the past.
XDG app, now known as Flatpaks, and of course, AppImage, and we've been talking a lot
about Snap packages on Ubuntu.
In the abstract.
Now today, today, some pretty big news came out.
I kind of smelt it coming, and you might have as well, Snap packages are launching on multiple
Linux distributions.
Essentially, the Snap is going to be available for pretty much all major distros.
Launching with some great partners right out of the gate, including Docker and Telegram
packages, and I think Corita is in there, and LibreOffice is in there, and they have
packages available for CentOS, and Elementary, and Gentoo, and Mint, and OpenSUSE, and Red
Hat Enterprise Linux, and Arch Linux, and all of those distros can now install Snap
packages.
It's Snappy time, everybody.
Snap packages are here for everybody, and I look at this and I go, brilliant move by
canonical.
Mark Shuttleworth said, one thing is definitively clear about today's announcement, I'm paraphrasing.
This is not about Ubuntu.
This is about all the other Linux distros.
Now I thought that was an interesting thing for Mark to sort of stress, that this is like
the antithesis of being about Ubuntu is what he said.
He also pointed out the Flatpak, the new GNOME XEG app initiative, is 95% of the contributors
came from one Red Hat employee.
I love it when he does that.
I love that.
He said he'd be delighted if they'd work with us.
God, that's so great.
It's so good.
Yeah, so the Document Foundation's got LibreOffice.
Dell Mozilla is partnering up with them, Samsung, and Arch and Fedora can run and install Snap
packages.
I installed it right before the show.
You have installed an elementary OS.
I do.
I'm not sure it's 100% working, but it's installed anyway.
Did you get the telegram pass?
You know, it's giving me an error when I try to launch it, but the rest is working.
I got SnapD going.
I can do SnapList.
I can do SnapInstall.
Interesting.
It's probably user error.
So, Rotten, let's start with you, and then I'm going to bounce around some questions.
You've gotten your hands on it during the show.
What are your initial impressions?
Yeah, so I started using it earlier in the show, and Snap is great.
And two things are really shocking.
NextCloud came out.
They announced a new version today.
There is now a Snap for it today.
And I just installed Krita, which by default, when you use apt, it installs like 500 megs
of dependencies.
The Snap was only 98 megs.
Wow.
Okay.
All right.
I don't know how that happened, but that sounds very promising.
I wanted to ask Wimpy, because I know he's had some experience recently with Snap packages.
Wimpy, do you think it's now just come down to a race of who can get the most packages
by the biggest names?
Because you've got Flatpak, AppImage, Orbit, Orbital, whatever it is, and now Snaps.
And it seems like whichever one, since they all work across all the distributions, whichever
one ends up being the sort of go-to to have the most and best software is going to be
the winner.
Don't you think?
Maybe.
Yeah.
Definitely, there's some first mover advantage there, and there's been a lot of people coalescing
around Snaps and Snappy.
Like QNAP recently announced that their line of NAS devices are going to be moving to Ubuntu
and Snaps.
Yeah.
That's pretty cool.
And they're going to be packaging all of their ancillary services and IoT bits and bobs as
Snaps rather than shipping them in the traditional way.
So I think Snaps might be edging out at the moment, but time will tell.
Yeah.
It seems also the KDE project is experimenting with packaging Neon as a Snap, which is really...
That's interesting.
Yeah.
And the other thing that Ubuntu have done is they've reached out to people in the other
distributions to get Snap working on the other distros, and I'm not sure if that's happened
the other way.
So the fact that Snap works in all these different places is because Ubuntu developers and community
members have made the effort to try and make that happen, to make it the cross distribution.
So they're reaching out to those distros and saying, hey, would you like to work with us
on this?
Yeah.
So that's a huge component of it, too, getting more and more adoption.
And not just cross distribution, but also across the flavors within Ubuntu and inviting
people and there's been a real effort the last two weeks.
It's a shame I've been on holiday for most of it, but yeah, there's been a real effort
to involve people and bring them up to speed and share knowledge and tips and tricks and
push the platform forwards and learn from one another.
Now, what about the concern that the back end isn't open source to Snap packages?
Poppy, is that a thing?
Is that a thing people are complaining about yet?
Is that a misunderstanding?
Which back end?
So Snap D is open source.
So Snap-
Help me understand.
The registry, right?
Yeah, like this.
Is there like a central registry I can search for Snap packages and that's locked up?
There is a store and we run the store and I don't know what the license on that is.
It currently isn't free software.
I don't know what will happen with that.
But who runs the store doesn't impact who can download a Snap and just install it on
their system, right?
The two things are not dependent?
You can certainly sideload Snaps.
You can grab a Snap from anywhere.
So for example, initially the Krita developers put a Snap as a downloadable file on their
website.
Or like I-
Just like a dev, right?
I just downloaded the Telegram Snap to my desktop.
Right.
So you can certainly do that.
And yeah, currently the store is non-free.
I don't know what the plan is for that.
And I don't know what the plan is for supporting multiple different stores either.
I know that discussions have been happening there because some people will want to have
all the devices within their own estate only talking to other devices within their own
estate.
Sure, right.
And they don't want them to reach out of their network and go to some third party store
and allow their users to install random Snaps that could contain games or stuff they just
don't want.
And so I know those discussions have happened, but it's early days and I don't know where
that is at the moment.
And then we have SnapD, which is an open source piece of software that seems to be the thing
that has to be specifically packaged for each distribution to make all of this work, to
make the cross distribution component work.
So there is an Arch package, there is a Fedora package, there is an OpenSUSE package of SnapD,
and that is the sort of bits and-
The shim layer.
Yeah.
You needed to install Snaps.
Am I tracking that right, Poppy?
Yeah.
There's multiple parts to it.
The SnapD part is, yeah, the bit that needed to be ported.
And that's the bit that we already have pre-installed on Ubuntu.
So we're halfway there.
And that's GoDemon, right?
Yeah, it's written in Go.
And the Snaps themselves get installed and removed by SnapD.
And there's a front end to SnapD, which is just called Snap.
So you can do commands like snap list to list all the Snaps that you have installed.
And that would be the same as you using apt or dpkg to see what you have installed.
And then you would do something like snap find, which is where you go out to find out
what packages are available in the store or in the archive or whatever you want to call
it.
And, you know, that's the equivalent of apt search or whatever.
I feel like people are going to misinterpret that as, oh, well, Snaps are trying to replace
my distribution's package manager.
Could you already see, oh, look at Canonical.
They think they're coming out with a package manager for all distros.
It's not really.
Go ahead.
Yeah, I don't know.
What I think would be preferable is if you see it from the point of view that your distribution
is giving your users the platform, your platform, which is the value that you provide in that,
whichever that is.
Sure.
There's package freshness in Fedora, that's clean upstream gnome.
And in Gentoo, it's, you know, build it the way you want it.
You know, however, whatever, whatever your platform is, what we're providing is the ability
for the users to get absolutely the freshest things from upstream in a secure manner.
Yeah, I actually am.
I don't know what universal package format is going to win out.
But this, to me –
We can even just get one.
Oh, that would be –
I'm really, really – I would love to have one that has a company behind it that has
a reputation in the open source community.
That seems like a pretty important –
Yeah, Linux has a history of like resolving these things and only having one of everything.
That's right, isn't it?
We only have one of everything.
Very good at that.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, but we do have – but I could see a dominant one.
I could see a dominant one emerging.
And the – boy, excuse me.
The launch across multiple distros on day one –
Huge.
Smooth.
Real smooth.
The fact that I could just – it was just in the AUR immediately and I could just go
grab it and install the Telegram snap.
I was kind of surprised that didn't leak out, that people didn't spot things appearing
in various archives and people say, hello, look at this.
What's this doing here?
I had heard some rumbling.
But –
Okay, so maybe people didn't –
Me and my little Ubuntu bubble, I didn't spot that.
I thought – I just – I don't actually know if this is going to be it, but I – even
if it's a well-supported one, the momentum you've already seen behind snap packages
is really good.
Oh, you like?
What do you got there?
Look at that.
Are you pasting from the web?
Yes, I am.
Okay, so read that error message on your screen.
So I'm pasting into the terminal from the web.
Copying commands into the terminal can be dangerous.
Be sure you understand what each part of this command does and then in big red button, paste
it anyway, which I am about to hit.
Look at Loki warning you about the dangers of pasting commands from the web, which is
ironic because a couple of – like LibreOffice was the one.
Ham Radio was telling me he was downloading LibreOffice using a snap package and the post
just tells you to use wget and has the app get install command and all this stuff.
Just copy and paste this into your terminal and you'll be good to go.
You'll be fine.
Yeah, that's not a good idea.
The warning about using – copying and pasting things in the terminal was actually in the
last version too.
I'm not sure about that.
I think – yeah.
It's still nice to see.
I think this is a pretty huge development, getting snap packages for all distros.
I don't know where it's going to go for sure but to me, I have always struggled with
– this is really a first world podcaster problem.
But when I talk about an app or we do a desktop app pick on the Linux Action Show, I experiment
with, well, what do I do here?
Do I link to the open source of build service?
Do I link to the AUR?
Do I link to a deb and an RPM?
And I have experimented with doing all of them and it just feels ridiculous.
And so what I have defaulted to doing is I generally link to maybe the Ubuntu version
somewhere and the version I installed from the AUR or something like that because that's
the one I did so you can reproduce what I've done.
And the ability now to say just go here and download this snap and whatever distro you've
chosen is going to work for you now, like Telegram and Herupad and Mumble, is going
to be a huge shift.
And if this all goes well enough where it's adopted by a majority of application publishers,
there could become a point in time where we simply just remember a time before snap packages
and then there's life after snap packages.
Matthew Feeney Exactly.
I will say as well like I'm just – I've been using LexD a lot which is also another
Go daemon written by Ubuntu and I've been quite pleased with it.
So I think if Snappy is of similar quality, I could be OK with this as being the universal
package.
Trevor Burrus Look at them using Go.
Hopi, do you have any – do you know anything about this?
Is Go sort of like canonicals, not to be punny, but go-to language?
Hopi Kile Yeah, it's funny.
I remember when I very first started at the company.
So three and a bit years ago, I remember Mark evangelizing about – Mark Shalworth evangelizing
about Go and saying it was the next big thing.
And like this is obviously pre some of the other new things that have come out from Google
and Apple and Microsoft and so on.
But it – he was evangelizing it for a while some time ago and now a lot of the developers
have picked up on that and said actually it is quite a nice language to develop in.
And so a lot of the tools like – but even if someone's just hacking together a little
command line tool, they'll do it in Go or a daemon, they'll do it in Go.
It seems quite popular with developers as well.
Ryan Lewis Yeah, I get a lot of good feedback about Go
and Rust and Dakota Radio.
And people seem to feel like Go is really something special and wonder why Google doesn't
use it more themselves.
Rod and I guess I'll give you a chance to chime in here as somebody who's packaging
up applications for different distributions.
This has got to be potentially offering a big relief.
Now how much do you expect users to actually go out and enable snap support on their distro
of choice though?
Ryan Lewis Well, hopefully it'll become – in a while
from now I expect, but hopefully it will become a normal thing.
Even if Ubuntu, the base of Ubuntu and all the flavors were just snaps and everybody
else use flat packs or App Images or whatever, I don't care.
That's at least tenfold better than what I currently have to do.
So for my – every time I make a new release, I have to – I've made 19 packages for
everything.
So I have – and that's not even the maintenance where I have to contact the maintainers of
each distro for packages we don't make.
So I have to deal with those two and then I have to make sure that the package builds
and the e-builds are all up to date and things like that, which they're not always.
And then – and that doesn't even take into account that I have to make new versions.
I have to make different packages for each version of a distro.
So like Fedora 22, Fedora 23.
So every time I make a new release of our app, we also have to make a new package for
that distro and every version of that distro that's still currently supported.
So for like Ubuntu, we have like four.
So we have so many packages we have to make and just – and if we have three new universal
things that take over, I would be so ecstatic for that, just to have three rather than 20
or whatever.
Wow.
That's funny.
On the subject of packaging, we've done a couple of events last Tuesday and this – or
a couple of days ago on this Tuesday.
We did a thing called the Snappy Playpen and the idea was that we would create a GitHub
repo in which we just dump the configuration file.
So to make a snappy package, there's a YAML file, a plain text YAML file that describes
the build of the application.
It's pretty straightforward.
Anyone can read it and it's not hard to break up.
But we – you know, Snap is quite new and we've been finding all the various edges
and pointy sharp places that we mustn't touch and it's a learning exercise for us
as well as people like Rotten who is developing his apps and wants to package them up.
So we've been doing this and packaging a random bunch of applications, some of them
less random kind of well-chosen applications in order to find those pointy sharp places
so that we can educate other people on how to package stuff up.
So when they say, okay, I've got my GNOME app or I've got my KDE app or I've got
my C++ OpenGL app, how do I package it up as a Snap?
And we could just point them at this GitHub repo and in there are examples.
So we're not necessarily uploading all of these to the store, they're upstream programs
like for example, I packaged up MindTest, the free software Minecraft clone.
So if you want to see how to package up an OpenGL C++ application and it packages it
from the tip of Git, so you could run this command SnapCraft in order to build yourself
a Snap package which is bleeding edge nightly build.
So you could run a cron job potentially, a cron job which built you a Snap package overnight
every night and uploaded it to a nightly version to the store so every day your users get the
freshest version.
I rotten, you had a response to that and there's a bit of a but in it I think.
No, not really.
It's more of a hopefulness.
So the point that Peppermint was making about how the upstream is controlling it, that is
something I've been begging for at least 10 years now even though there was never even
on the radar but I've been hoping for something like that for years and when I contact a maintain
of an app to get my app updated in the repos, it could take anywhere from a couple days
to a year and a half before I get a reply.
It's a horrible process that I understand why people have a problem with packaging for
Linux really but with the fact that Snappy allows for the upstream maintainers and developers
to control when stuff gets updated and pushed to the users, that is something I've been
waiting for and I am so excited I'm like beside myself.
So what you just touched on is exactly, I've talked about it before but we've been recently
talking about Nextcloud and Frank and Frank and I had an off the record conversation that
was sort of on the record in the sense that he knows I've been telling this story for
years now.
He had a very sort of unfortunate fight with Debian for a while because they were shipping
such old versions of own cloud repo that users were installing version 7 when version 8 would
be out or something like that or version 5 when version 8 would be out was actually the
case.
It was really bad.
They were riddled with security, no longer getting updates and he said really our pace
of development, the features that we are adding to stay competitive, the methodology in which
we publish it, all of it, it's just – it's more appropriate if it comes directly from
us.
It just works better for the end user.
It's more secure.
We can support it plus we don't end up having to answer support questions for five versions
of software.
So from a developer standpoint, I think people are really encouraged.
Just like that screensaver mess that's going on in Debian right now.
Yes, exactly.
And, you know, I think here's what it would really take.
I think Snap packages, if they could benefit from the Docker effect, I think it would be
like wildfire.
Yeah.
What really did – what really for Docker, what you were able to do, you could be just
the laziest Linux user ever.
You could be like one of those – not to insult you guys, but one of those web developers
that uses a Mac and then SSHs into his Ubuntu server and Docker came along and all of a
sudden you didn't have to deal with actually installing Linux software.
You could just pull down a Docker image and boom, you had it in time.
Someone already provisions it for you.
Yeah.
Oh, you want a Minecraft server.
You want a Mamo server.
You want an own cloud server.
You want a Zimbra server.
Yeah, just pull down this Docker image.
It's good to go.
If Ubuntu – if Canonical can get enough adoption around Snap packages where I can
install what we as Linux users used to consider extremely complicated installations, things
like entire desktop environments.
If I can reduce installing an entire desktop environment down to one or two Snap packages,
if I want to try out the latest Plasma desktop, I can download a single or maybe four or whatever
it is Snap packages and I have that entire thing and I haven't mucked up all the depths
on my system.
I was about to say, the other nice part is like when you want to remove it, done, gone.
Your system is going to be –
Another example, Ardour.
Ardour is universally known as one of the harder applications to install and get everything
working.
If I can pull down a single Snap package, double click that and have a working installation
of Ardour and you multiply this across all of the little edge cases in Linux where it's
hard to get this particular thing set up or it involves trashing your entire system with
libraries from something and you start solving that problem and get enough projects behind
it that people want, I think the idea of having to install SnapD first is – well, that's
a no-brainer because that's even easier than getting Docker set up.
So there is a bit of a Docker effect that could happen.
Go ahead.
I think I agree with you.
What you're suggesting really is there needs to be the killer app.
So I've been looking at – as part of this Snappy Playpen thing is looking at what are
apps that people really want and that are often updated with very high velocity, a fast
cadence like Nextcloud, that people want the bleeding edge version but other people might
want a stable version.
So you could have two snaps, a nightly and a stable and one of the ones I looked at today
was Ardour actually and so I started building a Snap for Ardour today and Audacity as well
and I came across a couple of bugs which are being filed and those will be fixed but yeah,
those are exactly the kind of apps and the cadence lives and the things that move quickly
where you want the latest thing.
I packaged up a Snap for FFmpeg because everyone wants the latest codecs and all that kind
of stuff.
Oh, from everyone.
Thank you.
So yeah, and MPV as well.
I did MPV today.
MPV was super easy.
That was like not hard at all.
So yeah, it's good fun.
And so now when you install the MPV Snap, will it automatically – how does it get updated?
So this is the thing.
When I was creating the Snapcraft configuration, the idea is that I would then give this to
the upstream developer and say, here you go, here's the configuration, here's how you
make a snap because rather than burden them with yet another packaging format, I just
tell them this is the configuration file, you run this command on a Ubuntu system and
you'll get a snap out of it or if you want to, you can push your code or mirror your
code to Launchpad and Launchpad will build you a snap for you much the same way as it
builds devs in a PPA and then you can just push that to the store as and when you're
ready.
And if you want, you can have two channels.
You can have a channel for beta tester users and a channel for stable users.
So some of your people might be wanting the bleeding edge version and you can canary out
to them and then they can play with it and then you can push it out to your stable users.
See, that's pretty nice.
So you would get updates when the developer uploads them.
I don't intend to upload MPV or mind test to the store.
I intend to put a contribution to upstream and say, here's how you package it.
You upload it to the store because then they control it.
They can see the stats.
They can see all that.
And they maintain it.
That is really cool.
And so you're doing a few proof of concepts there and saying, hey, if you want to know
how I did it, here's all the here's all information.
Yeah, we're putting it all on GitHub.
If you just go to GitHub and search for snappy playpen, you'll find them all.
That I don't know.
I feel like there's going to be a bunch of naysayers that will say this competes with
OBS in this way and this competes with that in this way and this is not invented here
syndrome.
But I part of me, I actually think canonical would have had a good degree of success if
this would have been Ubuntu only and if this technology never would have left the Ubuntu
platform.
And the fact that not invented here one is quite funny, though, Chris, just as a little
like nugget of information.
If you look at the very first commit done to snappy, it was done on the 12th of the
12th, 2014.
If you look at the very first commit done to XDG app, it was done five days later on
the 17th of the 12th, 2014.
So they're very close.
I don't know who could call that.
It's very close.
And I think, you know, I think part of it is I think we have to sort of change the mindset
a bit.
What we have to do is I think it's reasonable to expect Canonical to spend their time and
resources developing something that's ideal for their platform.
I think it's actually sort of surprising that you guys went to the effort to actually package
it up and push it out further because you really never had to do that.
That never really had to happen.
It could have been …
How dare we be good citizens in the Linux environment?
It could have been a nice competitive edge, I suppose.
You guys are a big enough ecosystem that you could have made it work.
I just think it's – even though it's another option, I think it looks like a pretty
good one and I think it has – there's a lot of positives to it.
I'm not saying I necessarily know if it's going to be the winner but I like the start.
The start seems pretty strong and the partners already on board seem pretty good and the
potential for it just being useful within the Ubuntu ecosystem seems strong.
So overall it seems kind of like a winner just depending on how much adoption it gets
from here.
I guess we'll just wait and see like so many other things.
But I know what I think probably pretty much going forward, I will be installing Snap D
on my Arch systems.
Why not?
I think that's kind of a big thing.
I haven't – I guess I did get Flatpak working too.
I do have Flatpak support too but – and I have done an app.
I wonder when we'll start seeing like meta wrappers around these things or like an AUR
built-in kind of support thing.
I feel like someone at home or in the car right now is like pulling out their hair though
and wants to argue with us because we haven't heard a lot of opposition in the virtual lug
today.
So that either means that people sort of universally think it's probably kind of a good thing
or that person who doesn't agree hasn't been properly represented.
If that's you, you should join us next week.
Join our virtual lug.
That's right.
Because we'd love to hear from you or you can leave us a comment at linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
We love those too.
You'll find episode 149 listed there.
Links to the stuff we talked about like Snap packages and all the other things will be
in the show notes.
You'll find episode 149.
We do the Unplugged program on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv and go to jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar to find out when we're live.
Probably can look forward to some NOAA stopping by in the future too when I go out around
the first week of July.
That's always an adventure.
Yeah.
All right everybody.
Thanks for joining us.
Remember you can follow live announcements also at Jupiter Signal.
That's always handy as well.
See you next Tuesday.
You know I was just thinking about it.
Really the benchmark where I'd be happy for Snap packages to get to would be if when I
get new people to switch over to Linux I can just say download this file and install this
program.
Yeah.
And it doesn't matter which distro they've chosen.
I know there's a high probability that most of the apps are going to want the Snap package.
That's really the only that's the bar.
That's really the bar for me.
Do Snap packages work on GNU slash K windows?
I mean it does.
Actually.
I wonder.
Yes they will.
They have to.
Yeah.
I mean why not right?
They would have to.
Because the subsystem is 14.04 but when they update to 16.04 it theoretically would.
Awesome.
Are they going to update to 16.04?
And how does that work?
Just talk about it.
Yeah.
Does that come down as a Windows?
I guess it would be like a Microsoft store update for your new Ubuntu 16.04.
Oh it's gross.
My brain hurts.
It's gross.
All right.
JBtitles.com.
It's funny because people are going to talk about it how like the flat packs are people
are already saying that Snappy wasn't good because it wasn't cross distro and stuff.
So now that that's done people can pick up other things to complain about.
But I think it's fantastic and I don't care which one is taking over.
I just want something to take over.
And a fundamental problem with the Linux ecosystem is the package distribution.
As someone who's maintained and developed on basically every angle because I work in
distros and I also make software, it is one of the most frustrating things of being a
Linux user.
I understand when a company says that's too much work because for the most part they're
right and Snappy and flat pack and whatever provides a solution to that fundamental problem
we've had for so long that I am – I could not be more excited for the horrible experience
of package distribution to be over.
Yeah.
I think it's – I think it serves – it still remains a well tool – how is the right
way to say this?
It's the right tool for maintaining the distribution and the core distribution packages.
It seems like it's probably not the right tool for a lot of applications we distribute
over the web now.
Right.
Yeah.
Chris, I think you've said before repos and downloadable distros 15 years ago, Linux
and Linux distros were way ahead of the curve compared to commercial OSes.
Totally.
We had a little bit of an advancement when PPAs became a thing but it's been stagnant
for a while and Apple with the iTunes store, Microsoft is trying to replicate things with
the Windows store.
Right.
They caught on.
They realized, oh, hey, we need a store.
We need a central distribution system.
So I guess here's where I'm going to dissent is how do we keep the benefits of a centralized
download repository and the security and the assurances that gives users while also easing
the difficulties for distribution and for package maintainers.
I think the way this happens is you have to have two components.
You have to have the front-end component and I think you already have canonicals fork or
whatever you want to call it of GNOME software that is going to work with snap packages,
does work with snap packages.
It already does.
Yeah.
There's no reason that couldn't be reincorporated back into mainline GNOME software I would
assume.
So there's your front-end.
Then I would imagine if this thing really took off and people were really shipping software
and businesses who depend on it to maybe earn a revenue are shipping software, I bet the
pressure on canonical to open source any remaining behind-the-scenes bits would be – they would
probably just do it.
I mean they would probably do that as part of, well, this thing has grown beyond our
initial vision.
It's now sort of become part of the ecosystem.
So here's the last remaining bits.
And even if not, that will just get re-implemented if it's big enough.
Exactly.
So my concerns would definitely be satiated if each of the districts, if they rely on
GNOME software, being able to read and understand flat packs and snaps so that – again, I
guess the biggest thing that I don't want to see come from this is that, oh, I heard
about this great new app, whether it's Telegram or New App X, and I just go to a random website
and download it as a noob because even if it is secured, even if it is sandboxed, is
it still trustworthy?
Yeah.
How do you avoid that though?
Because I see that every time I switch somebody over to Linux, that's the first thing they
do is they go Google it and go try to download it from the website.
Right.
It's just built in.
They never even think about the App Store or a repo.
It's just not even –
Some even like Mac users and stuff where they're supposed to use that.
You know, it's like you just – you type it into Google and you hit download and it's
supposed to work.
So how do you avoid that?
Yeah.
So many Windows users that I see coming over, they're used to – first thing they do
once they get a new Windows box up, they download night-night installer or night-night installer
to go download 7-Zip and LibreOffice and all of these other random binaries from the internet.
I show them Ubuntu Mate Welcome and I'm like, well, this is 10 times better.
Yeah.
But you see, here's where I feel like.
I feel like Snap packages sort of provide for both because you have GNOME software.
You could easily integrate it into – well, not easily, but there could be future improvements
to Mate Welcome to support Snap packages and also there is that back-end repository that
if you integrate with Launchpad or the back-end index.
So if you could convince a user just to use a front-end piece of software to do all the
searching, Snap packages provide for that.
But if you can't convince them, Snap packages also provide for at least a semi-streamline
standardized and hopefully secure way to do downloads off the web directly when users
opt to go that route.
So it seems like it provides for both.
And I would also agree.
So my hope is that Snap Packagers and the up-streams do buy into both pieces.
They see the benefits already with the ease of packaging and the improvement that has
over working with distro maintainers, but they also buy into the back-end integration,
whether it's linking to Launchpad or GNOME software or whatever the case may be.
Well I mean there could also be something like the UAP Explorer things.
I mean right now it's kind of messy, but if there was a website that just catalogs
everything that's in the Snap store, and then all you need to do is click a button
that would then activate either GNOME software or just load it up a thing to start installing
from the Snap.
They don't really care.
They're just used to going to on the web and finding it.
So if you say there's a store you could use it, like awesome, great, we'll do that.
If they just search by out of the normal expectation and they find something like the UAP Explorer
and they just click the install button, they don't care if they're downloading or not.
They would probably prefer it if it would just start installing.
So if you solve both of those issues of their expectation and also embrace the new store
concept, I think that they would have no problem transitioning whatsoever and would probably
like it even better.