I think we've got to talk about this. A new Dell XPS Ubuntu edition has shipped,
and I have a ton of respect for what our friends over at Dell have done with the Sputnik line,
and I understand that they're just kind of revalidating and rebadging an existing product.
There is an XPS 13 for Windows, but the XPS 13 Plus Developer Edition
has what they call a new radical look, and it seems that Dell's design team is about four years
behind Apple. We've got what is essentially a butterfly chiclet keyboard, the function
row has been replaced by touch LED lights, there's no escape key, and it has two ports, USB-C both.
Why? I think it was well proven that these things were not helpful for anyone.
I wonder what the meeting room was like that day.
Right, after years of Apple getting grief from MacBook customers about the touch bar
and getting rid of the escape key, and then them specifically, after years,
reverting those changes, and just as they do that, Dell comes out with this, and I don't get it,
because it also feels like now is the worst time to mess this kind of thing up in this product
category. Dell essentially helped create part of this category with the Sputnik line,
along with others like System76. It was their game to lose. They were the largest
OEM. They were one of the best options for enterprises that wanted an Ubuntu system.
And with this, it feels like they're just ceding their market to their competitors with the Dev1
and the new Lemur and other laptops, like lots of Linux laptops now, some directly from
distributions. Is this maybe a signal that even with the seemingly good support that the community
has shown for adopting Sputnik, for doing reviews, for talking about it on entertainment and
educational shows, that it's still a relatively small signal compared to whatever signals they
think, you know, the folks who are setting the direction for this whole line are receiving up
the chain? Because as you say, right, like the good side of this is they're committed to making
a Linux version of what they're selling. The bad side is it doesn't seem like what Linux users
might want is exactly factoring up into what that product looks like. Hello, friends, and welcome
back to your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Les, and my name is Brent.
Hello, gentlemen, coming up on the show today, we're going to take a sleeper distro. Maybe
you've heard of but never really looked at packed full of modern Linux technologies,
even though it has kind of a more traditional long term support release cycle. And it is also
the final distribution in our summer of a mutable Linux journey. And it is fittingly endless OS.
An old friend is going to join the show in a little bit and go deep into endless OS with us.
Plus, today is the day we are pulling names from our JPL hat to determine who is actually going to
join us for our JPL tour. Then we'll round out the show with some boosts, some picks,
and a lot more. So before we go any further, let's say time appropriate greetings to our
virtual lug. Hello, Mumble Room. Good morning. Hello, Chris. Hey, Brent, and hey, Wes.
Hello, you guys. Hello. Hello.
Great to see you in there. Plus, I think a record setter for our quiet listening room
in weeks as we transition our mainstream over to our PeerTube instance at jupyter.tube. I
think a lot of people are saying, hey, you know what I want? I want a high quality
Opus stream that's super low latency. And then go get Mumble. And then you have Mumble set up
for other stuff as well. So welcome in, everybody. Also, a big good morning to Tailscale. Our
friends over at tailscale.com have created a mesh VPN protected by WireGuard's noise protocol.
It's like peak WireGuard implementation, the kind of thing you hope somebody would build when we
first started talking about WireGuard. It's here, and it's a game changer. Go build a mesh network
just for yourself using Tailscale. Go say good morning and get it for free up to 20 devices
at tailscale.com. So this week, Gnome launched a new telemetry program to help, quote,
improve Gnome. We've talked about data collection before on the show with mixed opinions, I think,
from the virtual lug and from your hosts. Gnome has created this tool directly. It's not preinstalled
on any distribution or with any version of Gnome. It collects your Linux distro and its version
obviously, your hardware OEM model CPU, et cetera, that it can kind of grok from the system.
It checks to see if you have Flatpak, and if you do, if FlatHub is enabled.
It looks to see what applications in Gnome are pinned to the dock, you know, your favorites
in Gnome. It checks to see what Gnome extensions you have installed. I think we should come back
to that. And it checks to see what your default browser is. It's called Gnome Info Collect,
and it's out there right now for anyone who wants to grab it and run it on their own system.
They've got SUSE packages available, Arch package available, Fedora package available,
and a SNAP available. I don't know. I'm curious to know what you think, guys. But this seems to me
like perhaps the best compromise we have seen yet of this information collected. It's voluntary.
You have to go get it yourself in the download page where you go to get it. They tell you what
they're collecting. Wes, you gave it a go before the show. I did, although, you know, I thought
I'd try to be a little bit of a troll and try it out on a plasma system. It was too smart for that,
though. So, yeah, no dice. You got to run it from a Gnome system. But it's super simple. I really
like that. It's just a little Python app. They do ask for some help getting it packaged. So if
those are skills you have, maybe go take a look. But it's really easy to run. It doesn't have a
ton of dependencies. And, of course, it's all open source, seemingly including the bits that
run the server. Oh, that's an interesting observation. I wasn't aware of that. I notice
it's not yet packaged for Nix. Though I think someone in our Nix nerds matrix chat room did
create a flake for it, right? Looking at you, Kenji. That's great, Kenji. Thank you. Brent,
how do you feel about this stuff? I know you're probably one of the more privacy-conscious ones
on the show. This is pretty voluntary. It doesn't come pre-shipped, although I actually think it'd
be more beneficial if it did. And at the end of the Gnome setup wizard, it asks you to collect
this info because you're going to get such a tiny skewed demo that downloads and tries this. But
is this just the compromise we have to make? Well, I think having a choice is actually really
refreshing. We've talked about this several times in the past, I think. But to have it be
written in a language and be open source, so at least if you're really interested, you can go see
what's happening. And that they're so upfront about what's being collected, I think, is really
helpful. And that, to me, even feels like, OK, well, if that's what they're looking for, I could
see from a developer's point of view how useful that might be for them to target certain systems
and certain applications and user interfaces and stuff like that. So I think it's really just the
transparency that's helpful. If you know what they're collecting and you think it's helpful
and you want to help in that way, and that's a good way for you to help, then I don't see why
this is harmful in any way. So I would say, let it be a choice. And let them be upfront about it
in the installer, too. It's helpful. I am almost hesitating to really say this, but it's happening.
As Gnome becomes feature complete, or they settle on the features they want to support,
doesn't it seem natural that they would look towards extensions and what extensions their
community are using the most and then seeing if they have a way they could just safely build that
into Gnome itself? And so one of the things that jumped out at me on this is they're checking to
see what extensions are installed on a Gnome system. And I think that could be a significant
data point for them. In my personal opinion, I think for a long time, there's been a culture
of underplaying extensions for some of the Gnome developers. And so getting data like this,
where you're going to see there is some consistent extensions, and I can just tell this is, you know,
I've been using Gnome very consistently since Gnome 3.12. I took a break for a little while,
but came back around 3.12. And I've always had it on some of my systems since then. And you can
tell if anybody who's been running it for this long, you can look at the extension page, you can
see what developers update after Gnome release, you can sort by popularity, you get an idea of
which ones are getting feedback. And you can tell some of those extensions are probably on like 80%
of Gnome systems out there. They're just maybe pre-installed by a distro maker. So it'd be great
for them to get that signal. And you got to appreciate that, you know, of course, like all
open source projects, Gnome has limited time and resources. So I like how they framed some of this
data collection around like, how much should we be investing in static workplaces? Are people using
them? Now, obviously, there's some issues around folks with installs that aren't going to configure
this and how this all plays out. But it seems reasonable to sort of say like, hey, this is an
easy way for you to help shape the future of the software you're using. There's also the possibility
that somebody like me who does like static workspace on my secondary screens and a moving
workspace on my main screen, that's been working really well for me. Maybe I'm the only person that
uses that. And so they decide by the data, they're going to take that away and I'll be sad. So I
should prepare myself for that kind of thing. Go install it on more systems, maybe. Yeah, I'll go
spin up 30 VMs. Dan, you were pointing out that Plasma is doing something similar as well, right?
Yeah, they have the KUserFeedback thing that is incorporated. So I probably knew that,
but I think I just totally forgot about KUserFeedback. But I'm glad. I'm glad they have it.
Yeah, it's set to disabled by default, but you can increase the amount of information you want
to give them. I'm all for it. Volunteer the information you want on the systems you don't
want on the grid. Don't install these tools. Don't use these tools. It's a really nice compromise.
Kenji brought up another point that's worthwhile, I think maybe is, are we going to get to see these
stats down the road? So like all the stuff to collect it is open, but what kind of is it going
to be just internal to the GNOME team or is it going to be published in some way? I didn't see
any answers about that, although I didn't do a ton of searching admittedly. That's a great question.
I hadn't even thought of that. I'd like to know. Why not? I bet they will. I'll read through,
I'll read through their GitHub post and see if they say it. I actually don't recall them addressing
it, but it looks like, you know, if the backend is open source, they're being really transparent
about all of this. I wouldn't be too surprised if we see that. Now we're doing a little cleaning
right here at the top of the show, so we got some housekeeping for you. Big updates for our West
Coast meetups. The venues are in and with a little bit of planning, it turned out that we're going to
breweries for all of them. It's a brewery tour and they're all incredible. Every single venue looks
fantastic. And this is a big thank you to our West Coast crew. Our matrix room helped my wife
Adia narrow down all of the best possible venues. So if you're in Southern Oregon area, and I hope
even nearby, if you're in the Sacramento area, if you're in the Southern California area, if you're
in the Portland area, we've got meetups for you. We've got swag ordered. We have geo caches we'll
be deploying. It's getting really set up, guys. And I've been working for about three weekends straight
on just getting Jup's road ready. She's going to be looking sharp when you see her. She'll be
nearby at some of these places. So go sign up. We need to know if you're coming or not so we can
start telling the venues how many people to expect. Meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting for that.
And then get in that West Coast crew chat room. That's bit.ly slash West Coast crew. It's pretty easy.
I thought it should be West Coast crew with no tea, but you know, I got outvoted. Yeah,
get get the West crew in there. You know, get the West crew representing. I feel like that might be
the the Knicks nerds chat room. I bet they're a bunch of Oh, maybe I bet they're a bunch of West
fans. All right, well, so now before we get into our main topic today, we've been waiting weeks
to pull the names out of the hat to see who will go to JPL. Wes has run the scripts.
All right, here we go. Coming in right now. We have a chosen few. I'll just I'll say first names,
but we'll be reaching out via email as well. Michael J, you are in. Fern, you are in.
Valdall? Why you gotta do me like that? You're in. AJS, you're in. Greg, you are in. Oliver T is in.
Anyone Andrew, you're in. Joshua M is in. Bloodpath, you're in. I look forward to telling JPL that
Bloodpath will be attending. That'll be good. This is what we got when we allowed handles for
submissions, but it seems natural for our community. Mikey G, you are in. Tyler L, you are in. Eric P,
you are in. Jonathan M, you are in. David H, you are in. And Mr. Optimus Gray is in.
We have a few others we may be reaching out to directly as well, because I didn't see Jeremy's
name in this list, but we do have a slot for listener Jeremy who wrote in too. Oh yeah,
these were just the ones that were, you know, right. Rando picked right there. Boom. Very good.
Congratulations, everybody. Thank you so much for signing up. We hope to see you there.
Well, you better come because you committed. But you are the chosen few. You check the box. If you
can't just no, no hard feelings. Just let us know as soon as you find that out. We've got some
reserve names that we will draw from in the event that happens. Yep. So if you didn't hear your name
called, you are probably then on the reserve list. That was neat. That worked out really well. Again,
we used our next cloud instance to do this. So it's all using a free software stack. And then
Wes used some tools we'll talk about in a little bit in the show to sort of sort everything out
and parse it. But there you go. Oh, my gosh. That's a big moment. We actually have our list
of JPL tour attendees. It's real. It's real now. I got an email from Tim a couple of days ago,
which I got to get back to. It said, hey, what's your schedule?
So we had to get we had to get this done, right? We had to figure this out. So we got it figured
out and hopefully we got it with enough time everybody can get their travel plans in. But
like Wes said, if you can't, you can contact the show Linux Unplugged dot com slash contact or
reach out to myself or Wes and let us know when we can slot someone else in on that list.
Leno dot com slash unplugged. Go there to get one hundred dollars and sixty day credit on a
new account and you go there to support the show. Linode makes cloud computing simple, affordable
and accessible. It's fast and reliable. It's the best hosting in the business. Real humans
every day can help you. And it's what we've used for every project we've built and deployed in
the cloud for nearly three years now. It's really powerful. It's fast. Eleven data centers around
the world and they have an interface that everyone on our team can interact with at their own skill
level. Like you can use back end automation tools, which I really appreciate, or you can
use their really simple cloud dashboard, their API, their command line tool. There's a lot there
and it's made it really possible for us to work collaboratively on this new website that, yeah,
we're deploying on Linode. Where else would we deploy something like this? And of course,
Linode also has that S3 compatible object storage, that object storage, which I just absolutely
love. You put it all together with the performance, the support, and then it really seals the deal
with the pricing. They're 30 to 50 percent cheaper than the major hyperscalers out there,
but better than that, guys. This is the model you want. This is the model where you get a Linux box
where you can SSH into a Linux box and you actually get root access and you can control
the system, right? The hyperscalers, it's all abstracted away from you with their esoteric
language and their esoteric names and their esoteric interface. And God, I like saying
esoteric because it's so true for those different, I don't know, I'll just call them hyperscalers.
I won't start swearing, but you know how I feel about it. Like that is not the future that I
want to see. I mean, I'm glad that's a product for some people, but I want Linux systems that
I can get access to, I can install the packages, I can manage. That's my infrastructure and that's
the model Linode is continuing to make awesome and excellent. And they're doing it with the
best performance, the best support and 11 data centers for you to choose from. Go build something,
go learn something, try it for yourself and support the show. That $100 really lets you try it.
Linode.com slash unplugged. One more time. Go support the show and try it out. Linode.com slash
unplugged. Back home baller. Damn straight y'all. Yeah, that's right. It's time for some baller
boosts. First up from Tecario with 30,000 Satoshis. Cause I'm a back home baller. If I want
something I just holler. A long time listener crashed your mumble server at one time with
emojis. Hey, ouch. Hey now, but thanks for owning up to it anyway. Just want to say thanks for
putting this together week after week. It's been a great journey and this is the one podcast I have
always looked forward to for years now. Keep it real. Hey, you keep it real Tecario. We really
appreciate you. Yeah, thank you TC. That's amazing. Your baller boost also helped put us on one of
the top boosted lists for the Fountain.fm podcast player. So thank you very much. We didn't get a
ton of boosts this week, but this definitely made up for it. So thank you very much.
We got the boosts that mattered. Speaking of, here's a boost from our friend Gene Bean with 13,370
Satoshis. Cause I'm a back home baller. Oh, you might be interested in this one Chris. Gene Bean
writes, I think I found a good meetup.com alternative. He does know you can hit him
up on matrix if you want some more details, but the short version I asked around on the
Faustodon Mastodon server and got a lot of good feedback about Mobiles on. I don't know how to
say that. Mobiles on and a few other services though. Mobiles on seem like the best fit for
your guys possible needs. I did a little bit of time looking into this and it looks like it's a
free Libre and open source software set maintained by the same folks behind PeerTube from a soft.
What? Really? Oh, lovely. How do we not know about this? I wonder if it's like a play on
mobilization. I think it's French. So I'm sure I A said it wrong and B we're missing
several layers of nuance. Mobiles on. Oh, oh, Brent knows it. Yes, I do. I have the French tongue.
I got to say I've legit never heard of this. I've heard of some of the others like get together and
whatnot. Never seen this. So this is super interesting. I really appreciate that. I will
definitely take a look at that. Have you guys ever heard of this one? No, but it's got it's got
a nice website and yeah, it might be might be worth a look. That's great. Well, thank you very much.
If you'd like to send us a boost, you can get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com. What we're
doing now is we're splitting out the the baller boosts from the regular boosts. I guess we
appreciate all of them. But what we're doing is for the last half of the show towards the end of
the show, we're going to pivot to just boost quality. The signal is what we'll choose for
which boosts make it into the show. So we have a special spot to thank the people who are helping
support the show directly with the baller boosts. And then later on in the show for the feedback
section, any boost is welcome. It just has to meet a certain threshold of signal, I suppose.
I don't like that. I don't want to make that sound bad, though. But I hope you get what we mean.
Just trying to keep it tidy. We can only read so many. Thank you, Boost. But they mean a lot to us.
We just have to edit for the show sometimes. That's basically it. We read them all and we
appreciate them all. All right, guys, let's talk about Endless OS. Endless was founded in 2012 in
San Francisco, California, by Matthew Dalio and Marcelo Sampeo. And then in April of 2015,
it probably got on all of our radar. I know we covered it at JV when they launched a Kickstarter.
They raised one hundred and seventy six thousand dollars with one thousand and forty one backers
in less than 30 days. And initially, they were really going to focus on hardware. Over the years,
they've pivoted more to focusing just on the software. On April 1st, 2020, Endless became
a nonprofit organization known as the Endless OS Foundation. Endless is based on Debian,
roughly, with a whole lot of customizations. It is an immutable OS based on OS tree
and a lot of flat packs. And we wanted to kick the tires and see if this was the implementation
truly designed for a workstation, for end users, maybe for family, for an office setting.
Brent, why don't we start with your experience? Yeah, I was really excited to try Endless. I've
heard about it for years. I think it was back in like 2018. I started poking my eyes on it and
keeping track of it. And they're doing a bunch of really neat stuff around education and outreach
to, you know, countries that don't have super fast Internet. So they've got a bunch of really
neat features around that. So that that's what got me interested at first. And I knew,
oh, I know you too. And I figured you'd focus on the technical bits. So I thought, well,
I'm just going to approach this from a usability and sort of user friendliness standpoint. And
I think you both know I'm pretty good at that. So things were going pretty well. I, unfortunately,
though, started running into a few frustrating issues. I'm here testing Endless OS and feeling
some frustrations. I really want to like Endless OS. There's some really nice stuff about it and
some well thought out sections. But I'm running into some performance issues, which I never
expected. I was originally running it in a virtual machine on my ThinkPad X250. And it was running
kind of slow. And I thought, OK, I'm going to give it a good chance. So I pulled out my workstation
and installed it on an SSD, internal SSD, because I thought, I'm going to give it the best chance
possible. And I'm running into some issues. So there's, in particular, I think, a great example
of how frustrating this is, is there's one of the 12 icons that appears in the launcher. It's called
system, which is a little bit confusing. I thought it was going to be like system information or
something like that. It ends up being, which I think is also great, ends up being a teaching
tool for computer internals. And it's graphically cartoony and looks kind of fun. But it just brings
the entire system to a halt. The graphics are super glitchy. Whenever you move the mouse,
one of the cores on my CPU, which has six, it's not a slouch of a computer. I guess it's an AMD
Phenom 21075T. Graphics are AMD RS 880. So it's an old thing. It's got eight gigs of RAM. It's an
old thing, but not a slouch by any means. And one of the processors just get pegged whenever you
have this thing open and you're scrolling your mouse around it. But it also just
brings the entire system to a halt, to the point where it feels like I'm running this
on a Raspberry Pi or something. And that is so frustrating. It is like the slowest experience
that I've had in a long time. And maybe it's just that application, but it seems like the whole
system just, oh, comes to a halt. Just wasn't performing the way you wanted there, eh, Brent?
Yeah. And to be fair, I think it was that particular application that was causing
that issue. Unfortunately, it was the very first icon I clicked on when I, when I booted
endless for the first time. So, uh, because I thought, oh, that looks interesting.
Yeah, I did. I did pretty similar too. And it, it just kills the performance. It's just,
yeah. Yeah. And I don't know why that is because they have another application called hack, which is
a teaching tool for coding. And it's, it has a very similar feel to it in terms of like the graphics,
uh, that are presented as a user interface. And yet it seemed to perform perfectly. So there,
there's gotta be something there and maybe it's fairly trivial for them to address that.
And I don't think it's necessarily a perfect representation of the rest of the experience,
but I have to say it took, it took the whole experience down several notches for me because I
just, well, it just, it just wasn't great. But there were some other things that I really loved
like, um, the login screen was super simplistic, but had a ton of accessibility options, like more
than I even knew existed, which I think maybe considering their audience, uh, they're trying
to make it as inclusive as possible. So that was really cool to see, but I did run into a bunch of
other paper cuts and I'll, I'll be curious to hear your experiences. Like, you know, my internet
isn't very fast here in my little cabin. Yes, I'm back home everyone. Hello, Canada. So I thought,
okay, I'm going to try their metered selecting my wifi as a metered connection. I just thought,
well, see what happens. And I got some weird things happening. Like one of the, one of the
things that happened in the software updater was that it suggested it was downloading the newer
version of endless OS. Uh, the installer I had was a little bit of an outdated version. So it
suggested it was downloading, but it never would, nor could I cancel it and nor could I kick it off,
you know, on purpose. And so that was my intention with using the metered connection was like, well,
I don't want things to download in the background because I have some productivity that I want to
get done and downloading huge ISOs or whatever sometimes can take an hour or two here. I'm sure
that's an easy fix as well, but was just another one of those. Oh, it's not quite where I want it
to be. And I ran into something similar to with just trying to set a shortcut key for the terminal.
I was just looking to set a keyboard shortcut and, you know, it acts asks for what the terminal
application name is that you want to run. And so I right clicked on the terminal and went,
Oh, which terminal is this? And, uh, it opened up the software center and just says, Oh, sorry,
there's no details for this application. So there was a bunch of these little things that just
started getting to me. No dark mode. I know, I know it's an old gnome version and I'm sure there's
a, uh, an add on, uh, that I can do to get a dark mode. But that was, uh, hopefully they
get that with a newer version of, of gnome when, when they update that. So I think I didn't ever
run into any issues with the underlying OS and the technologies there and updating when I did
happen was super smooth and most of the interface was exactly as you expect. But I, in the end,
found all these little tiny paper cuts just kind of deflated my excitement to try it out,
which I feel is very unfortunate. And I hope maybe in a year or so, maybe that'll be a little
bit different, but I'm curious to hear, uh, what you thought, Chris. So I came at it from a,
could this work for my kids standpoint? Because I like the idea of an immutable distro for the kids.
Just the other day, some updates installed on Fedora 36, and now I'm having trouble getting
Dylan's Nvidia card to work at all. Oh boy. Like the system, it sees it when I LSPCI and
it's clearly there, but then like nothing I can do now to get the driver to actually work is
happening. And I just think to myself like, well, the primary job of this computer is to play games
for him really. And it'd be nice if I could just have rolled that back. And so an immutable system
does seem really appealing. And I don't think a lot of the stuff that you hit would really bother
him to be honest with you, it would bother my son, Dylan. I think most of that, it would probably
be unnoticed by him. But as I was setting it up, there were a few things I observed that I just
thought were kind of interesting. Like, uh, and I know you saw this one too, but just like one of
the absolutely most unique EULAs I have ever seen in a Linux distro. I don't think the last one's
the last time we commented on the EULA, right? It's true. Yeah. Right. I did read it. I think
you spent half your time with endless just stuck in the EULA Brent. If, uh, if your Slack messages
to me were any cute, that's endless EULA. Yeah. Well, they have like sections highlighted and
stuff like, make sure you see this. I'm like, okay, that's wow. They're really drawing your
attention. And it seems like it's a PDF embedded into the installer too. Yeah. I had a hard time
reading it actually on, on the monitors that I have here, just the way it was scaling the PDF
and then it would bound it as well. So I couldn't zoom in enough to really get it legible in a way
that I was, I wanted it was so it could use a bit of work, I think. But you did click agree,
right? Just so we know if you've, uh, yeah, I read it, I read it first and then, uh,
I read it first and then the three of us had about 30 minutes of conversation back and forth
about it. And then I hit accept. Yeah, we did. We did discuss it quite a bit. Uh, I actually like
the way they've done the primary icons for launcher. It has a very iPad OS kind of feel,
including the folders in which icons, uh, hide out in. So unlike most distros, which are turning
off desktop icons these days, endless comes with hack, which is what Brent was talking about in
sidetrack, which are those interesting heavy apps. And it comes with chromium as its default browser
and an app center and rhythm box, you know, shot well video, bunch of stuff, right? But it's on
the desktop, like spring pad or whatever springboard, they call it on iOS. It looks
like that. And then of course there is more applications installed and it has a launch bar.
It, and as a search to run your thing. So if you want, you can just, and it's a search and enter
to launch kind of thing. And I think all of that would work really, really well for most new users.
In fact, I would argue that's probably for, for new users or average users. That's probably the
most accessible desktop launcher setup I've seen in a long time. I think they nailed that. And I
don't think it's how most like a pro Linux users like it. It's clearly not how upstream GNOME does
things, which is interesting considering endless's relationship with GNOME, which we'll get to more,
but yet it's how they're doing things. I think the technological appeal to endless OS
is OS tree. Also they integrate flat packs at a level deeper than I've seen any other distribution.
Like when the system's booting up and you clear the splash screen and you just look at the services
starting, you'll see a ton of stuff is actually flat pack stuff, even at the lower level of the
system. I've never seen it integrated that low before. I'll talk about that more with Cassidy.
And it's hard to mess up because of all of these things, because of the flat pack and because of
the immutable nature. It also means that if it's not right, it's harder to tweak it to make it right.
But if it's working out of the box and it works for you, it'll pretty much stay that way. That is
really nice. I think the number one thing I hate is when I give a family member Linux and then they
come back to me in about three months and something broke. And I just find that intolerable. And so
I think this would prevent those kinds of things. And then ultimately it's easy to use.
It's obvious. I think anyone who has any familiarity with a computer at all could use
Endless OS. And not all distributions strike that balance. So I don't know if I love it. I think
I prefer seeing what GNOME's doing now. I want the newer stuff now. I already want GNOME 43, right?
So Endless just isn't really a distribution for me. But I don't think Dylan cares what version of
GNOME he gets as long as files works, as long as he can use the system. He doesn't care what version
of GNOME it is. He just wants it to be nice. He wants it to look modern. He wants it to be nice.
He sees dad set up and he wants it to look cool like dad set up. So dark mode would be helpful.
What about you, Wes? A few things stand out from what you guys said. One, yeah, the flat pack
implementation is just really nice. And that, to me, it led me down this train of thought here of
I can't really think of the last time I saw a Linux distribution that felt this productized,
and not in a bad way, just like very thoughtfully designed, clearly that these elements have been
selected and worked on and honed over the long number of years now that Endless has been around
to try to get this experience. I think maybe there's some questions around if that's really
the experience like you and I and Brent want for our systems because we're so used to sort of
taking all these bits, especially with something, you know, talking of immutability playing with
with Nix, where we're building our own custom systems from whole cloth, basically. Endless is
kind of on the opposite end of the spectrum. But what they've done is it's just really impressive.
And like you're talking about, you know, Dylan, I'm thinking kind of the reverse here. I'm thinking
my mom, you know, she's on a older 1804, 20 or four, either way, I need to do some updates,
a Monte system. I think I might just try Endless next for her. I could see that being a pretty
trouble free OS in that situation. I did find it a little funny to get started with. I do want to
give them a lot of credit for having a lot of different images available. I really enjoyed that
they had like a VMDK image. If you just want to try it out in a virtual machine, no fuss. They've
got Raspberry Pi, they've got pine stuff. They've got like a lot of different ARM versions. But
that also means you have a ton of different things to pick from. And you're like, well,
do I want this multi language? And like, they've got these minimal base versions, but then he's
also really fat, like 16 gig downloads if you want all the stuff baked in. But unless you spend
enough time sort of reading all the verbiage to understand what those options are and mean,
I don't know, I could I could see not getting the image I want. And then I was also just a
little surprised that you end up getting a dot torrent file instead of your ISO or
IMG. Yeah, I'm fine with that. I'm fine with that. But is the average endless user fine with that?
I don't know. I don't want to presume. But that's the end. That's where I have some questions. I'd
be I'd be real curious to learn more because on one hand, torrent files are kind of, you know,
kind of arcane if you're not a if you're not a nerd, downloading a lot of ISOs or other content.
But at the same time, you could see where you know, some of the use cases that endless is trying
to fit here. Maybe you don't have access to fancy CDNs, but you could see where you could
maybe you don't have access to fancy CDNs. But you do have a local community or a local school
or few organizations in a country that have these distributed. And that's where something like
torrents might really shine. Yeah, I could also see though, in school networks torrents being
totally blocked. You know, you just in a university, I could see them blocking torrent downloads.
You know, West to add to your confusion, I found that there were certain downloads of a certain
version of endless os at endless os.com. And then there were a few places at endless os.org, where
I think more of the development happens where I found more updated versions like 4.0 dot eight,
I think it is is the most recent and I was a little confused. I guess on the homepage, maybe
that's their like super stable, you know, 4.0 release. And that's what they're putting out
there. But if you I was trying to get the latest and greatest version, and I, I found like three
different places to get different versions that I thought was a little bit confusing. And the one
that they put it endless.org, they actually lead with a Windows installer version. Oh, that's
fascinating. Yeah, there's a lot more to play with here. I gotta say like, I don't think I've
finished my playing around with endless OS. I mean, as you say, right, they've got this whole
option to like, just install it alongside Windows, I definitely the next time I'm feeling up to
actually doing a fresh Windows install, I'd like to try that alongside. And then as you mentioned,
like they've got Raspberry Pi support. And I just I just want to see how that hangs together.
Yeah, it is it makes for a confusing set of download options. But I guess, you know, it's nice
to have those options. So either way, for an enthusiast, it's fine. I wonder how the cycle
for users are most endless users, you know, sort of setting this up for themselves? Or is it
something, you know, more institutional, where, you know, someone can get these ISO files on the
back end, maybe they're not even a computer expert, but they know enough to sort of get these
files going and start flashing laptops with them and hand them out? Because it seems like once you
get past that first phase, then yeah, I think we've all kind of thought like, Oh, yeah, I'm not
gonna be able to break this very easily. Or at least, you know, less knowledgeable Linux users
certainly won't. I think our buddy Cass will speak to that a bit. But I got a I got a vague sense
when talking to him kind of like, where their market is now for that kind of thing. And I think
it's probably a lot of pre installed, like somebody else's installing it for them. Yeah,
that makes sense. And, you know, really here, we're not experts, we're just kind of dabbling,
we've done our whole summer of immutability. Endless is a fascinating, totally different
approach. And I think it also speaks to sort of the usefulness of tools like OS tree and where
those technologies are going. But we wanted, you know, we wanted more details. And thankfully,
our dear friend of the show, Cassidy James Blady was willing to sit down earlier this week with
Chris. He's now working at Endless, and had a bunch of insights to share with us.
So a big welcome back to the show, Cassidy. It has been too long. I think the last time you
and I chatted might have been in person at system 76 last year. Yeah, yeah, it's been a minute.
A lot has changed for you since then. So I know you're now over at Endless,
I think probably last time you're on the show, you're still at elementary. Yeah. So tell us
what you do at Endless and what your title is over there and all that jazz.
At Endless, I'm the partner success engineer. And basically my job, it's funny because it's kind of
this almost, what's the word, amorphous job description. But it's basically like,
make sure that our partners are successful and whatever is needed there. And practically,
what that means is I'm a bridge between the engineering team and partner organizations.
So there's like other nonprofits, non-governmental organizations, sometimes governments that are
deploying Endless OS in various places around the world. And I help make that happen.
Interesting. Those sound like some pretty heavy hitter clients. It's interesting too,
because knowing what I know about you and your style and your tastes, I think it seems like
Endless is a really good fit because Endless OS itself is one of the most polished Linux
distributions that I've ever used. And there's a lot that goes into making a distribution this
nice, this well put together and this accessible to end users. But yet, I wonder if you agree,
because I know you've been around for a minute in the Linux community. It really doesn't feel like
many people are talking about Endless. Why do you suppose it doesn't quite get the attention,
maybe say a Mint or another distribution that's really desktop focused out there?
Yeah. Well, it's funny. It definitely is kind of a sleeper OS in a way, as far as within
the Linux community. And I think a big part of that is because the Linux community,
shocker, is not really the target audience of Endless OS. And that's fine. And that's
actually pretty cool. The target for Endless OS is these partner organizations and people around
the world who need a simple computer. And a lot of times there's a heavy education focus. We work
with educational institutions like schools or school districts, and they'll deploy this in a
school for kids who have only ever used a smartphone as their computer. And so this is
their first computer, their first real computer. That's a very different audience from what I think
most people using Linux Mint or Fedora or whatever are going to be. And that speaks to the diversity
of open source and why I think it's cool. You get a lot of flack sometimes. People say,
oh, why don't all the distros come together and make one super distro? That's recurring,
almost like a meme at this point, right? It's like, why can't we all just make one desktop
environment, one distro, one OS? And while sometimes I do think companies venture out on
their own a little too much and don't kind of work with the rest of the community, I think there's
also a place for that. I think there's a place for, we have a target market. We have, I mean,
at Endless, we have a decade of experience working with these organizations and these
deployments around the world. A lot of times it's places with really low power computers
with little or no internet or very expensive internet. These are very different users than,
say, a developer running Ubuntu. I think sometimes there's a place for that, for different
solutions for different people. It strikes me, though, that there's a bit of a dichotomy with
this distribution because I think you just really did a really good job defining who the target
user is. But yet, my early investigations into this, it feels like it's built on a lot of advanced
technologies. I feel like I see Flatpaks Incorporated way lower in the system than I've
seen other distributions incorporate Flatpaks. Can you talk about that a little bit?
And I'm actually not super clear on the origin origins of this. Rob McQueen, our CEO, would
actually be the person to dive into the real interesting history here with Collabra and
Lanaro. There was some, the origins of Endless OS comes out of that somehow somewhere. Basically,
it was the first or one of the first image-based Linux operating systems. So we use OS Tree for
the operating system at a low level. The whole OS is an OS Tree image and updates come through as
like a diff commits almost like Git. If you're familiar with OS Tree, it's like Git for operating
systems. It's actually the same technology that Flatpak uses under the hood. So the whole operating
system's an image and you get updates to it. And then the natural solution for apps on top of that
is Flatpak. Again, similar technology or same technologies under the hood. The biggest thing for
us is it has to be bulletproof. It has to just work really well and updates over extremely slow,
extremely expensive data connections. Updates have to come down and they have to be diffs
of the OS. You can't download an entire 100 gigabyte or more image with all the educational
content especially. And you can't download it halfway and then have it fail and download it
again because you're paying per bit. So it has to be bulletproof. On the other side of the keyboard,
on the user side of the keyboard, you have somebody who can't debug it, whether it's a kid
at a school or maybe an administrator, a teacher or an administrator at a school who is not an IT
person. The school may not even have an IT department. It's like, it just has to work. It
has to work really well. And so that's really the reasons we use OS3 image-based and Flatpak is. We
can't have package conflicts. We can't have any of that legacy issues that you might have had in
the past on Linux. You know, we've been spending the summer looking at immutable Linux distributions
and Endless feels like the absolute peak implementation where maybe even at first
pass, if you downloaded this and just use it, you wouldn't realize that it's an image-based OS
at all. That's fascinating. And I imagine to pull that off, to integrate Flatpaks like they have,
all of this, there must be a lot of upstream collaboration with the GNOME project and GTK.
And I think this is an area where Endless is probably heavily involved and again,
doesn't get very much attention. Yeah. I love this. Like what I talked to friends about,
they're like, Oh, Endless, I've kind of heard you guys, like heard about you guys. Like,
what do you do? I'm like, well, do you use GNOME software? Do you use Flatpak? Have you ever used
Flathub? Have you ever used the Power Profiles work? Have you ever done anything with Metered
Data? Have you ever, like, if you've done any of that stuff, you've used our software and because
we've written it upstream. Even if you've like gone super wild experimental developer, like if
you're testing GNOME OS, which is like the open secret GNOME operating system, that's, you know,
just for CI or just, just for testing in CI, not on real hardware, that uses the Endless installer
as its installer. Like we contributed that upstream to GNOME. Much of the work going into
GNOME these days, I don't want to take credit for everything. Like obviously there's so many people
and there's such a diversity of people involved in GNOME, but like much of the work that you don't
realize in the GNOME community and the Flatpak community is done by Endless people. I find that
absolutely fascinating. And of course, users get the benefit on all of the distributions, but
it creates this interesting situation where, yeah, Endless isn't necessarily shipping the latest
GNOME base. It's like what, 3.38 or something like that base still, you know, and of course,
GNOME 42 is out and they're working on 43, but yet a lot of the features I'm now enjoying in
current versions of GNOME are actually here in Endless already. Yeah, yeah. The Metered Data is
a big example of that. And it was years ago, I went to a hack fest in, I think it was in London
at Red Hat office with a bunch of GNOME people. And I was there, like I was half representing
elementary and half representing System76. Like this is the beauty of open source and all the
companies and organizations involved in open source is like, I'm still involved with the exact
same people as when I was working at System76, doing elementary in my free time, and now I'm
working at Endless. But yeah, the focus of that hack fest was Metered Data and Parental Controls.
And those were two features that didn't exist in GNOME and weren't standardized in any way.
They existed in Endless OS downstream and we, Endless sent people to like,
hey, how do we design it in a way that not just works for us and our use cases, we know
we have weird use cases for our weird users, you know, compared to the broader Linux community,
but how do we actually do it the right way upstream? And so now that's why Parental
Controls is built in. There's a, what's it called? Malkontent, which is a great name for a library.
It's a library for implementing like parental controls and content aware. And it piggybacks
on the Flatpak and AppStream data. So like you can restrict your apps that are open based on like
what kind of contents they have. Like there's all these efforts that like we've been kind of had our
fingers in that really make for a really good experience for any general purpose operating
system as well. Yeah. And it makes it safe as a family machine, desktop OS. And that's nice.
And not one you have to tinker with. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. We hear a lot of people who are like,
Hey, I heard this Endless OS thing. Like I'm a developer. It doesn't really make sense for me,
which first of all, that's side note. Like I do a lot of development and I use Endless OS,
but I get it. Like maybe, maybe an Ubuntu or Fedora install or something is better for you.
And that's fine. But like, we'll hear from these people. But I bought a laptop for my kid and I
threw Endless OS on it and I just don't have to worry. And it's like, yes, exactly. You don't have
to be an IT person to run it. You don't have to like worry about the content because it has parental
controls built in and it's proven by tens of thousands of active users out there around the
world of like different cultures and different deployments in different countries. So it's a
pretty safe bet. It's maybe one of the lesser known out there, but it should probably get more
attention. I hear from listeners all the time who say, well, I ended up getting a Mac or I switched
to Windows for a bit. I just got too frustrated. And my thought was, is always like, well, you
should try something like Endless because you still get to use Linux, you get that environment,
but you've got that bulletproof image base, flat packs for the applications. As we kind of
wrap up this little summer journey into immutable Linux, I wonder if you agree that it's going to
take a long time, but I could see in five to 10 years, your average users that are getting Linux
systems, maybe they're shipped from a manufacturer for office work and enterprise work and school
work. Doesn't it seem like just the trend is going to be all of those are inevitably going to be
immutable based systems, image based systems in some way just because of the problems that solves
for everyday users? It seems inevitable to me. What about to you? Yeah, absolutely. I'm actually
more surprised that it's not already happening sooner, if that makes sense. I've been using
Silverblue off and on. For a while, it was my way to see what Gnome was up to before I was as deeply
involved in the Gnome community, because I just knew I don't really want to fiddle with, honestly,
it was like for me, I wasn't used to Fedora package management. And so I was like, if I just
I can't do Fedora package management with Silverblue, I knew there's RPM, OS3 and stuff.
So that was the reason I started on Silverblue and I think it was on Fedora 34. And then that
install, I upgraded to 35 and 36. I upgraded to the alpha of 36 and rolled back to 35. And that
was flawless. That's what sold me and what blew my mind was like, oh, this is just the way it should
be. This is just the right way to do it. And I think all the right people, all the important
people working on things know that. I think the hurdles we have to get over is like developer
tooling, which I'll say with like with Toolbox and Flatpak Builder and stuff, the developer
experience is actually really good, too. I'm still kind of getting used to doing everything
in a toolbox, but it's really nice to have that separation between your host OS and your
development environment. It's a sound concept. Maybe here's my hot take. I would be shocked if
Fedora doesn't switch to Silverblue as the default within the next three years, maybe.
I was going to say five, but I was like, let's be aggressive.
Yeah, five was my bet. So three is a little aggressive, but it's wild and I feel like I've
had a blind spot on all of this really until about April and then June of this year when I really
started paying attention at the beginning of summer. It's just funny because you look at it
and after you've used it for a bit, you're like, oh, well, clearly this is the way it's going.
So it solves so many problems. I was talking with the GNOME design team last week and they're
working on some new features in GNOME software, some new designs, and it's like, you know,
this would just be so much easier if we didn't have to worry about devs and RPMs
and if it was just images for the OS and Flatpaks for the apps. And honestly, that's how I have
Silverblue. That's how Endless OS is set up. It really is nice once you kind of just accept
that's how it works. It's real nice. Yeah, you get that workflow and it functions really good.
It's really solid. You have modern applications. You're not stuck to just what's in the repo
and you have that bulletproof reliability. It's such a win. Well, Cassie, it's been really fun
to dig into this. Endless looks like just a beautiful OS. It's just a really great piece
of work and stay in touch. Thanks for coming on and chatting with me and keep up the great work.
Sounds good. Thank you. Bitwarden.com slash Linux. Get started with a free trial for yourself
or a team or an enterprise at Bitwarden.com slash Linux. I started as an individual user and now I
use it for my business and Bitwarden makes it really simple all along the way to just have
really great password and security hygiene and store your secrets in a safe place. I imported
from my old password manager years ago and then it was also very simple for others on our team
to import from their password managers and now we can all work collaboratively. And as a team,
we use that daily. But as a business owner, I take some security in knowing that Bitwarden
is open source and it's trusted by millions of individuals in their community. Wes and I use it
every single day personally and for our work stuff. And Bitwarden has been adding features
at an incredible clip. New stuff all the time, like cross domain identity management, of course,
username generator, which I think is just brilliant. And they've worked with email relay
services. So you could actually even give a unique email, a unique username and a unique password
for every site or service you use. And Bitwarden is the only way I think it's reasonable to stay
secure across mobile and desktop devices. And of course, they have a flat pack app. So it's one of
the very first things I install so I can start authenticating everything because like everything
needs a log in these days. And then, of course, I also have to log in on my mobile device.
And like, am I going to have like this crazy three or four sentence long password that I type in
manually every single time? Of course not. Of course not. And Bitwarden is the best way to
manage that. And it's all your secrets. And you can also put your two factor tokens in there,
which is really convenient. And they make it really simple to manage your personal stuff
and your business stuff. I can attest to that. You can keep them separated, but easily switch
between them. On top of all of that, you can get ease of mind with their vault health reports.
It's so great bringing it all together. And then when you add the new features,
just the really smart stuff that they've been like laser accurately adding to Bitwarden.
Oh, it's such a great time to become a Bitwarden user. If maybe you've already done it. You know,
I'd be surprised if you haven't because it is really self-evident. So if you have,
maybe you could suggest this to someone else. It's a great way to support the show as well.
Maybe your workplace could use this. We all have a friend or a family member that could probably
do passwords better, better than the sticky under their keyboard. I won't name names,
but I have more than one family member that used to do it that way. I gave the gift of Bitwarden.
You can too. Bitwarden.com slash Linux. One more time to go get it for yourself
or for a team. Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
As always, we got some great feedback this week. If you want to send us some,
you can go to Linux Unplugged dot com slash contact. Former Gentour sent two ideas I think
were worthy of discussion. The first is just a little feedback on Tailscale. They say,
Hey, wonderful team. I've been listening to y'all for a year now, and I'm eternally grateful for
Tailscale, which I learned about from you and which I've been using to roll out my own VPN
for the family. We're spread out through three continents. I take a good look at every single
one of your software recommendations. Thank you. Isn't that nice? That is nice. That is nice.
We can take full credit for Tailscale. You know, I think the team over there did some of the work
too. We just are standing on the shoulders of giants with Tailscale. We have the easy job of
just being fans. I do like it a lot. It's it's to me, it's the same type of game changer that
file sync was and SSH was like it's a it's a whole step change in functionality. And I guess always
some some shout outs to old Jason Doenfeld for WarGuard in the fricking first place. Also, another
favorite tool of the show is Nebula. It's another really great one that you can completely host
yourself. You need to set it up a little bit more versus Tailscale. It's like, you know, especially
for some of your you know, if you have like staticky backend infrastructure that you have
deployed, like Nebula is great and super minimal and fast and clean. If you've got you know, like
a great example would be just a couple of systems or VPS is spread out across a couple of providers
and maybe like the local box and the you're planning to keep them forever. You don't really
need mobile a mobile device in there. I think Nebula would work really well for that.
Former Gentooer continued. I haven't heard you mentioned Keybase at all. The client is open
source. The server is not ish. It uses GNU PG to implement and an encryption for several sorts of
things. Full featured chat, group chat, file sharing, git repos even, and general encryption
slash decryption of files. It can even act as a sort of social network where you follow people
and can view their public file folders as well as privately chat with them. Works right on Linux,
Mac, Windows, Android, iPhones, and of course it has a pretty capable command line interface as
well. The former startup was acquired by Zoom in 2020 after those first security shenanigans,
but everything on the client side still remains open source. Chris, I think you've used Keybase
in the past. Have you not? Or you've explored it? I remember that. Yeah, I guess I still technically
have an active Keybase account. I'm kind of sad Keybase never really took off more. It felt like
it was out of all of like the sort of social things. I think it was a little early. It was
a little complicated, but what it really gave you is a way to verify who you are, you know,
because if you go look at like a Keybase profile, you can find mine, keybase.io slash Chris LAS,
I think. And if you go there, you'll see sort of like these ways I've verified this is actually
my identity. And that's pretty useful in, you know, the current world that we live in. And so
I do that via some, you know, GPG keys. You can do that via Bitcoin addresses. You can do that via
by proving a tweet, a GitHub entry, your Reddit account. I also put a file at JupiterBroadcasting.com
that verifies that, you know, just to show that it's me. And I think that's a great concept. And
then now they have a Slack-like chat interface. It works on Linux. Yeah, they have built a lot of
kind of cool tools around Keybase. And it does seem like if you've taken the time to kind of set
up your Keybase infrastructure and, you know, verify all these things and connect all your
keys and identities, it can be well worth it because it kind of integrates all very nicely
in a way that feels a little disparate and thrown out all over the place sometimes with our other
solutions. I think the really the truth is, though, and you just can't overlook it, you can't just
shrug it off, is that Zoom bought them. And I think that just leaves everybody with a little
bit of a bad taste in their mouth. Especially considering the folks who were probably some
of the primary consumers of Keybase, right? Like it was never probably going to be a giant
mainstream thing. It was going to be for like privacy folks and tech nerds and all of whom
are a little sketched out by Zoom maybe. I think that's part of it, right? And it's not like they've
messed it up. They've pretty much just left it alone. It really doesn't seem like they've
screwed up the product, but I guess that could change at any point. And I think it's just a
non-starter issue for some people. Like, honestly, if I tried to get you on at Brent and I told you
all about Keybase and then I told you it's owned by Zoom, wouldn't that give you pause? There's a
hesitation for sure. Yeah, I would say so. I've been listening to you for about a year now and
a question just crossed my mind. Well, hey, hey, welcome to the show. We're glad to have you.
Their question, though. How do you guys all know each other or how did you all meet? That feels
like a big question. I'm kind of glad this came up because it's all starting to fade for me. So
I mean, I remember we tell me always known each other and we've always been doing this show.
I don't really remember it before. Right. This is just a side realized last week,
several weeks late, that Linux Unplugged has been running longer than Linux Action Show.
Whoa, that is cool. Isn't that mind blowing? I believe Coda Radio has been too. Perhaps not
in total years because we took some time off and we did a computer action show. We fooled around
for a little bit, tried twice a month for a bit, but yeah, definitely in episode numbers and maybe
an actual runtime. So I remember that for episode 100 of the Unplugged program, we did a barbecue
meet up. And Wes came with food and commentary, and then I think it's just been every week since
then. It's pretty much pretty much we got some like Mexican food and like talked about show
stuff at one point, I seem to recall. Oh, OK. And he invited me back like a couple of times,
like, hey, you want to come on again? And then at some point I just stopped leaving
where I started. I just started showing up, I guess. I don't know if I was invited or not.
I do like to warm people up with a little El Precios. That's one of my maneuvers.
Now that you're talking about it, I sort of recall us revisiting. It might have been for episode 400
that you did a revisit and you had a clip from the barbecue and Wes's first like on the air
clip. And I think that was pretty great. And I remember playing it back and it was like,
you'd think Wes had been doing it for 100 episodes. Like he just hit the ground running.
So I was like, well, this guy's got to get on the show. Brent, remind me, how did we meet?
I must have been through the shows Linux Fest. OK. Yeah. What else do you remember?
It's like I say, it's all fate. That's why we got it. It's good. We do this.
Yeah, it is. I think Linux Fest is probably a well, both a great place to meet people and
also a place where those memories just get sort of squashed and there's so much happening. And
yeah, this was Linux Northwest. So I think it was must have been.
Maybe 2017 would be my best guess. Wow, really? Yeah. And I had planned I was living in Northern
Ontario at the time and I had planned to see my brother who was out here in B.C. and also do a
little road trip to go to my very first Linux Fest. And that happened to be Linux Fest Northwest.
And of course, as a JB fan boy at the time, I wanted to meet all the folks and I ended up
driving from B.C. I think. Oh, yeah. Oh, that was what a crazy time. Anyways, I rented a car
and drove from B.C. across the border into the US and made my way to the Linux Fest Northwest
parking lot the night before the event started. And it was so late and I didn't have a hotel.
I had a tent, but there was nowhere to pitch it. And I was like, OK, I guess I'm going to sleep
in the back of this car that I've rented, which is not the first time I've done this.
And you're in a pinch, you know, you're very resourceful. Right. I did bring water and I ended
up sort of on campus where they hold Linux Fest Northwest. And I just so happened to find JOOPS.
And I was like, well, I think I'm in the right place. I don't know exactly where to go when the
event starts, but I know at least I'm in the right vicinity. Yeah, we were there overnight
camping as well. So we were there the night before. That's true. We're kind of hard to miss.
Right. And I and then as I was parking, I was like, well, I don't want to park too close to be
like that creep. That's, you know, just within the bounds of the creepy creepiness, but not so far
that I don't like. I don't know. So I picked a spot camp there. I think it was like two or three
nights in that car. It's crazy. So I met you at the booth the very first time. You probably met
100 people at that booth. So I don't think you remember. No. Is that true? I thought we met in
the I thought we met in the parking lot in the morning when we let Levi out to go to the bathroom
and you were out kind of like waking up and stretching. Oh, yeah. Oh, you're right. I mean,
I'm not a morning person. So you're right. I was like, I don't know, brushing my teeth or something
out of a out of a bottle or something. My first thought was, did this guy did he time it so that
way we'd be he'd be out there when we came out? Like, I was wondering, was he waiting for us?
Like, I do remember that night. It rained like crazy, too. And I had my windows open and that
caused some issues. Oh, man. Oh, yeah. Good memory. I was like, I don't know. I don't know.
Yeah, I was aware that I didn't want to, like, jump you guys at that point and be one of those
one of those people. So I was hopefully I left enough space. But, you know, Levi is a
conversation starter, and I'm pretty sure we got to talk and and, you know. Yeah. And so thankfully,
I that meant, well, you guys were great. You as as all the fans who've met, you know that
you just invited me in and gave me a tour of lady jupes. And Levi and I became friends
immediately. And I think that just started sort of friendship. And then a few days later, you
invited us, of course, to a barbecue at the studio. And I think I never left. I remember
sleeping on the floor of the studio one night. And, and I just had a great time post post Linux
fest parties at the studio. They got they got out of hand. Yeah. Yeah. Wonderfully so. And
Alan was there and a whole bunch of people. It was a great time. Right. We probably had
several projects going on. I'm sure you just got, you know, you know. Yeah. It's funny how those
those Linux fest can be life changing. That's exactly what it was. It was like me going to live
out a small dream that I had for a few years. And it was even better than I would have expected. And
I remember taking a bunch of photos and being able to share those, which was fun. And that
friendship just grew from there. And I was able to actually the way I started with Linux unplugged
just by chance was that at that time, I said to you, Hey, if I can help in any way that let me
know. You said, Okay, well, hit me up in like two weeks, because it's kind of insane right now. And
so I did. And you were like, Oh, well, actually, Wes is like going to Bali or something. And I
need a co host for Linux unplugged for a short time. You want to join me? I was like, sure.
Let's see how this goes. I've had that. Yeah, right. That was I was super nervous back then.
But you were you were kind enough to give me a try. And then I never left. I bet we talked about
digital photography. That was I was fascinated. You know, probably professional photographer
using Linux. It was, you know, I don't see those every day. Bronzewing, thank you for the boost.
That was a fun conversation and good refresher. Get all that recalled before we forget it.
But the boosts they must go on. Our next one is from solely 86 with 5000 cents.
A longtime listener in Australia here. I'm using fountain thanks to JB. So I'm boosting back the
free sets I received from them. Well, thank you, silly. Wow, that's a decent return there on the
stream of sats 5000 for listening to podcasts. That's a feature in fountain FM is they kind of
have like this incentive system. And so we've been getting more boosts from new from new timers who
are just listening to the shows, collecting the sats and then sending them back through boosts.
And I've been doing the same thing. It's been fun. Slowly goes on. I work in it. And of course,
we're all Microsoft. I have managed to have most of my workflow in Linux. However, the most
important thing is outlook and dot msg files. I like using outlook on the web. However, the business
workflow and ticketing system relies on those msg files. Got any ideas on how I can open msg files
in Linux without needing to convert the files? Thanks for the great content. The the not needing
to convert is tricky. I would say it's worth seeing what evolution can do. I think you'd be really
surprised at how easily evolution integrates in with an outlook ecosystem. But it's a lot to
install. Personally, I would just make a copy of stuff and I would convert it. I don't know about
us, but that's what my approach would be. Yeah, probably. It sounds like maybe there's some ways
to get Thunderbird to play decently there, too, although I have not tried that. And then as a
last resort, we'll have a link to msg convert, which if you have to go to a conversion based
workflows, it looks like I think it might even be derived from Thunderbird. And it's a little
pearl script to handle msg conversions. I think of it as backup, right? Don't think of it as
conversion and duplication. Think of it as backup. Wolfman wrote in with 500 sets,
just completed my resume, getting my amateur radio license, and then it occurred to me,
does anyone else at JB have their ham license? I've never heard the topic come up on air before
something like a DMR repeater or hosting a community DMR server sounds like something
the community may get interested in. I kind of agree. We don't talk about ham much. I don't
know much about it, but I think it's super cool. And every time Noah is around, I try to get him
to talk about it so I can learn some language. Noah's even left a few devices here, so we
technically have devices. I don't know if I'm allowed to use them. I think Cheese was interested
in that stuff too. I remember him doing some like emergency preparedness stuff in his area during,
you know, remember when they got flooded and stuff like that down in Texas. So I think he's got some
experience if I remember. Definitely seems like there's a lot of sort of kindred spirits there,
right? Like this sort of self hosting it yourself, learning how this technology works,
understanding the physics and computers all involved. Like, yeah, that's some excellent
geekery right there. It's the original decentralized. We got a boost 2222 sats row of ducks
from someone named Nix Dash Bitcoin is amazing. I love that. Welcome back. Nix Dash Bitcoin. It's
been a bit since we've heard from you. This is what got me into Nix. So nice. I obviously agree.
They're right. Have you considered an AC enclosure in your garage for the server?
The enclosure keeps the machines cool and clean. However, if the AC stops running for any reason,
then the enclosure will actually turn into a furnace. Chris, I feel like you and I talked
quite a bit about this, I think almost exactly a year ago when we built Oh, no, in January,
we built the server rack. And we had many conversations about this. And those were some
of the hesitations was like, Okay, well, if we put in some infrastructure, someone has to maintain
that infrastructure as well. So how can we do it? I had some ideas about doing it passively. But I
wonder what your thoughts are now that you've been living with the heat again. Of course,
I've been all over the spectrum on this. I am beginning to discount colo. We got we got more
boosts that came in just like I want I want a second that the colo stuff. Cool. Cool your role
on that. We got some people that that had that opinion. And, you know, we've talked about maybe
building a box in the garage. But Jeff and I were talking before the show started. You know, Jeff's
been out here he's seen the studio. You think maybe we could do it with some insulation and
decent cooling? Or at least we have a shot. Yeah, I think if we insulate the garage attic,
because those are typically not insulated at all, maybe double insulate, you know, where it usually
is at the barrier of the roof and then up top with the rafters and then definitely insulate the
garage door itself. That might be enough with a little you know, a fan a little bit of airflow
doesn't get too hot up there. Yeah. And if it you know, if we kept it somewhere in the 80 degree
range, you know, maybe even a little higher, I'd be fine with that. The servers have survived that,
you know, it's all used gear. Well, I mean, we don't need it to be necessarily perfect uptime,
you know, like if there was okay, there's two heat, we heat waves a year and we shut it down
for those. That's at least a lot better than where we're at now. I foresee me being in the
attic here in a week or two. I could see that coming. I'll bring a suit. You know, we'll bring
Jeff up with us after the road trip, right? And all of us will come up and we'll insulate the
garage. Let's make a plan and I'll take the time off. Let's go. All right. Well, that way,
Brent can record up there. Yeah. All right. You're right. That'll be soundproof. Very good.
I think it could work, guys. I think it could work. All right. Then I just have a couple of
shout outs. A 50 sats from a VIP torso listening from Finland for over a year,
sent in 50 sats. That's like a penny, but it's just amazing that you can do it, right? Like,
that's what I think people have to appreciate about Lightning. We got a row of ducks from Mr.
Quackers who said he's thinking about changing his name. Whoa. Yeah, he's thinking about changing
his name. I would be sad. I like Mr. Quackers. I think we have a really great sound bite that
goes with it. Quacka Wacka, it's a treasure. Pick your new name based on sound bite ability.
That's all we have. We got 2,000 sats from Trevdev who I said loves GUICs. Geeks. I call it GUICs,
but it's Geeks. I know we're drawing the summer of immutability to a close, but maybe I need to
sneak Geeks in there. Good. Now use this scheme. Yeah. There's only so many days in the summer,
though. We also got 2,323 sats from Logic. He boosted when we were live, and we were having
some trouble last week, and he was helping troubleshoot, so I'm going to be leaving
Helipad up during live shows. We don't actually have the live tag yet, but some people are still
boosting it during the show, so I don't want to miss those. If you'd like to send us a boost,
go grab a new podcast app, newpodcastapps.com. Podverse is totally free. It's in F-Droid. It's
on iOS. It's in Android, and it's going to be all over our new website. Then you really get the
trifecta because the web, the mobile apps, GPL, it's gorgeous. You heard us talk about Fountain.
That's one that lets you actually earn sats for listening to podcasts, and Cast-O-Matic is great
on iOS as well. There's a whole bunch over at newpodcastapps.com, including Breeze. You don't
have to change your podcast app and boost CLI if you really want to be a Geek. We got a bag of
picks here, and what do you say, Wes? Should we give just a mention to Visi Data? That was one of
the many tools that you used to go sort the hat to get our JPL names. Yeah, we definitely should,
just because you know how we love dirty command line picks, and this is one that multiple audience
members, you know, anytime we talked about fun little command line tools or especially like
command line spreadsheets or like data manipulation or charts, Visi Data came up, and I hadn't had a
chance to actually play with it until I was kind of going through these CSVs that we got out of
our next cloud and thinking, you know, there's got to be a better way. I don't really want to
do this in a browser. I definitely don't need LibreOffice installed on this machine. I have a
terminal. Visi Data was perfect. You can do operations on multiple rows, multiple columns.
You can do pivot tables. You can do charts, and because it's all like powered with Python,
you can just run your own Python scripts on the data powered by Visi Data. It's pretty rad.
It was very handy. I think this is probably a tool we'll be going to for these types of things
in the future, and I love that it has pivot tables. MiniMech sent in a Google Teller pick.
This one's kind of creepy, isn't it, MiniMech? Yeah, that's a really cool one. We will love
that one. So, I was reading my favorite news site, which is Der Standard Arteis, an Austrian
news site. Give it a try if you're familiar with the German language. So, they wrote an article
about that tool, Google Teller, and that is a tool that gives you some feedback from your internal
computer speaker whenever there is some data exchange between your browser and one of the
Google servers and services, like Google Search, Google Ads, Google Fonts, YouTube, whatever.
So, imagine the situation you have Google Chrome or Chromium open, and you type something in the
address bar. In these two browsers, you have the active word prediction active. So, whenever you
type a letter in there, your computer starts beeping, and that, in the end effect, means
every single address you type in in Google Chrome and Chromium in the address bar gets sent to
Google. Everything, everything. Other example, you have an ad blocker. You don't have an ad blocker,
and you start loading your favorite news site. Your computer is screaming because of all the
Google ads, for example. Interesting fact, you have the whole site loaded, and you start scrolling
around, and all of a sudden, you have these beeps again because, I don't know, some cookie sends the
exact position you are on that site or some other info to Google. It is really a weird, interesting
experience. So, that tool is really worth playing. You will find the code on GitHub. You have to
compile it, and it's only working in Linux for now because it works in combination with other
IP tables. But, in fact, the installation instructions and usage are well described,
and I guess you will do a link in the show notes. You got it. We will have a link in the show notes.
If you want a little audible indication that motivates you to get rid of Google as fast as
possible, that's the way to do it. Imagine combining that with a game plan to migrate
off Google in one week to just really get you across the finish line. You should treat it maybe
like a radar detection tool, you know, where you hear those little beeps and you worry about your
safety. And then, Brett, we have a feedback item that came in. It's a feedback pick. We do. Josh
wrote in and suggested Espanso. I think it's probably the best way to say that. It's an
open source text expander that has builds for Windows, Linux, and Mac with Wayland and M1
beta support as well. Get out of here. Whoa. Yeah, I know. As you might have expected,
it's also written in Rust. Are you serious? That's great.
So this is really handy because text expander is one of these independent tools on the Mac. I
think it's, I don't know. But you type a sequence of characters, you know, like some sort of short
code that you've created, and then it will expand that to a whole set of predefined text that
supports variables and whatnot. Super common for just doing rapid replies to emails or some sort
of repetitive thing that you have to type a lot. You add a short code for it, and then it expands
it out into a fuller sentence or whatever it might be. Maybe you want to insert your address
or your email address and you don't want to type it out every single time or a web address or
maybe it's a block of code. And it's a really handy tool. I've tried it. I find it to be really
heavy on the Mac and expensive, so I've never really tried it for a prolonged period of time.
But the idea that you can get this working on Wayland is huge because I kind of had given up
on this concept. I thought this was going to be something I could only do on X11. So this is a
fantastic find. Plus, it looks like it's GPL3. I mean, that's kind of rad and Rust and quick and
a really slick little website and a nice little repo and seemingly some good docs. What a find.
This is a treat. Like pretty often we've heard of the apps that get sent in, but
oh my gosh. And it has packages. Of course, all these things have packages so you can extend it,
add more stuff, shell script support, form support. Oh, that's nice. So you can add,
you can replace some of the variables. Oh, this is getting installed after the show,
gentlemen. That's what I say. They've got a tab. There's an app image here. Hey, yo. Hey,
Wes, see if it's in the next package. Not this problem again. I'm sure it's in there. You are,
dang it. Well, that was great. If you want to send us in something, either a boost or a regular old
email, that's just great. You can head over to linuxunplug.com slash contact. I'm curious to
know out there if anybody out there has endless OS in production or maybe you've deployed it for
somebody. If that's you, send us a boost or send us an email and let us know how you're using it.
I'm trying to get a sense of how well it's known in our audience. I guess on that same token,
I would like to know if you'd never heard about it. Let us know that too. I'd like some,
just some kind of data points around endless OS and how it's perceived out there or how it's
getting used. And if you want to join us live on a Sunday, we do this show over at jupyter.tube
at noon Pacific, 3pm Eastern. And something that we do for our members at unpluggedcore.com
is we record this live stream, which is huge. It's like two hours and 20 minutes ish. It's
getting close to that right now as we go. It's just a lot more show. We have some stuff we're
doing. We got business we're attending to and you get to listen in on all that. See how the podcast
sausage is made. And we also make an ad-free version available as well, if you just prefer
something short, concise and fully produced by our editor, Drew. That's unpluggedcore.com if you'd
like to support the show and keep us independent. That's like the turkey bacon to the sausage of
the full show. Yeah. And you can get the full, like what would it be when you do the Jupiter
party? Would that be like the meat pack or what is that? Like it's a veggie burger stack? Like
full English breakfast. Yeah. I get the full English breakfast over at jupyter.party. Support
all the shows, get all the features. You pick which shows the blood sausage though.
That's right. You had to go there, Wes. No, Wes. No. I'm going to get that visual out of my head.
I think I like mashed potatoes. Maybe one of them is mashed potatoes. Maybe one of them is catfish.
I don't know. You let me know. I don't know. Don't miss Linux Action News. That's all I know.
That's all I know. Linuxactionnews.com. We're covering the stuff that really matters in the
world of Linux and open source every single week. We'd love you to catch it. So go grab that. And
links to everything we talked about today over at linuxunplug.com 473. You get our mumble info,
our matrix info, the contact form, all of it over there. And go check out the new site,
new.jupyterbroadcasting.com. Let us know what you think. Thanks for joining us.
See you right back here next Sunday.
So let's talk about that new website. We're down to the final hours.
Is it hours? I thought we had days.
I think you could measure it in actual hours.
That's right.
It's true. We need a countdown. We need a countdown.
Some say it is the final countdown.
Final countdown.
Yeah, I see it.
We don't have a license for that. Dang it.
Well, I could just sing it. That's fine. It's definitely the last kind of week for what we
have. I had it, so I had to use it.
Well, if you got it, use it if you got it.
Yeah, I feel like it's definitely we can say it's the last week for our what we're calling
the 1.0 milestone of the website. I think maybe the three of us should have some discussions on
whether or not the current website does everything we need on the as far as the back end goes.
But as far as front end, I feel like the new website has gotten really far. Chris,
I know there's a bunch of like features that have been implemented in the last what week or
week and a half that have been helping you quite a bit, like the PeerTube embed and stuff like that.
That's my favorite one. Let's be honest. There's so much good work going in. So I don't want to
play favorites. I love all my children. But how awesome is this? So I may have mentioned this
already, but now when you go to the new new dot Jupiter broadcasting dot com site and you click
live, that site will auto embed the current live stream from PeerTube just automatically gives you
the current live stream. We don't have to do anything. We don't have to put embed code in
there. It just drops it right in there. No updates, no manual stuff. It's awesome.
And it's great because it's a static website, too. So the way you really have to do that is you'd
have to go edit the site, rebuild the site, redeploy the site. Right. So it's so nice that
it just automatically embeds and updates. It's coming along. I think it's getting really close
to a one point. I think there's a little few you know, there's a few things like down here we can
still clean up the bottom and stuff like that. But yeah, there's a bit of bit of stuff to do.
But I feel like the essentials important part is like all the you know, all the bones, right? All
the pieces that like are hard to figure out or can it work that way? It seems like that is all
resolved. And now it's kind of just the polishing layers. And I want to say a huge kudos to everyone
who's been helping on this project. I've been super impressed with how many people have been
involved in the matrix room, but also the number of people who've been committing ideas and changes
and opinions and all of that to the project. So thank you to everyone. And I think it's important
to say that Kyle Potts put in quite an amazing PR last week, and it just got merged,
I think a day or two ago. They wrote some intent testing via playwright for the site. And I am
still on the very edge of beginning to understand what that means. But I think it is it helps us
test the the commits that are coming in in a way that emulates browsers, that's going to be super
helpful for us not breaking the site in production, which we've done a few times in the last few
weeks. So that sounds like an amazing tool. I'm looking forward to learning it. I don't know if
either of you played with that, Wes, maybe you have, but we're certainly going to talk more
about it in office hours this coming Tuesday. Great office hours dot hair.