All of my thanks this saved the show today. Otherwise, we'd be still waiting to get started
We'd be later than we already are. No way. This is my best open source feature of the day g-edit
I didn't even realize this has this brilliant brilliant feature that allows you to
Cancel a huge huge file opening so I was on really I accidentally we're gonna play some clips from Brian control
We're gonna bust some myths and I accidentally spelled the dot MKV file dot MK
That's not the same thing. No. No, everybody knows that's the Mortal Kombat file. That's not what you want
So I double-clicked it and g-edit starts to open up because of course g-edit is my default editor for Mortal Kombat files
right up naturally and it
My whole system just kind of goes
What happens everything slows down g-edit sort of
What's happening and then a
A little blue window of hope slides down and it shows a loading bar
with a cancel button and
So yeah, I was able to click this and somehow not only did they manage to put in a cancel button?
But like they're properly threading the application. So it actually registered exactly. That's where that's where it's like. Yes, finally
Yeah, so it cancelled and boom my system came back immediately instead of opening up a multi megabyte
These are the things we want to be able to tell the Windows users and be like, this is why you need Linux
Yeah, it's almost like thank you G and thank you for being awesome in subtle ways that today was my favorite open source feature
This is Linux unplugged episode 167 for October 18th, 2016
And 16
Well, welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's busting myths and fun this week
My name is Chris. My name is Wes L. Wes this show
I was I'll be honest with you if I was new to podcasting
I'd have butterflies in my tummy about how big the show is this week. You know what to do with yourself now though
I have my good friend alcohol those no kidding. Actually, it's just a really great show
And I can't wait for us to get into it. We have
Legitimately multiple breaking news stories at the top of the show that we'll get into so some great project updates
We've got a really great picture from the KDE project about their long-term vision for the plasma desktop
then
We're gonna actually get into some fascinating kernel discussion. Yeah, I know I know what that is a thing and it's gonna be
Really interesting because we'll segue into some recent criticism that Linux has been coming under
That sounds really reasonable and would probably make you think if you heard this story you probably think oh shit
What is Linux doing right? This is embarrassing
So we're gonna bust these myths in this week's episode then at the end of the show, we're gonna get real with you guys
Let's talk about the role of free software in a world. It just doesn't care people just don't care
Microsoft Apple they're doing good enough. These are the names people know let them control the computing platform
Why bother with it? It seems to be going fine. They know what they're doing corporate masters. Why should I care?
So we're gonna we're gonna talk about the role of free software in a world that at least for the most part seems to have
That opinion so before we get started. There's one order of business that we must attend to and that's welcoming in our virtual log
time appropriate greetings mumble room
It's like it's almost like music except for not at all like music because it's
No better than music. So let's start with are you guys ready for me to just should I just get right into all of like
The the quote-unquote breaking news, you know, I have to do it. I can't I can't stop myself
Oh, man, it feels good every time I have an excuse to play that I got to admit it
So let's start with the lighter of the breaking news and and we'll do a little follow-up and look into this some of the stuff
And I'm really jazzed about but we've got the first story is just sort of the lighter one
We have the name for Ubuntu 1704. It's gonna be dubbed
You know what it is with?
Zesty's a puss. Oh you do. Look at you. Yep, and it's gonna launch on April
2017 that's coming from looked at the zepus. It's it's actually pretty darn cute. Oh, is it?
I have the pictures I saw online made it look like a disgusting rat
Well, yeah, but it's more like a cute little mouse like creature. No, that's a squirrel. Mm-hmm. Oh, you're right
Yeah, well, I'm sure they'll go for the cuter one that's for sure so that is that's sort of the
Lighter of the breaking news. What do you think of that name?
It's probably pretty hard. You know what? I mean, there's a lot of choices. There's fun things like zebras
You have to that's the obvious choice, right? I mean everyone thinks you're gonna go for zebra
So they don't want to seem obvious. They've had a lot of kind of good interesting selections before
I think I actually think canonical has broke
Release naming to a point where I just don't care
Like when you you know
They got these crazy names and fedora tried to go their own crazy one with the meaty hot dog or whatever it was for a while
but this
This this shenanigans that's been going on now since the 1204 series or whatever
I mean for a little while like they made them sound like they were sturdy and sound but now they're just like it's just
An animal now, they're just cray-cray and I think marks just delighting and making us all say these words
I honestly believe that's what's happening. It's on now. I'm like, yeah, this is broken for me. Yes
I can't think we they have the nice little numbers that everyone uses anyway
So I always have to like double check me like which one cuz you know, it's like on the mirrors
It's always by the name. I'm like, yeah. Oh, yeah, absolutely, especially after it's been a couple of years
I just can't mama room. What do you think of the name? Anybody have thoughts on naming in general? Do you care at all?
Fair enough. Yeah, I don't I'm just gonna need something to put on the the numbers
What matters is the number for the version that really matters?
Okay, I wanted to give a give the room a moment
To do any addressing or criticisms of ours while we're on the Ubuntu topic of our review in
Episode 439 of the Linux action show that came out on Sunday. We reviewed Ubuntu 1610
Did you get a chance to see it? Yes, I did
Do you have any criticisms or follow-up or any thoughts about our review? You know, I'm interested honestly, I I
Think you guys are the ones reading the release notes and like kind of the the hype after the immediacy of the release
It really seems like they're coming coming hard on the cloud
Data center scale. Those are the things that I saw that stood out to me that I was excited for right?
I like Lexi. I like that kind of stuff
So I'm interested and I feel like the desktop I didn't hear as much about and I haven't tried it myself yet
So I'm kind of waiting to see
Both both both of your opinions are interesting, but I don't know where I fall yet
Yeah, I think I think a lot of people in the audience are waiting anybody in the mum room by chance have 1610
I'm gonna bet no, but anybody have it installed
Yep, okay one guy
Excellent. All right. How are you? How's your experience been so far? Okay, two people. All right. Okay
First guy, how is your experience been so far?
It's been fine
Some things are broken, but nothing major
okay, well you say some things like
I had some problems with
The video monitors, but it's an Nvidia issue and I had it with 1604 and I had it before that with 1510
So this is like Linux release problems. Yeah
Who's number two?
Thank you. I have mr. Mav. How's your experience been so far?
For the most part pretty smooth. I actually have it on my c720 and also have it on my desktop right now
well, I've actually switched back to event to from
art for a little bit for stability sake and just to
Just streamline my workflow chillin out for a better working. Well, I will say 4.8 and in a bunch user land
That's pretty sweet. Yeah. Yeah
4.8. Oh though, which will get more on in a minute. Let's let's go to our next breaking news story. I
Can't help myself. I'm sorry. I'm
Watched a lot of CNN. I've watched a lot of news recently for actually a few years
This story is probably the most news relevant. Although not the only breaking news story
But probably when we all care a lot about are you familiar with VeraCrypt that's the they forked TrueCrypt, right?
Right when the project current maintainer the old maintainer said I'm probably shouldn't use it anymore
Yeah
I'm out
VeraCrypt is a fork of TrueCrypt and one of the best things about VeraCrypt is it's able to mount your old TrueCrypt
Oh, right because they right. Yeah, that's kind of a big deal. So VeraCrypt has been undergoing an audit and today
As we record just a few hours ago
The public release of the results has landed and here's the quick and dirty about VeraCrypt
VeraCrypt 1.18 and its bootloaders were evaluated this release included a number of new features including non-western developed encryption options and a bootloader
That supports UEFI. Oh, thank goodness
I
Quick labs the people that did the audit found eight
critical vulnerabilities three medium vulnerabilities and 15 low or
informational
vulnerability concerns now within the security audit industry that that's like best practice stuff and
consider this or could lead to
So the public disclosure of these vulnerabilities consides with the release of their crypt
1.19 which fixes the vast majority of the high priority concerns
So if you are using VeraCrypt and you get on version 1.19, you're pretty much protected from all of this stuff
Hey, that's nice. Yeah, really nice. And I think I
Don't think we should let the that that detail pass by the responsiveness of the project to the audit, right?
That's either half of I benefit of absolutely
It shows a strong project with an intent to keep their end users protected and it's polling on the core strengths of open source
Those are three things behind a security product like this that matter a lot to me
So version 1.19 which fixes the vast majority of these high priority concerns is out
Some of these issues have not been fixed due to high complexity for the proposed fixes
but workarounds have been presented in documentation for VeraCrypt to review and
Here's another takeaway I have for you if you use the ghost cipher for encryption
Its implementation was fundamentally unsafe
And they're ripping it out
So they're gonna leave in the ability to decrypt it for now, but new volumes cannot be created with this cipher
So upgrade to VeraCrypt 1.19 and move your data to a new volume if you use the go cipher
you know be interested to see kind of the further reviews of this some like
Once one one point one nine is that what people see as they say it because you know
It's some of these I'm not a cryptographer. Some of this is like a you know to kind of interpret
It's a little disappointing to see that the ghost stuff as well as it's ghost not ghost. I'm not sure. Oh, no, you're right
There's no H. I'm just being a spaz
Thanks
it is nice to see a lot of the issues are you know a lot of things that are
Fixing here's like the a lot of issues pointed out are in the bootloader those ones
I'm less concerned with so we'll see how how they continue to be responsive see how yeah
How much of the critical issues they fix?
We'll see that was my takeaway too is the bootloader was the source of a lot of the issues and that's not
Functionality I used from TrueCrypt and not functionality
I would use from Vericrypt and I don't know I don't know the long-term sustainability of this project
But it is nice to see active development. I do think
Cross-platform encryption is a worthy goal
Personally like Lux or other Linux based encryption tools meet my needs
So I'm I haven't used TrueCrypt or Vericrypt for many years
But it's a project or at least the idea of which I would support I did the same thing
I moved to Lux after the TrueCrypt tobacco. I just said right done with that going with the built-in solution and
honestly Lux on an external USB volume has worked remarkably well for me and
Lux has
Essentially become the default when you check encrypt my home folder on installers. You're almost always using Lux
So it's just kind of been the one I've I've landed on
Before we go on because this is some some pretty cool stuff
And if anybody has any thoughts on it, I don't I don't
Want to miss your input so since we have several new people in the mumble room aka the virtual lug today
I just want to let you guys know that if you want to get my attention
Just tag me in the chat room with mum
Mus so do like Chris ass Chris last mum colon and then what it is that you'd like to get in on the show and
I will try to I will call on you as we go along just that way
Keeps things organized yeah, yeah, so that's because I know we got actually good
We got good. We got a good mix of long-term errs and and newbies in there
So that's so could you know what good on the veracrit project for not only working with this audit, but again
Shipping one dot one nine, and this is how this works right the the auditors find issues
They work with the project on a on a like a gag order type basis to give them a certain amount of time typically to fix
up the problems
But if you watch tech snap you know that sometimes
This goes differently and the projects or the companies don't meet the deadline set by the auditors
And then the auditors go public
while the software isn't fixed and
It's it's a real catch-22 because it puts a lot of pressure on the developers to actually deliver a patch
But it also gives attackers a heads up to start going after end users that are unpatched and the fundamental issue here is
Even once you release an update. There's a massive lag time often for users to actually actually get all those updates
So that's still an issue even here. There's there are guaranteed way more people on veracrypt one dot
18 then there are now on one dot one nine
So there's a lot of users that are exposed so there's a window of time that attackers could take advantage of this
I will say looking at this at the PDF. They made as a report of this
It's pretty readable, so it might be something fun to check out even if you're not super interested in
Cryptography nice nice that'll be linked so if you go to the story in the show notes is that linked
Yeah, there it is right there at the bottom of the article
cool
Good stuff good stuff
And thanks to the veracrypt project for taking on true crypt because that felt like such a loss there for a little bit
It did so it was really cool all right Wes
I want to talk about something that's new and great from Linux Academy our first sponsor this week on the unplugged program go to
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and take advantage of their new seven-day free trial
Now I've been a member of Linux Academy for a long time so I can tell you it's worth it
But this gives you a chance to try it out yourself
Kick it see what happens poke it. There's zero raw at it zero risk bang on it
See what Linux Academy is all about take a look at their courseware take a look at their feature set you'll experience something
I think is unique because Linux Academy itself is unique
They're built by people who are really passionate about Linux people who were developers educators
system administrators Linux enthusiasts
They came together and they created the Linux Academy platform
And I'm not making this up because I spoke to the owner of Linux Academy
I've been we've known each other for years now, but even before they became a sponsor. We had an email thread about
How he was how he watched JB about doing podcasts and things like that and it there's a great synergy
But it was it was one of these situations where I he and I kind of landed on this
On a conversation thread where we got very honest, and I said God
You know I maybe I should have thought about doing this because it's really brilliant
It's a great way to advocate and promote the Linux platform while delivering in a content driven way because all of this is with
Content they have labs and self-paced courses that you can go through they have core
Schedulers that work with how much time you have available
They have learning paths that give you content planned by instructors for specific career tracks
I think it's also a great business model just to show you know
It's like they're working a lot with all these open source tools and platforms and and yet
They're also providing a very good service that you know it's it's it's affordable. You'll get a lot out of it
I think it's clever to like that seven-day free trial think about how much you can learn in seven days
You're gonna get hooked and you're gonna want you're gonna want more and now they have external profiles, too
So if you want to just sort of prove to either your employer or a potential employer all of the courseware you've taken
They've got it. They've got external profiles
they have a great community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members and
Check out their new quick starts about two hour courses with you get in there
It's like actually it's about two hours
And it can be up to like six or eight different courses that you take in that time
So it's a really great compact way to get a burst of information and knowledge right into your brain organ
Let's hang them linuxacademy.com
Slash unplug that's where you go to support this show and sign up
for a free
Seven-day trial. Thanks Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Now I go to the virtual log to ask anybody in there anybody a plasma desktop user anybody running
Plasma 5 8 or a recent version. I know tomorrow is but he's not in there today
Nope he's our big KTE guy. He really you know he's a he represents. He does. He's he's there fierce running the neon
Mm-hmm yeah, yeah cutting edge, but we do have a little bit of a picture for those of you that might be interested perhaps
people listening at home
Might be a plasma desktop user well we have a little snapshot of what's coming up
They say their general direction point towards professional use cases, which is
Hey, that's just that's music to my ears. Well. He is I love that
We want a plasma to be a solid tool a reliable workhorse that gets out of the way
Allowing the user to get the job done quickly and elegantly
we want to be faster and
Better quality than the competition. I like all those things are great goals now
Here's how it's all going to break down our plan is to move from a four to three
From four to three yearly releases in 2017 and 2018 which we think strike a nice balance between our pace of development and the stabilization
Periods around that our discussion of the release schedule resulted in a following plan. I'm gonna. I'm gonna underscore here
This is probably all subject to change right well. Here's kind of what they're thinking
Plasma 5.9. The 31st the 31st of January 2017 so this is all 2017
Plasma 510 in May plasma 511 in September
So you kind of get an idea of the cadence there plasma 512 in December plasma 513 in July 2017
Plasma 513 in April 2018 plasma 514 LTS August of 2018 so that's our next LTS in August of 2018
So this is this is this is interesting
So they're going from four to three yearly releases and so you can see it stretching out
But what I think that means is sort of a stabilization of the landing spot for plasma desktop users
I think this is a really really good
Kind of rough plan even if they can't nail it exactly and it's fascinating kind of being on the outside getting to look in
With this much transparency into like their inner working they say that they're gonna keep working on the breeze theme
They're gonna double down on this refinements and existing details
They're gonna work on icons across the whole UI and better theming for GTK
They have a feature backlog that they plan to get on including perhaps support for the global menu similar to the way unity or Mac
OS do it hey, what do you think of that? You know I don't use it myself, but
Kitty is already so customizable. I can see why you know if plasma had this feature as well
I think that'd be great also probably not a surprise to us. They're working more on Wayland
Kaywin brings them almost feature complete Wayland display server now
Which is remember how remember how you have to write your own Wayland display server Wow what a task for these desktop environments
Just to go from being a client to have to be the server which they say already works in most use cases
But hasn't seen a lot of real-world testing and lacks certain features that x11 users expect right now
Or ones they want to offer on modern hardware
so I like that too and of course they're gonna continue to work on plasma mobile, but
You know typically
We could easily say oh no another project is focusing on mobile
But um I actually feel like being three or four down on the list of things to do is just about the right spot
It's something you want to keep working on
It's something you don't want to lose too much ground on right
But it probably shouldn't be the primary focus of your project at least at this stage until something ships that makes it
That makes it make sense right yeah, so I think I again. I feel like they've got this online services. They plan
improvements and integration of online services and
Dependency handling for assets installed from the store
They have a developer recruitment outreach. They plan to double down on as well. Go help them out. I yeah, right yeah, I
Really think that this project is firing all cylinders right now. Don't it feel like it does it really does especially with that Wayland stuff
I'm excited to see that it feels like an I don't know maybe this time next year
We'll be talking about how great Katie. You know plasma is on Wayland. Well five eight is a solid release
I mean right I still have it no. I don't have it on any systems anymore. That's right
I had to I did I did a full full court install for a boon to 1610 and
That was that was a serious process um before we move on tech mav
I wanted to circle back you had more to say about the 1610
deployment go ahead
Tech Mav
If you tagged me you should hello. No
Hmm our loss you know if I could do voices. I would just pretend to be one of the entire mumble room like
That is worth thinking. I won't say a thing yeah, there we go. Hello, Tech Mav. Control not shift
So yeah, you wanted if you wanted to loop back to the 1610 stuff well because we're about to talk a little more about
So this is sort of be a good spot to follow up. Oh
Oh, no, I was just you were having about I've got eight for Katie and I switched
I was on a five dot eight K plasma before I went to the 1610 of Ubuntu
Okay, oh, and what were your thoughts I?
Mean the plasma that was actually the best experience of plasma. I've had a long time. It's very smooth
And I like how they are really focusing on integrating breathe across the board yeah
That's they've done really good at that and also it was pretty cool to see the Android connect stuff built-in
Do you have you did you get to play with that at all? Yeah, very good. I did some yes
Yeah, that's and works great with my Motorola. Yeah, that is that is super nice
And it really feels like the future when you're getting there all right
Thank you, Tech Mav for the fall of now while we're talking about Ubuntu stuff. This is CNN breaking news. I can't I'm sorry
I'm sorry. It's okay. It's just I'm not saying anything
How many how many days how many times do we have like three or four really big stories break in the Linux world right?
And thank God. They're just not about politics
So this is when you hear about this at first you're gonna say oh well great red hats already doing this
Suits Enterprise already doing this what's the big news Ubuntu once again?
Doing their own thing remember actually all of that is wrong
But you're probably familiar with the concept of hot fixing or hot patching or live patching a running Linux kernel
Red Hat has their thing to do it Sousa has their thing to do it the kpatch and ksplice for respect
Respectively right there's that Oracle proprietary one yes, it's a big issue in the enterprise
Especially that up when you're running VMs or when you got a bunch of containers you got a host machine that maybe has 30
Containers on or even five containers you to update that running kernel and get it secure
You've got to restart all of those subsystems as well, and it's just it often just goes undone right
And then you're left vulnerable and so Red Hat
worked
Really hard on their solution for this they've really they've put they put a lot of time a lot of engineers
They're very very proud of it and very shortly after that Sousa also well. Hey we've been working on this
We're very proud of this and just just behind the scenes
all of these companies now have have reached out from their PR people to tell me all about it to tell me all of the
Different things to make sure that I know everything about it, so they're all very
Each each of these companies have been very yes
Very wanted to make sure they get the message out there, but I actually think canonical has the best
Implementation they might be the last of the party, but sometimes that's a good thing right and
This is something that you listening at home with your one computer or many computers can use so you don't need an enterprise plan
You don't have to be a reddit enterprise user or a Sousa enterprise user if you have a buntu on your laptop or your desktop
It just has to be 1604 on x86, and you can do this
So this is the ability to patch critical security vulnerabilities live in your kernel without rebooting and
This is what they're rolling out today. It's called the canonical live patch service
Ubuntu 1604 LTS is a 4.4 kernel includes an important new security capability in
Ubuntu the ability to modify the running Linux kernel code think that's like the code in RAM
It's amazing without rebooting through a mechanism called kernel live patch
Today canonical has publicly launched the canonical live patch service and authenticated
encrypted
Signed stream of Linux live patches that apply to 64-bit Intel AMD architectures of the Ubuntu 1604
LTS release
Have to be running the kernel 4 4 generic
I think or something can't be running your own patch version
Addressing the highest and most critical security vulnerabilities without requiring a reboot one for it to take effect now again
Sousa and red hats are you okay? This is nothing new canonical is not the first to think of this
Why should I care they're doing a couple of things really interesting first of all crazy easy to set up
You do have to create an account on their thing, but it's really it's a it's it's a really interesting way
It is a it is a clever take on setting up something as complicated as kernel live patching
I'll just put it that way so I want to cover a couple of interesting things about it and a couple
Limitations the live patch service is available for generic and low latency flavors of the 64-bit kernel
Yeah, so you got to have x86 64 AMD 64 builds of Ubuntu 1604 LTS is kernel
Which is 4.4?
canonical live patches work on 1604 LTS servers and desktops on physical machines virtual machines and in the cloud the safety security and stability
Firmly depends on unmodified Ubuntu kernels and network access because you got to connect to the service
The ups this is why this is this is where they start to hint why I think they have the superior solution here
This is the first hint of it the upstream Linux live patch
Functionality upstream live patch functionality is currently limited to 64-bit x86 architecture at this time
However, IBM is working on support for power 8 and system 390 mainframe
Well, I guess they want that up to him and there's also active uptime development
Upstream, I'm sorry development on arm 64. Hey, that's cool. Yeah, that could be big
um, so that's where this is really different is this is an upstream thing that's already in kernel starting with kernel 4 4
every live patch by canonical is rigorously they say tested in
rigorously tested in canonicals in-house continuous integration continuous delivery system
They do a quality assurance which tests hundreds of combinations of live patch kernels hardware and physical machines and virtual machines
Well again, you are pushing out updates directly to people's kernels. So this has got to be that pretty seriously
This is a whole nother level. They aren't willing to reboot. So they are taking this pretty serious, right?
I mean if they're gonna trust your patches and and how how they do a little additional testing is interesting and I'm gonna get to that
But let me just tell you about this the canonical live patch service is intended to address the high and critical severity Linux kernel
Security vulnerabilities as identified by the Ubuntu security notices and the CVE databases
We if you watch text now, we talk about this stuff all the time
And so there's a certain level of CVE vulnerabilities and when they reach that they'll do live patches
There are some limitations to the kernels live patching technology
Some Linux kernel code paths cannot be safely patched while running
They say they'll do their best to supply canonical live patches for high and critical vulnerabilities in a timely fashion
Whenever possible there may be occasions when traditional kernel upgrades and reboots might still be necessary and they will communicate that through notifications
so
One question. Yes, do they have a catchy song advertising this service?
Because I don't I mean, I don't know if I can I don't know if I can deal if they don't they it's funny because
When they get to the comparison, that's one of the okay, I'll get there you're I'll get there
But this is the this is the details. I think that applies most to people listening that aren't in the enterprise
So if you're a home user or a small business, this is the stuff here. You're gonna care about
you do need a subscription possibly and
You definitely need an account the canonical live patch service provides a secure encrypted authenticated connection, which um
Seems pretty necessary when you're live patching your kernel. Yeah, I'll just take any old bit stream. That's fine
Throw it in the rain. Connect over HTTP. We're good
To ensure that only properly signed live patch kernel modules and most importantly the right modules are delivered directly to your system with extreme quality and high testing
They do have a subscription service if you have a lot of systems, but
Canonical is providing the live patch service
To community users of Ubuntu at no charge
For up to three machines desktop servers virtual machines in cloud instances. Well, damn I got way more droplets in that
Yes, but if you got up to three machines you can play with this live patch your house or that's your three critical servers
No, maybe my three my three droplets. I never want to reboot but I want to keep them secure that actually
Might work. The other thing is maybe you do it all, you know, you're using their fancy little XT thing
You get three big container droplets and I run containers on those. Oh, man. Yeah
And here's the other thing that I think is fascinating about the free mechanism
Because this is also how canonical is sussing out if these patches are gonna blow your system up and this is I mean
You interpret as you want, but they say a randomly chosen subset of the free users of canonicals live patch
Will receive their canonical live patches slightly earlier than the rest of the free users or the subscription users
as a lightweight
Canary testing mechanism
Benefiting benefiting all canonical live patch users
So the free users some of them will randomly get selected to occasionally receive the updates before the other users
That's gonna be you every time, you know what, you know what Chris that's you every time
Ah, you know to be fair. This is pretty common. This is how Microsoft rollouts
major
Winders updates once uh, once they get enough data back to the canary live patches apply safely all canonical live patch users
Receive their updates
So that's do your part. Yeah, I guess a preloader. Yeah
Okay, and then of course the big question what about the source what about the source the source code of live patch modules
Is found here and we have it linked in the show notes that got that all published. The source of the canonical live patch client
is part of canonicals landscape system management product and is
commercial software
I see now does the inner I don't think anyone in the enterprise gives one shit about that
They have enterprise agreements to protect them referred to our topic later in the show about that
Now the question is
How does this compare to the stuff that oracle's doing to the stuff red hats doing to the stuff seuss is doing?
The concepts are largely the same
But the technical implementations and commercial terms are very different oracle's ksplice uses its own technology. It's not upstream, right?
Reddit enterprise linux and seuss currently use their own homegrown kpatch and kgraph implementations retrospectively
Canonicals live patching uses the upstream linux kernel live patching technology. That's awesome
ksplice is free, but unsupported for ubuntu desktops and only available for oracle linux and red hat enterprise linux servers with
An oracle linux premiere support license, which is 2300 a year a node
Of course it is
2300 a node. It's a little unclear how to subscribe to the red hat enterprise kernel live patching
But it appears that you need to first be a red hat enterprise linux customer and then enroll in their special interest group through your
Technical account manager, which you have to have one and which requires red enterprise linux server premium subscription
Which is thirteen hundred dollars a node a year
Wow, and then the seuss live patching is available as an add-on
But to seuss linux enterprise server 12
We have to get a priority priority support subscription at
1500 dollars a node a year
But you do get that free music video. Hey, yeah, so that's got to be worth something
I mean, you're you're obviously relevant if you've got a music video. That's I mean look everybody they're relevant
Uh, then canonical they still owe a lot of money to those the people that made that video
That's where the subscription price comes from. So when you yeah, I gotta pay that out
So, uh when you do decide if you decide to subscribe to the canonical live patch
If you got more than three systems, you're paying 150 a node per year. Well, okay. Well, that's that's more reasonable
Yeah, and presumably you have to care about these nodes enough that you can get a free subscription
Yeah, and presumably you have to care about these nodes enough that you want a live patch, right?
So if you have six systems, you could probably go make two accounts
I'm not saying but you're just saying
Yeah
So this
Seems to be
a pretty
Huge release from canonical even though a lot of people will dismiss it as
Ah, that's that's been done before but I don't think it's been done like this
I really think what they did is they waited for the upstream code to just have it
Did right they didn't want to they didn't want to invent their own system. Yeah
And which probably means that uh, you know anybody that's running 4.4 could probably invent their own
method of doing this but
I think this is a pretty competitive. I also think it's a you know, it's like it's not
At least while it's competitive see how it used but I can definitely see in the future it getting thrown over the open source fence
And then here's the other thing that I think it shows
It shows why ubuntu is so much more popular on the cloud type vps instances
Than susa or red hat enterprise linux, which you think about it
It's almost a joke to suggest that you go buy a vps and run susa or red hat enterprise. Maybe centos for sure
Yeah, totally, but susa enterprise linux or red hat enterprise linux, which are built for servers designed to run on 24 7 workloads
It's a joke to think you go get a vps with one of those on there
and you can find them but it like nobody does it no and and
Why is that if you look at those prices that we just talked about?
It's a if you if you decide to go with this on your production vps with ubuntu on there
You likely did not a pay for the version of ubuntu that's on there and b
You may not even have a support subscription and c if you decide to get this live patching
It's 150 bucks versus 1500 bucks or 1300 bucks. I mean really so, uh
Uh red hat would you'd have to get the you have to get the 2300 subscription from oracle and the and the 1300
Subscription from red hat and with susa you have to get the 1500 subscription and only works on linux enterprise server 12
geez
And my
Who knows but my gut tells me that likely the next lts will also support this so they'll do this for every lts
And now you look at a system here that's sitting in production. I start thinking to myself. Why I wouldn't mind that
I don't like rebooting these ever. Mm-hmm
And 150 bucks. That's really not that much especially if it's only a couple and hey you get three free. Yeah
Pretty neat anybody in the mumble room want to jump in before we move on
I think does that wrap up our breaking? I think it's all the breaking news breaking news. Yeah, so that's
That is it. Oh, actually, no, it's not there is one more and I won't do the soundboard because i've been obnoxious with it
Um scraper you have a you have a uh, let's see scrappy paw. I'm not even sure what scrap job
Scrap job you have a comment about reboots. Go ahead
Yeah, you guys being in a studio that you only broadcast from you know once
Uh, you know a day. I know you have live things that are running throughout 24 7, but wouldn't you shut down unused machines?
You know you would think um
the big issue is
With hdmi video capture and god, I can't wait till we move away from hdmi
There is a display port everywhere. I hope there is a there is like a
sequence you have to go through for your capture and your output to see each other and
It has to be timed just right and when you have multiple systems. So we have we have
Three doing hdmi in and like we have like four or five hdmi outs
five hdmi outs and they're just they're just a catastrophe to work with and so we generally what we do is we run the systems in
Like a a low power mode where the display is still sending a signal
But like the screens are off the hard drives are spun down or something like that
but we leave them running 24 7 just because
um
The the schedule of doing daily productions and sometimes two shows a day is tight enough
There's not quite enough room for troubleshooting that because sometimes troubleshooting that can take like 45 minutes to an hour
And there are a lot of times where you're showing up here and then 10 minutes and you need to be on the air
Every now and then that yeah that that does that does tend to happen from time to time most time
I'm here before a show, but there have definitely been times where uh
there was one time for tech talk today where uh
Thank god for rikai because he's a miracle worker
I I don't know. I don't know how he knew I wasn't just not coming in
But somehow his beard spider sense was tingling and he knew that I was on the road
But was not going to make it on time and I I legitimately don't know how he knew
But he knew because it could have been I I guess because I don't ever just not show up
I guess that's how he knew I guess he knew because I know I always make it
And so he's like but he must have looked at the clock and said there's no way he's gonna get
So he came down in the studio and got stuff going and I literally walked in the door and sat down and started the show
And that was like the tightest it had ever been and it is wow
And if there's any outage right there, I spend the first half hour of the show
Troubleshooting that and then i'm all you're grumpy. I am wrecked. I'm wrecked by the end of that. I'm wrecked
So yeah, and you don't want to start a show all wrecked. No
Okay, so we do have one more break. Yeah, okay. This is cnn breaking news
This is something I think i'll be using in the near near future me too
This is really cool. It's a new tool that lets you easily install ubuntu touch os on your mobile device
It's a tool developed by marius
Quebec marius marius. What do you think on that last name?
Quebec yeah, I don't know. Yeah, okay, and it's called the magic dash device dash tool
Magic device tool the first stable version magic device dash tool 1.0 is now available to everyone and promises
an
Very simple and easy to use batch tool for installing canonicals ubuntu touch as well as android
Cyanogen mod or phoenix os so it's not just an ubuntu touch tool
You'll be able to replace your mobile operating system on your device with any of the following. Cyanogen. Okay
I just said all that. I don't know why they repeat that. Oh, oh, oh, there is one caveat
I wanted to know about though. They don't support the versions of images that have the google apps
Okay
So here's the devices though. This is what matters the bq queries e 4.5
The bq queries e5 hd bq queries m10 bq queries m10 fhd etc. So the us mx pro mu is pro 5
Now we're starting to cook with gas though. The nexus 4 the nexus 5
nexus 7
2013 Wi-Fi the nexus 7 2013 LTE the nexus 7 2012 3g the nexus 10 the one plus and the fair phone
To may not work
You don't think so. Well, that's what that says. Oh does it just at the bottom there?
Oh the fair point to you
That's okay. I don't think that's probably no, it's not a nexus 5 though. That's a big deal. Also the nexus 7
I've always wanted to do it on that
But I just don't have the time and this thing and also it can do backups here of your machine. It can do
Restorations it can unlock or lock the bootloader and it also supports installing the TW RP recovery image
This is amazing. Yep, you know, I've seen some similar tools for Windows that I think it's a it's a nice new
niche for people where it's like well, maybe you flash your phone or need to do this like
Once maybe a year and so if you're not like ready to jump down in the ADB shell or any of that
Here's a handy tool that you can use to do that or honestly for me
It's it's not that I haven't used ADB
But I haven't used ADB in so long that I would I would spend enough time
Googling around and reading XDA forms that I just don't want to spend that time
This thing already knows how to do it. That's what I really want is the end result. I don't I don't really care
You're not developing for Android. You're not making it. Yeah. Yeah, I'm that guy. I'm that guy
I I admit it when it comes to this kind of stuff
I'm that guy, but I think this is a super positive development and it's a tool all the I think
My pixel gets here. I'll be using this and that's trying out a bunch of
Did I did which one?
I got the smaller one. Oh, yeah, good call. I mean it just seemed I don't have huge hands
It's all about you keep it in your pocket. Do you keep it? That's what it's about
I got a 4.7 inch phone now and I'm all about that. It's in my pocket right now
I didn't even know I had to feel I had to touch my pocket comfortable
I've literally been sitting here for how long I didn't even know that phones in my pocket. That's what I'm talking about
See the 6p. It's a brick dude. Totally. So that's interesting. Did you get the 128? I did I did
I'm I don't know if I'll need it or not
But so we plan to have the phone for when it wouldn't they say when did you say you're getting it?
Because I went for the 128. I don't get it till like mid-november
So a month or so, that's rough. Yeah, it's rough mid-november, huh?
Geez, yeah
There have you read me the reviews that came out today? Yeah, that's positive. They're positive. Yeah, I
Think I think it's the Android phone to get right now if you're gonna get an Android phone. Mm-hmm, and
And I need a new phone and yeah, you do it
It's nice enough. Not only do you have a Nexus 5 but you your phone is busted the app. It is bad
Well, I've been waiting for this scratch yourself with that. Yeah, thankfully now
But it is dangerous. It is definitely dangerous. That's probably may explode. It's made by LG, but it may explode
You also are constantly charging that thing of notice. That's true
And that's one of the things that come back on the early news is by the way user air 7 just came out where we gave
You our full take on the pixel if you are interested as well as the app
Absolute very best way to get great audio on Linux
We talked about that and a few other tidbits that I think are actually I think it was a really good episode of user
I decided to listen to it user air 7 is out where we do talk about the pixel so I cannot wait to try it out
I'm kind of on the fence myself. I think I'm gonna let things go for a while
I'm good when you're in a position, you know, if you have a good phone that you like, it's not necessarily worthwhile
Also, I am I am personally until I am proven. Otherwise, I am an avid believer in optical image stabilization
I know that they have incredible post-processing but physically having a lens that floats I think is unbeatable
And so when pictures are a big part of it
I know it's got a great camera and a great sensor and so they say and the reviews do seem to back that up
But it does lack actual optical image stabilization that to me in 2016 nearly
2017 it's gonna be your phone in 2017. That's a bit of a yeah, that's a bit of a
Bummer, I guess we'll see we can do some photo shoots here in the studio
Yeah, I mean so far the reviews have been pretty good and loved and the video they say it really is impressive
So yeah, you know what? Why don't we take a moment?
And why don't we thank our sponsor ting go over to ting dot actually, you know what?
I can't believe it. I almost just I almost well
I almost forgot to say you can put Linux in your Linux Linux not ting.com Linux not ting.com is not only good a good way
To support the show, but it'll give you $25 off a device or if you bring a device like a pixel
They'll give you $25 in service credit
I would really consider this if you're gonna get the pixel too because tings no contract nor the termination fee and
You only pay for what you use
That's really the secret sauce to ting is if you can be kind of clever if you can download your podcasts
Over Wi-Fi or what I do on Spotify at Spotify on my phone
But I download the tracks on Wi-Fi and they play them offline because I like the super crazy extreme quality
Anyways, I can I so I just use that
I just there's just like really four or five things you can do differently and you can save so much money with ting
Yes
They just take your minutes your messages and your megabytes and they add them all up and whatever it is at the end of the month
That's all you have to pay
Ting keeps rates simple. We don't make you pick a plan instead. You just use your phone as you normally would how much you use
Determines how much you pay each month. You can have as many devices as you want on one account
That's good
Because when you use more you pay less per minute message or megabyte of data
Your usage plus six dollars per active device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill
Simple that's what we mean when we say
Mobile that makes sense
They also have incredible customer service and a fantastic dashboard you get to speak to a real human being when you call customer service
You're not playing that game
And if you do end up with something like the pixel from the Play Store, you can get a ting sim card for $9
You just put it in there you activate it. There's no contract nor the termination fee. Try it out
See how it works for you. Why not? Give it a go. In fact, I don't know
I haven't looked at the pixel
But I bet you could choose CDMA or GSM because things got both networks and if the pixels out of your
Price range because cheese it is an expensive. Oh, yes. I mean I bought two. Did you really offer a lady one, too?
Yeah, yeah. Yeah boy. I mean and that's nice for charging and all that kind of stuff. That's a huge thing
All you can see in USBC household. Yeah, I can understand the future
Yeah
If you want to save some cash ting has our semi recent blog post from the 11th about five wise
smartphone choices that are under
$200 so if you still want to get a big smartphone that has some functionality that's gonna get some updates
Maybe has a nice camera. They've got a post about that, too. So that's and that's
Super nice because you can either bring your device or grab a device directly from Ting
It's all I just make it so easy
Linux dot ting comm and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program
So do you remember a couple of weeks ago?
There were some headlines where Linux they went essentially like this Linus
admits that Linux 4.8 had buggy crap and
He raged against it saying there was no effing excuse to knowingly kill a running colonel
And he talks about how he it was his bad
For taking some patches from Andrew right before the 4.8 released. You remember all of this West does this ring about?
Yeah, I believe we touched on it here on this show just a little bit
so what I want to do is I want to take a moment and I want to go a little bit deeper and talk about what
They're actually discussing here because this turns out to be a topic that is now giving a lot of Linux critics
some serious fodder and
If you heard this you would think oh jeez if you if you're not familiar with intimate details you might think she's
What the hell is Linus doing you know this is Linus
He's raging out once again, and he's acting out of emotion, and he's bad press for the Linux kernel
Yeah, and it's it's I don't know a lot about this West, but I got some clips
I want to play you've had some time to think about it
It's about this bug underscore on that led to the Linux kernel stopping and we've got a post
linked in the show notes by Samsung's open-source group that say that they
They are working this is something they're working on they say it's a top priority for Linus to to change this bug
What are we talking about West? What do we what is bug on? What are we talking about?
bug on is a
kernel function or macro that
At least in some ways is used when is when you see you know when you see a
Kernel bug where you're in a position where and this is something they talk about in this in this thread as we'll talk about
You know when the kernels in a position where it there's no meaningful error recovery it right now
There's a current trend where it gets used a lot by kernel developers in development
So it's a kind of like in other terms
It's similar to like an assert statement where you're basically saying like well at this point
Everything that I'm doing this should be true if it's not true, then it's violating one of my assumptions going forward
It doesn't make sense to continue because you know my axioms have been violated
It
Gets used a lot as an development when you haven't written error code
You don't know what error code to write yet. You're exploring basically this triggers like oh well
The my new feature clearly didn't work crash the kernel we get a stack trace you can begin debugging
Sometimes this does then go through into the the real kernel and it does have a place and then part of why I think this
Thread is interesting is it's kind of you get to see the discussion of like yeah, when should this be used?
When do we crash the kernel and so it's sort of a discussion around should it be easy to crash the kernel because really
You know and and Linus is I think in a good way concerned about I mean
It's not like stupid
bragging uptime concerns
But there's lots of places like do you remember the bad press during when Windows 10 rollout when those there was like hospitals in Africa
Or other places where their machines were rebooted. So I was you know problems were caused their situations
Not in the data center where you don't want to go down
Or you won't want to go to the admin to be able to choose to go down yeah
And so you know they're very concerned about if there's anything we can do to avoid a situation
You know by all means if you're the file system code
And you can't you know you're gonna write damaged data to the drive stop what you're doing
But it doesn't also in that case it might not mean that you absolutely have to crash the whole kernel
So this is what's fascinating about this particular issue because what you just said there seems
Absolutely reasonable to me and seems like a likely use case scenario for Linux is number one deployment, which is the server
However Linux critics have taken this and spun this as well
This is Linus sick and tired of bugs crashing his buggy kernel
And they are just paper machine over the problem
and they're just suppressing the issue and if you watch this at this week's episode of BSC now a
Popular guest Brian Cantrell was on and they talked about this very issue
Brian is I I love every episode of BSC comes in it really is because he is
He is such a great Linux critic because he really sticks it and he's so outspoken. I love watching him
He's very opinionated. He's often right on the money. He's a
Terribly smart guy yeah, and so he tears in to this particular issue on this week's episode of BSC now
I fully recommend you watch the entire interview
We're gonna play like two minutes from a much longer interview
But this is him talking about them switching over from this bug on to something
less dramatic that doesn't stop the kernel and this is what's becoming the sort of
external community take on this particular issue and
Music
Sharp objects away from you. They are going to use like I know
Said can fix this bug. Yes said did not fix this bug
So they're gonna change every bug on to worn on it's like there I fixed it. It's like
Okay, and so now if you actually have a Linux kernel programmer that has I mean
The the poor right-thinking individual that is living in the ghetto of Linux
Just trying to do the right thing and has an actual legit bug on if this happens
Please panic the system that is now just gonna be turned into a worn on and now you've actually
Introduced bugs effectively in systems or certainly made any bugs that do exist in the subsystems much more difficult to debug
It's like how do you come on?
I mean, aren't you old enough to I mean like Torvalds and I are about the same age
Like but do you still have this many hormones running through you that you think this is a good idea?
I mean, don't you realize that I mean aren't we getting older and wiser but you know, whatever
Say worn on with butter FS what could possibly?
I do love the I got the whole like the system D will recover
Chris there comes a point where it's just like you're clearly you're just piling on here. You're just sorry
Like can I actually make him pass out?
I mean you buy you two things for a game are you gonna see if you can actually yeah
I think we have a betting game on the side
I mean, I see how long before we can make central stroke out life
My vision is kind of fading right now
So he's so frustrated with Linux that he's about to he's about to stroke out
And so you could hear a couple of a couple of assumptions that he's working from and it's not just Brian
Brian is is just a sort of representing an opinion that is forming and
I I wanted to address a couple of assumptions that I think he's working from when he makes these statements
you might have noticed that in his world Linus the man is
Irrational and makes code commits based on his emotions or as he put it his hormones not rational code commits
Which I think is probably not the correct assumption to make but if you if you believe that to be a fact
You could see how he's built a foundation of some an assumption there another assumption that kind of crops up
In his and you'll hear another example here is everyone working on Linux basically kind of just doing it their own way
they're doing it for fun and
It kind of ignores the fact that the vast majority of commits to Linux are from business enterprise
Developers who are getting paid by their company. They're serious people
And I want it before we completely respond
I want to I want to talk about this particular aspect the way this kind of gets spun and becomes
becomes the reality of the situation and
He continues to talk about sort of the pervasive bad thinking that's in Linux that led to things like butter FS
And I want to talk about that too. Did you before we go to that?
Did you want to interject on the on his on his take on the bug on thing?
Well, I think him highlighting the said point there they do mention that that is mentioned by a contributor
But they what what Linus says that's not that implementation that they would go with and then there's some debate about how it's used
but I think what's really missed is just
That the culture has not been using bug on and in this case, it's VM bug on as
A like oh, no, we you know, like we messed up the CPU stack and we need to crash
So it's not it hasn't been used in the situation
So and what Linus is really concerned about here is like minimizing that right?
And so like the issue is is that once something went out at scale and production
It got used in a different way than they intended and this one in particular crept by in like an RC 8 patch level, right?
So it's like it wasn't during the regular merge window. It didn't get all the regular testing it should have and like it's okay, right?
Yes, there are times. Yeah, he admitted it. It's probably his mistake and I think what he's just saying is that it's really it's it's a
Discussion now about like what are the semantics of crashing the kernel?
We we should probably make it so that the developer like it doesn't get confused with how you debug
It doesn't get confused with if you had heard that criticism on its surface
From an intelligent person like Brian. I I would think cod Linux is really falling apart, right?
I mean Brian has great credentials
He's a super smart guy and he's a joint and I think his argument is right in that like no you should I mean you
Should have asserts right? You should have what I think in Solaris. He says it's verified
You should have these things that say like, you know, if if the kernel memory algorithms are working correctly
This is this and if it's not we need to crash and Linux does have those and this is a conversation about where do you?
Set that level and what are the semantics of crashing? I also
I mean, I love all I love I love Alan and Chris and and I think Brian's great, too
but I love it when they when they
Poke fun at system D because I don't feel like it
I don't even need to respond to that cuz what I'm gonna do is is like a tiger
I'm gonna I'm gonna sit back and watch my prey and I'm gonna watch them
Take shots at system D for the next couple of years and mark my words five years from now
BSD will be fully rolling out their system D equivalent. They won't don't call it that they will be they'll make sure not to call
It that yeah, but the reality is system D
Despite what we might like to think in the Linux community
Not a new idea. No, no, it's not Sun was working on
Is it SMF SMF? Yeah. Yeah, and of course Apple had launch D. Mm-hmm
And I remember using launch D can configure services before system D was even a thing. Yeah. Hey, this is pretty sweet
I believe there are two if not three projects in the BSD community already to replicate system D like functionality
It's just none of them are necessarily mainstream
It's coming
So just as it just sit back as a tiger and watch your prey as they poke poke fun at system D now and then when
They will roll it out and all the all of the logical backflips
They'll have to do to explain why it's nothing like system D. So but let's go on about the pervasive bad thinking in Linux
This is a common. This is a common BSD culture
Projection on the Linux community that Brian manages to put in really great summed up words
And so this is a great point to sort of look at something that I think is a common misconception
No, they actually won't
And the other thing I think that is that is that is actively happening to Linux
I think this is the kind of the peril that they run is that right thinking individuals are not attracted to that culture
I don't think he means like politically right? I think he means right brain
They're talking about right-brained people earlier in this so right brain versus left brain
The the thing is he's saying is that Linux doesn't attract the right type of critical thinkers
right thinking individuals are not attracted to that culture and so
People even if you're interested in file systems, are you gonna go in your?
22 are you gonna go work on butter of us? Are you gonna go work on ZFS if you are interested in operating systems?
Are you going to go to a culture that is replacing bug-ons with worn-ons?
Are you gonna go to the BSDs or to a Lumos or what have you where you got?
Cultures that are not just more innovative but also more rigorous than they're thinking
Yeah, so cultures are subjective for the eye of the beholder
But if I'm 22 years old and I want to get a career in this field
I'm probably gonna go with the platform that has the demonstra
Just on German. What is the word demonstrably demonstrably larger deployment in the server space?
That's what I'm trying to say. I mean think about it. If you if you want an employable skill, it's obvious
The choice is obvious
So I kind of disagree with the premise to begin with but his core his core message is the way the culture is the professionalism
That's more appealing in BSD and people that think that way or a Lumos
Yeah, or a Lumos which is which is his baby interested in operating systems. Are you going to go to a culture that is
Replacing bug-ons with worn-ons or are you going to go to the BSDs or to a Lumos or what have you where you got?
Cultures that are not just more innovative but also more rigorous than they're thinking and I think that you know in an all-open-source world
There's total freedom of choice for technologists and the differentiators become almost the the cultures and these cultures become
Self-perpetuating and so they I think there's there's a danger that you end up with with butter offenses over and over and over again
Yeah, and I mean I just wonder how many of these is it gonna take before people kind of like connect the dots that okay
Let's talk about that point how many times we have gonna screw something up before we admit
That sometimes we just we think that there's bad ideas and we should just move on. I think he's kind of right
I think you still have butter fs defenders out there who are gonna argue with this very moment in this show
Yeah
Even though it's so obvious to everybody else watching from like a distance
That if you're an enterprise and you have serious data needs you're not going to deploy butter fs
That system is worked out to be for yeah, and it has enabled an entire product category for some companies out there
I will say it is interesting though. Just given Facebook's use of it. It is probably has a
Comparable number of deployments now. It's just that it's not for data. It's not for data reliability
You know, what are we going off with that Facebook thing though? I mean, I'm not if you're right if you're right
Then that probably is a massive deployment. But here's what I've heard. I've heard
Several things I've heard that that story is old and out of date trip. I've also heard that those systems run on RAM
The storage is RAM based the RAM disks and they wipe them every 24 hours. I
Could see that as well. So I I mean, oh no, and I'm not I'm not trying to argue for butter fs as a
Data storage solution, but that was always our go-to about our fast like well Facebook true
We had that we had that that was our go-to
But I don't actually know how much that holds up and I mean you don't see a huge number of patches these days or
that much improvement
But here's where I really think he starts to make a better point
he really kind of nails it when he talks about the the fundamental issue that I always had with butter fs and I couldn't put
into words as well as Brian does here is
It butter fs should have been production-ready
From the beginning it didn't have to be feature complete, but it should have been production-ready
cultures become
Self-perpetuating and so they I think there's there's a danger that you end up with with butter fesses over and over and over again
Yeah, and I I mean I just wonder how many of these is it gonna take before people kind of like connect the dots that there's
Actually something there are broader differences than simply the technology
Befuddled me was how they didn't catch this sooner
Because the test case they did for it if you know create the raid Zed and like DD zeros into one of the drives and then
run a scrub
Right free BSD handbook has every news NFS user do that on purpose to watch
To show them how a scrub works and repairs the data
Like right our newbie guide has every user
Do that exact experiment to prove that ZFS works and no one had ever done it with butter fs ever
What?
Well, and I think that this is the idea well you wouldn't do it because it's not ready for production yet
It's like yeah, it would be mean to do that because it's not it's like no
That's just setting us up for failure when also that doesn't it doesn't understand
What software is is born ready for production or not?
And if you the software that is especially software in the data path
It's not you don't make it ready for production later. It's like security
you don't retrofit it on to an extant system you either design it for production use or
you don't and
It's not something that you as methodically approach
Yes, there will be bugs in the system, but the bugs in a system that that is actually designed for production use
That is actually a salvageable system bugs in a system
That was never actually designed for production use or thought that production use something that would be done later or by the little people
It is not actually tenable and with ZFS ZFS was people don't realize this that ZFS was designed
To be used in production from day zero
So it's it just that it didn't have features in the beginning so I think that's a pretty fair point actually
And I think the the lesson learned from butter FS is a change in our perspective
Let's not wait for something to be production ready. It's just it's not
1997 anymore
we're just in a different we're in a different world now when it comes to this stuff and
Like it or not. How serious is used right? Yeah. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Yeah, and it's happening on people's laptop
It's happening on people's phones and it's happening on people's servers if you want to if you want to follow more episode
163 of the BSC now program the return of the control right episode
It was actually it was your suggestion because you'd watch and said we should talk about this
So thanks for thanks for the suggestion because I actually think it's good to talk about our weaknesses
Oh, yeah, absolutely, and it's good to be completely honest
But at the same time we do need to call it when people are maybe spreading a little bit of FUD
Especially around that bug on thing. That's just that's just fun. If you follow it closely enough, that's just straight-up fun
Yeah, you want to criticize you want to criticize us as a community about butter fs and say that maybe the culture of Linux
Allows projects like butter fs to succeed
Okay, maybe that just sounds like a really active vibrant huge worldwide community
That's just many factors larger than the BSD community
Well and ignores other subsystem communities as well as you know
I mean, it's not like we haven't had successful production file systems before and it's not that we won't have them again
But and we so we need the realistic criticism as well as an up-to-date assessment of the and it's not like you can't get see
You can't you can get ZFS right now
It's like that's not the the reality is Linux is such a natural force in the technology
industry that if you want your product to be relevant on the server, it has to work on Linux and
That even is true for ZFS
But it was a really good interview and there's a lot of good stuff they talk about and
I hope to have some of this very discussion with Brian in person at meet BSD. Oh, hey
Yeah, he's good. I think he's gonna be there the whole more about this the whole BSD now crew Alan's gonna be down there
Chris Moore is gonna be down there
Producer q5 sis is gonna be down there. I mean like it's a it's a full
BSD
Now crew plus Brian's gonna be there and
I'm gonna be there. It's November 11th or the 12th
Here's what I decided to do. This is I haven't I have not mentioned this yet on any shows
But I've gotten a few emails about it. I've got a couple of tweets about it people like hey
can we meet up while you're in the San Francisco area and
We really had this tight
Hadeah and I we plan to be there for the 11th and the 12th and then the other time was spent driving from
Washington and back and it was her idea. She said you know what? Why don't we just
Let's just take a couple extra days. I'll take a couple of days off from work
Maybe Noah can fill it on a show and let's spend a little time down there and let's let's meet up with some folks
So I will probably be also be in in the area the following Monday or Tuesday
And what I plan to do is I'll get down there. I'll get me BSD get my head around that and then I'm gonna start
Tweeting out what my plans are if you're in the San Francisco area and want to meet up email me Chris at Jupiter
Broadcasting comm or tweet me even better at Chris LAS. Let's start talking about sounds like a good idea
That sounds awesome because I kind of what I want it what I would like to do is maybe rent a car or maybe Ben
I'll let me let borrow his car an extra day if maybe and
Drive into San Francisco and just hang out and maybe people could show me some cool places and
Maybe we'll shoot a little rover log and all that kind of stuff
I think it could be a lot of fun. So I'm gonna take a couple extra days
Just you know, we have a lot of viewers
We have a lot we have thousands and thousands of viewers in the California area in the specific area
It's and so if you're in if you've ever wanted to see Chris last in person and maybe maybe show me your favorite place to eat
Maybe I'll do like a tour. I'll go Alden Brown
I'll just like I'll go around drink like
Coffees from all different places and have donuts and just get like all kinds of grub on and then record all for the rover log
That could be fun. And I think I think I'm gonna be there Monday or Tuesday
I'm gonna take one of those days and use it for a meetup and one of those days to play the tourist thing and just
Like take a day off and actually enjoy the area so that I'm hoping to have two extra days in San Francisco
And I want to use one of them to spend it with the audience and one of it to do the tourist thing
So I don't know which ones yet, but it'll be Monday and Tuesday and I'll I'll say more
I'll probably on my Twitter account at Chris. Oh, yes, but if you're gonna be at meet BSD
I'd love to see you or if you're in the Berkeley area and want to meet up
Let's do it meet BSD comm by the way, if I think I'm I I'm gonna tell you
If you're gonna go to one BSD event in 2016, I think this is the one it really seems like it now
There's some international ones that are pretty badass, too
But if you're gonna go to one in the US this year, there's probably other great ones coming up
But if you're gonna go to one, I think that might be BSD returns home
That's what they pretty Berkeley. Yeah. Yeah, the Berkeley systems distribution, right? All right
So let's talk about our next sponsor DigitalOcean go over to digitalocean.com and use our very special promo code of absolute power and knowledge
DO Unplugged it's one word. It's lowercase
You go create an account you go in their dashboard you apply it as your payment method
Now you're not putting a credit card in there. You're not putting your pay pals in there or whatever's they've got your back
You're going in there. You're putting in DO Unplugged. You're getting a $10 credit
Actually, if you already have an account too, and you you know, you you've not used our promo code
You can also get a credit. What a deal. I know digitalocean.com is a great way to get a $10 credit
What a deal. I know digitalocean is super cool to let you right think they've already got you
They didn't have to let you do that. Not at all. That's really cool
And so that's kind of gives you an insight to what a badass company they are
They're a really great simple cloud hosting provider
Dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to spin up your own super fast system on their infrastructure
They're all linux
They use KVM for the virtualization
SSD for the back end storage. So everything's super fast
You know it and you get to pick from all of the distros that you would run on a server
Plus free bsd if you're a bsd folk
And and and there's some cool things you can do when you start playing with their block storage and zfs
There is some cool things you can do
But really you can get started for five bucks five bucks a month
If you use our promo code do unplug you get $10 two months for free
Whoa, you can get started in less than a minute
You'll get a really nice system
And they have an interface that even if you've never set up a server before you'll be able actually it's so easy
If you've never installed linux even you could do it. You really you really could but what what I think is probably more
Noteworthy and remarkable about that is first of all, they've managed to do this in a web application second of all
They manage to do in a browser
Compatible compatible way that works like on your on your phone. It works on your linux box
You don't have to have java installed. You don't have flash installed. Yeah, you get a full html5
Console access to your rig. That's all nice. Yep
but beginners or
Advanced users that have been setting up systems for decades are going to be happy with this and then on top of that if you
Even know how to poke at ruby or php or python you can use their api
Like you can if you just know how to poke and they have tons of great open source applications
You can just take advantage of already
It's amazing. It's a great service and they're super fast and they got data centers in new york, san francisco
Singapore Amsterdam, london, toronto, germany and india so you can be like a boss all over the world
Just use our promo code do unplugged
I mean it is so awesome to see how linux and kvm can bring
The fundamental technologies to a company where they can focus on the things like the api the interface the documentation the community
Finally somebody took advantage of all of it and that's digital ocean digital ocean comm just use our promo code
Do unplugged and a big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring
the unplugged program
So we were kind of kvotsing about this a little bit ago in the show and we were talking about how most people in the enterprise
Don't give a single crap that the canonical livepatch client is
Commercial software or that the back end is managed by launchpad, which is commercial software, right? They could the
businesses that are more than ten people
Okay, I've never met a single one of them that would care unless their business is linux and open like system 76
They care right I don't but like there's like even less a lot of the enterprises
That's not what they're concerned if your business isn't open source and Linux you don't you don't give any shits
You really don't and let's be honest with this and and mumble room you feel field just disagree with me
But I thought this post over at naughty computer dot UK, which is a great domain name was pretty good
It says the role of free software in a world that doesn't care the free software movement is about personal and social
liberties giving the owner and the user of a computer control over it
But most people don't see the problem with a small number of multinational mega corporations having control over everyone's computers
They think Apple and Microsoft know what they're doing and they do a good job
So why would I need free software I?
Can see a lot of people's thoughts like that or or even worse?
They've never even thought of heard of or conceptualize a world of free software
They only see a world of apps and commercial software
And I would suspect without I mean I would I would find it very hard to dispute the idea that that is must that must
Be the very vast majority of consumers mm-hmm. I won't meet him and that's a that's a default right you need your next program
You you buy it off the shelf you get it for however long and support it
And then you buy the new one my lady friend is a good example before she met me
I think she had heard Linux mentioned as the thing that
Runs her server and she knew a couple of computer people that sometimes talked about Linux
but she didn't know that it was free or that it was open and
she didn't really ever even consider that there was such a thing because everything else in our life that we interact with is
Product eyes commercialized specialty thing you got to get by that model. It's branded. It's it's
Marketed yep
So you don't even your mo your mind doesn't even shift to that mode to understand that there could be something like free software
This country is created not by a company
But by a system of volunteers who are each scratching their own itch that idea isn't something that you just consider
You have to be introduced to it and like my lady friend when I introduced her to it
She well this is obviously the better way to go
This is unquestionably even as a I mean
I'm a small business person with like a couple of people working here, and this seems like an obviously good choice for my business
But until you understand and see it you don't you don't even conceptualize it
So, what is the role of free software in a world where that is perhaps arguably the reality?
Mom or do you have any thoughts?
Yeah, I think
The problem is that they don't understand the whole computer thing
It's not the thing that they don't care. They don't understand
So it's some kind of such protection to pretend that Microsoft and Apple care for them
Hmm, because you trust in a brand you trust in the name
Yeah, because really if they screwed it up so bad. They'd be out of business
Yeah, but if you don't know
You know how to drive a car, but you don't know what the car is doing
You don't know the whole moat. I don't know how to build the car. No, I couldn't replace my car's computer. No
so
So it's the same thing for a computer user a normal computer user does not know what the computer is doing
He can only
consume
Software and use software but doesn't know how it works. So it's yeah Mosenrath your thoughts
Okay, so if you can see in the the the chat room there we've been discussing it as well
but a lot of it is off of it's not a matter of really an
active not knowing or an active not caring what they see is as
The previous person said they just see a product they use it and as I was saying to others does it work?
Yes, then they use that product. They don't know if it's free
they don't know if it's
Not free in terms of free as in speech not free as in beer as that is one of the main things that comes up
Quite often but in terms of the see cult was just it's like the cell free software commercial software could be for your
Proprietary, right? It's a matter of does it work? It does. Okay. I'm good. I'm out
They're not worried about any of the other stuff because they know full well
Microsoft doesn't care about them Apple doesn't care about them. You know what those companies care about
Well companies always care about your pocketbook your wallet the moment that you open it up
They are happy to talk to you you close it up the conversation ends you go to something like say Cody or VLC
They say we don't need your pocketbook. The person says hey, I don't need to open up my wallet. Awesome
I'll use this. Yeah, it works. Excellent. I'm out. Yeah, so
This is where I find the absolute
brilliant silver lining in this concept
because so often as users who perhaps are
just solely consumers of open-source software
Maybe you you download the latest distribution you install all the great open-source software
Maybe you caveats online in the comment section about something not working
But you don't very often or if ever submit a bug perhaps you don't submit a patch upstream
You don't necessarily get involved in the mailing list
You primarily consume
But you do something else too
you
likely advocate
You spread the word about Linux you show maybe a friend who gets intellectually curious and it turns out
that's
fundamental to the survival of free software and so as regular Linux users we have an
Absolute vital role in the entire ecosystem of free software and its continuation and survival and I don't I don't think it's
Overselling it to say that this is one of the most important roles in free software is advocacy and education
Now how you do it the people you do it to
That could all be argued. That's the nuance
But there is such an important place for advocacy still even in 2016
Even when Linux has taken over the cloud and networking and mobile
This is still a fundamental issue and
There are people who are not even in tech who are not even necessarily tech heads or technologists
Who can see the benefits it just has to be a certain person who's intellectually curious about these things or has a motivation to learn
more and
If you you know look at Noah look how many people he switches to Linux and daily
Conversations just by like kind of just by sussing out their needs and yeah, well, here's how Linux could fix that for you
And here's how it's all that for you instant right like you don't have to wait to talk to a sales rep you don't
Have to it's just it's there. It's your right to have it. It's yeah, you've always had it
You just didn't know I and it may also I suppose this is very self-serving
I guess but it makes me very proud to to run a network that has many programs that talk about Linux and
open-source and BSD and and help people learn and discover more about it and make it useful in their daily lives because I
really truly believe that advocacy is a
Crucial part to the free software ecosystem, and if you've ever felt bad about maybe being a leech like that
If you've played that role, or you can play that role you are taking part now
You can do more at any time, and I encourage you to do so but there that is there's something to that Wes
I think that's pretty cool
and
That right there brings us to the end of this week's episode of the unplugged program if you'd like to join us live
Join us over JB live TV. Oh when?
What a great come on
Tuesdays well yeah of course about
Tuesdays what time you know that's 2 p.m.. Yes team. Yeah, you could also get it converted automatically
It's you have a magic robot. It just does it for us calendar page Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar
You can send us in your thoughts you put a broadcasting comm slash contact submit
Stories and community updates at Linux action show dot reddit comm and if you're on the youtubes
And you made it this far give it a thumbs up come on come on all right. We'll see you back here next Tuesday
So
I
So we're gonna start giving these away or selling them. I'm not sure look amazing. Yeah, I think it's a super great idea I
Think you could probably sell a whole sheet of them. I don't think see and I think she's just thinking about giving a few
Away at a time, but I think you could probably just so yeah
Yeah, I would because then why then I just happen for my future keyboards. I don't want that window shame all right
So I'm trying to cover up my super key like I got mine on I got it
It's a little tiny bit lopsided, but that's oh look at my pop
That's all mine mine's my my super key actually had a circular indent to begin with so I'm pretty happy
It's not great, but you see that looks like it fits in right in there doesn't wow yeah, that's nice
so
Yeah, that's our that's our super key, but yeah, yeah, yeah, so how's it look on yours?
Actually, not too bad. I'd say it looks as good. I'd say it actually looks better than the Ubuntu sticker
That's on the Librem 15. Yeah, so hmm. I wonder how it look if your keyboard lit up. Oh your keyboard does light up
Not too bad. It looks fine good. I was wondering if it would shine through, but yeah, it looks good I
I
Like it. Yeah, it does have a little bit of a shine. I'd say ah
Very good very good, so you approve it. Oh, man. This is great everyone should get them
It's funny because you know when you think stickers you think big stuff
But that little tiny super key sticker is legit, and I hate seeing that little Windows key
And I like you know most of the people should I have yeah, I don't have them
I know I know you can't do anything about the most of the way
I wish you know Microsoft they really they really had I wonder how they pulled that off
I would like to know this the history of the Windows key and how they worked like what I envision is I
Envision like they nailed a couple of manufacturers
And then the industry just decided to take off with it was easier to just have it all under yeah
Oh
Look at that dos keyboard sells a Linux keycap bundle. That's awesome excellent
It seems to be a lot of people are getting into replacing getting keyboards where they can individually replace the keycaps
Which is none of my keyboards?
I can do that with but I don't like any of my keyboards a whole lot except for my Logitech upstairs, okay?
Yeah, but like that seems a lot like a lot of fiddling
But at the end you end up with something you've crafted you have great pride in it
You'd have a lot of you have to have some free time though. That's not something you have a concept up. Oh, I see yep
Theoretically I can do that when my gateway laptop
Really it has keycaps on a huh?
Yeah, I learned that the hard way
About six years back and then when I went into a bit of rage
And then accidentally pop the you keep loose from the keyboard and that's why I had to quickly put it back on there before
Anybody noticed all right?
Well, we got ten Fridays left or nine Fridays left until Christmas
So you guys have enough time to get me a mechanical keyboard for Christmas?
I'm a kid. I don't I would not well actually I would probably use one
But not in studio, so you'd never get to see me using it because it'd be too loud. I would assume
Yeah, get one of the quieter ones, but then what's the point don't they not feel as good well?
I mean, there's there's many different
actuation
Love it. You know you can get lots of different feels
I have a code keyboard at home with the clear keycaps, which I like that. They're not too loud
I mean, I don't know if they'd be quite enough for the studio
But I bet you could find something and you can still be you know a lot of them
So I have nicer construction anyway, okay, so oh wait. Yeah, you know a deeper. So are you are you telling me that I?
Can I my understanding is that if you want the right feeling like you want that old?
old
mechanical keyboard feeling from back in the early 90s 80s and 70s or whatever the hell you know almost like
Clunk clunk clunk. I thought in order to get the right feeling you had to have a certain amount of sound
I thought there was you can't divorce the two
I thought so I thought if I as I begin to compromise on the amount of sound I also compromise on the feel is
That true I mean if I think if you're trying to read exactly recreate like the IBM buckling spring type switches
Then yeah, maybe you do, but I think there's a range of things that people like and that people appreciate and for different purposes
Right like a lot of gamers like the cherry MX red style series where it's like a linear press
So I think there's a wide range you might not find one
That's it you might find the you know like a loud one that you like more
But I think you can find something that's better than say that little Apple keyboard. You've got over there
Yeah, although I mean, but I think one thing here's one key so one thing I'll touch on there
So I first of all I'm afraid of my own personality when it comes to quieter keyboards
I'll get there, but to the Apple thing. I'm not a huge fan of them
But I also don't I don't hate them and one thing that if I was an Apple user
I think I would appreciate is I'm not positive, but I think
I'm not sure if this is true anymore actually maybe it's not true anymore
But for a long time like they had the same keyboard layout across the laptops and their physical keyboards
So you could interchange. I mean it was it was that that that muscle memory worked across a range of the products
Which is a great idea going back to the mechanical keyboard thing and I don't know if that's true anymore for Apple
But then what here's why I don't want to get quieter keys
This is the type of person I am I I have two modes
I don't give a I don't care about the quality of this thing
Mm-hmm or I care about the quality of it sure and if I care about the quality of it very best
And and if I don't what I'll do is I'll first buy the I'll buy the low-level one then I'll buy the mid-level one
And I'll try I know I will try to stay there as long as I can and I will guilt myself
I will internally beat myself up for wanting the better one when I have already bought the low one and the mid one and I'll fight
With myself, and it'll be like this ongoing thing that steals brain CPU for days or months
And depending on the price sometimes a year or you know and then I finally make the go and I love it
I love it way way more like for example
Perfect example, I bought the the rover right it was a great price
I got it on I forget consignment, so I got a great deal on it
And it was a nice travel trailer was a mid-level travel trailer
and then once I realized that I actually liked living in a tiny space and
That I liked the concept of our being and I liked how I liked how it's I use less I I consume less
I liked all the things about it, and then it was
Well now if I'm going to do this. I'm gonna do it right
I don't I don't want to and I didn't go out and buy like some
$300,000 diesel pusher I mean I have my limits of due to budget
But I I knew I knew almost within the moment. I knew I liked our being I knew then immediately
I was gonna be getting a class a RV at some point because I'm not gonna if I know I can do better and that same
Thing applies to production like I if I'm working on if I'm editing or I'm putting together something
And I know it could be a little better. I'm not gonna stop there
I'll go till it's as best as I can get it and so I'm worried about what the keyboard thing is that if I start
Caring about that. I will really care about that and then and then I'm really in a world of hurt because what do I do?
Do I start replacing all my keyboards and then some keyboards don't feel right so so far
What I have what I have allowed myself to do is I have a keyboard that I really like to use
Okay, and I would be sad if it went away
But I I don't let myself go any further in fear of have you found this to be true for yourself once you start
Looking into super nice keyboards. Did you slip into a keyboard like a keyboard snob range now?
Yeah, I think I was ready to become a keyboard snob
I have not as far as replacing everything I think the next on my list is getting one really nice one for work
What if you think about it, dude?
Like there are a few things in my life that my hands touch more of right and like that's one of the things you do
Let you consider yourself good at right like just be good with computers. It's a huge part of my work
It's a huge part of my hobby. It's it's like it's such a fundamental thing. Oh god now
I'm starting to care and I can also appreciate that like it's hard to like you you have to know like alright
Well if I'm gonna do this like I'm you can't do it half-assed, right?
You cannot you're gonna have to do it. Well, and that's takes a lot of research and time. Yeah
Sometimes it's just so don't okay
So I so somebody who must have been listening to Koda radio because this has been on my mind yet
It looks like t3 hit t3 late in the chat room is asking about I have a keyboard upstairs
This is my favorite keyboard and it is a logitech that runs Linux and I can't remember if it's like a
It's a gaming keyboard. I think it might be the g15. Let me go look
And it's an older. No. No, that's not it. That's not the g15
It's got a flip up LCD screen and it's it's super old
I actually did I'd actually use it as a runs Linux once on last because I mean, how could I not right?
Yeah, the damn thing actually runs Linux with a little flip up screen
And it's supposed to have like these widgets that interact with your computer and there is some Linux software
So here is a version of it this nope, that isn't it either but it looks kind of like this with an LCD screen
It's a logitech. I
Can't remember but it is it has a great feel to it. It's not all the way
Crazy, but I really like to visit here. It is this is it right here
I really like the positioning of all of the keys
I like the one of the things I really like about it is it has this roller knob right here
That's sunken into the keyboard for volume
yeah, and then a dedicated mute switch and then
logical playback controls that are laid out like they normally would be on a
Player device with play pause and skip tracks right there. I think like you'd find on your stereo or whatever
Yeah, so this is the logitech g19 and I don't even think they oh they make newer ones. Hmm interesting and
I don't know about any more but the version I have which does run a little warm
Has a Linux a Linux computer in there to do all the little witty stuff. Yeah, some
Ancient old version. Oh god. I'm sure I can only imagine so undefined. Let's see the new version
Oh, they don't even tell me the price because Amazon doesn't sell it directly
But it looks like you can get it used from a reseller for a hundred bucks, but new it's 280
280 290 here it is. Yeah, I think I remembered spending quite a bit on this
But you know looking back up looking back at it. Now. I have had it for a
Really long time. I mean I bought the first version that they years ago
And so I think the investment paid off you and for for for the idea
Here's the idea is while you're working on the LCD screen. You're looking at your you're looking at your CPU usage
You're looking at your memory stats like it's a little mini top
I do like that that's neat right or temperatures and of course they have a whole bunch of shitty software that makes it work automatically with
Windows, but there were ways eventually to get it work on Linux
But you know what?
I have not I had probably haven't bothered setting that up in two three years
I can think see that really handy if you could just like redirect one terminals output
Yeah, one of the other things you could redirect to it was VLC
So you could redirect VLC playback on the LCD screen Wow
Yeah, which was so cool for like just watching a little video or something also playback
You could you could see that like the track information stuff like that for like maybe a if your music application supported that
It was nice
Notifications notifications could go down there, too
But again, I I don't even know if it works and works
I probably haven't bothered setting up for two years is the version today
I just duct-taped my phone to the top keyboard. I just actually dude
That's exactly what I use that screen for a lot is because the screen rotates up and down it
And I so I haven't pivoted up and I lay my lay my script my cell phone on it
And it's the perfect cell phone holder right there on my keyboard
May I jump in yeah. Yeah, there is indeed a software again gnome 15 is called
Before there was the gnome 15 daemon daemon, but that's not maintained anymore. So now they use gnome 15
You can have a look at gnome 15 org
Well, you have to compile it yourself. It's not in the repository any distribution. I used I gave it a try
I have a lock attack
Speaker okay this
Does that 11 or said I don't remember set 11, I think and you can use the gnome 15
Software to display the same information your talk before so cool you search and all that stuff. I do like that
I do too. Yeah, that's quite cool. You know be the coolest geek project ever and I wish I could remember stuff when I say this
Would be to have a way to wire out
You ever watch Star Trek Voyager? Absolutely. Okay. Do you remember when they built in a bio-neuter gel pack?
No, do you remember when they built the Delta flyer and they put the the physical toggle switches in there that were like the ones
from their holodeck program and
the captain protons type stuff and it was so it was this 24th century technology that had a
What we would see as touch interface, right? Yeah. Yeah, I had more like a 1920s style physical toggles and stuff like that
I would love to take like
from a like a old old used parts or something where you can get like voltage meters and stuff and
be able to hook those up to an interface on a Linux box that would correspond the
Little needle to CPU usage so I could have physical boxes. Yes with like needles moving the rep represent CPU usage
I think that'd be so cool. Yep. We're like nixie tube spelling out things. Oh god. I'm totally rather
I actually go nixie tubes because then you can actually change up what it is a little more. Yeah, that'd be really cool