So they say it's a phone that's designed so you don't use it.
It's called the Light Phone, and Brandt
has his hands on a minimal phone with a neat trick.
It's got an e-ink display.
I do.
And I must say, this phone fits the hand so well.
If you remember the original iPhone,
it's kind of like it's a bit smaller than that, actually.
It's beautiful.
And light would be accurate.
It doesn't weigh hardly anything.
But this phone is really neat.
It's simplistic.
So you have to be sort of up for that.
And I'm struggling here to get the screen on.
There we go.
Is it slow with e-ink?
Does it take a second or two for things to update?
I think if you're used to a modern phone,
I would call this like a meditative phone,
because you have to give it a moment to react
to anything you do.
But it gives you that split second
to think about your life choices.
Does it have apps?
Does it do maps?
OK, let's call them apps.
But it does do things.
So here we go.
I'm pulling up the menu, which takes it
kind of like flashes between menus to clear the screen.
That's the kind of e-ink perk, I suppose.
Well, yeah, the mark of e-ink as it updates, yeah.
Implementation detail, perhaps.
Right.
I was kind of surprised, because the screen is simplistic,
but easy enough to read in full sunshine and stuff like that.
So that was impressive.
You asked about apps.
So I've brought up the apps menu, which
when I got my hands on this, it only
had three apps, which was phone, alarm, and calculator.
However, we've discovered that there are many more apps
to add, which includes directions, which
is very exciting, and I'll talk about it in a moment.
It does have a music app.
That seems essential.
It also has, Chris, podcasts, which I haven't tried yet.
You haven't tried that?
Come on.
How did you not listen to a Linux
unplugged first thing you did?
I know.
I'm sorry.
I've disappointed you all.
So Heather and I tried the directions,
because we thought, holy gee, that seems pretty advanced
for such a simplistic device.
And there are kind of two views.
Actually, it found the addresses of the local Home Depot
we were trying to get to very quickly.
So I don't know what the underpinning is,
whether it's OpenStreetMaps, or if it's actually
just Google in the back.
Maybe some handy listener can let us know.
But it did really well.
You have to expect that it's of this light phone design.
So the map itself is kind of like, hmm, imagine Pong,
but it's trying to tell you where to go.
So very simplistic lines and things.
And it's kind of delayed a little bit, which is not
that helpful if you're driving.
However, if you're hiking or something,
I imagine that would be perfect.
But we used the text instructions,
and it was perfect.
Got us there.
So I would say if you're looking for a phone that
is trying to keep you disconnected,
this is pretty good.
And it also has hotspots.
So if you want to carry your real phone around,
you could do that, too.
It definitely seems like it has a more simplified UI.
And they kind of brag about it not having social media.
From what I can find online, LiteOS, all they really say
is it's built with React.
So I'm not quite sure the details
on the underpinnings of it.
But it also seems like they're picking up
the bill for the cost to run those maps right now.
Wow.
That is something.
That's impressive.
I would say that's probably a feature that a lot of users
are asking for.
And if you're trying to get around with this,
I think it's there.
It's there.
So that sounds really quite amazing.
The battery, I think if you're not using maps,
and you're not using the hotspot,
it lasts quite a long time.
But it certainly doesn't if you're using those,
let's say, advanced functions.
You would hope that e-ink screen would
mean that it has a week-long battery life or something
like that.
But it sounds like it's a kind of standard battery life
if you're using sort of standard smartphone features.
Yeah, exactly.
But that being said, I'm sure the battery in this
is a fraction of the size.
So pretty neat phone.
There you go.
It's the Light Phone 2.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
It looks like it's about $299 if you buy the North American
model.
And there's a pre-order with the next plan
to ship mid-October.
I haven't seen it yet, but I saw pictures on their website.
And I think Brent's description of the original iPhone
that size, maybe slightly smaller screen,
that's about right.
So there you go, Wes.
Time to get rid of your Pixel and get yourself a Light Phone.
Uh-oh.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
My name is Brent.
Hello, gentlemen.
You know, this episode is brought to you
by the all new A Cloud Guru.
They have the leading cloud Linux and modern tech skills
training platform with hundreds of courses, thousands
of hands-on labs.
Get certified.
Get hired.
Get learning at acloudguru.com.
Well, coming up on the show today, about a month ago,
I switched to a new daily driver Linux distro.
And I didn't say anything.
Didn't want to mention it on the show.
I just thought it would be, honestly, a fading thing
that I just thought would a fling, a Linux fling,
if you will.
But then I started to realize, you know,
there is an important place for fun in the Linux distro world.
And I want to share a little diamond in the rough.
I even talked Wes into giving it a go and trying it out.
We're going to tell you all about that later today
and maybe even have a conversation
about the place for fun Linux distributions
in the overall ecosystem.
So welcome in.
And before we get to any of that,
I have got to say time-appropriate greetings
to our Mumble Room.
Hello, Virtual Lug.
Hello.
Hello, Chris.
Hello, Wes.
Namaste.
Hello.
Thank you for being here, everybody.
Yeah, we're going to need your support today.
Yes, it does.
It feels like it's an episode where we're
going to need people's support.
So we do have chapter markers.
So I'm going to give you everybody a brief update
on their reunion road trip.
But if you just want to get to the Linux stuff,
hit the chapter.
But since our last episode, since we gathered together
last time, my slides that I've talked about before
on the show have been fixed, thankfully.
It's great.
Very happy.
Working really good.
The shop doesn't necessarily want
me to give them publicity about it yet,
because they're still in the R&D phase.
But when they do, I'm going to be telling people about it,
because life changer for us.
And for a solid 15 minutes, I felt
like Lady Joops was in the best shape of her life.
And I felt amazing that my home, here it is, six years old,
was better than ever.
Like, I felt on fire.
It was just great, and not in a bad way.
About 15 minutes later, though, I
experienced extreme disappointment,
as I discovered a major issue with Lady Joops, my RV,
while pulling out of the shop that fixed our slides.
I literally discovered the next devastating issue.
I didn't even make it 15 minutes with the victory.
It was just awful.
So I had to park it again.
Our rear driver's side had a supposedly indestructible Sumo
spring that was ripped away from its top mount,
causing the spring to fall over onto our inner dually tire.
I can only presume, because I apparently
decided to take a tour of America's worst roads
and between Colorado, parts of New Mexico, which
parts of New Mexico are a lot better,
but some parts of New Mexico are not,
and Arizona, which is a hell-failed state,
has the worst roads probably in the country.
I can only imagine, because there are just
entire sections of the road that are missing.
So you literally can't have worse roads,
because there are parts where there are no road.
Did you take a piece of the road as a souvenir for your trip,
I hope?
I took a piece of the RV as a souvenir.
That's what happened, is that driving around
and all that stuff.
It was really damaging.
And when that spring fell onto our tire,
it's there for a while.
There's significant rub damage on the spring.
So I don't know what the condition of that tire is,
and a blowout there could be extremely, extremely dangerous.
So I determined it was just too dangerous to drive
with a broken rear suspension and a tire that had been
significantly rubbed.
I got the OK from the shop, and I never even
got to leave their parking lot.
No hookups either, of course.
And this was the Friday before the long Labor Day weekend.
About 3 PM, and all of Tucson had already shut down.
No shops, no techs, no parts departments.
Nobody was answering the phone.
You're just stranded.
Totally stranded, dude.
Totally stranded on a Friday when
we had been intending not only to be driving
the entire weekend, but I had an event
that I was going to where I wanted to potentially meet
two new potential hosts on the network for a show
that we were considering doing.
And I wanted to have an in-person meeting with them
to kind of suss them out, and talk to them, and see where
they're at, and really get a feel for it.
And now that's not happening.
So this has an impact on my business, too.
So we get stuck here the Friday before Labor Day weekend.
We check Amazon.
They've got these Sumo springs, but they're a week
and change out, like into next week.
And we just spent the weekend roasting in 105 degrees.
Most days about 105.
The sun from sunrise to sunset was beating down on Lady Joops.
When I was doing LAN on Saturday evening,
it got up to 122 degrees inside Lady Joops.
It's crazy, right?
Because it's a hot car in the sun.
And when you turn off any kind of airflow,
it just heats up in here like crazy.
And we're constantly managing the generator temperature,
and the inverter temperature, and the battery temperatures,
because everything's working at its max
to try to generate enough power to run air conditioning, which
causes everything to overheat.
And when it's 105 degrees outside,
and the sun is beating down on the bays that
contain your electrical system, it's
an impossible, impossible battle.
The food in our cupboards started to go bad.
Like cleaning sprays started to separate and get gross.
Up front where I'm recording, there's
the smell of burning plastic.
It starts around 10 AM and lasts all day,
just the smell of plastic burning.
I mean, we are literally baking our RV, and ourselves,
and Levi in this parking lot.
So we knew we needed to attempt a fix.
Even if nobody was available, nobody could help us.
We knew we had to do something, because we are dying here.
I mean, I'm literally getting heatstroke like every day.
When I record, I get heatstroke, because as I record,
like this show right now, it'll get up to 130 degrees in here.
It's absolutely mental.
It is inhospitable to human life.
Man was arrogant to ever build in Tucson.
So we decided to try to do something.
And we're from Seattle.
We're used to 70s this day.
I mean, Wes, what's the temperature right now?
It's the beginning of September.
What's the weather outside?
Ooh, checking the weather report.
It's 72 and partly cloudy today.
Oh, oh, yeah, 72, right?
So you can see, like, here I am, September.
It's 105 degrees.
The sun is beating down directly on the spot
where our tire and our suspension is.
We could only be crawling around on the ground doing stuff
down there for like 10 minutes at a time,
and then we're dying.
So what we realized is we got to get out here like 5 AM, 6 AM,
when it's only like 85 degrees Fahrenheit.
Only.
And I took a pass at it, and I went inside,
and Hadia went out, my wife.
She took a pass at it, and she managed
to hook the suspension up.
She hooked the Sumo spring up using bungee cords.
So it was hanging in place.
At least it wasn't touching the tire anymore.
And we thought, OK, we can make it 10 minutes down the road
where we'd seen an RV park.
We could test this.
We can make sure it's working before we go.
This is going to work out OK.
This is about Sunday.
This is Sunday.
Wes and I recorded Saturday, so that way I could use Sunday
to try to fix this for Linux Action News.
And Sunday rolls around.
Midday, we're feeling pretty good.
We're ready to test it.
And the first alert.
You know when you get like the amber alert on your phone
and it buzzes and stuff?
The first one comes in.
Severe thunderstorm alert.
OK, all right, that sounds bad.
The next one, major hail storm, massive property damage
from these giant hail balls stay inside.
I'm like, oh, God, that's going to probably destroy our solar
panels.
Then about 20 minutes later, maybe 15 minutes,
we get a dust storm alert instructing everyone
to remain indoors, not to travel, and to take shelter.
I'm like, jeez, a dust storm too?
And then about 30 minutes after that, maybe less,
maybe 15 minutes, we get a very alarming and very serious
tornado warning that a tornado is in the area.
And it specifically says in the tornado warning,
mobile homes will be destroyed.
That's what it says in the tornado.
We're sitting here in our RV, and we
get a push notification that says mobile homes are
about to be destroyed.
As that clears, then we get a flash flood alert warning.
This all is like within an hour, all of these alerts.
And the wind, it starts picking up.
And at first, we're like, jeez, it
doesn't look so bad out there.
We look outside, and it's clear blue skies.
Oh, it doesn't seem so bad.
And then I notice the awning starts to flap,
and then it starts to flap more.
So I pull the awning in, our only, only source of shade.
And then the winds really pick up.
It starts rocking the rig.
And I bring up the radar of the storm,
and I can see we're just on the edge of the storm.
So it's way too windy and chaotic to actually drive,
but we're not getting the brunt of this thing.
There was nothing about this in the forecast, which
I had been watching like a hawk, by the way,
because it's literally life and death right now.
So I watch it multiple times a day.
There was nothing in the forecast about any of this.
It just starts dumping rain on us.
But we figured we can handle the rain
because we're from Seattle.
So we go out, and we start testing the rig
in their parking lot, trying to get it to rock back and forth
to see if our bungee patch will hold long enough for us
to get 10 minutes down the road so we can hook up to power
and at least run our air conditioning nonstop.
And we test it in the driveway, and it seems like it holds.
And so we set off towards the campground
we had spotted earlier.
And about five minutes into the drive,
the rain picks up to monsoon level.
I mean, it just starts slamming Tucson, raining so hard
you could only see a few feet in front of the RV.
And almost instantly, parts of the road begin to flood.
Looking like almost a river rushing down the road.
And thankfully, Joups' heavy butt could manage it,
and so we kept on going.
But I couldn't believe how fast it was happening.
And when we arrived at the campground,
the rain slowed down, but it continued to pour.
So of course, I'm out there hooking up electricity
because that's why I'm there.
And it's still, even though all of this is going on,
it's still 9,800 degrees outside.
So you still need everything hooked up.
You still need air conditioning.
You need the water.
So I'm out there just getting completely drenched.
Horrible.
Everything's dripping.
And thankfully, power's good.
AC's been running.
We've been here since Sunday.
It has been livable.
With the AC going 24-7, both of them,
it maintains about 86, 87 degrees in here during the day,
during the afternoon, 87 degrees, maybe 88.
We can really only bring it 20 degrees below
whatever it is outside.
So as the temperature skyrockets outside,
we kind of go with it.
We just have a 20 degree buffer inside,
and it removes the humidity,
which is historically high in Tucson while we're here,
which has resulted in historic growth of bugs,
which has meant we are covered in bug bites
because they've never had this many bugs here before
while we're here.
It's been absolutely wild.
And because it's the Labor Day weekend,
we had no progress on getting parts.
We had to wait until this morning, Tuesday,
to start making as many calls as we could.
Shops around here have been shockingly misinformed
about how these Sumo Springs,
which are extremely popular and well-known, how they work.
It's been alarming, like some of these shops,
what they do and don't know.
And we're hoping to get some sort of temporary fix in place,
maybe get them removed even
so we can just make the drive home.
Ideally, I'd love to have the shop
that originally installed them fix it,
but I don't know if we can make it up to Oregon.
And the other issue is,
now that we've ended up getting stuck here for so long,
we've ended up pushing into another heat wave.
And so our drive home is over 100 degrees in many places,
all the way until Southern Oregon.
California is gonna experience a massive heat wave next week.
I-5 corridor will be over 100 degrees.
When does that happen in California, right?
And it's gonna be miserable everywhere.
So it has actually crossed my mind, as a last resort,
I've never really thought about this before,
but I am now considering abandoning ship
and putting jupes in storage
and driving home in our chase car
and then fly back down here later.
But of course it's super expensive.
Well, and that's just gotta be hard emotionally too, right?
I mean, you're abandoning your home basically.
Yeah, I didn't go on this reunion road trip
to abandon my home,
just after I got the slides fixed too, right?
Like that wasn't the goal here.
You don't go on a road trip to leave your vehicle behind.
And yeah, it is our home.
And it's like, so you'd wanna make sure
it's really well taken care of while we're not here.
And it's miserable because I don't know how safe it is
to drive on this or not.
I assume because the tire has been rubbed,
I should get it checked out professionally.
So I assume I shouldn't probably drive that far
until I make sure my inner dually isn't gonna explode on me.
I imagine that our temporary fix with a bungee cord
isn't gonna last 1400 miles.
In 100 degree weather, probably not.
Right?
And with roads that suck.
And so we're using the crap out of our suspension system.
It is become an impossible situation.
And I feel like the shows will suffer because of it
because I'm miserable.
I'm barely making it through the days.
There's almost every day I've gotten heat stroke,
mild heat stroke,
and I don't manage to recover
until about an hour or two after the sun sets.
And the days I record, the RV gets so hot
that it never really gets down until like 10 p.m. at night
and back into a reasonable temperature
and reasonable being low 80s inside.
So it's just, you know,
it's like I didn't wanna come to Tucson for the meetup.
I came to Tucson to get the RV fixed.
My slide broke in May.
And I waited until September
to just try to wait out the heat.
With three kids during summer break,
I waited with a broken living room slide.
So I wasn't in Tucson in the dead middle of summer,
like in August or something stupid like that.
And I still am getting screwed by this weather.
It's just, it's horrible.
It's been really rough.
And so I don't really know what I'm gonna do.
I don't know where I'll be next week.
I don't know where I'm gonna be later
for recording self-hosted.
It's just been awful.
Stay tuned for the next Linux Unplugged everyone.
Hopefully there'll be one.
Yeah, hopefully there will be.
And you know, and then to make things extra difficult,
the server is out at the studio.
We haven't had a chance.
There's nothing, nothing could be done while I'm not there.
And so like that is,
extra hoops have to be jumped through for production.
And just all these things,
like all these little things are adding up
to make this end of the trip really difficult.
And ironically, this is the wing of the trip
I thought was gonna be smooth sailing
because we'd have working slides.
It was just gonna be Hadia and I.
We went from three kids and three adults
to just two adults.
And smooth sailing with no hard deadlines.
Like we didn't have any meetups to get to
or anything like that.
It was just take our time.
And yet now here we are stuck in an area
we never intended to be for more than a couple of days.
And we're so desperate to get home now
that we are gonna have to push like hell
once we can get out of here.
It's a totally unfortunate situation.
And it's just sort of one of the random things
that can happen on a road trip this long, I suppose.
And the part shortage that's going on
affects the RV industry as well.
So funny enough, the shop in Oregon has the parts we need,
but the shops here at Tucson don't.
And so like, it's just one of those things
where if we were back at home right now,
we wouldn't have a part shortage.
That shop happens to have stock,
but these ones down here, they don't.
And where they would get their stock from
is the shop we use back up in Oregon.
Chris, may I ask how your tech infrastructure
has lasted in this heat?
There was one day where I shut everything down
just because we couldn't keep up with the heat.
And so I turned it off just to make sure,
it was getting so, so hot.
But otherwise it's been holding pretty well.
Thankfully the road trip to Texas last year,
I kind of, you know, I learned a few tricks
to keep that stuff running.
But yeah, not fun, not fun.
It is great to have working slides again.
And if it was, you know, in the mid eighties
and I was stuck here, it'd be no problem, right?
That'd be no problem.
Even low nineties would work because again,
we can get it down 20 degrees.
So whatever the ambient temperature outside is,
we can bring it down 20 degrees.
Of course, some of that's offset by the fact
that we're in direct sun,
but at least now we're at a campground with power and water.
So we can just turn them on and let them run.
And we don't have to worry about using up gasoline
and all that kind of stuff.
Cause that was another problem of course,
we were stuck, didn't have gas.
So let's talk about good news.
Let's talk about ingenuity.
You know, that little Linux copter on Mars,
it has really, really done well.
I mean, above and beyond.
We've talked before about how well it's doing
because it was only supposed to fly five times.
And yet the little helicopter on Mars
has completed 12 flights now
and given its stunning and unexpected success,
the US space agency has extended the admission indefinitely.
The little helicopter that could
has become a regular travel companion
of the Rover Perseverance.
So given all of its awesome success,
NASA says it's on board
with keeping this thing flying indefinitely, if possible.
Yeah, according to Josh Ravitch,
the head of Ingenuity's mechanical engineering team,
everything is working so well.
We're doing better on the surface
than we had ever expected.
And we've actually been able to handle winds greater
than we could really have ever hoped.
To add onto that, you know,
Ingenuity, it's not just a tech demo anymore.
At first, that was kind of the goal.
Could it fly at all?
You know, would this all survive the landing,
the harsh temperatures?
But now they're actually doing real helpful science.
According to Ken Farley,
head of Perseverance's science team,
photos taken by Ingenuity during its 12th flight
showed that a region that they might have wanted
to check out with the Rover,
which of course takes a lot longer to get there,
well, the photos showed it was kind of just boring.
And so they might actually not send the Rover there.
Okay, maybe that's boring,
but that means valuable time is saved
and they can go look for more interesting areas
to do better science.
That seems huge, actually.
That seems like a great use of the Linux Copter.
Yeah, it really does.
And hopefully it's gonna keep going, right?
I mean, in theory, it's been doing well,
but there is an approaching Martian winter,
kind of the reverse problem you're having, Chris.
So we'll see, fingers crossed that Ingenuity makes it out.
But regardless of what happens
with our favorite first Copter,
NASA now has a whole bunch of data from all those flights
and is already working on a next generation successor or two.
Maybe something in the 20 to 30 kilogram range,
able to carry science payloads.
Ooh, very cool.
I mean, just as a reconnaissance little robot too,
it's so awesome.
And I could see the winter being particularly challenging.
The great thing is if it survives,
you know the software is gonna run.
It's gonna just keep going, so.
You just say that because it's powered by Linux.
Yeah, that's right, that's right.
Well, let's talk about our friends over at Plasma.
Plasma's Wayland session is getting really, really stable,
at least just recently following a bunch of fixes.
And of course, KD developer, Nate Graham,
continues to publish his weekly development summaries,
outlining all of the work,
which we are very appreciative here on the show
and we read every single week.
This week, he's got good things to say
about the state of KDE on Wayland.
Gazillions of bug fixes,
including many for the Plasma Wayland session.
It's finally reaching stability.
I'm using it myself as a daily driver now.
And at this point,
my biggest annoyances are all with third party apps,
not any KDE software.
I know it's taken a while,
but I think we're very nearly there.
That's great.
If you just add another three releases on top of that,
it's probably gonna really be there.
I kid, but some highlights of this Plasma 5.23,
beyond just X-Wayland and Wayland support, of course,
is there is now improvements
to how the Plasma desktop experience is on Wayland.
Like for example,
virtual desktops are now on a per activity basis on Wayland.
Again, that wasn't the case before,
that was only an X11 feature.
And Plasma 5.23 will now correctly identify
the sending app for notifications
from flat pack applications,
both on Wayland and on X-Wayland.
And there are fixes for multiple Nvidia GPU issues
with the Plasma Wayland session as well.
And as Nate said,
these are really just the cream of the crop
of a gazillion other fixes and improvements.
KDE Plasma 5.23 is really looking like
it will be a great release.
I think it should arrive sometime in early October.
Really looking forward to that.
The daily driver I've switched to is Plasma based.
They offer a bunch of different desktop options,
but I went with the Plasma one and I am so happy.
There's a few tweaks that have been done to this one
that have made me extra happy.
And I'll share those with you when we get to that point.
But first, there is a pretty anticipated development
with NF tables.
The Linux kernel is, as you know, very fast moving,
but sometimes it seems like a few things
can take a long time to land.
And I would say NF tables is one of those.
Yeah, really this is a good example of just,
sometimes it takes a long time to get stuff right
or get it merged, get it to a place that's usable.
And as usual, Jonathan Corbett at LWN
has a really great write up on some of the history
and what's going on with NF tables,
which if you're not familiar,
aims to replace the kernel's packet filtering subsystem.
And it started way back in 2008,
but it's still not being used by most,
perhaps even many production firewalls.
That transition may be getting closer though,
because there was just NF tables 1.0
released on August 19th.
Now look, we're not gonna judge you firewall
how you want a firewall.
You packet filter how you like to packet filter,
but some of us see a need for a change.
And you know, that could include the fact
that the kernel has more than one packet filtering mechanism
so it's complex.
There's one for IPv4.
Of course, as you probably just guessed,
there's one for IPv6,
and then there's one for ARP and so on.
And each one of those subsystems is mostly independent
with a lot of duplicated work and codes.
Shock, surprise, right?
And beyond that, IP tables contains
an excessive amount of built-in protocol knowledge.
And I think some would argue it suffers
from a lack of a proper API
for people who want to manage it at scale.
And so I think that,
that has led people to look for an alternative,
all of those things combined.
It's not that IP tables is bad itself,
it's just everything in totality.
You know, for people who like to mess with firewalls.
And really more seriously here,
the core idea behind NF tables is to kind of throw away
as much of that protocol aware
and specific machinery that you can,
and replace it with a simple virtual machine
that could be programmed from user space.
So, and administrators would still write rules
referring to specific packet header fields and such,
because of course that's kind of what you need to do
when you're setting up firewalls.
But then in this model,
user space tooling would translate those rules
into low level commands and load that into the kernel,
which basically it means
you get smaller packet filtering engine
that is way more flexible
and has the potential to perform a lot better.
Me like fast packet filtering.
You know, I think a lot of us have probably heard
the name NF tables because it did make a splash
when it was launched, I'd say.
But then it just kind of, I don't know,
it just kind of disappeared from view.
In 2013, the project was essentially rebooted
and got a lot of code or all of its code,
I don't remember exactly, merged into the mainline kernel.
And they did that as like job one.
So they got done with that.
NF tables found its way into the Linux 3.13 kernel
back in 2014.
That feels like a million years ago.
And since then, kind of the hard work
has been just filling in all the little gaps.
The core engine was in the kernel,
but you actually need to make NF tables
sufficiently appealing that users
would want to make the transition.
The language that you use to write those filtering rules,
it's gained a lot of new features since then
for stateful tracking, address mapping,
and all kinds of other stuff like handling large rule sets.
There's also documentation to write, of course.
There is an NF tables Wiki,
which we'll have linked in the show notes,
but it sounds like that's still one area
that is maybe a bit lacking.
Yeah, I think though the biggest challenge,
and I bet people listening right now
are thinking this already,
it's that there's so many people
that are using IP tables already.
You know, they have their setup that they like.
They don't want to mess with it
because they've developed it over years
through blood, sweat, and tears,
and lots of hard lessons learned,
and they just want it to keep working.
It's been working for fine.
Why switch to something like NF tables
when IP tables is doing the job,
and it's perfectly fast enough for them?
I think that is going to be the biggest barrier to adoption
and people switching over.
Yeah, I mean, firewalls are a serious component
of your security, right?
Like you don't want to go changing this
and suddenly realize that packets you thought were dropped
are no longer dropped,
or ports you thought were closed are suddenly open,
but it may not be so bad because in some cases,
users might be able to make that jump without even noticing.
Linux distributions have carried support
for NF tables for a while now,
and work is being done to port some tools
like Red Hat's firewall D to NF tables.
So if you're using a higher level tool,
once they've switched the backend out,
you can just keep your rules and that engine
will handle converting things from IP tables to NF tables.
Right, or I suppose put another way,
it's like if you're going to transition,
maybe transition to this higher level tool,
so that way when these kind of backend changes happen,
you can move around.
And I mean, it's deployed to a point, right?
Like Debian got it in Debian 10 Buster,
which was released in 2019,
but Ubuntu didn't adopt it until 2104.
So I mean, most districts do have it,
but 2104 is a fairly recent release of Ubuntu
to actually have it land.
Yeah, really.
As with all these things, it just takes a long time.
I mean, in this case, 13 years,
but with 1.0, with Netfilter declaring IP tables now
a legacy tool at the latest Netfilter workshop,
it seems like now is a great time to give it a shot
and prepare yourself for what may be our eventual future.
Neil, I can hear your ears are burning.
You've got something to say about this.
Go ahead.
Firewall D 1.0 happened,
and that's actually going to land in Fedora Linux 35.
And it defaults to NF tables.
So it actually will transition everything over.
And if you're using most of the higher level
default behaviors with Firewall D,
like using services, telling it via add ports or whatnot,
it'll seamlessly translate those into NF tables rules.
Libvert has already been adapted for it.
Container engines are in the process of being adapted.
I think they're all done in Fedora.
So across the board, generally speaking,
with Fedora Linux 35, you're going to see NF tables
being used, and you won't notice
because it's all been done for you in the background.
If Firewall D has been told by the user
to add specific firewall IP tables rules,
because you can do that.
You can say, I want to add this IP tables rule
and Firewall D will manage it.
Then it won't auto flip, but otherwise it will.
So in Fedora, it's already done.
It's also the case in RHEL 8.
They actually did it before Fedora did
because initially it happened in Fedora.
It got reverted once and now they're trying again
and saying, this is now good.
And of course in RHEL 9, it will be there too.
I like that.
That sounds good.
A nice, smooth transition.
That sounds appealing.
Lino.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in credit on a new account
and you support the show.
You know, a Linux content creator out there,
Nick at the Linux experiment just went full time
a few weeks ago.
And yesterday, YouTube shut down his channel
with no communication or maybe by the time you're hearing
this probably a couple of days ago,
they just deleted his channel, removed it completely.
And then told him that if he didn't respond fast enough,
he'd be gone forever.
And then just kind of gave him the cold shoulder.
And he had just gone full time.
That's so scary.
Imagine that your livelihood just like that
taken away from you.
And that's why I want to just say thank you to everyone
who takes advantage of our sponsors,
who understands the model that we have here.
This is an independent business.
You know, it's just a small team of us
that are independently working our butts off
to make content every single week for you.
And the reason why we can stick around and do these shows
is because you take advantage of our sponsors
or you become members or you tell people about the show.
And the great thing about Linode
is it's a perfect partnership where we can work
with a partner that gets what we're doing
and you guys get what they do.
Because like JB, they're independently owned
and they've been doing this one thing for a long time.
They've been doing it longer than we have.
They have been focused on cloud computing for 18 years.
I mean, that's really something that defines an industry
and they have focused on just doing a really good job
at that.
And because they're Linux geeks along the way,
they understood the reason why they should reinvest back
into the community.
They get how that works.
They've helped projects out.
They've helped out this network.
I mean, they've really been there
for a lot of different groups,
including although we don't get to go to them anymore,
some of our favorite events like Linux Fest Northwest.
And as a long time Linux user,
I really can tell that they are fans,
that they have built tools around Linux
before the technology necessarily existed.
Like at the time when they became their own ISP,
it was extremely uncommon to run Linux on your routers
and on your switches.
And I just, that was insane.
Who does that?
Who runs Linux on their firewalls, routers and switches?
Nobody does that.
Well, Linode did.
They wanted to figure out a way to do it.
And as a result, they have a flexible service
that's been able to meet the needs of their users.
And now they have 11 data centers around the world
with nearly a million customers.
And man, they've just built a product
that you've got to check out.
And that's why they're confident in giving you $100
because they know if they give you $100
and they give you 60 days to play with it,
you're going to go on there
and you're going to build something.
You're going to try it.
And you're going to see that it's faster.
The UI is cleaner.
The documentation is better.
The API is fantastic.
And the customer support is the best in the business.
That's why I run my business infrastructure on Linode.
So go to linode.com slash unplugged,
sign up, support the show and get $100 to kick the tires
and see what we've been talking about.
Linode is the best way to host something
and they're true real Linux users.
So you can rest assured knowing
that they love what they're doing.
And I love it.
I love it when that works its way into a product.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
You can't just use Linux for fun, can you?
No, I only use it to get work done.
You know that Windows is for fun.
Right, it's only a serious tool.
And you should never download a distribution
just because you think you might have fun with it.
Except for that's exactly what I did.
A little while ago on July 22nd,
I decided to give Garuda Linux a try.
And I kind of laughed it off as a project
because it looked like Linux turned up to neon 11 to me.
And when it comes to ready-made arch based distributions,
Endeavor OS and Manjaro really serve that purpose
very, very well.
And I just sort of instinctually kind of brushed it off
thinking, yeah, that's what we need is another arch clone.
Yeah, that's going to solve the problem.
But then I decided, you know, I looked at their website
and I liked a few things about it.
I liked how opinionated it was.
It felt like kind of a distro of before
where they were going to kind of actually reminded me
a little bit of Mandrake.
I have to be honest with you.
Where they've got some tools to manage the distribution.
They've really picked a theme and identity.
They embrace it and they've optimized it
for the user desktop.
And that's been their sole focus.
And those are items that appealed to me.
And I was ready just to,
I was going to try an intermediary distro
before our next review anyways.
And so I decided to throw Garuda on my ThinkPad X1.
And my initial impressions were that it was gaudy.
That it was over the top.
That it was a little, it clashed a little bit
in a few places.
But as I started to use it,
I started to take it a little bit more seriously.
And I started to notice that my system felt
a little more responsive.
You know, they use the Zen kernel, for example,
which is, you know, you can argue for it or against it.
But some people say it's great for desktop loads.
They've chosen a CPU scheduler also
that's maybe more tuned for desktop performance.
And they've done things like they've enabled ZRAM
by default.
They've turned on an out of memory killer.
And they're using ButterFS as default file system
with ZTSD, ZSD compression.
I don't know, Z standard compression I guess it must be.
Z standard.
Anyways, it's a formula.
It's a recipe that I like.
And so I kind of tried to encourage Wes
to take a look at it.
And you've got fresher first impressions than I do, Wes.
So I'm curious to know, like, when you decided to bite
and you went over to the website
and you gave it a download,
just curious what your first impressions were.
Ooh, there's just a lot here.
The theme kind of is intense.
Yes, gaudy is probably a good word for it.
But it's consistent.
There's elements that I like.
It all hangs together very nicely.
And there's just a lot of attention to detail
in areas I'm not used to.
I think we're used to thinking about
the kind of attention to detail in the distro building
and maybe a bigger classic distro sense
and all the hard work that Fedora does
that we highlight on the show
to build the next generation of the Linux desktop
and integrate a lot of these low level tools
or the Ubuntu team putting together
an Ubuntu desktop release.
But because it's built on Arch,
you're basically just installing a bunch of upstream software
and so you get these tweaks in other areas
that you kind of don't on more mainstream distros.
Yeah, you know, you can see this with Manjaro too.
They provide you some tools to select your kernel
and they give you some wizards
and they work you through part of the setup process.
What Garuda does differently is they take all of that
and they kind of turn it up to 12 or 13 even.
And as I used it, they call their KDE look Dragonfied
and it's a variant of the sweet theme for Plasma.
And as I used it, it dawned on me,
I've always had a problem with Plasma's
sort of look and feel compared to GNOME Shell,
like an elegance factor that GNOME Shell
just felt like a little smoother in terms of look,
a little sharper, a little cleaner.
And on Plasma, I was always kind of attempting
to get to that normal level of polish,
but never quite getting there
and always left a little frustrated.
And I often just kind of just sort of gave up
and always just went back to Breeze
because Breeze works with everything
and maybe it's not perfect.
Just becomes kind of a workstation focus.
Yeah, you're like, okay, whatever.
It's not as beautiful as maybe I want,
but it works great, I love Plasma, so I'm happy enough.
Where Garuda comes along and says,
well, if it's not gonna be beautiful,
what if we just embrace the shit out of being different
and kind of like an elite desktop?
What if we just kind of lean into it a little bit?
And that's what Garuda has done.
Like the terminal is,
it's got like a kind of a blurred fade to it by default.
They launch it with like NeoFetch output information.
They've got a customized shell.
The icons are very neon.
The look is very, very unique
and it actually has won me over, over time.
And they have these management tools that I like
that remind me of the Drake tools from Mandriva
or the Drac tools.
Like they give you one to help you install curated games
and emulators, just check a few boxes
and you can get everything.
Like there's gaming software on there I'd never heard of,
like a free Epic launcher replacement.
I got that installed now.
They have boot options to let you tweak kernel parameters,
select the default OS that boots,
disable Specter mitigations and a lot more.
I mean, they just,
they have tools for managing common butterFS things
like getting an accurate free space reading,
running a rebalance if you need.
And it'll tell you, you don't need to do this.
It'll say right there, this is not needed right now.
Give you tools to manage the fact that you have butterFS.
And then on top of all of that,
they have enabled time shift snapshots by default.
And not only can you use the GUI
and a command line interface to restore snapshots,
but they also put a menu entry in grub.
So when you're booting up,
you can just restore from a snapshot
right there at the boot menu.
That's glorious when you're working
with an arch-based system.
It really is like kind of a new,
maybe not new is the right word,
but a different way of using arch.
Obviously the packages, right?
Are coming from arch.
It's a lot of that arch goodness,
but where I'm used to building up an arch system
for myself and kind of selecting stuff,
I feel like with Gruta, for good or bad,
I almost have to do the opposite
because so much of that has been done.
Like you mentioned the terminal,
that's probably where I crossed the line.
I'm like, I don't want you showing NeoFetch
every time I open the darn thing.
That's just wasting my cycles, but it looks really nice.
It's a good first experience.
And for some things, it might make more sense
to start with this if you like most of what they do,
to start with Gruta and then, you know,
just tweak things back down a little bit
if there's some stuff you don't need.
So I'll give you an example.
So I think they're trying to make arch
not for regular humans.
They're not trying to make arch for humans,
like Ubuntu's making Debian for humans.
They're making arch for geeks
that want a powerful workstation.
And you guys know that always pushes my buttons.
I'll give you an example.
Like you've ever had an arch machine
where you have key ring issues eventually,
like this happens to me on a machine
that if I don't update it frequently enough,
well, this has happened to some Gruta users.
So the team put together a tool that goes through
and works out these key ring issues during updates.
It automatically updates your key rings in the backgrounds
and it also lets you go through and install
what they have as like a hot fix package,
which resolves the issue.
It's just, it's a tool that really is only applicable
for a rolling distribution like arch
that has something like that.
It happens every now and then.
And then this just smooths it out for you.
And so they've built a few tools like that,
like, and you know,
or included tools that have been created
by other distributions.
There's a little bit of that too.
Like they're using the same installer that Endeavor uses
and timeshift of course is, you know,
it's available for any distribution,
but it's nice to see it.
And it has its own look, but you can change that.
And if you change the theme, if it's too much for you,
you've still got a lot of great choices.
Snapshots by default, butterFS by default,
current plasma by default.
I would also argue, although I think this is,
people could see it the other way.
I like that they're using the Zen kernel
and I like that they're using a desktop scheduler.
I think those things are tweaks and changes
that I've begun making to my boxes.
And in part, that's how I came across Garuda is I,
and Wes knows this, since I got my X1,
I have been on kind of this pursuit to make it faster,
to make it perform as well as it did under Windows.
I mean, I think you kind of want to forget that there's,
you know, anything between you
and exactly what you want the computer to do, right?
Like when you see those apps take a while to launch,
that seems to cause you physical pain.
It does.
Well, it really, it broke me after I,
on a lark, tried Windows 11 on the X1,
and it was faster and the battery life
was significantly better.
Ugh.
And I'm like, no, this cannot stand.
So I had been doing a custom arch install
and I had done the like Alan Cox kernel
and I was doing all my little tweaks to like pre-cache stuff
and put the browsers in RAM,
all the stuff I've talked about before.
And I was building a lot of this myself anyways.
And that's kind of when I discovered Garuda.
And I thought, well, this is silly,
but I'm exasperated at this, at this laptop at this point.
I'm just going to throw this silly distribution on there.
And I admit, I thought that way.
And then about a week into it,
I was like, that's not so bad actually.
And I thought the first thing I'd do is change the theme,
but I didn't.
And that never happens.
And so I stuck with it for a little bit.
And now here I am.
I'm like, man, I've been using this for more than a month.
And I think this is my new go-to Arch.
And I'm not recommending it for everybody.
I still think Manjaro and mainline Arch,
if you want to use Arch are the way to go.
That's my official recommendation.
But if you kind of line up with me
and how you want your Linux desktop to perform
and how you use Linux, it's worth a fun look
because if nothing else,
it's like visiting a version of Linux
that used to be very common,
where they had lots of apps and tweaks preloaded.
They had management tools.
They had a strong identity
and they tried to solve a specific problem
for a specific niche.
And that's what Garuda does,
including it has various different versions.
Cause like Wes, I know you're a huge gaming guy now.
So I installed the gaming version.
Yeah. Right.
Why not?
It comes with steam.
It comes with a whole bunch of handy tools.
And honestly, that's one area where it is kind of nice
because yeah, all right.
I like to play games,
but not that many and mostly on Linux.
I don't keep up with the latest and greatest
of optimizing Nvidia integrations with stuff
or like little tweaks to make gaming go better.
So if Garuda does, that's pretty useful
cause it's exactly the kind of thing
where I don't necessarily want to spend an hour.
I might want to go play with NF tables
rather than tweak my system for gaming.
So I can get something out of the box
that just makes it easy.
That's great.
Yeah.
They also in their management tools,
they have options to like check a box
to turn on auto CPU fric or maybe you want thermal D.
So they have a few things that just make it quick
to play with that kind of stuff,
which this was my take on it.
It's just, they have a lot of tools
that you can do something really quick.
That's just an alternative to you going
and looking up how to do it in the Wiki
and then doing the same thing on the command line.
Like it's nothing you couldn't figure out on your own
if you're this type of user,
but maybe you don't want to have to all the time.
And it's neat to see them working on that.
And it's interesting too, in the arch world,
I feel that, you know, some other distribution sometimes
I don't necessarily know where to look.
You know, I might be curious what that GUI tool is,
but because they kind of do it their own way,
I don't always know like exactly how that's implemented
under the hood, but because I mean, it's just on arch,
you can kind of tweak it in Garuda.
And then if you want to, yeah, go pull up the Wiki
and go find out where all that lives under the hood.
Yeah, and as far as I'm concerned,
it's staying on this laptop.
And the next time I need a quick arch box,
I'm going Garuda because they're doing 98%
of the tweaks that I would do.
And also, I think it's one of the funnest distributions
out there.
It is a blast to try this thing.
They have a clever community.
They have what about eight members on their team,
do you think Wes, roughly?
Yeah, sure seems like it,
and seemingly from across the world.
And it's fairly new.
I think it kind of came out last year.
So it's been around for over a year now.
And they've set up some services for their community.
I didn't bother looking into how to sign up,
but I did notice that they had a hosted Bitwarden available,
hosted Nextcloud, a private pastebin alternative,
collaborative like notepad thing.
They had a few services that they would make available
to their community.
And they also make a start page available,
which, you know, I don't need that, but it's nice.
It's a good idea.
And it's further extending open source,
other open source projects too.
Right, and I think it adds to that,
that feeling of community, right?
Like you feel like you're, it's not just like,
for better or worse in the arch world,
you're kind of left out on your own, right?
Like they've got the Wiki and there's forums,
but like you are the one who's doing this.
And Groota feels just a little bit more,
like people are out there to maybe hold your hand
if you want to hold hands.
You know, Chris, I was noticing those services
when I went diving in to try to find out how active
this project was.
And I expected them to be charging a little bit of money
for these services, but it seems to me,
I couldn't figure out a way to give them money
for the services.
They're just kind of giving it to the community.
There's certainly a donate page,
but it'd be nice to see a project like this
stick around for a while.
So they have a couple of ways to contribute right now.
The primary way they want you to contribute,
the problem there is that platform is really only set up
for monthly contributions.
Where I basically, I wanted to send them 50 bucks
and say, thanks for the great distro.
I don't necessarily want to send them money
every single month.
I like to annually give to projects that I'm still using
because my usage changes sometimes.
And then the second way they recommended things,
oh, also the first way they recommend things,
you can go in there and set up an account,
connect it to your PayPal,
but then when you go to contribute monthly,
cause I kind of just decided fine, I'll do monthly,
then it doesn't let you use PayPal.
So then you have to connect it to a bank.
And so I bailed at that point,
I switched over to just send them a PayPal payment,
which they have a link for that.
And I was going to send them 50 bucks.
And then I got an error saying that their PayPal stuff
isn't working and you can't send them money right now.
And they're using open collective to track expenses
and try to document everything.
So they're doing it in an open governance way.
So I like that.
And when they get their payment stuff sorted out,
I'll send them a few bucks
because it's been a great little desktop for me.
And I think they should keep it going.
I think they're doing something fun and unique here.
And even if it's just a testing ground for fun ideas,
I love this.
And that's where I kind of wonder
if there is a place for the fun distro.
Like hear me out for a second,
but I think you could make the argument
that experienced Linux users
who know how to submit bug reports,
who maybe can kind of suss out the nature of a problem,
they can probably help reproduce that problem.
I almost feel like we have an obligation
to use more mainstream distributions
like your Ubuntu and your Fedoras and even your Mints,
because those distributions need people submitting bugs.
And they need users who understand how to submit bugs.
And that's us, right?
But here we are using these sort of niche distributions
that maybe don't have a bigger impact
on the wider Linux ecosystem.
And that's where I wonder if it's slightly irresponsible
on somebody who considers himself a Linux advocates part
to use a distro like that.
What are your thoughts, gentlemen?
That's kind of tough.
You're right.
I mean, it is out there and you're not using some stuff
that's been customized by the distro as much.
Maybe you're just relying
on the more upstream arch packages.
So I don't know, I have two minds.
I think there is an element of truth to that.
But I also think that maybe the kind of issues
that you're going to run into as someone who gravitated
towards this kind of optimized distro for certain use cases
are probably different than maybe the wifi issues
that someone might have as a new user
trying to use an Ubuntu desktop.
So I think it's still important that you contribute
both to Garuda and also maybe start filing some bugs
upstream for stuff that doesn't work.
But I don't know that I would worry too much about it.
Seems to me like a project like this
might get someone more interested
or like get their minds thinking about things
they never thought of before.
Like some of the features you mentioned
that they just make very easy
to just kind of click and turn on.
Wes was mentioning that having it work by default,
but then diving in with curiosity to see how it all works.
That speaks to me and gets my ears up.
That is exactly how I love to learn.
So I could see a project like this
just getting us a whole bunch more contributors
than we originally had.
Yeah, okay, ByteBidden,
you had something you wanted to add on the subject.
Yeah, so I jumped in with the Dragon Eyes gaming version.
I was like, well, hit me with it.
And I was astonished by all the tools they deliver with it
or even giving you the choice
because I didn't know half the choices that I got
where I felt informed.
Do I want an emulator?
They got an entire page of that
and I can now check that information.
And only downside is that I can't get
my Nvidia proprietary driver working,
but that's where the ButterFast snapshot feature came in
and I was like, back.
And you can keep testing and testing.
And well, the only thing is that the Dragon Eyes version
is a bit too sparkly for me.
So I will probably step back to a normal version
and then use their tooling to get back on it.
But also you can install like five different software
boutiques and updaters and stuff like that.
So whatever you want, they have the choice for you
to just check the box, click install and it's done.
Yes, they have now a third configuration screen
that might be a bit troublesome
if you want to check for a setting
somewhere in one of those three.
But yeah, it's really nice.
And also a lot of things I found in Barchi
where I was like Barchi is my home system,
Geruda felt like a bit like a new home to me.
Yeah, it feels like a new home to me as well.
And I think my take on the using the niche distros
versus putting your attention
and focus on the mainstream distros is
it means the onus is on me to recognize
or at least attempt to recognize as best I can
that if I'm encountering a bug,
is it because I'm using a different scheduler?
Is it because I'm using a Zen kernel?
Or is it because I'm using a very opinionated theme
and this app isn't rendering correctly?
Like the onus is on me to figure that out,
but potentially because it is an arch derivative,
I'm using a lot of upstream packages
and I could still have an impact
on those upstream projects if the bug is legitimate.
And I think if I'm willing to accept that compromise
that, hey, the onus is on me to suss out
the cause of this and that is something
I'm willing to accept,
then I don't think it is a bad thing.
I think you can still have an impact
and because the beautiful thing about open sources is
if I report an issue with console on Garuda,
it's going to improve the situation for somebody
on a future version of Fedora using plasma as well.
And so I say, you know what?
To hell with it.
Go use the fun distro for a little while, have some fun.
That's why we got into this stuff.
Stop taking it so seriously all the time
and just have some damn fun.
That's what I say.
Also, I want to mention that our friends
over at a Cloud Guru have a course on Linux web services.
So it's a course that focuses on the tools
and utilities used to configure web services
on a Linux host.
So you're going to install Apache.
You're going to install squid, I believe, NGINX.
You're going to set up virtual hosts.
You're going to set up reverse proxying, which is dope.
You're going to mess with HTTP and SSL, load balancing.
It's all in there including how to collect Apache metrics
and all that stuff on NGINX as well.
So head over to our show notes or go to acloudguru.com
and search for Linux web services.
We will have a link in the show notes
at linuxunplug.com slash 422.
Thank you to a Cloud Guru.
Now we have some email to get into gentlemen.
What do you say?
Time for some feedback?
Well, yes, our mailbag today is quite on theme
because Oren has finally switched to plasma.
He writes, IJB, I finally did it.
After the recent episode in which you guys talked about KDE
plasma as a great alternative to GNOME, I finally switched.
I'm an Ubuntu user who prefers his desktop environment
clean and stable.
I don't like to install plugins and prefer to just use
what comes out of the box, which is why my GNOME desktop stayed
the same pretty much all the time.
I held off on KDE largely because every time you guys
talked about it, it sounded like you'd have to configure
and invest time to get the whole system into a usable state.
But I have to say, after a quick install,
I love every minute of KDE.
I feel like a younger version of myself
when I first started using Windows 95
after spending way too long in DOS.
I click on every setting KDE has to offer.
I've been going over it for over a week,
and I still find cool new things.
There's nothing that compares to it.
The system is fully customizable,
but it also works great with the default settings
right out of the box.
From my side, I'm sold, and I'm never going back.
Yeah, the trick is, Oren, is to still get your work done
and not spend all your time playing with all the settings.
That's why you didn't have the dock done this morning.
Yeah, I was too busy playing with my plasma.
I do love it.
I do love it a lot.
Thanks, Oren, for writing in.
And I'm glad you like it.
I think it's different folks, different strokes.
We got a bunch of suggestions for DWM
last week after I complained about wanting tiling
on particular virtual desktops.
But different desktops for different folks.
But plasma is working really great for us.
I think all three of us now are on plasma, right?
Yeah, it's your fault, Chris.
Thank you very much.
All right, well, I'll take that blame.
I'll take that blame.
We do have a bit of housekeeping.
And I just wanted to mention the lup lug,
because I haven't been able to make it for a few weeks,
because I've been dying in the heat.
But the lup lug continues on a nice, chilled, relaxed chat
with Linux friends.
You can get information about our mumble room
at linuxunplug.com slash mumble.
Go over there, enjoy.
And we'd also love to hear from you.
Fact, we'd love to do a feedback episode again.
It's been a bit.
So send your questions in.
We're going to start collecting them.
I just decided right now, linuxunplug.com slash contact.
Send in your questions to the show about anything
we've covered in the past that you'd like us to follow up on,
anything about the show itself, or a technology stack
that you got questions about.
We'll take them at linuxunplug.com slash contact.
And last but not least, join the conversation
that continues every single week at jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash telegram.
You can go in there, hang out.
There's members of our crew chatting in there all the time.
Oh, I suppose I do have one more thing.
So not quite last, but now this one is.
But definitely not least, the stickers.
Go over to jupitergarage.com and grab yourself a sticker.
They're great.
They're fresh.
And they're high resolution.
And they make your laptop just look better.
That's at jupitergarage.com.
We have a pick this week.
And this one is useful because YouTube
has a habit of just pulling down content these days.
So how about something to replace that YouTube
DL, which seems to be on the rocks these days?
Yeah, YTDLP, a YouTube DL fork with additional features
and fixes.
How about that?
I mean, I love me some YouTube DL.
I probably use it, if not every day,
at least several times a week.
But that's the beauty of open source, right?
You can take something, maybe it's
not seeing as much investment or maintenance,
or you just have some new ideas.
You can fork it.
You can remix it.
You can make it better.
Yeah, it has all kinds of interesting features
that they've added on top of YouTube DL.
In fact, some things are really simple,
just like the way it displays different formats.
But then other things are fascinating.
You can mark and remove sponsor sections in YouTube videos
by utilizing the Sponsor Block API,
and it has built-in support for that.
It supports all kinds of resuming scenarios
that YouTube DL doesn't, including workarounds
for when YouTube throttles you.
If anybody's a heavy YouTube DL user,
you run into this, where YouTube starts throttling you.
It happens to me.
They got workarounds for that as well.
But we have a bonus YouTube pick as well,
because I think the faster you can get content off YouTube,
the better.
And this one is YTMDL, or YouTube Music Download, YTMDL.
It's an app that just gets songs from YouTube in MP3.
It grabs all of the metadata you'd like, too,
and takes care of that, like the artist name,
the album name, all of that.
Yeah, that's the added benefit here.
I mean, sure, YouTube DL, you can tell it to download MP3,
but YTMDL, well, it's gonna go out to sources
like iTunes, Spotify, Deezer, Last.fm,
and pull all that juicy metadata
that if you want to add this to your personal collection,
you really need to have.
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm, that's pretty nice to see.
And you guys know we're big fans of PeerTube
here on this show.
We think that's a great way for content creators
that want an independent,
under their control media platform for video.
But there's a lot of other alternatives out there, too.
So the great thing about these apps
is they support just about every
semi-popular video streaming site.
So it's not just YouTube that they work with,
but we mention it because that's the most popular
and that's how they name them.
You know, pick suggestions,
another great use of that, contact form.
You get the sense, I really would like people
to email us in questions and ideas and stuff
just to help us out while we're on this road trip,
because my God, has it been miserable on this road trip.
We could use the help, you know,
and it's a great way to touch base with the audience.
If you've got something that you've added to your workflow
that you think other folks in the audience
might benefit from, yeah, please do send it in.
Bonus points if it's made with rest.
Totes, wow, yeah, I mean, we love to play the horn.
And then also, I'm still on the road for a bit.
I don't know exactly what my sitchimication is,
and I don't know how many meetups I'll be able to do,
but check out colonytracker.live,
and there's a micro meetup link there.
And if you can't meet up with me,
but maybe you know something about the area I'm in,
because we have the live map there,
the tracker's still going.
It looks like it's broken because it's been stuck
in the same spot for a while,
but this could be a way to help out.
If you know a spot where I could store the RV,
potentially, if I have to bail,
if you know something about the area I'm in,
or if you'd like to meet up and grab a bite, potentially,
there's a micro meetup link at colonytracker.live.
And I mention that because it sends a push notification
to me, and so I see those.
We have a channel that we collect those in.
So sometimes like the emails and stuff,
they'll slip through the cracks every now and then,
whereas that is a specific channel for that purpose.
So something over at colonytracker.live
if you'd like to help out.
In the meantime, if you do the Twitter thing,
you can follow the show over at atlinxunplugged.
The entire network is at Jupiter Signal,
where we have all kinds of announcements
for podcast releases and other show news
and stuff like that.
And if you work in the tech industry,
go check out Linux Action News.
Every Monday morning, Wes and I break down
everything that matters in the world of Linux,
nothing more, nothing less.
And sometimes that means it's a 15 minute show
when there's nothing going on in the dead of summer.
And sometimes it means it's a 40 minute show.
But what we do is we cut out all the BS
and we focus on just the stuff
we really think you need to know about
and we try to do the best analysis possible for you.
That's linuxactionnews.com.
And the show continues to roll on
regardless of where I'm at live on a Tuesday.
See you next week.
Same bad time, same bad station.
Yeah, 12 p.m. Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
Wherever I'm at, I just go by JB time.
It makes it easier.
Links to everything we talked about today,
including the contact page, the mumble server,
our matrix community, how to subscribe.
It's all at linuxunplugged.com.
Links for this specific episode, linuxunplugged.com slash 422.
And that's it.
That's pretty much it.
You can get links to everything right there.
Thanks so much for joining us
on this week's episode of The Unplugged Program.
Assuming I survive the heat,
maybe, maybe I'll even be lucky to get the hell outta here.
Man should never have built in Tucson.
Assuming all that works out,
see you right back here next Tuesday.
We'll be right back.
All right, JBtitles.com.
Everybody go over there and vote.
Let's pick our title, see if we can name this thing.
So I finally did it.
I wasn't even gonna mention that I was using Garuda.
I don't know why.
I just thought like, I'll keep this to myself.
You know, Chris, you kept it so to yourself
that even despite my living with you for what, two weeks,
I had no idea.
Yeah.
Well done, sir, well done.
So did you guys see that Boiling Steam had an interview
with the CodeWeavers folks?
And in that interview, they tried to clarify that,
hey, we don't think Valve meant that the Steam Deck
is gonna be able to run every Steam game
from a software perspective.
We think Valve just meant the hardware would be capable
of it if the developers put the effort
to get it working on Proton.
And I think that has been a massive misread.
People, because of that IGN interview that Valve did,
it sounded like Valve was saying,
every game in the Steam library,
they're hoping to have run on the Deck
by the end of the year.
And what CodeWeavers is saying,
the people that would be plumbing that,
they're saying, actually, it's just possible,
but it doesn't mean that every game will work.
I think that's a huge difference
in what the narrative is out there right now.
And it's gonna have a lot of people
who pre-ordered potentially disappointed
if they don't get the memo.
We'll keep you updated on the rest of the news.