I was just getting nostalgic about modems this morning and that sound that they make and
I don't know if it was just serendipity or what but you found the perfect
Perfect open source tool this week. It's pretty cool. West. It's called wave share wave share. It's serverless
It's peer-to-peer. It's local file sharing
Through sound I like all of those words. Yeah, it's using WebRTC. Oh
Signaling is performed through sound no server side is required
You just unplug headphones turn on a microphone and get another computer to listen and you can transmit data
So I'm going to send about this is about a 40 megabyte file and I'm going to send it at the fast speed
They have normal fast fastest and ultrasonic
I'll do fast so that way we can actually hear it
And if you were on the receiving side if you'd gone and we'd set up a session
This would actually be transferring a file to you. You ready? This is what it sounds like. It's it's pretty neat. Oh
That's it. Oh, it's transmitted. Isn't that cool? That's fascinating. I love that. It's so you can find it
We'll have a link in the show notes. It's actually kind of hard to search for
Wave dash share is what you would Google but just go to
Linux unplug calm slash 248. We'll have it there at the top of the links. It's so neat. It's like bringing the modem back
This is Linux unplugged episode 248 for May 8th 2018
Whoa, welcome to Linux unplug your weekly Linux talk show
That's watching all of the keynotes from Microsoft Google and Red Hat all at once and putting it all into something
That's actually interesting. At least we hope my name is Chris. My name is Wes. That's right Wes
It is a packed Tuesday Google Microsoft and Red Hat are all up on stage as we record and they're all talking about
Linux not entirely but it's a lot of Linux
We'll cover a couple of moments from Red Hat summit and from Google I owe that I think matter to our listeners
Plus we got a bunch of community news. We've already got speculation on the next version of Ubuntu and I I
Got really deep into Fedora this weekend, and I did some things. I want to hear about them. I made some changes
Oh, no, so I'm gonna tell you all about it. I did. I'm a maniac when it comes to that
I don't know. I I am officially a Linux nomad
I just hop around a lot, but I think I have the perfect setup this weekend is sitting for Mike Ubuntu workstation
SSH into Fedora 28 cloud instances. I
Consolidated three servers down into one
I'll tell you why I did it and what really made it click for me and why I think I'm going all-in on Fedora
28 on my servers for these jobs
Wow, I never thought okay. I'm going LTS on the desktop and for door 20. You're a bad man
I got a good reason though, and I'll tell you all about that coming up in the show plus we always have those folks
In that virtual look time appropriate greetings mumble room. Hey, yo, what's up, Jedi? Oh
Oh
Come on. We got more than that. Come on. There's more than that. I've got it. Come on guys. You gotta be food
Yeah, I'm hiding
Well, I'm glad to have you on there Jen
It's nice to have you sneaking in today because I know you got one of those I think people call them day jobs
So that's it's really much appreciated welcome. Yeah, especially on a day like today. Most people are burned out good thing
I'm working from home. Oh good move good move. I'm glad I'm glad you're able to make that work today
Most people are burned out because of everything going on
But the big news item like if you're gonna pull one thing out of Google IO
It's the story that we've been slowly building towards on Linux action news and on this program and that is Chrome OS getting full-fledged
real Linux apps
Coming all together in one place. You got Android Chrome apps and now Linux desktop apps on Chrome OS
It's it's a big announcement. We've seen it coming and it's released on the pixel book today
It'll be rolling out to other models later
Seems like a pretty big deal and we know that underneath this it's probably some sort of container eyes Linux environment where
Yeah, looks like they've got a sandbox and then a virtual machine the inside and then where it's like in the past
There's been other methods to get sort of Linux side loaded on Chromebooks
This is something when you go into the settings you'll check a box and now you have it
Yeah, it seems like maybe Google leveraging some of the the security things they've learned from the cloud here on their desktop platform
Whoo, this seems like it could make Chrome OS the largest
Desktop Linux operating system like we've it's always been Linux based, but it didn't have Linux apps now. It's got a
Multi-billion dollar corporate sponsor. It's running a Linux stack. It's got access to desktop Linux applications
oh, and if you need it, it's got Chrome and
features like power wash and
reasonable prices and while we'll throw in a few Google cloud services to which everybody's using those these days anyway
So why not?
I mean it takes the Chromebook to a new level in a way suddenly a major bump in utility at least for me
I mean you can install Android studio on it
Developers have been messing around with getting entire development stacks running inside the Chrome OS container for Linux
There is even people that have gotten wine loaded for different Windows
applications, it's I think it's hard to overstate how this could change desktop Linux this really could make
Chrome OS like the number one desktop Linux system
And I I want to just spend I just want to spend a moment with that because that's a good
This is Linux to the masses here. This is the success
That so many of us wanted for so many decades for so long now. I mean really since
multiple decades
and
It's arriving Linux. It's available to
Anybody that goes into like a average electronic store
They'll be able to buy a Chromebook that can run Linux applications seems like a pretty big deal to me
Yeah, it does and it's not even right. Yeah, it's not you don't have to flash it yourself. You're not doing anything complicated
It's in a safe sandbox environment
It's got a warranty and they're cheap, but it's it's deeply tied into proprietary services that spy on you
And so this is what our success ends up looking like and is it success? Is it a is it a clean win?
I don't know if it is
I'm not sure. It's a clean win. I don't think it
I don't think it feels like we thought this might feel like no, I don't think it does
I think I always pictured a Red Hat or a canonical being there
But something more traditional something like we're used to or what we choose for ourselves
Yeah
It can be interesting to see you like five years from now if this really changes the landscape much if maybe people are creating more
Desktop Linux applications so they could people can have richer application experiences on Chromebooks. I
certainly if I was if I had a if I had a fleet of salespeople or
People that worked in a warehouse or on a on a manufacturing line that I needed to buy a fleet of machines to go with
This would be pretty tempting
there is some seriously robust centralized management capabilities with Chrome OS that make it very appealing to businesses and schools and
It's really comparable to what you would get if you were to roll out Windows with Active Directory
And yeah all of that and they have it built into Chrome OS
Apple really can't compete with that
You could custom write that one or two one-off applications that you need that for some reason aren't web apps
Why would you buy a standard full Linux workstation or laptop or even a Windows workstation or laptop?
When you could do this now developers could use it too, right?
I mean they probably already could but even more so where does I wonder where does that leave?
Where does that leave Apple as well?
If you you know Windows has the subsystem for Linux Chromebooks can run Linux apps now
Yeah, I guess if you it's just where are you more locked into Microsoft Apple or Google and that's the one for you
I would like to ask Noah like are you would you consider selling this to clients?
Yeah, and I would like to ask the audience Linux unplug calm slash contact. Is this a win for us if this becomes
Overnight, I mean, I don't know obviously cuz I don't have the numbers in front of me
but it seems like there's some potential here that if they turn this on for the pixel book and say
half a dozen other Chromebook models
it would seem like the install base would all of a sudden at least be in the hundreds of thousands of maybe not millions and
That seems like that would outflank just about every distro but Ubuntu at that point for desktop penetration pretty much
So it could be within a couple of weeks the number two desktop Linux distribution in a way
Am I wrong? Am I overstating that and is this a way you say in a way?
That's the key right like it's still it's still very but when I say in a way
I mean in a way that it's in a way that's gonna be a big deal for end users
I think it makes the argument for a Sputnik for say mom or
So do you see you see it hurt hurt?
No, because it's not gonna it's not gonna change like you and I and our audience's preference
yeah, but for I think it's more like it's gonna go after Windows and Macs and they're gonna do it using Linux and I think
It's just gonna be sort of like how Android is far and beyond the largest deployment of Linux in
Average consumers hands. Yeah, this is gonna be the second largest
And so this in a way is going to be the face of Linux to the majority of people using desktop Linux
That's what I say in a way right because it's the Wi-Fi work the hard
The hard numbers are gonna be such that the gravity of desktop Linux will be here and so that has a way of influencing
application design
consumer purchases
I mean it just has a way of causing incidental factors in the marketplace
What apps will it be that this you know that actually get you so this this new weird hybrid?
I don't know. I mean I I would be really tempted to load Libre off as funny as it sounds
But I just the other night I had a spreadsheet
I uploaded it to sheets on Google didn't really like what it did with it. Open it up in Libre. It was great
You know Calc just handled it fine
I don't know man. I think I if I was if I was advising like friends and family
I think I'm gonna start saying get a Chromebook and I think I'm gonna just like then
I'll just load the couple of side applications that they need with this functionality
We just had a friend
this week her she had an old like
2011 2012 MacBook and the video card finally went out on her and
She's and the Mac repair shops like well if you buy your next MacBook through us
We'll transfer your data at a reduced rate, you know, so they get her like
So we'll save you 60 bucks if you buy a $2,000 laptop through us and I'm like, what do you need the laptop for?
you know like those questions you always ask and she's like well, I got to check my gmail and
I I do, you know online social networking stuff and there's this exercise group that we're going on a bike trip
I want you know, it's Etc. She just goes into the all of its browser based and she's got an Android phone already
She's already got all the Google account stuff. She's had it for years
She's been in the Google ecosystem for years
And I couldn't come up with a compelling reason for her not to get a Chromebook and you add this on there
The maintenance burden is less. It's designed for that type of user
So there I think there are actually a lot of advantages there Wow Wow Jed
You see you're seeing in Chromebooks for as low as 60 bucks. That's remarkable
That's a that's a Lenovo. It's the C grade. I don't know what the grades mean, but yeah
60.99
It's amazing four gigs of memory. Yeah, many Mac. There's other aspects of Chrome OS besides price that are appealing to end-users
I don't know how many uses you I've already converted to Linux, but often they have
Problems with updates. They don't doing it. They are scared because they know Microsoft and the problem is you you just do a reboot
You're done. So it's very easy for the user
Yeah
Not even getting to the power wash aspect just the just the self updating aspect and and really the fact that they don't have to
Worry about data backups if they do go in on cloud stuff
The thing is once you start putting local applications on these Chromebooks
You're gonna start running into the hard memory limits and storage limits
So then the next shoe that has to drop here is maybe this is a 2019 2020 thing
But they've got to start putting larger disk and more ramming these are Chromebooks. Yeah, I mean the pixel books pretty nice, right?
Yeah, but maybe a slightly different more options. Yeah. Yeah. So JJ. What do you think not necessarily cheap Chromebooks for Linux apps?
It might be limited to the more
Premium products seems like that could happen. Yeah
Possibly and also I know I know that the plate currently though you can get the place for a Chrome OS
but only on a certain yep certain hardware type of devices only certain Chromebooks that have the
That have been approved to run the play store
So maybe it'll be the same maybe limited to the to the same exact Chromebooks
But if you happen to have one of those Chromebooks
Like I said at the top of this thing you're getting and all the Android apps
It's possible to run on that thing plus all the Linux apps is possible to run on that thing and all the Chrome apps
It's possible to run on that thing. That's actually kind of slick. That's a lot of that's a lot of choice
I don't know how good any of them are gonna look or function on that device
I mean
Could this be employed to replace the Chrome web store that I've been hearing for the last few years that Google wants to get rid of?
Oh, I don't know about that
My suspicion my suspicion is that it's really about hedging as they transition Android off of Linux
But that's for a future episode. Yeah, let's talk about you there
I can't even this is the story that neither West and I wanted to do this week
But we got to talk about it because I know you guys are gonna be hearing about it
So Jonathan over at LWN has a subscriber only post right now
It'll be out in a little bit and it covers some drama around a G lib C
and it's about the removal of an old joke from the man page from the from the C library manual and
I'm amazed but yet not surprised that it can spiral into such a shitstorm. Let me give you the background here
So think about think about this, you know
You're coming across the manual and you see some old kind of off-color joke in there and you read then you go
There's no reason for this to be in here. Let's remove it and you submit a patch to pull that out and
from there it spirals into a confrontation with RMS because the author of the joke was RMS and I'll read you the joke
It's not even funny that's the worst part so it literally says in the comments put in by RMS
Don't remove
Says future change warnings and this is about the abort function in lib C
Proposed federal censorship regulations may prohibit us from giving you information about the possibility of calling this abort function
We would be required to say that this is not an acceptable way of terminating a program. That's the joke
It's an abortion joke that if they make abortion illegal, then they can't talk about the abort function in G lib C and
People come across this the people who actually are responsible for developing the software
RMS is not actively involved in the development of G lib C and they come across this like oh, let's pull this
Let's let's remove this and the developers have this
consensus based community driven development model and
They come to a consensus that people who are responsible for developing G lib C and if everybody agrees and there's consensus reach then they take
Action and they reach consensus
however
They didn't reach out to Stallman now Stallman is not directly involved in the development of G lib C
But of course, it is a good new project and that's where Stallman gets involved
He writes back after seeing on the mailing list. My decision is to keep the joke store just short and sweet
People respond respond back. He says nope. I stand by my decision to keep the joke
They apologize to RMS for not involving him in the conversation, but they say look, you know, we're the maintainers. We've reached consensus
We would like to remove this joke. We're not gonna we're not gonna put the joke back in
It's already been removed at this point. We're not putting the joke back in that's
When you might say Stallman got unimpressed with the situation and went for the authority play
He says this is a direct quote as the head of the GNU project
I am in charge of what we publish in the GNU manuals. I
Decided the criteria to decide by to he later adds I exercise my authority over G lib C
Very rarely and when I have done, so I have talked with the official maintainers
So rarely that some of you thought that you were entirely autonomous, but that is not the case
on this particular question
I made my decision long ago and it started where all of you could see it
What I love about RMS a statement here besides the pure authority play that just says I'm in charge of the manuals
And I've made my decision is the is like the sly
I have been pulling the strings behind the scenes the entire time, but you fools never knew it
He literally writes in his response. I
I've gotten involved so rarely that some of you thought you were entirely autonomous, but this is not the case
Like like he's sitting there stroking his beard with one hand while he writes this
So the maintainer who really is leading this O'Donnell they start the discussion back up, but somebody else who?
Alexander Olivia who? Apparently was on RMS aside just decided to on May 7th
Slip it back in the first change to G lib C in 2018 slipped the joke back in
He didn't post anything on the mailing list didn't ask any didn't say anything until he was directly
Questioned on it. And he says well we were waiting for a return to consensus. So I wanted to put it back in there
Which has now spun into?
this massive fight over who actually controls the project calling RMS an authoritarian leader and
I believe I haven't checked for the last couple of hours. I believe the thread is still spinning out of control right now on the mailing list
And it's all about this stupid joke in the manual at some level
It does just feel like an unfortunate waste of time. I'm not saying there's not legitimate things to be discussed, etc
Right, but if this all could have just been sidestepped and right. I mean the joke
Is really a proxy for a more significant question one which is relevant to both the developers and really the users of the project
the question is
How is a project governed and who makes decisions about which patches are applied?
Is it is it the overall founder of the GNU project and the person in control of the manuals?
Or is it the core developers who are the ones that actually have been doing the work for a long time?
And have made dissent consensus-based decisions on everything else really, but if you ask RMS, well, I've been pulling the strings all along
So they really haven't been doing their own thing, right?
It makes you question like is this the best governance model or what are the you know?
What are the limitations of our governance model and it's really when the dictator has bad taste?
Yeah, and RMS is sort of abrasive
Hardline no compromise style
Takes the conversation to an 11th and it's not a good idea to talk about it
But I guess it's really not about the joke. I just
It just comes across as he has a big ego and he puts himself first
And I wish that wasn't the case because I don't actually think that's usually his intention
But the abrasive nature in which he communicates and conveys himself often leaves one with that impression
And I think it harms the message to a degree
But I think it's a good idea to talk about it. I think it's a good idea to talk about it
But the abrasive nature in which he communicates and conveys himself often leaves one with that impression
And I think it harms the message to a degree
It sometimes would be a good sign to show that some lines are not worth fighting
It's not a good joke. It's old
Why not remove it?
Why not why not take the high ground here and go? Yeah, let's why not come up with a new joke?
Put something else in there. I think that's kind of what disappoints me, too
Uh swamp, uh had a couple of great interviews with rms up on his youtube channel
So look around for those. My next guess is rms. You can go youtube search that
Where he talks about what happens after he passes on
Like who's going to take over who's going to lead the who's going to lead the charge
and uh, I would i'll leave it to you I won't spoil it but uh,
I was surprised by his answer. I'll just leave it
I'll leave it as an exercise to go check that out because I think swap deserves the uh, the views so microsoft's most popular
product
Of all time their most popular big, you know, their big thing really is sequel these days
Where it's for software that they sell and stuff
And the most popular version is the one that runs on linux
coming out of build today
microsoft confirmed
That their most successful server product ever is the sequel server that runs on top of linux
This is the general manager of azure data in an interview with the register
He says it is this is a direct quote the most successful server product. We have ever released in terms of downloads
Our typical volumes are in the hundreds of thousands
We're looking at seven million downloads talking about cosmos db, which was introduced a year ago
It's a distributed multi-model database. So it supports um, sequel apis javascript gremlin mongo db
Azure table storage all of those to query data as you'd expect and it can be scaled to multiple azure regions or locally
Which turns out it's handy when dealing with regional data centers and it's become a big hit because people can mix and match the components
But the takeaway headline here is it's their most successful server product ever in terms of downloads
And it's the one based on linux and I think that just plays a little bit into the backstory of why they're getting so
So deep into all of open source and linux
Now wes I was all proud of myself
But uh, see we're sprinkling in app picks through this whole episode
We really are there's app picks sprinkled in all over the place
And we're going to start with our first one while we're talking about something microsoft related
I was like wes check this out check what check out what I found and you're like, oh, no
No, you don't need this. So with a disclaimer wes is going to tell you how you could do this without this tool
But if you've ever been like in a situation where a year ago
I needed to install windows 10 and I hadn't done it since windows 10 had come out
And I didn't I didn't know what the hell I was doing. I assumed you could just download the iso
And dd it to a flash drive or use etcher
And you're off to the races. No big deal
Nope. Nope doesn't work
The only way I could ever successfully write a windows installer iso that would actually boot into the windows installer
Was from another windows box
You can only do it from another windows box which totally defeated the purpose of what I was trying to do
Which was install a windows box to test something and so I found this tool called windows to usb
It's a bash script which writes windows 7 8 8 1 and 10 dvd images
To your usb flash drive or an external hard drive on linux
And it's really great because it's really fully automatic. You don't have to prep the thumb drive
It supports bios uefi fat32 and ntfs
It works with certain custom windows isos that are like corporate specials like smaller isos. It'll use stock windows bootloaders
It does not break efi secure boot chain and it's available as an app image. So you just download it market is executable
so it's a mod plus x and run it in your terminal and you're good to go and it'll start flashing a
windows iso that you already have
to a usb drive which
Is awesome for the next time in a year when I have to test out windows, but after I told wes about this
He was like, oh man. Yeah, I already got this figured out. You actually had to do this the hard way though
Yeah, that's true. Sometimes I like to do things the hard way
But it all starts with a little ntfs magic. I didn't know that yeah if you do it on on uh
Mbr you can just if you set it up, right?
You can just format it ntfs set the bootable bit and the ntfs partition headers have enough magic to
To get boot manager going and then the rest is an unfortunate operating system
So they have that all just built into ntfs. Yeah
That it's pretty slick actually. Yeah makes it very easy, uh to just to go from the iso
To having a fully functional thing
Efi also makes it easy because they're just booting with standard efi
So gpt formatted right set up all those standard efi file systems copy the rest from the iso and again away you go
Okay, so you so you get it formatted and then you just do like a like an rsync from the actually
Hmm. All right, that's not too bad
That's that's not actually as bad as I thought it was because I didn't realize ntfs had the boot magic
So that's there's a format option
I now that you say that I remember like a bootable option when you format something as ntfs
And when you do that, that's when you get that stuff that's cheating. That's cheating
I know it's just too it's just too slick, but we all have it now. Efi has uh saved us for better or worse
Yeah, yeah, but not everyone wants to do that or remember how to do that or look up the documentation to do that
So if there's just a handy app image
When it's already unfortunate that you have to install windows you might as well make it easy
I just pictured like a younger west pain like a year or two ago like
Rifling around the windows file system and the isos trying to figure out how the hell to get this thing to boot
Being frustrated that he couldn't just dd the iso image to the thumb drive
Like you had you had to do some uh, sherlock there some sherlock work many wasted hours attempting to administer windows from linux
That's right. Yeah. Yeah, you know what? Uh, you know what rms would say about that. I think that we should all
Make those businesses fail. Yeah, that's what he would probably say that about it. He takes a hard line on stuff
He takes a hard line on stuff. I take a hard line on my mobile service provider
They got to be great
And that's why I recommend ting go to linux.ting.com where the average ting bill is just 23 dollars per phone per month
It's six dollars a month for the line and then just what you use in minutes messages megabots whatever you use
That's what you pay. There's no contract. There's no really termination fee
They have nationwide coverage cdma and gsm and as you would expect from any jupiter broadcasting sponsor
They got a great control panel an excellent dashboard that gives you full control
Over your account your minutes your messages and your megabytes. You can get instant snapshots of what you used
Exactly what you can expect to pay at any given moment
They have an app on the android or the iphones that allows you to manage all of that and speaking of devices
They got a bunch that you can buy directly from ting or a whole bunch that they support
ting offers cdma and gsm networks
Which means they support a lot of devices and they have incredible customer service when I signed up for ting
I didn't realize I could activate my phone through their website because that seemed impossible back then but now it seems obvious really
I should have known better
Noob, but I called their customer service. Have you ever had to deal with ting's customer service? They're pretty great
They are great. Actually, I have it myself, but like not everyone some people I've recommended ting to have and I'm you know
I was like, okay. Well, how did it go? Never surprised it goes great. It does they're just so they're so friendly
I actually got a postcard once from one of the reps I talked to oh, see there you go
That's the extra mile. I left an impression. What can I say?
And it's just it's pretty great people love ting and when you switch over you get great customer service
So anyways, I called up the first time and uh, I was I was blown away by how how simple how straightforward
They will communicate with you. And uh, then yeah, I did get a postcard afterwards
So that really happened
It's smarter than unlimited because you just pay for what you use if you use less you pay less
And that's why the average ting bill is just 23 per month. I was paying
120 dollars for a couple of lines back in the day for three lines before I switched to ting
And now i'm paying usually around 40 something a month
linux.ting.com
That's linux.ting.com to support the show and get 25 off a device or 25 in service credit
If you bring a device linux.ting.com now that 1804 is out. We've got to start talking about 1810 obviously
Uh, that's what everybody does right and you can blame mark shovelworth for this actually because he just posted
Queue the cosmic cuttlefish
That's adorable
Super adorable. I'm in love already
I like that. Uh, he says it's time to start talking about 1810 because really it's really it's time to start laying the groundwork for
The next lts thing's got to keep happening 2004 2004
Oh, man, it's right around the corner
but in the meantime
We focus on 1810 and so he says he wants to take this early opportunity in the lts cycle to talk about
Things that he's starting to care more about and what a particular feature he'd love to see
People focus on is security. I like the way mark phrases
Like you guys are all going to work on whatever you're passionate about in ubuntu
But if we had one thing i'd really love to see everybody that everybody could incorporate into whatever project they're working on. It's security
Um, he says i'd feel great about that if we could systematically for everyone who uses ubuntu
Improve their confidence in the security of their systems and their data. It's one of the very true
true few unifying themes across every use case
That is that is so true that you know
It is it's something that the cloud people care about it's something the desktop people care about
It's it's something that all of the different uh aspects of ubuntu care about
I mean we need it to be to keep being a serious operating system, right? Especially yeah
Yeah, especially when it's uh, the core of so many services now and then uh mark
not putting the keyboard down for a moment wrote on the uh,
Ubuntu mailing list for development that it's time to start considering the new installer ubiquity next generation or ng
He says now let's start with a trip down memory lane
MDZ and I were shooting the shooting to the moon on a saturday afternoon in my apartment in london when the idea for ubiquity formed
It seemed crazy a live cd that would let people try out ubuntu and then drive straight into the install
Seemed like that was science fiction, but it quickly took shape on a piece of paper that i'd rather wish i'd kept
Now 14 years later
We have new kinds of magic to draw on and perhaps ubiquity ng could take advantage of them first
We have curtain which knows how to take a description of a machine and do the right thing partitioning
installing and cleaning up
In fact curtain is neat and efficient and it's super fast. So we have the beginnings of what also could be an html5 installer
Third we have electron which is an html5 app framework used by the world of world-class developers like skype
Spotify and a ton of great apps on ubuntu fourth
We have snaps which are just amazing
Amazingly tasty ways to get the latest bits in the hands of your community
So who is game to sketch this further? So we may be seeing a new installer in the works
Wow seems to be uh in the in the cards in the air. What's the phrase there? Everybody's got new installer ideas
I i'd say it's probably time
I i'd say anybody in the mumble room have thoughts on ubuntu replacing their installer good or bad
As long as it can be customized to what the individual flavors need then yeah, i'm all for it
Yeah, definitely something that keeps the flavors in mind
I mean
I guess if there's momentum right if people want to do it if there's enough momentum and energy
Uh to see the process through what do you think about it being based on electron?
Well if it's easy, I I guess I I will as long as it doesn't have a drawbacks
Right as long as it works if they can make it
Reliable enough for all types of devices that would need to be installed on then if the end product's good
I'm, all right with it. I would love it to have a um
Anchor's back end interface that I could use on the command line when i'm installing it on a server somewhere or something like that
Or make sure you know like the bootstrap still works cleanly and all those things. I'm sure that won't change but
All right, wes i'm going to install so it's another app pick i'm installing it right now on the show
I'm going to see if I can't break my computer live on the air
So this one's a snap that I saw going across the twitters and it's called stress
Ng and it's a tool to load stress on a computer. So if you have for some reason
The desire to punish the subsystems of a computer like the cpu cache disk memory
Your socket connections io the scheduler stress ng is a rewrite of an old stress tool
That has many additional features such as specifying different operations your bogo operations
And uh executions of metrics stress verification on memory compute operations that are more stressful things like that
So I just went installed it here on my machine
And i'm gonna go ahead and give it a go stress ng we're gonna kick it off to the uh-oh
Oh, no, this is no good. Some
It says here that some io tests may fail
Uh, I don't know now i'm thinking maybe this isn't a good idea dangerously chris. Come on now
I don't know wes
I don't know. It seems like this might be a bad idea to do to my production system during the show
I'm starting to get cold feet, but it's a pretty cool
App, I love punishing systems when they're in here for review or seeing what a new droplet can do and things like that
So stress ng. Wow, it's got a lot of options. Holy smokes
I I here's a here's a flag for you though. Maybe this is the one to run with
So you run stress ng and then tack tack aggressive
Yeah aggressive. I like the sounds of it. Also. There is an option called dash-dash ignite cpu
Which will try to make your cpu run as hot as possible
That actually could be useful for other things as well. There's also things in here about just smashing the ios for instance
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, it reminds me of that. Uh, you can smash your your disk ios
Uh, you can try to make your system timeout dash-dash thrash
Amazing. Oh, yeah force all pages and cause a swap thrash. That's amazing. That's
Have at this. I think this is going to be good. Oh some crypt some cryptograph stuff in here, too
Yeah, I could play with this for a while. All right. I'll play more with it. It's so easy
It is it's pretty cool. Don't break anything please this come on now just snap install the shows to do. I know right?
I know that's what I was just thinking. Maybe I shouldn't and then one more pick. I told you we're putting a bunch of insane
How did you find so many good things? You did it? It was really you that found this one
I found that last one, but you found this one castro. We've mentioned it once before way back in
The past maybe like six months ago. I'm not quite sure but it's castro is a command line podcast client
Those are all the words that we love right here on linux unplugged. Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm
So you can subscribe to all of your favorite jupiter broadcasting shows which is obviously all of them from the command line
And i'm actually using something similar to this. Although I think i'm going to switch to castro
for
Downloading reruns and things like that for like our automated idea. Mm-hmm
Just subscribe to the rss feed get it automatically and it just drops it in a directory
And then I got a player that reads that directory
And if you've got python already loaded on your system pip install and I sure do castaro castaro
That's probably not castro. It's probably castaro c-a-s-t-e-r-o
I don't know man. All I know is the command line podcast clients are the win. You're already on the command line
Command line music players are already great. Like this is just the perfect thing. Mm-hmm
I thought about I've thought about trying to get as many things like back into the command line as possible not because it's retro
But just because it's really convenient to have them running like persistently on a droplet
Yeah, right. I just did a tmux session. Yeah done. Yeah a tmux session, huh?
That's cool. That's fancier than what I was doing. That's good idea actually
I hadn't I don't know why I hadn't even I haven't even made that connection
I like having uh, I like also having the drop down terminal so the stuff I can put in the drop down terminal
I'm always about that. Oh, yeah, right got the ua going on the plasma desktop. Boom. So yeah, go check out castaro
Uh don't come to me for pronunciation folks come to me for the pics but not for the pronunciations of them for that
You gotta go to west pain. He is a pronunciation expert. That's right. That's what I say official official people come in town
I say go if you go if you want to if you want to know where to go in seattle get good food
Talk to wes and if you want to know how to pronounce something you got to talk to wes
It's a lot of work, but i'm happy to do it
Somebody's got to right maybe you'll just butcher it for everyone. I'm gonna have to bring you along with me
Because i'm going down to texas linux fest in a couple of weeks and if you're in the austin area
on the weekend of june at uh, uh, eighth and ninth
Come down and say hi to me at texas linux fest i'm going i'm going to be in austin texas
June 8th and 9th hanging out. It's the first time i've ever been i'm making it official right now on the show
I haven't even really made it. This is like the first official time. I've even said anything about it. What a commitment
Look at you all the way to texas. I know it's gonna be great
Which probably means the shows are gonna be crazy for a few weeks while i'm on the road, but time for adventure
Mm-hmm. It is it's that time of year and i've always wanted to go down to texas linux fest
And I had such a good time in texas last year. I was just looking for a good reason to go down
I'm, also going to go down and see our buddies from linux academy
And work with them on some of their production stuff. I have a suspicion that they're going to be
Some of their production stuff. I have a suspicion that you're just going to get all that all that tasty barbecue
Is am I right in this real the real motivator is to get levi back down to texas
Oh his homeland. Yeah, levi loves the sun
But yeah, once the dog gets to texas then barbecue then hang out with linux academy
And then hang out with the audience at texas linux fest. That's what is up
So if you're gonna be in the austin area june 8th or 9th, come have some barbecue with me
Maybe some brewskis. That sounds amazing. Come hang out with me and the linux fest guys
Is give noah a hard time for going to self instead. Yeah, I assume he's going to self instead because that's the
That's the really unfortunate thing is that it's at the same time self is so self in texas linux fest
That's the shape. I know what's going on
You got too much good linux in the world. Wow google io and redhat somewhat on the same day
And you got self and texas linux fest on the same day. Yeah, I could go i'll go say hi to alex jones
That seems like a great idea token run. That seems like uh, that seems like a really great idea
I've never installed gnu slash linux digital ocean do dot co slash unplugged go there to sign up and get a
100 credit when you create a new account and that'll last for 60 days when you go to do dot co
Slash unplugged its simplicity at scale spin up an entire linux rig in seconds
They've already got fedora 28 and ubuntu 1804 images good to go. They're updating their documentation
So everything reflects the absolute latest releases and with one click you can deploy an entire application stack
Or just the base rig and the real ninja combo with digital ocean
Is to take advantage of some of the built-in features of their excellent dashboard
For example, you can have dns and ssh keys already set up to go when that machine turns on
So within seconds of launching a new digital ocean droplet
I'm ssh-ing in with my key and my domain is already forwarding to digital ocean's name servers and bam digital ocean gets
It was assigned within seconds to my droplet. I'm up and running i'm using the real domain
I'm using something i'm going to have in production and as soon as I need to add more resources
It's easy to do so I added another 250 gigs to a droplet that i've been consolidating to in seconds
It's wonderful and they even cleverly name the device as do block storage
Uh, and so when I when i'm looking at it in in on the command line
And i'm looking at all the names of my devices. It's really easy to see. Oh, that's that's the 250 gigs
I just attached it just shows up right there and they've even labeled it for me and within seconds
I've added it to fstab and now it's mounted and it's it's brilliant because that's how I prefer to work
Digital ocean is my enterprise now
That's my data center with 12 locations all over the world 40 gigabit connections coming to the hypervisors ssds for every single rig
Linux runs the virtualizer kvm is the virtualizer
It's an ideal setup and go check them out because they're always adding new features new documentation
And new pricing like flexible droplets that are mix and match for the resources depending on your application
They also have cpu optimized droplets
If you've got some large compute workload and rigs with tons and tons and tons and tons of ram
Or you can just build something for five dollars a month. I just got done setting up a next cloud box
I'll tell you a little bit about oh, it's really nice. It's really nice. It runs so great
And it's just nice to know that it's under my control and I I really thought I really thought I would I would sort of
Scale back on some of that stuff as time went on and these things got easier to just go get some hosted service
No more than ever i'm building my own solutions and i'm using digital ocean to host it because
That part of it is so low friction that I can just get right to the work that I actually want to do
So get that $100 credit by going to do.co slash unplugged. It'll last for 60 days
Once you apply it to a new account, that's do.co slash unplugged
Now let's talk about the change coming to fedora atomic workstation
And this is going to lead us into some of the red hat summit news that we have
And it's uh, it's a rebranding. I suppose they're going from fedora atomic workstation to team silver blue
They're calling it a new initiative and they think it's a better realignment for the long-term goal
Of fedora workstation where they feel like workstation is terrible branding to begin with and they want to call it team silver blue
You can check out. Um, um, joe rezington did an interview with matt miller
From the fedora project in his new show late night linux extra where he goes into some detail about team silver blue rebranding
But that's sort of uh, that's sort of just a just a side note because there also is a lot of other things coming out
Of red hat summit that maybe are
Are bigger breaking news. So red hat summit is kicking off
It's 25th year if you can believe it and they're doing so with a big announcement with ibm
A big expansion between ibm and red hat's partnership and they announced it today. They're very excited about that
and ibm is going all in with containers on red hat enterprise linux and
And ibm is using red hat technology for their new ai and blockchain and internet of things solutions
One of those is probably gonna make a lot of money
And so red hat is probably pretty excited to be at the core of it
But the story that I am the most interested to share with you guys out of red hat summit
And this is the one that I think has some
Longer term ramifications and we've been wondering what was going to happen after the core os acquisition
Core os technologies are being moved into red hat container native products
And it looks like they're kind of doing a merger
They they write on core os.com with the acquisition of container linux. It'll be reborn as red hat core os
A new entry into the red hat ecosystem red hat core os will be based on fedora and red hat enterprise linux sources
And is expected to ultimately supersede atomic host
As red hat's immutable container centric operating system. Wow
I'm slightly disappointed. They didn't call it fedora core os
Yeah, okay, that's fun
I don't know what it means. I don't know what it means for um atomic
I don't I don't understand what it means for core os either
It sounds like core os and atomic are going away and we're getting red hat
core os
Is that the base then container linux is rpm os tree staying around what's happening?
Red hat core os will provide the foundation for red hat's open shift container platform red hat open shift online
And red hat open shift dedicated red hat open shift container platform will also of course continue to support red hat enterprise linux
For those that prefer its life cycle and packaging as the foundation for foundations to their kubernetes deployments
That's pretty thick and it seems like a huge huge development coming out of red hat summit
And I I don't know container linux will continue to provide a
container linux will continue to provide a fast free moving and automated container host and is expected to provide the basis for new operating system
projects from red hat
Seems like there is some something big happening between core os and atomic
So I don't feel any less confused than I did when they bought them. Yeah, I'm just gonna say they've got a lot of different
Initiatives coming out uh from red hat and that's kind of why I wanted to go down to the summit if it could have worked
off 25 years of summits
That's really they're in san francisco this year red hat surpassed 150 million customers. That seems like a big number, too
So big big developments coming out of red hat this week. You got red hat also, uh
Sharing like uh the success stories
They have an ai all of these all of these events are talking about ai so much machine learning
So, I mean I will say all of it is is confusion aside like it's great
There's a lot of really good technology here and it's cool. It it is exciting to see a lot of it continuing and good things
Will come hmm. Yeah when we were watching the build stuff yesterday
Uh, they had uh somebody up on stage that was deploying on a red hat enterprise server
So that was you know seeing that on microsoft stage
Yeah, and then uh, jj you just dropped a link in the chat room about uh, microsoft and red hat working together on a project
What's this is about? What is this about?
They co-developed the first red hat open shift
Uh jointly managed service. Oh, they say by extending our partnership with microsoft
We're able to offer the industry's most comprehensive kubernetes platform on leading public cloud providing the ability for customers to more easily harness
Innovation across the hybrid cloud without produce without sacrificing production stability
Open shift on azure will be a jointly engineered and designed to reduce complexity of container management
Red hat open shift on azure will bring flexibility speed and productivity
Huh, so that's the actual product is red hat open shift on azure. I see. Okay. All right
It's getting very incestuous in a way. It's so weird. It's so it's such a it's such a it's such a strange thud
It's like a re-bloom of all these different branded technologies that are intermixed right and red hat and microsoft getting all friendly
Yeah, and I know we got to get over it. I know we got to get over it, but it's still it's still
I guess everyone's just making that paper. Yeah, I suppose so i've i've been following, um, some of the red hat stuff
But not the traditional red hat angle i've been i've been getting really into fedora 28 since last week's release
So I decided to play around with it to just give it a brief review on linux action news
And in that process it sort of snowballed into me setting up a fedora atomic system and a fedora cloud system
And experimenting with what and how fedora atomic works, which is fascinating. Everything
Is is containerized if you want to install some management tools you install a container which might have another container that needs to pull down
Uh, and that's not necessarily a bad thing
It's just it's a different way of it's a different way of working and sometimes those containers have had issues
So it felt a little still fedora atomic still felt a little raw to me
So I started playing around more seriously with fedora 28 cloud because that felt like it was uh,
further along
And one of the things that is very very different from the last time I really messed around with uh,
Fedora or really red hat on the server is there is so much documentation now for how to do stuff. Really?
Yeah, there wasn't really a there literally was not a singular thing that I got stuck on that I couldn't within
Usually my first google attempt find the answer in the first link or two. That is impressive. Yeah, and I think that's
Especially as you're coming back to it, right? Like that is a very welcoming position
It was and it I think it felt like I was benefiting from the fact that
centos reddit enterprise linux and fedora are all sort of sharing similar command
Syntaxes like they're all using dnf. They basically all have the same stuff in the same place in etsy
It's really all kind of the same now now that they're all kind of caught up with each other and all using system d
Consistent base of yeah, just say what you want to say
So I you know every now and then would find a one-off guide to how to do it on centos and it just happened to work
On fedora, but for the most part I was finding guides on fedora and a lot of it was actually official
Project documentation. I really should give credit to the project here
A lot of it was on like official cockpit project websites or fedora project websites
It has really they've really upped their game. It has really improved the situation with documentation around fedora
Has really really improved and if you're somebody who
You can get pretty far but you forget like what what what do I need to go to do this or what's this command in fedora?
What how do what's even like what is the name of this package if you're capable of like searching on that stuff and getting answers?
I I think you'd be impressed with how manageable fedora 28 is and um
That extends into
A couple of other aspects of fedora and i've had a real ab comparison this week with free nas
And cockpit now, they're not initially comparable, but i'll explain so you might be familiar with when i've raved about cockpit on this show before
Cockpit dash project.org got a link in the show notes cockpit is server management
That makes it easy to manage fedora boxes red hat boxes. They say it's for all linux machines
I've only ever used it on fedora systems. Yeah, i'd like to kind of i'm going to try it on some
I will that would be fascinating. I will give you a tour of it after the show, right? It is
It's first of all, it's simple and easy to use
And and it makes it just you know makes it if you're not familiar with like um
Setting up docker or managing se linux. It makes those things very very approachable
One of the things that I super super super appreciate about cockpit is that it has a brilliant
Se linux troubleshooter. So you you know, for example, I went to go launch a next cloud container
And I wanted my next cloud container to store its data on block storage on digital ocean
So that way I could blow away the container deploy a new container and all of my data would be there
The container is ephemeral. The data is persistent
And se linux wasn't having this it was blocking it because that container wasn't supposed to be accessing that file system
And se linux caught that and it blocked it
But that was preventing my next cloud instance from starting and it I wasn't sure. Well, yeah, what the hell's going on?
Why isn't my why isn't my container starting? Oh, you know
Damn docker blah blah blah blah. Well, you know i'm looking around on cockpit, which uh was just me sort of just uh
I'm just gonna take a look around for a bit because I don't know why this container isn't starting and I look over and I see
se linux
So I click on the se linux thing and it's got categorized
Uh of the recent types of se linux alerts that it's discovered much like the gooey tools do on the fedora desktop
and it's got
Solutions on how to solve it with actual commands that I could run
To flag that stuff as okay in se linux and and mark it as okay in se linux
It gives me the actual commands to run to fix the problem
And when that doesn't work for some reason it doesn't work for me
To fix the problem and when that doesn't work for some reason it's got another brilliant feature
That is is great. It's got an off switch for se linux that disables it until the next realist restart
So you can be in the web interface you can hit this button
You can have that process execute on it's it's our sync job. It needs on the file system
and
You don't have to worry that you forget to ever turn se linux back on because worst case scenario you forget to flip that
Switch back on the next time you reboot it's back on
And you could disable it permanently, but I just think that was really really nice
But the other thing that really made using fedora as a server approachable to me
And this is where I make the comparison to free nose
There's no interference with cockpit when you're managing a fedora system
There's no interference between you
And what you do on the command line and what happens in cockpit?
If you start a service via cockpit
It can be stopped via the terminal
If an error occurs in the terminal
You can see it in the cockpit journal interface
If you make a tweak on the command line, like you add a user it's represented
In cockpit, they don't step on each other like it does in free nas like in free nas
You can ssh into a free nas box
And it's it's bsd, but it's not bsd. Like you know it. It's it's like a it's like a small
Strip down bsd
You could say optimized but yeah, you could different
Yeah optimize and the reality is you could make config changes in there that will be persistent while the system is running
But they lose and they're overwritten as soon as the system restarts or you change something in the gooey
They override each other constantly
And for me, it's got to be something where I can really lean heavily on the command line
And then if I want a gooey for remote administration or to look at your resource utilization
I can use cockpit
And uh using cockpit too
It makes it really really easy to deploy docker containers or start virtual machines
And it can search docker hub and so you can put in next cloud it can pull down the official next cloud docker image
And get it started for you and before it starts it'll ask you
Well, how do you want to do the network forwarding? What parts of your file system? Do you want it to get to?
What would you like me to do?
If this instance crashes, would you like me to restart it?
Would you like me to always restart it or only restart it if you haven't stopped it previously?
And you can go in there and set tunables like that as well
Like don't use too much cpu don't use too much memory and then you hit the play button
It starts up the container you decide you no longer want that
It's one click you destroy the container you pull down a new one you reattach it to your data
And you got a fresh system again
And that's what I started playing with this weekend
And through this process I ended up moving over a whole bunch of rigs that were running. Uh, one was an arch system
maybe two actually
and uh
Ubuntu 14.04 so I don't think there was a six there may be a 16.04 system in there that hasn't been moved yet. So
It was a smattering of arch smattering of uh older ubuntu systems that I needed to do something with that
They're just been getting neglected. So while you were talking about this I spun up a
1804 droplet and now cockpit's running. It's it's in the repository. You just apt install and yeah
There we go
That was easy that I wonder about and i'd be curious to see the ui is the way it works with cockpit on fedora
Is that like parts of cockpit are modular?
So if you want to manage the disks then you install that aspect of cockpit if you want to manage
Docker then you install that aspect of cockpit. So like there's individual components of cockpit. I see you can load or not load
I wonder is that is that true? Do you see multiple cockpit packages on ubuntu or do you see?
That's let me look do a little search there. I'd be curious to know that because shit
I'm gonna i'm gonna put that on my systems because the nice thing about cockpit is you can manage multiple systems cockpit bridge
Docker machines network manager. Yeah, that's it. That's it. Yep. Oh shoot. That's great. Well then
Then everybody should do this. So one of the things that I decided to do was consolidate down
To a single fedora 28 instance and you might be wondering why fedora why not centos?
Or reda enterprise linux or maybe 1804 with right? Why not that right? So I want I want to address that because
That was I think the linchpin decision that I made and it's based on a multi-year project that i've been testing behind the scenes
To sort of sort out where I wanted to go in the future and uh, I don't have a lot of these
But every now and then i've got like these three-year long projects that i've been brewing behind the scenes so that we can come
On the air and say i've been i've been skunk working this for a long time and this is what I found and so
That's one of these situations. That's what we're going to talk about next
So let's mention linux academy go to linuxacademy.com
Linuxacademy.com slash unplug to sign up for a free seven-day trial of a linux training platform you sign up
And you get access to everything it's nice and easy like that
It's a full feature training library with everything you need to learn about things that run linux and run it and linux runs on
Everything you need to learn and get hands-on experience self-paced in-depth video courses
Hands-on scenario based labs that spin up when you need them ushn learning paths, which are series of courses and content
Planned by instructors and speaking of instructors. They have few full-time human beings
Topic matter experts that are available to help
That's huge. Wow, that's huge
That really is that is a unique advantage
And they also have something that I think is brilliant for those of you who are busy a course scheduler system
You can pick a course time you set your time frame your learning goals and they'll help you stick to it
They also have practice exams and quizzes to help get you ready
Certification training which are courses created specifically to prepare you for exams to get the big certs
Of course, they've got mobile apps and study guides like lesson audio personal notebooks and other tools that help you study while on the go
They're always adding new features, too
They added 70 plus new courseware challenges and all other kinds of content to linux academy
Just last month and they're rolling out new stuff all the time and you can try it out seven days for free
When you go to linux academy.com slash unplugged linux academy.com slash unplugged to support the show and sign up for a free
Seven-day trial big. Thank you linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program go try out those hands-on labs take advantage of that platform
So fedora cloud has been kicking around in this in the back
Well really on digital ocean droplets, but I was going to come up with some some great story
But no really just on digital ocean droplets fedora cloud, uh, I think since they announced it in fedora 24
I don't remember when it came out, but it started as a fedora
23 22 system kind of got refactored around fedora 24 and since then
I've been running mb and nextcloud on and off on this system in production on and off for years now since really around fedora 22
Fedora 24 kind of did a big revamp and now with fedora 28
I can report that I have successfully been able to upgrade that box to every single release of fedora
I have drugged that box from the 22 days all the way up now to 28
and in that time
Nothing is broken
Not a single failure to update
Never has my nextcloud instance gone down. Never has my mb instance been broken. Wow, that's
That's some uptime. And I the reason why I wanted to do this is I said to myself I cannot use fedora
in production if I have to
roll the dice
And worry that every nine or ten months or so
I'm gonna break my system
And I thought well what i'll do is i'll put a couple of things that
That would be a pain in my butt if they go down but aren't going to wreck my day, right?
Doesn't stop shows from going on air. It's not right, but you still need yes, exactly
And so that was sort of the sweet spot for this job and I thought it's enough where i'll use it
But not enough where I will swear off the door if it breaks and um
I when I don't know when I when I did the update to 28 on that son of a bitch and it still didn't break
I sat back and went what the hell am I so worried about i've got snapshots. I've got backups
I'm putting all of this stuff in containers anyways, and all of the data is living on block storage
What do I care? And so um, that's when I started playing with fedora atomic and 28 cloud
I did a fresh cloud install of fedora 28 after I played around with atomic and I did just that I
I detached the block storage from the old 22 that had been brought all the way up to 28
Moved it over to the new 28 instance
installed cockpit
Loaded up docker
Set up a fresh next cloud instance connected to the old next cloud data
Same thing with mb and now I think I think i'm actually going to go even further
Uh and that when that worked that's when I went well then
Why don't I just add more ram and cpu to this system and just shut down these three other droplets?
Yeah, and move them all over if I put it all in containers. I have the data on block storage. I've got backups enabled
Uh, I mean it was just like this is really really great
And I thought I would just mess around with one or two things by the end of the night
I had everything moved over and i've also ended up setting up qo notes again where it's sinking back to my next cloud instance
Which is amazing. It's just been great
And that is slick. So i've moved i've moved over. Uh, my quosel backend is now, uh living in a uh, is living in a container
There is some usenet programs that are now living in a container. There is an audio stream process that is living in a container
There's an mp4 backup process that's living in the container you container hipster you i'm going crazy with these things on this fedora 28 system
It really seems like you uh, you're empowered to to maintain and to like set up your systems now
It seems like you kind of you came to a lot of systems that have been running for a long time
Not documented not easy to figure out what was happening. Yep. Yeah now it's clear and easy
It is really nice because using fedora. It feels very um professional grade
Not that and i'm not taking away anything from any other distribution just you know going into it
Sometimes I have bad experiences and it's like oh man, this is amateur hour
I tend not to share those sometimes but you know, I get very critical like this is ridiculous. I can't believe they ship this
This is embarrassing
I think we had a conversation about that earlier today when it came to yes
We did the other thing I was comparing it to recently anyways, uh fedora cloud is something a little different though
It's it's images that are really not meant to be ever installed on bare metal
They're really designed to run in a virtualizer
Um, they also make docker and vagrant images available
But you don't really just go get the image and dd the iso to a thumb drive
It's really something that is deployable by your cloud provider and it's a very bare minimal install fedora cloud
It doesn't really have much of anything, but everything's just dnf install away
You have your basic tools, you know, you can get nano in seconds. So everything will be all right
Right everything that you need is there or if not, it's it's right there you bastard
And so it's it's really simple to just dnf the couple of things you might need to get off the ground
and because the web services and the I set up also, um,
A mariah db server, uh, these are all in containers. So i'm not even using dnf
so the the core fedora 28 cloud install is
Is super minimal. It's the base fedora 28 cloud
With a couple of modifications to the ssh config and a couple of additional packages for cockpit and docker
And the rest is all running in these containers
which are destroyable
and um have their data stored outside the docker image
and that really was the
uh, just perfect for me because I I I can manage every once a year upgrading this fedora box
It works fine. And as long as my applications stay fresh i'm happy there, too
It was surprisingly pro. I think it might even be a sweet spot for you where it's it's not rolling
It's not arch, right?
You don't have to update it every week to stay safe
But it's also not a four-year lts where by the time you've come back to it your needs have changed
You've forgotten what you did or there's been a lot of different changes in like available software
One year might just be the nice cadence where you stay fresh
Yeah
Also, it does a lot of small defaults that I just don't really care to fiddle with anymore
like the ssh config is uh root login is turned off by default and
It only accepts key logins
Se linux policy is not intensely, um too stringent, but it's it's a
It's a reasonable default that I probably wouldn't have set up myself. The base package selection is just right
Um, which I wouldn't have had the expertise to respin a fedora. I could have done an archer ubuntu
Sure, but not a fedora one and um, the thing that put it over the top was the combination of the super clear
easy to find documentation and the
Totally solid implementation of cockpit. I really put it over the top for me
I hope you're not allergic to bees west. You're not allergic to bees. Are you? No, I am not
Hey, we got a visitor in the studio. Yeah, we do. Hey, buddy. We got a really big wasp in the studio right now
I don't know. I don't know what we're gonna do about that. We'll just keep going on. Hopefully no one's ready
Yeah, right. He is allergic to him. Anyways, I wanted to share that with you and I also wanted to share if you um,
Are considering trying out some nextcloud
Which if you have q own nodes and you do that nextcloud back end it is some sweet evernote killing magic
Check out uh flockus f l o c c u s
Which syncs your firefox bookmarks to nextcloud bookmarks and what's really kind of nice about it
Is you can sync just one folder of your firefox bookmarks if you want
That's nice, which is actually exactly what I do
I have like a current weeks bookmarks that are just for things for this week
And that's what i'd love to sync to nextcloud. So that's what i'm doing
Um, you do have to have firefox 57 and you can't be using I think the built-in firefox sync
So that is the downside to it, but it was kind of cool and i'll have a link to it in the show notes
It's uh f l o c c u s
all in all, um
I guess what I what I wanted to convey is
If you've been skeptical about using fedora in production
I'd say give it a go for a while do like I did do a little test do a skunk works
See if it works for you
Obviously, there's so many great choices that i'm not trying to switch anybody
But I was really impressed and I did think it was kind of funny to be sitting there like
I'm loving kubuntu on my workstations and i'm loving fedora on my servers. Yeah, I had a fedora server
I think it started at 17. It went to maybe 21 then it you know ended up switching things up
But yeah, it was it was really stable. Yeah, I remember when uh
When I was really stuck like in a position
I felt stuck at least of trying to support reddit enterprise systems really before they even incorporated yum
Um, but around that time it I really I really grew to sort of dislike me managing redhat systems and I and I thought
Apt and debian were so and then later ubuntu were so much simpler. So saner defaults easier to update easier to maintain
That I went into it with I think that's why it took me
Years of really trying this out before I would accept that it was possible to do it because I kind of had a bad taste
from my sysadmin days
You know just sitting there having to man. I mean, do you feel that way with the systems you manage in your day job?
do you feel like the redhat systems are more of a pain in the arse to manage than the
especially if you don't have like a enterprise subscription where you get the nice fancy centralized management, it's just
You know, I think it's gotten a lot better. I think I think these days it is quite reasonable
I like the security story a lot on redhat style systems
Yeah, I felt that too. I felt that way too. I felt like oh, okay
Yeah, especially now right especially if you're if you're running containers or or any of the other solutions
Application availability like I I don't necessarily have to install it with with dnf if I can get you know
If it's crucial it apt or dnf doesn't really matter if you're doing it all through containers
And then most of it's still there right like 90 is in the repository. It's just those last 10 miles and that's
That that 10 that's well covered. I think what you just nailed it is having all this stuff moved into containers is
Is really kind of making the underlying os a lot less relevant to me
And so then it's like well who's getting that little implementation right that that minimal shim that I need who's getting that right?
And uh, that's that's a competitive space for distributions to to try to figure that out right now. I think it's very competitive
Yeah, right, especially that's like it's the container os or it's some tiny vm os that lives in a droplet or ec2 instance
You want it to be tuned well and just work?
So this minimal layer is something that I think is going to be like the big area of growth for distributions
Google I don't really think as part of io, but they just announced their own kind of container runtime
I think you saw this. Uh, we were chatting a little bit about it, uh in slack the other night
Um the g visor remember this yeah g visor g visor is sort of along these same lines
It's an open source sandbox container runtime. And again, it's about kind of making the underlying linux os
irrelevant
I think that's worth thinking about for a minute
Like what does that really mean?
If all of a sudden the distribution you're using doesn't really matter anymore
And maybe the fact that it doesn't even need to be linux anymore. So this is from google's uh,
Uh, uh, um, what do they call this google blog.com I guess and they're open sourcing g visor a new kind of sandbox that helps
Provide secure isolation for containers while being more lightweight than a virtual machine
G visor integrates with docker and kubernetes making it simple to run sandbox containers in production, but it's not a container
Applications that run in traditional linux containers access system resources in the same way that a regular application does by making system calls
Directly to the host kernel the kernel runs in a privileged mode that allows it to interact with necessary hardware
And then returns the results to the application with traditional containers
The kernel imposes some limits on the resources that the application can access these limits are implemented
Through the use of linux c groups and namespaces, but not all resources can be controlled via these mechanisms furthermore
Even with these limits the kernel still exposes a large surface area that a malicious application could attack directly
Of course vms are too much overhead too much bulk to emulate the entire hardware stack
So enter g visor a lightweight container slimmer than a vm
That maintains similar levels of isolation as a vm
The core of g visor is a kernel that runs as a normal unprivileged process
And is capable of supporting most linux system calls
I like the one way that described it think about it as implementing linux by way of linux
So it's just a use a regular user space process
That is an implement acting as a kernel and implementing a subset of the all of the kernel apis
So they've they've put a kernel in my kernel, you know, I mean not I mean so why I guess for isolation purposes
I guess they just answered that but their kernel inside this g visor environment is written in go
Which they say was chosen for its memory and type safety
And just like within a vm the application running within g visor sandbox gets its own kernel and its own set of virtualized devices
Distinct from the host and other sandbox. Yeah, it's like a very minimalized set of what a vm might do
But without all the hardware aspects and it provides the kernel. So from the application side, you're still just doing software
You're not worrying about running your own kernel
It provides the kernel but it implements a very minimal set because that's that's been one of the biggest flaws with containers
Right is that even though they are contained in many ways a lot of vulnerability showed up because there's a huge amount of sys
Calls that we have to defend against if you can instead implement safe minimal set. That's the aim here
Then you have a lot a lot less surface area. Yeah
and it also sort of
Prevents you from writing directly to that dirty linux, you know now you can target the g visor environment
And they could make g visor available for fuchsia in the future. They can they can make g visor run on free bsd if they wanted
Uh g visor can be thought of as an extremely para virtualized operating system with flexible resource footprint and lower fixed cost than a full vm
Comes at a higher price per system call overhead and some application compatibility though. So those are the downsides
see this this this
Idea of running your applications in containers is the future like there is when we talk about like is that in the distros repo?
I love the aur
Drop in the bucket compared to what's on docker hub drop in the bucket. Everything's on docker hub
And so here's how it works
Now when I spin up a next cloud container
I'm also spinning up a mariah db and i'm connecting the next cloud container to the mariah db container
So that way my database is in one container my next clouds in another container my qualsal cores in another container
And uh, they can all talk to the database container if I if I choose right? That's one thing that they have an advantage
I was right they're thinking about and are used to construct systems, right?
It turns out oftentimes you need those and it's not just a command line tool that sits by itself
Yeah, and so now I don't think about getting the packages. I don't think about dependencies
I think about well, what containers do I need and a lot of times they'll pull down dependent containers, too. So it's um,
I don't know. It's a totally different way of managing software and it makes linux a bit less relevant
Which is sort of the creepy thing about it
You know, I mean like it really does linux is kind of just an implementation detail
Yeah, because you can put docker on mac os you could put gvisor potentially on mac os
I don't know how much of linux kernel is dependent on but it seems like that might be possible
Especially if at the application layer they're isolating that stuff out. So in the future they could yeah
How much does this become a platform? Yeah, I don't know. It seems like it is a platform in itself
It is a busy week for the enterprise with microsoft and red hat and google announcing a bunch of this services stuff
Um and linux is playing a surprisingly large role in all of it
It seems like a weird time though because there's a lot there's a lot of these efforts that are
that are open source that are fit a lot with our fundamentals but
Feel somewhat separate like it's its own special subset of open source
That's like enterprise open source and two giant teams somewhere use it
Yeah, it also feels like we have several things going in slightly different directions in this regard
You know, you got what red hat's doing with core os you got g visor out there
You got what microsoft's doing with hyper-v and and special hyper-v environments
and um
You still got rocket out there doing its thing. Mm-hmm. And of course that you've have you heard the word about zones, Chris?
Zones are the word
Uh zones and jails haven't you heard about the have you heard the good news about jails free bsd at first west
Don't never forget
All right, well, uh
One more tease there for texas linux vest if you're going to be in the austin area towards the end of june
Or no towards the beginning of june june 9th and 10th or whatever it is
Come say hi. Come say hi eat copious amounts of barbecue. Hang out with me. Come say hi to the folks at linux academy
He'll be the guy covered in barbecue sauce. Just look for that all the time
Like just in in if i'm not actively eating barbecue
So you can't tell if it's me look at my shirt if there's barbecue sauce on my shirt 90 chance
It's me plus the little barbecue covered dog, too
Oh, that would be adorable. Uh, mr. West. Why don't they go get more review? Where can they find a little more? Uh, wes
Oh, maybe you should check out tech snap data systems
I hear it's a weekly podcast that covers systems network and administration topics. It absolutely does
Hmm check that out tech snap dot systems. I'll give a plug ski for tech talk today
We've been staying on top of all of the news this week at tech talk dot today
Ange and I busting through the headlines. We've got one more coming up later this week if you want to check that out
And then why not join us live on tuesdays hang out here with the virtual love and then you stick around
Get the ask nor program extra special bonus and call him up ask him what's going on
See what he's up to see how he's feeling see if he watched unplugged just ask him that
Yeah, you see what see what he says just talk to him. Just ask him how he's feeling
Yeah
And uh, you get a linux you get a whole linux experience when you come here on tuesdays go to jblive.tv for that
And jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar for those lifetimes our website's linux unplugged.com
Linux unplugged.com slash 248 for links to everything we talked about and linux unplugged.com slash subscribe
For all the ways to get new episodes. Thanks for being here. See you right back here next tuesday
So
Man next week's gonna seem so low-key when all these events aren't going on. No kidding
It'll be a harder show
It was well this week I felt like was kind of hard because there's like so many things that aren't really interesting to talk about
But are important to the overall ecosystem. I feel like it was a rough episode really to be honest with you
Not not particularly happy with this one. Not particularly happy not not because you know anything we did well, I mean maybe but mostly just because
Uh, there's so much enterprise-y stuff and I feel like when we start talking dirty
Yeah, I feel like I feel like when we talk too much about containers people's eyes start to gloss over because
If you're not living and breathing this stuff, it's hard to connect with it
And yeah, we just want to talk about plasma. Come on. Yeah
Yeah, why are you stopping us?
I don't agree with that
Yeah, because you give the lots of views of the chance to try some things out and never heard of it because it's easy
I hope that's true
Uh, you know, I hope that's true
I I don't know. My sense is that most people find it to be sort of the least interesting aspect of the stuff we cover
But it is but it has so much momentum in that one space and it is so relevant to the marketplace like when you go to
To any trade event or you talk to anybody in the industry. It's only thing they're really thinking about. That's all they're talking about
It really has taken over the world