My latest Linux box has more connectivity
than a MacBook before 2021,
has a full QWERTY keyboard and it fits in my pocket.
It's the pocket popcorn computer.
It's still really early days with this thing,
but it's a handheld Linux device with a 1080p display
and a pretty nice battery that is user replaceable
and they're thin enough that you could legitimately
probably buy three or four off of Amazon
and just keep them in your backpack.
It's got a backlit RGB keyboard
and of course it runs Linux, right?
I mean, obviously it's not like fully done yet.
It still has a few rough edges,
but I really like it so far.
I just got it this morning and I've been playing with it.
How rough are the rough edges?
Well, they're rough.
I don't know if there's really even a full image
that's done yet for it.
So it's a pretty basic command line device.
Yeah, and there's some things like
if you turn the keyboard backlighting on
and then you don't turn it off before you shut it down,
it's stuck on.
But it's stuff that's like totally understandable
for an early device that seems solvable.
So it's not like I'm too worried about it.
And it's funny how nice it is to have something
that you can pull the back off of and replace the battery.
Like it just sort of, you run your finger under there
and it just kind of pops right off.
And it's within a second I'm in there
and I can swap the battery out.
What a concept.
I'm picturing an ASMR battery swap session here.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent.
Hello, gentlemen.
I'll be playing with this popcorn computer for a little bit.
I'll try to give you early impressions slash review next week.
But coming up on the show this week,
we've talked about a tricky problem in the past.
It's Linux fragmentation in a way that we don't normally consider fragmentation.
It's an actual tricky problem specifically for shipping applications
on Linux and desktop applications.
And there are several different types of technologies out there
to solve this problem from Docker and snaps and app images.
And Flatpak is one of the best known ones in our community and on the desktop.
But recently a very critical analysis was posted
that brings using Flatpaks into question to solve the various software
distribution problems we have on Linux.
In fact, you may have seen it.
The post was titled, Flatpaks are not the future or something to that effect.
So this week, what we wanted to do was work through some of those criticisms,
respond to the ones that make sense to respond to,
and maybe even discuss some of the changes already being made in Flatpak
that address some of those concerns.
So in just a little bit, Will Thompson, the director of Endless OS,
or the platform for Endless, over at Endless,
he's sort of like the king of Endless OS, will join us to discuss some of this.
And Endless OS knows their Flatpaks.
I'll have to get the number from Will, but it's a lot of Flatpaks.
So before we get into all of that, I wanted to say time appropriate,
greetings, virtual lug, hello, Mumble Room.
Hello, everyone.
Namaste.
We have quite the panel today, which is great,
because this is a topic that has been on all of our minds.
And it seems every solution we've come up with has its group of critics.
So I think it's going to be a good little chat.
Well, before we dive into the nitty gritty details of Linux packaging,
we do have a bit of early housekeeping to do today.
So a plan is coming together.
This is a big deal, and I wanted to give everybody a heads up as soon as possible.
We're really early days into this, so I don't have everything figured out yet.
But brace yourselves, we have some announcements to make.
We are moving our meetup for the new server christening party
to January 2nd, 2022.
We're going to have a new year, new server, and a new love party,
as well as the launch of a new Linux show.
So let's get this all out there.
We want you to come up to the studio on January 2nd, horrible virus aside.
We're going to have to keep our eyes on that,
because we just don't know at this point in time where that's going.
So we will be keeping an eye on the news.
We will try to stay flexible in that regard,
and we're going to have to ask that of you as well.
But right now, assuming things are OK, January 2nd, 2022,
LUP, from that point forward, will be live on Sundays.
This is a massive change, and it's not one that we're making lightly,
because we love our Tuesday time slot.
But we're moving a few things around.
We'll have more information in that regard soon.
That's one of the changes that's taking effect, starting January 2nd.
LUP will be live on Sundays the same time.
I'm going to make an effort, though, to participate in a live stream
on Tuesdays at the regular time most weeks.
I'll have more information on that soon.
So there will still be some live stream and mumble attendance at that time.
We'll also launch the new server. It'll be the christening party.
We'll have a potluck here at the studio with the audience.
And then what we'll do is we'll launch the server, we'll eat,
and then Brent, Wes, and I will go into the studio
and record a Linux unplugged, and our guests are welcome to stay here
and listen to us record the show live in the studio.
We both have a living room, which you'll be able to wait in,
and, of course, the studio itself.
And then that point forward, LUP will be on Sundays,
and we'll also have a brand-new Linux show that is launched
that I'll have more information on soon that I am super excited about.
So there's a ton of stuff going on.
New year, new server, new LUP, January 2nd.
Come hang out with us in the studio.
We will also try to live stream that party.
I don't know how the hell we will do that.
So it's like a 50-50 shot, but, you know, I'm willing to, like,
bring up some, like, a jitzy and set it up on a few devices
around the house or something.
We'll figure it out.
And if you are in the area or you can make it,
you're welcome to join us for the potluck and the new server christening
and the new LUP live day.
We can talk more about that, too, of course, in the post show.
You're always welcome to join us on Tuesdays
while we are remaining in this time slot.
I think we're going to be live every week for the rest of the year,
as far as I can figure, because LUP doesn't land on a holiday.
So we will be live for a few more Tuesdays,
and we would absolutely love to have you.
So check in on us.
Say goodbye, maybe, you know, if you're a Tuesday person.
And if you're a Sunday person, pencil it in.
Consider joining us.
And hopefully, hopefully, you'll love the new show
when it's launched and announced.
But I'll have more information about that later,
because we have a lot more to get into.
And hey, don't forget jupyterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar to actually find out when we're live.
Yeah, that's very, very handy.
So let's talk about one of the most popular solutions
to solve the Linux desktop problem.
And that is really that we have so many different distributions
with so many different library versions
and so many different this and that's.
Plus, you have a general requirement
to start sandboxing applications for security purposes.
If you want users to be able to download things safely online,
it'd be nice that those things are limited
in what they can do to a system.
And it solves a problem.
And Flatpak isn't the only one.
Snaps do this.
App Images do this.
In a lot of ways, just general containers can do this.
But today, we're talking about Flatpak.
And I like to think of it, for the end user,
it solves a problem where you can
be on an old version of Debian, and I
can be on a brand new version of Fedora,
but we can run the same application.
In a lot of ways, that's how it's going to impact end users,
ultimately.
But in a lot of ways, it also means
we have a way to preserve software.
It also means we can run new software on old systems.
And it gives users and developers predictability.
You can always expect that a subset of runtimes
will be supported and compatible.
So you actually have a versioned thing on the Linux desktop
that you can target.
So Flatpak solves those kinds of things with runtimes
and whatnot in there.
And it solves the sandboxing problem.
And it also lets vendors self-host their own repositories
and projects.
It does support commercial software.
And it also has a very popular distribution mechanism
through FlatHub that is being integrated into distributions
like Fedora.
But nothing is so perfect that it can't be criticized.
And the reality is there is quite a bit of criticism
out there about Flatpaks.
And the one that's really been going around this week
is a criticism of some of the design choices in Flatpak.
And one of them really comes down
to storage and just duplication of work and libraries.
Well, Will Thompson wrote a blog post this week
addressing this criticism.
And with Will's role at Endless, he's
pretty deep in this ecosystem and is definitely
one of the people to talk about this.
Will, welcome to Linux Unplugged.
Thanks, it's really great to be here.
Thanks for the invitation.
So you are the director of platform at Endless OS.
And I get a sense that means you're
pretty familiar with how many Flatpaks you guys ship
and the role of Flatpaks in the Endless distribution.
Is that right?
Yeah, I guess so, yeah.
I'm the director of OS these days.
Though it's a funny situation.
You'd expect from the name of Endless OS Foundation
we only do an OS.
We do other things as well.
But yeah, I'm responsible for the OS side of things.
The whole distro is based around Flatpaks.
We ship a small and shrinking number
of apps baked into the system.
And as much as possible is done with Flatpaks on top of that.
So a typical installation of Endless
comes pre-installed with 60, 80 Flatpaks out of the box.
My system right here has 160-something.
Wow, that definitely is more than anything
I've got in any of my boxes.
So you're really living the Flatpak lifestyle.
And so you must be just completely out of disk space
because one of the criticisms I've seen
is that once you have that many Flatpaks,
you have a hard drive full of runtimes and duplicate
libraries.
Is this true?
Well, it depends what you think of as full and big.
I ran some numbers on this.
This is one of the things that jumped out at me
from this post.
Because one of the first projects I worked on at Endless
was around a downloadable version.
And although part of the thesis of Endless OS
is that disk space, when you've pre-installed
lots of offline content, is much cheaper
than getting internet connectivity in a rural town.
So you better use the cheap disk space
to store as much as possible so you
don't have to download it later.
But then when you come to actually people wanting
to download it, you start looking a little closer
at how much space things are using.
From those 160-something apps on my system,
I can't measure the apps quite so easily.
Maybe I can.
We'll see.
We'll do it live.
Let's check.
But while I type and see if I can type fast enough
to type while I can talk.
Hey, real-time data is worth it.
Absolutely.
That's what we're all here for.
My fundamental point here is the data exists.
You just have to look for it.
So I'm running the numbers on the app.
So I have 56 gigabytes of Flatpak stuff installed.
And bear in mind, that includes a complete offline copy.
No, not a complete offline copy.
A large subset of Wikipedia in two languages,
loads of offline reference material in video form
and so on, as well as things you might normally
think about as apps.
And so that's 56 gigs of stuff, of which 8.7 gigs
is the runtimes, excluding some noise
around the edges for translations and stuff
like that.
So you may think that's 8.7 gigs of the runtimes for those apps.
That sounds like quite a lot.
But the basic OS is only 4 gigabytes.
So I think if you have a more conventional Linux system lying
around, it'll be interesting to look
at how much storage you have on there
for the apps versus the platform they depend on.
A little harder to separate them, perhaps.
Sure.
And if you install your first Flatpak,
maybe it's GIMP or Steam for some of our listeners,
you'll see a lot of runtime dependencies pull down.
And it does seem like, gosh, that's a lot
to install one application.
But then when you install your second application that
uses some of those same runtimes,
it's already on the system.
And the next app installs much quicker
and pulls down a lot less data.
Yeah, that's exactly right.
And I had a look at this as well.
And although there are a few stragglers
where there's one app using one runtime, which is not ideal,
the vast majority of the apps on my system
are shared across five runtimes.
There's more than 100 of them across just five runtimes.
So I think that if you amortize the cost out
across of all the apps using the same runtime,
it starts looking a little bit less scary compared
to the first impression.
That's exactly how I felt when I first
started using a lot of Flatpak applications.
When I went all in on Flatpak applications
for a few of my Fedora installs, that
was essentially my experience.
So let's move to some of the other criticisms
just to get your thoughts on it.
I think one of the other criticisms that resonated
for me was the sandbox still allows for essentially
full access to somebody's home directory
where a lot of their important information would be.
And it allows for writing to something
like the dot autostart directory, which could just
reinfect a user's system upon login over and over again.
And it makes the assertion that it's not
like Android and iOS, so therefore, it's
not good enough.
What are your thoughts on that?
Because this is obviously an important issue for Endless.
Yeah, it is.
I think it's a little bit more complicated than that post
set out.
Some apps can certainly write to those locations,
but the Flatpak sandbox, by default,
forbids all of that stuff.
There's a kind of tricky balance of pragmatism and security
here.
FlatHub would be useless if the apps didn't work.
And if the apps are written expecting
they can write to your whole home directory,
then they can't be made to work without that,
without someone going and modifying them.
And that may be intractable right now for various reasons.
But the preferred way for this stuff to work
is the apps don't have these kind of static holes
in the sandbox.
And they instead request access to just the resources
they need.
So that could be files.
It could be a webcam.
Hopefully, in the not too distant future,
your microphone will be treated the same way.
And one of the criticisms that I think is totally valid
is that previous versions of GNOME software
would claim that if an app is a Flatpak,
then it has a nice badge saying it's sandboxed.
And this gives you this false sense of security,
which I think is totally true, which
is why GNOME 41 software totally revamps this presentation.
So one of the big changes in GNOME 41
was a major revamp to GNOME software, which
Endless contributed a lot to.
And one of those changes is that now apps
have a kind of traffic light system of, are they safe?
Are they possibly unsafe?
Or are they unsafe?
And so this is based on sort of heuristics
about the kinds of these kind of sandbox holes
that they request access to.
So you can make a somewhat more informed decision.
I mean, whether people at the end of the day
would prefer to have Zoom work or not is another question.
But the information, I think, is a lot
less misleading these days.
And so if anything is shot in the other direction,
there's lots of apps which have the word unsafe near them,
which if you're taking a strict reading of this, they are.
So I guess the hope is that this can act as a stick
where the carrot is better APIs for getting out of the box.
Right.
I wanted to recommend a really nice graphical application
to review and modify Flatpak application permissions called
Flat Seal.
We'll have a link to this in the show notes.
And you can open that up.
It'll show you your Flatpak apps.
And it'll give you a really quick overview
of what they can and can't do.
And just even having that kind of information is nice.
And that's something that Flatpak enables.
So Flat Seal is that app.
OK, so, well, there was one other criticism
that I read in there that I thought, hmm, yeah,
that doesn't seem great.
And it's when he talks about namespace collision.
He says Fedora publishes a Flatpak of GIMP
as org.gimp.gimp.
But that conflicts with the official org.gimp.gimp
that is published by the actual GIMP developers on FlatHub.
And he says they should have solved for this namespace
collision problem ahead of time.
And now it's sort of too late.
Your thoughts on that?
Yeah, this is an interesting one, right?
Because one of the strengths of the Flatpak as a technology
is that it's possible to have multiple repositories.
And so Endless has its own app repo as well.
So Endless OS systems come pre-configured to install apps
and have apps pre-installed from FlatHub
and also from our own apps repository.
That's kind of mainly because we deployed and released
Endless OS with Flatpak before FlatHub existed back in 2016.
And over time, we've been careful to avoid
this kind of duplication.
So when an app appears on FlatHub,
we would remove it from EOS apps.
I mean, actually, in the early days,
often we would be submitting the app from our store
up to FlatHub.
And for exactly this kind of reason,
it makes for a pretty confusing user experience
when you're offered two apparently identical ways
to install the same app,
and they may actually be pretty different.
Maybe it wouldn't have been how I would have done it.
But the other side of it, I suppose,
is that because of the way the sandboxing works,
apps only have access out of the box
to data in a directory named for the app.
So you might hope that if you've installed
the Fedora version of the GIMP,
and then you think, oh, actually,
the version on FlatHub is fresher,
and you switch to that,
you would probably like it to not lose all your settings,
to not lose all of the dynamic permissions
you have given it through the portal system
in a future month, such a year,
when GIMP actually uses the portal APIs
that FlatHub already provides.
This is a problem,
and it's one we've tried to avoid endless
by just not doing this, if that makes sense.
Yeah, I mean, it does.
And that is sort of the nice thing is you can do that.
You can have your own repository.
There's also all these different types of apps, right?
I mean, it's one thing when we talk about GIMP
because it's free software
that multiple people can package
versus maybe some of the proprietary apps,
which the blog we're discussing also
maybe puts a little focus on,
and it might not have that problem with, say, Slack.
Yeah, it might not, and the nice thing,
one of the, I think, upsides of Flatpack
and the standard selection of runtimes
as an app developer is it gives you
the stable baseline to target,
and I think that's important
both for larger commercial developers
but also for small indie developers.
There are loads of apps
which have been written in the past year or so
which are popping up straight onto FlatHub,
and they haven't had to run the gauntlet
getting through, you know,
someone has to painstakingly submit them
to, you know, 20 distros or so.
So, yeah, I think one of the most interesting examples
is OBS, the live streaming software.
But backing up a bit, most apps on FlatHub
are maintained using a Git repository
on the FlatHub GitHub org,
with one historical exception has been Firefox.
The Mozilla, when they make a new Firefox release,
they publish the same official binary
directly into FlatHub,
so it's the same bytes
that you can download from their website,
which has its ups and downs,
but one of the ups is that it's got
all of the official Mozilla API keys baked into it.
And FlatHub now has, or is about to have,
I forget which, the second such app,
OBS, the live streaming studio software,
will now be published directly to FlatHub.
And again, it has, for the first time,
other than the Ubuntu package,
so I suppose the second time,
but non-Ubuntu users can get
an officially supported version of that
that has the API keys baked into it
to access various web services
that community source builds don't get.
And by publishing it to this one place,
they can reach all of the districts.
That's really exciting to hear, actually.
I think the other general criticism
that really kind of comes down to philosophy,
and not really a technical criticism,
it's common in our community,
and it's one that our community
is particularly quick to go to,
and that is just a general criticism
around the complexity of all of this.
It's getting so complex
that it's getting beyond the scope
of an average user's ability to understand,
and therefore, it's a negative thing.
What are your thoughts on that?
Well, who is your average user?
The technology seems,
some of it is pretty complicated.
The way that the portal APIs work
to securely pass access to a single resource
from the host into the Flatback is,
yeah, that's certainly more complicated
than just opening a file on disk.
But I think we all here, perhaps,
and I'm pretty sure the author of this post agrees,
that actually sandboxing is a thing we really do want.
We do want this fine-grained,
user-interactive runtime permission system
that requires the app to make Flatback-specific
API calls to activate permission dialogues.
I'm quoting directly from this blog post
because I agree, and that is what Flatback provides.
It has that.
So this is a nice point.
We agree on this.
This is good.
And you need some complexity that you don't have
with just simple file system access to enable that.
But one of the things that works well
with Flatback for EndlessOS is that it makes,
but by really wholeheartedly adopting it,
it actually makes the whole platform simpler
to administer, quote unquote,
particularly if you're not the kind of person
who essentially wants to administer a computer.
You just want to use it.
So Flatback uses OS Tree, which is this,
it's a bit like Git for computer programs,
or Git for file systems.
One of the things that works really well in EndlessOS
is that we've really adopted Flatback wholeheartedly.
Flatback is a footnote about podman containers,
but all apps on the system from a user
who doesn't know what a terminal is, is perspective.
They're all coming from Flatbacks
or they're baked into the OS.
And the OS is just like Flatbacks are,
it's distributed as a single immutable blob.
You can't add packages or remove packages from EndlessOS.
It is a single unit and it gets updated atomically
using the same duplication for updates as Flatback provides.
You can roll back to the previous version,
which is kept around in case of something terrible.
And so this actually makes for a really simple system
that for more than half a decade,
EndlessOS systems have been automatically updating
if they're online, both the OS and Flatbacks.
If the network connection is not metered,
this happens automatically in the background and safely.
So the resulting complexity for a user,
I would claim is actually less.
You have one place to get your app.
You have one button to hit to install it.
If you press Remove, it's gone.
You can't break the OS.
I would say that's been my experience too,
is there may be more going on under the hood,
but it has, from an end user's perspective,
especially when I'm using something like
GNOME Software and Fedora 35, it is very simple.
Will, if you wouldn't mind,
I wanted to give Wimpy a chance to jump in here
and a couple other people,
because I know they've got a few questions.
So Wimpy, go ahead.
Hello there.
This is a fascinating conversation.
And I read the blog post that you're sort of citing
in all of this.
And I suppose I'm coming out in support of not just
Flatpak, but, you know, containerized application delivery
as a philosophy as a whole.
The whole argument that it is complicated for people
to install applications using insert name
of your favorite, you know,
containerized application platform.
And by the way, I'm excluding app image from that
because it is not that.
It's bunkum.
It's simply not true.
The data that I had available when I worked at Canonical
showed us that overwhelmingly,
the people installing applications on the Ubuntu desktop
were doing it through the software center,
which was a rebranded version of GNOME Software.
And application installs are but a click away,
regardless of whether that's a Flatpak or a Snap.
And it could not be easier.
And all of that ability to do atomic updates
and reliable updates and having a single source,
authoritative source for application delivery
is far simpler than it ever was in the past
with, you know, scattershot copper repositories
or PPAs that you have to, you know,
tag on the end of your operating system
or, you know, the AUR on top of Arch.
So I completely reject that argument
that it's complicated for new users
because it could not be simpler.
I'm curious, maybe what do you think?
Because part of the thing in this blog post
is that we're talking about a lot of different groups.
There's the user perspective,
but then there's also the distribution perspective
and then the application developer.
And it seems like to some extent,
this post is maybe arguing, you know,
not necessarily for PPA,
but for the standalone simpler installations.
Maybe you're downloading a tar file
or you're running a standalone installer in the Windows way.
Curious how that rings to you, Wimpy.
I feel like it doesn't matter
which of the contemporary packaging systems you're utilizing.
Their integration with those software services,
those software delivery services, make that easy.
And the core principle,
certainly from a SNAP perspective, was this.
If you look at what popularized
in the mainstream app stores, which is mobile phones,
those applications are not curated, packaged,
or maintained by a group of volunteer packages.
Those applications are packaged and delivered
directly to those stores by the application developers.
So it's positive news that the authoritative publishers
of things like Firefox and OBS Studio,
and I know OBS Studio has been getting
a massive leg up from the fine work from George
and all that he's been doing in OBS in the last year or so.
It's fantastic work.
The fact that Flat Hub is pivoting to vendor published apps
rather than community maintained apps is the right move
because there are tens of thousands of applications
in our distributions repositories maintained by volunteers.
There are millions of applications in the app stores
for the mobile platforms.
And one of the big differences is
there are millions of bits of software on GitHub,
but they are not in our application repos.
If we pivot to a developer publishes their app,
that scales far better than spreading millions of apps
across a few hundred enthusiastic maintainers.
I couldn't put it better.
I think one of the kind of pragmatic things
about Flat Hub historically has been
you've got to start somewhere, right?
And so a larger proportion than I would like
for the apps on Flat Hub are community maintained.
And I think that is changing.
And the work like, yeah, George's work
on helping to get OBS Studio working well as a Flat Pack,
integrating well with all the modern portals
and getting this publication,
this first party publishing working is really superb.
The other interesting development in this area
is that Flat Hub has just put out a call
for contractors to work on Flat Hub.
It's on the Flat Hub discourse.
I can pop a link.
Maybe I can send a link over to pop in the show notes.
So the Gnome Foundation supports Flat Hub
with various things.
And they're looking to contract someone to work on,
or someones to work on a short term project
around these kinds of things, around identity,
being able to verify that yes, this app is published
by the person who or people or company that make the app.
To the end of being able to accept payments
to the app uploader, not to Flat Hub,
which is something that's alleged in this post,
to the app uploader.
Because if you can make a vibrant place
that individual developers, companies, organizations
can publish their own software straight to users,
the mobile platforms have shown us
that people use orders of magnitude more apps there
than they do on their computers.
Both because they're available
and because you can install them trivially and fearlessly.
Hopefully this project can be made to happen
and be really exciting to see it happen.
Yeah, that is some great insight, Will.
Thank you so much for taking some time late in your evening
to join us and discuss some of this.
I feel like I've learned a lot.
And I just wanted to say also thank you
for taking the time to originally post your response
because that's really what kicked off the conversation
between Wes, Brent and myself
and led to kicking this off on the show.
So again, thank you for all your work there,
Endless and for joining us.
Thanks very much for having me.
It's been a pleasure.
I'm glad to have sparked some useful conversation.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
And you go there to support the show.
Linode is cloud hosting done right under your control
with 11 data centers worldwide.
And they've been at this for 18 years
building the absolute best experience
for running applications on Linux in the cloud.
If you wanna build something yourself
or deploy one of their many one-click stacks,
Linode has excellent options for you.
And the performance.
The performance is incredible.
They've been rolling out MVME PCIe storage.
It's so blazing fast.
And I just simply wouldn't host
everything that Jupyter Broadcasting has built
in the last couple of years on Linode
unless it was super fast.
You know, I'm a performance hound.
Linode has screaming fast systems.
If you need fast CPUs, they've got AMD EPYC processors.
If you need super fast storage.
And of course they can always help you
dial in the right price to performance.
That is something they excel at.
They're typically 30 to 50% cheaper
than the major hypervisors out there.
They just wanna lock you into their crazy platform anyways.
And there's no way they can support you like Linode can.
Linode has the absolute best customer service
in the business.
They have super fast rigs, great networking.
They are their own ISP.
And a Linux culture that permeates throughout the company.
I mean, that's why they started the company.
So there's a lot of reasons to choose Linode.
And I didn't even get into like the dashboard
and the API and the one click applications
that are so nice to use.
I mean, they're there.
But have you thought like how great it would be
just to have your own GitLab or Jitsi server
in just a couple of clicks?
So I just, I really don't need to say much more
because I think what puts it over the top
is when you go grab that $100 and try it yourself.
Because you get to try something rad
and you get to support the show.
It's a great opportunity to learn
and a great opportunity to support the show.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go get that $100 in 60 day credit on a new account
and support the show.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Now, Chris, I think we have about two more criticisms
that are worth mentioning.
You wanna pick it up there?
Just a few more from the post.
One that's probably definitely worth talking about
because it's one that end users are going to experience
is it is complicated when it comes to
specific software packages that require drivers.
Like Nvidia video drivers, like the Steam package.
Because you could be on like Ubuntu, I don't know, 18.04
and Flatpak can't do anything about your kernel.
It's gotta work with the host kernel's system.
So it will then have to pull down a runtime
that matches your specific kernel.
So if you can imagine on the back end,
that's a lot of work.
It's a lot of different runtimes.
It isn't an elegant solution,
but it feels like the kind of problem
you do solve for fragmentation.
And yeah, it's a little bit technical on the back end,
but as long as the end user experience remains consistent
and the developer experience remains documented
and workable, it actually seems like
it's a pretty good compromise despite its complexity.
But in all of this, I think we've kind of gotten
a little carried away conflating a few technologies.
A lot of things are getting thrown around
like containers and sandboxing.
And the implication might be in these conversations
that you have to have Flatpaks or snaps to have sandboxing.
But that's not necessarily the case.
And Neil, I think you wanted to expand on that.
It's actually never really been the case
that security, sandboxing, these portals
and all that stuff are necessarily requiring you
to change the way the application is built and distributed.
Because the OBS Studio, RPM and Fedora, for example,
or Firefox and Fedora when running on Wayland,
activates those portals and does all the same things.
Your general computing experience
can be more consistent in this regard
if application developers know how to code to these APIs,
whether it's shipped as an RPM or a Flatpak,
a snap, a Debian package, or even just a bloody tarball
that you download or an app image.
And I don't think it's a good idea for us to conflate the two
because that leaves a large gamut of applications
that can benefit from these technologies
when they cannot be distributed that way.
Like system critical applications
or stuff that should be part of the base OS
so that you have a functional set of base software
should also be able to take advantage of these things.
There's no reason that you can't have
the bubble wrap based sandboxing with the portals
and all that stuff kick in for an RPM
like you do for a Flatpak.
Neil, I'm curious if you have any insights
into how Fedora is approaching Flatpaks
and especially some of those namespace concerns
that have been floating around.
The way we're doing it right now
is that the software centers prioritize Fedora sources
by default over third party ones.
So there's a priority level and ours is higher.
And if you click the button to install something,
it will prefer the Fedora source over the third party one
if the identifiers are the same
and the user hasn't changed any settings.
The reason why this comes up actually
is a fairly interesting one.
In some cases, it's just straight up
not a good idea to distribute
or a bundle the distribution
of something from a third party,
particularly when there are legal requirements
or the upstream developer may have questionable character
or things like that.
For example, Audacity from earlier this year,
the stuff that they're shipping
has some of those things going on,
but the Audacity RPM and Flatpak from Fedora don't.
And I think it's important to recognize
that there is actually a trade off to switching to a model
where developers are the ones
doing all of this distribution work themselves.
And that is, you no longer have a review or a counterweight.
That may be fine, that may not be fine.
It really depends.
Like a big part of in the Android ecosystem,
I know a lot of people were talking about this
about how people use apps more on Android and iOS
and whatnot, but like in the Android ecosystem,
there has historically been a problem of malware
before Google started getting into it
and started digging into all the things.
And even with all that, it's still a problem
because at the end of the day,
developers have no check against them.
There is nothing checking them.
And yes, the Linux distribution model
is certainly not perfect.
And maybe a balance of the two is certainly better,
but like, let's not get carried away
and throw out the baby with the bathwater.
It's still valuable to have people
being checks against each other
to make sure that we're all doing a good job here.
Yeah, especially with security in mind.
Wimpy, it looks like you have some thoughts
and I know you have some experience
on the deduplication conversation here.
Can you fill us in?
Yeah, so on the proliferation of libraries
and what have you, there are mechanisms
that exist in Snaps and Flatpak
that allow you to create reusable runtimes,
which still means there is some duplication,
but that duplication is one time only
for a common runtime that exists
across most applications that you're gonna run
on the desktop.
But this is one of the sort of prices you have to pay
for containerized applications
that it does come with that sort of bundling approach.
And there are technologies that are growing in popularity
that address some of this in order to trim out
some of that duplication of files.
And I'm not gonna plug this too heavily,
but where I work now, we have an open source project
called Docker Slim, which does precisely this,
using dynamic and static analysis,
will pull out all of the cruft that exists
in Docker and OCI containers.
And there's no reason why those technologies
couldn't be applied to the Linux desktop space.
And speaking specifically about the Linux desktop,
there are two very important points
that people need to get on board with regarding
contemporary application delivery on Linux,
the Linux desktop.
The first is, if you install, let's say Google Chrome,
in the traditional way, you download the RPM or the deb
from the Google Chrome website and install it on your system,
go and S-trace Google Chrome when it starts up
and go and look at just how much grubbing around it does
in your home directory, trying to hoover up everything
it can learn about you and your system.
And you will start to appreciate the efforts,
because I know that the Linux desktop users
are a huge percentage of very privacy orientated,
privacy conscious people.
The sandboxed applications prevent that kind of,
you know, just pillaging of your information and data
before you even go to a website and you get, you know,
tracked and traced there.
So consider that the sandboxing does play a role
in protecting your privacy.
You need to be thinking about that.
And the other is this, all significant investment
that happens in the Linux ecosystem today
is in container and virtualization technologies.
It is a multi-billion dollar industry.
Desktop Linux cannot refuse to get on board
with containers and VMs as part of the OS landscape
in the future.
If we do that, we are paving a way towards obsolescence
and irrelevance, because all the significant development
is in those technologies and desktop Linux users
need to embrace this sort of, it's an inevitable future.
If we resist it, then it's over for us.
You know, there is no future.
So it's a matter of embracing the technology,
the people that are competent and capable,
improving and developing the support
around those technologies.
And you do a great job of putting it all into perspective.
What we have to keep in mind is desktop Linux's bread
gets buttered by the enterprise side.
I mean, even like we've talked about recently here
on the show, PipeWire is the direct result
of businesses investing in automotive Linux.
And what a lot of very clever developers
have been very, very good at doing for a long time
is leveraging the investments for enterprise Linux
into desktop technologies.
And that's what's happening here.
And I think you make a great point, Wimpy.
It's kind of like, even if you wanted to make the argument,
well, the other desktop operating systems
don't have to do this,
well, they have a different business model.
No, but they are.
Mac OS is a hugely virtualized platform
and so is Windows these days.
It's just all transparent and hidden under the covers.
And that's where we need to get to.
Right, yeah, in fact, I broke this down
on Coder Radio recently.
The last three versions of Mac OS have,
each version has just completely re-architected
the file system directly underneath the user
without even them noticing,
to the point now where Mac OS is using
an immutable file system for its primary OS.
And the applications folder is a hybrid folder
of immutable applications that are grafted in
with the user applications that are stored
in a writable section of the APFS disk system.
And when they reboot and like stuff like that,
they're checking like the signature of a snapshot image
and they're booting into a snapshot.
And then when they do updates,
they're doing like the immutable switch over and reboot.
Like we've been talking about in desktop Linux now
for years with some of these things
and they just incrementally rolled it out
in the last three releases.
It's also important to note that for both Windows
and Mac OS, they did it without changing
the way developers deliver applications.
That's a huge difference from how the Linux world
is approaching it.
And that's, I think, a big part of why people
are resisting so hard.
Because in the commercial world,
it is recognized that you cannot screw with people
when you are trying to improve the user experience.
And that is something that I don't think enough people
on the free software side actually understand.
We probably need to wrap it here
because we have to wrap up at some point.
But the other thing that's been interesting
is I'm really getting a better sense
of what the future looks like for Flat Hub.
And I think I'm good with it.
I think that's actually going to be a good thing.
If it's some kind of paying mechanism
that I'm comfortable with,
assuming that it's something that's nice and clean
and doesn't feel gross,
I think that's going to be a great direction for Flat Hub.
I mean, it's something we've kind of talked about
needing more widely in our ecosystem, right?
And I mean, so far, there's been various attempts,
but none of them are necessarily widely successful.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, I think the elementary OS App Center
has proven it out on a certain scale.
And I think Flat Hub would be the next scale up.
And it's the thing that we've always looked for,
even back when we had quite the software store on Ubuntu,
we really always wanted something that was cross-distro.
And a few different places,
even the Lindos folks took a crack at that,
but nothing quite like this.
And part of it is because Flat Pack
is solving those fundamental issues.
And then Flat Hub is just a front end
on top of getting access to the stuff
and making it simple for the end user.
But with all of that,
I think we'd just like to leave it to the audience.
So if you'd like to give us your thoughts
or your opinions on this stuff,
or perhaps you think we've missed something,
please do let us know.
Sometimes the pushback emails
are our absolute favorite emails to respond to.
So go to linuxunplugged.com slash contact
and share your thoughts.
Now we did a episode, Linux Unplugged 4.31.
That's three episodes ago on command line love,
which was a bit of an homage to the Ubuntu podcast segment.
And we keep getting mail from that episode.
It's just incredible.
So here are three from that.
Costas wrote in and he says,
as a programmer, I would fight tooth and nail
before anyone took my command line away from me.
That said, I am familiar with two situations
where the command line is a no-go.
Any device without a physical keyboard at hand,
mobile phones, tablets, integrated gaming PCs,
think Steam Deck or its myriad predecessors,
including my beloved One X player.
These devices rely on software keyboards,
which are ill-equipped for regular usage of the command line.
I would have to totally agree.
And Chris, maybe that device you teased in the pre-show
is maybe solving that for you.
He continues, the lack of English language skills
is the other situation.
Let's take my parents as an example,
Greek retirees with a past end of life iMac
that I'm about to install Linux on.
My father was coding on a ZX Spectrum in his 20s
and relied on books translated to Greek to get him going.
I doubt he would be able to deal with man pages
written in English to get stuff done.
As far as I know, and correct me if I'm wrong,
command line interfaces don't get translated
as much as graphical ones.
I believe that we can find a lot of people in communities
where mobile phones are their primary computation device
and English proficiency is low.
The command line is cool and powerful,
but not always an option.
Now I was curious with that,
does anyone use translations of the command line
on a regular basis, maybe in the Mumble Room?
Yeah, it's commonplace.
Some people don't know this,
but like one of the major innovations from GNU
was adding first-class support for internationalization
and localization to the command line.
It didn't really exist in the way
that we have it today in Linux.
It didn't exist before then.
One of the reasons why the GNU core utils is so complex,
I know a lot of people say use BusyBox
or some of the other ones because they're simpler,
whatever, and less bloat.
A lot of the bloat actually comes from the fact
that they made internationalization
a first-class aspect of their user space.
And that has actually carried forward
to most of the important command line tools,
like your package managers, your monitoring utilities.
A lot of those things tend,
like even Docker has translations,
Podman too, like it's a fairly common thing.
Maybe not Manpages necessarily
because the Manpage translation infrastructure kind of sucks.
But even with that, go look at your file system sometime.
There's actually a good chunk of translated Manpages.
PyCrash, I wanted to give you a chance to jump in
because I think you've been involved
with some of these translations.
I speak Spanish and German,
and I provided translation for a couple of distributions
and open source projects, and they actually get translated.
I mean, the output from the command line,
one of the biggest problems I had
when I started using testing
is I needed to set my command line
to please do the output in English
because most developers want the output in English
when they look at the back.
So a lot of the command line utilities
actually are doing output in your language.
The only thing that is not translated,
it's usually the flags, for example,
are for recursive or stuff like that.
But otherwise, it's actually,
the output is actually really good in non-English languages.
Okay, that makes me feel a little better.
This is why it's so great to have an open Mumble Room
because I just really wasn't quite sure
what the answer was to that.
I felt like Manpages, that made sense
because there's so many alternatives online now.
Right, it's an area we're kind of blind to.
Yeah, it is good to hear
there's a lot of work, though, getting done there.
Listener Kevin quickly mentioned and remind me,
which I forgot, that in Brunch with Brent
with Stuart Langridge, he mentioned
that search engines are in essence a command line prompt
with an understanding by the user
that no mistake they make can harm their system.
So check that out.
We'll leave a link in the show notes.
Mind blown, mind blown, right?
It's a command line that average users
have just adapted to, they've gotten used to.
For a little piece of maybe some spicy mail that we got,
Forrest Lake writes in,
hey team, just listen to your command line love episode.
I hate to say it, but that's the biggest bunch
of elitist BS that I've ever heard.
You, the show and guests always talk about productivity
and how shaving off time can have such a big impact
on your day, but we expect people to waste time
jumping on forums, asking the hyper intelligent gurus
how to do things on the command line.
That is a waste of precious time and very unproductive
as the general response for the elite is Google it.
I'm not here to give you answers.
You need to learn young Padawan.
I've been a Linux user since the nineties
and will always look for a gooey way of doing things
as the forums provide no answers for people
without receiving some attitude.
If there was a gooey solution for every problem,
just like windows, then the year of the Linux desktop
would have been in the late nineties or two thousands.
I guess the question is,
do you want Linux to be omnipresent or an OS distro
for those who camp in the forums?
That is a very strong opinion.
I have used Linux since the nineties
and I could probably count on one hand
how many times I've actually gotten like an STFU
go Google noob kind of response.
It did happen more often in the early days in IRC,
especially when you come like charging into a room
and there's like a conversation,
they're all in the middle of like some heated debate
for like the last half hour
and you pop in there demanding an answer.
Yeah, sometimes you get told to take a hike
and that used to happen more often.
But now we have so many platforms
that are like specifically set up
to come ask your question and get an answer.
So the context has been set,
the table has been set for you
to come and ask your question.
Then I find that to be a lot less of an occurrence.
And then when you participate in more niche down communities
like the podcast communities or a distro specific community
or a project specific community,
you find even nicer people there
cause it's even a smaller group of people
that are generally like-minded
because they're organized around something.
And so it's pretty common in those groups
to have like people around that are like
sort of the unofficial welcoming committee
that are generally very nice on outreach.
I really don't find this to be an issue
and I'm just kind of using nearly 30 years of experience
to derive that opinion.
So from that, it's your experience
but that's not everyone's experience, right?
That's what my conclusion is from that.
I think the other thing I just wanted to point out
is that the response of how people talk
about command line tools
and the functionality of command line tools,
those are two different things.
And I'm not saying command line tool for every situation
but how people tell you how to use them
and what they are capable of doing are two separate issues.
Right, and of course there's different modes here, right?
You mentioned productivity in the feedback
and yeah, okay, I mean,
if you're having to learn additional tools
that might slow you down now
but you also have to think about the long-term
and some of the reasons we love the command line
is because if you do have stuff to get done,
it can often be one of the most efficient ways to do it.
Command line tools are just software
in the same that graphical applications are software.
And there are graphical applications
that are complex to use like DaVinci Resolve
and I had to spend hours watching videos
and reading documentation to even scratch the surface
of what's possible with that software.
So I think it's fine
that if you are doing something complicated,
you might need to seek some resources,
reference material, tutorials, use a group
in order to learn how to manipulate that software
to do what you need to do.
And I don't think it's strictly the preserve
of command line applications.
Very well put, I mean,
I've seen some really complex enterprise applications
that you have to send end users to training sessions
just so they can master 10% of its functionality.
And when it comes to supportability and whatnot,
like one of the positives and negatives, right,
is the community support,
but part of that is self-inflicted.
We just don't have the, you know,
outside of SUSE and I think also Canonical,
I don't know of anyone that directly offers
desktop Linux support anymore.
And you kind of have to go with what's out there.
And maybe in the future, if the desktop market share,
desktop Linux market share grows a little more,
we'll start seeing more and more of those supportability
options show back up again,
like they were in the nineties when everything,
when everyone was like thinking that it was gonna take over
the world immediately.
But right now we just don't have it.
You know, and I've thought about this since we've talked
about it on the show,
cause we have gotten a lot of feedback and I think where I,
what I really believe when it comes to this command line
tools or over graphical tools is I think if you're gonna use
Linux as a system that's important to you,
it's worth knowing some of the fundamental commands,
like how to change directory, how to list the contents,
how to look at processes, maybe how to read your logs,
maybe how to stop or start a service,
maybe how to reboot from the command line in case you get
stuck, you know,
you could drop to a terminal and reboot the thing.
Maybe even if I could go as far as to say,
maybe even kind of a rough understanding of grub or
whatever your bootloader is, you know,
those I think are, are things that are worth investing in
that, you know, you spend your,
you spend four to six hours learning that stuff.
You know, maybe you even spend, I don't know, 48 hours,
but it'll pay dividends for 15, 20 years.
Maybe not grub. Well, maybe actually, I mean, how,
I still see systems with Lilo.
So that's a scary thought.
I know.
I saw a vendor system running Linux two recently.
No.
Yeah. With an Apache, an old version of Apache.
Oh my God.
So, you know, it's just like, and, and I, you know,
the commands work, right?
Got on that box, figured out how much disk space was,
you know, did the old DF,
figured out how much disk space was available.
It was valuable still.
It's a very old system.
And so some of that stuff I think is, is worth learning,
but like at the same time,
if there's an application like flat seal,
that's going to give you a nice graphical overview of what
permissions your different flat packs have, I have at it.
I think that's a great use of a graphical application.
No kidding, right?
There's just stuff that, you know,
really makes sense to have in a GUI and there's other stuff
that works nicely in the command line.
We don't have to, as you often say, Chris, you know,
it's, you invent a new thing.
The old stuff doesn't go away.
Like these kind of co-exist together and probably will for
a long time.
Right.
Also, I think this has been sparked to some extent from,
you know, Linus's comments during his Linux challenge.
You know, he, he was very critical of, you know,
the Linux command line as we have to get away from it,
but actually the Linux command line is one of the
fundamental things that defines Linux.
If we do away with that, then what does Linux become?
It's differentiator is gone.
It's power tool goes away.
The thing that makes Linux, Linux no longer exists.
So I don't think we should throw it away or give it up.
I think we should embrace it and we can have both.
We can have fantastic command line utility and also great
graphical applications.
We don't need to choose one over the other.
Yeah.
I feel like we're really starting to see that too,
with things like fwupdy,
where you've got some command line components and some
libraries,
and then you're seeing different graphical tools being
built because system 76 has one gnome has one canonicals
building one based on flutter,
but it's all using the same stuff under the hood.
And those, if you wanted to,
you could do those same firmware updates from the command
line.
And that's, that's kind of,
I think what we have figured out over time and the kind of
thing we're getting better at building.
I think the aspect of what most people have an issue with in
terms of the total command line is that there's a messaging
problem.
You have the problem of some people in the community talking
about how the command line is easy.
And while it is efficient,
a hundred percent agreed there,
you can do a lot things faster in there.
Well, I wouldn't say FFmpeg or anything like that,
but there are certain levels of complexity that the gooey's
offer, like Wimpy said,
but I think it's more of the messaging that people often
say it's easy or simple.
And when you're talking about people who just get started,
there's not really a fair association to easy or simple,
but what they're, what they think is easy.
And what they think is simple is going to be different than a
lot of people who use those terms.
That's a good point.
Hello, Michael, good to see you.
I think what really kind of bears your point out is I think
of it in some ways FFmpeg is such a great example as simpler
than launching the gooey because I've got a terminal command.
I've got fish installed.
I type FF and like the whole thing just auto completes.
I hit tab.
I changed the file names and hit enter.
And for me, that's simpler than launching a gooey.
You have fish to help you.
The poor soul who's working with the distro default of bash or
God forbid busy box SH or something got nothing.
They got nothing.
That's true.
If you do FF play or FFmpeg or FF convert,
TAC TAC help your worse off than you were before you started.
No, that's, it's absolutely true.
I was really just making the joke that, you know, if you,
if you've been using something for a while and you get
comfortable with it, it's obviously the easier.
That's the best part about command line tools is it's very
easy to develop a rhythm for how to use things.
And that's where we keep coming back to this, you know,
to what extent are we embracing what we expect new users to
know and how much do we expect them to embrace the new
platform they're coming to and learn the tricks of the
trade there. And it seems like it's often a balance.
Where is that line? Yeah, exactly.
Okay. Well, we got to wrap it up there.
We could keep going all day, but listen,
the changes in the air and we'd love to have you show up on a
Tuesday while we're still here.
See you next week. Same bat time, same bat station.
I know, I know, but come join us on a Tuesday,
hang out with us.
And if you're around on a Sunday,
our virtual lugs getting together at noon Pacific,
having a good old time talking Linux,
open source projects and things they've been working on and all
kinds of folks from around the community pop in there and have
a good time. It's nice.
And then your mumbles ready to go for the show.
And then in the future, when the show's on Sunday,
well, you'll know where to find us.
If you're in the industry, be sure you're not missing out.
Go get Linux action news, linuxactionnews.com.
Don't miss an episode.
Join us back here Tuesday at noon Pacific,
3 p.m. Eastern at jblive.tv.
linuxunplug.com slash 434.
See you next Tuesday.
I don't know how we are going to title this one,
but let's give it a shot.
JBtitles.com. Let's go pick something.
We need your help. We really do.
We do. We do. We do.
Michael, don't worry. Don't worry.
The good news is we're going to be live on Sundays,
but we're going to be noon and you guys are usually done by then.
That is not why I joined, but also kind of partly why I joined.
Wait, what?
I'm just like, because I can't join anymore.
I know. I know. There is that.
Noon, what? Pacific.
OK, yeah, because you're one Eastern, which is.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, you're fine. Yeah, yeah.
It's not our first choice.
I actually really like being live on Tuesday because
often, you know, guests like Will can join us and stuff like that.
But we, you know, we can also record off air and things like that.
But there's just a series of changes going on.
And, you know, we're we got to make a few adjustments.
And so that's one of them.
There's a lot of positives to it, too.
It also means that more often than not,
Wes and I will be in studio together several times.
It'll be Wes Brent and I in studio together, which is going to be really nice.
I always really enjoy the shows where we can all be in the same room.
So that's going to be something that happens more often.
And we can do more meetups and things like that on Sundays and whatnot.
So there's a lot of other nice positives to it as well.
But changes are coming, and I'm both excited
and anxious about new shows and all of that.
So let's not stress about it and let's just title this thing.
Let's just get it figured out. We can do this.