You remember the Runs Linux segment on Linux Action Show?
Oh yeah, of course.
Check out this Runs Linux for this week.
NASA, NASA Runs Linux.
You know, there's this recent epic landing on Mars.
Heck yeah.
And on the live stream, I got a screen cap of it here.
I noticed up on the projector,
a kind of older Plasma desktop running VNC,
looking into another Unix box
to pull the images down live from the landing.
All on Linux.
You've got Linux, Linux,
and then I think that might be some old Unix possibly.
Chris, when you're landing on another world,
you don't have time for proprietary software.
That's right, you gotta make sure it works right.
And VNC is the old go-to remote control,
even for NASA.
This is Linux Unplugged,
episode 277 for November 27th, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged,
your weekly Linux talk show
that might be slightly distracted
by that keyboard over there
that's got a Linux box built into it.
My name's Chris.
My name is Wes, and I know I am very distracted.
It's the Keyboardio.
It's a wood keyboard with a pretty eclectic layout
and Arduino boards built into both halves of it,
connected via an ethernet cable.
And then USB-C back to the machine.
And it's all programmed.
You got LED lights.
You could do RGB if you wanna be a elite gamer.
So Wes is gonna be putzing with that project,
but that's actually not what we're here
to talk about today, no, no.
We're gonna do a bunch of community news.
A nice batch, not too much, but a good solid batch.
Wimpy whetted my appetite recently
with some really cool home server setup talk.
So we'll deep dive with Mr. Wimpress on that.
And then after the KDE Corner,
we're gonna talk about this proposal by the Fedora Project.
After Fedora 30, they wanna punt an entire release,
take a year and focus on themselves,
and wait for 31.
Now that's a massive proposal with huge ramifications
and kind of a precarious timing
with the other news out there.
So we're gonna bring on the project lead, Matthew Miller,
to explain what's going on, what the objective is,
what might go wrong, and what stage this proposal is in.
We're gonna get the whole scoop from him.
That's like everything.
He's gonna be on it a little bit
to tell us what's going on there.
And then we'll wrap it up with some pics,
some interesting year-end news,
including like when we're doing our special
for predictions and stuff like that.
We got all that nailed down.
And then for one last time, hopefully,
I'll tell you my current Dropbox hack,
which those bastards at Dropbox.
I sat down in a machine upstairs,
I started popping up that error message.
I just got so disappointed.
The XT4.
Oh, so frustrating.
You know what?
Let's focus on something positive.
Let's focus on that virtual log.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Good morning.
Hello.
Hello, everybody.
Good to have you with us.
Thank you for joining us.
We're gonna have a great show today.
And I wanted to start with a topic that just won't go away.
And Wes, you set it up so beautifully
the other day in our chat.
You said we're in the ascendancy of these projects.
And so we are not fully realizing
all of the long-term ramifications.
And what you were talking about
is how everything has its own package manager right now.
And we're gonna get to a new story that just happened here.
But we've talked about this before.
Docker Hub, flat pack apps that have been packaged
with old libraries or elementary apps
that aren't properly supported and distributed as flat packs
or snaps that had a crypto miner in them
or the most recent one that I think
has gotten a lot of attention is this Node.js package hack.
So for some context, a widely used MPM package
was discovered to have a dependency
with an encrypted payload in it,
which then tried to steal bitcoins.
Of course.
I mean, that's what you do.
That's always what they try to steal.
But when you start reading through the community reaction,
there is tremendous outrage at the developer
for essentially screwing millions of people.
People are very, very angry.
And they have not really a lot of ground to stand on.
Cause if you look at any open source software,
it generally comes with, it's provided as is,
use at your own risk.
I think that's what makes it so interesting
is because none of these are hard and fast rules.
It's all about community norms
and what we expect from software.
And these days, like everything you build
is gonna be pulling in six, 10 more libraries
that you're linking features and adding value on top.
And that's great.
But we do have to question,
like how do we be responsible about this?
And yes, it's not your responsibility necessarily
to do any of these things
if you're an open source project maintainer,
but if you're interested in doing that well,
what are some guidelines that can help you do that?
How do you, and when you're ready to not do it anymore,
which is totally reasonable,
how do you transfer ownership to somebody reasonable way?
Right, so it doesn't just die and become vulnerable.
But I mean, how deep does this rabbit hole go though?
Because you've got a distribution package repository
and maintainers, then you've got things
that have their own package managers built into them,
lots of software does.
Then you've got containers that have hubs
that people have automatically submitted software to.
Then you also just have rando drive by websites.
So like this rabbit hole is never ending to me.
And we're just building on top of it.
Like building a package manager now
is like the keen thing that's the bee's knees,
that everybody's doing.
And it seems like we aren't appreciating
the amount of work it takes to sustain these systems.
The more packages a system has,
the bigger it becomes, then it becomes,
it's like it's on a Richter scale.
Like it becomes way more work to actually maintain it all.
Maybe we need a minor free certification process.
There are three layers to this, right?
There's the ethical component,
there is the trust component,
and then there is the legal one.
Ethically wrong, just throw it away.
Trust, well, people trusted the repository
where things were sorted out.
So the responsibility really gets attributed to them
in my perspective, not so much the original developer
because transfer of ownership
is not immediate transfer of access to a repository.
When I think of that rabbit hole,
it seems insurmountable to solve at the management layer.
In fact, it seems like ultimately the responsibility
is on the sys admin who installed that on his own server
or the end user who decided to install
that desktop software.
I kind of like to get your perspective on this Brent.
I'm not saying I audit all of the things I installed,
but don't you think ultimately if you installed something
that stole your Bitcoin wallet, it's your fault?
Yeah, I think that is the case.
And we have to be careful
with the end user perspective there,
is that not all of our end users are educated enough
to know to look at all of that stuff
or pay that much attention, right?
Like Linux, we sometimes tout as really quite safe
for end users, but in this case,
they may not even know
what they're installing in the background.
So yeah, absolutely, especially as a sys admin,
should feel responsible for that.
But as an end user, you need to kind of have your eye out
for that kind of stuff too.
I'm on Arch and as everyone knows, the AUR is great
and can have some pitfalls, right, in that respect.
So I think, yeah, it is ultimately responsible
for what you're installing.
But I will say there's even a bigger catch
that is often missed and with this one,
which is companies that tend to use open source packages,
they generally will have some sort of artifactory
or internal repository that they clone.
If they can't just easily pick up from the original source,
they will stop contributing back
the little they already contribute back
because at this point, the risk is too high.
So I would refrain from trying to put these things
into this perspective of, hey, let's just,
the user is responsible because a company
really doesn't want to do that all the time
because then it just worth it to pay the developer
to write it in the first place
and we're the ones to lose.
So I really think that we want to take ownership
and responsibility for it while it's still convenient
for us to have that responsibility.
I think one of the problems that we see here
is in our quest for more software availability,
we've made it easier to get software
and that can make, like with the AUR,
it can mean that you can rebuild things
from Git really easily and get the latest security patches
or things can never get updated.
But I think some systems are doing it
in a little bit different because you'll never be able
to solve, or at least it doesn't seem likely will solve
the problem of people just didn't update
all their dependencies the right way anytime soon.
But maybe another approach is limiting the damage
that can be done like with snaps, right Wimpy?
Yeah, this is an interesting conversation.
So when we think back to 1970s Unix,
everything's a string, do one job and do it well,
and pipes, these were profound ideas
that have stood the test of time
and lasted for 40 plus years.
But back then when Unix was being created,
there were a handful of people
that were building the system.
And there was implicit trust that existed
between all of those people that were working
on the Unix derivatives.
And you can even trace that back to the level of trust
that existed in the networking tools back then.
Everything worked on a trust relationship.
Everybody knew who everybody else was.
Now, when you roll forward 40, 50 years,
that's not the case anymore.
There are tens of millions of developers just on GitHub,
and there are other places that you can manage
your source code in the world today.
There are millions upon millions upon millions of projects
in GitHub and other public source code repositories.
You as a sysadmin or a DevOps engineer,
or a developer who are pulling in components,
you may just pull in component foo,
but component foo may have dependencies upon dozens
and dozens and dozens of other libraries.
You can't trust all of that other stuff.
And this is where snaps are a re-imagining
of old 1970s AT&T Unix,
where you take all of those things,
you put them in a container that can't tread
on the host operating system or the other applications
that are installed in that way,
because we can't guarantee these trust relationships
that used to exist in the distribution models
and the creation of the distributions
in their earliest forms anymore.
It's a new era, and it seems like something that's actually,
now that we're this far into it,
has been a long time coming.
So, and there's also, obviously, as technology gets better,
there's other ways to solve this.
Almost every major repository is built in
some sort of basic scanning for malware
or trust verification system of publishers.
Like, there's other ways of tackling this
at the distribution end as well.
Somebody could build a machine learning model
which is good at smashing crypto miners or something.
Yeah, I bet you it's in the works.
That seems like something that would get a lot of hype.
Crypto miners by themselves are not illegitimate though.
True, true.
Yeah, basically scan for anything
that's not specifically flagged as a crypto miner.
Like, when you upload your package,
you get a flag that says, this is a crypto miner.
Yeah.
And it would come up on when you install a package saying,
hey, this is a crypto miner.
Are you okay with that?
You're like, yes, I know.
I want to get onto Bitcoin.
Yeah, let's not talk about Bitcoin right now.
It makes me sad.
All right, well, I wanted to also discuss this story
that's coming out of the United Space Alliance.
When's the last time we got to do that?
Too long, too long, I say.
May have been never on this show, actually.
We're going to take a look page
from SciByte here for a moment.
This is the group that manages the computers
aboard the International Space Station,
and they work with NASA.
And they just recently announced
that the Windows XP computers
aboard the International Space Station
have been switched to GNU slash Linux.
No way.
Wow. Isn't that awesome?
That's fantastic.
Yeah.
Yeah, they write, we migrated key functions
from Windows to Linux
because we needed an operating system that was...
Stable. Stable and reliable.
Of course.
Yep, yep, in specific, the dozens of laptops
will make the change to,
can you guess which version of Debian?
Oh, it's Debian.
I was going to say Fedora 29,
but no, that wouldn't make sense.
No, they had to wait around for 30.
It's going to be supported for a while.
Okay, so Debian 8, let's say.
Yeah, give me the number
because I don't remember all the Debian names
off the top of my head all the time.
So, all right.
Okay, let's see if anybody can,
see if you can guess what version of Debian
it's going to be up in space for a long time.
So you're going to want something probably recent, right?
Something current and well supported.
We'll have security updates for going forward.
It's an old one.
It is, you're right, it is.
All right, okay.
It is Debian 6.
The laptops will join many other systems
aboard the ISS that already run
various flavors of Linux.
These ones will be running Debian 6.
There's also Red Hat up there, as you would imagine,
and some scientific Linux, as you probably guessed already.
And after the transition,
there won't be a single computer of the ISS
that runs Windows anymore.
It was kind of interesting that
another reason they liked was that
they wanted in-house control,
which is a thing we talk about,
but you don't always actually see people using it, right?
But here they can just,
they can mess things up as much as they want to
and customize it.
Yeah, well, you know, they got a virus back in 2008.
I guess they blame it on a Russian cosmonaut.
Those Russians and their viruses.
Brought about a worm, I guess, technically not a virus,
which then spread to the other laptops.
And they think that switching to Linux will
essentially immunize them from that particular type
of attack in the future.
I mean, I guess against casual malware,
not perhaps a more malicious attack.
Yeah.
Yeah, but I don't think any of us
are too surprised by this, are we?
Because Linux is the scientific community's
operating system of choice.
We know that the Large Hadron Collider is used by Linux.
It uses Linux and uses KDE Plasma.
NASA and SpaceX ground stations run Linux.
DNA sequencing labs technicians use Linux.
It's pretty much anybody that has a serious job.
Yeah, a lot of astronomy software and packages
for analyzing images you get from telescopes.
That's already running Linux, too.
So kind of part of the course.
Did you see this bit on here about the robot?
They got a robot up there, too.
In other news, yeah, the first humanoid robot in space,
Robonaut 2, also runs Linux, is due for an upgrade.
So they got Robonaut.
And Robonaut 2 is also going to be like they got two robots,
but only one of them is in production.
And the one that's up there now, the one that's
being reassembled and built, has been delivered in pieces.
The last big pieces actually went up in 2011.
Right now, it's just a torso with two arms.
But they also have legs that they're
going to be giving it soon and a battery pack
that will be delivered soon.
And then eventually, it'll be able to perform
menial tasks like vacuuming, changing the filters,
the air filters, and possibly dangerous tasks
like during spacewalks.
Space butler.
You saw it here first, folks.
Running Linux, Wes.
How about that, huh?
If you like running Linux, friends,
if you enjoy the GNU slash Linux operating system.
And you like talking to people who also
enjoy that operating system.
Then I invite you out to Linux Fest Northwest,
coming up April 26 and the 28th in Bellingham, Washington,
the beautiful Pacific Northwest.
And it's at the Bellingham Technical College,
which is a great campus because they
got all kinds of things like robotics there
and they have gaming labs there.
So it's great for kids, too, if you've got little ones.
They have things for little ones to do.
They have a gaming room that is a ton of fun
that my young ones like.
And there is tons of talks to attend.
And of course, we're going to be there.
We're going to have a booth.
And we're even considering doing a little bit more this year,
maybe having a room where we're giving talks all day
and things like that.
It's all in the works.
It's all early days.
But I wanted to mention it now while we're still in 2018.
So maybe it could possibly be on your radar
because we're hoping to have a hell of a party.
It's been a good year for us.
We've had things to celebrate.
A year like no other.
Not only have we joined Linux Academy,
and now we have full-time people on our team.
And we have new hosts in the works
that are going to be able to join us there that you haven't
even heard about yet.
It's been a really good year for us.
And we're going to have a great party.
Plus, it's the 20th Linux Fest Northwest.
20 years.
20 years of Linux Fest Northwest.
Wow.
So they have a few things, a few surprises in the works
to celebrate that.
And they're doing a big past, present, and future theme
to kind of bring it all together.
All this kind of sounds like if you've
been wanting to go to one of these,
you want to go to a conference and hang out with us
or other JP fans.
Yeah, this is the one.
And last year, we did a barbecue outside of Lady Joop's.
We had a couple of barbecues going.
Plus, we had the kitchen inside Lady Joop's going.
Just a tremendous party that was a huge success.
And so I think we're going to do it again.
I haven't talked to the folks at System76 yet,
but I know they thought it was a huge success.
Yeah, I'm sure they'll be back.
And if not, hey, we've got the crew.
I mean, maybe we'll be lucky enough
to see Brent there joining us.
I can carry two barbecues on Lady Joop's alone.
So I'm just saying.
Yeah, Brent, are you planning to make it back this year?
I'm definitely going.
I think after the experience last year
and just the huge connection to the JB community
here over this year, there's no reason not to go, really.
Even if it's across the continent, really.
I'm feeling like this is going to be one of our big years.
I'm really excited.
I've talked to Noah.
He's going to be there too.
He'll be at the booth.
And we'll be doing live shows.
And it's just, oh, it's going to be fun.
JB family blowout.
It's going to be a JB family blowout.
So if you want to come out, and so far, it even
sounds like I've talked Joe into coming out and doing
the live Linux action news.
That mysterious, mysterious Joe.
The first live Linux action news
we'll have ever done live at Linux Fest Northwest.
And the first time we've ever seen each other in person.
So I'm looking forward to that just alone.
That's going to be great.
So if you can make it, it's one to go to.
Anybody else in the mumble room, anybody?
Anybody in particular?
Might make it for the 20th anniversary, yes.
Thinking about it.
Gosh, that'd be great.
That would be wild.
That would be so great.
It would be great to have a barbecue at the same time,
I think.
Absolutely.
Just a crazy suggestion.
A barbecue, we almost always have an after party
at the studio.
Although this year, I have a restaurant in mind
to go to just because the crowd's getting bigger.
And the studio's not that big.
So yeah, but we almost always have an after party.
Well, we try to have an after party each night.
So it gets a little ridiculous because you've
got Friday night, which is set up night.
And then the-
You need to blow off some steam after that.
The actual Fest is Saturday and Sunday.
So then you've got things to do at Saturday night and Sunday
night.
And then it's like Sunday, you're all done with the Fest.
You've done your live Linux action news.
Well, now you want to go have a party.
So then there's another party.
And they're not like crazy blowout parties.
Well, actually, sometimes they are.
It just depends on the crowd every year.
But I'd just love to have you there.
And you can check out and get more information
at linuxfestnorthwest.org.
Also, as we do this recording, there's still 65 days
left to submit papers.
I'm encouraging our team, Wes, and others on our team
to submit papers and for talks because I
think we have a lot to contribute that we don't
normally do those things.
But because we're going to have such a big crew,
we'll have plenty of coverage at the booth and stuff
so we can do that kind of thing this year.
Wow, very excited about that.
Well, Wimpy, I really, really do hope you make it.
That would be one of the highlights of the year, I think.
But while I've got your ear, you really
kind of piqued my interest on a recent episode of Ubuntu
podcast, big fan, as you know.
And you touched on a new setup using some software
that I have heard mentioned several times
by the audience, SnapRaid, and a couple of other projects
to really build yourself what sounds like, oh, I mean,
this might, you could correct me if I'm wrong,
but it almost sounds like a free open-source Drobo,
like a home-built Drobo in a way.
Yeah, I think a comparison with a Drobo is fair, yes.
OK, so this obviously sounds very tempting.
I just had another drive die in my FreeNAS server.
I don't know why this happens to me.
And I don't know, I don't grok in FreeNAS's UI
how I'm supposed to solve it.
I don't get it.
So then I get.
That's funny.
I had the same.
I just bought two replacement drives on Black Friday.
So I'm going to be rebuilding the array myself.
I didn't even notice until yesterday.
So I didn't even think to look.
So I don't know.
I'm just kind of sick and tired of this.
It's not that FreeNAS is bad.
I love FreeNAS.
But when I have disk die on me, I
feel like I can never clear the error messages out of FreeNAS
for the rest of the life of that install.
And it's just because I'm an idiot.
Because Alan sits down, and he has it figured out
in two seconds.
So it's my fault. But I have been thinking about,
if this was a Linux-based system,
I could probably just take care of it.
And it's because it's this quasi-appliance
without a full user land, running
on top of a kernel and system tools
that I am not as familiar with, that I feel like my data is
kind of in peril.
So help me, wimpy one.
You're my only hope.
Is this something where you could actually
hack it on the command line?
You can SSH into your box and mess around with stuff,
and you're not going to break it.
Explain this setup to me and how it all kind of fits together.
OK.
So yes is the answer to that question.
What I have started with is just an install of Ubuntu server
1804.1.
So just straight up Ubuntu server.
So yes, you can SSH into it.
And you can do all of the management from that point
onwards just over SSH.
With no fancy file system set up beforehand or anything
like that?
Correct.
Yeah, so this is where SnapRaid is interesting.
So let's just start this by saying ZFS is all well and good,
and it has its place in the world.
But I've specifically chosen these tools of SnapRaid
and MergerFS because I am addressing specific issues
that home users would have, not enterprises with terabytes
and terabytes of storage.
So is an example of that like mismatched disks,
or what's an example of that?
Yeah, so examples of that would be with SnapRaid,
you can use mismatched sizes of disks.
You don't have to create the array upfront.
You can use your existing disks with your existing data on it
and add those into a SnapRaid configuration
without any formatting or anything like that.
So in terms of the home user for budgeting, it's very flexible.
And for my position, I lost some disks a year ago
in last year's summer due to heat.
So I'm very sensitive to disks running and spinning
and generating heat.
And the way that SnapRaid works is you, so for example,
I have four drives in one of my arrays.
I just formatted all of them with, well, one of them
I formatted with XFS, and the other three I
formatted with ext4.
So you can choose what file system
you want to put on the disks you're
going to use in your SnapRaid array.
The way that SnapRaid works is that you just copy files
onto a file system.
So nothing clever, nothing fancy.
But consequently, a file exists on one
of the disks in your array.
An array is like in air quotes now,
because it's not like a RAID array where the whole thing is
a logical volume.
Which means when this is actually in use,
only one disk is spinning.
And I have SmartMon power down the disks
after 10 minutes of activity.
So this keeps the disks cool.
It keeps the power down, and it keeps the noise down.
So these are all important factors for home users.
Right.
That makes sense.
Instead of focusing on a constantly available,
high performance NAS system, this
is more of like, here's my backup server,
and I just want to keep things safe.
It doesn't have to be ready to respond at all moments.
I mean, it's sitting there idle a large chunk of the day.
Indeed.
That's a good point.
So SnapRaid is designed for media servers
where the files on the media server
are changing infrequently.
So let's just talk about SnapRaid for a minute.
I had four drives.
I formatted one with XFS, the other three with ext4.
We'll get to why I did that in just a moment,
because I'm sure that will come as a surprise to you.
I would have thought of an XFS myself,
but a gentleman's file system.
We'll get to it.
You'll understand.
And the drive that I formatted XFS,
that I used as my parity drive.
So within the SnapRaid configuration,
I say this disk mounted in this location is used for parity.
The other three drives that I formatted,
I say these disks are data disks.
And they are each mounted in their own discrete location.
So one is called HDD1, another is HDD2, another is HDD3.
And that's basically the SnapRaid configuration.
That's all it cares about, where the disks are,
which one has got parity, which one's got data.
And then you also specify the path
to what are called content files.
And these are the files that store the hashes.
So the checksums and hashes for the files.
And this is where SnapRaid has a great property,
because it offers you the same kind of bit rot protection
that ZFS offers you.
With checksums?
With checksums, indeed.
And it can recover from files where the data has become
corrupt over time, and repair that data from the parity
and the hashes.
You probably have heard a lot of people say this sounds
similar to Unraid, since you talked about it
on the Ubuntu podcast.
It is similar to Unraid.
It's far more robust than Unraid in my experience.
Yes, indeed.
Yeah, and Unraid is more than just a disk manager now.
It does a whole lot more than that.
Is it a web UI to manage it?
What's the interface?
It's just a config file and a command line application
called SnapRaid.
So once I've created that configuration,
that configuration defines my array.
And now I can just copy some files onto those disks
willy-nilly.
So I copied some files onto hard disk 1,
I copied some onto hard disk 2, and some onto hard disk 3.
And then I ran the command SnapRaid sync,
and that then builds the parity file.
So it inspects every file in the array, builds the parity file,
and builds the tables of hashes for all of the files that
are in there.
And at that point, my data is now protected.
So I have a parity drive, which means one of my disks can fail
and I will be able to recover.
And I have hashes of all of my data.
So if there's any bit rot, I can also
recover any data that's become corrupt over time.
Now, explain to me, because I feel
like I'm missing one piece, is I understand that MergerFS
is also part of this.
And I know MergerFS is a union file system,
but I'm not clear how that's fitting in with your setup.
Right, OK.
Well, I'll get to that in just one moment,
because there's one other important feature of SnapRaid.
You have to run the sync command manually
to rebuild your parity, unlike, say, something like ZFS,
where that's happening on the fly.
And this is where SnapRaid now has backup kind of functions.
So in the intervening periods where I haven't run a sync,
if I delete files or overwrite files I didn't mean to,
I can now go onto my volume, and I can say SnapRaid fix,
and I can undelete the files and recover them
from the parity that I have.
So in the times between the syncs being run,
it operates as a backup tool, and you can pull files out
of the backup.
That could be nice in a small office environment, too.
Right, yeah, or at home, when if I do a sync every week,
I've got a week's grace that I may have deleted something
accidentally, and I can go and recover it
without having to go to actual backups.
So because now the files are spread across three disks,
that's a bit inconvenient, because now you
have to know that this disk has got these files in it,
and this disk has got these files in it,
and this disk has got these files in it.
So then I've installed some software called MergerFS,
and that uses Fuse, and it uses wildcards in your FS tab.
So you can say, go and mount all of my HDD star
under slash media slash MergerFS.
And now, under that directory, I have a union
of those three disks presented.
And MergerFS then has some strategies about how files,
if you say, copy a file to the union,
how it decides where to place those files.
So I've got it in a mode where it will say,
does the directory, the endpoint directory
that I'm being asked to put this file in already exist?
If it does, put it on the disk that already
has that directory on it.
Or you can say, just scatter them willy nilly.
There's a whole different bunch of right strategies
you can use there.
But because I want to have disks generally,
only one disk spinning at a time,
I have it say, where does this data already exist?
Let's write it there.
And then I've got a configuration option
that says, and if there is not enough space
on that actual disk, then fail over
to the disk that has the most available space
and start writing those files there.
And now, how does the system respond
if you were, say, to slot in a couple of new drives
or put in one that's maybe six terabytes and another that's
two terabytes?
Right.
So the only thing you have to do is make sure
that the drive you're using for parity
is at least as big as the largest drive
that you're using for data.
Is there a migration?
Can you move parity drives?
You can now spread across, spread the parity
across multiple drives.
So you could spread it out, and then you
could reclaim that parity drive as one of your storage drives.
Yes.
Exactly so.
Yes, yes.
And let's imagine I have this terrible situation where
two disks fail, and I've only got one parity drive.
So I can't recover the whole array.
But the two disks that I have left,
because they're just file systems,
I have that data on those disks.
There's no special file system or RAID mechanism behind that.
That data is just accessible to me.
I can just plug that into an external USB adapter
and just suck that data off.
So it's extended for or whatever.
Yeah, exactly so.
Yeah.
But yes, if you want to add another drive,
you just plug the disk in.
You add, you format it, you mount it somewhere,
and then you put in the Snap RAID configuration.
Hard disk 5 is in this location, and that's it.
It's very, very simple.
That does sound simple.
And it's surprisingly fast as well.
So again, because this is home stuff,
I have these arrays hooked up over USB 3 even.
Right, because you're not even looking
for super high performance.
You're looking for storage.
Yeah, but even over USB 3, I'm pushing 170 megabytes
a second across the array.
So not too shabby.
No, what kind of hardware is that?
It's their ICDock Black Vortex enclosures
connected over just regular USB 3 to a NUC.
Is it like an i7 machine, or is it a NUC?
It's a NUC with a mobile chip, a mobile i7.
So it's a quad core mobile i7.
That sounds like a perfect home server for what you're going for.
That's a great setup.
Well, that piques my interest.
Wimpy, thank you for sharing with the class.
And we'll have links to the projects
that Wimpy talked about with their documentation
in the show notes, linuxunplugged.com
slash 277.
And he also went into some detail in the Ubuntu podcast.
So go check that out.
And I am definitely looking at SnapRate.
I wanted to mention for anybody that's
listening the week that this comes out,
or if you're listening live right now,
I don't exactly know what happened.
But Linux Academy decided to extend the $2.99 per year
deal, which makes it $24 a month to get Linux Academy for five
more days as we record this.
I think on Cyber Monday, the sign-up page
went down or something because of everybody
trying to get the deal.
So they're like, all right, well.
And it was only like, I mean, they freaked out
because it was like 20 minutes, right?
It wasn't like a hoot.
But they're like, we're going to extend it for five more days.
I think that's what happened.
But it's a great deal.
And if you didn't jump on it, you're saving 33%.
And the reason I mentioned that is because they obviously
don't pay us.
Well, I mean, they pay us.
But they don't ask me to do these ads.
But I know what they have in the works.
So if you get it at $24 a month, that's
going to be worth it for a long time
because it stays at that price.
Lock it in.
You can lock it in.
Well, the big news this week really
is that the Fedora project is considering canceling,
or maybe you should say significantly delaying,
the release of Fedora 31.
So following the release of Fedora 30 in May,
the project is considering essentially hitting
the pause button for a year, skipping the traditional 31
release cycle, and working on themselves,
retooling and those kinds of things.
It's one of those that they've gone through in the past
when they began doing additions.
And it's one that comes at a kind of precarious time.
So we thought the best route to go
would be to get it from the horse's mouth, as they say,
and bring the project lead on the show
and chat with Matthew Miller.
Matthew, welcome back to the show.
And thanks for joining us on the Unplugged program.
Hi, Chris.
Glad to be here.
Well, we are glad to have you on a day
where we're trying to parse the news that it sounds like there
is a proposal in the works to essentially bump the 31
release, hang out on 30 for a while,
while the back end, I guess infrastructure really,
of the Fedora project is retooled.
Can you explain really what is being proposed?
That's my understanding.
But what's going on from your actual horse's mouth words?
Yeah, that's basically it.
And I don't know if you remember back to five years ago,
we actually did this one time before.
And they worked out OK.
A lot of the problem is we have a six-month release cycle.
And a lot of the people who work on our Fedora infrastructure
also are people who are engaged in the business of getting
that release out the door, the release
engineering, the infrastructure stuff that
makes the bits ship, QA and QA tooling and things like that.
And so as we're going on that rapid cycle,
a lot of technical debt accumulates.
We get a lot of Band-Aids put on things that are problems
and not enough time to fix it.
And then just because this is Fedora 30
we're talking about working on now,
there's been a lot of releases.
And a lot of our tools have grown organically
in the last 15 years.
And so some of the things are scripts
that have another script that they run.
And that script does some other things.
So there's a lot of redundancy.
And performance isn't so good.
So specifically one of the things that's a problem,
when we do a compose, that basically
takes all the software in Fedora.
The packages are already built. But they're put together
into one tree and then put into the different images
for you making Fedora server, for making for a workstation,
and then for making all of our various spins, KDE desktop,
the Python lab, the Docker image, all those things.
That's the compose.
And that's one big monolithic process.
And we were up to that taking something like 18 hours to run.
Although there's been some improvements in that.
But so now it's down to like 12.
But 12 is a very long time.
So that means from making a change
to getting it actually to a place
where our QA can test it takes a day.
And so as we're putting out a release,
that can get very frustrating.
Because let's say we want to sign off
on a release on Thursday.
Well, in order for QA to have time,
that release needs to be ready on Wednesday morning,
which means it needs to be kicked off on Tuesday, which
means we basically have, during that whole last week,
two chances, Monday and Tuesday, to get changes in,
which leads to 20 changes or 50 changes being put in all
at once, which is not very scientific.
And if something messes up, too bad,
we have to delay for a week.
So getting that compose time down,
I think the proposal aims for an hour,
which is nicely ambitious.
But even getting it down to four hours,
so during one normal workday, you could start off a compose.
And then if something goes wrong,
do another one would be a radical improvement.
So that's one of the things.
But there are a lot of things in our processes
that are like that, where it seems
like taking some time to look at it
and focus on actually improving the tooling and processes
would be worthwhile.
Now, I noted, too, in the pretty well-written problem statement
that's on the Wiki, that it says,
currently Fedora can't scale for more community ownership
of the things we release.
Only a few people can build and push our releases.
Is that also a team retooling problem there?
To me, when I read that, it sounds
like perhaps the Fedora project is seeking
to be able to independently release
bits of software they cannot currently independently
release.
Yeah, and some of it's a process thing.
Some of it's actually tooling, because the tooling
to do this literally has no permission structure.
So it's a, you can build everything
or you can build nothing.
And so having the tooling being a little bit smarter
about who can do what, not because we don't trust people,
but just so you don't accidentally rebuild KDE when
you went to rebuild XFCE and then it caused trouble.
It doesn't have that fine grain thing.
And again, because it's all one big compose,
basically it's just a, you could trigger the compose,
but you couldn't say build XFCE.
And that's one of the things we actually, like our XFCE spin,
didn't get built properly for the final release
for Fedora 29, which was bad, because we've
got a lot of people who love XFCE,
and we want that, even though that's not our main offering,
we want that to be successful for people.
I don't know what's the matter with them,
but they just stick to it.
They sure do.
Yeah, you like your interface as it is.
It's very personal, so it's important for people to have it.
There's really only one XFCE user out there.
I'm giving a hard time, and he knows who he is.
Yeah, that's right.
Actually, some of the Fedora infrastructure team
actually have XFCE users, so it was close to home.
I bet.
Well, OK, so speaking of XFCE and other sort
of user-facing things, what does all this internal
infrastructure process work mean for user-facing features?
Fedora's doing a lot of stuff.
In particular, I'm thinking of things like Silverblue.
Does that mean these are going to be delayed,
or will that work continue side by side?
Yeah, no, that's a hard thing with this.
And yeah, I think we've done a really good job of getting
onto our six-month cadence and making that fire successfully.
So I actually have a little bit of skepticism
about this plan of stopping things.
So I want to make sure that if we do this,
we have a good plan in place for making sure
that we actually succeed at the things we want to fix,
and then also that we don't break things
for people who have become accustomed to
and happy with having fast releases and good upgrades.
I mean, that seems like a key point.
If you're going to take this break,
it's really got to be worth it.
Because I look at the market right now,
and I see there's going to be some uncertainty
around the future of Fedora, misplaced or not.
But also, really, on the desktop side,
that could potentially mean skipping a GNOME release
cycle, which is kind of like a hard time
to miss a GNOME release cycle right now,
because so many great fixes are landing in GNOME.
Yeah.
And we did do this with the Fedora 20 release.
And I think we put GNOME as a copper to update to,
mixed results there.
We could do something like that again.
Flat packs.
Yeah, put all of GNOME in a flat pack.
You watch, it's going to happen.
One of the things we have now that we didn't
is this modularity system, which lets
us have two different versions of things.
So one idea is to make a GNOME module
so users could opt in to the newer version
using modularity.
That seems brilliant, actually.
Yeah.
And that's kind of what modularity was made for.
So it's also a good test for, hey,
can modularity do something major like this?
Let's make sure it can.
And then for something like Silverblue,
which is more on the experimental side,
the Silverblue OS tree compose could just
pick the newer module.
So Silverblue could have the newer version of things.
So we could have a more conservative and a more
aggressive release.
And then the idea would be to maintain the 30
packages for that whole year.
So I mean, in some ways, perhaps as a server user,
Fedora 30 could be a great release
because it's going to be, in some ways,
an extra long supported version of Fedora.
Is that true?
Yeah, if this proposal goes through.
And yeah, we actually see that in our stats
for the Fedora 19 and 20 releases, which ended up
having a longer cycle because of this.
Those were very, very popular releases
and still continue to, you know, there's
a long tail of people who should upgrade but never have,
who are still using those releases.
And I think that extra year definitely helped with that.
Interesting.
So yeah, that's a side effect as well.
Yeah, OK, that makes sense.
One thing that stood out to me in some of the top level
proposals here is defining a base platform.
And maybe this is something Red Hat wants to see some focus on,
but we were curious, what does that mean?
Yeah, so I'll talk about it from a Red Hat hat on
for a little bit here.
Just slightly, if you looked at the rel8 beta at all,
one of the things that Red Hat did
is split into a base OS and an app stream
where they can have different life cycles.
And things are different in Fedora,
but the basic concept kind of is helpful.
One of the things in Fedora, I don't
know if you followed all Fedora's history,
but one of the important good moves
was merging together Fedora Core, which
came from Red Hat Linux, and Fedora Extras,
which was kind of the community thing,
into one big community project.
That was great and really good for Fedora
and helped Fedora grow and become something
that was really a whole community distribution
rather than something that was just a corporate thing
that the community could build stuff on the fringes.
So that was great.
But one of the outcomes of that is
that Fedora is one gigantic repository
of undifferentiated packages, where some little toy thing
that I am interested in playing with is important to me.
But if it breaks, like five users will care,
and I'm one of them.
That is undifferentiated from something
like glibc in the distribution, or gnome,
or the things that if it breaks, a lot of people
will have their systems not work.
And I've been talking about this since before
as Fedora project leader with the Fedora rings idea,
basically making different policy levels for some
of our pack.
All of our packages are important,
but some of them kind of need a focus in QA.
And we've never had a defined set of,
we've got some that are like critical path,
but it's kind of a loose definition
of getting up to boot.
But some packages that we basically
say this is a QA set of packages together
that maybe if we're looking at doing a longer term maintenance
kind of situation, these are the ones we'd focus on.
If we want to make sure QA focuses on these things.
So it's narrowing down from our whatever 15,000 package
set to something like 1,000 packages
that we can really focus on polish on,
I think is a good idea.
That strikes me, too, that it might provoke
a few deeper conversations within the project about what's
our focus and what does it mean to ship this set of packages
and things like that.
So that could be a really fascinating event to watch.
Yeah.
And I think one of the things, focus is definitely important.
We want to make it so that the core resources of the project
are focused on this enabling core package set
and that people who do have those other cares can focus
on their part of it, not have to worry about the base part
falling apart on them, but they can also
focus their energy on the thing they care about
and develop solutions on top of that and give that to users.
So we should keep in mind that at this stage,
as we record this episode, this taking some time
to refocus on the tools is in most part
just a proposal at this stage.
So what happens next?
What process does this proposal go through to either become
reality or get rejected?
Yeah, so one of the key things here
is there's not secret room cabals
in Fedora deciding things.
So a lot of these things, you're seeing the process in action.
So when somebody proposes it, that means they had in.
This is an idea that several people have worked on.
One of the things we have in Fedora
is the idea of an objective.
And so an objective is something that the Fedora Council,
our leadership body, has said, this
is an area we think the project needs to focus on.
So we have an objective around the Fedora lifecycle
and the Fedora long-term maintenance possibilities.
Fedora, if you go to fedoraproject.docs
at fedoraproject.org and look under the project docs,
I can provide an actual link for this.
There's a section about our different objectives there.
And you can find link to documentation.
So this particular proposal came out of that objective
because there are people looking at these problems.
And so the general process is you
have this community discussion.
And then the Fedora Council will talk about it.
And the Fedora Council will probably
give a non-technical heads up, yes or no, we like this idea.
And the Fedora Council consists of me, community action
and impact coordinator Brian Exelbeer,
some elected people from the community,
and then also people selected by different committees
to be on the council.
And so it kind of gives an overview of the whole.
We try to take the input from the whole project
and reflect that into a definitive decision.
And then also because this is an engineering decision,
the engineering committee will probably also want
to skip a yes or no to this.
So that's basically the processes we'll go through.
It'll be interesting to watch that unfold.
And how do you feel about it personally?
I know as somebody who sits atop of this project
and has been watching it now for I think what is a record
breaking run, what do you think?
Is this a necessary delay?
Is this something that's sort of like taking your medicine?
Yeah, so like I said before, I've
got mixed feelings about it.
I feel really good that we've gotten ourselves
onto a well-firing Mother's Day Halloween release cadence, which
has always been our goal.
But we've sometimes slipped off of that.
Every now and then.
You're right.
So we hit our target schedule a couple times in a row now.
That's awesome.
So just when we've got that going,
seems like maybe not the best time to mess it up.
The joke almost makes itself at this point.
I'm not making it.
I'm just saying.
Yeah, exactly.
So I've got some skepticism about it.
On the other hand, I think it did work for us
when we did that Fedora 20 release.
And I think the problems are real.
The compose problem has been something
that's been frustrating to me for a while.
So spending some time to tackle it seems worthwhile.
But I also do want to make sure that we keep the concerns.
The upstream GNOME community is concerned.
I'm proud of Fedora as a premier GNOME distribution.
I want to keep that.
Sure.
And I want to make sure that people who are packagers who
aren't involved in all of the day-to-day release stuff
are able to keep getting their work to users
and don't feel like they're blocked for a year
from getting the things they're worked on out to people.
So yeah, it's a balance.
Yeah, it sounds like it.
Well, maybe we can check in at some point.
Yeah, I'd love to.
I have been following the project
with more and more interest.
He is at Matt DM on Twitter.
And we will have links to the problem documents
they have in the wiki, as well as the mailing list and the docs
that Matthew just mentioned there.
Is there anywhere else you want to send folks before we run?
Getfedora.org is always a great place
to check out if you don't have Fedora already installed.
Yeah, do it.
Good answer.
Good answer, man.
Matthew, thank you for coming on the show.
One of the things he touched on there that is a little more
obvious if you follow the links in our show notes
is this is the result of a larger objective they
set a while ago as a project.
And this is how they, as a project,
think they can achieve the objective
that they set for themselves.
And it's kind of in a broader context.
I know every project struggles with these tooling issues
sometimes.
But at the same time, you're like,
this is such a precious time to take off because.
Everyone else is moving fast.
There's been lots of good releases.
Yeah, and there's a lot of good fixes coming down the pipe
to GNOME that people are going to want.
So I think they're going to have to come up with a way
to get fresh GNOME to Fedora users.
At least I would think.
Otherwise, people might get a wandering eye
and go to a distribution that's maybe shipping patches
with performance fixes or something.
But we'll see.
You know, we have been talking about a predictions episode.
And we actually nailed down a date and time.
Oh, and by the way, again, thank you
to Matthew for coming on the show.
No kidding.
It's really nice to just get it from him.
We don't have to speculate and just understand
it's a proposal right now.
But yeah, so moving on, we will be recording
a special edition of the Unplugged.
Our special edition of the Unplugged program.
Do you remember?
Oh, yeah.
I do remember what the dates are.
So we'll be doing a predictions episode.
And I kind of feel like maybe we should do the predictions
episode while it's still 2018.
That seems appropriate.
Yeah, I agree.
So instead of doing, see, Linux Unplugged
gets the holiday hammer.
It is on Christmas Day and New Year's Day, the 25th
and the 1st.
So it's both our live days.
So what we're going to do, and I know
this is difficult for some of you,
but I'm hoping maybe it'll open up for others,
is we're just going to move the show one day.
So it'll be on Wednesday for those weeks.
So it'll be the day after Christmas
and it'll be the day after New Year's, so the 26th
and the 2nd.
Same time, just move it one day.
So on the 26th, we're going to do our predictions for 2019.
And if you really have a great prediction
and you have good audio, I invite
you to record a clip and then tweet it to me.
And I will try to include it in the show.
If you can't make it.
But otherwise, our Mumble Room will be open.
You can be here as part of our great virtual council
and make your predictions and pontifications for 2019.
And then you will have world fame, if you nail it,
because we will try to review them the following year
to see how we all did.
So that'll be on the 26th.
And then on the 2nd, maybe if you're still in party mode,
join us for the Mumble Room extravaganza,
where we will do what we want to see.
Wishes, reviews of what happened.
Yeah, you can get a little hopeful.
You don't have to be realistic in this here more fun episode.
That one's a little more low-key laid back.
You're not going to get reviewed.
And we're going to be also doing look back
at some of our favorite stories and be doing the,
if I had a magic wand and I could make project XYZ do ABC,
I would do it.
And then we consider and go, that's a great idea,
because it would mean more users come on board.
It's a fun thing to do.
So those will be just moving one day from our regularly
bat time on our, but obviously on the same bat channel,
right?
Is that the message I wanted to convey?
Yeah, there's a lot of bats involved.
So if you're scared of bats, watch out.
But otherwise, just come.
It's a great time.
You're probably going to get sick of your family anyway,
or maybe you're all by yourself
and we'll be your family for a day.
Our plan is to try to have something for you to listen to
over the holidays, because it's nice when,
not every, we get like the lowest downloads ever,
but it's like for me, like if I'm ever in a situation
where it's like all of a sudden I have like a bunch of time
in the car because I'm traveling for the holiday
or like sometimes I have like these weird gaps
in my schedule where it's like been rush, rush, rush, rush,
rush for the holiday.
And then all of a sudden I find myself without kids,
without my significant others,
like I got half a day to burn.
And then when nobody's releasing stuff,
it's kind of a bummer.
So we thought let's try to stick with it this year
and we'll just bump the schedule a bit.
So it'll be out a day later those weeks,
but there will be a show.
And if you go to linuxunplugged.com slash subscribe,
you can just grab the episode automatically
and don't have to worry about it.
You can also go to Jupiterbroadcasting.com
and check out the calendar if you forget
just when that's happening.
Well, really quickly, one last item on the agenda,
it's that Dropbox quote unquote hack I've been using.
I mean, ultimately, this is a temporary fix.
In fact, big disclaimer here,
I mean, this could potentially even lead to data loss.
So don't do what Chris does, okay?
Is that fair?
Can we make that disclaimer?
Don't do as Chris does.
But I'm using the Dropbox file system fix project.
And the thing I like about this is it lets you run Dropbox
and any damn encryption or any damn file system you please.
And I think that's what's important.
It essentially fixes the file system detection
in the Linux client to restore the sync capability.
So bear in mind, it's doing some trickery here.
And if they introduce something in the future
to the Dropbox client, you could have some problems.
Oh, yeah, as you might suspect, this is an LD preload trick.
So you have to run make, you got to build yourself
a little.so from the included C,
and then it provides a separate Python script
that will start Dropbox with the custom library.
So it's making ext4 assumptions
that aren't just what file system is this,
there could be issues,
but so far, it sounds like it's working for you.
Yeah, it's been fine.
And I did have to build it.
And then I had to disable Dropbox from starting at startup.
And then I essentially just created a new desktop launcher
and added that to my startup items.
So the Python script has kicked off that way.
It's fine.
It's been working good.
It's been going for about half a week,
survived a couple of reboots just fine.
So I'll do this as I transition off.
I might do what Wimpy did
and might toss it on a headless box somewhere.
And that'll be how I begin the transition to something else.
A hacky solution to a problem we should never have had.
Yeah, I've sent them my feedback.
They know how I feel, Wes.
So also a little plug here for the TechSnap show,
the TechSnap.Systems, Wes Payne,
and myself are doing a show over there
that if you're in the IT field,
if you are a sysadmin,
if you work on servers or on the cloud
and want somebody to commiserate with,
hear about particular topics like WireGuard, eBPF,
what's some other things we've done recently?
Boy, we did, we had a great breakdown of the whole
Spectre meltdown stuff when that came out.
The show is just famous for doing the deep dives.
And we're gearing it up to do even more.
We'll have more details about that soon.
So check out TechSnap.Systems
because there's a lot of good stuff going on over there
and even more coming.
And then go check out the Gentleman Show,
Ubuntu podcast, my favorite show
that's not a Jupiter broadcasting show
that's not late night Linux.
Because I love all the-
Careful, man, careful, man.
I know, I have to be really careful.
It's a little awkward, but I try.
All of our brothers in arms.
Go check that out at UbuntuPodcast.org
and go check out Late Night Linux too
because they're doing some great work over there.
Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode.
You are always welcome to join us live,
hang out in that mumble room, chat with Wes and I.
Oh, please do.
We miss you already.
You get a little pre-show and you get a little post-show
in the released version, but there's probably 30 times more
than what actually gets released.
And to be honest, we say all the best things
when we're not in the release.
Especially when I'm cursing about YouTube.
Oh, it gets me so fired up.
Anyways, that's all for this week.
Check out all our links at linuxunplugged.com slash 277.
I'm at Chris Elias.
He's at Westpaint.
Thank you for joining us.
See you next Tuesday!
I'm Chris Elias, and I'll see you next week.
Hey, Unplugged Show.
Oh, man.
277.
Rapidly approaching the 300.
Oh, diggity-do.
Wimpy, before you leave tonight, I have a problem
and I want to know if you've experienced this.
I think it might be because I went with the GPU dock.
A little bit of real-time GPU dock follow-up.
I've got a vertical monitor and a horizontal monitor
at 2K resolution hooked up over DisplayPort,
and ever since I've done that, my window performance
has gone in the tank.
Like, on my main laptop, the quote-unquote prime display,
it's fine.
It's butter smooth.
But on the external monitors, it's choppy, it's laggy.
Like, resizing Windows is jittery.
Even my typing is sometimes stuttery.
It's way worse than I expected.
Have you had this problem?
Is this a?
I have not experienced that, no.
Oh, it's got to be something with that multiple GPU
setup then.
I would think it's all using the NVIDIA
because I can manage the panels with the NVIDIA Control Panel.
So it's all going through the NVIDIA,
and it should be able to handle three displays.
Yeah, it should.
I've only ever run two until recently, though.
And obviously, the third display that I now have
is a panel on the laptop.
But no, I've not experienced that.
I've only experienced that when I've moved a game off
of the prime display into an IGP-powered display,
and that's expected.
But you've got one, and I also run both of mine landscape.
I haven't done that mix of portrait and landscape.
Yeah, and I've noticed 3D performance
on the Prime main laptop display still seems perfectly fine.
I can play a game and have those other displays
with displaying stuff.
And it's good enough.
If I put things that's fairly static,
like chats and even a YouTube video is fine.
But if I want to resize a window or start typing it,
sometimes just can't keep up.
And I just don't understand what's going on.
I've wondered if it's a plasma problem, even.
But I doubt it.
But I've heard that there's issues with Plasma and NVIDIA
doing multiple monitors.
I'm not going to switch to GNOME over this,
because like I said, it's butter smooth on the main display.
And again, I can't speak to anything other than Mate,
because that's the only desktop that I've used.
I think we want to try it, though.
Tell you what, it has made me think about doing a live disk
and just seeing, does this?
You probably should.
I mean, that way is just fine.
I'm not switching.
And then what do I do?
Get frustrated?
We can tweak it from there.
I mean, for science's sake.
I got to know.
All right, thanks, Wes.