A happy Easter, gentlemen.
Did you get yourselves anything for Easter?
Yeah, I found a few eggs just outside the studio door.
I assume you put those there for me, right?
Well, they were for raccoons,
but I'm just hoping that Alex set out
a little treasure hunt for Brent.
How often is Brent down in the States for Easter?
I hope like maybe an egg hunt happened.
What happened this morning?
Tell us, guys, how'd you celebrate?
Missed opportunity.
Yeah, we didn't do anything.
We didn't even think about it.
But what did happen two days ago
was a massive, I mean, massive box of chocolates
showed up at Alex's place here,
and he's been trying not to get into it ever since.
Oh, man.
Yeah, care package from England, proper chocolate.
Did anybody warn them that you just spent a week
eating the croissants from the meetup?
Like, this is not what you need right now.
I literally did, yeah.
Yeah, I bet Brent's been cooking good, though,
so you're probably making it up on the other end
because he's a pretty lean cook in terms of caloric intake.
Yeah, I lost 20 pounds in the month before the meetup,
and I've gained about half of that back since the meetup.
That's how you know it's a good meetup.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk
show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
My name is Brent.
And my name is Alex.
Hello, gentlemen.
Glad to have you all here today because it is indeed a big show.
Ubuntu 2204 LTS and Fedora 36 are both landing soon,
perhaps the day you're listening to this or near.
They both feature GNOME 42 and lots of great new ideas
baked in, so we're going to take a look at both of them
and share our thoughts, and then we're
going to round out the show with some great boosts, our picks,
and all the stuff that we love to do.
But before we go any further, let's check the board.
Let's bring in the Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, Virtual Lug.
Good evening.
Hey, Brent, hey, Wes, hey, Chris.
Nice to have you.
Hello, hello.
Hello, guys.
You know, I want to say right here towards the top of the show
that you are always welcome to join our Mumble Room,
even if you don't want to participate necessarily.
I know that sounds weird, but I mention it
because Mumble's free software, so it has
kind of a nice advantage there.
And I want to encourage that adoption
because I think it's nice to have decentralized free software
voice communication tools.
It uses high quality Opus audio.
Also free software.
And you're getting a mix directly from our mixer
here in the studio, and Mumble has super low latency.
So it's just a great way to get a high quality audio feed
using free software, and you can load it on your phone.
We usually get the stream started
around noon Pacific time, which is, what,
3 PM on the New York side?
Indeed.
And around the world, you can do the math there,
but we'd love to have you join us live over at jblive.tv
if you want to watch it.
Or you can use Mumble.
Like, we've got a handful of folks in the quiet listening
right now just getting the lowest latency audio stream.
In fact, it is possible they are getting the lower latency
audio feed of my voice right now than Alex and Brent are.
I mean, Mumble's really impressive,
and it's great because we can just run it
on our own infrastructure.
Or Noah's.
It actually might be on Noah's server still.
Either way, we'd love to have you there or join us live
on a Sunday.
So let's get into the show.
Let's talk about Fedora 36 first,
because I think a lot of what we're going to touch on
is probably in its more upstream form in Fedora.
So I think it kind of makes sense
from a conversational standpoint.
We've all kind of been taking a look at it for a little while.
So there's a lot to unpack in both of these releases.
So we're going to try to break it up
to what's relevant to each one.
And Fedora 36, while outwardly I'd
say the headline feature for desktop users is GNOME 42,
it seems like when you look at some of the other things,
like Wayland support with NVIDIA.
About time.
Podman 4.0 under the hood, it kind of
feels like 36 is going to have some really kind of changes
that will improve the Fedora workstation and server
experience for a long time.
Fedora is making a shift here with Podman
and with NVIDIA and Wayland support.
I think this is laying the groundwork for something,
but we'll get into that in a little bit.
Because I'm curious, Wes, I asked you not to tell me.
You've been running them both, Ubuntu 22.04 and Fedora 36.
And I'm curious which one you've chosen
to run here on the show today.
I know I said pick the one you like the most
and wait till the show starts.
So which one did you choose?
Well, let's just say that SE Linux would like you to know
that GNOME Shell is trying to access its icon cache.
I am taking that to mean Fedora 36.
Yes, that's right.
So you like the 36 desktop?
I do.
It's very snappy.
And especially, I've been mostly using it here
on this ThinkPad.
So for the laptop use case, I like the stock GNOME
experience, especially with that new dark mode support.
It doesn't take much to get this into a state
that I'm happy with using it.
It all works.
And then I've been really impressed with just
with how good the pipeline setup on Fedora is getting.
Ubuntu has made some advances there, too,
which is also good to see.
I was able to download Reaper, start it up.
It figured out that it could talk Jack back to pipeline
without me having to do anything.
And then the whole system worked great with the new headphones
I bought without having to futz with it as well.
So it's kind of I'm living the pro audio when I want it,
and it just works on the other hand,
which that's hard to turn down.
Wow, yeah, you're getting both.
And have you done like audio playback with the headphones
and they've stayed connected when you stop the music
and then restart the music and stuff like that?
No problem there.
It's nice to see it getting to that point.
That is nice.
It's nice to know you can go out and get yourself
a pair of modern Bluetooth headphones
and you got a good shot of them working with your Linux desktop.
I'll save my thoughts, but I'm curious if Alex or Brent,
if either of you got any much time with the desktop side
of Fedora 36?
Well, we actually decided to kind of do it jointly
because as it turns out, Alex had a laptop here buried
in his little closet over there.
That's fairly modern, a T480, I think it was, Alex.
Yeah, Red Hat provided me a ThinkPad for work.
And I've been running Fedora 30, I think 3 was the first one
I put on there.
I've upgraded it now from 33 to 34.
It was on 35 when we started last night.
So we thought we'd upgrade to some beta software
and what's the worst that could happen?
And actually, the upgrade to 36 was completely uneventful.
I think boring in this case is probably a good thing.
What was interesting was we were actually
connected to my Thunderbolt dock as we did it,
which was a CalDigit one, which is typically
only a Mac compatible dock.
But my Thunderbolt monitor was picked up straight away,
no problems whatsoever.
Ethernet just worked.
All the USB devices worked perfectly.
And throughout the entire upgrade,
both displays, and I'm talking about the internal laptop
display and the Thunderbolt display,
were completely flicker free.
Remember that being added a while ago?
All the way through the upgrade process,
everything was just completely smooth
as far as the visual aspect was concerned.
There was a nice progress bar.
And I've got nothing really bad to say about the process.
It just worked.
I mean, it upgraded what, 1,700 packages or so?
1,756, I think, if I remember.
Yeah, a couple of gigs worth of updates.
And yeah, just worked.
You know, you did, Alex, mention the monitors.
We ran into a strange situation.
I'm not sure if it's the monitor itself
or if it's this hub you're using.
But one of your monitors, which I'm
sure you'll fill in the details, ended up with a refresh rate
that was really odd.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, so I've got a 4K USB-C monitor,
which I directly connected to the ThinkPad
using the single USB-C cable provided
with the monitor, which is a Dell 2723QE, I think.
And for some reason, when we had 100% scaling turned on,
we got 60 hertz, no problem.
If we went to 200% scaling, which
is about where I like my 4K monitor,
it dropped to only 30 hertz.
And that's painful.
Actually, 29.98, I believe it was.
Yeah, I've seen that.
It's nice that it can do it.
It is even better now than ever.
And I really feel like there's pretty much zero
Wayland penalty that I've run into so far, especially
with the 36 release.
And 42 is the best release of GNOME from the project ever,
including even the very later versions of GNOME 2.
In my opinion, obviously, this is the most refined,
most expressed version of what the GNOME vision is
that we have ever seen.
And if you don't like GNOME 42, you're
just never going to like GNOME, which is OK.
And if there's elements of GNOME you've liked in the past
and you haven't checked in in a bit,
I think it's going to blow your freaking socks off.
They have really nailed the light mode, dark mode stuff.
It is significantly better than just a hacked theme
to do dark mode.
It really is, yeah.
It feels like you get on some of those other platforms.
And they've made improvements to the default theme
that just look great anyways, that just
make it look like a polished, professional operating system.
And I even like it in the light mode now.
It's just great.
So this is a strong version of GNOME
that really realizes the whole 4D transition,
because this is where you really see the Libidwaita
and the GTK4 stuff really land.
You've got the new GNOME terminal called Console,
I think, and the new text editor that's
replacing GEDIT just called Text or Text Editor,
something like that.
But they're both pretty good apps out of the gate.
We used to have this problem on the GNOME side
where they would reboot an app, and you would then
wait for three releases before it
had the functionality that the previous application had.
That has not been my experience with the recent reboots
of these applications.
And they look like really nice modern applications
that are at home on the GNOME desktop.
The other thing that's really, I think,
palatable for those of us that pay attention to just
the way your screen draws and stuff like that,
with GTK4 in here, with the Vulkan back end for GTK4 stuff,
with a number of performance-focused tweaks
that they have laid into all of GNOME 42,
some of the improved tooling, some of the leaner-meaner apps
that are in this thing, like the new screenshot app,
like the new terminal app, like the new text editor app,
like the improvements to files, like the list
goes on and on, you guys.
It really all comes together for the smoothest desktop
experience on GNOME ever.
And those are even realized on the Raspberry Pi.
I can even tell an improvement on the Raspberry Pi.
Oh, you put this thing on the Pi?
Yeah, yeah.
And it's great.
It's really something special.
And to be fair, Tumbleweed got it first.
I already had Tumbleweed on the Pi, so I was good to go.
It was great.
We thought Fedora 36 and Ubuntu would get there first,
but Tumbleweed did.
The wizards.
I know.
They're always hacking away at that kind of stuff.
I think this is such a great release of GNOME
that I think it's going to be really hard for the team
to now kind of eclipse what this all accumulates to.
And one of the things I love about Fedora 36
is you get the real stock upstream experience.
Now, we'll talk about Ubuntu's take on that in a minute,
but that's one of the nice things about Fedora 36
is you get to see sort of the project's vision there.
The new Snapshot app is really nice.
I like to take little screenshots and send them
to Wes all the time, so it makes that real quick.
Yeah, it's true.
It feels really just native to the system, you know?
Yeah.
That's nice.
The other thing that was different for this release
cycle than like the last two or three Fedora release cycles
was how we should probably clarify too,
it hasn't quite actually been released.
We're getting here a little early because, you know,
schedules.
That's what we like, because it's
scheduled to land towards the end of April.
As soon as the week this comes out,
maybe as late as the end of April,
2204 is likely going to hit its target, which
will be this week.
But this is kind of where I was going.
This beta of Fedora 36 has been the most solid beta experience
I've ever had in Fedora.
Like, I have just about had every beta experience blow up
in my face once, which that's the name of the game.
Yeah, it's not a bad thing.
It's just part of the trying this out
while it all gets assembled.
And I'm just riding that horse, and I don't really
count that against, again, them in the review,
because that's the beta process that's what it's for.
It did not happen in this 36 release cycle.
It did not blow up on me once.
It just, I did my daily updates.
I like to do it daily.
You know, when I had new stuff, I installed it.
Every time I rebooted the system or whatever,
it always came back up.
And I think what's happened here is on Fedora,
especially, I've migrated to installing
most of my user applications via Flathub and Flatpak.
Yeah, me too.
So everything's kind of isolated from the system.
All of my work communication apps, I use,
I think my browsers are installed from the repo.
Of course, I'm using the desktop environment from the repo.
I mean, some of that stuff, right?
But all my chat apps, all the tools I use for work.
All the weird proprietary stuff.
Yeah, that's all Flatpak now.
And so you take that and you combine it
with just a smooth beta that isn't doing anything
too crazy outside the desktop space.
And it made for a really nice beta experience.
And I really think out of the gate,
it's gonna be a solid release.
I'm just gonna go right to it.
Like I was thinking with the last release,
it was so rough, I was gonna wait like six months.
But yeah, no, I've been using this as my primary OS
on the ThinkPad since we talked about GNOME 42
a couple episodes ago, and I've had the same experience.
Just rock solid, I think I'll keep using it.
The one thing I might want to adjust
is I'm still not used to these offline updates.
You know, like they can apply it almost Windows style.
Here I was playing with 2204, rebooting a bunch,
accidentally choose Fedora,
and then I'm waiting for updates.
You mentioned how bumpiness is a fairly standard thing
about running beta software.
My experience has largely echoed yours this time with 36.
It's been very smooth sailing.
No driver issues, no messing about with God,
do you remember Xorg stuff?
Like I had two external displays just working out the box
straight away, you know, no real issues.
The one thing I did have was in the mirrors for some reason,
they seem to be a little bit behind.
And my updates with DNF were looking for packages
that didn't exist in quite a lot of the mirrors,
like the 404s that came through, they were quite extensive.
And so that led me to dig into the mirror process
for Fedora a little bit.
And it turns out that you can sync as often
as every 10 minutes if you're a Fedora repo manager,
or, you know, like a mirror.
But there's no, or seemingly anyway,
there's no documented thing that says
you must sync at least once a day or something like that.
And it's all done through sort of our sync,
which I thought was interesting.
I suppose not too surprising,
but I've never really thought about that.
And of course that's gonna be distro to distro as well.
The individual admin who's configuring
those system detimers perhaps.
Yeah, and with, you know, depending on the mirror you pick,
you just, I guess it's sort of random
what they decided to do.
I think it's worth noting that it looks like 37 plus,
Fedora 37 plus, that's gonna be interesting.
First of all, they're switching to a newer version of RPM
just for better security.
We'll cover this as it comes up.
They're also planning to drop support
for legacy bio systems.
So long.
This is the most probably,
if you could label something controversial about this,
this is probably it.
There's a lot of mixed opinions here
about deprecating old hardware.
And of course there's valid arguments on both sides.
If you're interested, send us a boost
if you want us to cover that and we'll get to it.
And then also speaking of Xorg,
37 is considering the removal of legacy Xorg drivers as well.
So it's a big transition in terms of
the underlying hardware support
they're essentially gonna, I guess, support.
And it's gonna change.
It's gonna change the nature of the user base for Fedora.
And it's going to mean there's some users
that can no longer move forward.
But it also means that the team will be able
to focus their time, talent, and energy
on the broader user base, better security practices,
all of the optimizations you get when you reduce complexity.
And it seems like, especially these last couple of releases,
Fedora's really been shining on the leaning edge
kind of idea that they're going for.
And so I think these kind of things are in that spirit
and I'm all about it.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit
and you go there to support the show.
Linode's how we host everything.
And Linode could also be part of your multi-cloud strategy.
You know, one of the things that we're really proud of
is that we've used Linode in a way
that feels strategically smart.
We've got a lot of our user-facing stuff,
well, all of our user-facing stuff up in the cloud
where we can take advantage of Linode's scaling tools,
their incredible customer support,
their 11 data centers around the world,
their super nice UI with an API
that makes it easy to integrate with our tools.
Like, it's great for that.
But we mix it with kind of a multi-cloud strategy
where we have our own little tiny cloud here on the land.
And they work really well together.
In fact, Gardner estimates that two-thirds
of all cloud industry customers
will adopt a multi-cloud setup
as a means for avoiding vendor lock-in by the end of 2024.
And the reality is the largest hyperscaler cloud vendors
that try to present themselves as a one-stop shop,
inviting you to become wholly dependent on them
and centralize all of your resources.
And they'll offer everything you might ever need.
But you know the problem of relying
on a single cloud provider like that.
It's the same problem as relying
on a single commercial software vendor.
You get deeply entwined.
You get locked in.
And you get locked in to your infrastructure.
That can be dangerous.
And so with pricing 30 to 50% cheaper
than other major cloud providers,
Linode is great for the individuals,
but it's also great for businesses looking for a multi-cloud strategy.
Plus, they combine it with great things like object storage,
Kubernetes support, DDoS protection, VLAN,
a powerful DNS manager,
and, of course, that cloud dashboard
that's easy for beginners, total noobs,
and, of course, industry pros.
So go use our $100 offer to performance test your network,
troubleshoot something, build something, learn something,
maybe create a backup.
There's so many great options,
and they have tutorials to help you get started
on anything you might need and one-click application deployments.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
That's Linode.com slash unplugged.
Well, if Fedora is the leading edge,
I think it's safe to call Ubuntu the mainstream,
and Ubuntu 22.04, which will release later this month.
This is going to be a big release because, you know,
all your boring friends running the LTS,
they're going to finally upgrade.
This thing's going to be supported till April 2027.
So whatever we're getting right now,
it's going to be here to stay.
We are so spoiled with these LTS releases,
and the community just eats these ones up.
These canonical stresses this all the time.
Anytime we've talked to them,
the magnitude of difference is substantial.
And so we thought, let's take a look at this thing
because this is the one people are going to be considering
deploying on their VPSs, on their Raspberry Pis,
on their servers, on their workstations, and it matters.
And we also know that the interim releases
are often just building towards the climax,
which is the LTS release.
And so once again, we all kind of took a look at it
around the horn, and I'll start with mine
because mine are pretty straightforward so far.
I started by, you know, it's a funny thing for me.
My LTS systems are no joke, right?
The ones that I'm running Ubuntu LTS on,
I have something of value on them.
And so it's a serious calculation for me when I'm like,
which one am I going to upgrade
before it's even officially released
to test it for the show?
But I love you guys, so I did it.
And so I picked one of,
I don't know if I'll acknowledge this before on the show,
but I have what I call support nodes
that are in orbit of LadyJoobs.
And these run on different servers on Linode's cloud,
and they provide support services for LadyJoobs,
like synchronizing data, moving things around for me,
copying certain backups, stuff like that.
And these both run Ubuntu 20.04, well, they did.
But I decided to give these ones an upgrade
because it would be a major pain in my ass
if anything happened to them,
but I'm not planning a road trip right now
or anything like that, so I would have time to recover them.
And I have to say, I think one of the experiences
that I have over and over again
when I try out an Ubuntu distro
is when you use the server side of Ubuntu,
when you use that like in a headless environment
where maybe you're SSHing in,
it's elegant in certain ways,
where they've built tooling
where you can tell the team
really spent time developing something,
and they really built it well,
and they can just kind of iterate on it after that.
And that's how I felt about
their do release upgrade program.
It's a really handy tool that lets you upgrade
before it releases out,
or it lets you upgrade after it releases out.
And it just does a lot of sanity checking
on your distribution to try to make sure
you get the best outcome possible.
And where the polish is, is you can tell that the team,
they put a lot of effort into collecting
a bunch of information about your system,
and then relaying it to you
in a very relatable, readable way.
I put a link to an upgrade warning screenshot
that I got in the process of one of these,
and we'll put a link to this in the show notes
so you guys can check this out.
And it just walks you through here
where it says, you're gonna have to download
a total of 741 megabytes of files.
This download will take about two minutes
with a 40 megabit connection,
so it's benchmarked my connection.
And about 19 minutes with a five megabit connection,
or maybe it's just giving you examples, I guess.
Fetch and installing the upgrade can take several hours.
It just kind of walks you through everything
in very plain, understandable language.
And the other thing it does is it makes sure
you're not gonna shoot yourself in the foot.
Like maybe you're at a disk space
because you didn't realize that your overlay FS2 folder
had grown to 50 gigabytes.
And so your root partition is totally full.
And it checks that kind of stuff before you upgrade,
or maybe, maybe you were doing this upgrade
even though you know better.
Even though you know better,
you were doing this upgrade over an SSH connection
that wasn't in any kind of session manager
or using any kind of reliable connection like a MOSH,
but just raw dog SSH.
Maybe you did that even though you know better.
I'm not sure you've even ever used Tmux.
It will warn you and say, hey man,
maybe you don't wanna do this in an SSH connection.
And don't ask me how I know, but maybe that's you.
And it just kind of prevents those kinds of mistakes.
And then it works the system through the upgrade.
It does the reboot.
And the other thing it does that's really clever
is it notices that you are using a third party mirror,
which Linode does this.
Linode replaces the canonical mirrors
with local Linode caches.
And the package install times are bananas as a result.
Like they just stream down faster
than your new app could move,
probably at the maximum speed of apt.
Let's be honest.
Probably.
And so it says, hey, I noticed you're using
a third party sources.list file.
I can't guarantee that they're gonna have the packages.
I can swap the names for you, man,
but I can't guarantee they're gonna have the packages.
So I said, yeah, go for it.
Let's see if Linode is pre-caching the release.
Let's find out.
So I said, yes, it modifies my sources.list from Linode
to keep the Linode mirrors,
but puts the jammy name in there
instead of the focal fossil
or whatever the old release was, I can't remember.
And sure enough, Linode had the packages already mirrored.
And so my upgrade on both of these nodes
was bananas fast,
just because I was using the local mirrors to upgrade.
And Linode had what you needed.
And I only had to solve the storage issue on one box.
I mean, somebody did, not me, but maybe somebody.
And it went great.
And both systems came right back up.
They're running just fine.
And I really have no complaints.
I think it's gonna, you know, I didn't need to,
but I think it's gonna just be great.
I'll run these for a little bit.
And then my thought is,
when the actual shipping version is out,
I'll probably start upgrading my pies in LadyJuice.
And then I'll report back on the self-hosted podcast
on how that goes.
Oh, nice.
What about you, Brent?
Did you get a chance to kick the tires?
I did, and I was extra interested
because I actually got the chance maybe,
I don't know, three weeks ago.
They were doing the alpha testing week,
and I got my hands dirty in there and found a bunch of bugs.
And it was neat to see the progression.
Most of those, the ones that I filed,
which was about eight of them,
all had lots of action and got kind of all fixed.
And I was interested in seeing that.
So I would say from that perspective,
it actually went great.
Upon installing, I really was curious
about the new Flutter installer.
And I ran into a few probably edge case bugs
as I seem to have a knack for finding.
But overall, it worked quite well.
And I loved the look of Ubuntu as well,
the desktop edition, and no complaints really.
I thought as an LTS, it seemed stable to me
and really quite nice to look at.
I'm not a GNOME expert, I would say,
but it feels like, Chris,
that I'm getting in just at the right time
because everybody seems to have a really nice take on it.
I think 42 is a great release
if you haven't checked it out for a while.
That's my main takeaway from the show.
So if you haven't tried GNOME, it's time to try it again.
Alex, did you get a chance to try out the Ubuntu side?
No, I'm more in the production deployment camp
with Ubuntu these days.
So my file server is on Ubuntu.
So I think that's running 2004 right now,
and it will stay there until 2204.1 comes out.
Ah, yeah, that's a good strategy.
I'm debating something like that
other than just, I wanna talk about it on Self-Hosted,
how the upgrade experience goes.
Yeah, I know, I know.
The life of a content creator, huh?
I gotta make content, you know?
That's the job.
But also, it's like, sometimes I feel like
a little bit of like, well, I could do it,
and then I'll do it so they don't have to,
and if it blows up, I'll tell them about it,
and if it doesn't blow up, they'll know it's okay.
I really think Canonical has nailed
the Raspberry Pi support now for a while.
It's so nice.
It is such a first, it feels like such a first class
server OS on the Raspberry Pi,
which is such a silly thing to actually say,
but hey, it's where we're at right now.
I mean, when it's just now that Raspberry Pi OS
is kind of catching up, you need,
this has been kind of a haven for you
for saying OS for your boxes.
It's been great.
I like it, I mean, personally,
I like it a lot more than Raspberry Pi OS.
So Fedora 36, I believe, was Rockin' Linux 5.17.
Ubuntu 22.04 is Rockin' 5.15.
It's both pretty modern.
This one came with that, 5.15 is when they introduced
the Samba server in the Linux kernel.
Yeah, KSMBD.
You know how much I love having a Samba server
built into the Linux kernel.
What else could you want?
Now you can finally flip it on those pies, man.
Come on, replace your Samba setup at Chubb's.
You know, I mean, everybody says that Samsung
doesn't contribute much to open source,
but that speaks differently.
So what was your experience, Wes Payne, with 22.04?
You know, I'm liking it.
I think we've lamented a little bit about
how much has Canonical been investing
into the Ubuntu desktop experience.
And although I think I do kind of prefer
the more stock GNOME feel going on
on the Fedora side of things, GNOME 42 is great on Ubuntu.
It's a really nice experience.
And I'm almost not used, I know this will change
over the lifetime of the LTS, but for right now,
I'm almost not used to how close these two releases are.
You know, in the past, Ubuntu had kind of been
a little lagging on GNOME.
And then even just across some of the packages,
like, you know, you get Ruby 3.0, you get Python 3.10,
which is a pretty big release in the Python community.
A bunch of stuff like that, LexD, you get QEMU 6.2,
which also includes jack support for low latency audio.
There's a really nice PipeWire support on Ubuntu now.
It's not quite as shiny or like automated.
You know, they've still got the old media session thing
instead of wire plumber.
So there's a few trade-offs, but.
But I feel like for an LTS,
that's probably what I would have expected them to do
with the audio subsystem.
Yes, I think that's nice mix too,
because you still got Pulse going.
So, you know, that's all gonna work
just as you might expect,
but there's still PipeWire things you can plug into
if you do need to go above and beyond.
This release switches to NF tables as well, right?
It does, yeah, isn't that nice to think?
And another thing where Ubuntu's really kind of catching up.
And we get LexD 5 finally,
which we talked about on LAN recently.
Indeed, I was a little disappointed to see,
I mean, so there is a new little bumped release of ZSYS,
which is sort of the, you know,
their ZFS integration in the file system
into more of like the system level of the operating system,
but it was mostly just a compatibility bump
for the, you know, the newer version of ZFS
that they're shipping.
So not a ton of work there.
A lot of initial upfront work,
and then it seems very minimal iterative,
but maybe I have the wrong impression.
Also there, I gave the Flutter installer a go as well.
Seemed, you know, it's still early days.
It's quite minimal.
Towards the end, it looks a lot like what you're used to.
The time zone support seemed very early.
It did auto detect what I wanted,
but I didn't see a great way
besides manually type it in to change it.
And although you can have it do LVM for you,
there's no ZFS support.
Yeah, that was interesting.
I gave it a go early myself.
I see where they're going with it.
I think it looks fine.
I'll be interested as more people get experience
and exposure to that, what their take is.
You can Google search.
There's a build of the ISO that has the Flutter installer,
if you'd like to grab that.
I think it's also notable that one of the features
we talked about has been pulled,
and that is the switch of rebranding
the live patch stuff to Ubuntu Pro.
That actually didn't end up in 2204.
They ended up reverting back
to the live patch branding and whatnot.
Maybe they just felt, I think they actually did,
I think maybe Joey had an article,
somebody had an article that,
yeah, Joey has an article over at OMG Ubuntu
that talks a little bit about their motivation
and pulling it out.
Just seems like it wasn't quite ready yet.
Doesn't really change any actual functionality.
Live patch stuff is still all in there.
Right, yeah, you can still get the service if you need it,
but just a little more consistent for now.
Yeah, so the upgrade process
on the systems I tried went smooth.
I also ran this beta nearly the entire time
that it was in beta on and off in a VM,
just kind of checking in on it, not serious usage,
but checking in and doing the upgrades
to see if anything breaks.
Also very smooth upgrade.
And I think as time has gone on,
I have my take on canonical or Ubuntu spin
on the GNOME 42 desktop has softened.
When we saw Fedora's take,
which was basically upstream in the new Adwaita,
and then we saw the canonical Ubuntu version,
I thought this branding that they're doing
is starting to feel old.
It's starting to feel like the way we used to do Linux.
And when I see what the GNOME platform is doing
and the way they're iterating that design,
and my fundamental argument always was,
and I don't think I articulated it very well
until just recently,
if GNOME didn't want downstream projects
re-theming the desktop,
then the upstream theme
just simply needed to be better quality.
It needed to be a better theme
if they wanted people to use it.
And they've done it.
That's what they've done now.
And so there's a bit of a mind shift that happens
when you compare these two distros side by side.
And if you got some free VM space or something,
maybe give this a go at home.
Load up Fedora 36, load up 2204.
And I think you can objectively say it's nice.
They're both really nice,
but I'm starting to feel like the custom brand theming
is a bit akin to like OEMs loading up new laptops
with their like dashboards to help your PC health
and stuff like that.
It's not quite that bad.
That's not like they're putting software on there
that's stealing processor cycles and stuff.
So I don't want people thinking
like it's a bad thing necessarily,
but it doesn't quite sit with me right anymore.
Alex, what are your thoughts?
Why do both of the major desktop distros
both have to pick GNOME as their default?
Why can't we have some differentiation in the space?
Why can't one be plasma, for example,
and one be GNOME and that be the differentiator
rather than putting lipstick on a pig, you know?
I think you don't want me to answer why.
Oh no, I do, please.
What it comes down to is as someone who works
on both Fedora Workstation and Fedora KDE,
the most frustrating aspect of working
with the KDE plasma stack is how huge it is
and how discordant the life cycles
of each layer of plasma is.
So for example, the frameworks
has a completely independent life cycle.
It's released monthly.
Then the KDE applications were to release quarterly.
And then the plasma desktop itself
is released every four months,
and it's out of sync of every distribution release cadence.
And that makes it difficult for testing,
for integration and all that stuff.
Plus, because it's so big,
there's a large surface area of things to manage.
And differentiating on the plasma desktop,
in theory, would be great,
except for it is extremely difficult
to keep up with the plasma desktop
and differentiate on it in the first place.
Think about how Ubuntu was originally using Unity,
and it was a lot of engineering work
for them to maintain that in the first place.
And when they decided to let that go
and they switched to GNOME,
the primary reason for doing that
was because the other enterprise Linux distributions,
the main enterprise Linux distributions,
Red Hat and SUSE, both use GNOME,
and so they could benefit from the work
that was being done already
with the focus of those platforms.
Yeah.
Tiny, that's a bit of it, isn't it?
It's about retaining the developers
that already have the skills.
That's correct, especially because a lot of these distros
have long-term support tied to them,
whether it's Fedora eventually getting rolled into Red Hat
or Canonical, they would have to maintain
both a QT stack and a GTK stack for the lifecycle
while both of them are still around.
Yeah, and we've asked Karl and the team at System76
when they launched POP, why GNOME Shell,
and now building POP Shell on top of that,
why not Plasma and you could kind of just get
to what you wanted using the Plasma tooling built in.
And they were very honest about the answer is,
well, the team knows GTK tooling.
We know GNOME Shell, we know this environment,
and that's where our developer skills are.
So it's potentially just one of those things
where it's a network effect of,
and it just means because it's been around for so long,
it's been the default for so long,
there's inherently just more people
that the market can hire that have skills in there.
I don't know for sure, but that could definitely seem
like a pretty reasonable component of it.
Don't get me wrong, Chris.
It's not that Plasma isn't possible
to like build out and roll out and have a good experience.
Fedora KD is a great example of this where we have it
and Component 2 is another one.
And you can see this in OpenSUSE
where despite some people's protests,
it's very clear that the KD
is the most loved experience of the offerings.
But when you're trying to build a Linux desktop
that you're going to commercialize and sell,
having multiple desktops
and not having multiple groups of people
to maintain those desktops
means you're splintering your effort
and it's much, much harder to get everything going.
And if you think about all the work
that Red Hat's doing right now to push forward,
the Linux desktop's feature set
to be competitive with Windows and Mac,
think about HDR, think about the Wayland stuff,
the hardware acceleration things,
input stuff, touch gestures.
Think about how much extra work it would be
to pull that across a multitude of desktop stacks
and multitude of implementations across the board.
It's a lot easier for them to go wide on all these issues
if they're focusing on one stack as a reference point
and then leveraging that experience and expertise
to build it out and then everyone else
can essentially catch up afterwards.
Would I like Red Hat, to example,
have people working on both KD and GNOME?
Of course, but realistically,
with the kind of stuff that they're working on
and how far they're putting into it
and how much investment that they're doing
and how much that they're working
on all many different touch points in the experience,
I can't blame them for focusing on only just GNOME.
I think that's well said.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Get started with a free trial of a team or enterprise plan
at bitwarden.com slash Linux
or try it for free as an individual user
and you can support the show.
Bitwarden is the easiest way for businesses
and individuals to store share or sync sensitive data.
I use it for all kinds of things like passwords,
recovery keys, notes, it's fully customizable too
and in the enterprise context,
you can turn certain features on or off
just using enterprise policies
to adapt it to your business needs.
That's pretty nice.
And of course, I love the fact and I think you will too,
that Bitwarden is open source
and it's trusted by millions of individuals, teams
and organizations worldwide for securing their passwords
and other information.
It's what Wes and I have used for a couple of years,
at least I think Wes longer than I.
I use it for my two factor codes as well,
having it in one place.
It works so well for that kind of thing,
especially on mobile.
It makes having secure complicated passwords on mobile
a doable thing.
And Bitwarden has introduced account switching
so it's super easy to switch between your personal
and business accounts or maybe you have a personal account
and you have like an open source project
you're participating in.
And I think one of the things that gives me
and a lot of our community confidence
is that Bitwarden offers a really good self hosted option.
You can get that up and running pretty easily
or even faster using the Bitwarden cloud,
which is what I decided to do.
And if I ever wanted to move to the self hosted option,
I could and the nice thing is they have a large,
active community on their forums and on Reddit.
So I have to say a couple of years into using Bitwarden,
obviously I get the idea of good password hygiene,
but what I've really started to appreciate about it
is how fast and straightforward it is
to share passwords with somebody on a certain project
and it's really simple to say,
okay, just these passwords, I'm setting these aside
and I'm sharing these with you.
I think using a good password manager
and I bet you would agree with me
is one of the best things you could do online
to keep your account safe.
You might already know that really,
but maybe someone in your life,
a friend, a colleague, a family member,
maybe they need to hear that
and they need to know about Bitwarden.
So go yourself, support the show
or send people to bitwarden.com slash Linux.
It's easy to get started.
You just go to bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Try it for yourself, maybe try it in your business
and you'll support the show.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
As always, we got some great feedback this week,
but I figured since many of us have been flying recently,
I thought I would give a little insights
that we received in our mailbox.
Chris, you might like this one.
It was directed at something you said last week.
A listener wrote in and said,
since you were flying with Delta,
you had probably a very old
in-flight entertainment equipment.
Yes, the old monitors used to run Linux.
The new monitor hardware runs Android.
They have native GUI with X11
and like GTK, QT based GUIs,
the movies are just RTSP server connections
and games are launched locally.
The control units like your servers
and network modules are all Linux boxes.
The flight tracker or map can be two different things,
either a single stream channel where each monitor
and overhead monitors tune in and grabs images
or more advanced new hardware
where it launches native Android app
and gets information using more modern protocols.
So Chris, you were mentioning
how you saw some Linux scroll by,
so I guess you were in the old camp.
Yeah, and mine were old and crappy.
I think local apps would have been way better
because this thing, like you touch a button
and it wouldn't even register the tap for a second.
So you'd always do that thing where you're like,
did it register?
And then you have to do it again,
but that time it's like halfway through changing.
Every single time.
And even though you know it,
you still like it.
You still do it.
And the delay varies.
So it was not a great experience.
So I could imagine something locally work,
using some sort of network protocol
would be a lot better.
You know, I was on JetBlue for part of my flight
and it was an Android tablet right there.
And I saw it totally freeze up on the guy next to me
who unfortunately was actually using it to watch a movie.
It was just like tapping the screen,
like, well, what do I do?
So they just basically put a tablet
in the back of the seat?
Seemingly.
Yeah, okay.
I guess that would be the way
people would solve this problem, right?
But then like, are they all on wifi?
Are they hardwired over like the USB connection?
Because that's a lot of network traffic.
And if you get even half the passenger streaming video,
wifi is not gonna handle that well.
No wonder why it locks up.
I've seen some videos previously of the like computer rooms
that are included on planes.
Have any of you had insights into that?
Have you seen videos of those before?
Yeah, they're like full on aerial data centers.
It's insane.
Like how do they fit all of that power in a plane?
It seems like that's why we have such small seats, isn't it?
How much fuel are they burning,
hauling that gear around, right?
And how many of us just show up with our own devices
with our content already loaded on it anyways?
Yeah, we should probably have a protocol.
You wanna talk about saving fuel costs
and lowering prices and saving the environment.
How about you just take the like 700 pounds
of server hardware off the thing
and we just like have a mount for my tablet
because that would make me happy.
That's all I need.
It's not, I'm not asking for a lot, right?
And now as the French say, it is time for Le Boost.
Oh, we received a boost yesterday.
20,000 sats, thank you Silas, he writes in.
Folks, any suggestions for a backend file sync method
that handles a lot of small files well?
Hmm, I mean, I could just go the R sync route,
but I'm wondering if we could make the case
for like a ButterFS or ZFS send.
Sure, yeah, if you're, you know,
have those capabilities on both sides
that are willing to use those toolings.
You know, if there's bi-directional stuff,
then that might not work so well.
But if you're just trying to back things up, yeah.
Alex is moving files around the world all the time.
I'm wondering what you're thinking.
Yeah, ZFS send is a great shout
because that works at the block level.
So, you know, if you're talking about
lots of small files with R sync,
it would have to compute every time it loads up
a checksum of the source and the destination file,
compare them and make sure that they're not different
and then sync the Delta if required.
If you're talking about lots and lots of small files,
that can get quite expensive quite quickly
in terms of time and computing power.
Whereas something like ZFS,
because it's working at the block level of the disk,
it doesn't care that there's 10,000 files in those blocks.
It cares that there's, I don't know,
let's say five blocks worth of disk that have changed
and it will sync those five blocks only.
So you've got five transactions, let's say,
instead of 10,000.
So it can be a lot more efficient for that kind of thing.
So that's probably the route I'd go.
Alex, in one of our technical escapades here
where you show me all of the infrastructure
that you have set up,
which I don't even think I have a 10% grasp on yet,
you were showing me that you also use RESTIC
to do a little bit of file-based syncing.
And I wondered what is happening on the back end there.
I'm not sure.
I have even 10% of a clue
of what's going on in my infrastructure some days.
So yeah, RESTIC is an interesting one.
That works at the file level as well.
It monitors things like inode time
and M time for modified time on the file level.
So that's a file level based one,
which wouldn't be very efficient
for this particular use case.
But the reason I like RESTIC in particular
is because I send all my stuff
to an S3 compatible back end.
So on my Synology box that is in England,
that's running Minio in a Docker container.
And I sync all the files from here to England
using auto RESTIC, which is a wrapper around RESTIC itself.
And so I actually have two servers in England.
I've got the Synology at my mom's house and at my dad's,
I have a normal Linux box running ZFS.
And so I like it for the separation of concern.
So if something goes wrong with my ZFS backup,
I'm fat fingered in my Ansible configuration
and I screw something up,
there are two separate channels of backup
and my automation isn't gonna fail on both of them,
I hope at the same time.
Sounds like in some cases,
the cost of moving a lot of small files might be worth it.
Almost never, I would say computationally.
Computationally, it's very expensive.
In terms of disk IO, it's very expensive.
So I would try and steer clear from it.
Maybe you could compress those into a single archive
and sync just that one archive,
lots of different ways to approach that.
Gene Bean boosts in with 2000 sats.
I really appreciate y'all putting the effort
into running Synapse and promoting Matrix in general.
I think it's got a lot of potential
but needs the visibility and battle testing
that us home users just can't provide.
After you get the colony stable,
I'd love to see a dig into bridges,
especially double puppeting ones.
A double puppeting bridge?
Do you know what that is?
I don't know what that is.
Well, there's different classes of bridge
based on how much control you can get
on the different platforms, right?
Because some platforms say let you like add input
as if you're another user, but some platforms don't.
Yeah, I think that is the kind of the game plan
is get it stable and then once we get it stable,
we wanna embed it on the live page,
like in a read only mode maybe,
so you don't even have to have an account,
you can just see the chat on the live stream page
on the jblab.tv page.
And then once we got that figured out,
I think it's bridging time.
And I don't know how much bridging we're gonna do
because the place where we run our IRC room
kind of anti-bridge and like the Discord bridges
are getting shut down and the Telegram bridges
always kind of look like crap to me when I see them,
for the most part, not always,
but we'll experiment, you know what I'm saying?
We'll take a look at it and we'll see where it goes.
Gerald's mud, nope, that's not it,
boosted in with 10,000 sats two days ago.
He says, the saved podcasting message
should have its own URL, an easy one to share,
and maybe a different message depending on the audience.
I'm not tired of hearing about it.
And I really appreciated that
because I did kind of, I got smack down a lot
and I kind of stopped talking about it.
I just sort of thought, well, I'll shut up for a bit,
but I appreciate that.
I have decided, you know, a bit of what needs to happen
is there's sometimes content that we wanna share with you,
me, wanna tell you,
and I really don't have a lot of outlets for that,
other than this show or another show.
And so we end up stuffing stuff into the show
that maybe we should talk about somewhere else, right?
And so I'm gonna try creating essentially
an audio version of a Jupiter newsletter.
And I'm basically just gonna do
a really low quality crappy podcast
that nobody should listen to called office hours.hair.
You go to office hours.hair to subscribe.
What I'm gonna do is I'm gonna read some boosts
that don't make it on the air.
I'm gonna read emails and cover questions and feedback
that come in about the network.
I'm gonna cover things that the network is working on.
I'm gonna talk a little bit about my thoughts
on the podcast industry.
And right now I'm kind of thinking fortnightly,
but I don't know.
We'll see if you like it, office hours.hair,
if you wanna check it out.
And so some of the stuff that has ended up in the show,
we'll have a new home there
so we can keep the focus here on the show.
And if this sounds like a crazy idea
that's not gonna go anywhere,
that is literally the premise I launched this show with,
that we're doing right now.
So it could go nowhere, it could turn into a thing.
So go subscribe at officehours.hair slash subscribe.
And I got an old episode that I just put in the feed
because you gotta have something in the feed
and I did an office hours like 200 years ago.
And so that's in there, maybe a little bit less than that.
And then I'm gonna do another one.
And I think I'm gonna do them live.
And when I do them, I think I'm gonna do them
on Tuesdays at noon where we used to do LUP.
So if you wanna come in the mumble room
and give me feedback or ask me something,
you know how you like to ask questions,
you can come in there and ask your questions
and I'll answer them.
And I don't know, that's it.
So that's gonna be a thing I do.
Thanks for the encouragement, Gerald with your boosts.
Officehours.hair soon.
There's already one in the feed
but you may have heard it before.
I don't know, I don't know.
The computer guy writes in with a thousand sats, thank you.
I just got accepted into college
and their email runs on Outlook.
The IT department said on their website
that Thunderbird, which is my favorite email client,
was not supported.
Furthermore, they said that Linux
is also not officially supported.
I managed to get Thunderbird working anyway
and it looks like I'm gonna be at constant war
with the IT department as one of the few Linux users.
Any tips?
Mm, I have been here.
I have been here and a part of me wants to say don't do it,
just don't even bother.
But I'll tell you what you really gotta do.
Here's what you gotta do.
Stay the F off their radar.
Don't ever let, you may have already tipped your hand
too much, just stay off their radar as much as possible.
Do everything low key.
Find the holes in the system, use them to your advantage
and just be patient because you're gonna be using
the infrastructure in a way that they don't expect
and so that could go sideways.
And maybe consider just not doing it.
But if that's already been considered and rejected,
then stay off their radar.
Yeah, you can do things like have a backup system
if you need to, if you need to do it the official way
and then yeah, as Chris said,
be prepared to be your own support on this.
It can be fun to figure out and make work
and very satisfying when you do make it work.
But you know, when grades are at hand
and you don't need one more complication at 3 a.m.,
sometimes it's nice to have a backup.
And I will say web apps, web apps might be an allocator.
Yeah, I agree.
I think web apps are a lot better now.
I do think a backup's not a bad idea.
It could even be a VM, possibly.
Yeah, indeed.
This is how I started my dang career,
like back in, I'm not even kidding, in the year 2000.
And it was legitimately like me trying to figure out
how to get email off an exchange server
when the entire company used Outlook
and I didn't want to run Windows.
And I did all kinds of crazy things,
including buying multiple editions of Xandros
because it came with Crossover Office pre-licensed
and you could put an Office install CD
and it would auto run the installer and install Outlook.
And that's what they made money on, right?
This has been a problem that has been
in the side of Linux users for a long time.
It's way better now though,
so I think you could probably pull it off, computer guy.
You just gotta stay true and like Wes said,
have that backup.
I also feel for the IT department here
and I don't think it's really their fault.
I was in the same situation in college
where being slightly contrarian,
I may have tested some things.
But for the IT department, you're one person
compared to how many people that are running Windows and Mac.
So they just don't want to, they don't have the time.
Maybe they would love to have the time
to help you and explore this, but they just don't have it.
So I don't think it's really their fault.
And so saying, you might be constantly at war
with the IT department is maybe a little strong.
I think maybe it's just that they just,
they're encouraging you to take it into your own hands,
really.
It's only a problem if you make it a problem, really.
True, true.
Tiny also has a tip,
something he could try besides Thunderbird.
My work has very strict policies around the M365 products
and the Evolution EWS plugin works really well.
It even works with OAuth.
So if they use Duo or some other form of MFA,
it still works with that.
That's a great tip.
It's definitely worth giving Evolution a try.
That was one of my go-to solutions
and it still gets maintained.
So that's a rarity.
If you're out there with the new podcasting app
and newpodcastapps.com that support Boost,
send me a Boost and give us an update
on your NixOS challenge, how that is going,
and on any tricks or tips you have
for working in an Outlook-heavy environment.
We'll just put it that way.
A newpodcastapps.com, get one that supports Boost
and send it in.
I found a cool tool I want to share with you guys.
I brought this one to class today.
It's called RSS Hub.
I guess one way to wrap your head around this tool
is think of YouTube DL, but for RSS feeds from websites.
And what I mean is it's an open source, simple,
easily extensible RSS generator
that you can pretty much throw any kind of weird content at
and it will build you an RSS feed for.
Now with the caveat that it kind of has to know
how to work with the data.
So it has a huge wealth of websites,
you know, probably more sites than something like a tool
like YouTube DL even supports.
I mean, hundreds and hundreds of websites,
but also the tooling to create your own is just JavaScript
and it's easily extensible.
And you can also, the project is also willing
to just build it for you
if you give them a polite pull request.
They've been known to do this.
It's really simple to get running,
especially if you do it inside Docker
and the way you work with it, RSS hub,
once you get it up and running,
is you just throw it a URL
of the thing you want an RSS feed for
and it spits out the feed for you.
And then you throw it in your feed reader of choice.
They also work specifically with a mobile app
that works together with RSS hub.
It's slick if you're like me.
And one of the ways I can,
I'll sort of responsibly consume content.
Maybe I'm not in like a head space
where I wanna be on Reddit or social media,
or I wanna sit down and really analyze the news.
RSS feeds are just unbeatable.
And the only limitation is some content out there
isn't in an RSS feed.
That's what RSS hub fixes.
And of course it's open source.
The only challenge you might run into
is there is a bit of a language barrier.
So, you know, some things you kind of have to do
the translation in your head a little bit,
but it's super simple to get up and running,
uses Redis for the database backend
and takes very little resources.
Even when you run it.
So it's great.
RSS hub, go check it out.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
What do you think?
Do you like it?
Yeah, I can.
Trying to impress you here.
I'm already can think of like a million uses
for this thing, so.
I know.
We gotta start playing.
I'm wondering if we couldn't use it too, right?
To like make mixed feeds and stuff like that.
I mean, you gotta wonder.
There could be some potential with this tooling.
So I had to sneak it in today.
It doesn't really fit, I suppose, with the theme.
Now that I think about it,
I've been trying to get these on theme.
That doesn't really fit.
It's good enough.
Alex, Brent, thank you guys both for joining us from Raleigh.
I'm sure it's beautiful and wonderful there.
And you've got lots of projects
you'll be working on this week.
Yeah, it's always a pleasure.
I gotta say, maybe part of the recording
might be difficult because of all the birds singing
and the sunshine over here.
It's really, really, really, really, really nice.
Well, you know, when the deer walk through, they shut up.
It's hard to be angry about anything
when it's 75 and sunny.
Oh, you guys.
But as far as projects go,
we have an ever-extending list of temptations.
So I don't think we'll run out of projects while I'm here.
I love that you call them temptations.
Yeah.
I see them as ways to spend money.
I've been showing off your server rack
to people when they visit the studio.
It's one of the requested items.
I've gotten some feedback, too.
Some people suggest maybe we should have used metal,
but they thought maybe you should have
welded something from scratch,
but everybody has their own opinion.
Should we get into welding this week, Brent?
Should we do that?
Yeah, Alex and I were just talking this week about
maybe getting into welding.
Come back.
We'll weld a rack, you know,
because we're gonna have the heat problem in the studio
before we know it, too.
So we're gonna have to weld some kind of solution,
obviously.
It's gonna have to be welded.
All right, well, until then,
why don't you join us live for a show, huh?
Why don't you?
We do this show every single Sunday
at noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern over at jblive.tv.
If you are into the tech headlines,
you're maybe in the industry,
you wanna keep apprised of what's going on
in Linux and free software,
make sure you grab every single episode
of Linux Action News at linuxactionnews.com.
Lean, mean, news, just what you need to know.
None of the fluff.
We're not trying to waste your time.
We know you're busy,
but there's probably a few things going on
you should probably know about.
So that's Linux Action News in a nutshell.
That's my pitch for it right there, linuxactionnews.com.
See you next week.
Same bad time, same bad station.
All right.
Links to what we talked about today,
including the work on Fedora 37
and future versions of Ubuntu
and details about all of that,
including extra deets about all of the releases,
all that stuff at linuxunplugged.com slash four, five, four.
We have it all there for you.
You'll also find links to our feedback page,
our subscribe page, all that stuff.
Whole catalog there.
It's like a website.
It's great.
You can use it anytime you want.
Anyways, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode
of the Unplugged program.
If you can't join us live,
we're just grateful you listen.
We appreciate that.
And we'll see you whenever you want.
We'll see you next week.
All right.
Go pick our title at jbtitles.com.
What you can't see from here is how Brent spent
the entire outro air drumming.
Perfect time.
It's in his blood now.
Even the syncopations that Alex,
you taught me that word last time I was here.
Syncopations.
I know.
Look it up.
Listen, listen, listen, listen, listen, listen.
We got a title crisis here.
This is a title crisis.
I saw some pretty funny ones go by.
Did you?
Cause none of them say anything about distro being reviewed
or a bun to or fedora.
I said they were funny.
I did not say they were on topic.
We've got some good alliterative ones right here
with double distro debate and double distro detail.
I do like those.
You're right.
Hey, I thought it might be kind of interesting
to maybe itemize the tasks.
What did I call them?
Temptations that Alex and I might get into.
Alex has an entire,
Chris, did you see this when you were here?
Alex has an entire drawer of electronic to do.
It's a drawer, not a list.
It's a drawer full of like.
Oh sure.
Yeah, I love that.
Yeah, I've got a little crate that I store in the RV
of like, oh, this is something I got to get to.
All the crap that you bought
and then it takes too long to get there
and you think, why did I buy this again?
Or you bought it and then like something comes up
and like that's whatever came up,
took my like my Saturday afternoon
that I was going to work on that thing
and then like no other windows ever opened up again.
There's always something else to do.
Speaking of windows that open up again,
the skylight that we had in the bonus room last night,
that was a pretty good segue, wasn't it?
That was a great segue.
We took a, I had in this drawer,
I had an Acara Zigbee window sensor,
like a little magnetic one.
And so Brent and I put that on the skylight last night.
What did you think of the pairing process
with Home Assistant?
I was like getting ready to sit down
and absorb what the Home Assistant process
was going to be for this
and you were done before I even like got set up.
So it was kind of amazing and really slick.
From box to wall in what, eight minutes?
I would say it was literally a five minute job,
but it just reiterated to me like the progress we've made.
If you think about Home Assistant
and where it started way back when
and where you are now Alex,
I would imagine things are pretty slick.
We've come a long way,
but Chris is still going to be running Python 2
in 10 years time.
So, you know, we can do all the progress we want.
It's too soon, it's too soon, it's raw stuff.
Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha.