See valve has a new VR headset
Yeah, yeah your VR is dead it was never living ouch
All right. Well, I can use it today when we have a VR headset and my wife is sat there like in some
Stupid jewel popping game or something in 3d on the sofa and we never speak to each other anymore because she's got this fucking stupid
Or maybe it's the other way around and it's me. I don't know. Yeah, I don't know though
I felt that way too, and then I got an oculus and I changed my mind
Yeah, the thing about VR is I can remember going down to Piccadilly Circus in like
1993 when I was a student and put in this, you know
15 pound headset on my head and paying five quid to romp around in some line art
3d world and it was kind of interesting and kind of impressive for the day, but ultimately
Yeah, just something. Yeah, but now you could have one in your house, right?
So that's one big difference is the opportunity cost of you playing with it is you picking it up on your head, right? Yeah, the the
Hardware will be lighter and will fit your head better despite you having a massive
All true all true gonna torpedo torpedo you in however keep going
Go and keep making a big target for yourself. There is also the fact that you can now get immersed in games
Like well, let's pick an easy target Minecraft where you can spend six hours
Yeah, Minecraft. Yeah, big targets getting bigger and bigger. It's easier to shoot. Go on then go on then shoot me down
What's wrong with sitting there playing?
Minecraft is the same the VR today is sexier hardware and sexier graphics
But it's the same shit. We were doing 20 years ago. It hasn't actually moved the needle, right?
But it's just the same stuff 20 years ago. It was it was the the Nintendo Virtual Boy. That was no no
I'm talking about the stuff you could you could stroll into and use but but think about it
What about VR now the graphics are better the headsets are lighter
The resolution is higher, but it's the same
It's the same experience that they're trying to sell us that we were we were looking at 20 years ago. Just a bit better
Right. They were interesting
They were they were way ahead of their time back then well
Why aren't we now? Why aren't we thinking? Why aren't we 20 years ahead of the time now?
Why aren't we why haven't we got things that are pushing the envelope?
They're a bit shit and a bit rubbish because we haven't got the hardware and the equipment to to deliver
Okay, I want to do 20 years from now
I'm just improving on what we were already doing 20 years ago
They're rubbish by the by the end of next year by the end of 2016
So we'll get the first gen ones out first gen being oculus second gen being valve
We'll get these ones out of the way this year
Next year, you'll go on Alibaba and be able to buy cheap
commodity VR headsets super cheap
I mean, come on and what are you gonna what are you gonna do with it?
Well by then there'll be shitloads of games in Steam because valve are bringing them to market
Yeah, a shitload of shit games is what I envisage is what it's gonna look like 18 months from now, right?
but I can sit on my sofa and I can be immersed in a game and
My kids can be watching TV. Well, whatever game it could be Minecraft
You can't say that shit 20 million nine-year-olds can't be wrong
When I've played it, I'll let you know whether I think it's shit or not. Oh, you haven't played it yet. No, never
Apparently it's like Lego, but I actually do Lego in real life
Your fingers hurt and my I've been playing Minecraft all day and my fingers don't have well, okay
so I've spent the weekend helping to build a 20 foot tall rocket out of
Three hundred and thirty thousand pieces of Lego, right?
Compete with that
Shit well what I've built millions of people could come by and and
See my server and drop by and help and contribute yours is a photo on a on a dead social network Google Plus
That nobody's ever gonna see yeah
But then again the whole of North Hampshire community is involved engaged in building this absolutely epic rocket out of Lego
Which right is the real world and it's real 3d and everything and the definition you wouldn't believe the quality of the graphics
It's like it might be analog, but it's really good
Can you check? Can you change the theme? Can you change the skin? Yeah
Yeah, we're doing at the moment in red white and blue
But you know you could do it in just black and white or you could do it in puce
Cyan and yellow if you really wanted to but you'd have to rebuild it. You couldn't just press a button and make it
Yeah, yeah, but think about have you ever imagined what it would be like to tip over a 20-foot?
Rocket out of three hundred thirty thousand bricks of Lego. I mean just imagine
Have you ever wondered what it's like to blow up a house with TNT? I mean
No, that hasn't crossed my mind this happens you're not as deranged as I thought you were with me you really are
I'm disappointed
What about the Microsoft?
Microsoft hollow lens where they're gonna overlay over your environment now come on that is kind of useful because
You just like take something simple like you're taking a part of PC
And you open up the case and maybe all of a sudden you could have outlays of like here's all the tickets ever assigned
To this PC. Here's your company inventory information about it this video cards stuff like that hollow lens
Maybe that's real. So so what you're describing there is augmented reality. I believe that's the buzzword. Is that right? Yeah
Wow, you sound like an old man Wimpy. Hey, well, I'm an old man. I've got gray hairs and everything
Um, I think augmented reality has got far more mileage than VR, frankly
Now, you know see in Microsoft's world. They also have the ability
So I think in anything that's gonna be successful today. You got to have a whole ecosystem
You got to have like you got to have app partners like Netflix. You're gonna have to have they have Skype
They have an app store that universal applications that people write for Windows 10 and the phones also work on hollow lens
somehow, I
Mean so they even have the ecosystem to back it up. I
Think when it comes to augmented reality
It's easier to do as well
honestly, so not the full integrated thing, but actually just the
Basic level of you know, you have something that identifies the product that you're looking at in a in a in a store
Yeah, speaking of minecraft. Here's here's minecraft in your living room using hollow lens. I don't think this is ever gonna happen
this is Microsoft isn't Microsoft has never been able to pull this kind of thing off and
It's just like this isn't really gonna happen. This is a surface table all over again. Yeah, it's yes
This is not gonna happen. It's the surface exactly. This is the table. This is the table all over again
or
there's gonna be the three leading ones like as I said Microsoft valve and
Facebook and then there'll be loads of
Cheap and cheerful knockoff Chinese ones next year. I guarantee
Sources where in this
yeah, and
What are you actually going to do with these things? That's that's the other thing. I just don't see what the purpose is
so so I imagine that I would be able to see a 3d render of Chris's studio and
I'm sat here at home with my goggles on while I'm listening to him doing
You're describing the Internet when it was sold to us in 1994 right now, that's true. This is a Unix system
I know this, you know, it is exactly it's 3d and I want 3d and I want to be able to while we were working around this
Virtual cyberspace back in the mid 90s. I had some great demos, didn't they remember the Sun Microsystem demos where you have doing up?
Oh, man, you know what Chris?
I actually worked at Sun Microsystem and helped create some of those demos back in the day. Those are good
I wanted to live in that virtual world. I would never have to leave my house. I
Go to the mall and and at malls online stores weren't websites
They were represented as virtual reality first-person stores
You're gonna want and think how how out of date was that because look back what people were trying to create was a 3d
Representation of a shop that you would walk around in the same
Inefficient manner that you walk around a real shop. Yeah to do your shopping
It was so backward thinking a second life game is as close to that as possible. Yeah
Yeah, well, it's how we approach everything when we bring it into a new era
You know we we we we kind of put like all our the old way of looking at things out
And then as new people come along they they shake that stuff
Yeah, the two industries that are gonna push this are the same two industries that you're gonna push this
Oh, come on, baby. Go and get your credit card out. Tell it. Tell us what it is. You subscribe to the two things that you
buy are
Games and porn. Yeah, we go
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that honestly still feeling a little nostalgic
My name is Chris and my name is Matt and Matt. So we had last week
We had a show that was pre done for us because we were taking some time off during the beard apocalypse and during the scale
Coverage which we're gonna do a little bit more of in today's episode couple of interviews
One that I put back in the rotation based on a request from an audience member because it's for a really great cause and
One that really blew me away
I didn't expect to ever feature an interview on the Linux action show or Linux unplugged from this company
but Noah got it and we found out they use a lot more Linux than we expected and then also there's a
Really in-depth discussion with an Ubuntu representative at one of at the Ubuntu booth
so we'll play those coming up in the show a little bit and then also
After all of that
I'm gonna pick wimpy's ear on all of the developments going on with the Ubuntu Mate project
Some of their news and also just maybe any mate updates in general and some other stuff
So Matt, we got a lot of ground to cover
Good stuff. We got you know, we got to get down to business. So I thought first there's just a couple of like
Speaking of being nostalgic. There's just a couple things. I wanted to touch on the first one before we get into the main show. I
Don't know if this makes you feel old or what?
on this day in
1999 March 3rd 2015. Yeah, it's March guys. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. Yes. It's March
Gnome 1.0 was released on March 3rd 1999
Slash that headline goes as follows or blurb
Gnome 1.0 is now released for download
Please pursue the pursue the press release and then download it via a convenient FTP mirror
And then they also say and I forgot about this extension and then they have this update
The next the next day forgot to plug my own program if you've installed no more want scrolling slash dot headlines in your panel
Check under applets amusement slash app Wow
You know why I was reading them in between that, you know, cuz I had to stock my compound up for Y2K and all that
So I was you know busy with all that sort of stuff. That was a bit that year was the busy year
Alright, so let's bring in the mumble room time appropriate greetings mumble room
Good evening anybody in here old enough to actually remember the release of Gnome 1.0. I'm not gonna say
Yeah, I am old enough and also
Dare I say it that it was much easier to compile KDE back then so I was a KDE user back back in those days
Oh
Good times good times, you know what it makes me think of it makes me it makes me think of KD as well because that
Was actually a hardcore KD user back and back in those days. So it actually made me think of the same thing
Alright, so in the pre show which if you're listening on the download will probably be featured it in the post show
How about that for a little time travel? We got into a big discussion about smart watches and wearables
It's the big thing right now, you know next week's the Apple watch event and a pebbles got their Kickstarter going right now
which I
Think I'm totally gonna back and Poby just back during the pre show
But nobody's been talking about what the Firefox OS is doing watch wise
So I found this article over at Linux gizmo's pocket watch a pocket watch that runs Firefox OS
Screw putting on your wrist check this thing out with its slick sexy wood style. It's got a
Japanese style wood that's beautiful
and it has a camera built-in right it's got a metal ring around the front and
You can hold it kind of like a smooth pebble
It's a dish shape fits in the palm of one's hand and the round screen is fairly small
But if you it appears to be probably larger than most Android wear devices like the moto 360
Look at that. What do you know? I don't know, you know, I'm I almost want to say I'm skeptical
No, it actually sounds pretty cool. It does sound pretty cool
I'd had it's one of the things I'd want to actually try before I could really give a proper judgment
But it sounds different sounds pretty cool. So yeah, I don't know
Little skeptical. Yeah, I am very skeptical
Just
Does everybody have to be doing this really?
Like can we all do we all have to be doing this can can some of us just focus on one thing and just do
One thing right?
That would be nice. Don't ask poppy because apparently Ubuntu can't oh, yeah, I
Get you know, your guys's pre-show got me all riled up. I'm all fired up now
It's like they were really going at it now. I'm all I'm all ready to go
Which kind of while I'm at it, I'll take it. I'll take it just a quick shot at wimpy
Just a real quick one wimpy now. I got to give a thumbs down to the Amazon fire TV thumbs down
I I mean I wanted to love a Linux running rig like like no other but in my
Estimation for the money the Roku 3 is the much better by it is
so I heard you I heard you hint that you are not impressed with my
recommendation on on unplugged I think
Yeah, maybe it's a geographical thing because I think you're more spoiled in the US with online
You know media services I give you a basic here's a basic bar. There's first of all, there's no Jupiter broadcasts now, right?
No, there's that there's a dedicated Roku app now you could sideload it now
See a big part of my complaints are if you sideload most the apps it solves most of the problems
But I just find the Amazon app selection to be extremely limited. It's like I have three apps maybe that I like four apps
Yeah, that's why I sideload almost everything. I have a really great GUI a sideloader
Oh, I think so. I think this is where the difference is. So you have to sideload things to get what you would consider
normal service
Whereas in the UK what we would consider a complete service is available
Through the App Store, which is where it differs from the Roku. Hmm
Well, I also feel like the Roku kind of has a much more freewheeling open community where anyone can contribute
With us certainly true. Yeah, and I so I like that aspect of it a bit, too. I
Don't know. I just I mean it's they're both at the end of the day
Ding-ding. I'm trying to try not to say that anymore, but the end of the day
They both will play my Plex files. They've you both can you can sideload Kodi on them
All right on about the Roku, but you can sideload Kodi on the fire. So that's good
I mean that gives it a major plus in my book
But the thing I really like about the Roku is it does feel
It's a little bit faster to get just to what I want. There's less stuff. They're trying to sell me like all the prime stuff
It's all up in my face and then also
That there's a Jupiter broadcasting app, which is really nice. I
Would go so far because I have both I have the stick for for the Amazon situation, but it's the same same experience
I do feel like Amazon's experience is very much like a gigantic ad being blasted in my face the entire time
No question about that sideloading just to get it to work even remotely usable
That being said when you actually get into something like Plex or whatnot Roku feels painfully dated
Painfully dated. I mean just really bad. Although that is changing. It's actually got a new thing coming out
Yeah, they do there is a Plex update coming for the Roku but still not gonna be as nice as the fire then and you
Know the the Netflix app on the fire TV supports multiple profiles, but on the Roku it doesn't
No, it does now it doesn't. Yeah, it doesn't know I'm not in the UK. It doesn't
Oh, okay, so it doesn't work on the Roku
Yeah, so anyways working on a thing so maybe you know, we're playing a bit of catch-up enough
Yeah, I would say VPN is your friend. I think if you live in a region where you're not services that we have there
Yeah, maybe I mean I you might even get different firmwares for all I know that she has different may even different menus
Either way, I that was just my roundabout way to say that they're both good devices
They both run Linux, of course, but I wasn't quite sure that I was going to be able to do that
But I wasn't crazy impressed with with fire TV. I'm not crazy impressed with Firefox's attempt here
I mean, I'm totally willing to give it a go. Maybe it's not even the Mozilla project
So I literally just found this before the show just to talk to you guys about it
I kind of like if I if I step back and thought about it being possible
You know, you could think about maybe putting a GSM connection in this thing
You know if there was a way if there was a way to really kind of
Make this thing connected. So it was a true true legitimate computer
That would be that would be kind of interesting then you might have my attention
But I just I don't think you could put the horsepower or the battery life in it to pull it off yet
Maybe one day maybe you got to start somewhere right guys
Speaking of starting somewhere. I'll tell you where I'm gonna start right now
Let's start with our first sponsor this week and that's ting
Now this is a great time to move to ting because ting is rolling out the open beta to their GSM network
And you remember our buddy chase from how to Linux and he's actually been on Linux unplugged a couple times
He is setting up a pretty sophisticated security system and he said, you know what, you know
It's something you've never mentioned but a great use for ting is
Remote systems that need internet connectivity, but don't use a lot of data
They send off reports or they do a nightly upload like once a night or a weekly thing
He said tings perfect for this. He says I looked around I said I could buy some prepaid things
I had different routes to go but tings flat six dollars a month then just pay for what you use and I don't need any
voicemail and
He has the thing you can send the SMS text messages and then do image uploads and video uploads
And so he just when it needs to send a text message a couple of times a month
He pays for the text and it's like nothing. It's like nothing
It's so great and there's no early termination fee if he wants to turn it off because there's no contract
It's a really cool service
And in fact, if you go over to linux.ting.com, you can take advantage of the Linux unplugged discount and support the Linux unplugged podcast
It's a great way to say hey, I heard about this on unplugged. I really appreciate you helping them stay on the air
So go to linux.ting.com like $25 off your first device and then you can go grab like this ting GSM card
And this is cool because it's a pre-cut to multiple different sizes
So you grab this one thing and it fits in your various different devices
Ting also just added the moto G for $91. This is unbelievable. This is
Unbelievable phone for $91 and you get it with no contract. It's unlocked. It's yours $6
Go to linux.ting.com. Here's a here's another ride you could go
These novatel mi-fi devices. This is like internet in your pocket $6 for this mi-fi hotspot
It's tri-band LTE you get the signal coverage right there
This is a great way to go
And then of course if you want to spend just a little bit more just a few dollars more you can get the net gear
with the LED
Screen and it gives you the touch interface and all that kind of stuff
They've also now got the Kyocera hydrovibe
Which is a slick phone as well as the LG g3 the Nexus 5 the iPhones the Galaxy tab and the iPhone 6 and 6
plus
Unlocked and all yours including the HTC m8 go to linux.ting.com
Linux.ting.com try out their savings calculator give it a try see what you might save you'd be surprised
But your actual usage in there and then also check out the ting blog like right now
They're talking about like their customer service demands right now with their new GSM rollout, but also
Some changes in the sprint network, which they're dealing with and updating customers on their blog
And you can read more about it ting is really great about updating their customers
It's a great way to go because they have an incredible control panel no hold customer service
You only pay for what you use unlocked phones
I mean, it's just like it's just it's a really great way to go and like one of the things that I constantly
Constantly mentioned because it's just so damn useful is every phone just has hotspot and tethering
It's just part of the plan like it's just not like they don't try to trick you into some sort of gimmicky plan where you
Have to pay more you just turn it on and have it and I think about with the T with the GSM network now
Coming online for those of us who have devices like you know many of the multi-sim devices
But the Nexus 5 is one of them you now have the advantage to switch between
GSM or CDMA now you're gonna have to figure out how to do that and make sure you can manage in the tin control panel
And they're gonna have more information on that soon
You can switch between whichever area has the better service and then turn on the hotspot or tethering and you're just paying for the data usage
That's pretty slick
Linux dot ting comm go check them out and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program
I hope you guys are kicking butt keep up the good work
Okay, so then there was one more thing
I wanted to discuss with the with the panel because there's a there's a piece of software
We've talked a lot about on the Linux unplugged show
And I think a fair amount of us on the show have used it for at least different periods of time if not extensively
bit torrent sync
new version announced today
They're rolling out bit torrent sync Pro or just call it sync if you're hip
$40 a year
Okay
This this is they say as they bring the beta to an end
They're exiting beta as sync 2.0 comes out bit torrent is introducing a business focused pro tier starting at
$39.99 per year per user not per device
But per user to date there have been over 10 million downloads of the alpha and beta versions of sync generating 145
petabytes of data
According to the VP product management Eric pounds in an interview at TechCrunch the pro products $40 charge
They say is competitive when you compare it to Microsoft's
$90 for owner own cloud or what in our own cloud on one drive and the $99 for Dropbox
Here's the really big catch though the free edition if you don't pay the $40 per year for bit torrent sync now the free edition
limited to 10 folders
Unlimited in size in those 10 folders
So that means at the root level only 10 folders
So the other features of pro include control over folder permissions and ownership that can you can change at any time
Once you link all personal devices together via private editing all your shared folders available wherever you need them
Consume on-demand view contents of very large folders consume only the content you need and preserve the storage capacity
Which is useful especially say on mobile devices that is very useful
I use Dropbox. It's one of the reasons
I still use Dropbox very heavily selective sync and also adding private you get you get technical support like priority technical support
for the pro version
Limited to 10 folders now if you update to the new bit torrent sync 2.0
They just came out today boy, you know, I'm actually for now
I'm okay with it, but I think in the future I might have to start looking at alternatives
I don't know. Hmm. I feel I don't know. It's a boy. I mean, I'm not I'm not real happy with it
I know that but I sure am getting sick of the beta label being used as an excuse for making bait and switches
Okay
Cuz here's what I feel like what happened is here everybody go out and implement our technology help us prove it out
Make sure we bang on the code, but also get hooked on our infrastructure
Yeah, and then oh by the way now now thanks that it's no longer beta
So now we get to charge. Oh, but we're also gonna remove functionality
right because see the problem is is I have like I
Have a folder for all the unfiltered supporter shows notes all the notes for all the unfiltered shows
Well that I share that folder out directly
So when you subscribe to that folder you get every shows notes in one folder
Well right now that'd be that's hundreds of folders, right?
So I would have to restructure the way I do all my sinks and put that in this it just doesn't work
It doesn't work at all for me. It's this sort of this totally breaks the way I use BitTorrent sync
Well, I also think it proves a good argument for other alternatives at some point, you know something
It's open source that you know is not as likely to do that to you in the future. But the same. Yeah, so I
Go ahead with it. I've I've been testing alternatives as I
a full back plan for bt-sync because this has been rumored for yeah for some months now
Yeah, and the only solution I found and this is for my personal
synchronization of files that can rival bt-sync in terms of volume of files and size of files is
cfile s e a f i l e
Right see see file comm which is an open source solution. I I can't get sync thing to scale up to
What I'm trying to do, but see file does but I don't know Chris whether it's going to work for your use case or not
So you'll have to give it a try and see how it works
because being able to just give out a key and then anybody just has that key and now is thinking is
Even though that that big long key is scary-looking the in in actual practice. That is so elegant
No links needed no names nothing to search right? Yeah
I don't even have to like go like give them an email address to the bittorrent sync program to send them an invite link
like I could just
instant message them a hash key and
It's just so nice and miss that I'm gonna miss that so much
So this that's the and that's a major problem with sync thing. That's the major major problem with sync thing
Is I just could not individually add every single person to my swarm and and sync thing
Even if you've got, you know, four or five laptops, you know shared between your family
Then it gets in a pickle just managing that few number of devices
So yeah sync thing
Really doesn't work so well once you get beyond a few devices the other nice thing about the way the bittorrent sync works is
essentially a CDN
Because there's as a few people grab the file they then see the rest of the other files
So it's I really like the way it distributes large media files
So I wonder if I bought the pro
which is pretty easy to justify as a business expense if the everyone else subscribing would have to have pro or if
or if they just get if they just get the advantage of
Me having pro so I can have more than ten folders. That's fine. I'll spend $40 for that. I
Think that's an important differentiator because even if it's in fact that they don't have to have pro now
What's to say six months down the road? They're like, hey, you know, we could really increase our revenue
Yeah, that's the problem on both ends to get to that many folders
Yeah, that's the question like on Dropbox, right?
If you have a really big folder both people on both ends of the Dropbox have to have more storage on their account
So I guess historically if we look at this based on their pattern of behavior
We know that they have no problem shafting you for a buck
So it may be good to look into some alternatives now before it becomes even more
Later, man, you're making me sad dude. I know giving you a sad you are you are
Because really this this this works so well for what I need because it doesn't it doesn't require any centralized cloud storage
You know, it distributes these large files each person acts as a seeder. It's it's just the publishing process
This would be true with most sync things with the publishing processes. I drop things in a folder
So I think going forward because realistically you pulling the plug on it just out of spite right now
It's just not realistic going forward keep things as they're going now do what you got to do to keep it up
But in the background begin looking at alternatives that you have to pull the trigger
You literally just basically you switch the tracks versus going. Oh my god
Daredevil and you had something you wanted to jump in with yes, pretty much. I was just wanted to point out that own cloud even though
It's currently not supporting and they didn't even set up as in the roadmap of setting
Let's say the clients can actually go and work as a central place as well the client itself, but they have federated own cloud
A hosting so you could have to own clouds communicating together
So I'm not sure how feasible would it be?
But then I would have to have like everybody in the unfiltered audience that wants to participate with an own cloud instance. Yeah, I
Mean, it's like the same way you have the client though
So if you instead think of it as if you had it locally installed instead of in a server, right?
And that's the federation you have well, that's pretty much what you already have which is a client right now and
Heaven's revenge you wanted to mention pure io
Yes, I found this little programmer application called pure io
a few days ago it is
Kind of a personalized vault that you use. There's no
Limitations on file size. It's got a built-in messenger. It's actually built from the same person who makes mini lock and crypto cat
Everything is encrypted and you will only have the key
It is interesting because it's only for you and I know that you can send
messages to people and I can send you a link to the file, but it's not much of a
synchronization sort of
R-sync or bit torrent sync type thing which kind of link all of your things together
But you do you can send files around and there is no limitation. It's limited by your
Upstream bandwidth or downstream bandwidth and whoever you send the messages to it's more of a
completely
Seems like it'd be a good collaborative like little back and forth
Families use it. I've been trying to use it with a few like one friend, but it's not very I can't exactly give a full
Recommendation based on only using it with one person. Okay, I might I might play around with it a bit
It looks and there's a Chrome extension you can add it's native which can be on Mac Windows or any Chrome
That you want. So here I owe
Platform here. I owe comm and I'll have a link in the show notes appear. I owe comm
Okay, wimpy you wanted to jump in on the own cloud sinking point
Yeah, I've tried own cloud through version five six seven and eight
On its eight seven, which what was out now eight is that the new one?
I was blessed. Yeah, and it's great for sinking, you know contacts and calendar and stuff like that
I've had good success in using it for that, but I've never really got it to work. Well with with large
volumes of file synchronization
And I've really tried I really want that to work because everyone keeps raving about it
And I don't think that I can be so unusual because it's just just me and some some data that I need to shunt around
The place but yeah, I just cut I can't get it to work for me reliably and the thing is is it sort of fails
Silently so you end up with all of your devices out of sync and then you have to sort of unpick the tangle
by hand
so
Yeah, yeah
No, it's a nose experienced quite a few problems with the file sink as well bit torrent sink has been a rock for me
So even more so than bit dropbox has been
Yeah, yeah, it's been super reliable for me. And that's why I'm so
Disappointed that yeah, you know, we hoped that it might become open source, but no they've gone the other way
Yeah, you know that's part of that's part of what feels like the bait-and-switch is they were kind of
You know, they danced around that oh, maybe yeah, we'll think about it. Now it feels like that was sort of a mislead
Feels a little bad lucky, you know, it feels good Linux fest Northwest and I'm the reason why I'm plucking this because I want
To meet you. I want to say hi to you or say hi to you again
If you made it before come say hi to Matt too. He'll be there right now. You're gonna make it right now
Oh, absolutely talk. I'm sure by then we'll have a few episodes of how to Linux out
So people have all kinds of things to talk to you about and we'll also have as much of the crew coming as possible
so it'd be great to see you and
We are in the process this week
Kind of like really locking in some plans
So if you'd like to be involved somehow or something to contribute email Angela at Jupiter broadcasting comm and let her know
And it's it's April 25th and 26 Bellingham, Washington Linux fest Northwest 2015. I think we should be considered a sponsor
You know, I'm gonna talk to them. I plug them like every week
Yeah, you should I don't want to see you guys there because I'm gonna be walking around a bit more
Will there be swag, you know, actually so there's a lot of stuff going on in there
Will there be swag, you know, actually, so this is something
Where we are talking about we're talking about doing a limited run Linux fest Northwest shirt
Because one of the things we want to do is offer reimbursement for some of the people that have to travel
because if you think about it like Chris Moore is on the is on the east coast, of course
Q5 and rotten corpse are on the east, right?
So it to bring to bring them in and Alan as well, although Alan I suspect will probably volunteer to fund himself
But I would offer to fund his trip as well all on the east to bring them over to Linux fest Northwest
And then to put them up in a room
For three days or whatever it's going to be
uh
Yeah, that's going to be a nightmare expense-wise
So yeah
We'll probably run a limited run Linux fest Northwest shirt to try to not only give you guys something unique for Linux fest that
We can have there which means we got to start it soon
But to also help
Raise funds to cover some of those costs. I don't think it would cover even half of it
But maybe we could who knows so we'll probably have more about that soon and i'll let you know
Well and speaking of doing something soon regarding Linux fest Northwest i've been going for many years
I'm actually originally from Bellingham. So i'm going to give you all some advice when it comes to hotels and motels start reserving immediately
Don't wait
Yeah, get get in early because it will fill up so fast and you will be left with the places on the
The motels you might not want to stay in i'll just leave it at that
There uh, there are some really good ones too, but you get them good and fast. Uh, yeah Bellingham is um,
Um, it's a good taste of Washington in an interesting way. It's a little eclectic. It's a little hippie, but it's
Yeah, okay
Well speaking of hippie, um
If you the two areas you want to pay attention to meridian and fair haven that's pretty much where you want your hotels to appear
You want to avoid uh, sammich, uh, generally speaking. Yeah, there's some that's pretty hit and miss
But yeah
Also, uh, if you are a beer fan some of the best beer in the pacific northwest is going to be there
A lot of great breweries up there also some folks, uh at the fest usually every year who are uh,
Uh brewers that use linux we've featured them before they'll be there. I mean really good stuff
Traditionally also they've had an after party at the spark museum, which is a really great radio museum
Really really nice and they have a tesla coil there that they fire off and there's food. It's it's a really unique thing
Uh, and bellingham's all about the food and the brew for sure. Yeah, so it's a good trip
It's and and linux fest northwest. I I think you know having been around and seen a lot of them
I think this is got to be in one of the top three fests
Uh in the country, so
Well, it's cool to watch how it's matured over the years because I mean you remember the old ones
I mean, it's just very very different i've been going since not quite but since nearly high school a little bit after high school
Quite and it's been i've been going a really long time
I've been going since the first person I started going with was my high school one of my high school computer teacher
Oh my gosh, that's crazy
I yeah
Now that was a couple years after I was out of high school
But so i've been i've been going so long that i've been going angel used to go with me to help me take notes
And she'd be there for a while when she was pregnant and she'd be like trying to sit in those seats, you know
Be at ball perrego helping me take notes. Yeah. Oh man, that's wild
It really has it really has come into it's something else something else that's kind of unique that they do
Uh, and it's perfect because it's the pacific northwest is they have a college there that has uh, some chef courses
And they do a big barbecue. Now you can leave we often leave because we usually have a large crew but uh,
They're they're at the college campus. They're barbecuing up salmon and ribs and stuff like that
And the salmon's really good stuff
So there's also it's a good opportunity to get some pacific northwest barbecued salmon and they have these big barbecue grills
They cook them on
And there's enough local of uh folks of us that we you know, usually able to provide transportation for most everyone
So yeah, that's a pretty good time. So that'll be uh, april uh,
25th and 26th you can find out more at linuxfestnorthwest.org. They're not paying me to plug it
I just really would like to see you guys and it's a good is we only
It's the biggest one we do in the year because it's here in our backyard and we don't have to fly all the gear everywhere
So we can go a little bigger
Uh, that's right. Hopefully we'll have uh, we'll have maybe by linux action show on sunday. We'll have the uh, fest swag stuff ready
Uh, all right
So, uh, we gotta uh speaking of fest
We gotta talk we got a couple of more interviews to play from scale and then we're gonna talk
Um about mate because I mean damn it
Yeah, I I never would have expected so much exciting things to be happening with a desktop based on the known tomb paradigm
I you know
Like if you would have asked me a year ago where some of the most interesting things were happening
I wasn't I wasn't going to guess that so we're also going to talk to wimpy about some of that stuff because it's crazy exciting
Uh first i'm going to talk about digital ocean head over to digitalocean.com
right now digitalocean
Dot com
Yeah, I don't know i'm trying to make them a jingle we have a uh, oh my we have we do have a promo code though
That I do have do unplugged one word do unplugged go uh, go over there and use that that just keep that in mind
While I tell you about digital ocean now, you'll see why you want a promo code
Uh, so digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider and they're dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up
Your own cloud server and it's legit. You're going to get root access to this thing
You get to watch it boot all the way up
You get this great console to manage it and it's a it's a it's a free bsd or a linux rig
Come on, let's be honest. It's gonna be a linux rig, right? You're not an animal
It's a linux rig and it's gonna rock and it's super fast
I I would go recommend you just go spin one up over at digital ocean use the promo code do unplugged
You get a ten dollar credit and just kind of play around with that the package management the speed of it and just have some fun
You'll you'll you'll find too. You'll you'll get started in less than a minute probably about 55 seconds or less
Sometimes it's as low as 26 seconds. I've gotten some crazy tweets
And the pricing plans start only five dollars per month
I'll get you 512 megabytes of ram a 20 gigabyte ssd one cpu and a terabyte of transfer a terabyte
for five dollars
yeah, I
One of the things I do for a living is I distribute content
I can't look at that when I say five dollars, I think maybe i'll just buy like six or seven of these
Right, you know just actually the problem is is uh, let's see
One terabyte. Yeah, that would be a lot of droplets
So, okay wouldn't quite work out but you know you you might not have that problem one terabyte might is I would imagine is
Way more than enough and if you're thinking about maybe setting up something like c file or own cloud or bit torrent sync or sync thing
Isn't drop is you you could go pay for somebody's ridiculous amount of cloud storage or for way less money
You could have it on your own rig up in the cloud that you control at digital ocean
Right. There's a lot of opportunity there. They have one click deployment applications do some really great stuff
You can do full dns management over there. They have data center locations in new york, san francisco, singapore, amsterdam and london
I love that too because if you're going to do the sync stuff, that's something to consider
And then you know
You'll have that interface to manage it and that interface that they have is so intuitive the control panel is crazy powerful
But yet like they didn't make it very complicated
So you can get through to a really fast pace and get everything you need but not feel like
They've removed some sort of necessary feature because they've just they've just spent time to make sure you have access to all that stuff
But it's designed well run all on top of linux
Which is a boatiful at this tier with these tier one data connections go over there right now
Try it out do unplugged go spin yourself up something like a ghost installation or wordpress install
There's so many possibilities digitalocean.com
See what we've been talking about use the promo code do unplugged and a big thanks to digital ocean for sponsoring the linux unplugged program
You guys rock
now matt, uh, I love these clips that kernel linux or aka noah got at uh at scale because
I'd never been and I was kind of on the fence this year. It looks like i'm definitely going next year
There's some great folks to talk to
Uh, why don't we start with the kids on computers initiative?
This is one that a longtime viewer eb wrote in and he said you got to feature this one because I saw it on
Your live event, but you didn't play it in last
He says this is a really good cause and he wanted to know more information about it and he was right
Uh, I went back and I watched the clip and I thought he's absolutely right
So, uh for a good cause here's uh kids on the computer at scale 13 x
So as both a father
As both a father of two kids
That I desperately want them to be all involved in computers at least as much as possible and understanding
Uh the ramifications if they're not into technology and as a person who wants to see linux implemented wherever possible
I was beyond elated to come across stormy with the kids on computers project here at scale where they
Well, they do amazing things. They do amazing things. They not only do they bring computers to kids
They essentially build their own little mini internet to take to places that don't have access to the internet. How are you today stormy?
I'm great. I'm glad to be here at scale talking to everybody about this. Yeah, it's fun, right?
so so I guess my first question is
You obviously when you're dealing if you're if you're if your goal is to go out and put computers
To kids that don't already have them chances are that there's probably not a lot of money
The budget isn't real high for doing these kinds of things, right? No, they usually have no budget
So we actually we either collect donated computers and install linux and free software on them educational software
Or we we apply for grants and get money to buy new computers, but the schools themselves have no money
We do like the communities be very involved. So it's been really awesome at some of our schools
The parents do fundraisers are they pitching a dollar or two a month per kid?
Which is a lot of money for them and they've been able to like set up computer labs build the buildings
Um both parents, you know, they had parents build the buildings to put the computer labs in
Um, they hired computer teachers off of donations that they've they've gotten
So we work in communities where people are really willing to give and they participate but there's no money there. So
Can you can you tell me why?
Uh, can you tell me how that plays into linux first? I mean, why not?
Why not purchase microsoft windows or why not purchase a bunch of macs?
So our goal is to empower kids to be able to create and to do things in the world
And and so by giving them linux and free software things that they can like learn how they work
Maybe not in the beginning
But you know they can learn how they work and they tweak them and they can build on it. It's much more powerful
Than teaching them that the world is about pirated software that they have to steal from someone
Right on the head right on the head
So uh, so in a lot of these places
I understand that there isn't a lot of money and that that leads to not a lot of services and not a lot of services means
There perhaps might not actually be internet there. So tell me about the tools that you give these kids so that they can access
The internet without having access to the internet
Yeah, so the main thing we wanted to bring was like the knowledge of the world and education to these kids
Um, so we've worked with different things like rachel and khan academy and we give them essentially on every machine for sure
Educational software so they can play math games or things. We give them a full offline copy of wikipedia
usually in their native language and
I'm always in their native language so far and we we give them a complete set of the khan academy videos
Um, all the ones in their language as well. That's crazy. So we don't have wikipedia. We don't have access to wikipedia
So we'll bring the wikipedia to you. Yes, it's really amazing
They have an entire more than what it would be in a set of encyclopedias on every computer and they can look up their book
It's cool in one school. We were setting up the computers and this is in this little town in mexico
That they have they not only don't have internet cell phones don't work though
They're in a canyon and they don't have any like landlines
So they really don't have any communication and we had three moms come in while we were working
And they sat there the entire afternoon and browsed through wikipedia and khan academy
And this wasn't on the internet
No, no, like just in this little lab in this little town in this little canyon like these people played with it
That's unbelievable. Is there a particular distribution that you use when you go to set up these computers for kids?
We've played with a bunch of them. So we're not tied into any we've tried edubuntu. We've tried libuntu
Um at the moment we're using uber mix
Um, one of the things we need is something that runs with really low memory on really old machines
That's very customizable. So right. Yes, so it has to be new enough. It has to be new enough and late late late enough that
Those kids are getting a good that they're getting a relevant experience and at the same time it has to be a
Accommodating to very legacy hardware essentially. Yeah, it's the hardware and the amount of memory and stuff that were that limits us
Well, that's absolutely outstanding if people wanted to I assume that you guys could always use the donation or could always use a you
Know a plug for uh for your website
So people wanted to give back if people wanted to donate hardware people wanted to donate money. Where could they go?
They could get a ww kids on computers.org. Um, you can get involved there
We're always looking for volunteers whether you like working with technology or you're good at marketing or you speak another language
We've got something to do. Um donations help the money goes a long ways like, you know for very little money
We can bring a donated laptop to a country and give it to someone so donated hardware or money
Um, we're doing a fundraiser here for cool hats. They're made by a local businessman in one of the communities that we work with
Yeah, and so we're selling those as a fundraiser
All right
Well outstanding and this is a way that if you if you uh, if you care to contribute to this project
Not only are you contributing towards linux here?
Not only are contributing towards open source
But you are putting in the hands of kids that wouldn't not only they're not
People that you're not converting people from windows you are converting people from no computer at all
To a linux based experience and that that's essentially what they are going to know
You have the power to do that. So I you know, you know from the bottom of my heart
Thank you for doing what you're doing. Thank you for going out to do all this
This is a super cool project and i'm really excited to follow you and see how things go
Thanks so much for stopping by and spreading the word. Please please come help us out. We appreciate it
That's a pretty neat initiative, uh
I I actually kind of wish I could figure out more of those things and and help direct
More attention to them. I feel like I have just some stuff I could send to these places
We we should seriously one day
I don't know if we'd have to have somebody that would be committed to doing the leg work
but we should seriously consider one day doing a roundup of
Places all around the world maybe or at least in the uk and the us and canada
Uh where uh people could donate equipment that would get then loaded with linux
Like you have to you know stuff that would go for linux towards linux use and deployment. That'd be really cool. Sounds awesome
Uh, well, that was a really interesting, uh initiative. So that's kids on computers and uh, you can uh, you can check that out
So we have uh, we have two more interviews to play and this next one's a bit of a long one
And it's because there's a lot to cover
It's the ubuntu booth one and I saved it just for this episode because it is kind of long
But it's there's so much ground and then the one after that is the one that I never thought we'd feature an interview from
On any of our shows let alone that they were big linux users, but it makes a lot of sense
So we'll start with the ubuntu one first
Many times as I walk around these conferences I find it increasingly difficult to actually find linux
I know that sounds a little weird, but being at a linux convention sometimes finding the linux isn't so easy
I especially have a a place a special place in my heart for people that use linux on the desktop now
I'm here with nathan and he's from ubuntu the community outreach. They he very much cares about seeing linux on the desktop. Isn't that right?
Yeah, it's the most important thing in the world
I agree with you
I mean world peace and and world hunger those things don't pale in comparison to getting people to use linux on the desktop
I think because there's so many proprietary operating systems
On retail stores that that's why we don't have world peace. I agree. I agree
I think it contributes to all the problems in the world. I think if we had desktop linux that would solve all of these
So obviously, uh, we're here
We have some fine looking system 76 machines behind us
And of course the orange which represents ubuntu tell me what it is specifically that makes ubuntu such a great desktop operating system for regular
users
So we take um the hardware capabilities and stability of the linux kernel
We take the massive amount of software available for debian
And additionally for ubuntu we take that we polish it. We have a clear goal of what we want on the desktop
We have the unity desktop interface that scales beautifully to large screens laptops touch screens
Phones as well. Yeah, and so as we take this this uh software with a with a clear strong vision across different devices
Uh, I think that that one
Unified vision is what helps ubuntu be so so awesome on the desktop now. I see that you have the bq there
Uh now those aren't you said those aren't shipping actually until march
So you're kind of a special person in the us to have one of those. Yes
Uh, so there were about 50 people who were uh, ubuntu insiders that were flown to the launch event
I was not one of them stuart langridge was and uh, so I stole his phone
He was he was actually nice to donate it to the booth this weekend and jono might donate his uh tomorrow
So we'll have two of these
And this is just so the nexus fours we have our development phones and they run really beautifully. Um, but there's a lot of um,
The the specs in this are kind of low and people are really upset because they're used to really high-end android phones performing
Okay, well even just so optimized this uh, this phone works beautifully. Uh,
You know just even on on these specs so we're demonstrating that today
That's outstanding now
How do you like the actual usability of ubuntu?
On the phone because I I installed it and granted it was a couple months ago
But I found there were some very key features I found to be lacking
So for example, I didn't see an email client
So there is an email client, uh, it's it's been developed by um by uh, I think they're canonical members
But but by the community and it's a part of uh of uh, trello. I think it's called deco
Okay, and so it doesn't ship on the phone by default, but it is in the store for free
And once it's super stable, it's a little bare bones
Although it's getting just to where I think it's a actually really nice client
Uh, as that is that grows more mature it'll be shipped by default
But it is in the store and and it's a it's a really nice client
All right. There you go. And there's a little audio pop. So i'll leave it there
Um, boy, it was a good interview, too
But i'll have to uh, i'll pull out more clips if there's more in there
Maybe next week can play it because that pop in that audio happens sometimes from the conversion of the camera clips
All right. So, uh one last interview to round out our scale coverage
And this is the company I never thought we'd have an interview with on the show
Uh, and it turns out they use quite a bit of linux
Okay, we're here at scale 2015 scale 13x we're walking around and I expect to see a lot of linux when I go to these
linux conventions
Sometimes the linux isn't quite as obvious as you might think it is and that is exactly what I found out when I came across
Disney who doesn't love disney, so i'm here to talk a little bit
Uh, what exactly disney does with linux how you guys use linux and yeah for anyone that thinks that disney is all about cartoons
And animations all of that stuff is actually powered by linux
Correct. So we actually have linux running in
A lot of our operation environments and one question that you actually asked me was if we had linux running in our desktop environment
Right and that is so especially in our animation environment. They actually have fully linux based environment
So, um a lot of times individuals will sort of uh identify disney as a brand
And the affinity just to themselves
but the amount of technology that disney uses to actually support its business lines is
Huge and linux is actually a very large component to that technology line, which is why we're here
Yeah, well and so and you know, and of course it goes without saying that
The linux community in general always appreciates people like you that that that build a business on the backbone of linux that are willing
To give back that sponsor these kinds of events that come here and talk about I mean, that's you know, that that
Right from this perspective
It's about being able to go ahead and provide the community with a little bit of
Sort of support overall in general and letting them know what it is that we do with this line of technology
And just making sure that people understand that it can go hand in hand
So we have obviously a huge brand that's out there, but a lot of it is done with amazing technology such as linux
So and the reason I brought up the desktop thing is because you walk around and you see a lot of the presenters
They they talk about linux and they talk about building their business on linux
But at the same time they don't trust linux enough to actually use it on a day-to-day basis
It might be in it might be on the servers in the back end that does that stuff
But they're not looking at it
They're not interacting with it
And what was interesting when I was speaking with you is I get the impression that there are places in disney where?
When you walk into work everything is linux
I'd probably say in selective environments, especially in areas like animation or our feature animation environment
That is so the case
And that is just generally case by case in terms of how much linux is used overall within each environment
So it may not be the case for all environments, but specifically especially for our animation teams
It's a very big part of their day-to-day
That would be yeah
And what would really be cool is if someday those tools that you guys use
If those ever became available for purchase or for that would be absolutely awesome
If somebody wanted to find out more about uh, disney and disney's involved as linux. Is there somewhere you can point them or
um
In terms of disney and disney's involvement with linux
I probably say in general you can go ahead and sort of check out disney technology
Dot com or a little bit more so I would say, uh, disney tech jobs dot com
um through disney tech jobs dot com, you'll actually get a really good understanding of our overall technology environment and sort of
How we're able to go ahead and kind of use linux as well as other open source technologies within our environments
And that's going to be specific to every segment and every position that we have. That's absolutely outstanding
Thank you so much for taking the time to talk with us. Really appreciate it. Thank you
And as colonel linux points out in the chat room
They are hiring so uh, you can get yourself a gig at disney
Uh managing some linux servers
You know instantly my brain flashes to that song from frozen. Let it go. She's talking about proprietary software
Let it go. Let it go
Let it go
Get it out of here. I think is uh, yeah, let it go because it is wasted effort
Yeah, exactly. Yes. Nice. Very good callback, man. Very good callback. Uh, all right. Well, we gotta talk mate. We got umate
Uh don't pursue. Oh, thanks sarah. Well, you know, I thought if this podcasting thing didn't work out
I would okay. No, you don't think I could become a disney singer
Well, there goes that plan
Yeah
Guess I better stick to reading ads and that's why our next segment is brought to you by
Linux academy head over to linuxacademy.com right now
In fact, if you want a little pro tip go to linuxacademy.com
Unplugged get the 33 percent discount. Yeah
Yeah, 33 percent discount linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged so why go to like high because i'll tell you why linux academy is built by people who are crazy passionate
About linux they get the open source community. They're involved in it developers
And educators came together and created a platform that they call linux academy and it is awesome. It is a resource you can go to
To learn just about anything in the spectrum of linux open source amazon web services
Big technology stacks that you really want to deep dive into and walk away with expert knowledge stuff
You can go take the test and pass and I can't tell you how many success stories I hear
It's amazing and part of the part of the reason is because I understand what the problem is with all the other systems
All the other systems are generic. They're just general training platforms. This is built for this kind of stuff
I'll give you a few examples. Um, you just choose from any distribution you want
They have seven plus distributions you choose from the courseware
Adjusts to match those distributions the virtual machines for the labs automatically adjust to that distribution, right?
Because they get it you can download the study guides and just keep them. They're yours
They have live stream events where you can ask the educators
It's so nice because you can also go in and keep track of your progress and see right where you left off
See how far you've gotten see how much longer you have to get how long it's going to take you
It's really easy to wrap your brain around this stuff like for me
I go and i'm like, okay now i'm going to learn python now in the past before I had linux academy
And I have an active subscription to linux academy. I would have really had this nebulous ambiguous goal
Self I will learn python and and I would then what go get a book go do go google
Like but then how do I know like the guide i'm reading is any good?
It's just this just it's it was never really a way. I would actually take action on it
That was always the problem I would get to is I couldn't really conceptualize it and take action
Linux academy solves all of that because they really wrap it in something. I can put my brain around
They have an introduction guide that's going to take you five hours. Here's some course material. I get it
It clicks and now I can get the job done linuxacademy.com
Slash unplug go sign up make your skill set a little bit better
You're not familiar with docker, but you've been hearing a lot about it. Go take a course on it
You need to go administer some kvm systems go take a course on it
You're going to go work on aws go use one of those scenario based trainings and actually work with the technology
Before you have to go put your hands on it linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged and a big thanks to linux academy for sponsoring the linux unplugged program you guys keep it up
They have a whole bunch of new stuff coming up. So it's really a good time to become a subscriber
I'll talk about that more really soon
Mr. Wimpy if you still around sir
I had a few things I wanted to pick your ears and brains about
Uh, and that is the stuff coming up for the big ubuntu mattei project, which is now a powerhouse among distributions
That is not only an official flavor of ubuntu, but apparently is so damn rich
Is just giving out money to other open source projects. What's going on?
Well, uh, yeah
Powerhouse and rich is that so?
Um, I don't know where to start with that really
Yeah
It's all full of superlatives. Uh, how do I follow that? Um, yes. Well, uh, I suppose
Um the big news is we're now an official part of the ubuntu family
Which is just terrific and we're already reaping the uh benefits of being
part of the official canonical
uh infrastructure team and
having uh, and also getting consideration from you know, the the wider ubuntu group
On decisions that are being made now. So that's really great. So i'll give you an example
so today I was contacted by two of the guys that are
uh working mostly on bringing system d
Enablement 1504 and they wanted to make sure that ubuntu mate 1504 was going to play nicely with system d
And they gave me all of the tips about how I could test this
And make sure it was working. Okay, because they they want a tick in the box that ubuntu mate is going to work
And so now being official, you know, we're given that kind of due diligence and that's just terrific. Yeah, no kidding
That is really great. And plus you get also the hosting infrastructure for the repos and the iso images
Yes, yeah, so there's a number of other benefits. So we've got access to the build server now, so um
Uh, that's terrific and and more importantly the official build infrastructure because i'd had to sort of reverse engineer it as best as I could
and I think to
Most people the ubuntu mate images look and feel and smell like real ubuntu, but I knew where they weren't quite the real deal
uh, so now they really are so for example now on ubuntu mate you can now use the uh,
The oem config so you can you know install a batch of machines in oem mode and then uh,
Close them up and uh when you turn them on it asks you, you know who you are and where you are
Does it mean at some point?
I would maybe be able to be like on a bare ubuntu like server type install and do apt-get install ubuntu dash mate
That's all possible now. So that all happened a couple of days ago
So if you were to download the mini iso for example go really trim
Uh, you can now do a task cell install of the ubuntu mate, uh desktop
So, uh, it's all it's all you know fully enabled throughout the stack now
Wow, that is a big deal
Congratulations. Yeah. Yeah, it's terrific. It's been it's been a long old grind and and really the tipping point was um,
About a month ago. I was fortunate enough to travel to montreal with work
And one of the guys from canonical
Who i'd been working with to try and do all of the back end build infrastructure enablement was based in montreal
So, uh, I met up with him and uh, we went out for coffee and beers and went to
The montreal university and went to the montreal linux meetup for the evening
And we and we hacked away on this for sort of um until about four o'clock in the morning
And that was really where it all started to sort of gather momentum and and start to sort of fall into place. So, um,
Yeah cypher mox as he's known in the irc. He was he was terrific
He's really made a big difference and there's about uh, eight or nine people at canonical that have really really sort of made this
Happen in the last two weeks. It's been uh, it's been great
Now, uh, there's also a couple other things. I want to talk to you about number one is uh, you did something that I think uh,
Would be
Really neat to see a lot of other projects too. So you have some community funds, right?
Uh does help pay for the cost of the projects and I guess there was extra funds and so you kind of paid it forward
That's right. So, um, one of the things that came out of the community
back last year was um,
they wanted a community site that wasn't hosted through the social networks because
You have a lot of people that are uncomfortable with signing up to facebook and twitter and google and what have you?
So I said well i'd be perfectly happy to um host it all and and you know put it all together
But I couldn't afford to run it myself. So I started a
Funding campaign to just cover the costs of hosting a server
And the money started trickling in around november time last year, and I just gave it a couple of months lead time
So I knew i'd got a buffer, you know, so that um, it was comfortable
But um, it kind of uh overtook itself. So we're comfortably funding a rather beefy server
So it's a a quad core server with four gigs of ram and raid six disk and uh,
Six terabytes of um bandwidth per month and that's where we're hosting our discourse community
In addition to what we do in the social networks
And we're now using that to really sort of develop some of the teams in the project as well interesting because i've noticed
You know, the project's also pretty active on google plus in the ubuntu community. Yeah
Yeah, it's it's active on google plus also
Also surprisingly active on facebook as well. One of the community members started a facebook group. I wasn't sure whether that was going
To be any use or not, but i'd say that's almost as big as um,
As the google plus group and growing much quicker because it was it was
Some months behind
Um, but anyway, we've had all of this money donated which is terrific
And i've been thinking about you know, how we can can make use of it
And i'd originally been thinking of doing like, um, uh, you know code bounty something like that
But I thought it would be better to actually identify projects that we're already making use of
and sort of um
Fund those projects. Oh, very cool. So we've got to a point now where we've we're not rolling in money
You know, and I know a couple of months ahead of where we are, but we've got a little bit of surplus
So I wanted to pick a couple of projects that we're dependent on that sort of make
Ubuntu mate what it is that aren't part necessarily of of mate itself
And I was thinking about well, where will I you know, where will I look to support?
And then I got an email from um, marcos costales who's the developer for for two projects one is uh,
Gufw, which is the front end for the the uncomplicated firewall and he's also the developer for folder colors
Both of which i've integrated into mate
Gufw has been there since day one and folder colors. I added um, just a couple of weeks ago
And he sent me an email that basically said um, I really love the project. Um, uh, here
Here's how you do it
I really love the project. Um, uh here here's how you disable
The donation links in folder colors so it doesn't you know nag people
And i'm telling you this because I think the project's great and I really want to see it succeed
And I was like, well, there we go. There is the first person that we should reward
So, um, we went through the accounts and uh, we've donated 50 to g u f w
And then we've donated another 50 to folder colors and taking taken him up on his offer of disabling the
donation links in the in the folder colors, uh piece so that was a hundred dollars we've donated this month and also
we've got um when you download ubuntu mate through the ubuntu mate.org website, there's a
You know, could could you give us a download tip? It's not um, you have to fill it out
It's just there alongside the rest of the content and it suggests tip us two dollars
If everyone who downloaded ubuntu mate gave us two dollars
It would fund the full-time development of ubuntu mate and also the mate desktop
Um, and we've had quite a few people doing that. So from that i've been able to
um
Give uh, thirty dollars to the mate desktop team this month as well
Nice yeah, I really like uh, that approach
Uh, in fact, I I was wondering if maybe down the road if maybe this might be something that takes off a little more
Because open source really does depend on uh, everybody that you're building on top of and everybody that sort of is riding on top of you
And uh, like uh, not only did I not really know about folder color
Uh, but I by the way love that you integrated it
But uh now like hearing that backstory, too
That's just that's so awesome the way that the project worked together with you guys like that
Yeah, and I think that for a distribution it's easier to
gather
Donations, I mean we talk about you know, um people wanting free software as in free of cost
But people are so generous, you know, we're asking we're not asking for anything
We're gently encouraging them to give something but the the the money that's coming in is
Surprising quite frankly far far far more surprising than I I I realized
And we can really do things with that. Um, and you know, uh, I I can't afford to make a hundred dollar donation
Uh as an individual
But using ubuntu mate as a platform to do that that actually makes a difference to the developer of that piece of software
That's uh, it's not gonna it's not gonna pay their wages or anything, you know grand like that
It's it's still a small contribution, but it's much more than I can make as an individual. It seems sound
it seems like investing in the ecosystem and uh,
The other thing is it's made me kind of think about how I could apply something like that here
Um, and I don't know exactly how that would be but wouldn't it be interesting to take like if we if we had a milestone
Where if we reached a certain set amount of funding, uh, then we would contribute a percentage to maybe production linux software
Like video editors like, you know, or or uh, uh, audio editors or maybe other things like gstreamer or things like uh,
Ffmpeg or or vlc or or something like that
That's it gives me a lot to think about and I think a lot of projects could think about how they could apply it to uh,
To their their kind of uh setup and and sort of reinvest in the tools that they use like
Jupiter broadcast, you know, we're freaking lives and dies on ffmpeg
Like if anybody deserves a buck from us, it would be at the ffmpeg project
I don't even know how their funding is set up
but and the other thing is like I could imagine like so say down the road we did something like that where we set
Up a goal on our on our patreon.com today page where we said all right after this milestone
We're going to give we're going to give back to open source every month and then imagine like so I reach out and I get
I start, you know here ffmpeg project. I want to I would like to donate
Well, then maybe that starts a conversation with the project and then we land a great interview time
Well, then maybe that starts a conversation with the project and then we land a great interview too. Like there could be other types of
You know benefits to it too other than just yes quite
And now you have a dialogue with these projects, right?
Well, this is it. This is it now now, uh
We have a relationship because now i've exchanged many emails with mark awesome. We've actually started talking about some
Um spin-off projects so it actually then you know garners some involvement in the project other than what i've already
Seen is out there. So this is a mechanism. I'm going to try and use going forward to actually
uh recognize the efforts that people have put into their
Applications and try and use it as a way to bring them into the the wider ruben tumato project
And uh and and reward them for you know, um what they've what they've achieved
So it will be in a small way and as your plan is as this happens to continue to
Post about it kind of are you going to do like an online? What's your what's your plan?
They're kind of making it sort of transparent for the community
Well, yeah
So when when I first tabled the idea of taking donations to pay for the community server
I set up front and I do this quite regularly if there's anything that i'm not sure about
I ask the community so it's very democratic. I put a poll out and I basically say vote on this
How do you want things doing? So when I said, um, i'm going to open up for donations
How do you want the finances reported the result of that feedback was they wanted a monthly statement of accounts?
So that's what i've been doing since I think december time
So at the end of every month, I post a detailed list of these are all of the people that donated
This is the amount that came in. This is what the money was spent on
And how we've we've used it and I felt a little bit
Awkward about this
Last month or the month before because I spent some money on an ibook g4 that I bought off ebay
Because I wanted to work with one of the community members on the power pc port
And I was like, uh, you know 80 quid's quite a lot of money to spend on a second-hand computer
And I don't really know anything about power pc
But as a result, we now have power pc as an officially supported architecture
So I feel that that money was well spent and certainly for those people in the ubuntu marte community
That use power pc. They're super happy with that
uh, and I feel that you know, that was okay, it was okay to spend that money because there was a
a measurable result
As a result as a result of spending that so this month i'm going to buy
a raspberry pi 2
And an odroid c1
And this is a precursor to
uh trying to achieve
Um v7 hard float images for 1510
very nice and so 15, uh, but before we get to 1510 1504 is going to have
An official power pc edition. It's going to have one click compiz enablement for the desktop, right? I mean, this is fancy. Yeah
Yeah, so so some of the headline features for 1504
I've worked with the upstream compiz team. So i've i've
ported the integration layer to marte in compiz i've also ported the um,
um, uh the compatibility plugin, uh to marte as well. So now in
1504 uh, you'll see there's a proper marte compatibility plugin and then i've also added um,
Detection of the marte session for compiz so it knows
Compiz knows it's running under marte
And these are the plugins and this is the profile that it should use because this is marte
It's not gnome and it's not unity. So we've got first class. Um compiz support and i've spent
many evenings
Tweaking a sort of a default marte compiz profile with the same set of defaults that give you
Some nice transitions and some nice effects without being too sort of in your face and over the top
And uh, and i've just i've just sent another merger proposal
Um, I think yesterday evening which has been accepted to just tighten that up a little bit
But as a result as a result of working on um on compiz I had to sign the uh,
ubuntu, um
Cla
So I was invited to sign the cla. Yeah, and i've i've read the small print very carefully and as I understand it
Every second tuesday, I have to go to poppy's house and wash his car
Yeah, and every and every and every last thursday of the month I have to cook him dinner or something
And also I think you're also obligated to catch his chickens when they get out
Yeah, all right, and that too but but only if only if uh, the the day of the weekends and why
Well, everyone should be obliged to do this
Everyone should have to I I had one more thing. I wanted to talk to you about uh, uh wimpy and that is uh, i'm
I'm, uh pushing the buttons right now. I just became a uh patron
Uh of the project. Yeah, so talk about this a little bit. So I the reason I want to talk about this too is because um,
I I I suspect that this might be something more distributions pick up because to me it seems like a no-brainer
Of course i'm using patreon and it's maybe more geared towards content creators in a sense, but uh,
People can go to patreon.com slash ubuntu underscore matey
And if you're already, uh one of the patrons of our network
Then your stuff's already set up is just really click one click button
And uh, they have 29 patrons right now making 174 a month for the distribution
And I wonder if the other projects like maybe elementary os couldn't go on something like this. How's it worked for you so far wimpy?
Well, it's it's effectively the patrons that have funded the community server
So all of the setup costs and the server and the month-to-month server hosting, but more importantly, uh, the bandwidth
costs because um ubuntu matey
1404 and 1410 which are unofficial and therefore we're having to
Field the costs of delivering that for are being downloaded between 900 times and a thousand times a day
So that's a lot of bandwidth that we're having to fund
Yeah, so those those patrons are basically funding funding the distribution network
So without them, uh, it wouldn't have happened
um, and I went down the patreon route because
Um, you you could do you know kickstarters and crowdfunding and you get a gob of money up front
But there's no longevity. You want sustainability. So yeah, so I I went for it might take longer to build up ahead of steam
But I want to know month to month like the project can support itself what I the reason why I think it's actually kind of
Brilliant and yes, there's bounty source and there's other ways to do it
But the other thing that's kind of nice about it is it legitimately one-to-one translates to the interest in the community
So you can scale up your efforts and your investment as the community scales up their investment and it directly corresponds as they want
More they'll fund more and then you can afford more or you can come to them and say okay
We can do this next thing and the the milestones allow you to say
All right, once we reach this milestone, this is something the distribution can offer
Uh, you in fact, you need some new milestones in there as a matter of fact. Yeah, I do
And in fact, we don't listen to milestones are the worst part
I have I have got some that i'm going to add but um, you talk about you know, the community want more
so at the moment
There's uh about four of us that are discussing some
merchandise team
Because what we're getting quite often now is people saying that they want stickers for their computers or they want mugs and t-shirts
and all of that good stuff, so we're just putting together a team to try and uh,
And fulfill that requirement
And again, there'll be a little bit of kickback which can go into the project which we can then use to do
You know the next thing and the next thing so hopefully it's a cycle of self-sustaining
Self-sustaining uh that we can we can start to generate
Well, i'm looking forward to 1504. I think uh, I think we'll have a review when it comes out because I think that's
I mean, I think already
Uh, the distribution is in my in my estimation seems to be one that's worth watching already
And that's a pretty I mean there's a lot of distributions that sort of uh,
That sort of hover in that kind of I mean, I don't mean to really put people down
and it's not really the same thing but
Uh mandriva a little bit just a little bit. I mean, I love me. I love mandriva. I love you guys
I'm a mandrake user back in the day. I was a draft club member
Uh, so I got the special repos. I mean seriously, I love it. So honestly, but
I actually just just talking in terms of sheer relevancy. I just wonder
um
well
Yes, it'll be interesting to see what happens. So
So distro watch were refusing to list abuntu mate whilst it was unofficial and the day after we got our official status
distro watch
Put up an abuntu mate page on distro watch
And that was a week ago and we're at number 23 now
In a week, so I know they're hinky stats, but it's a it's an interesting barometer for you know
Uh interest let's say yeah. Yeah
Uh, I I can I can there's other ways. I don't know. I've watched this stuff for a long time
There's other ways you can gauge it. Yeah
And and it's the thing is now it's getting difficult to to follow the the downloads because now we're on the official canonical infrastructure
I can't track all the downloads. So I don't know
how popular 1504 is versus 1410 and you know 1404 so I start to lose some visibility the
There was a recent article on was it the register where they?
Yeah, the upcoming
The upcoming 1504 release and didn't he talk about the torrent stats or was that some?
Yeah, no, it was it was the register article. Are you familiar with the register? I think that's mainly
In the uk. Oh, yeah
Okay, so um, yeah, the register covered the 1404 beta releases and covered ubuntu mate and happened to remark that the
The the seed ratio for ubuntu mate was three times that of any other flavor. So
That's kind of interesting. Yeah, it is. Yeah, look at the register doing a write-up on that
I'll link to that in the show notes as well
Um, so yeah, we've got some good stuff planned and the other the other new feature in 1504
That's probably worth mentioning is yes. You've got compass that you can turn on
uh with a
drop down menu
But the other thing i've been working on is the user interface switcher. Oh, yes
Okay, so this was something I had the idea about because the default mate, um
Um desktop arrangement isn't how I actually use the system. So I created a number of panel layouts that that suited me and also
Another podcaster who has a particular requirement for how they drive their machine
And I created these and they said what you should do is you should you know make a gooey so you can switch between these
So i've i've now made this so um
Effectively, you've got the you've got the mate default arrangement. You've got the open suzer
Uh desktop arrangement as was some years ago
And then something that looks broadly like um windows xp like
And then something that looks somewhat macos 10 like and that integrates with plank and what have you so
You can you can quickly switch your panel arrangement to single panel top or button
Uh with with docs and or not or dual dual panel and you can just cycle through them very quickly find one that
That broadly reflects how you want to run your system and then customize it from there
But uh, hopefully, um, it's just something a little bit different
and the uh, the
porting the
menu to the mate menu and setting up the uh,
The windows thing makes it kind of feel like a windows 7
Interface so people who want that could easily get that really quickly
Um, yes. Yeah, i've called that theme redmond as well in sort of, you know hat tip to uh to xp
Uh, so, you know what i'm gonna do, uh, i'm gonna just I think everybody should go check out the distro watch
Uh link because that's number 23 right now
Uh, and so I I just tweeted it out right now and uh, you can check it out
It's distro watch dot com slash ubuntu mate
Uh, and I think a lot of people like to learn about this distribution because it's pretty compelling you can hear
It's got a lot of cool features coming
So go check it out. Maybe go up a little bit further in the ranks and people check it out even more
Wimpy, that's a ton of stuff. So are you uh, not you're not pulling your hair out. You're doing okay
You're not about to uh, lose too much sleep or um go insane from all the workload
No, I am working two jobs at the moment
I'm effectively doing my day job and then i'm coming home and then doing another like full shift
Most most nights until sort of you know one two o'clock in the morning. So I am
I'm properly exhausted
um, I just need to get over the hump of
Fixing up for the the 1504 stuff
Hopefully be done in a week and then it should be a nice easy cruise in through
Beta 2 release candidate to final and uh, and in that period we can uh, we can start to
Look at the planning for 1510 and i've got some gsoc mentoring i'm planning at the moment as well
Wimpy, I tell you what. You almost make me want to switch away from arch that close too bad
I could just easily install matte
Of course, you know what honestly is I miss all of the fine touches you're doing like the color like the file
Like you need to you need to like can you just can you make all that like a package that I could just install on arch?
uh, yeah
Yeah, no, no, you're a little busy. Yeah. No, no, I probably could it's just finding time
Um, some of it's there already to be honest with you other people are maintaining some of those packages. But yes, it's uh,
If I did that then I sort of dilute the the value. I know i'm to marta
And so you have to walk what I have to do is just watch everything cool you do and then just go try to rip
It off on my own desktop on my own
The thing the thing i've been working hard on is the the the mate marta tweak and marta menu
And marta menu. Yeah, i've made those distro independent
So those were forked from the mint utilities and now they don't carry any specifics
For either ubuntu debian or mint. So those tools could be used on on any distro now
so
Technically you could get all of that one click goodiness
for compiz on
On arch and a couple of weekends ago. I did update the compiz packages for
For arch linux for marta users as well because I maintain those there as well
So, uh lots coming power pc support eventually arm support 1504 and even 1510 in the works
Officially a flavor now of ubuntu and the patreon and the distro watch submission. We have links to all that stuff in the show notes
Thank you very much for taking such a keen interest in the project. It's been great to watch it wimpy
It's been a lot of been a lot of fun and uh, it's well it runs all my computers
I just signed up on the patreon because that's that's selfish interest for me. I need this to work
It's genuinely a great product just to that's the great part. I want to contribute
And and what you and what and what you get is the warm fuzzy feeling that if there's any money left over we'll find a
A good candidate that's worthy of some funding. Um
That that directly benefits ubuntu marte and every month now
Uh, I plan to support an open source project through our um our funding campaign
That's really cool. You keep it up as long as you can because that's a pretty neat deal
Uh, all right. Well, we'll probably wrap it up there
So, uh, did you know the linux unplugged show is live that all these people we just talked to they're not recorded
Well, they're recorded now that you're hearing them, but when i'm talking to them, they're live and you could talk to them
You could be one of the people we're talking to. Oh my gosh go to jblive.tv
We do this show on a tuesday at 2 p.m. Pacific go to jupiterbroadcasting.com
Slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone and don't forget if you can't be here live
But you still want to contribute because you know, you'll love us
We do have that subreddit over at linuxactionshow.reddit.com
We pull stuff in from there and we'd love to have that
You also have the irc you can participate in and you can always help out financially too at our patreon
Patreon.com slash today the money raised there goes to all of the network
And matt, you know, I think with linux fest around the horizon. I've already started thinking about spring now in summer
I'm thinking about doing an episode of the show around the barbecue
Nice, I should probably just focus on next week though. Tell you the truth
It's okay to have long-term goals, but you know your short-term ones can't lose focus, right?
Well matt have a great week and i'll talk to you next week
In fact, uh, maybe if you swing your timing just right when you come down here on monday for your super secret mission
I'll have some barbecue just there's a possibility. Sounds good. Yeah. Yeah. All right, everybody. Thanks so much for this week's episode of linux unplugged
We'll see you right back here next week. And also we'll see on sunday. We're gonna do our production under linux episode finally
So tune in for that. Thanks so much. See you next week. So
Oh
Dang it. I was just uh, I was just reviewing uh poppy's contract and apparently we didn't dedicate enough time to ubuntu touch poppy
How's the ubuntu, uh touch project going in the bq stuff all good?
I'm, sorry. I'm contractually not allowed to talk about that now. Oh, wow. Oh, wow
Shabang, huh? Okay, fine try to give you a chance to give us you gotta wash his truck if you want this to work out
Chris that's what's coming down to i was trying to give no, it's fine. It's really fine. Oh, it's good, huh?
Okay, it's trying to give a bro. It's right. It's fine
Hey jb titles.com jb titles. Do you see um?
There was a photo that went past on google plus one of the people at the meizu
stand the meizu mx4 is one of the devices we're shipping soon and uh,
There was a couple of samsung executives hanging around the booth
Looking at the meizu phone running ubuntu, which was nice, you know, yeah, I want I want that phone, you know
If if tyson ever doesn't work out for them, you know, we'll be there for them with proper limits
There you go. Next time we're doing this show next week
the apple watch is going to be announced like whatever features it has are going to be established and the price and shipping date is
going to be announced and uh
I don't know like
Here I am like before and i'm still like thinking i'm still not
I I don't feel like they've sold me on why I want an apple watch
Although I don't feel like pebble ever sold me all I want a pebble and google never sold me
I want an android where exactly i'm still kind of in this area where
So the thing I like about the new pebble is the fact that they're touting it as being more hackable and having
Um a connector on the back that you could attach
The watch to or attach the strap the band the band so the bands can have different sensors
It says it could be bands. Yeah, the bands could have sensors or they could be more batteries
Or you could just take the watch completely off your wrist and have that as the control unit for something else
Oh my gosh have all kinds of under stuff underneath it. It doesn't have to be
Things type gizmo. Yeah, exactly. But the thing that the thing that kills
Pebbles android and ios obviously i'm speaking from a perspective of someone who doesn't actually use android or ios anymore
I'm screwed. I can't use either of those. I have to buy into the apple ecosystem to use an
Uh the iwatch and I have to buy into the android ecosystem in order to use an android where watch so
You know i'm boned either way. I can't use either of them. Whereas pebble seems to be a bit more open
They're completely open source
I think the future of the watch is on having something that just receives dummy information
Has a framework for displaying ui and the back end is always elsewhere
And this is for the stores an open protocol
You just enter in the story and you get options on the watch
This is what pebble is doing you can push a pebble app with their api and write no code
And people can choose to install it and it's amazing nice
But still you install it like what I really am. You install it to the watch
You know, that's exactly what i'm saying. You don't do anymore that the app exists actually on the store computer
Yes, it's on the apple store. You just you just say go and then it starts showing the information. There's no
Choice, you know, there's no setup for it. You just oh I want this to show up
Someone's already put it together for me. You just say okay show it on my watch
I got over the watch thing when I was like 10 when I got a timex data link and I started programming it
It's a flashing screen the scratch flashing monitor and programming it that way
even though there was only programs that I could put and download to the phone via the
Sensor like the light sensor onto it. It was still pretty cool
I kind of got over that way back then the watches now aren't really attractive to me. So
So pebble have clearly got like first mover advantage because they were kind of first out the gate in this space
And with their e-ink displays and the battery life they've been able to offer something that they that is
Similar to the watch wearing experience that you would already have had, you know, because these other smart watches
They're trying too hard. Yeah
It's not about firmware updates it's about whether your watch will still tell the time at nine o'clock at night
So I don't know if you guys have seen this sony e-ink watch. It's not a smart watch per se in the same way
That you would call it but it takes basic bluetooth stuff
And the amazing thing is the whole thing is an e-ink display like the band itself and when you can go in like say
I want I like this design band and you can just go and say I want this design band
I want the phone the the the watch at the top to look like this and it's like you can do that
And I thought it was so cool. I was like that is the watch I want
And what is it running?
It doesn't run anything. It's like it's kind of a dumb watch where it takes in some basic input. Yeah. Yeah
Oh my god, this pebble thing is cheap
Yeah, yeah, yeah
I think I am on record saying that that is the business model to go on the show here. Okay. I've just backed it
Really? Are you gonna get a phone? Did you get a watch to go for the steal?
Yeah, you're just drunk on hot cross buns you poppy poppy. You should go for the steel while you still can
It's more posh. That's fine
I'm not much more expensive. It's so what are the I haven't actually looked at this
Only the steel does the cool bands
Oh, really so they have uh, 68 000 backers wow 10 million dollars, so they're definitely funded
Is this the right kickstarter? Am I which one do I look at? Yeah, you're on it. Yeah
You're right. I think they're going like an hour and a half or is that the original? How do I know?
I'm not looking at the oh, yeah. Okay. Yeah, this is pebble time. This has the new watch no compromises. Yeah. Okay. All right
So here we go. This is
Yeah, uh, this is pretty cool. All right. I'm gonna play just a little bit of it. Hey kickstarter. My name is eric
I'm the founder of pebble. You may remember pebble from our first campaign when a bunch of you supported our quest
To build the world's first real smartwatch. I do remember that. Okay, so
Oh, okay, so you right when you jump in all the price levels are uh,
Your choice of one pebble time steel, which includes your choice of color includes a leather strap an extra metal strap. Oh
Oh, I really want to do that
Hmm. Well, I don't know see this seems like it's hard to it's hard for me to gauge right now
Which is the wearable watch to go behind but seems like pebbles the one doesn't it?
At least for us maybe yeah
I think I want to back at you guys
I have a really cool completely online, uh,
Development environment for it too. It's sweet
You can be as long as you're on the same network as your phone
You can just write code and push it right to your watch. I think I want to back it. Should I back it? I kind of
I want and then I could if I got oh gosh, I want one now. Oh, this is the steel
We're we're at a tipping point chris. There's there's there's two ways. This is going to go
When apple come out with their apple watch that will set the um,
Direction for the wearables market if apple make a success out of it
Everyone else will jump onto that ship firmly and if apple's wearables flop
it will be uh
A novelty that never really gains any traction and it will be the likes of pebble that own that space
And it will be a relatively small market
So where do you want to be? Do you want to be either way pebble sounds like a safe bet? Yeah, I think so
I think I think well that you know, like I said, they've got a lot of different brands
I think I think well that you know, like I said, they've got first mover advantage
They're far more far further along than the others in actually delivering a wearable device
You know something that you can wear all day long that works
One of the better things about the pebble is that i've had mine for over a year now
And I think only two or three people have ever been like, oh, is that a smartwatch?
It's just it just blends in. I don't think that these other devices are going to do that
The thing apple has is giant gobs of money
And yeah, and that that's something that pebble never has which is going to be hard to compete with and maybe they get the
hacker mentality
That you know people like us will play with it, but apple
will have uh
premium stores and
Lots of news airtime on all the mainstream channels as a result of them being apple
But here is the trick. It's open source, right mostly so at least so that means that any
Low-end store that looks at the high fees to do partnership with apple. It still wants a phone
A phone. Sorry a watch is probably going to do with the pebbles
especially
Yeah, the thing is the thing is is uh
Uh, all the the hackability and open source stuff is great for the likes of us that are discussing this now
But if I say to my wife i'm going to get one of these smartwatches and she's going to say to me one
And i'm like, well it can tell me all of the things that's on my phone and the time
She's going to say well, why don't you just look at your phone?
Yeah, and and this is this
This is how I feel about it
It's nothing you see the problem is these watches in overall have been
Marketed as a device for a consumer to buy
I really think that these are devices for a store to offer to a customer to a member
But like that or a cheap one that is subsidized by these businesses
But for what what are you going to use it for? This is I haven't seen a compelling use case yet
I use my pandora
Or my
Membership card on the store. It gives you more information and to the store they win more precise information about your actual buying habit
But i've got nfc and my mobile phone. I already carry that everywhere. Why can't I do those things with my mobile phone?
It's great. This is remote without having to take your your phone out of your pocket
But my phone is out of my pocket. I'm sitting down. So why is that? Why is that compelling?
What so how big is your phone?
Uh, that's that's my like everyone that I see as these huge ginormous
Fablets, I'm gonna call them. Yeah. Yeah, i've I've I had a note too and today i've just replaced it with a nexus 6
So I I got I have the firefox west flame is my my my main phone and it's already to the point where it's like
This is kind of large and I don't want anything bigger than this and yet I can't buy anything smaller than that now
So it's it's honestly
You could buy an abuntu phone. Yeah about the same size as the firefox flame
I'm, actually I have both in my hand right now the firefox flame and the bq phone and they are pretty much identical size
Pebble is nice when I get an email notification and my phone's in the other room
But I can hear it and I can see the email and know that it's not worth getting up for
Yeah, when I want to skip a song that's playing and I don't want to unlock my phone and deal with getting into the app
To skip a song
on
Okay, so the song skipping if if you put yourself in an environment where that's more convenient
Because it's on your wrist like for example
If you're cycling for example
And you've got your phone in a backpack and you've got your headphones in and your watch is on your wrist and you're cycling along
You can be measuring your distance and velocity and all of that good stuff and you can skip tracks
You I can see a use case for a smartwatch
But you have to kind of think really hard and you can't see that most people are going to get value out of
a device like that
This is if you're an upper class businessman
You're sitting in a really important meeting and your phone's on silent, but your wish is you know
Giving you a buzz that your wife is calling you
Upper class businessman doesn't know how to use his phone or his computer and therefore he won't know how to use his smartwatch either
No
Way of saying other end of conversation would be look at your watch now when you look at your watch
You're gonna think you're looking at facebook
Well, it's true I do sometimes that's that's the other thing
Your guys are thinking about okay. Why I as a consumer will acquire a watch
That's why i'm saying the future of these watches is not on you acquiring it
It's in the companies that want the information from you will give it to you and then you're gonna start using some of these
Uh leverage I don't understand this approach because the watch doesn't collect any data
Oh, so this is the beauty of it once you are inside the store
Usually they have patterns on on okay what things you decided to pay on the cash, right?
On the cashier right with your membership card for you to get the discount. That's why they apply the discounts
Okay, what about extra information on a product based on you closing your watch to the divide to the product?
You take the watch doesn't do any sort of communication like that
Well, I guess are you envisioning like these stores like the watches will get so cheap
These stores will have like a branded watch. They give you as part of the membership program
That or they will collaborate in a pool of companies and they will have a system
And so you have a single membership card
And when you are inside of one specific store you get the system of that specific store when you're inside of another store
You get the specific of that other store and then they can share the cost of producing these watches