This is Linux Unplugged Episode 36 for April 15th, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's stuck between two studios.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey Matt.
So I'm, this week I'm recording Linux Unplugged somewhere I've never, ever recorded it before.
So it's a little weird.
So it's gonna, it's gonna, everything's gonna be a little different.
I'm actually in the regular studio that, hi, see I'm right here.
If you're watching the video version, I'm in the regular studio that we do the Linux
action show.
I'm usually not in the studio, but we're this week, we're beginning the transition to our
new studio.
So please forgive, pardon the dust as the old saying goes, because Matt, this week I
still want to try to have a great conversation about something that's sort of been brewing
over the last few episodes.
Last week we had Chase on and he talked about what kind of has been his blockers to switching
to Linux.
And one of the things he talked about is way too much choice and how, how that was really
a big part of the problem.
And I want to sort of just float the idea, playing devil's advocate, if you will, that
maybe suggesting the underdog distro to folks is doing them a disservice and hurting Linux
adoption.
And I want to talk about that.
And then if we have some time after that, I want to discuss that here we are Tuesday
and it is still open source is getting a beating over this Heartbleed bug and everybody is
condemning open source, the model for open source software, your buddy, Paul Throt, took
the web and said that this proves that the all eyes are on the source code philosophy
is bogus and that open source security is not any better.
And it's just, you know, people are piling on.
So if we have time, yeah, I know I've been harping on this one, but I want to talk about
a little bit.
If we get through the underdog distro discussion, that's all first.
So it should be a pretty good show this week.
And you know, the other thing is, too, while we're talking about this underdog situation,
it's kind of in the shadow of Ubuntu 14.04's release, which comes out between now and Linux
action show on Sunday.
And the 14.04 is getting a lot of praise right now.
And it's the epitome of the big dog desktop distro when we talk about underdogs, like
Ubuntu is on the absolute opposite end of that spectrum.
And so this conversation is happening with all of this with their release on Sunday,
and then we're going to have that review.
It's just kind of a very interesting time, so I hope folks stick with us for that.
But I wanted to give a quick, like, you know, just update about GNOME 3.12.
GNOME 3.12 hit the Arch repo stable since Linux action show on Sunday.
And I've got my main machine upgraded to GNOME 3.12 now.
And I wanted to pass along a little helper I found.
If you're having troubles with GNOME Terminal after upgrading to GNOME 3.12 on Arch, I have
a link in the show notes that does a pretty quick fix.
I didn't have any issues.
It runs really good.
GNOME 3.12 runs really great.
I'm really happy with this release.
And you know, one of the things that I've joked about, and I'm kind of actually serious,
is I started using GNOME 3.10 in anticipation of GNOME 3.12.
I was like, I'm going to spend the GNOME 3.10 release, I'm going to spend that time just
like totally learning GNOME, and then I'm going to, I'll be ready, my body will be ready
when GNOME 3.12 lands.
And I think that worked out.
I think that's pretty much where I'm at.
But I'm really happy with it.
And so at the same time, a new Cinnamon release came out this week.
And I'm thinking, well, it's worth checking out.
What I'm really interested in is how is Cinnamon handling these new client-side decorations
that the new GNOME apps, you know, like gEdit and Roller, and a lot of these, Nautilus,
a lot of these apps are, and in some cases, you know, Cinnamon Desktop has their own replacements,
NEMO, for example, to replace Nautilus, but there's, inevitably, on a Cinnamon Desktop
now, you're going to run a GTK app that has these client-side decorations, these new toolbars
that GNOME apps have.
And I'm really curious how that works, because I know they did some kind of support in the
new version of Cinnamon to support client-side decorations, but I'm not really, I'm not really
hip on how it actually works, I haven't tried it yet myself.
And then on the other side of all that, you know, I should grab the person's name, because
I don't know if it's the same guy, or if it's a couple of people, but they have been awesome
at submitting the KDE Design Group's Monday updates to our subreddit, like, they're just
on it, yeah, so, Euro Topman, is that you?
Are you out there, Euro Topman?
I don't know if you're the guy that's been doing all of them, but I want to thank you,
because it's really been helping me keep in touch with what the KDE Design Group is up
to, remember we had their lead designer on last couple weeks ago.
When he unveiled their, kind of the prototype, this is a mock-up, or, I don't know, not a
mock-up, because there's actual code out there you can get, but this is an early design iteration,
it's very flat, Matt, I don't know if you had a chance to look at the new KDE design
shots, but some people in our subreddit are calling it very metro-looking.
Oh, really?
No, I haven't actually had a chance to look at them yet.
They're very, I think they're very nice, as somebody who's enjoying GNOME 3.12 right now,
I think these actually look pretty great.
I'll put a link to this in the show notes, but it's a brand new theme that they're working
on, it's not going to replace any other themes, it's just going to be an option.
I think it's the cleanest-looking KDE theme I've ever seen.
I don't know, what say you, chatroom?
I'm curious what you guys think, but it's just a very interesting time right now for
all of this stuff, because we've got the latest version of Unity launches on the 17th, KDE's
working way at this new design and on their new version of KDE, and GNOME 3.12, it's a
crazy time, man, it's a crazy time to be doing a show.
So alright, well I wanted to get to some feedback from last week's episode, we got a lot of
good stuff.
We had Chase on, if you guys didn't catch last week's episode, and he was talking about
his challenges switching to Linux, and so some of these touch on that, some of these
touch on a few of the other aspects that we got to in last week's episode, so we'll start
with this.
Our first one comes in from Kerry, and he says, hi Chris and Matt, I've been listening
to LAS and CodeRadio and TechSnap from the beginning, I just started listening to Linux
Unplugged.
On the subject of Windows users coming to Linux, I wanted to give the perspective of
someone who recently, newly came to Windows.
The only time I've encountered Windows was using a Windows 95 box for gaming when I was
young enough not to remember using Windows, and just for Word documents at school.
Otherwise, I've been using KDE and OS X, and now mainly Ubuntu.
It was only a couple of years ago that I received a laptop that an office was throwing out that
I actually used Windows for the first time and I ran into many roadblocks that I've seen
other Windows users run into that they just brush off and don't care about, and he has
a couple of examples here.
The file manager, it's difficult to navigate, what's the difference between pictures and
my pictures?
I have no idea why no one else knows either.
Very true.
Yeah, very true.
Navigating the settings menu is difficult.
When an app crashes, Windows will try to resolve the problem for several minutes.
Sometimes the problem resolving Windows will start to freeze up as well.
When this first happened to me, it was really upsetting and I asked around, what to do if
this happens?
People told me, yeah, it happens when you just wait for it to, you wait it out.
He says it's insanity.
All the apps are awful.
If they aren't installing malware or a toolbar, then they use ads or annoying pop-ups.
I use Microsoft recommended PDF reader and I still use sneaky tactics to make the experience
awful for me.
There are so many more things, but these are just the kinds of problems that I never have
to deal with when I'm using Linux or OS X, and these problems should be pointed out to
any Linux newbie of the things they won't have to deal with anymore.
Gnome 3.12 was light years ahead of Windows when it comes to ease of use, and I didn't
realize that until I started using Windows.
PS, when Linux Unplugged was launched, I couldn't find it in iTunes, so I didn't listen to it.
But after a while, I stumbled upon the feed again.
You should remind the audience that the feed does now actually exist.
Well, point well taken, Kerry.
How funny is that to get it from that perspective?
Like the...
That's a fascinating perspective because it kind of proves that it's all in the eyes of
the builder.
Yeah, yeah.
I find it funny too, because I feel the same way when I now use Windows.
It feels very frustrating to me, and I think it's people that are switching have never
really experienced that phenomenon.
So if you're coming from Windows to something, you've never done that before, so you don't
realize it's actually...
You don't realize how much that familiarity plays into what you perceive to be usable.
And I think until you've switched around and hopped a few distros and desktops, then you
start to realize it.
Right.
No, I definitely agree with that.
I think it's something that really kind of makes us think twice about stuff.
It certainly makes us rethink what we've been reading in the media.
Kenny writes in.
He says, hi Matt and Chris, and Chase.
I was a little surprised the discussion regarding switchers to Linux went so long before someone
mentioned Linux distros are built around software centers or repositories.
This is the first thing that I explain to potential new users of Linux, and it's easy
to do.
It's critical to starting them off in the straight and narrow, and is a straightforward
advantage.
What?
You don't want to have to go racking around the internet and shoot off to PC world and
spend a fortune on new software?
Nope.
When I tried Linux for the first time circa 2008, it was because I couldn't afford a Windows
upgrade from Windows ME.
What had kept me from doing it earlier was not that there was too much choice or confusion,
but that I thought I completely borked my precious computer during the installation
of Windows.
Microsoft likes to impress you that you need to be an expert or crazy to actually want
to install your own OS.
The first time around, I got stuck between I didn't know what home and swap partitions
were.
But after some Googling, I was able to sort that out.
So here's my advice for Chase.
You can only do so much reading or research on a subject before you just have to try it.
Pick one of the larger distributions.
Go with the default desktop and settings.
And during installation, ensure you create a separate root or home and swap partitions.
Check on the official distro's website as to which proprietary drivers or codecs you
might want to add and how to install them.
And you're off!
Anyhow, Chase, good luck with the move and I'm sure it won't be long before you're feeling
right at home.
Great show as always.
I'm really looking forward to the how-to show.
I think his point about sometimes you just got to jump in is exactly right.
That takes a kind of adventurous person.
Yeah, I would tend to agree with that because I think you can only read about it so much
as they pointed out.
I think you definitely have to kind of stop running your face against the wall and walk
around and actually try some stuff.
Now that's why Chromebooks, I think, are doing so well because you don't have to really...
Your choice is what kind of screen you want, what kind of keyboard you want, the battery
life you want, and then you just buy it.
And I think that's why it's super appealing to a lot of XP switchers.
And then Linux becomes an implementation detail, which if you remember what Linus said in his
recent Q&A, that's perfectly fine with him.
That's how he likes it.
He doesn't care at all.
And that's why I think it's funny, you know, there are certain people, certain Microsoft
pundits out there that like to boast about how it's Linux, you know, users will never
care about Linux and they never have cared about Linux.
And you're silly to think otherwise.
What Paul is forgetting is that that's exactly how it should be.
That's what we expect.
Linux is the implementation detail.
Now it is a massive detail that we spend our lives here thinking about, but it is to the
user, it is but a detail.
And that's how it should be.
And that's how Linus thinks it should be too.
And we've heard him say it.
So that's why I'm warming up to the idea of Chromebooks, which I was initially pretty
cold on.
And I don't judge anybody who thinks that's the machine they should be running.
Just like I think Chase got hung up on choice.
I think the Chromebook solves that problem.
But I think as a community, we can help solve that.
And that's what I want to talk about in the second half of the show today is kind of that
hang up and exactly what our last email just sort of touched on is, you know, pick one
of the big ones to start with, at least.
And so often I see in the community advice in the other direction given.
Before we talk about that, before we get to the rest of our feedback, I want to thank
our first sponsor this week.
And that is Ting.com.
Go over to linux.ting.com.
Now what is Ting?
Ting is mobile that makes sense.
It's my mobile service provider, and it's Matt's mobile service provider.
And I got to tell you, what I love about it, and I think what Matt probably loves about
it too, is you only pay for what you use.
And if you're a work at home kind of guy, or if you're in an office that has Wi-Fi you
can jump onto, this is such a value.
Because you can use your phone when you need to make that actual call.
But 90% of my data usage is on the Wi-Fi.
So why would I pay into some massive plan that I, you know, I might need four gigabytes
one month out of the year, maybe three months out of the year, maybe more or less, you know.
And so every single month I pay into that large plan in the off chance that I might
need that.
Whereas with Ting it's like, okay, I'm just going to pay for it when I actually need it.
And otherwise I get full advantage of being on Wi-Fi when I'm on Wi-Fi, and I just pay
for the usage and there's zero stress.
When I'm out on the road, when I'm setting up the new studio, I don't have to worry about
overages.
I don't have to worry about getting $15 every gigabyte like some of the other big blue logoed
mobile carriers do.
Dang it.
I have to tell you.
You can support it by going to linux.ting.com and you'll save $25 off your first device.
If you already have a device and you want to bring it to the Ting network, check out
their BYOD page.
They support lots of great devices.
It's a great way to get started because then they'll apply that $25 credit to your bill.
And if you're like me, your first bill is going to be free.
They just recently also added support for the iPhone 5.
98% of people would save money with Ting.
And one of the things that's different about Ting is go to linux.ting.com.
That registers your interest.
It thanks them for supporting this show because they see that you came there because we sent
you there.
So linux.ting.com and then check out their blog.
And tell me you didn't wish your mobile carrier was as transparent and awesome as this.
Ting is constantly updating their blog with behind the scenes interviews that are real
and legitimate.
They have app comparisons that are really great apps.
We covered one on Linux Action Show.
They did a Heartbleed update because they had a lot of people send in and ask what the
status of Ting's Heartbleed security was.
And this is a great one too.
They're posting a little reminder about their personal shopper service which just turned
one years old.
You can go to Ting and be like, hey Ting, this is what I want from a device.
I don't want to buy it new.
But I still want to take advantage of the fact that when I get a device from you, I
own it outright.
It's mine.
And if you could find me a device that meets these specifications, then I could switch
to you.
And on average, in two days, Ting will find you a used mobile device that you can get
refurbished and then help you get it connected to the Ting network.
It's another great way to get started and really take advantage of Ting's value.
So go over to linux.ting.com to get started.
And finally, get out of your contract.
Never worry about early termination fees.
And by the way, if you are in an early termination fee, they have an ETF relief program.
You can find more about that at ting.com slash ETF.
They're going to pay you up to $75 per line that you have to get canceled.
That's a really great deal.
And then you're just going to start saving money from the now linux.ting.com and a big
thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged and their great support of the Jupiter Broadcasting
Network too.
We really appreciate it.
So Quickie writes in.
That's a great name.
And he says, you guys were talking about the terminal versus the GUI last week.
And some of you were floating the crazy arse idea that the terminal might actually be better
for new users in the GUI because you can give them the commands over the phone.
He says, hey, Chris and Matt, time zone sucks.
I wish I could have joined you live.
About the terminal versus GUI topic, yeah, it's a personal choice really, but nothing
is better than the other.
I developed GUI applications for Linux, but they aren't as powerful as the terminal since
text gives you a lot of advantages like almost infinite permutations and the ability to compose
features together.
About the text support part, though, it's harder to explain where to click.
But I don't think that is something that makes the GUI inferior to the command line.
It just points out bad design decisions of the GUI.
Try to explain to someone to change the default application for the document type on Windows
and elementary OS.
In Windows control panel, you go to the control panel, then you go somewhere and you right
click on that file and you go to open with and you select, he gets lost, and you can
eventually get them depending on the version of Windows to check the default application.
But in a more well-designed operating system like elementary OS, it's simple as pie.
You go to applications, system settings, defaults, and then you just select the application.
It's right there.
I think UI dictates the usability of the GUI, not command line versus GUI.
Interesting point.
And I agree, too, that we got some other people that are like, yeah, see, when you try to
read somebody a command over the phone, you never know if they're typing it in right and
they don't always read back the return right to you.
True.
Each their own, Matt.
Okay.
Before we get to our Valve update, Kyle wrote in and he says there was a big point that
we missed in last week's episode and I kind of agree with him.
We were talking about how Linux is especially right now in 2014, really better suited for
geeks, for technical people that want to switch away from Windows for various reasons and
there's a lot of them.
And it's not just XP going away, there's a lot of reasons why technical users who have
been Windows enthusiasts for years might want to move over to the Linux platform.
And we were trying to discuss the best way for that to happen and he says the point that
you missed, and though I enjoyed your conversation with Chase in the last show, is since I think
it dealt with the topic that all of us want to promote Linux, we struggle with this.
However, I think that you missed out on the biggest and most obvious point that you should
have considered.
I think that despite your claims to the contrary, that you remain stuck on the topic of the
mythical first time PC user or the grandma and grandpa user who have no technical knowledge.
If you truly believe that technical users are most likely to switch to Linux, you should
recommend experimenting with Linux in a VM.
The immediate objection to this idea will be that VMs are too complicated for new users.
However, complexity of using Linux on a VM is mostly handled in the host OS where the
technical user is already comfortable with the GUI and the software, not in the guest
where they are out of their element.
What is the biggest advantage with experimenting in a VM?
Snapshots are external to the guest OS.
They can be restored from the GUI and that is what the user is comfortable with.
This is a set of training wheels or water wings that a new user who wants to go nuts
with an experiment needs.
Want to remove Ubuntu desktop and try to install Ubuntu?
No problem.
Once you run into problems, just restore your last snapshot.
Feel like maybe you want to try another distro, but worry you might lose your work you've
put in so far?
No problem.
Just create a new VM yourself.
You yourself have often used VMs in the past to demo distros, so why wouldn't a technical
user?
This was the method I used to get into Arch Linux.
My first two attempts at installing the OS were a total catastrophe, but eventually with
some determination and a few snapshot rollbacks, I started to feel at home with it and now
I've installed on a number of real computers.
For most of my distro hopping needs, I still use VMs and if a user like Chase really wants
to maximize benefits they get out of their hardware, well, they can do that once they
get used to the basics of Linux.
Next, Kyle.
What do you think, Matt, for technical users is trying it out in a VM first a viable idea?
Well, I think if you have the resources that will support it, I think that's fine, but
I think that's a pretty iffy situation for most people.
Yeah, I think Chase could.
I think he has pretty good PCs.
Oh yeah, Chase could do it, but I mean for Joe average, just someone who maybe is not
a Windows power user, that might not be such a great thing.
I do agree with Kyle in the sense that I am surprised when we're talking about tech users
that the VM doesn't come up more because that is his point where the management of the VM,
like the snapshotting, all of that is done in the native OS that they're familiar with,
so like they are comfortable with pushing those boundaries.
That actually makes a lot of sense to me.
So when I think about it that way, I kind of feel like bad on me for saying, hey, if
you're a technical user, like Chase, for example, when we start how to Linux is going to make
that switch and I've been racking my brain, like I think the best way to get him to use
Linux is to make him run it to do a lot of things, right?
Say, hey, Chase, when you know you're doing your regular day-to-day stuff, do it in this
machine.
Don't default back to your Windows box or your Mac box.
And I was trying to think like, well, what am I going to do?
Am I going to like rent him a laptop, you know, am I going to set up a PC at his house
and then like I read this and I was like, yeah, he could just run a full screen VM.
I know he's got a machine nice enough to do it.
That would make sense.
I mean, I think in his case that definitely matches for sure.
Yeah.
All right, Matt.
Before we get into the main discussion in our show this week, I do want to have a little
valve update.
We got to talk about this because the valve news hasn't been making it in the big show
as much, but I try to keep up to date in Linux Unplugged and we've got a release date on
that valve controller.
Now you don't have to have a steam box to use the valve controller.
I know you've been doing some Let's Play videos, Matt, so you've been looking at controllers.
You'll be able to, so I don't know if you've seen the latest version of the valve controller,
but it looks much more like a regular controller with regular buttons.
It still has those, the areola controllers, I don't know what else.
Those are still pretty cool.
Those are still there.
And I guess it's October or November is when the steam controller is going to be available
with, right now they're saying over 500 compatible games.
And then I would think anything that really supports a controller.
So there you go.
If you want to get yourself a steam controller, you'll be able to pre-order it soon.
I'm going to get one.
Are you?
Oh well, I've got to, right?
I'm going to get one on the show.
And I play with the controller quite a bit anyways.
I'm already playing with a 360 controller.
I'm not going to lie, it feels dirty every time I plug it into my bonobo.
I feel like I'm committing some sort of crime or something.
I don't know.
So yeah, I think I'm going to get one.
I'm looking forward to it as a matter of fact the more I think about it.
I'm just a little worried it's not going to work as great because the thing is, the dirty
little secret, actually it's not that dirty of a secret, the Xbox 360 controller works
outrageously well under Linux.
Like you just plug it in, it works out of the box on every game that I've tried.
And Valve even just recently updated the kernel support for the controller so it's even better.
So the Xbox 360 has turned into the perfect Linux game controller.
And on top of that, it's not a bad controller to begin with.
It's one of my more preferred controllers anyways.
So I've never tried the one, so I don't know.
But the 360 controller, well I guess I have tried the one, it seems the same to me.
So I don't know, as ridiculous as it sounds, I think on my Linux box, Valve's biggest competition
is Microsoft's 360 controller.
I feel dirty.
Dirty thunk it.
Ugh.
All right, well before we get into our main topic this week, I want to thank our second
sponsor and that is Digital Ocean.
You guys, if you've been listening to the show a little bit, you know how much I love
Digital Ocean.
But if you're new to the show, let me tell you a little bit about them.
Digital Ocean is growing and exploding and they are probably both concisely put, consider
them to be simple cloud hosting, dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way
to spin up a cloud server.
And if you just think about like if you need to spin up a system, like I was just having
a little pre-show chat about a new server I needed and it's like, oh yeah, that would
work great as a Digital Ocean instance and here's the great part.
Users can create a cloud server in 55 seconds, however, however in our subreddit right now,
the record is 43 seconds.
And then I got an email today, this morning, saying, hey man, hey man, my record, if you
listen to like episode 26 of Unplugged, my record's 40 seconds.
So we've got people competing right now, 55 seconds is the average benchmark, but we have
people that can create an entire cloud server instance in 40 seconds in Digital Ocean as
data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore and Amsterdam.
And part of the reason why people can make these cloud servers so fast is because their
interface is simple, they have an intuitive control panel and power users can replicate
that on a larger scale with their straightforward API, which I've been told is quite beautiful.
And their dashboard is really great and one of the things I love about Digital Ocean is
once they implement a feature, they don't just leave it alone, they continue to do really
smart logical iteration.
You can see the evolution of not just the product features, but the design and how you
use the product.
Like I have watched them really mature the resize image stuff, you know, they've added
in some really great DNS management, the snapshot interface has never been better, their HTML5
console access to your droplet, you get HTML5 console access.
And they have one button install of WordPress and Ruby on Rails, and they're using Doku
on the backend, which is an open source project that they created that they sponsor that works
with Docker to deploy applications.
And listeners of Coderadio, if they use the promo code UnpluggedApril, of Linux Unplugged,
UnpluggedApril, you can get two months for free when you get the $5 droplet.
If you use the promo code UnpluggedApril, two months for free, that's a great deal.
And you can try out that $5 rig for a little bit and see what you can do.
I'm constantly finding new uses for mine, and we have a G Plus community thread where
they've been talking about all of the great things that they're using their DigitalOcean
droplets for.
So go over to DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code UnpluggedApril to check them out.
And an outrageously huge thank you to DigitalOcean for not only supporting the Linux Unplugged
podcast, but for just being so awesome.
I love your SSD drives, I love them, and I love your tier one bandwidth.
Tell you what, Matt, if you wanted to refresh some server hosting skills, or you wanted
to do a little MP3 stream or something like that for yourself, or maybe your own cloud
instance or a Minecraft server, or if you're like Michael Dominic on Coderadio, he uses
DigitalOcean to host the backend infrastructure for the apps that he sells to clients.
And some of the biggest sites on the web use DigitalOcean.
So the scalability is so awesome, and what we talk about all the time, we've talked about
it on this show specifically, is the technologies that are doing this are the technologies
that we are watching in front of our very eyes evolve.
Like Docker, like KVM, and all of this stuff is coming together, SystemD, it's all coming
together to work as a platform for DigitalOcean to make a whole new generation of servers
that are available to folks at unbelievable value.
And that's what's so exciting because we're actually seeing the realization of the stuff
we've been talking about in DigitalOcean, and they're blowing up.
They're hiring right now.
You can go over to their website.
You can get a job.
They just got a great round of funding.
They have an awesome video series on TechCrunch that goes into their office and kind of gives
you a little bit of behind the scenes about their culture.
They're a really cool company, and I'm really happy to have them on here.
So go over to DigitalOcean.com and use that promo code unpluggedapril to thank them.
And check it out for yourself and see what's so cool about having your own SSD-powered
droplet.
Okay, Matt, so I wanted to talk about the underdog a little bit, and I really don't
mean to...
I don't want this show to be ranty, and I don't want to get anybody offended that works
really hard on their distribution.
That's not my goal here.
So I want to give you the background on this, and then we'll go from there.
So recent discussions that we've had on Linux Unplugged, I think pretty much prompted by
the demise of XP, have really made me thinking about getting more people to switch to Linux.
And really, the scope of the problems that we have there.
And so many of those problems are really outside our ability to control.
They're OEM, or they're distribution channel problems, or whatever it is.
They're really just as regular, at the end of the day, regular Linux users, they're outside
our scope.
So I've been trying to think more of what's actually legitimately in our scope to solve.
And a lot of times that comes down to community, support infrastructure, helping onboard people
who are already maybe interested in making the switch, and maybe trying to find ways
to outreach to people who haven't made the choice yet.
And I think some of this is honestly in the shadow, some of this discussion we're going
to have about underdog distros is legitimately in the shadow of the 14.04 release, which
we're talking about soon.
And so I've been running Ubuntu again, and I'm once again on a distribution where when
you run it, you can genuinely feel that it is the wider used platform, like it's unquestionable
that the most people running Linux on the web are on Ubuntu because so much that you
find on the web is just automatically tailored for Ubuntu.
And that really comes through when you're using it.
It's got me thinking about this a lot more.
And so I think what I want to kind of pitch to you into the Mumble Room is, are we doing
a disservice to new users when we recommend these boutique distros, which I think are
great for experienced users, but essentially you're sending them down a path where they
become part of a niche of a niche, because Linux is already a niche desktop environment,
and then you send them onto a distro that is a niche of that already small slice of
pie.
So the support community is automatically out of the gate smaller.
Even if it's really sharp where it's sharp, it's smaller.
And the other thing that it's one of these unpredictable things that you can't account
for, but it always smacks new users right in that face, is that random, poorly crafted
Google search, you know, where they're just, they're less likely to get results for their
own distro.
Like I don't know if it was in the pre-show, I think, or I know it was in the post-show
I think of last week's Linux Unplugged, but Chase decided after using 14.04 for the whole
episode to try to install Steam.
So he went to Google.
He didn't even think about going to the package manager because that's a totally new concept
to him.
So he went to Google and he searched for Steam installation and he got a link for Fedora,
and he started downloading an RPM like he was off on a completely wrong course because
the title of the article was install Steam on Linux.
And you got to think about when these guys are searching for this stuff, if you have
them off on some boutique small distro, and I have a lot of respect for some of these
smaller distros that we've had on the show and talked to, but that right there is setting
them up for some level of failure.
Then you have to ask what's the long-term viability of any really small team.
There is a good shot it'll work out, but it's always questionable.
Larger distros like Ubuntu or OpenSUSE or Fedora, even if they're corporate backers
or their community pulled out completely, that code would still go on.
There would be a fork in the open source community that would maintain that for at least some
point in time.
But with these smaller distributions, sometimes when they shut down, they shut down.
And Matt, I know you've seen that, you've watched that happen, and we've seen these
smaller guys where they just kind of go away.
Well I also think that, it's a little bit like I was saying previously, that I feel
that if you're starting someone out for the first time, they should be starting out with
an Ubuntu base, whether that's Ubuntu with Unity or whether it's one of the other desktop
environments.
But I think by sticking to that, that actually provides you with enough flexibility to try
some new stuff, but you're pretty well grounded in not ending up in an experimental land,
which is where most people end up with boutique distros.
Later on you can try out the boutique distros.
Let me ask Crash Bandicoot, because I believe he recently switched somebody new to Linux
and he chose Korora 19 or Korora 20, is that right Crash?
Yeah, that's right, it's a friend of mine who, he's one of my housemates, and so I put
him on that because I figured, you know, every time he needs anything done, he just comes
to me and says, oh I need this done, all that done, what do you want me to do?
He's got the proximity advantage.
Yeah, so that's why I ended up actually switching him to Intergas, just because there was a
few things going wrong with Fedora, it was just running slow and stuff.
So you moved him to Tegra?
Yeah, because like I said, you know, I have SSH access to his machine, so updates and
stuff I just do every week or so, I just do it.
But I actually have another friend who, he came to me and he said, oh you know, I've
been looking at Harry's computer and it's really cool because, you know, Gnome Shell
and all the rest of it, and he wanted to give it a try.
And so I pointed him towards Ubuntu and he's had no problems with that at all, like he
just installed it, he used the Gnome Shell remix because he wanted Gnome, and he just
installed it and he's been loving it, like he's had no issues at all.
Whereas the guy that I'm sort of managing his system, if he was by himself, I'd probably
have pointed him towards Ubuntu as well for that exact reason that you mentioned with,
you know, if he Googles how to do something, he's going to get a guide for Ubuntu, he might
get a guide for Arch or whatever else, but he's definitely going to get a guide for Ubuntu
that works.
Now Crossroads, you were going to say that we should maybe consider custom tailing it
for each user.
That doesn't sound very scalable to me, to be honest with you.
Also, um, sorry.
Go ahead Riley.
Well, I was going to say, uh, there is an issue with Ubuntu, even still though, is because
a lot of the time you'll find outdated PPAs and like you'll find info, but it'll be
retaining like 804 or something.
It's way off.
So you got to be careful what you're searching for too.
Well, that's very true.
Yeah.
But it's also easier for Ubuntu anyway, cause it's like most time people will, the stuff
will be updated.
Like the forum, if you go to Google to something, a lot of the times the form doesn't show up
anymore and it's Ask Ubuntu now.
So that's an improvement.
Well that was a conscious decision actually.
We had a, uh, George Castro, a great talk at one of our, um, developer summits and, uh,
it was all about going through the wiki and deleting pages cause we're doing a disservice
to our users and our friends when we leave like some wacky how to from 804 detailing
how to use Endis wrapper, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, you know, we should get
rid of that page because it's no longer needed and point people at Ask Ubuntu.
Hmm.
Well, I guess, so here's what happens is people for whatever reason, uh, and I don't know
if I consider myself in this camp or not, I'm undecided, but people for whatever reason
sometimes hesitated recommending Ubuntu.
I mean, we just saw this New York Times article that we covered in the Linux action show and
the author of the New York Times article, the number one distro at the top of his list
was Bodai Linux and it was also the one he had the most praise.
Uh, I think Ubuntu was three on the list after Mint.
And so Mint is the one you hear like thrown around the most often is an alternative to
Ubuntu.
Uh, I want to, so I think if you guys are buying, it sounds like you guys are all kind
of buying off on this philosophy that if, if it's a, if it's a random new user who you're
not holding his hand or her hand and installing that Linux for them and then by proxy also
being their support, then Ubuntu is a good choice.
All right, so if we accept that, yeah, okay.
So if we accept that, do we also accept that about Mint?
Yes, but slightly different.
So I would, I would argue why is it any different?
Like so for me, then you get into the question, well, but cinnamon and mate are again onto
an island of their own.
They're not something that's super common.
They're not something that, you know, what the longterm prospects are, although they
look good.
Uh, and you know, you don't know if they've been as banged on as the rest of the desktops
that have maybe a larger user base because they're on more distributions or they just
have more users.
So what is the difference between a boutique recommending a boutique distribution and recommending
a boutique desk?
Well, well, they're not boutique and longterm support, but there's also not boutique like
Mint's not boutique.
I mean, it's, it's become a, just as popular as Ubuntu, but it benefits when having Ubuntu
support.
I don't, I don't, I don't, I don't buy that.
I don't buy that for a minute.
I'm not talking about, I mean, I think it's a great distribution.
I don't, I don't buy, I don't buy that.
It has nearly the install base that Ubuntu does.
It doesn't.
I'm talking about like you're, you're talking about the consideration of like, uh, as far
as like popularity goes, Mint has as much popularity, popularity, but out, but outside
of Linux community, it's, it's much lower and outside of servers, it's basically, you
know, there's, there's nothing.
But when you look into it, like just usability wise, people are going to suggest Mint purely
for the fact that Cinnamon is very user friendly to Windows people.
Yeah.
Whereas Ubuntu is like completely different paradigm.
Right.
So there's, there's, there's reason why Mint is picked because instead of Ubuntu, not because
Ubuntu is bad.
I mean, the people who bash Ubuntu, I think are a little crazy, but when you have, um,
the, the, the paradigm of the usability such drastically different, there are some people
who would be turned off by that.
When you give them Cinnamon, they, they look at it like, oh, okay, it's kind of like Windows.
So that has a benefit there.
Yeah.
I don't know though.
I mean, look, we just heard Crash Benedict's anecdote about somebody wanting to switch
because of Gnome.
And this has never been a problem for the Mac since time of inception.
That is never, the Mac OS 10 has never gotten a single switcher because it looks like Windows.
And I don't know if that's a requirement.
I think it just has to work and make sense.
Also, you know, forgetting to the whole desktop thing is Unity is going to be having some
pretty big changes in 1310 and, uh, we're not talking to, but 1410 and so on and so
on, but it's going to be a little, in Gnome, pretty changes every other month.
Yeah.
And Cinnamon has consistently remained the same.
I mean, since its beginning.
Paradigm wise.
Yeah.
It has, it's, it's had a very casual evolution, so it keeps people feeling safe.
It just adds some user friendly settings into it and that's very good for new users.
You could argue that, that Unity has not changed that much usability though.
Right.
And Unity won't change that much in 14.04, it's an LTS, remember, five year support.
So you put your user on, yeah, and I'm saying you don't need to, you don't, you don't have
to upgrade.
There's no, there's no one with a gun to your head saying you have to upgrade.
You can just stay on 14.04.
And also that, that is precisely what Windows XP users would be looking for, right?
Because they've been using the same operating system for going on 13 years now.
Yeah.
And that's what they want to replace.
That's what they want to swap out.
And that's the paradigm they're familiar with.
That's what, that's how they think of it.
They just want their security updates and just keep on rolling.
And the only, the only place where I see where, where Mint has, has an argument is, is that
the, the desktops it provides offer a familiar user environment that a Windows switcher would
be comfortable with, whereas Ubuntu is, is different enough to require, require them
to think.
Well, the issue is like the XP users are typically people who have never thought of updating
and they don't, they just, they're afraid to update, they don't want to change anything.
So those people going to Ubuntu, that paradigm switch might be too much.
The only reason I would suggest like people from Windows, it would be Windows XP users
to Cinnamon would be very friendly to them.
But if you did, somebody who's just a regular user for, and who's like, who has a computer
that can handle it, they not necessarily care at all.
So Ick, you wanted to make a point that maybe just offering folks what they already have,
isn't that, that appealing?
I don't think so.
I think when people want to switch, they want to switch to something that might be a little
bit different than what they're used to.
I mean, you know, Windows is Windows, Mac is Mac, let's let Linux be Linux.
They want it, they want their hassle to feel like it was worth it.
Yes, they want, they, they're going to want it to not necessarily feel familiar, but to
get to know something that feels a little bit different so that they, you know, it doesn't
have to always be about familiarity.
I, my biggest pet peeve is when I see us trying to copy what Microsoft or Apple has already
done.
And, you know, we've need to brand our own brand.
We have too many brands to brand.
That's the problem.
But I think Crossroads has a good point in the sense that if you have, you're going to
have to, we're going to, we're going to be the people telling people to switch so we
could just give them an example of what they could look like.
And I think the best option to get people to switch would not be here's what you should
use and not even give them distros, just don't even mention the distros, just get like a
grid of, or here's like a slide show of here's what you could get, here's what GNOME looks
like, here's what Unity looks like and then just let's say which one do you like the best
and then focus on the distro after that.
Huh.
That's a great idea.
So is that me?
Go ahead, you said your sister switched because of Unity?
Yeah, actually, when I was actually first getting into Linux, I was running Ubuntu off
a USB stick and she saw it and she's like, oh, that looks awesome.
Can I have it?
And so I set her up with a dual boot.
She actually only uses Windows for Netflix, but and she uses it all the time.
She loves it.
Yeah.
I don't doubt it.
That's just funny to me.
So Matt, I want to ask you something.
This is a very general, reasonable conversation about different desktop options, about why
Cinnamon makes sense, about why Unity makes sense, why Ubuntu makes sense.
These are all very logical.
So why is it you still hear so many people recommending some off the wall distribution?
Like I mean, I don't mean to label Bodhi as off the wall, but you know, in the grand
scheme of like support when you're searching the Internet, you're not going to get a lot
of Bodhi results.
Why are we seeing this, Matt, when Ubuntu seems, or Mint maybe, seems like a pretty
practical choice?
Well, I think it depends on who's doing the recommendation.
There's usually two separate groups that do the recommendations for a distribution.
The Linux users themselves, which they either love or hate Ubuntu, there's not a lot in
between.
So you have that person with their vested interest.
The second group of people is generally the folks that are doing articles, speaking to
someone that writes articles.
If you're not writing about Ubuntu, you're not writing because no one's going to hire
you.
That's just reality.
I hate to be the one to break that to everyone, but welcome to reality, kids.
That's what people want.
It's open source and Ubuntu.
Yeah, it just seems so mono, it seems so monotone.
Now unless it's enterprise stuff, then you can use Ubuntu, but otherwise it's Ubuntu
or open source.
That shows you though, right?
That shows you what the interest of the reader is.
Yeah, it really is.
And that's, and quite frankly, that's what ranks.
I mean, that's what people are searching for.
And for why that is, is debatable, but the point is, is that's certainly what's going
on.
So I think you have those two groups of people that generally you have to work with.
It doesn't necessarily mean, that doesn't necessarily mean that those other distros
shouldn't be suggested.
I mean, if the computer is old enough, I mean, Ubuntu might not be a solution purely because
Unity needs a decent hardware.
I feel like the elephant in the room here and heaven's revenge is like thinking like
I don't read the chat room or something.
I think the elephant in the room here is it's SUSE, right?
I mean like where does open SUSE fit in?
Is it, is it something that is for the enthusiast?
Is it something that is for these new switchers?
They've got their evergreen release now.
I'm very surprised that there's been no open SUSE representation at all here at the moment.
That's all representing Ubuntu right now.
Well, except for the shirt I'm wearing.
Well, it's just as big or even bigger than Canonical in terms of corporate power.
They also have a one for the windows power use and their distro when it comes to major
release upgrades have never screwed up like a Ubuntu upgrade as for me.
Yeah.
And they have a good presence in enterprise and they have a lot of partnerships there.
So there's a lot of folks who would be using it in an IT setting.
They might want to use it on their desktop.
They could be a great windows candidate switcher.
Here's the reality.
And I've had a lot of open SUSE experience over the years and I have never not had at
least one major groundbreaking issue with every single solitary installation I've ever
had.
On their own software?
Always, always, always something breaks.
It just happens.
I mean, it happens for everybody.
I'm just saying from my own experience.
So when I'm going to then experience that and then recommend it to somebody, it's kind
of like, it's really pretty.
I like it.
I love what they do with a lot of their features and stuff, but at the end of the day, it's
an RPM distro.
I'm sorry.
I just can't.
I agree with you, Matt.
I agree.
Yeah.
The only issue I've ever had with is the DILD service failing every once in a while.
That's a different thing though.
I've had open SUSE break more often than Arch.
I don't know how it's that.
Seriously.
I mean, I'm willing to work at it, but my God, it's like, I remember just basic sound
issues.
I was finally like, screw this.
I'm done.
I've had a few things where open SUSE is great, but there are certain aspects that it's kind
of falls behind because they push a lot of interesting ideas and they're innovative.
Some of them are awesome.
The SUSE studio is awesome.
The DILD service is awesome.
Yeah.
DILD is awesome.
I like DILD.
I have no problem with that at all.
One of the things they have a lot of awesome ideas, but they have some fundamental issues
that they just don't address.
I've never been to an issue that I've never been able to solve, ever.
Well, you haven't been able to solve.
That's based on individual user experience.
That doesn't mean that everyone around you is also having that experience as well.
I think everybody's mileage is going to vary.
I definitely give you all the benefit of the doubt that you are as capable as I am.
That's very gentlemanly of you, sir.
But also, in KDE, you can simply right-click that menu and get a nice XP-looking menu.
It doesn't have to be the Lancelot paneling menu.
It can be XP-ish.
Yeah, sure.
Yeah.
Yeah, but it's still KDE, though.
KDE is a pretty big barrier if you don't know what you're doing.
I tried showing that to people, and they're just like, why the hell would I use that?
You know, whatever the hell they call that.
Oh, activities?
Activities, yeah.
It's like, it's a cool idea if you're really geeky.
It's awesome.
Yeah, but I've tried it.
Anyone else that's actually ever been outside?
It's not.
Some use it.
So I'm like, no.
I've seen people use workspaces when I just introduced them, and then they're like, oh,
that's awesome.
And they'll jump to it.
But I think it goes back to the whole, there's so many options and so many things that we
just have to say, here's what the easiest thing to do if we can't talk to them, and
that might be Ubuntu.
And then they even turned off workspaces by default, I'm pretty sure, unfortunately, before.
So there's certain things that if, like, Ubuntu might be just like, we should, if you can't,
you know, you can't help them out, you can't find out what it might fit them perfectly,
like a YouTube video, it could be Ubuntu.
That might be the best option, because you got the upgradability, you got the ease of
use.
You got the Google tools.
Well, Crossroads wants to disagree with you.
Crossroads, what do you think?
You think the software at opensusa.org and KD and Yast, specifically maybe Yast, do you
think that's the advantage for the Windows switcher?
Well, I mean, yeah, Yast is much like the Windows control panel.
And software.opensusa.org appeals to the Windows users being used to searching it on the web
and then being able to install it just like a.exe file.
Yeah, but I would argue that a lot of people would ignore the control panel completely,
like an average user would just never touch the control panel.
But I think what I've been trying to get to and what I've been trying to wrap my brain
around on this whole discussion is, I think, you know, Ubuntu has had a pretty bumpy road
in terms of PR and community perception.
And so my question was, as I'm looking at the 14.04 release, right, I'm looking at this
and I'm thinking, how relevant is Ubuntu's role today in the general Linux desktop and
those people coming to Linux?
And to me, what I'm hearing from you guys is that it is just as relevant today as it
was the day 12.04 was released.
If not more so.
Yeah.
I really, I really feel that way.
And even though I might personally...
I don't even use it on a daily basis.
Right, exactly.
Like even though I personally am really glad I'm on Arch today because I have GNOME 3.12
and that makes me a happy boy, I can't help but acknowledge the still significant role
that Ubuntu plays in its piece.
And maybe you could still argue that it's, for the desktop user, the most significant
role.
Probably.
I think another thing, like, I just went to the, I mean, I know this is just Reddit,
but I went to the Linux subreddit.
It's got a list of the most popular distributions in it and I opened the subreddits related
to each specific distribution.
I just grabbed some.
And if you look at the numbers, Debian has 7,000 readers, Fedora is 4,000, SUSE is 1,000,
elementary is 2,000, and Mint is 5,000.
And then Ubuntu is, sorry, yeah, sorry, Mint is 5,000, and then Ubuntu is 45,000.
And that, it definitely makes a big difference when you can go anywhere and you don't even
have to be in a Linux-related context.
Like you could be on some forum, like I was on HarlowCP the other day on their forum,
and somebody had said something about, oh, you know, I was trying to do this or that
or whatever in Linux and it didn't work.
And some other guy posted, oh, you should try apt-get, da-da-da-da, and that worked
for him because of the fact that they were both on Ubuntu.
Yeah.
They, I mean, of course it's not necessarily a good thing that people think Ubuntu is Linux,
as we know.
Right.
But the fact of the matter is that people do.
And so if they're on a completely different forum, a completely, you know, they can be
on a forum about CAS or something and mention they're on Linux, the other person who responds
to them is likely also going to be running Ubuntu.
And look at that.
And they might even assume that they're running Ubuntu.
Look at that, the top of the Ubuntu subreddit.
Windows XP refugees start here, right?
I mean, that's exactly the kind of landing pad I've been talking about.
I mean, the subreddit for Ubuntu actually has more users than Linux, doesn't it?
All the Linux subreddits.
I mean, like the Linux subreddit itself.
Yeah.
No, no.
45,000.
No, it has 100.
Yeah.
42.
No, the Linux one, the Linux subreddit is much more popular.
Ubuntu subreddit is actually pretty friendly.
I mean, even if they disagree with you, they're not all ripping on you.
Yeah.
I'm not too big a fan.
So I think what's interesting is, so our email area, and I agree, is does that make Ubuntu
the ultimate distro that shames all others?
No.
But it makes it a hell of a damn good choice for switchers.
And people just need to get over themselves, stop rooting for the underdog in all cases,
run the underdog yourself, let them run Ubuntu for a while, let them get used to the terms,
let them get used to the command line if they need to, let them get used to the ecosystem,
and then let them expand out.
It doesn't diminish the other distributions, it just means that perhaps those aren't the
best landing spots when they're switching.
And that's, I think that's what, does anybody disagree with that?
I would say that it's good, it's probably the best landing spot for someone you can't
help.
But if it's somebody who you can help, it might not be, because you can put them out
to, if there's an issue, they would come to you anyway.
And for example, like Bodhi, or Bodhi, I don't know, that would be a good distro for someone
who has a low resource hardware, because then they don't have to worry about the, you know.
The overhead of Unity.
Yeah, the overhead.
But that's the same thing with Lubuntu and stuff.
That have actual other desktops that are still Ubuntu-based anyway, if you put lbuntu on
it, it'll run.
Well Bodhi's Ubuntu-based.
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
Well technically, Bodhi's, I think it was like, there's like three different levels.
It was based on something else, which was also based on Ubuntu, so technically, yeah.
So what would be the advantage between that and Sail, like some of the other desktop options
for Ubuntu?
It's Enlightenment, I suppose?
I think it's just Enlightenment.
Yeah.
Enlightenment.
Okay, that's good.
Yeah, I mean it's fun.
Enlightenment runs pretty great on, that was the point of the article, was that Enlightenment
runs pretty good on lower-end hardware.
Which you're gonna have from an XP to a switcher.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
There's a lot of stuff in Enlightenment and LXDE and stuff like that, but I think Enlightenment
doesn't actually have an official flavor.
So Bodhi's the only one that I know of that is officially, like their main focus is Enlightenment.
See, I'm on board with Crossroads.
I think people get a new machine and they want to just love the hell out of it.
What do you think, Crossroads?
Is it the eye candy?
Is it the more advanced features?
What is it that's gonna make people switch?
Crossroads.
It's GNOME 3, KDE, GNOME 3, KDE, and Unity are pretty, and that's, at least for kids
my age, is what is going to drive them towards Linux.
When they see my computer, and I'm running GNOME 3 right now, they're like, whoa, that
looks so cool.
How can I do that?
How can you do that with your computer?
It's things like, I mean, XFCE is great and it's customizable and I love it, but it's
not what's going to push people to Linux.
Yeah.
Yeah, and then of course, it's like the point you've been making is that for different folks,
some people will want the slower stuff or the more resource-friendly.
Okay, I want to put this topic to bed.
I feel like we've kind of reached a consensus, and I feel like I've kind of reached a good
understanding.
We don't have a lot of time left in the show, so I'm just going to point people over to
the show notes.
It's just, and it's probably good because I've probably talked about it too much recently,
but you know, this Heartbleed vulnerability has just been getting so much coverage, and
it seems like the coverage is now sort of pivoted from discussing the technical details
and how disastrous it is to playing a little bit of the blame game, and you're seeing a
lot of articles crop up on the web right now.
Articles that kind of cast open source and the open source development model in a bad
light.
We talked a little bit about some of that on Sunday.
Like here's one on ZDNet from Larry Seltzer, he says, open source does not provide any
meaningful inherent security benefit for OpenSSL, and it may actually discourage some important
testing techniques.
So panhandling is not a good business model for important software like OpenSSL.
And of course he's framing it in a very adversarial way, and he's painting it in the most light
possible, and you're seeing a lot of these crop up.
I've got a collection of them in the show notes, and I wanted to say, I guess what my
point was in all of this, and I won't lean on this too much because I know we've talked
about this before, but I think people need to focus on with this whole Heartbleed thing
is that while maybe open source is getting dragged through the mud on this, we should
maybe be focusing on the whole turnaround for the patch time, like how rapidly the response
was, and the fact that we now have the ability to audit for these kinds of things in the
future.
And maybe they'll pop up, maybe they won't, right?
But now we can look.
Well, I got two words for everyone, especially the guy that wrote that article, it's called
Blaster Worm, and it's called DMVs, hospitals, police stations, pretty much any civic entity.
It was like literally the apocalypse when it happened.
A month later, everybody was fine, Microsoft's great, we love Microsoft.
So if these same idiots that are writing this crap can forgive a company that allowed something
that, and keep in mind, when that happened, the patch was available.
That's how pathetic this was.
So things happen, but I think blaming licensing over it is just silly, I really do.
Yeah, and I'll run, we'll leave it at this, because I've got to go do some work on the
studio.
So we can't talk about it too much, and I've probably over-talked it anyways, it's stayed,
it's welcome, but if you would like to read some of those articles, and think about it
yourself, I'll have links in the show notes.
Look, we'd love to hear from you, this show, a huge portion of the show runs on your feedback
and your involvement, and if you can't join us live over at jblive.tv Tuesdays on a 2
PM Pacific, and we also would love to hear from you if you can't join us live, just go
over to the Jupiter Broadcasting page, click the contact link, choose Linux Unplugged from
the drop-down, and send in your email, and also visit us, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Matt, get your Ubuntu 14.04 ready, our review on Sunday, I'll see you then.
Sounds good, see you then.
Alright everyone, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged, see
you right back here, next Tuesday!