So Wimpy, you were talking about video games.
My friend, if you're going to get into games, guess what?
New Humble Bundle 12 is out, and they are finally, once again, rocking the Linux support.
And there's some good ones on here.
There is Gone Home, good game, Luftharossers?
How do you say that, Eric?
What do you think?
Luftharossers.
Let's take a little look at this one.
Let's see what this is about.
Because I think this is mild fantasy violence.
Alright.
Oh, that was a fun game, actually, yeah, I got really into that for a while.
Luftharossers?
Yeah, if it's what I think it is, it's a side-scrolling, uh...
Oh, this actually looks like a lot of fun.
Yeah, it's a super game.
Okay.
It's short, though.
It's actually a little short.
Ah, that's actually not a bad thing for me.
Is it like the airplane flying around in there?
Yeah.
That's not bad.
Okay, so then you've also got Hammerwatch.
Let's take a look at it and see what...
Oh, this is a really good game.
You've got SteamWorld.
Dig that.
I've heard a lot about this.
I actually have that one.
Oh, yeah.
Papers, Please is also...
Here, watch this one.
This Papers, Please is a great game.
Papers, Please.
It's like the whole game right there, too.
Well, that's sad.
Mm-hmm.
Isn't that interesting?
Denied.
What's funny about this is I have worked in a U.S. Customs facility in SeaTac Airport,
and I got to work in a U.S. Customs facility.
Oh, I see.
So you've worked in a U.S. Customs facility?
Yes, I've worked in a U.S. Customs facility.
Oh, okay.
I see.
So, yeah, that's a good game.
Yeah, it's pretty good.
Yeah, I can see that.
I can definitely see that.
All right, so we've got...
This is pretty good.
All right, so should we check in to see how the funding is doing?
You know I always like to look at this, right?
I always got to see how we're doing.
Oh, all right, we got to watch the video.
Come on.
They've always got the crazy voiceover guy.
Watch here we go windows mac and linux drm free and with steam keys for one low price
Introducing humble indie bundle 12. Okay, let's pay what you want
drm free cross platform and helps charity
Pay any price and get gunpoint
Making its Mac and Linux debut. That's always cool. Yeah, go according to your stealth plan the guns won't ever have to come out
Ha ha cool
Hammer watch leaving dungeons unexplored not on my hammer watch
And steam world dig I ain't saying he a steam world digger
Do you think in addition to steam world dig there might also be a steam world reddit?
And also get loose trousers come fly the unfriendly skies
Papers, please
Hey, what's the big idea here? I always remember to bring papers. Looks like a short drama called lady and the stamp
Should I rummage through these private doc? Have you played this? Well, you know what they say when in home
Pay ten dollars or more and get prison art. Oh, look how he did that prison is what you make of it in this game
That features architecture with conviction not adding it to your bundle would be a crime
As a special bonus everyone who purchases this bundle for sixty five dollars or more will also whoa
Even exclusive merch that's new right to you by fan game floppy disk
Plus a customizable portion of each contribution will go towards the child's play charity and the electronic frontier foundation
This promotion only lasts two weeks
So be sure to tell your friends like this video on YouTube Facebook share it tweet about it and gobble up all our Google
Marbles like a hungry hungry
What?
Have they ever done the swag thing before so, let's see. Okay now let's take a look
I look at this the top donator right now is
Is a bitly URL, you know for 200 bucks. That's not a bad ad spot that that'd be actually that's worth $200
Oh, yeah
If you put a URL in there like that
So, okay. Here we go. We average Windows price
$7.21
average Macintosh price
$8.84 average Linux price
$9.69
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's not yet chained down by the wrist proprietary hardware. My name is Chris
My name is Matt. Hey Matt, guess what 57 episodes in a row, buddy
Big five seven already. I know now we're like ketchup. You know what? That's cool
It's cool to be like ketchup Matt and you know to help us celebrate being tasty like ketchup in studio producer Eric
Hey, Eric. Hey Chris. How you doing? Good. Are you feeling like Heinz 57 today? A little ketchup a little bit great
Yeah, yeah
You and I are on a marathon broadcast in marathon broadcast mode still because we did that Apple thing this morning
Yeah, that'll be in tech talk today. It's probably gonna be out probably posted while we're recording. Yeah
It was like a two-hour show. It was a big show. Yeah, it was a big show like encoding nightmare. Yeah
Yeah, it takes extra processes. You gotta have more i7. We need more all of the i7
Well coming up in today's episode of the unplugged show. We got a lot of ground to cover
We have a little make good from last week. We didn't get a chance to talk about DNF
We're gonna do that in the latter half of the show
We also have I know you're gonna think it's crazy. You're gonna think I'm nuts
we got to talk about system D just a little bit more because I
Think I figured out where all the controversies coming from. Yeah, I think I've isolated it down
I think we can finally put this topic to bed once we just get it out there in the open
Who's stirring up trouble? Why are they're stirring it up? I think I got the answer for you
We're gonna talk about in today's unplugged call them out put it on the record
So that way we as a public can move on from all of this shenanigans
So we're gonna talk about that in the show and then our mobile room joins us to talk about open media vault today
I think we're supposed to at least we'll see how that goes
I did they've been doing a little open media vault review and
They've been preparing to come on and talk about their experiences with open media vault
So mama room time appropriate greetings to you guys. Welcome to the unplugged show today. Oh
Whiskey, yes
Wimpy are you ready to talk about open media vault today? Are you excited? Oh, yeah
Someone hold that man down free now is everybody review over free now
I'm not exactly the right person be asking because he gets overly excited about nothing. That's true
I didn't want to give away my true feelings
Well, let's see, let's start with our first email see if we can get to the true feelings behind talks
Travis wrote in to Linux unplugged says hey guys
I saw a water article on a little piece of a little project called you talks and I found it to be an interesting concept any
Plans for highlighting it during an upcoming show that you guys are probably familiar with talks
It aims to be a Skype replacement that's secure encrypted and it's more like a protocol where a front-end could be written for it
And no, you were just saying a little earlier you were experimenting with talks. What was your takeaway?
Yeah, so me and actually a couple other people in the mumble room
Tried to got talks installed and started using it and I want to say first I think it's a fantastic
I think it's it's the potential for the project is fantastic
And I think it's a fantastic idea and I think it's going fantastic directions
However, it's very much not ready for daily use at least not from my experience
We were able to establish a call. We were able to have a conversation and that worked really well
Unfortunately to get that call
I had to have my client already open and waiting for the the the thing to pop up because the notification didn't work
That was a gnome. I couldn't even get it installed. It wouldn't even install on 1404
What like I said once it got connected we were able to have a conversation and that worked for about five or six minutes and
Then the entire client would crash
In the middle of a call
Yeah, right in the middle of a call
group group
Conversate like like we're more than one person was connected. Yeah. Oh, yeah work at all group chat worked. Okay
But the like single one person to one person chat also would crash after like five or six minutes of use. Yeah
So you're saying it sucked. Well, I'm here's what I'm saying
I'm saying that you know
It's it's one of those things where when I'm sure once they get once everything reaches stable and it gets and it gets released
Yeah, it will be a fantastic project. It just it's clearly not where you know, for example Skype is today, of course
Yeah, it shouldn't be because how much longer right and how much more money you might have to develop sky. Yeah
Yeah, it's early days doing it a little bit wrong here talks is more of a client
No a server and a protocol you're judging the client one of many fair enough. Yeah
Although his experience sort of echoes experience with the other talks clients
I think just I think there's a I think the underlying aspect of it's still moving and I think of course the top you eyes
You're right. It's more like it's more like HTTP in a sense
It's you can have multiple web browsers that can browse the web. You're gonna have multiple talks front ends, but that might yes
I'm not I'm not
This maybe is going to be a data point to this to this potential
But I I think maybe what we're seeing here is this is the wrong approach for this type of product and service
I think you need to have a client that is
Integrated at the same time with the back end like it the two things shouldn't be developed in a vacuum. I don't I don't think
This seems like you have to have if you when you put when you build a feature into something that the back end can support
The client needs that and you have to build it, you know
Then see how the client responds to that and adjust the back end to how do you how can these two separate things be?
Fully feature compatible. How will they ever sync up in terms of what the back end can do versus what front ends can do?
And etc. It seems well, you're absolutely right in order to have the back end work
You have to have a front end that works with the back end and if the two do not work together then what's the point?
What do you think dare Devlin? So they are actually from what I understood and I tried all the clients listed on the page
Toxic is the client that is been worked and doing that kind of iteration that you're talking
That's the one I like the most and that one never failed in doing any of the tasks that it already says it does
So it only doesn't do audio yet
However, it does already the other things ready really well
And I think it's on progress because they are trying to refine it step by step
Other clients are focusing on the experimental
Experimental API that it's available for the toxic library
Well, it's a to the actual protocol and I think it is actually right approach if we want these
produce
Protocol to propagate like there's already people working on that. I have knowledge of that are working on a WebRTC
Proxy that we talks so you can use your browser to communicate with a tax client, which is amazing
WebRTC already works fine. So why does it need to be integrated with talks?
So you don't have to use two apps. So
Your browser and people can use their own desktop application or phone application, which works
we've also I featured a couple of QT based talks cool clients, but
There seem to be the one that actually performs best under most circumstances and tests. Yeah
In my experience, it's just to me so far away from a hangouts or Skype replacement right? Yeah
It's just it is not production ready and there are people who they're people who start Google Hangouts
And then leave them running all day long at their workplace
It's got a long way to go before it's ever gonna hit that level
But maybe for for enthusiasts enthusiasts that are just kind of messing around with friends and stuff like that
It's probably getting close to that. Oh, yeah. Yeah, absolutely and toxic
I do have to say I didn't experiment any kind of crash at all
Maybe because I built all the clients on my distribution set up actually
Mmm, that's good theory. Yeah. Yeah, I like that. Let's do a follow-up from Sven
He wrote in on the Linux action show on Sunday about setting up his home server
And my main concern was he had he was using like three different distros in his house and he was using CentOS
But he was kind of a Linux noob and I was a little worried that he might be spreading himself too thin
So Sven writes in with some follow-up. He says hey guys. Thanks for reading my question
I thought I'd get back to you on the questions you raised so regarding the server OS my reasons for choosing CentOS over core
OS or openSUSE is primarily academic
I researched core OS extensively and would have opted for it
But was what got me using CentOS was that I am from time to time called upon to manage Linux servers or a few at work
Which is really stressful when you suck at it since all of our Linux servers and firewalls run CentOS
I decided it was in my best interest to become more versed in that OS once I'm comfortable with CentOS
I'll probably move to core. Yay, Docker. That's a great reason. Yeah, that is great. It's an excellent reason
Yep, so on the topic of using three different distros at home and my concern there was like well if you're gonna use CentOS
Maybe you should just use CentOS though. You just learn one thing
And so he says you're probably right and I feel the same about keeping things simple
But I think for the time being that my wife will need to acclimate to Linux in general
I need a distro that was both easy to use and visually attractive and elementary OS
Represented the least dissonant experience for her as a first-time Linux user
My long-term goal is to empower her to choose her own distro. Yes
And even command-line if she wants and while it would be nice to see her on openSUSE
I want her to learn a distro that she considers home
And then he says that way I can claim ignorance and won't have to answer questions
Regarding backups. So he says my current backup strategy is rudimentary at best since things are still in development
I'm using a series of Python scripts adapted from my old Windows server
They package things into btsync folders from there
It gets uploaded to spider oak and needs something simple that worked right away
So I haven't really given back as much attention. They deserve it this time any thoughts. That's not bad
What do you do for backup Eric? Oh, well
What I do is I use just Deja-dupe and I back up to a SSH server on my home server
Deja-dupe is a great way to go
Oh, yeah, and in this case you could back up to the folder that spider oak is backing up
I like I really like spider oak as my backup system. Yeah, that's a good one it you know, I
I have very little experience with spider oak to be honest. Yeah. Yeah now what you playing with anything back up wise these days
Well, I used to use spider oak, but it just it's so bloaty. It is slow
Yeah, I mean for me it's like it's really bloody so I've been kind of bouncing back and forth
I'm at one time. I used to use jungle disk one time. I used to use spider oak
I think right now I'm pretty much married to kind of going with a bit torrent sync
To a specific box in the house and spread all over the place
Yeah, yeah until I figure out something a little more permanent
I'm kind of in between right now part of my backup strategy is the fact that I got copies of stuff everywhere
Yeah, that is I mean, it's not a great backup strategy, but it is part of it saved my bacon the other day
I actually accidentally
Deleted my music folder what? Yeah, I actually thank God though. I had a bit torrent sync over to my tablet
So did you catch it before it synced the the delete? I sure did. Oh my gosh
Are you hustling like a fool over here?
Here's the funny part is that bit torrent sync what hadn't been running for some reason?
So I went ahead and just grab the SD card out of my tablet in my computer
Just dropped them all back create this create a new sync
Yeah, she's Louise. I totally looked I like daredevil ins approach recess. I just swap out hard drives. Yeah, that's a way to go
Yeah, that's another way to go
Oh, yeah, it's simple it works for me. I just have
Video another for music and
Yeah, you know, I always want something automatic yeah, I want something automatic so that's why
Bit torrents he keeps my constant scene going on
Yeah
But then deja dupe does my once a week backup because you have the bit torrent sync isn't really a backup because it could have
Synced the delete action. That's right. It could have synced the delay got lucky. I got real lucky. Yeah
I got well, there's two things that bit torrent sync has going for you in your favor one
There's unless you actually manually set it differently
There is a delay a fairly significant one
And the second thing is the fact that unless you decide to turn off it turn this off in your folder preferences
It will actually keep a archive. Yeah, you get the revision. Yeah, that's true. Oh, you get the revision
That's no isn't that what that is? Isn't that what it's like? Oh, it's like a revision copy. You can
Never explored it. I was just like it is in bit torrents. It's gonna just completely it does
Now the where I lucked out and is that it wasn't running on my tablet, right?
So it wasn't running on my tablet. Yeah, right then. Yeah, it was running on my computer, but was not running on my tablet
So I was able to just copy. Yeah, I've always so the here's how I use bit torrent sync
Yeah, is I have obviously I have to have machines that have write access
But the majority of my scenes are using the read-only key. Yeah, so that way I so I've never I never delete on the remote
End really almost ever. Well, I have no reason to either because I mean, it's basically I'm just playing back to me
It's like I'm not. Yeah, exactly for me
It's like clips and stuff
Yeah
And that like I don't ever need to delete and then when I do need to delete them
I'm usually sitting at my desk doing like show prep and where I clean things up anyways, and then I have yeah
Go to that machine. Yeah. Yeah, it's kind of just I just do that as a little security thing. Yeah
Um anybody in the mumble room want to chime in on a backup solution?
They're particularly proud of before we move to our next topic. I'm still a big fan of our sink and
I try I try to ob-nam recently
An attic and I found they were slow and pretty inefficient. Although, you know the dedupe
Functionality and ob-nam was pretty good, but it took forever. It was really slow. Mm-hmm. Gooky sprite
That's exactly what I'm doing as well. Yeah. Yeah, and you know our sake actually saved my bacon
Oh our things amazing tool and there's a lot of pre-made scripts
You can kind of take and then adjust to work the way you need if you don't want to write it from scratch
And just cron tab and then you never have to worry about it
Yeah, and the other thing is and the thing that's important to me is I understand every single thing that's happening
Was that with BT sink? I'm just I install the software and I just kind of have to hope that it's working magic
We can see that. Yeah. Yeah
The thing I like about our sink too is you can do the dry run so you can kind of just write get an idea of
What's gonna happen? So is this gonna be a huge massive file transfer?
Is this gonna be a quick thing? And of course it also all my files gonna get deleted. Yeah
And the other thing is you can throw it was sometimes these systems like you'll lose that you'll lose the right date or time or
Last modified and and our sinks really good about this guy an interesting solution. Yeah, go ahead with me
well, like like most of you I'm using our
Bit sync to move my data around the place. So all my various workstations and what have you but for backups
I use our snapshot which gives you a point on time recovery. Yes our snaps
The same it's just got I in my opinion just a little prettier
Yeah, our snap that I think we've mentioned on the show before but I think it's been a long time since we gave it a plug
Yeah, so I use our snapshot on open media fault. Oh
We might get into that in a little bit. Yeah, I'll explain how I do that a bit later if you like
Yeah, that's a good tease. I like that. All right, that's an our sink front end. I believe right it is. Yes. It's on top of it
Yeah, okay. Got it. Okay, cool. Okay, so we've got we got a follow-up on a couple of other things
We need to get to another email
I want to and a Chrome extension that will actually make YouTube suck less
You're not gonna believe this Chrome extension and what it can do. It's incredible
And so before we get to that I want to stop and I want to thank our next sponsor on the unplugged show and that
Is the awesome folks over at team go to linux.ting.com linux.ting.com
Linux dot ting.com right now won't you go there because you'll get $25 off your first device if you've already got a ting device
Well, then they'll give you a $25 credit towards your account and ting is super awesome
In fact Kyra is in studio today to tell us about how ting rates work. Ting keeps rates simple
We don't make you pick a plan instead. You just use your phone as you normally would how much you use
Determines how much you pay each month. You can have as many devices as you want on one account
That's good
Because when you use more you pay less per minute message or megabyte of data
Your usage plus six dollars per active device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill
Simple that's what we mean when we say
Mobile that makes sense
You go to linux.ting.com to get started they got a lot of different devices here and feature phones
Ranging from well under $100 like 60 bucks here all the way up to the latest like the Nexus 5 the
All of the latest galaxy lines the iPhone lines. They got it all over there at linux.ting.com. Yeah, you do
Hey, you know what speaking of which if you want you can play a little bit with my L
You want to play with my L?
Yeah, check out how long it's been running on battery you tell the folks how long to you you go if you can find it
Okay, and see if you can tell the folks when you go over to linux.ting.com
To you'll see their savings calculator you go in there you plug in your current usage of what you pay on your current cell phone
Bill and see how much you'd save with ting since ting's only charging you for what you actually use that gives you a ton of
Flexibility and if you're savvy and you know when to make a Wi-Fi call and things like that you would be
Astounded at the savings. I now have three phones on my ting account
And I'm still paying a hundred dollars less a month than I was for one line on my previous provider
It's kind of amazing and what's cool about ting is they're great with however you want to use them if you want to use them
Extensively as as a phone you can if you want to use it mostly as a wireless ISP you can and they have no whole
Customer service if you ever get stuck you call me one eight five five ting FDW and a real person answers the phone
Linux dot ting.com all right, so what's the battery life on that Android L phone there battery life
You've got four days left at 44% and does it say how long it's been running on battery
I couldn't we go up on the go up on the chart if you're on the chart there
I'll give you the date. I think it's instant
Says the fifth yeah the fifth yeah, so I haven't plugged it in so fair. That's impressive. Yeah
Long yeah, you know what it is. There's two things so it's Android L
That's the first thing second thing is I don't make a lot of calls right so there's three things and the third thing
This is the biggest I believe is that I don't have it signed into my Google account
Oh, so how many days has that been on battery that Nexus 5 well?
Let's see since the fifth and today is the nine eight there you go
And it's got how many days left it's got
Four days now you said yeah
Unbelievable, and I seriously think is because I don't log into my Google account, and it's on Android L
Otherwise it's just a standard Nexus 5 and what's crazy you put sailfish on this and you're or
Ubuntu touch and you blow through it in like two hours. Oh, yeah, yeah
So there's a lot this was so awesome about ting is you're I'm rocking the Nexus 5 I own this outright
I only pay for my usage and I can put my OS on there and it's sailfish Ubuntu touch Firefox
It just jumps on the ting network and work. Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah, it's awesome Linux dot ting comm
Go help change up the mobile industry by switching to ting
make the rest of the industry take note of what ting is trying to do by voting with your wallet Linux dot ting comm and
Maybe grab yourself a Nexus 5 and then try out the L beta. I'm kind of impressed. Yeah, I just seeing that
I'm impressed too. Yeah, I mean you got a Nexus 5. How long is your battery last right now? Let's see
I also synced to Google. So yeah. Yeah, that's a huge thing. Ah, just
See, I'm thinking I'm thinking I'll have to sign it up with my Google account then see I'm on KitKat and I have 79%
Remaining I charged it just this morning
I've got four hours 46 minutes and seven seconds on
Well, wow, and he's got four days. Yeah
Yeah, that is huge right it's astonishing that's a huge set enough to drag you back to Android then
Maybe we'll see. Oh, I
Battery life is like the killer feature as far as I'm concerned good news. Good news. Look at this
Oh, look at this our Apple videos or our keynote videos already been pulled off off of YouTube
There we go, that was the that was the moment right there right when they're showing the ladies boobs
Right when they're showing the ladies boobs, they're they're pulled down our tech talk today episode a bunch of jerks
Seriously seriously, this has been a bad week. I have one two three marks just from this week
How do you put up with it? I sometimes I just don't even pay attention. I just
All right, the appeals process is easy, right? I mean no
It's it's fruitless is what it is
And in fact, you can even put your account in jeopardy if you try to dispute something that turns out to be legitimate
Then your account can actually
So Elroy wrote in with our next email to help us all cope with YouTube a little more
and I
Think I think maybe all of you will want to go grab this
So Elroy writes and he says I've just become aware of the most important
Fantabulous extension for Chrome that's ever graced the face of this earth
It's called herp derp for YouTube which significantly improves YouTube comments by replacing them with random herps and derps
I'm certain in some way that Matt must have been involved with this great piece of work. It seems inspired one user
Explains it thusly in the beginning God created the Internet's and the Internet's were without form and filled with chaos
Trolls and idiots spread upon the face of the deep discord with their fire and rage as their fuel
thusly the tanner son of ganner and son of Goden who fought during the legendary battle not known as the flames of boxy and
His bacon of hope shined upon the wretched world and tanner said let there be derp and there was herp derp and
Tanner saw the derp and the derp was good
No comment even remark was no comment even remotely remarkable was ever missed since that fateful day
You can find in the Google Play Store. He included a shortened URL. He says please spread the word of this great extension
So there you go herp derp for YouTube. I love it not exactly Linux related, but I think Linux users can
Can probably all say we've suffered a little bit from YouTube comments, so I've already installed in a micro. Yeah, there you go
See I like the before and then the derped so they have the poor than the dirt
Here's the first review yeah, you sir are a genius second review. Oh, thank God third review. This is fabulous
Couple of youtubers would love this actually
That's great. Matt are sorry Martin writes. Oh my god. How did I live without this extension honor rights? Goodbye to dumb bitches on YouTube?
Exactly, that's it right there
Did you already install it? This is awesome. Yeah, this is great
Bubba says herp herp herp derp derp derp derp
And wow that's awesome
So there you go
I said I can actually read this stuff. Yeah, I figured to make it much more palatable
So even though they're pulling down my videos at least I'll have a good time when I go there to read it
So that I thought that if you click and if you click on each comment it becomes English again
So if you want to read it you still can
So that's awesome because now I don't care what anyone says this is great
Rekai points out Rekai points out that you could you could pair this sort of like a good wine and cheese
You could pair this with the well-known cloud to butt extension that turns all references of cloud into the word
But have you guys seen this?
Oh that's genius
Because you know actually it bit me the other week because we did my cloud exposed
And then somebody sent in a screenshot with the cloud to butt extension where it said my butt exposed
Tech talk today episode 51
So there's a negative side to it as a content creator
It could be a little awkward
That's just brilliant
But you match up the herp derp for YouTube and the my butt extension and your browser is a much better place I think
Who needs net neutrality right?
Yeah, yeah
Okay, we got our last email that came in from a EB
He says proud Papa my 10 and 13 year old boys took to a Chromebook guy gave them
I hit up Google and put the thing in a developer mode installed crouton and got Ubuntu installed and they did it all by themselves
As a parent I feel like my work on this world is now done EB
Good dad
Right
Good game
Yeah, that was good
I have the C720 sitting right there
I'm gonna that's gonna becomes Dylan's school computer same thing
I'm not even I don't even think I'm gonna I think I'm gonna leave
My thought is I'll leave the Chrome OS installed for dad
So like if I just need to grab his machine and look something up I'll have Chrome OS
And then when he needs to use it I'll have it in elementary OS
Yep
I don't know about elementary OS though
Oh yeah
Am I making a mistake?
Ubuntu, sugar on a stick
Arch?
I love both
He's looking at what it does not what it runs
So I think
Yeah, I know he is
But I'm thinking I'm thinking but I would rather have my son run Arch
Yeah, well
Nice
Yeah, that's all
That's the dream you can only hope for
And here come all the Arch fanboys again
Right
So anyways congrats to EB
And you know that was one of the things that we did that we did this episode on Sunday about the Chromebook
It's kind of ridiculous
Yeah
It is a phenomenon
And one of the other common comments we got is yeah Chromebook is great
I can't wait till those $200 Windows laptops come out like we've talked about before too
Yeah
It's great for Linux
It's funny though because at first it took me a while to sort of recognize it
At first I thought the Chromebook was kind of a threat
Yeah
And the Chrome boxes
But now that you can replace the freaking BIOS entirely
When you pull off that Chrome OS BIOS
And you put on a custom flashed version of
Because it's just an open source
That's right
It is a full fledged laptop at that point
And you can always flash the Chrome OS BIOS
Yes, I did actually
Yeah
I did it as a
Go ahead
I've been super happy with my C720 for like I don't know six months running Ubuntu
I keep it as a backup in my backpack next to my Ultra Pro which runs Arch
And then when battery life drains
Because the battery life is insane on the Chromebook
Yeah
Wimpy you were going to make a comment about compatibility
Well yeah the thing is that because the Chromebooks are running Linux
In the main they're extremely Linux compatible
Totally
More so than some of the you know mainstream PCs
That are preloaded with Windows might be
Right, right
Well and plus also because you can put CBIOS on there
And then you can have an open source BIOS
I mean it really is
Yeah
Yeah I wonder if
Yeah I mean Stallman should be happy
Yeah I wonder if these things are getting close to being Stallman approved
I'm sure there must be like stuff for the Wi-Fi or something that's still
Probably negative in the freedom dimension
Yeah in his opinion if anything does allow something that is negative in the freedom dimension
It's
And the value of this is negative
Exactly
Yeah that's true, that's true
Alright well let's take a break before we get into our first major topic of the day
I want to talk about Linux Academy
Go to linuxacademy.com
Right now go check them out linuxacademy.com
And if you go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
You can still take advantage of the Summer of Learning 33% discount
I don't know if you can still technically, is it still in the summer?
Can we still call it that?
I hope so
Yeah it's summer like
Okay alright I wanted to make sure it was still summer like
Because I don't want you guys not to get the Summer of Learning discount
It is too darn important
There are few things in life that are as important as your education
As your mind as Ben Folds 5 would tell us
Think about your mind
Sitting there floating in space
Go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
They've got step by step video courses
Downloadable comprehensive study guides
And you'll love this
If you're in somewhere in the course material
You're getting your learning on like a fool
You're just sucking it up like a sponge
Getting all kinds of smart over at Linux Academy
And you get to a point and guess what
In the course material you need to build a server
Well this is what really sucks about Linux Academy
You've got to stop what you're doing
You've got to go build a server
Take a couple of days
You've got to get the OS
You've got to order the parts
You've got to get a monitor and a keyboard and a mouse
You've got to install your
Not with them
No oh wait that's right
You don't have to do any of that
Because they spin up a server for you from the fly
Right as you need it boom as the courseware requires
That the server is spun up on the back end
That's part of the server
Doesn't matter if it's AWS
Doesn't matter if it's a Linux box
Doesn't matter you guys
They have all of it there
Because they are a bunch of Linux experts
And educational enthusiasts
Who've built this system for you
Because it's from the community for the community
They're all about it
They recognize the issues that exist
With all of the educational platforms out there
The shortcomings
The problems that they have
Trying to reach out to Linux enthusiasts
And they've solved a lot of that
Almost all of it
Because the only thing that's remaining is the content
And they are working at an unbelievable pace
So many courses are over there right now
It could take you years to work through all of it
And they're not done
They're adding more stuff every single week
I just had a little chat with one of the guys
That runs Linux Academy
And I got just a hint of what's coming
It's gonna put them
It's gonna set them so far ahead
Of anyone else in the industry
For the next several years
I mean it has never been a better time
To go over to Linux Academy
And just double down on yourself
You can take the step-by-step courseware offline with you too
So that way you can educate yourself when you're in the car
If you're in the shower like Scooby Sprite
You can listen in the shower while you listen to Linux Academy
You know these kinds
It's flexible
They also give you the tool set you need
So that way you can attack it in a way that
Is actually manageable
That doesn't like induce anxiety
Because for me one of the problems is
I start to get these things that weigh over me
And then it bothers me that I'm not getting it done
I start to feel like I'm
You know not accomplishing everything I want
I start to feel kind of bad about that
Linux Academy gives me the tool set
Where I can attack things as I have the time
Where I can really easily conceptualize
How long something's gonna take
What's gonna be involved in that process
And what it's gonna require for me to commit to do it
And that gives me the opportunity to succeed
Which just keeps me going
It keeps me going back for more and more all the time
And if I ever kind of have a lull
They have a really great community support system there that helps me out
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged
Go check them out
Get the Summer of Learning discount
And you'll see all the new content they have
I have a list right here I could read off to you
It's really amazing
And I think you're gonna be impressed
And I'll tell you if you go there right now
There's so much stuff
There's so much stuff you can start with
It's never been a better time
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged
Save 33% and start learning right now
And they have a Nagios tutorial now up there
Which is pretty cool
It's like a five part thing
Which was a big deal for me
When I signed up with them forever ago
I was like, give me Nagios, give me Nagios
Because I've never done it
I've never set up Nagios
And they have the whole thing up there now
We were talking about backups
They have a whole thing on backing up with rsync
So you can go take that course
Oh really?
Yeah, yeah
So that's another good example
Or if you want to set up NFS
If you've been wanting to do NFS file sharing
You're ready to get off Samba
Because you're just talking Linux to Linux
And you want to take advantage of the speed of NFS
They've got a whole course on NFS
And the thing is when you walk away from that course
You will have implemented an NFS server
So it's a one to one translatable skill set
And it's great for stuff that you maybe have done
Once or twice for work
Like four years ago or whatever
And now you need to remember how to do it
For your home or whatever
That's what I use it for
Yep, yep
And let's be honest too
A lot of us are self taught
And there's just little areas that I have found
That even when I go back and take the most basic stuff
Like I did Linux
I think it's called Linux A Plus
I can't even remember anymore
Is that even a thing, Linux A Plus?
It was a really basic rudimentary course
I took years ago
I think it was Linux Plus I think
Oh yeah, Linux Plus
Yeah, thank you
Linux Plus, yeah
It's been a while
I actually found it
You know what?
It showed me a couple different ways
I could consider doing things
I actually kind of like
It picked my game up a little bit
Even though it was a really intro course
This was a long time ago
But I find it to be
And that is true across the whole board too
A Plus is one of those certifications
Where you can use a mouse and keyboard
Uh huh, uh huh
That's very true
That is very true
I want to talk a little bit about SystemD
And then we'll do our Open Media Vault review
Okay, so let's do the SystemD thing first
Because I think this might be a little quicker
We've been following SystemD since the beginning
And we now are in a phase
Where a lot of adoption has occurred
But there's just an immense amount of pushback
And I've been trying to get a sense of
Where is legitimate complaints?
Where do those follow?
And then what is just like clicker baiting
To get traffic to drive clicks for your ads?
So I've been sort of doing some digging
And trying to get my head around all of this
And I don't know if you guys have noticed this
But I certainly have noticed that
The vast majority of anti-SystemD articles
Are coming from two places
And they're coming at an unbelievable fever pitch rate
And it makes it seem like
It's just people after people after people
Talking about this
When in reality, I see two people talking about this
And then the rest of the internet shitting their pants
Every time they talk about it
And then of course it drives traffic
And gets everybody talking about it
Let's start with my favorite, Paul Valencia
Over at InfoWorld.com
Paul Valencia recently wrote
You have Windows in my Linux
He says the schism over SystemD
Could lead to a separation of desktop and server distros
Or a mass exodus of Linux server admins
Leaving to FreeBSD
Okay, that's just one of his many
And what's great is you can go look at Paul Valencia's post
And you can just read through his anti-SystemD crap
Then another, okay so that's InfoWorld.com
Then number two, number two
IT World, Jim Lynch
Oh yeah
This is the other guy
And in fact, these two guys
Cite each other as examples
To support their arguments
So here was, this one got a ton of traction
Over the weekend when I was prepping for last
Funny how the story didn't make it into the Linux action show
So here's the headline
SystemD rampages through the Linux community
Like Godzilla through Tokyo
Oh my god
And I've got a good little collection
In the show notes of their more recent stuff
And I just went back two weeks
I just went back two weeks
Here's another headline
It's time to split Linux in two
Here's another one
These are just the same guys
Over and over again
Writing these kinds of stuff
And here's another story
All in their thread
All their timeline
Here's another one where he suggested
Here's the other thing I love
This is so great
When they also
When Paul self-references his own previous articles
To support his new article
I love that one
That's a fallacy right there
This thing I wrote a while ago
In this case last week
Still totes legit
So let's just reference that
My insane hyperbolic screed from last week
You know, designed to
Oh god
Right
And so here's a couple of things
That we can probably agree on
The arguments against System D
It violates the Unix philosophy
Hear that all the time
It's one big thing doing a lot of things
Which is false
Too much stuff crammed into PID1
What's another common System D
Oh, the logging
The binary log
It's bad for servers
This is the new one
Which is insane
It's bad for servers
How is it bad for servers
It was
The concept came for the requirements
Of modern day servers
That's why
Exactly
Yeah
It was designed for service
The idea that Paul Valencia argues
That what we need to do
Is we need to split Linux into two
And you have System D for the desktop side
And then the server distros don't use System D
Totally madness
Absolute craziness
It is absolute craziness
And I wonder
At some point
Do we just ignore these people
And move on
And does it actually dilute the
You know what
Okay
You guys know who Alex Jones is?
Yes
Right
Everybody's like
Your buddy
Yeah
Alex
You think I should play the mustache clip?
Yeah, I think so
Grrr
You won't be able to hear the mustache
So you just have to wait a second
Oh, no worries
Grrr
What's driving me crazy
Is that photo right there
Zoom in on that
It's one of those cops
In a black uniform with a mustache
And you just look like
An absolute clown freak
That works for murdering terrorists
That jack our food and water
I think you're a big joke
Grrr
Oh, you got a mustache
I'll just worship you
It's okay
Nothing against mustaches
So my point about Alex Jones
Is like
Some people think that Alex Jones
Is such an out-there conspiracy theorist
That he makes all conspiracies
About him
But he doesn't
He doesn't
How does he even know
That he makes all conspiracy theorists
Look bad
So guys like paul valencia
And Jim lynch
They are just so far out
There with systemd
They make all systemd haters
Look bad
I just want to say
They've been caught
Yeah
Exactly
Hey, that's a good point
Right there
I mean if you look at it
They've figured out
A way to drive traffic to IT world
And info world
And that's just to keep
Writing about systemd
Yep
And then the linux drones
Just keep clicking it
That's right
And that's because it's controversial
much controversy anymore, not since DBNeo adopted it, I mean where's the controversy
anymore?
They're making it.
Exactly, exactly.
And is this argument that it's not, okay let's just, let's take the it's not very Unix-like
argument.
Is this a valid argument, A. And B, does it matter?
So I think A, I don't think it's a valid argument only in the sense that nothing else implements
some of the things that System D does, and so because there's nothing else, it's somewhat
of a valid argument.
Well, it's the most valid argument only in the sense that like it's the one that comes
closest to being factual, accurate, and sense-making, but it's not that great of an argument in
of itself.
I mean, yeah, sure, you could do, you know, you could control your mouth with, you know,
scripting that you've done, you know, by yourself, but no, System D does it for you.
I don't know.
It makes me angry.
What do you think, Evans?
Well, it's the agglomeration of tasks that are on System D that were separate to a large
degree.
That's the argument there.
Yeah.
Now, I know Evans said he has a counter to that argument.
Now, as the importance of the argument, I would say that one of the things we were trying
to achieve is POSIX compliance and this POSIX concept was approached because it will allow
us to have portable applications across operating systems.
That does require that other distros and other operating systems do apply POSIX standards,
which they all have variations, and to a large degree, the applications still don't work,
so the benefits are not there.
Right.
There's, that would be the, okay, so that's the technical, like Unix compatible definition.
Then you have the philosophical, lots of small tools do one thing really well, working together
in concert to make the overall system.
Well, and the fallacy with that is that System D is a collection of tools, it is not one
single tool.
Exactly.
Well, but it's repackaging all of those single tools into one tool, which is the philosophical
disagreement in terms of like the Unix side.
System D is a re-implementation of some of those tools that have existed for a while,
and I think what people push as the falsehood, which is that it's all crammed into this one
process called System D that happens to be PID 1 as well, which is crap.
It's not all one binary.
I still want to hear what Heaven's Revenge has to say.
Well, I do believe it is very Unix-y.
There is, a lot of people really do still misunderstand what System D is.
It is one thing.
It's an abstract scheduler that the user space uses to schedule things.
That's its purpose.
That's its only job.
Everything else has been built around that, which uses that functionality.
That's why it's so applicable to so many things, and that's why the System D project, the Umbrella
project, has grown to encompass so many different things because it's an abstract scheduler.
So many things just need simple scheduling.
We can't use a CPU scheduler.
We need a user space scheduling system.
That's what it is.
It's just an IPC mechanism for communication and a schedule.
That's it.
It is Unix-y.
It's just one simple thing.
It's just so applicable.
So many things can use it.
Okay, Wimpy.
Why don't you jump in?
Okay.
Well, I want to be clear.
I'm not a System D hater by any means.
I think it's a great advancement for Linux, but I'm going to be devil's advocate here.
One area where System D is squarely not in the Unix philosophy is that you can't pipe
the utilities together, so that was really the crux of all of the Unix utilities that
everything is text in, text out, and they can be joined together with pipes to make
a new utility by joining them.
And that simple-
I don't care.
Well, there is something to it though.
It gives you the ability to build such an amazingly powerful suite of tools together,
but at the same time, it seems like maybe we've moved from that to a different need
now.
We're modernizing in a sense, and it's not necessarily bad.
It's not necessarily good.
I think it's-
It's called innovation.
I mean, deal with it.
Right.
Well, it's called moving the platform forward to the demands of the future and not just
to the demands of the past.
Totally.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And I think the other thing that I recoil at when I hear people talk about System D
is a lot of times people will say, well, System D creates lock-in, and one common example
they will cite is GNOME now requires Login D. Login D is part of System D.
So, in extents, to get later versions of GNOME, you must have System D because you need Login
D.
Not true.
Well, and I'd say, is that just because of the binary logs?
I mean, how does a system lock in?
It's because Login D implements a set of functionalities that no other project is currently implementing.
Oh, I see.
But-
It's called progress.
Well, the thing is, is at each level there, there is an API available.
Somebody could write a replacement, a Login D, that doesn't require System D. That is
technically possible.
And this week we have seen, and this has actually happened five weeks ago, but this week I saw
the physical 100% truth.
It's in the code.
There is code out there right now called System BSD.
And System BSD is a reimplementation of System D APIs for freaking BSD.
So you can use things like Login D and Time D on BSD that are supposed to be System D
calls.
This is a physical literal demonstration of the portability right here.
They are moving this functionality to a completely different operating system.
That's right.
So the idea that we couldn't reimplement Login D functionality in Gen 2 is bullshit.
Yeah, exactly.
We're moving it to BSD now.
It's also emblematic of how efficacious the whole System D project has become, like Heavens
and Wimpy were saying.
That's one thing Wimpy wanted to talk about, System D shims, I believe.
Oh, go ahead, Wimpy.
Well, this is what Chris has just touched on.
One of the GSOC students for OpenBSD this year has created those Dbus APIs to replace
some of the System D layers so that things like Nome 3 can run.
But this is what Canonical have been doing for a little while now.
They've got their own System D shim that provides Login D. And that's how you work around that
issue at the moment and why they're able to move their Nome 3 components that they rely
on.
Isn't it, in a sense, almost a good thing because then it just gives us a common thing
for us to ride against?
Exactly.
Of course it's a good thing.
It gets rid of the fragmentation.
It's just IPC.
Yeah.
I mean, good ideas succeed and bad ideas fail.
That's one of the greatest parts about Linux.
When we talk about it at a factual level like this, it seems clear.
I mean, it seems, yes, there's some disadvantages like we've mentioned, especially when it comes
to binary logs as an old sysadmin.
I'll be honest, that's hard for me.
That's a fallacy.
We can shoot that one down now.
If you install a syslog daemon on a System D-enabled machine, Journal D will push everything
to syslog.
And that's not the only one.
There's a couple of ways.
There's a couple of ways to pull it off.
Yeah.
That's not...
There's a couple of different methods to get your old logging system back, more or less
running on top of System D. So, blah.
That's garbage right there.
All right.
I mean, we could keep going on.
We could keep talking about it.
But I just thought with this System BSD shim thing, this was particularly interesting.
Oh, yeah.
Narrowing it down to info world and IT world and seeing how they're playing off each other
to generate a lot of controversy, which it's interesting the way it works, too, is because
the things they talk about there then sort of leak their way into the communications
of the regular community, and all of a sudden people take it as their own opinions and their
own stances and start arguing these points that are being sort of just ginned up for
traffic.
Yeah.
Which is what's scary about it, because these guys are considered to be thought leaders
or whatever in terms of IT or whatever pseudo-IT information you want to, you know, blah.
And so this just creates just endless controversy that's actually damaging to forward progress.
I think it's damaging.
You know, also, I just got to say to both Jim and Paul, if they happen to listen to
this show, you guys have been caught.
You're done.
Busted.
I almost, you know, like, I don't know.
I almost wonder, do they do it intentionally?
Who knows?
We can't prescribe their motivations.
Well, no.
We can't prescribe their motivations, but at the same time, we can look at it and say,
these are clickbaity articles.
They are that.
Yeah.
So, yeah, especially with the headlines.
That's the only explanation I can think of.
And also, just to them, we have an open mumble room.
So if either one of those gentlemen would like to join us and talk about it.
That's right.
They're absolutely welcome.
We would love that.
If they want to call us out on our calling them out, absolutely.
Well, I can speak intelligently on just a piece of it really quickly in that if you've
ever seen the South Park episode where they explain how Family Guy comes up with their
show titles, writing in tech is a lot like that.
Our editors give us a big tank full of stuff, and then we pick words and make sentences
out of them, and then we pick an article topic.
That's essentially how it works.
These guys know this is absolutely linkbait.
There's no debating this.
I would encourage them to come on here and tell another guy that writes for a living
that this isn't linkbait.
That's right.
It is.
Yeah.
I'm sorry.
Sometimes I'm paid to do it too, but I try and come up with a little more positive stuff.
I don't know.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think you do a good job of that.
Well, and that's why I think it's so damaging.
I mean, I'm speaking from five years of working as a print journalist.
You know, I mean, this is your only two arguments for self-defense for this are either I am
technically illiterate or I am being, or I am a tool.
Well, it seems like peeing in your own pool too, like you're eventually poisoning the
well that you draw your content from.
That's right.
Exactly.
Generally speaking, yeah.
A lot of times you've got editors that are like, especially if you've got like someone
above you that's like saying, you know, if you don't hit this target, guess what?
You're collecting unemployment tax.
Yeah.
And that's the problem.
And it's a short term thing, you know, to them.
It's like, I got to make money for this month.
Let's pour the turpentine into the aquifer, see what happens.
Exactly.
If I just have a few drinks, take a few pills, I can get through this article.
I'll be all right.
I can swallow it.
I can make it through.
But that doesn't excuse it.
It just creates a causality.
This is why this is happening.
Yeah.
You know what?
We'd all be a lot better if they just go write about the iWatch.
There we go.
I totally agree.
That's a good point.
They should go be information reporters for terrorists, you know?
Yeah.
That's right.
Okay.
All right.
This is getting bad.
You could tell it's been a long broadcast day.
Yeah.
It's been a long day.
Yes.
We're getting punchy.
Yeah.
So why don't we talk, let's talk about DNF here in a second.
Fedora 21 coming down the pipe, we just last week talked about restructuring from the ground
up how you deploy software on Linux using butter FS sub volumes.
I mean, this is not that.
The DNF is not that, but it is still a new tool that's coming to manage software and
producer Eric has had a little hands on time with it, so we're going to talk about that
in a second.
All right.
I'll thank DigitalOcean.
Head over to digitalocean.com right now and go get yourself your own server backed by
SSDs connected to tier one bandwidth.
Oh, you don't know what DigitalOcean is?
My friend, let me tell you.
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy way to spin up a cloud server.
Users can create a cloud server in less than 55 seconds.
And pricing plans start only $5 a month, which gets you 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte
SSD, and this is the best part, one terabyte of transfer just right there.
And so, you've got a CPU that backs it, you've got 20 gigabytes of SSD for incredible IO
density, and you've got it connected to tier one bandwidth with a terabyte of transfer.
And DigitalOcean has data center locations all over the place.
They've got them in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, brand new one in London,
which is great.
And on top of all of that, they manage it all with their incredible intuitive control
panel, which power users can replicate on a larger scale with DigitalOcean's awesome
straightforward API.
And they just got a little more awesome with the introduction of CoreOS.
This is an amazing opportunity for you to go over there and try it out.
And if you use our promo code, because we've got a promo code for you, unplug September,
$10 credit.
Like, in the past, when a server grade operating system like this came out that was truly something
new, that you can tell by the industry response is already a success, it's already on the
path to success, think about how awesome it is that if you go over to DigitalOcean.com,
if you use the promo code, unplug September, you could create a CoreOS cluster and play
with one of the most advanced server operating systems on the planet connected to tier one
bandwidth on top of SSD drives using their super fast control panel for free, for two
months, using the promo code, unplug September.
It's huge.
I mean, when have we ever been in this position for technology at this scale that has been
this democratized that we have this level of access to?
It is amazing to see this happen, and it's all backed by Linux on top of KVM.
This is something that we saw at OSCON.
People were getting fired up about CoreOS, and now it's available to everyone.
Yeah.
Yeah, and I thought about playing with CoreOS, and it's not the kind of thing you're going
to throw in VirtualBox.
That's not the right place for that.
And this is such an opportunity.
I mean, of course, they've got all kinds of great distros you can choose from.
CoreOS has just been added.
It's new.
They're going to be working with CoreOS, and it's going to be...
It's a game changer.
It is totally a game changer.
DigitalOcean itself is a game changer, matched with a bunch of game changing technology powered
by the open source technology stack that they ride all that on top of.
Now matching that up, and they didn't just go get a CoreOS image.
They worked with the CoreOS project to make this happen because there's some management
stuff they needed in there.
There's some changes they needed to make, and they want to work directly with CoreOS
to make sure that your images are backed by the CoreOS development team.
It's awesome.
And that's the beauty about doing that is that they can create their own custom image
for what they need to give you guys a custom image.
And then you manage the droplets with their great interface.
That's right.
DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code UNPLUGGEDSEPTEMBER when you check out.
You'll get that $10 credit, and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring Linux
Unplugged.
Okay, Eric, so let's talk about a package manager, DNF, which literally stands for nothing,
right?
DNF has no acronym properties.
So YUM was what, yellow update, was it manager or...
Yellow dog...
Updates.
I can't remember now.
Something manager, but yeah.
Yellow update, yellow dog update manager, modified.
Yellow dog update or modified is what YUM stood for.
That's right.
And DNF was created by the Fordora Project and also Red Hat Sponsoring to take what is
YUM and make it better.
I know.
But at first I didn't quite understand because I didn't really see a big benefit to DNF.
So for example, I would be using DNF to update my packages, to install a new version of something
or to install Chromium or something like that, right?
I would now call on the DNF command instead of YUM command.
Correct.
Now here's what it is.
It's a drop-in replacement for YUM that is going to actually take on the name of YUM
come Fedora 22.
And you actually literally mean drop-in, like you were playing with symlinks and stuff,
right?
Yeah, exactly.
I took and I renamed my YUM binary to YUM-Legacy and then I made a symlink for DNF to YUM.
And now anytime anything in my system calls on the YUM command, it's actually calling
on DNF.
Now why did you do that?
I did that just to experiment to see if it would work and it does.
It's flawless.
In fact, it runs faster than YUM.
DNF is still using RPM packages on the backend.
It's managing dependency resolution just like YUM does.
It's using repo files like YUM does.
It's using the exact same file structure that YUM has.
The difference is that where YUM pulls down each package individually, when one package
gets done, it will actually pull down several packages simultaneously, therefore using your
bandwidth to the best of its ability and also using your system processes to the best of
their ability.
And they've recently introduced Delta RPM support.
Correct.
They introduced Delta RPM support by default before that they had it just as an experimental
setting it could make.
Now it's in there by default.
And I guess it looks like they have a DNF package history.
Maybe you could do some rollback stuff.
I don't know if that's in there yet.
That's right.
Is that in there?
It's in there, but that's one of those things that still has to be enabled by config file.
So it doesn't sound like it's a huge change, but it kind of sounds like it's a direction
to just, it's like we're starting here and we're going to move this forward a little
bit.
Right.
It's actually a rewrite.
I'm not asking if it's completely new or if it's modified.
It's actually a complete rewrite from the ground up.
And I think this is going to be across Red Hat Enterprise, Fedora, and CentOS will all
be using DNF.
Correct.
By the time those versions release in the future, I mean we're talking, the first one's
going to be Fedora 22 and then the next one is going to be, well you're going to see CentOS
and Red Hat in whatever version they decide to release that in probably like a 7.2, 7.3.
I was always kind of surprised that we didn't see any other RPM distros adopt YUM.
I wonder if we'll see DNF adopted by that.
Yeah.
I see other RPM distros like, Sousa's got Zipper, and Mandrake has RPMI or Mandriva.
They have their own thing.
I have yet to experiment with that because I haven't, I don't know, it just seems like
an irrelevant.
RPMI was, I don't know if that's what they still use, but back in the day when I was
a Mandrake user, that was almost RPM good enough for me.
I could almost, Matt, did you ever play with Mandrake's URPMI, I think was what it was
called?
No, I didn't.
I never spent as much time with Mandrake as I should have.
I kind of toyed around with it a little bit, and then of course the RPM stigma hit me initially
and I just ran away almost immediately.
I seem to remember like-
I remember that.
I don't remember it.
I seem to remember URPMI made it easy to add repos.
It had like a lot of app-like features.
Oh yeah?
I always pronounce it your erp me.
I think they still use it.
Okay.
Interesting.
Anybody in the mumble room had a chance to play with the DNF or the new Fedora release
with any thoughts?
I'm looking at you, Colonel Linux, and I'm thinking, you're a CentOS guy.
I am a CentOS guy, unfortunately.
I've been out of town for the last week.
When these kind of things, though, come down the pipe, do you load up Fedora and think
to yourself, okay, I'm going to learn how this is going to be for my servers in the
future?
Or is that like a thing that you Red Hat guys do, or how does that work?
That used to be exactly what I did.
In fact, it's so much to the point that I would teach myself new features of Red Hat
on Fedora.
Unfortunately, it doesn't work like that anymore.
The projects have split so decidedly in two different ways.
There's almost no similarity between the two.
That's interesting.
So I look at... In fact, when I was at LinuxCon, I actually learned that I should stop looking
at CentOS to see what Red Hat's like, because apparently those two are going to become very
different.
That's a little confusing.
That is very confusing.
Yeah, for real.
Yeah, but so apparently even now, and I haven't had a chance to confirm this, but apparently
even with 7, there are differences between Red Hat Enterprise and CentOS.
They're no longer just recompiled binaries.
That makes me unhappy.
That's not good, because-
I'm holding out judgment until I find out exactly what the long-term plan... Because
let's say they take CentOS and make it into an enterprise desktop operating system.
I'm okay with that, as long as projects like... What's another one?
Scientific Linux still exist.
As long as it's something I can go to where I can build binaries on some sort of a cost-free
platform that has access to repos.
As long as I can do that, I think-
I think that's going to be Fedora.
I think Fedora.cloud and Fedora.server are going to... Yeah, Fedora.cloud, Fedora.server.
Whatever they name it is fine with me, as long as I have something.
And that's one thing that's coming out, is that the next... Fedora 21 is going to be
the first one that goes by that Fedora Next moniker.
Yeah.
Boy, that's going to be a transition that is going to take a while to play out, and
meanwhile Red Hat Enterprise Linux will be standing still.
At some point, Red Hat Enterprise Linux will have to catch up to all this Fedora Next stuff.
How do they make that transition?
Because Fedora Next is a totally different beast.
You can have a real minimal Fedora Next, and they're even talking about a Fedora Next version
that's essentially rolling in a way.
Well, especially... Well, yeah, they have Rawhide, but if you look at it, they're going
to have to deal with the server, the workstation, cloud, and whatever that fourth one is.
I'm not talking about Rawhide.
Yeah, I'm talking about RAIL.
No, I'm saying in Red... I'm saying one of the things they're talking about in Red Hat
is making it so that way... I don't think they're going to be there yet, but I think
they are designing it with the intention of sort of like Core OS, where you isolate out
the server applications and the base OS is rolling.
Yeah, and Fedora's already doing that.
RAIL's probably just going to take on what they're doing and have a workstation.
That's one thing RAIL does not have, is they don't have a workstation.
Fedora could have redhatenterprise.workstation.
That's right, Red Hat Enterprise Workstation.
It's going to be CentOS.
Well, I mean, if you look at the way SUSE does it, they have workstation and server,
so why doesn't Red Hat have something like that?
I wouldn't say because SUSE does something, Red Hat should do it.
Yeah, I'm not saying that.
I'm saying... I just think it's surprising that they don't have something like that already.
Well, like Noah mentioned when he was down at LinuxCon, it's like, come on, give me a
distro that I can put on the desktops that matches the servers.
We'll see what they do.
Yeah.
Well, I'm looking for... Yeah, there's some Fedora haters in the chat room, but I actually
think Fedora's starting to become a really interesting project again.
Yeah, well, honestly-
I agree.
Honestly, beginning of July, I could have been included with one of those Fedora haters.
I decided to go ahead and try it.
You've been running the 21 beta?
No, I've been trying 20.
Oh, 20.
I've just been running the solid 20.
What are you, a masochist?
Yeah.
What's the matter?
No.
Come on, man.
No, I did it because I wanted to get familiar with the system, and I wanted to learn how
they do it, and what they do-
Well, you see cool stuff coming out of the project.
Exactly.
Yeah.
You know, I've been saying this for a little while now.
We're seeing... Most of the innovation is coming from the Fedora project.
Like ALIGX?
Yep.
Wait, what?
What?
No.
Random assortment of letters.
Don't you guys remember ALIGLX versus XGL, and those were the two back-end compositors,
and then you read Compass Fusion on top of that?
Come on.
It's not that old of a reference.
Jeez.
Thankfully, perfect.
What I'm saying is that Red Hat and through Fedora is pushing most of the innovation in
Linux that I'm seeing, other than Canonical with their thing.
Yeah.
What?
Yeah, I know, right?
Oh.
No, unless Popey's here, we pretend like Canonical doesn't do anything.
Oh, okay.
So, anyways, some British company, I don't know.
I kid.
Wow.
Yeah.
No, I see where you-
They're pushing the innovation.
They're pushing things forward, and you wanted to be there.
You wanted to see it.
Yeah.
I wanted to see what it was like, and sadly, I think that as far as they push it, it doesn't
run as well on my hardware for some reason.
I've got a little bit more experimentation to do, but-
So maybe back to a different distro for you?
Perhaps Arch or Ubuntu.
I don't know.
Have you considered trying 21, just to see if it runs better?
I might.
Yeah, you've got this weird UI leg thing that happens from time to time.
Yeah.
That is really strange.
That would drive me crazy.
Yeah.
It's like, and I can watch it in like Ahtop or something, or even Top, and it's like,
I get this random spike from Gnome Shell, the Gnome Shell process, and it shoots up
to like 13% and back down, and then 13% back down.
And that's Gnome 3.12, right?
That's Gnome 3.12.
Stable?
Stable.
Yeah.
I don't know why it's doing that.
It just is.
Have you played it all with Korora?
I have.
Which is a sort of a re-spin of Fedora with some-
I have not.
All it really does is include RPM Fusion and a few other things.
RPM Fusion and like Codex and like Flash.
Yeah.
All of which come from RPM Fusion.
Binary drivers.
Yeah.
So-
It just makes it a little bit easier to get going.
Yeah.
It does.
It definitely is a time saver.
I have yet to actually try it, but it's not a bad idea.
Just try it around.
Yeah.
We'll have a review of Fedora 21 whenever they eventually ship it.
They've just delayed it again.
Yeah.
So-
It's been two weeks delayed so far, and we'll see what happens.
Yeah.
We'll see what happens.
I don't know.
All right, Matt.
Well, I think that was everything we were going to cover in today's episode.
We'll have episode 330 of the Linux Action Show on Sunday.
Wow.
So that'll be a big show.
Yeah.
Huge.
That's a lot of shows.
Wow.
That's show after show after show.
So if you'd like to get a hold of us, we'd love to get your feedback.
Go over to jupiterbroadcasting.com, click the contact link, and choose Linux Unplugged
from the dropdown, or maybe even better, be part of the in-crowd, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com is a great place for comments, feedback, what were you saying?
Open media vault.
Oh, God.
Yeah.
We're going to do an open media vault review.
All right.
Geez.
We better do that before we go.
I can't-
These shows have been going long, these shows.
Oh, it felt like a marathon today.
It has been a marathon.
We can do it next week.
No, no, no.
No, we said we'd do it.
We can do it, right?
I mean, we should do it.
Yeah.
We should probably get it done today.
So let's start with open media vault.
Now, the open media vault is something that we've had many requests to review on the show,
and it's something I haven't gotten around to, because I'll be honest, I'm pretty happy
with my FreeNAS setup.
Pretty happy with my FreeNAS setup.
But I'd like to hear, well, maybe you guys can convert me away.
Yeah, yeah.
So Wimpy, do you want to start on the... Because I know you gave it a kick the tires.
I'm not sure who else in the mumble room today got a shot, but Wimpy, I'd love to hear what
your thoughts were with it, and maybe what your use case was.
Right.
Well, I run open media vault at home.
I've got two open media vault servers.
I've got one which is the current stable version, which is 0.5, and I've got what will be the
1.0 release, which is coming up soon, running on the other box.
And primarily I'm using that for NFS and Samba sharing, and Plex media serving, and torrenting
ISO images, and just about everything you can imagine.
There's a plug-in for everything.
Nice.
So the 0.5 version sits on top of a Debian squeeze base OS, and what will be the 1.0
release sits on a Debian Weezy base.
So you can install from an ISO image.
It's super simple, it's preceded, so you have the ISO in, it tells you it's going to trash
all your disks, which it does, and then you end up with an install, and you can boot into
the web UI, you manage everything from the web UI, and it does, if you've ever used any
of the...
It's very FreeNAS-looking.
Yeah.
Well, the guy that started Open Media Vault actually departed from the FreeNAS project.
So he was one of the original FreeNAS developers, and they had some sort of disagreement.
I'm not quite sure what the details were, but the guy that's doing this is a refugee
from FreeNAS.
A refugee.
A refugee from FreeNAS.
Wow.
What was the file system?
Well, you've got a choice.
So when you actually create your disks, it's got Linux software RAID on there.
I'm talking about the stable version at the moment.
There's a plug-in for LVM, and then you can choose any of the file systems with the exception
of ButterFS, which is not available in the stable version, because in Squeeze, that's
really, really experimental.
I hear talk, I don't know how far along it is, that they're working on a plug-in for
the 1.0 release to natively support ButterFS without the use of LVM and software RAID,
so that you could go completely to ButterFS, but I don't know if that's definitely happening
or how far along it is, but I've seen several references to it.
There has been some talk about ZFS as well, but I can't quite tell whether they're serious
about that or not.
So disk management, adding additional storage, sort of like if you wanted to go drubble on
this thing and just sort of add disks over time, sounds like I'm kind of falling back
on traditional disk management utilities in Linux to add capacity and grow volumes and
things like that?
Only if you want to.
So for example, I think you've talked about SnapRaid in one of the shows somewhere ago,
and also GreyHole, so you can also use SnapRaid and GreyHole if you want to instead of traditional
RAID solutions.
Okay.
That's not bad.
I like that.
I mean, like I said, there's plug-ins for everything.
There's some boring stuff.
And the plug-ins would be things like, I would assume things like Plex backup, stuff like
that?
Well, let's look what I've got at the moment.
So at the moment I've got, hang on a sec, let's bring it all up.
And I'm sure Sync Tools too, right?
I'm sure that's another...
Yeah.
So I've got BitSync installed on there.
So when you install the plug-in, it installs BitSync as a service, as a daemon, and then
has a UI that then integrates into the web UI of the OpenMediaVault thing, and you can
put your shared secrets in there and all that kind of stuff.
Actually I would say the UI looks a little nicer than FreeNAS.
It definitely looks cleaner.
I've got a plug-in for Calibre, I've got one for Potato, another one for Cups, another
one which is just a generic downloader which I use for grabbing torrents and web links
and stuff like that and YouTube videos.
It's got a web front-end for navigating your file system.
Like I said, if you want it, it's got Grey Hole which is an alternative storage pool,
file system manager, headphones, mini-DLNA I use for streaming to amps and stuff that
only speak DLNA.
And then there's a MySQL plug-in, an NGINX plug-in, oh you'll like this one, there's
a ToneCloud plug-in, OpenVPN, Roundcube mail server, and then RSnapshot which I touched
on earlier, and then SabNZB and SickBeard.
And all of these plug-ins, they don't just install a bit of software, but they actually
have a front-end GUI that integrates into the OpenMediaVault web UI.
This would sound a killer.
To take a box and dedicate it to this.
Yeah.
So it all runs through the browser?
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, this sounds awesome.
And then it looks like the browser management software also will go out and update the plug-ins
too.
It does, yeah.
It has an update manager.
It's like a front-end to app to basically, so there's an update manager.
I mean there's another plug-in here, I've used it a bit, there's one for VirtualBox
so you can create virtual machines on there, transmission plug-ins, VDR for DVB and DVB-S
and DVB-T.
What's it using for a base?
It's all Debian.
Wow.
So this is one of the reasons I like it, because although I've got the CUPS plug-in installed,
I've got, I think Google called them a classic printer, which basically means not a cloud
print enabled printer, but because it's all just Debian underneath, I've been able to,
someone's written a native Linux implementation of the cloud print API, which sits on top
of CUPS.
So I've been able to install that on my OpenMedia Vault box to turn my classic printer into
a cloud print printer, so now we can print from our Android phones and tablets.
Oh, that's cool.
So because it's straight up Debian, I can do everything on the box that I would want
to do.
I was just looking for a solution for that.
Yeah, I was thinking about the same thing.
So is that also how you got Plex running on it?
Plex is just a plug-in for OpenMedia Vault.
Oh, this is so cool.
Yeah.
Wow.
So the standard plug-ins, there's maybe about a dozen, there's then a website, it's omv-extras.org
and this is where the community publish their plug-ins and this is where you get all the
good stuff from.
omv-extras.org.
Oh yeah.
I'm looking at this.
This is great.
And you can see they've got stable testing and unstable repositories.
WordPress.
Uh-huh.
Oh, this is pretty awesome, actually.
It's brilliant.
There's couch potato.
That's where they're right there.
See, can you see why I keep banging on about it?
Yeah, I do.
Yeah.
Wow.
Don't stop either.
Yeah.
Rochure, WordPress.
Mumble server if you want it.
I love it.
A mumble server.
Wow.
Mini DLNA.
I can't believe it's Roundcube.
I mean, Roundcube.
Wow.
You run your mails around.
Me likey.
Yeah.
That is really cool.
This is amazing.
Makes me want to put on a droplet too for some of the mail features.
I know, right?
That'll just open up another droplet right now.
It's going to happen.
So if you want to put it on a droplet, I've got some instructions here about how to install
a Debian system and then overlay and I'll paste it in the IRC now.
Cool.
I'll grab that.
You can convert an existing Debian install.
You can convert a base Debian Weezy into an Open Media Vault install.
Wow.
Score.
And they also have ISO images, I imagine.
Yeah, they do.
They have ISO images for 0.5.
Log it into the demo right now.
Yeah.
What I suggest is create a virtual box machine with one disk that you allocate for the OS
and then add like five virtual disks for your RAID.
And when you install it, install it onto the OS disk and then you can actually go in and
use all of the disk management tools and actually experiment with LVMs and RAID or SNAP RAID
or whatever.
And once you've figured out how to do it in a VM, then you can go and reproduce it on
real hardware.
Yeah.
Boy.
Wow.
See, I was kind of expecting Open Media Vault to be a bit of a stinker because I was like,
how are you going to compete with FreeNAS?
But it sounds like it's a pretty big contender.
Big time.
The only difference for me with FreeNAS would be, of course, ZFS support, but...
I wonder if you could just install that.
I don't know.
I know that in the forum, some people have been talking about it.
So I can't quite tell whether the lead developer is anti-ZFS because of his falling out.
Oh, that's a good one.
Right.
He got burned.
Whether he just doesn't want to take on supporting it under Linux.
But I think at the moment, very much it's sort of the traditional tools and then the
plugins for SnapRaid and GreyHole, which give you those, you know, disks at random.
Yeah.
I think that would do it.
GreyHole and SnapRaid are pretty good.
Could be a FreeNAS killer.
This looks deadly.
JBLive3 in the chat room says that he installed Open Media Vault on a Debian install with
LXDE.
And then he used that to migrate from Windows Home Server when Microsoft pulled the plug
on that.
Someone saying that there is a ZFS plugin for Open Media Vault 1.
I can't see that on my system, but apparently it's there.
Okay.
Cool.
Rikai has a link in the chat room right now.
I will grab that too.
So I will put links to converting a Debian install to Open Media Vault.
I'll put a link to ZFS on Open Media Vault.
So we'll have all of that.
Is there anything else we should talk about on Open Media Vault before we run?
Performance is stellar.
So I've got really, really humble hardware and I'm using it as a Plex server and it does
real-time HD transcoding.
Wonder how it would run on my Netbook server thingy.
What sort of processor have you got in it?
It's an Atom N270.
Okay.
That's probably better than...
Hang on.
Let me just find out.
I've got something terrible.
Are you serious?
Wow.
What have you got?
A couple gigs of RAM on it?
You're probably right.
I've got AMD Turion 2 Neo.
So...
Yeah.
So mine is more powerful.
So...
This is all cringing.
Well, the other thing I was going to...
What about...
It's good and bad.
On FreeNAS, when you install a plug-in, they're sandboxed.
They're isolated in a sense.
But on Open Media Vault, when you install Plex, is it able to see all of your file shares?
Because to me, one of the disadvantages of the way FreeNAS does it is then I have to
do this funky way to mount my data into that plug-in or into that jail.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Totally.
Right.
But if Open Media Vault could just see the file system, that would actually be better
than Torrent Sync.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So that's how it works.
So in the UI, you have a section for physical disks, which is just all your drives.
From there, depending on how you want to set it up, you use either LVM or RAID or SNAP
RAID or whatever.
And then you end up with some file systems.
And those are the things that you actually format with your file system of choice.
And from there, using the UI, when you're in Plex, and it embeds the Plex UI in the
tool, you can point at anything that the OS can see.
But by default, it wants to use one of the media shares, as they're so called.
Okay.
Yeah.
So I create a file system.
On there, I create a shared folder called Music.
And when I go to Plex, I say add the media music.
And off it goes.
Easy.
But you can point it at anything in the system if you wanted to.
Okay.
Interesting.
That's cool.
That would be a tool that I would want that is not in the plugins page that you referenced.
The OMV extras.
I mean, it's pretty awesome.
Yeah.
And someone's just posted in the chat room, and I found it.
In the 1.0 version that I'm running, you have to enable the ZFS repository, and now the
plugin shows up.
Okay.
Yeah.
Rick, I just posted more up-to-date instructions as well.
That's awesome.
Putting links to all this stuff in the show notes for folks that are listening on the
downloads.
You guys can grab that.
Wimpy, thanks for the review.
Anybody else in the Mumber Room have any Open Media Vault experience to chime in with before
we run?
Is that?
That's a good cover.
We got great coverage from Wimpy.
So, yeah.
I'm going to be checking it out, so thank you very much for filling us in on that.
And keep us posted as you discover new things or try new things with it.
Let us know how it goes.
You mind being our Open Media Vault correspondent?
That's absolutely fine.
Okay.
Good.
Along with Ubuntu Mate.
Mate.
Yeah.
You know, just add it to the list, Wimpy.
It's good.
Yeah.
Just a few.
All right.
Well, thank you very much.
Okay.
So, that will bring us to the end of today's episode.
Don't forget we do Linux Unplugged live, like today.
Boy, was today live.
Wow.
Go over to jblive.tv.
We usually start at 2 p.m. Pacific, but jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar has that in your local time.
And if you don't join us for next Tuesday, at least show up on Sunday for the big show.
Linux action show Sunday, 10 a.m. Pacific, jblive.tv.
Matt, that's going to wrap us up.
Have a great week.
All right.
Yeah, you too.
I'll see you on Sunday for episode 330.
That's crazy.
Eric, thank you for joining us in the studio.
It was great.
Any time.
And thanks for joining me earlier today.
If you guys want to watch our coverage of the iThink event, it'll be posted on Jupyter
Broadcasting.
It might not be on YouTube because they're pulling our crap down like crazy, but you
can hear Eric's commentary and insights as well as mine in the mumble room from today's
event.
You can watch that in Tech Talk today, episode 55.
All right, everyone.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
I'm so glad I learned about Open Media Vault.
Yeah.
That was crazy cool.
That was way cooler than I was expecting.
I mean, you have to-
I've only covered like half the plugins as well.
I mean, there's just so much to it and there's a bunch built into the stock system.
I mean, just reading that page is absolutely nuts.
There's nothing I could think of that I would want from network attack storage.
And they're the community-contributed ones.
There's a whole heap of useful stuff built in, so I've got the UPS monitoring online
as well.
Yeah, I saw that too.
That's cool.
Hey, Wimpy, I forgot to ask this.
Is there a way that I could stick it to a virtual machine and just play with for a while
before I actually install it on real man?
Yeah.
Toad, yeah.
When I first got started with it, I did it all on VirtualBox.
I created five drives, one for the OS, four for pretend disks, and I raided them and stuff
in Open Media Vault.
We have...