Hey Eric, I was it you that submitted the imp to the to the subreddit you guys
Did you see this we have we have another crowdsourced Linux computer. I'm a sucker for these
I love like you get the promo video
It's like you get the you get the will it make its funding like it's not gambling
But there's a there's an element of it
It's it's so it's a lot of fun and it's interesting to sell these independent hardware guys, too
they've been doing a lot of
social outreach shall we say if you follow the
The Twitter feed just go and have a look at the tweets and mentions of their marketing person
It's pinging basically everyone in the free software community asking them. Hey, what do you think of our thing?
Can you reshare it please? So I said to them? Well, it's not open source
It says open source, but it isn't because there's binary blobs in there and they were like, yeah
Yeah, that's binary, but everything else is open source
I said, yeah, but at the top it says fully open source and it isn't so let's so we should talk about that
Cuz if everything works out the the Librem 15 creator the laptop that I crowdfunded
A couple of weeks ago in the last news segment is gonna join us today
And I I think this is a question we need to ask
How do you promote yourself as like do no evil all open but yet still manage to ship something that is competitive, right?
Which event which is my nice way of saying, you know an actual GPU that has a binary blob driver and closed source drivers
So I think that's a really good question. I want to play this video wimpy
I'm gonna toss the link to that guide in the show notes for people that are listening after the fact
But let's let's play this a little bit
And then we'll talk about it because I love I love the fact that all these come with videos
That's like the best part for me. Oh, we got some music
Technology has virtually exploded
Surprisingly only one thing has stayed the same the desktop
Imp is here to change that
Imp resolves your entire home computing needs in one ready-to-use unit that fits in the palm of your hand
Just plug it in and see what it can do for you
Imp is a full-blown desktop computer that suits all of your everyday home use needs whether it's browsing the web
Checking your email being social or even if it had this holographic interface that would be a slam dunk
So it's looking I'm trying to figure out what the desktop environment is do you guys know
Yeah, so it's a cinnamon theme perhaps
Because I don't recognize look of it, but I've seen or heard about this somewhere so touch my head work
I think it's interesting. There's talking about media streaming capabilities, too. It can even back up all your phone's media
So it streams to yours it streams to your television and it backs up your phones and it uses the cinnamon desktop and
It's called imp MP. So oh
This is this is that we got more video
But what do you guys think was it implying that there was some sort of NFC when you set your phone next to it?
It's gonna start sinking. No, yeah, they showed in the video. They showed him hooking up a USB cable. I got you
Yeah, so it's got it's raised
33,000 USD it's trying to get to 100,000 33% funded 35 hours left only 35 hours at 33%
That's stretch goal. Yeah, that's that's tight. I
guess
See what you have to be buying here is their custom software solution that sits on top of this because otherwise you'd probably just buy
A knock although the prices are cheaper than a knock. Yeah, but it's it's it's way lower spec than a knock. It's an odroid
Yeah, yeah, yeah exactly and that's one thing
q5 sis pointing out
Odroids are not legal in the u.s. Because the FCC will not recognize them. What?
Yeah, no, I think there's devices here that have a droid processors, isn't it?
Well, it took q5 sis forever to get his odroid machines into the like a licensing issue. It'd be like it'd be like oh
Well, that's because they are FCC certified. I'll tell you I had a problem
I've ordered seven or eight odroid products and I've never had a problem with any of them
So yeah, hmm. I wonder if it depends on the model. So this is using the odroid youth three
It looks like I'm not they're not gonna hit their target. So no, I don't think so. Probably not
Is this the wrong approach though, I mean maybe the better
I mean is it is it possible to do is it is the crowdfunding required because you have to reach scale?
Because if I could just buy one of these, I mean, maybe they just sell them one-off
I don't I guess I guess that never really works. I suppose. Well, the problem is that the
Crowdfunding is a way to go from zero to hero in a very short period of time
What they don't want to do is they don't want to put in the work that every other company that exists right now has gone
Through which is sell a small number of one item
Then so the slightly larger number of your next revision of that item then the next and then the next go through iterations
They want to go from nothing to big bang and sell one device
However, here's the here's the devil's advocate to that. So in their specs, right?
They're going up against the Chrome box
Now the Chrome box is a pretty hard competitor because the hardware is literally being subsidized by Google and Intel, right?
On the x86 versions of Chrome boxes
so if you're an independent manufacturer and you're going up against these industry Titans that have can they can
Substitize the hardware cost there by lowering the cost of the Chromebook or the Chrome box then maybe your only way to be competitive
Is to have some scale so that way you can buy in at lower prices and charge lower rates, right?
And they'll make it scale crowdfunding when you're not their only way of having a USB
They've got other USP's that the Chrome box doesn't have like all this home syncing stuff that that I haven't seen on
Any computer out of the box? So that's a USB
So you're saying that that that service value add would justify a higher price
I think not justify a higher price, but justify it existing in a normal retail channel and not having to go the yeah
crowdfunding
Built-in apps and services. They've got the Microsoft Office suite listed in one drive
So I assume that they're they're linking to office 365. Yeah, I think so
This particular doesn't this this is on the go-go and it doesn't matter if they reach it or not. They're keeping them from hunting regardless
That's right. Yeah, they get they get a larger cut taken from IndieCo go there. Right, right, right. No, it's a fixed funding
Funding that you get it all isn't it?
Funding campaign. Yeah, it is if you have if you hover it it says that if you hover the question mark next to it
It says they're still gonna keep it
Oh, yeah fixed this campaign will receive all funds raised even if it does not reach its goal. So they're already gonna make 33,000
Maybe they use that as investment seating to go out and make a product that does go to retail. I don't know
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that has a totally legitimate reason for wearing pajamas all day
My name is Chris and my name is Matt
And you wouldn't believe the day I've had today
So, I mean we got a great show I mean not to overshadow episode 69
It's gonna be great Todd from purism is joining us to talk about the ultimate free Linux laptop
And then there is a major Docker competitor that has been announced by the core OS project and I'm super excited about it
It's really geeky, but I'm really excited. We're gonna talk about that. Plus we got feedback but Matt
Matt
This is Matt. This is the thing Matt. All right. I woke up this morning to the sound of somebody
Pouring water a glass of water maybe like a jar of water on the floor upstairs
Oh, no, and it hears how it goes my wife reaches over sick. Hey, wake up. Hey, wake up
Do you hear that and my wife's first conclusion is somebody is broken into the house and the whole purpose of breaking into our house
There's a poor glass of water on the floor, right and I immediately discredit that theory. I'm like, no, that's not so I go out there
My three-year-old daughter didn't quite make it to the bathroom. Oh, no
Yeah, so that that was my morning is I had to clean a little bit of a mess right there good
Well, actually, I just I you know what I did. I'm gonna be honest
I just put a towel on but you know, somebody had to clean up head mess
I don't know who and I get then and then I leave Matt
I drive to the studio in you know, it's arctic 21 degrees Fahrenheit out here
Oh, yeah, and I get out of the truck in in a very and the jb1 studios is a fairly public street
It's not there's not much privacy to be had there, right?
I step out of the truck and my favorite pair of jeans Matt not like a pair of jeans
I like to wear but my a pair of jeans that I've worn for years. Love it. Take care of them
I barely wash them, you know all of the things you do with your favorite pair of jeans
I step out of the truck and it's they're old. So it snags the like the step on my truck
Oh, no, okay rips the jeans all the way up to my butt cheek all the way up to my butt cheek Matt
It rips them all the way up
I'm standing out there with half of my ass hanging out in the road in
21 degree weather and I'm thinking to myself. I haven't even made it into the studio yet. What could possibly go wrong?
However, this is this is where you cue Swedish volleyball team driving by the bus
As they go by you know, I'll have to you know
I kind of a story along those lines off to share another show one day
I got I'll have to have a few drinks before I share that story because it's it's it's scarring but so I
Realized though. This was an opportunity to make some lemonade and you know, I'm always looking for life's lemonade opportunities
Oh, yeah, because I had as every good podcaster does let's be frank
I had a backup pair of pants in the studio a pajama
You know, I had pajama pants in the studio
So I've legitimately had a had a solid excuse to wear pajama pants all day long today
And at first I was kind of upset about it because my favorite pair of jeans then I realized
Pajama pants no guilt that is almost worth it. Plus. I think the wife might be able to fix the pants
So all in all that's cool. Yeah, it's not so bad
Well, we do have a lot to get to I probably shouldn't mess around too much because tons of stuff to cover
So I'll bring in our mumble room and they can help us comment away on things as they come up
But time-appropriate greetings mumble room great to have you here. Hello. Happy Tuesday. Oh, yeah, you're right about that
And welcome back colonel Linux on the cheap rig. Good to have you here, sir
How's the cheap rig sounding today? I I think it sounds pretty good. Wow. I think it sounds better than I do
All right, it's official we're doing a segment on on colonel Linux is cheap podcasting Linux rig setup
We've got to do it before the end of the year colonel Linux. So you got to figure it out
Maybe I'll game people can make it their end-of-year purchase
All right, so we got to get into some follow-up as per tradition on the Linux unplugged show
We like to keep the continuity
so those of you who listen to every episode you get rewarded by some continuity for every show and those of you who don't get
A chance to listen you kind of hear some fragments of stuff
We've covered so you get an idea of maybe it's worth jumping back into the back catalog. So Chris not me
Writes in with our first emailing says hey Chris Matt and the mumble room I just finished listening to Linux action show and unplugged episodes
Around Linux in the Penn Manor schools and I got to say wow. I am and I I am in IT for a district school system in
WV and that's I think if I'm right
That's the Volkswagen bug and I have been trying to introduce links for 15 years in my district. It's been very hard
We have 22 sites 11,000 students 4,000 staff and only seven in the IT staff
I was envious of Penn Manor with their nine. Anyways
Last year we introduced some Chromebooks and I thought maybe Linux is finally gonna be a possibility
Until this school year the State Department made a deal with Microsoft every employee and student in our state gets unlimited storage on one drive
Yes unlimited it started at one terabyte
But it's now actually become unlimited for them every employee and student also gets five installs of office 2013
Oh, there's a winner that they can download and manage from office 365 and our state has
unlimited
licenses on Windows 7 and 8 installs
The price of office and Windows is now gone
We only pay for server licenses and cows client access licenses. So Microsoft is fighting back
I know this cannot be I know this cannot be free and the state has to be paying something to Microsoft
But districts never see that money and it doesn't even cut into the district budget this
I think cut into our plans for more Chromebooks this year, but I have now seen Microsoft's I've now
I have now seen more Microsoft services come through the shop
Just thought you might want to know that Microsoft is fighting back and doesn't want to die
Boy, it sounds like they're not just fighting back, but it sounds like they it sounds like they're going long
I think they realize that you know
There's no sense in trying to drill down on the school districts go along get people brainwashed into using the product and you'll get them
Later, you know, they're gonna buy this and it sounds they are trying to go hardware
It sounds like a little bit like maybe get the state to bear the cost. Yeah, and you know, I got a wonder though
Is
This a sign that Windows 10 is gonna be free. Oh
It will be I I would be sure it'd be stupid at this point if they don't it's the only thing it's cuz it works
Right. It's hard to argue with free if it's crap. Yeah, and you can see here. They're responding to Chromebooks
And devices like it
by
Selectively making Windows free as they can, you know not making a big deal about it not making it public
But when it comes down to it, they're making it free and you got to think they're doing that
Specifically because they know that the cost of the operating system is like look Apple gives it away now, right?
You know, it's a commercial OS. They're giving it away. Linux is free Chrome OS is quote-unquote free Android is free
So what's Microsoft gonna do? They're gonna have to do this
That's right, and it's honestly I I'm kind of surprised it took him this long
Well, believe it or not there have been
Miscellaneous leaks from multiple
Executives at Microsoft that have said that Windows 10 will be free. No. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I'm not surprised
I've read a lot of articles that basically there was a
Somebody like what the executives in Indonesia did say it would be free free as in cost we should point out. Yes
Free as in cost. Yeah. Yeah, but surely that will be some special version of Windows that's free. Oh no, they're talking free upgrades from 8 and 7
Yeah, I don't think in their cash cow is enterprise, isn't it?
With all of the extra enterprise services and surely they can continue to charge for that. To Wimpy's point, it's gonna got no business
Yeah, it's gonna be like a not necessary probably not as limited as a starter edition
But I there must I mean there must be some restrictions in order to get enterprise to pay. I
I don't know. Were you gonna say something rotten?
I was gonna say that Windows 10 home sounds like it'd be free
But they're like the like the pro version would be the expense
Yeah, I could totally see that and Windows and probably for most consumers. It'd be fine. I
Don't like it
They rip us off and then they make it free
They rip off the ideas of comp is and and and desktop management and and all this crap
And then they also rip off the whole pricing structure. It's damn it. I just don't like it at all
Oh, but are there Windows wobbly?
You can probably edit the registry to make it happen man
Right exactly good old start menu say stop
Hey, why don't we do one more bit of follow-up
So a big thank you to Gabriel 3 in the subreddit who's been a very active poster in there recently with some really great content
Especially for those of you trying out open SUSE
So Gabriel mentions that we covered the sync thing GTK front-end on the Linux action show this Sunday and since then there's actually been
some updates and he points us to the web update article web updates really been doing a great job of following the sink thing project and
They do a great job of breaking some of this out for those of you who maybe aren't familiar with this sink thing and you
might have heard of pulse there
Now two different sink solutions that are similar to Dropbox or bit torrent sink or a sparkle share. It's totally open
It has a really interesting trust model, which works really well if you're just thinking
From you know in between some of your machines and now there's a GTK front-end
It's under heavy development, and there's in a couple of weeks
There's been a several updates and now has an auto updater for the by for the binary of the daemon
Which is really cool?
It's not enabled by default on Linux
But web update will tell you how to turn it on a link to that in the show notes and now as a first time
Run wizard to help get you all set up
And what directories you want to point at speed throttling options are now exposed through the notification icon menu
And I thought this was kind of neat
It's doing it's doing and I talked about this on the next action show
but it's actually using the file system io notify to know when files have been changed and then
Making sure they get synced up which is just nice and slick and integrated
So I'm the reason why I'm talking more about sink thing these days is I think people are getting more and more upset with bit
Torrent sink, and I just want to make sure people are aware of a free alternative in every sense of that term free
That's out there, and now it's nice to see it getting a GTK front-end and web update is
Linking you right here to the PPA if you're on an Ubuntu install, and it's also available in a you are
Looking good. I don't know if I'm gonna switch yet, but it's looking good. I'm I'm I don't know why I'm so gun-shy about it
I'm becoming an old man young Chris young Chris would just jump whole hog and you know part of it is
I don't know if you guys saw this but
a spider oak had a one terabyte deal for cyber Monday and
And I grabbed that because it was a great one terabyte storage deal for spider oak
Some kind of I don't know probably have a spider oak is the clients not it's not my favorite
yes, true sink thing is called sink thing GTK and
You just need Python and GTK on your system, and you can start playing with it if you haven't switched anything yet
Check out sink thing. I think it's the one to get behind for a little while
At least for most of us Linux users unless you need to distribute publicly then you might want to look at bit torrent sink
Hey, I'll tell you about something else. You might want to look at for a little bit
That's our first sponsor this week, and that's Linux Academy
It's Linux courses created by people that truly understand you and Linux because they're Linux users themselves
And I think we all know the difference that can make I'm I'm gonna recommend you do something
Just take a minute and go over to Linux Academy right now in fact if you go to Linux Academy
Check out their tour. They have a tour of all of their great features, but go to linuxacademy.com
Slash unplug start there linuxacademy.com slash unplugged it's gonna get you a 33% discount take a look at some of their training courses
They've got everything and I've been hearing from some of you who've been signing up and trying out different things stuff
I never even think to mention they have I think a good one and
If I ever if I ever get around to actually hosting all of my config files on my own git lab server
This course that they have on git basics and all of the introduction to git installing and configuring git
Working with github or git lab
Working with Atlassian or bitbucket just so I have I like this just so I have an idea of
What the alternatives would be like like that is super valuable for me?
And it's so nice to know that Linux Academy's just got this content available
It's part of my subscription and I get access to it
So when I get around to finally getting like my home director whatever
A great sync solution I get or maybe it's our publishing system for Jupiter broadcasting. They stick up on a git lab server
I'm gonna want to make sure I take this course and it's like that for everything Linux Academy has seven plus Linux distributions
You get to pick from and then they automatically adjust the courseware. So that way it reflects the distribution you've chosen
They have on-demand training you go in there and say I need a learning plan for this amount of
Availability and it will custom build that training for you
It'll give you the timeline the estimates if you're at work and you know down the road boy
2015 is finally the year we're gonna get off our butt and get puppet implemented. We're gonna finally do this, right?
Well, why not use that this time now to go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and take their puppet training
It's a great opportunity to sort of get in there do their scenario based training use their automatically generated VMs that go along with
The courseware you get public access to those. It's so neat
You get to keep track of your progress as you go along to give you a good visualization and display
So you get a really good sense of where you're at
You can get exactly how much time it's gonna take if you need to expand out to AWS for some scaling or something
You might want to load on there. You can go take all of the courseware available on AWS
They have a bunch of courseware on OpenStack if you find yourself in that gray area of DevOps that I like to tease people about
But it's a real thing, you know
It's something you find you kind of sometimes you go into a job this DevOps and sometimes you realize your job is DevOps
It can go both ways and Linux Academy has you covered. It's so great. They also have team accounts for groups
So if you're part of a team or a small business or even a large business and you want to all work together
They've got that they have a community support infrastructure to give you that motivation you need and they're always adding new labs two to
Three a week at this rate. It's really awesome
And I think the scenario based training is not only unique to Linux Academy because you'll work with all of these technologies. Let's
Take anything for example
You know, maybe it's an implementation of nginx. Maybe it's an AWS implementation
But the great thing is with these scenario based trainings
You'll actually use the technology you're going to be supporting the technology
You're going to be responsible for the technology. You're going to be on the line for what Linux Academy. You'll actually do it
You'll implement it
That's the kind of confidence that you can't just go out and get you have to use somebody who you have to go with
With a training platform
You have to work with with a group that really knows this stuff that knows the scenario you should be building out and that it
Actually is one that you would face in the real world that difference
That's Linux Academy and you can take advantage of by going to linux academy.com slash unplugged
It supports this show and it also helps you get ahead
It's a great way to bump up that resume fill some time or even just challenge yourself Linux academy.com slash unplugged
They've got courses on pretty much everything if you're just if you're if you're not really sure where to start
Why not go in there and scratch an inch?
Maybe this is the time to finally make that backup solution for your photos holidays are coming up
You're gonna be snapping a lot of pictures
Wouldn't be great going to know in going into that to know that you could create your own backup solution for that
They've got coursewares on that. It's really
It's so much opportunity and they're always adding new stuff
Linux academy.com slash unplugged and a big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring Linux unplugged programs you guys
Rockstars over there. I can't believe how hard they work and make me look like a slacker. I don't even like
Okay, just we'll get a cup before we bring Todd on from purism
I just want to get to a couple of more emails
Just so we can get through these because I feel bad when we don't get to all the emails
And this next one is a perspective that it's hard for us to sometimes take on the show and yes
I know we talked about system D a lot, but I think we should make a little more space up for it considering that on Sundays
Linux action show it's gonna be a lot of positive stuff because we interviewed Lenart Pottering about among a many many things
System D and we're gonna hear a lot of his side of the story. So mr. P writes in from the slackware side of the camp
He says hey Chris and the rest of the crew. Thanks for all the hard work on the shows. I'm a slack wear user
since
1995 both private and in my daily work. He says I'm a programmer for an embedded Linux and I do some system administration
I've listened about all of the talk regarding system D and I'd like you to address part of this discussion. That's missing
We don't use system D in slackware
The big problem for us in slackware is that many packages nowadays are requiring system D to be able to build or to run
The tone in the slack or community is respectful towards system D
But it's hard for us to see the impact on all 30 on all third-party applications
And I think by that he means it's hard for us to see this when we don't use system D
But yet these requirements are coming up when I listen to you on air
It seems like you're surrounded by only pro system D people regards Pierre or para. I'm not I'm not sure so I
Wanted to give I wanted to open the floor to anybody in the mumba room that has some concerns about system D
Maybe we could just have an open discussion about them. I don't know if we have anybody
I think Fred was our biggest of vocal anti system D user last week
Is anybody in the mumba room have concerns about system? Do they want a voice?
It's an open. It's not lower
Not really. I think this might be an opportunity for us to try and get one of the one guys
Yeah, he mr. P recommended somebody from slackware that we could bring on and I'm gonna forward that in contact input of the production staff
so
Here's what I'm trying to get to here's why I asked you guys because we have it
we don't we have a good sized room here and
You know, I I suspect that the reason why there's not a lot of anti system D commentary on this show is
I think it's reflective of the overall opinion
I think a lot of us maybe have concerns, but we also see that it's sort of a competitiveness necessity for Linux
Wimpy you say you you might have some concerns. What would those be?
Well, yeah, I mean in general I'm very supportive of system D and I think it's a good thing, but my one concern about system
D is
scope creep
it doesn't seem to have a well-defined road map of where it's heading and
New facilities and features seem to be blossoming
into the system did yeah and
Isn't clear where where the edges of that project are right? Well, I think you know
It's not to speak for Lenart, but I think he would define it as
Anything that kind of sits between user land and kernel could be fair game
And and it's quite a big stretch of land. Yes, it is, isn't it?
Yeah, it is it is a very big stretch of land and
I'm trying to think of like how other operating systems do it and I'm you know
When I think of the commercial OS is like when I think of Windows
Windows has what comes to my mind and maybe this isn't a fair parallel
But Windows has a SVC host right SVS host am I getting that right?
Which is this huge parent process that controls?
Ungodly amounts of things and I it is totally opaque to me. I have no idea what it does now
Here's the thing about now. Here's my response to what you're saying wimpy is
The way system D is going about and replacing these individual bits of functionality like take NTP for example, right?
It's doing it with individual programs. It's not like it's all
There's not a system D binary right that it has all this code in it
It is individual programs that are part of the system D project
But they are they are broken out in in small bits of functionality
Which I think a makes it easier to kind of it gives you insight because you can see the tool
B it makes it easier to replace just that component if you replace it with something else, right?
Because it's just this NTP piece. I have to replace or just this DG DHCP client piece
I have to repeat replace. It's not the whole system D binary. So I
Agree that that is a problem
But I think the balance of system D strikes by replacing it with individual small tools
That just happen to all communicate really well to each other
Is a pretty reasonable approach to that and I think too like you have to look at some of the things that have been replaced
And be honest and say, you know, some of these things were kind of neglected, right?
And not in all cases, but in some cases, they were just kind of a hot mess that were neglected
Yeah, I
Appreciate how system D is put together and that everything isn't lumped in together in one binary and there is a set of tools
And I don't thinking about it. I don't think there's anything that's been added to system day that I haven't found useful or
Can see a rationale for?
My concern is more looking into the future
Where will it continue to grow and what will the scope of the project become because that isn't that isn't clear?
Nobody knows right dare Devlin. Do you believe that system D taking over these more and more functionalities?
Actually will make for a more nimble Linux system
Yeah, I
Think it's the closeness is actually something that I feel that we're missing other departments as well. Actually
What do you mean as things that actually go and talk to each other but are being developed in this?
widespread
Multiple repos pretty much it's all over and I
Think the closeness that the system deep project made for the multiple programs is essential to actually
Keep the projects in check and actually in pair with each other
Mm-hmm, although I do kind of also agree with what peacemaker is saying in that
It doesn't leave a lot of rooms for distros like slackware or gentoo or or any of the others dev one that
Don't want anything to do a system deal. Like there's not a lot of air left in the room
So that is a difficult thing because I think we I think most of us would agree monoculture is bad
even if the monoculture is made up of a lot of little bits, so I
I think these can so one of the things that I maybe well then we'll move on because I we've touched on enough but
one of the things that I think we forget is
That the future is changeable
And if we get to a point in the future where there is a big downside to going with system D
The open source community will write itself
It will it will write that ship and it will make a course correction and it's the future is not set in stone
So if a lot of input a lot of things today are written for system D
That does not mean that in five years. Everything is going to depend on system D
It it might mean that we go through a period of time
Where a lot of things but you know what?
We went through a period of time where a lot of things were written for ulcer and now a lot of things are written for
Pulse, right? It just changes things happen and technology is fundamentally changeable and
especially
especially open source software like like I I totally legit get the concern if this was Windows or Mac OS X and it was
Happening happening behind closed doors and we as a community could do nothing about it
But anyone can write code anyone can write a patch and it just takes one person to start a change
We are not under the same constraints. We would be in a totally proprietary commercial system
But yet I feel like our reaction here is like the future is set in stone if we make this decision
Everything is ruined. We can never write the ship it but that's that's that's totally opposite of how open source works
So for me, it's like I I totally respect like god
It does suck that the slack where project is getting the air sucked out of the room then again
It doesn't mean there will always be no air in the room
There could be air that comes back in the future and it's not it
It's just we should move forward
And I'll just leave it at that and it with the interview with Lenart goes into some detail about this
I think it's a good pre setup for that
so if this topic interests you at all or any of the
community trolling topics or future of software distribution on Linux and how that might be
Accomplished all of those were covered in the interview with Lenart and that'll be in Sunday's Linux action show
So far, that's what we have. That's when we have a scheduled to air
so hopefully we can just sort of air that and and I totally I'm still willing to take input and and
Talk about the topic, but also I have to respect if the audience is done with done with it
I don't want to dwell on it
but I find it to be a fascinating change and
there was an article that I talked about the Linux action show about how net BSD community reacted to the same kind of thing 14
Years ago and it does really feel a lot like history kind of repeating itself
Just you know, a lot of us don't remember there was a huge debate over X, right?
There's a lot of things that have happened in the community that have kind of gone by the wayside now
There was a huge debate over not as big as system D but over a gel a GILX or XGL
For composited desktops and we don't even use either of those anymore and there was a big debate about it
So the future is not fixed that that would be that would be my my ending piece for our system to discussion
All right, so we're gonna talk to Todd here in just a second
Why don't I do one more sponsor break and then we'll bring Todd in and it's kind of a special a special sponsor break
So everybody knows ting we love ting go to linux.ting.com. You're gonna get a $25 discount off
Your first device ting is mobile that makes sense and Matt and I have been using ting for cheese man almost two years now
Wow already good grief
It is nuts and I got some I got some stats
Right here from ting about the Jupiter broadcasting audience that I thought I'd share as we as we approach our second year
So the average bill for Linux action show audience members and the Linux unplugged and any JB audience member
That has one device the average monthly bill
$26 whoa now
Let that sit for a second. This is a full-featured smartphone. You only pay for what you use. There's no contract nor the termination fee
$26 is the average Jupiter broadcasting audience members monthly bill now
What are you paying today for your cell phone bill? Is it more than $26?
Do you have a contract on top of that go to linux.ting.com, but?
Now right now is truly the best time to ever switch to ting if you've been thinking about it
So you you've probably heard me mention that ting has an early termination relief program
And they're gonna give you 25% of the ETF which is you know about $75
So if you figure the average bill is $26, and you're gonna get a $75 credit
That's almost three months of free ting service. That's a really good deal. Yeah, that would be I would I would take that deal
But ting is upping the game for a little while until January 5th
They're gonna take that ETF relief program, and they're gonna make it 50%
They're gonna give you a hundred and fifty dollars in maximum credit when you switch to ting if you have a contract right now
So noodle this over
You go to linux.ting.com you're gonna get a $25 service credit if you bring a device
Or you get $25 off your first device if you don't have one you bring a device
You're gonna get $25 of credit if you have a contract to terminate you're gonna get another
$150 in credit that means you get a max of
$175 in ting credits just by going to linux.ting.com and by taking advantage of the early termination relief program
$175 in service credits for no contract
Only paying for what you use just your minutes your messages and your megabytes plus the flat $6 for the phone
No hold customer service their incredible dashboard
full access to your phone
Great community if you want to run one of the alternative operating systems like Ubuntu touch sailfish OS or Firefox OS they have an active
enthusiastic community around that
And you could turn it on right now
You don't have to call anybody if you don't want you can use their web interface you can get up to $175 in credit now
If you go to linux.ting.com you don't have a contract you're still gonna get our $25 service credit
Which will still get you probably more than your first month
this is such a great time and
If I were you and by the way if you want to read more about it for yourself
You can go to their blog
They've got all the details up on their blog like they always do ting is super great about that
It's really easy to track what this company's up to because they they're really transparent
They put it all up there
And you can read it through it and you can it's such a great way to get your mind around what this company's about
But check this out. I think one of the best smartphones ever made
The HTC one the m7 with those awesome front-facing speakers, which are amazing for podcast listening
You can own it outright three hundred and forty dollars from ting right now. No contract
$340 and you only pay for what you use that is the with this phone
So I don't I don't have like Bluetooth in my truck. I don't have like an aux in Jack in my truck
I don't but I don't listen to the radio
I only listen to podcasts when I drive and I use this phone I did with these front-facing speakers
I didn't need a soundbar now that I have my Nexus 5 I'm back on a Bluetooth soundbar
This I this is the phone like this is the one that got away. I gave it to Rekai. I
Gave it to Rekai's got my HTC one and I I I covet it and you can get it now for three hundred and forty dollars
Go to linux.ting.com. They'll give you a $25 discount on that device if you have a contract you need to terminate
They're gonna pay more than they've ever paid until January this only good till January 5th, so why not do it now
I get it in this year, right
$75 used to be the old deal
Now now there's no $150 if you got if you have a contract you got to go and then your contract free you can turn
On hotspot tethering when you need it. It's so slick linux.ting.com
Seriously do Chris us all go get yourself treat yourself. It's the holiday season the HTC one. It's the Cadillac
I mean the M8s they have the M8 too. I think it's more probably I who needs it
This is such an amazing phone the HTC one m7 three hundred forty dollars
Linux dot ting comm and a huge thank you to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged you guys are crushing it for the holiday season
Just a great opportunity to if you wanted to give somebody a phone and then not have to stick them to a contract
Ting's a great way to go
You avoid that nastiness well
Matt let's well. Let's welcome Todd on the show
Todd is from purism, and they are currently crowdfunding the Librem 15 a
Free Libre software laptop that respects your essential freedoms, and I've crowdfunded it. It's currently
29 days left on the crowdfunding effort. They've raised
$41,000 with a goal of
$250,000 and Todd welcome to Linux unplugged why don't you start by telling us?
Why are you doing a crowdfunding campaign for a Linux laptop? What's the goal here?
Yeah, well, thanks for having me on and
So what we're doing is we are clearly crowdfunding to reach a minimum order quantity to manufacture a motherboard that has
the best
free software support
on any laptop
So this quantity of two of two hundred fifty thousand dollars is essentially to meet the obligations of a custom motherboard
That's correct. Yeah, and actually the way that that typically works when you manufacture motherboard is you're talking about minimum order quantities of 5,000
What we've done is worked with the manufacturer of the motherboard to pay to prepay the NRE fees
So that we can get a small enough order quantity in
So that way we can do a smaller a smaller run of units
So that's why we can actually do it for just a quarter of a million dollars as opposed to what's typically a five million dollar
a
Minimum order quantity so Todd you you you pitched the Librem 15 as the first high-end laptop that ships without any mystery software and
That obviously resonated pretty well with me. I like the look of it. It's it's a metal housing. Is it aluminum or is it plastic?
What is it? It's aluminum housing. Well, it looks really sharp and it's got a
decent range of specs
And it ships currently with Triskel is the distribution of choice, right? So if it doesn't
Okay
So I the first thing that jumped out of me and we can get into this maybe because I think this is probably the biggest
questions on people's minds is
It sort of struck me a little bit as Google's don't be evil
Slogan where as soon as you say it, right then everybody's looking for every little evil thing you do
So in this one, you know, you sort of pitched it as the totally free Libre laptop
But there's an asterisk in this sense that it does ship with a BIOS that does require a binary blob
Can you tell us a little bit about that?
Yeah, correct. So it's something that we try to be very clear about actually
so we put it right on the front page of and also the
Certification and pretty much everything we put out there is that we we have everything from the software on meaning bootloader the kernel
The entire operating system as well as all software as of course by running Triskel all software. We even install is
Free and we also promote free software by by doing so
The area that we want to free but is not currently freed is the BIOS
there's actually a binary the Intel FSP, which also includes the
Intel memory engine me
That is a binary provided from Intel and actually it's technically provided through a subcontractor of Intel
And what we want to do is have that freed
That is our goal and then we have a and that actually once we reach that goal
We would actually be able to get free software foundation respects your freedom
certification
But we want to go beyond that and actually certify and free firmware that actually goes into
The microcontrollers at the hardware level. So really what it comes down to for us is
We are as free as humanly possible right now, but we want to push upstream into the manufacturing which no one has done
to be able to free the
Microcontrollers as well as that bias. So that seems like a pretty ambitious goal. How how
realistic is a goal of that level of ambition for a
A company that's not the size of like an Apple or a Dell
I mean to be honest that seems almost like a fight that would be hard for an HP or Dell to win
So how does purism plan to win that battle to convince them to open these and free these? Yeah, so that's a that's a great question
So initially it's really it's about business negotiations
So initially those large companies like let's say Apple and Dell Apple and Dell have no incentive
Nor no belief system that will ever care to actually free anything upstream
so
When when we sit down at the table and negotiate with purchasing a hard drive or purchasing memory
Then we can the number one thing we're discussing is are you a company who's going to back providing us with your source?
under NDA or
where we can scrub it and release it or
providing that source under an acceptable license and then we will purchase from you or in some cases actually work with them to
Provide the documentation to the Linux kernel developers to
to free the
hardware, so it's really mostly about
That our number one topic when we're negotiating is is freeing the source code
So do you is it your observation now perhaps that perhaps other OEMs are not really concerned about this matter and not really pressuring
the manufacturers to do this
There's well Google clearly has and and they've actually made some decent progress on freeing the the BIOS
Working with core boot and a number of engineers who work for core boot. So that's
That's so Google is an exception to the rule clearly
They have other concerns for privacy and freedom
But as far as pushing upstream Google has actually made attempts to do so and and in some cases been
Has done quite well. The the main thing is that
There the push upstream has has really not gone all the way to the manufacturer who actually
Manufactures the actual microcontroller. It'll be to whomever's reselling it and then it'll kind of fall on deaf ears and not actually make it upstream
Enough. I see that makes sense. So the next thing that I think would probably jump out at the
sharp-eyed viewer is
It ships with an NVIDIA card now we are aware of the new driver
but tell me a little bit about the choice because if this is a custom motherboard that must have been an explicit choice on your
Part to include not just an Intel graphics, but also a separate NVIDIA chip
So why why include that when the Intel is there?
Yeah, it's funny. We had we had actually had an ongoing debate about this and
We could save about 75 bucks if we just throw out the NVIDIA chip
So it was a conscious decision to include it
which actually the debate was if we're going to include the hardware that can run with a
Free kernel level driver, but I also want to make it clear that if you even use the free kernel level driver
you're still loading a
binary from NVIDIA into the BIOS
So you actually be able to use it and you can look at the source of the nouveau driver to see that it makes a
lot of firmware calls
BIOS level calls, but so the important thing is that
by including both we can
honor our
purest beliefs that we
That you can run completely free software and just discard the NVIDIA, but those people who really want to include the NVIDIA
Have that option. So it's really more from a customization standpoint
But it was a debate that we went round and round
And one of the issues actually comes from the free software foundation, which is if you include hardware that
Requires or only operates it at full capacity
with a proprietary binary then it's not certifiable. So that was something we actually toyed around heavily with
the certification for free software foundation and
The end result was sort of it's not if so for somebody like me, you know
I think I I might not have been inclined to fund it if it didn't have the NVIDIA chip
So for me, it was I might not use the proprietary driver
But I'd like to know that in the future of my workload needs that I have it
How will that work for say this meets its goal and we get the funding? How will that work for me as an end user?
How do I switch between Intel and NVIDIA?
Well, it's actually called a hybrid so what I actually it's a NVIDIA 3d graphics controller
So what happens is when you're it boots and runs off of the Intel, but whenever it needs to access
3d acceleration then it uses the NVIDIA graphics so you can run full
The entire system off the Intel
And then use NVIDIA when needed you can't do it the other way around
You wouldn't be able to just use at least my understanding and our testing is that you would not be able to do that
And our testing is that you would not be able to just use NVIDIA
NVIDIA is added for the 3d control and you can see from
LSPCI output that you can actually tell that the 3d controllers on a separate PCI bus compared to the VGA. Okay, okay
Wow, so it it's it it does the driver stack handles live switching
So it sends what it sends open GL calls off to the NVIDIA chip and standard 2d calls off to the Intel chip
That's my understanding but that's actually outside of my range. I have to bring in a developer to explain more about them
Interesting though. So how are you feeling right now looking at the funding you guys have?
Let's see. I just said it but 29 days left. It is the holiday season. It's kind of probably a tough time to raise money
Do you how you feel about right right now 29 days in 16% funded?
Yeah, so, you know clearly what the the trending for most crowdfunding is
that you initially have a pretty good push and then it kind of plateaus for a while until the end because there's a lot of
People who will sign up for the mailing list or notify me when it's ending. So we're getting an awful lot of
interest
specifically with you know notify me as the as the days start to
Dwindle, but you're right in the fact that launching during this time was actually a tough decision for us
We we actually considered running it through the middle of January
Because
Getting after the holidays and people clearly aren't buying for themselves and this is going to ship in
You know end of March
April timeframe anyway, so we decided to go ahead with it now
because
Just the mostly trying to bring it to market the timing is right for our negotiations and trying to get some leverage with the manufacturers
So we decided to take that leap, but I feel really good right there right now
so
I guess kind of what I'm grokking from what you're telling me is
There's not really a straightforward way to do a custom-built for Linux laptop in a one two
Three four level quantity maybe one sale two sales three sales every day in order to have leverage with the manufacturer
You've got to be able to cut them a big fat check
And so that kind of does that is that dictating the crowd supply funding approach instead of just taking an order here and there as people
Want them?
That's exactly right so I mean clearly we can we can buy you know something off of the shelf
And then install Linux on it and ship it and then that's really what I consider the the old days of Linux
I actually want to change that in the sense that I want to push the GNU Linux system upstream where we're actually shipping it by default
Manufacturing it specifically for that
So to be able to do that. We can't just buy onesie-twosie
and if we did we could just launch it on our site and sell them you know one-offs the the point here is to see if
there's enough interest in
producing
Manufacturing and basically backing a company that wants to push the free software movement up into the manufacturing chain
so that we can design and manufacture and ship products that's
Specifically targeted towards this audience. Yeah, I mean that seems like a total catch-22 because to make this experience better
For future Linux laptops you have to have that initial leverage at the negotiation table to make it worth their time to go to the
trouble of freeing these binaries in this documentation and the source code up so
It seems to be a unique situation so why crowd supply versus something like Kickstarter?
I'm just curious because I see a lot of hardware open source hardware funded these days
And I'm seeing different sites use so what crowd supply offer that maybe a Kickstarter didn't well. There's a couple things
The first is actually I got to meet the founder of crowd supply and I was quite impressed with their capabilities
They also
Did back bunny bunnies novena project which I think is a great
Project clearly from a maker standpoint right where he actually manufactured the motherboard himself
That's fantastic. And so they had you know experience with
Supporting the free and open source world and they also actually have worked with the free software foundation through my introduction actually to
Make sure that people can buy with without JavaScript enabled. So they're going to become the first free
software and foundation endorsed
Crowdfunding website. So that's great. That's also great in my mind
So those are those are a couple decisions why we went with crowd supply over anything else. So
Todd give us a little bit of your background. Have you been involved in free and open source software for a while?
Yeah, I've been
ever since
Debian
0.2 days so about
1994 been a Debian developer
I was actually a Debian developer before it took arm and a leg to become a Debian developer and then
since fell out of that and
I've been installing Debian forever
Over a hundred thousand units installed when I saw when I was system architects at a couple different companies
I'd use fully automated installation to
build deploy
Debian based multimedia services or
Audio based services. So if you go into most retailers, you'll go into and you'll hear their audio over the
in the store and that'll run a system that's
60% of them are going to be a system that I was a system architect on which are all going to be a Debian based
multimedia system
Very cool. That's a pretty big runs Linux and I I suppose then have you is is this in some way?
I'm imagining you're probably a bit like me where you finally been like none of these laptops have satisfied me and I've
Found myself to be pretty happy with a certain subset of laptops
I'm mostly one of our sponsor system 76 makes some great laptops that run Linux really well
But when I go out in the market and I look out I look for laptops that are custom-built for Linux
There's there's not a lot out there
There's plenty of room left in the market and something that's metal and really tightly will belt will well built
I often will look over the Macbooks and go man. If those could flawlessly run Linux I would consider it
But until that day it's not for me
So I always felt like I've kind of been in this zone of searching and never really found the perfect solution for me personally
So is that what sort of motivated you to start this project?
That actually it's interesting. I mean I might as well have recorded that and played it back
That's that is one of the driving forces of why I formed purism is for four decades
Well, maybe not decades, but over a decade
I have been hunting for you know every year right or every year and a half or so getting a nude laptop
Where I bought from I think penguin I bought from the system 76
and
You know I've always liked the fact that what they believe in and what they promote has been great the laptops themselves arrive
And you know they are
off the shelf
products that can be purchased in ones or order quantities of ten usually and then
Stripped installed Linux and delivered it so I've never really been
Perfect you know really satisfied, and I think to your point is you know I have for one consulting gig
They ship me a Macbook Pro
And I really like the hardware
I you know I thought it was it was well-built it clearly would last and so for me
I wanted to get something that was custom built for specifically for GNU Linux where all the chips would work
without any binaries and and then just decided to
If no one else had done it that I might as well be the one yeah, I could I could understand that well
So in my room if you guys have any questions go ahead and speak up
But Todd I I would I'll have a link in the show notes, and I would encourage people to go check it out
So it one last question say yeah, this makes its funding. Can I put more than eight gigabytes of RAM?
What's the limitation because I see right now in the drop-down?
It's eight gigs is that a physical limitation
Or is that just the specs you've offered like can I put up to 32 gigs or give me an idea of like the expandability in
This thing that's that is our number one question, so
So right now we actually are going back to our reference design to actually increase that to 32
It is a physical limitation right now in our design. However, that is something we can change the issue actually it comes down to
The space within it
So what we're doing is we might end up having to do something where you can go with a secondary solid-state drive in the in the
CD-rom DVD-rom drive bay and then be able to expand your memory
So we're basically looking within you know trying not to because I can't change the case right so I'm looking at
ways in which we can fit
More memory within the same footprint sure and you know what as somebody who I've bought a few CD-ROMs recently
Are my more recent purchases and haven't used them like once I used them like the for the first time this last weekend
So I would totally take that offer that off
Yes, we end up when we have that offer now you can swap the CD DVD for a second bay of solid-state driver
Or hard drive if you want, but the so the issue ends up being clearly a drive is
Smaller in footprint so we can end up it would be almost it would be a requirement
Potentially a requirement to drop the DVD and go with an extra RAM
but we're still toying with that and we'll update the the
Project page once we get the confirmation to be able to go up as much but a lot of people like on the cubes OS
Are they really want to have more than 8 gig because for running VM software? It's you know you need to have a lot more
RAM
Alright, that was all of my questions wimpy. I know you had one that'll probably be of interest to the audience go ahead
Yeah, so you already spoke about the FSS certification
And I wondered if you might try and find out if they're going to be flexible on that if you can run the laptop in
Say an Intel GPU only mode and therefore you're unlocking the full potential of what that
Configuration is capable of if they may endorse or certify the the laptop
Yeah, actually the that is that would happen the the hang-up with the free software foundation certification is actually the BIOS binary
the Intel FSP or Intel me
That binary is the one that is the we have to free that
Which we're working towards we have a couple of avenues to produce a free
Completely free BIOS so we use core boot, but we'd have to still use this Intel FSP binary inside of core boot to
Actually boot the machine
It's and it's a long-sorted story of what as as you know
It's moved out of the kernel and more and more into the BIOS level for these controls
So to answer your question directly the free software foundation
The main blocker for us getting the respects your freedom
Certification is the Intel BIOS to free the BIOS. It is not
Having a secondary video card that is
Available to use as a binary. We're with a binary
That makes sense. So I think the other this is a common question
I see it right now in the chat room and I've seen it when I covered it before
I don't actually hold this opinion
but I think a lot of people think it's
Expensive for the specs and I'm thinking that might be due to the quantities or the scale of the build
Do you want to touch on the pricing and out and why it is the price that it is?
Yeah, it's I mean clearly I'd love to sell it for 200 bucks
I could but the the issue is exactly to describe when when we're talking about manufacturing a motherboard
we have a minimum order quantity to be able to
to
Place that order to actually have the motherboard manufactured. It's all about the tooling
So we paid an NRE fee to get it down from a 5,000 unit order to really in the few hundreds
So what of course that means is that our per unit cost has to go up
And so we're taking us
We have the belief that people will back
The business because of the belief system and what we're trying to do and understand that it's a short-term
a
Larger price tag to be able to get to a completely free manufactured
Device later with the lower price tag when we can actually order it in larger volumes
So if we were to be able to place an order for 5,000 units, then we could actually have that price probably cut at least
At least it would be it'd be close to a half the price Wow. Well that makes sense, too
I mean, it's that's sort of just the dynamics of the market
So Todd, I really do wish you the best luck and you guys can go to crowd supply.com
And look for the Librem 15 from purism and we'll have a link in the show notes
You can go directly to it
And if you all go back at then I'll probably get mine and then I'll give you a review on the Linux action show
But Todd you are welcome to stick around
well, we're gonna continue on with the show and I wish you the best of luck and I
Hope I get mine in around March or April timeframe. That'd be really cool. Hey, thanks so much for having me
So we're gonna I want to talk about
Something the core OS project is doing and I want to break it down because I think it's huge
And I think it's super necessary and it's already been piled on by the free software press
That's not that's not even a thing by the people who pretend to be press of the free software movement
They've already called it the container war
Battle I'm gonna tell you what's really going on
We're gonna break it down for you guys and it's actually a really really good thing
But first I got to tell you about a really great thing
That's digital ocean head over to digital ocean comm right now and go get yourself your own simple cloud server
Digital ocean is dedicated to offering the most intuitive an easy way for you to spin up your own
Server and you can probably do so in less than 55 seconds pricing plan start at only five dollars
That'll get you 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer
It's awesome because digital ocean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam and London
I got an email from my listener Patrick today, and he's like Chris
You've taught you've talked a lot about things you use your digital ocean droplet for but have you ever considered the fact that five
Dollars a month is cheaper than most any really good minecraft hosting solution out there and with digital ocean
Not only do you get the ability to host your own minecraft server?
But you get the snapshots and the backup and the templates right and it's of course minecrafts one example
It could be wordpress gitlab doesn't matter bit torrent sync sync thing
Why not roll your own sync thing solution and the digital ocean droplet could be the off-site cloud storage?
You know you don't need anything else
But it's really about the interface. This is kind of why I think digital ocean
They sort of broke through the barrier when it came to making this something that's accessible to anybody like you know you can be
A 15 year server admin you could be a 10 minute server admin, and you're going to find the digital ocean dashboard is amazing
It's intuitive and power user can replicate it on a larger scale with a straightforward api and for
Me I can't use that api I couldn't I couldn't use an api to save my life like I could look at him
Oh, so that's how you do that, but to actually use it no now
I know for a lot of you out there your roll in your eyes and like oh Chris
You're such an old man, and that's great because it's then you can take advantage of it today
But for me I take advantage of all the awesome community resources built around that api
There's applets for your linux desktop. There's ways to snap it in with your existing management infrastructure command lines
It's so cool, and one of the things that we love about digital ocean you can go over there
And you can apply our discount to your balance
This is a great way if you forgot to use it when you signed up now
We're doing the transition between months right now, so we have two promo codes right now
I know that unplug November works for you
So you can go over there and use the promo code unplug November and get a ten dollar credit
Then you can try out the five dollar rig for two months for absolutely for nothing for free, but it turns out
It's December so unplug December is probably going to start working later this afternoon
And you can go over there and use that as well and get the ten dollar credit go check it out
Really if you're even a casual linux user
This is such a fun experience and since you get it for free
Why not just try it for a little month for a couple of months and just play with it. It's so neat
I have right now. I have my Quasals core up there and one of the things that turns turns out didn't know this about Quasal
But when you're in all these chat rooms logging all the time that database
Gets big like eight gigabytes big
And if I didn't have that sucker sitting on an SSD drive
I I would be in a world of hurt every time I go to open up my IRC client
But because digital ocean has incredible bandwidth speeds has those SSD drives when I open up my IRC clients boom it all gets pushed down
To me it's amazing the amount of transfer. I get and it's all I get to a terabyte for free
And then digital ocean has easy step plans to upgrade to the pricing in fact
They have it all listed out on their site. You just click that pricing tab, and it's really straightforward and the other thing that's cool
Hourly pricing you know like your favorite hotel
They have hourly pricing over digital oceans if you need to scale for a little while you're doing a big deployment something like that
You can spin up a server and then shut it down when you're done and digital oceans up in the game on the tutorials for
The community in fact Patrick who sent in the email about his minecraft server
used a digital ocean community tutorial to set up that minecraft server and this what's neat is they realize this is a
Massive advantage that they have over their competition so instead of just sitting there and just kind of sitting back and be like oh yeah
Everybody write it in no
They're actually gonna pay you and they're gonna have editing staff that's gonna work with you you can earn up to
$200 to write a tutorial for digital ocean now if you are a Linux geek
And you know how to set something up like a frickin minecraft server why not go make $200 seriously now somebody already took that one
But there's hundreds of other topics you could write and work with their staff
digital ocean comm unplug November to get that ten dollar dollar credit try out that five dollar dollar rig for two months for
Absolutely free so freaking cool. It is the coolest thing ever seriously as somebody who's worked in IT for 15 years
When I see this, I'm sorry. I cannot help but geek out today after all of this time
I've been using digital ocean for months and months and months. I still sit down. I think
The holy smokes this is crazy cool the fact that they saw the potential behind SSD when nobody would touch SSD because of the cost
The fact that they saw that KVM was an awesome
Virtualization platform before anybody else saw it and then they build it all on top of Linux and they integrate with core OS
They're all about that Docker one-click deployments. It's so slick
It's such a good system and on top of all of that you get the satisfaction of supporting your favorite podcast network
Digital ocean comm use the promo code unplug November
Seriously go see what I've been talking about and a huge. Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplugged
Alright, Matt. I don't know if you saw the big hoopla
But you know dockers all the rage these days everybody's talking about Docker right well core OS wants to talk about rocket
Mm-hmm wimpy did you see the announcement about rocket I?
Have not no all right all right good. I'm gonna teach you something today wimpy so buckle up here we go
I am super excited about rocket so you put your pants on the outside of your trousers now my pajamas
The fact he's wearing pants at all is just like it. No. I'm just keep in mind his pajamas. Let's not get crazy
All right, so you if you listen depending on who you read like the register
I apparently a new Linux container war has begun. That's crap right. That's that's total crap first of all
I want to set something up right up front
Core OS is not moving away from Docker Docker will continue to ship in core OS and be well supported
And I want to give you the recap because the core OS guys which who we've interviewed on Linux action show I
Tried to talk to Mark Shuttleworth about it last week
And he very quickly changed the topic which to me was
Maybe an indicator that he's a he's aware of the heat that core OS is bringing. There's already major clients
Enterprise great clients that use core OS the whole idea behind core OS right is you you isolate out a lot of the
Applications and the server services into containers, and then you just roll that base, baby
You get that open SSL patch you get that shell shock that you patch patch patch mother because you know what all the maps are
In containers, and it's safe well. That's the idea, but the problem is and this is something that's been bothering me for a while
Docker has gotten big, and I don't mean like big code wise I mean big like
publicity wise big company wise big
Contracts wise and docker is expanding out way way beyond the original vision right it's a whole platform docker is not a
Container anymore docker is a platform of services in which container ization is one of those things
So that's where core OS picks up
They say when docker was first introduced in
Early 2013 the idea of a standard container was striking and immediately attractive a simple component a composable unit
That could be used on a variety of systems the docker repository included a manifesto of what a standard container should be
This was a rally cry to the industry and we quickly followed Brandon Phillips the co-founder and CTO of core
West became a top contributor to the docker project
He now serves on the docker board the governance board
We thought docker would become a simple unit that we could all agree on
Unfortunately a simple reusable component is not how things played out docker is now building tools for launching cloud services
Systems for clustering and a wide range of functions from functions from building images to running images uploading downloading and eventually even overlaying networking
All compiled into one monolithic binary running as root on your server the standard container manifesto was removed
We should really stop talking about docker containers and start talking about the docker platform
It's not becoming a simple composable building block. We had envisioned so they're introducing rocket
We still believe in the original premise of containers that docker introduced
So we're going to do something about it while we're at it
We're cleaning up and fixing a few things we'd like to see in a production ready container
And the things that they lay out here are things that have fundamentally bothered me about docker. I am a huge supporter of docker
I think it's great. I think it continues to be great, but a few things have bothered me
Isolation should be pluggable and the crypto primitives first trust should be strong image auditing and application identity
Need to exist from day one ie
Signed containers signed applications so that way when you get them distributed to you
You know they are legitimate from the original source that you expect them image distribution now
The docker hub is neat because you can check in something like smoke ping
Check it up to the docker hub and anybody can check it out boy
That's great, but the problem is it's centralized right? It's an open source thing. That's centralized well
We know what happens when you centralized things
Core OS thinks that discovery of container images should be simple and they should have a
facilitated by a federated
Namespace
So you can do distributed retrieval this opens up the possibility for alternative protocols to distribute these images
potentially like bit torrent and
Deployments inside private environments without the need of an external registry like the docker hub
That's a huge one for me also
They believe the format and runtime should be well specified and developed by an open community with implementations and tools that can run
The same container consistently across different platforms rocket is what they're introducing
It's a command-line tool for running app containers an app container is a specification of an image format container runtime and discovery mechanism
So it's an app container tells you what it is
What the runtime stuff is you need and how you get this container?
That's what an app container is rocket is the first implementation of an app container and they expect there'll be other ones
And all of this information is linked up in the show notes, but they they have a fact that I think I want to cover
They say here. Why are you doing this now?
They say at Core OS we have a large serious
users in enterprise environments
And we cannot in good faith continue to support docker's broken security model without addressing these issues
This is something we've talked about on tech snap on several episodes of tech snap
There is fundamentally some issues with the docker security model
And rocket plans to address those they go on to say will core OS continue to ship docker. Yes period
We will continue to make sure core OS is the best place to run docker. So this is
Not exactly a war so much as a fundamental
Divergence of how container technology on linux should work
Now the docker project very quickly posted a follow-up
There's a lot in this, but I highlighted a few important areas
They say while docker continues to define a single container format
It's clear that our users and the vast majority of contributors and vendors want docker to enable the distributed applications
Consisting of multiple discrete containers running across multiple hosts and I in other words some of the things we're doing is
Because people want us to do them
We think it should it we think it would be a shame if the clean open interfaces and anywhere portability and robust set of
Ecosystem tools that exist for a single docker container applications were lost if we went to a world of multiple containers and distributed
Applications they say we'll provide more detail at dockercon conference this week in amsterdam
they go on to say we are committed to an ecosystem of users vendors and contributors whether people add value in the form of
contributions to docker as independent projects that build on the docker container format or as plug-ins to the docker orchestration api's
Or otherwise we hope that the open layered approach
Provides the best options for all so docker says we are an open layered approach. Yes
We have some bits and components here that we keep secret sauce
But we have open governance
But we have open governance. They say in some cases of course there are technical or Phil's
Philosophical differences that appears to be the case with the recent announcement of rocket we hope to address some of these technical arguments
posed by the rocket project in a subsequent post so more to come
Now I thought it was interesting. I this is some of you might not care at all
But what I found to be interesting is two things
Containers obviously a huge deal not new to linux
Not new to operating systems in general, but there's a lot of heat around them right now
I think that's undeniable you can look at the billions in funding that docker has gotten or I think it's a billion now
you can look at the massive pickup that a
Freshman project like core os has seen because it's based around containers
Red Hat Enterprise 7 kind of I think some could argue rushed to implement docker support because it was such a talked about feature
The largest enterprise linux distribution in the world the top granddad of enterprise linux issues that everybody recognized. Oh, it's right
Oh, it's right. That's right
They rushed to ship docker support because they felt the pressure to be hip and modern and have docker in there right so to have
To have core os one of the biggest contributors to docker
Come along and announce something else
People have reacted kind of strongly to this and matt you can probably guess some people have thrown their arms up in the air
And said oh, this is the problem with linux
Everything's always forking it yeah, it's like fork this fork that fork everyone
You know and I think that's kind of the attitude that comes to what kind of dwelled out of this whole thing
But I think I think they're actually I think rocket is actually going to address some serious competitive
I think it's going to bring some serious competitiveness to docker
I think it's like it's addressing issues that I've watched docker
Go from this is a really great way to make sure this application runs the same exact way on any distribution to
The docker platform, which is this is huge thing. It's almost too big now. I think so
I think you know of course
There's the old marketing law first, but as we saw with Google they can you can obviously trump that but I think the real key
Is what they're pushing forward is their big claim to fame is security that'll resonate with enterprise folks
So that may actually work out in their favor, and they may get the traction they need yeah, and I like this federated discovery system
They're talking about where the protocol to distribute the container is pluggable like it could be bit torrent
There's obviously some advantages to that especially for like smaller projects that don't have huge bandwidth capabilities
That's kind of a neat way to distribute things. I like to that. I maybe could have a private
Quote-unquote hub of these things maybe we could have like a you know an internal JB server
We check things in and out doesn't need to be up on the centralized docker hub
So I think they're actually doing and oh and also they're doing a some actual real good like serious crypto signing
They had a Google hangout today where they talked about some of the technology
They're using and why they chose it and it I think some of the hostile
attitude that people are taking away in the press is they're kind of calling docker out for not totally being enterprise ready and
Not everybody really wants to hear that, but it's the truth. I think you nailed it
I also think the fact it seems like they did wait long enough for docker to kind of absorb major funds and say okay now
What are you gonna? Do about the security issues and and then it was just dead air and so now
I think they're kind of like okay. You know what fine. We'll do it. Yeah
Yeah, and I think you know core OS obviously has a lot of skin in the game because they're sure and they're this isn't core
This is not going to be core OS specific code. This is gonna be open code
That's available to anybody use just like they did with etc D
And I'm I'm I'm thinking for us Linux users. This is a really good thing and
You know every time we talk about this of course the free BSD guys always say oh
We've had jails forever and the slayers guys always had zones
And you know somebody's like oh, but I've been using LXC, but the thing is is this whole?
Plug-in software and pull it down thing is is unique and special and it's I think it was sort of the tipping point that made
This sort of more of a common popular concept
I'm kind of excited about what the core OS guys are working on and so producer q5 sis is
Working to line up a chat with folks from core OS to talk to us about it
So that way we can pick their brain and kind of maybe get directly from them where they feel like docker was maybe slightly
Deficient and it needed to be replaced and what some of those serious issues
They think they have that don't make it ready for enterprise. I'd like to get their answer on that too. Yeah, it's interesting times
It just like came out of nowhere. I wasn't really of course. I don't follow core OS super closely, but I wasn't expecting this
Mumble room any thoughts before we run on this topic last chance or forever hold your peace going once going twice and
No, and sold so q5 sis in the production chat tells me right now that we might have Brandon on Sunday to do an interview
I don't know if we'll air it in Sunday show since we have like an hour-long chat with an art
but if you tune in for the live show, you'll catch the live taping of it, and I don't know when we'll air that but
We'll work that out. But yeah, so we should have Brandon on from core OS Brandon is one of the top contributors to Docker
He sits on the governance board of Docker. He works on the core OS project
He's one of the people behind rocket and he'll be joining us on the Sunday live stream to answer those questions
If all if all the scheduling works out, so I should be tough
Okay. Well, we just have a couple of things to cover before we run
I'm still looking for the best of so if you go to the show notes
You'll find a link for a form to fill out for the best of moments of Jupiter broadcasting
We're gonna try to take the holiday week off and give people a recap of some of the best stuff
You can find a link to that in the show notes
We need your help and your suggestions of moments that you liked doesn't have to be a lot
But you'll see the form we got all the stuff in there and don't forget
We'd love to have you contact us go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact
Choose Linux unplugged from the drop-down and send us in your feedback
We love doing the feedback at the top of the show and you can always go to Linux action show dot reddit comm
We'll have threads for this specific episode, but you can start your own thread
Just comment on existing threads vote things up or down helps make a better show got lots of stuff, too
I mean more and more coming up
It's funny because I thought we'd have a big slowdown with the holiday season, but our producers are there a crack team
They're working on keeping content flowing and with all the news and thanks to folks like Todd for coming on
We've got lots of good stuff to talk about. So I think it's gonna be a couple of good weeks of shows
So don't go anywhere
Even if you get the time off don't forget your Linux action show Linux unplugged shows will be here and you can join us live
We do this show Tuesday 2 p.m. Pacific go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get that converted to your local time
All right, Matt. Well, I'll see you on Sunday with the chinat with our chat with Lenart Pottering. All right, sounds good
See that okay everybody. Thanks so much for tuning in this week's episode of Linux action show. Nope of Linux unplug
I'll see you right back here next Tuesday
Well, what show am I doing what day is it Linux action show I got too many what am I doing? Yeah
No, it's pajamas there's pajamas I tell you all right, so go to JB titles calm go pick a title everybody go vote
I got kind of
To run together. Yeah. Yeah. Well, you know what turns out pajama bottoms are way more
Like they keep the heat in a lot more than jeans do so it is hot. It's hot
Yeah, I've been wearing myself
What I'm I'm I'm sat here in my pants Chris because it's so humid
Yeah, remind me where you're at again
Whimpy's on the road. I mean, I'm in Kuala Lumpur Kuala Lumpur
What are you doing? What are you doing?
Really?
Well, that's a really good question
I'd love to tell you all if you if you promise not to put it out in the in the show
Oh, yeah, I'm gonna have to tell me later. Thanks. I'm still recording. Yeah, I don't want to get you in trouble
Doesn't mind if it goes out on the live stream just don't put it in the in the edit
All right
Yeah
For you before you tell me I want to give a plug to something that I meant to mention in the show and then I'll turn
Off the recording and you can tell it just to the live stream
Um, so before we go, I want to give a plug and then we'll wrap up there is a QMU advent calendar
And this is the best thing I've seen all year
so every day they're doing a QMU virtual image pick and
Today is day two
So we're just at the beginning of it and it's modern dos
The free dos disk image contains the latest and greatest from the land of the disk operating system besides checking out dos
with a TCP IP stack
He says you can relive id software's early shareware hit commander Keen as a bonus the free software edition of jetpack is also included
For your crazy jet-powered platformer action. So QMU dash advent calendar org
I'll have a link in the show notes day one was slackers time travel so you can go back and get the old ones
This is what when you dig up the earliest slack or image to be had and you can go play around with it
It ships with colonel zero dot nine nine dot twelve. Yeah, I said zero
Dot nine nine dot twelve
So it's not a great idea a QMU advent calendar. That's crazy. Yeah. Yeah, so all the Lincoln thing I've seen a week
I just had a great experience
Just a few minutes ago for the first time I needed to actually print from like my my desk workstation
I have printing set up on the machines here in the studio like for notes
But today I was up in my office and I realized I had cups installed
but I didn't have like the PPD file for my brother laser printer and
I bought it because I had read that it was a fairly well Linux supported laser printer
And so I just did a packer search for for the model number of my brother printer
And then the one result I got back was the PPD file for my exact brother printer
I packer dash s that that file name that package name and within 30 seconds
I had all of the cups printing set up for my my brother laser printer and I printed out the notes for today
It was a pretty it was it felt a little it fell a little 2014 is all I'm saying
It just felt like the future a little bit. Like that was the easiest printer setup I've ever had
Yeah, there's lots of brother support in the AUR
I think I maintain two of the brother printers there because I've got one at home and yeah what I've done
AUR actually has the exact same printer drivers that you get from Ubuntu in terms of the extras
Yeah, yeah, they're usually deb files that are then extracted and sprayed around them at the appropriate places
And what I've done recently at home to avoid that whole printer driver
Sort of arrangement is there's somebody's implemented the Google Cloud Print
API and services that integrates with cups
So I've got a Debbie and Weezy box that has got cups in so actually running open media vault
And then put the cloud print API
Into that and in order to get it to work, you actually have to put the printer drivers on the cup server
so now that printer
Advertises itself through the cloud print API for your Android phones and your Chromebooks. Not that I've got a Chromebook and the Chrome browser
Oh, yeah. Yes, but it also makes publish it over multicast DNS on the LAN
So you just get a Wi-Fi connection and that printer appears and you do to it without having to install anything on your machine
So it works from like live ISOs and stuff like that
That's really so you just you just set it up once on that dedicated box and you set it up once on that box
And then it's available forever and always on everything. Hmm. Yeah, that Google Print thing is actually pretty handy
I got to admit it is kind of nice. Yeah, it's a bit janky to set up
But it works really well once you go through the steps
Mm-hmm. I've been thinking about doing the exact same thing using my server
Only thing is it's running open Sousa and it has been for several months now
The problem with open Sousa is it's running an old version of cups that's incompatible with that framework the Google Print
So I don't know. We're really which for you to open Sousa
13.1. Okay, but it's like running 1.5 and they haven't updated it even in 13.2. Yeah, okay, huh?
I so my experience was sort of it was just it was so hassle-free that I thought to myself
I I'm pretty confident if you have the right conditions met and I think that's always a big if but I think if you have the
Right conditions met setting up printers is a lot easier under Linux
It isn't than it is under Windows
Like if you guys I don't know when the last time you guys have set up a Windows printer
but like you still have to go through this arcane wizard and it it still asks if you want to search a disk and
Like all of this stuff that like you you would never expect a regular user to go through
Every time even for eight HP printers, it's worse because you have to go and get a 600 megabyte
executable and install
boatloads of shit last time I bought a printer I
Plot I unpacked it all
Took the little strip off the printhead and plugged it into my laptop and sat it down put some paper in and then I went
And sat at my desk and there was a little pop-up that said your printer is installed and ready to print
And on Linux and this was like four years ago
And I went to Amazon to review it because that's where I bought it from and I reviewed it and left a shining
Review and every single other review was really terrible panning it not because of the printer but because of the Windows Drive. Yeah
Yeah, I'm
Because my my brother had like constantly kept asking me like you fixed this printer stuff
And there's a ton of issues with his Windows thing and I shut up my laptop
I plugged it in added it to my thing. It took like 20 seconds
I showed him his already connected. He's like, okay, give me that. Yeah, and now he's been using it for a couple months
Yeah, that's the thing about cups. This is just amazing. Yeah
Yeah
When I when I when I started using cups that to have all of your printers manageable through a web interface was groundbreaking from a tech
Support standpoint just totally groundbreaking not having to remote desktop into a Windows box
And then and go into the print queue and by the way if the Windows box and this is still the same today if the Windows
Box is struggling with a print job for some reason
Sometimes like the the spooler is just totally non-responsive like you can't go in there and delete documents
It is so out of the 80s
It's it's almost like you go into a time machine when you manage print jobs in Windows and like, you know
I became proficient at net stop quote print spooler at close quote enter net start
You know to restart the spooler service because it constantly crashes under
Windows and I'm talking in high load right for home printing
it's probably not so bad but I just
When cups came along and I could I could actually manage a failing print job and I could view all of the printers in one
Window in one screen. Oh, it was so powerful
So and then you know here I am
You know thinking this is gonna be way overkill for just a home printer setup because honestly my experience with cups is multi hundred
Printers, it's not one printer. So I'm thinking to myself
No, here I go. I gotta go. This is this is the problem with arch
I gotta go install cups and I'm gonna spend 15 minutes configuring it
And then I got to figure out to get my printer to work and I'm just going through this whole list and then it
Ended up being like a 30-second process and I just that back good cups is amazing
It starts it works for one printer all the way up to hundreds of printers and it's got awesome things about it in the whole
Range, it's a really powerful printing system