This is great that the WikiLeaks just sent out that one the this one tweet from the OSB projects
Oh, yeah, OSB projects y'all. This is from the CIA's own documents. You know we got all the dankest Trojans
No, I didn't see that. That's amazing. Oh there it is. Yeah, I've ever read the dankest Trojans Wow
You know we got all the dankest Trojans
Oh
My god, I'm gonna work for the CIA now. Yeah, well, maybe maybe that's why they got some good hackers
They're actually fun on the inside. I mean sure on the outside. They're all about killing and droning but on the inside
They got the dankest Trojans
You got the dankest Trojans. This is Linux Unplugged episode 187 for March 7th, 2017
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's very well traveled this week with stories from all about my name is Chris
My name is Wes. Hello there Wes. You look very dapper today, sir. Thank you. It is a big show
Oh, yeah, so much stuff
We of course as has been tradition for now three weeks in a row are gonna start with some wolf blitzer style breaking news
We're gonna get all blitzer up in here cover some big news and how it applies to Linux
Everybody's talking about it this week. Then. Mr. Brian Lunduke will stop by the show. He's actually secret spoiler already here
I'm gonna talk a little bit about the last the final
Linux sucks
It's an end of an era. We'll get the inside scoop on what's going on. I suspect
It's all about his hairdo now later on in the show. We're gonna hear from mr. Wimpy and mr
Popey about their trip to mobile world Congress and then if that's not enough if that's not enough like, you know
We got a little scale in there a little mobile world Congress. We're gonna get you amped up about odd camp 17 what?
Then we're gonna work back to scale
We're gonna go to the gnome booth and talk to the gnome guys about some of the stuff
They've been working on why they like endless OS the new endless OS PC. I think it's called the mission
Yeah, so Noah got to see it. He got to talk to the guys at the booth
We're gonna play an interview from that and then at the end of the show
New piece of hardware touting elementary OS by default. However, the elementary OS project
Super silent on the issue kind of like they don't want any attention on it and the hardware
It looks like it might be a bit of a scam not sure exactly what's going on
But producer Michaels been following the story from the very beginning
Asking questions getting the inside scoop. So we'll dig into that and talk about the light or I'm sorry the little light
I think it's called the light book which is a $250 Linux laptop. Is it too good to be true a
$250 Linux laptop preloaded with elementary OS but before we can get into any of that
We must say hello to our virtual log time appropriate greetings mumble room
So everyone it is a big news day today and it's if you've been following any of the news have any of news outlets
I mean, they're all just I'm sure just talking about in great detail. Well, maybe a little bit of detail
Maybe maybe not as much detail. Yeah, so it's up to us then it's up to us
It is it is our duty to go wolf blitzer on this
We're gonna do a little breaking news right here on the show
So this morning a little earlier than expected Richard Stallman was once again proven, correct
In fact, this isn't even I don't have to point this out WikiLeaks tweeted this DNU founder Richard Stallman its famous quote
resonates today at WikiLeaks publication
with software
There are only two possibilities either the users control the program or the program controls the users if the program controls the users
And the developer controls the program then the program is an instrument of unjust power
Now I this is this is sort of a pungent. Is that the right word a pungent smells a little bad
It's really no you never like to hear this because you know
Everybody has well except for I I want to be able to play games or well except for I want to be able to record
Video and ProRes or except I want to be able to make phone calls on my iPhone
Everybody has these these little accepts where they don't want to give on this particular quote and then something happens
It seems like every cup every couple of months and this quote comes back up
And it's more right and more true and more correct than ever and it just stings
It just tastes bad a little bit cuz like damn it. Damn it. He's right
He might eat toe jam, but he is right today WikiLeaks revealed vault 7 a
Whole batch of CIA crap. Yeah, like almost 8,000. Yeah. Yeah over 8,000 over
8,000 documents Wes and
And it has it has been dubbed the year of zero
Yeah, you're zero which is I probably in reference to all of the zero-day exploits that are contained in this
So there is actually something in here. That's a little applicable to Linux. I'm gonna save the most you know most of this for
Unfilter or tech snapper wherever wherever it may lie as we go through it
but one thing I thought was interesting and it just came out today is the CIA has malware that
It's pretty sweet because it can target Windows OS 10
Linux or some hardware routers
It's called hive and it's a multi-platform
Automated malware attack and control system. Oh also Solaire's shouldn't I shouldn't forget Solaire's and
It it's also related to the cutthroat and swindle tools
Wow first of all I love the names cutthroat swindle hive totally love the name
I think all of this is great, and it goes into more detail in fact
They have and I have these linked in the show notes
Guides on how to use this
Developer guides end-user guy nice documentation really good information about how I see MP
Pings and air ICMP errors work, and which ISPs might reject them quite fascinating actually they've done some good work here
It's it's remarkable to read through this and go okay, so everything you kind of suspected is
Probably true that conspiracy that you thought was totally out there and crazy now
It looks like it's more and more true every day there was software there
They have supposedly tools in here that help them target computer systems in cars. Oh, yeah, totally
That's something a lot of people have suspected before
Mr.. Lundic you and I were talking about this before the show anything about anything in the vault 7 leaks Brian jump out at you
is either preposterous or
Fascinating in the context of Linux or just worth noting
There's only really one thing that's worth noting in all of this and that is that the CIA has the dankest Trojan yes
Yeah, I
Love that that is that is true, and you can't deny it now
I mean if they didn't they would they be doing their job they make the NSA look like a bunch of middle schoolers
Right they do come on CIA is like we want our own exploits
We're not going through those guys giving them our operational deets
This is how the CIA talks because they're soups hip they're soups hip so they go out there
Go what a totes get our own zero days, and they're gonna be the dankest zero days
They're kind of talking like Trump a little bit. It's a little Trump Ian in the way. There's down
This is all all new relevant stuff to
from
2013 to
2016 is wait a minute wait a minute Chris Christopher Fisher
I got to call you out for a second here go for it now
I'm not the biggest Trump fan in the world
But I don't believe I've ever heard Donald Trump get up on stage and say damn that is dank all
I would like that, but I don't believe he's done that so I'm gonna call Shanann can we wait and hope I mean
Maybe it's only just started. We totally it's the first hundred days man. It's the first hundred days, so you never know
That's the new distraction so yeah 2013 to 2016 is where this documents are from
It sounds like they got it
essentially because people were passing this stuff loosey-goosey around the government at this point and so people inside the government got it over to
WikiLeaks
They've been sitting on it for a little bit. There was some discussion in the last few weeks. I think it was even just
Last week Julian Assange, so they would get it really sometime this year
But they were going through it they were redacting not just names and some dates now, but they're also redacting portions of code
Which is an interesting thing they have to do
Avoid easily weaponizing the information at least this is part one of this was obtained recently in covers through
2016 details on the other parts will be available later on and then in there
This is amazing, so they're not just creating malware for Linux
But they're also using Linux to hack Macs and they have a guide on how you can use Ubuntu or mint
Whichever you prefer
Users choice CIA hackers choice you meant or Ubuntu, but at least let's be honest at least
It's gonna something that supports snap packages like a gentleman and they say in here. You can configure
If the Linux or Ubuntu mint install to hack the UEFI
firmware on a Mac
That's actually pretty neat. Yeah, and they have they have apparently they have their own internal repos
And they even look they even have instructions on using hit this covers using GCC
This is this is the CIA's documentation on using GCC to build hacking tools on Linux
Or the UEFI driver wizard. Yeah, yeah, this is this is what it is here
Huh, it's a long page like this is pretty legit documentation
That's really kind of a mess look at this. They even have a little gooey like a look at that
It's with the with the screenshots with the default Ubuntu theme there
Ubuntu is everywhere now. Oh yeah, yeah, it's really popular
Well when you're hacking at home when you're hacking at the office you want to be on the same platform
Yeah, that's true right it makes it much easier when you're building in and also they talk about using
Public VPS's for the command and control servers to make it even more confusing they talk about tools that intentionally leave quote-unquote
Fingerprints that look Russian or whatever else they want
This is really it's a really big treasure trove of stuff
But the one thing that I thought was interesting was this hive thing just in context of this show
It's a multi-platform malware suite and control software the project provides customizable implants for Windows Solaris micro tech routers and
And Linux platforms. Yeah, yeah, it also has a listening post which is what they call the command and control infrastructure to communicate with these
Implants is what they call the the Trojan is an implant the implants are configured to communicate via HTTPS
With a web server on the domain that they've chosen which is usually like a cover domain of some kind and each operating
Each each operation utilizing these implants has separate cover domains and infrastructure can handle any number of cover domains
So you can have one server for the command and control but appear to be hundreds of domains on one VPS
If you want it to be each cover domain resolves to an IP address that is associated with a commercial
Commercial VPS provider and the public facing server forwards all incoming traffic via a VPN to a blot not a bot
But a blot server that handles actual connection requests from its clients
I don't know why it's blot not bot
But apparently it's this little server that sits there and handles the incoming connections
Manages it it's set up for optional SSL if you want if the client has a valid cert it can do that
And it says it's forwarded to a honeycomb tool server that communicates with the implant
How about these words here, huh?
If a valid certificate is missing the traffic is forwarded to a cover server then delivers it via an unsuspicious looking website
The honeycomb tool server receives
Exfiltrated information from the implant and an operator can also also task an implant to execute jobs on the target computer
So the tool server acts as a command and control server for the implant as well
Now there is a bit of a downside if you manage to infect a Windows box at the time of this
Writeup didn't support automatic client update on Windows
Yeah, however Linux rig can totally remotely update the implant totally good to go. Haha. It's got a cron job updates in the background
Yeah, it is
Yeah, that is Poby. Did you have I saw I saw you go by did you have something you wanted to jump in with?
No, I just thought you know the fact that using like Ubuntu or whatever Linux distribution is interesting
But I wondered if they'd used
Anything that uses the JSON license given that their license explicitly says the software should we use for good not evil
Hmm whether that would be a a way in which we could legally go after them for using the software
Well, you know
I was also reminded of the VMware lawsuit because there is some use of busy box in here
They you they bundle busy box with some of their tools which made me wonder if maybe they're violating the busy box license
And she's gone with VMware in trouble before wouldn't that be hilarious? It'd be like the Al Capone of the CIA
Yeah, it really would be the busy box like yeah
I saw some discussion of how like they couldn't some of the stuff isn't classified because because of the command and control nature for instance
If it was transmitted or put on a machine that wasn't couldn't have classified information
Oh Wow analysts could be fired or disciplined because it would be breaching the protocol for classified information
What a what an interesting catch-22 can't like you you know leaked classified. It wasn't classified Wow
I did not catch that part that is that is particularly interesting
It's been it's been really interesting also speaking of things that guess what are interesting reading Edward Snowden's Twitter feed today
I
Think he's right
And he says the big story is this is the first public evidence that the US government is secretly paying to keep US software unsafe
So they they discover they they even they have teams that discover these vulnerabilities or they buy the known vulnerability off of
Someone or some trading site
They discover these things that are critical to devices that the American public has in use every day that they're doing
God knows what with and they're not disclosing it
They're leaving these flaws open
nothing preventing another foreign government from discovering or buying the same flaw and
Taking advantage of it instead of working
The sort of the story that came out after the NSA leaks was well
We yeah, we hold on to those zero days for a while, and then we inform the Microsoft's and the Apple of the world about them
Oh except for these really important ones, okay?
We don't tell them about those either
But otherwise we totally work with them and then Microsoft even came out with a statement saying we do have a program that works
With the NSA where they discover vulnerabilities, and we have included
Vulnerabilities they've informed us about in previous patch sets like they just talked about like it was the standard operating procedure
You're like okay. Well. This is just something that the private sector and the government have set up working together
Nothing wrong with that sure what could go wrong right probably no problem sure
Then you see this and you discover. Oh no no no they have a huge treasure trove of zero days
hundreds of them actually and
They just don't tell anyone and they just use them for their own benefit and just I guessed hope
They just kind of hope that nobody else figures out these vulnerabilities exist. They just kind of hope it's all gonna work out
it seems that way I mean I guess we were supposed to assume or trust that they are weighing that risk versus the
intelligence
Advantage of having these zero days, but is that really the case?
I don't know and that I guess that's something maybe we can analyze now that we have these documents
Is it also mean that people are more likely to start digging into what these are now that they know they're out there
Yeah, hopefully all right anyone in the mumble room have any closing thoughts on this story before we move on probably not it's not very interesting
No, no, okay. No all right well speaking of things that are interesting
Whoa whoa did you hear that voice right there? That was the that was the up-the-nose shot of one mr. Brian Lundu
It's a nice nose, and he is holding his final
The last there will be no other
Linux sucks talk. It's scale 15x this year and Brian
Yeah, I just want to say as somebody who's you know been around when these started
I think this was a long time ago
This was your best hairstyle out of any Linux sucks talks you've ever given I think you really nailed it this year
Why thank you. I did a full and complete
retrospective of all of the various hairstyles because I felt like that was probably the most important thing to talk about that's why people would
Be tuning in sure yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah most definitely yeah most definitely
Yeah, most definitely yeah most definitely it was pretty fun. It was good. It was the last one
I'm ever gonna do we did it on Thursday night at scale
Rad yeah, yeah, I was able to watch some of it
I was watching live because I didn't get to go to scale this year, and man was that live stream rough
That was that was rough. Yeah, that was pretty brutal
But you know it's it's conferences got the conference live streams and recordings always they always kind of suck like even the big ones
I'm like the big festivals with like a tons of corporate backing. They're always pretty right to get right
So the number one question everybody asks now is so what's the deal does Linux no longer suck, or do you just get tired?
Of doing it. Oh, no, it still sucks
It's just the same thing every time you remember Chris remember remember when we first started doing those back in
What year was that 2000 2008 2009? Yeah, we started doing those remember the first three years
I did it it was like the same slides every friggin year
Yeah, like like it was the exact same slides and part of it is because I'm the laziest bastard on the planet
But part of it was that it was like the same stuff to complain about every year
I you know after after almost a decade of complaining about essentially the same things at one point
You got to just like wrap it all up put a bow on that and say there
Everyone just go reference that video until it's all fixed and then we can revisit
Yeah, it's all it's now enshrined here. It is. This is the final version fix these things
It's just that go do that right because that's worked so well since 2009. It's obviously
It's played out perfectly winning damn strategy my friend now
Did you find that it was there was trepidation early on trepidation?
I guess early on do people little
Larry of having somebody come out to their Linux event and talk about how Linux sucks because I could see some people not getting
The right, you know not getting the inside joke. Remember we when we did the first one
We did it up at Linux fest Northwest and we didn't call it Linux sucks
We called it Linux sucks and what we can do to fix it
Yeah, I made a very big deal about how this was a positive thing
It wasn't just about complaining and whining and then once once that kind of was successful
We were able to drop that whole
Charade off and just focus on the sucky stuff. No more couching. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, I mean, I mean after I mean after the video start getting a million views. I mean people are like, oh, okay
Yeah, you can you can come here and give my conference a ridiculous amount of press. Yes, that's fine
Yeah, and it seems to always it always seems people see that, you know
And even if they haven't seen the video before you see it on the program. You're like what? What is this?
Who is this guy and what could he say? It's a you know, it's either you know about it or you're upset
You're like, yeah, the only thing I so there I feel like there's probably two possibilities
either you've thought of another way to get attention that's gonna be even better than saying Linux sucks or
You're rolling the dice and assuming you're just gonna figure one out. Which one is it a
little bit of both
There could be something in the works there might be and if there were I would choose to be very sneaky about it and not
Say anything until at least Linux fest Northwest rolls around. There you go. Yeah Linux. There's a good
There's a good plug too for Linux fest Northwest. So I will be there you'll be up there this year, right?
Yeah. Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. Nice. Hey, I'm gonna live there for a couple days, you know, you know
I've heard that you're good at using your words and talking perhaps you're gonna give it you're gonna give a speech
You're gonna give a session you're gonna get up in front of crowd this time at Linux fest maybe
You know, you know how much I hate crowds, you know me and you know me and
It would depend maybe if Wes could fill in for me at the booth for a bit. I'll tell you what I'll tell you what
What Chris I will do one with you. What would we do a talk about? What would we talk about?
I don't even fucking care we can get up there and talk about shoes for all I care
We'll get up you give me something good to talk about I'd do it
I mean, I just you know, I got nothing to talk about because I talk shoes. I talk way too much during the week
So what do I what else do I have to say, right?
So I feel like it's all in the shows
But if you gave me something new to riff on I could do it man. People would love it dude, right?
People would get a serious kick. I don't even care what it is
People in the mumble room and the audience of this show, whatever tell Chris what you would like me and Chris to riff on
Yeah, or one hour and we'll do it. Yeah, although I
There I think I think I think with this audience it could be kind of random. Yeah say potatoes good
Yeah, no, I see I did I did potatoes for like half an hour at the oh, yeah
So I gotta come up with something more esoteric than potatoes. Okay. Well, maybe we'll see we'll see what people say
Let us know maybe something
Something great. Yeah gripping. We got it. We should do something technically the the call for papers is already closed
But I'm sure we could squeeze something in man. They'd get a kick out. We'll just go take over a room
Yeah, I mean if we walk in there with cameras and microphones and lights people are probably gonna get out of our way
So right they'll move either way. It's content
You could almost do the history of Linux fest Northwest
Could almost do that. I just don't really think that would be I
Don't know. You'd have to have I don't know. It's either nothing like years of no, that's boring. Yeah, come on, man
We gotta do something rad something gripping something that really grabs you by your cockles and just gives it a good yank
I think we can do it. We could how about let's do stop using Ubuntu
Well that that actually could get some attention stop using Ubuntu. It's a really not that much different than the Linux sucks
Honestly, that's pretty much the gist of it. So we'll have the the final Linux sucks talk. It's up. Yeah
Yeah, the fight the final one was out
Just got a couple days ago yesterday. Yeah yesterday. Yeah, yeah less less than 24 hours ago
All right
So we'll we'll see how that one does find that on Brian's channel also have that linked in the show notes if you guys want to
Check it out. It's also in the subreddit
And and there is I don't know if you saw this Chris
But one of my favorite shots from any of the Linux action shows or any of the videos the one with the flag
The flag I saw that I did
God about that
Too I told was that from coding with Brian though. That was from coding with Brian
Oh, no, that was just that was just the Linux action show remember we recorded it and you remember the year
We went up to Linux fest and we had like a classroom. Yeah, we were gonna stream live from the whole time
Yeah, the Internet sucked. Yeah, the audio it was terrible
Yeah
And so we recorded a little intro with the American flag behind me where I was telling oh, no bad the audio
That wasn't even green screen
That was legit flag. No, no, no, that was green screen. Oh, okay. We green screen. Oh, we did green screen
Okay, right after we got that green screen. That's hilarious
We and we were like we were just like farting around with like try to like do stuff
So we also it's gaudiest American flag like, you know, how much better is that picture with that stash?
I don't think it would have the same. I don't think it would have the same landing if you didn't have that
I
Am just eating beef in that picture and I don't even have beef in that picture. It's amazing. I
Think it's the same jacket to no scarf anymore, but it's the same jacket. It was it was I realized that when I was up there
I grabbed the same blazer the same brown corduroy blazer
I had on and that was I don't know that was 2010 2011 something like that was forever ago, dude
Yeah, but you just now breaking it in
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Well, you know, it's just starting to get soft. Fine. Yeah
Yeah, you know, this is a 40 year blazer here. You got it. It's just getting warmed up
particular category the 40 year blade
Alright, mr. Lundu. Well, I know you had to go around this time
So I do I I hate to jump in here be fantastical and Jared when I know my good friends
Popey and wimpy are in the crowd, but guys you're gonna you're gonna have to do something rad without me
You guys carry on do something somehow they will manage you'll manage I bet well
Thank you for stopping by and congrats on a long run of the Linux sucks talks the Linux sucks
Yeah, not not too damn shabby. Also. I was looking at it and if anyone wants to see early camera work from Chris fish
No, you don't. Oh my god
Don't do it the first year or two. We had a tripod and then like the third year we did it
We were just like
Yeah, you know what? I don't understand is like how come we never got that dialed in like I mean even now you're still shooting
Up your face right here. Oh
It's crazy. So this year right this year we had a sponsor for it. We had really good cameras set up for it
So we had four cameras set up. Whoa, two of them came out awful like it was nice DSLRs
They recorded it the image quality was good, but like the shots were just bad
Like it was just terrible the one great like good-looking one. It's just like this like webcam. That's like up my nose. Yeah
Yeah, we it's always always something. It's always something
I feel like that's the style of Linux sucks though
Like that's it's big like we had we recorded two completely separate years on those old and 900 camera phones
Oh, yeah, and I know her phones. Yeah, just with some guy sitting in the audience really nice
I just think they're holding it or freaking out
And the and the battery didn't last very long on it
So we had to have an extension cable run so we could hold it there
So it was charging over USB while he was holding this cheap cheap little camera phone and then that
Particular show goes on to get out like a million. Yeah, go figure right go figure. That's see that's how you do it
Chris you got it. You got to go cheap cameras. Yeah cheap microphone, right? Make sure it's as bad as possible
Okay, and then you get like a million views. Okay, I'm taking notes. I'm taking no
Yeah, I'm just you know a little bit schooling little bit schooling help you out a little thank you
I appreciate that I got it all I'm gonna get rid of this microphone. All right. All right. Hey guys. Hey guys look behind you what?
Where'd he go?
Well, there you go. We'll have that all linked up in the show notes. And hey Brian, you're still here
What are you doing? Don't you know how to work mumble close that thing?
Get out of here. Come on. All right. So before we go on
Let's stop and thank Linux Academy for sponsoring this week's episode of the unplugged program so much more to get into Linux Academy
Unplugged that's where you go to sign up support the show and
free seven-day trial
Oh
That's amazing that is me and my mind literally exploding at the awesomeness of this key get into the platform
You can dig around and really figure out how Linux Academy might work for you
They have labs to give you hands-on scenario based learning instructor mentoring when you need videos with self-paced in-depth courses
Whether you're an experienced sysadmin or new to the world of Linux Azure and AWS
OpenStack and DevOps a sharp skill set is an absolute necessity to succeed
meet Linux Academy
online Linux and cloud training platform that uses self-paced video courses and hands-on labs to give you real-world experience
for a wide range of skills
Trained for your certification learn the latest DevOps tools and grow your skill set to do better work
Linux Academy is not just a video library our scenario based server labs and quiz system allow you to learn hands-on
We also have full-time human instructors who answer questions love that help you earn that certification
Yeah, or promotion at work. We add new training every week
So you'll always be up to date on the latest tech
sysadmins of every experience level use Linux Academy to stay on the bleeding edge of the Linux ecosystem. You should too
Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged one of the things that I love about Linux Academy is they have a little breathing room now to engage with the community
And it's really exploding. I mean they have a great community on their own, but they're now engaging with the wider Linux community
They're going to a lot of these events. They were like scale. They're at scale
I'm hoping they go to Linux fest that way we can get a chance to hang out with them
It's a company in a really sweet spot of growth right now
They're not only they're doubling down investing on their content and their staff and making your subscription more valuable all the time
But they're doubling down on their engagement with the community Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged in a big. Thank you the Linux Academy for sponsoring this here Linux unplugged program this one this one right here
I want to give a I want to move on I want to talk about Mobile World Congress and
Odd camp, but maybe to slide us into that to prepare us to get our bodies ready
Let's talk a little bit about the story of Firefox OS
I thought this was an interesting piece and just this shot of the booth
It's really something it really is look at that look at that look at that investment
Just right there now. You know canonical is just at Mobile World Congress
Massive booth really a housebooger that crazy bigger this booth bigger than bigger than my house
Bigger than maybe as big as the studio. It was a big-ass
Big-ass big-ass booth, so I'd like to tell you this is the guy writing this from Firefox from boot to gecko all the way
up to the software project
Dying in 2016 and he writes out where they went wrong. It's an interesting write-up about Firefox OS
I don't know if we need to spend a lot of time going into it
But I thought I would point it out to the audience who's curious about these these free software
Operating systems for mobile devices and maybe where they've gone wrong now that these folks involved like this guy
Who was a product developer have a little hindsight? Yeah perspective you can look back at it and go well
Where did we go wrong? So that's it's interesting from that perspective now. I
Want to segue not so brilliantly into Mobile World Congress
Where popi and wimpy have just returned from this is this is a comparison that people will often make we'll look at canonical
They're investing so heavily in mobile
Which is kind of like how do you how do you know where they invest their money? How do you know?
What are you basing that on? What are you basing that? How do you know what returns they get from that?
But anyways, it's a common criticism that you hear lobbied at them quite a bit
And they did indeed have a big presence
So I kind of wanted to get a little perspective from a couple of the booth babes
I mean a couple of the guys that were there popi and wimpy what they thought of it all and and sort of walking away
From it. What is the reason canonicals there? And I don't know maybe if I was gonna go what should I expect?
So popi, I'd love to start with you. I know that I think following your Twitter feed
I saw I saw several different tweets about about the event about having fun. I'm guessing you must have had a great time
Yeah, it's my first time at MWC
I've never been there before and I kind of had to ask around in the company to find out what to expect but
overall it was an overwhelming experience and I
Like the size of the place I couldn't get over it. It was just humongous
So many halls that are the whole building buildings were built specifically for MWC
Wow, it's it's just gigantic and we had a sizable booth
I mean you look at other people's booths like the giant companies like Huawei and Nokia and and
Companies like that. They had really gigantic booths that were like the size of a town
Whereas ours was you know, pretty big for a free software development company
Part of the town
Yeah, it was comparable in size to LG who were opposite us on the on the strip
Keeping up with the Joneses
It wasn't it wasn't like we had a tiny little postage stamp size one compared to all the others
But what was really nice was like the diversity of stuff that was on the stand
It wasn't just here come and get an Ubuntu CD or here's a Ubuntu phone that you can't buy
You know, there was there's a there was a whole load of stuff and it wasn't just canonical
It wasn't just Ubuntu
There was a whole lot of their demoing stuff and I I know while we were standing there
Demoing our stuff that me and Martin were talking about there
there were just so many other things to see and do which was great because people spent ages on the stand and
Spent ages talking to us now
Limpy I was curious from your perspective
This is a pretty big event where you're going and showing off some of the hard work of either yourself or teammates
Was it did you feel a bit on display? Was it was it like here's our hard work?
What do you think or was it was it a different vibe?
Yeah, it was to some extent it was here's what we've been working on
So specifically what Popey and I and our team with Eve and Jamie
We're we're showing was all our stuff to do with Ubuntu core and snaps
And we were introducing that to developers who are at MWC
hmm, and it was interesting because those conversations went very differently from the conversations that you have with
traditional open source projects so
Software developers who just want their software out there and they want to get it on as many devices as possible as easily as possible
the whole snaps and Ubuntu core story really resonated with them and
the feedback was
overwhelmingly positive
But then you're saying, you know Ubuntu has
From our you know from the discussions we've had here
The Ubuntu mobile story has been about the phone and the tablet in the past
But going into this what I've learned is just like the rest of the IT industry has embraced
virtualization and
containerization in order to
Get more value out of their servers and pack the most amount of functionality into the equipment that they've got deployed in places
The telecommunications sector are doing exactly the same thing
So they have been buying great big devices that have single purpose and single function and these are very expensive
bits of kit
but they are now moving to a software defined platform where they are rolling out their new era of
networks based on open stack and
software to define software defined radios software defined networks
virtual network function infrastructure, so it turns out that because Ubuntu is the dominant platform in the cloud and
supports
open stack Kubernetes and LexD
Transparently throughout the you know, the stack of offerings that Ubuntu has the telcos are queuing up to
rework their internal infrastructure on Ubuntu using those cloud technologies
You know Wes and I went to the open daylight summit that was put on by the Linux Foundation
I bet you were yeah, because it was a lot of this was really was yeah exactly that a lot of
Data centers that look like they're there multiple data centers that look like one flat network
That is all both spun up on-demand different connections are created by software defined networking
Now they were hoping people would be using open daylight to manage it all or to I guess it's back to network. Yeah
Yeah, anyway, but hmm. This is you know, it's it's big. It's a big and it's a big
Infrastructure reorganization on the back end. That's totally transparent to consumers
Yeah, exactly and we don't exactly you don't even realize it's happened. I mean we hardly know and we're we wait
Yeah, we went to an event about it
We can hardly tell and it's you know
It's interesting to hear you echo that wimpy because it's that's that's exactly what we observed too
And the and the driver for the telcos is that they're they're losing sort of they're losing the fight against the big cloud
Providers and the data centers of the world
And they need to compete there
They need to be in that space and that's why they're going to be using many of the same
Technologies to offer much of the same capability
Interesting probably you were gonna say something
No, I was just it was interesting to me that the people who were coming by the booth
the way the MWC works on the first day you get these scouts come by the
By the booth and these are scouts from some of the like biggest companies you've heard of
Checking out what's on the booth and checking out the demos and they go away and then the next day on the Tuesday
they come back with their CEOs and CTOs and the execs to actually see the thing for themselves and
It was it was interesting to me to see these scouts going around and asking loads of questions and then coming back the very next
Day with different people alongside them to demo
You know, whatever it is software-defined radio or Ubuntu core or OpenStack or whatever
And and seeing our salespeople talking to their people was was quite entertaining
Yeah, a boy wouldn't that be wouldn't that just be one more perfect industry for Linux to completely take over?
Just and and not because not because the bunch not because they're like big Linux enthusiasts
But simply because it's solving a problem for the whole problem
and the reason why I like that is it it forces these companies to get involved in a way that is beneficial to their
long-term viability and
Once they get all in on something like this
Linux and all of this technology stack becomes part of that
Well, we have to we have to get involved from a long-term viability standpoint and Wes and I talked from I think it was two
different people from AT&T
somebody from Ericsson
Where else I know we talked to we talked to a wide range of companies that were getting involved in open source simply because they're
now moving into this field
It becomes the toolset that they use and
the way to get the easiest way and the best way for them to get the things that they need changed or fixed or improved is
Contribute to upstream and the Linux Foundation is trying to figure out a way to you know
Kind of get in on this a little bit because they feel like well
We should be there setting the standard setting this, you know
so I and I don't know if they're getting I can't I don't have a good sense if they've
If they've got a lot of traction, did you guys see a lot about anything about open daylight or the Linux Foundation at mobile?
world congress
Nope, no. Oh
Yeah, that seems like the event should be at though
One thing that I did see like conversely the flip side of the the big wigs and the execs and the scouts on the Monday
Tuesday Thursday, they open the conference to local students who all come in. So it's a very different crowd
Wow, yeah, and we got rid of them lanyards and stickers that
Number of people who came by and told it like before we'd even talk to them about anything before we'd ask them any questions
They were like, yeah, I already use a bun to it's on my
It's like so many people every single day telling us how yeah, they they use a bun to they love it people telling us
They've got their Dell XPS in their bag and they carry it with them everywhere and stuff like that
That really made it worthwhile going and seeing like the real people and not and not just not just the students coming in
who are studying computer science, but at the
The food stands because obviously we were all in a bun to orange, you know
Full full brand regalia, huh? So we got we got four urban two shirts at the start of this event one clean shirt for every day
And when when you're at the food stands buying your food the number of people that were serving me said
I love a bun to or going into the conference, you know
The security guards and the people on the gate saying I use a bun to and people smiling at you from a distance as you're walking
along and then when you get there like ha, you know
I use a bun to or that is me walking around in your lunch break and people running up to you and tapping you on the
Shoulder you have a bun. Yeah, it was it was really great. Really great. That was particularly enjoyable
Wow
Yeah, really now rumor has it that there may be a new episode of the Ubuntu podcast
Soon to be released that may go into more details. Are these true rumors? Is this can you guys confirm this rumor?
No, we can confirm those rumors I was scared there
Yeah, okay, I tell you what I tell you what mark do you do you wanna do you want to explain what we've been doing this
evening
Well, we've been recording the Ubuntu podcast. Of course, very good. Probably talking a little bit about things that
You can hear it on on Thursday. Very nice. In fact mark you're here with a little more breaking news
in the
Unplugged program. I believe another rumor came out on the 26th of February. This is a breaking
It's just really late breaking news here that on cam 17 is on and a location has been chosen. Are these rumors true?
These rumors are extremely true not fake news
No, no, we don't do fake news over here or old facts. Yeah. Okay good one. Yeah, sure. So what's the details?
What do I what are the dirty details that I need to know if I might want to go to our camp?
So if you if you've not heard of our camp before our camp is what we call a free culture on conference
so it's a conference with
Not a lot of schedule but a lot of room for things if you want to come along and talk about your favorite thing
and it's happening this year after taking a year off on the 19th and
20th of August and it's happening in Canterbury in the UK. Okay
so we've got a
Building at the Canterbury Christ Church University and we've also got some accommodation at their student accommodation
We've got a deal with them. The details of that are on the website
I'll come to org and if you go to our camp to all you can also sign up for your ticket
And as we've have done in previous years, we're doing pay what you want tickets
So you can you can come for free or you can give us a bit of money if you want to nice
I think that's really cool on camp 17 glad to hear it's back and I've always heard it's a good event
Oh, yeah, definitely. Yeah. Oh one nice thing about the location actually this year is if you're in Europe
You can actually get the train
quite easily to Canterbury because you just get the Eurostar under the channel and
Then you either change in Ashford or London and then you can get straight to Canterbury from there
So it might be a bit more accessible than it has been when it's been up in the other end of the country
Yeah, that is really nice. Especially for oh, I'd love to go. Oh, I got a good ticket. I got a I got it
Well, hmm problem number one is I can't believe I'm in my mid-30s and I still don't have my passport
So that's a that's something is problem
It simply comes down to who has the time to do that
Who has the time to drive around to three different places or whatever?
It is get some stupid little picture and then get it put on another stool
I don't have that wait around or to come my daughter's had a passport since she was four years old
It should be ashamed. I am I literally only have the one really close neighbor and you don't need a pass, right?
That's the thing that is the thing that is I just go up to Canada with it
And in fact, if you take the boat, you don't even need the enhanced
Oh, I can't I don't know what that's true anymore, but you didn't use a long time. Yeah. Yeah
Just drop some inflatables to the RV. You'll be over in no time. I would oh if I could that'd be so great
I really got to do it. I got to do it
I just need a way I just this is why I need an assistant to have it
You know take a picture of me go go do these things now
If you want to hear more of these fine gentlemen, check out Ubuntu podcast org
So this is gonna be season 11. Is that what's starting off 10? Oh, so it's already up then
No, this is episode zero zero. Oh, it is
Oh you guys are so confusing with the zero zero, so I like it though. It looks good
It looks like just from a title that looks that looks good. Yeah
This is the one thing to regenerate the guy who the guy who emailed in season one saying that we were
We were sort of had ideas above our station for using a leading zero. This is the season that proves him wrong
awesome
Not that you guys hold a grudge
We're gonna churn out 42 episodes just to prove him right
Well, that might have been in his best interest in the long term
I am boy I'm excited about our camp and even if I if I can't make it
I'd love to hear a report back here on the show about it because that does look like it's gonna be a lot of fun
You guys gonna record a live Ubuntu podcast there?
Quite possibly. Yeah, that might happen. Yeah, that doesn't surprise me. Okay
Well, although we should we should also mention we are going to be recording a live podcast later in the year on June the 24th
in London
So fostalk live that happened last August organized by Joe Ressington from late night Linux
He's organizing another fostalk live this year and we are on the bill
To do that
So if you head to fostalklive.com when tickets get announced
You'll be able to find the details there and get a ticket for the event. They'll be in very short supply small venue
It's worth going for the laminated show notes alone. Oh, yes
Well, yes, and if you're lucky if you if you make friends with poppy and buy him a beer, he might sign them for you
Nice producing in Gobi in gobs as we used to call it
So, you know guys I'm just putting this out there
But if you actually stream the recording of the shows live some of us would tune in
Just saying there might be an audience out there for that. It's not hard. Maybe you can do it
You can do it. You don't even have to show your faces. You could just do an audio stream
It'd be really fun. I know I think one day this whole live stream thing is gonna take off
John I don't know. I've live streamed before. Yeah, okay
I think maybe now that we've got a big telegram channel we can we can pimp it to them
But before it was it was more effort than it was worth. Yeah. Yeah, I you know doing lie
I remember doing live streams before Twitter and the only real reason I was
Thankful Twitter kind of came along in some sense was because I had a way to let people know we were live
Really?
There was really no other mechanism and that makes me feel like an old man. All right, so we got to talk about scale
We got a warp back to scale. I got a great interview by Noah
With the gnome booth
But before we do that
I want to thank our good friends at ting for sponsoring this show linux dot ting calm linux dot ting calm you go there
Support the show and get $25 credit now this $25 credit can be applied to a device you buy from ting like a maniac
Direct from ting why not makes it nice and easy
They can even find a device for you or if you bring in device, they'll give you $25 in service credits
They like oh $25
Pay for the line
What are you stuck in some sort of duopoly quote-unquote agreement?
Ting ting is mobile. It's different. You only pay for what you use. It's a flat rate boom six dollars for the line
That's it. Six dollars six dollars six dollars guys for the line. Are you hearing that?
I mean I could say it one more time, but it's just crazy at that point and then you just pay for usage on top
of that
What it's that straightforward?
You got six dollars for the line. Oh, I did it again. Then you pay for what you use minutes messages megabytes
So if you don't use many messages, you don't pay for them. You don't make a lot of phone calls
You don't pay for it. You see how that works. It's simple
And then it's uncle Sam's touch right off the top. That's gonna depend on where you live, bro
I don't know. I can't put that don't put that on me. I don't know. That's what depends on you
Anyways, you find out you go to linux.com you click on what would you save you get a little chart?
It starts telling you about numbers you do the math you start realizing holy crap in two years
I could have bought an entirely new laptop. I'm like three and a half years into this
I got multiple lines a ton of laptops to I'm
I'm all up in the tank. I got it for myself
I got it for the business. It really makes a lot of sense and if I ever get stuck
Which is really nice when I'm on the road
Really good support really good really good so good
They they stayed on the phone longer than they should have I didn't need I did not I did not expect that to get fixed
I thought I was I legit was done like a half hour 40 minutes before they were I was like
This is unsolvable. This is unsolvable. I don't even I you know I've been in IT for 15 years
I can tell you this is unsolvable. You don't need to bother
They stuck with and got it fixed which was super thankful and through it
We was we were I was in Montana and through it was stopping by I was about to do
I can't remember what show I think it might have been code or it might have been this show
I was about to go live on the air my my fire died
I didn't know what was going on
I was parked in a gravel parking lot and ting save the day linux.com you go there
You get the best mobile company in the biz you bring a device. They don't honey badger. They just go crazy
They don't care. They're honey badger about it. You just use it however you want minutes messages megabytes, and you pay for it. It's simple also I
Really like this blog series
They've been doing if you go to linux.com and this is sort of applicable to any carrier
I suppose but the five capable smartphones under $100
Like we always talk about like you get like Wes over here with the pixel
That's right, although you did rock the Nexus 5 for like ever ages. Yeah, so you totally earned that pixel
Kind of you know you know if you're not ready to buy
You're not ready to blow seven hundred dollars on a smartphone or even a thousand dollars in some cases way
It's great about ting right whatever phone. You want whatever phone makes sense totally linux.com and a big
Thank you to ting for sponsoring the unblocked program
So let's talk to and well let's talk let's talk no let's talk endless
Let's talk endless PC, and let's talk a little fedora. Oh, yes, that's right my friends. It's Noah at scale
Walking around the scale floor we have to stop at Gnome anytime
We see him obviously one of the favorite desktop environments of anyone that uses Linux. How are we doing today pretty good?
How are you excellent so tell me a little bit about what the Gnome team is up to these days and also
I know that you work for endless
I would like to hear about endless the endless PC and the operating system that you've designed around no
Yeah, for sure, so this is actually good timing because Gnome 324 the new version of Gnome is gonna be out
In a couple of weeks. I think March 17th March 20th something like that and there are some pretty cool features
In a new version of Gnome including a night shift filter like you have for instance on your phone
That will tend to your screen with a natural light at night so that it doesn't strain your eyes as much
There's a lot of features also for developers
Gnome builder and flat back are two big pieces of our ecosystem
and they're receiving a lot of new features for 324 and
Christian is right here behind me busy writing code on ground builder right now
Excellent so I know that you work for endless PC and you guys have designed it a very interesting operating system
Around no might one might even say that it's like the anti cloud operating system it runs so offline, right? Yeah
Yeah, so that's that's actually one of our core tenants at endless we
we were the company was born a few years ago with the mission of bringing computers really to the whole world population to as
many people as possible and
There's really two barriers to doing that and one is the price of the hardware
And that's why you know you see here some of the computers that we've made. They're pretty affordable. They're nice
They're very compatible with Linux. They run very very well you turn them on and you know everything is ready for you the other
Barrier typical barrier is the access to internet so the cost of connectivity or the access to connectivity at all
So we bundled inside the OS a lot of features
for consumption of content offline
So we want to almost bring a lot of the value of internet into the box itself so when you buy it
You will come preloaded with
something like a hundred and fifty
Offline applications on a variety of topics that you normally would Google things for life such as farming
encyclopedia or
Math or physics or biology or all these things?
So it's a it's a really good value for for people that don't otherwise have access to that information
The same way that we do here
Excellent if people were interested in in endless. What is the what is the what is the?
compelling use for the operating system if I didn't have an endless PC can I just can I go get the operating system and
What kind of people here in the US where we do have an abundant internet? Where are those?
What is that? What is your target audience here if any?
Yeah, so that's a that's a that's a good question. We launched actually this hardware line specifically for the US market this year
You can buy this from our website endless OS comm and also you can download a free
The free operating system from there so you can download the exact OS that you would find inside the box
For free from our website here in the United States. You're right
Internet connection is much better
But it's not that's not true everywhere so even inside the United States. There's a lot of places where that is useful
And you know even in California
There's a lot of remote areas where internet just doesn't get there because there's not enough people
So if you live in one of those areas this could be useful for you another
Interesting use case that we really had not thought about before when when we when we designed this but it turns out
It's it's a pretty good match. It's actually
prisons so they
you know, there's there's a lot of people there to have time and they
Want to study they want to learn new things, but they cannot access internet as a matter of policy, of course, so
We're doing some pilots with prison systems in a few states in the u.s
To see if this is a good match for them outstanding and how is that working so far?
It's been working pretty well. Yeah, the feedback that we've that we've received is pretty good. There were some
Things like we were shipping for instance open arena, which is a slightly violent game. We had to remove it
So there's you know, you have to adjust things for specific for the use case, but it's been working well so far outstanding
And so and you're providing the machines the hardware the software
I mean, that's a story right in of itself that you guys are reaching out to these people that are you know
That are in some ways underprivileged and and and providing them with with with skills and abilities that they can use if and when
They ever leave the prison system
They can become functioning adults back into society and they will know how to use a computer system exactly exactly
Yeah, so yeah in some cases we've donated hardware in other cases
we've partnered with associations that were already working in the prison and
We installed it on the computers that they already had so endless is at the end of the day like another
Linux based OS is compatible with the whole variety of a hardware that you know other districts like Ubuntu or Fedora are compatible with
So you can run it on anywhere take a given that you also have a Fedora laptop is have you found that Fedora is a
Is a good operating system for exemplifying. No
Absolutely, I think Fedora is one of the distros that always strives to give the
Vanilla gnome user experience to the user and actually in Fedora 25, which is what we have on the laptop there
It's the first distro that I know of that ships with Wayland by default. So
You know, we've been waiting for this moment kind of for many many years the point where we stopped using X and it's it's there
And I have to be honest. I didn't even notice that I was using Wayland until maybe you know two weeks later
I saw some like minor bugs, but it is really really polished. It's a really great distro. That's fantastic
So you personally use Fedora on your computer?
Yeah, I have on my work computer. I use Endless, but my personal computer is Fedora
Nice, that's outstanding. And so is Endless a rolling release or is it a static build?
Are they static build? Endless is
It has a about a three-month release cycle. So we have
major quote-unquote updates every three cycles
So we go from version 3.1 to 3.2 to 3.3
And then we have point releases about every three weeks to a month depending on exactly why we need to make a point release
Sometimes there are critical bugs to be fixed though. We have to you know, make it quicker
But no, new features only get out every two or three months. It's not a rolling release
Now tell me what was the design thought behind this idea of on the screen here
We have you can see where like these icons are in the center
And if I if I click down, you know here there's like a traditional menu structure
But we have occupied the majority of the desktop space with application shortcuts and interestingly enough
You know
We started back in the 90s where we had a bunch of things cluttering the desktop and then we kind of went away from that
But the reality is now like a mino machine. It's just I just have a pretty picture
It's really wasted a desktop real estate and you've you've actually taken that up with useful shortcuts
Almost kind of like in between a dock. Tell me about that. Yeah, so the idea for the icon grid specifically
Is to be familiar for users that are used to smartphones and tablets
So that's actually how you know your Android launcher or your iOS
application list works so endless the desktop works
Similarly, you cannot put your files on the desktop
It's really the launching page for all of your apps. So we try to start with a minimal
number of apps on the desktop so that the user is
Invited to explore the App Center
Which is based on GNOME software where you can you know add more apps to your desktop or download more things
from the internet download more bundles and expand your
list of available apps basically outstanding if people were interested in more
Information about GNOME or endless. Where could they go? So endless OS comm is the endless website from there?
You can find everything. There's also
Forums and a slack community if you're interested in participating
for GNOME a GNOME org is our main website and you can also find us on IRC IRC.GNOME.org and
The GNOME Wiki has a lot of information about the release and you know
The whole release process if you are interested in contributing back
So wiki.GNOME.org but GNOME.org is the main homepage outstanding cosmo GNOME.org. Thank you so much for your time
We really appreciate having you. Thank you. Thank you
That endless PC is actually pretty interesting because they got this mission now
The mission one is a gorgeous Linux powered desktop. Yeah, it's like on a bamboo case
Which has always kind of pushed my buttons the wood PC cases have always kind of done it for me
And I haven't really tried out endless OS yet
But after that interview, I was a little more tempted to maybe go give the ISO a download. So the mission one is
$250 and you can either get it with 320 gigabytes of storage or 500 gigabytes of storage and
I don't remember
Oh, yeah, here it is
Yeah, it's an Intel Celeron N2807 in it. It's got two gigabytes of DDR3 RAM
So that's kind of your base performance metrics. Then it's got two USB 2.0 ports one USB 2.0 port
Hopefully one of those three
So three USB ports maybe or maybe one of those actually it's a typo and I meant to write USB 3.0 VGA HDMI out
headphone jack Ethernet
Built-in Wi-Fi and Bluetooth I guess
You know for 250 bucks, that's that's not too bad that's not too bad and they really are
you know, you listen to that guy they really got an idea of philosophy behind this and
I kind of thought I'm not always a big fan of yet another derivative
No, but I don't know what I don't know how much they've I don't know how extended of nomad is I from what I did
I did a little reading a little research for the show
It looks like it's based on a slightly newer or I'm sorry slightly older version of gnome
I want to say 320, but I'm not positive. It was somewhere in that range interesting
So it's it's it's a fork or at least as a layer of extensions on top of gnome 3. I'm not quite sure
but it didn't look very usable so I
Might be I might be giving the endless the endless ISO download trying to think of like who in my life would would or could use
that
But I suppose if you're just really using web apps and you know
You don't want a big ugly weird box in your nicely decorated living room or computer room that it sits nicely on the desk
I guess I could see that. Yeah, I think yeah
I think if you had yeah, I could see a lot of family members that yeah
I could see a lot of people why we're talking about gnome see I'm give a little gnome love because are you still using plasma?
By the way, yep, I wish to talk about that
But there's also a write-up at fedora magazine org on getting more out of gnome notifications
Which is a thing no notifications, which are not bad not bad at all my friend and with a few tweaks
Maybe a few extensions or things like that you can get even more
Include including creating your own
Notifications like things on the command line so that's also linked in the show notes so Wes
Did you end up playing around with like controlling where the screens will go or your where your windows go on your screen based on?
Keyboard commands, I know that was something a little bit
I have a list of things to try that I have not gotten to so I started playing with that
I got a couple things set up, but there's a couple
Plugins and settings that have been recommended to me that I have not got around to trying yet
There's some stuff. That's a little more replicate replicate some of the stuff that I three or similar does
So I'm looking forward to extend it more or see if it can meet my needs because I'm really liking a lot of the other
Stuff the one thing that I keep messing up though
I'm used to like when I have the lock screen on gnome
I have to hit enter and then I type you don't have to but I'm just used to doing it
But if you do that on the plasma lock screen boom now. I have the time out
Yeah, I have to learn something so but I'm trying to I want to stick with it long enough that those things have all gone
Away, and I can give it really a better understanding of if it works for me
So I had two things this week with the with my adventures with plasma
And I thought they were both noteworthy for mentioning here on the show
I finally got a chance to getting around to play with KD connect because I'm back on
Android and back on my Nexus 6p, and so I just took advantage of I was like well
This is one more way. I can use the plasma desktop now. I really like that. I really do like it
I'm not so sure if I want notifications that are showing up on my Android device show up in my desktop yet
I'm still like feeling that out, but just some of the basic functionality. It's it really feels like
2017 I mean it's nice and it's so much more practical than what I seemed to grok with the like that the iOS
Functionality, I guess maybe iOS I don't know if there's a way to like share your clipboard with the Mac desktop with where with their
Handoff stuff, but I know you can like open up like links and web pages
But it's it's not nearly as nice as like it is with Katie connect can a kitty connectors
It seems very thoughtfully made it's one of those things that would make me want to stay on Android mm-hmm
I'm also working on iOS support. Oh really well there you go. I wonder if it'll be nearly as functional
Yeah, that's something to watch yeah, because it's it's always running on the phone, right?
It's you can get it from the Play Store and
Then the other thing the other just sort of noteworthy
Adventures with plasma this week would be I decided to set up the Macbook Pro that we set up
Months ago on the show running arch I've switched that over to the plasma desktop from no hey
Yeah, and this was my first time setting up plasma desktop on a high DPI display where?
Everything was high DPI by default. How did that go? I'm curious. I I it was great
I think I tweaked the mouse cursor a bit, but on all my previous installations of plasma on a high DPI display. I've always
My first instead right after install. It's everything's tiny
It's all really tiny and you got to go into the settings
And you got out you guys turn up the scale and turn up the font DPI and you got to change you know
Some of your window sizes
I did still have strange windows that like rendered way too small like it like the size of a 640 by 480
Resolution just tiny little window they have to resize to see the entire UI
but out of the box after I installed plasma desktop just
Logged out and logged into the plasma desktop and everything was high DPI. I didn't have to change a damn thing. That's awesome
It is it is really nice to see him going that direction
So I still so I guess my my take is I'm getting deeper into the plasma ecosystem now with KDE Kinect and
I've put plasma desktop on my main driver at home the the Macbook run an arch with now plasma
Yeah, I haven't really I haven't really felt the need to reinstall and go to like KD neon or yeah
Same thing yeah, yeah, and plasma 510 is just around the corner sure
Never hey, that's sure yeah sure all right. Let's talk about the light book
I think producer Michael's been following this one pretty closely
I'd like to get his his thoughts on it because it seems like a pretty good deal, but is it too good to be true
I'll tell you about something. That's great, and it is true
That's digital ocean go over to digital ocean calm and use our promo code do unplugged you apply it after you create your account
You get a $10 credit you support the show and you can play with their $5 rig two months
For free digital ocean calm use our promo code do unplugged take advantage of their all ssd-based cloud
They're lightning fast networking with 40 gigabit connections coming right into them hypervisors. Oh those hypervisors. Yeah, they run Linux
They use KVM for the virtualizer pal
You got Linux for the base operating system SSDs for all the disk i.o. 40 gigabit connections data centers all over the world in choice
Locations highly available block storage which you can attach up to 16 terabytes love it and an interface
The interface is beautiful. It's the best interface. It's huge. It's great
It is so well done
And it doesn't matter if you're a total noob like you barely even understand that web servers are a thing and you need a website
You could manage to use this to somebody who's been setting up virtual servers for literally their entire
Career will find this to be a great interface. How do they do it?
I think they're from the future. Yeah, I can't really I can't square it. Otherwise
Either that or they had this great API and they're like damn
This API is so dank that we need an interface that comes close to being as dank as our as our API
That's the only two things I can figure I can only it's either they're from the future or that dank API is so dank
They had to have a dank interface. That's the only thing I can figure so you got to check it out yourself
digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplug spin up a rig try out a different Linux distro
Maybe go outside your comfort zone. What you're so important can't go outside your comfort zone. Try it
They also now have load balancers monitoring service coming soon
You can sign up for holy smokes digital ocean look like a pro and use our promo code do
Unplugged and a big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring
This on here this here right now
upload program
So the light book is it a scam is it a total scam is it from?
2014 for two hundred and forty nine dollars
they say you can get a 32 gigabyte msata drive or you can pay a little more and get up to 512 gigabytes of
Storage they say it's got Linux by default elementary OS at that a 1080p display 4 gigabytes of RAM and
an Intel Celeron quad-core
processor
Hmm
250 bucks it seems to be the new sweet spot right everybody's trying to hit 250 bucks and
The only the only thing that's weird about this outside from just things
I've noticed just looking at this all of the product images are totally gimped
There's no there's no real shots of the computer
But it looks like you can also find this exact image with like a video game
Gimped into it or you're probably in this case. It was photoshopped
Just probably I would assume running Windows just the exact same product shot just a different complete
Operating environment on the screen
Going back for years now. It's so that's a little weird
That's a little concerning, but but maybe but maybe but maybe what they're doing is they're taking something that's been around since 2014
They're rebranding it and because it's fairly old the margins are super low so they can sell for 250 bones
that's the reasonable take but
Producer Michael you've been sniffing around. What's your take you think it's a scam
Do you think there's something else going on here, or is this a legit rig?
I've no idea. It's it's more the thing of it looks really promising
But it feels a little sketchy with the photos with the fact that
There is no name associated to the company that there's no person's name when you go to their forum
It just says director as the person replying like there's absolutely no name. There's no photos
There's one video on YouTube where it shows a person's face because he's recording the lap the light book
With his phone and then the reflection of the of him is in the in the screen
so
It's just which is kind of feels weird, but like the photos thing
Every photo that's on their website except for the the software photos
But all the product photos are also on like Alibaba and stuff like that
I I it just seems odd that they're not being more
Transparent about the company structure, but I mean I found out they are supposedly
Located in Tampa, Florida, and that's where they ship from so there's no international shipping
for US people and
The price like I found out what the processor is it's a 3050 Celeron, which is a pretty good Celeron
It's better than a Chromebooks normal typical processor 31 50 right 31 50 I
Yeah, I think 31 50. I don't remember exactly number, but I'm pretty sure it's 31 50 and so it's a decent
Yeah, it's it's better than the average Chromebook
There's a couple things I tell you that and I think this came out via reddit posts
And they were applying to people's questions a couple of things that are odd
So they asked well is elementary OS getting a cut of the sales a pretty reasonable question for a laptop featuring elementary OS
And the quite the response at first was well
Yeah
About two to four dollars and then and then when people ask a little bit further it turns out well it kind of depends on
Bugs and we run into because we're actually doing this via the body source. Yeah
They're gonna do it via bug bounty the bounty source like okay, so I'm not getting a cut of each laptop
You're you're just gonna use their bug bounty system if you make some profits okay, all right, okay?
So then it turns out well is this really elementary OS or are you modifying this no no no we're not modifying it except for
Well, we have updated the kernel to kernel 48
We've pre-installed play on Linux also King soft office and Firefox is now the default web browser, but otherwise
It's stock elementary OS honestly
I didn't see them saying that they didn't modify it every time I someone asked someone asked a question about
Modifying it they say they give a list of everything. They've done. Oh, I was told they denied it at first, but okay
Yeah, there's also there's there's articles out that are reviewing it. They're acting like he deliberately ignored
No, he didn't it's in it's in another thread. Yeah, so you go through
There's a couple of them you go through and it's you know a lot of it is just odd stuff
Nothing that jumps out of you
it's just odd stuff and you the thing is that happens with something like this is is
You you really have to kind of I just think of all experienced like
The Kickstarter that's gone wrong or the gofundme or IndieGoGo that's gone wrong
It's everybody has to goes everybody has to go total skeptical mode when they see this stuff
So I'm not actually I don't I don't actually want to put them down too much
But it does seem to me like there if anything where we are okay, though
Like the stuff they keep saying like if you go to their forums though
The way they're doing it is sketchy their responses
They give a kind of promise and back get a best case what we what we have here is a 2014 laptop
That's been rebranded right and then they're they're just selling that with some support. I think it's probably
It was probably what's happening
I don't know if the laptop is like manufactured in 2014 or is it like that model was first released in 2015
I couldn't find information about that or not
That's just what one of the articles said was that 2014 is from there like well, yeah
But they could have just you know reiterated it
But I don't know that it's hard to tell on those will and all like Alibaba's
subscriptions because they're all like
buzzword heavy
So what was it that set off red lights for you then?
It wasn't it wasn't like it wasn't like a red light thing. It was just like all of this stuff together is sketchy
Like if it was one of these things I went out
It's like if it was just at the Alibaba thing
But they're like presenting it and marketing it very well and they have a lot of information about who's running it and all this other
Stuff I wouldn't care because you know
Rebranding things like people do that with clevo all the time
So it's not that big of a deal. So if if that's all they were doing
It's just like all of these things combined feel weird
so like they could have just said we don't have product photos that are really genuine yet because we don't have a
Photographer and we're not good all we have a camera phone and that's probably not a good way to present your products
You know that kind they could have done that
There's there's plenty of options. They could have done to make me feel
Not so iffy about the issue
But it's just like if you go to their YouTube channel, they have like weird videos that are weird
One of the videos is like vertical
Recording with the phone vertically and
Then also horizontally so like they started a video vertical realized it was vertical and then turned it horizontal yet
The video is still vertical. So it's really awkward. Love it. I love that. Yeah
It's just that kind of weirdness that makes me feel weird
But like if I could play with a laptop
I would definitely do that because if they had like, you know
Yeah review units or something they could send that would be cool
But that would probably be that would be the real way to tell well, you know what?
I guess the other thing I would say Michael is it sort of
Sort of was an indication to me the total lack of enthusiasm or plugging or hype coming from
Elementary OS which would seem to suggest that they're not on board with this
Well, I mean they definitely aren't like involved in the situation
so I mean, I wouldn't try to promote it if they if I didn't know about it as much either but
They were aware that it was happening before it was announced. So
They weren't like they were just denying involvement. They're not denying what they're not
They don't have any assessment whether it's good or not. They're just basically staying out of the situation
And I understand yeah, I understand why they're doing it
But I also don't think it's a big deal that they are like it like a lot of companies aren't you know?
Ubuntu is not, you know advocating for specific
Products and stuff like that. They'll say they'll give you a list about what works and what what doesn't
You're right and from a licensing standpoint you're correct
I would think though that if any distribution out there is going to be hypersensitive to their product being
It's because look think about who's who really loses here is the customer and that sucks for elementary OS because
Who's gonna want something like this is gonna be an elementary OS enthusiast, but they're not actually getting elementary OS
They're getting something that ships a different kernel a different browser and other things that have been modified to it
So it's not something actually supported by the elementary OS project
So if they're if it's an elementary OS fan, they're actually they're getting it's a disservice and that's got to piss off
I would think Daniel I would think that well, I wouldn't be happy about that. It's a bit unusual
So there's been a few
Vendors that have shipped Ubuntu Marte on their laptops
most notably
Entroware, but a few others around Europe as well, and they've all had the courtesy to get in touch and
Express their intent to do this and just make sure it's okay now our
Preferred Ubuntu Marte's preferred vendor is Entroware, but there are others. There's slimbooks and
Tuck something or other in Germany. I forget the name
and they're all selling Ubuntu Marte and they're adhering to the terms of the
Ubuntu trademark requirements, which is they ship the vanilla image. So I could understand why
Elementary would feel a bit put out by having a device
Probably piggybacking off of elementary's brand to ship a product
Without actually involving them. Is this a Chinese vendor by any chance this white thing that I'm looking at on your YouTube?
It sounds like it sounds like yeah, you saw there
I'm sure is a Chinese company is okay. Yeah the builder
But the the company who is selling it as the light book and they're also rebranding it because so I'm they must have a deal
Because there is like, you know label like branding etched onto the laptop
That's in one of the videos. You can see him says alpha on the back of it
And that's the name of their company alpha light, but where are they based? They're in Tampa
Huh, Tampa, Florida, but they haven't like that's all I could find out because it says they ship from there
but I haven't found like, you know a business address or anything like that, so it's
It's weird. They have the elementary logo on the site, too
Yeah, this just feels like the same the same kind of thing that you get from any like Alibaba a Chinese vendor who
Just picks up a piece of software sticks it on a device and ships it out the door at the lowest possible
Price, so this seems this is a lot different because in the reddit AMA they did
people have asked a lot of different questions and every question they you know responded to was
You know that the responses were very promising. For example, they asked about what processor was they gave the details
They asked about if it's possible to get bigger RAM like pull notes. It's a you know, SD RAM type
They were asking like is the battery replaceable as a hard drive placeable and like they were listing about how to replace the things
Like it wasn't like they even get to the point where someone said well
What if I want to have a different icon set like mocha and they said put it in your order and we'll add it before
You so it's it they are
Very attentive in the sense of the questions that are asked and if you go to the forum, they're also very attentive to that
Yeah, in fact, they say here in one of the in the AMA
Somebody says did you make this laptop as the post claims or are you just reselling somebody else's machine with elementary OS pre-installed and
Lightbook team who's been answering all the questions from lightbook says we are buying it at business to business
Prices and then selling it with our logo engraved higher specs and on a modified version of elementary OS
The majority of laptops made by smaller companies are just straight-up resales just like ours
It's part of an OEM and then they talk about the Windows keyboard key. It's part of the OEM keyboard
They'd have to order a certain amount from their supplier in order not to have the Windows key on there
So it's yeah, it's kind of like exactly which I think they're speculating
Yeah, and they also said that someone was like well, that's unfortunate
You can't really code the key, but they said every laptop comes with a sticker of elementary OS on it
So and in a way there is a
So in a way there there they are addressing stuff
It's just like their marketing needs work
I would say that what would jump out at me?
what jumps out at me as a
Systemic problem would be
if your product
Depends on elementary OS to sell
It is in your best interest and longevity to work with elementary OS just like entryware works
With wimpy because it's in their best interest for the project to know about you and like you
Because they want to sell more products theoretically and so if you don't care
We don't know if they contacted elementary and the elementary said no or not because yeah, you're right
Although i'm pretty i'm pretty much
I would be willing to make a bet that
Yeah, I I mean I agree with I agree with your bet
I'm just saying like we don't know for sure and it does feel sketchy
But like the responses they keep making on reddit, they still continue to respond to reddit questions
And on their forum you can go and leave a question and they'll you know, that's good. So that's a good answer really quickly
like it's it's
as far as like
You know sales uh in customer service type approach. They're very good at responding and they're very
Uh open and they're not trying to pretend about like different things. They're not trying to be like, you know
A uh, a fake company like a fake chinese company using chinese products and just you know, pretending that it's a new thing
They are admitting what they're doing
It's just their mark the way their marketing feels really sketchy because there's like no one associated to it. There's no
Like there's no original photos, but they do actually show the video in gray that the laptop engraved. So it is
Like their claims are legitimate. They have proof of that, but it's just feels I don't know it still feels sketchy
I if I had a spare 250, I totally would try it
I think I also agree with the beard in the chat room
He says, you know, the thing is is how much of a discount could they really be getting?
With the expected amount of sales numbers they're going to get these are probably going to be under a thousand easily I would say
But who knows but even let's just say it was five thousand. They're not going to get some sort of massive discount
So where is the room for profit?
So what that seems like they have like if you can get 150 with uh,
You can get a laptop those laptops at a buying a quantity of 300 you can get them for 150
So that's all there's another problem then because that's that's too easy. That's that's that's too easily accessible, too
There's this is this is not a we don't know if that's actually what they're doing
I just know I just saw that myself. They might actually be better for them. I don't know if they do it
Yeah, they say, you know, they're saying they're buying they're saying they're you know
They are buying business to business and getting some sort of bulk discount. That's all they've said
Uh, I would be wager. I'd be willing to wager if I was going to be looking at this and it's something I'd be
You know, this would be part of my calculus would be they're probably not going to sell tens of thousands of these things
So they're probably not getting some astronomical discount and they don't seem to be directly working with elementary OS
So they don't seem to have a clear path to profit and they don't seem to have a good relationship with the distribution
They're shipping. They're also not
As michael's talking about they're not really presenting a human face, right that you can become excited about yeah
Understand the motivation, you know, we're left to speculate
But here's something that I have learned over the years and this is where I kind of give them some room is
When you are just setting up like I go back to the purism folks when you're just getting set up with this
It is there is so many little things that you have to get just right for a product like this that it can take a company
A few times of trying this before you can actually get it
A few times of trying this before they really start to fire on all cylinders
And this could be their first foray into this area. I I know lightbook is uh, I mean, I I guess it's available now
Isn't it actually I think you can I think they say order now at least so I I guess they are shipping it
So it is it's a it's a product. It's gonna get out there
They'll have customer feedback and we'll see if they iterate on it. I I it's enough to pique my interest
250 to 270 depending on your amount of storage
That's it. You know, that's that's enough. That's enough to kind of pique my interest and go there might be something here
that's worth to worth discussing but
It oh you can get it in black. There you go. Wes. I know how you like everything
Oh, really you got to get one of each got to get I mean if you're real patient
there's a there's a white there's a black and there's a
One that's got white base and black. I mean a red back of the led led screen
This is pretty great
You mean you could in theory you walk away with a laptop with 540 gig 40 gigabyte 544 gigs of quote-unquote hybrid storage
Which I assume is spinning with a on a solid little bit of solid state. No, no, no
It's it's two different drives one at one ms m.2 say to uh, in a ray gig ssd
And they're set. They're set as the they're set at dil boot. I'm, not sure how they've structured it
But one is they're basically they're saying hybrid approach, but it's not a hybrid drive
It's two different drives one ssd. That's 32 and one that's the hard drive. That's 500. Yeah, they call it hybrid storage
Okay, so that's where you get the 544 gigs
Um, and so for all of that, so whatever like raid or whatever they're using to pull that off
for that
And a black one that's you know got a decent seller on quad core in it. Um, 283
That's a pretty amazing deal and when i'm looking actually yeah, you know specs wise especially that it's a 1080
It's a full 1080p. Yeah, I like that. Yeah. Yeah, 1366. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. And you know, it's better than a chromebook
Yeah as much ram as a chromebook did hey and they take bitcoin damn it
Let's just put it in danger territory
damn it
It's interesting, huh?
yeah, it's uh
Something to watch was there was someone on reddit that said that they were going to buy it to do a block a review
on their blog, so uh
Yeah, i'll i'll try to like, you know bookmark that yeah, okay do it. Yeah, maybe follow
I keep following it for us
Maybe you know because it'd be interesting to see if they actually turn this into something, you know
Maybe you don't actually turn this thing into a real product
Maybe they'll get to the point where they'll their elementary OS project is comfortable working with them
And maybe they have to get to a point where they're substantial and demand the attention of elementary OS before and maybe it's who knows
I don't know. They should just give me a call and i'll help them with the marketing too. There you go. There you go
Find him
He's in the mumble room
He did a fight
Uh, i'm gonna give a real quick plug before we run for linux fest northwest coming up soon may 6th and 7th
I'll be there. Wes will be there. It's gonna be a hell of a show. I think I think right now, uh,
after after reviewing our
Adventures at scale this year and kind of looking at the news that came out from scale
I think it's safe to say there may be a new contender for the number one linux event
in the united states
run by the community
i'm not saying it's gonna be necessarily as big as something maybe the linux foundation could put on right
but as far as
run by the community
free to freaking attend
With a great venue and great talks. I think we may have a new pack leader stepping up
This is this so I mean I am so happy i'm so happy. I mean i've scaled
I i'm sure they'll pull things around too. They'll they're gonna they're gonna get that live stream taken care of and that whole
Attendance thing figured out they're gonna get it pulled around
I believe in them, but I think this might be this might be linux fest year right here
2017 is the year to go. I am really looking forward to it. Noah and I are already rubbing our hands together making plans
Yeah, we've oh
Very excited about it. You can find out more at linuxfestnorthwest.org
And we'll have a booth there we'll have swag there we'll be doing a live show from there
We'll be doing after party in there. We may do all kinds of things
So check it out. If you could make it we'd love to see you at linuxfestnorthwest.org
All right, that's going to bring us to an end of the show
I wanted to say thank you to the live stream for making it this week
You can find the show over jblive.tv on a tuesday
In fact, if you show up you get a little extra because after this it's the tech snap program
It's like the pre-show for that's right
It's the pre-show right here warm up. Yeah, we're warming up. We're warming up find west on the twitter at westpain
That's right. You can also find mr. Wimpy mark and poppy and the ubuntu podcast at ubuntupodcast.org
Follow myself at chrislas
Get our live times at jupiterbroadcasting.com
calendar submit content to the show at linuxactionshow.reddit.com and get your emails at jupiterbroadcasting.com
Contact and last but not least if you're still listening on youtube smash that like button because come on
Long-form content needs your love, right?
Right, right back here next week
music
Awesome. Thank you everybody in the Mumba Room. It was great to have both Popey and
Wimpy back. Nice to hear from Mr. Lunduke. Now we gotta go pick our titles. Go get your
titles. And then Mr. West has got to get his business up in here. You know what I'm saying?
That's right. Turn on JB1. So JBtitles.com. That is bright. That reminds me of the Kodi
Android situation in a way. It's not exactly similar but it reminds me of that. Yes Mr.
Popey. Hey Chris. So a couple of things I didn't want to mention on the show but I thought
I'd tell you now. There was a Red Hat booth at MWC as well and loads of our guys went
over there because they had some of the best coffee at MWC. That's awesome. Good on you.