As long as everybody keeps showing up. We'll just keep using mumble for voice is what I figure cuz you know power to the people
Yeah
I've um, I've not reconfigured my new IRC with
Geek shed so if I can just fire up discord that is easier new IRC, huh?
I've switched over to IRC cloud. Oh really and and
This is a controversial move apparently because when I did this I got a whole bunch of crap for it
But I think it's actually kind of a practical use to for IRC. It's just makes it simple
And you make you set it up in one place and you log in when you need IRC
Yep, so the way I've been doing it is I used to run ZNC on a droplet
which is an IRC bouncer and that effectively maintained a persistent connection to the
Dozen or so servers and the thousands of blooming channels that I'm in
And then I had to fire up hex chat which connected to that and that was fine if I was on my desktop
but I didn't have a convenient way to do stuff on my mobile devices and
IRC cloud is brilliant and it even has IRC cloud desktop app now. Yeah, which low and behold is electron. Yes, and
Now I just fire that up login login to any browser on any machine and I'm just there and on my phone and when people
Ping me in the various channels. I just get notifications on Android. It's just glorious. I'm never going back
It's great. The mobile support is really top-notch since it's it's server-based IRC
The server always remains in the IRC room and then the way they're able to send it to your mobile device is pretty smart
Of course, they have full support for
Notification settings and granularity there is it's nice
I kind of every now and then still like to fire up a traditional IRC client that's just connected like a single room
but
recently becoming enamored with
A riot actually. Oh, yeah did for quite a while, but right has inbuilt IRC bridging
As well as some other services, right?
Right and the cool thing about it now is that you when you create a room
You can add your own kind of widgets to the room including things like, you know gdocs and everything else
But what really blew me away was it allows you to add a gypsy wizard widget
So you can actually have a gypsy conference room inside your matrix room
And it looks exactly the same okay as a conference room, you know, I tree bridges to me. I love it
I'm really proud of us. We managed to start talking about IRC and we still brought it to matrix. The matrix hype is strong
This is Linux unplugged episode
213 for September 5th
Oh
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show
It's surrounded by smoke. My name is Chris and this is a less hipster more bearded Wes
Also known as Rekai. Haha. All right. Well, he might take that he might actually take that
Yeah, Wes is out today more on that in just a moment
But let me tell you about what we have coming up on your unplugged program
We have lots of community news Linus passed a few stones and a new kernel
Microsoft is turning Linux into the ultimate runtime and I might be having an existential crisis about it
Heli packer just sent a Linux supercomputer up into space
We may be saying goodbye to Solaris a major feature that all of you have been wondering about is coming to Wayland
finally and
No one's removing some more features and they're pretty sure you don't need them. Hmm
Although I can't imagine life without it
We'll tell you about that and then later on in the show Ubuntu has got something cooking over in New York City
The guys over at canonical have a big party plan a rally you might call it
But tell you about that and then we're gonna wrap it up with something that I think maybe when I say it's gonna sound like what?
But stick with me stick with me here for a moment. There is a revolution a revolution in the works and
It's bots and it's not robots
It's not like crazy AI. It's just simple bots that are gonna replace our jobs
They're either they're already in the works
We'll tell you about how Linux is missing out on this why that matters a lot
And maybe how some of us here at JB are trying to make a difference about it
I know it sounds it sounds like almost like talking about VR. I wish it were true
But if you stick with me you make it all the way to the end
I'll try to explain to you why I think that it's gonna come harder and faster than any of us expect and
Unlike self-driving cars unlike virtual reality or even just AI and machine learning in general
Which are actually now starting to finally pay off after decades, you know, you and I just watched war games. Mm-hmm back from 1983
They were talking about this stuff
But they're actually starting to pay off bots
You're not gonna be like that. This isn't one of those hyped up things
this is gonna be something that scales of economy are gonna ram down our throats and
Microsoft and Google are gonna be the ones making all the money, but we'll talk about that later
We got so much Linux community stuff to get into a bunch of topics that I want to chat about
But before we before we bring in the Mamba room, I'll just address West couldn't make it today. He had he's on assignment
He's like on a mission
No, no Chris. You're wrong. I've just been slowly killing off all of your co-hosts on all your shows
Very good, sir. Smart move very cling on of you. So he couldn't make it today, but
We had thankfully beards been been stepping in so that worked out pretty well and I because of this
Totally blaming hashtag hashtag blame Noah hashtag blame West we're gonna
We're gonna we're gonna we're gonna punt on the gentoo challenge for one more week. I'm
Sorry, but look I couldn't I couldn't do it without West here. It's okay if you're scared
It's not that and the value of this is negative. It's just without West here
It's not a complete challenge
So and I got a couple of notes from people in the audience who've been taking the challenge
Most of them are done, but not everybody so I guess I guess not my fault, you know
It's just it just happens so many excuses
Let's bring in that virtual log time appropriate greetings mumble room. Hello
Hello hello, it's good to see you. It's good to see you I craves EFS
So let's talk about some some news from Linus
I guess I guess when you get famous even passing a kidney stone is newsworthy at least over at the register
Linus Torvalds has passed kidney stones and squeezes out linux 4.13
There's a couple of interesting things of note in here. By the way, Linus is okay
He said it was seven hours of pure agony. But other than that, he's okay
Here's some changes in 4.13 that I think are noteworthy for all of us
Finally finally, it's almost laughable. It is laughable. It's embarrassing
They finally changed the sifts behavior the default sifts
Which is basically the protocol that Samba uses to communicate with sift servers
They've changed it from SMB 1.0 to SMB 3.0 and Linus himself admits. It's embarrassing that we hadn't done that soon
Yeah, it only took a few major
Vulnerabilities to make that happen. It's naive
Now the reason why it hasn't been a major issue is because Windows servers stopped refusing it around Windows Server 2013
Depending on your group policies, so the server would then have to automatically try to negotiate up
But that takes time and then it negotiates to the lowest common denominator that it can get which isn't the best security approach
Here's what our friends at canonical are probably excited about
This also is the mainlining of the app armor code that will tie to
Snap confinement is this wimpy is not to talk out of turn here
Is this am I right? Is this everything we need for app armor to be bolted in? Yeah. Oh, yeah, that's a big deal
there's been an ongoing effort to make sure that all of that stuff got upstreamed for some time now and
There was a tweet by
Dustin Kirkland few days ago who highlighted that two of the canonical kernel engineers are in the top
Committers at the moment because of all of the work that's going on in that space. I saw that. Yeah, that is really impressive
So this is a big deal. This is this is 4.13. I think might also be the
Is this going to be what the future LTS is based off of is that right?
I think it might even land in 1710. I'm not certain
Hmm, but I it'll certainly be at the start of 1804
I I'm I'm not sure but the other interesting thing about 413 is this carries?
Most I think all of the important patches for the GPD pocket to run. No kidding. I missed. Yeah
That's great that now that makes me want one even more
Jeez that is one of those toys that I really regret I couldn't have got at the time because I
Had I really I really am excited by something. Yeah, I have one. It's really nice. I love it
You you do you you have you have I have I have one. Would you be happening to bring it to New York? I
Will be bringing let's talk about that
I have I have it on authority from the lead developer of Ubuntu multi that there may be a GPD pocket spin in the works
Oh boy, how about that? That is so cool. So do you I mean just quickly, I mean, are you satisfied with the purchase?
By and large, yes, the the only thing that's a bit sketchy is the the quality of the keyboard. Mm-hmm
Or rather the only bit that's a bit sketchy from the perspective of an end-user is the quality of the keyboard
And I haven't worked out yet if that is universally across all of them or it just depends what?
Manufacturing run you had. Yeah
So well you and I think we'll talk much more about that
But I wanted to cover some news that was happening right now
August 31st posted over at Tech Republic comm
the Tech Republic reports that
Essentially the way I read this is Microsoft's trying to position themselves as the ultimate Linux runtime
for people developing software on Linux and Windows and this is
Insidious as long as you don't need a GUI of any kind, right? Yeah, good disclaimer
So Craig Lowen, I think is how you say his name. He's the program manager at Microsoft
He's showing off a new feature for the Windows subsystem for Linux. Yep. They're adding features everybody and
What you can do and it's fascinating is you can chain commands together
From different distros and call them from all inside of Windows
So from the Windows command line, you could pipe data output from say Windows IP config
Into OpenSUSE which then could parse it for a few things and then pass it on to Ubuntu which then could do some other work on it
And then send it back to the Windows command line and it all happens under a second
You've run a Windows executable
You've fed that information into one of the Linux distributions has taken that output and feeds it into another Linux distribution
The chain of commands was relatively simple just in this example
But it even included like taking out IP information added color coding
They also demoed the ability to run multiple Linux distros side by side in Windows
Showing windowed versions of Ubuntu and OpenSUSE Leap 42 side by side
Do it using different tools just each in different command prompt Windows
So as well as allowing users to run bash tools and commands inside Windows
The subsystem also allows Windows software and files now to be called from bash
So is it just me or I will admit I have a bias in this particular
I can't help but see this now as exactly what Microsoft did to NetWare
Which was hugely dominant in the file server and print server space and authentication and directory services huge
And then Microsoft came in and implemented the NetWare compatible tools inside of Windows
So you could talk IPX you could log into NetWare networks
You could use their network directories for file permissions and provisioning of you could use the groups and all of it
And they just they gave it a they gave it a grade a experience
And then they made it really easy to move over and then they just slowly degraded that grade a experience until you just ended up using Windows
And I could see something similar where they do this
But with the real end goal is to get you in to get everything on Azure to get you on to you Windows is the ultimate runtime
All right well if you're going to use Linux if you've got to use that free tarred crap
Then you run it on your machine under Windows 10 in a window and then you run the services on Azure
I can't help but see it this way I can't help but see it as almost as a contempt for the Linux desktop
It feels to me like it's a it's a it's a it is a diminishing of the platform
I
Don't know the more they features they add
I really hope the subsystem for Linux would get implemented it would be what it was and it would just stay there
And it would just be a great easy way to run bash which my co-host on Koda radio has been trying
He says it's not perfect, but it would be a way to do it
but now this this is actually starting to bug me a little bit because
If you are if you are not really very comfortable with the Linux landscape one of the hardest choices is which distribution do I use?
Or how do I main compatibility across distributions especially when I'm trying to develop software and now they've solved that problem
And they've solved it with Windows
Am I misreading this I mean this feels bad to me. I mean you could you could take the opposite tack and say that
They're giving a good command-line experience for these distros which would ease the transition if people wanted to switch to a full-time Linux distro
Yeah, okay, I like that yeah, well are we interested to see how much more
of the sort of
Polishing of the the rough diamond Microsoft do because there are a number of things that don't work in WSL that I think for many
serious Linux users would be a showstopper and also I still feel like this is
Going after Mac's audience, you know, you know Mac OS these audience and demonstrating that you can have a solid
Linux user space on Windows and provide all of those
tools that you know front-end and back-end developers are using on Windows rather than
Leaving for Mac OS. Hmm
Yeah, you you're right. It probably is more of an assault against Mac OS or keeping people stopping the bleeding might be the other way to put it
Yeah, I think yeah, I don't know that many people will come back, but it might stop a few from leaving
Yeah, but if these features keep coming, maybe it will attract some people back. I don't know I I don't know enough about the
Mentality of developers using Mac and what's what's important to them to understand why they would choose Mac over Windows
now I'm
I'm curious actually because
obviously Microsoft invested quite a bit again to the whole PowerShell experience and
The fact is they're gonna be dumping that in favor of Linux
Which makes me wonder exactly what direction they think they're gonna go in. Are they dumping it? I don't think so
No, I've not heard that. I mean certainly PowerShell is available for Linux as well now
Yeah, and the thing is is there's a whole there's a whole ecosystem of Windows admins that are are using
Microsoft tools all day long that have no interest in Linux subsystems. So I don't think they could replace it
I mean you could make the argument that they could maybe
Just integrate PowerShell into the Windows subsystem for Linux and just make it one nice big package
Well, there is one more step to this world domination that Windows is driving for it's on the tip of your mind
I know it's the elephant in the room and it's it's
Dominance is impossible unless they implement this feature. Obviously, I'm talking about butter fs support. So
Posted on github this week win butter fs version 1.0. I guess probably wasn't posted this but the version this update
Win butter fs as you might guess is a Windows driver for a next-generation Linux file system and by next-generation
Well, that's that is a very that's a very polite way. It's more like the Voyager of Linux file systems
It's a reimplementation from scratch. So what could go wrong? It contains no code from the Linux kernel
It should work on any version of Windows 7 onwards. And of course because we like our
Our butter fs beta file systems to go with alpha drivers
This is really the perfect combinations and this guy of course is taking donations to support this work
Win butter fs version 1.0. It has read write support
Win butter fs version 1.0. It has read write support apparently has support for raid 5 and raid 10
So in raid 6 what could go what could go wrong? What could go wrong?
Have at it everybody
If you want that link is in the show notes for all of those thumb drives you formatted in butter fs and can't get
on
Windows
I don't I don't know. I don't know how we missed this next story
August 11th this happened and just it flew right over our heads
He let Packard sent a supercomputer into space on one of Elon's rockets one of the SpaceX rockets and
On a jono shuttle and it's kind of cool
it's more interesting than you might even think because
The the thing about these computers they usually put up there is they have to make serious modifications and they end up running like
Decade-old power PC processors and you know
They have 16 megabytes of RAM and they have these crazy old AB failover ROMs and all this weird like ancient stuff
So they can't really fully take advantage of high-end computing
well
We have a Mars to get to and we're not going to get there with
Emacs in our shuttles. Well, and you know, not only that but you know
One of the hardest things to deal with with these supercomputers is cooling if you it's true
But it's very cold. Well, so check this out. So this is this HP a HPE Apollo 40 that runs Linux
And it's using their new interconnect memory system and they made no hardware modifications to the server
They created a unique water-cooled enclosure. I'll show you a picture here in a moment
For the hardware and then they develop purpose-built software that runs on Linux that monitors the environmental constraints and
reliability requirements of a supercomputer in space and so normally so normally you'd have to just totally lock this thing down
You'd have to rugged eyes it you'd have to harden it
You'd run you'd clock everything down you do this crazy cooling and then you go through a NASA testing process where they test
146 different things about it and then they certify it and without making any modifications by using this software
they could automatically change this the load on the server and
Dial it up or dial it down clock it up clock it down based on radiation levels and things like that
They were able to without making any hardware modifications just doing it in software pass all
146 safety tests to put this freaking super server up into space
Here's a here's by the way. Here's a picture what it looks like. Does that mean that Linux officially has the
The most powerful supercomputer not on this planet it would have to be because we've never we don't do this normally
This is like a big deal and it's sort of a historical event for a supercomputer to be up in space and for to be running Linux
Is awesome and for the greater goal to be well when we go to Mars
We're gonna need to be able to play doom. This is how they're gonna do it
I'm just waiting for the
asteroid data centers
Yeah, that's gonna be great
With like with like these just like they'll just go on there and glom on and we'll just orbit around
With like these just like they'll just go on there and glom on and we'll just orbit around and they'll be their off-site backup
Connected via microwave. Yeah. Yeah, that's where back blazes future expansion actual cloud storage space cloud
You ever notice how every website wants to send you notifications is anybody turning those on?
I could only imagine how awful that be if you actually said as an experiment on a system
I'm gonna nuke after like a week. I should just allow all notifications on websites and see what that's like
I think I have mine automatically set to deny all oh, yeah. Yeah
All right. So let's talk about one of our cousins
Solaris seems to be dead as well as the ZFS teams and spark teams that were employed by Oracle
This is a process that's been going on since December 2016 really
When they laid off 2500 people from the Solaris division 2500 people. Holy crap
And then in January another 450 were laid off
But then get this
This is so cold
This week
September 1st
Oracle employees
started getting
FedEx packages
from Oracle America
Incorporated that you had to sign for and they either sent to the home some were sent to deaths and
That was the note that was the notification
They were getting laid off is these FedEx envelopes arrived that they had to sign for and there was no pre-warning
So people around the office start getting these packages just random people around the office like but not everybody
And so people start opening these up and like I just got fired
And then the person sitting next to him didn't get a package and they don't know if they're getting if there's this coming yet or not
It's and you sign for it. So they know that you saw it
Yeah, so Simon Phipps, I'm sorry
Simon Phipps tweeted for those unaware Oracle laid off all the Solaris tech staff yesterday in a classic silent end-of-life product move
It's such a crappy way they're going about it too
And so then people are able to see like that's their standard mo though
I mean Oracle known for handling anything with anything with tech to diplomacy
Yeah, it is true. It is it is it is really true
Now you can wonder if some of these may be able to join some of these developers might be able to join the Illumos project
Which is a you know an open source fork of open Solaris
And of course ZFS will continue on
There's different projects for that but she's Louise just I don't know it seems like Solaris is so here's how you know Solaris isn't
Obsolete even though it seems like it might be toss Linux users
But Oracle knows there's some people that still absolutely need it for their workload
So these these cold bastards are going to run virtual spark on on x86 systems
And they're launching a migration there's they haven't officially announced this new service yet, but they're on October 1st
They plan to launch this
Move your or your your Oracle Solaris instance to the cloud
And then they're gonna they're gonna emulate spark on x86 which you know, that's just gonna rock
That's just gonna rock and they'll label it as virtual spark on x86 your legacy Solaris app survival
on an x86 spark emulator and
People are gonna have to buy it because you know, there's these mission-critical organizational apps that run on these legacy installations
I've seen it myself
I've you know, I've worked at places
They've used it for weird things like massive statement printing and batch processing jobs and all these weird things
You think there'd be better systems and faster systems for but they're just they're totally dependent on it
And so Oracle's gonna try to get them to sign up for that virtual spark on cloud
Probably great performance
I think I think I think what people ought to do is if you're stuck in this spot
There's a there's a developer we've talked about before Brandon Greg. He works at Netflix
And we've talked about how he's on performance tracing on Linux under really high streaming loads
I know the BSD now guys like to tell you that they run all free BSD over there
But the dirty secret is they run quite a bit of Linux too
And he's he has done lots of great blog posts Brendan Greg comm about Linux under crazy workloads tracing processes
Metrics on Linux CPU usage and all that stuff and he's written a massively comprehensive guide on
Solaris Linux migration tips. This is current. He just posted this today
And he goes through all of it moving to a Lumos moving to Linux
He talks about the future of ZFS ZFS on Linux and open ZFS projects
He talks about observability, which is something that he has a unique perspective on like this
These are the performance things you should expect
This is how you're gonna be able to if you do these kind of performance tracing and metrics on Solaris
Here's what you're gonna be able to do or how you get that information under Linux. It's it's fascinating
and Maybe very very useful and it's you know, it's coming from this guy who's got a lot of experience
Working at Netflix and he does a piece here that may be more relevant than ever
Zones versus containers, which if you're interested about this
He's got a good space on sort of a nice transition guide from a smart guy. Yeah with a lot of experience, but wow
That's so it's so weird because like I don't know
You know Solaris has literally been around since I've been in the industry
I think I mean I think so I I just it to me it seems like one of those never like IBM's
System 390s like they're just never gonna go AIX. It's just never gonna go away
But Solaris or Oracle is ruthless, I suppose
All right, any guys any any Slayer stories or closing thoughts on saying goodbye to a cousin of ours before we move on
We do have many things to cover
Just very sad. I used to work at Sun used to work on Solaris
1993's my first internet chat room experiences were on some machines
Yeah, this is really the death of Sun is as a as any kind of organizational structure that remained
Honestly the way they let them go just does not surprise me
I mean Larry Ellison is a very famous jerk and
It just trickles down throughout the company and he he set the clock
Yeah, well, you know, hey at least we've got unbreakable Linux. So everybody go install unbreakable Linux because that's the future obviously
That's the way to go known as Red Hat. Oh
Well, so whenever we talk about Wayland the thing that everybody always writes in or comments on an episode is
When we go to Wayland, how the heck am I gonna have remote desktop?
Well, remember remember there's a technology we talked about a little while ago
PipeWire, I think it's called when it may be here to solve our problems. I'll tell you more about that in just a moment
First I'm gonna tell you about ting you go to linux.ting.com to get $25 off a device or
$25 in a service credit if you bring a device and you support this here show
You're still rocking the s6 over there on the ting that way until it dies. Are you feeling like it's time for an upgrade?
Um, not quite yet. Yeah, although some of that new Android Oh stuff is looking pretty good
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, like the notification grouping stuff is what I like the most. I think I like the the fact that you can upgrade your
your
OS without having to upgrade all the drivers. All right, cuz it's the first one to ship with treble. Yep
Yeah, that's what's so great about ting is they're really just mobile the way it's meant to be they get out of your way
So I have a Nexus 6 on ting. It's running the day. Oh came out. I got it
It ting doesn't get in the way. They don't have to like skin it with the ting experience, you know, or the ting video store
The ting app store. There's none of that
If you whatever your device ships with that's fine
They don't care if you want to get it from play and bring it over if you want to go grab a device from their store
Their honey badger about it. Just check their BYOD page and here's why it matters
You just pay for what you use you got Wi-Fi where you're at
Then you're not on the ting network. You're not paying for it
If you're on telegram or whatsapp or whatever you're paying for it
You're not on the ting network. You're not paying for it if you're on telegram or whatsapp or I don't know
Whatever messenger you like to use then you're not using SMS so you don't pay for it
I never make phone calls unless I have to like I was just talking about I will call somebody through slack
Through slack before I will use the phone
So I really don't need to pay for minutes unless I have to make a phone call
So it's just your minutes your messages and your megabytes
It's six dollars for the line and then whatever uncle Sam's cut is and that's it
You're always in control. You can see your usage at any moment
You can take complete control and set usage alerts and they have a CDMA and GSM network
So good pretty pretty good. Here's my question Chris
When is ting gonna start making phones? I know right the ting phone that way I can just get my updates day one
For non Google devices in the meantime, they are giving away a moto e4 plus
You can get in on that go to the ting blog just start by going to linux.ting.com linux.ting.com and thanks to ting
For sponsoring the unplug program
I'm really excited about pipewire. It's going to solve so many problems if they manage to pull it off and I like where they're starting
So a quick recap pipewire is a skunkworks project to potentially replace pulse audio and G streamer with one rebuilt
From the ground up media pipeline like a proper media API for a desktop
But it's starting in different areas and I think this is kind of genius so remote desktop under Wayland never been a thing
Wayland don't got time for that is Wayland is a protocol. It ain't Wayland's problem
So that's the thing that's what's really been holding it up is that it's not the job of the Wayland project to implement this
Then you have it then it comes down to like your mutters or your K wins of the world
And they're gonna have to implement something and this is where pipewire comes in
It's an API they're building for Gnome remote desktop
It's going to be a service that works with Gnome and it uses Dbus APIs to talk to lib mutter
Mutter is the Gnome window manager and the Wayland compositor
They're implementing two new APIs and they're like ones like a screencast one and one's a remote desktop so screen casting is also part of this
And the pipewire stream containing the contents of the system stream will be sent to a system
The new APIs can create full screen streams streams of just individual windows, which that sounds amazing
Which we could totally use that in production and and the form has already been implemented in this code
The new API allows for services such as RDP or VNC servers to be piped through this
Which really opens it up to the type of clients you can use there's all kinds of VNC stuff you can do with it
It's not really clear like when this is going to hit mainline Gnome
It could be a way off but there the test codes out there have they said what language it's in
I don't think so. I wonder we'd probably have to whatever pipewire is written in. Yeah, I guess I would imagine, you know
I'm just wondering how Gnome independent it is for other people to pick up. Well, it talks directly to mutter
So you don't yank out mutter yank out any of this and nobody but Gnome is crazy enough to use mutter
Well, yeah, but you could you could maybe write bindings for something else
Um, yeah. Yeah, I suppose so. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. What do you I mean, what do you think?
As I mentioned a couple of weeks back that the, you know, Wayland default compositor system had it built into it
So everyone's free to implement their own version of it. Oh, OK. So it has to be done to the actual compositor itself
You're talking about Weston. So are you saying Weston has is that what you're talking about?
Yeah, Weston had a patch for it a long time ago. Really? Yeah, yeah. I know I don't remember us talking about that
But that's great. And so the problem is, is that people people don't use Weston, of course
So they have to get that implementation in their own compositor
Mr. Wimpy, I'd love to kind of pick your brain about this from a Matei perspective
And the fact that this is tied directly into mutter. You have any thoughts on that and Wayland in general?
Well, it's not so much this tied into mutter, but the more I look at Wayland, the more I realize
If you are wanting to write a Wayland compositor and all of the other stuff
The Wayland compositors that exist at the moment extend the Wayland protocols
That's the first thing. And the second thing is you have to implement much of what X does for you already
In each of the compositor implementations. Absolutely. And it feels like a lot of heavy lifting and duplicated effort
And in the smaller projects, there is not the breadth or depth of skills to do that
I also agree with that. So I have a concern that if we don't coalesce around some standards that are not tightly coupled
To a particular desktop implementation, then some of the desktops that we have could become irrelevant in the next five to six years
Because I still reckon that's the time it's going to take for Wayland to really replace the functionality and serviceability of X for most people
I think that's 100% spot on. 100%. And when I see these kinds of things, like this is great, this is going to be great for Gnome users
This is going to be really great. But if it is only useful for Gnome and desktops using mutter, then it's always going to be a niche implementation
I agree with Wimpy. We need something that's common across, we really need something common across all the
Well I suppose if they're all talking RDP and VNC, it might not matter in the end, but if we have varying implementations or varying levels of performance
It's the exact kind of shitshow that Windows and Mac never have to deal with. It is almost the prime example of a Linux shitshow
That causes hassle for system administrators, end users, and everybody to understand, and it causes a difference of development time
So on that point, imagine this then, I'll be devil's advocate, what if this move towards Wayland and the technologies that are being developed
With most momentum to support this new way of doing things are coming out of the Gnome camp
What if all we're left with at the end of this is Gnome and also KDE because they're able to keep pace with this
What if the Linux desktop is Gnome, so just like Mac OS and Windows, there is only one desktop environment that you have to now focus on in order to target Linux
Is that better or worse?
Well here's where I begin to get a little concerned. This alarms me a bit because you could see it going this way even if it wasn't as black and white as that Wimpy
But say all of the enterprise market, all of the business market ran Gnome, the dev ops market runs Gnome
Where it's such a huge percentage that it becomes the only relevant one in terms of industry, which we could already be sliding in that direction
Not in terms of community weight, but in terms of industry weight
Given that Mood 2 has been dropping Unity in favor of Gnome, it hardly makes Gnome niche applications does it?
Well that's true. See the thing is, the more I hear about Gnome, the more it feels like a hacked together desktop
And you will need somebody that really knows what they're doing to give you a good Gnome experience
So there's an update on Alan Day's blog about status icons being removed from Gnome 3
Have you guys heard about this in Gnome 3.26, status icons going away?
You know, the ones like your Dropbox icon, your Skype icons, your Discord icons you might have right now as you're listening to this show, VLC
If you want to keep them, the official recommendation of the project is to install top icons extension
I think that may be a Wayland limitation actually, because I noticed when I switched to Wayland, my icons just disappeared
There's a few, they say this long term the change will be good for end users, they're going to provide a better experience
It goes into some detail, here I'll give you the rationale before we go too far
The main reasons relate to two things, they think it will be a better experience for users
And it will align with Gnome's wider design philosophies and goals
Which is always a great one, so they're going to implement new APIs, notifications, MPRIS which is media playback
Search providers and libcloud providers for things like file sync
Here's their core rationale, the design of status icons goes against Gnome's principles
They know from observation that people often only care about a small fraction of their status icons that they are exposed to
But the rest that just get stuck in there don't reflect their interest or any of the activities they're doing
And it stems from an old status icon API and the ethos behind it
Users do not opt into status icons
How do they know?
Well, observation they say
What usability studies have they conducted to back up that point?
What usability studies have they conducted to remove all the other features that they've removed?
So this is where I'm going with this
Shouldn't that be known from the Gnome extensions at all?
Because I'm not tying to your individual desktop
Can we pause for a moment though and can we have a discussion about the fact that
Perhaps one of the most relevant Linux desktops, the official recommendation of the project
Is if you want that basic functionality, install an extension
And that to me doesn't feel like a sustainable good route
Like we can't have our most, like this stuff has to be, some of this stuff has to be, it can't be extensions
It has to be baked in
Well yeah, because if you think about the knock-on effects from that, every time you update your Gnome desktop
If the extension is not updated, you don't have status icons anymore
And talk about ultimate fragmentation
Just a support nightmare, a standardization nightmare, a developer targeting nightmare
You have no idea if a user is going to have a status icon
Again, I want to pick your brain, Wim, because I know you guys over there at Canonical have been
Churning out this 1710 desktop, working with Gnome
You guys have got to be coming across stuff like this
You know, with the dock, to status icons, to testing Wayland
Is Gnome 3 not it?
Like are we going all in on something that's just, it's hacked together with extensions
Mudder is a performance hog
Like I'm JavaScript all over the place
I know I'm hitting typical Gnome talking points
But we are really on the precipice of something here
And I'm curious what you think about it
Being right there on the front lines of implementing a modern Gnome desktop right now
Well, I'm not on the front lines of implementing Gnome
Okay, near the front lines
You're much closer than the rest of us, let's put it that way
I have some sight
I don't know what the position on indicators are with regards to the Ubuntu implementation
I imagine that we will find out in fairly short order what with Gnome 3.2.6 coming along next week I think
And we're obviously releasing our first Gnome based desktop a month after that
So it remains to be seen
There are some rough edges that we're running into
You know, we're seeing some processes are crashing way, way more than we've seen in the past
There are some Gnome services that have a colossal number of duplicates that are crashing in the same way
And that's because we have a lot of users
And there are a lot of users that are very interested in the 17.10 release
So there's lots of people that are banging on it even at this early stage
But that gives us the opportunity to use those as data points
And identify where the rough edges are and where development effort needs to be focused
And as I understand it, there are good lines of communication upstream
So if we've got good data to support investigation into stabilizing particular pieces
Then I'm sure they'll be open to us helping do that
We have a new update
Is it didrocks? Am I saying that right?
Yep, that's his handle. Yeah, Didier
Yeah, didrocks.fr
He's been posting these basically road to Gnome updates
And day 9 is talking about the theme
I like it
I can see it getting iterated on a bit for the LTS
I can see some areas for iteration
But it looks really good
It looks a lot like the Unity theme
But a little more modern, a little more pro
It has sort of that Gnome 3 polish to it
I really like how this is turning out
And I really like getting these updates too
I was fortunate in that I was at the fit and finish sprint in the canonical offices in London a couple of weeks ago
And Didier was there and other members of the desktop team
And we had some feedback from the community as well
So we saw and helped this sort of take shape over a couple of days there
And there's still some work to come to refine it a bit
But it's looking like Ubuntu now, isn't it?
Really? Yeah
I already saw some people getting all worked up about the Amazon button there
Yeah, well, it's inevitable, isn't it?
We could actually dedicate a whole other show someday to it
Perhaps we will
Because to me it's nothing like the old Surge
It's a great way for Canonical to make revenue
Yeah, if you're going to go shop on Amazon
A lot of people use Amazon
It's a clean looking theme
And I think it's going to be a great implementation of Gnome
And I know you've been following Didier's posts about how we're using some new facilities
To segregate the settings for the vanilla Gnome session and the Ubuntu session
Okay, so talk about that a little bit
Help me crystallize that in my head
Right, so this is all happening in GLib
It's a new feature there
So most of the GTK desktops have this ability where you have default configuration
And then you can override it with your distribution or desktop settings
And at the moment, for example, there are certain things where Ubuntu set things up in stock Ubuntu Unity
A particular way a Mate might have the same keys but configure them differently
And Ubuntu Budgie may also configure the same keys differently
So when you install the three desktops beside one another, they clatter
And you don't necessarily get the Budgie experience on Budgie and the Mate experience on Mate
Because it will be whatever settings got inherited first
So not only are we using this ability to namespace settings
So now each session has keys that are specific to the session it was launched under
And this is how you get that customization under the Ubuntu login versus the vanilla configuration under the Gnome login
But Word was put out to the Ubuntu Mate team and also to the Ubuntu Budgie team
Because we are using the same mechanics to configure our default experience
And now we are able to namespace our configurations so the Mate stuff doesn't tread on Budgie
And doesn't tread on Ubuntu and doesn't tread on the default Gnome configurations
So this mechanism goes far wider than just segregating Ubuntu's
That's great! So it's sort of a flavor-wide improvement
People are going to use it
Yeah, and then all the flavors that are can jumped on, well not all, but the flavors that can jumped on, that's awesome
And then the theming that you see of Gnome Shell is an extension, well not an extension, a Gnome extension
But it builds on that technique
So the Gnome Shell has its own CSS to style it
And when you log into the Ubuntu session it looks for a different named CSS file
So we don't have to mess with the default styling of Gnome Shell
We have our own separate styling and that's what's used to style the Ubuntu session
I would love to see more distributions, take that on
I'm looking at you Antair Gross
I think it's going to happen because this is a new capability
So we're using the final dev versions of GLib in order to do this at the moment
But that's all about to get released alongside Gnome 3.2.6
So this is stuff that will be available to everybody in a matter of days
And other distributions are going to be able to take advantage of this and they almost certainly will
So 17.10 is going to have support for all known driverless printing standards
I don't even really know, I don't grok that fully
Gnome 3.2.6 and possibly maybe we'll see kernel 4.13
Possibly
So I know a little bit about the driverless printing stack
So there's a specification that means that printers these days don't have to have all of their own bespoke drivers
They implement a common printing language
So printers that support this you don't require a big hefty lump of cups drivers and filters and what have you to make them work
So the guy that looks after all the printing stack in Ubuntu
Who just so happens to be like the world authority on cups and printing in general
He's like this amazing guy who's dedicated his life to just doing printers well
He's put the whole stack together so driverless printing just works
So if you've got these modern printers they just magically appear and you can just print to them without any setup or faff
You know they should give it a name like the common unified printing standard
Well that's the services that power it all but there's another spec for actually in the printers to define how they operate
Very cool well that actually sounds like it's going to make things one of those just works experiences when you have a modern printer that supports that
Which is probably, every time you have a win like that it really impresses people
Like it really endears them like you imagine you sit down to use Linux and you go oh crap time to add the printer
And you go in there and it just kind of shows up yeah that sells Dells that's what that does
That's great okay well so don't go anywhere MP stand by
We have a rally to talk about but let me get a moment in here with DigitalOcean my friends over at DigitalOcean
I love it I love DigitalOcean for all of the reasons that every single day here at Jupiter Broadcasting we find them more and more valuable
You can get spun up in less than 55 seconds they have all SSDs for all their machines
The virtualizer is a Linux box running KVM oh Linux powered
You know every software that we don't run locally Chris is on DigitalOcean
It is I know it's just so solid
People watching the live stream right now DigitalOcean
We will talk maybe more about this later but when you have a service like this that you can integrate into your business
When they make an API an actual priority it really is it's a game changer for us
Because not only is there just a ton of open source code to let us remotely control our DigitalOcean infrastructure
But we've been able to write our own around it
Our bot is DigitalOcean inception because it runs on DigitalOcean and also starts DigitalOcean droplets
That's awesome it has lightning fast networking 40 gigabits into the hypervisors
Highly available block storage you can just add up to 16 terabytes as you need it shows up as a block device
Load balancing as a service pre-build open source apps ready to go or you know build it from scratch
Don't forget about the crazy storage stuff Chris
Yeah they have their storage these days is such a cool way to play around with things like ZFS or even ButterFS or LVM
And then at the end of the day just destroy it all
And you didn't have to go out and buy hundreds of hard drives because you can attach these things as individual block devices
And you can start messing around with the storage managers and do some cool stuff
You know if you're going to get into like high end CPU intensive stuff you need to do a batch of a bunch of image processing or video processing
Or I'm not going to judge what you're doing they now offer really powerful CPUs with the Skylake Xeons and Broadwell Xeons with like hundreds of gigs of RAM
But they all start like five dollars a month my favorite rig is three cents an hour DigitalOcean.com
You go over there and of course I gotta I gotta tell you the most important part you have to use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED
That'll give you a ten dollar credit DOUNPLUGGED one word and then you can spin up that five dollar machine two months for free
Or run the three cents an hour one for a while it's it's a great deal DigitalOcean.com
Just create your account and then apply our promo code DOUNPLUGGED it's one word supports the show and thanks to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged program
Heyo!
So the Ubuntu Rally is an event taking place in New York City September 25th through the 29th
It's like a five day hackathon and
I'm I'm really excited because I think it's gonna be the like the timing of the event
Is with the new Ubuntu 17.10 and all and you know Mark's back as the CEO he's gonna be there
It's I think it's gonna be I think it's gonna be a pretty big event but Wimby's gonna be going Wimby's gonna be there
What do you think Wimby is this something is this something that I should definitely try to make it out to?
Yes
That's hoping you should definitely
Good because I'm planning to
No no is that because of the contents of the rally or you just want to see the hair?
No I just want to see Wimpy
No I'm talking to him
So yeah Chris is in a unique position where he can you know look at this with observers eyes and also see you know how the sausage is made
So the event itself is very much you know developer focused and it's a sprint a five day hackathon sprint
Composed of major software vendors Ubuntu engineering people from every level of the stack and community contributors as well
And it's a doing sprint so there is going to be a lot of furious energy and activity this week
So we've got a lot of people from canonical going we've invited some people from around the community to attend
And we have because space is limited we have some slots remaining for non sponsored places
Which basically means if you're local to New York or you can arrange your own travel and accommodation
Then let us know if there's something you really want to work on and we'll review those proposals
And if we can accommodate you we'll extend you an invitation to join us
That's not a funded invitation that's a you can you know get in the room because we have a limited space
And we can't just have people walking in off the street and filling the filling the place up because we have got a tight schedule of stuff
And it's a it's meant to get work done yeah exactly yeah I'm going to be a fly on the wall when the work happens
Because I don't want to interrupt that I just want to observe and I'm I'm I'm paying my way I'll haul my way there
And and I think that's going to be a I'm hoping a good chance to like wimpy said not to see how the sausage is made
But rekindle connections that I haven't met I haven't seen some of these people in person or met them in person
But only talk to them online like also many great opportunities around that I watched your your your short little vlog crazy
I was super excited about it I was yeah well you know it's it's it's funded I love to travel
So any chance I get to travel I'm down for there's there's a lot of buzz around this at the moment
And you know that there's some interesting people coming along who are from outside the company as well
So it will be a rare opportunity to sort of see those interactions anybody you want to name or do you want to just leave it vague
Well there are some some large companies coming who I don't want to name at the moment because I don't want to steal their thunder
And then there's also people that we do know in the community so the likes of Aiki Doherty from Solus is going to be there
The elementary guys are going to be there KDE representation is going to be there
So you know a lot of those those people in the community that we're working alongside some Gnome developers going to be there
I hear there's going to be some more work on Wayland and high DPI taking place
And then you know IoT manufacturers and PC OEMs you know getting their input on the direction of the desktop
Active community contributors and
People working on snaps and you know language and ecosystem developers you know people that are working on the new generation of languages and stuff like that
You know this sounds like it might be a good way or a good place to talk about some of that Wayland standardization stuff
You know it could be something that gets discussed
So I was wondering so does Canonical have offices in that area was New York picked because it's a high profile location that people can get to like what's the story there
You know my understanding is that New York was chosen because it's a hotbed of technology companies in the area and companies that make it
You think that was the main reason yes.
Yeah I will that'll be my first experience of New York I've never been so I've always wanted to go never thought I would sleep in the truck when I went to New York
Pretty intense Chris So if anybody's got some New York tips for truck camping I've got I've got a tip for you Chris Yeah don't sleep in the truck
Yeah I know I know I think before I go I'm considering maybe I should get my front windows tinted my back windows are tinted but you know I gotta think about these things
Be prepared for complicated driving that's all I can say Yeah but you know you know I am I am I am
Well you gotta remember this is a city that's only a couple like couple miles across and it's got a higher population than some states
I've been yeah I've been through some bad traffic so I'm not too worried about it because I can be a monster you know I can
This is next level Watch out for Chris New York New York needs to worry about me That's what I'm saying
I can't wait to see that city crush you That's going to be a vlog right there Yeah that is going to be a vlog The whole thing's going to be a vlog actually I think it's going to be
You know I'll try to vlog the trip there and as much as they'll let me run the camera I'll sneak around and try to get my vlogging done as I can
Don't tell Wimpy that though because he might I heard nothing Good good Well I'm I'm really looking forward to it I think that's going to be a good event
And I'll report back and I'll go for the audience and let them know what it was like I've always wanted to kind of see how you guys do that too
And it's a good way to sort of show some of the community involvement I think that's sometimes overlooked
All right I want to talk about something that I think is is a is a potential missed opportunity for Linux
We've talked a lot a lot about a lot of things though So if there's something something we talked about that you want more experience with something that you think might be an area of interest
Especially what we're about to get into I want you to consider going to Linux Academy Linux Academy dot com slash unplug you sign up for a free seven day trial
And you support the show Now it's a platform that's built by Linux enthusiasts to teach people more about Linux and they've done some really smart things
They have probably the most sophisticated courseware virtual machine infrastructure that I've seen on any any online site
It's it's particularly built for Linux users You choose your distribution the courseware in the virtual server match that you can SSH into the box
It gives you an address to connect into you can use whatever you want to interact with that so it's nice and smooth they have hands on scenario based labs to give you real experience
And course planning Yeah that is really nice for busy schedules or if you got a particular thing you want to learn and instructor mentoring
So if you do get stuck and you need that human touch they've got it practice exams before you go take the big test flash cards that are forked by the community which is stacked full of Jupiter broadcast
You remember stacked these flash cards and they're stacked Oh I did that I did that I did that they also have Android and iOS apps that you can study on the go
And speaking of studying on the go they also have offline content you can like you know listen to when you're not connected to the Internet or maybe while you're driving or you know doing the dishes
It's it's great and you can go in there just really wrap your head around anything you want to learn because they break it all down for you and easy to process chunks of time
Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged Big thank you Linux Academy for sponsoring the program Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged
So the bots are coming and they really are I mean they're coming and it's not for like the stuff that we think like customer support
And all these external facing things where you chat with a bot to get help Yeah that's coming too but that's that's not that's not what I'm worried about
That's old school bots Yeah that's that's basic B bots right there That's basic bot That's what that is It really is actually I think the future our bots like our friend Michael Dominic has created over at the mad botter dot com
And he's made a bot called Alice Here's a free plug for you Mike It's it's a PMO It replaces the PMO You know maybe not for like a large large large company but definitely for like a small team or remote team
You never know it could scale Yeah and it's it does all of the project follow up and all of that even does the client follow up when they haven't paid bills like it's it replaces the PMO role
And it's it's so obvious when you think about it because you have these huge back end infrastructure where you can like Microsoft will give companies like the mad botter free credits to run on their serverless architecture
Where it just fires off batch processing and then gives you the results Amazon has something similar So does Google All of these are proprietary back end infrastructures But these bots that are actually useful like we have a few we talked about here on the show
We're building more It's going to start replacing the compute jobs jobs where you're taking data from one field and trends and translating entering a different field where you're working with spreadsheets or approving documents
A lot of the back end work is going to be handled by bots stuff that we attributed to human jobs stuff that we think is more like you know the blue collar work that isn't going to get replaced by automation too soon will be replaced sooner because these bots can be controlled and built and innovated
And it's all the buzzwords all the buzzwords way faster than any of these actual physical robots that we're building or a eyes because a eyes are supposed to be these all purpose intelligent machines but bots are very task driven They have a set of things they have to do and they can do them really well
We had a great email that came in Dakota radio weeks and weeks ago And this guy was really stuck in a hard spot He was in a total moral problem because he essentially botified his work He created a bot a basic bot that automated 90 percent of his job
And he was basically only working 10 percent of the time and the error rates had gone down so far that this guy had to introduce a little used the modified the bot after a certain point to start reintroducing error rates So it looked like human work and he's like what guys what do I do because if I tell them this I'm basically out of a job
Yeah and he's that he is a sysadmin He's an I.T. worker And they're all built on like these Microsoft and Google frameworks Linux is like out like there's Mycroft out there but that's not really happening This you know this would have been great if Mycroft could have gone in this back end direction Mycroft is more generalized
It's more like Alexa as well Yeah Well you didn't trigger it That's amazing Cancel Somebody else right What do you think Am I Am I Am I I'm worried that Linux is missing out on what is obviously going to be a huge moneymaker for developers for people running the back end services
It's going to need a lot of deployment of back what I really I should probably round this out because I get so excited about this and I miss out major pieces I want around this out I think the type of bots that are going to be successful will be the internal company bots ones that maybe have slight rough edges but do their job
And they're built internally they're hosted internally or they're hosted using like these Microsoft services
They're not customer interfacing They don't have to have perfect understanding of human English If you just go through the right steps you get it to do what you need Yeah you just need a purpose built bot that can connect into all these APIs So I think it's these internal bots
They're going to go pervasive throughout companies and replace a lot of data processing and input and these kinds of jobs just like a virus
And the problem is right now I believe the best like built ready to go Here's an API and all runs on Windows
And we've been following the story on Koda radio and it seems like they're getting a lot of traction with it like it's becoming to be a part of Microsoft's business now I think it's only going to be a problem if we let it become a problem though because like it's not particularly difficult to write these bots
It's just nobody's doing it Right well I think it's going to it's going to be like the app gold rush This is like the next app rush Yep All right anybody in the Mamba room want to take another side or want to contribute a bit and have any thoughts on if Linux is missing out
Sort of like you know we've missed out on some other trends some of which like VR have sort of fizzled others which seem to be holding more and more getting more traction
No I don't think Linux is going to miss out because I do agree that bots are a new wave of technology and services are going to be deployed on top of bots but they'll be available through discourse and slack and telegram and WhatsApp and all the rest of it
So I don't know that we're going to be excluded from that I was thinking more from like an infrastructure standpoint I'm more worried about Amazon and Microsoft They're already there super serving giving away credits
You can you know if you're a small business they have like these you they have these programs you sign up for and they just they give you hours and hours of free runtime Yeah locking the developers into their platform and I'm really yeah that's where I'm worried we're missing out
It's not so much getting access to interfacing with the bots but being the back end infrastructure sort of like you know how Apache and that whole lamp stack was such a boom for Linux
And in a big way the economy has to like a lot of these apps that are on people's Android devices and phones they're connecting the Linux boxes on the back end
But in this case is these bots they're connected to Amazon they're connected to Microsoft and in Microsoft case they run on Windows and if you want on premise you also have to run Windows
That I'm worried about
You're supposed to make me feel better about that
No I'm thinking about it and I don't have any soothing words for you right now Yeah it's it could be one of those things where there's going to be something that really kind of comes together like you could actually see Matrix playing
Speaking of Matrix you could see Matrix playing a role in this even and that being run on Linux Yeah I I'm officially making a call out to awesome Linux developers to make awesome bots on Linux Yeah well let's get started
We're working on some Yeah our bots run on Linux Yeah well we're rewriting our bots to be more task oriented I guess Yeah breaking it out Yeah to be more focused on individual tasks and spread across more platforms so we can replace a lot of the manual things that we do
Yeah I think for a lot of us we won't even know like it'll be an internal thing that happens like the audience never knows what we use bots for to automate like it's just a it's a transparent thing so it's going to be a it's going to be a very silent revolution
One day one day J bottle just show up on Discord and you can do all the things there Yeah you know this is great when we do projects like this because it it's a great way for people to get in and work with us and have where there's there is a novelty for a community to rally around and work together on
And it's a great way to get involved in open source projects I know it's very self serving for me to say that but if you do want to check it out Discord dot me slash Jupiter colony and look for the Jupiter dev channel And on top of that for anybody interested tomorrow at six o'clock we'll be having a audio and text based developer meeting for this stuff specifically
That would be Wednesday September six at six p.m. Pacific time Correct We could put it on the calendar if you remind me All right And then people could just get it converted Yeah and I'll stop plugging but the thing that is appealing to developers developers with these bots is you get to work against a set of document documented
APIs and integrations So it's sort of like the breadcrumbs are laid out for you and the companies have a lot of momentum behind these areas So it's it's sort of a sort of a fun area to get into And the sort of like also you have what do you call a bumper when you have those bumpers in the bowling alley What is that called just called bumpers
Yeah sort of like yeah it's like bowling with bumpers Everything's there it's documented for you You have a community that's already structured together They're rallying around a common cause And all you need to do is write a plug in on top to interface with whatever you want to use rather than write the whole stack
I just can't I think back to that I.T. guy Who he was he replaced himself with a bot that did so good It did better than he did I think And he was worried about getting caught so he had to I think that he actually shouldn't worry because even if it replaces him there needs to be somebody to maintain that bot Yeah that was I think part of my advice on code or radio if I recall
Because you're right Yeah somebody I said maybe the bot could fix other problems too What he should pitch is he should go and show them his bot and tell them that it can replace all these other people Well that was part of his conundrum is there was I think three other people involved in verifying the data and when the data was perfect they didn't have anything to do
And so he was essentially working them out of a job too and he felt bad about that was another reason he introduced errors Is it he so he had the sys admin they got the systems talking to each other and did the data exports and tried to then move that into like an excel file and he would do that by hand
And then handed off to these these three ladies I think it was what he said in his email I can't remember now that would then go through an air check it and fix it against the master data or whatever I don't know I barely understand the process
And he replaced all that Yeah I think in a couple years I think jobs are going to be a very different concept There's going to be less doing the work and more maintaining the things that are doing the work Well that could be good you know that could be Yeah but that also means there's probably going to be less jobs
I suppose if you think about it in a weird way it has enabled us to do more in the studio with less people Yep You know there's less things for me to worry about when I'm setting up a live show because with one command I execute like four different things in the background
Mm hmm That's pretty handy It's only a matter of time until I figure out how to automate video editing Chris Well we just need some sort of like sonic marker every time there's a every time you hear the bell you just make an automatic edit you know like if you could do with NIT TV and commercials back in the day we should be able to do with JB shows
Yeah but who's going to be able to figure out the most embarrassing clips to put in at the beginning of the shows That's true that's true well we need machine learning for that part you see All right Beardsley where should people find you throughout the week?
Over at twitch.tv slash rkylep or twitter.com slash rkylep Well a big thank you to Wimpy for making it I know he had recording and he was recording his show check him out at Ubuntu Podcast anywhere else you want to send people Wimpy?
No just Ubuntu Podcast we've recorded the sessions where the winner of the entryware Apollo laptop is announced and all of the entries that people created it's fantastic Cool and also if you're an interested developer to New York Yeah yeah let me know if there's any New York stuff any New York tips for me
All right we'll see you back next week Wes will be here for another episode this was Lucky 213 we got through it so far thanks for joining us see you next week
Oh shout out to Caster Soundboard playing under Solus using a snap taking us in and out of the show officially the first time we've had a snapped version of Caster Soundboard on Solus that worked really well by the skin of our teeth
Yeah by the skin of our teeth but we got it we did actually get it that was fun all right so what do we get for titles? What do we get? Well you guys I wish I wish I had a way to capture what it's like here today so I woke up and it was ominously yellow outside it was very yellow and we have essentially all of eastern Washington's on fire in parts of Oregon
It is it is brutal how many if Harvey wasn't going on this would probably be a national story it's less yellow now it's more of like a jaundice yellow yeah now it's turned jaundice as the day has gone on but when the sun is lower higher in the sky it's this weird eerie and there's smoke everywhere and it's snowing ashes
Well even when the sun got high in the sky like up until like noon it was it felt like it was like dawn or dusk yeah oh yeah and but it's also it's 90 degrees today so it's extremely hot and humid yeah and very humid it's wet in here I think we're near 50% humidity
And so Angela said she's having chest pains today from the smoke because it's so thick and when I'm driving around it's I'm driving through ash like there's been a volcano it's really it's really something like when my car sits the truck sits it gets covered in ash
Pipewire pipe dream that's pretty good Stonic that's pretty good butter smooth very tuned his loan luck solar solaris sunset oh son was here wow you know the worst part Chris is because of you we are under a wasp attack and I have to have my room window closed
No no the screens don't you have a screen I do but somehow the wasp still got in oh why this other screens will work alright anybody else have an off the cuff recommendation for a title the bots are coming is the top one but was that really the was that the thrust of our conversation.
I don't know if people are going to be into that.
If you saw that with that would that entice you to listen.
I would have a comment about the status I can see straight thing you mentioned oh yeah we never had that we never had that with enlightenment because the reason was the developers said that there was never a clean implementation following the free desktop standard so they never really implemented it.
What about known which I find.
Sorry no you're right go ahead sorry I thought you were done finish your thought no I found that very interesting because for years people were asking for a sister in the enlightenment desktop the developers always say there was never a clean implementation so we don't do it.
It is funny how sister icons have been this ongoing nonstop problem really since unity.
Well it's because everybody creates their their own version of it and there's no standardized implementation it's maddening it's mad well no there is so KDE came up with the status notifier got what the I stands for status notifier indications or something and that's what the Ubuntu indicators are based on it's the same specification so why isn't enlightenment using that then no no don't know.
So I guess this is the part I meant to put in the show because here's what I but I was I was distracted by the other things about no I want to say but here's the problem with their new approach I think their new approach is solid if everyone that writes a gnome application starts using their new API is the new for API is they've made to replace.
Trey icons the issue is gnome doesn't have that kind of weight we've seen this over and over again now with gnome 3 they make these changes that are great if the entire world is writing applications only for no which is happening more and more but it's not the state of the Linux desktop and so that's why this is a problem and so they're essentially forcing the hands of the majority of no users to use top icons at least for the foreseeable future until developers update their GTK applications and let's be honest the developers that are going to update their GTK applications.
Are the most passionate GTK apps and they're also the ones that are the most feature.
Mmm what's a polite way to say this.
I don't want to say the rich well I would say there I would say your apps that are most feature rich get updated the slowest unknown and your apps that here's another way to put it your apps that are newer and still missing features how about that thin and light yeah okay yeah that's I'm trying to be nice about it because they're going to get there eventually but I'm you know look at Polari or look at the new known photos or look at known games.
The known calendar these are all early days applications and these are the applications that will update to support the new standard the ones that have the minimal amount of use and classic applications like Thunderbird you know and lightning the calendar and all and Firefox aren't going to aren't going to support the new APIs and users will suffer from the way they phrased it it kind of sounded like maybe they don't want a lot of these apps to update because they think that the tray the tray icons are too cluttered so maybe they just are expecting a lot of these to not update.
Not have tray icons so I submit it as a title something about known I can't remember what I suggested what was it you know Chris your your name is known takes over that was my title suggestion known takes over.
No how about known does it again.
No I don't we don't have to be incendiary but it seems like people would listen to that you know I'll be honest ever since we talked about New York all I can think about is bacon pancakes.
I'm sweating bad so we got to come up with a title because we are dripping it is so wet here and hot that's the best thing about Washington is just so humid it's so great people talk about Florida Florida worse than this because geez geez geez I'm sorry guys that's rough.