Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent.
Hello, gentlemen.
All of us are in studio gathered together for two episodes today.
We're going to record them back to back to get us ready to hit the road for our West
Coast tour.
So coming up on this episode, we dug deep this week to find our perfect Google Photos
replacement.
So this week, we'll share our setups that we think work great, are easy to use, and
are fully backed up.
Get rid of Google plus a new tool that might help do just that for Google Maps and, well,
at least the hopes and dreams I have for it and why it might just be landing at the perfect
time.
Then we'll round out the show with some great boosts and pics and a lot more.
So before we go any further, guys, let's say time appropriate greetings to our virtual
lug.
Hello, Mumble Room.
Oh, hello, guys.
Hello, Chris.
Hello, Wes.
Hello, Brent.
Hello.
We also have a whole bunch of people up and quiet listening because, well, they get a
low latency Opus stream when they do it that way.
And of course, there's jblive.fm and jupyter.tube.
We are live on Sundays except for next Sunday.
We're not going to be live.
We're going to be prerecorded.
Then after that, we're doing that just to buy ourselves one easy Sunday on the road.
That's the first Sunday.
Sunday the 25th.
Yeah.
Thank you.
That'll probably be a pretty, either we're going to be napping because we'll have been
exhausted by that point or we're going to be trying to put in miles.
I'm not sure which one, but we needed that flexibility, so we're going to do a prerecord
for one of them.
But then from then on, all the other shows are going to be from the road.
Hey, we better start thinking about that, huh?
Yeah.
We probably, maybe we should chat.
And you know how we're going to stay connected while we do that?
TailScale.
So go over and give a good old good morning to TailScale, TailScale.com.
It's a mesh VPN protected by WireGuard's noise protocol.
It's really straightforward to use, super secure because it's using WireGuard's tech,
and really, really easy to set up.
Really easy.
Two minutes per device, maybe?
I don't know.
So go say good morning.
Try it up to 20 devices for free at TailScale.com.
You know, I've been using TailScale this week to set up my new dev one, which we'll talk
about in next episode, and it's been amazing.
I've just been using it to shorthand host names because I'm here at the studio and I
don't know what the heck all the IPs are and stuff.
It makes things so easy.
Yeah.
It's a use case I haven't used yet, and I was so thankful for it.
It was just super simple.
So thanks, TailScale.
And you could just set your bookmarks and stuff to use that TailScale IP.
I'm using the magic DNS actually.
And didn't you test that if you're on the same network, they actually do transfer locally
even when you're using the TailScale IPs?
Yeah.
I was doing some R syncing using that, and it was real fast.
It was really a wonderful, beautiful, like transparent operation.
I really loved it.
So you can just always use the TailScale IP.
That's it.
You just memorize that one.
Yeah.
So great.
All right.
Let's talk about Headway.
This is essentially your own Google Maps in a box.
Now let's not oversell.
I'm sure this is a very hard job, and I'm sure it's not complete.
But the idea of this resonates so strongly with me that I wanted to talk about it on
the show.
And they write on the GitHub page, quote, with just a few commands, you can bring up
your own fully functional map server.
This includes a front end, a base map, a geocoder, and a routing engine.
Choose one of the 200 plus predefined cities, or provide your own open street map extract
covering any area from the neighborhood to the whole planet.
I have for so, so long wanted to run my own mapping software on my Raspberry Pi server
in Lady Chupes.
I mean, it just makes so much sense.
First of all, it's one of the ultimate tracking tools for Google.
I mean, everywhere you go, right?
Yeah.
But also, there are so many scenarios where I'm offline and I want to do route planning
and I don't have access to anything.
And wouldn't it be great if I started building these routes and all these favorite locations
for camping or great signal or quiet spot to record.
I've always, always wanted a database like that, but I don't want to build it around
Google Maps.
And the idea that maybe I could install Headway and create something like that on my mobile
RV, such a cool idea.
So it sounds like it's maybe the sort of the open source components for maps.earth, which
you can go try.
I assume that gives you a little bit of a somewhat of a preview of what you might get
out of the box.
It could at least route us from the studio to JPL.
So that's promising.
I think we got it.
We absolutely got to play with this after the show.
Headway is working on AMD 64 machines.
I don't know about ARM machines, but you know, for this test, I'd totally do it on a laptop
or something.
As far as the project status, they say Headway is currently capable of showing a map, searching
for points of interest and addresses within OpenStreetMap extracts, and providing directions
between two places within that extract.
Supported modes include driving, cycling, and walking.
Transit is a work in progress.
Oh, exciting.
Now, obviously, for something like we do, you also need another form of routing, which
is basically like commercial truck routing.
You need large vehicle routing and extra tall vehicle routing because there's overpasses
that are under a dozen feet or something like that.
What are you saying about Jubes?
She's tall.
She's proud and tall.
And so you have to use special routing software that takes her dimensions into consideration.
That sounds expensive.
It does.
But in theory, someone could build something like that for a tool like this.
Yeah, that's what's so neat about it.
And some folks in our matrix are making just this point that OpenStreetMaps is a great
project, because now you can get this data and sort of a common language and place for
all of this to collaborate around, and then you can build your own ideas into this stuff.
You know, I've been using OpenStreetMaps as a back end for my navigation apps for years
and years now, actually.
And it's gotten a lot better.
So I would imagine the more stuff like this gets out there and the easier it is to use
and the easier it is to sort of update all the maps as well from a user standpoint, the
better and better it'll get.
So it's like open source, long game, always wins.
Yeah, that's a fair point.
You're sitting in that seat right now, having used an OpenStreetMap powered app.
Do you want to mention what it is and maybe make some disclaimers about it?
I mean, it's not perfect.
And that's probably the caveat with all this is how could anything be as good as Google
Maps when you have so many users constantly providing data and you have the financial
budget that Google does to actually invest in routing it, taking pictures, getting satellite
imagery.
So clearly it's going to have its limitations.
But Brent, you're relatively an authority on this, having just driven from Canada to
Seattle using this.
And I know you used it in our Denver trip as well.
With only a small, you know, few small incidents here and there.
Only three extra mountain passes, it was fine.
Wes, you'll probably find this while I'm chatting about it.
Almost exactly a year ago, Chris, if you remember on Self-Hosted, we sort of explored using
some of these open mapping applications.
And I know some of us suffered a little and some of us had some more experience.
You were fresh at it, I think.
I think you had a hard time with it in Denver.
It really, yeah, it struggled with the complexity of that city, we've got to say.
So the application I'm using primarily is OSM and it's an Android application.
And there are a few others.
Some of them are more simplistic or more user friendly, perhaps I'll put it that way.
I'm not quite remembering them to mind in memory.
But I generally really think it's great for going between large places.
So between cities, things like that.
That has worked out fabulously for me and I find it quite accurate.
What I appreciate about it is the customizability of the interface itself.
So you can add different layers and, you know, I have mine in dark mode all the time because
I like it that way.
And those are some things you can't do with some of the other, you know, bigger proprietary
apps.
And you've also, one of the things I like about your UI that I wish I could do is you've
configured it to show not just the next turn, but the turn after that.
So you can start doing some of the math ahead of time and only some nav units do that and
you can just turn that on in yours.
Yeah, actually, I wonder if that's a symptom now, but I found it really super useful to
know, you know, as a driver, whenever I have time, I could just look down and just have
an idea of what's coming up next, next.
Yeah, get an idea of which lane to be in.
It's helpful for just you for quick turns, right?
Yeah, because sometimes, especially when you're downtown and four lanes to get across.
Although now that we're talking about it, I wonder if it's a symptom of the fact that
I've noticed that this map mapping application has a bit more of a delay.
So I find sometimes the turn, you know, I'm right up on the turn and then it sort of suggests
that I'm there so that I have found the interface legs a little bit from reality compared to
some of the other alternatives.
So I wonder if that's just my way of trying to solve that is to get ahead of the turn.
Still seems useful to me.
I wish I could turn it on.
It is kind of somewhat common sometimes in some open source things like, all right, there's
some deficiencies, but you can customize it so you could probably work around and no one's
spying on you.
I mean, there's that now and that's becoming more important to me as time goes on.
The other thing I appreciate is that I can bring up, you know, on the heads up display,
whatever I want, really, there's tons of options.
And so some of them that I like is, you know, navigational directions, like compass directions
a certain way.
But also like total distance that I have to go, what time I'm going to arrive there, things
like that.
But I find the layout, I guess, more predictable, like all that information is in the same place.
I was using Google Maps a little bit recently and I found it difficult because that information
kept moving around and I found that kind of tricky.
So I tend to go to it first, but I will say if you're trying to get to like a business
address, especially in a city that businesses change quite often, the search is tricky.
You can search by like address, but you kind of have to do it backwards.
You have to search by, you know, province or state first and then city and then street
name and then number.
So it's a little bit backwards from like human readability in that sense.
That's a little annoying, but understandable.
I understand like it's a hierarchy, so that makes sense once you get used to it.
But as a first time user, you're like, I've seen that in some of the built in navigation
systems as well.
Yes, I was thinking the same.
I like, though, that OpenStreetMaps, first of all, makes apps like that possible.
I think it's such an important project.
The other thing, too, is if you had a tool like Headway, which is what we started talking
about, the self-hosted solution.
In theory, Brent, you could kind of plan ahead and then just supply the needed information
to the nav unit, right?
Yeah, that's a great idea.
And then you could plan on your larger screen on your laptop or whatever, which I think
would be preferable, too.
Yeah, get it all sketched out in advance.
Yeah, that's how I like to do it.
And I like to like look for parking spots and all that kind of stuff.
You could even like print it out if you need it.
Do you remember?
Did you ever drive when that was a thing?
MapQuest.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, totally MapQuest printouts and stuff.
And they sucked.
And of course, you had to have like the get to the interstate on ramp, all that stuff.
Oh, yeah.
And towards the end, some of them will let you, like Microsoft had one, they'll let you
like drop off some of the first steps.
I know how to get to the freeway.
I'm good.
You know, and the big innovation with on your phone is you could start the nav once you're
on the freeway and you didn't have to get all the, I want to just mention because I
know people are going to ask me what I do use for the RV navigation right now.
If you have a large vehicle, I think the Garmin RV 780 is a really good device and it'll take
into all that.
I like having a dedicated device, too.
I could see replacing it one day.
I think that'd be pretty cool.
Replace with like a Raspberry Pi with an LCD screen running headway and some open street
maps all take into account how big JOOPS is.
Well, a boy can dream.
Chris, I'm curious.
You mentioned you want to eventually put this on a Raspberry Pi.
Do you think the Pi can handle it?
Well, I don't know.
Have to find out.
By the time Chris gets around to that, the Pi will have like 32 gigs of RAM.
I'm already planning projects for the Pi 5 boys.
I'm already waiting.
Soon as they announce, I'm ready to go.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
That's where you go to get $100 in 60-day credit and you can go there to support the
show.
Linode is easy, accessible, affordable cloud hosting and you get that $100, you can really
try it out and see why we rave about Linode, why we have for years.
Linode is how we run everything including our new website that we've built recently
and it's in part because of the great performance.
I mean, that's an absolute minimum line for me.
It's got to meet Linode's level of performance now if I'm ever going to switch away which
just honestly nobody does.
They got 11 data centers around the world.
They're constantly investing in their infrastructure, improving the hardware instead of just like,
you know, coasting like some companies do and then milking that hardware for like 10
years and charging you the same thing.
They're charging you the same great price which is 30% to 50% cheaper than the major
hyperscalers out there and just behind the scenes, they're constantly upgrading things,
making things better both on the hardware side but on the UI interface side too.
They just introduced a brand new marketplace interface.
That's what they call their one-click application deployment screen, their marketplace.
You don't really buy these things.
I mean, they're open source free software.
In fact, sometimes I go there and I just look at some of the different projects and see
what I want to play around with for the evening and they've made that even easier now because
they now highlight the new applications that have been added to the marketplace and they're
adding more than ever now.
So that's a really cool tool and honestly, it's all really cool.
That's what I love about Linode's interface and not only are they always upgrading the
hardware and the infrastructure but they're also upgrading the user interface, the front
end and they've just recently introduced their new Linode marketplace interface which is
what they call their front end to let you see the different projects that you can just
one-click deploy on the Linode infrastructure.
They're always adding new stuff but they made it even easier now.
They have a filter on just the new apps and I go there and I look at that and I think,
all right, let's check it out.
And I found myself just discovering and tinkering around with new cool free software projects.
It's the best.
I love it when they add features like that.
Just incrementally making it better all the time.
That's why they've survived nearly 19 years in this business without VC funding, without
raising crazy loans but just by making a great product and selling it.
And on top of that, you get some of the best support in the business.
You get full Terraform, Kubernetes, Ansible support and you also get something that's
30% to 50% cheaper than the major hyperscalers out there.
That's a big deal when you combine that with the support and it's a great way to support
the show.
Go try it out.
See why we've been building our future infrastructure on Linode and why I think you will too for
yourself or for your business, linode.com slash unplugged.
One more time to support the show, it's linode.com slash unplugged.
All right, Wes brought the vacuum so it's time to clean up a little bit around here.
So thanks to our generous audience, Brent's tank was fueled with sats.
Thank you.
And he took a really cool route out here.
Yeah, I think we should share that route actually.
Yeah.
I just wouldn't take it at night or when it's raining.
Well it was only partly at night and only partly raining in the mountains.
But the most treacherous part was at night.
We do tell a little story in Office Hours 12 of that adventure that I think is probably
worth hearing.
I don't know if you caught it, Wes.
I did.
All right.
If you had, we'd have to tell you.
Yeah.
Also, we had a little surprise outage that left Wes and I scrambling after we launched
the website and we talk about that in Office Hours 12 as well.
Yep.
All good though.
All fixed up now.
Those West Coast meetups are coming up.
Our first one is on the 20th, which is two days from now as we record.
How is that going to work?
I'm going to be in Southern Oregon in two days.
Wrap your mind around that.
Especially that's tricky considering I'm going to be recording Coder right here in the studio
on Monday.
At this point, two shows to go.
Yeah.
But the meetups are logged in.
Details at meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting.
Turned out we're doing a West Coast brewery tour.
All of the meetups are at really great brewery locations that can accommodate us and feed
us and supply us with beverage.
We'd love to have you there, but do sign up so we know.
And it's getting down to the final moment, meetup.com slash Uber broadcasting.
If you need any deets, you want to figure out like carpool and stuff like that, bit.ly
slash West Coast crew is the chat room for that.
And we'll spin up other regions we have.
There's actually a whole bunch of regions already, but we'll spin up more regions as
the meetups extend out.
So do get yourself a Matrix client.
It'll be coming up soon.
Hey, we do have a couple of baller boosts this week.
The biggest boost that come into the show we read early and John A comes in for a third
week in a row with 50 sats, gentlemen.
How about that?
That is amazing.
You filthy animal.
I guess we better start dancing.
Yeah.
Can you keep the streak up?
Because here's the tricky thing.
We're prerecorded next week.
Oh.
We're on a really solid streak right now.
Four episodes in a row.
Nobody's ever done that before.
So we'll see if he can pull it off.
I don't know how he possibly could, but we'll see.
He says in his boost, thank you for doing a show dedicated to all the reasons I love
Gnome and for validating my preferences.
Did I do that?
I thought I did the opposite.
You know, we have to say Nate reached out to us.
Nate writes the This Week in KDE blog, and he offered to come on and chat about some
of those problems.
Not so much as like an argument, but just kind of a back and forth to get an understanding
where the project's out and that stuff, and I think we're going to probably take him up
on that.
It's just the travel schedule and all of that, but I think that'd be a great conversation.
We figured we'd give a little more time for Brent to find additional bugs just to stock
up.
Well, I've got a list.
Oh, Brent Lee, of course you do.
It's to help.
Like I think that's in the name of progress, right?
Sure.
Awesome.
I'm going to show you generously one of our baller boosts this episode with 30,000 sats.
He clipped that.
He says, also, I think part of the problem with the baller clip in general is that it's
just been one clip.
All the other boosts get some variety.
They don't get old because they largely have some variety.
I think there should be a small pool of baller boosts that you can pull from depending on
the mood and ambiance.
Yeah, I think we're getting that.
We have some really great submissions on a GitHub link that we'll put in the notes.
We'd like some more and the community is coming together and really, I think, coming up with
some great ones.
So thank you, everybody, who's contributed to that GitHub thread and thank you, Awesome
Matt, for that.
And our last baller boost, we're very privileged.
We've actually gotten three baller boosts and that one came from Gene Bean with 25,000
sats.
I hoard that which your kind covet.
Brent, I'd love to see you dig into this KDE topic in a brunch with Brent, maybe that includes
Michael Tonnell from Tux Digital and maybe whoever hosts the KDE Corner on Late Night
Linux.
Ah, Phelan.
Yeah.
Phelan.
Maybe the cross section of y'all's experiences would be really interesting to hear.
That's a great idea.
Thank you.
Yeah, we can get that cooking.
We can at least get it cooking.
I don't know if we can get it pulled off while we're on the road.
That would be tricky, but we can at least get that ball rolling.
Nice to have projects to come home to.
True.
I just want to say thank you to Gene Bean.
He sends in a lot of high signal boosts just under like the 2K level so we have the option
of reading them or not.
And that works great for us.
We read them all.
We bring some of them to the show and I just want to say thank you to Gene Bean because
just a ton of great support.
Yep.
Thank you.
We really appreciate it.
So let's talk about how we are finally divorcing from Google Photos, a topic that has come
up on the show before, something we are following closely on Self Hosted.
There's several projects in the works like Image, something that really was finally motivated
by that story that involved Google sending over a dad's entire Google account history
to the police when they incorrectly identified a C-SAM flag on his Google Photos account.
And that was really just the, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
I've got kids.
I use telemedicine.
I've got Google Photos turned on on one of my devices.
Really just was the line that was too far for me.
And since then, I have been actively looking at ways of just getting myself off of Google
because these models only increase.
What they're looking for only increases.
The accuracy is so-so.
And the automatic nature and how they transferred all of that guy's information to the authorities
for him to review every chat, every email, every purchase.
It's gross.
It's also like Google Photos is less of a good deal than it once was.
You know, they kind of try to sucker everyone in and then change the terms, which is fair.
That's part of the risk of I'm going to put all my photos with you, and then you've got
them and can have me pay whatever you'd like.
It feels like the trade-off cost has shifted more and more to the negative.
And now the trade-offs of having a system that isn't fully managed, that doesn't essentially
have infinite storage, that doesn't have maybe the best machine learning discovery, the trade-offs
of that are worth it now, I think.
So we wanted to build something that pretty much anyone listening could deploy, something
that would run for years, that wouldn't be super expensive and would be fully backed
up.
And I'm on iOS.
You gentlemen are on Android.
We wanted something that accomplishes both.
I know.
You still won't text with me.
They're green, Wes.
They're green.
And if I was on Android, I have to admit this may have been slightly easier because on iOS,
you have the challenge of background tasks are heavily throttled, better or worse.
Hard to compete with the built-in, you know, Apple Photos magic, right?
Yeah, exactly.
And you don't have all of the tools.
Like you Android users can use SyncThing.
I love SyncThing.
SyncThing doesn't like iOS.
They don't want to release SyncThing for iOS.
Now Mobius Sync has come along.
I think it might have been Gamma that told me about this, which is a third-party app
for SyncThing that allows you to use SyncThing on iOS and other devices.
Wes, it is a full SyncThing instance.
I couldn't believe it.
Like when you install it and you run the app, it just brings up the whole SyncThing UI.
That's just SyncThing right there.
Isn't that funny?
And it's pretty limited in what it can get access to because iOS.
And there are some hacky ways you could possibly get it to look at your photos and back your
photos up, but it's not ideal.
But it would work for like, can you get access to various documents or some other, what can
it see?
It can see like its own folders, so you could put stuff in its own folders.
So if you wanted to sync stuff to have handy on your phone, that could work for that.
Yeah, that would work.
Yeah, exactly.
But not a great solution for what I'm looking at.
And so if I was on Android, maybe I would use just SyncThing.
I don't know.
I can't say.
But that wasn't an option for me.
And we got a bunch of different solutions.
And I tried most of them that seemed reasonable.
And the one that stuck, and I think Brent saw my kind of, because he's been here at
the studio for a few days, he saw my kind of evolution of going through these different
apps and finding the one that really seems stable and reliable and ran in the background
and supported everything I needed.
And that absolutely, hands down, was Photosync.
Photosync-app.com.
This is a really good piece of engineering.
How often have you heard me come on here and say how good an app is engineered?
This thing is beautiful.
Photosync will transfer to just about darn near any network protocol.
Whatever you got, Samba, SFTP, WebDAV, it'll work with that.
You got Nextcloud.
You got a Western Digital My Cloud.
You got TrueNAS, Open Media Vault, Seagate.
What do you got?
It'll support that, right?
It'll do just straight up file protocols that you got, or it'll work with specific services
that have APIs, including Photoprism.
It has direct support for Photoprism.
We'll get to that in a moment.
But I want to stick just for a little bit longer with Photosync because this is a really
impressive app.
This is a critical component for me, getting the photos off of my phone because that's
my primary device.
And Photosync has really intelligent syncing abilities, really easy to select what you
want and what you don't want sent up to the server, crazy easy to manage that happen automatically.
It works with so many different services.
And on top of that, and I think this is just a great feature because I actually was doing
this already, if you plug in a SD card reader to your phone and transfer your photos off
of your digital camera, Photosync will read those and it can sync them up to your service.
See, that's nice.
It's super nice, Wes.
It's super, super nice.
So yes, it has camera support, it also do Wi-Fi cameras.
It can connect to your Wi-Fi camera and transfer all the photos off of that.
It also do like a USB flash drive.
It has baked in Amazon S3, Backblaze and Wasabi support.
If you don't want to go to your own server, you just want to send it off to the cloud
as a backup option and you're happy with just having local photos on your phone just backed
up, Photosync will do that.
That's handy.
So Photosync could be basically for some people the entire solution.
Such a simple app is available for iOS and Android.
Really like it.
It does have a premium version which I haven't gone with yet.
Now I was going to ask you about that because it seemed like maybe you needed the premium
if you wanted the automatic in the background.
You got it.
Yeah.
That's the thing.
And then the models are a little different it looks like.
I played a little bit with Photosync and I tried some other software just to mix it
up here.
But you have the premium version on iOS and then on Android there's various sort of extensions
you can get.
You can get a pack if you just need a little bit more protocols or you can get like a sort
of premium equivalent pack that has all the standard extensions built in.
Yeah.
It's a little confusing.
Maybe a little bit better of a deal on the Android side.
It does seem that way.
Yeah.
But I'm cool with the premium version because that automatic backup is big for me.
And it also feels like the kind of project you want to support and keep it around because
you want to just use it for years.
Right.
You want to keep them.
I'm not going to stop taking photos.
If anything it goes the opposite.
Yeah.
Only more.
Right.
So it's like a large ProRes video and 4K video and stuff like that.
And it handles all of that.
I also simulated like I crashed the app.
I forced closed the app mid-transfer.
I put the phone to sleep.
Yeah.
You got a phone call during one of your transfers.
I got a phone call which canceled the transfer and made sure that every time I opened it
up it just figured out what it needed to do, finished it up and it didn't have any weird
like orphan files on the server or anything like that.
So really got the solid confidence in Photosync to use it as my daily backup solution to get
the photos off of my phone.
There is like a companion app for the commercial OSs.
I don't know what that does.
Maybe it backs up the photos.
Yeah.
I think it does allow you if you put the SD card on your Mac desktop or whatever.
Okay.
All right.
Yeah.
That'd be really nice too I suppose.
So then you have the whole matter of how do you display your photos?
How do you search your photos?
How do you collect them?
Yeah, because right now you could just go to photos.google.com and everything's there.
Search for RV.
The RV shows up.
I do that kind of crap on the stream all the time.
Or when I'm making like a home video, Dylan Christmas tree and boom, it shows up Dylan
with a Christmas tree.
And because you've had those features available, you're not necessarily, I mean sure you build
some albums, but you can kind of rely on just if I need to find something by theme, it's
auto done that for me.
Totally.
That is so true.
It's a little lazy, but I just don't have time to sit there and go through all the photos.
The amount of photos and stuff, I don't, right?
You take it and you forget it.
So PhotoPrism comes in and we've talked about PhotoPrism before and I'm going to talk about
it now because it's gotten a lot better since we've talked about it.
It is an AI powered photos app, which they say is for the decentralized web.
All right.
Talking my language.
It makes use of the latest technologies to tag and find your pictures automatically in
the background.
You could even run it on a Raspberry Pi.
It's going to be a little slow, but you could run it on a Raspberry Pi and it will do face
detection.
It'll classify pictures based on their content and location.
It can identify animals, but one of the things that I really want in an app like this is
I want to discover old memories.
I want to be reminded about things.
I want to see things and I really enjoy just the process of browsing through PhotoPrism
and remembering moments.
One of the ways they do that is they have the map interface and they'll show you where
you've taken various photos in different places and I can go in and I can look at some of
our favorite Montana moments and be like, oh yeah, that was great when we went there.
Or Brent and I were planning to take a little bit of the coast on the road trip and we'll
look, here's the first photo of JOOPS on my very first road trip when we took the coast.
I was like, oh yeah, boy, how much have we learned?
It's just re-experiencing those photos because otherwise they just sit there and they do
nothing.
Last of time.
And PhotoPrism is really good.
The other thing it does at helping you discover them is it has this thing called labels and
it automatically categorizes the pictures.
Like here's an aircraft.
These are the pictures when Listener Mike took us up for a ride in Denver when we went
on the Denver road trip and here's a video because it also works on video, right?
There's a video of that moment of us walking out on the tarmac to go ride in Listener Mike's
airplane.
And what an incredible memory that was and it just automatically tagged that.
I didn't have to do that.
There's a tag for Levi, I think, as well, I spent a lot of time in that one.
Yeah, there's a tag for Beach.
There's a tag for Camper or something, whatever they call JOOPS.
Isn't that the European term for it?
Yeah.
Levi tag automatically just finds all these great photos.
When you hover over the photos, if they're a live photo, it'll automatically animate
them.
I kind of witnessed you going through this memory palace, let's call it, when you were
first setting this up and not everything was loaded yet because it was just really fresh.
Yeah, still classifying.
I can say confidently that, yes, this photo prism did it for you because we sat there
for maybe, what was it, like 15 minutes just going through a bunch of memories and like,
oh yeah, check out when we were at the coast and this is one of our favorite camp spots
and we spent that quality time, just you and I going through those memories.
I can imagine when you sit down with your family and do the same thing, how really great
that will be.
Yeah.
Photoprism just makes it easy to have that experience, to casually do it because the
Photosync software is sending them up via web dev, really, in the backend to Photoprism,
but it's pinging its API, so somehow, maybe it's file system events, maybe it's an API
event.
The Photoprism is immediately aware of the moment a photo lands.
See, that's a nice little test, right?
How long is it from, take it on your app, take it on your phone and it actually makes
it all the way into here.
Right, because you want to look at it sometimes right away.
I ran it in verbose mode, the server in verbose mode for a couple of days just so I could
see what it was doing on the backend and it'll go through everything, it'll process everything
and then the last thing it does when it's all done is then it does the face analysis
and you can see it light the cores up, man, it really does.
It cooks that thing for a bit, but it rips through it much faster.
I don't have like a coral accelerator or anything like that.
I'm just doing it right on the old CPU and it's working pretty quick.
So it's a great experience in just using it day to day and it's just staying on top of
your photos and I've been checking it throughout the weeks to make sure that it's captured
everything that I've taken and they're all in there.
It's all working just as expected.
One thing I noticed, Chris, that you may not have is I noticed that there were some raw
photos from, I believe it was your phone, I think they were Apple Raw format and those
just came out as white, just white squares.
Did you notice that?
Yeah, that is actually Alex's Canon R6.
And I don't know why.
There is a premium version, a membership version of Photo Prism, but it doesn't give you any
more formats.
Well, I know from my work in professional photography stuff that sometimes those raw
formats are really tricky, especially for open source projects.
I mean, there's a lot of work that has gone into that, like dark table and raw therapy
and stuff.
They've kind of reverse engineered a lot of those formats, but it's possible that maybe
either the software hasn't tapped into those resources yet or that it just hasn't been
reverse engineered.
I mean, I don't think Alex would be able to tell us because I think he's still using some
of the big software, let's just call it.
And the truth is Google Photos didn't have that problem.
I didn't even know those were a special format until I imported the originals of everything
when I was doing this.
I went back and got the originals of everything and so I just threw it all up there and discovered
some of that was different formats and it handled everything but those.
Now Chris, I wondered, did you try going through the exercise of exporting from Google Photos
and importing it into here?
Because I would imagine that's a workflow that would be pretty common if you're trying
to switch from one to the other.
No, because I have the originals still and Google Photos was just my backup.
That'd be an interesting experiment.
I have in the past done that with some other apps and it's doable.
It's a big download.
For Photoprism itself, they recommend two cores for your CPU, at least three gigs of
RAM and a 64-bit operating system to get all of the face finding and stuff like that and
the automatic classifications.
And I'll link in the notes a demo they have.
They have a demo app too of their classification support and they give you an idea of the range
from animals to cars to pieces of land.
It has this thing called moments too and I don't know what it's doing but it's a moment
that it thinks is something special to you or something like that and it's actually really
nice and it was a surprising label that I had no idea what it did but then I started
looking and I like all of them.
They have fantastic documentation, really good docs to getting all of this set up.
They support some external sharing, it's hit and miss.
They'll let you share to Twitter and Instagram but Purple Dog using Breeze boosted in with
a row of ducks and I agree, he says, the thing I'm missing is I want to be able to share
an album and it doesn't really support that.
I agree the sharing support is not a big aspect for me but it is not as strong as I would
like it with Photoprism.
But the free version that I am using, the community edition, includes nearly everything
except for vector image support and you get simple maps instead of like fancy, really
accurate maps.
And hardware transcoding for the videos is limited to the paid version, wasn't an issue
for me though.
And private support chat is limited to the membered version.
That's reasonable.
Otherwise, it's pretty much everything.
I did notice, I think as a photographer anyways or someone who has a fancier camera and likes
to do some extra editing on the side, you need to keep in mind that Photoprism is basically
a really nice viewing suite.
It doesn't do any editing capabilities, you know, if you want to crop a photo or anything.
I at least haven't found that yet, I've been poking around, not extensively, but I haven't
found that anywhere.
So I think that is something maybe that'll come in the future.
Some simple editing tools might be nice if you want to, you know, edit something quickly
there and then export it and share it with some family or something, but that's something
to keep in mind.
I got an idea for that.
I haven't done this part yet, but this is like my to-do when I get back.
I don't see any reason.
I couldn't point SyncThing at the Photoprism libraries because they're just folders on
my hard drive and use SyncThing in send-only mode from the server if I want and receive-only
mode on the client.
So you could have just a mirrored copy on your workstation using SyncThing or you could
do it in send and receive mode and in theory, it would actually work fine if you made an
edit on your workstation and then use SyncThing to sync that back to the Photoprism directory.
I think since Photoprism is just reading from the file system, I think it'd be fine.
And that might be a really, if as long as you had enough local storage to have a copy
of your entire photo database or maybe a subfolder, then you could essentially just open them
up and whatever editing app you like, it'd be a local file, you'd make the changes you
want, you hit save and then SyncThing would send it back up to Photoprism, Photoprism
would re-index it and it would be available to you.
So I'm going to experiment with that further, but that's how I'm planning to address that.
If anybody out there has tried something like that, please let me know.
It would also be interesting in that vein to know if you have some XMP files or something
for your raw format, if it keeps track of those, that would be actually kind of amazing.
Somebody with some experience out there, let us know.
We'll find out eventually though.
So that's okay.
So we're getting it off our device.
You could use Photosync to get it off your digital camera.
You could use Photosync to get it off of your phone.
There's other tools out there.
I really like Photosync and also Photoprism recommends Photosync as well.
We'll have links to this in the show notes.
We're using Photoprism to view it, search it, categorize it.
How do we back it up?
And I got a lot of photos.
I got a lot of photos and I'm looking to save a buck, but I want them protected.
So I needed an edge.
I needed something a little different because everything out there wasn't going to work
for me.
I mean, I'll consider others.
I'm not completely sold on this, but it sounds pretty amazing.
It's called storage.
They build themselves as fast, secure, decentralized cloud storage.
They also call themselves a web three company.
So red flag.
Danger.
I'm not sold yet.
Go on.
I found out about them through IX Systems, who has announced integration with TrueNAS.
So they seem to think it's legitimate.
So that raised it up a little notch in my book.
They call themselves the first open source decentralized cloud storage layer that's private
by design and secure by default.
They say when an object is uploaded into the storage DCS, it is encrypted, split up into
80 or more pieces and distributed across thousands of diverse nodes and ISPs in nearly a hundred
different countries.
There's no single point of failure or centralized location, so there's no outages, downtime
or bit rot.
Failure doesn't affect you and data breaches are virtually impossible.
The node goes offline for any reason.
Your file can be reconstituted from just 29 of its distributed pieces.
I do have a link that has a video that explains how it all works.
I don't know, guys.
I mean, it sounds almost too good to be true when it comes to storage.
It is usually too good to be true if it sounds like it.
But what they're essentially doing is they have a plan that anybody can participate in.
Maybe this is the web three part.
I don't know.
And you can essentially somehow get into this program and allocate some of your data center
storage to their network or something like that.
I've genuinely tried to get to the bottom of how it can be so cheap and I am still a
little unsure.
But here's the pricing.
The free plan, which I'm currently using, which I'll have to upgrade from, is you get
150 gigs of S3 compatible object storage for free.
It's pretty good.
Then after that, you get a pro plan.
The pro plan still includes 150 gigs for free.
And then it's $4 a terabyte after that, which is a really good price.
And a $7 a terabyte transfer rate.
That is way lower than just about anywhere else I can find.
And it also claims to be fully encrypted and fully distributed.
And it claims to be all open source.
And I can verify this at least, it is fully S3 compatible.
It's just too good not to try.
I don't know anything else about storage.
I always go into low cost storage extremely skeptical.
But if it's true that they really are distributing it like this and they're splitting it up like
this and they're encrypting it by default like this.
And you're going to test it for us on the show with it being the sole backup of all
your photos.
I'm doing it right now.
Here we go, buddy.
Well, I'm also that's why I'm going to sync thing it to my workstation and stuff.
So I mean, I'm not crazy.
But I haven't set that up yet.
So currently it is the way I'm doing it.
And here is the beauty thing about storage.
It's S-T-O-R-J, by the way.
But here's the great thing about it.
My backup app of choice that I've already using to back up all my server configs and
all my Docker composes Duplicati has built in support for storage.
Is that right?
Yeah.
And Duplicati is such a great tool.
If you haven't checked it out, it's really easy to get going.
It supports a ton of cloud storage options.
It'll do local AES encryption first.
So one of the things I do is I save my home assistant databases on Google Drive, but I
encrypt them completely locally with Duplicati.
And then Google just gets this big old encrypted tar file that just sits on Google Drive.
And then Duplicati can download if I ever need to restore, manage all of the encryption.
It is like an old school program where you actually can like browse and restore individual
files if you want.
You can get status of your backups.
It's really a great backup program.
I've been using it for years.
So the fact that storage support was built right in and they have docs on how to set
it up was so killer for me because it meant I didn't have to like learn a new backup application
or implement something entirely new.
I just added one more additional backup config to my existing application, which was brilliant.
And set it up, Duplicati sends all my photos up to storage.
It's been doing it for days.
It's been working great and was really easy to get going.
So if you have never tried Duplicati, even if you don't use storage, this could be a
great tool to backup.
You could go to Amazon S3, you could go to Dropbox, you could go to Linode's S3 object
storage, all kinds of services in there.
Really like that application.
I also noticed when I was investigating storage that they have a canary on their website.
You might have seen this with other like privacy conscious VPNs and such.
And the purpose, as far as I understand, is to just kind of make that canary vanish if
they ever get, Chris, you would understand this better, but if they ever get sort of
subpoenaed to give information that they are typically unwilling to give, but if they're
forced into it, then this canary will just kind of go away.
The situation there with the national security letters and the what nots is such that they're
not allowed to say that they've been given this order and they've disclosed information
to the government.
They can't say that.
They're under an embargo when they get served in NDA.
But when you pull a canary, you're not saying anything.
You're removing a statement that you had previously before.
So you make a statement saying we've never been served this.
And then when that disappears, you know that it's happened without them having to come
out and say it.
That's the canary.
It's kind of wild that that's the world we live in.
Right.
It's a bit of a loophole, I think.
Thanks, George Bush.
Appreciate that Patriot Act.
So there you go.
Storage has a canary.
It has a warrant canary, which is actually really a good thing to see.
And it's actually one of the best I've ever seen.
They include like recent news headlines in the canary just to prove the fact that the
date would be accurate.
So you can kind of do your own homework to make sure that it actually was.
And they do say, oh, we'll send this canary once a month, this warranty canary, and include
headlines and such.
And I thought that was really neat until I noticed that the date is from last.
It's actually from July.
And so I wonder if the canary is out or not.
Someone just forgot to update.
No, because you're supposed to pull it.
That's the idea.
Right.
You pull it when that's happened.
But yeah, I don't know.
If you set the expectation, you're going to update it.
You better keep updating it.
So the pro plan is you pay for what you use, essentially.
I haven't gotten to that tier yet.
I'm so skeptical on this kind of stuff, you guys.
But they're checking all the boxes.
And I felt like I wanted to get my hands on it so I could at least come on the show and
give you my experience in a bit.
So I'm trying it out.
This is what I'm using for my backup.
I really like it so far.
I think the pricing is ridiculous.
And I'm going to embrace it while I can.
And the fact that I can integrate it with duplicati is just a huge win for me.
Yeah, I feel like if you're doing the encryption on your side, that makes me feel a lot better.
Yeah, I agree.
That's the thing I want.
I want to control that encryption on my side.
I want it to require my key on the restoring side to actually decrypt that stuff.
So I know, Wes, that you've been digging into this too.
You've been solving this problem for a while.
Tell me what tools you've strung together.
Well, you know, there are a lot of different options in this space.
One I noticed that I'm not using but I thought was an interesting approach is called Stingle.
And the client is all open source.
But they do the hosting on the back end.
So it doesn't really fit with the whole self-host everything.
But if what you were looking for is, you know, something that is at least partially open
source but isn't sending things to Google in particular, then this might be for you.
The app looks quite nice.
It's simple.
You just pay, you know, for the back end hosting costs.
So right there, you're at least paying for what you're using.
Seems reasonable to me.
Now, I don't know anything about them.
I don't know.
Would I trust that as my sole backup of my photos?
Are they going to disappear at some point?
And can you get your photos out?
I'm not sure.
But you do have some options if you're not quite willing to take on the full load of
like, oh, I got to find storage for these things, and I got to make sure that my server's
up and the sync is going.
Right.
That does sound nice.
And it would at least get you off of the Google threat model.
Right.
Yeah, at least there.
I don't think Stingle at least has as many GPUs to mine all of your data from.
Also a great name.
Exactly.
Stingle.
Yeah.
That's great.
I love it.
Now, you're right.
I have been using SyncThing for a long time to do photo sync.
And I mean, what can you say?
SyncThing really just works.
Like it just syncs, it keeps going.
I think for using it for photos can certainly work on Android pretty well.
You do kind of have to know and understand a bit about SyncThing, I think to feel fully
comfortable with it.
So I don't know that I would recommend that maybe for like a grandma type figure in your
life, especially because you might need a couple you might need to think about the model
you can kind of play with like, send or receive only.
But then if you're deleting stuff from your phone, there might there's sometimes like
a notification that's like, hey, just so you know, you're out of sync, you could ignore
that.
SyncThing works fine.
Another approach is you could just imagine it as a sort of bi directional setup all the
time, where you're just imagining that you're making a copy of whatever's on your phone
on a server somewhere, and then you have a separate sync process that sort of copies
from there and syncs whatever's new that shows up to your real back end folder where, you
know, whatever photo viewer your gallery is actually going to pull from.
So if you're comfortable with that, or let's say you already are using SyncThing, you have
a SyncThing network going, you have other stuff on your phone you want to sync to or
from, that seems like a really solid option.
I did look a bit at photosync, it does seem like I mean, I think that is probably what
I would recommend for someone who wasn't super competent, but just wanted to suck photos
off their phone because it's polished around for a long time.
It's like an appliance kind of app.
Yeah, exactly.
But I know you were playing with that.
I want to try something a little bit different.
So yeah, I found low mirage.
Okay.
Oh, you you can give it a shot of pronouncing if you prefer lumarage.
I almost think it's like something to do with lighting.
I don't know.
It is definitely not as polished, but it does have an iOS and Android app as well as actually
a Windows and a Mac desktop version.
I haven't tried those, no version for Linux just yet.
It's pretty bare bones, but it comes with a lot of the features, not all of them as
shiny as say PhotoPrism has, but it has a built in gallery, which also means from your
phone, if you're looking at a photo, you can share it right there from the app on your
phone.
And it just has a little token that embeds, you can send that link.
So that's pretty handy.
That is.
I should mention PhotoPrism has a progressive web app, a PWA that does work pretty good
on mobile, but the sharing is still, I'm not my, I think that's its weakest area.
So far I've been pretty impressed with the actual sync functionality, you know, the Android
app connected right away and it held right up.
I think like the full backlog of however many thousands of photos I had sitting on my phone.
And then over the past week or so, it's been, you know, sucking up new ones as I go on walks
with the dogs and go explore the neighborhood.
It's not the easiest to configure, it's definitely not a pretty app.
It's more of like a, you know, like a technical users app.
But unlike the experience you get with sync thing, it's focused on photos.
So like when you open the app up, it shows you all your photos right there.
You can view them there and it'll tell you like, oh, you've synced this.
You can configure which folders you want to sync.
You could, instead of doing all of them, if you just want to sort of manually pick and
choose, it makes it really easy to sync individual photos that you can just select your group.
I mean, it looks like they got pretty good docs too for the server installation.
I mean, look at this.
They got Docker, they got app, they got Raspbian images, they got Unraid, Synology, OpenWRT.
That's awesome.
I love to see that.
Yeah.
It's pretty lightweight as well.
So you don't need, you know, it's not super heavy.
It doesn't have a ton of functionality, especially the gallery that you get on the web.
Like it's not super fancy, but you can go scroll through them.
You can, as I said, you can link from it.
One downside is it doesn't seem like the client is open source.
Now that doesn't seem, there's no ads, there's no, doesn't seem to be any spine that I could
find.
Yeah, you got to weigh that.
It seems like unfortunately we're, besides anything, there's not a ton of great open
source options, maybe because we do want something that's really polished and reliable.
Yeah.
Maybe that, maybe it just takes a lot of investment of time and so people want to make a buck
off of it.
Again, like you were saying though, it's sort of the threat of a loomerage, how are we going
to say it?
Loom range?
Luma range?
Luma rage?
You got to give a shot, Brent.
Oh, well, I don't know why I want to say it in French.
I'd say loomerage.
Luma range.
Okay.
All right.
Been saying Lomo.
Maybe they're dirty French Canadians, I don't know.
But I don't think they're going to be profiling me, indexing all of my data, analyzing my
photos for CSAM violations, and then sending my entire account history to the police automatically
and then shutting my account down, including disconnecting my phone service.
I doubt there's that risk, you know, so this is better.
And it's not, it doesn't seem to have a huge team of development, but I've seen the developers
active on some subreddits, the GitHub repo does have some recent commits.
So it seems to be, if not the fastest project, at least a project that it's steadily adding
features and continuing to be worked on.
They also had a blog post from earlier in this year talking about how it works just
fine with photo prism.
So you know, it's a good, they sort of promote right out of the gate, like, yeah, you know,
you can use this for sync, you can use it for more mix and match with whatever tools,
other tools you might want to use.
Well, that's a great.
That could have best of both worlds right there.
Very nice.
I did take a look at a couple of different options on the view side, too.
I feel like we should mention Pi Gallery, too, just because it's been around for a while
and just a simple app, if all you're looking for is something that can easily display photos,
no editing capabilities, nothing super fancy, but it has a nice snappy UI and because it's
meant to run on a Pi, you know, it's easy for these things to take more resources than
they should.
Yeah.
But this is like legit snappy, even if you've got thousands of photos or big photos.
And what I like about this, too, is you could still use a tool like Photo Sync or Folder
Sync or Lumrage and, you know, you move it over and you can manage it and organize it
yourself on the file system and then just throw this on top of it.
And it's a really simple, straightforward Raspberry Pi with a big old USB disk hanging
off it problem solved kind of solution.
I also like that it supports both OpenStreetMap and Mapbox.
Some of the ones I checked out, they mostly just had Mapbox support, which is fine, but
you need to go like register for a key and, you know, it's only free up to some amount.
All reasonable, but it is nice to have sort of options there.
The other two I took a look at, Photoprism seems really nice, but again, I knew you've
been playing with it, so I wanted to, you know, go farther afield.
I took a look at Photo View and Libre Photos.
Oh, okay.
I've heard of Libre Photos.
Yeah, Photo View seems to be a little bit newer on the scene.
It has some of the same aims as Photoprism, but at this point, it's just a fair bit simpler.
It does have some autosmarts to try to build albums for you and figure out your timeline.
It does have map support as well, but you do need to go set that up.
That was kind of a theme here is like if you wanted some of the extras like map support,
you kind of had to do that plumbing.
It didn't work right out of the box, but it had no problems identifying all of my dumb
selfies right out of the way.
It found dog pics and it found some, I mean, kind of its own weird set of tags, which was
fun.
I think one it found was shrubbery.
Yes.
Was it pictures of shrubbery, was it accurate?
Yeah.
Well, there you go.
Not a shrubbery.
And then Libre Photos, a little fancier, not quite up to the level of Photoprism, but it's
got things like a place tree, it can do word clouds, it has a timeline, it has a social
graph, and also kind of looks for face clusters in the data.
They've also got a nice little sharing functionality built right in that has a concept of public
photos.
So you can mark some photos as public if you're just like maybe you're trying to, you know,
want to display some of the stuff that you don't mind the public world seeing.
Does it spin up a web server for people to view them?
Yeah.
And you can just link to it from the web server that it's got.
And then you can share stuff between different users.
That's one thing.
Both of these support having different users on the server, which is nice.
So if you did want to have maybe, you know, just a gallery that you didn't share with
the wider world, but you had some friends that you go on trips with, or you have some
family that are all using the same system.
Occasional things like family events and whatnot.
Totally.
Right.
So you can give them a sort of internal access to it without having to worry about the whole
world having access.
That's a really nice feature.
I like that a lot.
That's the kind of sharing stuff I'd love to see come to Photo Prism.
I don't know if I want it in a web server locally.
I know they do offer some cloud stuff.
They may offer some cloud sharing with the membership program, but that sounds like what
you just described there sounds really great.
And that's Libre Photos that does that.
Now one other piece that I'm kind of watching for you, I can't you can't easily try it out
yet is I found a Libre Photos Android client looks pretty modern.
So modern that it's actually in private beta right now.
So I haven't actually tried it, but it looks really nice.
It's trying to add that mobile front component to it.
Right.
So it's trying to compete a little bit more with Google Photos, have a really rich client
right there on the device and then handle the syncing for you if you want a little more
fully baked together platform experience.
Image IMMCH or something like that is doing something similar.
That's when we're watching closely on self-hosted.
This is a category like I mentioned that self-hosted tracks because I think going through this
looking at what you found and looking at the tooling and hearing Brent's thoughts about
Photo Prism where I'm at right now is it's there.
The tooling is there.
The capability is there.
It is absolutely totally possible to replace Google Photos now.
It's just up to people to decide if they want to do it or not.
It's absolutely a doable thing.
It's totally manageable even for people that are really busy because a lot of this is you
set it up, you get the plumbing done once and then it's just going to run.
I really like these selections.
Uhura Photos is what it's called.
Uhura Photos is the Libre Photos client app for Android that's under development and the
UI is very similar to Google Photos.
I think this is one Android user should definitely keep an eye on.
That looks really good Wes.
And with all these you know if you've just got photos in some folders all of these were
friendly with that.
Like they didn't necessarily need to have their own proprietary database.
They would build that on top.
Now you might want a solution down the road to help you organize things but I think that
was nice because I didn't feel locked in to the you know I could I had all of them stand
up on top of my synced data with the low mirage so I didn't have to you know I could try them
all out easily.
I didn't have to like migrate things between them or worry that one of them was going to
muck up the structure and then the other one could no longer read it so that was handy.
As for backing things up, low mirage did have an interesting I think they're kind of imagining
you're doing this at home.
You're syncing things to your house.
So they've got this concept of a backup drive so it's got a primary target that it's going
to stick things to and if that fills up or is unavailable you can configure it with an
automatic backup.
So I thought that could be handy maybe if you want to stick things on some spendier
cloud storage that you've got mounted but you don't always want things so you could
have S3 at home you know you could have it dumped S3 if you've run out of stuff at home
if you're worried about that but not always have things on there.
I was lazy though so I just started with S3 or S3 compatible storage right from the get
go.
You know S3FS has an option you can supply your own key if you want to have things encrypted
on the back end using the key that you provide.
So that's a real low you know you don't have to worry about extra programs if you just
want to use S3FS have it mount that storage and then you know the containers underneath
are none the wiser.
That's a great idea.
That's sneaky and performance is fine for what you're doing.
Yeah it was totally fine.
That's good.
Now one question I've kind of been having and I haven't totally resolved.
Do I want all of my photos hot forever or am I willing to set some horizon somewhere
where I'm like willing to transfer those to something else.
I don't always you know that could be in something like Amazon's glacier maybe or if you got
your own tape backups.
I don't know.
I could see a work case for that.
That would be one workflow I haven't fully thought through yet is like do I want to put
stuff in longer term storage that I just don't need access to if it's over 10 years old say
or.
I feel like for my use case I want all of them online so that I can use that location
thing that shows all the photos you took in this place or all the faces of the kids.
Right.
So you want the whole history but not everybody has those use cases.
I could definitely see especially if there was a way to do a low res JPEG preview of
the image and then store the really big version like on that glacier that'd be really nice
wouldn't it.
Yeah.
Something you know like OK I can at least check to see if I want to go pull the full
thing without getting in for it to go find it.
Yeah I could see that.
Maybe people out there doing something like that.
For now I think I'm taking your route though I'm just gonna I'm just gonna pay for the
photos I take and so be it.
Well we got a lot of great links in the notes today.
There is some really good resources in there and of course we haven't touched on every
possible permutation or setup.
So yeah you know in the past I'd used I just see Matrix folks talking about this I had
used Nextcloud to do photo sync and that was all right.
I found it to be annoying in some of the particulars of the weird photo formats.
So I would take one of those you know fancy fake bokeh type portrait mode photos and it
worked fine but each one of those would make a little folder on the Android disk on the
file system and then Nextcloud would tell me it discovered a new photo or new folder
oh it's going to sync that for you.
Yeah.
I don't ever need to see it.
So in the particulars I was less pleased.
Yeah I mean if Nextcloud's working for folks then you know you could take out Lumarager
or sync thing or photo sync in my case and you could just use that.
For me Nextcloud's just way more than I want for this whole pipeline.
I don't want this I don't want it involved.
I just don't want it and I would still throw a Photo Prism on top of it anyways.
But and it's harder to do because Nextcloud's got you know it's mapped all the files through
its database most of the time.
True but you know if it was working for you it was one that got sent in a lot.
We got a ton of great ideas and setups that helped us tinker with different stuff and
try different tools.
So thank you everybody who sent in your emails and gave us ideas and inspirations and we'd
love to keep hearing them and of course the boosts are welcome as well.
I think though for us this is our working setup.
I can safely say I'm done with Google Photos and now I just got to actually take the next
step and go on there and tell it to delete all my data.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Go get started with a free trial for a team or an enterprise or yourself as an individual
at Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Bitwarden is simply the easiest way for yourself or your business to store share and sync your
sensitive data.
I love that Bitwarden can be customizable you can turn certain features on and off in
the enterprise that you don't want with policies or as just a user yourself.
And of course Bitwarden being open source and the fact that it's trusted by millions
in the community gives me confidence.
I know that even way way down the road I'm gonna have access to my passwords.
It's what Wes and I use to manage our passwords and also other sensitive data too like two
factor codes some passphrases for some of my apps like matrix and Bitwarden just keeps
getting better all the time so they make these reads really easy because it's great to see
them add fast mail alias generation now.
Picture it Sicily 1984 you're creating your first online service you're logging in for
the very first time you want to make a complicated password you make it like oh this is a good
password you write it down you come up with your clever clever username oh it's a good
one and you write it down and you sign up you fast forward now it's 2022 you're still
using that same username you still using that same password or you have used it in a lot
of places that's no good.
You know it I know it the whole internet knows it everybody knows it has probably been leaked
more than a dozen times.
Now with Bitwarden you can generate a unique username a unique password and a unique email
address that's only to that site to that service so if anything goes sideways you know exactly
where it came from but also you know you're only compromised just in that one unique set
of credentials everything else is safe nothing feels better than that when that situation
happens nothing feels better than that it is so great and of course Bitwarden is always
adding new features both to the browser extension to the mobile app even to the desktop apps
go check out Bitwarden at bitwarden.com slash Linux see why we like it so much and then
if you know someone out there who is not practicing safe passwords maybe point them to that URL
get them on board it's probably the number one thing they could do to improve their online
security if they're not doing that right now come on bitwarden.com slash Linux let's all
go over there help out family or friends or workplace or I don't know a stranger on the
corner everybody could use better passwords bitwarden.com slash Linux
I did want to say thank you to the listeners for sending in some great feedback we got
a lot of suggestions on which photo applications to try so thank you for sending all of those
in Bob did write in about CASA OS hey guys what do you think about CASA OS looks interesting
to me but I'm just a noob I want something to run on my Pi 3b plus just doing document
mp3 and photo sharing mainly what do you think community-based open source software focused
on delivering simple home cloud experience around a docker ecosystem it's a project that's
focused on like leading with the best dashboard the prettiest dashboard yeah that's clearly
their focus none of us have used it but it's it's that kind of typical Linux system with
a docker plumbing underneath these seem to be really solid and popular but I think each
has to be evaluated on their own and you know I really like umbral and they've just added
a bunch of really great stuff but there's these projects are all still really early
days and some of them have some security considerations and whatnot hey you know CASA OS has photo
developers I was just gonna say that that was totally unintentional but very very nice
it also works with looks like it makes home assistant easy to deploy you know these can
be really compelling the thing that's tricky is like home assistant also wants to do this
job where it wants to be your applications platform everyone wants to manage your apps
so it's getting to the point where there's almost too many of these but I CASA does I
have to say look like a decent one just going through their website but I definitely have
to try it to know and it does seem like an area that's that's useful at least if we want
broader adoption of some of these stuff right we might be comfortable spending a day or
two getting you know figuring out oh this project has docker commands but I gotta put
that a compose file or they have instructions for the base OS but that's fine I know I can
just stick it over here or let me go find and vet an image that someone else has built
for this but what are you gonna do if you want you know some of your friends who want
to take over some of their self-control but they have less skills you know I was trying
to figure out if we had talked about this on the network previously and I did a little
search at notes.jupiterbroadcasting.com and I think it's important to note that you shouldn't
get confused between CASA OS and Nooboo CASA which I was like oh yeah we've definitely
talked about that but they're two distinct things yeah Nooboo CASA is the company behind
Home Assistant and CASA OS is a Linux distro based server platform I guess a friend of
the show wrote in as well regarding the conversations we've been having recently about malware on
Linux and how to protect yourself they write I run hundreds of servers many with well-known
public IPs IPs from decades-old running class a networks yeah those class A's oh fun I have
some straightforward suggestions that have kept my public facing bits from getting owned
okay I'd be happy to elaborate but basically number one failed to ban failed to ban everywhere
number two SSH D config with a permit root without password so that means to only allow
root SSH logins when using private keys and number three OS sec and was a or other log
reading aggregators for when you miss things I've been told that many people turn off se
Linux on their servers during the kickstart installation script I would not know about
that though but it hasn't seemed to hurt them yet wouldn't recommend that's one of those
don't do as I actually do they say things yeah all of us at some point of probably disabled
se Linux a few more times than we should have let's admit it now it's true it's true it's
getting better it's getting better on newer fedora installs but if you can get it working
it is a nice little peace of mind I have to say Jason also wrote in a bit on malware and
security yeah mentioning crowd sec which I hadn't heard about before but I did read the
description here crowd sec is a free modern and collaborative behavior detection engine
coupled with a global IP reputation network it stacks on failed bands philosophy but is
IP v6 compatible and about 60 times faster so it's go versus python uses grok patterns
to parse logs and yaml scenarios to identify behaviors crowd sec is engineered for modern
cloud containers and VM based infrastructures by decoupling detection and remediation once
detected you can remedy the threat with various bouncers firewalls nginx HTTP 403s captures
it etc while the aggressive IPs can be sent to crowd sec for curation before being shared
among all users to further improve everyone's security you know I believe Westpain has a
global IP reputation network he runs as well yeah I sure do yeah I do have to send you
the IPs in the mail so it's you know it's not the fastest to get identified but I do
send them you do and it's been it's been a really good system it's just something West
does for free in a spare time don't know why but you know Jason we got a lot of people
that said crowd sec is a must recommend and I'm really glad I don't have to think about
these things anymore very very very glad there was a time and a place that time and places
no more I keep I keep all my systems behind firewalls I no longer have any inbound ports
on any of my firewalls except for one of the ones here at the studio I just realized I'm
saying that but that's the problem with them you forget about them right yeah but you know
it's I feel a lot better I don't really I don't worry about it too much we could probably
think about this for our cloud instances though I'm impressed recently with how this kind
of crowdsource security is getting pretty common I'm thinking also of crowdsource like
ad blocking and such I think in the last few years these have shown up and it's impressive
what all of us kind of working together can come up with I really like that concept yes
as long as it isn't abused these things are always have that potential like I'm just thinking
of spam blacklists they're mostly good but they also have made it nearly impossible to
self-host your own email now because of these shared blacklists if you accidentally get
on one for some stupid reason right what are the other processes in place who do you you
know who do you appeal to to remedy things if anyone or at all and now it is time for
the boost we got some great boost into the show this week and I want to mention if you
don't hear your boosts on here we are recording two shows today so we save some for this episode
and we save some for other episodes and we're curating them now we're picking certain boosts
we're reading all of them and getting some of them onto the air and hey citizen boosted
in last week with 69 69 sats a citizen and it gives me just an opportunity to talk about
something I love he says he loves Linux and he loves lit now pop quiz for you guys can
any of you guys describe what lit is what does it mean if our show is lit now I should
I mean I know in the sense of the fire emoji I should I'm on board with that yeah that's
true I see here it's you've spelt it specifically or they've spelt it specifically capital L
small I capital T so maybe that's an indicator West for you I can give you a hint yeah but
it might give it away so I'll just tell you it is the live item tag in the podcasting
tutorial oh that's embarrassing now yeah and so apps like pod verse and others have the
ability to actually stream our live stream in their app and you just looking at your
podcasts you know this your list of shows to listen to and Linux unplugged shows up
with a little live badge next to it and wouldn't click that and what's brilliant about it is
it's just done through the RSS feed and if this is one of the namespaces in there's this
live item tag you put that in there and then the podcast catcher sees that and it just
adds it to the list as a live show and it's one of the beauties of the podcasting tutorial
stuff so much good stuff getting developed over there yep so I just appreciate the opportunity
to actually talk about that because I love it and I think it'll come it'll be it'll be
here one day we first have to get to the stage of completely generating all our own RSS feeds
on our own we'll experiment with office hours and member feeds and then we'll roll it out
to all the shows someday in the near future yeah stay tuned and hey pro tip to you boosters
out there if you mention podcasting 2.0 you're pretty likely to get on there that's true
Blake Collin boosted in with 10,001 sats coming in hot with the boost I love that one he's
got a pro tip speaking of podcasting 2.0 you can boost from the podcast index web page
our Linux unplugged entry there oh right from the source just have to have the Albee extension
which is top-notch software and we have a link to the Linux unplugged entry at podcast
index org but yeah you don't need it you don't need a mobile app you could actually do it
from your web browser on your fancy laptop or desktop from the podcast index page and
Blake sent in 10,001 sets doing that and then I guess I just picked all the ones I felt
like talking about today Molybdenum boosted in with just 500 sats but I like the message
she says I don't like crypto at all but I love the idea of the lightning network and
the use for stuff like this or maybe a game server you're playing on could see how be
able to boost into a game server would be extremely useful I agree I don't like crypto
either don't like it don't like web 3 so far and hasn't impressed me much maybe one day
it will so far it has not and we get into all of that in office hours episode 9 we hate
crypto too and I try to explain the difference between Bitcoin and crypto the green eagle
boosted in with 2,000 sats I'm still using sync thing to backup photos off mine and my
wife's phone as a bonus it allows me to sync other files like notes unfortunately though
I'm still using Google for sharing organizing searching etc so sync thing is really only
a secondary backup I always intended to self-host a solution but I'm afraid the effort won't
be worth it because the bar for spouse approval is too high I run into that issue every time
I start down the path of switching something off a Google service yeah that's an important
consideration and I I strongly believe that the setup I described today with photosync
and photoprism and duplicati is a totally spouse approved stack because the UI on photosync
is great the UI on photoprism is great you can have different user accounts on photoprism
so they can have their own login with their own albums and stuff if you want to do that
really top-notch stuff and then duplicati you know she's never really gonna have to
see that but if I were sick and she needed to check the status of the backup she could
just check the bookmark I have and it's all in a web UI it gives you error messages that
are clear and easy to read for the most part so I think that stack is probably as close
as you can get to a commercial product in terms of polish of UI and it seems like things
are only getting better right I mean you mentioned image and just more solutions coming along
to try to fit that role more polish over time and more on the whole the whole pipeline in
one place just fewer moving pieces and I'd say this Westpain photoprism has gotten noticeably
better since we talked about it last time on the show so solid yeah continuous improvements
over there too the whole stack also a green eagle if your wife is unhappy I mean you can
just blame Chris so center yeah that's totally cool man people do it all the time he guaranteed
that's possible approval Belf Winnie Belf in we Chris we do this one I think you'll get
this one Belf in we I like it all right Belf in we well done boosted it with 512 sets they
say love the show and so glad you talked about Linux Mint every now and then as it was my
first distribution and still my favorite also trying boosts for the first time after listening
to this episode and noticed a few days ago my boosts stop accumulating in my wallet oh
probably talking about fountain earn there I'd imagine right yeah probably talking about
fountain earn perhaps yeah perhaps I love when we get the first boosters into the show
so 512 stats good enough for me I love hearing that that's so great and also yeah we try
to be aware of the fact that there are a decent amount of Mint users out there and even though
it's not our daily driver as they say we still want to try to be represented from time to
time as best we can as non-Mint users ourselves you know I started on Mint as well and oh
well actually that's not entirely true I started on XFC but we don't talk about that too often
banned from the show yeah I was on there for a year but then moved to Linux Mint for many
many years and really loved it and still have a few friends that I support who are using
it and still loving it so it's just like the distro that just keeps on ticking I know you've
told me but you were a Cinnamon user at that time too right yeah yeah I think I originally
moved to Cinnamon because it was okay I did a bunch of research because I loved GNOME
2 at the time and I knew yeah I knew at the time moving to GNOME 3 was a hot topic we
all had feels about a brand yeah yeah so I thought Cinnamon being a fork might be a nice
thing and it was not the most stable thing back then but it seemed to be getting a ton
of development I mean they even had a button to like restart Cinnamon that was just a built-in
feature which was if you remember is that still there Wes I think you might have yeah
I think I think so I say keep it but it actually for the most part was really great and was
just customizable enough and so yeah it was a great experience I had nothing wrong with
that and I'm proud to say that I used Mint for a while T-Kario boosts in with ten thousand
sets boost with all the decentralized and open source software that y'all use at JB I've
been wondering what the heck are you using meetups for there appear to be options like
mobile zone get together and I believe meetups is paid so perhaps some of that funding you're
using on meetups could go towards another open source project instead though I acknowledge
you may lose some of the organic discovery provided by meetup and their network effect
be great to hear what y'all think about it though that's a great question I feel like
we kind of over time move to decentralized or free software tools as that tooling kind
of meets our needs and in some areas like the hackintoshes were a great example and
Wirecast for a long time we had to just live with a proprietary solution that was just
painful and then because I mean from the business perspective you kind of start with the like
we need to do X because we've determined we need to do X to accomplish the goals we're
doing and then ideally we can do that with open source decentralized software but you
got to get a start from that angle there's definitely that aspect of it and then I mean
not to not to be this guy but there is some truth to this is like sometimes we're just
early and we start using something and there isn't a free software solution available like
that we've been using meetup for ever before it was ridiculously expensive to use right
but meetup is like number one with a bullet on our services list that we use that we want
to replace we've experiment experimented with get together and we haven't been super happy
with it we would love to use something that our community could also use to self organize
their own meetups because we've heard from dozens of people that want to organize meetups
in their area with other JB audience members but we just don't have a platform for them
to use so it seems like whatever we switch to should probably be the same tooling and
then that just like is a huge lift and that's where we're at right now but it is number
one with a bullet and in the meantime it gets sort of a pass because of that network effect
that you mentioned it is valuable to let people know hey we got a new meetup in this area
that's but we would hope they would come over to whatever new platform we have and we're
not using it I mean it's it's quite public in one sense but in the other hand it's you
know we add some entries there and there's a little bit of back and forth we put some
details maybe some comments but it's not otherwise it's sort of tertiary to a lot of the rest
of the systems yeah wise Papa John boosts in with 2674 satoshis b-o-o-s-t I'm a serial
audiobook listener and I only listen to podcasts between books so I'm usually two or three
episodes behind and I actually enjoy having a handful of episodes to binge all at once
I get that I get that I continue to request people send in your listening habits I've
been doing this for 15 years and I still find it absolutely fascinating oh yeah I want to
know how you find the show I want to know how you listen to the show I want to know
how far behind you are these are all things that we try to factor in when we're planning
content so actually having that information super valuable to use the chapters do you
want do you need us to do stuff that makes it easier the chapters did you know we have
chapters chapters did you know everything is chaptered these features let us know because
you know as podcasters we don't get a lot of data that's the way this decentralized
system works we don't really know we just put an mp3 for it and I think everybody likes
it that way so let's just keep it that way so just tell us because you know some of these
podcast out there with their dynamic ads they want all this data you guys know what I'm
talking about hey I want to say thank you to a group out there too first of all we don't
read all of the boosts on the air we do have another episode coming up but not everything
makes it on the air we are curating the boosts these days but we read all of them and it
still makes me smile every time it comes in Brent knows it now that he's here yeah yeah
you hear the little pew that pew that we play the helipad interface plays that in real time
and also does an explosion of confetti and it's a real celebration every time a boost
comes in in this studio it's great it makes us smile so shout out to bond who just caught
up on the show and got current after falling behind great to have you back on board we
got 1500 sats from Prozac who just wanted to toss a little bit to Brent's gas fund thank
you we super appreciate that what an amazing thing that's been we're gonna talk more about
that on the road we have plans to talk about that it's just stuff we're not getting to
today we also got a row of ducks from Elrey Elrey I thought we decided we were just calling
them 741 the old seven yeah lucky number he's thanking us though for trying to get
the name right still trying and it's I think I think I have like name aphasia or something
like word aphasia okay cuz like um I just it doesn't stick and I've read that is actually
a problem for ADD people so there you go if you if you wanted a symptom here it is I'd
also like to do an extra shout out to Elrey and chance as well and also CG bass player
while I've been traveling this week and just totally wrapped up in all of the studio projects
we've been doing some may have noticed that I've done a little less appearing on our website
project on GitHub and but the three of them have really taken things up and have been
committing you know there were some merges that I wasn't even aware of Chris and I visited
the website I was like oh look isn't that amazing it's incredible can we just stop for
a second to acknowledge how incredible that is how incredible that is our community is
improving our website while we are heads down preparing for this road trip and planning
multiple shows and Brent and I have been working very diligently on a project that we cannot
tell you about yet that has also been consuming a ton of our time and he's been traveling
and we're gonna be away traveling and so to have our community keep that going and add
new features that we've talked about amazing it's just it's kind of perfect too right because
like I mean I don't really use the website right I mean it's not for me we're behind
the scenes yeah yeah but it's the audience's website that's why we have it it's for them
to make the show accessible and be and so they have way better ideas on how to make
it awesome than I've ever had this is that this is the true incredible aspect of value
for value right I mean the kind of value they're returning right now it's just amazing so yeah
we absolutely should be thanking them and don't worry I'll be back in time but I think
they should be generous we're like we're gonna be a little slow on matrix and telegram we're
gonna be kind of slow on the github because we're gonna be we're either driving sleeping
or recording for like three weeks straight if we see you and appreciate yeah we will
still be looking as much as we can and all the messages and checking the helipads and
all of that too we got a hello out there to mr I'm gonna say bench nice he just found
luck for the first time using oh that's awesome the fountain charts so thanks to the boosting
we're getting away we're yeah I'm getting these things I'm getting this message a lot
I'm getting a lot because what happens is people send in their baller boost using the
fountain app we show up on the charts and then people say well this must be a good show
because people are actually totally wrong but they get but anyways bench thanks for
joining us thank you everybody who boosts in we do appreciate it if you'd like to join
the fun you can go to newpodcastapps.com and get a new podcast app or you can actually
just boost from the podcastindex.org website if you got the Albie extension or you can
really be a geek and get boost CLI set up I feel like that's whole there's a whole other
world of self-hosting you have to wrap your head around so if you manage to get boost
CLI up and running I think that's legitimately one of the more impressive technical tasks
you could pull off right now so boost into the show if you get boost CLI working and
that brings us to the end of this week's episode of the unplug program links to all of the
really great tools we talked about today at linuxunplug.com slash 476 476 really simple
there and of course you can also get it at the new website at jupiterbroadcasting.com
now just a note we will not be live next week but you will have an episode in your feeds
for our members and for our regular listeners and thank you to our members too who really
invest in the ongoing content creation here at Linux Unplugged you can become a member
at unplugedcore.com or support all the shows at jupiter.party you got to get Linux action
news that that show continues to roll on we're going to be recording that live from the road
covering the world of Linux and open source like don't stop we can't it sure don't and
it's a real companion to this show we got some great clips from the plumbers conference
the announcement of the Linux Foundation Europe edition yeah Chris will only let me nerd out
about eBPF or IO Earrings so much on love these days I just crammed it in Linux Action
you managed to get a kegzak story in there recently too so go check that out at linuxactionnews.com
just get more Linux also thanks for listening you can check out the live versions at Jupiter.tube
and we'll see you right back here in a couple of weeks.