You know you got your this is it. We got it. We'll do a moment in RV here on the live stream and
Emily's Emily's considering getting herself a fifth wheel RV now the fifth wheel RVs are big
They're like apartments because they don't have an engine and they don't have like the steering area so they can make extra living space out of
It there. They're a pretty sweet way to go. It's essentially like living in an apartment so obviously Emily
I'm gonna say yeah, go for it
I like it a lot
We today was kind of an interesting day from an RV full-time or perspective because I'm about two hours out from the studio
I'm not even that far, but it's it's a long ways out from the studio
and there's a big storm today lots of wind the powers out and
It's funny when the when that happens in an RV
It's it's not like when the power goes out normally that because at first it's uh yeah, did the power just go out
Yeah, yeah
I think so because nothing really in the RV changes because you've got house batteries and some units even have generators so pretty quickly
It's just another day and today in particular is like that is really really handy now
The flip side is that I got outside, and I smelled something a little funny a
little a little stinky
kind of like rotten eggs I
Know immediately is propane and I start going home some dumb son of a bitch around here
They got their propane linking out of there out of their RV
But they're about to blow up their whole damn house those wait a minute. Is that me is that mean?
Couldn't be me could it I better to go double-check so I I walk over to my rig
This is my trucks already started
I'm about to leave to come into the studio, but I you know I'm like I better double-check this and I think it's just because
It was so windy is just sort of been waffling it around because I we sure enough had a leak
I opened up the bay where our propane tank was and I heard this little
No, and so I quickly turned off the propane valve to
To you know just solve the problem immediately and what must have happened is is we have an adapter on there that I think got
a little loose when we drove and
We just didn't really catch it because the wind hadn't really been blowing much
And so we you know possibly could have been blown up our home
So there's always that line just a slight danger nothing nothing terrible at the same time though
It's it's pretty great to be out somewhere where we are it's it's it's like stereotypical
Hollywood fall time road driving like if if they were gonna show a car driving down a fall road with all the beautiful colors
that's where we're at so it's neat to be able to go there for a few weeks spend some time there and then come back and
Get a little bit closer to work when we're done, so I say go for it Emily
I think more and more people are gonna be doing it. This is Linux unplugged episode
219 for October 17th
Oh
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's reformatted and reinstalling every spare machine
It's got my name is Chris. My name is Wes or so I think because I've lost all my documents
Oh, no. Well, hello Wes and over there is beard. Hello beard. So guys
This is an episode you could say
I'm a bit pumped up about bit pumped up. This is one of those episodes
That reminds me why I got into podcasting. I am very much looking forward today's episode
We're going to review Ubuntu 1710 in just a little bit in the show and we're also gonna cover some rather
Important community news this week that we're gonna break it down as they say that's what we say
I'll break it down. We're gonna analyze and break it down. Yeah, we'll get through some of the community news and events that we
Want to talk about including some projects. We just recently covered that needs some help and
then
1710s here now, even if you're not an Ubuntu user
I encourage you to stick around for the review coming up in the show
In fact, I you more than smart maybe more than anybody else. I challenge you. You're a long time an anti Ubuntu
White, is that it? Is that a thing? It is now an anti Ubuntu er, I don't know. But if you're one anti Ubuntu, I don't know
Yeah, it's a hard one. I asked I asked for you to stick around for a bit
And if you're considering the upgrade debating it, I also encourage you to stick around
obviously, I had a lot of hands-on with 1710 at
the Ubuntu rally
We've been running it here for days. I've been running it for weeks and weeks
And so this is one of those reviews that we get to do rarely and I'm really looking forward to doing that
But we got to get to some of this news. This is big big new stuff big new stuff
So let's holla at our virtual lug time appropriate greetings mama room
Hello
Hello, that was nice and concise Wow
Top of it. Yeah, they like gotten a cue. Yeah, they took turns
No, I want to say right here at the top of the show next week as an experiment
I think we're gonna try doing discord just so we can do an AB and let the audience decide what they thought worked better
So if you'd like to help us participate in that test go to discord.me slash Jupiter colony to join our discord
You can use the web browser discord app or you can download their electron app
And I guess there's a snap of it and there's probably other ways you can get about it
Anyways, we're gonna do it a little AB and we'll let the audience and the audience being both the participators and the listeners decide which
Worked better. So join us for 220 in discord next week virtual lug. We're not switching. We're just testing for one episode
starting with
221 we'll be back in mumble until we make a decision. So we're not switching. We're just trying for 220 in discord
I'm installing the snap right now. Oh, yeah, that's right
So yeah
Give it a go on that and I'm gonna see you know
And the other thing I have to consider too is like guess because we bring guests in via mumble and all that stuff
I'll say my bias is to stick with mumble right off the top. That's my bias because it's worked for us. It's free
It's open source and it's part of the show. That's my bias, but we're gonna give it a good AB. See what how it goes
okay, so let's start with a news story that's kind of a big one that is
Complicated and it's this new enforcement statement around the Linux kernel Greg KH Chris Masson
Rick van rail
I want to say and Sean Khan all got together and wrote up a big old post about this new signing statement
Essentially that's going to be attached to the Linux kernel
But I wanted to start with a little bit of information
That's kind of kind of interesting Greg has talked about this every single year that the the kernel continues to change faster than it did
the year before
Which is nuts since it's 26 years old now
so this year
This year they're running around eight point five changes an hour
10,000 lines of code added
2000 modified
2500 lines removed every hour of every day Wow
Those numbers are just insane. Yeah, and so there's been a problem going on in the background. You're familiar with netfilter
I am and there's been
Some shenanigans as a result of the developer of a developer from netfilter
Patrick McCarty and it's causes the kernel developers to rethink
aspects of the kernel license
Now we're not going gpl3 here, but stick with me for a second BST MIT
Apache what's happening Chris so Greg and others right the same processes that we use to assure fulfillment quote-unquote of license
Obligations, you know to make sure that companies that are violating the GPL come into compliance
The same obligations and availability of source code all of those can be used to unjustly troll active in unjustly trolling activities to extract
personal monetary rewards from GPL software
The kernel team appears to call it monetization for short these they're trying to monetize their code in
Particular issues have arisen as a developer from the netfilter community Patrick McCarty has sought to enforce his copyright claims in secret and
for large sums of money by threatening or
engaging in litigation
Some of his compliance claims are issues that could easily be resolved however
He has also made claims based around ambiguities in the GPL, too
That no one in our community had ever considered part of compliance to begin with so here's an example
This is really something examples of these claims have been distributing over-the-air firmware
Requiring a cell phone maker to deliver a paper copy of the source code offered letter
claiming that the source code server must be set up with a download speed as fast as a as the binary server based on the
Equivalent access language of section 3 ie he's trying to take section 3 language of the GPL
That that talks about equivalent access and apply that to download speeds
And if you don't if you are in violation of that then he's going after you
He's also saying that it mandates that paper copies of the GPL be distributed that it gets that it gets
Translated to other languages and if you fail to do any of these things you're out of compliance and because of the way the GPL
To a structured he demands immediate action and if you fail to take immediate action
Then he gets to claim damages at some insane amount for the and for the amount of time that you don't make these corrections
He gets to claim damages, then he goes after you for those damages
Because of this and help clarify with the majority of the Linux community members feels a correct way to enforce their license
the technical advisory board of the Linux Foundation has worked together with lawyers in the community and
individual developers and many companies to participate in the development and now rely on
The draft of the kernel enforcement statement to help address both the specific issue
They're facing today and to help prevent any future issues like this from happening again
Now it adopts some termination provisions that are from the GPL 3 and essentially layers it down on top
And isn't re-licensing because what it what it essentially is is it's an agreement
And it's a statement that says the copyright holders of this kernel code
Interpret this clause this way. This is our collective understanding of this line of the GPL 2
And as a result we also now assume these additional new things and these new things are
The additional permissions given to companies that have confidence of the copyright holder to reach compliance
So you're you're essentially allowing people time to reach compliance
And they hope this will re-establish user slash business confidence and help direct enforcement activity back to the original purpose
Which is actual compliance and not screwing people for?
Failing to get the right download speed and then suing them for damages when they haven't corrected immediately
by
bastardizing language from the GPL 2 to use as a hammer so they're lacquering on top of
Agreements that the the stakeholders of the Linux community
Kernel have agreed upon it's really complicated
But because essentially the top developers hold the bulk of the kernel code copyright
As long as you get this top tier group of developers to agree to this
New layer this enforcement statement then essentially you have something that is law in a way because
By making it very clear how the project interprets that legal ease
That means you are accepting their interpretation when you now use the project and so you can't come after them afterwards pretending like you didn't know
That's my rough non-lawyer understanding of this. It's very complicated
Well, it's the law
If you want to know more or think I got something wrong
Please feel free to let me know and also linked in the show notes. I have
A fact that Greg KH has posted. I have more information about Patrick McHardy and his copyright profiteering
That many developers in the Linux community have been worried about this is something that's been brewing in the background for ages now and
apparently
Software Conservancy is all in with this statement
They have they have a press release. It says they applaud the Linux community's promotion of principle
principled copier left enforcement and they say the soft the statement includes additional permissions under the Linux license
Which is GPL 2 so they agree this does not change the kernel from GPL 2 to GPL 3 and they applaud this new statement
So there you go. Yeah, apparently Greg Greg says at some point more than like 200 kernel developers
Discussed the complexities of a problem. That's a yeah to come to that
Well, it seems like it was a good a good decision. I can certainly see why the Linux Foundation be concerned and why people be concerned about the
You know lack of assurity that businesses would have when trying to use it and obviously that's a big goal to keep businesses invested in Linux
Yeah, and now let's talk about the other really kind of big story this week
So that's the probably the biggest and it's hard to really break it all down and it's for desktop users
It really has no big
Impact either way, not really. Yeah, but this one has more of an impact on desktop users. You guys probably all know about crack at this point
k-r-a-c-k
crack is whack WPA 2 is broken now and
You guys just got done covering this on tech snaps. That's not a good spot to to point people's tech snap and also ask Noah this week
Both have really good coverage on the on this problem. So it's not really our domain necessarily the Linux distribution
Are good at putting out the patches man, but boy they sure talking about Android and Linux a lot in the reviews
Yeah, there's a lot of other systems and OS is that I mean and and maybe some of that is for good reason about like
Well, you know Windows already has a patch for instance, but some of our Android phones will not see those patches
But if you're not explicit about it, that's just kind of confusing. Mm-hmm dance here from elementary. I'm Dan
I'm curious if you have any like
Any any insights to share from the well there? Well, that's some timing well on the distribution side of pushing the patch
Is that pretty smooth for you guys? Is it is it something where somebody?
Somebody sits up in the elementary team and says, okay. Let's make sure this one goes out or how does that process work for you guys?
Actually for us, it's completely transparent because we're based on Ubuntu
We just get it directly from canonical security team like everybody else. Yeah, I figured that out
Probably be the case Dan and then they got it out pretty quick a lot of the distributions did Linux really kicked butt on this particular one
People will people notice too, which is really cool. This is a lot of times
We're right on top of the patches, but people just take it for granted
But because this one got so much publicity and it affects desktop users to people notice this update coming down
Then you saw some real hustle. That was cool. All right. Well, thanks for the insight there damn
I I got to say
We have been fighting some problems here in the studio for four weeks again. We have these these frequent now
Gnome 3 crashes and what seems to happen is gnome takes a crash and then when gnome crashes
It seems to crash our audio server which then we lose about 25 seconds 30 seconds of audio on our live stream and in our episode
recordings
No, this is not deja vu. Yes. We've talked about this before
We actually had it resolved for a while for weeks and weeks and weeks. We resolved it with with really no
No complaints like beard fixed a few things did a couple of updates and put a new Nvidia driver on there
I can't remember what you what was it? What was it? It wasn't anything that complicated. It was basics
I basically just updated the drivers and sell the new Nvidia driver and it went away
Yeah, and so we thought okay, we're good. We can we can we can proceed on sanity and we have the LTS kernel
So yes, it's arch, but we have the LTS kernel. Yeah, right. So we thought okay, we're good. We're good without changing
We haven't done any updates because it's working and it's only been you know a few weeks
Without changing anything and only just a handful of reboots now all of a sudden gnome threes begun crashing again on us
There's not really anything of any detail in the log. It's it's
It's one of those things where I think by the end of next week. I'm gonna reload this machine
It's just got a half an hour to go
And I've been waiting to see I've been waiting to see which way am I gonna go? Where's it gonna break?
What am I gonna do? Do I go solace? Do I go fedora? Do I go Ubuntu?
Do I go arch again with the LTS the kernel and the LTS drivers?
So that's gonna be part of what we talked about today
Because it's it's in the background. It is a brood as they say
But first I want to thank Linux Academy before we go much further in the show Linux academy.com slash unplug
That's where you go to sign up for a free seven-day trial and support the show. It's a platform to learn more about Linux
And they have really nice hands-on scenario based labs to give you experience on real servers
They have self-paced in-depth video courses on every Linux and cloud and DevOps topic
And if you get stuck anywhere, they have real humans instructors full-time humans
They can help you one of the things that's really nice about Linux Academy is their course scheduler
If you're busy you got kids you got a job you got a lot going on. Maybe you're like West you live in downtown Seattle
So you're always busy and that's true, right? That's right
Yeah, but I still got to learn things course scheduler West you pick a course
You set a time frame and it just helps you stick to it gives you friendly reminders
If you want them about your goals, I was looking in here just yesterday for
Getting started on Android development six hours and 40 minutes or something like that
And you get started on Android development breaks it all down. I like to think I'm pretty good at unstructured learning
Figuring stuff out for myself, but I don't know how long that's gonna take
Even if you have a good note sheet to use like Linux Academy makes it so easy back
Okay, I have two hours right now because my plans fell through I'm going to learn something concrete
Yeah, and they have offline stuff
You can take with you to learn on the go
Including iOS and Android apps and those video courses check it out Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged it's a platform to learn more about Linux Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and a big
Thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplug program. I
Want to do a quick little mention for the Linux vendor firmware project
We talked about FW update last week. What a fantastic project
That is got to version 1 0 lets you update your firmwares on your Linux's now. Here's the problem
They're looking a little low on funds right now
And you would think that like Dell and HP and these companies would pay them, but no that's not how these things work
Unfortunately, and so there's some hosting costs here, and I really feel like these guys are an undersold
Asset to the community and they are asking for humble things
They say at the moment the secure part of the Linux vendor firmware project is hosted on a dedicated scale-away instance
So any additional donations would be spent on paying this small bill and putting it on the table
So any additional donations would be spent on paying this small bill and perhaps more importantly buying some secondhand
Hardware to include as part of our release QA checks
Now if this was a business that delivered if Linux if Linux was a business that delivered firmware updates to its customers
They wouldn't be scrapping together a couple of thousand dollars right and buying secondhand hardware
And this is some this is one of the unsung hero aspects of open sources often this stuff is being done on budgets that
Are inconceivable to multinational companies and I would I would be wonderful if this was not a project
That was hurting for time and resources and money if they could pay for developers if they could pay for hosting
I really think that would be a good use of people's time and money if you want to donate they accept payments via
Libra pay or PayPal they have details on their website which we have linked in the show notes just such a such a great
Project you know getting getting your firmware updates out there like your microcode updates and your all the other stuff out there
Yeah that was previously you had to boot into some crazy free DOS or load up your windows system
Just and hope that you don't brick everything and it's still early days too so you have more that needs to be done
We have more work that needs to be done still so help them get there
He's got some work on his hands I struggle to understand this completely but it is essentially a compatibility layer for steam
That could work across all distributions using snaps and a new feature of snap 2.28 called bases which allow you to create a soulless
Base snap whoa take that in for a second a soulless base snap so he can create an environment based on the soulless base snap
That you could put on an Ubuntu bugs and a fedora bugs and energy bugs you know I'm saying I want that right now
Yeah it's kind of a neat feature and I guess technically everything right now is just sort of based on like a core snap
Everything's dependent on a core snap which is like base Ubuntu system but it could be a fedora or soulless right it doesn't matter
So Ike is using this newfangled base technology to create this Linux steam integration layer
That is basically a replacement for the runtime stuff that's done now with steam in theory
So we could all get access to all the hard work they've done over in the soulless world of having that top-notch steam runtime
The core thing you're you know I know we won't talk about this much but the the core thing you're trying to get out of this
Is you have a lot of good hard work that's gone into libraries and drivers and all this stuff that Ubuntu 12.04
Simply does not have because it's from 2012 think about that that's a long time ago
Great year that it was right be it in the past but that is what the steam runtime is based on
And that's why early on Ike was trying to solve this problem with the little menu
But it's a little menu that comes up and it asks you to choose native libraries or steam libraries
It's like the steam integration chooser or whatever and that was the first that's the first attempt at this
This is like the final attempt at solving this problem and it solves it for all distributions too
They talk about it more in the most recent late night Linux if you want to hear Ike talk about it
Because he could explain about it and I could but I would love to see it as somebody who jumps distros
That's really you know where I find this to be interesting is it would allow me to distro hop but still have the same consistent steam experience
Right
And this is how they're gonna do it they're gonna have to target these these bases like this
But it's really also nice to see like that snap functionality really coming along because like snap has come a long way as a format
And as just like the tooling is available that now that seems totally reasonable and maybe in the future it'll be
You know once we have snap on more distributions or at least more like in the defaults
Telling people how to start gaming on Linux should be really easy and we can be confident that it'll just work
So Dan I've seen I've seen a recent insight post over at canonical about elementary working with snap packages
But I've also seen the elementary Twitter account say you guys are also excited about flat pack
So what's going on? What's going on over at elementary with snaps and flat packs and future integration of stamps?
What's where's all that at at least right now?
I mean, I think overall the consensus is that it's early days on kind of both of these projects
And there's a lot of people doing really interesting things to kind of push it forward and get ready to start shipping it
I know that Martin's working on
Distributing snaps in Ubuntu matei, but for us when when we're
When we're looking to adopt a new technology or change kind of the way that we do things
Like we subscribe to this idea of having a one true development path
And so we want to make sure that if we pick a technology and say, hey, we like this and we're going to go with this
That we've tested it really thoroughly and that it works for like everything across the board
And that it's something that we can tell our third party developer community that it works right now for them to use
So we're still trying to like explore and we're totally happy to like attend events and work with the upstream
Feel like there's some political waters though. You have to navigate a bit like you don't want to upset different camps basically
Yeah, I mean, there's some politics, but there's also some like brand management to it as well
Like, you know, I had third party developers messaging me after the canonical blog post
Asking like, hey, you know, do I need to start getting my apps ready for snaps?
You know, so they're expecting more communication from from us on that
And, you know, it's kind of like, hey, you know, no, not yet. We're still looking into it
Yeah, it's of course, you know, like we it's like a big topic right now
But it feels like it's got another nine months at least before like it really like we're giving it the
It's good that we're talking about it, but I think it gets probably more discussion than it totally warrants
But it's one of those things. It's this is what's here. It's happening now
So I guess that's what we're talking about, right?
And this this thing that Ike is doing this Linux steam integration project
This looks like it could solve real problems for different distributions down
I mean, I know it's it's using a solace base, but if this really worked and it became
Sort of a ubiquitous way to get steam working across distributions. Would it be something you guys would take a look at?
I mean, I definitely think that for certain third-party packages that being able to do these kind of things are super important
Like like you said steam targets, you know 1204 right and and they're never going to build a version of steam for elementary OS
So there's always gonna have to be like a side loading story and it seems like container formats like snap are the best
Side loading story that that we could have going forward. Yeah, and it it also solves that that well, there's no applications available problem
Well, that's not really true. You know once you start getting a couple of these things in in container formats
And you start you start making targets like this like this Linux team integration target
Yeah, it starts changing because then you start targeting these you can start targeting these base snaps instead of targeting distributions
Right and that could have big ramifications on the availability of applications
And look at Ike here, you know, he's he's not holding I give him credit here. He's not holding this in just for solace
Yeah, right. I mean that's kind of a big selling point for solace, but now you can get it anywhere
Mm-hmm. So anyways, we'll follow it with some interest. I'll probably kick the tires you have thoughts beer
I just find it interesting that everybody's talking about snaps and flat packs and app image is just like been pushed off to the side
I mean, you know what the thing about app images is that it only kind of solves cross-platform
But it like what's really important is all the security and privacy features that come with like containerized formats. Yeah
Yeah, the sandboxing is kind of a nice feature
Yeah, definitely and it's it's like when I when I first thought of application sandboxing
I thought about how Apple did it on the Mac and it's not like that. It's it's it's much better and it's it makes sense
It keeps especially especially if in business environments where you can have business applications that can take decades between updates
I just really like it
It's gonna make it's gonna make deploying applications that would sometimes be harder to deploy on newer versions of Linux
Possible in business environments. I ran into that myself personally where you had to load a really old version of Linux
Yeah, right to get an application to work and I think that's gonna start changing finally
So I guess it is I guess it is relevant to be talking about I was especially with all the like the you know
The security minded support and other ways to secure snaps like I can already think of multiple ways
We're like, okay. Well, I really need to run this Ubuntu 10 software. I don't trust it. It's really old
I can't change it but a snap is just like that would and then I can secure the 16 workstation or 17 with my standard tooling
Yeah, and we're using them to you know, we have a snap for the soundboard. There's a snap for discord. Yeah
It's happening. It's happening. Oh my gosh, you know, I think what it is is I'm just really pumped to talk about Ubuntu 1710
So I'm like, let's get through all the news. Let's get through the news so we can talk about 1710 because that's what I'm here to do today
That's right. Yeah, you're so giddy
It's literally why I came into work today. It's like I get to talk about seven first thing out of your out of your mouth
Bum too. Yeah, so let's let's clear the way you see what else we have
We have a couple other things but um, I'm gonna bump them. What?
Well, we're gonna bump them. I can't hold my breath much longer
DigitalOcean.com go over there create an account and then apply our promo code do unplugged
It's one word do unplugged gives you a $10 credit now you hang on to that $10 credit because buckle up
DigitalOcean is a simple way to get started with really fast systems in seconds
Everything's SSD from the $5 a month system to the ones that have unbelievable gigs of RAM
Yeah, gigs of RAM have a simple intuitive API if you like doing it that way
I know we do and they have a dashboard for days
It's it's if they had dashboard awards this thing would be an award winner. They should have dashboard awards
They really should. Oh my gosh, like can we can we do that?
Service provider dashboard awards. Screw the dashboard. Tell me about spaces. Oh
Beardsley the spaces. I wasn't sure what it was gonna be like I've been impressed with a lot of the features that
DigitalOcean has rolled out over the years. But you were a little skeptical. I just didn't think it was gonna be for me
You were like what am I gonna do with these objects? I didn't think it was gonna be for me. I really didn't
I thought okay great for you developers
Great for you
It's so great though for me because if you just want to use their did I mention their wonderful dashboard
If you just want to use their great dashboard, you can go in there and just drop some files in there generate a link and
Have it destroy within like say, I don't know a day and then give people a link and then it will download wherever they're at
At as fast as their freaking connection can take it. It is so great
I I had I was pulling down files at 10 megabytes a second and I'm like, all right
This is I know that's the max this connection amount is gonna be able to pull that down
They're ideal for storing static or unstructured data like audio and video
So if you're working on podcasts and you want to send the files around to your co-host, it's perfect for that
Images also text all that. It's it's it's really well done. And of course, it's all programmical like magical
What's the term for that? It's Dev a medical, you know with that API you could step a medical
You don't even have to use it. I think it's just good. Oh
But I want to make a new word
digital ocean comm use our promo code do unplug then you can spin up like their five dollar a month rig run it two
months for free and just try it out if you want to try out Linux on a server free BSD or play around with spaces
Digital ocean comm use our promo code do unplugged and a big. Thank you digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program
How's it going over there West?
Pretty good. So before we started the show West had to recover his bootloader. Yeah, it's actually I haven't bothered to fix it yet
I just I just K exact from my other installation because that's like just the easiest way for me to do things now
I don't know what the state of my life is like. I love it
so you nuked your bootloader trying out of into seventeen ten did and
Are you in seventeen ten? Yeah, of course
It's seventeen ten episode day Chris. Come on. I know and you use gnome right using no I sure am
Yeah, actually it it crashed on me while you were doing that ad read. So that's the theme of the day
Oh, no, no, no. No. Oh, no. Oh, no. I know I appreciate your support the hug here. It's great
Oh, I just well have you actually feel bad for me
But I so let's so let's talk about Ubuntu 1710 because this is a pretty remarkable release
Even if you're not an Ubuntu user and as you're listening to this
It's within hours of download if well if you're listening to this when this episodes released
It's within hours of release and download Ubuntu 1710. The ISOs are final. They're done. They're baked and
It is it's a notable release
For the obvious reason which is this is canonicals first released back on gnome
But I think it's also a notable release for another
major reason that we aren't talking about as much and that's the meta story around this release and that is the fact that this
is the first release after a
significantly dramatic restructuring at canonical that saw the layoff of hundreds of employees and
saw a complete refocusing of the company and
and during the midst of all of that this was being free software kept going and
I think that's a pretty that's a particularly remarkable achievement because I have seen that type of restructuring and thinning of the herd
Completely derail a company for years even even into oblivion
So some some companies never even make it through that so it's kind of remarkable that they also are shipping on time
With a product that well, we have we're very excited to talk about so
That's the meta story
I think around this release and then the other the other big meta story about this release was when mark announced all of these changes
and the grandfathering of or the sunsetting I guess of
unity 7
The screenshots that got passed around and the general sentiment that got passed around
Was it was going to be a basic bitch gnome implementation. It was going to be stock gnome and
And there was no there was no Ubuntu soul. There was no heart. They were getting out of that game
They weren't making a desktop anymore. I'm sure you'll have one but everybody everybody it was a skew is that everybody knows the screenshot
I'm thinking of with the green gnome background and the Edwardia gray theme
Default that was that was the image that went around on the stories everywhere and the character of Ubuntu was gone and
the of course the alternative would have been
or
They really muck this thing up and they make it like some crazy gnome fork
To make it like unity 7 so we don't want that either
so it seemed like there was two routes in front of us and neither one of them were any good and
And people assume that Ubuntu is out of the desktop game
Now here we are six months later and
This thing definitely has the soul of Ubuntu if you just look at the screenshots, you know, this is an Ubuntu system
And I have heard multiple different users now who sat down for the first time
Both of them that I'm thinking of actually
Or plasma users and and Beardsley over here. Yep. So when they said like though, this is unity. This is unity
It feels like it from the yeah
It's uh, it's pretty remarkable that they they got here and they did it in a way that didn't piss off upstream that
listened to the feedback of the community and as a result in a project that is
significantly different than any release we've seen from Ubuntu in ages
Significantly, we've never seen an Ubuntu release like this in in modern Ubuntu releases
It's a new era is what it feels like. It is definitely a new era and it's also right before their next major LTS. Yeah
So it's it is the release to work this stuff out because the next LTS has got to be pretty rock-solid
So it's it's it's a hell of a release to review and and sure enough if it's not the kind of thing that
legitimately gets me up in the morning makes me want a podcast because even if you're not an Ubuntu user there's a lot here to
Take in and to appreciate and so I wanted to start with you guys to just start talking about our impressions of Ubuntu 1710
I'm coming at it from somebody who's been watching the development very closely
From day one and so in in such I have lost a little bit of the wow. Look at this in its totality
Because I've sort of been there as each step has come along. Well, you've also literally traveled across the country to
Witness some of that development. Yeah, that's that yeah, there's that too
So I'll tell you I guess what I what I I would start with just to sort of kick it off is
The dock that they have decided to implement in this is where we need to start because this
This was the necessary piece if you remove this from this gnome setup. This doesn't really feel much like an Ubuntu setup
if you take especially if you change the background and
They did it in a very sort of a polite upstream way that seems to be working
well and having gone to the Ubuntu rally I
watched firsthand why it's sort of important that they own this piece of the desktop for themselves and
in the in the last post Ubuntu gnome shell and artful day 15 did rocks talks a little bit about the
Quick fix that they had in the rally around their dock
This simple sort sort of
Mild fork I think is going to be an area they can continue to work on and
Really kind of just be a small thing they add to their desktop that makes it stand out
Without having to really own this huge complex code base
and
it I think was such it's such a critical thing that they actually do own this piece themselves and
They have they've done that they've done that part right the other thing. I like as a gnome desktop user
Is I like that?
I'm finally able to install a version of Ubuntu and I get the most recent version of gnome gnome
3.2 6.1 is shipping in 1710 and this is not a
Luxury that Ubuntu users have had very often
Generally, you got to go to your fedoras or your arches your seusses for that
Yeah, right exactly or you were installing like something yourself from maybe some other PPA or weird repo
But you didn't it wasn't just there for you. Yeah. Yeah
And these things for me are like really ticking boxes for me. I like that. I like they're I like they're nice minimal dock implementation
Mm-hmm. I really unobtrusive. It's not in the way. Yeah. Yeah, so what do you thoughts?
I've talked a lot now West I got more to say but I want to give you a chance to jump in
What do you what do you thoughts? I'm enjoying it a lot. Honestly, if this is more than you expected
Yeah, kind of I mean, okay. So way back when unity was first introduced
I guess you could say I was one of the one of the fleeing masses that was like, I don't know about this
I'm gonna go it wasn't out of any like hatred or whatever. I'm I use unity at work
I have no problems with it. It turned out to be a pretty good, you know, window manager just display whatever desktop there we go
That's the one
But still it's been so it's been a long time since I felt
You know that the Ubuntu desktop was the desktop for me that like I was gonna put it on systems and use it and that it
Would be a workable day-to-day system like work has different constraints, right? But like on my personal machines
This feels like I'm not saying that I'm going to but this feels very close to like I could be excited about it
The combination of like really good snap support a modern kernel modern
Gnome a lot of this like features and things system D has really all that all those changes have really shaken out in Ubuntu
And sure, there's like differences
We were talking before the show about like, you know
I'm used to arch where everything's under user bin and that's not quite so on in in Ubuntu
So there are differences, but it's gotten so small that it's just super it's just a super usable setup for me
Hmm. I will be curious like at work
I have three monitors connected all by display port and unity handles it pretty darn well not perfect not perfect
But I'll be really curious to see like, you know, you did pretty well with multi monitor setup
So is how does gnome cope with that?
I'm not sure speaking of using in the work environment
one of the things I I use a lot when I'm working on my laptop during the day is
Bluetooth because I have a I have a Bose sound link or whatever
It's called and oh, yeah, pretty good sound and I I before Ubuntu 1710 before Ubuntu 1710
Every day every morning. I would have to delete the pairing and repair with my Bose what for audio to work?
Yeah, it would show up it would connect but pulse would never sound send sound to my bluetooth audio device
but if I delete and repair which is a
Fairly painless process then I could so I just made that part of my morning routine when I was getting down to work
But now with 1710 I have not had to do that Wow
So they the I know that they claim a thousand upstream fixes to Bluetooth or bluesy
It would if one of those thousands fixed the fix my problem. I'm very great
I will have to do some testing with that. Yeah, I encourage you to have more and more things or Bluetooth
And I've also had some anecdotal notes about better mouse pairing and things like that like accessory pairings
I've only been testing speakers myself, but because I've all I have I have it. I have another speaker
I had the same problem. It's called the 808 thump same exact problem
I was having with the bow
So I know it wasn't unique to the bows because I had the same issue with another Bluetooth speaker both of those work
Very very very happy about that because it's just it's just so nice that I just turn it on and now that becomes my default
Sound device and it's that's the way it feels like it's supposed to work along that same line
Well, I'm talking about my my work laptop. I
have a very sort of mixed results with battery life and
one of the things that they've done in this release of 1710 is they've spent time on actually getting GPU accelerated video playback to
Actually be GPU accelerated. What there's a lot of stuff that claimed to be GPU accelerated playback on Linux Chrome and
Odom Odom, I have a totem in my sorry and other there's anyways
There's some others that claim to maybe be hardware accelerated but weren't actually hardware accelerated
And so we're sucking a lot of extra CPU
Which was using up a lot of extra battery and so I'm hoping to start seeing battery life results
I don't really have a good base because the main machine I've been trying I went to on is the first OS
I've ever ran on that machine. It's the Libra
but
I'm hoping when I try out my other systems to see an improvement. They're just gonna work. Yeah that that stuff
I'm looking forward to what about you beard? What's been sort of your takeaways with 1710 so far?
Um, it just feels like unity to me
Yeah, pretty much it
It's just it doesn't really change at all in terms of you know, how I'd use it. So
Good, is that good or bad? Oh good. I didn't mind unity. Yeah. Yeah now I'll I'll tell you it's to me
It's it's it's the small stuff that's gonna make this really stand out that I think gonna make this stand out
above and beyond
the other
Ubuntu flavors as much respect and we're going to talk about the flavors at a moment as I have for the other flavors
There's some stuff in the in my opinion in Ubuntu. No proper or I guess now it's just Ubuntu proper
that
Are the kind of refinements that I deeply deeply appreciate and did rocks points out a couple of them here
They said with our trend he says with our transition to gnome shell
We're following more closely to gnome upstreams philosophies and we've dropped our header bar patches
And they did some of these patches to you optimize vertical space in the past
But it could that they the the downside was is it created a different class of issues
Action buttons are generally now on the top and they're pretty much not noticeable with that ambience and radiance themes that Ubuntu ships with
Now I'm stopping here for a moment because this is the type of problem that I see in
Just about every damn distribution out there with their default themes with maybe the exception of like elementary OS
It's this attention to detail where it doesn't really you know
The people don't really care that the buttons don't stand out and if you're watching the video version
I have a screenshot up where the save and cancel buttons
They're there, but your eyes aren't really drawn to them if like where West is that can you even tell where they're at from across the room
It's a little hard. Oh, that's that's the problem. I ran into earlier where I couldn't find the unlock. Yeah. Yeah, exactly
That's exactly that exact one. So they are introducing some some fixes
They've introduced some styling for the suggested action and the story behind where they got the green from is actually kind of worth going to read his blog for
And
They're there. They apply these subtleties
So here is they've applied a subtle a subtle change to the disabled button
So it's obviously disabled and a bold change to the suggested default action button. It draws your eyes immediately
But yeah, it makes it clear and easy to see it's something that if I put this in front of a non-computer user
they'd still understand where to click and this is done a hundred times over and over again throughout
This theme another example is they've just made small changes to the way the header bar looks when you maximize it
So that way the gradients don't conflict with the with the shell gradient. Thank you
I mean, it's it's minor stuff, but it flows better and it eases my brain
It's like it could it simmers my brain the F down and I stopped thinking about my desktop environment and I think more about
The work I'm doing I was having a conversation with West over lunch
And I said what's one of my problems I have with both plasma and mate is I end up thinking a lot about the desktop
Environment, I think about the fact that this icon is slightly smaller than the icon next to it
And I think about the fact that maybe the click targets are a little too small for close and maximize and minimize
I think about the fact that the fonts wrapping in the menu which makes the whole menu offset and all weird and
None of it really matters except for it steals about 10 to 20 percent of my brain
It's the micro distractions that you're constantly keep seen and constant micro abrasions and
These have been polished away in this theme that they have for gnome shell it'll edit at a level that
feels really professional
And that's something I'm really excited to sit down and just use such a solid implementation of gnome
And the best part is if you want to bail on any of this you can install
I think it's just gnome session you install gnome session, and you just log out and log in a gnome session
And it's a just a stock gnome install with no canonical tweaks, okay?
That's super simple and then theme it do whatever you want exactly just start from there
And you know load up no tweaking that's easy. Yeah, I think it's I think that's a good way to go and then last
but not least
Long-term one of the features. I'm also looking forward to and this is what I think is going to
This is what's going to change my my mind about where we use it they're integrating livepatch now into the GUI
So you can use for free the livepatch service
At the GUI level and I think that's gonna
That's gonna spur a lot of adoption and it makes me want to use it here on our studio equipment
So just for the GUI level you can I'm kind of I'm kind of liking the livepatch service
I've been sitting back and watching it and for a production system that I don't reboot often
But I want to stay secure because it's connected to broadcasting to the internet all the time
Yeah, it's great. It's great for that. Mm-hmm, and
We've been having we've been having we had a crash today in the middle of the show
We've actually had to cut the show and restart the show because no I'm crashed on us today and and I'm whole
Being that the 1710 implementation and I'm hoping that three dot two six dot one will be more reliable
And I'm hoping that with with a reliable
well manicured gnome shell
That's been really well thought out and really well implemented by Canonical
Plus livepatch so I can keep it secure and I am hoping that that will make a decent production environment
That'll be easily updatable to 1804 and then I can just stay at 1804 for a couple of years
Well, I let this stuff work itself out
That's kind of my plan right now can actually have like this is an LTS that works on the desktop
I can install it once. Mm-hmm. And for the next couple of years just small changes. I don't have to worry about it
Mm-hmm, and for the next couple of years just small changes. I don't have to reinstall. I might not even reboot
Yeah, that would be so beard when you get back from twitchcon that week when you get back
I think you and I because I'm gonna wait because I don't want to break it before you go
We should reload this both these systems with the boon to 1710 and just we'll report back in the show how that's gone
And we'll just give you guys an update on
On how putting the production went what we ran into what it was like to get OBS working and how the performance is compared to arch
And all that stuff
I'm sold in a big way on some of the work
They've done and I really am curious to see where this goes for 1804
Because if they just keep what they've got and don't screw it up 1804 is gonna be great
Because this is really great and I was looking and don't you think don't you know?
I definitely think don't you think this is yeah, I you and I were talking at lunch
Like this is one of the releases that's really actually got us both genuinely interested in years and actually maybe using a boon to on
the desktop again and
I was looking at some results that Joey got over OMG Ubuntu
almost
11,000 votes on this poll which is pretty good
and
Still 24% of people said they're not gonna upgrade huh no plans to upgrade now 61% say they do have plans
And these are OMG Ubuntu users, so these are like hardcore Ubuntu. Yeah, these are Ubuntu people
Yeah, and only I was surprised 24%
Because it's a good release
I guess maybe if you're worried about unity which is we're gonna that's why we're gonna talk about the flavors here in a moment
But anybody in the moment room want to jump in with their thoughts so far on the 1710 release or upgrading to 1710
Or anybody been trying it. I'd love to get if anybody's been trying to get your thoughts, too. I
Have been trying and it seems rock-solid
I even installed pretty much all of the desktop environments at once
No problems
I
Just decided well hey, let's go all out. Let's just go ahead and try it and
Yeah, it works perfectly fine. Nothing's crashing on me
I haven't I actually had you know you every now and then you get that crash bug popping up to report a bug
I haven't had that happen once the entire time. I've been using nice. Yeah, it has felt really solid to me, too
I have I have been really even impressed with the beta is being solid early on
I I sort of waited a little bit, and then I jumped in I really had I was pretty impressed, okay
So I also tried out mate. I've been trying out a bunch of budgie edition and in the past
I thought although not recently had tried out Katie neon
So I got I got some flavor discussion to me too if you if you will indulge me
Oh, please, and I know I'm sorry. I don't have any kabuntu stuff. I'm sorry. I have not tried out kabuntu stuff
That's on you audience you guys go go try that out come back next talk about it
I can talk about that. Have you okay? Yeah, how has kabuntu been have been anything noteworthy?
Extremely noteworthy they are kind of a release of plasma behind there on 5.10 as opposed to 5.11
Which just came out however 5.11 will be in the backports
Repository the PPA that they have so you can just go down and get that
But other than that
Man rock solid like I said, but it's saying about everything else good
This is going to be a bunch of new people coming to know I bet I've got a lot of new people
And then there's going to be some people that are mutiny we'll talk about that in a moment
But first let's talk about linux.ting.com go to linux.ting.com to support the show and get $25 in ting credit or
$25 in purchasing power
How about that off a device you can buy a devices from ting directly if you bring one will give you a service credit and they
Have a CDMA and a GSM network so it's a lot of devices pretty much works
Anywhere pretty much you might be able to just find a device that works with ting check out
Linux dot ting.com it's pay for what you use wireless your minutes your messages and your megabytes whatever you use
That's all you got to pay. We have to pay for what you use nope
You don't got to pay you know you know and you don't have to pay for what you might use
Which is how they actually get you which is really incredible
Imagine if you had to pay for things like in all the things like how much gas you might use
That's crazy. I mean crazy
You're doing a lot of things so like yeah, oh for sure like TV like health coverage. Yep. Yep. Yep insurance
Yeah, there's I know it's we hate all those I do
I really do yeah ting is doing way the way the mobile is like if they had to like
Everybody to start over like right now like everybody had to hit the reset button and everybody had to compete fairly
This is how the entire industry would work. Where's where's our king insurance?
I well
I think you know what they should come up with some sort of plan like that like like ting plan pay for what you use
Healthcare with so we need more people to go sign up for ting try them out. Yeah, get critical mass
Yeah, I'll be forced to ensure us it would it would take Canadians to say are already expanding into internet there you go
There you go. Anyways, get in now other than phones linux.ting.com go there. Try it out. No contracts
No determination fees. They got a great blog to lots of good stuff on the blog recently lots of good stuff Chris
I want that tank fiber so bad. Mmm, man, that would be a life-changer
Life we'd be launching the Jupiter broadcasting data centers. I tell you what
Oh, man, JB DC. Yeah, cooled cooled in oil
Mm-hmm. Yeah, the the the jb pain to service but oh, yeah
Yeah, but coke is a real good fry coconut oil cooled servers. That's right fiber connected
Anyways, get started by going to linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring the unplug
Linux dot ting calm Linux dot ting calm put that in your history bar and support the show
Remember how history bars used to be a big thing. Oh, man
All right. So let's start with the Internet's favorite. That would be a buntu matte
1710 and this is all this work. This I would say is the release for for unity refugees
People that aren't ready to go to know they like the HUD. They like comp is
They miss what wouldn't you used to be a bit?
Man, it did wimpy and team nail it
so the thing is most of us know but if you don't that they have going for them is they have this
mate tweak tool and you go in there and you choose the mutiny layout and
You know snap your fingers and next thing, you know, you've got essentially the unity desktop
But really like that like all the people I put my time. I showed them all the options most universally people have picked mutiny
Yep. Yep, same same same but you see what right you can see it right there
You see how that button is smaller than the Firefox button. Oh, yeah, huh?
Oh, man, and you see how this is a circle
but then that is two shirts that aren't a circle and then that's a square and
Then that one has like this extra thing that goes above the square and then these are different shaped squares. Yeah
Not gonna have that. Oh
What you're saying is can't do that wimpy should have gotten a Chris last consult. Yeah, I don't know
Maybe you will so I also want to give a tip of the hat to brisk
My favorite part of using mate was the brisk menu really good
I know it's a seems like a small thing but having a super fast launcher that gets my searches every time I type them and
Then I hit enter and it launches the app. I expected every damn time
Dad made me happy. I like that a lot that really so the the mate layout
Oh and then and then you guys know I just professed recently again
My love for comp is and the way it makes my windows look all this you get with Ubuntu mate
right now I
feel like
Ubuntu budgie and Ubuntu mate are the number one landing spots for unity refugees
Because Ubuntu budgie gives you sort of the advantages of the nice clean budgie desktop. They're also GTK
But you get that Ubuntu base
So I think those are two very competitive alternative flavors for the 1710 release and then you're gonna have your folks that are willing
To go to XFCE or willing to go to plasma if they're if they're gonna take an extra leap
But I think I would predict Ubuntu budgie and Ubuntu mate this release cycle will pick up the most converts
From the from core Ubuntu, but I think core Ubuntu is going to benefit from a lot of new people coming in to check out
What they're doing on gnome. I am I'm coming back. I'm coming back to Ubuntu
I'm I I have been I have been distro hopping for six seven months now and
It's been awful. I just hated it. I just don't like it. We installing things. No solid foundation
Okay, is this the system that has all of my stuff synced or is that the other system is this one have dropbox installed?
Is that one does this one have last pass?
You know all this crap software that I have to drag around with me now that is just awful to set up constantly over and over
again
It'd be nice to be past that. Yeah, I
Just I wanted it to be mounted
I really didn't install it if you if you ever need to I really wanted it to be because I you know
I I've I've been having known issues recently as we just talked about so I was ready to just be like screw the whole thing
Middle fingers up in the air. I'm out of here. Peace out. Thanks for all the fish so long
But then after going through the whole round of them
The one that compels me the most and it actually fires me up to use is this new Ubuntu proper?
It's just such a solid release. It's such a good implementation of it
Even if I don't stick with it
I've got to use it for a little while cuz I've just got to kick the tires on this this this
This kind of thing. It doesn't happen a lot in Linux anymore. No, not really
They've we've had very slow and steady progress releases for years now
Not that that's a bad thing. No, it isn't it's I just in fact, I figured okay, it's good
It's actually time for like we're just slowly gonna iterate and fix things
We could use a little more of that sometimes
so I didn't think of it badly but I
Think we've forgotten sort of what this feels like again to have a to have a company
Come along and make something where they ask us what we want
And then they actually listened when we said what we wanted and then when they went and had and made their own changes to it
They wouldn't they talked to the developers upstream. It's just weird, right? That's crazy. It doesn't happen very often
So I really enjoyed using it now
Are you gonna stick with it on any of your machines or what would it take to get you to switch away from arch?
No, because you got pretty good software availability. I sure do. Yeah. I mean, yeah, I very well might I'm doing more and more things
With a bunch of on other systems, especially like cloud servers, etc
And so it is I gotta say it is real nice to have just the one
Operating system going and it's gotten a lot easier to like one software availability is better
And it's pretty easy to run
These days with all the tooling a bunch who has like to run an arch user land or an arch container for other things that I might
Need or an arch VM. So there's a good possibility
It'll be on some of my systems at least for a while for me
If it's my work system the number one feature that they're really competing with when it comes to arch
It's not the AUR which I think is what everybody assumes it is
It's the fact that if I play my cards, right?
I never have to reload that system
That install of arch will last as long as that physical hardware lasts and that is so nice because when you move into a distro
Like that when you can get like a five or six year install going and it works good
Mm-hmm, and it's still good performance
Especially on a machine where you don't like, you know what you do with it. You just you get in you update it
Yeah, mostly doesn't break. Yeah, that's why I think if I was really gonna use a bunch you I might actually
Ironically be an LTS guy. Yeah
And I don't really cuz I haven't run Ubuntu on as my daily driver for so long
I don't really know what the upgrade
Success rate is like if I if I have a semi customized system with a few snaps
Maybe a couple of PPAs and a few theme modifications or whatever and then I upgrade that to an 1804
What tells me you're gonna find that out and it'll be the first time that you're doing it with gnome 3 on Ubuntu
Yep, so it's there's no guarantees
So I don't know. I can't sit here and say I'm gonna have a smooth upgrade 1804
I can hope for one I can expect for one, but I can't say it's gonna happen
But I'm gonna roll that dice and I'm gonna load my current systems with 1710
Assuming that I can get to 1804 one way or another right and if this is any sign 1804 will be that thing that you've wanted
We're like, okay. Well, I'm just gonna sit here for a while. Yeah. See you in four years
Bluetooth fixes alone GPU video accelerated fixes and
No, three two six one almost make it worth kicking the tires right there
then if you would like to get into like their live patch stuff and if you want to play with snap packages and
This is a really competitive distribution, but even if you're not into that stuff
There's a few things I'm gonna so this is the first review. We're gonna talk about this next week
I'm going to I don't know if this will work out
I meant to try to lock this down before the show
I'm going to invite will cook and some of his team to come on the show next week
Awesome host released to talk about it. That's great. Hopefully it'll work out
We talked about it a boon to rally, but I'm sure this is a busy time for him
And I did mean to try to confirm with him before the show, but we've been so giddy about the plane
We really were I forgot to so that that's that's my fault
But I want to follow up next week talk about putting in production a little bit
I want to talk about using a live patch service a little bit next week some of those things do some follow-up stuff
So I bet by then two more people hell have pulled down after the actual release and tried it out
So if you'd like to join us in the discord for trying out discord next week
You can do that come into discord and let us know your take on it
I'm hoping will and team will be in there with us discord Ubuntu 1710 release party next Tuesday
Yeah, sure. It's a little late, but better late than never mm-hmm. Hey, I can't believe I'm gonna be installing Ubuntu
That's awesome. I'm like I have one Ubuntu machine here in the studio run mumble right now, and that's it
I've been one meaning to reinstall it was gonna be arched on one of my like my main work
Non-portable machine at home. I think tonight. It's gonna be paved with Ubuntu. Oh
Mom, I'll give you guys last words on 1710 or on any of the flavors if anybody else has any thoughts, but otherwise
I'll leave it there, and I can't wait to see
1804 what about you beard any other closing thoughts on this?
Release I'm a bit trepidatious over the fact that you're gonna be loading these machines with the boot. Yeah considering West has already had a gnome crash
Yeah, that is the thing isn't it although it can't crash more probably, but maybe it could I'm thinking I'm gonna
These will be the last machines, so we'll do these next week, and then before then I'll do air master and
I will I will reload you're reloading everything. Yeah. Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah, I'm going all-in
I thought you'd keep like one machine anchored somewhere
Yeah, but I'm so hodgepodge right now. I've got solace, and I've got arch, and I've got Ubuntu
I've got all all the mixes and I've even got a pop machine in the mix
It's hard to keep that all in your head sometimes
I mean it's fine when you're on one system
But like when you rapidly switch you really kind of start feeling the cost and I just kind of want to settle down
Just want to get settled, so I'm I'm motivated to start wiping motivated to format West. It's just so much fun, too
I'll be here to
Comfort you when you come to cry on my shoulder, and I actually like the Ubuntu installer like I'm just not an anaconda fan
So this one, and I don't use I mean most of my installs are arch right so like I don't usually use a gooey installer
Yeah, but a bunch of want like it's really not too bad. I know it. It's easy
So it's just quick to get through yeah, it really is it's it's non-offensive. It's not like the most powerful
Right and but I usually just do all my partitioning beforehand, and I just bit basic stuff, too
Yeah, I didn't really I you did have a bootloader problem. I did and what was that about well
I'm not a hundred percent sure I might actually try it again and see if that same issue crops up
But I have multiple machines on here, and it's UEFI. Yeah, so I know so my systems are all you
Yeah, for some reason it did not it might have been a discrepancy between where arch did you mounted versus where?
Ubuntu mounts so you create a slash boot yeah, and you created it using extended for
Exa fast butter fence would you I reused my existing slash boot which was already?
If I and fat and set up which had my existing bootloader on it. Oh, okay. I'm tracking now
Yeah, that could have been what it was in the past
It's worked fine like okay
So do anaconda's credit like fedora installs just fine and just replaces my arch bootloader with you know the EFI
Executable that gets picked is that one instead I assume this will work, too
So I'll give it another shot because I normally it works pretty well
But this time it didn't so I'll be something I'll fix after the show yeah
I I had I had one system where I almost accidentally installed my bootloader on the thumb drive
Because you know with MV&E drives, and I'm so used to watching for Dev SDA as my first drive
Oh, yeah, but in this case the thumb drive was Dev SDA, and I for a moment
Almost clicked the wrong drive in the installer and it took a moment go no Chris. Don't don't do that
That would be a very embarrassing mistake. Don't make that mistake and so I
I almost did it, but I caught there well the good thing about installing it on a thumb drive
Is you make that mistake you just take the drive and throw it away. That's true. Nobody ever knows that's true
Yeah, except for I almost would have just outed myself here on this podcast
So that would have been that would have been good enough all right well
I would love to hear your experience with the new release, and I'm pretty excited about it as I said
I think it represents just an incredible amount of work
and in a way
Better than I expected it to be too. Yeah, and it just feels
I don't know. I don't know like I feel like we've had a hard time explaining it
It just feels good to be this excited about in a bunch of release again. Yeah
I think that is like a coming home kind of feeling I
Think it's just nice. They didn't blow it
I think it's really nice that they figured out how to work upstream in the right way
It's it's a bit too soon to say they didn't blow give them time. Yeah, maybe I haven't had a unless something sneaks its way in
I haven't really had any any show-stopping issues yet. I have had any gnome crashes either with it
But then again, I've only been primarily using it on Intel. Are you on Intel hardware to them? I sure am hmm
When you have a optimist system at home hybrid graphics, so I'll be trying that yeah
This is gonna be when we loaded on the production systems here. This will be in video
This would be yeah, maybe maybe that'll be a different bottle of wax
I guess I guess that also means I guess that also means I've been using Wayland now for weeks, and I didn't even really
You to get you two bastards are using Wayland right now, too. Yeah
Don't don't let our secrets out. Holy crap you guys
We don't get these this pixel perfect frame rate just by accident. We're all a bunch of Wayland users now
Oh my goodness that I didn't see coming. There is your big development right there
Wow
well
I'm looking forward to kicking the tires some more reformatting my machines losing a bit more data
I kid do your backups kids do your backups go put it all up on the cloud somewhere where somebody can index it real
Good for you. You know what we didn't even mention what ZFS support still continues to be rockin on a bunch
You so yeah, I thought about it, but I have to install ZFS a little more
I want more backups there. Give me more. Okay. Give me more ZFS integration. Where's my ZFS gooey, right? Yeah, okay, right?
I want a paperclip wizard, etc. All right. Thank you for being here guys
Join us live next week over to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar for our lifetime
JBLive.tv is where you watch it and go to linuxunplug.reddit.com to thanks for being here
You
Know the more I think about it. It seems obvious like on our production system. I'm gonna use X
That's I'm not gonna use Wayland on the OBS system. That's probably why you crashed
Maybe it might be what's up. That might be it. So I guess I should go look at some logs
Do you have your titles calm? Thank you mumble room. Yeah guys here. Yeah. See you later. I gotta get my son. All right. All righty
How did how did an episode I've been looking forward to for doing for six months end up being short and low-energy
How did that how did that combination happen? It's because we didn't start the caffeine till a Chris you think
Maybe I don't think so
I'm surprised you didn't have Martin or Alan here. I
Had a sense. They weren't gonna be here today, although I don't remember why
I
Forget I like get finished ready and up for this release man. No, I have no idea
Yeah, cool for us, but it's kind of good, you know, so that way we can you know, this is our take unbiased. Yeah, no influence