Oh
My gosh you guys
You know, I'll tell you Noah. I had to have a talk with myself after your ThinkPad review and last that was a
Legitimately tempting review like after the things that the the the main things that really sold me was the problem-free
Built-in LTE modem and
The
Temporary battery so you could swap you could swap batteries. I'm big on that
I'm big on battery swap and I was I was king of battery one of the one of my favorite laptops of all time was
The Apple Pismo and it was like when Steve Jobs was gone and every bay was modular and compatible with each other
So DVD bays could also be battery bays
So you could have two batteries or two DVDs or a hard drive and a battery and I love that man
Cuz I get eight nine hours of battery life, you know
I don't want to make you I don't want to make you I don't want to make you too jealous
But Chris, do you know what my latest thing is on the ThinkPad what have you heard of the battery slice the what?
The battery slice is a battery literally the footprint of the laptop itself
Oh, and it goes underneath it kind of right underneath and that's not even new that's been around for a little bit
Actually, I've never I've not had one before and I had I had I had a 10-hour flight to Tokyo
I had a five-hour flight to Seattle. I had a one-hour flight to Minneapolis
I had two hours in the airport there at 200 in the airport in Tokyo and
I had my laptop powered on pretty much the whole time. Yeah, it went almost 24 hours
So this actually goes like in the docking port, right?
Yes, the battery slice attaches to so you have your extended battery plus you now have this battery which goes in your docking port, right?
It's crazy. Yeah, they've had that for a while. That's super cool
I used to I used to have one between all the batteries because of that power dock or they
Yeah, what do they call the power center at the yeah, you know, you know too bad. I really really really don't like Lenovo as a company
This is Linux unplugged episode
151 for June 28
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's ready to go on vacation and is trusting the post-production
Process my name is Chris. My name is Noah. Hello there Noah. Thank you for joining me this week
You're actually back. You made it back from Tokyo. It wasn't it wasn't without a vent
Well, I'm glad you could make it because we have a great show today coming up a Linux mint 18 is just hitting the interwebs
I'll give you my quick take on that
I've got it installed on a machine and I kick the tires and then later on is desktop Linux almost dead
I don't mean actually like Linux on the desktop
I mean desktop computers in general now with these massive machines that are desktop replacements devices like the NUC and of course the penetration of
Mobile, you gotta wonder is there really a role for the truck anymore?
At least let's zoom out like 10 years and talk about the future of Linux on the desktop
Especially in light of some recent new hardware releases
Plus we've got great updates from the Red Hat summit from the Docker group
There could be in a new a new Ubuntu phone and develop
What and much much more so Noah I am
Super looking forward to Linux unplugged 151 because 152 will not contain any Chris
So this is my last episode before I go on vacation
You'll sit down in the center seat at the helm and command the ship and your time. I couldn't I can't even believe you're here
I can't even believe you're here because I figured you're coming back from Tokyo. You're a busy guy
You got a lot of stuff to cover. I didn't catch up on
1159 at night when there's no flights to Grand Forks
So you end up spending a good amount of time in Seattle
it sounds like I ended up spending from 8 in the morning until like
650 in the Seattle Airport and I was to the point where I thought I was going to inadvertently be doing Linux unplugged in studio
And then and then I made a last last ditch effort flight and and got back to Minneapolis at midnight
And then rented a car and drove for four and a half hours back. Oh, no
I had a client that I had to take care of this morning and so I was I really I was expecting to be back on
Saturday and that didn't work out and then I was hoping to get back on Sunday and that didn't work out and so ended up
Being Monday very very very late man. It's always down to the wire, isn't it? Isn't it funny how that happens?
Better that way. It's true. That's true. I have this, you know, I'm my road trip. I'm coming. I'm going to Montana
I'm gonna do some soaking. I'm bringing Dylan with me. It's his first road trip. He's seven years old, you know
It's it's it's summer break between first grade and second grade for him
So this is like a big deal trip. This is like this is like the stakes are high
This is his first impression to road trips
So we really trying to make sure we just stock it full of fun stuff for him to do
So we're gonna stop along the way we're gonna be like the Lewis and Clark caverns
We're gonna go to water parks and all we basically have activities planned every single day
But as of right now, I still don't even have lady dupes back in my possession
Jeez, man, I know I am it is down to the wire. No, you are you're cutting it
Down to the wire. I'm really glad that you give yourself
Well that that that the circumstances have turned out so that you have so much leeway when something goes wrong
So so here's what I've learned. It's like owning a boat
I think I own an RV is like owning a boat where every time you kind of take it out on a major voyage
stuff breaks and
that's why you own RVs that have warranties that cover everything and
to their credit, you know, I
Everything has been covered for totally absolutely for free
The only problem is the delay as you authorize parts and you wait for that and that kind of thing
So, right, I don't even think this road trip is gonna be possible except for we've gotten great customer service by one individual
I'm gonna give him a shout out right here to Jeff. He's down at sunset RV
Now they have it
They have a main five location where we bought our rig but at a Buckley is where their maintenance divisions run and Jeff like
He's been calling up Thor and verifying. Are you authorizing this? Where's this at?
Can you put rush shipping on these parts and then he's gonna drive it up to our campsite as soon as it's ready to go
So that way we can start loading it up and pack it up
So we don't have to do that whole drive my truck down there jump in the rig and hit the road thing
We can actually pack it up at our at our regular site
so he's gonna drive it up there when as soon as they get done working on it, even that's Thursday night Friday night something like
that and I told him a few if he can bring it up there, I'll take him out for a beer
I leave Saturday morning. I leave Saturday morning. So it's like yeah. Oh
And then at some point you'll be hearing a lot more from Noah because he'll be sitting in in the seat right here
So let's jump into some of the stories. We have to get into this week
We got a lot of project updates a lot
And so without going too far without getting to them
I think we should probably bring in our virtual lug time appropriate greetings mama room. Hey pep
I'm okay. Hello. Hello. Hello. Well, hello. Hi there, you know, I wanted to talk about something
Right at the top of the show because mr. Drum edrum or perhaps you might know mishawn in the mumble room has worked on
Yeah, what I'm known
he worked on something special for me as a gift for last his 10th birthday and
It was a nice totally set up. We'll talk more about why it's super super cool
A setup installation of matter most for the Jupiter broadcasting community now we've talked about matter most in the past. That's that open-source
Alternative to slack always rocket chat. That's another one and this week
I wanted to highlight an article over at open source comm because I really ragged on them last week
So I thought it'd only be fair to highlight when they do something pretty cool to actually give them some credit. So I
Don't know if you had a chance to listen to last week's episode, but I I kind of called him out for a few things
and this week though, I thought they had a great post up here by Adam Hyde on
Open-source software needing to sell the user experience and I think a lot of us that listen to the show or participate in our virtual
Lug agree that user experience is a super important part of the end result and he talks about how matter most is doing open source
The right way about how they're creating a compelling project something that definitely competes with slack takes advantage of its open source heritage
Uses that to build into features have things like code highlighting and snippets that are way better than anything slack can do
while also providing a great interface and
So it was sort of I thought a great opportunity with this article just posted full link in the show notes if you guys want
To read it. Maybe we talked to Sean and and get his sort of back-end take on
matter most what it was like to set it up for something that could potentially be used at large scale and
Just sort of his overall thoughts on it. So Sean first of all, thanks for the 10th anniversary gift of saying that matter most
We had a cool opportunity to use it during our fedora review
We had a back channel thread going during last worked out super well
I kind of just want to hear your thoughts on setting up matter most for a production deployment and what you think of it as a
software technology
Yeah, it's really I think it's really it's really runs really well
During the floor of you everyone was John there the load on the server
Cp load was like point zero five. Yeah, it was seems like it was like 200 megabytes and it just just purrs like a kitten
Set up wise back when you did the rock the matter most and rocket chat review
I is when I started working on this and I actually created a script for digital ocean to put in the user data
field and so
You just paste paste that in there?
Set the variables for your configuration and
Let it rip. No, it goes through and it takes care of setting up the firewall setting up your admin user and generates
all new salts all passwords
sets up
The whole stack
And it also does sets up let's encrypt
So if you already have your a record cool, you can just set that up right during the install if not there are two
two admin scripts in the admin users home directory and
At that point you can just run one won't install a self sign cert and the other one will set up let's encrypt
And it'll also create a cron job. So auto renew. So what would you say once all this is set up?
Sorry, then you can go I just thought I just want to know for people that are that are listening right now that maybe
You have an open source project
They're involved in total commit time to getting matter most at a decent matter most installation at that set up
Total commit time. What would you say it is?
if you use my script
Three to five minutes. Can you link that to me in the IRC so I can put in the show notes and go ahead?
No, yeah, and to be clear when he says a script
He doesn't mean like you have to set digital ocean up and then log into the droplet and then run a script
That's not what he's talking about. He actually custom designed the script so that it can be dropped in
In the digital ocean control panel and then spun up. That is awesome
Yeah, and I wasn't even aware of that feature digital ocean and during Linux fest Northwest like two months ago
We were in the hotel lobby at like three. Why is it that the meeting time of the hotel lobby is like three in the morning?
Either you're there to pick up hookers or you're talking about Linux. That's
That's true. That's true. Well, there were no hookers and blow that night
So we were working on
We were working on our laptops and he was showing me how he could literally drop this script in you change like what?
Sean sevens variables and then you click on the button. There's
mostly you need to change variables, but there's like
30 other variables you can change if you want to really set it up and not have to do any configuration or if you want
to keep the configuration that you already have and set it up on a
Second droplet is like a failover or if you want to test something you can use the same configuration for both
You know, here's why Sean I think this is kind of an important thing and I'd I actually wouldn't mind just sort of double downing
on the double downing that sounds like a sandwich on this because
one of the things that
One of the reasons why Jupiter broadcasting
Accidentally started using slack
Was because it took me 35 seconds to try it and then I was like, oh
Well, we could actually use this and so this is basically the way the way the decision tree works for me
Is is this going to be a critical piece of technology to the operate to the successful operation of my business if it is
I would like to own it control it deploy it. However, if
Owning controlling and deploy it takes way more time than I have to dedicate to it. Then I will never do it
I will never get it done
So then I might as well just go use the hosted solution that seems to be from a reputable company
It's gonna be around for a while because at least then I'm using something versus not using anything at all
So by creating a script that makes it super fast and easy to deploy matter most you're you're you're making it much more competitive
I think with slack Sean. What was the first thing? I told you when you first telegram me and said
Why aren't you guys using matter most?
Because Chris would have to set it up
Did I say Chris's decision is based off of
Path of leaf is resistant Greece the least resistance
Damn it. You make me sound like a bastard. No, it's not
Oh, no, I just make it sound like like a person who has a lot of really important things to do and so
Delving in to to the specifics of setting up a server on a relatively new software platform is not really something you have the time
Or energy to tackle
Be willing to use it especially when you're not sure how much value it's actually gonna return to you
So, you know, you're not really willing to commit a half a day to something if it's maybe something nobody uses
Right because who would think that setting up something that's basically IRC would actually be useful. Why not just use IRC
I mean, that's that was my default thinking about it. And that was my my essential
Bias that I had my old man bias coming in until I actually tried it. So I don't know
Mr. Drum anything else you want to touch on on matter most before we move on? I
Don't think so then they're working on a federated system so you can have multiple matter most connect to each other. That's cool
That will be very nice. That will be very very nice. That's always something. I'm a big fan of
Speaking of fans. I I there is something going on over at system 76
They have a it's only going on for a little bit too
But they're lowering prices with that with with retweets of the or tweets of the hashtag
Ubuntu 76 for two days up to 350 dollars off and I I'm not saying I have inside knowledge
I'm just saying I have inside knowledge. That's all I'm saying and you have a little inside knowledge to know
There is someone in the works here. I'm just saying it's in your benefit to get in on this
Just put that out there. So if you check them out twitter.com slash system 76
they're tweeting about it right now the key is to tweet with hashtag Ubuntu 76 and
There's something they've been working for quite a while on really hard and they're super super excited about I've been getting telegrams
I mean, I shouldn't say this
unidentified sources
Have been informing me about what could be in the works and I'm just saying I'm pretty excited about it
So I've been retweeting and you guys should too because it'll be worth it
All right, speaking of what might be worth it. This might be worth buying
This could be my next and finally I might add the first Ubuntu phone I buy
It's called Midori and no it's not a GTK web browser based on web kit that you wish you could use but just doesn't have
Enough features it could be the next Ubuntu phone
That's at least according from reader Richard s over at OMG Ubuntu who pointed OMG Ubuntu to bug
155 1811
Obviously, I know what you're all thinking. It's right there in the name
This obviously points to a new Ubuntu phone actually the bug mentions a device code named Midori
With regards to a trust prompt issue that causes a reboot on the MX4 and a mystery new handset later on in the bug report
Director of engineering over at canonical who says the block says this will block Midori RC. Of course RC
Being a release candidate channel for Ubuntu touch images a quick googling around shows the Midori would be in keeping with the code names
for previous Ubuntu devices because they're based for some reason on
on Dragon Ball franchise references
So you have a couple other bits of evidence to there's some discussion in IRC channel about working on a fairly large change
Interesting could you define the term OFONO for me? What is that? What is OFONO?
Ofono, it's the radio stack that we use for doing like
It's what it's part of the radio stack, you know, think of it like network manager and all that stuff
So they they're working on a fairly large OFONO change at the moment for a new handsets as an IRC
We're expecting to land and land a new version of OFONO soon. Oh
What could it be a new device is expected all of a sudden code name Midori
hmm Noah
Noah I think where there is fire and there is smoke. There is an Ubuntu phone. What do you think? I
think you might be onto something the
Every time I see the Ubuntu phone in person I am I tell myself I'm like, this is perfect. I want this
Did you know action itself? Did you yeah. Well, so Michael Hall that's his exclusive phone, right?
So that like and we took him they so canonical ship them a computer for their demo
But they may or may not have forgotten the euro cord that goes in the back of it. You're old card, dude
really power cord partner so they we had to go to a store to go get a power cord and
We and so we're I was in the car and I was I was talking with him and I was like man
You really use that all the time. He's like, yeah, it's you know, it's a great experience. You're like, let's be clear
You're like no, you're in the car with Michael Hall driving to a collection store. You're like, holy crap
You're you're not shitting me. You actually use Ubuntu touch. That's your reaction. You actually are using that thing
You didn't pull out an Android device when we go to find electronic store. That was your reaction
So I just to me I just have a problem and I think you're in the same boat of like using
The same using a phone that doesn't have the the available apps
But you know and they have the necessary ones right they have like a terminal in an email client and telegram and stuff like telegram
And telegram but um, but you know, there's a couple things that are missing
And so I guess I was a little surprised that that was his exclusive phone
But it seems with a couple of exceptions seems to work very very way
Are you saying that there wasn't a maps program on the phone there? Well, yeah, you know, so he doesn't have GPS
So I was doing oh, oh the phone doesn't have GPS. Well, I think the phone does it it does
He happened about he happened to have a broken one. Oh, that's that's a bit of a bummer
So so so in any case so there were there's like there's like little pitfalls the thing though when I get back though is I
Just have such a hard time to actually make the leap like when I'm sitting here and I'm using my s6
And I'm not a huge Android family. I don't particularly like Android
I just don't know that I dislike it enough to go to a completely different
Hmm a completely different system and it's I was looking through you know
Like even small things like, you know, we switched over to OS ticket for all to speed now
I'm not gonna have an app for that and I use that daily, you know to upgrade update work orders and get push notifications
When new ones come in and and all that dare Devon, what do you fall down on this particular issue?
For me, I think it will happen and the transition in the same way transition happened for me in Windows like windows
Yeah, that's when I transition from Windows to full-time Linux
I was like this decision of like I'm not gonna care just gonna deal with all the circumstances that show up as they show up
Because I believe in it. So I want to see where it goes and be supportive. Well, that's usually no one's line. I
Did that and I don't regret it and in the phone
I think it will happen that I've been saying that I'd like a convergence thing
But you know, I think when I do the jumping will be something like that
I'll just drop my phone and say whatever if it's not there. I'll work on getting it there
You know what? I think I need I guess what I need is I need a me in the mobile space
I need somebody to come along walk alongside me and and solve my problems so that I'm not so and and hold my hand
So I'm not scared. That's what I need. Hmm
poppy how how
realistic would it be for someone like me to assume that this might be an
Image for a device that already exists versus a brand new device
So this was reported on OMG Ubuntu, I think there was a photo of the device as well
There's been a couple of photos
I've seen a couple of myself. Yes. Yeah, one of them was a bit pixelated and the other one
I think is a bit clearer
But they show convergence in full effect and they show it docked to like in one case it shows a docked in there and you
See that you see the unity 8 session up on the screen
But when you mentioned the image, it's pretty much the same image on every device
So when you know some new features enable it's enabled for everyone unless it's like hardware specific like a fingerprint reader or something
Then it you know, everyone gets it
So if there's new software which fixes bugs in network manager or something that fixes bugs in the radio or GPS
Then everyone gets the fixes on all the devices. You want to do you want to playstation 4 poppy?
No, I'm
PC gamer PC master races. I just wonder because I just saw this leaked photo with the ps4 and I just wonder where it came from
That's that's you know when you're compiling something
I think that's that's a you know, when you're compiling stuff you like turn to the screen next to you
I really I find it to be exciting that
There's a possibility that there's such a new there's a new device already because I feel like we just got the pro
The muaz or whatever you say it pro, which was a brand new would seem like a really nice high-end phone
Meizu, thank you. Yep. And so here we are just
It feels like Mobile World Congress was just a couple of weeks ago
And we already are hearing possibly rumors about a new phone plus last week. We talked about the one plus three
Getting a community around it to get a bunch of touch running on that which is an extremely well-reviewed phone
So perhaps it is finally
Happening as the Ron Paul meme says speaking of mobile. Let's talk about ting. That's right. That's right
Go to linux.com and learn more about ting ting is a mobile service provider my mobile service provider
No is mobile service provider. It's just mobile that makes sense. It's only pay for what you use mobile with no contract
$6 for the phone line and then just your usage on top of that. It's super straightforward
Super super crazy simple no gimmicks. No like on Tuesdays
You're gonna get this and over the weekends you can do this and if you don't use this well rolled into this but only for this
Amount of time like it's ridiculous or you want to you want to do hotspot or tethering you have to call in and enable that
Like that kind of stuff is the 90s. It's done. It's over with and what's nice about ting
Is they have two networks to pick from CDMA and GSM and all the devices are unlocked
So if you're like crazy Noah, and you're traveling to Tokyo
You can take your everyday driver phone and just pop a new sim in there. It's no big deal
Or like sometimes, you know like needles Noah and I will swap phones because we're not hardcore junkies
We're hardcore phone nerds and we swap phones and it's just pop the sim and pop the sim out
It's true. Like we and and legitimately the when Noah travels to the jb1 studios
He usually brings a tink sim with him true or not Noah. You know, I travel I travel everywhere with one
And I actually I made this guide actually
How to I'll have to get it to you I I stole it from from the the the ting website
But I went through and I started identifying different like ideal phone specifications and which models
So nice. Yeah specific which models you can buy so that when people ask they say I want the XYZ
I can say well
This is the specific model for that phone that you want right that would work with with ting or whatever in that
That that's been really neat because if you buy one that has all of the the I think there are
Five bands that you're looking for for LT if you buy one of those phones with five with all five bands
It will work not only on ting but again if you're roaming abroad into Europe or in Japan
So I just you know and you can buy a prepaid sim in almost any country stick it in and then you have a local number
Yeah, like a local. Yeah, and you know
It's getting way more common to have all of the bands just built into the phones, especially the most recent phones
That's just sort of what the chipset brings now. So that's making it easier
But so ting has a CDMA and GSM network and so we're like with the Nexus devices
You can have either or it depends on your phone and what its capabilities are
But if you understand that there's a thing called GSM and there's a thing called CDMA
You're pretty much good to go ting is gonna really help you out
They have great customer service so you get to speak to a human being they have a dashboard that makes managing all of this crazy
Easy, they have a store online where you can get things from feature phones. I started like 60 50 bucks
Just I mean imagine that you need a backup line
We can just make phone calls and you only pay for when you use it get a $50 feature phone and put it
You know just put it on ting or go all the way up and get yourself a full-fledged computing device
That's unlocked and you own it outright. I
Personally as much as I can I am advocating for the Nexus ting combo or iPhone ting combo. I think
having been back on Android for a few weeks now since Linux fest and
And sort of now getting an appreciation for those monthly updates from Google it makes Android to me a much more palatable
much more secure much more like feels
Much more in line with my priorities from my room a really important computing device
You know something that's getting security updates directly from the vendor and ting never gets in the way of that process
They don't have an agenda. They don't have to like brand the update before it gets out there
So when you get a Nexus device from the Play Store and you bring it over to ting a couple of really amazing things happen
First of all when you go to Linux not ting comm your first month is gonna probably be paid for
Because average ting bills like 23 24 bucks for a line
So you go to Linux not ting comm you get your first month paid for you bring the device on there you pick GSM or CDMA
What's ever stronger in your area because the Nexus devices are doing all of it once you get it online put it on Wi-Fi
Get all your updates get all your applications installed and then just sit back and enjoy the savings
It's it's such a great combination
Even if you're from outside the US and you're just visiting the states for a little while
Bring go go on eBay get a cheap GSM phone put it on the ting network and that travel account
They're traveling from the outside outside the US a lot of phones abroad have two SIM slots. Yeah, I know
Yeah, just bring a phone. There's
It and it's so simple because at the end of the day you have the safety net of the ting support where they're actual geeks
That love this stuff and they're willing to engage with you
So you actually have really great support to go to check them out at Linux not ting comm
Also, if you want to just support the show by visiting that page go read their blog
They got a new post on a hundred and thirty over-the-air TV stations coming to us cord cutters
I have not had a chance yet to read this
But man does that sound like music to my ears as someone who's probably not gonna be getting cable and it may be
Satellite during the election of things get crazy, but I just for right now
I'm trying to do everything over-the-air in lady tubes and that's a blog post. I'm gonna read so go to linux.ting.com
Calm. Hey Noah, how about we get super geeky for a second on the show you ready for this? That's great
I love getting super geeky in the air. I know you like yourself a VPN and that secure networking
So this is what I am looking forward to it hasn't hit mainline kernel yet
But say goodbye soon to open VPN say goodbye to IPSec and say hello to the next generation secure network tunnel
announced for Linux
Jason Donfield is the
Developer and it's called wire guard. It's described as a next-generation secure network tunnel for the Linux kernel
It's built into kernel space unlike open VPN which runs in user space and inherently when you're dealing with all this crypto stuff and networking
Stuff we're running in user space and then communicating with the kernel kernel. There's just it's just an inherent disadvantage there
So Dunfield explained to a briefing to for Onyx last week about wire guard
He says IPSec is overly complex and impossible to actually use in a secure manner
But it's the fastest thing out there for a VPN and secure tunneling open VPN very popular
But it's super slow and by virtue of being in user space. It contains a whole buggy SSL x59 x509 stack
He says I've started from scratch and written an extremely simple yet powerful
Cryptographically secure replacement in around 4,000 lines of code called wire guard
It's much simpler than anything before it with peers exchanging short curve 25 519 public keys
Just like an SSH secure network interfaces can be added and removed
using the usual IP link and IP address tools and
From there. Everything is easily taken care of by the kernel and secure tunnels are made quite simple
Not only that but the performance is in fact better than IPSec which is basically a huge accomplishment
Now this isn't brand new. He's been working on this for a while
It's been detailed at some kernel conferences. So it's not like it just showed up out of nowhere
It's using industry standard cryptographic standards and they have a brand new website at a wire guard dot IO
Which they say there it aims to be an easy to configure and deploy as as SSH is
but gives you a VPN connection made simply by exchanging very simple public keys just like exchanging SSH keys and
All of its transparently handled by wire guard
Roaming between IP addresses just like mosh is also supported. There's no need to manage connections be concerned about state
Manage daemons or worry about what's under the hood?
very basic but powerful interface
This is a whole new way for doing secure networking under Linux. It's not a mainline kernel yet
But man does this look super promising. No, I'll start with you. What are your thoughts about kind of just sort of
Wiping the slate clean and starting over with VPN technologies under Linux
So anyone who's worked especially in the commercial side of VPN knows what a pain it is to get some stuff set up correctly
but
Part of me says that like the last one I did which is just a couple of months ago
It was literally as simple as I log to the routers are supporting it. Now. I logged into the router. I checked a box
I specified the the DHCP leased space that I wanted the VPN clients to log in with I created credentials and I was done and
That is thanks to the fact that that open VPN is just like
Natively supported on like every major, you know device now
So on some level I feel like we have already gotten, you know a long ways and we've made a lot of headway and
And things are actually pretty good now, though
I do respect and understand the concept of you know
It may not be as secure as it could be and I got to tell you Chris
Having fought with VPN for almost 10 years in various different forms if we could get to a point where it was as simple as
SSH or I can install one package on the on the destination, you know server side one package on the client side, man
That's appealing. Yeah. Yeah, I totally agree and you know, I started picturing like
just
essentially
Using these types of links and connections as standard by default
Here's the there is one
Major issue the internet is taking with this new technology and I wonder if anyone in the mumble room feels this way
One of the big pushbacks coming in right now. Well, there's two
but the big first one I want to talk about is
What about putting something that is network accessible
That is essentially a core networking technology like this in kernel space because if there is an exploit against this thing
You've just owned the entire kernel. You're now running your exploit now runs with kernel level privileges. You're in
Doesn't anybody in the mumble room have any concerns about this? I?
Thought for sure somebody would I thought for sure somebody would because that is genuinely I think a legitimate concern
The other I think number two issue and the open VPN developers have already raised this one is
Why not just spend this time making over open VPN faster? Why can't we why can't we risk?
Take all this energy you guys have and put it in open VPN. What do you think about that? No, I don't think so
Yeah, I think that open. So the the the the the thing about
Starting over right is it I think to some degree it suffers from the not invented here syndrome
I think it's it's it's you know, you get these people that say well I could do this better
I could restart from scratch and I think that then you essentially
We're reinventing the wheel on some level on the other hand though
Every time I've seen this happen in the past where you take a technology
You look look at system D for example, and I know there's probably a sore subject to bring up but you look at system D
And look at what has happened and we have taken taken something and completely redone it from scratch and
Everyone kind of said the same thing is oh you're reinventing the wheel
There's no reason to do this and I got to tell you we have gone from you know, minutes
Minutes of boot time to seconds and if you and if you don't if you're not working in a field where you see that
Then maybe it's not as clear to you. But to me it's there there is there is there should be no discussion about this
It was a it was a it's a clear win might have been a little quick on the draw
But it is definitely the direction we should be moving. And so if if a new VPN
You know protocol system
integrated at the kernel level if we have that same kind of success and that same kind of cleanliness and that same kind of
You know increase in performance and security. I'm all for it. Okay. Well, here's his arguments
He says, you know, you just can't get the performance in user land applications. It's not that we don't want to support open a VPN
It's that open VPN from a performance standpoint is just sort of doomed
And he said the developer the other thing about wire guard is this why it's 4,000 lines of code. It's insanely simple
It's meant to be the the smallest attack surface as possible. I was on the fence about this until I read
Greg KH's post on Google+. Now. He's not a
Networking developer, right? He you know, he focuses on the Linux kernel
He were focuses on the LTS branch and on the USB stack and lots of important subsystems the networking subsystem
Not one of them, but he writes a new VPN VPN protocol and implementation for Linux
It was announced last year at the kernel recipes in Paris. It's great to see a
Releasable state at this point. I recommend taking a look at it. If you're into this type of stuff disclosure
I have reviewed various versions of the kernel code over the past few months and
It seems safe. So I'm not going to go into that
And it seems sane, but he says note. I'm not a kernel networking developer
So Greg says, you know what? It looks like good sane kernel code to me, which is pretty encouraging
I mean, I I definitely can't disagree with his opinion on the topic. So I just have one thing
It's a network thing
It's about doing this type of but it's in the kernel level when we have to understand what it actually means
Being the kernel level also means that a potential flaw on it. Yeah, ten times higher to danger
It's an immediate serious issue. It's an amoeba. It's especially if it's remotely exploitable
Exactly exactly and not only that
It's also something that if it's buggy for some reason crashes the entire system too because it's in the kernel. Yeah. Yep
Yeah, so those things should be in mind. Yes, you're not gonna get the performance in the user space
But I think it's a good trade-off. Maybe the performance for the security layer. Yeah, I don't know maybe yeah, yeah
I
Think I pretty much agree with your assessment. Okay. All right. Well
We have great news today on the unplugged program finally
after years of waiting Linux users our
prayers have been answered
Universal application installation is now available
Thanks to a brand new standard called sub user
That's right offering portability security and maintainability for a user application installations on Linux
We have ourselves a brand new
Standard called sub user you got your flat packs go screw yourself. You got app images good for you
You got snaps you got I don't care because now we got sub users. Are you excited Noah? Come on sub user buddy
Yeah
Oh, you know that xkcd comic problem we have 13 community. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah
special news correspondent
Wes is joining us in the field right now for reporting on this West you are at the launch event for sub user, correct?
Yes, I am. And this is truly the one universal installations
Solution for all Linux users, correct West. Is that what you're learning on the scene?
Well, I think doctor was there already and this just makes docker every place else. That's right
That's because this is application installation with docker
So you take your docker containers and now you use them to distribute all your applications with sub user. That is oh
You like you know what and here's the crazy thing
this
almost could work
Because there is just a lot of stink behind docker containers. There's a docker container for everything. It's unbelievable
So if you take that and you whittle it down a little bit and you make it as an application delivery platform
You are utilizing the built-in knowledge set of all of these people that have already composed docker containers
Which is a lot and it could almost by default just be a way people end up distributing applications
At one point though, at what point do we just stop I don't I don't know
I just don't know what to do with this anymore. It's too much. It's too much. My head kind of explodes
But there you go. It's sub user and you can read more about its docker and
Python and a little bit of git combined with a little bit of docker. I
Think and to complement this we need to have some universal window managers. Yes, right
Yeah, yeah, gotta make sure you gotta make sure you're doing the right thing
You got to make sure you got to make sure that you got to make sure we get a couple of those though
Can't just have one. Yeah, you know, it's amazing. It's amazing how on one side of this argument
I started out like two years ago if you'd asked me two years ago what I thought about universal installers
I would have told you that it was the number one problem on Linux and I don't care what anyone said
the the number one resistance I think that happens links the reason that people don't port software to Linux the number one reason is
Is there is no universal, you know app installer
It's you gotta figure out which distro navigate that whole mess and now
like I'm I've almost gone to the complete other side of it because I'm I just I'm not I
Guess I'm not as convinced today that a universal installer could ever work in the Linux ecosystem
I don't know if I don't know if I believe anymore that
That it's that it's a viable solution for for the very nature of Linux. Oh girl you crazy
I just I I almost don't know how and I know I get so much crap for this
But I almost don't know how you can't see it. It's such like out of all of
I'd say it's the number one problem with Linux desktop
I agree. I agree, but I don't think it's a solvable problem unless we all agree on one distro to use. I disagree
Well, the whole point of the
Snaps for example is to be on multiple distros
It doesn't matter what district use as long as the top-level application layer is not directly
intertwined into the distro
But then don't you have a handicapped version of the application potentially? No, what do you mean?
Well, so for example if you have if the if the if the if the arch system for example works
You know has is is not capable or works differently than Ubuntu then
Isn't the isn't the snap package packaged for the lowest common denominator?
No, it'll all work the same
It's just that the current the current reason with the arch thing doesn't work as well as the Ubuntu one is because the Ubuntu
one has been out for
Two months and it has been developed before four months and the arch one has been out for well
Four days. I'll tell you what. I think here's what kernel Linux is talking about rotten is he saying
The application itself sort of has to assume the lowest common denominator when it comes in the library
So for example when I installed the VLC snap on fedora 24
I got a version of VLC that had really really crappy fonts compared to the rest of the fedora 24 desktop
Which this is one of the areas they they specifically worked on for this release. And so it seemed like
That's probably a early an early problem that's gonna get worked out. But right now
That VLC snap doesn't take advantage of the better fonts and better font rendering on my host system
That seems like a bit of a downside, don't you think?
Well, yeah, it'd be kind of annoying. But if there was no one
At all putting effort into like a shared library system for snaps that would suck but they're doing that
So I'm okay with it. I think it's it's definitely less annoying than not having the application at all
Yeah, that's true. That's true. And the other thing and they can also they could just include the font they want
Yeah, that's true. Yeah, that's I wonder about user experience like
Where app image to me feels like it's kind of the easiest from the like Windows user download and run it
I wonder how much we'll see that pushed
I think canonical could do it, but it doesn't seem like it's at quite the same level
Yeah, and that will probably determine a lot for the desktop user
It's not even app image is not even that simple for the users
It's more simple than an exe or a DMG in general because you you have to be able to do permissions
But if as a user of app image you have to know that you have to do that
So you have to exp you have to give them information about that you have to you have to set the permissions so that it can
Execute you also have to know how to do that in the first place
So there is still you know a stepping stone that you have to go through for app images
that doesn't make it the best whereas in in certain cases the
Their goal for snaps is to have just an installer that you would go to the you go to the Ubuntu software
App or whatever they're calling it now and then you just install it and there you have it and it's a snap and you're done
We'll be I know you want to try to train people to go to that app
That's the thing that is actually
Website and download the snap and it worked the same way or or if the website could somehow
Initiate the software centers page. That would be nice to like it's like an apt colon. Yep. Yeah
Yeah, I wouldn't I think you were about to try to jump in there during the crosstalk. So go ahead
Yeah, I was just gonna say on the point of that VLC application or rather snap
Um with because I've not seen it, but I understand what you're describing the first
GUI application that I tried to make with a snap had no fonts whatsoever. The menus didn't render correctly and
PNGs didn't render correctly and I fixed all of those problems and it now looks like a themed
Ubuntu Marte
application again
and that took
some changes in
snap craft to support that and or rather snap day to support that and
learning
How to do this stuff and then that got abstracted away into the way you build snaps. So
Don't assume that all applications are going to look like that by default
just take it that somebody has made a VLC snap of a
Pre-release version of VLC and they may well still be finding their way. Yeah
How to act that was sort of my impression when I used it and I think that you know
And when you see that represent itself in a couple of different ways, that's funny people will jump on it
remember when LibreOffice
Shipped their first snap and it was way bigger than it needed to be
People jumped all over that
Yeah, and that's another thing, you know you you have
all the debug symbols in there by default at the moment for example, and you know
Unless you there are mechanisms to say these are the own bits that I want in the squash FS file system
This is the stuff that is the runtime and the executables for example
And you can ignore all of these things and the first few times you make a snap
you just include everything because you just get the thing to work and then once you've got something that works and
Looks right then you can start refining it and actually trimming it down
You know and just as an indication of how early days all this stuff is
I ran into an issue during my fedora 24 review where I was trying to install GIMP
And it just downloaded an empty repo folder into my home directory. It turns out
That was a bug in Flatpak. I was hitting a bug and I didn't realize that I thought I was just doing the commands wrong
And I got him I got a note back from our review as bit of feedback saying yeah turns out bug we fixed it now
So it is super early days for all this stuff
And it's it so with that when I guess what I'm trying to convey is not only is it early days for the back-end
Implementation like the store what its source code is how the packages are delivered
But it's also early days for all the people that are packaging the software
And I feel like right now in terms of snaps
I feel like we're up against a wall that's about to break and then a whole bunch of snaps are gonna come out
But there's not a whole a whole bunch at the moment that you could just jump on
You know for the from a dumb user perspective because that's that you know
It was it was kind of a it was kind of an eye-opening experience
I hadn't followed
You know the snap packages in the Flatpak and the app image a whole lot prior to obviously until we you know covered it on
The show but prior to that I I knew that it existed, but I hadn't really played with it
And so my first foray into it was I went to download our app pic
which was the that image burner that Rick I had suggested and it was an app image and
I had no idea how to use it. I just downloaded on the site and double-clicked on it and it installed
I was like, well, that's cool
Then I did it on like three other distros and then that really started to click with me and when I went
To install my first snap package
I had no idea how to do that
And so I was googling for snap packages found one online downloaded it from the website
Tried to double click on it
Like I did with app image and that didn't work and then I googled around a little bit and found that you could do it
From the command line you want to go into or what? Were you on?
Fedora that was yeah, that was about you. Yeah
Okay. Okay. Yeah, and and so and and so basically I guess all that to say that
If you are a person coming over from macOS or Windows the software installation of app image functions
exactly how you would expect it to and you acquire software exactly how you would expect it to and
Because it's cross distro. I know you no longer have to worry about training users to search for you know
Look no, look
I feel like I feel like I feel like your criticism right there is
Temporary I feel like I feel like the next the next the next Ubuntu say the next release even will just they just have to
Associate the snap files association with an application that can install okay, but every distro has to do that for that to work
No, hang on a minute. Okay, you say that you downloaded an app image and you double clicked on it and it just did stuff
It did not. Yes, that is right. Yep. You didn't have to make it executable
Oh
Did I
Yeah
That didn't double click them. No, you're right. It's not associated with anything. I had to download it
I had to make it executable and then I could execute it and yeah, you're probably right. See that's that's
That it wasn't so we looked at we looked at cha because itches that you know disk
Creation utility right that runs on Windows Mac and Linux
Rewriting all of our how to make a USB drive
Using etcher so that every platform could use one tool
But the process of actually installing etcher on Linux is so alien to how people would install things on Linux
What we're actually going to do is write the instructions for Windows and Mac to use etcher and then use
GNOME disks for Linux because isn't that isn't that now can we just talk about that for a second Wow that you know a distribution
Is in the position where it is easier to write how to get it set up under Mac and Windows
Than it is under Linux that right there perfectly defines the problem. We are trying to solve
We're not I'm not arguing for the replacement of repositories
I'm not calling for the end of Debs and RPMs
But that right there is so such a wonderful illustration of the problem
It's that's amazing well, but so I guess
So what would be the alternative that we allow by default for applications to?
When you download off the app well
fast forward fast forward five years from now and and let's just say
Flatpak snaps or app images have taken off one of them is is so predominant that
that you can you can pretty confidently write a how-to and say download this app image and
You can almost know with absolute certainty that they've downloaded an app image before and they know how to install it or if it's a snap
They know what that's about and so now imagine what wimpy's process would be he'd have the same download page
He'd say here's the instructions for Windows
Here's the instructions for Mac
And if you want to do in our Linux
download the snap and he could link to the most recent snap or he could link to the you browse page or whatever it is you
apps page and and it would just be double click the snap and follow the instructions when it launches it would literally be a
Less instruction set than it is for Windows
I mean, it's a fundamental shift in the friction
And it's a fundamental reduction in that friction for users to start with matei I mean
Do you think I'm wrong wimpy or do you think I'm right?
No, you are right. We're constantly trying to find ways to make to lower the barriers to entry and
For many reasons
snaps and
Universal package installers solve a number of problems. And the thing is is that you've talked about
putting snaps on the vendor or you know authors website so people can download a snap and
Install it the same way that Windows users do I?
Feel that's a bit of a retrograde step because I think the central repository where you can search for find and install
Applications from one place is the superior
Mechanism but snaps support both paradigms. You can have
a snap store or many snap stores
Depending on you know, if you've got an iot device that or a nas, you know in the nas vendor wants their own snap store
but
companies like viber for example
Could make snaps and have them download off their website
So both paradigms are supported with snaps and I think that's um, that's a a particularly useful
useful use case
Do you think it's going to be problematic though for users?
If sometimes you obtain it from a central software center and other time I go to that
I do and that's why I I would prefer to see that people
Embrace the snap store
Paradigm and we keep what we're used to and what mobile phone users and tablet users are used to which is all of your
Applications are in a central repository and frankly what macOS and Windows are going to write both have an application
Yeah, yeah
So let me so how about this is would there be a way for
For for active for somebody to add if you know if the if the snap is on a website is would there be for somebody else to
Take it off their website and add it to the store and then it would the reverse be true
Would it be possible for somebody like me?
Who really likes to have local copies of things to be able to download those those snap packages and store them on my device?
Yeah, so when I build a snap package, for example
I build it locally on my computer and I end up with an architecture specific snap so a an AMD 64 snap
and the snap is a squash FS file system that encompasses the application and
All of the shared libraries and assets that that application needs to run that snap file
You can install by typing snap install path to snap dot snap file
so you can download a snap and install it if you wanted to download all of the snaps in the world and stick them on a
USB hard drive and carry it around with you and
Install from those you could do that
And if you have the snap yaml file the snap craft in the file, yeah, if you've got the yaml file
You can build it yourself. Yeah, so dare Devlin
What do you think about it being a centralized repository and that being with canonical because don't you think then?
that means every single aspect of getting these snaps into the central repository has to be as
Easy and simple as possible and I don't think we're there yet. What do you think?
what I think is
essentially, I agree with wimpy and that I prefer the model to have a repository and
if we want to see the repository still to prevail as the way to install packages what we have essentially to do is
just make the process easier for third parties to come and put their package in and
Once we do that
There's no excuse to why they're not deploying through that mechanism and why are they are distributing, you know?
Through their website instead and perhaps make it easy
To make their website put something that you know
Like you do in Android you be doing a website in the text that it's an application from the Play Store and opens the Play
Store you might want something that is similar to that
That goes and opens your software center and install that so the website will do not actually have a download
But actually something though because the store yes, that's true. Yeah rotten
I wanted to give you a chance to jump in and just I was curious your thoughts about the process right now of getting into
That central store
Yeah, it's actually very easy. Like wimpy was talking about how he builds the snaps locally. You don't have to do that
You can actually just make the yaml file and then send it to the launchpad
we'll build it for you through the snap craft tool and create all the
architectures snaps that you want and you just push it to the store and if you and if you get
You on if you have a if you are a part of a project and you were like the official person
You get the namespace of the official project. If you're not you get for example telegram
It's telegram dash the name of the guy who did it then so that way you can there's there's no one fighting over namespace
So then to get into the store is very simple and as long as your stuff runs and when you know
It doesn't break anything. It's all good and you get it in there
And then if you have let's say you see a bug and you want to fix it
You just do it again through launchpad push it to the store and then the user gets the access to it and gets the update
Hmm. Yeah, it actually is so it sounds like the biggest convenience here
Sounds like the biggest inconvenience is you have to have a launchpad account
I don't know. Yeah, that's about the size of it
For some that's a deal-breaker
And don't think it's a good thing. It's free and open-source launchpad is yeah
And the the Ubuntu snap store implementation is just a snap store
Implementation I think others will sprout up
Yeah
I I want their own to be only to be one because then if there is more than one there creates more
Availability issues, but if there was a structure for example like Ubuntu's
Store was like the core base that you could build on top of and have your own snaps
But if you don't have a snap for a particular application you got it as like a fallback
Yeah, or it could end up like repos where you could have multiples. You could have your local installation of snap
Pointed at multiple repos just like you can't a flat pack today
Couldn't it could be like that too. It might not be a hard-coded to a single story. Maybe you could have
You know, let's say I'm let's say I'm Ubuntu mate. I could have
When when my users launched their version of the software center
it could be looking at can all of canonicals snap store and a
Ubuntu mate snap store that maybe has
The the welcome screen in it and maybe a menu launcher and a few other things that you know
They've created that to ease the process and it may be it's only four or five things just like today enter gross does
Enter gross does repo priority and you have anti grosses repo at the top and then they have the regular main
repos and they they can pull from all the different sources just like a lot of like
Like we see today with a lot of derivatives only this would be a snap version and be it
It might not have support for it today
Snap and snap and local snap do you know that might not have support for multiple stores today?
But this is an open source project. I mean in a year it could it could do ten times what it does today
Right. It has support for a store like having your own custom store now like, you know
So it's only been like two weeks since that was even announced like they were doing the different distro stuff
So that's already been proving that they're gonna do other things
But there's actually something that a lot of people aren't aware of is that when you have a snap in the store
You actually don't just have that snap and that branch you have multiple branches
You have the stable branch the unstable branch like the constant testing branch
So you can actually have like betas and all this and it's all still one snap that you control
They just can the user can select which branch they want to use
So if they want to lay absolute latest they can get it
What about licensing issues like for you know, Adobe Reader or you know, they'll be flash or something like that. I
Guess more so so more specifically, I guess here's my question
The the concern I have about the whole repo idea is you're gonna wind up with I'm afraid that anyway that you're gonna wind up
With some distros having certain repos and those repos not being added by default in other distros
And so what you wind up with is again certain packages available in one distro and and and not another well
But they're all snaps. They're all snaps. You can always just grab the snap right if you know where to but yeah, you're right
Yeah, here's what I think though about that for when it comes to licensing and stuff like that
I don't know if there's a direct answer because
For all we know in six months snap or flat packet have have an option at install where it enables user prompting to accept
EULA's and so that I'm not so worried about what wait the point
I think you're touching on is if
Something were to happen where you had multiple stores and you had like the chairman's talking about multiple people submit telegram
How would you know which telegram is the one that's the most secure most updated most reliable?
I think what you would see if that truly existed
I think you're gonna like this answer is the market would respond by creating a directory like like GNOME files
And like the you app browser that's already created there
The open source community will step up and create a platform where you'll have everything indexed. You'll have comments
You'll have votes. You'll have just like the AUR or just just like at GNOME files, right?
It'll be that what so I don't use the
As much as you do
But you know
I I go back to the most effective way for me to research products nowadays as I go to Amazon and sort by number of
Reviews and if 10,000 people bought something and really liked it
I know that I can try and buy the same product and probably a good experience right if we could bring that to software
Jeez, man. Yeah, exactly
Exactly. I think the market that's just what happened
So wimpy I there's something you want to jump in before we wrap up because I didn't talk about this for that long
But I wanted to give you the last shout. I
Can't remember. Okay, no problem. No problem. You know what? I'll just say this
we should probably move on because right now as we record this there is actually a news event happening and we
Like I don't even know how long into the show and we haven't even mentioned it if you get to the point where you want
To host your own flat packs your app images or your own snap store digital ocean.com use the promo code do
Unplugged support this show and get a $10 credit man. Digital ocean is great because it's all KVM
So the virtualizer I think I mean just my opinion the best virtualizing platform. I have ever used KVM is the bee's knees
They've stacked that on top of SSDs
Of course, it's all running on top of Linux 40 gigabit e connections into the hyper visors data centers all over the world and
Literally the best interface that could have possibly built sitting on top of the shenanigans
I don't know how they do it and the nice thing it's all HTML and even if it was an if they
Like if if they had a native app that looked that worked this gotta be like man
They got a great desktop app and then they have a functional website
No, it's like better than I would have ever expected even from a native app. It is extremely functional
You get HTML 5 console access to your rigs. You can deploy SSH keys to multiple machines at a time
You can spin up applications like the entire frequent stack from everything from the you know
The kernel of whatever distro you chose all the way up to the final crazy Ruby on rails application
You want to run or just the base system?
They got data centers in New York, San Francisco, Singapore afternoon, London, Toronto, Germany, India
They're growing like crazy and they've matched this great interface that I just freaking love with a super cool
API an API that's so straightforward and simple and something they take seriously that a really great community has cropped up and built a ton
Of open source code around that speak in a community. They have some of the best documentation out there
Literally, even if you're not digital ocean customer, it's still
One of the best resources out there check it out because they take that very seriously
Which means between the application stacks they have available the base distros they have to choose from and their documentation
Experts and beginners can make super super good use out of a digital ocean droplet
They also have hourly pricing available because you can spin up and destroy a rig in matter of seconds with snapshots
You can restore and get right back to where you're at
It's really nice to take advantage of their hourly pricing and we use our promo code do
Unplugged one word lowercase you get the $10 credit that hourly price is gonna last you forever
So if you want to experiment with something on a machine that has a crazy great internet connection tons of CPU
You want to have multiple people bang on it? You want to put it in production for yourself?
If you want something you can access between your work and your home and also on your mobile device and not have to mess
Around and fuss with your crappy router
Digital ocean just use the promo code do unplugged and if you ever get to a point where you're ready to put this thing in
production
It'll work. It'll do it and they make it easy to expand the machines to especially now with a new block storage beta program
You know right now
Jupiter broadcasting is taking advantage of digital oceans infrastructure like never before
It's so nice to know that when we just want to try a concept we can mess around on digital ocean
We don't have to worry about the costs. We know we get great performance and we're ready to go into production
We have enterprise grade features like their API like the snapshot capability like the application stack deployments
and
Go ahead. I'm just gonna say you're slowly moving your studio up to the
Cloud it's just a cloud that you can control so that you can get to it from anywhere in your RV
I was just I was just gonna say and now with the new team features
I'll just never have to worry about and let Noah do everything. Oh
Digital ocean
Well, that's Rekha's got the post-production work
Noah's got the server side work and you know also they make it nice
They like if you want to set something up for a client and transfer it to him you can transfer droplets
It's a pretty great service digital ocean comm just use the promo code do unplugged in a big. Thanks to digital ocean
So I was saying there's a news event going on right now
I got a little audio to get you in the mood for those of you that didn't know and I almost I
Considered making it but I would have to mess with the whole road trip plans that I I have right now
So I couldn't do it
But going on right now is a Red Hat summit or as the Red Hat folks that I've been talking to you call it
Summit summit is going on right now, and I got a little audio to put you in the mood
Whoa
Now no you might I always heard about it. You know you might be a little jealous new to Red Hat
I've only been doing it for over a year now my job thought it would be a great idea and a great experience for me
to come to Red Hat summit
My
Excitement here is to learn about a lot of things that I heard this morning
12 plus new release announcements. I'm like yes
And I'm just looking forward to the next four days. I mean there's so much going on around application development containers
Which is part of my world. I think there's a you know opportunity to figure out what's going on all in one place
You have a lot of vendors at summit who are in starting to embrace open source in new ways one of the things that we're really
Trying to talk about with customers is the fact that we have this cross portfolio experience including services
And it's not just product by product and these solutions can really help them solve specific problems all right
I was excited. I was stoked until that until that last executive spoke there
And then then the entire thing kind of lost me. I don't
You didn't hear it. Did you the smurfs is the fact that we have this cross portfolio experience, okay?
So one of the things we're trying to communicate to customers that we have this cross part proof a cross portfolio experience, okay?
Yeah, including services, and it's not just product by product including services
And it's not just product by product and these solutions can really help them solve specific problems
But these solutions can really help them solve specific problems
I'm gonna play it once in its entirety Noah and then once it's done
I want you to tell me what she just said okay trying to talk about with customers is the fact that we have this
Cross portfolio experience including services, and it's not just product by product and these solutions can really help them solve specific problems
things you just saying that the red hat solutions stretch across a
Vast so they partnered with or they're working with Microsoft, and they're and they're working very hard with all of the different problems
Here and hired industry experts and have look available
All right, so you
All right
Yeah, okay, okay, okay, so that's what you think all right? No that was a good try. That was a good solid effort
We have good. We got nice music. Ooh
Yeah, okay, so I mean I'm digging this piece overall wimpy. Could you could you explain to me what she said?
Yeah, they've got I'm duck woods
You know I that wasn't helpful actually that didn't help Chris
You of all people should understand this that poor woman that poor woman is standing there
It's dead she's standing there with her computer
And she's working on a couple of things and everyone is like tapping her on the shoulder and finally this guy turns around
He's like hey
I'm John from the from the from the media marketing department, and we're gonna shoot this thing about we're interviewing people
So tell us about red hat and she's and she told him. She's like. I'm not really good on camera
I don't you'd be fine. You'd be fine. I don't even really know to you. You'll be fine here
We're gonna start rolling okay. Go and then that's what came out. That's definitely a possibility
That's totally what happened. I I think I think what it was
Now here's what I think it was Noah and picture it okay
It's it's two days before the floor opens you finally just got all the banners up the executives are arriving for their pictures
Whoa who's getting aggressive in the mumble room daredevil and you were getting aggressive there in the mumble room everybody's arrived for their pictures
You haven't actually opened the doors yet, but from a corporate standpoint
You have decided what your core message about this entire event is so you get your marketing team there with their eight with their DSLR
Camera, and you say summit who are starting to embrace open source in new ways one of the things that we're really trying to talk
About with customers is the fact that we have this cross portfolio experience including services
And it's not just product by product and these solutions can really help them solve specific problems
What I love about it is she ends with these solutions can help them solve specific problems
What what's so what's so corporately wonderful about it is we can help you solve your specific problem after making the most vague
Possible with generalized statement we could ever come up with that's what's so amazing about and I really respect Red Hat as a company
But when they actually outwardly communicate
So they don't they don't actually allow all the cool people in the company to brag and talk about all the neat stuff
They're doing and so when they communicate with their Red Hat voice
Even their CEO who seems like a pretty great guy
Communicates in this style that feels like Microsoft at its clumsiest
Yeah, I don't I guess I don't know I guess the problem is you're you're dealing with a couple of things, right?
You're dealing with a you're dealing with the most litigious country in the entire world
Yeah, that's such a that's such a tired Red Hat excuse
I'm so true when you have a company that big that's worth that much money
Yeah, they're walking around with a constant target on their butt meanwhile companies that are
Jillions of times larger have their top CEO a top top people sitting down and talking to podcasters by anything the podcaster asks them
That's such a tired tried excuse for all of the things that are wrong with Red Hat and fedora. I'm just sick of it
I just I guess I guess I would agree with you and you I know for a fact you've been there with me
I would agree with you if it wasn't for the fact that we've talked to those people and what they say on camera and what?
They're able to say I think I don't think I think there's I think there is a culture problem at Red Hat and I think
That the employees absolutely fear all these legal things. I don't think I think they all are the biggest bunch of paranoid
People out there. I mean it is ridiculous. I it's given their clientele
Do you think it I mean is it is the community involvement or a better presence?
Just not in their interest in the long-term fiscal sense. I think giving their clientele. It's expected
This is how you communicate so it's part of the reason they communicate this way
Yeah, that's that might be part of it
I guess I guess I just every time I every time that we've had somebody on
Camera, it seems like they they they follow this the the strict rudimentary procedure and then you get them off-camera and they're geeks
Just like you and me and that that just tells me that they have hired legal people that have specifically told them
Hey, these are the things that you don't want
These are these are the approved things that you say because these are the things that we can get right sure
I feel like that does feel like what they say
Why is it that the no other companies like that? No other company?
We talked to no other company in the Linux ecosystem has these same concerns other people are worried about these particular issues
But nobody is literally petrified the the employees from Red Hat are terrified of this particular issue. Nobody else is like that
What's the down?
I'd claim that none of them is as big as Red Hat and that's one thing and they have to be risk-takers if they want to
Be in the platform discussing when Red Hat is discussing things
You know what? I will also claim that they mentioned solutions, which is you know keyword to we provide for everything
But what without committing into any specifics and you come with us you talk with us
Yeah
We're really trying to talk about with customers is the fact that we have this cross portfolio experience including services
And it's not just product by product and these solutions can really help them solve specific problems
You know, I've heard that 30 times and I still just doesn't make any sense
And I guess it doesn't matter. It's it's just a it's just a part of how they communicate. That's my that's my main point
They need some cross vocabulary solutions
Maybe they just think which company provides products and always advertises their products and it's their competitor
While they're providing solutions and that will be more pleased more pleasant to their customers to hear
Yeah, just think about that. Who's that usual canonical for example? Yeah
Focus on their products. It's there. What's the downside?
Yeah of saying something like that. Like where where is that? Where is it? Where is it problematic?
It sounds like disingenuous bullshit by people that don't actually even know the very products
They're selling and which makes me have doubt in the people that run the company
But because there's a clear communication style
Isn't that doubt alleviated from the from the from from the from the people that do have the expertise
No, because they're not the ones making the decisions
The people making the decisions don't even know the product
Right and they're not listening to that spiel as well
Right, and they're not listening to that spiel. Anyway, they don't care the deals are made elsewhere, right?
But I feel like the entire culture at red hat is the is the idea that anyone in the company
Has the ability to offer input and in there is no top-down hierarchy
And that was entire that was the entire purpose of jim whitehurst's book
Was that he thought he was going to go into this company and teach them how to run a company from the top down
And what it taught him was that that's not the way that a company is run
Okay, that's much I mean I just that does sound that's the way pretty much every corporate company
Every you know cover integer speaks when you they do any kind of press like why what hurts?
What is hurting red hat in this case?
Maybe it's because no one listens to what they say because they never say anything. That is exactly it
And I don't really I guess I wish we weren't dwelling on this because i'd rather move on
But my point is is when you don't speak clearly you don't connect to the to the linux audience
You don't connect to the to the linux audience if you have an audience in the open source
This is this is a summit for technical people. Okay. This is not a marketing event. This isn't ces
This isn't the this isn't something for consumers
This is at the red hat summit for people who are sys admins and people that make their livings on red hat systems, right?
So I think I want to be clear
This is an introduction to why you as a technical person should come to the summit that was posted on the red hat youtube channel
I get I guess that wasn't my impression of of uh of red hat summit. I thought it was for more like high level
you know like uh
like uh, you know
Absolutely, then there's there's all kinds of yeah, there's people vars there and all kinds of stuff and another
Another group of people there is microsoft, uh, and they made some huge announcement announcements at red hat summit
Which I think is sort of a big news story kind of in on itself is that microsoft is making these announcements at a red
Hat summit the company announced the general availability of dot net core and asp.net core 10 the microsoft announcement
uh is kind of a big deal at red hat summit and one of the motivations in open sourcing dot net is
They really want to collaborate more with red hat and red hat has a couple of web pages dedicated on their website now to making
red hat the premier dot net platform
Uh, the red dot net foundation will be the steward of overall dot net development and red hat just joined that foundation
So that's kind of a big deal
That's one of the that's an example of some of the folks that are at uh, the summit
And it's really microsoft kind of delivering on this this promise of opening dot net and getting it running on linux
Yeah
Well, they seem to have some serious motivation because they announced that nearly one in three azure virtual machines are now running linux
Microsoft is uh sort of seeing a huge growth because just the same time last year they said one and four
So now they've gone in a year at least according to racinovich who runs azure
uh, this is microsoft's gone from one and four of its azure virtual machines to one and three
and uh
The other the other uh, two-thirds are just azure customers running windows servers and virtual machines
So they're they're seeing a big uptick for linux at azure and you know
It's one of the reasons linux academy has launched azure training is it's just big over there
So yeah
That's a big. I don't know guys to me that seems like uh
It seems like the microsoft stuff changes how I think about it a little bit like I wouldn't previously like if I was going to
Make a project. I wasn't going to start it on dot net and maybe java if I want like a nice object oriented garbage collective
Etc
But if they're going to have first class linux support and you know really stand behind like that then
I mean they don't they make some good software
They have a lot of talented engineers there if they're really down with the openness, then maybe it's something to be worthwhile
So I just looked at the registration at 1600 bucks, uh for the for the full pass to go there
So it and to me this seems like a this seems like the oscon and the linux con of conferences
Except it based more on linux
And so in that regard, I don't know that I don't know that highly technical down to earth, you know unfiltered
You know technical talk is is necessarily the most appropriate to marketing video
Dude, you are really just all in with red hat. Well, I just I just I just I really am
You know, i'm not I guess i'm just not you're telling me you're telling me
I mean, I I feel like this is sort of almost like it doesn't even need explaining but
What are what are the number who are the number one attendees of oscon?
You know, we've talked to a lot of a lot of big business people that could care less about no those are the vars
Those are the people at the booths
The attendees are our sys admins and dev guys who are sent there by their company because their company's paying for the ticket
That's the people walking around the floor. Those are the people attending the talks. That's I mean, come on
Those are the people filling up those rooms listening to the talks
I I I I guess I I guess I don't I guess you're right there
I mean, there's definitely a large majority of those but there's also a healthy there's also a healthy majority of
people that are you know that are
That are just you know decision makers just you know executive types that are there to learn about their technology, too
They're not actually the ones implementing that stuff the low level developer kind of people
Uh, but I you're right. I mean we walked into that. There's a whole group of people that were that we talked to
Was at oscon, I think and all of them, uh, you know
I think the funnier thing is that you're bringing it back up after we moved on
I just I went and looked at their website and I was like, all right
A little bit i'm looking at the keynote speakers and i'm looking there's a guy from target. There's a guy from uh, from from uh, intel
There's a guy from dell
It just it it very much feels like a very corporatey conference and it seems like corporatey speak is appropriate there
So what do you think about what do you think about?
Uh red hat enterprise being the premier platform to build dot net on a proven and trusted enterprise linux
Dot net on red hat enterprise linux gets started right now if you go to developers dot red hat dot com slash dot net
What are you excited noah?
I am excited that a company like microsoft is going to have the incredible influence of red hat over them
To help them push them in the right direction
Uh, well, that's a very political way to say that that is very nice. Very nice. Um,
Are you okay if we move on or do we do we do we gotta hug it out if we gotta hug it out
No, we're good. I mean because you know, I know I know you don't like it when we talk bad about your red hat
No, no, it's okay. Just they they red hat is why i'm on linux is because they made such an amazing product
Ha ha
All right. Well
Speaking of running linux. I have been running linux mint 18
And I gotta tell you
It's not so bad
Uh by the time you're probably getting this down
Listen, if you're a download audience member linux 8 linux mint 18 cinnamon and mate additions will likely be released softpedia
Noticed it a little earlier. Thanks to a tipster. They have links to the iso downloads which are in our show notes
And this is as of june 28th
um now
This is the uh, this is the new version after a lot of talk about xapps and all of that kind of stuff
It has the new of cinnamon 3.0 goodness in it that probably a lot of you have been anticipating if you're a cinnamon user
And this release is going to be supported until
So this is something that'll be around for a while. In fact, it'll be the base of future releases until 2018
So like I was mentioning this has the new xapps in it
Which I had a chance to try out a little bit. It has high dpi support. Well, he's much improved high dpi support
um
Has the uh, it has the brand new
Info screen when you launch the update manager for the first time that gives you a little bit more clarification about the different
upgrade options
What is there's somebody like
There is somebody there is somebody going on with the jacksaw in the back. I don't know what's going on out there
Uh, and uh, it's got uh, I the new theme that is based on arc and the mocha icon theme
uh the mint y theme which actually
When you put it in dark mode looks, uh
It looks pretty nice. It looks uh, pretty nice. So this is the new mint 18 sort of at a very high level
I've only been using it for like um
Three hours, so I only have very very first impressions
I did hit a few bumps
So I want to give you guys a few warnings and things like that
Anybody in the mumble room had a chance to try any of the betas of mint 18 or been looking at it as the release
Has been getting closer
I've been doing competitive research. Yes. Oh, really? And what is your uh, reconnaissance, uh showing you?
Uh, it's linux mint
Same stuff but newer
so, um
That was sort of my impression too and I was actually kind of hoping you would have more because I didn't have much
That's kind of oh my god. Sorry. Sorry for stealing your wind. Yeah, you did
And my wind was not much. I had very little wind, uh, which is not normal right now
I think right now like what we were talking about at least we're talking about like 17 71, etc
I think
We kind of know what linux mint is
And where they really shined in the past was on some of that polish and integration
And it's kind of hard to assess that this close after release, right?
So maybe in a week or two we can see really are they excelling at what they're trying to do or not?
Yeah, I actually think wait a week or two would be good advice because uh, so I decided to put this on the libram
Which is as you guys are probably well aware a laptop built to run linux
No, did you know that?
What are you laughing about? It's a laptop built to run linux. What's the problem? What's undoubtedly about to leave your mouth?
So, uh the linux mint, uh first pass on the install, uh wouldn't work
Uh, it warned me about some uefi issue. Uh, basically that I had another os on there and that uh,
Yeah, there's some shenanigans where to occur with a with a bios simulation that I may not be able to boot into their os
Is to which I said the entire reason i'm installing mint is to not boot into those other os
So go ahead and nuke and pave. All right, so I figured this problem solved. Oh, no
What you didn't switch the hard drive, did you?
No
Okay, so we just blew away our obs. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, and and I realized that and I realized it doesn't boot. It's just so
Good at all. So that's good. So that's sweet
And then I did manage to get it to boot but uh, I don't know why but my wi-fi is not working
And I haven't and that's kind of so I just ended up using ethernet, uh usb adapter to play around because
I didn't have time to troubleshoot the wi-fi at the moment
I did notice the settings control panel is also a little cleaned up and there's uh, there's the you know
There the overall uh, the new theme and all that and the new version of uh, sentiment is really nice
It's a really nice stuff to click yet
So I tried to figure that out for you because I thought you might ask me that and they've removed the mouse and trackpad
Uh control panel applet from the settings thing now you might
Some stuff you can still search for like so for example
If you wanted to search for uh proprietary drivers
You don't you no longer can find like the drivers or software sources entry in the settings
But if you search for it in your mint menu, it will come up
Ah, that's good that that makes a lot of sense. I'm glad to hear that
So yeah, it looks like I was gonna ask if we can enable touch to click. Yeah, right. I know I know no not no
No, not no, I hate apps to click. I don't just and I don't mean like click during the show. No, uh,
quietly click
Here's your the thing is I actually not only I don't just like kind of dislike it. I actively like I can't stand it
I can't stand I can't even use a computer if it has to happen
He gets super grumpy west and then if it's like one in the morning, he gets like all diva about it. It's bad
It's real bad. We don't want that and you could ask rikai
My son dylan was over here at the house last night at the studio and uh, he was going on a rant about track pads
And then him and rikai started labeling me as a track pad as a track pad supporter as a tracks
I know it got it started getting heated in my own studio over track pads
So I you know, and i'm just i'm just a track pad indifference. That's all I don't like them
But I don't dislike them that much and I started I started taking a lot of track bad heat
So no, you are you are leading a revolution, you know, who else is leading a revolution?
That'd be red hat in their communication
Is one of the things that we're really trying to talk about with customers is the fact that we have this
Cross-portfolio experience including services and it's not just product by product and solutions can really help them solve specific problems
Yeah
Uh track bad works under fedor just saying oh good. Yeah. Yeah the new lib input, huh? Yeah, that is nice
I can go ahead and disable tactically. That's it's fantastic. You know the first time we used the new fedora 24
There was like 20 seconds where the mouse felt really weird
And then yeah, go ahead. Are you looking for are you looking for cross cursor solutions?
Yeah, could you have any specifics because uh, I wonder if you don't have it from any specific division maybe as a service
All right. So this is yeah, can't you tell this is my last lup for a week? Yeah, I know right
All right before we get into these desktop killers that wimpy and I have been drooling over and I think noah
You're perfectly suited as a orx pro owner and as somebody who also has the 13 inch side of this
we're going to talk about um, is linux technically dead on the desktop not because of linux itself, but because
Just statistically speaking in 10 years five years
Is is the desktop really going to be necessary
We have a couple of new products out in the market that are just unbelievably powerful and they're portable
I I can't even as somebody who works in video production
I can't even believe i'm about to ask this question
But realistically I gotta look at I gotta look at the specs
I gotta look at the sales stats and I gotta ask the question. So before we go there, let's go somewhere nice
Let's go to this new. Oh, there it is. There's the one just on time. There's that weed whacker good
This is uh, we're then we've added that weed whacker in post. We sweetened up the linux academy spot
We wanted to make sure you know what else and then we add a few other things like we brought in bill hammer from
Our himmer from uh, fox news
See there's bill so that's nice and megan kelly's here too to help us omg omg omg
I don't know why I don't know why but we also have a little background music for linux academy
That's right. Go over to linuxacademy.com
Unplugged friends and look at that new site. Oh, look at that site
Oh friends
Look at that thing. They they I tell you what
They ain't stopping over at linux academy. They're adding new content all the time
They've expanded their staff to make sure the old stuff stays relevant. It's linux enthusiasts
trainers developers
Educators they've came together. They created a linux academy platform and you can get started at linuxacademy.com
Unplugged you get a great discount
They have hands-on labs
So you get to work with this stuff instructor mentoring when you need to talk to humans
Video courses with self-paced in-depth courses. We can download comprehensive study guide
The courseware automatically adjusts to the distribution you want to use
Learning plans
learning paths
Availability planners all of these things help you structure a learning plan when you don't have a lot of time. So if you get busy
Going on a road trip those kinds of things you're going to tokyo
Linux academy's got your back. I like that too for the this is like when you're just
You only got an hour. They got nuggets deep dives. They have ios and android applications
They have note cards that can be forked to help you study
And they have a super active community packed
Full of jupiter broadcasting members
Or if you have 13 hours of free wi-fi on an airplane over to tokyo
then
You can continue to learn
While lounging about on an airplane. I like that in business class too at that you swath son of a gun
That's right getting your getting your knowledge on at linuxacademy.com
Go check them out. They're growing like crazy
It's a really great platform committed
To expanding linux all of the technologies linux core technologies and also the technologies built
On top of linux academy go there now
Because time my friends
Is running out
Linux academy.com
Unplugged and a big thank you to linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
And thank you to that weed whacker for adding a little bit of extra context to that spot a little extra buzz
Yeah, you know a little bit of layers a little bit of flavor. So, uh, there's this guy named martin wimpress
Uh, I don't know who he is
But he's got a lot of nerve teasing me like this
This son of a gun over here posts that intro where will soon be announcing a new laptop that he had the privilege of naming
the entry where athena
Well wimpy that sounds pretty cool
Tell me about the process of naming a computer and maybe a little bit of backstory here about the athena
And then the big reveal if you will
Okay, so I obviously have a relationship with intro where um
And i've known that they've been working on this computer for some months now
And as it was getting close it had like a code name
Uh, and we were exchanging details using the code name and uh, and then they sort of said oh
We're going to call it this
And I was like, oh, okay. I said, oh, uh
Oh, we're thinking of calling it this and I was like, oh
I'd like uh coming up with a name. So I came up with the the name athena which they liked so
It's the intro where athena
That is pretty an athena. What is there any special revelance or uh connection to the name? Well, um
Um, all of their machines are named after greek gods and goddesses
uh, um, and I like the classics and athena I think is the uh,
the uh
most interesting
Uh of the goddesses. So she's the goddess of war and peace
and wisdom and craft and uh, all sorts of things so she's uh, she's
Got more attributes than any of the others
So, uh, this is a pretty well-specced machine and depending on your different options
It could be a powerhouse now
I I happened to a little birdie told me that you may have ended up purchasing one of these athenas
So you must have had it for at least a bit wimpy. How is it? How is the machine?
Why did you decide to purchase it? What are your experiences like tell us all about it?
So I have sold every computer I own
My own in order in order to make some money to buy this
So once I knew this was on its way i've been ebaying my com my computers
and um
Uh, i've also I don't if remember a few weeks ago. There was a sharp uptick in uh, the bitcoin price
It went up about 20. Oh, yeah, I did notice that as a matter of fact. Yeah. Yeah, so I I I cashed out some coins
Between you know, and I were playing the bitcoin market for our hardware. Yeah
To uh to uh, sort of cover the balance
so I
uh, i've gone full full metal
intro ware athena, so uh
The one I have has got the uh skylake i7 6820 hk
Which is a quad core and that can push out a turbo 3.6 gigahertz
64 gigs of ddr4 ram
all right, um i've got uh
Uh, i've only installed three of the hard drives at the moment. So i've got three ssds in there at the moment
a 256 drive which is boot
and two
one terabyte drives
And i'll be i'll be adding another one and the reason for the two one terabyte drives one is for
Uh the home partition and then I also create myself a second logon. That's just called steam
And I mount that second drive on slash home slash steam
So that all of the games sit in there and then uh as as I reinstall and what have you
I don't have to download all of my stuff. Oh, that's a really smart idea
I put mine all on a drive called slash big and it's just like a pool of drives
So that's a clever name. Hey speaking of names, uh wimpy. I have I have one question for you
Did you consider?
naming the laptop
laptop mclappy face
No, I didn't
I spoke about this on the ubuntu podcast and they all pointed out I missed the obvious thing is that I should have called
it the intro where martin but
Nobody
Would have gone for that. Yeah
Yeah
So, um, this has got the it's got uh, intel iris 5 30 pro graphics in it
And it's also got an nvidia gtx 980 m in it as well
um, so with optimus switching
Oh, and is that working?
Yeah, well, um, it's you have to log out and log in so I it doesn't do diane on the fly switching
I I imagine if I messed about with bumblebee I could get that to go
but I usually i'm using the intel graphics the only time I use the nvidia graphics is if
I want to do uh some game playing or
Or uh, i've just started recently experimenting with the nvank stuff
But those tend to be specific work cases and i'm quite happy to log out and log back in to handle that
But I wrote a utility from for marty, um, or rather forked a utility
And extended it a little bit that um sits in the tray and it shows you which you're using and you can just toggle
And then uh log out log in
Wow, that is quite the mission. That's a multi-year machine. I can tell you somebody who's bought some workstation killers before
Yeah, any chances are going to be?
Sorry, any chances are going to be available in the us at some point?
Uh, there are no immediate plans for entroware to ship in the us as far as i'm aware now is this
Yeah, go ahead
I do know despite despite the politics in the uk
Uh last week. I do know entroware are very close to launching in some european countries
This seems this seems very similar to to the orx pro from system 76
So that's it. Yeah, so noah, you may already have something very similar to this rig
Yeah, I know I I figured that the I figured the odm, you know manufacturers probably the same but it just there are small
Differences of course across them because they're both building them assembling them separately and making right
And the other thing is is in in in limpy and I had talked about this a little bit is
That you know various little components inside are are sometimes different and that leads to drastically different. Yeah, it does. Yeah
Yeah, it does. Yeah, and this also you can get with ubuntu mate from uh, entroware, which is kind of nice
Yes, it uh, it arrived pre-installed with ubuntu
Yeah, have you have you experimented with battery life much
Uh, no. No, I I haven't plugged it into the main since I received it. So
Um i've been playing with it on and off during the day
I've probably
Well, I don't know how long we've been sat here this evening. So it's done several hours and yeah
It's about half halfway exhausted at the moment. Well, congratulations. So, you know
Now kind of so this is where I started thinking about this on the high end
You have these athena's bonobos orx pros these real desktop killers
They're they're not super portable but they can get you a few hours
They can move they can move you between your different work spots and then on the other end
You now have very efficient performance and capabilities from something like the nuke skull canyon
So compare and contrast those two machines for me wimpy. Do you think uh, when you look at the two spectrums there?
Is there less and less of a role for you with a traditional desktop tower that you assemble and you put together or you buy?
pre-built is there
Where's the tower fitting in?
Well, the the tower computer that I bought in 2008 is one of the boxes that i've sold in order to
Make the funds available to buy this computer
So that that computer back in the day in 2008 was a dual quad core xeon with 32 gigs of ram
Uh, and it had two nvidia something or others in it at the time
Um, so that was a fairly stonking machine when I bought that and that just about expired in time
It was still worked, but it was it was you know, breathless
Um doing gaming for example
So i've sold that and it was massive and it had a 750 watt power supply
um, and the by comparison the skull canyon nuke
Um is about three times faster than that quad core xeon from 2008 in terms of cpu
performance
And this this uh box had an nvidia when I sold it had an nvidia
680 in it
And the skull canyon nuke with its iris pro 540 could outperform it
Um on 3d as well, you know for gaming and what have you, you know, isn't that something?
So i'm using nux so I bought a nuke back in november which i'm very happy with and i've still got
And the only reason I got the skull canyon nuke is because i'm about to replace
My plex server and I thought i'd buy a nuke to be the plex server and i'd plug external drives into it over usb3
Okay, because i'm trying to find smaller form factor lower power
Um solutions and then I thought huh? Well i've got this nuke
and it's really
Beefy and then I saw the skull canyon was coming along
So what i've done is i've bought the skull canyon to become my new
New desktop workstation and my old nuke which is only six months old is going to become the plex server nice
Um, but the reason I like the knucks is they're so small. Um, i've now mounted my skull canyon nuke onto the back of my monitor
So everything's now behind
the screen
And because I i've got hubs and stuff built into the screen, you know, it's just tidy, you know, I had this massive
sort of 40 kilo
Mm-hmm
Del precision workstation. Yeah, and it's got bricks in it. Yeah, and and now it's this tiny little device and uh,
It's it's great. Uh, so I really like the knucks. They're great workstations and i've the one laptop i've kept is my apollo
So I still have my apollo
and that's my
lightweight i'm
going out so
Those are people that know me sort of see me in real life
Uh, I have a habit of going to do coding in the pub
um
So, um, I I I take myself away for sort of a couple of days
And I go and camp out in a in a pub and just sort of have a one-man sprint
um, and that that apollo is the computer that comes with me and it's great for a one day, you know
You can go anywhere, you know, the battery's going to last you can get stuff done. It's lightweight. It's easy to carry
but when I go away for a bit longer
And i'm going to probably work on different things
I want something a bit more powerful one of the reasons i've got this machine is because I run lots of virtual machines
So i've got the disk space for that now and i've got the ram and the cpu for it
Yeah, we were talking about snaps earlier
when you build snap packages on your own machine, you can now do that by um
Um building them inside, uh lxd containers. So each build is isolated and clean nice
But you can also build simultaneous snaps
different snaps simultaneously
So if you're working on several projects, you could actually have three or four snaps building
So another reason for this machine is that I can have all the cores that workload. Yeah. Yeah, of course
cool wimpy well congratulations and you know, I
As somebody who recently just got a semi-upgraded desktop here in the studio
Uh, I I feel like desktops aren't going away from me for a long time. I want capture cards
I want multiple drives cooling
but I think and I would be curious really to get the audience's reaction to this is
If we remove ourselves from the equation and we you know, we just like if you're looking at a chart
You know, we just chop off our our percentage
How many people realistically that are buying computers say?
From best buy or going into costco are really going to want desktop towers for much longer
It seems like that's a dying breed just and it's not to be the not to be the uh, not to use the steve jobs analogy here
But it really does seem like cars versus trucks. There's going to be a lot less people driving trucks
Um, and I don't think they're going away
But to that end I think one of the hazards of it becoming a smaller and smaller market is the components are becoming crappier and crappier
Yeah, and when you build, you know when you buy when you're trying to build multiple machines and you're buying all the parts
Most the parts are bad. It's it's becoming more and more of a commodity or i'm sorry
A niche market and the parts are becoming more commoditized in the val and the um quality is going down
For for the uh, enthusiast market and that's sort of the downside of it all
So that's why I think when you have companies like entryware and companies like system 76
And you have dells out there that are shipping linux rigs
It's nice to have a good set of answers now for pre-built machines where they're being the front line for that kind of problems
Uh, but there are still options for the rest of us. So my question to the audience is realistically
What's your over under?
What's your long shot on how much we have less left on desktop computing for average people linuxactionshow.reddit.com?
That's where you go to leave your thoughts. I won't be here next week, but mr
Noah will and they have plenty of good things planned for you
So if you'd like to help them put together a great show
You can submit topics to linuxactionshow.reddit.com vote them up and comment on them there
You can leave feedback at jupiterbroadcasting.com contact. Don't forget to join us live over at jblive.tv. We do the show live
Well, I I don't I assume you guys are doing it live at the regular time. No, but if you're not
Jupiter broadcasting
Two in the morning two in the morning great idea great idea. It's time. I'm kidding
Yeah, if that was everybody that shows up at two in the morning
No, and we apologize already check the calendar jupiterbroadcasting.com
Calendar, otherwise it's out for download later on in the week
And don't forget your stickers at jupiterbroadcasting.com stickers, and i'll see you back here in two weeks
So
There we go, there we go, there we go
Oh, this is that was it with no music that was it and we're not doing the west
You missed but we're not doing the music live anymore for a little bit. Okay, which is hard for me. It's hard for me
That's weird. Why I I tried to convince him west
I was telling him if he just put the theme song in telegram, then he could play it to himself sure your phone sure
Yeah, that makes total sense. Oh, yeah, I would like that too. JBtitles.com here. I'll show you west
I'll tell you why JBtitles.com JBtitles.com everybody go vote
Uh, so here's the thing west as noah would say is uh now no you won't be able to hear this because i'm playing
This on the computer that you're connected to academy. Okay, so uh, prepare yourself for silence. No, i'm I apologize about that
But let's see. This is going back to 150
Right. Uh, so here we are west. This is you and me commuting about a kickstarter
5000 so they're they're they're scratching some itch but it's yeah, it's essentially a read only live gnome desktop
With a decent gnome theme. Yeah, I mean it doesn't look you can hear it
You know
Why is it a keyboard as well?
It well because then it's the tamper proof device where it freaks out when it gets broken. Yeah
You know what guys this is what it tells us. It doesn't matter about the technical. All right
So here we're about to start the intro music now
We didn't hear this live west during the show but in post it's obvious. Here it comes
What it does tell you is that we are in the wrong business
This is linux unplugged episode 150 for june 21st, 2016. I see what you mean
Yeah, it sounds horrible
That's rough
Yeah, so we're just gonna play it in post and then there'll be no processing of it
So, you know, I think what it is when we try to level out all the different mumble levels
I think it just butchered the mosaic right that makes sense. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. All right jb titles.com
Um
Let's go boat
Universal package paradigms not just a packaging solution snap a packet ship it. Can we do three weeks of packaging?
I don't know if we can guys
Universal divide that's not bad. Love packaging. Oh, dude. We love it
Love it. Noah is number one intro where pub laptop going full intro where the red hat summit
cross packaging solutions
I think uh, I think uh
I think I owe no apology because I upset it as I upset him when I talked bad about his bay
I am sorry. Noah. I didn't mean to make you upset
Uh my apologies. Here's the thing. You just you you said something incorrect and I and I corrected
You have the right to be incorrect this is america, okay. All right good good good
Yeah, all right. So that's it. That's all it was fuck the eu what don't say that
uh, I say balder dash jb titles.com jb titles.com
I
experienced life in freedom
I don't know about universal package paradigms
I don't I don't know if I want my last show before vacation being about being titled about packaging. I just
that feels like a
A failure on my part like I didn't show up for duty
Although we did have a good organic discussion about it. They're fools
Yeah, jb titles.com. No, I've you gone do you see when you like what about you?
Did you see when you're like, thanks for making it west. Where are you right now? Where are you?
I'm at the beautiful east hotel in downtown portland
downtown portland, I I I I just
You know last I heard you were just uh rubbing elbows with linus. So
You know, we're just best buds now. He's a very nice guy face to face. I heard you were making him breakfast
He loves his eggs bacon and turkey toast. He made fun of my suit
Yeah, that's true. That is true. Yeah, that is that is that is noah's experience with linus
Yes, yeah
I was at the next one and I was there a client had paid for for my trip down there
And and paid for the hotel and everything and um, and so I was representing them
I was in a suit and I was with there's other people there from the company
And and I walked up met him and shook his hand got my picture and he's like
Why are you wearing suit kind of like that's amazing. Yeah, he's like you shouldn't wear a suit
This is this is you're the only person here wearing a suit. That's that's very strange
I don't know why you'd wear a suit here and i'm like not because other people because the company wearing suits
So he questioned your linux like credentials, basically
Yeah, exactly that's rough man, that's right I got a chip on my you could never make a curl yeah
Yeah, yeah, which I mean is true I couldn't either but whatever
What do you guys think of universal divide?
You like that? I like the universal divide. Yes, i'm voting for it. I just voted for it. I think now it has 11
Okay. No, it's just the chat room. Shout out
No chat room. Shout out right here
There you go, let's shout out
Okay. Yeah, that's way different noah is chat room. Shout out in the drop box. Uh, well the soundboard no
Yes, well, probably everything's in the drop box at some place
Okay, maybe the soundboard's right here on the machine. But yeah, I don't know about i'm sure it's in there
Okay. Yeah, you're welcome x metal. You're welcome. That was a literal shout out. Yes
I do it for you guys because you guys are voting over at jbtitles.com
So universal divide looks like it's our winner. Yep. Sounds good. Okay guys. Well, thank you for being here
I appreciate it very much. Uh, chris i'm gonna miss you in a whole week for several without seeing you
Oh wimpy wait you had intro where news that I missed what was that?
Oh, well, they were listening live, uh, and they were just saying that the european shipping stuff is is about to launch any day now
So, uh if oh
If you're from europe and you can hear this coming soon coming soon including keyboard options. Hey
very nice
All right. Well everybody's for them. Everybody treat noah nice
He may or may not be in studio next week for that
I think we should switch them up server two or three times maybe
Yeah, no, no, I changed the website that'd be good address actually
All of that's actually happening between now and the next show so
The mumble server's changed we got to shut down the old mumble server and the website's moving this weekend. So
You're welcome though
Uh, no the site the site for the null server's done. Yeah
The transfer for the old thing's already done
remember
Make jb great again. Noah. Okay, that's your mission, you know, here's my mission
Here's here you're gonna start a new slogan
I'm gonna get you a hat and a flat brimmed hat and everything and it's going to say
Screw it. We'll fix it in post or no. No, no, no, no screw it. Somebody else will fix it in post
No, come on, you know me I do
Out of all the people on the network i'm the guy that least puts it on rika to fix it because yes
You know unless it's comcast
Yeah
Well on the other point the other point of view i'm just saying there might be other people on the network that are worse
About it. Welcome to bsd unplugged. I won't call out names
But there may be people on the network. This is bsd unplugged
They expect a lot done in post and it's not me those bsd guys don't know how to make anything
What how did you know it was them? I didn't say anything what what?
All right, we gotta get out of here. Thanks you guys I gotta go
Uh, thank you very much. Have a wonderful vacation. I will enjoy yourself and relax. I will thank you
Network will be fine. Yeah, wait now I thought it was until you said that now i'm worried out of here
Get out of here. Okay. Bye guys
Bye. Bye noah. Thank you. You're a darling. Bye. Bye now. You're the best assist. Enjoy the rest of your craziness
Thank you for making it noah hugs and kisses
Yeah, hugs and kisses. All right. Bye