it's called slap and it's a sublime like terminal based text editor so yes sublime
text comes to your terminal I think it's actually I don't know it does I think
it's actually a pretty beastie installation because it runs on I think
it runs on node and you have to install it using npm but it didn't try no I
wasn't I wasn't I wasn't actually compelled but I don't know is a big
sublime text fan so I sent this over to him this morning to give us his full
review isn't that funny like I think for some people the you know if you're if
you're a javascript dev then it's a it's probably like a super easy installation
for you that's a good point this beer is delicious West I know right I was
surprised it is really good oh it's a blonde ale yeah for an easy beer in the
in a warm afternoon mm-hmm all right I want the West take on the VR
backpack it's a PC that doubles as a backpack for VR but then you can put in
a big old docking station whoa it's a desktop PC HP is making this thing what
do you think of these backpack PCs have you seen many of these so my first worry
what if you're walking uphill you're working up a sweat on a sunny day is
that going to ruin the PC water damage yeah I mean yeah yeah well I think they
envision like you're in the living room still it's for VR but without having to
have all the cords all over right I I actually think it'd be awesome is like a
live stream broadcaster like put put Linux on this put OBS on this connect it
to some LTE modems and now you got yourself a portable broadcasting machine
on your back seems like it'll all come down to weight distribution and heat you
know like is it comfortable to wear can you do it right multiple hours right it
could enable citizen journalism in fact if you built an LTE modems into this
thing I mean I enable citizen journalism with like a pie and cell phone to just
yeah Nexus 5 well I guess you don't really need a PC you know what they ought
to do you know they ought to do us they ought to just make the VR headset
super-powerful here's an idea why don't they put a PC in a headset that's crazy
talk or I was thinking like it what's the size like on this can you get
smaller could we get like a knock and then one of the little things that you've
just duct-taped on your the back of your shirt yeah it's got a 1080 graphics card
it's got the Kaby Lake a7 processor you got to buy the dock separately the
dock is $600 on top of a $2,500 computer and I'm sure that dock works with all
kinds of other systems you're like yeah I'd say that's definitely future-proof
look at all those ports I see three I mean how could you not buy this with all
of those killer VR apps this is Linux unplugged episode 200 for June 6 2017
welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's been going for
200 episodes strong my name is Chris my name is West hello West I don't think
we've missed an episode I don't think so we've had like some holiday specials
yeah flashbacks oh absolutely this week we're postpone we're perspiring for
perspirating perspiring perspiring conspiring and postponing it is getting
a little warm here we're gonna hold off on the 200th birthday celebration for
July 4th more about that in a little bit instead after we get through kind of a
shorter compact amount of project updates and stuff we're gonna do a love
letter a love song and maybe maybe a maybe a little more they'll tell you
more about that for gnome 3 I'm you know I'm loving gnome 3 I think it's a great
desktop and we're gonna cover some ways you can make it better and why I'm
pretty positive on the future of the gnome shell some things that are coming
up very soon to gnome at things that are long long down the road but I think are
gonna have great long-term impacts in fact one of them is developing even
today as we go on the air so we're gonna cover things to make known better for
you today even if you're not a gnome user please stick around as after we get
through the updates because I kind of want to just show you how the other side
is living this week better or for worse we want to get your feedback on that and
then we'll talk about sort of where GTK is going where the gnome shells going
improvements to mutter GTK for and a company out there that's making some big
hires that could have big long-term impacts on the direction of no so 200
a packed episode a packed packed episode and before we go into it too far you
know we have one thing we got to do every single week we got to start it we
got to start right here sometimes I like to wait a little bit but I'm feeling I'm
feeling in the community spirit time appropriate greetings virtual log
greetings so we have we have the virtual lug joining us every single week but to
celebrate our 200th episode on July 4th on America's birthday now known as
Linux own plugs birthday we're gonna have a virtual lug barbecue the virtual
lug becomes real at least some of us yeah yeah way it's official the meetup
is set up you can find it at meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting if you can
make it we'll be cooking and grilling and sous vide all the things yeah yeah I
think my lady will be here is that right yeah idea will make it the kids will be
here this could be a lot of fun I think Angela's gonna make it so you are you
are also welcome to bring a significant other or or somebody else we won't say
no yeah what happens at the studio it stays that's right that's right it's
like mini Vegas right here so meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting that's
when we're gonna be celebrating our 200th episode but since we're not doing
that today we have some work to get done oh we got some really really great
information in an interview that happened over at Engadget or no I'm
sorry ours technica with folks on the Android project they talked to Android
execs Dave Burke and Stephanie's yacht kubertson I you know what I shouldn't
have even started nope I shouldn't have I'm trying to learn just Android execs
just yeah and I could have just left it at that nobody would have cared no it
would have been fine but I just kept going you'd think I haven't been doing
this maybe 101 you'll be oh my gosh anyways you don't care about half the
stuff in here I'm betting unless you're a huge Android fan and you're probably
listening to different podcasts if you are or additionally but there was
something in here that was really good and juicy for us Linux users they talk
in here about the really freaking old Linux kernels and if you have not
listened to a recent episode we've kind of gone over this a little bit current
Android pixel the one that like Wes has got there is that in his pocket it is
shipping with a really old version of the Linux kernel one from 2014 and that
was an LTS kernel which is no longer being maintained by Greg KH pointed he
made on Greg is a point he made a lot of noise about in fact he even did like one
more like sympathy release of patches because he knows so many Android devices
oh yeah 3.18 dot 31 yeah which is no longer getting support upstream so
Google is now essentially running a unsupported unmaintained version of
Linux kernel and hopefully back porting fixes I mean it works so well for my
router Chris I thought maybe on the phone it would be good too of course and
this is by the way best-case scenario this is on the pixel so if you got like
a Samsung s6 or something in your pocket I'm betting it's even worse and so
rightfully so rightfully so ours asked them about this and they say what is
your thinking about the Linux kernel you ship a super old one right now from 3
dot 18 that's from 2014 what are you gonna do about this you're stuck
maintaining this until 2019 because the pixel yeah and and so Burke comes right
back and says well we have 4.4 working internally now here's the problem with
4.4 is that means they're not shipping it yet it means it might be shipping on
the next Android device possibly that's a possibility the next official Google
Android device but if they don't have shipping now that's not that's not very
4.4 is already getting old yeah and it's maintained until February of 2018
Google wants to provide three years of security updates so it's gonna have to
maintain kernel 4.4 on its own from 2018 for basically the beginning of 2018
until 2020 it's a long time so even though they're just so we it's great
they got 4.4 internally but it's it's like not enough too little too late it
is I think a big problem and I think it's one that could really kind of bite
them in the butt especially because what's holding them back isn't their
their effort or their enthusiasm for it it's silicon manufacturers and this if
you recall goes back to project treble yeah where they're trying to abstract
away the hardware manufacturers so they say take the pixel for example it's a
Qualcomm device so we have to stick with what Qualcomm supports now we're gonna
try to be more prescribed about which kernel version you have to ship with a
new device and we're going to work with the Lenaro community where's my bell
that's a key that's a key point the Lenaro community that is an
organization in group that is structured in kind of like two main
parts Lenaro is for my understanding and this is my rough understanding is Lenaro
has a has a core fork of the company that's super focused on Linux kernel and
drivers and Linux core subsystems on ARM then they have another fork of the
company the second branch of the company which is really focused on ARM chips you
know the whole system on a chip ecosystem environment getting those
vendors to work with patents and licensing and all that stuff that's
that's my rough understanding of Lenaro so what they are planning to do from
reading this entire interview now I'm summarizing for you is they're planning
to work with Lenaro to essentially pick up Greg KH's work and Lenaro may become
sort of an extended LTS maintainer with their own fork of the Linux kernel that
Android is using and they say in the interview that they're gonna get more
directly involved with that interesting so we could have like an Android fork of
the kernel that gets maintained for an additional year outside of what the
standard I should be like pleased because I want more official or better
maintenance or more upkeep or to be like this feels like a compromise on all sides
mr. Veritunda you had a question about communities maybe moving to other
projects well it just occurs to me okay right that there are hold on say again
you cut yourself off it just occurs to me that there are already embedded links
projects out there like you know open wrt and LED project which have recently
merged again which already target no Android or sort of you know on
platforms I don't understand quite why okay everyone's trying to reinvent the
wheel okay when it comes to sort of like these kind of projects because I mean
you know open wrt very up-to-date with their lake of tunnels they get in lake
expects and they have a good ecosystem in packages and stuff so why can't they
base it around that well you know I don't think they're gonna base it on
open wrt that if they're gonna do it they do it something like a fuchsia or
whatever it's called their new the new OS that's not Linux based that they're
toying around with I think though the real answer is is that Android is just
simply its own beast now it's its own ecosystem it's its own everything it's
it's it is its own market force and so it just doesn't matter what you what
else is out there because it's so huge you you still enjoying the pixel are you
it's are you well I just heard a lot of questions about the WWC event and the
pre-show and I thought maybe Wes has been looking over the fence and you know
because I I look at these things and I I'm not gonna I'm not gonna go on some
sort of Android rant here but I find it a little disappointing I feel like
Google is a pretty big company with a lot of really smart people and I think a
lot of them get open source and Linux there I think you're right about that
yeah but yet it feels like they've really compromised on this stuff and
they just keep compromising on this stuff and I mean I would certainly say
it is not up to it's not it's not so far away but it's certainly not up to the
fit and finish of iOS or an iOS device for me that's okay the pixel is at the
point where it's like pretty much good enough in that like it's not ugly it
doesn't offend me to have in my pocket or carry around the performance is good
it doesn't bother me with lots of the old Android you know oh why is my app
just stalling or whatever so I don't see those things so it is like day-to-day
use cases the camera I like and it's fast so those problems are mostly gone
at least in my day-to-day uses yeah it doesn't have the kind of
seamlessness it doesn't have all the thought that's put into it obviously but
you're touching on something there at WWE I'm not I'm wondering are you an
Android user WWE yes I'm stuck on some older versions right now unfortunately
I think I'm on KitKat on my phone is your phone nearby because if you go in
today about I'd be curious and what do you think do you think like this stuff
like the kernel version on the phone and stuff is it just something that only
matters to me because I even understand what a Linux kernel is it maybe I'm the
only one that thinks this matters because it works right at the end of the
day it's a tool I think it matters because you want it to be secure I think
most people would want their phone to be secured in the most average of users
because of the ecosystem how people like the vendors are pretty much it's Google
works with these third-party vendors whoever it is that they're not in
control of it like Apple is they're the ones who are being bent over the barrel
and being told oh no we're not going to support this right there's no if all
calm says we're done they're done yeah exactly so it's like like I want this is
why I'm sad like a good to phone or edge or whatever didn't take off as well as
it should have because or in Firefox mobile sure yes and do well because we
were stuck with these companies that don't you know get that there are people
that want these phones either cheap secure ones or maybe they want a more
for a better one that's secure and it's not happening yeah I would I would love
so the pixel to me seems like a premiumly priced phone so I would love
if that meant you get premium and I would love it if it meant you got
premium security to how has there not been more of an enterprise angle here
to say that again run I said or reasonable security I mean the fact that
it's they're gonna update to that was released two years ago I mean you think
they're back porting right they're back porting fixes and whatnot well they say
that but we don't know yeah I mean and part of it is well that's a good point
like part of it is they're back porting they're back porting the big things that
they are aware of that doesn't mean they're getting everything I think it's
I think it's a little naive to assume that every fix makes it onto the bug
list and every security patch isn't just which isn't just considered a bug fix is
properly addressed in fact Linus himself says that he considers security fixes
and but and just like bugs to be the same kind they're the same level of fix
it they're just fixes and I wouldn't be surprised if that mentality isn't a bit
pervasive and so sometimes things that might be a little iffy on the
security side are just marked as a bug fix nobody notices because the
developers himself found it or herself found it makes the fix submits it it
gets accepted and it's patched and it just rolls out the next version of the
kernel and because there was never a CVE attached to it it means that it just
sits there rotting in these old kernels right I mean it's like it works okay I
guess if you have the you know just update your kernels which I think is
pretty much what the kernel community would tell you right just update your
kernel we try hard not to break things update your kernel that doesn't work
when you have based your project on this 14 relationship so ww's on 3.4 kernel
3.4 ouch I have an Android 6 I think that's not super old but it's in there
it's getting there now well I also have a Nexus device so I you know the fact
that I'm and I think it's some like probably six months or so they said
they're gonna just continue my device entirely so that's fantastic oh wow yeah
I so very tune do you think it's kind of a shame that Android isn't known for one
of Linux is better traits which is supporting older hardware yeah there you
go you're good you're good you just got to hold down that push to talk you're
good you just got a hold of that yes okay so the like I said okay I mean
Linux is pretty much well known for running on old hardware and you know
even if you go back to sort of like the the kind of last incarnations of you
know PCs ten years ago you can still run a pretty modern kernel on that kind of
hardware you try and do that on a phone not a chance because you know for one
thing here are the hardware match actually stand up start to update the
drivers to fix you know new problems Carol and new systems or anything like
that so I don't know what's going on with that yeah it is it is a bit it's a
bit of a shame you know that's a bit of a downer let's talk about a part of a
solution this is just a natural segue it's ting I mean really a part of it is
the carrier there and ting is a mobile is mobile in a totally different it
totally different light it's a much simpler approach it's a much more
understandable way to do mobile and they don't have like this huge branding
strategy where they need to integrate in a certain part of their branding to the
phone which holds up releases they just they don't even play in that arena
that's why I love ting those are the top features for me but what really draws
people in is the way that the payments system works so it's it's just six
dollars for a line just six thought so you want two phones you want one phone
okay it's six dollars one second phone six dollars you want third phone six
dollars really simple and then you're just your usage on top of that so your
minutes your messages and your megabytes and it's really clear and you often the
average ting bill for a line is like 23 bucks they have nationwide coverage
there's no contracts there's no real determination fees you just pay for what
you use they have a very very well built control panel they have a full range of
devices or you can bring your own CDMA or GSM you pick and if you bring one
they'll just give you a service credit which probably pay for more than your
first month they have such great customer service too and check out their
blog as a small business owner who uses ting I got to say it really does work
well for a small business and they've been featuring a couple of different
businesses recently I I probably would say I encourage family plans Morris you
know if you got kids or people you just want to have several people or in my
case when we had a nanny for a while we actually got her a phone so we always
knew we'd have good reliable communications with her when she had the
kids and to us that was worth the six bucks a month and now you look at it and
I'm now I think about it so much more as a business owner about how I can when we
have events and things like that how I can use ting and they actually just
highlighted a lavender farm oh yeah business pretty cool you can get
started by doing us a favor visit linux.ting.com linux.ting.com take $25
off a device or get a service credit and then visit the blog and read around if
you even if you're not ready to switch yet check out all the stuff just so you
are familiar with so when that time does come and it will my friend you will be
ready you will be prepared linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for
sponsoring the unplugged program linux.ting.com little community service
announcement before we move on because I've seen a few people getting caught by
surprise your old version of Skype that you've been hanging on to clinging on to
version 4.3 yeah the cute version of Skype is being retired before our
barbecue on July 1st 2017 well it goes away no more Skype for you you will not
be able to use it you must switch over to the new Skype for Linux beta which I
think as we record right now is at version 5.3 it's really getting pretty
good actually yeah I was gonna say what do you what do you think about I know
like there were some early issues we had here in the studio with it you tell me
you've been using it now for weeks on tech snap working pretty good yeah it
really does seem to be the video picture seems fine the audio quality seems
pretty good I haven't had any crashing or it seems like much better than it was
when the beta first launched and it's nice that it has you know the Linux
hopefully this time around there you know it feels like they're doing Linux
with Linux in mind from the get-go so hopefully we won't end up with like oh
yeah never mind you'll never get updates again yeah I know the word on
the street is is that that that Linux client is the new Skype for life like
all platforms guys see that they're treating it seriously yeah so it is
actually pretty decent the thing is is there's they really they have no choice
because all the competitors are getting pretty damn good too and WebRTC is maybe
yeah thing now yeah WebRTC is looking pretty good like Jitsi is is great I use
that a lot for guests yeah because I can just send them a URL and Skype really
has to up their game that's pretty much what it comes down to I have I'll leave
this more as a resource linked for folks in the show notes but I hear this
question a lot what's the difference between Google Chrome and Chromium on
Linux specifically like why do I want to run Chrome over Chromium or do I maybe
want to run Chromium for privacy reasons so I guess the main difference is just a
couple is colorful logo on Chrome blue only logo for Chromium obviously user
metrics are sent if they're turned on report crashes are sent if they're
turned on out-of-the-box video and audio codecs for Chrome are AAC, HD64, MP3, Opus,
Theora, Vorbis, VP8, VP9, and WAV. It has the sandbox to PP API non free flash
plug-in which they maintain it's code tested specifically the sandbox is
turned on by default single deb and RPM package and it stores them in slightly
different locations because one's called Google Chrome and one's called Chromium
the major differences on the Chromium side so here's what you don't get by
using Chrome you don't get HD 64 out of the box it's dependent on your distro it
does support the Netscape API and those are unsandboxed which is how it runs
flash which means it's a little more dangerous version of a flash living on
the edge it's quote-unquote considered maintained by distributions not by
Google directly and the sandboxing depends on the distribution you can go
to about colon sandbox to confirm if yours is on or not pretty much
configures that in the same save in the same place except for the folders hold
Chromium also you don't get that colorful logo right new only and maybe
the other big thing is is the new releases are and testing are depending on
patched up by the distro right which is kind of a big difference whereas when
you install the deb or RPM of Google Chrome it adds a repo and then you get
updates from the gooks I end up running Chrome myself I just go straight Chrome
I have Chromium like over here on a system I don't use a lot it's not like
one of my mains my mate like the soundboard system right here I have
Chromium on that but this system that I'm here presenting I want to make sure
that HD 64 and a AC work that's kind of if it's just a browser because hey I
might need to look up something on Stack Overflow works just yeah so I just wanted
to pass that along so that way you guys would just maybe could reference this or
reference that link in the show notes that people ask you because I get the
question at time yeah you know the Google GOG they're not good old games
anymore they're having a sale the AI war fleet command is the one I picked up
today it's pretty cool-looking game it's like this you you have a whole
bunch of bots and you send them to fight off against each other and it's that
sounds fun it actually it was but you're telling me there's a Linux oh oh my god
jeez good old games autoplay fail oh sorry guys if you didn't just so you
know that hurt me more than hurt you this is oh yeah oh yeah full-on full-on
Linux support $1.99 right now for some of these games it's like some of these
games are 80% off or something that's why I mentioned it it's their summer
sale going on right now okay I'm gonna have to take a look after the show no
sponsorship intended no no what is it called no product placement this is just
the loose of the game I picked up this morning before the show and it looks
pretty good and with that big old sale going on it's kind of neat it's kind of
neat they have a whole bunch of other stuff on there too so yeah $1.99 crazy
$1.99 you can't go wrong with that can't go wrong with that all right mr. West we
are gonna be talking about gnome a lot today that's kind of what I wanted to
make the bulk of this show about was just so we had an episode that was just
sort of dedicated to this where the title kind of matches with the contents
about assuming we have a gnome title you can do it guys hint hint hint hint
hint so this is one of our last community updates for the week before we
get into the gnome topic and that's just because it sort of segues us perfectly
into it there is a collaboration going on right now at canonicals office in
Taipei where gnome developers and Ubuntu developers are in attendance and
they're working to greatly improve gnomes high DPI support oh so hot damn
if canonical hasn't even yet shipped an Ubuntu based desktop and they're already
I mean this is the exact kind of collaboration I wanted to see yeah when
Ubuntu switches to gnome and they're working on something called a
fractional scaling which is more like how unity and I think elementary OS is
Luna desktop instead of just like one or two you can have like in between there
yes exactly and it kind of requires a whole reworking our gnome supports one
to one and two to one scaling only and on multi monitor systems is the same DPI
scaling across all displays which drives me crazy and so it's annoying some of
the issues this hack fest is aiming to fix is to support different fractional
scaling values in mutter and gnome shell by upscaling the widgets and then
downscaling to the requested value at the compositing time so they want to
draw shell you at a higher resolution they're going to draw the UI for the
shell at a higher resolution than what the logical pixels correspond to then
they'll do non integer scaling adaptations and they're also working on
ex whale and client support to a degree so I I'm I'm really really really happy
about this because this particular type of high DPI support is really sort of
next-level high DPI so yeah and this is one area that I would like I mean it you
know it impacts buying decisions it impacts how I want to build system oh
yeah sure so that's good really change a lot of stuff yeah and so there's more
info in the blog post at the blog.nome.org site that we have LinkedIn here
for the developer who's going a really cool to see this happening also crazy
the canonical as offices in Taipei yeah they're just all over the place today I
learned today yeah indeed so that's pretty neat and when when do we see the
fruits of that labor who knows who knows maybe that but maybe that'll get things
a little bit just a little bit closer so that way your terminals look even better
I actually can't need those sexy terminals I actually kid but you know
the the high DPI terminal that's no joke that is that is no joke Wes you know
you're a gnome user right that's right okay so let's let's get let's get ready
to talk about gnome because I I have many things to discuss here and the
future looks bright Wes is running the gnome shell I'm running the gnome shell
live in person we probably have some people in the chat room and in the
mumble room running the gnome shell maybe you at home are running the gnome
shell that's so exciting so let's take a moment and thank DigitalOcean for
sponsoring Linux Unplugged digitalocean.com and use our promo code do
unplugged do unplugged one word after you sign up then you get a $10 credit
and you can deploy a rig on their infrastructure in no time spin up a
Linux rig and Ubuntu Fedora Debian CentOS core OS free BSD all with SSD
performance regardless of which one you get a simple intuitive API lightning
fast networking highly available block storage and now check this out cloud
firewalls you will have a central location to define access rules and
apply them to all of your droplets they will enforce these rules on the network
layer in their data center unauthorized traffic will never even reach your
droplet I like the sounds that is so cool digitalocean.com create an account
sign up use our promo code do unplugged you apply that then you get $10 and you
can play around with that $5 rig two months for free do unplugged over at
digitalocean.com let's start with my favorite gnome
extension getting a really solid update this is the one that I think everybody
who starts installing a gnome extensions installs this one and I want to
actually maybe stop for a second because I know I just realized I'm gonna get
flamed but yes I I'm this is gonna come across as like hey load your gnome
system up with all these extensions and have that at Haas just go crazy this is
a disclosure here the Linux unplugged show recommends that you have a balanced
diet approach to your extensions don't overdo it moderation is key people we're
just gonna give you some cool ones right here off the top we're not advocating
you run a thousand extensions and a lot of you plasma users will probably be
laughing at us as we do this but so dash to dock is a very popular gnome
extension maybe the most popular that takes the favorites and puts it as a
dock a persistent dock that can hide well version 59 which is available right
as we go on the air has added multi monitor support boy we're getting real
folks yeah multi monitor groups now it's just the same damn dock on each screen
right now but there are a couple of nice things there's also improved high DPI
support ding ding ding ding and if you're not using something like the app
indicator extensions that puts them up in the by your clock if you're like you
still have that little tabby default gnome thing where all your tray icons go
they've specifically built in some smarts to to make sure that they're not
blocking that anymore so dash to dock solid extension you already knew about
gets a pretty good update so go update now let's start with something new that
maybe you haven't seen big props to Joey over at OMG Ubuntu for just really
killing it yeah dude is recognized a need for a gnome coverage and is
killing it arc is a new applications menu for gnome shell so not everybody
likes the activities overlay this fixes that arc menu is an alternative app
launcher for gnome shell replaces the activities button the top bar with a
traditional start menu style launcher and it works nicely with things like
dash to dock and panel extension what happens when you super key does it does
it can I still type to complete that's what I want to know I think so although
the big thing I miss from other versions I don't know see for me I'm not big on
this is being existed in an extension I will not be installing yeah I like just
that yeah super key to type three letters and launch I'm good but I want
you know this comes up because I'm kind of playing with like what systems would
I have for my mom right and so one of the problems I have I like the like
mate approach of you know explorable but it doesn't work well once they've
migrated to like they know the applications it's way too tedious yeah
they do need some I like that like I love that about the gnome desktop and I
don't understand why they chose arc as the launcher name it's a bad name it's
named it's good it's overlapping with the most popular gnome theme and I I did
some digging I can't tell I don't think the projects are related I don't know
it's very confusing very confusing this one's also gonna confuse a lot of you
xmonad awesome tiling window manager users out there g tile is an extension
for gnome that turns gnome when you want it into a tiling desktop and once it's
installed you click a little tile icon in the gnome menu up top you'll see a
little overlay come up with a whole bunch of squares the g tile overlay will
hover over an open window and then you can click one or more of the squares to
place the window in that area so it's like a grid the row of icons then
display the dimension control and the controls of the screener is titled right
there so you can see what the screen title is if you just want to divvy up
your screen into 16 equal chunks you can do that by choosing four by four the
really nice thing about g tile is you're not locked into tiling new windows
aren't automatically put on the grid boom and existing windows aren't locked
so you have the best of both worlds and that's one that I might actually end up
installing because there are times where I want to organize AF and then there are
times where I want to just be wild yeah that one's one of my favorites
especially because like the default of just left and right is not enough oh go
on yeah it's not worth even bothering oh really it's it if the reason to do
tiling is because you're you're using your keyboard g-tiles a hundred percent
miles controlled oh the reason I yes I guess I kind of agree the reason why the
reason why I like tiling though for me we just before organizing a whole lot of
windows and stuff right every time you every time you close that window or you
know the next day you open it it's not there that you the reason I do it is I
organize my tiling so that it the next time I load the application it's all
tiled together in the same way yeah g-tiles always you have to do it
manually every single time what I really want is I want perfect never fail
placement of my windows when I hook up my second screen I want I want all my
windows to go right back where I had them perfectly there's there is a an option
for people who want the tiling that does have features that are more like recall
into tiling this called a shell shape and it's not really an extension it's a
replacement for gnome shell so it's it's gnome shell but it's a modified gnome
shell to make this possible because the reason why g-tile doesn't have these
features is because gnome itself can't do the the full-blown structure based on
the way it's built well Michael you're a you're a you're a fan of the gnome
workflow so what is it about the gnome quote-unquote workflow that you try to
adapt over on the plasma desktop well I'd say the the the style of having
everything all in one so when you like the act the activities overview where
you have the windows and you have the the the top bar and the the dock and the
workspace I guess it's a dock to all that in one thing and also the flow of
having all the workspaces in a vertical structure rather than a grid yeah
because it's a lot easier to scroll up and down on your mouse or rather than
having a keyboard shortcut where you got to do the different arrows in different
directions and stuff you know there's that but the I don't know if you could
give the whole one-click button start searching for whatever you want as a as
a gnome thing I'm not really sure what started that just like a launcher thing
in general and krunner does a fair job of that I mean windows does that yeah so
yeah yeah when it's actually I know I think about it's probably when I give
the nod to quicksilver myself I think that's where it started was quick so
quick silver and then the gnome dude came over in synapse and yeah well
Windows Vista had it and now I think about it huh so what's older quick
silver somebody in the chat room go do some sleuthing online you what's older
the mag launcher quick silver or Windows Vista I wonder although Windows Vista
probably was in development before a quick silver ever hit the market so
there's that okay I've got I just got a couple more extensions unless would you
have any other workflow things well I mean the other thing is I do like the
dynamic workspace and that's the only thing that's not possible in plasma I
that would be really nice to have but as far as like the gnome workflow that is
really cool yeah yeah I do like to have workspaces as well there's there's also
this one more thing that has absolutely nothing to do with anything and it's
really the only thing that bothers me that I can't have on plasma there's an
extension in gnome called quick close overview and all it does is allow you to
middle click a window in the overview to like grid thing and just close it from
there and that is such a huge time-saver hmm you know what this is so stupid but
you know what I miss when I'm on plasma is none of the plasma applets whatever
they're called the check the Bitcoin price work they all just unfortunate and
I and right now it's just it's so much fun right there you're watching at it
it's fun I really that's the glint in your eye I really you know there's small
things about like I really like the top bar on gnome especially when I have the
top icons extension that way all of my system tray stuff is up there and then
it's the rest of the UI is completely just my my application I'm using full
screen I just have a very tiny thin bar with the time day an elegant little bar
I like it yeah especially what's very functional theme and then you hit you
hit the super key and you got a you got a pretty good built-in launcher they can
even launch things like the display control panel and stuff like that which
is between that and then like the improvements to dash to dock it's really
kind of the whole deal so quicksilver came out three years before Vista oh it
might be quicksilver then damn that is a long time ago yeah I'm surprised even
remember the name of it or surely someone will tell us about an obscure
window manager that was doing it totally I would think so let us really yeah and
the command line actually yeah right the original launcher I got one more
extension okay am I the flight I might have to and again I'm just telling you
these are this one kind of feels like maybe a lighter one that maybe wouldn't
wouldn't wreck things this is a Nautilus a git integration extension now hold on
don't get don't get excited what don't get excited it's not like you're not
checking in out of github with Nautilus here I actually think it's better than
that though it is instead a simple extension that just adds important
information about the current local git directory you're browsing so when you
browse into a git directory on your file system it gives you relevant things like
the git directory info the status of the git files you can open a remote URL you
can select a specific branch you can compare commits in Nautilus so this
again I the reason why I bring this up because I have this picture I have this
picture after going to Dell of developers that buy smart Sputnik laptops
by the millions to SSH into Ubuntu boxes and they're they're pushing and
pulling help me cloud github with their continuous integration and they're doing
all this stuff and now when they want to browse a local github directory they've
checked out they get a bunch of great additional information just overlaid
right into their file manager I'm gonna have to try this and because the damn
thing's not trying to be a whole github client it's not like it's some huge hack
in the extension it's just pretty simple information yeah wow it's pretty good
that's great I mean I know a lot of people get this kind of you know you
already have it maybe in your terminal and stuff so it seems super helpful yeah
yeah I think it's pretty nice it would be great if they added things like side
by side diff and there's PPAs out there if you're on the Ubuntu's and of course
it's up on the GNOME extension site and github and then ladies and gentlemen the
one that out of all of these I think I will be setting up for our studio
machines if they stay known is app folder management so this is an
extension that allows easy management of app folders directly from the
applications view that looks nice yeah so you can create folders and as a
bonus feature it's possible to change columns in the folder and stuff like
that so it's actually you can you get additional nice features but you can
create new app folders you get a nice dialogue to do it you can add those
applications with cool sub menus and stuff you can remove applications from
the folders you can delete the app folder and the files go the application
icons go back it's sort of like how on Android or iOS you can you can move all
of your launcher items into folders and it creates a dynamic folders and it kind
of seems like a obvious feature like I when I thought about this is like I was
kind of amazed that this isn't built in so this adds that a lot of the kind of
customization that you would probably assume that you do so here in the studio
I could do like you know we could have in one folder we could have the x32
mixer stuff you could have the Skype stuff the mumble stuff easy for me yeah
and we are back so no I'm just crashed on us that's kind of ironic I'm not
joking summary of the show folks this is a this is a bit of an awkward thing for
me right now this is my love song to gnome because I think it's such a great
desktop and I think it has such a strong future and yet I think I'm switching
away and I'm gonna be talking about that more but I just I want to continue
being positive about gnome but I do have to acknowledge that we just had to stop
broadcast and we had to stop and re-edit here and all of that because no crashed
on us again so we are going down a path but and this is a system by the way the
one that crashes the most is the system with almost no extensions just for the
record the only extension that has is dash to dock and the ping extension
yikes there you have it yeah yeah it's good times it's good times do any other
machines suffer from this in the studio we have three gnome desktops that crash
every day they're all similar hardware Nvidia arch core i7 like a generation
ago yeah it's happening quite a bit that's kind of wow yeah yeah that's a
bit of drag it really is like yesterday I was in the middle of working and so on
my system upstairs gnome crashes three times it crashed crashed crashed and the
reason I know is because I was looking at the log and looking at journal CTL and I
can see it crashing reloading crashing and then reloading and every time it
crashes I just get a segfault and then I then I get a whole bunch of like a
bunch of errors from extensions and I get a whole bunch of garbage from when
gnome starting up and looking for icons and loading caches and stuff and then
and then it dumps again and then it tries again dumps again and here it
seems to dump twice or something like I haven't quite because it's always when
I'm in the middle of like broadcasting so I don't like I don't study it like I
do at my workstation and then on Sunday before Linux action news I was just
sitting here nothing was happening on this computer in front of me with except
for Chrome but I wasn't even using the mouse or keyboard I was just sitting
here chatting with Joe before the next action news and it crashed on me that
sucks yeah so that's three different systems all with similar builds though
yeah I haven't seen very much of that but I don't have any Nvidia systems
running gnome right now or systems that are up for very long it's making me like
rethink like goes go minimal go small go go X F C E go L X D E just go tiny
desktop for the OBS machine because I just don't want that to be a factor
instability we wanted big like we have a lot of people that are you we have
different people some people use Linux more some people use Linux less they're
using all of these systems yeah and so we wanted something very approachable we
wanted something people who might be familiar with and so gnome shell seems
like a good idea yeah yeah and it's also my if I'm gonna use a Linux desktop it's
my preferred Linux desktop so if I gotta sit in front of a bunch of Linux
machines all there it just works yeah and then I'm comfortable and I'm quick
when I'm on air and my my my sort of muscle memory to use the computer I can
rely on that while I'm talking so I can edit something on OBS while I'm still
talking and I it it all changes when you're in a desktop environment you're
not super familiar with but I think the crashing it almost it almost impacts does
it hit tech snap yet oh it's you know maybe not it's almost hit every show
I've done I'm sure it will at some point this same machine before it was running
gnome ran for a year with I was gonna say yeah right and it's only been and
these the machines that are exhibiting crashes now it's only been with the last
couple of months because they too have been running gnome 3 on arch for quite a
while now so anyways yeah yeah there you go I guess that's all I have I don't
see oh yeah you're right beards totally right that's what I was thinking I was
getting confused because it's happened on this show multiple times yeah yeah I
couldn't quite but it did happen it did happen to text nap yes that's kind of a
trick it's kind of a trick and it's even with systems that are pre minimal gnome
shell desktops they're just kind of the stock basic stuff yeah yeah it happens I
guess it happens anyways we shouldn't let it drag down the show because there
is still actually a lot of really good stuff to talk about for gnome what's
coming up and things like that so you can find links to all the extensions we
talked about I think the the one that was sort of appealing to me a bit was
g-tile for light usage but I don't actually think I'll end up using it but
app folders the one we were just talking about app folders does seem like it
would be a good way to go especially if you have other people using your system
and if you are using get a lot the get integration stuff yeah I'm gonna give
that a try just because you know I don't know how much I'll actually use it but
it seems like it would be handy if I just happen to navigate into a git
folder why not now I'm gonna just toss randomly a topic bomb into the mumble
room there but does anybody else have like a gnome tweak or extension or
setting or something that they do for their gnome desktop that makes it great
and usable for them that you would want to pass along to somebody else trying
out gnome for the first time I got two real quick here I get caffeine should
probably be talked about caffeine is pretty useful yeah the other one that I
don't have installed now but I've used in the past is like it's one that just
installs a Wi-Fi refresh button it doesn't refresh when you open the list
of Wi-Fi those are two great ones caffeine keeps your system awake and
yeah the refresh button should just be built into gnome to refresh the Wi-Fi I
thought so I thought I might be heard something the moment yeah I was just
gonna say that I think auto move windows is an extension that's pretty
much vital for my usage okay I've seen that one a lot what does it do it allows
you to specify what applications which which workspace and a specific
application goes to do you get to say where in the window or is it just go to
workspace to but you don't get to say where in workspace to technically gnome
remembers where you want it if you have this like the location of the pixels
wise but it doesn't remember the workspace and this kind of makes it
combine the two the only negative thing it doesn't have is that it doesn't if
you have more than one monitor it doesn't remember the other monitor but I
think there are is someone else working on a different extension for that that
function okay I kind of like that when I have multiple monitors that my second
monitor stays static when I switch workspaces so I'll throw slack chat
telegram maybe a live stream I'm watching VLC something like that I'll
throw that on my second vertical screen and then I'm switching between four
virtual desktops on my main screen and the slack chats and all that stuff stay
persistent across those desktops lights I can definitely you know there are use
cases for both ways I think yeah oh yeah yeah yeah that's the hard part yeah
because you sometimes it is nice to have a separate that's all yeah yeah there's
one more it's the Maximus to extension it's a automatically removes a title
bar or you know the top part of the window when you maximize hmm nice oh
oh yeah okay okay make it a little tighter oh yeah so it like gives you
more more real estate for your window yeah yeah okay good one anybody else in
the number room have any other ideas they don't want to toss in for their
perfect gnome setup chaotic has a sound input output chooser that's a good one
yeah and that's really nice because you hit the menu and then right there in the
drop-down menu you can choose what your output devices and that's handy it's
really nice if you have like a couple of Linux systems of mine in the past when I
booted up they always defaulted to the HDMI audio out and so I always had to
just change that really quick and that drop-down makes that super easy now what
I want yeah exactly yeah one that I find quite useful is the num lock and caps
lock indicator on the top bar as well as my keyboard doesn't have that at all
doesn't so yeah I got a couple of keyboards that like smaller keyboards now
that I have that don't have any lights on them for what the keyboard and them
like yeah so that's a good one too yeah all right and then Yuri in the chat
room says that not only does he give a plus one to caffeine but the taskbar
which I played with a bit oh I have not yeah it's it's kind of nice to have a
taskbar so it just puts a really small taskbar of all your open windows across
all your desktops and it's nice but I find myself because I've used known for
so long now that I never click it I very rarely click it because if I really lose
a window I just hit the activities overview and I see everything and I feel
like it's it's one of those things where if you just switched from a desktop that
has a taskbar you're gonna be inclined to add it and you're just gonna probably
use it forever however if you sort of follow my take a balanced approach to
how many extensions you have I would encourage you to just try to follow the
workflow of gnome and maybe cheat by putting dash to dock on the side where
you can see dots for which apps are running back in my day we learned the
gnome workflow and we stuck to it you know I've said it I've said it a hundred
times but you know that's what happens when you have 200 episodes the way I
made gnome work for me when I first switched like back when 312 came out
yeah oh those were the days yeah that was like the note 310 3.8 310 and 312
were like okay no I'm starting to get no it's like where plasma has been now for
like releases and after release where it's just unquestionably getting better
and better and it's like features that you like every release has several
features you want and I decided at that point alright I'm gonna try to make a go
of this and what I'm gonna try to do is I'm gonna spend 30 days and every day
I'm gonna try to do something the gnome way that I was sort of resisting and I
that included trying it without maximize and minimize buttons which I decided
after trying that for a couple days wasn't for me but I gave it a shot yeah
but like the things I did get wrapped my head around was dropping the taskbar
using the super launcher and not like installing gnome do or synaptic just
like using the built-in note like using the multiple desktops embracing
maximizing my screens more than I used to I used to just have tons of windows
all over my screen and now I have one or two windows and then I then I switch
over to another virtual desktop and using some of the snapping out aspects
of gnome taking that 30-day quote-unquote challenge which was just
I was personally doing for myself made my process of adopting no more of an
adventure and it made tolerating the rough edges I felt at the time easier
because what's only for 30 days and but then by the time I got done with it I was
like oh shit oh no I'm actually working faster and better than I ever have on
the Linux desktop before oh that's what they were going for and then I was a
convert and it's really only been until recent stability issues and shell
performance issues that I've really been and obviously the constant improvements
of plasma and the great future of Qt that I've been drawn into the plasma
desktop more and more but gnome shell isn't sitting still no it's certainly
not I mean there's a lot of good things I think we'll both be very curious to
watch this Ubuntu canonical yes we already just talked about some of the
fruits of that labor already and there's other companies they're getting
involved with gnome that I think are gonna make a big difference we'll talk
about them here in a moment there's a big release of gnome coming up just
around the corner and there's an application that I think is gonna change
the ecosystem but first Linux Academy Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
that's where you go to support the show and sign up for a free seven-day trial
this is a platform that's being continuously updated and improved by
Linux advocates educators developers and now a whole team Linux Academy has been
growing and growing for years I think I think you know really it's been a sort
of a rocket ship because they're they're so properly addressing a large demand in
the market specific Linux training not just one of the things they cover it's
what they cover with hands-on labs scenario based labs that give you real
experience on real servers self-paced in-depth video courses on every Linux
and cloud DevOps AWS as your open stack containers security nitty-itty bitties
they got great courseware for all of it instructor mentoring for when you get
stuck you need some help they have real humans full-time staff members who are
there to answer your questions they have learning paths which are a series of
courses and content planned by instructors practice exams to help you
get ready for the big test study tools which are guides and lesson audio that
you can take with you and notes stuff you can download iOS at Android apps
which are great and flashcards that are forked by the community and that
community is stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged that's where you go to support the show sign up learn more
about any Linux topic and get a free seven-day trial linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged and thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Gnome Shell has a big release coming and on the road to that release we're
getting Gnome 3.252 it's the second milestone in the development cycle of
Gnome 3.26 which is the big one and is expected to launch around September 13th
the fall goes as planned now they've been doing steady improvements and
there's many things we could call out I'm just gonna call out a couple of
things because there's a lot that may or may not make it but what has landed is
mutter 3.252 and it's a big update to mutter it fixes some performance issues
not the big ones that I've outlined in user error but it fixes some especially
on non Wayland builds it improves copy and paste operation between the Wayland
and x11 display servers which is huge yeah and it fixes some glitches that
hoping that occurred when opening windows and maximizing windows under
Gnome and a few other issues that people have talked about including support for
other stuff so new mutter really great super excited about the new mutter
which will be landing in the new version of Gnome like I said there's gonna be
other stuff in Gnome some which may make it some which may not but it looks like
one that is gonna make it is a new Gnome disk utility this is great this is
getting to be a fully baked application now it's available for testing if you
want to try it and it's gonna bring a number of improvements under the hood
and cosmetically for example it offers a more clarified meaning of the
encryption settings and in mounting options well that's good yeah and it
implements an intensive autoclear switch for unused loop devices it also is going
to support different types of mime reading for disk so it can give you some
of the names and model types and information that's on there it's gonna
prompt users to stop running jobs that are running on devices before you eject
them which is really nice I'm surprised and do that before actually and it will
also have the ability to implicitly autoclear the handling for the lock and
auto mount buttons and also will have a new app menu entry that lets users
create an empty disk image adds a tooltip for the autoclear switch displays
the UUID of selected volumes by default and implements hints for your pass
phrase fields and removes the unused erase disk dialog this is like a usable
tool now yeah I've kind of avoided it just because I'm more familiar with
other tools and what not yeah exactly but hey yeah yeah it I've played around
with the current version a little bit before the show and they're really
they're really putting something that is confusing and difficult and they're
making it easy to use they're gonna make it easier to create blank images so you
can use the ad super helpful yeah you can use them for like as volumes to
store stuff you know put your porn in here put your home clips in here put
your documents in this one then lux encrypt them and now you have these lux
encrypted volumes on your on your system that you can mount and unmount easily
using gnome disk that's really neat isn't really neat so that's a gnome 3.2
6 if you're a gnome user is just looking like such a solid freaking release let's
talk about an app that I think is gonna help the whole gnome ecosystem yeah it's
called builder and you can find out more with the link in the show notes it's an
IDE for gnome that's focused on bringing the power of the gnome and GTK platform
to users and developers in a way that's never really been accessible before and
they're they're they're doing it in such a smart way so not only is the
development just continuing along at a pretty good pace with great features but
they're intelligently adding in support for new features of GTK when the timings
right they've got autocompletion for some of the favorite GTK languages the
things go like C C++ Python Vala rust those things that's awesome yeah so it
makes creating gnome desktop applications much more possible much
easier much more straightforward using a tool that's really really well supported
right now by no so that's gnome builder and I think it's gonna have a big impact
in the long term applications for gnome making them good like look at this this
it's basic but it's really nice it's got an integrated system-wide profiler for
performance along with like I remember when they launched it a couple years ago
and I was like okay great that that seems neat but boy like you know now
it's got performance profiling for your apps and stuff to might have to give this
a shot just yeah some Python because that's and mark down yeah oh mark down
and then I want to talk about a company that in some parts in some ways I should
say is a little mysterious to me and I hope to know more someday but they seem
to have a lot of passion around gnome and they have some funding and they're
making some hires it's endless do you remember endless oh yeah yeah the
creators of the endless computer with the endless operating system about this
a little bit mm-hmm yeah endless OS oh look look at this
way look at this we can explore we can you want to do what you want to explore
let's we can explore in English let's do that let's explore in English endless OS
is a free Linux based operating system that makes using a computer simpler and
accessible for everyone endless OS works easily from the moment you turn it on
just like a smartphone apps are open from the home screen with one simple
click endless OS is designed to be useful even when you're offline quality
content is always at your fingertips so you can find the information you need
when you want it there's an encyclopedia with over 50,000 articles plus tens of
useful information about parenting health culture and so much more there's
a built-in App Center where you can access over 100 applications and add any
favorites to the desktop the best part is they're all free and pre-installed
endless OS is a great tool for school work or home it comes with LibreOffice
completely free so you never have to pay for software licenses there's a word
processor for creating documents a spreadsheet app for budgeting and an
app to make clean and professional presentations you can also open and edit
Microsoft Word PowerPoint and so if you're watching the video it's kind of
obvious this is a gnome based desktop running on top of Linux and endless you
might remember them they had like the bamboo covered ducks remember seeing
those they have these endless computers they have this circular dome computer oh
yeah that's right yeah this thing that kind of looks like a subwoofer almost it
really and then they have mission the mission mini which is so cute yeah the
little okay I want it I kind of want it yeah and this is this is for a different
market than us like the mission of one is a $249 Intel NUC that's wrapped in
bamboo though I mean that's that's like the most badass looking NUC ever look at
run arch on that that's fine damn right so endless is doing some hires a long
time canonical employee Michael Hall recently left canonical Wow and I
believe has gone to endless and other individuals I probably should name have
also been contracting and working with endless several actually so they seem to
have some funding they seem to have some products they have a couple of deals
with a couple of different stores where they're selling this I think in
California in the store so you can just go into a store that's where they're
based out of okay well yeah I think they have two offices right now and they are
actively contributing my understanding upstream to know because they they plan
to base this thing around no and they plan to use flat packs to distribute
their software it could be it could be interesting because they are specifically
hiring people to work on the community and to work on the code of the gnome
desktop you don't often get a lot of companies that that do that for first
for an end user type like you'll get companies that want to improve the ARM
code or the power management but you don't all I mean not a lot these days do
we get companies that want to come in and specifically make the Linux desktop
better they they're trying to build computers for like the next billion
people essentially so you know they bit ambitious bit ambitious they they say
our team were small but global we were in 17 countries we have assembled a
world-class team across design software hardware and operations united one goal
to make computing available for users everywhere using Linux and gnome would
be a great way to do it absolutely yeah I'm I'm fast like the gnome you know it
seems like their their base is pure enough for this kind of thing like where
you can build on it and you can get something that's simple enough for
people to use especially with what we're talking about like the gnome the disk
manager things like that where we've been griping for a long time about like
yeah you know we don't have these features for things you've redefined
things you're building from the ground up now but maybe we're at the point
where what we what they have is like is it's really sound if I recall the idea
is that they're going to they're gonna deliver updates forever or something
like I can't remember why I can't remember what the endless part comes in
but yeah you could be right West I'm gonna you know what they probably say on
their website endless os.com if you guys want the endless OS comes with
everything your family needs there you have it can we get a clip of that yeah
could be right West just right there yeah it's pretty cool company and they
seem to be pretty involved with gnome so you you combine that now with things
like gnome builder and the path of GTK so I also thought maybe we'd talk a
little bit about GTK 4 which is oh coming down the road not it's not going
to be like a game changer like GTK 3 was from GTK 2 there's gonna be some things
that change right now they're at GTK 3.91 it's available that's going to
become GTK for the toolkit they have support for mac OS now GTK apps will be
a target mac OS probably a smart thing cuz cute can do it yeah totally and now
you can run on so now you build a run on Windows you can run GTK apps on a
Mac yeah there's a lot of other work they have queued up for GTK 4 which you
can follow up in the show notes if you want but it's it's actually just want
the cocoa apps on GTK right like that you know somebody needs to do the
reverse let's get some of the Mac apps on the Linux desktop yeah I either way I
think it's it's the future is bright if you look at GTK 4 they seem to be where
they really have their senses about where it's going like there's there's
some improvements there's some things they're adding like some nice Vulcan
support in there yeah I mean there's some good stuff but it's not like a
throwing everything away and we will have forks for a decade because of the
change it's not gonna be that dramatic yeah yeah it's gonna be Rick I says I'm
sure GTK on the Mac will be just as native as it is on Windows hey at least
you can run gimp on Windows it can happen and that's all that matters
that's all that matters I've used that really actually more times than I can
count so it really does it is actually quite useful yeah and you know I think I
think Apple killed off their X server a while ago and so did they think so I
just remember seeing it yeah so I think without this you wouldn't have a way
because you could always do X on the Mac and then run the GTK apps but now I
think with this this will solve that problem so future is bright not only for
GTK and GTK 4 but the future is also bright for the gnome desktop for the
companies you're getting involved you've got such this is such a debug term but
you have quote-unquote bilateral support if I could political term we have
bilateral corporate support for the gnome desktop we've already got canonical
working on ways to improve it you got system 76 working on ways to make it
more palatable to consumers you got endless working on ways to make it more
palatable to the next billion computer users gotta be endless yeah and they're
and they're hiring actual people and paying them to work on this stuff gnome
4 is just around the corner it's all pretty good it's all pretty good it's
happening it's funny it's like what kind of dick am I for now switching away
right but you're the gnome desktop Chris where are you I know it is the year of
the gnome desktop and I'm like all right well peace out guys thanks for all the
fish and I'll be over here in plasma land trying to make it as gnome as
possible this is the curse that you have bestowed upon yourself oh man I mean
what are you going to do are you go wait till Ubuntu comes out in October with
their gnome version and hope that doesn't crash get pushed to no man they
go yeah we'll take that or no it's gonna go no we're fine we're not gonna do well
like in the case of this fractionated coconut oil high high DPI scaling they
are it's a gnome developer and a canonical employee working together in
the same room and canonical you know has the nice thing about that is the guy
shared this on Google Plus canonical has a whole bunch of high DPI monitors they
can put in the room for testing which he didn't have access to so it's not like
they're just developing it in a in a in a in a room somewhere in some white room
and they're just gonna throw the coat over the fence they actually you know
have the guy on the gnome project working on this in their office so
that's like that's a whole new level of collaboration for them it really is it I
think the future is bright there maybe maybe I'll be back sooner than later you
know cuz this like this crashing problem if this went away the performance issues
I suffer with I feel like yeah you know what I could read I could reload the
gnome shell every few days easy enough right it's easy enough it's not ideal
it's easy enough but the crashing that's that's where I draw the line right that's
where that impacts business mm-hmm and so if but I but I am I am confident that
whatever it is it will eventually get worked out if it is an Nvidia bug issue
if it's a if it's a gnome issue if it's a will be green again some weird USB bus
issue for all I know it's weird that also when gnome shell crashes our audio
cuts out a little bit in OBS I don't know what that's about either way our
problem to figure out no one's making good progress so this is sort of my love
song to gnome as I begin to switch away for a little while I'm sure I'll be back
one day friend but thank you for all the great times gnome shell thank you for
all the fun extensions and the enthusiasm and energy around gnome shell
is higher than ever cool great extensions are being created that weren't around a
year ago Joey over at OMG Ubuntu is doing great write-ups making it clear
and easy how you get this stuff that he's talking about which is one of the
things Joey really excels at is he's like here's the thing that's really
great here's a few screenshots of it and oh by the way if you're on one of these
distros this is how you get it I love that I tried to do that too we have
links to everything we talked about in the show notes it is going to be the
note the year of gnome it really is so don't take my switching away as a sign
that it's it's going away and I'm condemning it I'll be back I'll be back
in the meantime I heard plasma 5.10 hurt hit the arch repo stable today oh boy
so all they got to do is go upstairs and update my system and I got plasma time
for Chris tries a tiling window manager all over oh don't start that again I
want to see this time on Wayland what about plasma desktop and window rules
maybe that'll just do what I want where it puts everything where I want I don't
know maybe I'm dreaming let me know linux unplug dot reddit.com don't forget
the barbecue is official meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting if you can
make it telegram group bit.ly slash JB telegram join us live Jupiter
broadcasting.com slash calendar. Wes say goodbye. Goodbye.
okay producer Michael did you leave or are you gonna can you break me the bad
news am I am I gonna be screwed with my dreams and hopes for plasma window rules
no that'll do it that'll do what I want good it's awesome okay good I think I
when I read your comment the chairman was like oh that might not be a good way
to go I said I was saying I do this okay awesome so like oh good good good window
rules is it's it's more complicated to set up but it is awesome so it's
actually you have to you have to set up individually so you set the window
however you want it and then you apply a window rule and then what the best part
about is that once you set it to however you want like regular just movement
moving around and stuff it's detecting what the current settings are so if you
try to just make a window rule in the system settings it's a pain in the butt
but if you do it from right clicking a title bar it'll give you an option is
like oh okay just activate this and whatever you currently have it will use
that setting okay so it's actually not that hard to do if you know what to do
in the right order okay but the other part is that plasma has built-in tiling
essentially it doesn't have the automatic you know it's gonna tile it
based on what people expect tiling window managers to do okay but it has
these shortcuts where you can do you know horizontal top and bottom the site
left left and right like people you know are used to it also does quarter tiling
so you know the bottom right tiling okay but none of that is none of that has a
shortcut by default the functionality is in the system it is there you have to
manually go and put what shortcuts you want that I've run into that before and
been confused trying to get those shortcuts right yeah what I do is with
my keyboard the it's perfect because the you know that the insert home page up
that little set of six things cluster I have I have a super plus the top left
like the insert key is top left of the screen tiling and then you know etc for
the rest of them and home and end or like horizontal tiling hmm it's like
what I do is set it up I want to can keep it however it is I just set it I
just use the shortcut puts it where I want and then use window rules to
remember it okay that sounds actually pretty maybe we need like a plasma 101
yeah I may if I end up switching to a few yeah I'm actually working on doing
that all right my idea is to like kind of how to use plasma and avoid the you
know the headaches of not understanding well how to use everything yeah cuz
like I've got the gnome thing down like I can stall gnome a couple extensions oh
yeah it's there but I don't have I would like to get there in plasma too