So, we kind of got this all thrown together.
We weren't quite sure where we were going to get a spot, and we weren't quite sure what
kind of connectivity we were going to have, but they do have like these connectivity stations
with power and USB, and like these tables, and they built these boxes on top with plugs,
four plugs on each side, and so we kind of just came over and commandeered one and took
it over, and now that's where we're broadcasting from.
I actually predicted that as we were walking in.
I said, you know, and he goes, how are we going to make sure we get that spot?
And I said, well, if we just start setting down microphones and mixers and like, excuse
me, sorry, everyone will just kind of move, and sure enough, they moved.
It was great.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 106 for August 18th, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's live from LinuxCon 2015 in
Seattle, Washington.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Noah.
Hey, Noah.
Are you ready for an exciting show today?
Jeez, am I ever.
It's only taken us two hours to get here, three hours to get here.
It's exciting for us because we're live on the floor, and that's always, especially when
you get here and you don't know where you're going to be live from, it's a bit challenging,
but not only are we here, but we took the con experience up to the next level because
we're also here with our Mumble Room, time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, hello, hello, hello, hello.
Hello, guys.
I'm glad our virtual Lug could be here.
They know the Seattle Greater Linux Users Group is upstairs.
We should talk to them at some point.
They have-
That'd be really cool.
Their Lug is here.
And it kind of got me thinking, we could bring the Mumble Room with us to after show parties
and just bring them on a phone.
Oh, yeah.
That'd be really cool.
Oh, that'd be heck of fun, yeah.
Maybe if we do that.
I got the Mumble Client installed on my phone.
Yeah.
Well, coming up on today's episode of Linux Unplugged, we have a couple of things from
the floor we're going to play.
Bruce Schneier, renowned security expert, gave a keynote talk this morning and he had
some interesting points he wanted to make.
You-
Me?
You managed to finally get somebody from HP to go on record and talk about some of the
behind the scenes stuff that they have not shared publicly that they're doing on Linux.
I did.
I've been sitting on that information for over a year and it was driving me nuts.
Yeah.
Absolutely nuts.
Because they would not confirm it publicly.
It's like this big thing, this big huge thing inside of HP that everyone's using Linux and
they wouldn't talk about it on camera.
And I harassed the heck out of them last year and I didn't get anywhere.
And then this year, a person found a guy who found a guy who knew a guy who knew a guy
that was able to talk on camera about it.
And so we got it.
So LinuxCon Seattle is about three floors of goodness.
There's your basic floor, then you've got your second floor where, to be honest with
you guys, we thought was the main floor when we first got here.
And we'll get to that in just a second.
And then there's a third floor where people have sponsored and some other showcases are
up there.
And it's right here in Seattle on sixth and I think it's Pike.
It's at the Sheraton Hotel and it's a really, really, really nice location because if you
get a little burned out and you want to go get some fresh air, you can just go for a
walk.
And there's tons of nice places here in Seattle to go to and so we've taken advantage of that.
And we'll probably tell you a little bit more about that later on in the show today.
But I wanted to tell them about our first impressions when we walked into LinuxCon.
It's a little embarrassing but I'm willing to admit it.
Kind of.
But I mean I don't think that was really our fault.
I think that's more of a layout issue.
Yeah.
You think so?
So we got in and the first thing you find is the registration desk and that's where
you get your badge and your shirt and your swag bag and stuff like that.
So we go over there and had a nice lovely conversation with the lady who, by the way,
told me to walk through a wall and she sends us upstairs because you register at one booth
and then they send you up to another floor which there's another registration booth where
you hand a ticket from the first registration booth to get the rest of the stuff that you
thought you were going to get at the one that you went to to begin with.
So after we got through the two registration booths, one to register and one to get the
stuff that I should have got the first one, then we walk out like right out of that second
registration area and we see what appears to be the show hall.
And there are like nine booths and Chris looks at me and goes, well, is this all there is?
And I remember last year the expo hall was actually so small that they actually put it
inside of the keynote room and it was just, there was the keynotes and then at the back
wall, along that back wall were the booths.
That was it.
You missed a key part of our trip too because our first stop was actually the media room.
That's where our first, we didn't actually go to the expo floor first, we went to the
media room.
Oh, that's right to drop stuff off.
And then we bumped into a friend of ours and he said, did you guys see how small the floor
is?
And I said, what?
And he's like, did you see how small the floor is?
It's unbelievable.
And that is why when we got there we thought, oh, this must be it.
This must be the floor.
And the other thing that was sort of fascinating about it is when we got there, we realized
every single one of these booths was basically a deviation on itself.
Like they were all the same product, just different makers, like it was all container
management software.
And we were like, oh wow, this is it?
And so then I was a little bummed, I'm like, I'm not sure who we're going to talk to.
Container Con 2015, man.
Yeah.
And it really, you know what, that first impression does kind of stick.
It really is Container Con 2015.
Docker, and we're going to talk about that more in a moment, but this is Container Con.
But however, it turns out when you go up to the third floor, you get your more traditional
vendors like here we've got Cloud Foundry and Cisco and Citrix and Canonical and Docker
and Digital Ocean is here, GitHub's here, and Google is here.
Of course, the Linux Fest Northwest guys are here and SUSE is here and Stack Exchange is
here and Samsung and SanDisk and a couple other well-known folks.
You probably know of Amazon Web Services is here, Atlassian is here, and a couple that
we're going to place some interviews for you are from here too.
So once we got to the third floor, it was actually, it seems like a pretty happening
event and the sessions are really intense.
A lot of sessions this time all about containers, not all containers, but a lot of sessions
about running software in container, managing applications in containers, putting your desktop
applications in containers, like it's all about the different specs, the app spec, and
the different initiatives.
Maybe that's why they've codenamed it Container Con.
Yeah, it's definitely the theme here.
I got a couple of clips I want to play, a couple of interviews I want to get into.
We had a few people in the chatroom that asked us to kind of compare the difference between
Linux Con and Linux Fest, so I want to do that in a little bit as well and kind of give
you our general impressions.
So before we get to the first interview, I do have a bit of an outtake I could play.
Do you want me to play our first outtake?
Sure.
Yeah, let's do that.
This is Chris and Noah entering the Linux Con and I was going to record, you know, build
this beautiful theater of the mind for you guys so we'd really be able to illustrate
what it's like to get here, but, well, Noah was very, very enthusiastic about creating
that theater of the mind and he might have gone a little overboard with painting the
picture.
Here we go, Noah.
Linux Con 2015.
All right, let's walk through the door.
Inside.
Head to the escalator.
Step on here.
You're so bad.
I'm trying to give them a story.
What's happening?
You're too obvious.
What's happening right now?
You don't know.
You just paint the scene with the sound.
Paint the scene.
There's no sound.
So we got here and we do have a couple of interviews to play.
We went to it.
The first thing we got to work was we knew we had to get some stuff for Linux Unplugged
because we had a live broadcast and that was our first drop-dead thing.
So before we get into that, I'm going to tell you about Digital Ocean, the first sponsor
on today's Linux Unplugged.
Digital Ocean is super, super handy.
We're bouncing clips around and things like that and it's very, very easy to spin up droplets
and when you combine it with something like Docker and man is Docker huge here at Linux
Con and of course Digital Ocean is here as well.
You really have something special.
Use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED to get a $10 credit and here's the best part.
Digital Ocean has $5 a month plans.
So for $5 a month and less than 55 seconds, you can spin up a droplet with 512 megabytes
of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU and a terabyte of transfer and they've got data center locations
in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London and a brand new one in Germany with
lots of great connectivity and good regional locations and Digital Ocean's interface is
so slick and straightforward.
Zero resistance to get something up and running or deploy an application.
You want to do Ubuntu LTS with Apache or something like that.
It's clicks away.
There's so many great ways to deploy software using their interface but even better, they
have a straightforward API you can take advantage of and snap it into your existing management
infrastructure or just use some of the great apps.
They have so many good community tutorials that have been written by the community with
professional editing done to them.
They pay people to edit them.
It is a really good experience and it's great for testing and production.
We use it for all of the above and it is our go-to Linux deployment platform in the cloud
and if you use Docker, if you use CoreOS, if you're using FreeBSD, if you're using
CentOS, Ubuntu, Debian, you name it, you can deploy it on Digital Ocean in seconds.
Go over to digitalocean.com and use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
You can use that at any time and that'll apply a $10 credit to your account and you can also
support the Unplugged podcast.
Go to digitalocean.com and use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED and a big thank you to Digital
Ocean for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
All right, Mr. Colonel, Linux over there.
What do you say we jump into a couple of our interviews that we got here and then we'll
kind of chat about it a little bit.
Man, would I like to do that.
And I wanted to start with the core infrastructure projects announcement this morning.
They had a keynote this morning and they covered a lot of things but one of the initiatives
that keeps getting better and better is in the wake of Heartbleed and Shellshock.
We saw the Linux Foundation along with a bunch of other stakeholders in the industry come
together and launch the core infrastructure initiative.
And the core infrastructure initiative project has been giving out money.
They just announced they're going to be paying for the main developer of NTP, Father Time
is what people call him.
And he's been working on NTP just making nothing but pennies.
And now they just announced they're going to support him which is great.
Hopefully they'll help with some of these NTP reflection attacks.
All the different projects they're investing in have been extremely important.
But there's been one thing that we really haven't been able to kind of agree upon industry
wide and I think we could all agree that if we don't come up with a common set of agreements
and standards, governments will.
And so the core initiative project is setting out to create a open source best practices
program that's going to be hosted up on GitHub and this clip tells us a little bit about
it.
What we're doing is announcing essentially an open source project which will be rolled
out later this year but we wanted to get community feedback on a best practice program that essentially
allows open source projects to meet a set of criteria whether it's having a security
mailing list, peer checking of code, doing static analysis on your code, doing threat
modeling on your code to essentially indicate that you care about security and that it's
important to your project.
People who receive that badge will be able to display it on their project site or in
GitHub and indicate that they have met that criteria.
What we really want is all of your feedback and we don't want it in the form of a bunch
of comments.
We would love it in the form of GitHub poll requests.
So we are doing this, this goes live today.
We're actually announcing this later on this afternoon at a media exclusive luncheon on
the core infrastructure initiative so you all are getting a sneak preview of this today.
Now I think this is a fascinating idea so it's sort of a voluntary program submission
and you get a certified, you meet the best practices and I've been talking about this
on and off with Alan on TechSnap but how do we solve this problem where as a business
you want to use open source in your enterprise but you don't know if it meets a certain,
I don't know if quality standards is the right word but security standards.
You want it to meet a standard, whatever standard that is and actually that makes a lot of sense
right because we do that in basically every other field.
Aviation, anyone can make something but they rate it to be used in aviation.
Or like for example Oracle right?
They go out and get their software better business bureau certified for certain amounts
of software to be free of certain amount of flaws which is kind of a total joke but there
are industry certifications now and this is one that I think what's cool about this is
it's going to be open up to the general public and I don't know if anybody in the Mubroom
has any thoughts on a program like this or maybe any potential downsides but since it
seems volunteer based to me, it seems like a pretty good approach to this and I like
this being run by the Core Infrastructure Initiative because they seem to have their
priorities pretty well aligned.
Anybody in the Mubroom have any thoughts on this?
Going once?
Twice?
No takers.
Okay, all right, well then we'll move on.
I thought it was a good move.
I think I really like what the Core Infrastructure Initiative is doing in the wake of Shellshock
and things like that.
I'm very, very happy about that.
All right, Mr. Noah, then I'm ready for my next clip here and this one was kind of interesting.
It was from Bruce Schneier and he was talking about attributions of cyber attacks and why
attribution is so hard and kind of using the Sony attack in sort of the lens to look through
this problem and if you recall, Sony was using Linux and Apache web servers and things like
that so it's kind of relevant to us because a lot of times Linux is in the server infrastructure
so if there's a problem there, it very much falls on the Linux system administrator to
manage that.
So Bruce Schneier, he was connected in via Google Hangouts this morning for the keynote.
There's a little bit of audio glitchiness because his computer had bad audio but the
content is super critical and important especially with what's going on these days in cybersecurity.
So here's Bruce Schneier talking about how attribution is difficult.
The other big issue and I think the biggest issue that Sony brought out is that attribution
is difficult.
I mean, compared to attacks, in 2006, Israel attacked a Syrian nuclear power plant.
They did it with planes, planes and bombs and the recipient of the attack, Syria, could
look up in the sky, see the planes, see the flags painted on their tails and know where
the attack came from.
2010, US and Israel attacked an Iranian nuclear power plant.
We did it with a cyber weapon, with Stuxnet.
The difference is that there was no way for Iran to attribute the attack.
Actually, Iran didn't seem to have known it was an attack until either the press outed
it or possibly Israel or US called Iran on some diplomatic channel and told them.
It's very difficult to attribute attacks on the internet.
We know this is true, packets don't come with return addresses and it's easy to false flag.
It's easy to pretend your attack comes from somewhere else.
My belief is that a lot of attacks from the western countries go through China simply
because everyone knows a lot of attacks go through China and that's a perfect way to
hide where you're from.
I actually was really glad he made that point.
It's very possible that attacks from western countries are just being routed through China
because a lot of times they're just a Chinese attack.
Now one of the things that jumped out at me about that talk, and he's talking about security,
is one of the main things that the vendors here are showcasing is how to patch your applications
in containers.
Everybody has a different solution for that, how to manage container security, how to update
applications in containers, how to know when the applications in the containers have gone
behind, how to know when the application quits working.
All of that is, I would say, and maybe do you agree that it seems to be the number one
product that's being talked about here, the number one problem?
The container technologies themselves, we've built communities and the standards exist
for that.
What's left, where the market is, where there's left to make a business or money is in products
managing those things.
It's like we're talking about the drive, is you're not going to, nobody is going to manage
that stuff from the command line, even if it's possible.
You need some sort of a solution, especially if you're doing it at a stand.
The other thing is containers encourage you to have a lot of them because not only is
your density higher versus virtualization, so on a server that could have 10 virtual
machines maybe you can now have 20 containers because you don't have the emulation overhead,
but you also are encouraged to do a container per application.
You put your mail server in a container and your web server in a container and your group
collaboration thing.
All these different things go in containers, all of a sudden you have a dozen containers
for one small office.
One of the things that they're finding and talking about here is that container proliferation
is just exploding and then even small shops have all of these containers they have to
manage.
Then the other thing they want to do is move them between services depending on which is
more cost effective.
Schneier talking about attribution and tracking all of this and security patches and updates
is kind of relevant, so that is a problem they're trying to solve here.
I actually really liked his point about why we are seeing so much attribution to China
and Russia these days.
Whenever you hear about a cyber attack, it's Iran, China, North Korea, or Russia every
single time.
It's never anybody else.
It's never Canada.
It's never Mexico.
Sometimes it's the Syrian Electronic Army, but not so often.
It's usually one of those guys.
He tells us why and it's genius.
What I love about Schneier is for the first 5, 10 minutes of his talk, I was like, oh,
this is no good.
Why is this at LinuxCon?
Why is he saying this stuff?
Then the second half of his talk was all like he took what he had set up and kind of re-looked
at it in another lens.
He's connected a few dots for me that I'm not quite like why are we just so publicly
slamming these massively powerful nations and saying you're hacking us with the OPM
breach or whatever it might be.
It's China.
Why are we doing this?
He explains why.
I thought it was fascinating.
Then after that, we have the HP interview, which they also were here talking about the
machine.
That was interesting too.
Before we get to that, I'll tell you about Linux Academy because we were chatting with
some folks in the hallway about different educational resources.
I think Linux Academy has something unique that the other guys don't have.
I tell you, it comes up all the time, especially with containers, is this technology is a moving
target.
App spec is relatively new.
Not much of the courseware out there really reflects that fact.
In fact, pretty much almost none of them do.
The difference with Linux Academy is those enthusiasts there at Linux Academy are following
this stuff because they want to.
They're following this stuff because that's what they're passionate about.
Then they got together with educators and developers and they created the Linux Academy
education platform.
You go there, you figure out what you want to learn, they tell you how long it's going
to take.
You choose from seven plus Linux distributions.
They automatically spin up the virtual machines to match the distribution you choose from
and the courseware adjust.
They've just added new courses as well because they're adding new content constantly.
They have team accounts as well, so if a few people want to go in and learn something,
you can.
That's a good way to motivate each other.
They have an active community stacked full of Jupyter Broadcasting members.
I encourage you to go there and look at the different programs.
Get started by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
That'll give you our 33% discount.
When you're there, log in.
Look how long it's going to take you to learn Python or Ruby or Apache or backing up your
machine using TAR, whatever gap you have in your knowledge set that you want to fill in.
Linux Academy has courses on it.
They also have these nuggets.
You can find them and you go there in like two minutes to 60 minutes long.
They just deep dive right into exactly a course that you want to learn about, which is really
kind of nice because I've been able to use their time availability planner when I'm kind
of like getting on more of a routine, and then when it comes time to just really focus
in on work and I don't really have time to get in something deep, I can still do a nugget
from time to time.
My certification's coming up at the end of this year for Red Hat.
My last certification was in RHEL 6, and now I'll be doing RHEL 7.
I have gotten the practical things nailed down so that I can start rolling out because
we want to be using the... RHEL is, I don't want to say behind, but as stable as it is.
When you go to... If you're not using the latest stable version, it's really stable.
I have nailed out the practical things, but what I haven't quite got down is all the nuances
that they're going to ask me on the test.
I don't have time, as you might imagine, to take off a week to go do all of my recertification
stuff, but I need to learn all the stuff that they're going to ask me.
I found out Linux Academy actually has a course on that.
I use them to learn the practical things.
Now I'm going to go back and I'm going to actually retake the course this time and go
all the way through and learn all of the differences between RHEL 6 and RHEL 7.
That's only possible because I can do that from my laptop while I'm here in Seattle because
everything always takes longer than they think it's going to, you know what I'm saying?
That'll be great.
That's nice.
Go to linux.com slash unplugged to go get the Linux Unplugged discount and support this
show and just take your skill set up a notch.
Linux Academy.
Thanks Linux Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
You guys rock.
Okay, let's play this Schneier clip here.
This Schneier clip is our last one from Bruce, although I might go through his talk and see
if there's any more we want to pull out, but I wanted to grab these ones because I thought
these were short enough but extremely poignant and just for anybody involved and interested
in technology, very relevant.
So here's Bruce Schneier on why we're seeing so much attribution these days, basically
why we're seeing the blame game from different nations.
And there's an arms race here, which I think is important to think about this arms race
between attributing attacks and hiding the origins of attacks, attribution versus deception.
And the US is in a singularly powerful position here.
The NSA surveils much of the internet for a bunch of reasons, right?
They have a bigger budget than everyone else, actually than everyone else combined.
And the way the internet is routed, a lot of traffic goes through the United States.
Big article on the 15th last week on how AT&T is doing quite a lot of eavesdropping for
the NSA, both within the United States and in their network points all around the world.
2012, the US Secretary of Defense, Leon Panetta, he said publicly, he's talking publicly about
attribution and I'm going to read a quote of his, that the US has made significant advances
in identifying the origins of cyber attacks.
That's an interesting statement.
And we actually don't know what that means.
We don't know if the NSA has some fundamental technological advance in identifying packets.
Probably not, or that their espionage is so good that they're monitoring the planning
process.
I mean, we don't know what sort of secret evidence the NSA had.
I mean, did they have recorded phone calls from North Korea discussing the plan?
In my fantasies, I think they have the document of King Jong Un's signature on the approval
to go through with this.
We actually don't know what.
But it's interesting that attribution leads to deterrence.
In the past couple of years, the United States has been more forthcoming in identifying who
attacked them.
They've in several cases identified North Korea.
Last year, we indicted five North Korean government officials in absentia for hacking.
We've attributed Russia, oddly in the OPM attack, there was one statement by Clapper
where he said it was China and then everyone kind of backed off and there's no official
attribution.
But by and large, we're seeing more attribution.
I think that's because it's in the U.S.'s best interests to signal that they can attribute,
to say to the world that if you try this, we will know it's you.
And there is deterrence here.
Actually, I think that leads to over attribution in some cases.
But the thing about attribution in cyberspace is that providing evidence is tricky.
Initially, the United States fingered North Korea, but provided very minimal evidence.
And there's broad mistrust in the security community.
So there was a lot of people, myself included, who just didn't believe them.
And if you think about it, there are several types of attribution.
There's the lowest, where I know you did it.
There's a little harder, I know you did it and it can prove to you I know you did it.
And then the hardest of all, I know you did it and it can prove to the world I know you
did it.
The United States succeeded at one, possibly we succeeded at two, but we failed at number
three.
Attribution based on secret evidence is untrusted.
We all remember Iraq and weapons of mass destruction.
And this problem only becomes worse as more of our attribution relies on secret evidence.
We're going to announce who attacked, we're going to expect the world to support us in
retaliatory action, and yet we won't be able to prove who did it.
And this is going to be complicated.
Hmm, complicated indeed.
So sorry about the little crackly of the audio there, but that was just his feed coming into
the con today.
It wasn't anything we could do about that in the recording.
But I thought it was really interesting.
He says, essentially, one of the reasons we're doing attribution is because it kind of defers
people from doing further attacks because they know we'll call them out.
It's kind of interesting.
Maybe that is why we call out China or call out...
You can tell he's from the internet.
Why is that?
It's just that that's the recourse that you have on the internet, right?
Just calling people out on things.
Yeah.
Trolling, I guess.
So Schneier went on for a little bit longer and talked more about the problem.
And I'll see if there's any more clips you want to pull out of that.
No, I want to talk a little bit about the differences between LinuxCon and a LinuxFest.
And I think, trying to keep in mind, there's two different audiences for each.
Do you want to describe what you think?
So I tell you what, maybe you want to take the...
Maybe you can take one and I'll take the other.
So I'll come at it from the ultra-speed perspective.
So I have attended LinuxCons for many, many years, probably going on, well, since 2009.
So I've been there numerous times.
And only in the past year, I have come from the eyes of the community member that's interested
in the projects.
Prior to that, I've always come to LinuxCon with the idea of I need to come back with
ways, with solutions for my customers, and ways that I can make money.
Because at the end of the day, while talking about the community and open source and software,
that's all great.
Somehow, I have to find ways to buy McDonald's and buy hotels to come out here and do stuff.
I can't do that if I can't sell solutions.
And so LinuxCon, and OSCON really, are both conferences that are really geared towards
doing that.
And I know that that kind of rubbed you the wrong way in some circumstances, in that this
idea that everyone is selling something.
And there is a difference there.
And as a community member, as somebody who's just interested in seeing Linux and playing
with Linux, it's really not that exciting.
But for somebody who can take a solution back and say, you are selling a solution that's
maybe $10,000 or $15,000, but I could put that into, I have four or five clients that
we could implement that in, and then we could net a $50,000 profit to me.
That's very valuable.
What do you think about this as a high-level differentiator between the two?
Linux Fest is where you go to meet the people who are creating the code.
LinuxCon is where you go to meet the people who are selling the code, or OSCON.
The only objection I have to that is there is a lot of development-focused sessions.
If you look at the sessions, a lot of the people that are speaking here at LinuxCon
are speaking as a developer and two other developers.
So I don't know...
It's a bit of a mix.
You could also kind of tell, another way to tell is you can kind of tell by the attendance
price.
Yeah, yes, yes.
Very good.
So these are the ones that are a little more expensive, where generally they kind of probably
are figuring maybe your department or your business is sending you.
Picking it up, yeah.
I guess I would change developer focus to you're meeting the people in the community
versus you're meeting the people selling the products.
I think that, I might twist it a little bit that way.
And that's not to say that this isn't a good conference, or it isn't a pertinent conference
or valuable conference.
Oh, I think for some people it's extremely valuable.
One of the conversations I've noticed a lot happening here is folks that don't quite understand
everything that's involved in sort of switching their infrastructure over, and so they're
coming here.
And I overheard a couple of conversations, I forget the name, but it's one of the Docker
container managements just right here on, it starts with a ranch or something like that,
right here on the corner.
Sure.
And a couple of different gals were talking about how they're coming from some Microsoft
mom management system and they're moving over to different systems and they don't really
quite understand.
There's the one gal, there's why this story even sticks out, it's because she called it
the, I don't quite understand this whole open source trend and I just kind of thought, oh
how cute.
It's not a trend anymore, sorry.
We have taken over the world, kind of.
Yeah, you deploying a Windows machine would almost be a trend.
So yeah, I thought that was particularly funny, is there are a lot of people here who are
not necessarily totally plugged in to the community aspect, but they're more plugged
into the utility aspect of it.
And in their defense, there's nothing wrong with spending your money to come to a conference
to learn how to make more money using a technology that, let's be frank, is actually very profitable.
Yeah.
There's nothing wrong with that.
And good, secure, scalable.
Right.
It's just that it is a very different lens than you or I might take to get there.
I think that's why we're having a little bit of a challenge keeping our get go up.
Yeah, I don't know.
Yeah, I suppose so.
I think, yeah, well, I'm looking forward to, in the Linux action show, kind of putting
it all together, the whole, like we want to really kind of try to capture the experience
coming.
I don't know how successful we'll be, but yeah, we're going to try to give you more
of the, this, what you're getting right now is really, you know, we've been here for one
day.
This is our mid-game impression right now.
We're only midway through the game.
We still have the shirt contest tonight.
We still have the booth crawl tonight.
We still have the meetup.
Yeah, the meetup, I think, is where the rubber is going to meet the road, because that is,
I think, if there is anyone that's coming from the meetup that's been at LinuxCon, great.
If they're not, just fine, yeah.
But that is where we're going to hit that, that's where we're going to hit the community
part of it.
And I think that's where you and I kind of both have our passion.
We both kind of shine, is in that space.
And so, but nonetheless, what we're trying to do here, what we're trying to accomplish
is we are trying to be that network that goes to these conferences.
We bring all this equipment here, we set up and we stream, and give people that don't
have the opportunity to be here an idea of what's here, and pick the best parts.
I just realized something, too, that would be kind of fun, maybe, if you're not normally
at these events, especially LinuxCon, more so than almost the other ones I've been to,
because LinuxCon is a Linux Foundation event, so this is kind of like the official Linux
event, right?
Right.
And so that brings out all of the open source journalists, for the most part.
Like a lot of them are here, and a lot of people in the industry, like Mark Shuttleworth
is here, the CoreOS guys are here, the Docker guys are here, SUSE guys are here, tons and
tons of Red Hat people are here.
And what's kind of neat is you get to meet people that have built things that you're
familiar with, packages that you've installed, tools that have solved a problem for you.
And these people are here, and in some ways, for some of us nerds, they're kind of celebrities
in a sense.
Yeah, very much so.
And, you know, hey, that's that name I've seen on a blog post a thousand times, or their
picture next to their post.
And literally as we were going on air, we had a journalist stop by and take a selfie
with me, because he and I have never actually seen each other in person, we've only seen
each other online, and it's like, hey, good to see you.
And so it's kind of neat, like when you're coming from the outside, you get to kind of
see the people behind the scenes that work on a lot of this stuff at LinuxCon.
Like even eventually, the rumor is Linus will be here at some point, he doesn't go to the
other ones, because this is LinuxCon.
Well, this is really ContainerCon, but this is LinuxCon.
It might be a little more than a rumor, it might actually be on the schedule.
I just don't, you know, until we have tape of it, I don't want to commit to it, but we're
going to attempt to get tape of Linus Torvalds, I guess they said tape.
Yeah, so, I don't know, NorthRanger says, I'm curious how it compares to LinuxCons from
the first dot com bubble.
Back then it was all venture capital, now it's real profits driving attendance.
That's a really interesting observation, NorthRanger.
It's smaller in scale?
Yeah, they have been on the decline.
So I guess, to me, this looks smaller than it was last year.
I guess the attendance is up, though, from last year, which is a good sign.
Yeah.
Well, that is actually the interesting thing, is both last year, OSCON, oh, I'm sorry, Ohio
and LinuxCon have scaled down, but their attendance has gone up, and the vendor participation
has gone up.
So the interest from the public and the vendors is going up, but the con organizers are scaling
down, because I think cons in general, with a few exceptions, are scaling down.
Yeah, I think so.
And part of that is that you are able, that as people become more self-reliant and become
more educated themselves, I think that they're able to find the information that a lot of
people would have gotten at a conference, and then as the internet kind of exploded
and things like blogs and wikis and forums have taken off.
Sorry to interrupt you, the head of the Fedora project just walked by and gave us a wave.
Yeah.
So that's nice.
I think that as that happens, people are able to get that information and they go, I don't
need to spend that money to come out to the conference.
And I got to tell you, speaking from my own wallets, I have always made money coming to
LinuxCon.
Coming to LinuxCon and taking those solutions home and reselling them, I have always come
out ahead.
You know, and the key point of that, and I've liked it a lot, is TechDog in the chatroom
says I'm used to the kind of CES show, where most of what interests me turns out to be
vaporware.
But here, everything here is a shipping product that they're demoing.
There might be a couple things that are about to ship, but 98% of everything here, if you
get an introduction to it, if you get hands-on information and you get a name and a number,
when you go home, you can call that person and they can ship it to you.
That's true.
But as far as the feel of the conference, very similar to CES.
Have you ever been to CES?
It's a very similar feeling conference.
But yeah, that's true.
I guess they don't show not released stuff yet for them.
There's a couple of that, actually.
Yeah.
There's a couple of things here and there.
And that's actually, though, but you don't really mind that.
You like seeing the code before it's finalized.
And so one of the things that was announced here that is pretty neat, in fact, before
we go, I want to get a picture in front of it, is IBM's mainframe one.
Oh, yeah.
Making a big stink about that here at LinuxCon.
And that, are we allowed to say that that's going to be coming out on last?
So we have an interview with them and we have, that's probably the coolest video I think
we've ever shot.
Yeah.
And that's going to be, we'll have that uploaded.
In the Linux action show this weekend.
Which right now, we tentatively are planning to do Friday at 3 p.m.
But that might change, jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
So yeah, and the Canonical guys here announced, I don't know, I don't know if you know anything
about that.
Not to put you on the spot.
I don't really know anything about it.
But if you do, you're more than welcome to chime in.
But Canonical announced that you'll be able to get Ubuntu.
They are, yeah, they are shipping, they have just released Ubuntu 4, this IBM Z series
mainframe.
Of course, the SUSE guys are doing it too.
And you know, but it's really neat.
And Shuttleworth, Shuttleworth did a surprise.
Go ahead, Pope.
Giant, pretty black box with orange stripes down the side is all I know from the photos
I'm seeing.
Yeah.
And Mark was there up on stage.
He came up and surprised everybody during the announcement.
So that was pretty neat.
But we're not here to talk about HP.
We're going to talk about IBM.
We're going to talk about IBM and Linux Action.
So why don't we talk about HP?
You want to do this?
Yeah.
All right.
So this next clip, Noah tells me, is super cool.
It's one I've really wanted to get to for a long time.
So last year, I think I can tell the story now because they've come out on camera and
addressed it.
But last year I was here and I was talking to a couple of the HP guys and I said, you
know, I wish there were more big names that like actively supported Linux like inside
like on the desktop, not just on servers, but actually running it.
And the guy tells me, he goes, I run Linux on my laptop, my work laptop.
This is an HP employee?
Yeah.
This is last year.
And he goes, I run it on my laptop.
And he looks over and he goes, her over there?
She runs Linux.
We've never even installed Windows.
Our work laptops come this way.
I said, well, how does the company treat you?
All they treat us great.
All the software supported.
They support it.
And he goes, and it just works out of the box.
Everything works.
And there's a big majority of us that are doing that.
And I said, wow, that's really cool.
Would you talk to me about it on camera?
And he goes, no, I don't want to do that.
So this year I came here and I walk up and same story.
I started running into the HP employees and they're like, oh yeah, we all use Linux.
I'm like, why won't anyone talk to me?
And they're like, well, we know a guy who knows a guy and he's friends with this other
guy who knows this guy who was trained to speak on camera.
He'll be able to talk to you.
And I'm like, does he work for HP?
And they're like, yeah.
And I'm like, does he use Linux on the desktop?
Oh yeah.
I'm like, find him.
And they're looking all over the conference hall and this guy comes over and he goes,
can I help you?
And I'm like, do you run Linux on your desktop?
And he goes, yes, I do.
And I'm like, I have a camera.
Stand right there.
Yes, you can help me.
All right.
So we're going to play this interview.
You know what?
Before we play it, why don't I tell you about our last sponsor in the show today?
That'll be Ting.
And I want you to check them out because right now this whole show is running off of Ting
and it's pretty awesome.
We actually started on the event Wi-Fi, which is pretty solid during the setup and we thought
we'd be okay with that because they're like a dog with a bone when it comes to finding
rogue wireless signals around here.
So we started on the event wireless and that was walking for a little bit, but I got to
tell you, you go to linux.ting.com because at the end of the day we were so glad to have
backup connectivity, linux.ting.com, Ting is mobile that makes sense.
Look at the signal strength.
Look at that.
Full signal.
Full bars.
Yeah.
Full bars of LTE.
That's nice.
Inside of here.
And you can look around people dropping on and off.
Well, we were, now the only thing we did a little clever is we positioned ourselves next
to a gorgeous view.
Yeah, that's true.
So we have beautiful windows nearby.
So that's helping, but that's just us being savvy.
And so go to linux.ting.com, they'll take $25 off your first Ting device or $25 off
your Ting account or credit wise.
So you get $25 of service credit and then just like for me in my first month, that paid
for it.
It's wireless service with no contract and you only pay for what you use.
It's a flat $6 for the line and there's just your usage on top of that and that's what
you pay.
They have CDMA and GSM, we're on CDMA right now, right?
Actually we're on GSM.
Oh, okay.
We're on the GSM Ting network right now rocking that and you can too and you only pay for
what you use.
And what's great is when you need to use a lot of data, maybe one or two months out of
the year you pay a little more.
The rest of the year your bill's so low that it more than evens out.
It's gorgeous.
Linux.ting.com, go there and try out their savings calculator, plug in your actual usage,
see how much you would save.
I'm saving more than $2,000 in two years.
I can buy a laptop.
That's nuts.
Of course I need a laptop more often than that.
Actually my Bonobo was more than three years old.
And still going strong.
Yeah, so there you go.
That's not so bad.
Linux.ting.com.
Try out the dashboard.
Check out their blog.
It's a great service.
We're using them here at LinuxCon.
We're broadcasting to our Mamba Room and to our IceCast server using Ting.
Live LinuxCon coverage powered by Ting.
It's great to have data in your pocket if you're in IT and they have great phones.
Everything from super, super, super value phones for like under $60, you know, like
feature phones, up to like the greatest hot rods like the S6, the Nexus 6, Moto X2, all
that good stuff.
Linux.ting.com.
Noah, I'm going to play this interview you got from HP.
I'm really looking forward to this because I haven't heard this yet.
I've been waiting.
So here we go.
Here's Noah and HP.
We're here with HP and with Keith.
And I noticed that in the back here he has this big sign that says HP breathes open source.
And as a fellow breather of open source I thought it might be interesting to stop and
talk with Keith.
So tell me Keith, anyone at HP use Linux?
A few people, yeah.
So I'm actually the architect for Linux on the machine.
The machine's a new hardware project we're working on and the operating system we're
developing that we're porting to that hardware is Linux.
So we're doing kernel modifications, user space modifications for that new hardware
project.
We also support Debian Linux in our cloud offering.
So our public and private cloud, HP Helion environment uses Debian natively.
And we use Linux for all of our other server hardware runs Linux as well.
How about people, how about customers that purchase your machines and want to go install
Linux on them?
Do you think that's going to be a smooth experience for them?
Is that something that HP supports?
Yes, we've supported Linux on our hardware for the last 15 or 20 years.
And we've always tried to make it as seamless and easy process as possible.
We provide Linux drivers.
We work with the upstream projects to make sure that the Linux kernel and the Linux user
space stuff works well on our hardware out of the box.
Outstanding.
Tell me a little bit about some projects that HP is either working on or projects that HP
uses or projects that HP supports.
So obviously we work at Linux kernel because we have hardware that needs to run on that.
And then we also have a large investment in the OpenStack ecosystem with a huge number
of contributors to major OpenStack pieces in the HP cloud environment.
And then we also work on other networking NFV stuff, telco stuff, the whole gamut of
enterprise computing.
HP aside, what's your personal favorite distro?
I run Debian.
Oh, okay.
And how long have you run Debian?
I've run Debian for almost 20 years.
Okay.
And is that something that you find that it may, can you get your work work done on Debian?
My business laptop runs Debian exclusively.
Really?
That's pretty impressive.
And HP is pretty supportive of you doing that.
Oddly, yes.
Debian is a very important operating system to HP.
And so they're very supportive of me running Debian as my daily work environment.
That's outstanding.
Well, thanks so much for taking the time to talk to us.
We really appreciate it.
Of course.
Thank you very much as well.
Oh, that was cool.
That was pretty neat.
So that last line there, Debian is very important to HP.
Yeah.
And I'm actually listening back.
I wish it was culturally appropriate to set a camera up and then film all of the surrounding
stuff because it leaves off, it leaves off some of the picture if you don't get the surrounding
thing of like all the people that were standing there that were running Linux on their work
computers as well, you know, and I don't know, I just want to lurk there and watch, show
them.
It doesn't quite paint the picture as well as it did it in person, but I guess you have
to take my word for it.
No, no.
That's neat.
I like to hear the passion there about in that too.
I thought that was pretty cool.
You know, one of the things that was pointed out to me and I haven't seen it anywhere yet
on any of the brochures, but somebody mentioned to me in the hallway that LinuxCon is also
offering childcare.
Oh, no way.
Yeah.
Isn't that cool?
Oh, that's awesome.
And you know, when it's kind of an expensive conference, that's really a nice perk.
It is, especially because I know firsthand couples that both work in the open source
community and have kids and that is an issue for them.
Yeah.
That's really nice.
And they, for a lot of folks, not all folks, but for a lot of folks, they've provided lunch.
You know, they treat the media exceptionally well here.
Yeah.
We have.
So that actually, a shout out to Dan Brown has been outstanding.
I mean, every little thing I have, I just, my email to Dan is like my lifeline for our
lifeline really to get things done here.
You know, when we need permission for something or when we needed them to make a couple exceptions
for us and a couple of rules, just everything is that guy's animation.
Or even when it was just a sandwich, you know, Andrew's able to grab me a sandwich that they're
giving out to the media folks and they provide a media lounge, which isn't too uncommon,
but still really nice.
Yeah.
And I think that everyone at LinuxCon has done exceptionally well.
And you can actually tell it's a really polished conference.
If you look at the way that they have the keynote hall set up, right?
Yeah.
They take the time to put all of the par and all of the DMX, by the way.
So I have a lot of sympathy for the poor guy who had to set all those up and channel them.
But you know, they put the little extra pizzazz to make it, you really do get your money's
worth coming out here.
Yeah.
And they got display screens up everywhere.
I mean, it feels like a high value production.
Yeah.
They do a really good job.
With that, there is the highly sponsored angle.
So the companies that sponsor, they get placed in an area called, let's see, where is it
right here?
It has a name that's essentially like the sponsor ballroom or something like that.
And if you, yeah, here we go.
Let's see.
Sponsor ballroom, which is harder to find than everyone else.
Yeah.
But if you're a sponsor, you get like really fancy placement, which I guess that's fair.
I don't like.
Because the difference is stark.
It's like the sponsors go in a brightly lit room that looks the nicest room.
And then everybody that's in exhibit that wasn't a sponsor is like out in the hallways
and kind of in the peripheral.
As a business owner, I have no problem with them treating the people who make it financially
possible to do a conference like this, treating them, giving them a little extra treatment.
That's perfectly fine.
But what I object to is the fact that it is so much more difficult to find that room than
what we originally thought was the expo hall.
If you're going to have an overflow of the expo hall, have it somewhere else where-
It's not the first thing you walk into.
Right.
Exactly.
And have it maybe in a room that is maybe a little bit more difficult to get to than
the people that are paying the money to be there.
And that's a personal preference.
I'm sure that the fine people at the Linux Foundation had a very good reason for organizing
it that way, and they spent a lot more time planning this stuff and thinking about it
than we do for certain.
Yeah.
And it is nice.
But it didn't make a lot of sense to me.
They have a giant hacking lounge, which is kind of cool, and they have a Birds of Feathers
signup lounge.
So the sponsor area is done really well, and Microsoft has a decent booth there.
So does IBM and HP.
And I'd say one of the nicest booths here, too, is the SUSE booth.
I really like the SUSE booth because they have green apples out.
They have green snacks and stuff, so that was really neat.
And the Red Hat guys are handing out red hats for certain folks.
That was pretty cool.
Yeah.
And I think you stopped by that, didn't you?
Yeah, I did.
I got a chance to talk to them.
But don't spoil it.
That's coming on Sunday.
Oh, that'll be on last, too?
Yeah.
Yeah, that'll be on Friday.
Man, we've got a big Linux action show coming up.
This is the last chance as we wrap up here, chat room or mumble room, if you guys have
any questions from LinuxCon.
Hey, Ange.
Ange.
Yeah?
Why don't you come over here and give the people a quick five-second, your impressions
of LinuxCon.
What did you think of those since you've been here today?
What do you think of it so far?
It's pretty cool.
I love seeing JB shirts.
I've seen a couple.
I've seen a couple of people that we saw at LinuxFest Northwest, and I'm already angling
for a booth at another con or fest or whatever.
Yeah, it's definitely, I say a lot of suits, but there aren't a lot of suits, but it feels
that way.
It's very business-y.
Yeah.
All right, Mr. WW, you had a question about the con in the mumble room.
Go ahead, sir.
So have you come to a conclusion yet what the cons or pros are of going to LinuxCon
versus going to like a fest where it's more casual, or do you think you'll have to?
It kind of goes back to our answer.
It's like if you want to kind of rub elbows with more community aspect, people that are
more writing the code and thinking about the code and thinking about community and standards
and collaboration, then you kind of want to go to a fest.
If you want to meet the people that are creating solutions and selling the code and that maybe
you're going to solve a problem you have at work, then you might want to go to a con.
Not that Fest doesn't have that stuff too.
I would just ask, what are you going to get out of it?
Do you want to talk about your passion for Linux or do you want to sell Linux?
That's a little black and white, but that's kind of what it comes down to.
If you have to make a decision about a flight and a hotel and the tickets, then you need
to know that.
Yeah.
I guess I say that because that's the metric that I've used.
I would never go to a... I mean, being honest here, I would never go to a fest and expect
to come back with profitable material for my business.
I would never go to a con without expecting to be able to make a profit on it, and transversely,
I would never go to a fest and not expect to build some relationship, but I would be
perfectly okay with going to a con and coming back with nothing more than a business sense,
even if we didn't have a community bonding.
There is no going out to the range and shooting here.
There is no going out for burgers and stuff unless you range it privately, as opposed
to...
What do you think of North Ranger?
He says, maybe it's a mullet.
It's a mullet of gatherings, business in the front, party in the back.
That's not bad.
I like that.
Okay, that's a good...
We can go with that.
All right, so Linux Unplugged is live on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv.
We do the show at 2 p.m. Pacific.
You can go to cheaperbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get that converted to your local
time zone.
We'd love to have you join us live in our virtual lug in our mumble room.
You bang mumble in our IRC chat room, and you can go to cheaperbroadcasting.com slash
contact to send us an email, or if you'd like to get content or discussions or any kind
of feedback or topic generation like that, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Noah, is there anywhere you'd like to send people throughout the week?
Yeah, I'd send them to ultispeed, ultispeed.com.
We are continuing to work on expanding the ability to do remote support.
We just finalized the final in-production test of doing cloud-based Wi-Fi.
We now have the ability, yeah, we now actually have the ability, and this hasn't actually
gone out to the website, and we haven't sent flyers and product literature and stuff, but
we actually now have the ability, if you have a property and you want Wi-Fi on that property,
we can actually ship you an entire box of stuff, and you plug the cables in, and we
take it from there.
Wow.
And we manage the whole thing remotely.
Ultispeed.com?
Yeah, ultispeed.com.
We rolled that out at a hotel in Mankato, Minnesota.
There was actually a guy on Twitter that was asking where he could stay where we had
managed the Wi-Fi.
It was a quality in Mankato.
That's our first place that we've rolled that system out, and so far, it's been 100%.
So cool.
All right, everybody.
Well, thank you so much for tuning in to this episode of Linux Unplugged, and we'll see
you right back here next week.
Hey, Noah, I have a question for you.
All right.
I have an answer for you.
Hey, wouldn't it be cool if your question and my answer match up?
Could we have done this whole transmission over SIP back to the-
Yes.
Yes, we could have.
So why didn't we just use SIP?
Well, I have never tried a SIP call that long to know if, A, the quality would be sufficient,
although I suspect it would, but my big concern is I don't know if the... SIP is very, very
finicky if you actually lose internet because it has to re-register with the server, and
then we'd have to reinitiate the call, and we'd have to try a test call for an hour before
I would really feel comfortable saying try it, although I suppose technically it's no
worse than Skype.
Skype has to...
Hey, Noah.
I do SIP calls to conference calls all the time for very long periods, like two, three
hours at a time, and on my home Wi-Fi, it never drops off just to be able to call SIP
client.
Really?
Well, obviously, you're on conference Wi-Fi.
It might be a bit tricky.
Yeah, we're not actually.
We've provided our own, and our internet's actually pretty strong, so I'll have to give
that a shot.
Now, Popey, did you modify the codex at all, or are you just using the default ones, whatever
comes set with the SIP client?
I was just using the default that was on Android.
I'm connecting to an asterisk server in the office.
Oh, my gosh.
You're doing it over Android?
So we could...
Yeah, that's fine.
So we just bring a little interface?
Oh, my gosh, dude.
How cool would that be?
All this can go away.
We just plug into...
Yeah, it'll work.
What could go wrong?
Run the whole show on Android.
I don't think anything could go wrong.
No, it'll be fine.
That'll be fine.
It should be nice.
Actually, and the app has local recording as well, so it can just record the whole conversation.
I use it when we're having internal calls, and we call them and then make them available
for other people.
That's a good idea.
All right, so we've got to pick our title.
We've got to go to JBtitles.com and pick this thing.
Hey, I suggested a title.
You did?
Yeah.
For once in my life.
How was it?
I don't know.
I don't remember what it was.
Do you want to vote?
JBtitles.com.
Yeah, sure.
Sure.
Why not?
Oh, I went to JBlive.tv.
Oh, how come I have no JBtitles.com?
I don't know.
Why don't you?
Oh, I don't either.
Oh, here it goes.
Now it's going.
Connecting the Docs.
That's kind of funny.
Oh, yeah.
Connecting the Docs.
That actually is.
That kind of works.
Containing LinuxCon 2015.
That's not bad.
LinuxCon 2015.
Molot Party.
That's not bad either.
There goes Greg KH.
All right.
I have voted for...
Colonel Maintainer Extraordinaire.
Absolution of Attribution.
Hobnobbing with the celebrities.
Look at us.
Yeah, yeah.
Hobnobbing.
That must be...
That must be a...
I've heard of Hobnobbing before.
Oh, really?
Oh, yeah.
Totally.
All right.
I'm trying to educate, man.
Has Popey told you about his new snack that he really likes?
Haggis.
What?
What's Haggis?
Am I pronouncing that right?
That's delicious.
Yes, it is.
Tell them what it is, though.
It's awful.
Mixed with oats and spices.
So it's like a breakfast?
Boiled.
Yeah, you often have a slice of it fried with breakfast.
Fried?
If you have like a full English breakfast, you'd have like a...
Sausage, bacon, eggs, beans, and all that, and black pudding, I'm thinking of black pudding,
but black pudding and, yeah, Haggis, very similar.
But no, you'd normally have Haggis with potatoes and vegetables.
It's lovely.
It's like stomach and kidneys and stuff.
What are you fried in?
Like what kind of grease or oils?
I don't know.
Sorry, I was confusing.
Oh, that was black pudding you fried.
Got you.
Yeah, but Haggis comes in like a bag.
It used to be like sheep stomach, but now it's like a bag.
A bag.
Sheep stomach, yeah.
And you boil it.
Yeah.
Boil sheep stomach.
Come on.
Let's not.
It's delicious, man.
Delicious, see?
Yeah.
My wife won't eat it.
She won't go anywhere near it.
What's it smell like?
You married up.
When she goes out, it smells delicious.
It smells like a bag of offal boiled.
What else is it going to smell like?
You married up, my friend.
Do you put any sauce on it, or you just eat it as is?
Actually, I had it the other night with some sriracha on it, which was even better, because
sriracha makes everything better.
Sriracha does.
You know what Rekai put sriracha on?
Pizza.
Sure, yeah.
Totally ordered pizza with sriracha.
It was really good, actually.
Yeah, yeah.
No, I've seen that.
That's a thing.
That's good.
But can you barbecue a Haggis?
Oh, stop it.
Damn it.
If you dig a pit.
Connecting the docks containing LinuxCon 2015 are my favorite.
Connecting the docks is good.
There is a vegetarian Haggis, by the way.
Connecting the docks is good, but containing LinuxCon suggests LinuxCon.
I think actually connecting the docks is good.
Yeah.
If you're going to have containing, it should be can't contain LinuxCon.
Containing LinuxCon 2015.
Can't contain.
You can't contain LinuxCon.
I don't know if you get it.
You don't get it.
I think connecting the docks is better.
If you don't watch the episode, you don't get it.
So I think I like connecting the docks better.
All right, NorthRanger, you win, sir.
You win.
What was yours, ColonelLinux?
Can't contain LinuxCon?
Ah, I see.
See?
Get it?
I got that.
So, Mumbo, were you able to hear the clips okay?
Yeah.
It's a little hokey.
Hey.
But every time we get it, we learn.
So, thanks for making it, you guys.
I love your faces.
Welcome.
We actually didn't even remember you guys until this morning.
That's not true at all.
Chris remembered you.
Oh.
Well, Noah didn't.
And so since I was planning equipment, I was still figuring out how I was going to do
this morning.
That's true.
That part is kind of true.
All right, you guys.
What?
We're going to expect some flowers and then we'll be fine.
Okay.
All right.
I can do that.
Flowers and Haggis.
What about chocolates?
And Haggis.
Oh, and Haggis.
Yeah.
Poppy can supply the Haggis.
All right.
Question on Bruce's talk.
Will they have a full link to that somewhere?
I think so.
Yeah.
Yes.
Yes, they will.
They will publish it.
They send it off to their media guys and then they send it out to Mount Kilimanjaro where
monkeys chew on it for a while and then spit it back out and then a hiker brings it back
down from Mount Kilimanjaro and they publish it and that takes a couple of weeks.
I believe that's how it works.
It's a big mountain, you know?