have you guys I think we talked about this like a really long time ago the the
sole laptop the solar-powered laptop well now we're getting we're getting
prices 495 Canadian I don't know what that is in real actual money but in
Canadian money it's something now remember this is the one where the box
yeah where the back folds down and the and the panels come out and then it
charges it runs Ubuntu and I haven't looked at the specs yet I was saving for
the show so let me find it right here see if I can oh yeah specs here we go
all right so it's it comes with Ubuntu 1404 or you can get with Windows 7 it
has an Intel Atom 1.8 gigahertz dual core processor 2 gigs of RAM 320 gigabyte
SATA hard drive yeah it's got an Atom so I don't know but it's solar-powered
that's kind of cool right would you buy one Eric if you had the if you had the
cash dude if I had the cash I'd be all over that just because it's a
recognized laptop I wouldn't have to worry about my kid you know and then I
could take it places like into the back woods you know take pictures I'm sorry
what oh I got you I was I was losing you there for a minute hey Colonel Linux
could this be the ultimate travelers laptop never have to look for a charging
board at the airport again he says no no because you have to sorry yeah yeah no I
well here's the thing right so as far as a traveling laptop I think it would be
hard to charge it it would have to be able to actually get to Sun to get it to
charge right man get a window seat
so it's not like you're stuck with just solar power boring all right what about
okay okay where are the specifications when we so slow it's painful it's got a
that's well I mean I don't know 1.8 gigahertz isn't that bad dual core that's
not I'm not talking about the technical specifications of the computer rather
than the power intake and solar size and generate well frankly I've seen some
really significantly large solar panels through what I do with work and they
generate tiny little sips of amperes that barely power an electric biro so
I'd be amazed if this thing can actually charge and power a laptop for any
significant time whatsoever yeah okay that's a good point I mean
that could be a major issue is how long it takes to charge I noticed they're not
actually throwing that out on the pages I'm looking no I can't find that is the
most important specification item for a laptop of this kind and I don't see it
readily available hmm hmm boy look at you just dumping cold water on this like
sorry sorry well the thing is is that I've got customers that would really
like to use an equipment like this because they operate aircraft for in
sort of pseudo military environment so for the United Nations and stuff like
that and they upload their flight data over satellite phones so they would love
a computer like this that they can open in the middle of Africa or Afghanistan
where Sun is available almost all the time mm-hmm and yeah that bit of
information isn't on here boy that is an interesting catch and of course one that
once you think about it is sort of the critical piece of information I thought
when we first heard about this it was gonna be an arm machine to the second
issue I have with it with your live as far north as I do half the edits
completely useless oh I don't know I'm an optimist Eric I like to believe it's
funny I guess I don't know I like to think it's nicer in the Pacific
Northwest than everybody thinks it is like I don't know I I find all these
things to be supplemental what I really want is I'm waiting for the day when
they can integrate a solar panel behind the LCD screen of my smartphone and then
when I just have my smartphone down on the table or on my dash it's secretly
like you know trickle charging it's absorbing the yellow Sun like Superman
that's that's what I look forward to okay yeah okay sorry and I've heard some
some stuff on science shows recently that they've got a completely clear
glass that they are planning on putting in two new phones and new tablets I'm
ready charger I'm ready for that whether it completely charges it or just keeps
it from charging so fast did you find the charging info and I found the
information so I'll read it back it says this really depends it says how long
does it need to be in the Sun to be fully charged and it says this really
depends on the exposure you're getting right in a fully sunny day it should
take a couple of hours to get fully charged duration will change with
conditions such as and this is they oh by the way this is our get out of
clauses to why it's never going to work position of the Sun clouds location on
the earth and even air pressure and temperature yeah that's basically it
doesn't work it's never gonna charge the laptop that is everything you can
imagine because where are you on the planet exactly I'm sorry you're not
exactly on the equator on this specific aren't you gonna bake the components
like aren't you gonna cook the laptop now you're really digging into this so
now I'm gonna find temperature temperature operation the temperature
conditions I guess I know I guess I like the idea of this being a feature on
almost anything where there's some integrated self-charging you know like
okay I'm not saying everything it comes down to Star Trek but it turns out seems
like everything comes down to Star Trek and something the Enterprise D got
really good if you look at the back area of the Enterprise D between the warp
missiles that's all solar panels and it's not their primary source of power
but it's like a solid trickle charge for their power cells and they could just
you know they don't depend on it but it's just sort of supplements it's like a
multiple different ways getting that power up and I look at the battery
technology and I think these batteries are not getting better fast enough you
know like they're they're just like I want to I want a phone that lasts two
three days that's that would really be perfect for me or at least a solid two
days but the battery technology doesn't seem to keep up but if they could have
trickle charging like through solar and stuff like that to sort of supplement
the battery shortcomings Chris I can solve that problem for you the thing you
need is a Nokia 9660 there you go that will last you five days in a single
charge network really the night Nokia that's the old in other words get away
from your stupid smartphone that's what you're saying yeah that's well yeah go
back to my old that was advertised as a smartphone but yeah back in the day I'm
looking right now oh boy yeah yeah exactly that was too fast what I'm
sorry what sorry Noah I meant to say okay thank you welcome to Linux unplugged
your weekly Linux talk show that's already preparing its defenses against
the con crud my name is Chris and my name is Matt hey man I'm taking like
vitamins I'm trying to drink water I'm trying not to get sick when I go on this
trip but I'm already paranoid because I've been sleeping very well and that's
that lowers the defenses right there Matt oh boy I'm starting on a
disadvantage so if if I get sick what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna implement a
bubble quarantine it's gonna make Monday's Linux action show a little
awkward so I'm gonna be in a bubble but we'll communicate over the microphones
and headphones so you'll still be able to hear me however I am gonna need you
to slip the bacon through a slot okay okay you know when it comes to slipping
bacon I can do that okay good good all right well we got a good episode today
episode 63 of the unplugged show we're gonna talk to the Linux grandma I went
to a meetup recently of kabuntu users you know me Matt I'm a kabuntu guy oh
yeah so I went to a kabuntu users meetup and met Valerie she's gonna join us today
and chat about kabuntu KDE specifically the KDE project something neat I learned
that the KDE group is doing it coming up right now and a few other things that
come up and plus just a little bit about her blog as well plus we've got a ton
of feedback and then Microsoft apparently quote-unquote hearts Linux
we're gonna talk about that as well as a bunch of other things coming up later in
the show so big show today accidentally did a big show I don't even know your
show a huge show so let's start with some feedback from Sunday's Linux action
show Dave wrote in and he wanted to kind of take us to the mat Matt get it oh
boy I see how that works he's calling us out though he's like hey guys great show
I've been a listener for a long time you ready for this Matt I use a Windows
sysadmin oh I know a few of those that's okay they exist and that's why he likes
listening to last because he likes to get info about all the OS's but he
wasn't so hot on the negativity towards Docker on Windows he says I get a
feeling from your and Matt's comments in last 335 you're irritated that Docker
would dare roll out their products to Windows hey Windows Server guys want
containers too why do you Linux guys got a hog all the good stuff I would love to
be able to use containers instead of virtualization to keep applications
isolated also you made it sound as if you could run Linux Docker containers on
Windows that's not the case the container share the kernel so Windows
Dockers only run a Windows containers I think we actually didn't make that point
pretty clear so you know you know what it was Matt is we get these terms in the
industry that just drive me crazy and I think Docker is turning into a buzz term
almost because when you start taking out the Linux component of Docker doesn't
seem like Docker anymore now it just seems like you're taking the concept of
container ization and you're just calling it Docker all right pretty much
I mean it becomes a branding thing it's yes that's what I was rolling my eyes at
right I in a way it also shows like what a player Linux is right now in the
market because not the first OS to do this right I think those BSD guys would
have you check out something called jails and I think they're pretty proud
of it in fact I think they think it's still a lot better so Docker comes along
and it kind of does stuff that other things can already do except for it has
this great Docker hub where you can pull down images and it goes from that to now
it's this it's like the concept of container ization is just it's like when
we started calling DVRs Tivo's and it's like no it's not a Tivo that is your
cable company's DVR or that is a play TV you know it just that's what I was
rolling my eyes at well and going from my perspective what kind of irritated me
about the whole thing is that I have no problem with Microsoft getting on board
with this what I have a problem with is the fact that as per usual they waited
to the very last minute to where they didn't have to innovate anything then
they kind of slopped they kind of belly flopped onto the platform out of the
pool limped along a little bit and said oh hey look at this grand jewelry thing
that we're coming up with it's so awesome and we're so innovative they
just the entire experience that they're presenting had a very it just felt like
that they were doing something unique and different it's like but that's not
the case you're a me too product I'm sorry yeah and like like Linus Tech
points out in the chat room I mean they're depending on LXC docker is built
on that and we wanted to remind us of a little history right well yeah I mean
open vz has been around for a long long time now and that was sort of the
original Linux container platform and I've been using that successfully at
work and I was a late adopter for about five years now so yeah docker is great
I've had a go with it and I can see the advantages and how it extends on what
open vz offers but then containers jail CH roots it's not new yeah I agree I
mean I've got Proxmox here in the studio right and I've been using LXC on
that but I think what my I think what my point is is a lot of times we as the
technical crowd we see that the groundwork was already there and we
failed to recognize the innovation in making it all work really simple in a
way that a lot larger of an audience can grok and what what is different about
docker is it broke into that gray area that's called DevOps where you've got
developers who maybe didn't fully understand containers and namespaces and
virtualization and kids and Zen and KVM and LXC but they get github right and
they get that docker has this github like functionality and I can pull down
this container and now it's just working and it from end to end it is presented
in a product like fashion that you can completely wrap your brain around you
understand what it is from a concept and so it's easy to talk about it's easy to
understand and then you understand that has this github like functionality for
images it clicks and I think we as as more technical users sometimes fail to
fully appreciate sometimes just bringing it a little bit more polished bringing
to that edge can really make the difference obviously look at that's what
Apple really makes their money on right what's your number one comment you
always see after a new iPhone or iPad is launched XYZ Android device had it first
Apple pay is a great example of that right there's my Nexus 5 device is
ancient now in the smartphone land sorta it's had wireless payments this entire
time I've never used at once right that the difference is that final 10% gap
closing that seems to be where you can make the difference and that's what
docker did because there's other operating systems that have it as well
so good for Windows I don't think Windows is a fantastic platform for
service to begin with but that's probably too much of a surprise to
anybody and so yeah I mean that's pretty much that's kind of where I'm at with
it's like hey they want to go have a go with it that's great but you know lose
the oh my gosh we're so are they're trying to be like Apple in this regard
it feels like they're just it's like they it almost feels like they're
saying they innovated this whole thing and it's like but you didn't really have
any no you didn't I mean not really all right I wanted to open the floor to
feedback on the Ubuntu 1410 review that we had in Sunday's Linux action show we
got several different emails and comments about it but there wasn't any
one particular theme that jumped out so just as a as an open door to the mumble
room did anybody have any feedback follow-up corrections or arguments they
want to make from our review of Ubuntu 1410 on Sunday show now is your chance
for hold your or forever hold your going once going twice sold this style of it
they they're looking at the different flavors you think that worked out with
because that was kind of something new we were trying you think that worked out
okay yeah at least for me it it feels like a deeper look into the different
yeah the different flavors because I never liked the first Ubuntu I tried
but I really love both Kubuntu and Ubuntu but there was little little less
information from reviews and all that on those flavors right so maybe now
somebody looking for more about Ubuntu will see that and learn about those
other flavors and obviously Mate played a big role in our review so wimpy I used
you want to give a chance to follow up on some of that well first of all thank
you ever so much for covering Ubuntu Mate in your roundup not least because
Ubuntu Mate is not an official flavor yet but also because it's really good to
get good feedback so there was a few things that you mentioned in your review
which if you dig into the Ubuntu Mate website little bit this is one of the
links that isn't and top in the top there on the roadmap I've got a few
things outlined that you touched upon so would you like me to okay so there was
there was a few things obviously you'd gone all compies addict mode there and
you'd you turned on wobbly windows never way way way back for one there was
actually an Ubuntu Marte dash comp is meta package which was put together
based on the feedback of one of the guys from the Ubuntu Marte compete community
quickly worked out that this was going to require a bit more work than I had
time to put in so I put that on the back burner but what we're going to do is
comp is is never going to be a default option for Ubuntu Marte but it will be a
meta package so a compass is still hugely popular in Marte community so I'm
going to make a meta package available so that you can install compete via a
single package you get a same set of default and you get that traditional
compass experience for those people that love it now you know next thing you're
gonna have people are going to ask for barrel support so that way they can get
their crazy window decorations I love I love wobbly windows I draw the line at
3d cubes but there is actually a practical application to all of this and
that's with them talking to Jonathan NATO from the accessible computing
foundation in his opinion the best desktop zoom application for individuals
with low vision is the enhanced zoom plug-in from compass for all that for
all the fun and games there is actually a practical application for for making
comp is easily available you know I used to use I totally forgot about that I
used to use that during shows to demonstrate something's on a specific
area of the screen I would just zoom into it yeah yeah yeah so for all for
all the wobbly windows fun there is actually practical application and a
couple of other things you touched on was launches and docks if I actually
sent you a screenshot of how I run Ubuntu Marte I think it'd make a lot of
Ubuntu Marte or Marte users shriek because it's unconventional I have a
dock at the bottom so I have a single panel at the top with your applications
places and system yeah and a few few applets to tell me when the discs are
rattling and all of that sort of stuff and then your system tray a dock at the
bottom and I use plank for that yeah and then I have an oversized auto hiding
panel on the left of the screen with a huge workspace switcher on it which is
remarkably like what you find on the right hand side of the screen in GNOME
3 with their workspace switcher so that's how I how I drive my system so
I'm obviously looking at a way to integrate docks what what's so funny
those Katie users don't listen to them I know I thought I was being all right
I'll move on I'll move on very quickly then so again docks won't be a well they
may be a default setting I'll ask you been to Marte community if they want as
a default setting but one of the things I'm planning on working on is that the
working title is shapeshifter so you can choose a workspace setup so not just the
panel arrangements but also things like docks launches and and the general
appearance so you know what are the other things we've been seeing a lot is
people want to see that like the whisker menu or something like that that they
can use yeah and that's and that's something else I'm looking at is some of
the launches so I use synapse for example which gives me all of that stuff
that you were looking for so you can yeah you can hotkey type TRM and hit
return and there's your terminal yeah guys I mean I we've talked about synapse
multiple times on the show obviously I know about and also gnome do although
when I installed gnome do it locked my limit a session up but first can't shut
me up about yeah we know about the thing is is I just wanted to find a project
that was still active and I just haven't found yeah yeah so so synapse has got a
PPA it's recently been restarted so that's under active development oh yeah
yeah docky and plank of merged so if you look at the latest docking plank
they're effectively identical awesome and in addition to synapse there's
slingscold which is another launcher which looks very interesting and another
one I think it's called the duck launcher and there's one other that I
found so what we'll be doing is is looking at these having conversation
with the community finding out which ones they like the most building some
meta packages and some default configuration and then providing
utility when you install them into my tape for the first time you can have a
this is a visual representation of the different ways the desktop can be
arranged and the tools that are on offer and you can say snap and go and in some
little way that's available now so if you deeply deeply want a Windows XP
classic look there's a Redmond panel layout and if you go to the Ubuntu mate
website you'll find in the release notes the instructions on how to enable the
Redmond layout and that's the first baby steps towards the shape-shifting
create your desktop with a single click the way you want it to be oh I cannot
wait to see that well I'm still running it here in fact I was just thinking
today as I set up I really appreciated how snappy it was and I feel like even I
don't know I feel like even my web browser start faster and I don't know
why the desktop would make the difference I obviously granted it
probably uses less resources but it's not like I'm starved for resources so
yeah it's and it's not about saving resources it's about preserving
resources for the things that matter so by having less resources allocated to
your desktop you've got more resources available to your Steam client or your
web browser for example good point good point less fluff less fluff well great
work on the Mate edition and thank you and it was it was good for the Mate
desktop team to see as well because this is an opportunity for that for them to
see their work showcased as well sure well I look forward to keep checking out
boy something sounds like some of those improvements are gonna be really really
incredible alright so I think Valerie's been waiting long enough before we get
to that I'll thank our first sponsor this week and that's Linux Academy here's
where you need to go right now stop what you're doing oh my gosh what are you
doing you got to go there right now Linux Academy comm slash Linux or slash
unplugged I think both of those work but I like Linux boom why not right Linux
Academy comm slash unplug to get you the discount I know that lock that in go to
Linux Academy comm slash unplug to make sure you get the awesome discount you
can get up to a 33% off and the great thing about that subscription is you
just constantly get all of the new content you get access to everything
pick and choose what you want to start with so have you heard about Linux
Academy you should go check them out right now Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged you can get step-by-step video courses they'll walk you through all
kinds of things thing one of the things I like about Linux Academy too is I've
used it to just sort of test the waters and see what topics interest me but you
could absolutely surely use it to just sort of increase your skill level and
whatever your industry is in or maybe get yourself up to that next level if
you've been just thrust into a project and you've got to move from like a red
hat box to a Debian box and things like that's one of the great things about
Linux Academy is whatever course where you're taking you're gonna be able to
choose from seven plus Linux distributions and then they structure
all the courseware off the distribution you pick that's a great opportunity if
you're moving between distributions or you need to refresh or you want to
figure out maybe the way the other side does things and I'm showing you some of
the courses you can take now if you take some of their Linux training it's
awesome all kinds of things you can take all kinds of courses over there and one
of the best parts is is they have these learning plans now they will
automatically customize the amount of training time you have just based on the
availability you select and it can send you reminders about courses and it gives
you an idea in a snapshot okay it's gonna take you this long to get through
this course when you log in and by the way you can download these study guides
some of them are an audio and video and listen to them on the go Seth
Scooby Sprite sometimes joins us during Linux unplugged or tech talk listens in
the shower most people listen in the car but Seth listens in the shower and you
know I realized I do some of my best thinking in the shower so maybe I would
do some of my best learning in the shower like that could actually be total
genius I don't know how cool how cool would it be to have like some sort of a
shower proof whiteboard that if you're coming up with these ideas well quickly
jot it down it's funny you say that he actually mailed me I'm not even kidding
a waterproof notebook all of the pages in the notebook are waterproof and he
hangs it I'm not even kidding this is not made up he hangs these in a shower
and with the right pens and he takes notes in there and he sent me a set like
this is what he does this is his system and it works for him this is what's
awesome about Linux Academy is you can literally customize it to whatever your
scenario is you know if I've gotten emails from people recently said you
know Chris I'm gonna be a dad soon I'm a little worried about keeping my skill
level up Linux Academy can customize to your availability or you know you're
like Seth you're only free times when you're in the shower he still makes it
work and finds value out of it they're constantly adding new things and they
have scenario based training so you actually implement something so say you
take an AWS course you'll implement the s3 back-end storage the ec2 front-end
boxes the load balancing the DNS management you'll do all of that and as
each part in that lab in that scenario based training not only will you be
implementing and at the actual stuff the actual application so you'll have
hands-on experience but they will spin up the service for you as you need them
on-demand just part of their service it's really cool Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged time to go do some more training it's always time to learn a
little bit more and it's never been a better time Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged all right well I would like to welcome Valerie to the show she is
hanging out with Eric they might sound like they're at the bottom of a pool but
they promised me they're not swimming right now but you never know with those
two but you're just lounging sure how would we know it's an audio only show
how would we know well Valerie welcome to Linux unplugged and I feel bad like I
shouldn't call you the Linux grandma but that's what you go by isn't it I don't
know I don't know but that's what you go by I go by you embrace and I think I
love that you you break a lot of stereotypes that when we got we we met
Valerie at a Kubuntu users meetup and when we got there Valerie showed up with
the thumb drives preloaded with plasma 5.1 so that way we could all get
installing if we didn't have you that's how that's how cool Valerie is and so I
wanted to kind of start with your involvement in the KDE project and I
don't know if you wanted to jump right into it but you told me about something
that I didn't know KD he does it's kind of reminded me of the Google Summer of
Code so you can start wherever you want what you do with the KD project probably
a great place but I'd like to get there so tell us what you do for KD well
Google Summer of Code I'm one of the administrators you're actually largest
or one of the largest research and contributors I guess you would say
because I don't know if your listeners know about Google Summer of Code oh
sure yeah okay so Google puts up the money and then the free projects
actually do the mentoring for the students and so the students work for
summer and get paid for it and we possibly get new members of the
community right like KD connect was started as a Google Summer of Code
project right exactly yeah and all kinds of cool stuff and there are two other
actually two other mentoring projects that we do one is called season of KD
which has no money and we're just actually we're kicking it off late this
year it's just kicking off now it'll go through the end of January participants
get a t-shirt and a certificate and it's open to students it's really open to
anybody who finds a mentor and wants to do it and then Google code in is
relatively new I think Google's only been running it for four or five years
that is for junior high and high school students it is awesome and our mentors
come up with small tasks that students can do in a day and the top prize which
I think about ten kids win is a trip to Mountain View for two or three days
oh what a treat parents oh yeah and you can see that that's really awesome for
Google because they get a first look at all of these uber smart uber driven kids
of course it's wonderful for the projects when I got involved I had just
started writing user documentation for Amarok and I set up a page for every
little sub subject and then the students did wrote wrote the page did the media
wiki coding and did the screenshots and all I had to do was point clean up after
them it was wonderful and then years later up at Linux fest Northwest I met
my prize student who was working for own cloud by then Wow yeah so it's just a
win in every way that you can think of although the mentors work really hard
and it's right during it's in the winter so are you are you serving as the as the
interface like the go-between between the Google reps and the KD project like
are you helping coordinate some of that people they're getting by me I'm one of
the I'm one of the administrators yes so we get all the infrastructure set up we
make sure that mentors are around to talk to their students how critical just
whatever how critical to the KD project would you say the Google summer of code
involvement has been I think that especially in India it has helped us a
lot because it has spread the word because it's Google spreading the word
and not just us spreading word and we have had we've had two KDE conferences
in India that the students themselves started with like hundreds of students
each and set the EV paid for you know KD people to fly over there and do the
talks and stuff it was really cool but we've got we have some American students
not as many as I would like but also lots of European students so that's
pretty cool one place we're lacking is Africa I
think the word is just not spreading and I also think that there's not good
enough connectivity for African students to get involved well so let's talk a
little bit about organizing a community and getting involved so we did this
meetup it was fun it was what like eight or nine of us eight of us or something
like that not very big you know I'm about to get on a plane and fly to Ohio
Linux fest which I suspect are probably one of the larger Linux events of the
year and it's such a huge like one-to-one difference it couldn't be two
two more opposite sides of the spectrum however I kind of think there's probably
we should be doing more of these small group meetups I feel like this is it's
it was interesting because we we had we had a gentleman there from the visual
design group at KDE we had the developer of KDE connect there we had yourself
there and we had folks that are involved with you know deploying KDE on recycled
machines and all a whole range of different areas and it was just a nice
one-to-one conversation everybody had a chance to chat we didn't even we were
we were we were having so much fun talking with each other we didn't eat
the cake we forgot to eat the cake like we forgot to eat cake so that when does
that ever happen can't waste it so what would you impart on pond is it is it
just do you think part of the issue is is that we as geeks are just too
antisocial so we won't just take the next step and organize the meetups what
is holding us back with tools like meetup and on all these ways to organize
why aren't we seeing more of these local events do you think well I think in this
case Andrew I didn't even know him I had never met him before I'd never talked to
him before I talked I was talking to KD connect guy and he's like I just moved
to Seattle let's get together and I said okay well let's have a release party so
he's like oh there's this meetup thing like what that you know a couple days
before somebody had set that up so I think that it's just people taking the
initiative yeah I years ago my first computer was an Coleco Adam and I didn't
know how to use it so I started I started an atom users group and we met
for about five years we became such good friends I mean we were meeting when none
of us were even using the Coleco added anymore because you know 80k doesn't
know you know I don't know how many people started a user group because they
didn't know what they were doing but that's what I did I was like how else am
I gonna find out let's find some experts here I know that there are some the
internet came along we got hangouts we got mumble and we all just kind of stop
going and meeting up in plate in in person you know you used to have to go
to the computer store to get even your to get a box copy of your distro I try
to figure out what it is because I'm just as guilty of it but I want to try
to get out and see people more because it's neat to actually meet and discuss
stuff and is true because remember the computer user newspaper yeah oh wait for
that every month yeah and that's how we got users actually was advertising in
there right yeah free advertising of course yeah um yeah I think part of it
is time everybody seems so busy also a lot of people who started as teenagers
are now getting married and having children right and that sort of puts a
cramp in your style so you know here I am now I'm I'm retired and I have time
that's really why I got involved in open source I had been using Linux for over
ten years and I thought I have time now I should give back that was my next
question for you because you know we just got through a couple of weeks of
pretty tumultuous community drama and you know sometimes some of the KD
community members are involved in some of the drama I don't think they were
this last round but that can happen from time to time and I wondered like so when
you get to the point where you're ready to retire and kind of just indulge a
passion you got you go pretty far into the community you're in all the IRC
rooms IRC rooms how do you deal with the drama does it bother you what's your
approach to that in KDE I'm on the community working group and that that is
a group that the EV got together to actually deal with conflict in the
community and I am not scared of conflict I think that when people are
fighting about things that means they're passionate there's energy there so
what's usually happening though is that people are talking past each other
rather than thinking together and if there's a lot of energy around a subject
there's obviously a problem therefore we need to think together so rather than
clashing we should be listening to one another and thinking together and trying
to work our way through whatever the problem is yeah and I think sometimes
what would help is if we stopped talking to each other through our blogs and talk
to each other maybe chat or mumble or the phone yeah face-to-face to me there
is at back to what you were saying the small groups there is absolutely nothing
better than sitting and talking to somebody right you know it's funny too
like for example in a face-to-face meeting you can have a bunch of Linux
users and if one of those Linux users pulls out an iPhone nobody would say
anything but on the internet if one of one of if you're having a group chat and
somebody somehow figured out you had an iPhone they pulled out all of the Linux
users would jump on that person say oh you have an eye you have an iPhone what
are you doing like over the internet we're just we're just a little bit more
sometimes of jerks to each other like we just don't quite care as much but in
person you know we're nicer we're more understanding we listen a little bit
better and part of the reason that I'm in KDE I mean KDE runs on Windows and it
runs on Mac so we actually have as part of our community people who work oh sure
on making sure everything works on Windows and works on Mac and it's true
every once in a while they get disparaged no I shouldn't leave that I
shouldn't leave up these BSD either but I was just making kind of a like a
dramatic comparison because really yeah we're more critical over the internet
than we are in person is really what happens and it's just I think that's why
even these small meetups are really good because it can happen in small little
doses too it doesn't have to be these huge events I think it's it's happening
in our culture at large if you look at our politics and it's starting to
happen not just in the US but around the world that we're getting these polarized
groups and so we need to figure out how to you know and some people say that
that's because people used to have more time and used to pull together mm-hmm
and maybe maybe there's something to that I don't know well it all say what
you're taught what you're saying is something that I am actually trained in
is I have had a degree in leadership and everything that you're touching on is
exactly what I was trained on in in terms of Chris you're mentioning these
small groups but also you're mentioning getting together face-to-face you know
talking on the phone over as opposed to over each other's blogs that speaks to
everything that I was trained you voice communication and personal
communication is so much more important than say oh just fighting over blogs
that's just ridiculous yeah well fighting over fighting is generally not
very constructive anyway but it does show you that there's there's a point
around which there is a problem and there's energy that means it can be
solved mm-hmm and seriously I have a lot of hope both in the political sphere and
and you know look at all the energy that there is in free software we can we can
get past these things and we can solve the problems mm-hmm I really do I like
that it's optimistic too I like that all right well I'm gonna move you and
Eric up into the into the main group here and we'll just move on with the
show and Valerie and Eric stick around and we'll we'll chew through a few more
topics and I'll open up the mumble room to any questions for Valerie as well we
have a couple of emails that I want to help some folks with some some switching
to Linux problem so everybody stick around don't go anywhere we got a lot
more show but first I want to thank our next sponsor and that's ting ting is
mobile that makes sense my mobile service writer man I tell you it's never
been a better time to be a ting customer the Nexus 6 is gonna be coming soon to
the ting network and you can switch right now and start saving start saving
right now by switching your team because you'll only pay for what your users no
contract it's a flat six dollars for the line and then just your usage on top of
that ting just takes your messages your minutes your megabytes whatever your
usage is that's what you pay so I've got three lines right now it's six dollars a
line I was just last night looking around at another cellular carry to see
what they charge when you add another phone and it is forty freaking dollars a
month just for another line unbelievable and then they make you sign a two-year
contract on top of that no none of that anymore stop it you know that's not the
way it should be that's not where you're gonna get value from your mobile
provider go with ting go to linux.ting.com linux.ting.com not only is that
like a little quick way of saying yo thanks for supporting Linux unplugged
but it'll also get you a $25 credit towards your first ting device take $25
off your first ting device then you've got a ting service you're only paying
for your usage there's no contract no early termination fee and you've got a
real person who will answer the phone if you call them try it right now 1855 ting
FTW anytime between 8 a.m. or 8 p.m. business hours then they got a real
person there and that real person solves your problem because they're geeks and I
mean that in a loving way you guys know that over at ting they're geeks like
we're geeks and they can solve your problem that's why when you go you want
to call somebody you want somebody that's really into the phones that they're
talking about that's what so I like their approach about that and their
dashboard they just gave it a brand new upgrade and it's better than ever they
have such a great ting dashboard that gives you a full oversight of where
you're at so go to linux.ting.com and I was doing some digging around using big
data you know man how I you know how man I'm a big data analyst did you know
did it oh absolutely like your side gig yeah big data Matt big data so I was
looking at the big data over what turns out Linux unplugged audience is sneaky
they've been picking up the Moto G I don't know where I'm they probably find
themselves a CDMA sprint compatible Moto G and they've been bringing over to the
ting network and any on their own map they went to linux.ting.com they got a
$25 service credit they found the ting user forum where there's Moto G users in
there talking about how to get it to work I'm not exaggerating when I say the
Moto G is one of the most popular phones among Linux unplugged audience members
and it's not even a phone ting sells directly this is a super cool about ting
is they have a support network in their forums where you'll find people that are
trying out things like Firefox OS Sailfish OS on different phones and ting
doesn't go in there and go shut up stop talking they don't stamp it down in fact
sometimes you see some of the employees and they're giving a few tips it's
awesome and it just gives you a little insight into ting's culture so go to
linux.ting.com to get started no more contract my friends no more get out of
that contract they also got an early termination relief program if you is in
a contract they'll pay up to $75 per line you gots to get cancelled go to
linux.ting.com and a big big thank you to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged
okay so let's see if we can help and then we'll get into one of our topics so
I want everybody get your heads together Jose writes in he says hola Chris and
everyone in the JBU community I'm writing to see if there's a way you guys
can help me out before I go on sorry if I get any of the technical terms wrong
I'm a forensic psychologist and I've started to learn more about computers
and tech stuff so naturally because he's gone down the right path he's wound up
at Linux so here's this problem I want to switch to a Linux distro full-time
currently I'm a Mac and Windows 7 user this guy I love him already Mac and
Windows 7 user this is our bread and butter right here however I've been
playing around with Mint Debian Arch and Ubuntu on VirtualBox so far I love it
there's just one huge issue that's keeping me from doing the change I think
it's my HP laptops hardware every time that I try to boot from an ISO the
kernel starts up I see it's do its thing and after the screen goes black it never
comes back I've tried Arch, Mint, Ubuntu, Manjaro, Fedora, you name it the only two
that I've managed to boot up and install is Mint using combat compatibility mode
and Manjaro with hot with the hardware detection tool the problem is after
installing it happens again starts to boot up I see some kernel stuff and then
black I got an HP Pavilion with an AMD Radeon HD he doesn't say
specifically which eight gigs of RAM he's got a SATA 640 gig blah blah blah
what can I do is this a stupid mistake can you help me he just wants to switch
and I know I don't have an HP anybody in the Mumble Room have an HP Pavilion laptop
that has experienced any problems with booting up getting their display
showing I know it's not super uncommon but it's not a problem I've had for a
while I haven't had that exact problem in an in an HP book but I've had that
problem numerous times on other laptops and the way I've always fixed it is
booting with the no-mode set yeah I were kind of discussing here that almost
sounds like he's having a UEFI secure boot problem you just need side of
disabled secure boot or something well we said it's Windows 7 right well Windows
7 well he's a Windows 7 user but the system may not have come with Windows 7
probably no so the thing is I mean I've tried no I have a HP laptop it's a
pavilion that has that issue every once in a while and I've actually had a
couple computers that have a problem where HP has this weird flaw in some
laptops where it's the display is actually working perfectly fine but the
brightness level is completely off yeah so you have to add you have to
manually add the brightness higher but you can actually do a script that will
also automate it so a dog Z and the IRC says he has an HP pavilion laptop no
mode does work no mode set to get his gentoo yeah that's so you add so here's
what here's the problem is is I think Jose kind of got that when he did like
compatibility mode it probably like the you know the option and grub probably
just appends no mode set but the issue that he's been running into well maybe
not but like he got that far but the problem is is he maybe could append it
to the to the live CD but then he has to remember to also once the systems
installed he's gonna have to hit II at the grub menu there and append it to his
installed boot menu to until he gets his graphic situation worked out and then
maybe if he gets a new graphical environment stalls the proprietary
driver I don't know at least Bantu and Fedora if you when you boot when you're
going through the installer if you if you append no mode set or if in a bunch
I think you can actually at f6 and there's a there's a thing for options
and you can choose it it will automatically add it to your grub
config so it's persistent can you do that in a bunch too yeah you can I
believe so yeah yeah yeah I think it's f6 and it whatever it says modes at the
bottom and then you can just check no so you're saying if you hit f6 and you add
that and then you boot up the installer the installer will then append that to
the final installed version of grub yes but don't quote me on the f6 quote me on
whatever it at the bottom look from yeah like it when it boots up you see English
hit English and then it will give you an option install or boot to live
environment at the very bottom there's F keys and whatever one says mode you
click on that I think it's f6 it should be f6 the last time I installed it was f6
the other thing you can do is just add it to the kernel perimeters in etsy default grub
right yeah if he's already got it installed could do that boot to elastin
but okay so what though once he's up and going what do we think a proprietary
graphics driver would solve the problem long term so once once X starts you'd
at least get a desktop again because it's never coming back and if he puts it
in no mode set won't that be like low resolution once X starts up no with an
AMD card I would go I would go proprietary just because you're already
dealing with a problem set up as far as I'm concerned I AMD cards especially in
laptops are just a nightmare okay I would go proprietary based on the
experience I've had with AMD cards on laptops and I banged my head on this for
so many years I would if it was me yeah that is that is the thing right if it's
an older Radeon yeah and Rekai has a great suggestion the chat room as well
it might be an issue of function f3 to manually up the brightness oh yeah maybe
yeah but I might like Tripoli my S is Tripoli I actually have to go in and
code in there's an actual a grub information you have to add in to
actually get it to any of your function keys to work at all I mean including
your brightness I have an HP Pavilion can't remember it's like a 17 inch
laptop with a Radeon 5800 something in there I can't remember if I have this
problem so I if I might power it up tonight and so it would be no mode set
I'll add that to the boot options and now here's a foolproof way to know for
sure if it's an if it's a brightness issue or if you're truly getting a no
display server you take a flashlight I'm dead serious about this go into a
dark room and with it booted up shine on there you'll see whether or not if it's
on or not yeah yeah a couple people yeah it's a brand because the pixels are
there the backlight just doesn't shine bright and I actually actually the
backlight inverts so like when it boots up it sets the backlight to a hundred
you guys deal with this crap seriously Jose what you do is just stick stick
with Windows until you can afford to buy a computer just a run no I'm kidding I
don't know though I mean like killing about these issues it feels like we're
back in the 90s all of a sudden and I guess but it does develop good skills I
guess the other thing I was gonna suggest is I wonder if he couldn't just
hook up I mean maybe just a troubleshoot and maybe look at logs and stuff like
that an external monitor I'm sure probably especially depends whether or
not if he's going like you know s-video HDMI or VGA a lot of depending on the
age of the laptop it could be VGA or s-video I mean just really depends but
if it's a VGA or HDMI it'll probably work if it's s-video shoot yourself in
the foot right now yeah all right we got we got two two bigger thicker topics I
want to get to but first I just I wanted to just talk about Steam OS for a second
because you know we have no idea what's gonna happen there but I like to
speculate and Zach the Penguin wrote in he says hey guys long time since I wrote
I was messing around with Steam's whole steam from a Windows computer thing
which is pretty awesome and the thought popped into my head what if the
long-term goal here is for valve to stream games to steam boxes like on
live did it would completely eliminate the Windows only problem and adds value
to steam to serve it as a service I know right now it's only a local network
deal but it might be possible for steam to do this from their own servers in the
future so here's what he's suggesting is that perhaps the LAN steam streaming we
see today is the early groundwork for something that valve would then deliver
over the internet down the road so you buy a steam box you don't have to have a
local Windows PC they go all on live on you and they stream the game let's say
let's say this is valve and if they do it they're gonna do it right so let's
just let's assume it's gonna work right let's just take that as a grant as a
granted we'll see all the piping challenges gone right do you think a
this is something valve would consider Matt and B would this sort of solve a
huge problem for steam machines as then you get all of these great native Linux
games and if you want a legacy Windows game from the quote-unquote PC era or
whatever they would call it we'll stream it to you from the valve online service
do you think that you would you see him doing only two ways I see this working
realistically speaking if I'm valve the only way I would reliably do this
especially with games that might require a little bit more back-and-forth data
would be to team up with Google and the reason why is because then you know for
a fact that you've got a partner who has a vested interest in connectivity that
you guys can kind of sync up what's needed to get that data back and forth
boy that's dirty though but yeah Joe blows ISP emporium you know they may not
care they may be like oh yeah you want us to help you know saturate our network
yet but you can go buy this we're not gonna help you yeah so that would be the
downside otherwise lower end games maybe you know I don't know right vault
vault you say Nvidia tried it and it didn't work yes they if I remember
correctly they tried making a it was displayed during e3 or something I
believe it was sort of like a cloud hosting for your games where it was
speculated like oh you can put it at your ISP and ISP can actually deliver it
to you hmm yeah and it they store it for you and then stream it to you yes sort
of like that like the these people can or companies can be oh we want to buy a
rack or something of these dedicated processing and then rent it off to our
customers yeah I don't see if steam ever wanting to get into that kind of
infrastructure investment to want to render all these games and stream it to
people and all the ISP agreements it just sounds like so much bureaucratic
telco BS I just don't see anybody at valve having the will to suffer through
it and it will never ever be comparable to local gameplay and I think valve at
the end of the day cares a lot about the local gameplay pay play experience and
they know that people are willing to pay to have slightly more powerful systems
if they want to play those kinds of games I think it is lit I think the steam
streaming is what it is what it is it is a transitionary tool to migrate from
your old crappy piece of junk Windows PC that has all kinds of problems into this
nice new steam box now I think it was a little bit envisioned during the time
when everybody thought the tablets were gonna rule the world and PCs were going
away but I think it still has some potential that's tough yeah that's a
tough one all right so we we do have some big topics including Microsoft
announcing that they just full-on love Linux now
Satya Nadella I'm not dude I don't know did you see the picture did you know he
was up on stage doing a live stream in Satya Nadella behind him on the
projector has Microsoft Hearts Linux I got I got a picture for those of you
watching the video version right there is there a knife sticking out of Tux's
back or oh I see it now okay yeah isn't that something Microsoft Hearts Linux so
we're gonna talk about what that means and where Microsoft is going with that
and then also you might have heard about the initiative to fork the Debian
project or at least some veterans are considering it and then forking Fedora
came up but that conversation ended fairly quickly we'll talk about that in
just a moment but first I want to tell you about Digital Ocean head over to
digitalocean.com right now and get yourself ready for this one you're never
gonna guess it unplugged October that's the promo code right all lowercase one
word unplugged October we'll get you a $10 credit over Digital Ocean you're
like what is Digital Ocean Chris because I live under a rock and do not know
about super awesome services that are blowing up like crazy well I'm glad you
asked me Digital Ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering
the most intuitive and easy way to spin up a cloud server some of you can get
started in about 55 seconds some of you can get started in about 32 seconds 22
seconds it's nuts send them to me take a screenshot email I'm Chris at Jupiter
broadcasting.com you guys is crazy and by guys I mean guys and gals just a
little disclaimer here's what you get for five dollars per month 512 megabytes
of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD yeah they're all SSD one CPU and a terabyte of blazing
fast transfer why because Digital Ocean has tier one bandwidth providers at
their data centers in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam and London
I blows my mind you guys I log in there and I like updating my system just
because I like seeing download numbers that high I'm not even joking at all
it's that awesome and one of the great things about Digital Ocean is that
dashboard it is super simple and intuitive but yet extremely powerful
you can take snapshots backup migrations move transfer droplets to different
users DNS management one-click installs of the entire LAMP stack GitLab WordPress
all sitting on top of KVM it's really slick and I think the best part is that
API and you can use that API to take advantage of some of those services on a
much larger scale and Digital Ocean right now for a little while I don't
know how long because it's crazy to me I think this is nuts but I understand why
they're doing it because they're crazy about getting the quality of their
tutorials up crazy Digital Ocean I tell you what they're willing to pay you up
to $200 if you write a tutorial for them and they have editors that will work
with you so you don't have to be like a wordsmith you don't got to be a
wordsmith they'll work with you if you've got a great tutorial they'll pay
you for it and that's Digital Ocean's commitment to getting the tutorials up
on their site the highest quality possible because their dashboard is all
about getting you going the way you even fund your account is about making it as
simple and out of the way as possible the API all of it everything is about
making sure you can get your infrastructure up and running as fast as
possible to get on to your work and that's why they're trying to have the
best documentation as well digitalocean.com use the promo code unplugged
October to get a $10 credit you can try out that $5 rig for two months for
absolutely free and a big thank you to Digital Ocean for sponsoring Linux
unplugged okay Matt put your crazy hat on because you're not even gonna believe
some of the ridiculous shenanigans going down right now so our buddy friend of
the show Satya Nadella was up on stage today talking about how great Azure is
and how wonderful Linux is with Azure he says did you guys know it's like peanut
butter and chocolate that's not actually what he said but isn't it more like
peanut butter and motor oil I mean he did talk a little bit about how great
Azure has become and I just wanted to touch on this because this is the new
Microsoft this is the Microsoft that is now competing with Linux not on the
desktop but in these service like infrastructure type ways so a Microsoft
has rolled out 300 major new features and services in the last 12 months to
Azure bullet point number one there are 10,000 new Azure customers per week there
are currently 350 million active active directory users on Azure so they have
active directory up on Azure over 2 million developers are using Visual
Studio Online to connect directly to Azure and customers are using once we're
only using basic Azure services 60% are now using higher level services and
number one core OS is now supported in Azure the container optimized Linux
distribution with a minimal memory footprint is available starting today in
the Azure marketplace so they are all about Linux guys is this okay so I'm an
old fart when it comes to Microsoft I grew up in Microsoft I grew up in
Microsoft's backyard I've been in and out of there checking judge you know
chatting with friends for years I've watched them for a long time and the one
thing that I'll tell you that really stood out is they are some competitive
SOBs over there at Microsoft and can I really trust that they're all in with
Linux or is this embrace and extend again Matt I go to you first personally
I feel like that yes in the sense that they've tried like butting heads with
you know the Linux direction the Linux ideas the Linux all the all anything to
do with Linux they tried that it didn't work that's kind of the bomber air I
think in this case they realized that if they're gonna remain relevant 10 15
years forward they're going to have to start playing nicer with their
neighbors so I think it's legit I think it's legit for selfish reasons they're
not there to be your buddy they would soon as you know they're not they're not
there for nice reasons they're there out of preservation I think and you keep in
mind I know people that are Microsoft admins that work for Microsoft events
that put on you know that like some behind-the-scenes stuff yeah it is but
because they're being put there and they're not thrilled about having to
learn this stuff they're literally in lockdown mode learning stuff in a hurry
because they're suddenly this has become a thing long term you know they're
they're hoping that they're basically just trying to remain relevant I think
that's the big the big piece of it will it matter 10 15 years down the road I
don't know yeah I think it's legitimate but it's not legitimate for the reasons
why people might think oh they've changed their mind and they're being
nice now it's not it at all it's survival honestly it's it's being able
to remain competitive with things that are frankly it's a it's a pragmatic you
know it's a pragmatic Microsoft it pretty much wimpy why is it that you and
I kind of feel a little dirty when we talk about this what is it why are we
why do we have this bias what's going on well it just it feels uncomfortable this
is not this is not Microsoft's area I used to work as an enterprise architect
for Windows platforms and before that I was a Unix admin and since then I've
worked exclusively in Linux and these are not the same market spaces and I
would be really interested to know how sort of the Windows admins feel about
this statement from Microsoft that they love Linux they must be shitting their
pants right now that is a good point I didn't think about it from that
perspective let's ask Valerie since she has some perspective on the matter
Valerie do you do you buy the new Microsoft or are you skeptical oh she's
not in the room right oh what do you think you take it
with the whole Microsoft thing um Adela really wants to go towards for if the
cloud infrastructure sure he knows that Linux does better in cloud than Windows
server does so I just think he's come to the realization and the company is
coming to the point where they can't serve survive with just Windows Server
alone they have to start branching out and using something like Linux and yeah
I think I think he's trying to take the company in the right direction in terms
of the service market yeah I think it's interesting to watch and it's more
options for more deployments of Linux that seems like a good thing okay anybody
else want to comment on that before we go to the next kind of crazy thing that
I was like what this week that just made me kind of flat-footed alright next one
did you guys see the roll up your sleeves we may need to fork Debian site
did you guys catch this and I'll just read the first paragraph here we are
veteran which is bolded by the way veteran Unix admins and we are concerned
about what's happening to canoe slash Linux Debian edition and they're
considering forking the project I want to stop right here okay I think that's a
great idea I think fork it like instead of instead of delaying the progress of
the distribution or the direction yeah fork it and go your own way that seems
like that actually seems like the right approach to take especially if you're
never going to be satisfied with the system D version of Debian you know that
seems like a pretty reasonable response and I I hope they do I think the
competition would be good the thing that I can't get past it seems like a lot of
other people have picked up on it is is the language used there veteran Unix
admins and bolded that what that does is sort of projects old farts and I'm not
trying to be derogatory I'm just saying like from a messaging standpoint people
are saying that makes you sound like a bunch of old farts and it people sort of
write it off wow what do they care a bunch of stick in the muds and it's sort
of like it immediately makes people not take it very seriously well you know
looking at from my perspective I think it's a combination of quote-unquote old
farts as well as people that are of the mind that if it isn't broke why fix it
at least from their perspective and so you might have an inner mixture of
individuals in that space wimpy do you think they're just crazy well they're
exercising their right to free speech and all power to their elbow and
everything and if they want to have a go at forking Debbie and then I think
everyone should just stand back and let them get on with it and let themselves
burn yeah just just let's just try to take those two words together fork
Debian okay forking is hard I have first-hand experience of forking really
small projects in the comparison with Debian so they want to fork Debian just
think about all of the infrastructure that's involved there and all of the
platforms and ever it's just crazy nonsense and Ian Jackson's obviously got
an opinion about this and he posted his thing to the mailing list to suggest
that this was you know evaluated one last time very expressly stating he
didn't want to turn this into a system D versus whatever in its system debate
and then the internet explodes with system D inferno again this is so
disappointing it's just it's just laughable and and if they want to fork
Debbie and yeah do that thing I'm all for it I'm gonna watch that gleefully
from afar yeah I would be pretty skeptical myself and vault you think no
no don't fork don't don't do that we need more resources as it is not less
people working on the same stuff well that's obviously the but my actual
practical point is no don't fork it find a way to accommodate you know multiple
in its systems in Debbie and if you want to for Debbie and yeah go on to me if
they're never gonna be interested in being involved with the project in that
state then they should just fork it you're not really losing resources
because if they weren't gonna cooperate anyways you're not losing them they
already they're already lost so let them go off and do their own thing well no
the thing is is that no well yeah okay if they want to fork Debbie and fork
Debian but there's their system BSD there's useless day yeah there are
shims around system D if they were really serious about coming up with an
alternative they would be looking at those projects in terms of developing
them and supporting them within the Debbie and community rather than saying
we're gonna fork Debbie and which is frankly insane oh yeah you're talking
the biggest distribution there is the mother of most of our distributions yeah
that's a huge undertaking if you think would you do a would you do a complete
fork or would it be more like sort of a clone of straight-up Debbie and where
you're just constantly swapping out the system D parts for something else well
one thing that comes to mind that I want to point out here is that now last time
I checked most computers with blogging platforms attached don't have
breathalyzers ready so it's entirely possible they were fit-shaped and they
got on a year maybe no I'll tell you I'll tell you who's a little s-faced how
about this one how about this one fork fedora org shall we fork fedora not
really it's doing great maybe we're not veteran enough that's great that's
really that is fantastic they sound like they're really housed you know what yeah
yeah they're really housed right yeah no Matt did prove that that he did
actually later up on G plus I think like ten people on the whole internet but
still we exist yeah that actually is getting housed as a term I don't it's
like got a ridiculous origin though or something I don't remember it's
abbreviated from you know okay but this fork business like shall we fork
fedora time to fork Debian I've never well actually we have the only time I
think we've ever seen the Linux community this riled up and just unable
to just move forward for a long time was like the Microsoft Novell deal where you
had boycott Novell prop up and you had all this stuff and there was such
decisive lines and it went on for like two years but really not I mean you know
it was it was not as bad two years but it really went on for a while and this
is like we haven't had a good old classic drama like this since then it's
like the good old days again who are all right I remember the old Novell thing
and I'm sitting there going thinking that's great I'm gonna go watch TV now
because I'm just like this is gonna be a week-long thing and people are gonna
blow it over yeah that still cracks me up just all right wimpy go ahead ask the
question that's on everybody's mind well I'm putting myself out there again is
the bloke that says you know system D is really quite good but I I often wonder
reading what some of the people say about system D and also listening to
other podcasts and what they have to say about system D and I'm left with the
impression of you've never actually used it not only have you never actually used
it you've never actually sat down and written a unit file you're not a package
maintainer you haven't had to deal with init scripts and you haven't seen the
benefits of migrating package from an init script to system D and and the
many other benefits of system D now I can appreciate that people are very very
firm in their opinion that they like the way things are and and there's a place
for that but I think a lot of the speculation and commentary about system
D is being had by people who simply do not know what they're talking about now
I'm not suggesting necessarily that fork Debian falls into this camp they would
claim to be seasoned Linux administrators and every and veterans
quite so maybe they do know what they're talking about and they have legitimate
reasons as to why they feel system D is not going to to suit them but there are
some podcasts where I've heard them debating the the various init systems
and talking about the pros and cons and then admitting partway through there you
know slacking off of system D they've never used it yes think well how are you
qualified to have an opinion my my so my stance on the system D discussion I
think if you look over the history of this show has an arc where I'm pretty
neutral don't give a crap and then I become pretty pro system D and then I
get to a point where I was a little belligerent to people who didn't who
didn't seem to think going forward with system is a good idea because the reason
I've I don't know belligerence right word but I'll just label it that the
reason why I felt that way is because as as a sys admin of like 14 15 years there
are literally things that I see in system D that I think if I had that when
I was managing servers I would have hated my job so much less like it's not
just small stuff that I see in system D some of the things that system D brings
as a whole I see as fundamentally necessary for Linux to remain
competitive at scale like without those things and with and without those things
free BSD could easily eat our lunch really because essentially we're we're
just as capable and but system D offers so many things and the problem is you
really don't know how important they are until you've deployed Linux at scale or
you have a you know a very network demanding thing or you have something
that has to be as absolutely minimal as possible and support socket activation
or you need something that's integrated with namespaces all these things that
are edge cases but together matters so much and may and are so important to
keeping Linux competitive not just on the server but also in mobile that when
you when you come when you argue against system D what you have to realize is you
have to really come with something that's extremely compelling because what
you are arguing for is essentially removing what I in my personal opinion I
and I'm not saying it's right but in my personal opinion are fundamentally
critical features to keep Linux competitive so if you're gonna say no
system do you've got to have an answer for those problems and and yeah I don't
think you and I can have a debate about this because I think we're clearly on
the same side of the fence and we've got we've got our personal opinions it
sounds like a largely similar reasons so really what we need is somebody to step
up and tell us why we're wrong and I I think part of it is some of the more
vocal people debating this are not the same people who are as impacted by it
like I think there's a group of people that care a lot but they're just not as
vocal about debating it I think I'm trying to because I get emails that seem
really well reasoned but I even then I've still not been convinced the
biggest things that convinced me that it might be a problem are always the what
if scenarios and I think yeah if that happens we could have a problem but
that's not a today problem that's a what-if problem anyway so how do we get
talking about oh yeah the forks yeah so there you go the system D conversation
once again has been stirred back up by these project forks and you know what's
interesting is you check the Linux forms like r slash Linux and just general
discussion forums and people are constantly still asking about it it is
genuinely a topic that even though it seems like we've talked about it at
nauseam people still seem to care about I guess that's sort of the fun of being
a Linux user is you get to care about such nitty-gritty things like your
display compositor and system D and all that stuff so I guess that's why we're
that's why we do it all right well so you probably already know this but Linux
action show won't be live on Sunday it's gonna be on Monday and I think I don't
know if Ange told you Matt but I think we're gonna try start at two o'clock so
you probably want to get to the studio around 1 30 because then we're gonna try
to fit in a foe too and then we'll be able to show all the highlights from
Ohio Linux fest so if you're gonna be in Ohio this weekend come say hi to some
of us there some of the crew will be there and we'll be going out and getting
our party on in the evening so join us for that as well and then join us for
Linux action show Monday afternoons we'll have the time in your local times
and over at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar and Eric is reminding me
dutifully so that you can also say hi to him at seagull is there anything you
want to plug about that Eric say hi to Eric and Valerie at the sea it's seagull
right that's how you say it yes se a GL and you can find it at just google for
seagull but I think it's like seagull org and it's a it's a Seattle Linux
users group meetup right or who's put on it's a Seattle GNU Linux conference
thank you thank you I don't know why I can't remember that but anyways there's
a ton of stuff going on so come out and say hi to us Valerie thanks a bunch for
coming on and I can't wait for our next meetup maybe in December or something
like that yeah is there anything you want to mention before we wrap up we
have a like a couple of minutes you know what you know why is because we we we
talked about it quite a bit on Sunday show so we just kind of got our we just
kind of got our come into one but if there's anything you wanted to mention
or specifically with the 14.10 release have that we have the we have the
release it's going to be pretty stable now it's coming after a long-term work
but so we usually are wild and crazy this time we are doing an alternate ISO
for the plasma 5 stuff oh awesome people should not except expect that to be
completely stable but we sure would love to have some testing and we don't know
if it will be ready six months from now for a release and without testing it
won't be so it's actually that plasma 5 ISO is what I used for Sunday's review
when I did that so that's so it's reasonably stable some people have had
some problems getting things to work getting it set up but once they get it
set up it's pretty cool awesome oh my god I need it and bug reports so and if
people wanted to connect with you online what's the best place for them to find
you in IRC or Valerie at kde.org b a l o r i e dot k error at kde.org awesome
all right well I look forward to our next meetup and I'll remember to
schedule time for beers next time I will not make that mistake again Valerie I
will not make that mistake again all right well that'll wrap us up for
today's episode of Linux unplugged will be we our regular Linux unplugged time
next week I don't think the Ohio Linux fest will affect our our regular
scheduled Linux unplugged so should be on Tuesday which is at 2 p.m. Pacific you
go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get that converted to your
local time well Matt so it's gonna be a little extra longer as you're gonna have
to go an extra day before you get to see the hair again are you gonna be all
right I think I can get by you know what you need to do is just like marathon a
TV show you got Saturday and Sunday to just really pound through something and
just show up Monday ready to do a show all right everyone well thanks so much
for tuning this week's episode of Linux unplugged don't forget we really want
your feedback go to Jupiter broadcasting comm click the contact link choose
unplug from the drop-down Linux action show dot reddit comms another great
place to go all right everyone thank you so much for
tuning this week's episode see you right back here next Tuesday
oh yeah oh oh yeah there we go all right so value will record the post show
too if there's any other couple into a bits you want to get in there while
everybody go to JB titles calm right now and vote JB titles calm everybody vote
all right so yeah there you go there you go once again we got in another system
D conversation where wimpy and I painfully agreed with each other we need
to encourage some people to have a rational argument for not system day
because I think both you and I have different similar but different reasons
as to why it suits what we're doing and we really need somebody yeah well it's
quite a little bit isn't it oh I know there are alternatives and I'm familiar
with some of them and I've obviously used a lot of them but I need somebody to
remind me why is there better because I've forgotten do we really think oh one
second I want to spawn I'm good no no no the fork fedora thing was a joke it's
not it's just a joke but no we're not yeah I still want all right sorry I
didn't mean to interrupt go ahead I think I was just gonna say one of the
districts I tried recently was um Phoenix it's a live CD distributor that
uses run it that's right and it's very functional Microsoft Hearts Linux fork
you Debbie in fork it all I like that too yeah so I've used running in the
past for some for some for demonizing some processes because it has some
features that traditional in it's didn't have so yeah that's very good
Valerie you should twist Eric's arm to leave the mumble info behind so you
could join us in the future whenever you feel like it yeah I actually did paste
that into the Katie could go into off topic chat room did I not oh good good
yeah so whenever there's anything kaboom to related that you want to get the word
out about or or Katie or anything you can you could always just pop in the
mumble room and we'll give you the floor for a couple of minutes okay so let's go
to JB titles and so are we liking for forks sake we like that not Katie or not
to fork Debbie in I like the wimpy is like think about that fork yeah quite
the task so tonight and you and I are gonna mail out hopefully a whole bunch
of boxes of swag and stuff we're gonna bring to Ohio Linux fest so that should
be cool Colonel Linux are you in here I am oh you haven't said anything for so
long I thought maybe you left I missed you no I'm still here that's the base so
yeah so I didn't want to come off too strong in the recording but I'm like 100
percent sure that no modes that will fix that guy's laptop okay cool yeah and I
see I thought I see the reason why I for some reason I thought no meds no mode set
just sort of put X in the light crappy mode mmm it's funny I actually couldn't
tell you what it does it stops kernel mode switching happening it doesn't do
the resolution detection and auto resolution adjustment it just goes with
the basic BIOS so but why is it not being resolved when X starts if it's
that if it's the console resolution then how come when X is starting it's not
fixing the problem because wouldn't that whoa so that was the only thing I
wasn't sure about is it it seemed like to me that if no mode set would fix it
then it then it shouldn't be happening next that the only thing I thought the
only thing but I don't know I don't use no I don't really ever have to I
seriously have bought system 76 laptops for so long now that I haven't had to
fight with someone I tell you what here's here's how sure I am here's how
sure I am you put a filter on that guy's name if you send you another email
saying no mode set fixes it you pick out a beer you want I'll send you a 12-pack
no I'm looking right now there's other people talking about and talking about
no mode set on askabuntu.com too well here's here's the other thing like for
this is for my machine it will not run a kernel older than 3.12 efficiently 3.11
I have to use no mode set otherwise it doesn't render graphics at all several
people like Recon Chomper saying could be a brightness issue too so let's see
all right so for fork's sake is currently at the top here so we can just
go with that I suppose all right Noah Noah can I ask you a question about
your Ubuntu unity review yeah you you mentioned about crypt setup can you just
talk me through what you saw exactly because I've got some background in this
and I just want to hear what you saw precisely what I saw well okay so excuse
me if this is a little too dumbed down I apologize but so I opened my laptop I
clicked on my encrypted drive and it said unable to decrypt kernel Linux or
well slash media slash kernel Linux no crypt setup found and then I had to get
on to Wi-Fi pseudo apt-get install crypt setup and then I was able to then
decrypt my hard drive so so this wasn't at boot time when Plymouth should give
you the password from put your passphrase in correct however the fact
that that option exists that I can encrypt my hard drive at boot time means
that the package which was I found out was all of like 4 megabytes is clearly
included in the install media so why not just install that what what possible
reason would I not want the ability to decrypt my decrypt encrypted drives like
what advantage does that serve it sounds to me like that's something he ain't a
few people to fix like ha ha if Popey was here as if so I've been chasing
people around at canonical for two months about this issue now and I've
been pestering Popey until he's probably bored of hearing from me because
anything I mentioned now is by the way you can't decrypt full disk encryption
with the new version of Plymouth and it's one of the things that I attempted
to fix in the current release candidate of Ubuntu Marte I have effectively fixed
it it's actually a Plymouth bug and I think canonical have just released a
fix for it this evening so Crip setup does get installed the issue is is that
Plymouth doesn't pass the passphrase through properly or wasn't passing it
through properly well in this the absolutely ridiculous thing is I
understand like so open SSH server doesn't doesn't come with default but
that I get right because there's a security implication I cannot think of a
one single reason of how having that package there other than the fact that
it occupies four megabytes of disk space which even even in today's world of
solid-state drives that are ridiculously small still is is negligible so it just
infuriated me I had four hours I couldn't get to any of my files and I'm
like 12 before 1210 1304 and 1310 all had Crip setup installed by default I
guess I didn't check it 1404 does but really like what the hell guys yeah Crip
setup is installed by default that's not the issue it's the fact that Plymouth
doesn't invoke it correctly to decrypt your drive when you chosen to do full
disk encryption and like I say there's been three of us in the Ubuntu Marte
team aware of this for months and we've been adding logs and messages to I don't
know about eight or nine bugs in launchpad about this for months now and
it's just got fixed today well at the same time Plymouth has quite a bit of
breakage I mean even in arch like 0 9 0 the version that's on the AOR it's
broken in broken in fedora it's broken upstream it's frankly not fit for
purpose so I've back ported 0.8.8 and giving it a version of 0.9.0 plus really
0.8.8 yeah I switched to mate the Ubuntu mate edition I'm at a mate mate
hi dang it dang it all right maybe we should wrap but I wanted to leave with
this if anybody in the Ohio area who's listening to this knows of some great
places right around where the Linux fest is gonna be at that we could go to some
holes in the wall or something like that tweet him at me at Chris Elias you got
it you're my intelligence network I need I need people on the ground is what I'm
saying I need like people there boots on the ground taking care of the situation
they're they're they're not combat boots though they're just there as advisors to
advise me about Ohio Columbus any boobs on the ground would be great too if it's
not if it's not right around the hotel that also should be okay because we have
vehicular transportation yeah all right so I so Chris yes before you dashed you
want do you want one little bit of inside information always but I'm
recording wait do I have to stop recording okay no no you can record you
don't put it out necessarily and it's me I'm not gonna give away any names because
I don't know them all yet all right but you remember the whole gun was buck
deployment on open Sousa and Marte and that good stuff yeah small town of 50,000
people and you asked me what I knew about that and I said I don't know very
much what I know about the next one the next one is going to be in Germany the
next one is going to be a remote terminal services deployment based on
extra go and I happen to know that the desktop operating system they're going
to be using is up into Martin you know I should I should do an extra go segment
I still have Marte installed I mean not that I wouldn't uninstall it but I'm
probably gonna go back you can use it on a number of distros but I mean I'm get
this I've got an expenses paid trip to Germany at the end of the month and I am
getting to stay in get this the Linux hotel