Now, Wes, I know that you, maybe not home automation, so to speak, but you have found
a way to do a lot of little things with free and open source technology, right?
Like the open source Plex alternative.
Are you familiar with anything that you might not think off the bat could be home automation,
but in fact could be?
What do you mean?
Say that again.
So I think a lot of people wouldn't necessarily consider Plex to be part of a home automation
thing, but I would because it goes into the home theater, goes into the living room, goes
into the master bedroom, wherever, and then provides essentially automated media, right?
I can access my media on demand.
I would consider that part of my automation system.
I'm wondering if you know of any other, if you have any other suggestions or any other
ideas or anything else that you've tried like that, that one could use to free and open
source-ally automate one's home.
Yeah.
Well, one I was just looking at is a, I know many people frown on it, but frequently I'm
faced with routers that use UPnP.
Yes.
And, you know, some applications are UPnP aware and they will automatically forward
the ports, but some are not.
And sometimes, you know, maybe you're visiting a family member or who may not even know the
admin password to their router.
You're in a situation where you don't have the freedom to open ports willy-nilly as you
see fit.
Right.
And for that, I found a nice little UPnP-C, it's called, or UPnP-D that have a daemon
and a client, and it lets you to interact with any UPnP-compliant router to specify
ports to forward or delete port forwards as you want, so you can customize it for whatever
application you're using.
That's awesome.
See, I do, as a network security guy, I do have some reservations about using UPnP.
You know, and I do as well.
But sometimes you're on a network where it's already enabled and you just have to work
with it.
You know, if you're...
Yeah.
So, I found it useful there.
I personally don't use it at home, but...
And it sure is convenient, isn't it?
Oh, yeah.
It's awesome.
You know, and they also have, they have like the project that's doing it, they have a user
space implementation, a lot of the BSD, TCP, IP stack, and so they also use that to provide
the daemon.
So, if you did want to use UPnP and you didn't have a device that used it, you can use their
daemon protocol to run it yourself if you'd like to have it stick it on your PFSense box
or anything else.
Why you would do that, I don't know, but you can.
That's the beauty of free and open source.
Why did you say that you think that some people frown on it?
Is it just the UPnP aspect?
Yeah.
You know, I mean, I think a lot of people, and I know certainly Alan's talked about it,
but just that, you know, the idea of people opening ports in your firewall without your
express permission or especially apps, maybe you're running proprietary applications that
you don't, you know, you don't really have a handle on what it is they're sending.
Right.
So, that's a big problem that I see, you know, and that's why I don't use it on my own home
network, but I know like in my parents' house, they have a ISP provided router that is UPnP
and client, and well, I do have their, you know, admin password.
Sometimes it's just easier if you're not, you know, I'm not going to be there for a
long time.
I don't need to leave a hole in their firewall.
I can just open it up while I'm there.
Sure.
Well, that does sound really cool.
I'll have to check that out.
Maybe we can get a link in the show notes and then people can go check that out.
Have you heard of Icebergs.io?
I was just checking that out this morning, actually.
Really?
So, I had not heard of it before, but apparently Icebergs.io, Ubuntu with an XFCE gives a
highly productive desktop experience in the browser with a quick and responsive on an
all-modern internet connection.
Now, they've actually optimized for touch devices, so you can run it on your phone,
for example, and you can access what essentially is a mobile operating system through a web
browser.
Do I have that right?
Yeah, absolutely.
You know, I just tried out the free account that gives you two compute hours a month,
and it also won't save, so anytime you're done with it, whenever you turn it off, it's
gone.
Whereas if you upgrade to a paid plan, then they'll be persistent.
How do they calculate a compute hour?
You know, I'm not sure.
I haven't looked into that yet, but that will be the sticking point because while they do
give you, the first paid plan I think is like $10 a month, and they give you two instances,
but you're also limited to compute hours there as well.
25 of them, if I'm not mistaken, right?
Yes, I believe so.
I think you can have multiple instances running, and each of those adds up to your compute
hours, but exactly how that gets built, we should check that out.
I was impressed though.
You know, it took a little bit to start up, but once everything was going, it was surprisingly
responsive and pretty easy to use.
Now for $9 a month, I could see this being really useful, and I've actually tried to
implement this.
I don't know.
Have you played with X2Go very much?
Yes.
Yes, I have.
You know, I frequently recommend it to people just because it's so easy to start using,
and it works a lot faster than most of the other alternatives.
So yes, I don't think I would...
For the price point of Icebergs.io, I'm not sure it's there for me yet.
Oh, really?
Well, that depends.
That depends on how willing you are to roll your own solution.
Yeah, that's true.
That's true.
Because if you already have the skills or the infrastructure to set up an X2Go server
with an environment of your choosing, provided you have enough bandwidth, then that would
probably be my preferred solution.
But I am intrigued by the idea of desktop Linux in the browser at a whim, kind of.
You know, so there are a couple of things that stand out to me.
One is, if you go with the service type solution, you're essentially cloudifying your existence,
and in doing so, you're losing control of your data.
One of the things I like about my X2Go machine is that it physically sits inside of my office.
I can go put my hand on it, and I know where that hard drive is at all times.
And there are some additional benefits to having that device physically located in a
place I can get to it.
For example, I have a little SATA hard drive reader that is plugged into my X2Go machine.
And so, if I have a lot of things off a staff member, they'll say, hey, boss, you know,
we're doing XYZ, and we're having a problem with it, and you know, I can't get this file
to open, or I can't get this file to do this, or I can't get these permissions done on this.
And I'll say, well, just take the hard drive and stick it into my drive reader.
And they can put it into the drive reader, and then from wherever I am, I can access
that data.
And then I can, you know, I can move it over to my laptop so I can work with it locally
if I need to, or 90% of the time, 99% of the time, I can get my work done actually on the
X2Go machine, provided I have a decent internet connection.
And that is, that's something that no matter how robust and how cool Iceberg becomes, I'll
always be missing that functionality, right?
So, it limits my ability to scale, I think, a little bit.
You know, I would, I would agree, and I think it ties into a lot of what some of our user
base, you know, a lot of the Linux user base has problems with a lot of proprietary software,
you know, one for maybe philosophical reasons, but also just because when you hit the edges
of things, you know, when you hit, you try to stretch something to a little bit different
purpose, or you need to customize something on a one-off thing, you're met with boundaries.
Whereas if you've rolled it yourself, you used free open source software, time is just
the limit for how much you can accomplish, you know, on the thing of the day.
Something though, that's interesting that it's like, it's kind of like a similar option,
but it's more of a app-based thing.
It's called RollApp, and it's rollapp.com.
And basically it does a server rendering of an application to your web browser, and it
also works on your phone too.
So in a way, like I've tested it and you can actually like use LibreOffice on your phone
through this service.
Wow.
That sounds slick.
It's actually like $7 a month or something, and you get like unlimited usage or whatever.
And it's impressive.
Like it works on your phone, it works on your tablet, it works on your web browser, and
it does like all different kinds of apps.
Like I think their total count is like 200 or something, but I tested with LibreOffice
and it actually is like not the most latest version, but it is like the next latest.
So like 5.0.1 or something like that.
Sure, sure.
But it actually works quite well, and they have like custom features built into the app
so that you have like double tap or two finger tap the phone to lay out a toolbar and all
kinds of stuff.
Like it's pretty impressive.
Can you give us an idea or an example of something that you've used with it?
I've just used LibreOffice with it so far.
Okay.
Yeah, but actually even that alone, I could see tremendous use case for it.
Yeah.
And it actually supports GIMP too.
Oh wow, really?
You can do imaging and everything, yeah.
Can you imagine the practicality of doing that?
Can you imagine the practicality of like modifying this image, like especially with like a touchscreen
device or something?
I know people are already complaining about GIMP's UI and now we'll hear no end to it.
Yeah, yeah.
Exactly.
Exactly, right?
In this case, you could probably maybe if you had like the single window mode is what
is necessary for like desktop stuff, but maybe on the phone, the separate windows would be
better because you could like full screen on the phone each of the windows.
I don't know, it might be a better solution.
Yeah.
So when Chris was here, we did some electrical upgrades to the RV.
I don't know if some of you, if you're patrons, you got the email from it and he actually
recorded a video.
That's pretty cool.
But essentially what we've tried to do is get everything to run off of 12 volts and
the advantage of that DC 12 volt is that one is he can charge on the solar panel and two
is he can actually run all of his equipment then off of those batteries.
So he's not reliant upon AC power.
I don't know, Wes or Rotten Corpse, have you guys had any experience with self-sufficient
powering yourself?
Not myself.
I have some friends who live on the big island of Hawaii and they're working on setting up
a hydroelectric system.
Oh, cool.
But before that, they were kind of reliant on friends' use of electricity to charge a
lot of the batteries they had, so they had already converted a lot of their infrastructure
to DC when they started playing around with this hydro.
So it was kind of interesting to see, you know, they had lots of, kind of the same kind
of modular setup, kind of plugging everything, every which way with those, they had the same
kind of connectors you were highlighting on the show.
Really?
Yeah.
The Anderson Power Bowls.
Yeah, yeah.
They were, they were showing, I didn't remember the name, but when you, when you show that
on the show, I was like, oh, those, that's exactly what they had going on.
You know, I don't mean to go fanboyish, but I absolutely love Anderson Power Bowls.
If you're not familiar with them, they are genderless low voltage connectors.
And so essentially they'll handle up to like 30 amps, the small ones, they have bigger
ones that'll handle like up to 250 amps, but it's a different, it's a, it's a bigger version
of the, of the smaller Anderson Power Bowl.
But the 30 amp guys, they, you can put them on to, I've used them on 12-Aug wire, I've
used them on, I think I've used them as high as 10-Aug wire and as small as 18-Aug wire.
You have to fold the 18 over a little bit and use some solder, but the nice thing is
they're genderless.
So you don't have to decide, is this going to be a power receiving source or a power
providing source?
You can, you, they can, you can be interchangeable with it.
And that's the case when it comes to something like a battery, sometimes the battery is providing
the energy and other times the batteries is receiving the energy from like a charger.
And so it, it offers a tremendous amount of flexibility and because of the standardization,
it will hopefully the idea is that it will give Chris the freedom to plug things in willy
nilly.
If he has to make a change on the fly, that becomes, you know, very big, very easy to
do.
Now it's interesting that you say that they're using, that they're using hydroelectric.
And that's DC because if you're, you, if you start with DC, if you generate DC and then
you run it off of DC, you're not losing any energy in a conversion process.
Right, right.
Yeah.
I think that's what they were going for.
You know, once they've got that running, they'll almost be self-sufficient except they, they're
still importing a large amount of propane for, for a lot of their utilities, but, but
other than that, they're, they've got their own farm going.
It's quite the project.
Awesome.
Anything else we want to cover in the pre-show before we get started?
I mean, if you want to go back to the icebergs thing, you could mention that there's os.js
if you wanted to.
Tell me about os.js.
It's a JavaScript based operating system thing and it's not full fledged or anything, but
it is legitimately ran through the browser, like dependent on the browser.
Okay.
So it's, it's, it has got a few, it's got a, it's mostly web app based, but it has other
things too.
Like it can run stuff on the backend and it, you can like put it, you can, you can install
it on like a DO droplet or something and have a interesting operating system available at
any time.
It's not, it's not like X2GO or anything, but it's still interesting.
See that, anything that, anything that I can install on top of a droplet or anything that
I can install quickly and then access everywhere has, has huge appeal to me because I can think
of so many practical places of where I could, where I could use something like that.
Have you tried it?
Yeah, I've tried it.
I haven't, I haven't put it on my own droplet, but I've tried their demo and it's, it's interesting.
It actually has like its own custom UI and everything and it runs apps pretty fast.
I mean, if you have to have a pretty good machine to do it though.
But it's, all I can say is interesting.
It's not practical at all right now, but it is, it is fun to play with.
You know, the nice thing about having its own UI is I bet it actually runs a little
bit more efficiently inside of a web browser then, huh?
Oh yeah.
It actually has like, I mean, I can't really describe the UI, but it had like the menu
system it uses is similar to like a Gnome 2 style.
Wow.
Do you know what the, the license is on that?
I'm pretty sure.
I know it's open source.
I'm pretty sure it's GPL'd.
That's that's awesome.
I, I, I'll have to take a look at that there.
My problem is when I run into things that like compete with something that is already
working so well, I have a hard time prying myself off of my current solution.
So for example, in this case, X2GO has worked for me so well and I've been able to get so
much done with X2GO that I'm having a really hard time.
I would have a really hard time prying myself away from X2GO to, to, to try something else
even if that something else is better and, and it wouldn't be the first time that I've
gone back and decided, oh yeah, actually, you know, XYZ worked a lot better the second
time around.
I just didn't know that it existed.
Yeah.
Okay.
So this one doesn't have, it's not GPL'd, it's a license that technically would be compatible,
but it's very limited in the license.
It's basically just keep the copyright there and then whatever else, you know, user your
own risk type thing.
But I wouldn't say that this was better than X2GO.
I think that X2GO is probably the best solution for someone who wants to roll their own cloud
based servers or desktop, whatever.
But I would say that if somebody wants just to kind of run stuff through the web roll
app is definitely worth looking into, especially considering you'd have like LibreOffice on
your phone and you could also roll it out to like hundreds of people and have the same
version available to all of them.
That's pretty awesome.
And you know, the thing is X2GO, I know that there are extensions that you go run inside
of Firefox, but primarily it's designed to be run inside of its own native client app.
It's not, you know what I mean?
It wasn't really designed to run, you know, in the browser.
So something that is, that is designed from the ground up to run in the browser, I like
again, I would think that would be a little bit more efficient, maybe have a little bit
more pleasant of an experience to it.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 112 for September 29th, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux show that's being brought to you today by
nothing short of a freaking miracle.
My name is Nolan, joining me from the Seattle studio is Wes.
Hey guys, it's Wes, pleasure to be here.
Now it's my honor and privilege to step in anytime Chris is off exploring somewhere yonder
this week, as it turns out in Utah, in the Jupiter Rover.
By the way, did you know that you can get minute by minute updates and follow his adventures
over at JupiterBroadcasting.com slash Rover?
Some of you might be wondering what I meant when I said that the show is being brought
to you today by a miracle.
And the answer actually starts back on Saturday at the meetup.
So first of all, huge shout out to North Ranger, who's in our chat room right now.
And everyone else that made the meetup on Saturday in Grand Forks, following Chris's
arrival and then subsequently his departure.
We were sitting down, we're having pizza, and we started talking about what the rest
of Chris's trip is going to look like.
And it is going to be, he's going through Utah.
And so we laid out a map, a route for him to take, and we're all kind of figuring that
out.
And if he had the cellular connectivity over his planned route, he was not going to have
coverage.
And if he did have coverage, he would have to drive like 10 hours in between Koda Radio
and Linux Unplugged to make both shows work.
That sounds fun.
Yeah, it sounded great, right?
It sounds like a great one.
So Sunday, he figured that out and he goes, you know, would you mind stepping up and helping
do the show?
And I said, yeah, I would love to, because Linux Unplugged is one of my favorite shows.
I love the community aspect and I'm friends with a lot of the people in the mumble room.
So it's kind of fun that instead of just, you know, chewing the straw off the air, you
know, at two in the morning, now we can all be on air and have productive conversations.
But the studio wasn't really set up for that because when Chris got here, we had reorganized
the way the studio was set up to accommodate the shows that he wanted to do in the way
that he wanted to do them.
And then additionally, my studio isn't really set up for hosting shows with music coming
in and all of this other stuff.
So I ended up buying some more audio interfaces and some new cables and redid everything Monday
to make things just more smooth so that we could go on the air and do this today.
Tuesday I wake up and my first trouble call is not from a client.
It's from my own office and my staff calls me and they're like, hey boss, guess what?
The internet went out today.
And I'm thinking, oh no, this isn't good.
Yeah.
No, we're an IT company.
We can't not have internet.
We have no access to emails.
We have no access to our SIP phone system.
We have no access to our work order system.
We can't get to the call center.
I have no idea what's going on in my own company and as I'm trying to sort that headache out,
it dawns on me.
Oh no, I have luck this afternoon.
So I immediately stop what I'm doing and I'm like, you guys fix the internet.
I have to get stuff ready so I can do love in a couple of hours.
So I start, I grabbed extra mixers and I'm grabbing audio cables and I'm grabbing cables
and microphones and I'm, I have all this stuff in my arms and I'm running down.
And Wes, have you ever done this thing where your arms are full and you start trying to
like fish your keys out with your pinky and you're like, you don't want to drop anything,
but you're, you don't, there's no real way to set a clump of stuff down.
Every moment knowing you're going closer and closer to everything on the ground.
Yes.
Exactly.
So I'm doing that and I finally fish my keys out and I get the car unlocked and then it
dawns on me, where am I going to go?
Where am I going to go?
Because I can't go home.
My house is for sale and there's an open house today.
And even if there wasn't an open house today, people are looking at the house every couple
of hours.
And even if that weren't the case, I have two kids, two dogs and one wife, a Learjet
taking off is more quiet than my house is.
And so I decided I'm going to take over my in-laws house.
I'll just, I'll go over there and I'll set up all of my stuff and I'll just, I will do
the show from my in-laws house, all willy nilly like, and kick them out of their house.
That seemed like a good idea.
Easy peasy.
Yeah.
And thank God it didn't actually come to that.
Mid continent in their infinite wisdom was able to get the problem resolved very quickly.
Made a call with within one hour, they had an internet backup and I'm able to safely
do the show from my studio and we seem to have a working internet connection out to
Seattle.
And so Wes can join me and thus this is Linux Unplugged and we have a cool show, I think
lined up.
Don't we?
Yes, we do.
Oh man.
That is quite the story.
It's wonderful to be here with you.
And now I know all that.
Yeah.
So I want to start out first with a, with a little bit of feedback.
Our first piece of feedback comes in from Mathis and he writes in with hi DPI versus
VGA.
And he goes, hi Wes and Noah, in three years I will still have my VGA ports for two reasons.
One, VGA will still be a superior connector and two, CRT monitors that will, that I will
still be using only have VGA, I think, and RCA.
Appreciate and love all your netcasts, Mathis.
I wanted to get your take on that.
Do you think that VGA is still going to be a thing in, in the next five years?
Well, we'll see.
I didn't think laptops with less than full HD would be a thing three years ago, but it
still is.
So I could see them still having VGA connectors.
I can too.
You know, and it, it's a decent form factor.
It does, you know, it's analog, so it just, just works even if it's not, you know, it
doesn't have fancy features.
You can't really chain it.
It doesn't, you know, it doesn't have the, the kind of resolution that a lot of us would
like to see these days.
I imagine that at least some section of the hardware market will still contain VGA.
Will I be using it?
Huh?
We'll see.
I think so too.
I, I agree with him when he says that VGA is a superior connector, if only because of
the two little knobs on the side.
Oh, I love the knobs.
Yeah, me too, because then you can securely connect it to the freaking computer.
So it doesn't get ripped out.
It makes tons of sense.
I don't know why we went away from that.
And you know, the same thing could be said about serial versus USB the, the, the DB nine
connector had little screw things.
And like when you attach one of those puppies to the computer, it never crossed your mind
if the cable was going to get pulled out or become disconnected.
Like that just wasn't a thing.
It worked.
Yeah.
If it was connected and it was tied down, it worked and you can trust that it was basically
as secure as having it on the inside of the computer unless of course somebody like tried
to climb up the back of the tower or something.
You weren't going to break it off.
And these days, like even before we started the show, I had to restart my machine because
my USB connector came unplugged from the, from the computer.
So I agree with you that it's, that it's a superior connector.
I think that the lack of screen real estate is enough to make me switch.
And I think it's going to be enough to make a lot of other people switch.
I also find it convenient even just when I'm short on, you know, maybe I don't have splitters
or I'm in a different situation and just, just having the extra VGA port that a lot
of computers do have means I can, you know, have an extra monitor that I might not otherwise
get without buying a specialty piece of hardware.
Very good.
Over at reddit.com slash r slash Linux action show, you can submit things of interest for
this show or for our big show every week, the Linux action show.
Twist X 77 writes in and he says, hi Chris, I've been a list, I've been a Linux tester
for more than 10 years, but I've never actually had the possibility to use Linux as my main
OS.
I have finally done that almost two years ago and I'm really happy with Ubuntu Gnome.
Well, I wanted to let you know that all my electronic devices today use an ACE that use
an AC, have an internal rectifier and a regulator.
So they end up using DC so many, so many times, just bypassing the rectifier part, you can
hook up 12 volt or 24 volt directly from your RV's DC supply.
I guess you probably, you guys already know that anyway, I'm an electrical engineer.
And so if you want to know how to use a soldering iron, I could help you bypass those AC devices
and use DC when possible.
So let me know if you need any help with any electronic related problems.
Last but not least, thanks for the great shows.
I listened to you guys when going to work almost every day.
Well thank you so much for writing and we really appreciate it.
Actually I do have an electrical question for you.
Oh, perfect.
Yeah, I did.
Yeah, that worked out right.
So Chris has a compressor gate combo that runs on nine volt AC and I want to get it
to preferable, eventually I need to get it to 12 volt DC, but I can live with a nine
volt DC because I already have a step-down transformer from a 12 volt DC to nine volt
DC.
You could help me solve that problem.
That would be a huge help.
Jupiter broadcasting.com click on the contact link, choose Linux unplugged from the dropdown
menu.
And if you have a solution for that, or you would like to help me come up with a solution
for that, that would be amazing.
At the moment, to my knowledge, that's the only remaining thing that he has in the camper
that he has to have on day-to-day production that isn't running on DC, so that'd be really
cool if we could get that solved.
Wes, have you been following Chris at the tracker?
Yes I have.
You know, it's a weird little voyeurism, but it's very enjoyable just to be able to kind
of creep along as he adventures across the West.
Did you watch him when he arrived into Grand Fork?
Yes I did.
It was awesome.
I, it's been kind of funny because the tracker is actually in the truck, not in the RV itself.
And so when he goes to like the market or whatever else, it's kind of funny because
like people will come over and like knock on the door and say, oh hey, how's it going?
Or they'll come find us, or him rather.
In fact, I had even one of my employees took a selfie with the JB Rover.
Oh wow, that's awesome.
Yeah, he was trying to find me and I had left my phone at home.
So he's like, oh, I'll just use a little Rover thing and I'll go find Chris.
It was pretty neat.
You know, I actually, I was looking at the equipment that he was using.
Chris was showing me in detail how that Silver Cloud thing was working.
And I actually went over to Amazon and I found a box for 35 bucks that kind of does the same
thing where they will update your, where they'll update your status.
But instead of charging like a monthly like account that you have to put money into in
order to get a certain amount of updates, essentially you just provide your own GSM
card and then it will update.
Isn't that kind of cool?
Oh, that sounds really neat.
Kind of roll your own service and as long as you can, as long as you can reach them,
they'll give you updates.
Exactly.
And I'm thinking I could get the cost down on this.
I'm going to have to run this by Chris, but if, if someone were to go to linux.ting.com
and you, you, the SIM cards right now are on sale for five bucks, so you could buy this
SIM card for five bucks and, but you get $25 of credit, so you could use the rest of the
$20 credit to pay for the first month of service.
And with Ting, you're only going to pay for what you use.
So in my case, what I'm talking about here is I would only be using data.
I would just be updating my locations.
I wouldn't be using text messages and I wouldn't be making phone calls.
And so I'm not going to pay for that service.
I'm just going to pay for the data that I'm using.
Of course, if you do plan on sending text messages or making phone calls, they're moderately
priced and you, because it's no contract, you can cancel the service at any time without
any penalty.
So I'd suggest everyone go over to linux.ting.com.
Pick yourself out something nice and use that $25 we're going to get you for being a listener
of the Linux Unplugged Show.
A huge thanks to Ting for sponsoring the show.
And it just goes to show you that the limit of what you can do with those devices is limited
only by your imagination.
You know, Ting really saved my butt this weekend.
I just have to say.
Oh really?
Tell me about it.
You know, I was working from home there doing some construction in the office, lots of concrete
dust everywhere, nothing we wanted to be a part of.
And you know, just as my shift was coming to an end, my ISP's connection of course decided
to fail.
It starts with the letter C.
They planned that, you know?
Yes, I believe that they did.
It was just perfectly timed.
But thanks to Ting, tethering, you know, it just uses your data.
It's included in your plan.
You don't have to worry about it.
There's no fuss.
So I was able to just spin up my LTE connection on my phone and I was VPN back in in no time.
It was perfect.
It saved my butt.
That's for sure.
If I think that I have found the limit of what I can do with Ting, I end up buying another
device.
Even when we were out, when we were out doing the meetup, I still get questions about that
little credit card phone.
Have I showed you that or have you seen it?
Oh yeah, that is so cool.
I'm thinking about just getting one.
They seem so handy and you can just, you know, just keep it when you need it.
And dude, they're 30 freaking dollars.
That's amazing.
Yeah, you can buy a brand new phone for 30 freaking dollars and you throw that $5 SIM
card in there, which by the way, you won't pay for because Ting's going to give it to
you for free by going to linux.ting.com and then you have $20 of service credit.
And if you're like me, that paid for, that paid for my first month of service.
And then if even with my wife and me and my son and my dad, who's all of which are on
my plan now, I would still probably get a good chunk of that month paid for.
Of course you can just buy a device.
We're going to run over to blog.documentingfoundation.org and they published an article titled today,
headline five years of LibreOffice, LibreOffice was launched as a fork of openoffice.org on
September 28th, 2010 by a tiny group of people representing the community in their capacity
of community project leaders.
At the time it was a brave, although necessary decision because it was rather clear to everyone
that openoffice.org was not going to survive for a long time under Oracle stewardship.
In fact, the group of 16 founders launched an independent free software project under
the stewardship of the Document Foundation to fulfill a promise made by Sun Microsystems
10 years before.
At the time, at the time of the first announcement of openoffice.org of the independent free
software foundation capable of pushing forward the free office suite to the next level.
After five years, LibreOffice is acknowledged in the marketplace as the sole Microsoft Office
contender based on sheer feature by feature comparison and on the number of successful
migrations.
Migrating to LibreOffice has never been easier thanks to the migration protocol drafted by
the most experienced people at the Document Foundation, which outlines the best practices
adopted by several large projects worldwide.
A success confirmed by the future of open source survey in 2015, which has put LibreOffice
amongst the most seven valuable open source projects based on the answers provided by
over 1,300 professionals worldwide.
It has been an amazing journey.
In five years, LibreOffice developers have not missed a single time-based release with
major announcements in late January and late July and minor announcements on a monthly
basis.
Thanks to the sustained pace, LibreOffice has reached a richness and feature and a level
of interoperability which are second to none.
I use Office on a daily basis.
How about you, Wes?
Yeah, pretty much.
Pretty much every day.
You know what?
I was trained as a Microsoft Office user specialist.
So supposedly, I had these letters after my name that said I was supposed to know something
about an Office suite.
And as Microsoft Office continued to push newer and newer versions out, I found myself
literally getting lost.
And the most embarrassing thing, I think, to date that's ever happened to me in an Office
suite was I was giving a presentation, and the presentation computer had the newest version
of Microsoft Office.
And this is when they switched to Ribbons, right?
And I couldn't find a core function, and I had to look up to a group of IT professionals,
and I'm presenting.
So supposedly, I'm supposed to know something that they don't.
I'm supposed to be teaching them something, and I had to ask them to come up and show
me how to use a function of Microsoft Office.
And it was about that time when I realized I didn't want to be beholden to Microsoft
Office anymore.
And I switched to LibreOffice, and ever since then, every client that comes to my company
that is looking for help with an Office suite, we move them to LibreOffice as well.
Do you use LibreOffice as like a daily driver, or is it something that you use just to modify
a document or to write a letter or something like that?
You know, it's definitely more of the latter, but I kind of started back with OpenOffice.
I wasn't really a Linux user then, but to think about it, back in high school, my high
school actually had Linux on a lot of the workstations.
I remember getting in trouble for a long-running C program that I left running on the network.
But we started with OpenOffice, and then I migrated to Microsoft Office when I was in
college, and like you, I was also responsible for doing some training of people using those
suites.
Sure.
And I have just been continually impressed with what the Document Foundation and LibreOffice
have done.
You know, even if you ignore the elephant in the room of Microsoft Office, they have
just been able to create a standards-based, very usable productivity suite that if you
use it, especially internally, if it's a consistent deployment, you can pretty much do anything
that you would reasonably need to do efficiently, productively, and in a very pleasant environment.
And they seem very responsive as well, so that new features get added, compatibility
gets improved.
It's really like a testament to the open source software in general.
You know, Wes, I had a chance to head over to Red Hat, and when I was at Red Hat, I was
talking to those guys, and I said, how is it that a billion-dollar company, a billion
dollars, how is it that you guys manage to avoid using Microsoft Office?
And he said, honestly, when it comes down to it, the basic stuff that you do in an office
suite is there.
Like, all the functionality is there.
The way you go about doing it, sometimes the buttons are in little different locations.
Yeah, exactly.
Layouts are a little different, but the functionality is there.
And so I think that people that say, oh, I can't do that in open office, or I can't do
that in LibreOffice, I think those people, I think that's just a cop-out, and I think
that it's not that you can't do it in LibreOffice, I think that 99% of the time, it's people
just don't want to do it in LibreOffice.
Yes, they don't want to warn that new workflow, and you know, that's a barrier, but if you
get over it, it's a glorious thing on the other side.
And the other thing is, too, is what I see is you are trading the comfortability of Microsoft
Office for the known future of LibreOffice.
I don't know what changes Microsoft is going to make, only Microsoft knows that, if Microsoft
knows that, but when it comes to LibreOffice, I can have a voice in that conversation.
I can reach out to the developers and say, hey, you know what, this is a feature I'm
really looking forward to, and I do do that.
When I bump into those guys, and they are at most Linux fests, when I bump into those
guys, I tell them, I say, hey, this is the kind of feature I'm looking for, this is the
kind of functionality I really need, is that something that you can accommodate?
And most of the time, the answer is yes, sometimes the answer is no, and then usually with a
yes, they're able to give a timeframe of about how long that's going to take before that
functionality arrives.
How about the Mumble Room?
I kind of want to open it up to you guys.
We haven't really even said hello to you guys.
Time appropriate greeting, Mumble Room.
As far as LibreOffice, I mean, the only thing that it can't do very well is the Microsoft
Office formats, and it's still getting those much better in the recent releases.
So I mean, as far as like most of the time, LibreOffice is all you really need.
Yeah.
I guess I suppose I'll have to backtrack just a little bit.
I'll have to eat a couple of my words.
I suppose if you're doing something very, very, very, some very special formula in Excel-based
formula or something like that, I guess I could see a couple of times where it would
be a lot of work to use LibreOffice instead of Microsoft Office, and that didn't really
dawn on me until, Rotten, you had mentioned the concept of transitioning from one office
suite to another and keeping file consistency.
I have done that a couple of times, and 99% of the time it goes well, but you're right.
Every once in a while, if there's a Microsoft Office format and you try and open that up
in LibreOffice, something goes a little kiddy wonker, and then that causes some problems.
There's also big companies that have implemented large software solutions which only integrate
with Microsoft Office, and there's a big one that most large companies use, and that's
LibreOffice, and for a long, long, long, long time, and it may still be the case, I haven't
looked in the last three years, but while you're inside your SAP system dealing with
your customers, your HR records, your finances, your materials management, whatever it is
inside SAP, if you press any button that is export this as a document, the only thing
it will talk to is Microsoft Office.
You absolutely cannot integrate with LibreOffice or OpenOffice or any other office suite.
It just doesn't do it, because really, if you're implementing SAP, you're a Fortune
500 company and many more, and you could be pretty much guaranteed that the desktops will
have Microsoft Windows and they will have Microsoft Office.
Exactly.
There's no point in them even implementing that kind of integration.
That may well have changed in the last three years, but I seriously doubt it.
How about letting that software export to Microsoft Office and then opening it with
LibreOffice?
Well, it's not just a case of exporting data out.
It doesn't spit data out as like an XLS file or a doc.
This is reaching into the Office install on your machine, placing calls into the application,
so it integrates tightly, and it might even embed.
You might be looking at a screen in SAP, and then you press a button that says, give me
a graph, and that reaches into your machine, downloads some stuff to your machine, and
then makes some system calls into Microsoft Office that then renders that inside the GUI
for the application.
And SAP is not the only one.
It's the one I've got most familiarity with, but there are plenty of these Office applications
which are used by large companies and which there is no way you're going to move these
people off of Microsoft Office, because they're dependent upon something which costs them
millions and millions in maintenance fees every year.
They're not just going to switch away from that.
That's just not going to happen.
So it's somewhat, I mean, for small and medium-sized enterprises and for the people who are doing
the basic stuff and home users, yes, LibreOffice is perfectly fine.
For education, yes, perfectly fine, but for the very large deployments, it's a lot more
difficult.
Now, do you think those companies are not taking into account a certain level of risk
by banking on the fact that their software is going to continue to talk to Microsoft
and that Microsoft is going to continue to provide Microsoft Office in a way that that
software can talk to it?
So for example, look at Office 365, a lot of businesses have switched to Office 365.
I would imagine that that to some degree changes the ability of a third-party software being
able to talk directly to Microsoft Office, doesn't it?
No, not at all.
All these large software companies have people who work for Microsoft embedded in the company.
They have people who work for Oracle embedded in the company.
They have partner status with them, so they get access to this stuff early on, and they
will integrate so that in the next release or the next release two years down the line,
remember, corporates don't tend to move super fast upgrading their back-end ERP systems,
and these people will say, coming in the next release or two releases down the line, we'll
have integration with Office 365, and that'll be fine because significant numbers of those
companies are still running on Windows 7 or some of them maybe even on Windows XP.
They're not itching to move on to the next release.
The reality is with Office 365, it is somewhat operating system independent.
I can run Office 365 inside of Ubuntu, and it works just fine.
Not necessarily recommending anyone should do that.
But I wonder how that SAP system would talk in if it can't talk to the operating system.
I bet that, would that screw it up?
It's a prerequisite.
I mean, if you were to try and install the GUI and you try and do something in the GUI
that requires Microsoft Office and the client doesn't have Microsoft Office installed or
it's not a Microsoft client, then that piece of functionality will fail.
And the net result of that is that employee can't do their job.
And if that employee can't do their job, then you're not going to migrate away from Windows.
So it's a lot more complicated than just what's the most complicated Excel spreadsheet you
can think of?
Does it happen in LibreOffice or what's the most cunningly formatted Word document that
makes sure it renders correctly inside LibreOffice docs?
Most of those things are covered.
Those bases are fine.
It's when you're dependent upon Microsoft system calls and things like that that you're
screwed.
You can't move away.
That makes total sense.
I stand corrected.
You know, I have obviously I have very limited experience with very, very large companies.
Certainly have even less experience with very large companies that have very large deployments
of Windows.
But and I say that unashamedly.
But there are certain things that I don't think Microsoft Office will ever be able to
compete with LibreOffice.
And one of them is, for example, the Document Freedom Day.
And it's this idea that we can celebrate and raise awareness for the concept of open standards
and I really wanted to participate in this last year.
I'm really looking forward to participating in it next year.
But and probably maybe you have have some insight.
Did you personally or did you at work support or have any involvement with Document Freedom
Day?
So the last time I was involved in this was when it was before Document Freedom Day, when
it was Software Freedom Day.
Many, many, many years ago, there was a Software Freedom Day and we decided to take part in
the UK.
And in London, we had a bunch of CDs that were provided by Canonical, the Ubuntu CDs,
and we had some leaflets that we printed out and we went for a walk.
We all met up in a park in London, we went for a walk through London, and then we met
up at a venue where we gave talks and talked about software freedom and all the all the
kind of topics that you'd expect to hear at a conference or an event about software freedom.
And as we walked through London, we were handing CDs.
And you know, you know, those people who stand in the street who try and like thrust something
into your hand and you really don't want to make eye contact and you don't want to talk
to those people?
Well, yeah, that was us.
And in England, you know, I'm sure it's somewhat different, the British reserved personality
where, you know, we'll do absolutely anything to avoid eye contact with you.
And we would we were testing, like, as we walked along different phrases that we could
use to get people to take the CD out of our hand like, you know, would you like some free
software?
And you know, free software, free culture or free, you know, we were trying all kinds
of phrases.
And some of them weren't better than others.
I documented those.
Yeah, well, we Yeah, we wrote up our, our, our event.
But one particularly memorable, we were standing outside a store that was like, you know, like
a Best Buy, like fries you would have over there as PC World over here.
And it was at a junction where there was some traffic lights and a big red London basketball
pulled up.
And one of the guys took the opportunity to walk up to the bus driver and handed him one
of the CDs and said, Hey, would you like some free software?
And the guy looked at it and said, Ah, is this that replacement for Windows?
And our guy went, Yes, that's exactly what it is.
But this was like, nearly 10 years ago, eight years ago.
And you know, people, some people knew about it back then.
But no, I haven't been involved in the Document Freedom Day more recently.
I know some people have, but I am.
I would love to get more, more involved with that.
And the stories that I've heard from people that have participated in are absolutely outstanding.
And you can actually get some funding, as I understand it, from the Document Foundation
for the Open Document Foundation for putting on a Document Freedom Day in your area.
That's definitely something I'm going to look into.
Anyone else in the mobile room have any experience with, with LibreOffice or enjoy using LibreOffice
or more to the point experience with switching people from Microsoft Office to LibreOffice?
Yeah, I've worked with several friends and family members that, you know, we just bypass
the whole Microsoft Office compatibility issue entirely when you're creating documents for
distribution, just save them as PDFs.
Yeah, totally.
That's a great option.
PDFs are great.
The thing that bothers me about PDFs is if, if anytime you need to edit something or change
something right, that becomes kind of problematic.
Wouldn't they have, didn't they have like an embedded format where you can embed a Open
Office or a Open Document format in a PDF or maybe it was vice versa?
Yeah, that could be.
If they're, I'm not, I'm not personally familiar with it, but North Ranger, how about you?
You know, I did not try that, but like the biggest example I had of, you know, distribution
was resumes.
Oh, sure.
Yeah.
The nice thing about resumes is that you can actually download a lot of the templates for
Microsoft Office, open them with LibreOffice and then go in there and, and, and just plug
in the information and it works.
And I've actually done that a couple of times or helped people do it a couple of times.
Never really run into a snag doing that.
There's also a Linux converter so that if it's just a command line tool that you run
it, you can convert a PDF that doesn't have editability or have any texts connected to
it and convert it into an editable format that is still PDF, but fundamentally lets you
change things.
Yeah.
I just see on LibreOffice's website here, they have support for hybrid PDF where they
do embed an ODF file.
So a PDF viewers will see the PDF, but if you open LibreOffice, it's a fully modifiable.
And I assume when you save it, then that's updates the PDF.
Oh, that's great.
Yeah.
That's absolutely fantastic because the nice thing about that is it requires people that
are, that the people that want to monkey with it are going to know how to monkey with it.
And the people that don't know how to monkey with it probably aren't the people we want
modifying the file anyway, right?
Yeah.
And there's no, there's no excuse with LibreOffice, you know, it's like you sent this document
and you do want to edit it.
Well, it's free software.
You can download it at no cost.
It's available for pretty much every platform.
So you know, perfectly interoperable.
Rotten Corpse, you want to jump in there?
Well, I was just going to say that there is actually another, there's a, there's a cloud
that this is not something you want to use if you care about like privacy of your stuff,
but there's this cloud converters system.
It's a service called a cloudconvert.io I think, and it, I've tested it in certain cases
where you can convert a PDF, no matter what kind of weird formatting it has to anything
you want.
Like I tried to convert a PDF to an HTML file just to see if it would do it.
And it did it perfectly.
It had all the pages, how the formatting, like everything was perfect and it kind of
blew my mind how like exact it did it, no matter what format I picked.
That's awesome.
It's worth saying for everything I've said about Microsoft Office, LibreOffice is incredibly
flexible and over the last couple of years it's being bent into different shapes that
you probably wouldn't have expected it to, or that you wouldn't have expected the same
code base from so many years ago that originated, you know, StarOffice, OpenOffice and now LibreOffice
that now, for example, there's a tool that's part of LibreOffice called LibreOffice Kit.
And with LibreOffice Kit, you could take an installation of LibreOffice with no GUI, so
you don't actually use LibreOffice on the desktop, but you could have an install of
LibreOffice say on a headless server and with LibreOffice Kit you can pass it any supported
LibreOffice document and it will give you back a bitmap of what that document looks
like.
No kidding.
It's amazing.
And we're actually using that on the Ubuntu phone.
So the document viewer has inside it a copy of LibreOffice and when you open a document,
it throws the document at LibreOffice through LibreOffice Kit, LibreOffice then renders
the document, throws it back a bitmap and we display that on the screen and you just
move that around.
So you're scrolling the document as you're moving a bitmap around the screen.
It's pretty amazing.
And it does this all this in real time.
Yeah.
But you can throw it a bitmap and say, show me this part of the document.
So if the user is zoomed in, you might want to show only the top left hand corner of the
spreadsheet or something.
So you tell LibreOffice Kit, here's the document.
Show me the top left hand corner of that document and it will throw you back a bitmap only of
that bit.
When you page down, it will render only the second page and when you page down, it only
renders the third page.
So it's incredibly flexible what you can do with LibreOffice and in some ways more
flexible than Microsoft Office.
And I think that's a good note to end on that.
Well, I guess this is another good note to end on.
LibreOffice 5.0 launched in early August and has been the most successful major release
ever, triggering an unprecedented 8,000 donations in just 30 days.
Of course, the success had been reflected in the number of adoptions, which has soared.
The icing on the cake has been the announcement of the Italian Defense Organization, which
will be migrating some 150,000 PCs to LibreOffice starting from October in 2015.
You know, I think it was last month or the month before actually we went over into a
clinic and we migrated their entire clinic over to LibreOffice.
We went in and systematically removed Microsoft Office and switched them all over to LibreOffice.
And along with LibreOffice, we had to move their database, their main medical database
over.
And it had been hosted on a seven-year-old server.
And the problem was it was slowing down and it was starting to crash or actually just
unexpectedly shut off.
And they didn't have the $2,000 plus to purchase a new machine.
And even if they did have the money, they didn't have an in-house IT staff, which would
have meant that we would have been quoting out either a service contract to come out
and replace hard disks when they fail or add memory when it goes off or bring up backup
internet when the fiber line fails and all those good things.
And we were actually able to solve all of their concerns for just $120 a year over at
DigitalOcean.
DigitalOcean, if you're not familiar with them, they're a VPS that does servers, Linux
servers in fact, on demand.
You might say it's like the McDonald's of fast food in the server world.
We move dozens of businesses over to DigitalOcean.
And just like when we move a business from Windows over to Linux or we move a business
from Microsoft Office to LibreOffice, they never look back.
In the two years that we've been moving people over to DigitalOcean, I don't think I've ever
had a client that has told me they want to go back to buying servers and paying a yearly
fee to maintain them.
Their intuitive dashboard makes spinning up servers or as they call them droplets, super
easy and efficient.
At least once a week, I try to spin something up just to play with something.
I try to start up a new droplet and try something new just to kind of keep myself fresh and
kind of keep myself exploring.
I don't have the time to install an operating system on a bare metal box.
It just takes too much time.
Now, I'll give you a pro tip.
If you go over and spin up a DigitalOcean droplet and you use the code DOUNPLUGED, DOUNPLUGED,
all one word, all lowercase, you're going to get a $10 credit.
That basically means you get the servers that I use all the time for two months for free.
That's a $5 droplet with a terabyte of transfer, a 20 gigabyte solid state drive, and 512 megabytes
of RAM.
If you know how to use Linux correctly, that gets you a long, long way.
I have EMR databases running on it.
I have a Mumble server running on it.
I have an Airtime instance.
I have my Quasocore running on it.
I have the chat server that we were using back when we were doing the video portion
of the Linux action show.
All of that stuff was running on a $5 droplet.
Head over to DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGED, DOUNPLUGED, all lowercase,
all one word, and you'll get $10 credit to spin up your own Linux rig for two months.
I want to move on and talk about the Ubuntu installer.
Now things are changing in the Ubuntu installer, and the installer is called Ubiquity.
Wes, have you seen this?
Yeah, I've used it a couple of times.
So they are changing the slide show, I understand.
Have you read about this?
I was just reading about it this morning, actually.
So the one thing that I have noticed is the first time I install a new distro, or the
first time I install what would be a new operating system, essentially, I'm paying attention
to what's on the screen.
I'm looking at how the UI elements are designed.
I'm looking at the screencaps that they share and stuff like that.
And I think it makes a lot of sense to update a lot of the stuff that's inside of the installer,
because I think that's the first impression a lot of people are getting with Ubuntu.
Would you agree?
Oh, yeah.
And that first impression is so important.
You really need to lay it home that this is a modern operating system.
It's uncompromising on all the kind of stuff that you would expect from it, that it's easy,
that it welcomes you, and that it's going to create a really good experience, really,
from the get-go.
Yeah.
So a couple of months ago, we were redoing Angela's MacBook, because we were selling
it on eBay, and one of the things that I noticed about it was it plays a video when you start
up macOS.
This is really one of the few times I've ever used macOS, but of all the things I didn't
like about the operating system experience, I thought that was kind of cool that it had
like this welcome video, and it showed like the hello in a couple different languages
and stuff like that.
Oh, yeah.
I'm familiar with that.
Have you seen that?
Yeah.
It is pretty slick.
It makes you feel like you're already using the computer, even though you haven't quite
finished installing it yet.
Yeah.
So I thought that was kind of cool.
But it was kind of like a welcome to your computer sort of a thing.
Exactly.
Since most of us are installing Linux, the installer and the images that come with the
installer are what is greeting us to the operating system.
And Chris had put some of the show notes together, so I'm not exactly sure.
I'm a little confused on a few of the details here, but I think that the graphical interface
is really important.
I think it's kind of cool.
Popey, do you have anything to add about Ubiquity and feedback that you guys get from it?
Yeah.
So this was a surprise to me as well.
So the design guys, they mostly work in London, in the London office at Canonical.
And if you ever go into the London office, if you're ever lucky enough to go in there,
there's post-it notes all over the walls.
They're big on post-it notes.
There's loads of prototypes, drawings, and mock-ups of user interfaces that may be in
the future or might have been if we'd gone on a different path.
And one of the things about the installer is, I'm not sure I agree with you.
I think the installer, it may well be the first impression that people see of the distro.
I believe that it shouldn't be because users shouldn't be installing Linux.
They should be buying a machine that has Linux pre-installed.
And therefore, they wouldn't see the install process because it would come pre-installed.
That's what happens with Windows.
Nobody cares about the install process of Windows.
Nobody cares about the install process of OS 10.
Most of the time, the users see the install process of Windows or normal users.
I'm not talking about not your listenership, but your average Joe, most that they're going
to see the installer is looking over the shoulder of someone else doing it, and they don't care.
Or if they're being super techy and someone told them to reinstall because their machine's
completely hosed and that's the only way out.
I'm not sure that the installer is the best thing as the showcase.
However, what you will notice in the blog post that is on design.canonical.com about
why the first impression matters, you'll notice that the screens that they've talked about
changing are the ones that you see after an OEM install.
So it's not the full install.
It's not like the partitioning scheme and all that kind of wacky stuff that you and
I know all about and can skip through nice and happily.
It's the stuff that an end user would see.
And the stuff that an end user would see on first run is, okay, what language do you want?
What Wi-Fi connection do you want to connect to?
What time zone are you in?
Do you want to set a password and do you want the system to lock and automatically unlock
for you?
That kind of thing.
And so I find it interesting that actually that kind of corroborates my perspective that
the first thing that we should be showing people is a great experience out of the box
when you buy a machine.
Now I would love to see a funky video, like you say, or something pretty that we can show
a user when they first take their thing out of the box.
Because let's face it, when people do unboxing videos, they love these things.
When the Nokia N900 prototype phones or early adopter phones were sent out, they came in
a special box that had special buttons and you had to send code over a serial cable.
And when the box opened, smoke came out.
It was amazing.
So that unboxing experience, it should feel special to everyone.
I'm not saying we should provide like smoke and stuff inside of it.
Sounds hazardous.
Every laptop.
Yeah.
And somewhat expensive.
Intel did with the NUC, so you open it and it has a little Intel sound.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
See that and the Exploding Kittens card game that was on Kickstarter, that when you open
the box, you hear, you know, beautiful things that you get when you take the thing out of
the box means you cherish the thing a little bit more.
And I think that's one of the factors why people who tend to buy Apple products cherish
them a lot more is because of that whole out of the box experience.
It means you want to love it even more, like, you know, going and picking a kitten up for
the first time when you when you've like got a kitten from a rescue center or something,
when you pick it up for the first time, you cherish it even more after that first meeting.
Do you know what I mean?
Right.
Yes, absolutely.
Especially if it, you know, sometimes, let's face it, some people's first introduction
to Ubuntu or Linux in general is met after several hours of troubleshooting.
Yes, very much so.
Right.
So the worst thing is it is because then then then it is tainted and the trust for the operating
system is almost lost a little bit.
So I definitely I agree with what you're saying.
Even the issues like like the Apple thing is a good point, like because the Apple boxes,
they will just they'll they'll keep the boxes and display them because of just the way they
present the out of the box experience.
You know, if there was something like that for the the UI or I don't know, before you
install something like maybe they should put like the Ubuntu has the demo where you can
just like use Ubuntu in the browser for a little bit and kind of experience it that
way.
If they put that more give more attention to that.
Well, in fact, it's interesting you should say that in China, I think you do actually
get that out of the box.
There was a there was a government directive, I believe, that in China many years ago that
was, you know, when you ship a machine, you have to provide some kind of tutorial out
of the box, because a lot of the people who are buying these things are farmers out in
the middle of nowhere.
And they've had met, they've never bought a computing device before in their life.
And they've got no idea what to do when you turn it on.
And that and that's not unique to Ubuntu, you know, any computer, they turn it on, and
they wouldn't know what to do in the same way that a farmer from the middle of America
or middle of UK wouldn't know what to do if they never touched a computer before.
But, and so we did used to put I don't know if we still do the the web based tutorial
on machines that were shipping in China.
And in fact, Dell, I think on the XPS 13, I don't have one, I've never bought one.
But I'm led to believe there is a funky little video at the start of that.
And I believe Dell made that we didn't, we didn't create that and it doesn't ship on
the CD.
It's not on anyone else's, like if you buy Lenovo, you don't get that video.
So there is a, you know, move towards making that whole out of the box experience a little
bit better.
Well, that's good.
That's good to hear.
Now, I have been automating my home for some time and joining us in the mumble room, we
have a very special guest.
Ana is here.
Good afternoon, sir.
How are you?
Good afternoon.
I'm fine.
Thank you.
So tell me a little bit about CrowdStone.
Yeah, so what we created here in Rotterdam, like one of the harbors in Europe, of course,
is a little device that you can plug into a power outlet, which is completely open source.
So can be hacked by anyone who likes a little bit of like the firmware hacking.
And what it does is actually two kind of things at the same time.
Of course, you can dim lights and you can switch devices and things like that, like
the usable home automation stuff.
But it also has proximity and indoor localization functionality.
It does that by knowing how far your phone is.
So it measures the distance to your phone.
And at the same time, it also has device recognition on board.
So if you plug in your TV or something else, it knows what the difference is between those
devices using the consumption pattern over the day.
Wow.
That's crazy.
It can identify the device, huh?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
So we use multiple ways to do that.
So one of the simple ways is actually just using the power consumption itself, of course.
But you can also see the pattern over time.
My background is robotics.
So I use a lot of algorithms we have been developing over the time.
And so if you use a collection of reclassifiers, they can use all kind of features, for example,
temporal features or other kind of features.
You can collect them.
And collectively, they are able to distinguish a lot of devices.
And there is a third way you can use.
And that is, say, every device leaves a kind of a signature on the grid.
So if you plug in a LED led light, you will have some signature that is different from
if you plug in a normal light bulb.
You can use that on a single sine wave.
You can already see what the difference is between certain devices.
Now, I understand that this device can actually recognize a certain form of rudimentary logic.
So for example, if my TV, I don't unplug it.
It just sits in the living room and stays there.
So if I were to unplug my TV, that would be a bit unusual.
How does your device respond?
If you, yeah.
So these are the kind of events we want to be able to register.
So if you would unplug your TV at night, it's probably kind of events you want to receive
as the owner of the building or of the home or the apartment.
If it's your microwave that gets plugged out, you probably don't need to know it.
Tell me a little bit about how the child lock feature works.
How does it know if there are adults in proximity or not know if adults are in proximity?
Oh, yeah.
That was a nice feature.
I was actually, we had a group of 50 students that were working on our product, under covers
to say, in Rotterdam.
And one of those groups were coming up with this feature that was first like, yeah, but
I don't want to have children carrying phones with them.
But it was the other way around.
So it was really parents that are walking around.
And when they are in proximity, certain devices can be turned on.
When they are not, they are not turned on.
And the proximity detection is just by using the Bluetooth low energy signal strengths
that are already on your phone.
So basically by measuring kind of, say, between three or five meters, something like that,
it should be on.
If it's beyond that, it should be off.
Now I understand that we're kind of in early days here.
In fact, you have a Kickstarter over at crownstone.rocks.
Is that correct?
Yeah.
So if you go there, yeah, you will automatically can go.
You will have one go button and you can go down to the Kickstarter.
Tell me at some point, will there be a way that I can integrate this inside of the box?
Because I know one of the things I'm seeing right off the top of my head is I would be
perfectly okay with this, my wife, however, is not going to appreciate a protruding object
from the outlet.
If this project takes off, maybe an iteration two or three, would there be a way that we
can get this so it actually replaces the wall outlet itself?
There is one version that you can actually put behind the power outlet.
So yeah, so you should have enough space, of course, there is a little bit of space
required in your junction box, but yeah, then for your wife or so, nothing changes.
She can just turn on and off the lights and you can basically rule it over kind of by
doing it wirelessly and then she will be like, oh, it's not going on, but she will probably
flip it another time and then for her, not so much changes, she can still use the physical
switch.
Wow, that sounds fantastic.
Now, you said that all of this was designed with open source in mind.
Tell me how I can interface to this device.
I get the little plug, I assume there's some way that I can program it to tell it, I want
you to act as a child locker, I want you to act as a motion detector, I want you to act
in this way or the other.
How do I go about actually programming the device?
Yeah, we decided to actually put a lot of logic onto the smartphone.
So first of all, we have open firmware, so you can do everything on the device itself
if you want to, but that is a better device, so it's difficult to program for certain people.
It has 16 kilobytes of RAM, it's like the radio takes up 10 kilobytes, so it's very,
very little space you have on a device like that.
You won't be able to run JavaScript or something.
So our Bluetooth of Energy interface basically is an API that people can use from whatever
kind of device they have, a laptop with Python scripts or Raspberry Pi or things like that.
But the main advantage is also that we provide libraries on the smartphone, different ones,
so Cordova-based and iOS and Android-based, so they can actually write applications like
they normally do for smartphone apps and they can directly interface with those brownstones
from their phones.
Yeah, what's also different from normal or different Kickstarters, quite often they stream
everything to a server like, for example, the Fitbit or something like that.
You cannot actually get your own data out except for it via a REST API online.
We decided to do it directly on your phone, so you really can get your own data.
You don't need to go through a company server or something like that.
Oh, that's awesome.
So there's no centrally activated server.
See, that would be my first line that would rule me out of your product, because if you
told me, well, there's a little serial number and you have to go to our website and activate
it and then use our web portal to program it and stuff like that, but you're telling
me basically if I really wanted to, if I got needy and gritty, I could actually plug in
with like a serial cable and program this thing with my laptop.
Yeah, we will also add a pledge for developer edition with separate connectors, but at the
moment you will need to do it over the air.
So we have Bluetooth low end, yeah, so we have the MQ, yeah.
How does the over the air programming work if I want to do it directly on the device?
You spoke about being able to do that or the two mutually exclusive?
No, so via wires you need connectors on it, but the default is that you can do it wirelessly
and you can do it via say a standard application that's already on the market or you can do
it actually also via shell scripts, Python scripts.
Now there's a lot of home automation type equipment that is already prevalent in the
market.
So for example, universal remote controls or URC, they have templates on how to talk
to other devices either via TCP IP or over RF.
I assume because it's an open standard, that should be a pretty simplistic thing that should
be a pretty rudimentary thing for me to tie your device into my remote control, is that
right?
Yeah, absolutely.
Any kind of hub that exists that has Bluetooth low energy and it doesn't even need to have
that because there are a lot of switch like little dongles available for only a few bucks.
And then yeah, it's very basic to hook up to other stuff, absolutely.
Wes, do you have any questions about this smart socket?
I'm just really impressed with how open it appears.
A lot of the other platforms that we're seeing in this kind of space are so closed off.
A lot of them, if you download the SDK, you have to sign an agreement that you won't use
it to create interoperability with other products.
So the idea here that you could take something that you've already bought or maybe someone
you're installing this for already has some sunk costs and then just create something
to bridge it and take advantage of this is awesome and I think it's one of the best things
going for it.
Yeah, absolutely.
The fact that it's open really appeals to me.
How about our mumble room?
Do you guys have any questions, comments, concerns?
Yeah, if your laptop has Bluetooth, for example, can you use your laptop to interface with
the device?
Yeah, absolutely.
Your laptop is fine as well.
I'm only using Linux, so I don't know how it works on Windows, but he knows how to get
our interest.
Yeah, no kidding, man.
You just earned yourself 10 character points.
Yeah, yeah.
And as a hobby, I have been actually backing a lot of Kickstarter projects and most often,
if I cannot get to the data, I try to do it myself.
So with the FitBit or the Mimoto camera thing or whatever, but I find it a pain that they
make it so closed.
So that's why we really wanted to make this product so open.
It really shows.
That's great.
You really probably should check out that video where we go through the house and go
through how everything works.
One of the things I demoed is my scene selector in my house where I can hit the bedtime mode
and it turns all the lights down so I can kind of wind down at night.
One of the things I've done is I used to watch TV.
I actually got back into Walker, Texas Ranger, the show from the 90s, and I liked that show
because it was light.
So I could watch it.
I could wind down for a little bit and I would go to bed, is take for contrast 24.
If you watch an episode of 24, you have to watch what happens to Jack in the next episode.
And so what ends up happening is it's like seven in the morning and you're like, oh crap,
I didn't sleep all night because I sat up all night watching 24.
Really I have been winding down with a new hobby and that is I'm learning how to develop
apps on Android.
Very cool.
Yeah, I know.
I know.
But here's the thing.
I know what some people are saying.
The chat room is about to freak out and the mobile room is about to freak out and say,
no, you're not.
You're not a, you're not a dev.
You're a sysadmin.
And I know that.
Okay.
I know that.
But with a 33% discount over at linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, I can't think of a more cost
effective way to relax at night.
And I've had a blast being able to go through those modules and you know, I'm, I'm a little
bit ADD if you haven't picked up on that yet, Wes.
And so I zone out every once in a while, like if I'm listening to somebody talk and I try,
I mean like bless my wife's heart.
She is so good at putting up with this show.
She'll start talking to me and I have every intention of listening to all the words that
come out of her mouth and then like three minutes into it or five minutes into it.
I just, I like, I fade off and I just, I go into la la land and then then it's lost.
And with, with Linux Academy, I can go back and rewatch some of that stuff that I missed.
And Wes, I got to tell you, when I first got into IT, I remember how expensive things were,
how expensive things were to get trained, how expensive things were to get certified.
Yeah.
It's a huge roadblock.
If you're trying, you know, you're just trying to get started out in this industry.
It really is.
It really is because you're competing with a bunch of people that, that, that are on
a different playing field.
They're essentially on a different level than you are.
And you can do that for pennies on the dollar over at linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Do you know what opportunity cost is?
Opportunity cost is the price that you pay for not getting that job because you didn't
have the training and you didn't have the certification because you're not at linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged taking advantage of literally a third of the cost reduction.
And you know, the cost isn't even all that expensive to begin with, even at full price.
I think with the, I think with the discount, I think my whole month of training for Android
worked out to be like 15 bucks or 16 bucks.
Oh man.
That's nothing.
Yeah.
It really isn't.
It's really cheap.
And even without the discount, it was only like 25 bucks, I think.
So I mean, this is the way, if you, if you're listening to the show and you're listening
and saying, you know, I really want to do what Noah does.
I really like the idea that Noah doesn't, doesn't ever have to troubleshoot Microsoft
windows.
I mean, I just don't do that.
If you want to get yourself a career started with, um, in Linux or using open source and
related technologies, this is the way to do it first.
You have to get current with the technologies and there's no better way to do that by taking
a professional online course.
You know, you can do the YouTube thing where people were, you know, Joe Blow in his basement
makes a little video with a handicapped, um, and you hear his baby sister crying in the
background and his mother calling him up for dinner and the dogs barking.
You can do all that, but don't spend a couple of dollars and get yourself some professional
training and, uh, and then get certified.
And they, uh, they offer, they, they really, really, uh, do a good job with someone like
the red hat certification.
So that's a great certification.
I know that anytime I have somebody that sits down in my office and, and, and when the,
when their resume slides across my desk and if I see that red hat cert, man, that cert
means something to me because I know that they have practical skills.
Uh, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, take advantage of that 33% discount while you can
over at ZD article that is looking, uh, at open Seuss leap.
Have you seen this West, you know, only just a little bit.
So the, the current stable release of open Seuss is 13.2 and that came out on November
4th of 2014.
Um, the next release is scheduled to be available November 4th, November, uh, excuse me, November
4th of 2015, exactly one year later.
Um, and the new release will not be called 13.3 or 14 dot, you know, whatever, but rather
it's going to be called 42 dot one, 42 dot one.
And so appropriately they're codenaming this leap.
The reason for the name slash number change and the extra attention that this release
is getting is that they are making a philosophical change in the development and release strategy.
The reasons for this change and the results of it are discussed on the open Seuss leap
Wiki page.
A lot of the discussion has been focused on open Seuss getting merged with Seuss Linux,
enterprise Linux, but I think it's important to note, this is the author speaking on me,
but I think it's important to note that this is more of a two way street than it is.
In fact, as it is explained in the Wiki, what happened, which what enabled the merge was
that SLE sources and maintained updates have been released to the open Seuss build service.
Now, um, in theory, this is ideally what I, as a Linux desktop user have been waiting
for a commercial enterprise Linux distro that is centered around the Linux desktop.
Um, I, I seem to be stuck on, on two sides.
Either I get bleeding edge and things aren't really ready for enterprise and I have problems
or I wind up with really, really old outdated packages and there doesn't seem to be a middle
ground and that seems to be what they're aiming to solve here.
And I got to say their, their, their desktop experience in the past has been really good.
So this, this gives me a lot of hope.
Uh, you know, open Seuss in the past has been one of those distros that I know I can just
install on someone's machine and they will have all the resources there that they need
to use it and to explore and to, you know, in the same way that they could use windows
that they'll be able to solve all the problems and make all the changes they might need.
You know, Wes, I don't know if you've noticed this either, but when I move people over from,
uh, from windows to Linux, a lot of times, um, for whatever reason, they are very comfortable
in open Seuss as opposed to a lot of the other, uh, a lot of the other alternative distros
out there.
And I haven't exactly been able to put my, my finger on why that is.
If that, if that, I, I suspect it has a lot to do with KDE, to be honest with you, I think
that windows users kind of gravitate towards having a bar at the bottom where they click
on a button that gives them a menu.
Yeah.
I think, I think there is something there.
And yes.
Yes.
Goes a ways too.
Yeah.
And so I think that, uh, yas goes a long ways.
Yeah, man, does it ever, especially if you are a, a former windows administrator.
I think that's going to go a long ways.
Um, but I'm looking at, uh, I'm looking at this open Sue sleep and the screen caps that
I'm looking at are absolutely awesome.
I am really looking forward to taking a look at some of this and, and playing with this.
In fact, I have so much so that I've actually dedicated an entire machine to this and it's
going to be my main machine for the rest of the week.
And I'm going to take a look and see, um, what it is that, that open Seuss is offering
and see if it appeals to me because like I said on paper as I'm reading it, this is what
I have been waiting for.
I mean, quite honestly, I guess I've kind of been waiting for red hat to do it simply
because then I would have, um, you know, it would be like this nice, easy transition.
Right.
It's your home turf already.
And then since I'm already administrating red hat servers and I just, it would make
kind of nice, but this seems like they are, you know, they're really cracking down and
aiming.
I am their target audience.
They're like, I am the person that this is, is reading that this is written for.
And it also seems like they're also targeting, uh, arm guys, which is really, really encouraging
because you're seeing those arm devices becoming more and more prevalent and lower and lower
costs.
Um, and I think that's a big deal.
That's a huge deal.
You know, it goes, it goes with the whole, the whole Linux way.
If you can get a cheap, easy processor and you know that Linux will just run on it and,
and open Seuss has got that huge build service.
So you know that they are ready to, to build any open source software that can be for your
platform.
Then, you know, you can, you can build the whole solution on that.
Yeah.
That's the promise.
Have you used the open build service?
Yeah.
You know, I, I think it's great.
I've used it to find, um, supported packages.
I've used it when I'm using open Seuss and then as well, you know, it seems to support
other distributions as well.
Uh, random projects that use it to supply, you know, to build different packages for
all kinds of things.
Yeah.
So it builds for, uh, Ubuntu Debs, Debian Debs, uh, RPMs for both Seuss and Fedora and
Magia.
And it also builds for arch packages and a couple other things as well.
Yeah.
I love that arch package integration.
That's, that's just great.
Yeah.
I've actually, uh, the only, the only thing is, is that it has a custom spec file you
have to learn how to use, but so basically you build a script using their spec file and
then it will upload your source to their servers and they build out everything for you.
It's, it's pretty awesome.
And I wish more people would use it.
You say it's actually better than I think, uh, via Tumbleweed, could you expand on that
a little bit?
Yeah.
And what I was saying is that, uh, people are thinking that it's, it's, it's more like
a workstation thing, but it's actually a more cohesive sharing structure of what they're
going for.
So like they're having, uh, SLE has released all of their stuff for the OBS so that the
open Seuss can have, they can spend less time on open Seuss stable or, you know, the regular
version and more time on Tumbleweed.
And because of this, Seuss has like a deal sort of thing struck structured where open
Seuss, uh, base is going to be based on SLE.
Then open Seuss is going to do extra stuff on top of that to do, uh, you know, more up
to date packages and provide a more user experience for the average user.
But they're also doing Tumbleweed and Tumbleweed is the rolling release, like the arch thing.
And in certain cases, um, you know, people always talk about how arch gets things faster,
but Tumbleweed actually is getting stuff faster.
I haven't tested for 318, but no, they got known 316 in before arch did and like staple
and running and everything.
And they're doing, they're doing things like that are really impressive in this sense.
But another cool thing is that Tumbleweed is going to be the base for SLE in the future.
So every three years or so, Tumbleweed is going to be like snapshotted and then that
becomes SLE, which then comes back into the, you know, the, the, the workstation type structure
for open Seuss for leap.
So you'd get a Tumbleweed snap snapshot, then you get a SLE, then you take SLE stuff, put
it into a leap again, and then it keeps this, you know, a whole cycling structure of open
Seuss.
Like just everything is shared between the enterprise version and the workstation and
the rolling.
So in certain cases, like for example, every year SLE does like a service pack that will
also be instituted into the leap packages.
So you even get a yearly update as well as just, you know, the whole, you know, stuff
sitting on top of it.
You're not getting just open Seuss editing things and giving you more up-to-date packages.
You're also getting Suse enterprise updates as well as the open Suse updates and the Tumbleweed
updates.
That sounds various, like, like a leaner, meaner, Debian plus enterprise backend and
kind of the best of all worlds.
That's impressive.
It does.
It sounds like not only is it the best of all worlds, it sounds like somebody is sitting
there going, what does Noah want as a Linux distro?
And then that's what they're making.
You don't think those people exist, Noah?
Come on.
Yeah.
I'd like to believe that they do.
I mean, on the, the, I just, I have a, I am comfortable in, in a multitude of different
Linux distros.
I am comfortable on Centos.
I'm comfortable on Ubuntu.
I'm comfortable on Fedora.
I'm comfortable on Arch.
Suse and open Suse is maybe the one, one of the, one of the few main distros that I haven't
used extensively.
And this article is really making me reconsider that like big time.
I'm downloading the ISO at home right now.
Yeah.
There's actually something you should check out.
Another thing that's going to, a lot of people don't even know about it, but it's open Suse
have built the open RA system.
So it's like a automated testing structure and it's, that's the, I just put the link
in the chat room.
This is a cool thing because they're, they're tested, they're not only just doing leap testing,
they're doing tumbleweed testing with this, they're doing, they're, they're working on
sleet testing as well.
And the coolest thing is that if you look at a test, I'm going to send you a link for
that too.
If you look at one of the tests, it will go through the process of automating it and then
it shows you a screenshot of every single test and whether it passed or not.
And this is a beta one, so there are a couple of fails, but this is one of the beta builds.
So and it goes through like the entire installation process, the entire setting up Gnome, the
running Gnome, testing different applications in Gnome, and it gives you this full automated
testing thing and it shows you where it works and where it doesn't.
And if that wasn't cool enough, they actually made a video version of it.
So every single test has a video attached to it.
You can watch the test just run.
That seems awesome.
It really does.
I'm going to have to, I'm more of a hands-on learner.
So I'm following 90% of what you're saying, but I think to really get the full scale of
it, what I'm going to have to do is play with it.
And so like I said, I actually have a laptop that is dedicated to trying all this out as
soon as I get home tonight.
And so I'm going to be playing with it the rest of the week and I'll have to report back
in and tell you what you think.
And Wes, you said you're considering doing the same, huh?
Yeah.
You know, I've been looking for a replacement.
I've been using Linux Mint on my work workstation, mostly because that was one of the provided
images when I was hired.
But it's feeling a little, you know, I've got the distro hop and itch like many of us
do.
So I think this will be a great thing to try out and see if I can use it as my day-to-day
at work.
Yeah.
Anyone else in the mumble room have any thoughts on the OpenSUSE situation, story, release?
Anyone else going to try it?
I mean, I'm already trying it.
I've got one machine running, Tumbleweed.
And I haven't tried Leap yet, but I do plan on trying Leap as well.
But Tumbleweed is just impressive.
And especially with OBS in conjunction with Tumbleweed, you get, like, it's not really
like a PBA, it's not an alternative to PBA, it's not like an exact same thing, but it
is very similar and you get a lot of packages up to date as well.
So it's a really good experience.
So you should try both if you're interested in just seeing what they're, what SUSE is
doing with all this and OpenSUSE is doing.
It is really cool.
And another cool thing is that they have turned, like, you should look at their installer.
Like their installer is nice, looks great, and it's all in Curses.
Oh, really?
I love in Curses.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
It looks like a real, like a regular installer, like a GUI installer, and it is presented
like a GUI, but it is all through in Curses and it's all, like, I'm pretty sure it's all
based on Yast.
So it's like Yast is handling it all.
It is really slick and it is also, like, super fast and lightweight when it runs.
And like, it's kind of like, it's kind of so cool, it's hard to actually describe it.
So I'm so excited what SUSE is doing.
Yeah.
It is rubbing off.
Sure is.
Yeah.
And so I'm going to have to try it and report back.
And like I said, it's a little bit hard to conceptualize all this stuff, especially because
a lot of these services, associated services with open SUSE, you know, don't mean a lot
to me because I haven't really used it a whole lot.
I tried to implement it one time in a commercial setting and I ran into, the first little problem
I ran into, I'm not even necessarily blaming open SUSE, it was just, it was a dumb little
problem that I had and I just said, just went to Ubuntu.
And that was probably a little unfair and in hindsight, maybe that was a little foolish
and short-sighted, but I'm going to give it a real world and report back.
Now I have a request from the community and from everyone else.
We are looking for Runs Linux.
We are looking for really cool and unique Runs Linux.
We are looking for a picture or a video of something that runs Linux.
We see the things that like in restaurants and stuff and that's super cool.
And if you see those, please send those in.
But if you have something unique, especially if you are part of a project like the guy
that wrote in that did the school bell.
Oh, I love that one.
Yeah.
Wasn't that cool?
Super cool.
I mean, that, that is, that combines everything that is cool.
It combines open hardware.
It combines open software.
It combines a maker and you put education, education.
You get all this stuff together and you get something really cool out of it.
I know that you guys are out there.
I know that you guys that are doing cool Runs Linux people, I know you guys are out there.
So I want you to upload a video to YouTube or submit a link via the subreddit or email
Linux action show at jupyterbroadcasting.com or go to jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Click on the contact link and choose Linux action show from the dropdown menu and let
us know about your Runs Linux.
We really, really want to hear it.
Also, the network is, could really use your support, um, patreon.com slash today.
I want to make a plea with you guys, um, to think about, uh, supporting the network.
If you're not supporting the network, I know that, um, you know, there's, there's a, there's
a wide variety of, of opinions, um, on, on, um, on, on the current show lineup and the
current way that we're doing the shows.
Um, but the way I have always looked at contributing to the network was I pay my cable bill and
I pay $80, $90 and, um, I'd flipped through the channels and some of the shows I liked
and some of the shows I didn't like and some of the episodes of the shows I liked and some
of the episodes, the shows I didn't like.
And at the end of the day, I still paid my cable bill, um, because it was a flat fee
and right now the network is, is in need of you guys to, to, to step up and help out.
So if, if you can afford it, um, we would really appreciate your support, patreon.com
slash today.
If you like the content, if you like what you're hearing, and I assume you do, if you're
listening to the episode, um, uh, throw the network a couple of dollars, every dollar
goes a long, long way and we would really appreciate it.
And if you get to swag level, uh, sponsorship, I just have to tell you, I, I feel like it's
Christmas.
The other day, Angela sent me this really cool, um, like, uh, like Jupiter broadcasting
pin.
Oh, I'm jealous already.
I know it's so like, I like ding dong, the door rings and I go up to the door and here's
the mail guy.
And I'm like, but I didn't order a package.
I did not spend any of my hard earned money.
Why am I getting this?
And I rip it open and then there's like, there's a little, there's a, there's a little treat
in there and I've gotten, I've gotten mouse pads and I've gotten coffee mugs and there's,
there's all sorts of things.
And I don't know, you know, I see sometimes some of the cool stuff that they're thinking
of sending out or, or trying to work out sending out.
It just, it's a cool thing to do.
So if you can get to swag level supportership, that's something that's in the budget for
you.
I highly recommend it.
It's super, super fun.
And it's really rewarding to know that for literally half the cost of what it would cost
you for direct TV or half the cost of what it would cost you for cable TV, you're supporting
a, uh, you know, you're supporting a, a small, a small business plus all that product for
Chris's hair.
It just doesn't buy itself.
No kidding.
Right.
Pay for that as a community.
He does.
And, and he, and you know, even living in the RV.
I was a little worried.
I was a little worried, Wes, when he showed up and he was talking about like doing the
dry shampoo.
I'm like, what if, what if all his hair fell out?
And like, he's the network.
It depends.
I know it is, is, it's a huge deal.
And so when he stepped out of the camper for the first time, like I was holding my breath
and I'm like, and I knock and then he opens the door and there's her master Chris.
And it looked amazing.
Yeah.
Looked amazing.
So patron.com slash today really, really, really would appreciate it.
If we could get, uh, if we could get some supporters, let's do this, let's, let's open
this up in a browser and let's look, let's see, um, let's see what we can accomplish
as a team.
How many, how many patrons does he have right now?
Right now he has 554.
Let's see if we can just get to 560.
But I like round numbers.
Do you ever, do you ever do that thing where you go to the gas station and he scored a
little bit of gas into the car and, uh, and you, you, you have to bump it up to the next
dollar just so it's a nice even amount.
It's like a fun little game.
I know.
Yeah.
So let's see if we can get it to exactly 560.
And, and so, and so Chris wakes up and goes, oh, that's kind of cool.
Look at what, look at what my, look what the podcast based on the community was able to
accomplish.
I think that would be super cool.
Agreed.
And you know, I always look forward to the next, the next program, you know, it's something,
it's something that I kind of define my week with is, is JB, is JB podcasts.
And I know a lot of you guys do too, so it really doesn't take very much to, to keep
Chris going.
No, no, it really doesn't.
And it, like I said, every dollar goes a long, long way.
Also join us Friday for the Linux action show.
And I can't tell you what we're going to talk about.
Top secret.
Yeah.
But I can tell you that in order to pull it off, we are going to need some Coca Cola, some
beef jerky, a blanket, a USB drive.
And I gave Chris a dedicated laptop before he left Grand Forks.
So make sure you tune in and you can see what we have planned.
It's going to be absolutely awesome.
And you can use your imagination and see what you can come up with.
Wes, is there anything you want to say before we get out of here?
No, just that it's been a pleasure co-hosting with you Noah.
Yeah, I really appreciate it.
We should do this more often.
I really think we should.
Who needs Chris anyway?
Yeah.
Why I need Chris.
Oh wait, nevermind.
But he can, but he can go on vacation every once in a while and enjoy himself and uh,
and we can hang out.
That brings us to the end of this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We should be at our usual time next week, over to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
to keep an eye on that.
Chris may change a couple of things while he's on the road.
If you have feedback about the show, jupyterbroadcasting.com, click on the contact link and choose Linux
Unplugged from the dropdown menu.
Also, if you miss Hair Master Chris, follow him on Twitter at Chris LAS or go to jupyterbroadcasting.com
slash Rover to see where he is right this second.
You can follow me on Twitter at Colonel Linux.
Thank you so much for tuning into this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
A special thank you to our producer, Michael Tennell, and our mumble team.
We'll see you right back here, next week.
That's a wrap.
Great show, everyone.
Individually.
It's such a pleasure having all these wonderful people.
Oops.
I hit the wrong button, Wes.
I hit the wrong button.
Uh-oh.
And so then I couldn't hear your voice in my ear hole.
Ah.
What will you do without my beautiful voice, Noah?
I know.
All right.
Now it's time to go to jbtitles.com.
Jbtitles.
I think I get to pick the title today.
I think I do.
You're not.
Yeah.
Oh.
I know.
We're in trouble, gang.
That makes me sad when I see things like a title that says, Who Needs Chris?
That's so sad.
I would miss the hair vest.
I would start crying if I didn't hear from him for a week.
I think it would cry.
It would make me sad.
Open source power outlets.
That's not bad.
Um.
End user dilemma.
Oh, man.
We don't have many.
You know what?
Now I know why Chris says bang suggest all the way throughout the episode.
Now I know.
You gotta goad the audience.
Yeah.
If you don't, you get 12 title suggestions.
And who doesn't want to say bang suggest?
Who doesn't want to say bang suggest?
I think we could have a lot of fun with God mode.
This is Noah in God mode.
Bang suggest inside of the chat room to come up with excellent titles that we can vote
at JBtitles.com ultimate Linux podcast in a world where no one has submitted a title.
Why does every single advertisement for a movie always start with in a world?
Like we don't live in other worlds.
We all live in the same world.
Maybe that's the the fantasy draw.
Maybe.
All right.
We need titles, guys.
We need time.
It's a.
Oh, we got multi universe type thing.
Noah in God mode, open source power, open source, your power outlets, open source, your
power outlets isn't bad, especially because it's close.
Yeah.
So do we like open source power outlets or open source, your power outlets?
Maybe not your just because it's shorter.
OK.
All right.
So open source power outlets is winning by seven votes.
All by four votes, total seven.
I mean, either one, I think are great.
Not the same just because I did them, but not anyone.
Unbiased rotten as always.
Protect the beard.
I was focusing more on moving you guys around than anything else.
Thank you.
Yes, thank you very much.
I really, really, really appreciate it, because the way that the setup is, if I if I if I if
somebody were to talk to the Mumble Room, I would reach over and mute the Mumble Room,
but then that would mute West and there's no way for me to separate West unless you
put us into our own separate.
Our own separate channel.
Don't worry.
We got this.
Yeah.
You guys are amazing.
Just just amazing.
Did you like my thank you to you rotten corpse at the end?
Yeah, that was fantastic.
So.
All right.
Open source power outlets is the winner.
Yeah, I declare it as a winner because it has to be because it has the most votes out
of everything.
Oh, you know what?
I'm not going to say it.
I'll say it.
I won't say it right now.
Okay.
What are we going to talk about for a post show?
We're going to talk about the open QA dot open source dot or open source dot org.
But yeah, I know that we've got there already.
I didn't know that was a photo impressions there.
Oh, yeah.
No, it doesn't matter.
There's tons of things to talk about.
What else should we talk about, guys?
To you, Mumble.
Hey, thanks for the meetup shout out.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
All right.
Let's talk.
Well, I guess I was kind of the pre-show topic.
But yeah, thank you so much for making the making the time to be at the meetup.
I, you know, it'd be really cool to get up and do that every once in a while.
I think that should be a thing.
Do, do, do.
Yeah.
And since I assume Chris isn't going to hear this part, I'm not going to break it to him
that they spelled my name wrong, but.
They spelled your name wrong?
Oh, yeah.
I had the Rover Rambler.
I didn't I didn't leave a card that since my name is Reed with an I.
Oh.
OK.
It'll be our secret.
It's not like it's going out over the air or anything.
So nobody will ever know.
So there's there's one thing this is more of an interesting topic or less, but it's
not really.
I guess it's perfect for post-show, I guess.
But there's a there's some new stuff with the like the Devils Canyon stuff and the new
hardware stuff for running.
Hard like running virtualization pass through.
So you have the hardware, hardware acceleration and everything in a virtual machine.
So you could use something like KVM or you could use a bird manager or whatever.
And I think even VirtualBox has this.
So you can play Windows games inside of a virtual machine with your hardware and everything.
So it feels like a full.
You know, you have a full machine, you basically have, you know, everything you absolutely
need.
And even like 60 frames per second games and stuff running now, are they using KVM pass
through for that?
Yeah, there's KVM pass through and well, it's PCI pass through, but you basically get access
to your graphics card and you get the full processor ability.
So it limits like your main host.
But if you're playing a game, it doesn't matter.
But it gives you like the full access to all of your hardware.
And only like the latest like from Haswell and newer has these like these features like
pretty solid.
But you need to have like a motherboard and the processor needs to support it.
Both need to support it.
Otherwise, it won't work.
What is it?
Intel?
Is it BTD?
Is the name of the?
Yeah, I think so.
Yes, BTD.
I've always had this crazy idea that I could have like one physical machine that sits in
my basement and then have like four video cards and then a KVM switch so I could KVM
through my different computers, but they're all physically one machine.
I don't know how realistic that is, but I dream or maybe not to definitely possibly
three or might be a little bit over the time.
Don't push your luck, Noah.
You know, separation is so nice, like even things for different tasks.
The amount of times that I have thanked myself for having a separate video production computer
than everything else.
It's not because video production is so like it's not like I can multitask doing video
production.
Either I'm editing video or I'm not, but the mere fact that it's on a separate machine
means that I can slide my chair over, get a little bit of work done, and if I have to
do something else, I go to a different machine to do it.
Not only am I not interrupting my workflow, but I don't wind up with extra junk on my
machine like I don't wind up with Thunderbird with misconfigured email accounts because
the password changed, but I hadn't opened it in a year or so that, you know, just didn't
work or something like that.
And I don't wind up with, you know, weird files and my huge long list of Firefox bookmarks
on my video editing machine.
All I have is resources for editing videos.
And as we know in your life, everything changes pretty much all the time.
So it's probably essential to have some a little firewall where you can say this is
the purpose and it stays that way and I change it only when needed.
Wes, I call it an ADD firewall.
Perfect.
It's a firewall for my ADD and it helps me separate things out into separate machines.
You have a toy machine over there.
Don't install that package yet.
That's the one with the shiny stuff on it.
Exactly.
But yeah, so that has been where I have found that's been hugely helpful to be able to compartmentalize
stuff and if I could, that's a promise, it's very, very expensive to buy different machines
to do multiple different things.
Yeah, boy, the number of computers you have, that's right, brings a tear to my eye.
Yeah.
So you need a KVM switch with a keyboard and mouse shut off so it limits the access to
that machine.
Well, if I had, so if I could pass through, so the KVM switch will give me four USB connectors,
right?
And four video connectors.
And so I could plug all four video, I could plug all four KVM connectors into the computer
and I'm hoping there would be a way that I could tell it this USB plug is only passed
through to this computer and this one is only passed through to this computer.
And I don't know, I might end up having to use separate like little PCI, you know, cards
with a separate USB controller, huh, to be able to get that to work.
Oh, you know what, I just saw somebody on YouTube that did this, was that Logitech has,
what the heck they call it, it's the mouse that has like multiple Bluetooth dongles and
a switch on the bottom of the mouse that you can go back and forth.
Oh, that is awesome.
And like, you know, it's intended to be, you know, you can plug, you can pair with two
different computers, but if you plug the USB dongle into the same computer and then pair
the USB port that the dongle is plugged into your KVM, then, you know, you've got the same
mouse that's paired with two different machines on the same physical host.
It's like a hardware synergy.
You know what's funny?
You took the words right out of my mouth.
Those are my words now.
Yeah.
That's what I was, that's right about what I was going to say was it's like what I look
for with synergy and except not in synergy.
Well that'll be really cool.
I will have to keep an eye on that.
It's something that, it's something that I really think I could put into practice.
Again, it's, I'm going to run up against that problem of, since I have a working solution,
I'm going to have to pry myself away.
Anything else anyone wants to add into the post show before we get out of here?
Well the reason I brought up the hardware thing is because it creates a potential discussion
topic of when Linux adoption is something that's really hard to do right now, you know,
for a, you know, forever basically because trying to convince them about a certain application
blah blah.
Do you think it would be better and that Linux would be more likely to kind of take over
the world if, you know, there was pre-packaged applications that you could just run and like
instead of having to see, oh, does it support it?
Doesn't matter.
Your virtual machine has an app.
We have an instead of a wine wrapper, we have a virtual machine wrapper and all you do is
install this and there you go.
I've done that on a basic scale for my parents before where I had a Windows application listening
for a file at startup and I would have a shortcut on the Linux desktop for like, you know, when
my mom, for instance, would need to use Microsoft Office for a certain document, you know, once
in a while that she could pass it, open it up just like a regular application, it would
open the virtual machine, the virtual machine would know to open Word.
So I think there's something there.
Long term solution maybe not but it could be a really good, you know, a wrapper for
someone who wants to transition but still requires a certain amount of Windows specific.
You know, I keep coming back to, I really hope I'm not wrong on this but I'm really
hoping that as we move forward, that web centric applications begin to take more dominance
and as that happens, the need for a compatibility layer just kind of drops.
I mean, hopefully.
Yeah, but the web layer can't really work with the hardware that well.
Yeah, that's true.
Something has to talk to the hardware, you're right.
So there's certain things like, I don't know, it's kind of like the web apps have like,
I use web apps a lot and they're great in certain cases and they're awful in other cases.
So like stuff like WebGL are making that a lot better but I think that there's, you know,
I don't want web apps to become the norm.
I would like them to become a novelty that it's a very highly used novelty.
Yep, yep.
I'm right there with you Rottencorpz, I really am.
I have seen web apps, I have always looked at them as a necessary evil.
I would prefer that my software run locally but if I have my choice between running the
software on Linux in a web browser or running Windows software only, if I have to pick between
those two, I'll take the web software every time.
Yeah, I would agree with that.
Windows users migrate to web software, Linux will keep our awesome desktop applications.
Yeah, exactly.
See, now we're on the money, we can agree on that.