It is really fun. There was a there was a very fun and sort of rewarding feeling
to be sitting in a gravel parking lot that I just kind of found somewhere not
connected to anything and broadcasting and doing a show. Totally free just yeah
like it's like whoo like no wires no connection just I plopped down and I'm
streaming on the internet and you know one of the funniest things when that
happened is that's when that's when Anthony found us and came up and joined
us for Linux Unplugged. It was like totally random and awesome and I didn't even
realize the time was part of a vlog that he was doing so like he had started he
had started like watching us on the rover as we came into town and so he was
doing his overall vlog update to his YouTube channel and so hit the visit was
part of the update so it was like a show within a show happening and I didn't
even know it until the end. How about that? This is Linux Unplugged episode 113
for October 6th 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's once again
broadcasting from the JB one studio my name is Chris and my name is Wes. Hey
Wes it's good to be back with you sir. Pleasure to have you. You and Noah did a
great job last week fantastic it was actually a really good collaborative
production by the whole crew producer RottenCorps and the producers helped out
a lot you were great Noah was fantastic. He sure was. I heard he was the Segway
master. Yep oh yeah you might learn a trick or two from him. Yeah yeah the
Segway master I love it although when you combine Google Glasses with the
Segway that's a pretty nerdy image. Yep half robot half Noah. That's a strong
brand so thank you to Noah for sitting in there for the show and I actually
invited him to make it I'd invite him if he could make it he said he's pretty
busy today but he might be able to stop by later in the show. Hey that'd be fun.
Might join us in the Mumba room so we'll just see. You know on today's episode we've
got a few things we're gonna dig into. Number one it's Microsoft Day happy
Microsoft Day everybody did you enjoy that? Was that good for you? Yeah they
actually had a pretty respectable showing they unveiled the Surface Book
now we're gonna look at and see if it's possible it could run Linux and what
that would mean and you might be surprised at the answer about that then
later on in the show we're gonna talk about keeping Linux performing well over
the long time I'm talking about desktops I went away on the road trip as you guys
know and when I got back my tried-and-true my favorite workstation the
one that never disappoints is not running very good and we're gonna talk
about ways to maybe speed up your Linux system if it starts to slow down over
time and maybe hopefully get some input from the Mumba room and then last but
not least we're gonna talk about some updates from the Linux development
community so before we dive into all of that stuff let's bring in the Mumble
room time appropriate greetings virtual lug. Hello you guys it's good to hear you
without dropping about 75% of my packets that's nice now I know I actually have a
good connection oh yeah that's cool that's cool all right so I wanted to
start with something that came out yesterday it's just sort of a warm-up to
the show today and perhaps maybe something we all should consider a
possibility of a world without Linux yeah well sort of this is the Linux
foundations attempt to kind of make us stop and think what would the world be
like if Linux hadn't come along and they just released episode 1
hey what's the name of that Michael Jackson song oh how does it go
right you know the one huh da da da da he something like that oh yeah shoot
what is it um let me look it up
he goes to the library obviously that's how you look things up there's no
internet got it Billie Jean Billie Jean now it's
nighttime a world without Linux would mean a world without the internet
did that come out I think you're going to need these picks up the keys a world
without Linux is hard to imagine thanks to hundreds of thousands of individuals
and companies who support Linux we don't have to learn more and help support
Linux today hashtag world without Linux of course there's a hashtag well there
has to be yeah yeah so there you go the Linux so it's not bad right that's not
so bad they're gonna have another episode are we there yet and then they're
gonna have they're gonna like four episodes what do you think West I think
North Ranger in the IRC's got it down the BST folks probably will not
appreciate this that said I think it's good to point it you know well Linux may
not be the only free internet scale you know operating system that exists it is
widely deployed and it gives us a lot of freedoms that we would not otherwise
have so I'm glad that they're doing this some of the points might be a little
strong-armed but it was a nice video yeah the production value yeah it's okay
yes that's actually good it was good production value I know Poby is excited
about this next update I just wanted to talk about real quick before we get into
the main show and it's the n1 it's a beautiful open source email app for
Linux and it clocks in at a pretty hefty think like 20 megabytes or something
like that but it's it's like it's here to kick Thunderbird 64 64 megabytes
thank you that was 20 Wow and does anybody know like West you have a guess
why it clocks in at 64 megabytes those static dependencies I believe it would
be based on top of chromium it's like it's like Haru pad or Adam right the
chromium and no jazz I think is bundled in there as well you got a no jazz for
the events yeah naturally so I don't know do we hate this or are we okay with
giant applications look at look okay what if we get a really great functional
app that comes with Linux support out of the box don't we don't we like that you
know if it if it works really well I'm mostly curious to see how personal
deployments of the back end servers go that's what's gonna make it a break
it from yeah yeah what do you think wimpy yeah I agree I'm actually I've
just received my activation key for it so I'm actually oh great eating it right
now yeah okay but yes I'm I'm interested as well to know how the back end
integration is going to work longer term so are we just don't just what don't
give them your like primary email account because yeah right well the
sync engines open source right so I mean people could go poke around in there and
well I guess it probably I guess if the server is closed up I'm not sure what
the code of the server license of the server is but I assume the server is
open source too if you're installing it right yes okay so alright do we not then
hate the fact this is a 64 megabyte application that you have to run just to
check your email no I don't care I don't care the file size that's tiny really if
it means it's gonna work and it means that when they do an update the thing
isn't dependent upon some other random library on my system it all just works
that's great yeah especially if that means it's easy to deploy to you know
random machines that you just need it to work oh right that's a good point too
huh all right I think I'm gonna containers as well I think you could like
slap this in the container and you're done you know you don't have a truckload
of dependencies that it needs all right I'm signing up for I'm asking for an
invite right now boom oh look I can connect my github account isn't that
lovely all right I'll do that too I'm not sure why I have to oh okay you have
to do that and and star it and that speeds up your I wouldn't hurry too much
because it doesn't work oh thank you thank you all right well I did it
anyways please try to connect to your account again try again something went
wrong so yeah okay so we're we're starting to see a more and more
applications like I mentioned another one that I believe is also built so
similar to n1 is heru pad which is the the markdown editor I use which I not
only love but now I consider to be essential tool one of the things it does
is not only does it hotkey all the markdown stuff but it does live
rendering and you can apply your website CSS file to that live rendering so you
literally see what it looks like on your website as you're writing it you know
the fonts and the way you you know the way the block quotes look and
everything it's just such a fan but here's the downside I mean this is a
pretty fast system of course I just launched it so it's probably gonna
launch pretty quick but I just clicked it I mean it's it's it's heavy I can
tell it it's it's one of the slowest launching applications I have in my
desktop and it's a damn text editor right yeah I find that people have
similar complaints with it does not me just a little bit right but I don't
give anyone a shot so all right cool guys well wimpy let me know how far you
get in the process well I'm a bit further along but now it won't actually
proceed through this I'm at the point where it says choose your layout style
and there's a button says looks good which doesn't we have a layout style
called looks good that would probably never but now you've got list view or
split view so I can I can select those and I can say what key bindings I use
so gmail Apple Mail or outlook your options and interesting good looks good
and that's me clicking the mouse and it not doing anything I managed to get my
my install done before you lot all jumped on it so I was playing with it
early in the morning and was like yeah this is good then I tweet it and it all
breaks and they put a paywall invite thing in front of it so oh so poppy what
jumped out at you the kind of you were impressed by when you say it's good so I
like the UI it's quite clean it's very familiar if you're using if you're a gmail
user it's very obvious what's going on you've got the folders down the left and
the emails in the middle and then you get some detail about the contact on the
right-hand side it's quite pretty I'm just very wary about the fact that this
server can retain my email for 60 days even after I revoke their access to my
email that's yeah yeah okay it's working now oh so are you guys there is like a
couple of apps there's like a mailbox is one but Google bought them but inbox is
another it's sort of similar for it's like a mobile it's a mobile app that
does something similar like it's almost proxies the mail and then categorizes
it for you it's becoming like a service that is a little creepy and so that is
an area that see the problem with email right is that you get all your password
reset emails very personal you get I get credit card I mean credit card companies
are now starting to email statements they're like all this kind of stuff that
if somebody got compromised and it seems like anybody can get compromised these
days so I'm using a gash account to get it set up it's actually running now but
I had to go into Google Mail and actually tell it to have access to all
mail folders you can't use the you know what the tick boxes to filter out what
gets displayed in the mail client and basically somebody said it looks like
Google Mail it does it looks exactly like Gmail just in a window the way the
folders are laid out and I'm not actually a big fan of the Google Mail UI so I'm
just thinking what's the what's the USP here hmm I guess well it can connect to
multiple different accounts right it will it will look the same with it like
if you're if you like the the Gmail paradigm but the way you view mail this
thing can connect to Yahoo Outlook and all the others and you have that unified
interface so it all looks consistent rather than having four different user
interfaces for those four different accounts yeah plus I connect to your I
map but see I can do that but I can do that say with Gary right now and the
the other one that I was talking about earlier is Zimbra have a desktop mail
client Zimbra desktop and that has integration with all the popular email
services and it includes integration with you know your contacts and your
calendars and that's built on web technologies as well so that's a very
competent email client I think hmm I'm I'm I know and producer rotten corpse
would recommend claw right now I'm I'm I don't want to I don't want to
disparage you because I have a couple things they just inherently like about
it is it's it looks like a pretty good product that's just available day one on
Linux but now looking at these screenshots I can totally see what you
guys are saying about Gmail it yeah it's I would think that is a screenshot from
Gmail yeah yeah yeah so I do like though that it if you pulls in multiple
services I'm going to check it out I'm just not quite sure what it's gonna give
me I think I know it's gonna give me over Thunderbird Thunderbird just feels
like a 90s product now I mean I love it still it's my boo and I love the fact
that enigma is super easy to integrate with it that's my favorite thing about
it yes but Gary and now and one are knocking on the door and the thing is
email is a monster for me it is a demon that I have to slay a couple of times a
week and it is a take no prisoners event and I want anything that makes me get
through that as fast as possible and does a little tree and anything that
helps me triage is good and that's not really Thunderbird Thunderbirds strong
sweet and strong suit and it's just I could I am definitely looking for
replacement the one thing I like more about Geary is it feels like it's
faster to move through but important if you're doing a lot of emails yeah is
this I the one thing I like about this is the label support and the starring
and also it looks like a little bit of thread support and then you have reading
this helpful and you have contact information on the far right pane which
is useful for me too especially because then sometimes I can put faces to
listeners names and stuff and that's really nice for me so that that is I
something I achieved today through extensions that I would really like to
have that so this I mean I emails a serious enough task for me that I'm
willing to burn some drive space and CPU cycles on something that's a really good
tool yeah I'd love to go to use this for my my work exchange server yeah it'll
just all depend on that back end stuff yeah well they think they're gonna
support they do support plugins so somebody might be able to write an
exchange plug-in I think it supports exchange already no I'm just worried
about these data retention no way so if I can deploy it all locally yeah you
can't change mail retention yes exactly you don't want retention might not be
pleased yeah but wow it does have exchange
support yeah which is impressive I have to check out this open it's been in
development for nearly a year okay so looking at the github repository the
first commits for about 11 months ago and yeah it is working now so a little
bit of a bumpy start with them how it was you know getting the setup going but
now it's working now I found some of the options it's quite nice I use gearing
myself at the moment I've been using that for a month or so and I think I'll
give this a try basically I've just got mailing lists and everything on this
account hmm so I'll use it for that because that's where I get sort of
volume of email that I have to filter and work through so I'll give it a go
but um it does look nice once I've got it in split for you now and that looks
much better that's much more usable I might follow up with you and see how it
goes fascinated yeah all right good job thank you and one nice stuff they call
it a beautiful open source email app I don't know it does look like I don't
know if it's beautiful it does look pretty good though it looks kind of like
a Mac app to me yes it does look like a Mac don't know if that makes it
beautiful it's clear to it's clear to read good yeah the screenshots it does
look pretty nice yeah all right current anyway yeah yeah if you guys listening
at home want to check it out we have a link in the show notes I'll give a plug
now that I'm back there's probably gonna be one more rover log and the hat we
have them all posted now so far at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash rover
and there's some electrical stuff we did in there you guys probably heard about
last week the rover logs I'm just give them a plug because they've people have
been I think surprised when they watch them that they've enjoyed them they like
they thought I actually have been I've been surprised people enjoy them in fact
we've gotten some attention from YouTube over them as well they were featured on
the YouTube travel section which is pretty cool turns out you're pretty
interesting guy Chris well I don't know about that but the rover logs at least
work out to be interesting and so if you haven't checked them out there's
probably one more coming at least and then I'll decide where to go from that
and speaking of the rover you know one of the things that was awesome about the
road trip was the rovers internet was provided by ting you can go to right now
Linux dot ting comm to get our Linux unplugged discount and support the show
ting is mobile that makes sense as my mobile service provider and we have the
a netgear zing on the road and I you know for the most part the netgear zing I
really like it and sometimes it was a little slow for me just on the UI but I
very often had to interact with the zing seems like a really good product and I'm
I'm surprised that there's not more of them out there there and perhaps maybe
that's just because of the networks that ting's on ting has a CDMA and GSM
network and I was using the zing on a CDMA network and it's a really nice way
to go because now that I'm not going to be on the road trip this is not
something I would use a ton and that's what's really nice about the ting model
is in aggregate it's gonna save me a ton of money because you only pay for what
you use and there's no contract so it's six dollars to have the zing and six
dollars for any line and then you just pay for the usage on top of that well
say I go on a two-week road trip and I use a lot of data maybe that month I pay
for that data right but for the rest of the year I'm maybe not on a road trip
and it is incredibly cheap to have a my fi device ready to go on the ting CDMA
network now like I said ting does have two networks you probably have a pretty
good chance of having a compatible device and if you do and if you do when
you go to linux.ting.com they're gonna give you a service credit that'll
probably pay for more than your first month they also have an early
termination relief program which helps you get out of a contract if you're in
one of those duopoly contracts right now which come on let's be honest that
contract thing is starting to feel like a dinosaur you got to get out of it if
you're still in one and ting will help you save money you can go to their
savings calculator and putting your actual usage in there before taxes crazy
how much I'll save yeah I don't like to over $2,000 for two years which is
basically you could get a computer for that I think it's you know right now too
with the new with the new Nexus devices check this out West if you go to
linux.ting.com they're gonna take some money off these devices so these
devices are unlocked you own these right there's no contract when you buy them
and I'm flipping through them right now if you're watching the video version I'm
gonna land down here on the new Nexus devices where I just saw them here and
the Nexus 6p you can get it directly from Ting right there look at that that's
awesome the Moto X pure edition $399 unlocked directly from Ting LG Nexus 5x
$379 unlocked no contract pay for what you use $6 a month for the line comes
ready to go no problems that is nice that is really nice I I'm I'm attempted
I I'm they finally added a freaking fingerprint sensor to the Nexus and I
USBC yeah and those are I'm looking to try that that new standard out those are
check boxes that got ticked for me so you can get that one 379 when you go to
linux.ting.com and I think with this one they're gonna because that price is
already so low they're just gonna give you a service credit so quite literally
for 379 your first month you wouldn't probably even have to pay for it
especially if you're Wi-Fi savvy when it comes to data usage I mean it's $25
service credit is gonna last you that first month that's how low Ting is and
and you I mean that's oh that's a really actually a really sweet way to get that
phone unlocked linux.ting.com go over there check them out just see what they
offer try out their savings calculator see if maybe it works for you and a big
thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged and thanks for the rover data
all right so today I couldn't help it because I was back doing tech talk today
in studio and I was immersed immersed in Microsoft Day and I just want to cover
it right really quickly on the Linux unplugged show the surface book yeah I
get it out of your system now they call it surface book was announced today and
be honest mumble room it's not a bad rig is it it actually looks like a pretty
impressive piece of kit anybody disagree pretty good so it just for those of you
that are not familiar with it it is a 13 inch laptop it has a high-resolution
like 246 or whatever is 214 ppi screen it's really high-resolution screen it
has i7 or i5 core processors it comes with an NVIDIA GPU with DDR 5 so it's a
pretty current NVIDIA GPU USB 3 connectors and the key feature about it
is that it breaks off and it actually also becomes a tablet when you break it
off from a tablet it still has pretty good battery life it switches to Intel
graphics on the fly you snap it back together and now it's it's a full-fledged
laptop and Microsoft has developed this latching technology that actually
electrifies the latch so it's not like a spring-loaded latch they created this
tough wire that they call it and when they add current to it it seizes and it
latches it and you're able to from the hands-on demos say you can hold the
laptop in the corner of the screen and bounce it and it feels like a solid piece
of connected machinery and then you hit the release valve and it discharges the
tough wire and it comes right out and it disconnects from the base now when it
disconnects from the base it goes to an integrated GPU but otherwise it remains
a pretty nice machine now here's the full specs it weighs in at 3 pounds 13.5
inch pixel sense display with 3000 by 2000 resolution which does work out to
be a 267 ppi as a sixth generation Intel core i5 or i7 processor that means you
get the HD graphics the 520 graphics and then the discrete is the NVIDIA GeForce
graphics you can get an 8 or 16 gigabytes of RAM up to a 1 terabyte of
SSD has 802.11 ACBGN Bluetooth 4 obviously 2 USB 3.0 ports and mini
display out 8 megapixel rear 5 megapixel front windows hello face
authentication and up to 12 hours of battery life ships with Windows 10
obviously price of 1499 base you get it with an i7 and even 512 megabytes of
storage now it is PCI Express storage and that price very quickly shoots up to
$2,700 in some of the configurations that we were trying but in the demos
they showed it actually has pretty impressive performance they showed live
transitions in premiere they showed live edits and AutoCAD and the thing can flip
around and and act as a tablet it can break off and just be a standalone
tablet but you can flip it around and have it on the keyboard still have the
GPU and discrete have our still and having tablet form factor we started
looking into the specs trying to figure out how likely this thing could run
Linux and PCMag had a hands-on at the Microsoft showing and they were looking
specifically at the latching mechanism and they talk about how the GPU is
located in the base of the system back where the keyboard is and supposedly a
pretty decent keyboard too and they say the latching mechanism has a wide
electrical connector and they say no doubt a PCI based interface to
facilitate communication between the GPU and the rest of the system so we were
speculating the pre-show that if this is a truly a PCI interconnect between the
top of the machine and this keyboard accessory it is very possible that the
keyboard and that trackpad are coming in over USB on that interconnect and the
battery obviously is coming over the PCI connector now we don't know exactly
what the solution would be for graphics but it's very likely this would work
with Linux yet that if it has enough standard compliance stuff that you know
we can with a little work people can get drivers adapted for that would be great
and I'm thinking worst case scenario you would have to just use the discrete
graphics or just the Intel graphics right if this was a reasonable approach
West if you if you were in the market for a really high-end quote-unquote
laptop and you wanted to run Linux I would consider it you know I mean it
depends on how well the laptop part works I do a lot of stuff on the command
line obviously but it's really interesting to see Microsoft as a
hardware vendor if they do make stuff that Linux can run then I wouldn't be
opposed to it you know I don't need their included bundled OS and let's say
let's say a work is buying well if it works fine yeah I would definitely
consider it yeah if it ran Linux with the you know only a reasonable number of
tweaks then I would definitely consider it so if yeah if you were like I say you
worked in a workplace and they were decided to start buying the Microsoft
gear I don't know I hope you would you like this would you try this would this
be something you'd be willing to run well well my first reaction is when you
when you suggest like you break down the connectors and how things interconnect
that's all magic and great but have you tried an Nvidia Prime or you know
bumblebee based system how long have they been around and they're two GPUs in
one laptop without any wacky connector that pulls them apart and puts them back
together again and we can't even get that working properly yeah let alone
something that dynamically appears and disappears off the PCI bus where there
may or may not be you know data currently in flight so then is this
Microsoft successfully bringing a type of convergence to the market in your
opinion no I mean we've seen this before there's this I mean that that
device is not glaringly different than the surface ASUS ASUS transformer or the
transformer yeah I mean or something like that if you think about it it's
not that much but really if you think about it it's not that much different
is it than the surface Pro well the fact that they've put some of the brains
inside the keyboard is a bit interesting and it's a bit different but I'm not
interested if it's if it's running Windows to be honest right yeah I don't
need yet another Windows machine yeah okay so anybody else in the mumble room
would you be tempted if maybe work was buying or the even for yourself if you
knew for fairly certainty that's in some way in some form Linux would work
anybody want to bite Sean I'm looking at you I'd bite but only if I could get
Linux running smoothly I won't have that Windows baloney on my system what if it
came down I see here's here's why I'm wondering if this is doable because I
think people make bigger compromises today to run Linux on a MacBook often
you know simple things like your Ethernet port doesn't work unless you
boot the operating system with it connected and that you have to figure out
how to get your webcam to work every time you want it to start and the
thermal controls are just recently been added there's a lot of compromises I
know I always bring this up but there's a lot of compromises people make for
their hipster hardware and Microsoft may have made a device here that may be
easier to run Linux on than the MacBook Pro we will have to see change things
I'm not it's I've still I've got a I've got a five-year-old MacBook Pro here and
they still doesn't run Linux the bar is not that high like they could do it this
to me is the real test of Microsoft by the way one of the things that Satya
set up on stage today is they don't want people to feel like they have to run
Windows they want them to they want to want to run Windows and we'll see if
that's true with this surface Pro or surface book sorry if it if it requires
Windows to make that magic work and it's not done at the hardware level then I
don't know how much I believe them in that statement but if this is something
that developers could buy and load any operating system they want on then I'm
starting to believe them I think this is a real good test because this is the
first time they've ever made a laptop yeah it's interesting in the new Satya
era yeah as they say and and I do I do agree I think the convergence
comparisons are a little are a little weak I've been seeing a lot of that
online it seems a little it's not really convergence the thing that's just a
fancy new connector really yeah tell me it's convergence when you open up
Internet Explorer windows file explorer tell me how converge that is yes it's
not convergence all right so any other thoughts guys on the surface I just
wanted to touch on it because it's like the big topic today everybody's
Microsoft blew it out of the park Microsoft stock went up a whole bunch it
was a pretty good presentation I got to give the guy that he at least had his
own take on it so any last thoughts going once twice all right we'll leave
that if you guys want to read the specs you can find the link in the show notes
I'll take a moment and mention digital ocean I love me some digital ocean
because they're a simple cloud hosting provider that's dedicated to making it
really easy to get your own Linux rig up on a cloud server that's super fast
they got tier one connections all connected to SSD drives and for like
five dollars a month you won't you won't believe how much you're gonna get so
you'll get start five dollars a month five dollars right here that's I less
than a hamburger a month you can get 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one
CPU and a terabyte of transfer but if you use our promo code do unplugged do
unplug that's one word lowercase then you're gonna get a $10 credit you can
try the $5 rig out two months for free there's so much you can do with that and
their pricing plans are really straightforward they step right up very
simply they have a whole bunch of distros you can choose from maybe it's a
good opportunity to play with core OS or free BSD hurts me hurts me a little bit
to say it West but they do have free BSL it's gotten to you well you got to
respect how they do it too like they work with the projects to make sure that
it's like totally legit and you're getting updates from the projects and
they're coordinating and then like they roll out a ton of documentation that's
really well written and edited and it's just like it's a full package deal and
ironically you know it's their commitment to using things like full
heart you know KVM virtualization that let them do this kind of thing oh yeah
oh for sure for sure and they just launched a new data center up in Canada
too so if you want to store some data up in Toronto they have tour one one of the
many data centers they have been New York Amsterdam San Francisco Singapore
London Germany and now one in Toronto and you can deploy up there it's they
have one-click application deployments too it's very very nice so just remember
do one plug also if you want to just build something around the digital ocean
infrastructure they have a really nice API that makes it very easy to develop
your own app to do deployments and because they have hourly pricing really
if you want to just be a boss like if you like say you're launching something
or maybe you've got a project and it's day one for very very very little just
like very like cents on the dollar you can run a digital ocean server hourly
just scale up as you need it using their API shut her down when you don't and
it's serious on-demand infrastructure it's really cool so just use our promo
code do unplug to support the show there's lots of different ways from own
cloud sync bit torrent sync sync thing X to go there's a lot of ways people in
our community minecraft mumble in most users our virtual lug is running off a
digital ocean droplet right now it's really cool do unplug is how you can get
started and a big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged
program okay I I can't believe I'm about to say this because I feel like I'm a
frickin Windows user all of a sudden little embarrassing not to be
derogatory to those of you listening using Windows I shouldn't said that but
I got back from my road trip and I said I mean I'm not even joking when I say
this is I love this machine so much that when I sat down on it for the first time
I got back from the road trip I got a little excited like I like oh I get to
use this computer again I've missed it does anybody if you know what if you
have a computer like that you know what I'm talking about it's your bae your boo
is that what the kids say okay yeah you're very hip I thank you thank you I
try it's I try to be very very hip it's it's my thing and and the value of this
is negative so I sit down to use this computer and something something
something bad happened something real bad happened producer Matt was clipping
shows for on filter like crazy and the Dropbox folder sitting on my home drive
grew to unbelievable sizes and filled up my home drive ouch XFS partition I
thought no big deal I went in uncheck some selective sync stuff deleted a few
dozen ISOs that had been sitting in my download folder for a while good to go
you know just those little things you forget about yeah time to time and I get
back I'm now 70% free on my home drive it's funny of space yeah however however
the machine is running like dog crap like it's taking applications very
noticeable load times I can hear the drive crunching like crazy I my flash
video is like all hyper sped up it's all weird all of a sudden like the machine
is just hurting and I've never really had this problem with Linux but you know
I noticed that the Linux Foundation has launched a Linux performance tuning
course LFS for 26 for the low low price of $2,500 and I change really I thought
I bet I bet here on Linux unplugged we could come up with a few performance
tips for absolutely free that are maybe not 20 maybe but not as good as the
$2,500 ones but I thought maybe with between you and I in the virtual lug we
can come up with a couple of tips to just kind of keep your Linux rig running
a top performance over its lifetime I'm not saying this is like registry
cleaning kind of tools and crap like that but you know just ideas maybe
to just tricks people have picked up along the way yeah and so I don't know
if you guys in the mumble room if you want to think of a couple and if you're
in the chairman you have one and you can join the mumble room feel feel free to
jump in the mumble room and make your suggestion but I'm gonna I'm gonna start
with the elephant in the room the one we're all gonna probably talk about
that's the swap file that seems like the easy one to go to now all of us have
plenty of RAM I'm sure maybe maybe not but I guess if you have to swap the
number one thing that I'm I'm feeling right now is I think my swap partition
is on the same drive as my home drive I think I made that mistake when I set it
up I'm gonna just say right here and right now if you've got an old SSD you
want to burn through really bad or something like that if you can try to
put your swap files on a separate disk I actually I know a lot of you probably
listening just completely disable swap and if anybody wants to make that
argument in the mumble room you're welcome to for me I'm not comfortable
yet I don't know if it's just because I used to I just to me it seems crazy what
if I need to debug a crash I don't know I don't know how this works without my
swap file so I just have to put I just mentioned out there if you need a swap
file try to put it on a separate disk I think that's one of the things that I am
for some reason feeling the pain of right now you can also mess with your
swappiness but I'll leave that to so like heavens in the in the chatroom says
I sweat my I set my swappiness value to one which depending on your swappiness
value is how likely your system's gonna go to use it I'm a con the chatroom says
that he hasn't used a swap file for a few years now I know that's really super
common yeah it is definitely yeah do you have you ran a system without a swap
file yeah I think some of mine do it's kind of hit or miss depending on when I
set them up and how I was feeling that day but what would be like the deciding
factor for you you know if it's if it's something where I'm running a more
defined set of software I'm not worried about crashes I kind of know what
performance I'm expecting yeah then it's fine yeah you have plenty of RAM yeah
and if I have plenty of RAM then it's not a big deal you know some systems you
can always you know is there some on there yeah mumble room anybody in there
going swap free forever oh no on some machines I'm already swapped for a yeah
now why is that would be if it's not a laptop and I don't need it for
suspending and hibernating okay then I just use that RAM instead for a swap
maybe I should maybe I should kill my swap file poppy you were sounded pretty
adamant that you you would always have a swap file yeah I never don't have a swap
file now is that for sleep reasons are you always on laptops or is there
another reason because disk space is cheap and there's no reason not to have
one that's kind of been my approach is it but now I'm wondering if maybe I'm
paying for it by having it on the same drive as my home folder well that's
what's using it it's only a problem if you're you if it's swapping that's why
it's that's why it's not a problem so if you're not using it why do you care
come on in the chat room says what a what is swap so think of swap is like a
space on your disk that's been allocated for the operating system to store stuff
that doesn't necessarily need to be in RAM so that way the stuff that needs to
be in RAM has space extra slow really horrible RAM yeah when your system is
going to swap you're in a usually you know in a bad state so I I might
consider just because you know I could turn it off I could swap off yeah and
just see see how it goes maybe you have some homework for next week yeah I'm
gonna I'm actually gonna write that down yeah go ahead you said that you were
running on XFS yes is that right yeah and you've just deleted and purged a
load of stuff mm-hmm have you checked the defragmentation status of the volume
no I haven't really they actually just did it this morning so I could definitely
do it check the frag check the defrag level like on a good old Windows box
yeah an XFS has got online defragmenting right so the the fragmentation factor
that it reports is between 0 and 100% and the closer to 0 the better so if
your fragmentation factor is up you know in the 70s 80s then time to defrag the
volume and the utilities exist to do that so you've got XFS underscore DB
which is for debugging but that's the tool that you can use to expose the
fragmentation factor and then there's XFS FSR which is the file system
reorganizer and that can actually do the defragmenting I see yeah and I found
that ArchWiki actually has a really nice write-up on it yep naturally and there's
also XFS BMAP and you can use that to defragment individual files hmm so if
you've got a large ISO for example that has been downloaded whilst or many
fragmentation or something I mean I used to use it because I had large data files
from crash recorders or from aircraft hmm and I'd get loads and loads of those
and you'd find that in individually those were then fragmented and I could
defragment those and speed up the analysis time oh interesting made it
that much of a difference huh well oh yeah oh yeah significant it can it can
take your system from being sloppy and slow to being like you've just installed
it now rotten you wanted to make a special mention of but Abel but Abel yeah
I was gonna I would I don't know how to say it either but I would say like
baobab yeah yeah yeah now what is this it's a disk usually disk usage analyzer
mm-hmm oh yes of course yes yes that's a good one also West wanted to give a
plug for ncdu yes that's just you know one of those tools in my toolkit that I
turn to yeah much all the time nice and fast right love curses interfaces yeah
that's a that's also a good one I so I guess I guess I wanted things that so
I'm taking notes I'm gonna I'm gonna do the defrag obviously I'm gonna turn
swap off what are you guys's thoughts on West the the tool that you mentioned to
store your browser profile on RAM tell me about that oh yeah profile sync Damon
there's also anything sink Damon I'm not using them currently but I've used them
in the past and it just it just kind of transparently handles moving all your
browser profiles kind of stuff that can be resource-intensive to grab from the
disk or to frequently update on the disk so it keeps them in rain so this is a
Damon the design so I'm reading from the wiki here designed to manage user
specified directories referred to as sync targets from here on out and temp
FS and periodically sync them back to the physical disk this is accomplished
via sim linking step up and sim linking step and an innovative use of our sync
to maintain a synchronization between temp FS copies and the media bound
backups additionally and with there's a typo with features such as crash
recovery so ASD features okay so this so if I'm understanding West this is a
system sink Damon that sinks between my disk and a RAM disk and then it with the
applications end up using sim links which point to files in a RAM disk
exactly and then and it manages you know copies on the disk periodically so that
you if if your system goes down you won't lose everything that's pretty cool
that is that would I mean a big part of what I do is I'm sitting here doing show
prep or I'm or I'm showing a website on air it'd be really nice to have my web
browser performing really well and one of the things that seems to have taken
the biggest hit is my web browser yeah right and so you know especially if
that's that's the kind of workflow you have you ever used it yeah I've used in
the past I was using Firefox exclusively it was it worked pretty well though I was
happy with so there's two of them anything any anything sink Damon I'll
have a link to that in the show notes and then what was the other one profile
sink Damon which is made I think anything is an extension or outgrowth of
profile sink okay that one's just for browser profiles ah that might be a
little safer yes but this can be useful to if you have other applications that
you would like you know certain things to be in RAM I've played with not using
this but you know played with however having running your all your root system
in RAM people do that this is kind of fun this might turn into this might turn
into an ongoing series of me trying to run more and more crap out of RAM all
right so any other tips before I ask I'm gonna ask the doozy of the question
anybody else in the mumble room have any other performance tips they do on their
rig to keep things running fast anybody still do pre-linking anything like that
well Chris you said that you were running your home directory on SSD and
what I what I concern with is if you're running swap on there wouldn't that be
actually doing way more rights to the system than it should yeah I can if
you're using it yeah I can't remember how often I mean I only now have the
sense that maybe I'm swapping I in the general in the past I don't really ever
have the sense I'm actually using the swap file so that is a good question I
don't know how frequently it's being updated maybe another good reason to
swap off I only have SSDs in the machine and then I have a I have a raid
zero of drives I use for editing or Steam I mean to be clear you should also
know that most people if you have a significant amount of RAM you won't
really touch swap unless you're doing like high computations and stuff or a
bunch of virtual machines it's not a ton of RAM I think it's like 16 gigs it's
not like a ton which is kind of crazy that's that's a ton in consumer level
really is it though yeah yeah I run yes the average like a consumer starting
thing is like four to two to four he's still no XPS 13 with four gigs that's
no they haven't gotten better about that yet now you can get six and eight and
stuff very commonly for about like 350 to 450 I can't even imagine less than
decent price how you gonna run multiple VMs with less than eight how you gonna
VM how you gonna do that come on get out of here get out of here don't you
optimize actually what I think them I can't no I I got actually I actually
could see it working especially with a lean Linux desktop I mean it's
definitely doable and containers will help you there yeah I could honestly see
getting by with less RAM especially if you're using on the server side I kind
of I'm half joking but at the same time I I really am kind of disappointed that
they're not selling it with more RAM these days because I really would like
to I mean I I would like to have like 32 yeah exactly when you go to five 500 or
more you get into like the 8 gig grams yeah okay I I guess for me I I I feel
like boy if I could afford it I'd be up 32 on most of my machines now okay
anybody have a thought because this is a suggestion that's coming to the show a
few times I've never actually I almost pulled the trigger on at once but I
never have actually switched out my IO scheduler now for those of you that
don't know you can get different schedulers in the Linux kernel it just
depends on which one it's built with that support different types of disk
input and output operations you could say so there's the CFQ scheduler the
completely fair queuing scheduler there's the NNOP scheduler and deadline
and then there's the one that probably is that the one that people know what
I'm talking about that the BFQ scheduler the budget fair scheduler and it's
available in some Linux branches right now and a lot of people say the BFQ
scheduler is significantly faster if you have SSD drives I don't actually know if
this is really worth the switch okay heavens heavens you can post the
correction in the chat room but this is my rough I'm giving you a layman's
understanding of how the how the how the BFQ scheduler affects disk IO operation
so essentially there is requests that come into the kernel and the kernel has
to handle a lot of things you know get something off a disk feed something to
somebody else talk to the network and the BFQ scheduler can give say preference
if you have an SSD drive to the disk IO scheduler versus the network controller
things like that right so BFQ is perhaps maybe another way to put it is more
bias towards the disk scheduler in a sense and so if I'm getting it if I'm
understanding correctly you say you have BFQ and as your as your overall queue
scheduler then your disk performance can be much higher instead of waiting to go
to the disk it more often goes to this now this is just based on what I've read
reading on people that have tried it and said that performance is way better
right and people are typically looking for responsiveness on the desktop yeah
and so for example a great example is you know if you have a bunch of GDK
dependencies in the background that are loading instead of just sitting around
there waiting for those GDK dependencies to finish BFQ might go check in with the
disk scheduler and see what it needs and take care of that for a minute and have
the data ready something like that is really layman's understanding but that
seems to be the end result which you see as a user is things open up much faster
you can run multiple applications you can launch multiple applications at the
same time in the launch while the disk is already being heavily accessed seems
to be the general takeaway from BFQ anybody in the mumble room ever played
with anything like this rotten yeah I do maybe yeah I do one I do on not so
powerful equipment I don't bother on more modern systems you do notice a
difference on so for example on the Raspberry Pi I definitely notice the
difference by changing the combination of file systems and IO schedulers and on
older much much older hardware sort of Pentium 4m type devices even retrofitted
with SSDs you can see a measurable improvement in disk performance by
changing my ways is that performance sort of show itself well the most
obvious one is that you can see that the boot speed is dramatically decreased
hmm that's a good time so that's probably launching of simultaneous files
and things like that just as yeah but where you really notice it is if you're
extracting a large archive in one process and browsing the web in the
other you don't get that stop start pausing you know and and stuttering as
you you know launching tabs and switching between tabs it all happens
far more fluidly mmm I like that usually I believe it a cost to the
decompression throughput but but that's fine if you use your desktop yeah right
right right right right and it's interesting because in a server
workload that might not be what you want no probably not but on a desktop work
now that is what you want and unlike I say I only do this on on the older
hardware where you know there's there's clearly measurable benefit on the newer
hardware that the differences are so so small it's not worth the time to tweak
it interesting I that was sort of my takeaway seemed like from the reviews I
was reading it was in some cases so a couple of them that were seemed pretty
obvious were simultaneous application launching like everything just remained
very fluid they all didn't nothing really stuttered it was all very smooth
but outside of that I didn't see huge differences and it seemed like a lot of
work for a minor return so that's why I was kind of putting it out there when
if people have actually experimented with it because every now and then when
I when I I guess what brought it up again is I remember watching that demo
and then today using this machine thinking oh these applications are
launching so slow and like I launched telegram which is not a huge app and
like everything seizes on the machine that was loading and stops loading for a
second like even the terminal window and it's this is performing horrible and I
started thinking I remember the BFQ scheduler was much better about
prioritizing these kinds of things on the desktop I saw I did a little reading
into it read a few reviews and it's I don't know it's something to try anyway
it seems possible and worth trying but I'm a little skeptical since nobody's
really building it in if I would imagine by now if it really made that much of a
difference some distro would be yeah I think one does I think one distro out
there based on arched I ship with it built in but yeah if you guys also does
the BFQ or BF that was the one I was thinking of yeah it's Abbey on and and
have you noticed any difference when you play with her have you played with it
I have played with it I haven't really noticed well from my personal attempts I
haven't really noticed much of a huge increase because I really noticed much of
a difference when I'm compiling and doing a whole bunch of stuff and it's
really stressing like my rig Sabian is built from Gentoo right not arch if I
recall yes yeah and I think one of the reasons I was drawn to try it from a
while ago was because it uses BFQ and I don't remember really noticing any
difference now I think about it but they you know out of the box they're trying
to make it as performant as possible and it's an interesting take on it so I
wonder I don't know we'll see where it goes there are some branches Linux
kernel out there that have it already too if you if you have any suggestions
Linux actually showed at reddit.com and look for a lucky episode 113 of Linux
unplugged and leave a comment in there and I'll try it if it's a reasonable and
quick I don't want to rebuild my kernel necessarily well that's that's what's
nice about the IO scheduler you can change that yeah yeah that was actually
one of the neat things about one of the demos I was watching is he would
literally turn he would switch them and you could watch it you could watch the
difference I think he was using Fedora and that was pretty remarkable so all
right you know another way you could maybe make your sister run a little
better is probably just learn more about it go over to linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged Linux Academy is the sponsor of the Linux unplugged program and man
do they have some really cool stuff coming up so on October 15th they have a
really big live show they're gonna do and they've been working on this thing
that I'm gonna I have the notes here but I can't tell you yet because it's a big
secret but they're working on it for a year and there's a lot of updates coming
not only that but they just rolled out a new HTML 5 player with a new CDN back
end so all of that great content works even better now and you know one of the
things about Linux Academy that really stands out is they allow you to choose
from seven plus distributions the courseware the virtual machines they
match that the other thing though is instructor help is available with that
stuff the stuff that the self-paced courses can still have actual instructor
help that's awesome they have new lab features that are launching later this
month a new practice exam phase one system will be launching this week and a
new community feature we're gonna hear more about very soon there's a lot of
really good stuff coming out also they have the new Linux Foundation certified
system administrators course and the Linux Foundation certified engineer
course have to definitely check that out and they're also proud to announce
they're an open stack corporate partner now so they're officially an open stack
training partner you can check that out too at Linux Academy go to Linux
Academy.com slash unplugged and learn about the whole stack around Linux
everything from small nuggets just deep dive into a single topic like using
tar to back up your system or our sync to the really big stuff that's scenario
based training where you get real hands-on go to Linux Academy.com slash
unplugged to get our discount and you can take the tour it's a really great
service and it's built by people that are crazy passionate about Linux I love
that about them and they're working so hard Linux Academy.com slash unplugged oh
and they just rolled out a new dashboard hey fancy that yeah got a whole new look
check that out as well if you're already a member Linux Academy.com slash unplugged
and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program you
guys are awesome so I don't really know how to cover this next story in fact
it's so I'm dreading it so much that Wes and I were trying to figure out how to
handle this on the show because it's really not our area of expertise and
there is very valid points on all sides but some important things happen this
week I just want to touch on them and I want to keep the conversation as light
as possible but I also don't want to ignore it I think that would be and it's
one way sort of disrespectful so this week Matthew Garrett and another kernel
contributor her name is Sarah Sharp yes thank you both decided to step away from
the Linux kernel community in a sense and in both site essentially the tone
the language and the overall interacting with people on the Linux kernel mailing
list and mostly you could sum up as it's accused of being a toxic environment
and this keeps coming up as a theme over and over again and it may give us some
insight into some of the change that happened earlier this year perhaps when
it comes to the code of conduct that was submitted to the Linux kernel and I'm
trying to wrap my head around why we keep running into this and I simply I
simply wonder now this might sound maybe too simplistic but I definitely noticed
just on this road trip that I just went on and I think I was telling you about
this at lunch too like there is a difference in culture from Washington to
Grand Forks like everywhere I went each location people talked differently
different expectations they behaved differently like I was telling you about
the guy at the whiskey store who gave us the you know the the squinty eye then
you go to another town and it's like they're pouring you free drinks and if
they're embracing you get like everywhere has its own culture and its
own way of doing things and you take that and you blow it up on a global
scale and then we're all working together but then the other thing that
seems to be completely counter to a organic open environment is you have
people that are coming at it from the corporate standpoint where this is their
job and they're here to do a job and then you have people that are doing it
because it's their life's work and their life's passion and they're they would be
doing it whether they're getting paid or not and you have two completely
different types of work mindsets coming together to work on something and they
the two different groups completely behave differently not to mention a lot
of these people may have never met each other face-to-face right right and then
you have people that you know handle different types of language completely
differently trying to work together and I just look at this and think how is it
possible to have any project at this scale and not have this happen I'm not
trying to justify the actions but I'm wondering is it are we are we are we
capable at this stage of our ability to communicate online to really solve this
problem is online communications just still too primitive to truly solve this
problem could it be if Linus is it possible if if Linus just spoke a little
more nicely and treated new people with really you know with a really more
gentle touch would that really change things what do you think Wes does is it
possible you know you know I'm not sure and it's it's a it's it's tough to try
to draw the line between you know making improvements and versus different styles
you know I think Linus has touched on that on the mailing list before you know
different different people have different expectations and take things
different ways which is which is entirely valid but that said it does you
know it gives me pause that you know both of these people are clearly very
talented technically you know and they've contributed a lot to the kernel
and so it is yeah it's at least interesting that they choose to leave
obviously well we're lucky that we still get to enjoy what they do in other
open-source projects mm-hmm but as a Linux user I'd like to you know I'd
like to have an environment where people are excited to join and are not turned
away right yeah that is definitely you don't want to have a reputation for
being I'm a con did bring up in the chat room did bring up a good point though
there is the issue of you know do we want you know is this something where
you need to step away and and this is of course a personal choice but or should
there should there be a stand-up of people who want to change and represent
that change within the kernel community mmm I don't know if people just leave
them there's not representation right does that just leave the people you know
who are interacting in the style that a subset of people don't enjoy yeah this
is a tough this is a challenging one because it's it's it's unfortunately a
topic that it's really it's it's a bad it's a bad image to have it's a really
bad image to have right and it's really at the core of Linux anybody in the
mumble room have a thought on if this is problem is something we're at anywhere
close to solving because I feel like we're so far out from having an answer
here I think one of the first questions you asked was you alluded to the fact
that this keeps happening and that things aren't changing and there's a
good reason for that the same people work in that team you know if if you
don't change anything then nothing is going to change it is as simple as that
if and if the people who are at the top and who control the style of
communication that happens in that team and have other people looking up to them
and take guidance on how to act if those people don't change then nothing will
change and this will carry on and you'll be left with only those people who have
a very strong stomach and a very thick skin and who can cope with the kind of
beatings that that Linus gives out and you won't be able to have the other
talent from the people who don't have a thick skin and and aren't willing to put
up with that crap and so you're you're you're limiting the contributions that
you can possibly get not because of someone's technical ability but because
of their willingness to put up with the crap that they have to in that group
hmm I I just that so your argument which is a good one is sort of assumes the
foregone conclusion that something must change that the way it's being done now
is wrong and I don't necessarily disagree but I guess the thing I don't
like about that is that begins to walk a path that leads to Linus and I don't
really want there to be this sort of Linus must go sentiment-building because
that seems like that could be destructive but he's not a god he's he's
a guy who is an unpleasant person he is he said that himself yeah recent Linus
conference he said I'm not a nice person to deal with you know it that's a kind
of it's one of those phrases that people use that that people say oh well I tell
like it is and what I am and I know that's the way I am and I say what I
like and yeah you know that's that's it well okay that's fair enough but stay
the fuck away from me because you're not a pleasant person to be around I do
follow that logic why you have to be around these well and unfortunately some
of these people have to because it's their job I I just I the the only of
course the counter argument would be the very success of Linux itself right and
so I the when when the line of logic is that Linus is the problem then I say
well then what was everything we've accomplished so far how he has been not
necessarily the person developed it but you do have to wonder if we would really
have the world's best kernel right now if he wasn't extremely critical and I'm
not trying to justify I'm throwing that if that's a possibility it's sort of
like it's sort of like Apple is a nicer softer company without Steve Jobs but
they have also lost something without him correlation is not causation there
isn't you can't just say that because Linus wears glasses everyone who wears
glasses must be a really good kernel hacker you you can't necessarily say that
no no no no no since I've been wearing glasses that's what he's like and Linux
is has been successful doesn't mean it is successful because that's what he's
like right now I agree no I agree with you I agree with you I just I think it
is still is a dangerous line of thinking but it maybe it's I mean maybe it is
time I okay let's let's okay let's put it to you if you were in if you're
working in an office and someone was talking to you the way that Linus talked
to Sarah would you you know if you you would you just shrug that off if it
happened repeatedly and your your main line of work was to interact with that
person would you let that stand I put it to you that most people would probably
take that person to one side and say hey I think you're being unreasonable I
think you're you're acting like a dick I think you're the way you're acting in
front of our peers because this is public it's not like these two people are
sat in a room right and they have a tete-a-tete in the room this is like
wider than people sitting in a meeting room this is public on a mailing list
everyone is seeing him tearing strips off people that's unreasonable and in a
business place he would be reprimanded why the Linux Foundation not doing
something about this well I you know I've read the quotes I'm not I can't
really think of one that is particularly offensive people have gone through no I
mean people have gone through and collected the quotes that they believe
are in question here right but you're not on the receiving end of them no I'm
just saying they're not none of them are none of them are all that particularly
so the worst one I could find and I know this is just through my reading this
morning but the worst quote I found was something that implied sucking Microsoft
off that was thrown at Matthew Garrett wasn't thrown at Sarah was thrown at
Matthew Garrett that seems to be the worst I could find on the kernel mailing
list and it's okay that's crude but you know I don't know I I the the sometimes
from the outside the story looks a lot worse to be honest with you poppy to
answer your question I have worked environments where people yell and
scream like that and it's not wonderful it's not great but sometimes it just is
how those people work unfortunately and I don't like it but it's sort of it's
sort of posted everywhere when you walk in the door what happens I mean
everybody's not like it's a secret like you said all that stuff is in public so
right but in a place like that you can you know you can act and effect change
you know if whether whether you feel it's really unreasonable or not you know
the person who's the recipient that can effect some kind of change by
approaching management or approaching the other person's management or the HR
department or whatever the process is in that company there are processes is the
point yeah it's very difficult I mean they're already they already they
already have submitted the code of conduct then the new updated one that
Craig's image doesn't actually identify anything that you're not supposed to do
in any way but the problem is there's only one person at the top of this tree
and that's Linus you can't you can't say our screw this I'll go to that other
Linux down the road like you would quit a job and go to a different job mm-hmm
you know if your if your job is to contribute to Linux chances are if it's
if it's high enough up the up the food chain you're gonna interact with the
LKML at some point so it's it's it's difficult because there is only one yeah
there can only be one so heavens you wanted to jump in about Linus being
blunt and harsh what are your thoughts well he's been this way for quite a long
while and this problem hasn't popped up until recently mainly with her just
because everyone else can deal with it and she can maybe she should you step
down so she's not doing but doesn't that assume doesn't that assume that other
people that assumes that other people haven't burnt out and left and just
didn't say anything well possibly more engaged with other
communities yeah what was that wimpy also what didn't get started in the
first place right now go ahead BST go ahead heavens ideally of course would be
a slightly nicer place to be but the Linux kernel yes I do believe he should
be very blunt and straightforward to be really that's that's your solution if
you don't like it you should find another project clearly technical as
possible the problem that she was talking about in her blog post was not
about the fact that any technical mistakes that she made was insulting to
her she said that she wanted that if she made a technical mistake that she wanted
in the color color out on it and that she didn't have a problem with technical
insults it was the personal insults that they were thrown at her I don't know what
they were I couldn't I couldn't find any myself but the I didn't look that hard
but the the point is is that if if there are personal insults then what is the
net what is it necessary to actually insult the person who's providing the
code if they're genuinely trying to provide good code rather than saying
here's where you screwed up like this is garbage code here's how to fix it or
here's a new suggestion or something and when that happens they usually say okay
yeah you're right I'll take care of it but if it goes to a personal level why
would you be too busy for a person one he's also wanting to retire you know
you're you're so setting associating this to Linus it's not necessary yeah I
guess a lot of the maintainer other maintainers are where so that's a good
point right she was she was talking about the community as a whole she did
not specify Linus or anyone at all right right and I think I think that kind of
when it obviously when it crosses line into personal that's where it gets
unfortunate and it should that there's no excuse for that really that's just
being mean it's just that is straight up just being mean North Ranger I wanted
to give you a chance to jump in yeah I mean rotten corpse makes a great point
about you know when you cross that line into a personal insult and I'm kind of
torn because I want to see you know people like Sarah people like Matthew if
they are being personally insulted to you know to call out those bulliers but
on the flip side I don't know that they can do that because of you know
potential backlash they might have for for being tattletales or whatever you
might want to call it it just I guess going back to the core point it
frustrates me because here we are in episode 113 I feel like every two months
we have a story where maybe it's not that frequent but it feels like we've
done plenty of these stories about people getting hurt upset and it seems
like this just keeps keeps happening in the blog post Sarah did say that things
are changing and things are right improvements she just doesn't want to
deal with it having to be involved with it anymore regardless of that there is
being there are changes being made she just doesn't want to be there in the in
the midst of them change I think it's I think it's fair to to say that it's very
unfortunate if this is something that singles out and happens to women but we
have seen it happen we've seen it happen to blonde white men I mean supposedly
Lenart Pottering had his life threatened over system D so this has been an issue
where it just goes too far over and over and over again and passionate community
yeah I just I don't I mean I don't I don't know quite how to make reason out
of it it doesn't it does seem to be a problem that doesn't just be unique to
Linux kernel mailing list either although I think you could make an
argument that's an area where perhaps conduct needs to be above bar as much
as possible because it's under so much scrutiny and it represents as a core
part of its business critical now you know yeah it's yeah yeah there's and as
I said there's only one but the business critical thing actually adds more
importance to making sure everything is right yeah yes I think the idea that the
the way that they handle the technical aspects of it is perfectly fine and even
if they're yelling at each other and because if someone does something that
is worthy of being yelled at they should be yelled at because that's the only
thing that's effective in a even though they're people being paid for and it's
their job they aren't being paid by the Linux
foundation for most I think it's worth making the distinction to that what some
people consider being yelled at other people do not consider yelling too
because there are cultural differences and there's very large cultural
differences in some cases right and the main thing is though like these people
are saying like you know they're being paid to work on it so they don't have a
choice but the people who are yelling at them aren't paying them so how can they
you know convey the message of how the severity of their mistake when they have
no actual control except for this is not coming in like that's all they can do
though like here they if they maybe you know in certain cases be severe or not
it depends on if the technical aspect of it isn't merit or not so as in my
opinion if the technical thing happens and you get yelled at because the code
is terrible well then the code is terrible whatever fix it so here's the
as long as it doesn't go personal as Noah would say here's the thing and this
is sort of my big takeaway is if you have something that's open and you want
contributions and you want quality contributions it's probably worth the
project's time and effort to make contributions feel or make contributors
feel as welcome and invited as possible because that only is going to make your
project better and so I think it is in the best interest of open source
projects health to have a good community and part of that is how you interact
with that community so now the Linux kernel isn't really suffering from this
particular problem they can afford to be rather aggressive but there are a lot of
projects out there so many of which we have talked about today that could use
contributions and for them it's in their best interest to work with the community
now what I would hate to see is a bunch of middle management PMO types come in
and try to tell all these projects how to work with their community but that is
a topic for a future show if anybody has any closing thoughts I'll hear it but
I'll go ahead run well you'll I'll give you the closing word yeah I just wanted
to play devil's advocate here in the sense of like the way you just said
about how that they need to you know be more opening to people but there are
certain cases where there's some people that you you don't want to submit code
to because it takes more time to weed through their code to see if it's
actually useful or not that there have been people who have been banned from
the mailing list because they were submitting code that was complete
garbage yeah just so that they could get their own for a couple reasons they
could get their name in the kernel or certain things like that and in certain
cases they were like actively breaking you know user land and everything and
right like a cardinal sin of a colonel so they were basically doing like they
have to set an environment that is a weird hybrid of community and hostility
so it's you know how can you really I mean it's it's a situation where I don't
think anyone could really you know find iron it out it's gonna be hard to find
the balance that's what I say is it's just gonna be an ongoing problem too but
I do hope it tends towards making people feel more welcome and getting more
contributors because that's gonna make the projects better and get new ideas in
there too so why don't we kind of end it on a positive note right there episode
lucky 113 in the bag if you have any comments or thoughts on anything we
talked about today Linux action showed our reddit.com find
lucky 113 or go to Jupiter broadcasting.com slash contact and choose Linux
unplugged from the drop-down I'm gonna give a plug too for the patreon we're
trying to get a push to get the numbers back up over at patreon.com slash today
and if you've enjoyed the rover log there is additional exclusives just for
the patrons and once you become a patron you get access to everything we've ever
posted there that's exclusive to them. Wes thank you sir for joining us. Always
a pleasure. Do you ever have anything you want to plug? You can find me at at Wes
Payne on Twitter. I love it. I'll be working on some tutorials for posting in the
subreddit soon here. Oh nice tease nice tease alright everybody well thank you
for tuning this week's episode of Linux unplugged join us live over jblive.tv
for episode 114 next Tuesday go to Jupiter broadcasting.com slash calendar
for the robots to convert that for you automatically and we'll see you back
here next week.
if I'm being honest my my strong desire was actually to just reload my machine
with the latest Androgros ISO I already had written to a to a USB thumb drive
like new install I'm like no no I can recover it I can rebuild it I can make
it stronger and better than before I've seen some people on the arch forums who
just have it set up every night they just reinstall yeah well you know you
just pull them especially if you already have like maybe you cash the packages
locally you know you have a some you know chef for ansible and just build it
all up again it's ready to go in the morning Androgros is good I'm telling
you I'm loving the latest Androgros build loving their installer option for
long-term kernel support is brilliant when you're doing a desktop arch machine
and one checkbox steam installation you know it's also my default for installing
arch now I don't I don't use their installer but it's such a nice live CD
to boot into and then you just install arch in a shrew every now and then every
now and then I swear I get like a bad ISO or something and the installers just
totally wonky but I either then I just jump either between the daily build or
the latest stable release and whichever one fails me I just switch switching
one of those gonna work yeah and I have to say I just recently reloaded a
machine that we had set aside for Windows 10 testing that I was like no
more gone with you and I just was like I'm gonna do Androgros again and I got
their latest their latest build and the fact is is this machine now that I think
about it I'm giving it to somebody that's gonna be using it that won't be
doing updates very often and having that LTS kernel I feel a lot better about
giving them an arch system all of a sudden even though for me I don't do it
right right but for someone in a different a little different use case
yeah that's a little more peace of mind installing and and of course anybody
installing arch could do that but for some reason when I was setting up this
machine for them it didn't cross my mind I tell you if I had done the arch
installation myself yeah I probably would have just neglected to think of
that yep so I was pretty appreciative of that just had the option as the default
or it really makes arch super approachable yeah you don't have to have
you know carefully designed your system for a day beforehand you can just
install it and yeah away you go yeah and the default the default gnome desktop is
the one I generally go with is pretty nice I change it up pretty quickly but
it's easy enough to do that yeah so yes in fact I think probably the only time
I'll ever install arch vanilla straight a standard old arch is on a server right
if I'm for some reason deciding that server should be running arch mm-hmm but
I don't know how much I'm gonna do that I'm on the fence on that still I do it
for a for a few machines that I use daily but anything beyond that I wouldn't
depends on how willing you are and how much time you have and so I think it
also depends on what's the server doing right exactly so is the server is a
server hosting web pages over nginx and a pad or Apache and and it has a
database or is it a Plex machine with Dropbox and BitTorrent sync yes exactly
and I'm more inclined to say Ubuntu is a good is a good solution or CentOS is a
good solution for the first one yes and arch is a better solution for the Plex
media server type thing because then you have the AUR and you could just right
off the top of my head I mean the advantage there is in the AUR you've got
the Plex and the Plex pass version yep you can also get like the git versions
or whatever like the beta builds and stuff the nightly's or whatever you need
yeah and so it's a very minimal update and if you so we have two servers the
run arch that hosts Plex one here at the studio and one at my house nice and both
of them are just really minimal installs with Plex and a couple other things yep
and then it just keeps the updates fairly small and so I think now we're at
like two to three months in between updates but it really hasn't been an
issue yet yes you know that's what I've been doing for the one that runs MB at
my house and and there are ways to you know you can you can update frequently
if you need to or you can take snapshots if you know Sousa style if you're
worried about you know if you need it to be a little more productiony and you
know ever the the evergreen releases from open Sousa are a good LTS but I
think maybe for me the the leap stuff might be even better hey so what do you
think about this user in the chairman says how do you manage your dot files and
integral so I'm looking for the best way to do it and when he says manage I'm
thinking maybe keeping them consistent across his machines is that what you
think he's talking about when he says manage yeah you know yeah it could be
consistent it could be versioned it could be backed up so I used to try it
I used to try to do this over Dropbox and that burned me so bad that I never
bothered again and actually what it what the way it kind of burned me was is one
machine got updated to a new version of KDE and then the other machine stuff
synced over and it was just a mess and it's like of course that was gonna
happen to me I was just kind of trying it and that didn't go well have you ever
used anything West to like get or anything like that to keep your yeah you
know and it depends again like so many things on how involved you want to be
how often you need to touch it how you know like magically behind the scenes it
works yeah but yes I have mine I use a good new stow to create sim links for my
configuration files in both Etsy and my files the new stow yeah on now hold on
now hold on that sounds app pick material I gotta take a look tell me
about good news still I just got a sim link manager GNU oh okay
STO okay and I'm slightly I learned to use it for a particular project several
years ago that's why it's on my toolkit okay but it lets you set up it lets you
easily set up sort of sort of like you would see inside of like an RPM package
where you have a tree that gets mirrored out to the real file system and so it
makes it really easy to keep your configuration files okay you know so
usually when I set things up or if I'm converting a server you can just move a
file to your to your storage location and then in stow will automatically if
you set it up create a sim link so you can edit your files just like they
actually lived in Etsy yeah but they can all be under one folder yeah and then
that way whenever you have changes you know you can make a new branch on get
you and then you're backing up that one folder yes exactly so that's just a git
repo and you're sinking out across your machines yeah well and then and then
that's you can have you know you can have different branches if you have you
know different configuration files that need to be in a different syntax that's
sounding to get a little complicated though yeah and so it depends you know
most of my machines are similar enough that I can just sync them you know I
can just pull down the repo you could have a easy little script that would
keep it in sync if you'd like who it really depends on how you know how
different your configurations need to be yeah per machine so user links in the
chat room an actual specific how-to on how to use stow to kind of do exactly
what we're talking about how to manage your dot files so I will throw a link to
that in the show notes so here it is using the new stow to manage your dot
files this might be exactly what you know and this will work well if your
idea of a file manager is the terminal so it's not for everyone but yeah yeah
I've had some good use use cases I like that it seems to me like kind of an
intermediate step you're not ready to go full ansible or chef you know what's
funny about that statement though is the the command line I laugh at the command
line being my file manager until I really need to get something done or I
don't have any damn time to fool around and then all of a sudden but you damn
right the command line is my file manager that's all I'll you move is move
and it will always work and LS responds immediately I don't have to wait for
Nautilus to enumerate icons or whatever no preview files no I just want the file
list I want to know who owns this file right now