Okay, all right, so I wanna talk about
tools that we can't live without.
So today started a very interesting day.
I woke up and the first thing that happened
was every device in the house is going off with alerts.
And the alert was that my kids are not going to school today
because they can't in school.
Okay, all right, that's fine.
And then the next set of alerts
were all of the places that are closed,
the city offices and stuff like that.
And then the alerts after all of that
were in our ticketing system
where a bunch of businesses were like,
well, we're not open today.
This would be a great day to rip out
key parts of our infrastructure and replace it
because we're not gonna be using them.
Of course.
So yeah, so my day is quickly filling up.
And I thought, okay, well, I need to prepare
for Linux Unplugged today.
And I need some time to get everything set up in the studio.
So I'm gonna get in my car,
I'm gonna go drive to the studio
and I'll take care of that.
Well, I step out of my front door
and my foot just goes about a foot down.
And there's like a foot of snow, yeah.
And so I'm not taking my car.
I'm gonna go to the Jeep, take the Jeep, go to back out.
I cannot get out of my driveway
because the snow plow has come down the street
and pushed all the snow that's in the street
into my driveway.
Nicely building a blockade for you.
Yeah, now I can't get into the driveway at all.
So I think, all right,
so I'm gonna go start the snow blower
and I will blow out my driveway,
then I will get into my car, then I will drive to work
and then I will fix all the problems
so that I can then go start Linux Unplugged.
Snow blower doesn't start.
Now there's something wrong with the carburetor.
So I'm not gonna work on the carburetor
in 15 degree weather with 40 mile an hour wind
buried in snow, you drop parts, you lose them.
So the only thing I can do
is I take the snow blower into my kitchen,
which my wife is thrilled about.
So I'm disassembling this carburetor in my kitchen.
I clean the carburetor,
I get everything put back together
and I'm not gonna take it outside and test it
only to find out something doesn't work
and bring it back in, right?
Yeah, right, like bundle up just to go outside, test it.
Yeah, exactly.
So I put some gas in and I start it up
and it starts right up.
So I did a good job fixing the carburetor
but then it dawns on me that exhaust
is going pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop, pop
and just like every puff is just filling the kitchen.
Well, I don't wanna shut the snow blower off
because I just spent three hours getting it started.
So I take my snow blower running through my house
and push it out the door, blow out the driveway
and eventually I end up,
a bunch of other bad things happen too.
Right, that was obstacle one of many.
Yeah, that was obstacle one of like 10, right.
But it made me start to think,
what are tools that we can't live without?
Today for me, it was a snow blower.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 174
for December 6th, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that fought the weather, sacrificed a laptop
and built a computer all within the last hour
to be here with you today.
My name is Noah and joining me remotely
from Seattle this time is Wes.
Hey Wes, how are you?
Hey guys.
I'm doing great, it's a pleasure to be with you here.
Thank you for being the host today.
Okay, I'll be honest with you,
I appreciate the effort you took to be here
but let's be honest, I put in more effort to be here today.
I do think that's fair.
It sounds like you had quite the day, Noah.
I almost died.
Like basically like that followed me.
Yeah, that's just almost followed me.
That's bad for the network.
At every turn, it was crazy.
Do you know what I am excited about though, Wes?
I bet it's our giant show today.
Our giant show that revolves around Linux.
And specifically Fedora, we're gonna be talking with,
we're gonna be talking about Fedora
and some potential changes they're making.
Now, these are speculation.
It's just speculation at this point.
There's no confirmed, there's no confirmation
that any of this is going to happen.
And it is possible that Matt Miller might stop by.
We spoke with him and he thought he might have some time
and so he might be here with us later in the show
to talk about some of the speculation
and what Fedora is up to.
So, quick recap, I have been a Fedora user
since version Uno, since the very first version of Fedora.
Basically forever.
Yes, I was using Red Hat back when it was Red Hat
and then they did the split
and they did RHEL, Red Hat Enterprise Linux
and they did Fedora.
And I was there when that split happened
and I have used every single version of Fedora
from Fedora one on up.
Now, somewhere around Fedora, 2021-ish, somewhere in there,
the direction of my company started to push me
in a direction that required me
to use a little bit more Ubuntu.
And so, I hate distro hopping inside of my own home.
I hate having one computer that works one way
and one computer that works the other way
in different software.
It's hard to have that inconsistency
in your day-to-day life.
It is.
And when you sit down to do something,
I want things to work the same.
And so, I had kind of moved myself
a little bit away to Ubuntu
but my main big workhorse downstairs always ran Fedora.
The thing I did most of my work on had always run Fedora.
And recently, I wiped every computer I owned,
at least that I use personally, and put Arch on them.
You can follow that in the Linux action show.
We talked about it a couple different times.
Some of the challenges I ran into.
But I still had a Fedora machine
and upgraded that recently to Fedora 25.
And again, you can check out our review of Fedora 25
in Linux action show.
But my real reason for going to Arch over Fedora
was the update cycle.
And I got a lot of criticism from that.
A lot of people wrote in, they said,
you're complaining about the Fedora
six-month support cycle, but you went to Arch,
which literally has like a one-day support.
I mean, every day there's new updates
and you have to push them, right?
So it doesn't seem to be very consistent.
The problem is, and I spoke about this
in our last review of Fedora, I don't trust their updates.
I don't trust updating from one version to the next,
upgrading, I should say.
So for you, it then means a reinstall.
It does, it means a Nuke and pay.
And the obvious problem with doing that
is I don't have time to Nuke and pay my system
every six months or every year even.
I could do it every five years,
but I'm not willing to do it every year.
In fact, really, to be perfectly honest,
I probably get a new laptop every five years.
So I have always wanted Fedora to go to an LTS-like version
and there hasn't, and at the same time,
there's a lot of people that have been pushing
for the Fedora project to go the rolling style,
which I have questioned because I don't know
where Fedora would fit in then,
especially when you kind of compare that to Arch, right?
It might change its place
in the Linux distribution ecosystem.
The folks at Red Hat will tell you
that Fedora is bleeding edge, and I don't agree.
I think Fedora is leading edge,
and I would classify something like Arch
as truly bleeding edge.
And so to take Fedora to rolling,
I don't know that that makes a lot of sense,
but I know there's a lot of people
that would like to see that project take that route.
Now, Matt Miller wrote a phenomenal post
on a mailing list here.
And basically, he talks about how he's really pushing
for a change in the release cadence of Fedora.
And if I'm understanding this right,
and I've done a little bit of research,
if I'm understanding this right,
there are two major changes that would be occurring.
The first would be that raw hide
is going to become the gated rolling release,
and the release will deviate,
he says, and the release deviate from it
by stability and life cycle.
This is essentially what SUSE has done
with Tumbleweed and Leap respectively.
So my understanding is they're going to break it off
and have essentially two Fedora versions.
He goes on to write and he says,
what if instead of a two year release cycle,
we updated the core on a cycle aligned with the kernel,
so roughly every three months,
and had just one June release of Fedora workstation
and Fedora server every year,
with an optional one update in November or December.
Fedora would keep its two week updates
as a rolling release.
This seems huge to me.
I'm interested to see what you think, Les.
Yeah, it does sound,
it is a very different model of how to do it.
I do kind of like that cycle aligned with the kernel.
It seems to work well for the kernel community.
Obviously there's a big difference between a distribution
and releasing the kernel,
especially not necessarily the LTS kernel
or anything like that.
But I do appreciate how much the Fedora represents
kind of Linux next on the desktop, in the gnome world,
a lot of things like that.
System tools that they had system D early,
they have Wayland now.
And so it would kind of,
I could see myself doing that.
It's not quite the burden of Arch,
it's not that model,
but it does give you fresh packages, fresh kernels.
It seems like a really good thing to build a workstation
where you're willing to update,
but you want new tools and you want the new hotness.
Right, right, exactly.
And the thing is, and I struggle with this from time to time
because sometimes I struggle to really articulate
why I value this.
But to me, there is an inherent value in having a company
that's backed by a billion dollars or more really.
I think they're approaching 2 billion
or they've made 2 billion,
backing the Linux distribution that you're using.
And if I could go into a client and say, look,
cause I mean, here's the reality.
We can fight about distributions all day long.
Nobody has ever gotten fired for putting RHEL on a server.
They are, in 2016, they are like the IBM of computers.
So 15 years ago, you bought an IBM computer
and you sold somebody IBM computers
and you stuck them in their office.
Nobody ever got fired for doing that.
That was just, that was a very sensible, solid choice.
And RHEL keeps that.
There's an expense associated with it,
but it's a good, solid choice
from a technical perspective.
Now, if I could go into a client and say, look,
you have, you know, whatever, 15, 20, you know,
the University of New York, Dakota, for example,
has a cluster of Red Hat servers, right?
If I could go in there and say, look,
you guys are running Red Hat on these servers,
the same company will back a distribution
that is designed for the desktop.
One of the things I hear all the time
when we get in, when we have this discussion is,
well, why don't you just use Red Hat on the desktop?
Why don't you just use CentOS on the desktop?
And the reality is, the distribution
is not tailored for desktop use.
It does, it's not easy to install things like VLC.
It's not easy to install things like, you know,
I don't know specifically because I haven't tried,
but I know VLC is a huge pain point,
but it is just not optimized for desktop applications
because it's not designed to be a desktop operating system.
It's designed to be a workstation.
Sure, right.
Yeah, maybe, yeah, work fine,
maybe where you're running, you know, instrumentation
for a scientific tool or machine tool,
but not for something that end users need to use.
They might need to use the tool of the day,
whatever's popular.
You know, calculations, stuff like that,
that workstations will, the workstation will do fine.
Photo editing, video editing,
like installing Lightworks, for example.
We're talking about that in the pre-show, right?
Installing Lightworks on CentOS,
I will get no help from Red Hat because it's,
they're gonna say that's not what it's for,
and I will get no help from EditShare.
So using the, so we can rule out using Red Hat
on the desktop, except for extremely rare circumstances.
We need a enterprise grade desktop, though,
that we can use, and right now,
I don't feel like we have it.
That should be the promise of Ubuntu,
but every release of Ubuntu seems to be getting worse.
Either they don't move forward at all,
or in the case of 16.04, they break key components
that I need to make the desktop work, i.e. wireless.
I don't have wireless in 16.04,
and that wasn't fixed in 16.10.
So the prospect that Fedora would be moving to a system
in which we would have two versions,
one would be kind of LTS-like,
and the other would be rolling,
seems brilliant for a couple of reasons.
One of the things that originally drew me to Fedora
was that I could find out what was going to happen
on the server on my desktop first,
and play with it, and experience the pain,
and then watch those problems get resolved,
and then when it went into production,
we were all ready for that.
If I could do the same thing,
I could run rolling on my laptop,
but put my clients on the LTS version,
or whatever they call it, that would be huge.
That would be game-changing.
And I'll make a vow right now, Linux Unplugged,
at 4.37 in the afternoon Central Time,
if Red Hat decides to do this,
even if it's a year or two year support.
It'd have to be more than that though,
because I can't reinstall every year.
But if we could get anything above like two years,
I'll switch every computer I own back to Fedora.
100% of them will run Fedora,
and 100% of my servers will continue to run CentOS.
What do you think, Wes?
You know, that does sound interesting.
I'm also struck by some parallels
in terms of some of the benefits here.
They talk about more time for QA and release engineering.
I know like in the software industry,
we have seen that as well,
a push towards continuous integration,
a push towards continuous delivery,
where you're adding, you have small changes,
but you're iterating quickly,
but when you make those changes,
they're fresh in your mind,
you can go fix them as soon as you notice problems.
So that strikes me as something that may be beneficial.
I don't know what we'll see out of that LTS,
but I could see if they're continuously working,
they're getting better,
and then are able to kind of cherry pick,
all right, here we go,
this is a great stack that we've got ourselves on,
we found ourselves in a really good place,
everything's working well, support this for some time.
It might work better than the release model now,
which it seems like maybe they've struggled with
a little bit, they're not always released,
you know, we've talked a lot about on this network,
a lot about like, you know,
after a couple of weeks or a month,
then yes, it's really solid,
you've got everything that you can use.
If we can get away from that,
it seems like it'd be a good thing.
I agree.
Mumble Room, what do you guys think?
Well, I mean, it kind of sounds like
the same thing OpenSUSE has been doing for a year.
Yeah, it does.
What do you think about,
so you are or were an OpenSUSE user,
I believe you're using KDE Neon right now, right?
Yeah, I'm using Neon now.
What do you think of the comparison
between the company that backs Suice Linux
and the company that backs Fedora?
How do you draw that parallel and say,
well, or how do you view that and say,
well, I trust this company more than that company,
or I think this company does a better job
at paying attention to the community than that one.
Where do you fall on that?
I think they both are pretty close in community aspects,
and I think they're both fairly large
in the sense of different parts of the world.
Red Hat's more North America,
whereas Europe is more dominated by SUSE.
But the only thing I would say
that makes me slightly hesitant of SUSE versus Red Hat
is that Red Hat is owned by Red Hat,
and SUSE is owned by who knows any of that right now.
It's like Novell purchased them,
and then that was then sold again,
so it's kind of weird that that slight hesitation from that,
but other than that, they're both solid in the same ways.
Except for also, Fedora is not using rail packages.
They even say that they're not compatible with each other.
Oh, yes, right.
OpenSUSE is actually using sleep packages,
so you kind of have the more enterprise workstation
type desktop with the OpenSUSE approach.
I'll be very honest with you.
About the time, and it was around,
I'll tell you exactly when it was too, Fedora 15,
about the time that they started to do this split
where Fedora was no longer really going to be
what the next version of RHEL is going to be,
or you know, well, a couple of versions,
because RHEL, you know, a couple years in between.
About that time that they made that switch
was about the time that Fedora started to become
less appealing to me, and as a system administrator,
that was something I really appreciated,
so I thought that they gave up something huge,
but at the same time, I think that it reflects well
on Red Hat as a company that they are willing
to let the Fedora team, the Fedora project,
be its own project.
It's not just the beta grounds for RHEL.
It is its own distro.
It's its own project, and so I think that reflects well
on them, though from a corporate business,
I need to make money, and this was a tool
that I used to facilitate that.
I was a little unhappy about it.
Do you think that SUSE is becoming any less relevant?
Actually, I think SUSE is becoming more relevant,
specifically for their switch, their infrastructure
of the leap and tumbleweed approach.
Like, before those happened, which has only been a year,
like, they've only had two leap releases,
42.1 and 42.2, and that was only like a month ago
they had the second release.
Actually, less than a month, like three weeks ago.
So they've been becoming much more and more
getting attention and just more relevant in the community
because of this massive change,
because it is revolutionary at the time,
and it's still, it's kind of like getting people
to consider other things, and especially like
their infrastructure of open QA.
Like, there are people from Fedora saying
that it's amazing, and they would love to use it,
but it doesn't work for their stuff, so they don't.
But if like more people hear about the stuff
that OpenSUSE is doing, it's just gonna continue
to improve in their, I guess, market share.
Do you think that those changes that they're making
and the ability to run that rolling
or run more of a stable platform,
do you think that that increases the saleability,
so to speak, to businesses?
Like if you're a new business,
you're a new business, you're starting up,
do you think that gives them a competitive advantage
over other distributions?
Absolutely, well, not only in certain cases,
like as far as like server stuff,
if you're gonna use SLE, that you can use,
you can have that connection between your desktop
and your enterprise, and your servers
and all this other things.
So you can have like your personal desktop,
or you can have a rolling desktop that also uses SLE,
and also some parts that SLE uses parts of Tumbleweed,
things like that.
Like it's a really interesting infrastructure
that they're doing.
The only problem in the OpenSUSE case
is that Leap doesn't have very long support.
Like I think it's a total of 18 months,
which it sounds good, but it means that once a new version
of release, you only have six months to update.
So that's kind of like lackluster,
but overall it's still better than,
you know, it's not five years,
but at least it's almost two years, so.
Would the argument that you could try on the desktop
and run on the server not also stand true
for Fedora workstation and Fedora server,
and Ubuntu desktop and Ubuntu?
If you're using Fedora, yes.
More, Ubuntu's more in line,
because like the server packages
and the desktop packages for Ubuntu
are essentially in the same repo
and the same compatibility structure,
whereas Fedora, they split stuff off
so that if you're gonna use Fedora server, great,
but if you're gonna use CentOS or Red Hat, not really.
Yeah, yeah, there's definitely a difference.
You know, when we were doing our review
or our How to Pick a Distro,
which is the last episode of Linux Action Show,
Chris and I did, and you know,
I think really that was one of my favorite episodes
I think that we've ever done.
I think that, because both Chris and I come at it
from very different perspectives,
and it was interesting that we both kind of gravitated
and arrived at kind of the same conclusions,
which kind of gives me a big head,
and I say to myself, well, clearly,
I think we're doing something right.
I think we've landed on the right way
because somebody that I very much respect, his opinion,
has arrived at the same conclusion.
And one thing we didn't really get to
was I had divided that post out.
He basically asked, how do you choose a distro?
And I said, well, basically, I would divide that out,
desktop users, server users, power users,
development users, and specialty distro users,
and we focused then on desktop distributions
because that's what the original post was asking.
But you know, I think server, picking a server distro
has an equal amount of questions,
and I think the conversation that Michael and I
are having right now really exemplify that.
I think there's a lot of good reasons to choose RHEL.
I think there's a lot of good reasons to choose CentOS.
I think there's a lot of good reasons to choose SUS.
And one of the arguments that I have made to every client,
and you know, basically, if you ever watch,
if you ever know somebody that's in the military,
and they were assigned a specific weapon system,
a lot of those guys will go buy similar weapon systems
when they get home to shoot
because they're very comfortable on it,
they were trained on it, and they're very accurate with it,
and this, that, and so forth.
And I've had conversations with them,
and I would say, why would you use that particular rifle
in this particular scenario?
It doesn't seem like it really fits very well.
And they say, well, I'm very comfortable with it.
And that actually kind of rings true
because I started on Red Hat,
and so I'm just very comfortable with Red Hat.
And so when I go in, anytime I set up a server,
it's just Red Hat.
And one of the things that works so well for me
is being able to go into a client and saying,
hey, listen, I tell you what,
this is a project that you want to do,
and so I'll give you an example.
We were working with the University of North Dakota,
and they wanted to do this chemical calculation server.
So basically, the way it would work
is the students would submit these chemical values,
and the server would do all of the crunching.
Now, they bought like this $28,000.
I mean, it was crazy, just crazy.
Custom build, everything was just amazing.
And they were trying to decide
if they were gonna contract with us
to set this particular server up.
And I said, well, listen, we have a lot of experience,
probably more than anyone else
in the Grand Forks surrounding area,
in setting up Linux and working with Linux,
and I will tell you that not only is this possible,
but we can make this amazing for your students.
We can put it on a public network and give it a public IP,
and your students will be able to access this box from home
and submit their chemical calculations from home
and submit them from anywhere.
And they said, we don't know about that.
Is it secure enough?
Is it really gonna work?
And I said, all right, I'll tell you what I'll do.
I will give you, for the first month,
I will give you a server to use.
And they said, you have a $28,000 server?
And I said, well, not exactly,
but I tell you what I do have.
I have access to some really powerful machines,
and I will give you access to one for free for a month,
and you try it, and if it works, then you call me back,
and I will come set your server up the exact same way.
And they said, oh, okay, that's great.
When can we get that rolling?
Next week, next month?
And I said, no, right now.
I'm gonna do it right now for you.
So I opened my laptop up,
and I went over to digitalocean.com,
and I used the code for DO Unplugged.
And they gave me $10 credit.
Now, I had to buy a pretty beefy rig
because of the sheer amount of bandwidth
that we were gonna use,
and the sheer amount of CPU power that we needed to use
was gonna be incredible.
So I bought a pretty beefy rig.
It didn't really save me a whole lot,
but if you're doing something like a Plex server,
or if you're doing something like a simple FTP server,
or a web server, or maybe you wanna host your own blog.
Or you're connecting to our IRC room,
and you're using Quasl,
you wanna have a Quasl core up there,
it's perfect for that.
Exactly, as long as you're not using it for production
so it doesn't crash,
you, at Quasl, not Digitalocean,
you would get two months out of that
because you can do it on a $5 rig.
And if, I'll tell you what, let's do this.
Let's sign into my account right now,
and let's see how many rigs I have
and which ones they are.
I would say the majority of my rigs are $5 ones.
And the reason I say that is
because most of the things I do are pretty simplistic.
So let's see here.
Now this is my personal account.
This is not our company, my AltaSpeed account.
So let's see here.
Yeah, we can tell.
So any of these that say 512,
so that's a $5 server, that's a $5 server,
that's a $5 server, that's a $20 one,
that's a $20 one.
The amount of work I'm able to get done
with just a $5 rig is incredible.
So head over to digitalocean.com,
use the code word DOUNPLUGGED and get yourself $10 off.
You have no idea the world that you are entering into
with hosted VPSs.
You've not played with VPSs.
You are missing out on like a whole spectrum of Linux.
You think you like distro hopping
and you think it's fun to do it on your desktop,
just wait until you can do that with a click of a button.
And if you use the Yubi keys,
then that's really where the rubber meets the road.
Let me tell you because I literally click on Noah's SSH key
and then all I have to do is type in the SSH command
in my laptop and it prompts me for a pin.
I enter a four digit pin, no emailing me the password,
which you know they CC the NSA on that stuff too, right?
Like anytime a password goes over the internet,
like basically the NSA is grabbing that.
That's terrible, it's terrible.
So use the Yubi key, way better.
I want to talk about something that I came across
that just made me sit back and go, huh.
I, as I said earlier in the show,
I recently switched to Arch.
So you can imagine my reaction when I saw
that RaspArch is going to be a thing.
Arch Linux on the Raspberry Pi 3 and it ships with York,
which is an important distinction.
I'll get to that in a minute.
That's our thing.
If I have a Raspberry Pi,
usually I am putting a Raspberry on it, right?
That's just kind of what you,
that's kind of like the go-to of the noobs installer
or whatever, as an Arch user,
being able to choose one distribution
and run it on everything,
now that has been extended,
not only just from my servers to my laptops,
now we can go on a Raspberry freaking Pi.
Michael, were you going to say something?
Yeah, alarm is Arch Linux arm, it already exists.
Oh, but was there a Pi image?
Was there? Yeah.
Was it easy? There's been a Pi image
since the Raspberry Pi had been.
Are you telling me that Arch for the Pi has existed
and I didn't know about it?
Yes.
Well, that's embarrassing.
Technically though, it's a separate distro.
It's not actually made by the Arch Linux group,
but it's the Arch Linux,
Arch Linux has an agreement with the Arch Linux arm project
so that it to use the name.
So they are in conjunction,
but they're not officially,
like Arch Linux is not powering it.
So it's more like-
Let me ask you this.
Did it come with Yortonstone or Packer?
Any of those?
No.
No, it comes with the ability to do those, yes.
Yeah, right, right, right.
Yeah, I mean, yeah.
So when I first started using Arch,
one of my biggest mistakes was I wasn't aware
of some of the package managers that were out there.
So I was downloading these files and extracting the thing
and doing the make and all that stuff, right?
And after use, one of the things I appreciate
about Antragos and one of the reasons I use Antragos
instead of Arch proper is because it handles some
of that stuff for me.
It comes with Yortonstone.
I don't really like Yort, to be honest,
to ask me too many questions,
but I can simply open a terminal type,
yort-tac-s-packer-enter.
And then once I hit yes, no, yes, no, yes, no, yes, no,
yes, yes, no, no, yes, no, yes, no, no, yes, yes, no, no.
It's ridiculous.
And they have to bounce between,
like I wish I could do all of the edits first
and then do you want to continue last
so I could like get into the habit of pressing no
a certain amount of times and yes, they don't do that.
Once I get Packer installed,
then I can just move on and Yort makes it very easy
to do that.
I think that all Arch systems,
if you're not actually doing Arch from like scratch,
like the way that you're supposed to do Arch,
I think it should include a package manager of some sort.
And particularly on the Raspberry Pi
where it takes a long time to compile stuff,
I feel like that's a big, big, big advantage
to have just a built-in package manager.
What do you think?
I just checked,
Yort is not available on Arch Linux arm or alarm,
but Packer is.
Oh.
Packers in the official repos?
Yep.
Nice.
And being completely honest with you,
I'd actually, I would only use,
Yort to me is only useful to get Packer on there.
Packer is really what I want to use.
Now let me-
I just skipped a step.
Let me draw a contrast because I have a feeling
you're going to be on the other side of this,
and I think that's a good thing.
Seuss has also announced that they have images available
for the Raspberry Pi, specifically Seuss Leap.
And when I first saw this, I guess I was honestly,
if I'm being, you know, if I'm being frank,
I was a little confused.
You know, part of it is the, you know,
the article goes on just, it goes in here and it says that
having a stable code base for leap images,
which provides fewer updates than the tumbleweed
for the Raspberry Pi 3 gives people stability
and expands opportunities for those
who are wanting to use the Raspberry Pi
for home automation.
I am wondering how many people are concerned about stability
from a $35 computer.
Am I missing something?
Yeah.
I mean, I guess, I don't know.
I would use Debian if I was caring about stability.
Right.
Well, so that's the, I mean,
so that's a conversation all in itself, right?
We're using Leap, but I just,
I understand the argument for using Seuss on the server.
It wouldn't be necessarily what I would choose to do.
I don't necessarily think it has enough advantages
to pull me off of Red Hat,
but I could definitely see it if Seuss was already in place
or if you're a business starting up and there's,
you know, you have somebody,
you know, you hired assistant administrator,
maybe he knows Seuss very well,
or maybe Seuss happens to be the predominant server platform
that a lot of your competitors are using.
And so a lot of the industry software is written
and works very well.
And, you know, there's a number of arguments
where I can make to see how Seuss works in the enterprise.
I am really not getting it.
Why somebody would want to run Seuss on a,
like what the compelling reason to run Seuss on a Pi
other than, well, because we can,
which is a perfectly valid reason.
I think you answered it earlier when you were talking about,
you know, that analogy of people leaving the military.
There are people who like to use, you know,
Seuss in production.
And so, you know, if you're also starting to do things
like using in Pis to automate around your office
or in your home, you know,
that's probably what they're most comfortable with.
And then now you have an option.
I think it's also just nice in the,
just the aspect of the Arm, I don't know for you,
but the Arm world still sometimes a little weird for me,
or, you know, it has different paradigms.
There's different things available.
So the more sort of parity between like the X86 world
and the Arm world where, you know,
I have the tools and distributions I like here.
And I kind of expect, even if that's a wrong expectation,
I expect to be able to use them in the Arm world
and the Pi world.
And so this kind of just goes a little way towards that.
Hurricane Hernandez, am I pronouncing that right?
Yeah, you got it.
Okay, so as you guys know,
I'm one of the main packagers for Envy.
And when I became a developer,
I mean, I started distro hopping
and somehow ended up on Seuss
because I just couldn't get packages
that were up to date on Debian or Ubuntu.
Now, when you bring Seuss and Arm,
I think Seuss becomes even more relevant because of OBS.
The power that OBS gives you is to compile the packages
and anything you're working on their system,
which means you're not bogging down your Pi.
Now I understand Arch and I understand Packer.
And if I'm correct, yeah, I mean,
the AUR most of the time,
you're compiling those packages on that Pi.
So that's gonna be taking a hit on your system.
That might take days.
Right, right.
So I think that's when Seuss now becomes even more relevant
is if you're using a low power system
and OBS is there and available for free to every user.
That's slick.
I like it.
That's a good point.
I guess I can see that.
I guess I can see that
from both a comfortability standpoint
and just a drop in desktop,
like everything is just ready to go for you.
So essentially I go to work and I work on Seuss servers
and then I sit down at my Seuss desktop
that's provided me from me by work.
And so when I get home, I can use that same operating system.
I guess that makes sense.
You can also build and do custom builds on OBS.
So you can have a company specific stuff
being built for you or something like that.
Let me twist it a little bit.
So I guess all of those arguments make sense
from a desktop standpoint.
Do we think that those arguments stand true
if we're talking about like a home server?
Is it still important to have all of that familiar?
Because I mean, you have to think about it.
The Raspberry Pi world is kind of its own bubble
inside of the Linux ecosystem.
And so a lot of people that are making something
that works on the Pi,
they typically you would use the distribution
that they're using, right?
And you're probably not gonna run more than one service
on a Raspberry Pi,
and one service is right taxing it to be honest.
So if you're using a whatever,
a home automation controller,
would you not be using whatever distro
the home automation controller people are using
so that you kind of stay in sync with them?
Am I off?
I mean, you may want to.
If you're using an appliance, yes.
But I think there's also, that does happen.
And I think you see those in wider distributions,
but it seems like, at least to me,
that the majority of people who pick up one or two Pis,
they're just playing with a couple of things.
They want custom projects.
Maybe you're writing a little homebrewed script
to run something that prints out
or sends you messages or whatever.
And in that case, you might just want whatever distribution
is easiest for you to run that code on.
And also people say stuff about how the Pi is not as,
like you only can do one thing.
That's not true.
I mean, you can have a sync service activated
and you can have a full desktop with like Raspbian
and you can have a bunch of other stuff working.
I mean, I have a Pi doing that
and it's not even the newest one.
It's like the model B before the B plus came out.
So years ago. Nice.
So, you know, I have a problem with the Raspberry Pi.
I'm not really with the Raspberry Pi,
but what I call the misuse of Raspberry Pis.
You know, I think the Raspberry Pi
is a great educational tool.
And I think it definitely has some production value.
And I'll give you an example.
We have a client that has a PBX phone system
and there is an RS232 serial output
that basically dumps every console thing that occurs.
So every time somebody places a call or receives a call
that call gets spit out to RS232.
Well, basically the client wanted to log
all of that information.
And so attaching a Pi and, you know,
pulling that serial output
and just dumping it into a text file was trivial.
In those kinds of circumstances,
I think it works really, really great.
But I have some reservations.
A while back at the Linux Action Show
was featured a Raspberry Pi
that was being used in a medical device, right?
And I think that we have begun to stretch the limits
of what the Raspberry Pi was intended for
and what it is capable of.
And that is an opinion that formed
after having a very deep discussion with Jason,
who is one of the, he's an ArchArm guy.
And he just, he lives, eats and breathes ARM architecture,
loves it to death.
And can tell you anything you want to know
about every device ever made that is ARM.
Guy knows more about ARM devices that people will make.
I mean, he's incredible.
And he was showing me some of the different ARM devices
that are designed for commercial applications
that are designed to be used as embedded servers
and this, that and the other.
And I have noticed, even on a small scale,
that if you have a Raspberry Pi,
it doesn't seem to run for more than a year or so
without running into some sort of problems.
And I'm wondering, you know, Michael specifically,
have you experienced that?
No, not really, no.
So how long has yours been in production?
How long have you been using it?
Off and on, but I don't have them all the time
because I don't use it.
Like the syncing is all the time.
I've only been doing that for about six months.
But I've been using the same Pi's.
I've had two Pi's and they're both the same version
and they're both very old.
And I've been using them without any kind of problems at all.
But you've reinstalled.
On one of them, yes.
The other one is still, one of them runs Kodi
and I haven't reinstalled that one.
Oh, that's interesting.
Well, maybe it's time for Noah to update his opinion.
I think maybe, Noah, where you were coming from is,
you know, it's like you can't really do something
where you need throughput.
It doesn't make a good file server.
You wouldn't edit video on it,
but there may be some things where you really just need
the lowest common denominator of Unix system.
I mean, I tried what I thought was a pretty simple thing,
which was I wanted it to run a Quasso server.
Didn't handle that very well.
Then I tried it just as, if anyone's familiar with OpenEMR,
it's not anything, it's not terribly complicated.
It's basically a web server with a database backend.
And it wasn't like it was in production or anything
with a lot of users.
It was just me, me and my wife.
We were both trying and she does billing
for some of the clinics that I do IT support for.
And we tried it between us and it couldn't handle that.
It would crash.
I'd get a year out of it,
but a little bit after that it would crash.
And so it just kind of turned me off from the pies.
And I was actually voicing that frustration to Jason.
And then that's kind of where
that whole conversation transpired.
But you guys are giving me a new hope.
And I'll tell you kind of what that hope is.
It's that the small arm devices,
you can combine them with other little pieces of hardware
and produce very, very cool things.
So you were talking about a USB serial port.
One of the things I've always thought about doing
is taking one of those raspberry pies
and combining it with one of those like USB GSM modems,
and then heading over to linux.ting.com.
I can't get over that URL.
It's such a great URL, linux.ting.com,
where they'll give me basically
three months of service for free
because they're gonna give you 25 bucks.
And I have so many Ting devices.
I would load it on here for you,
but they wouldn't all fit on the screen.
That's how many Ting devices I have.
I've got my mother on Ting, I'm on Ting,
my wife's on Ting, got my dad on Ting.
And then I have all of these other things.
I call them auxiliary devices, right?
Like my laptop has a GSM card in it.
I would love to put a GSM card
in one of those little USB modems
and have a full functioning like all-in-one
or desktop computer that has its own connection
to the internet.
Man, would that be nice to have inside of the shop
or even here in the studio.
If I needed to check on something,
I wanted to check to see if the stream was up.
Somebody reports an issue says, we can't get the stream.
Sure be nice to have a secondary internet connection
just to check that.
And the thing about Ting is,
they only charge you for what you use.
So if I, I'm not gonna make any calls off my Raspberry Pi,
I'm not gonna use any voice minutes, so I pay zero.
I'm not gonna send any text messages.
The idea that people still send SMS in 2016 is ridiculous.
Exactly.
No stickers.
If you have MMS, which is really kind of a,
screwed up version of SMS,
then you could use, you could send pictures.
There's a stupid character limit, 140 characters.
Have you guys heard me?
It's like sending a telegram
and not the good kind of telegram.
Have you heard me on any show?
Do you think I could express any thought at all
in 140 characters or less?
It is ridiculous.
Anyone who knows me knows I'd blab on for hours.
This episode of Linux Unplugged that you're hearing,
it probably took Rikai seven hours to cut out
all of the inconsistent babble
that occurred throughout the usable bits.
I can't say anything.
And so the fact that people still send text messages
is ridiculous.
Move on to something like Telegram or Viber,
whatever you use, but don't use text messages.
So that's gonna be zero.
The only thing I'm gonna pay for is the data I use.
And Ting's data rates, they started out crazy good,
and now they've gotten even better.
Do you have somebody, one of your friends,
are they bragging about their Google Fi?
Well, now Ting has as good, if not better, pricing.
And let me tell you something,
you don't have to buy some super special $600 phone
to use on Ting.
You can buy any unlocked GSM device.
Me personally, I bought my last device from Best Buy.
I walked into Best Buy,
I went over to their unlocked phone section,
I picked out a phone, I walked up to the register,
and I paid for my phone and I walked out,
and I had an activated phone.
In fact, the guy at Best Buy actually put my Ting SIM
into it, and then we had a discussion
about how great Ting was.
It was kind of cool.
You can buy unlocked phones on Amazon,
you can buy phones on Ting's site.
Right before Chris took off,
he was talking about how great it would be
to buy a phone for your loved one
or even for yourself for Christmas.
Now, I'll tell you something, here's a little,
here's a pro tip.
See this, where it says $9 for the SIM?
That's not what you pay for a SIM.
If you wait, Ting runs dollar SIM specials.
Dollar SIMs, you can get a SIM for a dollar.
So, I ordered 20 of them because why not?
And now I hand them out to people.
And I actually mailed one.
Yeah, and I actually, I handed one out to a viewer.
So, linux.ting.com, the coolest URL ever.
And save $25 off your first device or your first,
I'm gonna say if you're using it as a test phone
or if you're using it as an auxiliary device,
you'll get three months out of that, 25 bucks.
And because it's only $6 per line.
So, make sure to check them out, and a huge thanks to Ting
for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
I hear a lot of talk about mesh networking.
And I'm really gonna be interested to hear your opinion,
Wes, because I know that you do
a lot of system administration.
What do you think of mesh networking?
Specifically wireless mesh networking?
I have yet to actually participate in one,
but I eye them with much interest.
I would like to,
it just seems like a very interesting idea,
sort of as a people's network, if you will,
or even just for isolated communities or otherwise.
And just, it may not always be
the most efficient design necessarily,
but having all the nodes be able to talk to each other,
have this sort of network that you can dynamically
add things to, build, take away, reshape as you need to,
and have connections be resilient.
It seems like it could have a lot of places,
especially as we do more like IoT things,
you have more connected devices all around
in many different places.
I will tell you something, I'm gonna burst anyone's bubble
that is really excited about mesh networking,
particularly over wireless, it is not scalable,
and it is the most inefficient use of bandwidth
known to man.
So if you have this dream that someday
you and your neighbors are gonna each buy a radio,
and you're all gonna put them in your neighborhood,
and one guy's gonna pay for the internet connection,
and he's gonna send it to you,
and you're gonna send it to the next guy,
and he's gonna send it to the guy after him,
and you are living in a pipe dream.
It is never gonna happen.
It never works.
It cannot work.
It is so inefficient, you can get two or three hops,
or maybe four, or maybe five, and then it's dead.
So, I'm just wondering.
Well, what if the goal isn't perhaps efficiency?
What if in some use case of any communication,
or connection, or signaling is better than none?
I'm gonna say, and William, I'd be interested
to get your take on this.
I'm gonna say by the ninth, or 10th hop,
or 12th hop, somewhere in there,
I'm gonna guess it's totally unusable.
Is that fair?
It's kind of hard to say,
depending on the latency of all the links.
I mean, you take many hops through the internet,
so it wouldn't be unreasonable
to do many through the mesh network.
Yeah, but you're not, maybe 30 hops would be bad.
Right.
But yeah, okay, I mean, we can pick a number,
but you're bottlenecking every step of the way down, right?
Like, at some point it comes to a grinding halt.
Oh, absolutely, well, you're adding latency
every single step of the way down.
You're adding more potentials for congestion
and all sorts of stuff, so yes.
But what I'm saying is, like, the guy at the top,
if he has, let's say, a 10 meg link,
and now the guy below him, everyone has a 10 meg link,
but the guy at the top is funneling
everyone below him's traffic.
So, you know, if you're third in line or whatever,
like, everything that's below you
is getting passed through your network,
and ultimately hits your upstream pipe.
Like, it just, the very concept is impossible.
It can never work.
At least.
But you're talking about, like,
some kind of centralized architecture, I think,
where you have a small pipe way upstream
and you're getting funneled into that,
but it doesn't necessarily have to work that way.
Yeah, it could be a mesh network
where there are many paths through the network
and based on congestion avoidance algorithms,
you pick different paths.
Well, a company claims to have figured this out.
This article comes from The Wirecutter,
and basically, this is the best
Wi-Fi mesh networking kits for most people.
And they basically went through
and evaluated a bunch of these kits,
and they settled on the Netgear Orbi,
which they say is the best for most people.
And basically, what it is, is it's a kit
that you can put access points all over your house
and have mesh networking.
So basically, you plug the first one into a router,
and then you put these little hops all over your house,
and then you can get the supposed perfect Wi-Fi network.
Okay, so these are the localized mesh networks,
like an Eero or the Google, whatever Wi-Fi thing?
Yeah, I think that's what they're comparing them to.
Yeah, Eero, yeah, mm-hmm.
Okay.
Which, admittedly, will you probably have better success with
than trying to do like a neighborhood network,
which is what I hear about.
Yeah, I was thinking this is way different
than your larger scale mesh network
of maybe thousands of nodes,
where this is only gonna go to like four or five,
maybe 10. Right, so I think that you'd have,
I think you'd have better luck.
Here's the thing.
Well, these are all pretty low bandwidth nodes.
This could definitely screw you,
and depending on what parts of the spectrum they use
to transmit between each other,
this could actually be pretty slow.
Can you dive into that a little bit?
So I think for the Google Wi-Fi,
you can actually wire them all up
like a normal access point system,
say like your Unifies or something,
and then you don't have any of the bandwidth
sharing problems.
They're all separate APs,
and they all connect back over a wired interface.
That wouldn't be a mesh network, though.
No, it wouldn't be a mesh network,
but it would achieve the same purpose,
which is to cover your whole house in Wi-Fi.
So that's kind of where I was going with this.
If we live, at least here in the United States,
where we have Western construction homes,
I have yet to be inside of a residential construction
where I can't get access to the attic.
Sometimes it means cutting a little hole
out of the sheet rock, but.
But you'll just patch that up later, it's fine.
You could, or you could simply just put a little door on it
and then you have access to your attic,
which I don't know why you would not want access
to your attic.
It is, Cat 6 is so cheap, and I mean so cheap.
I mean, we're talking two, three cents a foot, if that.
Why would you not just run wires in your house?
Why would you, why would you?
Because you don't want to tear up your walls
or your ceilings or whatever.
It may be easy in some types of construction,
but in others, and some people just aren't capable
of dealing with it or don't want to hire a contractor
or whatnot.
Or they value their time.
It makes it easier to just take all these nodes,
throw them next to random power outlets
and kind of spread them throughout your house,
and then have them all automatically connect to each other
and go back to one central point.
It doesn't make it easier.
You know, it's the wireless range extender all over again,
but they're more easy to manage set up.
So you don't have a separate router
from a separate wireless range extender.
It's all the same device,
and it just configures itself for you.
How'd those range extenders work out?
They were terrible.
But that's not to say with five gigahertz band
and everything, it couldn't be better today
because you have a lot more wireless channels to deal with.
And as long as you place them somewhat close to each other,
you do potentially have more bandwidth too.
And your far away nodes may only need, you know,
like 20 megabit.
You're not trying to do like gigabit rate file transfers
across all your mesh network.
You're just trying to like access Facebook in these cases.
Definitely targeting a very simple user.
If you're hooking up internet of things,
I'm guessing that might be useful to have something
that's not the best for bandwidth,
but you know, that'll cover your millions of devices.
And to address everyone in the chat,
yes, wifi kind of sucks and wired is better,
but sometimes, and depending on your technical capability,
you don't have a choice.
Yeah, and sometimes one is good enough
and you don't really, you know, diminishing returns
would get you to wired and you really don't need it.
Yep.
I'm gonna go ahead.
Especially if you're just using Facebook.
We can, I guess we can, what's the old saying?
We can agree to disagree.
I don't think there is a time when I could look somebody
in the face and tell them, you know, I mean,
if you're looking at what, like what we charge
through structured wiring, I bet we could easily do,
you know, an average 2,500 square foot house,
I would say 200 bucks, 250 bucks to drop some,
to put in some, put in some structured wiring
and put in some access points.
I just, I'm not seeing it.
I'm really not seeing the, the,
That's your cost.
I mean, Yeah, exactly.
You're gonna be paying a contractor thousands of dollars
just to get in there and do that.
No, no, no, come on now.
A licensed contract?
I just, I mean, I pay electrician to come in
and run service.
They're gonna charge me, not for the materials
but for the time.
Right, but that's different.
That's different though.
You need a licensed electrician when you're working
with 110, this is low voltage.
There is no, there's basically, other than you can't share,
so electrical wiring has to be strapped every two feet
or three feet or whatever it is, right?
And you can't share a strap with low voltage.
But aside from that, there really isn't a lot of regulation
on where you can throw low voltage wire.
I mean, you can go up in an attic
and throw it around if you want.
Well, but you're gonna have to pay more for plenum wire,
technically, to be within code.
There are a lot of places that make it easy to run
if you're not actually.
Yeah, if you're not strapping.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, you can buy plastic straps too.
I did the janky thing.
I bought really cheap Cat 6
and I ran it through plenum space through air ducts
and I don't care, but I'm gonna have to rip that out
at some point if we sell the house.
Right, right, yeah.
So, I mean, I don't know where you live
that you think it would be thousands of dollars
to have somebody come put some low voltage wiring in,
but I gotta tell you, I mean, I know a lot of people
in the industry and people that do this all over the country
and I think $500, especially,
depending on how big the house is,
I mean, really, I could cover a 2,500 square foot house
with one, two, maybe at the most three access points.
And so, three runs of wire and then down into a basement
or out into a garage or something like that
into a punch panel, I'm not seeing the return on investment
for what you're gonna pay for this system
and for what you're gonna get out of it
versus hiring a professional to come and drop some wire in
and then you put your access points.
And the great thing about putting wire in
is you can go and upgrade the access points
and you got an all new system.
You know, when it goes from 802.11n to G,
or sorry, other way, G to N and then to AC,
I just replace the access points and I'm good to go.
I don't know, I guess it works for some people
and if you're looking for a cheap solution
that doesn't require much, I guess,
maybe that's the way to go.
So, anyway, I don't know, it might work for some people.
I am not into, there is a line, I will admit,
where, I'll give you a great example.
There are times when I'm willing to take less
because overall, sometimes less is more.
And a great example of that is when I am going to do my,
when I'm trying to keep up to date
with things that are happening in the field.
It's very difficult for me sometimes
to stay current on some of the things
that are happening in the field
because we don't use everything, right?
You know, I work with some technologies and not others.
How do you stay current with that stuff?
How do you stay up to date?
And typically what I used to do was take a week off of work
and drive to Minneapolis,
which is the closest place to me,
and enroll in a basically one week training session.
And what I'm doing nowadays
is heading over to Linux Academy.
And basically what Linux Academy is,
unlike this mesh network stuff,
Linux Academy actually provides the same quality
of education that I would get
if I was at a training session.
And I know this because I have done
the in-classroom training,
and I have done remote training.
I have done all of it.
And I paid $2,600 for an instructor
to sit and teach a class remotely.
I took it remotely.
And I remember you couldn't attend the class.
The instructor was, he was doing it basically in his house,
but he didn't invest in a good quality microphone.
And so it basically started like this
the entire time he was talking.
Well, that's just great.
It was terrible.
Like, I could listen to that for hours.
As a person, the speakers that are in my basement
that I listen to my music on
are Sunfire CRM2 ribbon speakers.
I mean, they're $1,800 per cabinet,
and they sound incredible, right?
So as a person who can appreciate that kind of quality,
I'm not, I don't demand like a perfect system,
but oh my God, dude, go to OfficeMax
and spend $35 on a Logitech headset
and you would sound better.
And it was so distracting.
I had a very difficult time comprehending the material.
Well, Linux Academy is,
these instructors are true professionals.
These are the people that they live, eat, and breathe Linux,
and better yet, they live, eat, and breathe teaching.
And if you use our website, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged,
they're gonna make it even better
because they're gonna make it cheaper.
So what, I guess what I'm trying to say is
this is your opportunity to get the same quality
for a fraction of the price.
Instead of spending two or $3,000,
you can spend 20 or $30,
and you'll come home with the exact same thing
because you'll get the same skills.
Learning is really what you put into it,
not necessarily what you're pulling out.
And so, you know, I always say,
knowledge is the one thing people can't take away from you.
It doesn't, people can put you in prison,
people can take away your money,
they can take away your possessions.
Something that you learn is something you have
for the rest of your life.
So add something, you know, this Christmas season,
maybe you can buy it for somebody else too.
That would be a nice thought.
Paying it forward, you know,
somebody that wants to make a career transition,
maybe buy them a, maybe buy them a membership
to Linux Academy.
That's a great idea.
Yeah, I thought so.
Would you appreciate that?
Heck yes.
Everyone would.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
So one of the tools I wanted to talk about
that I don't think gets nearly enough attention
for the amount of money that it has made me
and the amount of hassle that it saved me is Clonezilla.
Oh man, I totally agree with that.
Right?
I tell you what, I bet you, just right on the spot,
Wes, tell me the last time you used Clonezilla.
That'd be like two weeks ago, I think.
I don't know, it seems like at least
I can't go with like six months without using Clonezilla
or thinking that I could use Clonezilla
or wanting to use Clonezilla
and being upset that I don't have it on me.
I will also just say Clonezilla is just,
anytime you have an Andrew Gross Live CD or anything else,
Pac-Man does ask Clonezilla, it's there,
you have wifi, you have Clonezilla,
mount, you know, SSHFS something
and then you can just take a Clonezilla of anything.
Anytime I get a new computer, I get a new upgrade,
anything, just bam, take an image of it,
store it away somewhere, delete it in the year
if you don't need it.
You know you always can go right back to where you were.
So we actually have a small USB hard drive
that is in a bag we call the imaging bag
and we take, we have computers that go in
at client locations and we,
the first time we set up that computer,
we take an image of it and so when clients buy,
when they buy computers after that,
instead of having to install and set that up
every single time, we just take that client's image
and dump it onto their computers.
Then when they upgrade and we go to,
you know like we had a client that went from 12,
they just upgraded from 12.04 to 16.04,
then we make a new image and then we roll that image out
and it's been absolutely incredible.
It's a tool that I couldn't live without
and I would pay thousands of dollars,
if that's what it costed, to keep using it
because I need it.
The good news is it is the most advanced
open source disk-cloning utility
and it doesn't cost anything.
This article is saying that it's the first release,
it's the first release to use the kernel from Linux 4.8,
specifically 4.8.7.
We don't talk enough about Clonezilla
and what it does and I'm interested,
is anyone in the mumble room using Clonezilla
for something incredible or just to save their bacon?
I don't know, man.
I would at least like to use it in the future.
I'm really against cloning disks in most cases,
unless the disk is absolutely failing me or something
and I want to recover data from it.
Why is that?
I think rebuilding, whenever you have
some kind of catastrophic failure
or you're setting up a new system,
I think rebuilding is just more worthwhile
to give you a fresh file system and everything.
I think I do agree in many cases,
but a NixOS user would say that, I think.
But there are a lot of cases,
and I do really appreciate that Clonezilla
has fancy features so that it at least does take
like, it won't copy blank space.
It's not quite as good as having configuration management
or an OS where you can really rebuild things very cleanly,
but it's a much better middle ground
than just DDing things.
So I appreciate that a lot
and it makes it a lot easier to work with.
What's the disadvantage of using Clonezilla, William?
If you have, let's say, 50 clients
and all of those workstations
are essentially set up identical,
where is the advantage in building each one
of those from scratch?
Or even when one fails, building it back from scratch?
I guess I'm just not seeing it.
It seems to me that when you wanna deploy something
at scale, I mean, yes, you can use things like Puppet
to individually configure those systems,
but a lot of times, that much intervention is not needed.
And I gotta tell you, as a person who has managed Puppet
numerous times for numerous different clients
on numerous different occasions,
there's a lot of work in setting Puppet up.
It's one of those things I really dread doing.
I think only second to Pixie servers.
I hate setting up Pixie servers.
That's a shame, I really like setting up Pixie servers.
I like Pixie.
I mean, I don't love it, but I appreciate it.
I feel like I haven't had much trouble with it.
I guess I like what Pixie does,
but the actual act of setting up the Pixie server,
do you not run into a bazillion problems
that you have to troubleshoot along the way?
Yeah, there are, and particular firmware implementations
and those kinds of things.
I mean, it is at that bottom end of the stack
that's always kind of troublesome, right?
That just makes my stomach turn just thinking about it.
I do think you do have a point.
I mean, there's, it depends on what your environment is.
It depends on where, what your bottlenecks are.
So I do think there's probably also a middle ground here
of like, can you make yourself,
you shouldn't just like make a crude image,
not clean it up, not set in place,
first run scripts or other things.
So I think there is a middle ground
between like just a simple copy of an image
versus like something that you've set up a nice copy
that's ready to go.
It boots up, enters a network, configures itself.
Maybe you don't need full configuration management
like Puppet or Chef or Ansible.
Maybe you do, but there's like, you can have something,
some stage in the standard image stage
and some in the configuration management
and maybe you just need the standard image.
Yeah, I don't know if I could go back.
And again, when I compare the two, I'm like, man,
Puppet would sure be overkill in a lot of situations,
most situations really, where we have a large deployment
because you're not making a lot of changes system-wide.
Per class, per host.
Yeah, right, right.
We know with the exceptions of updates
and software management, and even those,
a lot of times if you're making a lot of changes
to software management,
it's because of different roles in the business.
You have the graphic designers
and they needed a different version of this
or they needed a different program installed or something.
And it's something I wouldn't really want to manage
at the level because I'm not making those changes
to every single machine.
Right, one use case I've had a little closer to home
is as Linux users, well, I think the network,
we do espouse trying to buy from Linux first to vendors,
but a lot of people end up, certainly I have as well,
ended up buying a machine that ran Windows
or maybe you bought a Mac.
And I've used Clonezilla several times
to just take a factory image right there.
If I need to send it in for warranty or something,
I can just apply that
and know that they're not going to futz with me about,
oh, you break your machine.
We're not going to pay for this.
Right, you know what I've done the last couple of times?
I just DD the drive and I send it back to them
and then when they ask what they say anything,
I'm like, listen, you can go and put whatever you want
on there, but I'm not sending, my excuse is,
I'm just not sending you a laptop with my data on it.
So I'm wiping the drive before I send it in.
And if you need to install something to test,
then you're welcome to do that.
Most of those guys have, you know,
drives anyway that they use for troubleshooting
and actually use user, because they don't have passwords.
Right, yeah, it's a liability nightmare.
I knew, I know back in, you know, a while back,
I don't do this anymore,
but I used to keep a Clonezilla image of my laptop.
So if my laptop ever crashed, I could restore
a already configured and set up version of my laptop.
Anyone doing something like that?
I would like to, but I just don't know how to just yet.
I'd say that sounds like a good idea, Noah.
Uh-huh.
Yeah, and I would probably do it like maybe
at least every couple months or so.
Gotta be honest with you, as far as how to do it,
it's literally as simple as downloading the ISO,
booting off of it, and it asks you questions
and you answer them.
They have a super slick system going.
You know, it says, do you want to start Clonezilla?
Yes, what image, what drive do you want to image?
This one?
Which one do you want? Yeah, I love it.
And it'll give you the command too,
so if later you want to make this like something
you do on a cron job or, you know,
set up in an automated way somehow,
they give you like a one line command that you can do
that'll just do exactly what you,
the backup that you just performed, which is great.
Oh wow, that's awesome.
I met, actually, I had the privilege
at last year's Linux Fest Northwest.
There were a couple Clonezilla guys right by
the Jupiter Broadcasting booth,
so I spent a little while talking to them
and I have to say they were very nice to talk to.
They were excited about the project
and they were surprisingly humble
for the cool software they've created.
Shoot, man, that's really disappointing.
I would have loved to meet those guys.
Well, maybe they'll be back.
We'll just have to hope.
Maybe.
Anyone else have any other closing thoughts
about Clonezilla or other useful Linux tools
that don't get enough attention?
All right.
ProSync.
Yeah, right, ProSync.
All can sit.
Yeah, all right, guys, well, thank you so much
to the Mumba Room for being here.
We really appreciate having you taking time out of your day.
Thank you very much, Wes, for joining me remotely.
My pleasure.
A huge thank you to Michael Tunnell,
our producer for this show,
Rekai, our hardworking video editor
who makes everything sound and look amazing,
and of course, the entire team at Jupiter Broadcasting
for making this show possible.
You can find out more at jupitabroadcasting.com.
Check me out on Sundays,
Linux Action Show, where Chris and I host,
and we'll be back here next Tuesday
with the same show next week.
Bye.
Okay, bye.
I sit down at my desk and I'm going through links that Wes provided things
that we're gonna talk about today and I came across this link which was an
article from System76 talking about how they are working with Canonical to
improve high DPI support in Linux now for those of you who don't know high DPI
support in Ubuntu specifically has been kind of a disaster and a lot of laptops
now are shipping with high-resolution display 1080 is the minimum I will
purchase agreed agreed Wes how do you handle working with lower resolution
because I know your XPS that's a 1366 yes unfortunately that's the only one
left in my entire life thankfully how do you how do you work around that you know
I usually end up using a tiling window manager or something with easy control
so I can rapidly shift between things and then I'm most places that I end up
going you know if I'm not at a coffee shop or here at the studio I have an
external monitor configured and so at that point it's not such a big deal hmm
yes that makes sense but I mean I would never buy one now it's frustrating even
today that like how in 2016 does the laptop market still have those
resolutions offered because it's really I mean it was fine for what it is it's
better than no monitor but it is just the worst well I think part of it is
cost right I think a part of it is just that they the manufacturers are you know
they can get a three two hundred dollar laptop about three hundred dollar laptop
if they're not putting in a terribly expensive display and and that works for
the you know guy or woman that is sitting at home browsing Facebook and
checking their email doesn't really matter for you know pixel density isn't
a big deal it is a big deal for people like you and I though that work in the
field and need to be able to scale three or four different windows at one time
right yeah exactly right you need to be able to have a lot on your screen at
once you're doing many things at once you know you're professional so 4k has
been a great promise and system 76 has been kind of on the leading edge I don't
know of a whole lot of other laptops that are shipping with 4k displays you
know like there's the you know the Google pixel shipped to the high
resolution display when the the XPS does but for the most part you know the the
you're lucky to get a 1080p display most of my 1366 and the problem is if you get
a 4k display and I have a 4k display on my on my oryx is or no I don't know I
don't I have the 1080 version but if you have a 4k display the problem is it the
Ubuntu looks terrible all of the buttons are tiny and you can't see them even you
even if you fix even if you go through like there's a recommended you know like
kind of tutorial steps that you go through to kind of fix some of the
issues and one of that would be like dragging the the the slider scale and it
increases the windows but that doesn't fix everything so for example Firefox it
doesn't fix the buttons in Firefox and stuff so that's still huge so then you
have to go to about about colon config and you have to scale Firefox individually
and just it's it's a very hacked together solution and so it's something
that's needed some attention for a long time I'm interested this is anyone in
the mumble room any of you guys using 4k displays and what's your experience been
like under Linux specifically Ubuntu if you've tried it I'm not currently using
4k I'm still stuck on 1080p but I am shopping for monitors but I don't feel
4k has or I need more better GPU for 4k okay so you need a better video card but
you would go to 4k oh I thought I totally would but I'm so kind of waiting
for the technology to get up higher for the Hertz for the gaming side because I
hate having monitors that only do one thing I need I need I need color
reproduction I need performance I need reliability all that kind of things and
I hate spending money on just one thing that I'm going to have to replace a year
or two later to get just the same thing but better quality so yeah so kind of
waiting for 4k to get up there and then display poor and HDMI and all that fun
stuff right right yeah I think that makes a lot of sense anyone else using 4k I
have to have a laptop that is around 13 inches that's 4k and I have a 27 inch
HP IPS 4k display now which laptop is that your is that your thing pad yeah no
it's an Asus oh I see okay yeah yeah right no the thing that's actually just
1080p which yeah and I actually like that more to some extent because scale
isn't an issue for me sure but the 4k at 27 inches is really nice and even though
I do have to scale some things up you get much more clarity and screen
realistic at the larger display size yeah the screen real estate seems seems
legitimate at a 27 inch I wonder that's not much more expensive if you don't
want to go like 144 Hertz or something and you're just sticking at 60 Hertz 4k
is not terribly priced and these are really nice monitors nice stands well
built you agree that do you agree that fit 4k on anything under 15 inches is is
a poor resolution to screen size ratio it's a little ridiculous I don't think
it's necessary I think 1440p around that size is fine and even then you're still
scaling stuff up we'll see how has 4k worked under Linux for you 4k has been
fine but I mostly run xman ads so I kind of customize everything myself and a lot
of what I do is in the terminal and scaling that up is trivial it's it's
basically just increasing the font size right sure and the browser has add-ons
and things to deal with high DPI I mostly use Chrome and Firefox so okay
not a big deal so you're so basically your approach is handle every
application individually pretty much mostly because xman ad doesn't give you
anything to deal with it in some unified way yeah sure you could change GTK in a
unified way and QT in a unified way individually but I don't really use that
many applications and I can deal with the ones that aren't scaled correctly
you have a well-defined set that you have yeah I have a pretty small limited set
of applications and even like Gimp and stuff has been fine though I'm probably
pushing the envelope here a little bit but have you tried Ubuntu by chance
nope I basically only run NixOS and my fork of it so that's what I don't really
know okay that's fair that's what I'm doing all 1080p and that's on 1404 and
it's fine yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah today I mean it 1080 even on a I've used
I mean our ThinkPads you have the same we do we have the same both of us have
the same laptop at 12.5 inch laptop I find 1080p to be perfectly workable oh
yeah anyone else have experience preferably preferably experience with
Ubuntu on 4k or is that it well long story short I I am happy to see that
somebody is working on this problem because I think in the near future this
is going to be very important I think all desktop computers are basically
going to be I think you know obviously 4k is gonna become the next go-to
standard it's certainly going to become the next go-to standard in video
production yep and so this is going to be a very important problem that we need
to tackle and so it's very nice and reassuring to see that you know both
system 76 and canonical are aware of this problem and working on it and I
and I guess it's kind of just like a thank you to all of the people that work
so hard and put a lot of effort in to make sure that we have the tools that we
need I wish I would have had the tools that I needed this morning to make my
day go well at least I know that down the road when 4k becomes a standard and
it's just something that we go to and expect it I know it'll be there thanks
to a hard work at system 76 and canonical