I know you know this already, I'm sure, but we used Ubuntu Mate 14.04 for our broadcast
station and it worked like a champ, it was great.
I was grinning ear to ear when I heard that that's what you'd use, that was brilliant.
It was perfect because it gave us enough of a...there are certain things we needed to
be able to do that are sort of like a traditional workflow, like for example I was syncing over
art assets and no one needed to be able to look at a bunch of files in Nautilus or whatever
the file manager is called, and open them up in Inkscape and modify them.
So there was some need to have sort of a more traditional work desktop environment on the
broadcast machine but it doesn't need to be anything very high end because it really doesn't
do much more other than the broadcast, it's just when we sit down to use it.
So it was perfect because the low resources meant that the rest of the resources went
to the broadcast and it was just perfect, it was exactly what we needed.
So I know that you've been using Ubuntu Mate for some production use and there's a podcast
that I'm now, I think I'm an officially a member of the team, I think that happened
last time or the time before, anyway but there's a podcast that I do with Popey and Laura and
Mark now and 50% of that is done with Ubuntu Mate and I know a couple of YouTubers that
are doing all of their stuff on Ubuntu Mate and I know of a radio station in the US that's
using Ubuntu Mate for their radio.
So it's becoming quite popular as a broadcast platform and when I heard Noah and Alan talking
about their trials and tribulations with setting up that machine and sleep deprivation and
all the rest of it, it got me thinking maybe there's the opportunity to create an Ubuntu
Mate broadcaster alternative image which comes pre-packaged with the tools that a broadcaster
would want to use.
So things like Mumble and OBS and video editors and audio editors and I don't know what those
tools are but if you can speed up the deployment and have an out of the box, I mean there's
already Ubuntu Studio which does that by building on top of Zebuntu but yeah it got me thinking
maybe there's some collaboration potential on that.
Yeah and that is very, it is already a bit of an advantage we noticed because a lot of
times when we would set up a production machine then there is sort of setting up the, actually
installing the OS is sort of the fastest part of it because then you go to the vendors website,
you go get your login because you purchased the software and you have to login now and
then you get the download links and then you download it and then you generate the serial
number and of course you install it and then after you install it you restart and all that
good stuff and then you come back online and then you launch the application and then you
put the serial number in and then you activate the application and then you begin the setup
process right of course and that's assuming there wasn't any drivers you had to load for
the capture card which there always are.
So all of these things are just completely eliminated when you do it under Linux.
It's already so much faster that we were just like blown away.
So I can only imagine like if it was even more streamlined and I know one thing we're
thinking about doing is an image but the primary challenge is that, this is one thing I've
always kind of worried about the nut to crack under Linux is there is a fine line to walk
where the system would get so stagnant that like OBS would be held back or OBS would be
held back for example because maybe we need a newer version of FFmpeg or something like
that.
So there's this line where I'm like okay today we can use a 14.04 installation.
I'm not so sure if next, in fact I would be shocked if next year at Linux Fest Northwest
we were still on Ubuntu 14.04.
I would bet that all the underlying technology since it's being developed so rapidly is going
to move forward and I would bet that it just it won't work for us.
I don't know what we'll be on but I bet it's not 14.04 next year.
Yeah quite possibly.
One of the things I've been looking at is the idea of software channels.
So there's lots and lots of PPAs out there but it's up to you to decide the quality of
those PPAs and if they're just delivering a single package that they want or if it's
everything under the sun you don't quite know what else you're going to drag in as a result
of adding them.
So I've had this idea of software channels with a UI where you can turn on like the FFmpeg
software channel or the mumble software channel and it's by application and instead of you
having to go and find the PPAs you just enable the applications that you're interested in
and it turns on sort of pre-vetted quality PPAs that deliver those packages so typically
the PPAs that are made by the developers rather than you know enthusiasts and hobbyists that
might have a PPA of just you know a load of stuff that they want on their machine.
That would be and of course that's how users think of it too is by the application.
Yeah exactly so you have an icon and you say enable mumble channel or enable FFmpeg channel
or VLC channel or LibreOffice 4.4 channel or whatever it might be.
Yeah that's interesting and you know the other thing that's great about Linux is when we
decide okay well now it's time to add in the audio stream it's like okay well we'll just
go install DarkCast and it's just it is once all of the stuff gets in place it is so much
easier to do it under Linux once the software is ready.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's still hungover from Linux
Fest Northwest 2015.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
Hey there Matt.
I swear I had two beers over the course of the entire Linux Fest Northwest and yet somehow
I feel hungover.
I felt hungover for a couple of days and then I realized it wasn't so much the Fest itself
it was like the six or seven days leading up to the Fest that crushed me because I actually
like Saturday night after Linux Fest I went to bed like at nine o'clock like oh yeah yeah
we went to the after-party.
The after-party wasn't so good but we went to the after-party and then I left after about
ten minutes and Iamacon shamed me in the chatroom for only having two beers.
It gets worse Iamacon.
After that I went back to the hotel room like around nine o'clock and I fell asleep after
watching Obama's White House Correspondence thing and the rest of the group went out and
had like played the Cards Against Humanity and where that was up to like one in the morning
and meanwhile I'm sleeping I'm saying even though I went to bed early I still didn't
get enough sleep.
I don't know what it is Matt.
So today today we're gonna cover some of the best interviews we got from the floor of Linux
Fest Northwest 2015.
If you watch the Linux action show you saw the interviews we got live as people stopped
by the booth during the show but Linux Fest Northwest went Saturday and Sunday and it's
something it's sort of a phenomenon that happens at these fest is the sessions let out and
man it is like a herd of people just they swarm the floor and it gets nuts and then
it kind of sessions fill back up and the floor kind of empties out and all of the cool people
that are sitting at the different booths all of a sudden have nothing to do and so they
stopped by our booths and they talked to us and so we sat down with Alan of course Alan
from TechSnap he's gonna give us an update on the state of ZFS on Linux and describe
how boot volumes work for us.
Also a guy from Intel who's working on getting the Intel Minnow board to be a premier Linux
device and he talks about why Linux is just the best platform for these Intel Minnow boards.
These are these boards that are designed to compete with like the ARM type boards.
It's really fascinating because it's what you get from an ARM board like a Raspberry
Pi but an x86 chip on there like a full-fledged Intel chip so he's gonna talk to us about
that and running Linux and then the guy who brought Netflix to Linux originally and got
the whole snowball rolling that eventually brought native playback joins us to talk about
all of that and wine's critical role in moving people over to Linux.
Plus towards the end of the show we might just have a clip that could land us in a bit
of legal trouble.
So it is a great show today and audio or video there's gonna be a little something for Irver
Bottom Matt.
So why don't we start getting into it before we go too far we got to bring in our awesome
mumble room so time appropriate greetings mumble room like a wave of yeah it's like
doing the wave a little bit all right guys well you guys are like our virtual Linux fest
every single week who needs to go anywhere we'll just talk to you guys that's not that's
not actually true at all that's not true no it's not true but it doesn't matter hey so
we have many things to cover but I had one story that just kind of slipped out between
Linux action show and this show that I wanted to give some coverage to because it's a pretty
good release and it's one I've been looking forward to for a little while now excuse me
I'm mr. sis I'm getting an echo back from your mic over there thank you sir all right
so it's a it's a it's a news release that I've been looking forward to for a while it's
plat it's KDE plasma 5 3 this is a big big deal this is a really big release of the plasma
desktop this is one where I think people might want to consider switching to plasma 5 if
you've been holding back and it adds a few new interesting features as well specifically
around enhanced power management and boy did these guys go for it and gals when they decided
to make this feature they've built in a lot of features from Intel's power top application
right into the KDE info GUI Center now Matt if you bring up the like the power management
section in K info center they will now integrate the power top readings right into the graphing
so you can see what applications are consuming the most power and it generates you an energy
consumption graph kind of like you see on Android it's really sick well this pisses
me off because now I want to use KDE again it just totally it's like come on guys stop
it stop innovating damn it I'm trying to like find a desktop and stick to it knock it off
I know I know hold on I just decided I'm a gnome guy don't do this to me right do this
oh wait there's more you know I don't know what this means exactly but also now screen
brightness changes are animated on most hardware I don't know what that means I don't know
how you animate a screen brightness change other than I'm glad it's animated I like that
I know yeah well that could go a couple different ways I mean were we talking about like doing
a Disney cartoon or are we talking about actually like a transition I don't know yeah that could
be interesting it's like an OpenGL fade or yeah or is it something completely different
so they completely revamped the Bluetooth management applet so it looks really good
and much clearer to connect to available Bluetooth devices and the touchpad configuration well
I don't know if I'd say it looks good I mean it's a touchpad configurator but boy is it
cray it'll even emulate little like areas for you to drag and click to test stuff and
set up action corners for like the top left top right bottom right bottom left of your
trackpad you can do tap and drag gestures you can set locked drags and tap detection
timers and all of these things that of course you'd only be able to do under KDE and I'm
not going to say it's the best UI to do it but at the same time I'm glad they're not
taking away some of the power toys so I'll take it that is now see this yeah this changes
everything improved widgets all along to new clipboard applet gain support for showing
barcodes which is kind of crazy but easy to transfer something from your clipboard to
your Android device the recent they now have a recent contacts and recent documents menu
that's been cleaned up the menu whole menu thing looks really that's just the whole thing
looks really good and the tech preview of plasma media center has been added to this
release it's a full it's they say it's fully stable but missing features so version one
will have more features but they say it's stable now wow yeah also a huge steps towards
supporting Wayland so boom shakalaka the plasma desktop keeps chugging right along I mean
like I go out of my way to dislike KDE and I'm having a really hard time right now because
it's like this is really compelling I mean and I'm not a fan so this is saying something
I'm not gonna I'm not gonna dig any I'm not gonna dig a hole any deeper but I'll just
say I'll just give you this I'm impressed yeah there you go hey so we've before before
we even started the show wimpy jumped on and wimpy wimpy asked me said so Chris what's
the latest with Angela switch to Linux how is it going and I thought I would open up
our update on Angela switch to Linux and her whole I switched to a yoga three by capturing
a special moment that happened on the live stream at Linux fest this weekend think penguin
was there and they were giving out stickers for you to place over the Windows key on your
keyboard and so we thought the proper way to Chris and Angela's new laptop was to get
rid of that Windows super key and put a tux penguin on this all open up the yoga update
segment with this clip okay to put that wind that that that tux sticker over the Windows
key or you can use that one if you want yeah there you go if you want to tux that that
Windows button all right the tension no it gets the sticker ready all right as I fold
the yoga screen back I get the power vested in me yeah by the canoe and the penguins and
the beard I now pronounce you no longer freedom hating garbage but instead freedom respecting
that's beautiful though it's so beautiful keyed give me now kissy yoga there we go ladies
and gentlemen it now has a tux somebody better kiss that computer then Noah kisses the computer
not a dry eye was a very emotional moment so now Angela has a Linux penguin on on the
button now okay so what did we end up doing so the MacBook sold thank goodness the MacBook
sold so the yoga is going to be paid for thank goodness now I I left the studio that night
after Linux unplugged and I said to Noah and I wish Noah's here so we could get an answer
and if anybody in the mumble room knows the answer it's mr. sis you might know the answer
I don't know but if anybody or blaster might know I left here thinking that we were gonna
put Ubuntu Mate 1404 we're gonna go LTS and then we sort of you know you know what we'll
do this we'll do LTS and we'll do gnome 314 we'll do the gnome PP because she likes gnome
and all right so we'll do that and one thing led up to another and I don't exactly know
exactly what transpired but I kid you not when I got back in here the next morning it
was running arch he was installing Ubuntu I literally have no idea quite what happened
why we switched from Ubuntu LTS with gnome PPA to arch but we did and so that's what
she has is an arch box with gnome 3.16 on it so far she's quite happy and everything
seems to be working mr. sis do you know why he didn't go with LTS were you in the room
when that decision was made yes I was I was there I was part of the decision I can't confess
to that however there is a non-disclosure agreement that was agreed to at the time so
all members would have to be around to then agree that we can't disclose that decision-making
process okay so before we can reveal the reason we have to bring Noah on the show and get
his consent and maybe Alan too since he was present and and Rekai okay okay I might have
to get consent from Rekai off air perhaps but why this is either way what I want to
focus on is that she actually she said something to me over dinner that made all of the work
worth it she said I think this is the time it's gonna stick because the difference and
I and I want to I want to reiterate and underscore this if you can afford to do it the difference
is she really likes that hardware she likes that laptop she feels like she got something
nice and it is something nice and it's set up just for her and you know we also went
through and cleaned up some of her old data and offline some of it and we just sort of
did some general hygiene stuff as well and I think overall she's missing a few things
and there's a there's a couple of threads going to the Linux action show subreddit like
she used a pixel mater which is sort of like a Photoshop alternative under OS 10 she doesn't
have anything quite equivalent to that she's looking at Corita and Inkscape not I don't
know if that's gonna do it for her not but there's threads going on and on about that
but so far it looks like it's actually gonna stick and I don't know I'm not I'm not like
totally like totally comfortable with the arch thing but I since we were gonna do before
and I was okay with it I'm okay with it now I'll stay on top of it for a little bit I
guess delegate my friend delegate I'm telling you oh we got to get that reason we got to
get that reason in here and find it out or you know or Linux Academy you know I mean
one of the other either way actually she was she was also I think this whole thing has
given her a boost of confidence because then she was kind of giving me a hard time teasing
me that she was gonna learn Python before I do so my wife's enrolling in Linux Academy
next month I mean it's happening yeah she's actually gonna learn the Linux basics I mean
you know I think I'm just gonna do it too and yeah it is it is you know actually this
would be I could just why don't I just take a moment right here and I'll just mention
Linux Academy that'd be a great spot to mention Linux Academy they're a sponsor of the Linux
unplugged program go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged that'll get you the unplugged
discount that's linuxacademy.com slash unplugged go check them out they have been sponsoring
us for a while now but I feel like every time we come on the show we have something new
to talk about and that's pretty exciting if you think about the rapid amount of innovation
and development work that is required to make that happen wow that I have right here let's
see check out I have printed off some of the stuff they've done recently it's so much stuff
that I actually decided I'm just gonna print it so that way I can just go through some
of it with you from time to time and read it that it's I really really respect what
these guys are doing so let me tell you a little about Linux Academy they're different
than all the other online educational resources it's created by people that are truly passionate
about Linux and they really care about open source they got together with their friends
that are education education educators and developers and they've created the Linux Academy
platform they built it from scratch and it is custom-built for us when you go there you
recognize it is created by people that truly get this kind of thing and the reason why
I want to emphasize that is because I think that really closes the gap that makes the
big difference that's the difference from all of the other large websites that cover
all of the other areas that don't truly love Linux they don't cover it right they don't
care they don't closely watch the trends and see where things are going they don't know
that there's many distributions you might want to choose from Linux Academy does they
have seven plus Linux distributions you get to choose from that automatically adjust the
course where that automatically adjust the virtual machine that spins up on-demand it
comes with the machines as you need them they have scenario based labs at Linux Academy
in addition to all the other regular labs they have for servers and things like that
they'll do specific deep dives into scenarios we receive access to scenario based training
to put you in the middle of a task common to everyday environments you'll work in advanced
lab environments while completing those scenarios from beginning to end on their live servers
as a member of Linux Academy also have abilities to ask their instructors they have live streams
where you can ask the instructors questions and they've introduced this new feature just
recently called nuggets which is a deep dive into a single topic not necessarily part of
an overall part of a training course but like everyday tasks that you just need to know
that if you know these little nuggets better and better you get things done faster and
faster and I've taken some of these and learned you know there's a better way to do this that
I've always done it and it's a little bit of humble pie from time to time but I'm always
very very very grateful that I've learned a new way to do something or improved a way
of doing something I've done for a long time Linux Academy also recently announced they're
going to start up an open source grant they're going to be giving away five thousand dollars
to a qualifying open source project now to qualify you have to be an open source project
now they're going to have their founders club members vote on which projects get the funding
but it's pretty awesome it's a way it's another way they're going to give back to the open
source community so they had their big content push bunch of new content has hit Linux Academy
the Red Hat certified services administrator the art I chat room you tell me our HCSA it's
going to be released it was actually just released a couple of days ago 50 new video
nuggets you know those new nuggets I was telling you about 50 of them just hit the site how
about that AWS CSA Pro available for the founders club members and then everybody else gets
it on June 15th DevOps essentials is available now that was just added as well lots of good
stuff as well as new office hours tons and tons of things in the community as well and
if you want to learn things like Ruby or OpenStack PHP Amazon Web Services Android development
or just how to back up your Linux box go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and take
the training courses go do a deep dive download the comprehensive study guides listen to them
offline when you're going like a podcast get the in-depth resources it's training materials
for the stuff that you need to use stuff to make you better at the job that you do or
challenge yourself that's what I use it for Linux Academy comm slash unplugged it's a
great resource and a big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program
and like you know like Matt said there's always a great opportunity to go in there for all
kinds of folks I don't get a chance to really give you a picture of all the types of content
that are available but if you go check it out there really is courseware for everybody
it's starting sort of at the absolute beginner level like like maybe Matt's wife would be
all the way up to you know the really hardcore stuff that's super advanced and putting you
on the very edge of the things like Docker and and really just everything that I was
looking at some of the recently added stuff here engine X and the limp stack introduction
to Ruby on Linux Linux essential certification course for just all the different certifications
right there new 20 new AWS CSA additions were just put on here get in GitLab from start
to finish deploy and manage open stack on Ubuntu it just it's just these are just recent
ones that's just really good stuff Linux Academy comm slash unplugged thanks like you said there's
something there for everyone and I love the fact that they're able to take you by the
hand at the very very beginning and you know you can know literally nothing about Linux
at all and they can take you from that point all the way up to where you're ready to be
certified and something you're wanting to get into it's really cool and there's for
folks like me who've been in it for a long time but just want to kind of just keep tipping
our toes and keeping keeping ourselves up to date exactly it's really useful and speaking
of keeping our toes in the waters I've been experimenting with different file systems
under Linux for a while the one I really haven't spent a lot of time with because just doesn't
feel like it's time yet but maybe it maybe this clip is going to change my mind is ZFS
or as our buddy Alan says ZFS and Alan gave a talk at Linux Fest Northwest about open
ZFS and he talked about a lot of things and one of the things that seemed to grab the
crowd's attention was this feature called boot volumes and it goes into some detail
about how it works and how maybe we could see it under Linux and how maybe in the future
it could be integrated with docker so a lot of things that could be coming to Linux and
ZFS so Alan is our first take from Linux Fest Northwest did did you go into much much detail
on boot environments because that seems like in a particular area that would be of interest
to Linux users yeah they're all like we want that yeah so one of the things we do with
that is so instead of actually take snapshots that's pretty normal but you can also clone
them which basically makes them a new file system that's writeable not for our default
file system we don't we don't have snapshots no no yeah so yeah but there people are familiar
with what snapshots are you mean better file systems that have snapshots yeah yeah okay
but but people are familiar that there's such a thing yeah like even if even if it's actually
coming from even if our file system doesn't have it right or specifically you know you're
using virtualization and it can kind of pretend right yeah sometimes I get to play like extended
for as snapshots with like virtual box yeah and I'm like oh this is what a file system
feels like yeah a little bit just a little bit and so you basically with a clone it allows
you to like fork a file system kind of like you for open source right yeah so you have
the common blocks only take up space once even though you're using them twice and then
the differences in the difference yeah and then you have the differences take up the
space and so with that what you can do is if you have forks of what your system looked
like from different times you we push that into the grub menu and when you start up the
system what publishes it to the grub menu just a utility that Chris Moore wrote oh okay
so it just loops over the ZFS data set and reads that and then it figures out what menu
entries to make based on and then when you boot up the system you may like well I can
have the system that like the latest version I run it it's okay or I just installed an
update and it broke everything yeah let me just select the other one in the menu one
from before yeah and he set it up so it automatically makes one for you when you start a package
upgrade because I always forget that's a good idea and then oh look you know this latest
package upgrade left me in dependency hell some app I depend on doesn't work now yeah
well hey I can just reboot and give me what my machine looked like 10 minutes ago or and
the best part about it is with ZFS you create basically an infinite number of partitions
you can create many many partitions but they all share one pool of free space right because
usually the the only reason we don't create a separate partition for like every directory
on our systems is that you have to set how much space each partition gets and you lock
yourself in yeah your free space gets broken up all over the place and it's useless yeah
well with all the free space coming from one big pool now you can create as many as you
want and so when you're setting up these snapshots and stuff when you're rolling back you can
say roll back only the system but leave my home directory alone oh all the documents
I updated but the files and can I can I once again repeat that extended for is not good
enough and I just say once again repeat that every time you've tried another file system
it totally blows your system away and I've run extended for for the last like seven years
never had a problem working for you know I don't have snapshots my system doesn't crash
so we'll go with that honestly on my development laptop I actually have boot environments
are created on purpose where I'm actually have three different versions of the operating
system that I can boot from yeah that's cool too but sharing more of the data rather than
if I did it like a multi boot type setup right yeah like they're all sharing the same installed
apps and stuff because they're sharing their package database because it's compatible but
the one thing that makes this a little easier on BSD is the separation between the operating
system and your applications yeah previously forces all applications you install from the
package repo to be rooted in user local whatever right so even your config files so you know
yeah the config files user local Etsy is user local Etsy yeah so when you upgrade the operating
system and it changes some default stuff right changes an etc right so you can your snapshot
can have that separate and yeah you can see which last etc is just the OS setting exactly
and so when you're upgrading and and if you roll that back yeah you didn't lose the change
you made yeah in your server application or whatever yeah you know and Linux sometimes
like apps that run with the user level privileges they'll write their config to the home directory
so you can accomplish that a bit yeah but like yeah overall package settings and like
you know for your for your applications you install from like the AUR and things like
that yeah they get mixed in with the slash Etsy yeah so having that separation makes
things a little bit easier to kind of with finding control decide exactly what you're
going to roll back and what you're not yeah and that that's the the other big advantage
with that over other types of snapshots and roll backs is that you can roll back part
of the system but not all of it so that you know you don't lose the file you're the stuff
you're doing well and yeah so with that what PCB SD is taken to doing is actually basically
forking the file system setting up in a jail and installing all the updates and stuff in
the background while you're working on your live system and then when you reboot you just
reboot in a newer version of the system but all you're in this all your other stuff is
happening and and so you can be doing your package upgrade in the background while still
running applications without having a problem because that was a problem I used to have
is like while I was installing the update you know it's downloading a button it's going
to do stuff well I want to be using the browser but how do you use the browser well the dependencies
are being upgraded yeah it's like oh the browser can't launch because the dependency is a newer
version now yeah and so yeah having that happen in a separate one and then just switching
out underneath right it's kind of like a puppy Linux and having the overlay yeah yeah overlay
so it the way I look at it and and really I mean people as much as it's fun to joke
about it really people should be thanking you for trying things like butter FS and then
letting it crash on you twice because then we all know where you know what the state
of I mean really you're doing everyone a favor by by actually I'm not serious but then but
you add to that in building upon that then we look at this idea that if if I would rather
see Linux get to a point where Linux does everything well and we can all that stuff
sounds really great and fancy and cool but I'm thankful for for a reliable usable file
system like exe for that I have and I can fall back on that that I don't lose any data
on and if and when Linux can adopt those things I think it'll be really cool there is there
is ZFS on Linux it's a project from Lawrence Livermore National Laboratories right and
while they're a little bit behind BSD and a Lumos mostly because they started much later
and they have a lot of catching up to do but their latest release I think is 0.6 up for
it has the biggest improvements like the compression stuff and it's it's quite stable and people
are using it and they're quite happy with it I'm waiting for a checkbox in the installer
that I can just check and says yes at a fast ironically Debian might be the first yeah
that'd be really cool yeah there's a I forget the name of the project but there's one that's
looking at Docker and ZFS put together and being able to do interesting things there
is some interesting things you could do there now a lot of you probably out in the audience
might have already tried ZFS into Linux or some of you might be doing it now wimpy didn't
you say on the pre-show that you recently set up a NAS with ZFS just this afternoon
oh wow that is recent and is I assume Linux based right it is it's open media vault 1.0
which is Debbie and Weezy based oh yes and that has a plug-in that adds ZFS support there's
a storage back end with the management utilities to support it as well so the OS is what extended
for and then the data volumes are ZFS that's right so I've got a next for OS drive and
then four drives in ZFS pool and how's the management UI for it I'm something of a newbie
with ZFS so I don't know how comprehensive it is but I was able to set up what I wanted
to do so from a new to ZFS point of view it does what I need and I don't know if it's
going to be stable or not or if it'll work or if it'll fall in a heap but it's an experiment
to try it out do you do you recall is it a pretty current version of ZFS that they're
using it's compatible with the feature flags that are in free nas 9.2 so I don't know what
changed in ZFS between free nas 9.2 and 9.3 right but if you but you can find free nas
yeah yeah you can find a feature flag system works is that would be that'd be true across
any any system that has ZFS with those feature flags it wouldn't just be free nas yeah so
I know that you can import a Z pull that's from free nas 9.2 into this open media vault
system but I don't think you can import a Z pull from free nas 9.3 because the required
feature flags aren't in open ZFS in this Linux implementation yet any initial impressions
on performance well I haven't done it for the performance so this is this is going to
be my Plex server I've really done it to help prevent bit rot and gray holing so your requirements
are stream the HD file fast enough yes just fast enough to get downstairs to the TV yeah
that makes sense I'm still curious though for some reason like I like to know I don't
know I just kind of want to get a sense of what the performance would be like under Linux
yeah well I'm gonna go ahead I will compare that I've got two systems that are identical
ones so they're running the same OS they've got the same hardware same drives runs running
on LVM with XFS over the top and this one's now got ZFS and I will do some sort of finger
in the air kind of benchmarks but performance isn't my main requirement it's really yeah
about date data quality is really what it's about and that totally that totally does make
sense and that's I mean that's why we use it on our NAS here Kitson is it I don't think
it's it is fair to say that ZFS has no more legal concerns necessarily where do you get
that well the Debian team seemed to have analyzed it and if it is good enough for Debian shouldn't
it be good enough for open Susie or fedora I'm wondering how how how did they come to
this conclusion so it appears to me that they got a consultation from either the free software
conservancy or the I'm not actually I don't remember actually who they got their cons
I remember talking about the story now but I'm trying to remember who they got the details
on but if I recall it essentially sounds like Debian as a project might be able to license
it or something is kind of what I was gathering not so much that the legal status has changed
yeah here it is I'm pulling up the article on Phronix right now as we talk about it here
it is he says Neil McGovern he was he's elected as a Debian project leader and as the former
project leader was stepping out he posted his final remarks and his formal formal project
leader was Lucas his final management he said we received legal advice from the software
freedom law center there it is the software freedom law center about the inclusion of
lib DVD CSS so that's the DVD decryption stuff because oh we're all clamping at the bit for
that still and our champ what is that what is that chomping at the bit or and then of
course ZFS and Debian which should unblock the situation of both cases and enables to
ship them in Debian soon we've received legal advice about the inclusion they say that's
pretty ambiguous I don't know what the hell that means well I think at some basic level
it indicates that rather than just looking at it strictly from an engineering point of
view or a software point of view they actually got a hold of someone that has studied law
and at some some inherent level and has actually looked at it from can you know what is the
likelihood of a successful lawsuit on this that's that's what exactly what it sounds
like to me and it sounds like it's a copyright aggregation agreement with the software freedom
Conservancy that's where I got software freedom Conservancy from the Debian project and the
software freedom Conservancy have now now have an agreement that enables Debian contributors
to assign copyright of their works to the Conservancy a couple of the DDs already expressed
interest in some time ago and if you're interested to please get in contact blah blah blah so
that's one thing that came in and I have no idea if that has any relation now to the ZFS
but it sounds like to me man I think it sounds like to you Debian seeked out some legal advice
specifically for the project themselves and got the legal advice that they could include
ZFS not ZFS was legal for Linux to use license wise across the board right I think that's
exactly it yeah yeah Darrell did you know did you have something you want to add about
the license yeah just looking at the perspective that the GPL still complies with the BSD license
there's no technical reason to like legally speaking that is by in violation of the BSD
license in that case so the common scenario in warring is mostly related to shipping by
default with it and also how to make GPL not contaminate the BSD code so to do that you
kind of have to make an exception while releasing the software on your GPL license so I'm guessing
that these that you just mentioned and this is me guessing is the assigning to this institution
allows that institution to make that grant right ability to ship with that code without
GPL contaminating that code if that makes sense that does make sense it's well it makes
as much sense as I think it's gonna make sense to me which is good enough so and then I know
a lot of you out there they're listening right now are smashing your heads against the keyboard
saying guys guys guys oh yeah right ZFS is not BSD license yes I know I know a lot of
you out there smashing against the keyboard saying guys I've been using ZFS on Linux for
years Jed for example which we'll have an interview in one of our shows soon is using
in large-scale production well I'll talk more about Jed in a little bit right ZFS was created
by son it's a the CD DL or whatever the hell that is I know you're using it so I'd like
to hear it but if you could do a post for me so that way we could get a discussion going
on the Linux action show subreddit that would be extremely valuable if you've got a really
awesome setup I wouldn't mind I could I mean I know this is asking for a lot but like a
diagram or something like that you could post it over there just so we could take a look
at it it's Linux action show dot reddit calm I'd like to talk more about it just because
it's something that we're gonna have to tackle here in production I think it's something
we're gonna have to face at JP so basically it's a necessity it's about to come about
you're gonna have to basically do what I feel like I feel like I have just a little bit
of time to before I have to tackle it so I'd like to really I just like to give what people
have to say yeah oh and this would allow you to benefit from other people's experiences
their successes and their failures hey we've got a we've got a lot more coming up including
the Intel middleboard guy which is a fascinating conversation but first I want to tell you
about our second sponsor and that's Ting go over to Linux dot ting dot com why Linux
dot ting dot com well I mean what are you gonna put Windows dot ting dot com in your
browser I don't why would you ask me a silly question like that oh no I Linux dot ting
dot com it supports this show and it's gonna get you twenty five dollars off your first
device and if you already have a ting compatible device and you probably do well then they'll
give you twenty five dollars in service card that paid for more than my first month my
first month of what ting what is ting oh well I'm glad you asked ting is truly finally mobile
that makes sense and nobody can beat them people others have tried there you got people
to think they're the uncare here and as long as you wear a pink shirt and a leather jacket
that's all you need to sell phones apparently and then other people think that they can
just roll into the wireless industry but yet still fail to understand that people don't
want to have to pay per device I got too many devices see if you keep making all these cool
things I'm gonna buy them like tablets and watches and phones and multiple phones I got
too many phones and I'm not gonna pay for data and a contract for every single stinking
device I'm not crazy so I switched to ting I go to Linux dot ting dot com no contract
no early termination fee yeah no contract you only pay for what you use it's a flat
six dollars for the line six bucks so I've got three phones I pay six dollars no that
crazy SOP he's got like five or six phones on there you know and if you're a small business
you've got more than ten lines it's seriously a no-brainer because it's only six dollars
and then you just pay for your usage well I'm on Wi-Fi all the time so no bigs I hardly
have any data usage and I hardly have any minutes used up so for three lines I'm paying
like forty dollars a month it's absolutely outrageous they just take your minutes your
messages and your megabytes they add them up and that's what you pay and then it's really
as simple as that if you have any questions you ever get stuck you call one eight five
five ting FTW and a real human being answers the phone I've never needed to do that though
why because their dashboard freakin rocks nobody has anything on the ting dashboard
you can do everything you need including disabling devices transferring devices activating a
device setting up alerts all these kinds of features it's really nice because if you don't
need a device for a little bit you can just turn it off that's really great like if you
go get one of those my fi access points if you don't need it for a little bit just turn
it off and you can do it right there in the ting dashboard go to linux.ting.com you get
a $25 discount if you have a GSM or CDMA compatible device that works on ting because they take
both now they'll give you a $25 service credit and that's pretty awesome because that paid
for more than my first month and I got a couple of devices you might want to check out they've
have a whole range but I just picked a couple out here first one is this I just I can't
believe they're gonna I figure this is gonna go fast but if you go to linux.ting.com you
can get an unlocked Moto G for $91 ooh that's that's an amazing Android phone it's like
one of the it's I think it's running that Android 4.4 later and it's a well-built phone
people really like the Moto G it's very well reviewed $91 no contract pay for what you
use that's you own that right there that's not the contract price that $91 is you own
it that's just a crazy outrageous great deal you can also get the ting GSM SIM card and
put it anything that takes a GSM SIM for $9 and then it's just $6 after that I'll go check
out all the great devices they got everything from a $47 feature phone all the way up to
the Nexus 6 they got it all and on their blog they also have tips like saving battery and
Android 5.0 very very helpful well I'll tell you when it comes to saving battery stuff
anytime I can get tips on that means I have an opportunity not to deal with that I mean
that's a beautiful thing all right go over to linux.ting.com check them out and if you
have any questions give them a call 1-855-TING-FTW I've been using them for I'm going over like
I'm thinking like two years about two years and two months in two years and three months
in or so so I'm about $2,200 in on my total savings by switching to Ting yeah $2,200 so
go check out much you would save click that savings calculator linux.ting.com click that
savings calculator thank you very much Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged all right guys
so I want to get into this Intel Minnow interview it's very interesting because I think we get
very excited because the Raspberry Pi is very affordable we get very excited because there's
a lot going on in that space with ARM processors there's a lot of different boards to choose
from it's not just the Raspberry Pi I'm gonna admit though the comfort of x86 is appealing
to me in this space if I could get that same form factor and that same power savings but
run my x86 stuff that appeals to me so when John sat down from Intel to talk about the
Minnow board I was excited to see what they have and what he thought the reason was that
not a lot of people are talking about them compared to all of the other ARM based projects
out there and so we have John here and John you said you're at the Minnow board project
yeah I'm with the Minnow board project Minnow board's an open hardware platform that's being
jointly done between Intel and some industry partners to kind of put an Intel face into
the embedded world we've got I mean if you look at the embedded world and everything
it's dominated by ARM and you know from the Intel perspective we don't exactly make it
easy to work with us I mean if you're gonna buy like a million chips from us we help you
out all over the place but we don't really have or we haven't had a lot of really good
open hardware platforms that people can just kind of pick up with and tinker and thus was
born the Minnow board project so one of the things that I really know I really liked was
I was at LinuxCon two years ago and you guys had a Minnow board demo and they gave everyone
a Minnow board and let us actually set the whole thing like unbox it play with it and
we got to make LEDs flash and here's the thing is it sad that like this is the difference
between between and I'm gonna go there I'm gonna say the difference between a traditional
Mac users and traditional Linux users and that is that that most most people that that
that appeal to that Apple ecosystem want just something handed to them into work and I got
this Minnow board and I was like blown away I'm like I could hook this up to my freaking
garage door SSH into my garage door when I get home yeah like that makes no sense to
most Mac users because they would say well that that's silly why would you just not want
to push the button and then the garage door will open I'm like but it's much cooler to
do it over SSH and that's something that you guys you know you guys really nailed and that
that was hands down my favorite exhibit that year nice yeah actually we're giving away
I we gave some of these away at ELC but we're giving them away here we've got these little
proto boards called the tadpole and they they've just got a little RGB LED on them that you
know on the Minnow board if you hook it up it just you know you can twiddle an RGB LED
from GPIO and that's really cool yeah and so we're giving those away here and we're
just we're trying to make the embedded world a little more approachable I mean we can run
stock Linux distributions on the Minnow board yeah so I mean what's the price range on the
Minnow board is that is how competitive are they there so we're a little bit more expensive
we're a hundred and forty nine dollars for a dual core with two gigs of RAM dual core
x86 x64 bit x86 and you're also getting Intel HD graphics gigabit Ethernet USB 3.0 yeah
I mean we've got we've got a lot of the same kind of low-speed IO that similar boards in
the market have yeah but what we're really bringing to the table on top of just the x86
story is we've got all the high-speed IO that you would expect yeah from our kind I could
actually use that in a production environment with that kind of like I mean gigabit Ethernet
for me has always just sort of been the biggest pain point on a lot of these boards because
we're doing such with such large data sets and things like that that the hundred megabit
limitation is a killer for us oh yeah and the fact that x86 being x86 based means I
can take advantage of all of the tools we're already using in-house that are built for
x86 oh yeah no I mean I'm fundamentally running the exact same operating system on my laptop
as I am on an embedded platform now I mean admittedly that's not the way most people
think of as an embedded platform but as CPUs are getting bigger and more powerful in the
embedded space these really are becoming the PCs that were around you know yeah even five
years ago yeah yeah it's kind of remarkable and I think of like computers for our kids
now and things like that and giving them something they can tinker with something that's a little
lower cost but also still very capable so that way they have a good experience and systems
like this are perfect they really fit into that and as computers are becoming more sealed
up and more consumer grade it's so nice to see this this area sort of opening up again
for people that might want to start learning and tinkering again oh yeah well I mean you
nailed it when you said that you know PCs and everything are getting more sealed up
you don't have access to even a you know simple GPIO on your laptop there's no room for it
I mean the best you're getting is USB right which don't get me wrong USB is fantastic
but just making an LED blink from an operating system or even from you know just a controller
so cool yeah yeah it feels like the operating system sitting right on top of the hardware
it's just right there now what am I you said you're giving some of these minnow boards
away we're not giving the minnow boards away here we're giving the tadpole which is tadpole
which is just like I said it's a just a like an RGB LED and it's very small proto space
actually if you go out to minnowboard.org there's a link on the front talking about
the tadpole it'll take you to our wiki and it's got the build instructions right there
and you can see the finished item so what do you think about this trend I'm seeing like
everybody a lot of ARM compute sticks they're like you know the entire computer on an HDMI
stick I see and I think I saw something from Intel in this regard but this seems to be
an area that's really really just taking off what do you think about these in comparison
to sort of the more traditional boards and stuff like that so the the the compute stick
kind of things I mean you're probably talking about the the I'm gonna forget its name but
Intel just yeah really or it is releasing one and right there's been some press about
it in the last couple of days right and the really great at least the article that I was
reading last night they really hit the nail on the head with that one which was it's great
for just giving you an intermediate step to just plug into your TV it's a little bit more
powerful than what you'd expect out of you know like a Chromecast or something else that
you would plug in but it's not quite a full PC so it's just another sealed up sort of
consumer device that maybe has its purpose but it's not it's sort of limited in its full
scope yep yeah well so if people want to learn more about this kind of stuff would be like
some good resources they could go check out if they're watching at home or something so
for the middle board go to minnowboard.org there's a link right at the top for our wiki
and that's got all of our tech specs for the small board computers in general I mean they're
all over the place just do a quick Google search and yeah if I could remember the name
of the little Intel stick but I know I talked about it like a week or a week or so ago on
the news and it's a pretty neat little device and the one that ships with Linux would look
pretty good yeah I could see it likely working even as a receptionist computer hooked up
to a monitor or you know somebody that just needs a basic web browser hooked up to just
an LCD screen and a Bluetooth keyboard and mouse in their home yep and that's kind of
exciting yeah so I but I find more of the board stuff more fascinating for my for my
you know tinkering kind of nature yeah no I mean you're definitely not going to tinker
with you know some of these things that are just plugging in the HDMI ports and I might
watch a YouTube video on it but that's probably about it well thanks for stopping by it was
great chat with you and so do you are you a free agent roaming or do you guys have a
booth no we've got a booth here and I've got a talk this afternoon where I'm gonna network
boot a computer over the Internet awesome really so I'm over there well I open that
connection is gonna work I was gonna say I am taunting the demo gods on that one let
me let me just let me assure you this is the week to try something crazy at the last possible
moment and it will succeed so far yeah I was gonna say it's been lucky yeah it's been well
see it's network booting a computer off of a server in California will be I've done it
to England before and that one did not go well oh really it's always trickier when you
had a conference too yeah conference Internet is always special that's and of course with
my laptop I've like I had to bring my USB ether after gotta be wired oh yeah that seems
to solve a lot of yeah no I'll be a VM on stage yeah over Wi-Fi tomorrow we've got a
talk on the middle board as an open hardware platform cool I'm really glad to hear that
you guys are pushing that area so it's really cool to hear you're talking about it and getting
the word out because I think there's a little late to the game I don't like the games right
word but at least in terms of knowledge share it seems you know and so I think it's pretty
compelling especially for Linux users because it's just slam it right on there and you're
good to go and you know full-fledged Linux box yep well thank you sir no thank you chatting
with you good luck and have good luck with talking enjoy the rest of no thank you I wonder
if anybody in the Mamba room has any experience with any of these Intel mini boards I know
Noah picked one up is anybody the Mamba room experience with any of these like x86 small
boards from Intel that look like they might be interesting the only place I've seen it
was in conferences maybe I should get one and see what they can do might be kind of
fun yeah could be kind of a fun toy to play with and it could be who knows who knows what
we could discover all right well we've got an interview with the guy who who was sort
of core at getting the that variant of wine that made it possible to get Netflix to play
under Linux you remember before we got the HTML 5 playback under Linux there was that
stopgap where you could do like this funky way to get a Silverlight environment and do
all this stuff and get like the next the Netflix desktop PPA and remember all this Matt pipe
lighter pipe pipe there's several there were several iterations of it and it turns out
that behind the scenes it was pretty heated what was going on and it turns out also that
Silverlight is a huge piece of garbage and that one of the reasons that we got HTML 5
native streaming of Netflix is because the project that was getting this to work was
discovering fundamental flaws in Silverlight that they believe Microsoft never wanted to
see the day of light so I'll play that interview now so tell me where Netflix was a couple
years ago and how you felt about it well so a couple years ago we didn't have Netflix
at all on Linux except through VMs and yeah it's very true the one of the big problems
with that of course is the performance issues and for me actually at the time I was doing
a little bit of playing around with it but the thing that really drove me to trying to
get Netflix working on Linux was that I was really pissed off at the administration at
my university I was trying to get my PhD at the time and I just needed a break so that
I wouldn't want to murder them and so I just kind of sat down for a week and started trying
to diagnose how Silverlight worked and was just kind of poking around at the things that
it did on on the system and discovering all sorts of really crazy stuff that they did
that I probably shouldn't talk about because yeah it would tell you how to get the raw
video data right that doesn't surprise me and wouldn't that be a heyday yeah so for
obvious reasons I was not trying to get the raw video data from the Netflix feeds I was
trying to get it to work properly on Linux so that I could give the community something
and not have Microsoft breathing down everyone's throats and want somebody's head right exactly
so the thing that was really challenging with that is that they've put a lot of stuff into
it to try and detect anything that you could possibly be doing I bet to see what it's up
to and so there's all sorts of things that it's doing in the background that actually
have nothing to do with the video feed really like it's just trying to like figure out like
like whether or not you're trying to interfere with it so there's some things example something
I check for well so like one of the things that it does is that it has in the background
the debug helper running and part of that is for reporting problems that happen with
the software okay but part of it is that if that process dies which happens when you try
to attach a debugger then the rest of it shuts down and so even if you didn't start it running
a debugger if you attach one later then it knows and says oh you know it's time for me
to say goodbye to you going on here I'm not even gonna risk it yeah exactly and so you
know who knows how Microsoft actually debugs their own software in that case but I'm sure
that they have some sort of maybe they don't that would explain a few things it would it
would explain a few things especially some of the weird video acceleration stuff that
yeah that Silverlight does it it uses some really old API's and and one of the things
is just crazy to me is that the the key that they use for all the drivers is a 1024 bit
key so like so not the driver key the driver key is better but the master key they used
to sign all of the drivers is like a really ridiculously small so what would be the point
of that like well they made the key in like the 2000s yeah and they never updated it
and it's actually the same key that they're using for OPM now so the the cop the old system
uses the same key now for OPM because it needs to be backwards compatible right and so like
hmm it wouldn't really take all of that much time on a supercomputer figure out there's
a whole bunch of them to be honest but like it's it's kind of ridiculous like some of
the so you may be aware that we actually kind of created a project for staging wine changes
as a result of some of that work that I wasn't sure if it was there as a result but I noticed
it kind of happened yeah so that was before he goes on into the to the wine stuff I thought
it was his comment there he's basically saying look there is this crazy soft spot right here
in Silverlight that you could take advantage of if you if you knew where to poke if you
rented oh I don't know some GPUs on a server somewhere and on up an Amazon you might be
able to start working on this you might be able to crack it he I think I think that guy
knows some major secrets and if it turns out EB in the chat room was playing Call of Duty
with him that night didn't even know and that guy's wife kicked EB's butt in Call of Duty
so he's a hell of a Call of Duty player apparently as well I want to get into he gets into how
they've made how they sort of changed the wine project and how eventually it sort of
cascaded into Netflix getting a native HTML5 playback and the changes that needed to make
to the HTML5 spec before we do that though I'll mention a DigitalOcean our last sponsor
of this week's show DigitalOcean is really making the show possible I tell you what not
only from their support by supporting Linux Unplugged and by you for us out there by using
our promo codes but the technology now just to synchronize these edits that I made all
happening now under Linux all being synced through own cloud droplets that are powered
up on DigitalOcean it's so slick to have the complete workflow from beginning to end for
this entire Linux Fest all done under Linux these interviews that you're playing that
I'm playing back right now that you're watching these are edited well I should back up so
first they're recorded on a Linux rig then they're synced up to a DigitalOcean droplet
for offline storage we had a hundred megabit upload at Linux Fest Northwest they rocked
us with a great connection and so we were able to send footage up to our droplet in
near real time store it off-site which is brilliant because we're shipping that rig
back to Grand Forks North Dakota so Noah could continue to work on it so we wanted to get
all the footage off it and safe immediately we took advantage of that hundred megabit
connection and of course our DigitalOcean droplets rocking fast so we sent all the footage
up to the DigitalOcean droplet almost as it was done we just delayed a little bit because
we weren't in any rush and we didn't need to consume a ton of bandwidth it goes up there
it then sinks back down to my primary workstation here at the studio that runs Arch I've got
Lightworks and Avid Mux ready to go on that thing I bring all of that footage in I had
to remux all of the footage into a new container which don't worry what that means but I was
able to do that very quickly because it was already sitting on my file system when I sat
down I saved the final encoded versions to another folder in own cloud which then sunk
to my bonobo and I'm playing them back here I never once had to sneak in at any files
I never lost any data it was always backed up to my DigitalOcean droplet and the entire
workflow all happened using open source free software and DigitalOcean was the back-end
engine that makes it all possible and when you go over to DigitalOcean and you use our
promo code DOUNPLUGS you'll get a $10 credit go see what you can do for free for two months
with a $5 rig I'm doing this with a $5 rig seriously it's amazing what you can do up
at DigitalOcean they're a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way for you to spin up your own cloud server you can get started in less than 55
seconds and the pricing is nuts it starts at only $5 a month it'll get you 512 megabytes
of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer and that's a great thing because
that means I'm never worrying about this all of these data all these huge files are moving
around we're not going to break a terabyte with this stuff because we're recording them
in a very high resolution very high bitrate x264 file they're large but they're not that
large and I never have to worry about it with that terabyte of transfer it's so nice to
have that peace of mind and for $5 a month it's totally nuts and if you use the promo
code DOUNPLUGS then you get the $10 credit oh my gosh for two months and you get it for
free I mean it's a great deal it's super powerful it could probably really fundamentally
change the way you work it's changed and improved the way I work I feel like digital ocean is
my data center infrastructure on demand they have data centers in New York San Francisco
Singapore Amsterdam Germany and London and their interface is so impressive I love that
aspect of it because it doesn't mean we waste a lot of time tinkering with stuff we get
in we set it up we're done and it's very intuitive so I know anyone on the team can manage it
no problem and the best part is they have an API that lets me take it even further if
we ever want to automate some of this stuff and I hear from people in the audience that
do it all the time and there's tons of great apps created by the community to take advantage
of that API that control panel is really the icing on top of the entire stack it all starts
with Linux and KVM virtualization which is a great virtualizer I think KVM is the best
they use SSD so that way you get super high IO that's awesome because then they have it
connected to tier one bandwidth at the best data centers in the world and the entire package
is then managed with this then they have some of the best communities on tutorials on the
internet between arch and digital ocean like some of the best documentation on the internet
is being created it's really good stuff go over to digital ocean dot com use the promo
code do unplugged that keeps digital that keeps Linux unplugged on the on the air because
it tells digital ocean hey I heard about it on Linux unplugged so you get the $10 credit
which means you don't have to have a credit card to try out digital ocean and you support
this show you keep us going when you use the promo code do unplugged go try them out if
from anything from developing an application to your back end infrastructure digital ocean
can handle it trust me I've done it digital ocean dot com you guys no matter what load
I put it under have never disappointed me digital ocean do unplugged alright so let's
go back to our interview and I want to hear a little bit more about how these changes
impacted the wine project kind of a result of that stuff and that some of those changes
weren't something that AJ wanted to bring into main wine and so what we said is okay
well what if we set up this thing where we can kind of make these things better so that
then eventually they can be included and part of that exploration we started going around
and trying to ask the driver manufacturers okay is there something that you can do for
us that then we can support some of these more advanced features in Silverlight and
integrate that into the driver right and the answers to that were very interesting mostly
in the form of like no comment things but we got somebody off of the record to tell
us oh well there's actually an agreement you sign when you create these drivers that Microsoft
signs off on that you will not make it work on other operating systems what yeah so apparently
so like the reason that you can't have the HD video through even what we've done and
that's all shrouded in NDAs I'm sure right yeah is that we can't make the cop work on
Linux because we can't access the part of the driver we would need to access to do that
legally and so we would have to give you a substitute of what the driver has to do which
involves you having a driver key which you can actually get a hold of if you try but
then it becomes you know kind of like the issue with DVDs and that kind of thing like
then you're distributing one of these numbers that's supposedly a special number yeah special
legal privileges yeah and so there's like all of this stuff around that and you know
a lot of the people that are on our farms like oh well we just want to be able to watch
our HD videos it's like no I'm sorry we have the stuff we just can't give it to you like
if we did then Microsoft would kill us yeah yeah that's a really interesting thing to
sort of pull the rug or pull the carpet or carpet what is it the curtain pull the curtain
back and realize there's there's a lot going on here that you never even realize as somebody
that just sits back and watches the Netflix thing to think you always think it's these
technical hurdles or things like that and it's like no here's the exact spot and if
we could just get access to that but there's this legal barrier that prevents it that seems
like that's only gonna stick for so long until eventually somebody somewhere decides they're
not scared by that well so one of the things with that and actually one of the reasons
we haven't put a lot of effort into that recently is that the inclusion of the HTML 5 stuff
in Chrome that allows you to watch it in Chrome and the DRM stuff extensions or whatever one
of the things that we kind of heard through the grapevine is that the reason that that
exists is that we got things working through Silverlight and they know that there's problems
with Silverlight and so they wanted to take the pressure off they wanted to take the pressure
off that somebody might go in and it's like all things right like it solves a few other
problems for them as well so it's like that you can't deny the timing of it all oh yeah
it does seem like it lines up yeah so that was one of the things we you know we're poking
around some of our driver friends and being like it does this have something to do with
us and they're like yes this has something to do with you like whoa somebody noticed
they're paying attention yeah did you have that moment like oh they are watching well
I mean we've always tried to be very careful with the information that we give out we want
it to be something that like they don't shut down so yeah like you're always from the onset
kind of aware that they're probably gonna find out right yeah because I mean it's a
big deal for them and for the movie industry if that system were to break yes and so it
was something that we were always very cognizant of it kind of seems like they got lucky then
in a way because I think they got lucky that somebody was even cognizant of it because
other people would have just been focused more on the free the movies yeah and they
would have gotten in trouble it wouldn't have worked long term and it probably wouldn't
have sort of encouraged the kind of larger scale change that brought the you know more
native playback using HTML5 extensions I mean if that if the group had gone about if your
group had gone about if you've gone about the wrong way it could have blown it well
yeah and that that was really a big concern initially was that even though we had done
all the right things it's still a question of yeah like even doing all the right things
yeah you can still get in big trouble right and so you know one of the things you know
now that I have a PhD it's actually a little bit harder because you know it's like I'm
a researcher like I I can disclose all sorts of stuff and that's amazing yeah and so but
you know what when you do that what you want is for the community to have that that capability
and not for them to take it away because at any time they could just change the system
and take it away and and that's not what you want them to do right yeah because then it
kind of means you only bought yourself time really right yeah and then they catch up yeah
and so what's the point but I mean now that you know kind of Silverlight is headed out
the door and you know it's pretty much only used in Europe now for for that kind of stuff
yeah like apparently the Amazon service still uses it in Europe even though like they have
HTML5 here in the US and I know some sports events still use it but yeah I mean even Microsoft
themselves seem to be pulling back from Silverlight yeah so but like I was actually on a plane
the other day and they use Silverlight for the video streaming and I was like you know
I wonder if I can get it to run on my laptop and it's like oh sure enough yeah really yeah
I think it was on Southwest really and how did you get it well I mean I just downloaded
the oh the whole Silverlight file yeah oh so it's their web interface yeah so and so
I was able to watch you know the movies on the plane because yeah the Silverlight was
working properly at least as far as you know I can tell that's so funny but yeah I think
I think they they Microsoft made a bold bet and they tried to make they wanted to make
I think they wanted to make Silverlight an entire runtime environment oh yeah they definitely
did yeah it was and it's really clear in the way that it's architected that yeah it was
going to be their dot net for the internet right and it just you know the world did not
want another plug-in based thing no they were moved past it well and all the security issues
involved with it I think people were kind of done with it because Microsoft wasn't you
know they weren't in the same position they are now and it wasn't it was like oh it's
a it's a flash competitor it's Microsoft version they're trying to come in and they just people
were not receptive to it so it was a big like that that whole thing that seems like you
know over the history of our show watching all that Netflix stuff unravel just getting
to the point where yes it is now possible to get Netflix working yeah it's a huge it
was it was a huge step forward yeah you know it's like that and Steam are the like almost
in the entire history of Linux are like the two biggest desktop yeah right that if two
of that just hit and it's like wow I can't believe I'm doing this on Linux yeah it still
blows me away when I start Netflix or start Steam yeah and then I still have moments where
I'm like wow and then of course there is the there is of course April 24th which was the
first day that you know we live streamed from using the OBS software and a last-minute built
Linux rig yes that has not crashed once I might add that is very impressive it's believe
me when I tell you that this was a last-minute job that like the 11 people talk about the
11th hour no we're we are at the 11th hour in the 59th minute like I mean like it is
it is we woke up we woke up I came to the studio he hadn't even seen the box which to
some degree actually implies a certain amount of trust on your on your end because he came
in he went to bed the night before just assuming that that he was like well I trust you guys
I'm sure you'll give me a solution in the morning and to it to my credit we and and
Al's credit we had it done and so he walked in and like I was about ready to pack it up
and he's like well um could I see it work oh yeah yeah yeah we could do that I suppose
so we do that and we I showed him for like 30 seconds and then from that we packed up
and that that is essentially what made the decision so it was not it was not it's something
we want to do for a long time yeah right yeah I mean you you're constantly doing that right
you're constantly looking you're saying this is what I need to do what projects are out
there and we've said it's closed for a long time yeah but you know not fully there exactly
yeah yeah really it's kind of a hacked together solution but and the other thing too that
I think sometimes gets lost is people think oh Chris isn't aware of OBS Chris is aware
no Chris is fully aware of OBS Chris has installed OBS and tried OBS and realized that it was
quite there yet and I looked at the publish date for OBS was two days ago so if we had
tried it one day earlier it probably wouldn't have worked wow yeah well one of the things
that I've seen with a lot of people is that usually for an individual there's one thing
yeah there's really just one thing they tell me about it yeah and it's different for everybody
everybody's got their one thing a lot of people with Netflix and sometimes it sometimes it's
this crazy it's this crazy like side thing it's some program you haven't even heard of
but they cannot live without it right and then that makes it all the more difficult
because like for instance I had there was a girl that we are switching to Linux she
was she was a college student and she used the what was the Microsoft Zune the Microsoft
Zune and they had a media manager for specifically for the zoo which I had never used and to
date I have never met another person that has ever used it right so I don't think it's
real popular I think that iTunes by far and above has the advantage yet she liked the
way the Zune thing works and then Microsoft in traditional Microsoft fashion had all of
their stupid WMAs that were all protected that wouldn't convert and play on Linux right
and it was just it just it just made my job that all the harder yeah that's actually one
of the things that I think that the wine project is really important I know a lot of community
members feel differently about that but man for people that just their one thing is some
piece of commercial software that's only available for Windows like that is the only way that
we're ever going to get those people to switch yeah yeah and there's it's so great for legacy
applications that would never ever be ported there's applications that we use in media
production it's like we just need this one program we can do the whole thing under Linux
and and thankfully thanks to wine we're able to do it so I love it is extremely complicated
some of them are 3d capture of the desktop compress it to an h.264 signal transmitted
over the network to a receiver and we're doing that under wine you know here's where I come
down and what I come down and unlike this I am glad wine exists I like the fact that
wine exists I'm even more happy that certain things run better under wine than than under
Windows itself but I am saddened that we have to have it I am saddened that that people
will only write applications for Windows and thus we need a translation layer to get that
to Linux but I agree that you know that in in in the other thing is when you're moving
people to Linux if you try to just rip the rug out and put a new rug down you're going
to fail you have to baby step people into it and part of that processes and this is
why I kind of separate from from a lot of a lot of the free and open source guys is
let's get everyone on Linux first then we can worry about free open source and then
we can worry about true Libra software but when we try to go from this extreme from proprietary
just everything works and it's being controlled from a company all the way to a niche of a
niche of a niche of a niche of a niche the experience is so poor and so drastic and in
a short amount of time I think it causes problems mm-hmm yeah so I definitely agree I mean I've
seen before a lot of times where people like oh well you know I want my Visual Studio tools
and it's like I mean we have Eclipse Eclipse does a lot of the similar stuff but if you've
become familiar with the Visual Studio workflow then yeah I mean you're asking for people
to make a multiple disruptive steps at the same time yeah yeah that's exactly right multiple
disruptive stuff I'm stealing that so I thought that was a fascinating chat with that guy
and I never really thought about how closely they had to walk that legal line and if they
had blown that whole wine and Netflix thing we might not have ever gotten in the native
playback that we have now which for better for worse I guess but yeah that was pretty
tight line I guess never really appreciated that well definitely seems like they walked
not only a tight line but they were able to do so with restraint and finesse and still
get the result that everybody wanted because that's really tough when you're dealing with
all that kind of legalese yeah yeah and I agree per the chat rooms request we can fire
off a single shot of it is negative in the freedom dimension we can or how about a special
we'll do this a value is negative how about that there you go negative there you go chat
room based on your request mumble room did you guys anybody you want to throw out that
the one app that finally had to come over before they could switch to Linux on their
desktop I thought that was an interesting comment they made where sometimes wine enables
that one application and I remember for me it was outlook back in the day oh really yeah
I was able to you know because evolution wasn't cutting it for me and I had to have exchange
integration for my job so it was outlook oh z3rq7 in the chat room says an MMO yeah that's
not surprising which one do you want to say z3 was it wow you know I still use wine to
play stow today from time to time so wine wine wine I think has helped a lot of us switch
to Linux with me I wanted to yeah go ahead with me yeah my my last Windows computer was
finally ousted when I could run the utilities to configure the scaler and the amplifier
in the home cinema at home using using those tools under wine and USB to serial port adapter
in order to configure that stuff and that was when I finally kicked the last remaining
Windows computer into touch yeah it wow is the threes yeah yeah you know it's funny wimpy
there are things like there are little things like that like like I had a little device
that I required Windows to do firmware updates for a while when I finally got rid of that
device and I was like I don't need that anymore it's just slowly check things off the list
and it was all years ago now so we have a show on the Jupiter broadcasting network called
women's tech radio and one of the hosts on there should her name is Paige and she sat
down quite a bit on the live stream had a lot of really interesting stuff she works
heavily in open source development she talked a lot about doing angel development for small
projects that need angel development of angel funding although angel development she talked
about all of those things but her and Noah I grabbed a little bit from a conversation
on the stream that her Noah had that I thought was particularly interesting because I've
never really thought about it being a white male I never really had to but Paige mentions
and Noah kind of talks about it they're both coming from a minority standpoint about how
a minority has a bigger chance to make a huge impact in open source than they do when dealing
with commercial software development and they talk a little bit about that and it's it's
pretty powerful stuff by that stuff but the nice thing about open source is it doesn't
necessarily have to be a core member of the group that can do something like that if if
if just one person is bothered by it hey listen that's the great thing they can just open
it up they can go edit that stuff and they can push those changes and then they can be
accepted right yeah exactly it's one of the things that is so powerful about open source
is it has that community component and you know I've been doing kind of some sound bites
here at the conference and it's the most common thing that people are saying like oh I'm into
Linux and open source even as a woman because of the community and I think that's a great
point that you know not to throw stones but like trying to get involved as a woman in
the.NET community was painful like they're just it's very much an older crowd it's a
lot of dudes and those and it's very much that that culture of what I know is what I'm
worth so they don't want to share and never mind share with a girl like it really is it's
it's unfortunate that it's still there and I'm not saying that all.NET developers like
this right but it's the experience you had yeah and that's perfectly valid at the same
time like going to a Linux users group they're like you're here you're awesome we don't care
who you are that's funny you say that because statistically proprietary software actually
has a better track record of having acceptance of male-female split I don't remember the
numbers off the top of my head but it was something it's open source is notoriously
low for that it is actually it probably does yeah and so and that's something I think we
need to work on I think it's because the proprietary software is the more traditional path and
I disagree I mean I just I guess I disagree why that is I disagree because I think what
it is is that there is a groundwork laid for proprietary vendors so for example they have
a code of conduct they have human resources to enforce that stuff and when somebody goes
on on the mailing list and says what I need is a such-and-such to do such-and-such while
I'm coding and that would make me code faster and that goes out to a mailing list and offends
a bunch of women they get fired well you but they don't get fired because it's open source
not open source but in the enterprise so that's my I think that plays a that's I think plays
the biggest role per personal opinion I think that that definitely influences it but like
so how would you explain the idea that Ruby Ruby on Rails is there women women who code
in Ruby on Rails is about four percent like developers who identify as women who code
in Rails is four percent sure open source but it's also proprietary and I think that
part of that answer is that the numbers for women in computer science are still decent
they're not great they are growing sure but so like proprietary software is the path that
you come out of a comp sci degree you generally go into proprietary software you don't usually
go into an open source career or into a web dev career like a web dev is more the non-traditional
path my path you know I have a degree in theater like technical theater design it's clearly
not a comp sci degree but my non-traditional path wound me up in web dev which is where
a lot of people end up because it's kind of that crafting side of body it's interesting
you say that because a lot of the people that I knew that originally went to school for
graphic design are now much more sought after for doing design for doing application development
they want those people they want those people with the keen eye and the people like me that
were that you know kind of from the old school open it up and do everything and G at it we're
not so desired anymore we actually had a an interview about this recently they call those
people unicorns you know they're designers who can also be developers yeah yeah we had
an interview on that in yeah I was just looking you actually it's been a little while it was
episode 15 unicorns don't exist that was one yeah yeah hey while you have that site pulled
up maybe Paige can tell us where so if somebody was interested in women's tech radio what
time what day how does that work what does the schedule look like for that comes out
Wednesday mornings over Jupiter broadcasting.com all right yeah and it's hosted by Paige and
Angela and I was just looking Paige you you actually the interview you were the interviewee
in episode 22 if people want to know more about Paige yeah that's actually the I'm long
winded shocker that's a good that's a good problem to have if you're gonna do a podcast
it does seem to be so you guys actually just got kind of the back end of my story and the
interview is the front end of my story yeah exactly yeah and then 23 just came out this
week network is your net worth and then which I'm feeling this week episode 21 the importance
of meetups yeah yeah yeah man what a great week for that yeah I would have to say if
there's one thing that we have had as a consistent thing across all of our interviews it's how
important it is to get out there and meet people yeah I know right yeah I noticed that
too it's hard but you know yeah especially as a nerd if you're an introvert yeah and
you can really easily convince yourself that Twitter and Google Plus and Hangouts and Skype
solve that problem for you yeah and you can kind of just live in that for a while so I
promise I won't judge you for the answer to this question you run medics I do when it's
useful okay yeah I have a I have a question for you too Paige what technology gets you
the most excited right now awesome for me it's I would agree with one of our interviews
from today renewable energy oh yeah yeah I'm all about it about the Tesla home battery
you know I have not I'm a little behind we just had a big project at work so they just
announced it for Earth Day yeah so I love solar specifically I think it's phenomenal
the idea that if we could cover what is something like 15% of the US in solar panels we could
more than exceed our energy needs and that's with current solar technology yeah wow so
I check out page on women's tech radio they come out on Wednesday mornings and they got
some great interviews with some open source developers at Linux fest Northwest this year
they they had some portable recording gear and it makes it a little easier when you don't
have a camera so they're able to go around and find people at the booth and interview
them but it was really good talk with Paige on the live stream if for those of you got
to see the whole thing well Linux fest was really great this year Matt don't you think
it was maybe the best Festa yet it seems like it's it's always hard to equate it because
it's like every year is better than the last but this year definitely felt really really
explosive in a good way and I think a biggest piece of that is we didn't seem to have any
Mac equipment at the table that was like a thing I kept looking around like well there's
I know there's a Mac here somewhere actually not very very much Mac equipment at the whole
there wasn't but yeah but it was really cool and it seemed like a huge crowd yeah it seemed
like a it seemed like a ton of people showed up which is lots of swag which was really
awesome and now we look forward to the next events I know coming up the guys are going
to be itself we're also going to be at OSCON and I'm working on BSD can which isn't locked
in yet sit on my passport yet but I'm working on so those are upcoming events self and BSD
can and OSCON and OSCON I think is in July or something like that in Portland sounds
right yeah I know it's in Portland yeah that'll be a that's a nice one because I'm just gonna
take the train down there possibly or go down with the family and stay on the coast and
then drive into town so that'll be good stuff it's really cool to see everybody in person
and if you'd like to go to a future meetup meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting is where
we're going to schedule those including non like really big things like Michael Dominic
from Kota radio is going to go to a Microsoft event in New York in a little bit and he'll
probably have a meetup there and schedule it at the meetup page that's a lot of fun
and we brought a few people back to the studio after Linux fest and we had a barbecue here
Albert and his brother brought in some burgers and we had dogs and we had chicken skewers
and and we all celebrated by everybody queued up YouTube videos on the Chromecast the blaster
box was fun yeah and so we just watched those all night and I think they kept going till
oh I don't know I don't remember what time you left Matt but they kept going for quite
a while after that oh did they really yeah I think I left I left not too long after so
I could I could see them going well into the night yeah well you know because everybody
was just like couch locked and nobody wanted to get up even when it was time to get food
people didn't really want to get up everybody was exhausted it was very little sleep but
boy I tell you what it really makes me think I think we have the best crew in the world
like it was unbelievable the stuff we pulled off he had you know unbelievable obstacles
you guys you've heard about some of the stuff but you have no idea you just have no idea
it's so amazing so it was really cool to have everybody here and get to get to do that in
person I mean it's I'm always impressed with what we're able to accomplish with all of
us all over the place all remotely yeah right but geez Louise it was unbelievable what we
accomplished in the time that we all had together unbelievable well I think the secrets the
behind the scenes guys the folks that you you know you see them in the video clips walking
in the back you don't really hear from them and I can I can think of three off the top
of my head that just I mean it you know everybody yeah it was awesome yeah and so it was great
we got we had almost everybody out to dinner for the whole crew which was really cool and
all that stuff right all right Matt well we'll wrap it up right there that'll kind of bring
us to the end of this week's unplugged but I'd love to hear you guys's feedback especially
on that ZFS stuff so don't forget you can go over to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash
contact and then choose Linux unplugged from the drop down or even better you go to Linux
action show dot reddit dot com and you can start a thread in our subreddit and the rest
of the community gets to engage and if you're gonna do the ZFS one I'd really really like
that I think that'd be really awesome and I have a quick plug if you want to keep up
with me make sure to head on over to Matt Hartley dot com there's lots of stuff happening
there please subscribe definitely want to keep up on some of the stuff you will care
I trust me on that yeah and Matt Hartley dot com slash t-shirt yes it's I'd love to get
that tipped because that will help these new projects come to fruition very very close
Matt Hartley dot com slash t-shirt check it out they got a great design over there don't
forget Linux unplugged is live on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv join us won't you Jupiter
broadcasting dot com slash calendar it's where you get that to your converted to your local
time zone alright everybody thanks so much for this week's episode see you right back
here next week
okay I have one more clip that I want to play from Linux Fest Northwest but I feel like
if I put it in the post show then I'm abstained from any legal ramifications and and I don't
believe I actually now Matt you you may get implicated in this video but I don't believe
I'm implicated in this video but but Matt and I had no knowledge of this we had this
this we can both say this was not premeditated but I'm not like pole dancing or nothing
right you know what happened the last few years at Linux Fest Northwest our booth has
come under attack now broadcasting does not start a war Jupiter broadcasting would never
start a war but Jupiter broadcasting will finish a war and every year every year nerf
guns are brought to our booth while we are live on the air and we are assaulted we are
assaulted and this year this year we struck back this year this year we brought guns to
a knife fight and I play you the clip as it was captured on the live stream and I gotta
hand it to you Matt you are two for two last year you had the money shot and this year
you have the money shot again man you're two for two you gotta watch this now this is something
that happened for those of you who have not watched our coverage before so you know we
got a little we got we got a little problem here we have to have a serious conversation
your Jupiter broadcasting booth is about to become under attack tell me how it's gonna
become under attack there is an aggressive sect of Linux users present at Linux Fest
Northwest they are armed with nerf weapons and they attack us and you better arm yourself
Noah and get your camera ready because all they have to say now under the table there
I may or may not be handing Noah arms Matt may have may or may not have passed I was
putting them down both ways I was like we're dancing let's get her on as I'm talking on
camera I'm opening them but I have to be sly because they're monitoring our feeds before
they attack it is it may be dawn Noah we are being armed as we speak this is this is troubling
and for insurance purposes I would ask that you all make your own local recording so now
you can Jed walks by okay no you go go Noah go what am I doing oh you're oh oh all right
all right all right okay all right okay so you're giving us a gun now what I didn't know
at this time but if you watch the video playback closely Jed is implanting his children strategically
in the crowd yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah no Alan Jude
member of the Jupiter broadcasting crew host of tech snap and BSD now wearing a Jupiter
broadcasting shirt note Alan you're not even in the camera shot first shot fired by Alan
Jude now Jed that was mine okay now we sit there we take it for a minute right now the
silly string goes crazy mr. system blaster nailed and then there goes Matt Matt breaks
out the silly string nails kid nails kids kid again and then Matt nails my silly string
actually had a broken nozzle so when I initially sprayed it it sprayed everywhere so I had
to like reposition it before I could get to my shot and I wanted to make sure it counted
and then Matt and then Matt's going in for the kill and this is me I'm calling Matt out
we have spilled enough blood right now this is going for it oh my gosh liability liability
I did not I did not ask well if you look at where all the silly string has come and gone
none of it points back to us kick the silly string out get it out of here get rid of the
evidence get rid of the evidence can you believe Alan turned on us I cannot believe that now
one thing I want to also point out that's really really important is the man that was
on the ground really early on Albert was out there with a broom yeah he was wasn't he was
out there sweeping that stuff up yeah you know I mean I think I think because Albert
did that prevented us from getting any trouble because we got right up on the cleanup crew
and that was good yeah the red shirt walked by you know I gave him kind of a original
serious death look and you know he kept walking and we you know it was all good